<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 21:30:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Environment variables are a legacy mess: Let's dive deep into them (184 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://allvpv.org/haotic-journey-through-envvars/</link>
            <guid>45570537</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 16:49:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://allvpv.org/haotic-journey-through-envvars/">https://allvpv.org/haotic-journey-through-envvars/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45570537">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

  <meta property="og:url" content="https://allvpv.org/haotic-journey-through-envvars/">
  <meta property="og:site_name" content="allvpv’s space">
  <meta property="og:title" content="Environment variables are a legacy mess: Let's dive deep into them">
  <meta property="og:description" content="Programming languages have rapidly evolved in recent years. But in software development, the new often meets the old, and the scaffolding that OS gives for running new processes hasn’t changed much since Unix.
If you need to parametrize your application at runtime by passing a few ad-hoc variables (without special files or a custom solution involving IPC or networking), you’re doomed to a pretty awkward, outdated interface:">
  <meta property="og:locale" content="en_us">
  <meta property="og:type" content="article">
    <meta property="article:published_time" content="2025-10-13T15:00:00+02:00">
    <meta property="article:modified_time" content="2025-10-13T15:00:00+02:00">
    <meta property="og:image" content="https://allvpv.org/haotic-journey-through-envvars/pattern-rendered.png">

  <p><time datetime="2025-10-13">
    2025-10-13&nbsp;
  </time>
  
</p>

  
  
  


  
  
  
  

  



<p>Programming languages have rapidly evolved in recent years. But in software
development, the new often meets the old, and the scaffolding that OS gives for
running new processes hasn’t changed much since Unix.</p>
<p>If you need to parametrize your application at runtime by passing a few ad-hoc
variables (without special files or a custom solution involving IPC or
networking), you’re doomed to a pretty awkward, outdated interface:</p>
<h2 id="environment-variables">Environment variables.</h2>
<p><code>export SECRET_API_KEY=2u845102348u234</code></p>
<p>There are no namespaces for them, no types. Just a flat, embarrassingly global
dictionary of strings.</p>
<p>But what exactly are these envvars? Is it some kind of special dictionary
inside the OS? If not, who owns them and how do they propagate?</p>
<h2 id="where-do-they-come-from">Where do they come from?</h2>
<p>In a nutshell: they’re passed from parent to child.</p>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>    841 ?        00:00:00 sshd
   1520 ?        00:00:00  \_ sshd-session
   1616 ?        00:00:00      \_ sshd-session
   5521 pts/0    00:00:00          \_ bash
   5545 pts/0    00:00:00              \_ nu
   5549 pts/0    00:00:00                  \_ bash
   5560 pts/0    00:00:00                      \_ ps
</code></pre><p>On Linux, a program must use the <code>execve</code> syscall to execute another program.
Whether you type <code>ls</code> in Bash, call <code>subprocess.run</code> in Python, or launch a
code editor, it ultimately comes down to <code>execve</code>, preceded by a
<code>clone</code>/<code>fork</code>. The <code>exec*</code> family of C functions also relies on <code>execve</code>.</p>
<div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="c"><span><span><span>SYSCALL_DEFINE3</span><span>(</span><span>execve</span><span>,</span>
</span></span><span><span>		<span>const</span> <span>char</span> <span>__user</span> <span>*</span><span>,</span> <span>filename</span><span>,</span>
</span></span><span><span>		<span>const</span> <span>char</span> <span>__user</span> <span>*</span><span>const</span> <span>__user</span> <span>*</span><span>,</span> <span>argv</span><span>,</span>
</span></span><span><span>		<span>const</span> <span>char</span> <span>__user</span> <span>*</span><span>const</span> <span>__user</span> <span>*</span><span>,</span> <span>envp</span><span>)</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>This system call takes three arguments: <code>filename</code>, <code>argv</code>, <code>envp</code>.
For example, for an <code>ls -lah</code> invocation:</p>
<ol>
<li><code>/usr/bin/ls</code> is the <code>filename</code> (the executable path),</li>
<li><code>['ls', '-lah']</code> is the <code>argv</code> array of command line arguments – the
implicit first (“zero”) argument is usually the executable name,</li>
<li><code>['PATH=/bin:/usr/bin', 'USER=allvpv']</code> is the <code>envp</code> array of envvars
(typically much longer).</li>
</ol>
<p>By default, all envvars are passed from the parent to the child. However,
nothing prevents a parent process from passing a completely different or even
empty environment when calling <code>execve</code>! In practice, most tooling passes the
environment down: Bash, Python’s <code>subprocess.run</code>, the C library <code>execl</code>, and
so on.</p>
<p>And this is what you expect – variables are inherited by child processes.
That’s the point – to track the environment.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Which tools do <em>not</em> pass the parent’s environment?
For example, the <code>login</code> executable, used when signing into a
system, sets up a fresh environment for its children.</p></blockquote>
<h2 id="where-do-they-go">Where do they go?</h2>
<p>After launching the new program, the kernel dumps the variables on the stack as
a sequence of null-terminated strings which contain the envvar definitions.
Here is a hex view:</p>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>    484f 4d45 3d2f 0069 6e69 743d 2f73 6269  HOME=/ init=/sbi
    6e2f 696e 6974 004e 4554 574f 524b 5f53  n/init NETWORK_S
    4b49 505f 454e 534c 4156 4544 3d00 5445  KIP_ENSLAVED= TE
    524d 3d6c 696e 7578 0042 4f4f 545f 494d  RM=linux BOOT_IM
    4147 453d 2f76 6d6c 696e 757a 2d36 2e31  AGE=/vmlinuz-6.1
    342e 302d 3333 2d67 656e 6572 6963 0064  4.0-33-generic.d
    726f 705f 6361 7073 3d00 5041 5448 3d2f  rop_caps= PATH=/
    7573 722f 6c6f 6361 6c2f 7362 696e 3a2f  usr/local/sbin:/
    7573 722f 6c6f 6361 6c2f 6269 6e3a 2f75  usr/local/bin:/u
    7372 2f73 6269 6e3a 2f75 7372 2f62 696e  sr/sbin:/usr/bin
    3a2f 7362 696e 3a2f 6269 6e00 5057 443d  :/sbin:/bin PWD=
    2f00 726f 6f74 6d6e 743d 2f72 6f6f 7400  / rootmnt=/root
</code></pre><p>This static layout can’t easily be modified or extended; the program must copy
those variables into its own data structure. Let’s look at how Bash, C, and
Python store envvars internally. I analyzed their source code and here is a
summary.</p>
<h3 id="bash">Bash</h3>
<p>It stores the variables in a <em><strong>hashmap</strong></em>. Or, more precisely, in a <em><strong>stack
of hashmaps</strong></em>.</p>
<p>When you spawn a new process using Bash, it traverses the stack of hashmaps to
find variables marked as exported and copies them into the environment array
passed to the child.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Side note:</em> Why is traversing the stack needed?</p>
<p>Each function invocation in Bash creates a new local scope – a new entry
on the stack. If you declare your variable with <code>local</code>, it ends up in this
locally-scoped hashmap.</p>
<p>What’s interesting is that you can export a <code>local</code> variable too!</p>
<div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="bash"><span><span><span>function</span> locallyScoped<span>()</span> <span>{</span>
</span></span><span><span>    <span>local</span> <span>PATH</span><span>=</span><span>"</span><span>$PATH</span><span>:/opt/secret/bin"</span>
</span></span><span><span>    <span>export</span> PATH
</span></span><span><span>    env           <span># &lt;- sees the PATH with /opt/scecret/bin</span>
</span></span><span><span><span>}</span>
</span></span><span><span>
</span></span><span><span>
</span></span><span><span>locallyScoped
</span></span><span><span>env               <span># &lt;- sees the PATH without modification</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>I wouldn’t have learned this without diving into Bash source. My intuitive
(wrong) assumption was that <code>export</code> <em>automatically makes the variable
global</em> – like <code>declare -g</code>! Super interesting stuff.</p></blockquote>
<h3 id="the-default-c-library-on-linux-glibc">The default C library on Linux: <code>glibc</code></h3>
<p><code>glibc</code> exposes a dynamic <code>environ</code> array, managed via <code>putenv</code> and <code>getenv</code>
library functions. It uses an array, so the time complexity of <code>getenv</code> and
<code>putenv</code> is <em>linear</em> in the number of envvars. Remember – envvars are not a
high-performance dictionary and you should not abuse them.</p>
<h3 id="python">Python</h3>
<p>Python couples its environment to the C library, which can cause surprising
inconsistencies.</p>
<p>If you’ve programmed some Python, you’ve probably used the <code>os.environ</code>
dictionary. On startup, <code>os.environ</code> is built from the C library’s <code>environ</code>
array.</p>
<p>But those dictionary values are <strong>NOT</strong> the “ground truth” for child processes.
Rather, each change to <code>os.environ</code> invokes the native <code>os.putenv</code> function,
which in turn calls the C library’s <code>putenv</code>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Note that the propagation is one-directional: modifying <code>os.environ</code> will call
<code>os.putenv</code>, but not the other way around. Call <code>os.putenv</code>, and <code>os.environ</code>
won’t be updated.</p></blockquote>
<h2 id="liberal-format">Liberal format</h2>
<p>The Linux kernel is very liberal about the format of environment variables, and
so is <code>glibc</code>.</p>
<p>For example, your C program can manipulate the environment – the global
<code>environ</code> array – such that several variables share the same name but have
different values. And when you execute a child process, it will inherit this
“broken” setup.</p>
<p>You don’t even need an equals sign separating name from value! The usual entry
is <code>NAME=VALUE</code>, but nothing prevents you from adding <code>NONSENSE_WITH_EMOJI 😀</code>
to the array.</p>
<p>The kernel happily accepts any null-terminated string as an “environment
variable” definition. It just imposes a <em>size</em> limitation:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Single variable</strong>: 128 KiB on a typical x64 Intel CPU. This is for the
whole definition – name + equal sign + value. It’s computed as <a href="https://elixir.bootlin.com/linux/v2.6.24/source/include/linux/binfmts.h#L14"><code>PAGE_SIZE * 32</code></a>.
No modern hardware uses pages smaller than 4 KiB, so you can treat it as a
lower bound, unless you need to deal with some legacy embedded systems.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Total</strong>: 2 MiB on a typical machine. This limit is shared by envvars and
the command line arguments. The calculation is a bit more complicated (see
the <code>execve(2)</code> man page):</p>
<pre><code>  max(32 * PAGE_SIZE,  min(MAX_STACK_SIZE / 4,  6 MB))
</code></pre>
<p>On a typical system, the limiting factor is the <code>MAX_STACK_SIZE</code>. Remember,
initially the envvars are dumped on the stack! To prevent unpredictable
crashes, the system allows only 1/4 of the stack for the envvars.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="quirks">Quirks</h2>
<p>But the fact that you can do something does not mean that you should. For
example, if you start Bash with the “broken” environment – duplicated names and
entries without <code>=</code> – it deduplicates the variables and drops the nonsense.</p>
<p>One interesting edge case is a space inside the variable <em>name</em>. My beloved
shell – <a href="https://www.nushell.sh/">Nushell</a> – has no problem with the following
assignment:</p>
<pre><code>$env."Deployment Environment" = "prod"
</code></pre>
<p>Python is fine with it, too. Bash, on the other hand, can’t reference it
because whitespace isn’t allowed in variable names. Fortunately, the variable
isn’t lost – <a href="https://github.com/bminor/bash/blob/a8a1c2fac029404d3f42cd39f5a20f24b6e4fe4b/variables.c#L126">Bash keeps such entries in a special hashmap
called</a>
<code>invalid_env</code> and still passes them to child processes.</p>
<h2 id="the-standard-format">The standard format</h2>
<p>So what name and value can you <em>safely</em> use for your envvar? A popular
misconception, repeated on StackOverflow and by ChatGPT, is that
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/POSIX">POSIX</a> permits only <strong>uppercase</strong>
envvars, and everything else is undefined behavior.</p>
<p>But this is seriously <strong>NOT</strong>
<a href="https://pubs.opengroup.org/onlinepubs/9699919799/">what the standard says</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>These strings have the form name=value; names shall not contain the character
‘=’. For values to be portable across systems conforming to POSIX.1-2017, the
value shall be composed of characters from the portable character set (except
NUL and as indicated below). There is no meaning associated with the order of
strings in the environment. If more than one string in an environment of a
process has the same name, the consequences are undefined.</em></p>
<p><em>Environment variable names used by the utilities in the Shell and Utilities
volume of POSIX.1-2017 consist solely of uppercase letters, digits, and the
&lt;underscore&gt; ( ‘_’ ) from the characters defined in Portable Character Set
and do not begin with a digit. Other characters may be permitted by an
implementation; applications shall tolerate the presence of such names.
Uppercase and lowercase letters shall retain their unique identities and
shall not be folded together. The name space of environment variable names
containing lowercase letters is reserved for applications. Applications can
define any environment variables with names from this name space without
modifying the behavior of the standard utilities.</em></p></blockquote>
<p>Yes, POSIX-specified utilities use uppercase envvars, but that’s not
<em>prescriptive</em> for your programs. Quite the contrary: you’re <em>encouraged</em> to
use lowercase for your envvars so they don’t collide with the standard tools.</p>
<p>The only strict rule is that a variable name cannot contain an equals sign.
POSIX requires compliant applications to preserve all variables that conform to
this rule.</p>
<p>But in reality, not many applications use lowercase. The <em>proper etiquette</em> in
software development is to use <code>ALL_UPPERCASE</code>.</p>
<h2 id="my-pragmatic-recommendation-is">My pragmatic recommendation is…</h2>
<p>…to use <code>^[A-Z_][A-Z0-9_]*$</code> for names, and UTF-8 for values. You shouldn’t
hit problems on Linux. If you want to be super safe: instead of UTF-8, use the
POSIX-mandated <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portable_character_set">Portable Character Set
(PCS)</a> – essentially
ASCII without control characters.</p>


<h2 id="wow-i-really-enjoyed-writing-this">Wow, I really enjoyed writing this…</h2>
<p>…and I hope it wasn’t a boring read.</p>


  
    
  

  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Android's sideloading limits are its most anti-consumer move yet (456 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.makeuseof.com/androids-sideloading-limits-are-anti-consumer-move-yet/</link>
            <guid>45569371</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 15:24:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.makeuseof.com/androids-sideloading-limits-are-anti-consumer-move-yet/">https://www.makeuseof.com/androids-sideloading-limits-are-anti-consumer-move-yet/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45569371">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

                            <div data-nosnippet="">
                                            <p><a href="https://www.makeuseof.com/author/afam-onyimadu/">
                                    <img src="https://static0.makeuseofimages.com/wordpress%2Fwp-content%2Fauthors%2F689ee4bbf182f-Afamefuna.jpg?fit=crop&amp;w=90&amp;h=90" alt="4" loading="lazy" decoding="async">
                                </a>
                                                    </p>
                                    </div>
                        
                                            
                                
                                    <div data-nosnippet=""><p>Afam's experience in tech publishing dates back to 2018, when he worked for Make Tech Easier. Over the years, he has built a reputation for publishing high-quality guides, reviews, tips, and explainer articles, covering Windows, Linux, and open source tools. His work has been featured on top websites, including Technical Ustad, Windows Report, Guiding Tech, Alphr, and Next of Windows.</p><p>

He holds a first degree in Computer Science and is a strong advocate for data privacy and security, with several tips, videos, and tutorials on the subject published on the Fuzo Tech YouTube channel.</p><p>

When he is not working, he loves to spend time with his family, cycling, or tending to his garden.&nbsp; </p></div>
                                    </div><div id="article-body" itemprop="articleBody"><p>I’m a huge fan of open source, and that’s one of the reasons I’m drawn to Android. However, new requirements surrounding sideloaded apps, which will start rolling out in October 2025, may be the most anti-consumer move yet by Google. Mandatory enforcement of the requirement will begin in September 2026 (starting with specific countries), marking a turning point where the freedom to install any app comes with conditions set by Google.</p>    <!-- No AdsNinja v10 Client! --><!-- No AdsNinja v10 Client! --><p>I’ve used apps like NewPipe (a media/YouTube client) and Blokada (an ad blocker) for years now. However, these apps aren’t available on the Google Play Store, so I have to obtain them from third-party sources, such as F-Droid. With Google tightening the rules around sideloaded apps, I fear I may lose access to some of the apps I love most on Android because they aren’t verified. <a href="https://www.makeuseof.com/google-android-sideloading-restrictions-switch-to-ios/" target="_blank">Sideloading isn’t going away, but people may seek alternatives</a> because it may feel like the gates are narrowing.</p>    <!-- No AdsNinja v10 Client! --><h2 id="what-google-actually-changed">
                        What Google actually changed
               </h2><h3 id="the-rules-the-timeline-and-what-ldquo-certified-rdquo-really-means">
            The rules, the timeline, and what “certified” really means
    </h3>

                
    
    
    
                
    
                
        
                                                            
                                                                                                                        
                                        
    
    

    
    <div data-img-url="https://static0.makeuseofimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/10/google-sideloading-restrictionsanti-consumer-move.jpg" data-modal-id="single-image-modal" data-modal-container-id="single-image-modal-container" data-img-caption="&quot;&quot;">
                                                                                            <picture><source media="(max-width: 480px)" data-srcset="https://static0.makeuseofimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/10/google-sideloading-restrictionsanti-consumer-move.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=500&amp;dpr=2" srcset="https://static0.makeuseofimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/10/google-sideloading-restrictionsanti-consumer-move.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=500&amp;dpr=2">
        <source media="(max-width: 767px)" data-srcset="https://static0.makeuseofimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/10/google-sideloading-restrictionsanti-consumer-move.jpg?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=800&amp;dpr=1" srcset="https://static0.makeuseofimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/10/google-sideloading-restrictionsanti-consumer-move.jpg?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=800&amp;dpr=1">
        <source media="(max-width: 1023px)" data-srcset="https://static0.makeuseofimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/10/google-sideloading-restrictionsanti-consumer-move.jpg?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=1" srcset="https://static0.makeuseofimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/10/google-sideloading-restrictionsanti-consumer-move.jpg?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=1">
        <img width="825" height="521" loading="lazy" decoding="async" alt="Google sideloading restrictions anti-consumer move" data-img-url="https://static0.makeuseofimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/10/google-sideloading-restrictionsanti-consumer-move.jpg?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=1" src="https://static0.makeuseofimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/10/google-sideloading-restrictionsanti-consumer-move.jpg?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=1">
        </picture>
            
        </div>
<p>Google's talk around "verified developers" sounds harmless and, in some ways, helpful. As reported on the <a href="https://android-developers.googleblog.com/2025/08/elevating-android-security.html" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Android Developer Blog</a>, it is like "an ID check at the airport which confirms a traveler's identity but is separate from the security screening of their bags." Google's analogy, however, may be oversimplified. When this is enforced, the only way a developer’s app will be installable on devices that include Google Mobile Services (GMS) — which typically provide access to the Play Store — is by completing ID verification using government-issued documents or contact information. This will be rolled out globally in 2027.</p>    <p>Apps will be blocked from installing on most mainstream phones if their developer can't complete this verification. However, there are certain devices that will remain unaffected, even though they are just a tiny fraction of the total devices. These categories include all devices that do not pass Google's certification test, primarily custom ROMs or de-Googled phones.</p>    <p>Strictly speaking, Google is not removing sideloading, but it is redefining and limiting participation in the Android ecosystem by creating a mandatory Google-controlled choke point. While this may be a subtle shift, it clearly takes an open source project from anyone being able to participate (including anonymous or pseudonymous distribution) to only those whom Google allows to participate (via centralized developer identity verification).</p>    <h2 id="security-theater-or-real-gain">
                        Security theater or real gain?
               </h2><h3 id="testing-google-rsquo-s-justification">
            Testing Google’s justification
    </h3>

                
    
    
    
                
    
                
        
                                                            
                                                                                                                        
                                                                        
    
    

    
    <div data-img-url="https://static0.makeuseofimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/a-person-holding-a-samsung-galaxy-s24-ultra-running-niagra-launcher.jpg" data-modal-id="single-image-modal" data-modal-container-id="single-image-modal-container" data-img-caption="&quot;&quot;">
                                                                                            <picture><source media="(max-width: 480px)" data-srcset="https://static0.makeuseofimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/a-person-holding-a-samsung-galaxy-s24-ultra-running-niagra-launcher.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=500&amp;dpr=2" srcset="https://static0.makeuseofimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/a-person-holding-a-samsung-galaxy-s24-ultra-running-niagra-launcher.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=500&amp;dpr=2">
        <source media="(max-width: 767px)" data-srcset="https://static0.makeuseofimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/a-person-holding-a-samsung-galaxy-s24-ultra-running-niagra-launcher.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=800&amp;dpr=2" srcset="https://static0.makeuseofimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/a-person-holding-a-samsung-galaxy-s24-ultra-running-niagra-launcher.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=800&amp;dpr=2">
        <source media="(max-width: 1023px)" data-srcset="https://static0.makeuseofimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/a-person-holding-a-samsung-galaxy-s24-ultra-running-niagra-launcher.jpg?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=1" srcset="https://static0.makeuseofimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/a-person-holding-a-samsung-galaxy-s24-ultra-running-niagra-launcher.jpg?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=1">
        <img width="825" height="464" loading="lazy" decoding="async" alt="a person holding a samsung galaxy s24 ultra running niagra launcher" data-img-url="https://static0.makeuseofimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/a-person-holding-a-samsung-galaxy-s24-ultra-running-niagra-launcher.jpg?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=1" src="https://static0.makeuseofimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/a-person-holding-a-samsung-galaxy-s24-ultra-running-niagra-launcher.jpg?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=1">
        </picture>
            
        </div>
<p> There is a rational justification for tightening rules around sideloaded apps. It could be framed as user protection against malicious apps or against bad actors who cloak themselves with fake identities. While this is reasonable, the real question is whether it adds significant security for everyday users.</p>    <p>This is a valid question because security checks already exist. <a href="https://www.makeuseof.com/tag/google-play-protect-android-secure/" target="_blank">Google Play Protect makes Android secure</a> by scanning sideloaded apps. Android flags unsafe installs, and it’s always given us the choice of blocking apps from unknown sources. Even if these are imperfect, they’re defenses that already exist.</p>    <p>Google’s new move almost feels like it’s based on the assumption that identity equals integrity. Does a verified government-issued identification equate to user safety? This logic is flawed: historically, we've seen malware slip through the Play Store—signed and “verified”—several times. However, what the new rule does is shift the basis of trust away from existing on-device security warnings and your best judgment.</p>    <p>Critics may even contend that this new rule erodes your right to make informed decisions about your own devices, and that feels more like selective control. Ultimately, many people may view this as Google’s way of shielding itself from criticism over sideloaded malware and protecting the integrity of its ecosystem.</p>    <h2 id="there-will-be-collateral-damage">
                        There will be collateral damage
               </h2><h3 id="the-ecosystems-that-depend-on-openness">
            The ecosystems that depend on openness
    </h3>


            
    
<p>This may be the most significant anti-consumer move, simply due to its profound impact. It could hit big developers or commercial apps, as well as entire ecosystems built around freely distributed APKs without verification. F-Droid hosts an incredible number of apps not available on the Play Store. Many of these tools exist because they see a need to operate outside the long, controlling arm of Google. This sideloading rule may make them unavailable on mainstream devices even though they’re safe.</p>    <p>This is a risk that also affects indie developers and hobbyists. Certain apps can no longer justify the time, effort, or privacy trade-offs required for identity verification. Many one-off projects and apps for niche communities may fall under this category. Ultimately, what we may end up with is a shrunken ecosystem, and if this happens, it will hurt all of us.</p>    <p>However, innovation may be the biggest casualty in all of this. Android is great because of its flexibility. It is an ecosystem for everyone. The imposition of a single, centralized gatekeeper will stifle grassroots innovation, as not everyone will be willing or able to contribute, and this will invariably impact the pace and extent of innovation we see on Android.</p>    <h2 id="the-new-reality-for-android-users">
                        The new reality for Android users
               </h2><p>Although Google would argue that the intentions behind the new rules for sideloading apps are to protect and secure users, it will likely feel limiting to many Android users, let alone removing the sense of autonomy on our devices. Of course, sideloading will still be possible, but it creates friction for people who use or make apps that aren’t officially available on the Play Store. The fear is that it may be the beginning of the end for independent developers, hobbyists, and niche app communities.</p>    <p>Of course, there are workarounds: using non-certified devices, backing up APKs, or exploring alternative app stores. Sadly, the trade-offs for each workaround may range from technical complexity to potential security risks. You should <a href="https://www.makeuseof.com/sideloading-android-apps-drain-bank-account/" target="_blank">be careful when sideloading apps on Android</a>. However, one thing is clear: Android's openness is closing. What we don’t know is if it will become a completely closed ecosystem someday.</p>    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[NanoChat – The best ChatGPT that $100 can buy (615 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/karpathy/nanochat</link>
            <guid>45569350</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 15:22:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/karpathy/nanochat">https://github.com/karpathy/nanochat</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45569350">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">nanochat</h2><a id="user-content-nanochat" aria-label="Permalink: nanochat" href="#nanochat"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/karpathy/nanochat/blob/master/dev/nanochat.png"><img src="https://github.com/karpathy/nanochat/raw/master/dev/nanochat.png" alt="nanochat logo"></a></p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">The best ChatGPT that $100 can buy.</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto">This repo is a full-stack implementation of an LLM like ChatGPT in a single, clean, minimal, hackable, dependency-lite codebase. nanochat is designed to run on a single 8XH100 node via scripts like <a href="https://github.com/karpathy/nanochat/blob/master/speedrun.sh">speedrun.sh</a>, that run the entire pipeline start to end. This includes tokenization, pretraining, finetuning, evaluation, inference, and web serving over a simple UI so that you can talk to your own LLM just like ChatGPT. nanochat will become the capstone project of the course LLM101n being developed by Eureka Labs.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Quick start</h2><a id="user-content-quick-start" aria-label="Permalink: Quick start" href="#quick-start"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The fastest way to feel the magic is to run the speedrun script <a href="https://github.com/karpathy/nanochat/blob/master/speedrun.sh">speedrun.sh</a>, which trains and inferences the $100 tier of nanochat. On an 8XH100 node at $24/hr, this gives a total run time of about 4 hours. Boot up a new 8XH100 GPU box from your favorite provider (e.g. I use and like <a href="https://lambda.ai/service/gpu-cloud" rel="nofollow">Lambda</a>), and kick off the training script:</p>

<p dir="auto">Alternatively, since the script runs for 4 hours, I like to launch it like this inside a new screen session <code>speedrun</code> (and also log output to <code>speedrun.log</code>):</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="screen -L -Logfile speedrun.log -S speedrun bash speedrun.sh"><pre>screen -L -Logfile speedrun.log -S speedrun bash speedrun.sh</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">See the <a href="https://gist.github.com/jctosta/af918e1618682638aa82">screen cheatsheet</a> if you are less familiar. You can watch it go inside the screen session, or detach with <code>Ctrl-a d</code> and <code>tail speedrun.log</code> to view progress. Now wait 4 hours. Once it's done, you can talk to your LLM via the ChatGPT-like web UI. Make sure again that your local uv virtual environment is active (run <code>source .venv/bin/activate</code>), and serve it:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="python -m scripts.chat_web"><pre>python -m scripts.chat_web</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">And then visit the URL shown. Make sure to access it correctly, e.g. on Lambda use the public IP of the node you're on, followed by the port, so for example <a href="http://209.20.xxx.xxx:8000/" rel="nofollow">http://209.20.xxx.xxx:8000/</a>, etc. Then talk to your LLM as you'd normally talk to ChatGPT! Get it to write stories or poems. Ask it to tell you who you are to see a hallucination. Ask it why the sky is blue. Or why it's green. The speedrun is a 4e19 FLOPs capability model so it's a bit like talking to a kindergartener :).</p>
<hr>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/241138/500544377-ed39ddf8-2370-437a-bedc-0f39781e76b5.png?jwt=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3NjAzODA1MDIsIm5iZiI6MTc2MDM4MDIwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii8yNDExMzgvNTAwNTQ0Mzc3LWVkMzlkZGY4LTIzNzAtNDM3YS1iZWRjLTBmMzk3ODFlNzZiNS5wbmc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjUxMDEzJTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI1MTAxM1QxODMwMDJaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT0xMjE4Nzc0YWZhMWUwOGZjNTQyMGEzYmIyZDA1NGNkMGVlMjNmMzA1MGY5YWMzZGE4OTYxYjZhNzBjODI2YWE4JlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCJ9.H7XZJsilpHSvwTxSXHiqAJpxAn0xG_2v1Nd9lHGQHKk"><img width="2000" height="1520" alt="image" src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/241138/500544377-ed39ddf8-2370-437a-bedc-0f39781e76b5.png?jwt=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3NjAzODA1MDIsIm5iZiI6MTc2MDM4MDIwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii8yNDExMzgvNTAwNTQ0Mzc3LWVkMzlkZGY4LTIzNzAtNDM3YS1iZWRjLTBmMzk3ODFlNzZiNS5wbmc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjUxMDEzJTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI1MTAxM1QxODMwMDJaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT0xMjE4Nzc0YWZhMWUwOGZjNTQyMGEzYmIyZDA1NGNkMGVlMjNmMzA1MGY5YWMzZGE4OTYxYjZhNzBjODI2YWE4JlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCJ9.H7XZJsilpHSvwTxSXHiqAJpxAn0xG_2v1Nd9lHGQHKk"></a>
<hr>
<p dir="auto">You can also <code>cat report.md</code> file which appeared in the project directory and contains the "report card" of the run, i.e. a bunch of evaluations and metrics. At the very end, you'll see a summary table, for example:</p>
<hr>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Characters: 333,989</li>
<li>Lines: 8,304</li>
<li>Files: 44</li>
<li>Tokens (approx): 83,497</li>
<li>Dependencies (uv.lock lines): 2,004</li>
</ul>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Metric</th>
<th>BASE</th>
<th>MID</th>
<th>SFT</th>
<th>RL</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>CORE</td>
<td>0.2219</td>
<td>-</td>
<td>-</td>
<td>-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ARC-Challenge</td>
<td>-</td>
<td>0.2875</td>
<td>0.2807</td>
<td>-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ARC-Easy</td>
<td>-</td>
<td>0.3561</td>
<td>0.3876</td>
<td>-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GSM8K</td>
<td>-</td>
<td>0.0250</td>
<td>0.0455</td>
<td>0.0758</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>HumanEval</td>
<td>-</td>
<td>0.0671</td>
<td>0.0854</td>
<td>-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MMLU</td>
<td>-</td>
<td>0.3111</td>
<td>0.3151</td>
<td>-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ChatCORE</td>
<td>-</td>
<td>0.0730</td>
<td>0.0884</td>
<td>-</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto">Total wall clock time: 3h51m</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto">(Your table might be missing the RL number by default). For a lot more information around the speedrun script and what to look for and expect, please refer to the walkthrough that I posted in Discussions of the repo: <a href="https://github.com/karpathy/nanochat/discussions/1" data-hovercard-type="discussion" data-hovercard-url="/karpathy/nanochat/discussions/1/hovercard">"Introducing nanochat: The best ChatGPT that $100 can buy"</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Bigger models</h2><a id="user-content-bigger-models" aria-label="Permalink: Bigger models" href="#bigger-models"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Unsurprisingly, $100 is not enough to train a highly performant ChatGPT clone. In fact, LLMs are famous for their multi-million dollar capex. For our purposes, I think there are two more scales of interest. First is the ~$300 tier d26 model (i.e. depth=26) that trains in ~12 hours, which slightly outperforms GPT-2 CORE score. Second is the $1000 tier (~41.6 hours), just because it's a nice round number. But both of these are not yet fully supported and therefore not attached here in the master branch yet.</p>
<p dir="auto">That said, to give a sense, the example changes needed for the <a href="https://github.com/karpathy/nanochat/blob/master/speedrun.sh">speedrun.sh</a> file to train a GPT-2 grade model d26 only involve three changes:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="...
# you'll need to download more data shards for pretraining
# get the number of parameters, multiply 20 to get tokens, multiply by 4.8 to get chars,
# divide by 250 million to get number of shards. todo need to improve this...
python -m nanochat.dataset -n 450 &amp;
...
# use --depth to increase model size. to not oom, halve device batch size 32 -> 16:
torchrun --standalone --nproc_per_node=8 -m scripts.base_train -- --depth=26 --device_batch_size=16
...
# make sure to use the same later during midtraining:
torchrun --standalone --nproc_per_node=8 -m scripts.mid_train -- --device_batch_size=16"><pre>...
<span><span>#</span> you'll need to download more data shards for pretraining</span>
<span><span>#</span> get the number of parameters, multiply 20 to get tokens, multiply by 4.8 to get chars,</span>
<span><span>#</span> divide by 250 million to get number of shards. todo need to improve this...</span>
python -m nanochat.dataset -n 450 <span>&amp;</span>
...
<span><span>#</span> use --depth to increase model size. to not oom, halve device batch size 32 -&gt; 16:</span>
torchrun --standalone --nproc_per_node=8 -m scripts.base_train -- --depth=26 --device_batch_size=16
...
<span><span>#</span> make sure to use the same later during midtraining:</span>
torchrun --standalone --nproc_per_node=8 -m scripts.mid_train -- --device_batch_size=16</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">That's it! The biggest thing to pay attention to is making sure you have enough data shards to train on (the code will loop and do more epochs over the same training set otherwise, decreasing learning speed a bit), and managing your memory/VRAM, primarily by decreasing the <code>device_batch_size</code> until things fit (the scripts automatically compensates by increasing the number of gradient accumulation loops, simply turning parallel compute to sequential compute).</p>
<p dir="auto">And a bit more about computing environments that will run nanochat:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>The code will run just fine on the Ampere 8XA100 GPU node as well, but a bit slower.</li>
<li>All code will run just fine on even a single GPU by omitting <code>torchrun</code>, and will produce ~identical results (code will automatically switch to gradient accumulation), but you'll have to wait 8 times longer.</li>
<li>If your GPU(s) have less than 80GB, you'll have to tune some of the hyperparameters or you will OOM / run out of VRAM. Look for <code>--device_batch_size</code> in the scripts and reduce it until things fit. E.g. from 32 (default) to 16, 8, 4, 2, or even 1. Less than that you'll have to know a bit more what you're doing and get more creative.</li>
<li>Most of the code is fairly vanilla PyTorch so it should run on anything that supports that - xpu, mps, or etc, but I haven't implemented this out of the box so it might take a bit of tinkering.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Questions</h2><a id="user-content-questions" aria-label="Permalink: Questions" href="#questions"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">nanochat is designed to be short and sweet. One big advantage of this is that we can package up all of the files together and copy paste them to your favorite LLM to ask arbitrary questions. As an example, I like to package up the repo using the <a href="https://github.com/simonw/files-to-prompt">files-to-prompt</a> utility like so:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="files-to-prompt . -e py -e md -e rs -e html -e toml -e sh --ignore &quot;*target*&quot; --cxml > packaged.txt"><pre>files-to-prompt <span>.</span> -e py -e md -e rs -e html -e toml -e sh --ignore <span><span>"</span>*target*<span>"</span></span> --cxml <span>&gt;</span> packaged.txt</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">This includes all py, rs, html, toml, sh files, excludes the <code>rustbpe/target</code> folder, and chooses the cxml output format. Everything is written to the <code>packaged.txt</code> file, which atm measures ~330KB (i.e. well below ~100K tokens for a state of the art LLM), and ~8K lines of code in 45 files.</p>
<p dir="auto">Alternatively, I recommend using <a href="https://deepwiki.com/" rel="nofollow">DeepWiki</a> from Devin/Cognition to ask questions of this repo. In the URL of this repo, simply change github.com to deepwiki.com, and you're off.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Tests</h2><a id="user-content-tests" aria-label="Permalink: Tests" href="#tests"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">I haven't invested too much here but some tests exist, especially for the tokenizer. Run e.g. as:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="python -m pytest tests/test_rustbpe.py -v -s"><pre>python -m pytest tests/test_rustbpe.py -v -s</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing</h2><a id="user-content-contributing" aria-label="Permalink: Contributing" href="#contributing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">nanochat is nowhere finished. The goal is to improve the state of the art in micro models that are accessible to work with end to end on budgets of &lt; $1000 dollars. Accessibility is about overall cost but also about cognitive complexity - nanochat is not an exhaustively configurable LLM "framework"; there will be no giant configuration objects, model factories, or if-then-else monsters in the code base. It is a single, cohesive, minimal, readable, hackable, maximally-forkable "strong baseline" codebase designed to run start to end and produce a concrete ChatGPT clone and its report card.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Acknowledgements</h2><a id="user-content-acknowledgements" aria-label="Permalink: Acknowledgements" href="#acknowledgements"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>The name (nanochat) derives from my earlier project <a href="https://github.com/karpathy/nanoGPT">nanoGPT</a>, which only covered pretraining.</li>
<li>nanochat is also inspired by <a href="https://github.com/KellerJordan/modded-nanogpt">modded-nanoGPT</a>, which gamified the nanoGPT repo with clear metrics and a leaderboard, and borrows a lot of its ideas and some implementation for pretraining.</li>
<li>Thank you to <a href="https://huggingface.co/" rel="nofollow">HuggingFace</a> for fineweb and smoltalk.</li>
<li>Thank you <a href="https://lambda.ai/service/gpu-cloud" rel="nofollow">Lambda</a> for the compute used in developing this project.</li>
<li>Thank you to chief LLM whisperer 🧙‍♂️ Alec Radford for advice/guidance.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Cite</h2><a id="user-content-cite" aria-label="Permalink: Cite" href="#cite"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If you find nanochat helpful in your research cite simply as:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="@misc{nanochat,
  author = {Andrej Karpathy},
  title = {nanochat: The best ChatGPT that $100 can buy},
  year = {2025},
  publisher = {GitHub},
  url = {https://github.com/karpathy/nanochat}
}"><pre><span>@misc</span>{<span>nanochat</span>,
  <span>author</span> = <span><span>{</span>Andrej Karpathy<span>}</span></span>,
  <span>title</span> = <span><span>{</span>nanochat: The best ChatGPT that $100 can buy<span>}</span></span>,
  <span>year</span> = <span><span>{</span>2025<span>}</span></span>,
  <span>publisher</span> = <span><span>{</span>GitHub<span>}</span></span>,
  <span>url</span> = <span><span>{</span>https://github.com/karpathy/nanochat<span>}</span></span>
}</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">MIT</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A16Z-backed data firms Fivetran, dbt Labs to merge in all-stock deal (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.reuters.com/business/a16z-backed-data-firms-fivetran-dbt-labs-merge-all-stock-deal-2025-10-13/</link>
            <guid>45568842</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 14:42:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.reuters.com/business/a16z-backed-data-firms-fivetran-dbt-labs-merge-all-stock-deal-2025-10-13/">https://www.reuters.com/business/a16z-backed-data-firms-fivetran-dbt-labs-merge-all-stock-deal-2025-10-13/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45568842">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.reuters.com/business/a16z-backed-data-firms-fivetran-dbt-labs-merge-all-stock-deal-2025-10-13/: Error: Request failed with status code 401]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ofcom fines 4chan £20K and counting for violating UK's Online Safety Act (148 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theregister.com/2025/10/13/4chan_ofcom_fine/</link>
            <guid>45568767</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 14:34:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/10/13/4chan_ofcom_fine/">https://www.theregister.com/2025/10/13/4chan_ofcom_fine/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45568767">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="body">
<p>Ofcom, the UK's Online Safety Act regulator, has fined online message board 4chan £20,000 ($26,680) for failing to protect children from harmful content.</p>
<p>The fine could rise by a further £6,000 – £100 per day for a maximum 60 days – if it continues to ignore its duties to comply with the regulator's request for information regarding two separate matters.</p>
<p>4chan can stop the additional fines by providing copies of its illegal content risk assessments and information about its qualifying worldwide revenue to Ofcom.</p>

    

<p>The enforcement action announced today is months in the making after Ofcom first opened an investigation into the notorious image board on June 10.</p>

        


        

<p>It requested the aforementioned risk assessments on April 14, and to this day 4chan still has not complied, the regulator said.</p>
<p>When opening the investigation, Ofcom said it was looking to understand whether 4chan has failed, or is failing, to abide by its duties under the Online Safety Act.</p>

        

<p>The watchdog also highlighted that the maximum penalties for these failures, as specified in the legislation, are £18 million ($24 million) or 10 percent of an organization's qualifying worldwide revenue, whichever is greater.</p>
<p><em>The Register</em> contacted <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/04/28/4chan_back_onlin/">4chan</a> for its side of the story.</p>
<p>Ofcom's fine is the first made under the Online Safety Act since in-scope organizations' illegal content duties came into force on March 17. It also announced two provisional decisions to take action against file-sharing service Im.ge and pornography service provider AVS Group Ltd for similar failures to respond to information requests.</p>

        

<p>In Im.ge's case, this relates to its duty to implement measures to prevent the circulation of child sexual abuse material (CSAM), and AVS Group was rapped over its duty to implement <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/10/09/discord_photo_ids_leaked/">age-check mechanisms</a>.</p>
<p>Both organizations have the chance to appeal Ofcom's findings before it makes a final decision on how to reprimand them.</p>
<p>Another porn provider, Youngtek Solutions Ltd, is also under an expanded investigation over its failure to respond to information requests regarding age-checking requirements.</p>
<p>Tech secretary Liz Kendall said: "The Online Safety Act is not just law, it's a lifeline. Today we've seen it in action, holding platforms to account so we can protect people across the UK.</p>
<p>"Services can no longer ignore illegal content, like encouraging self-harm or suicide, circulating online which can devastate young lives and leave families shattered.</p>
<p>"This fine is a clear warning to those who fail to remove illegal content or protect children from harmful material. We fully back the regulator in taking action against all platforms that do not protect users from the darkest corners of the internet."</p>
<p>In total, since March 2025, Ofcom has opened 21 investigations into the providers of in-scope apps and websites, and launched five enforcement programs.</p>
<h3>Playing by the rules</h3>
<p>In brighter news, others under Ofcom investigation have shown improvements, and several of these cases are now closed.</p>
<p>Four file-sharing services under investigation for their child safety measures avoided further action by geo-blocking UK users, much to Ofcom's delight. Krakenfiles, Nippydrive, Nippyshare, and Nippyspace have all blocked British IP addresses instead of following other measures set out in the regulator's codes of practice.</p>
<p>Ofcom said it has closed the cases into these sites, and that the measures have "significantly reduced the likelihood that people in the UK will be exposed to any illegal or harmful content."</p>
<p>"We will continue to monitor their availability in the UK and reserve the right to reopen our investigations if we have reason to do so. We are pursuing further lines of inquiry against file-sharing services Nippybox and Yolobit, and these investigations remain ongoing."</p>
<p>A suicide forum is also now geo-blocking UK IPs after Ofcom began enforcement proceedings.</p>
<p>Satisfied for now, the regulator said it will keep tabs on the unnamed provider to see whether that block remains in place over the long term, and ensure it does not provide information on how to bypass it.</p>
<ul>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/10/09/discord_photo_ids_leaked/">Discord says 70,000 photo IDs compromised in customer service breach</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/10/08/germany_chat_control_opposition/">Germany slams brakes on EU's Chat Control device-scanning snoopfest</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/10/01/imgur_exits_uk/">Imgur yanks Brit access to memes as parent company faces fine</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/09/19/ofcom_osa_enforcement/">Charities warn Ofcom too soft on Online Safety Act violators</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Bypassing these measures has been a hot point of discussion since the Online Safety Act's most noticeable rules came into force in July, triggering a <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/07/28/uk_vpn_demand_soars/">surge in VPN subscriptions</a> within days of Brits having to submit their ID cards for age verification purposes.</p>
<p>While platforms are forbidden from guiding users toward these types of workarounds, this alone is unlikely to prevent VPNs being used to bypass geo-blocks and similar measures.</p>
<p>They do not appear to be going anywhere either. The UK government has previously stated that it <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/08/19/uk_commissioner_suggests_govt_stop/">does not wish to ban them</a>, since they have many legitimate purposes. But if platforms promote VPNs and other workarounds to children as a means to access their services, then Ofcom will pursue action against them.</p>
<h3>First look at beefed-up requirements</h3>
<p>Among Ofcom's <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/09/15/uk_lords_take_aim_at/">proposed amendments</a> to its obligations to platforms was the requirement for in-scope apps and websites to make use of hash-matching technology, which is seen as a more accurate, automated way of preventing the dissemination of illegal content such as CSAM.</p>
<p>Hash matching involves a system fingerprinting an image and comparing the hash it generates to a database of known harmful images, which are also hashed. If an image's hash matches or shows signs of similarity with one in the database, then it can be removed entirely autonomously and reported to local authorities for follow-up investigations.</p>
<p>Ofcom previously identified "serious compliance concerns" with its CSAM enforcement program at 1Fichier.com and Gofile.io, leading to investigations being opened into them both.</p>
<p>After constructive engagement with the regulator, both now deploy hash-matching tech and escaped further action.</p>
<p>Suzanne Cater, director of enforcement at Ofcom, said: "Today sends a clear message that any service which flagrantly fails to engage with Ofcom and their duties under the Online Safety Act can expect to face robust enforcement action.&nbsp;</p>
<p>"We're also seeing some services take steps to introduce improved safety measures as a direct result of our enforcement action. Services who choose to restrict access rather than protect UK users remain on our watchlist as we continue to monitor their availability to UK users." ®</p>                                
                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Software update bricks some Jeep 4xe hybrids over the weekend (244 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/cars/2025/10/software-update-bricks-some-jeep-4xe-hybrids-over-the-weekend/</link>
            <guid>45568700</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 14:28:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/cars/2025/10/software-update-bricks-some-jeep-4xe-hybrids-over-the-weekend/">https://arstechnica.com/cars/2025/10/software-update-bricks-some-jeep-4xe-hybrids-over-the-weekend/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45568700">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                      
                      
          <p>Owners of some Jeep Wrangler 4xe hybrids have been left stranded after installing an over-the-air software update this weekend. The automaker pushed out a telematics update for the <a href="https://arstechnica.com/cars/2021/02/hands-on-with-stellantis-new-android-based-uconnect-5-infotainment/">Uconnect</a> infotainment system that evidently wasn't ready, resulting in cars losing power while driving and then becoming stranded.</p>
<p>Stranded Jeep owners have been detailing their experiences in forum and Reddit posts, as well as on YouTube. The buggy update doesn't appear to brick the car immediately. Instead, the failure appears to occur while driving—a far more serious problem. For some, this happened close to home and at low speed, but <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Jeep/comments/1o47064/jeep_4xe_shut_off_mid_highway/">others claim</a> to have experienced a powertrain failure at highway speeds.</p>
<p>Jeep pulled the update after reports of problems, but the software had already downloaded to many owners' cars by then. A member of Stellantis' social engagement team told 4xe owners&nbsp;<a href="https://www.4xeforums.com/threads/wrangler-4xe-ota-update-10-10-2025.8078/?nested_view=1&amp;post_id=103140&amp;ref=thestack.technology#post-103140" target="_blank" rel="noopener">at a Jeep forum</a> to ignore the update pop-up if they haven't installed it yet.</p>
<p>Owners were also advised to avoid using either hybrid or electric modes if they had updated their 4xe and not already suffered a powertrain failure. Yesterday, <a href="https://www.4xeforums.com/posts/103207/">Jeep pushed out a fix</a>.</p>
<p>As Crowdstrike <a href="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2024/07/major-outages-at-crowdstrike-microsoft-leave-the-world-with-bsods-and-confusion/">showed last year</a>, Friday afternoons are a bad time to push out a software update. Now Stellantis has learned that lesson, too. Ars has reached out to Stellantis, and we'll update this post if we get a reply.</p>


          
                      
                  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Smartphones and being present (170 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://herman.bearblog.dev/being-present/</link>
            <guid>45568613</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 14:20:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://herman.bearblog.dev/being-present/">https://herman.bearblog.dev/being-present/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45568613">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    

    
        
    

    
        

        <p>
            <i>
                <time datetime="2025-10-13T13:04Z">
                    13 Oct, 2025
                </time>
            </i>
        </p>
    

    <p>I read an article yesterday, stating that on average, people spend 4 hours and 37 minutes on their phones per day<sup><a href="https://explodingtopics.com/blog/smartphone-usage-stats/#time-spent-using-smartphones-annually" target="_blank">1</a></sup>, with South Africans coming in fourth highest in the world at a whopping 5 hours and 11 minutes<sup><a href="https://explodingtopics.com/blog/smartphone-usage-stats/#time-spent-using-smartphones-by-region" target="_blank">2</a></sup>.</p>
<p>This figure seems really high to me. If we assume people sleep roughly 8 hours per day, that means that one third of their day is spent on their phones. If we also assume people work 8 hours per day (ignoring the fact that they may be using their phones during work hours), that suggests that people spend over half of their free time (and up to 65% of it) glued to their screens.</p>
<p>I never wanted to carry the internet around in my pocket. It's too distracting and pulls me out of the present moment, fracturing my attention. I've tried switching to old-school black and white phones before, but always begrudgingly returned to using a smartphone due to the utility of it. The problem, however, is that it comes with too many attention sinks tucked in alongside the useful tools.</p>
<p>I care about living an intentional and meaningful life, nurturing relationships, having nuanced conversations, and enjoying the world around me. I don't want to spend this limited time I have on earth watching short form video and getting into arguments on Twitter.</p>
<p><img src="https://bear-images.sfo2.cdn.digitaloceanspaces.com/herman/img_1438.webp" alt="Scarborough">
<small>This is what I enjoy. Picture taken yesterday in Scarborough, South Africa.</small></p>
<p>I've written at length about how I manage my digital consumption, from <a href="https://herman.bearblog.dev/notifications/">turning off notifications</a> to <a href="https://herman.bearblog.dev/slow-social-media/">forgoing social media entirely</a>. The underlying premise here is that if you're trying to lose weight, you shouldn't carry cookies around in your pockets. And my phone is the bag of cookies in this metaphor.</p>
<p>We're wired to seek out distraction, novel information, and entertainment, and avoid boredom at all costs. But boredom is where creativity and self-reflection do their best work. It's why "all the best ideas come when you're in the shower"—we don't usually take our phones with us into the shower (yet).</p>
<p>According to Screen Time on my iPhone, on average I spend 30 minutes per day on it, which I think is reasonable, especially considering the most-used apps are by-and-large utility apps like banking and messages. This isn't because I have more self-control than other people. I don't think I do. It's because I know myself, and have set up my digital life to be a positive force, and not an uninspired time-sink.</p>
<p>There are many apps and systems to incentivise better relationships with our phones, mostly based around time limits. But these are flawed in three ways:</p>
<ol>
<li>I'm an adult, I know how to circumvent these limits, and I will if motivation is low.</li>
<li>Time limits don't affect the underlying addiction. You don't quit smoking by only smoking certain hours of the day.</li>
<li>The companies that build these apps have tens of thousands of really smart people (and billions of dollars) trying to get me hooked and keep me engaged. The only way to win this game isn't by trying to beat them (I certainly can't), but by not playing.</li>
</ol>
<p>The only way I've found to have a good relationship with my phone is to make it as uninteresting as possible. The first way is to not have recommendation media (think Instagram, TikTok, and all the rest). I'm pro deleting these accounts completely, because it's really easy to re-download the apps on a whim, or visit them in-browser. However some people have found that having them on a dedicated device works by isolating those activities. Something like a tablet at home that is "the only place you're allowed to use Instagram". I can't comment too much on this route, but it seems reasonable.</p>
<p>My biggest time sink over the past few years has been YouTube. The algorithm knew me too well and would recommend video after engaging, but ultimately useless video. I could easily burn an entire evening watching absolute junk—leaving me feeling like I'd just wasted what could have otherwise been a beautiful sunset or a tasty home-cooked lasagne. However, at the beginning of this year I learnt that you can turn off your YouTube watch history entirely, which means no recommendations. Here's what my YouTube home screen now looks like:</p>
<p><img src="https://bear-images.sfo2.cdn.digitaloceanspaces.com/herman/45-1.webp" alt="Screenshot 2025-10-11 at 08"></p>
<p>Without the recommendations I very quickly run out of things to watch from the channels I'm subscribed to. It's completely changed my relationship with YouTube since I only watch the videos I actually want to watch, and none of the attention traps. You can turn off your YouTube watch history <a href="https://www.youtube.com/feed/history">here</a>, and auto delete your other Google history (like historic searches and navigation) <a href="https://myactivity.google.com/activitycontrols/">here</a>, which I think is just good practice.</p>
<p>I also used my adblocker, AdGuard on Safari which has a useful "block element" feature, to block the recommended videos on the right of YouTube videos. I use this feature to hide shorts as well, since I have no interest in watching them either, and YouTube intentionally makes them impossible to remove. If you're interested in a similar setup, here are the selectors I use to block those elements:</p>
<div><pre><span></span>youtube.com###items &gt; ytd-item-section-renderer.style-scope.ytd-watch-next-secondary-results-renderer:last-child
youtube.com###sections
youtube.com##[is-shorts]
youtube.com###secondary
</pre></div>
<p>The only media that I do sometimes consume on my phone are my RSS feeds, but it's something I'm completely comfortable with since it's explicitly opt-in by design and low volume.</p>
<p>While I still have the twitch to check my phone when I'm waiting for a coffee, or in-between activities—because my brain's reward system has been trained to do this—I'm now rewarded with nothing. Over time, I find myself checking my phone less and less. Sometimes I notice the urge, and just let it go, instead focusing on the here and now.</p>
<p>I think that while the attention-span-degrading effects of recommendation media are getting most of the headlines, what isn't spoken about as much is the sheer number of hours lost globally to our phones (3.8 million years per day, according to my back-of-the-napkin-math). And while people may argue that this could involve productive work or enjoyable leisure, I suspect that the vast (vast!) majority of that time is short-form entertainment.</p>
<p>My solution may sound overkill to many people, but I can say with absolute certainty that it has turned me into a more present, less distracted, and more optimistic person. I have much more time to spend in nature, with friends, or on my hobbies and projects. I can't imagine trading it in for a tiny screen, ever.</p>
<p>Give it a try.</p>
<p><img src="https://bear-images.sfo2.cdn.digitaloceanspaces.com/herman/img_1439.webp" alt="Scarborough">
<small>Happily on the beach for sunset.</small></p>


    

    
        

        
            


        
    


  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[No Science, No Startups: The Innovation Engine We're Switching Off (249 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://steveblank.com/2025/10/13/no-science-no-startups-the-unseen-engine-were-switching-off/</link>
            <guid>45567877</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 13:02:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://steveblank.com/2025/10/13/no-science-no-startups-the-unseen-engine-were-switching-off/">https://steveblank.com/2025/10/13/no-science-no-startups-the-unseen-engine-were-switching-off/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45567877">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

					<p>Tons of words have been written about the Trump Administrations <a href="https://thehill.com/opinion/white-house/5419855-trump-administration-cuts-science-funding/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">war on Science</a> in Universities. But few people have asked what, exactly, is science? How does it work? Who are the scientists? What do they do? And more importantly, why should anyone (outside of universities) care?</p>
<p>(Unfortunately, you won’t see answers to these questions in the general press – it’s not clickbait enough. Nor will you read about it in the science journals– it’s not technical enough. You won’t hear a succinct description from any of the universities under fire, either – they’ve long lost the ability to connect the value of their work to the day-to-day life of the general public.)</p>
<p>In this post I’m going to describe how science works, how science and engineering have worked together to build innovative startups and companies in the U.S.—and why <u>you</u> should care.</p>
<p>(In <a href="https://steveblank.com/2025/04/15/how-the-u-s-became-a-science-superpower/">a previous post I described how the U.S. built a science and technology ecosystem</a> and why investment in science is directly correlated with a country’s national power. I suggest you read it first.)</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>How Science Works<br>
</strong>I was older than I care to admit when I finally understood the difference between a <em>scientist</em>, an <em>engineer</em>, an <em>entrepreneur</em> and a <em>venture capitalist</em>; and the role that each played in the creation of advancements that made our economy thrive, our defense strong and America great.</p>
<p><strong>Scientists<br>
</strong><em>Scientists </em>(sometimes called researchers) are the people who ask lots of questions about <em>why</em> and <em>how</em> things work. They don’t know the answers. <em>Scientists</em> <em>are driven by curiosity</em>, willing to make educated guesses (the fancy word is hypotheses) and run experiments to test their guesses. Most of the time their hypotheses are wrong. But every time they’re right they move the human race forward. We get new medicines, cures for diseases, new consumer goods, better and cheaper foods, etc.</p>
<p>Scientists tend to specialize in one area – biology, medical research, physics, agriculture, computer science, materials, math, etc. — although a few move between areas. The U.S. government has supported scientific research at scale (read billions of $s) since 1940.</p>
<p>Scientists tend to fall into two categories: <em>Theorists</em> and <em>Experimentalists</em>.</p>
<p><strong><img data-recalc-dims="1" decoding="async" data-attachment-id="33114" data-permalink="https://steveblank.com/2025/10/13/no-science-no-startups-the-unseen-engine-were-switching-off/types-of-scientists-2/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Types-of-Scientists.jpg?fit=1467%2C612&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="1467,612" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="Types of Scientists" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Types-of-Scientists.jpg?fit=300%2C125&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Types-of-Scientists.jpg?fit=468%2C195&amp;ssl=1" src="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Types-of-Scientists.jpg?resize=293%2C122&amp;ssl=1" alt="" width="293" height="122" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Types-of-Scientists.jpg?resize=1024%2C427&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Types-of-Scientists.jpg?resize=300%2C125&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Types-of-Scientists.jpg?resize=150%2C63&amp;ssl=1 150w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Types-of-Scientists.jpg?resize=768%2C320&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Types-of-Scientists.jpg?w=1467&amp;ssl=1 1467w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Types-of-Scientists.jpg?w=936&amp;ssl=1 936w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Types-of-Scientists.jpg?w=1404&amp;ssl=1 1404w" sizes="(max-width: 293px) 100vw, 293px">Theorists<br>
</strong><em>Theorists</em> develop mathematical models, abstract frameworks, and hypotheses for how the universe works. They don’t run experiments themselves—instead, they propose new ideas or principles, explain existing experimental results, predict phenomena that haven’t been observed yet. Theorists help define what reality might be.</p>
<p>Theorists can be found in different fields of science. For example:</p>
<p><em>Physics</em><em>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; </em>Quantum field theory, string theory, quantum mechanics<br>
<em>Biology</em><em>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;</em>Neuroscience and cognition, Systems Biology, gene regulation<br>
<em>Chemistry</em><em>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </em>Molecular dynamics, Quantum chemistry<br>
<em>Computer Science</em>&nbsp; &nbsp;Design algorithms, prove limits of computation<br>
<em>Economics</em><em>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </em>Build models of markets or decision-making<br>
<em>Mathematics</em><em>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; </em>Causal inference, Bayesian networks, Deep Learning</p>
<p>The best-known 20th-century theorist was Albert Einstein. His tools were a chalkboard and his brain. in 1905 he wrote an equation E=MC<sup>2 </sup>which told the world that a small amount of mass can be converted into a tremendous amount of energy. <img data-recalc-dims="1" decoding="async" data-attachment-id="33115" data-permalink="https://steveblank.com/2025/10/13/no-science-no-startups-the-unseen-engine-were-switching-off/einstein-at-the-blackboard/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Einstein-at-the-blackboard.jpeg?fit=2294%2C1782&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="2294,1782" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="Einstein at the blackboard" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Einstein-at-the-blackboard.jpeg?fit=300%2C233&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Einstein-at-the-blackboard.jpeg?fit=468%2C363&amp;ssl=1" src="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Einstein-at-the-blackboard.jpeg?resize=162%2C126&amp;ssl=1" alt="" width="162" height="126" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Einstein-at-the-blackboard.jpeg?resize=300%2C233&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Einstein-at-the-blackboard.jpeg?resize=1024%2C795&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Einstein-at-the-blackboard.jpeg?resize=150%2C117&amp;ssl=1 150w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Einstein-at-the-blackboard.jpeg?resize=768%2C597&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Einstein-at-the-blackboard.jpeg?resize=1536%2C1193&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Einstein-at-the-blackboard.jpeg?resize=2048%2C1591&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Einstein-at-the-blackboard.jpeg?w=936&amp;ssl=1 936w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Einstein-at-the-blackboard.jpeg?w=1404&amp;ssl=1 1404w" sizes="(max-width: 162px) 100vw, 162px">When he wrote it down, it was just theory. Other theorists in the 1930s and ’40s took Einstein’s theory and provided the impetus for building the atomic bomb. (Leo Szilard conceived neutron chain reaction idea, Hans Bethe led the Theoretical Division at Los Alamos, Edward Teller developed hydrogen bomb theory.) Einstein’s theory was demonstrably proved correct over Hiroshima and Nagasaki.</p>
<p><strong>Experimentalists<br>
</strong>In addition to theorists, other scientists – called <em>experimentalists</em> – design and run experiments in a lab. The pictures you see of scientists in lab coats in front of microscopes, test tubes, particle accelerators or NASA spacecraft are likely experimentalists. They test hypotheses by developing and performing experiments. An example of this would be <a href="https://science.nasa.gov/mission/webb/">NASA’s James Webb telescope</a> or the LIGO <a href="https://www.ligo.caltech.edu/">Gravitational-Wave Observatory</a> experiment. (As we’ll see later, often it’s engineers who build the devices the experimentalists use.)<img data-recalc-dims="1" decoding="async" data-attachment-id="33116" data-permalink="https://steveblank.com/2025/10/13/no-science-no-startups-the-unseen-engine-were-switching-off/experimentalist/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Experimentalist.jpg?fit=375%2C314&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="375,314" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Experimentalist" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Experimentalist.jpg?fit=300%2C251&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Experimentalist.jpg?fit=375%2C314&amp;ssl=1" src="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Experimentalist.jpg?resize=184%2C154&amp;ssl=1" alt="" width="184" height="154" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Experimentalist.jpg?resize=300%2C251&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Experimentalist.jpg?resize=150%2C126&amp;ssl=1 150w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Experimentalist.jpg?w=375&amp;ssl=1 375w" sizes="(max-width: 184px) 100vw, 184px"></p>
<p>Some of these experimentalists focus on <em>Basic Science,</em> working to get knowledge for its own sake and understand fundamental principles of nature <em>with n</em><em>o immediate practical use</em> in mind.</p>
<p>Other experimentalists work in <em>Applied Science, </em>which uses the findings and theories derived from Basic Science to design, innovate, and improve products and processes.</p>
<p>Applied scientists<em> s</em>olve practical problems oriented toward real-world applications. (Scientists at <a href="https://www.nps.gov/articles/000/manhattan-project-science-at-los-alamos.htm">Los Alamos</a> weretrying to understand the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Critical_mass">critical mass of U-235</a> (the minimum amount that would explode.) Basic science lays the groundwork for breakthroughs in <em>applied</em> science. For instance: Quantum mechanics (basic science) led to semiconductors which led to computers (applied science). Germ theory (basic science) led to antibiotics and vaccines (applied science). In the 20th century Applied scientists <u>did not</u> start the companies that make end products. Engineers and entrepreneurs did this. (In the 21st century more Applied Scientists, particularly in life sciences, have also spun out companies from their labs.)</p>
<h3><strong>Scientists</strong></h3>
<p><strong><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-attachment-id="33123" data-permalink="https://steveblank.com/2025/10/13/no-science-no-startups-the-unseen-engine-were-switching-off/science2-2/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/science2-1.jpg?fit=977%2C441&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="977,441" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="science2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/science2-1.jpg?fit=300%2C135&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/science2-1.jpg?fit=468%2C211&amp;ssl=1" src="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/science2-1.jpg?resize=468%2C211&amp;ssl=1" alt="" width="468" height="211" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/science2-1.jpg?w=977&amp;ssl=1 977w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/science2-1.jpg?resize=300%2C135&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/science2-1.jpg?resize=150%2C68&amp;ssl=1 150w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/science2-1.jpg?resize=768%2C347&amp;ssl=1 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 468px) 100vw, 468px"><br>
Where is Science in the U.S. Done?<br>
</strong>America’s unique insight that has allowed it to dominate Science and invention, is that after WWII we gave Research and Development money to universities, rather than only funding government laboratories. <em><u>No other country did this at scale</u></em>.</p>
<p><em>Corporate Research Centers</em><br>
In the 20th century, U.S. companies put their excess profits into corporate research labs. <em>Basic</em> research in the U.S. was done in at Dupont, Bell Labs, IBM, AT&amp;T, Xerox, Kodak, GE, et al.</p>
<p>This changed in 1982, when the Securities and Exchange Commission ruled that it was legal for companies to buy their own stock (reducing the number of shares available to the public and inflating their stock price.) Very quickly <em>Basic</em> Science in corporate research all but disappeared. Companies focused on <em>Applied</em> Research to maximize shareholder value. In its place, Theory and Basic research is now done in <em>research </em>universities.</p>
<p><em>Research Universities<br>
</em>From the outside (or if you’re an undergraduate) universities look like a place where students take classes and get a degree. However, in a <em>research</em> university there is something equally important going on. <em>Science</em> faculty in these schools not only teach, but they are <em>expected to</em> <em>produce</em> new knowledge—through experiments, publications, patents, or creative work. Professors get grants and contracts from federal agencies (e.g., NSF, NIH, DoD), foundations, and industry. And the university builds Labs, centers, libraries, and advanced computing facilities that support these activities.</p>
<p>In the U.S. there are <strong>542</strong> research universities, ranked by the <a href="https://carnegieclassifications.acenet.edu/carnegie-classification/classification-methodology/2025-research-activity-designations/">Carnegie Classification</a> into three categories.</p>
<p><strong>R1: </strong><a href="https://carnegieclassifications.acenet.edu/institutions/?inst=&amp;research2025%5B%5D=1"><strong>187 Universities – Very High Research Activity</strong></a><br>
Conduct extensive research and award many doctoral degrees.<br>
Examples: Stanford, UC Berkeley, Harvard, MIT, Michigan, Texas A&amp;M …</p>
<p><strong>R2: </strong><strong><a href="https://carnegieclassifications.acenet.edu/institutions/?inst=&amp;research2025%5B%5D=2">139 Universities – High Research Activity</a><br>
</strong>Substantial but smaller research scale.<br>
Examples: Baylor, Wake Forest, UC Santa Cruz, …</p>
<p><strong>R3: </strong><a href="https://carnegieclassifications.acenet.edu/institutions/?inst=&amp;research2025%5B%5D=3"><strong>216 Research Colleges/Universities</strong></a><br>
Limited research focus; more teaching-oriented doctoral programs.<br>
Smaller state universities</p>
<p><strong>Why Universities Matter to Science</strong><br>
U.S. <a href="https://ncses.nsf.gov/pubs/nsb20243">universities perform about 50% of all basic science research</a> (physics, chemistry, biology, social sciences, etc.) because they are training grounds for graduate students and postdocs. Universities spend ~$109 billion a year on research. ~$60 billion of that $109 billion comes from the National Institutes for Health (NIH) for biomedical research, National Science Foundation (NSF) for basic science, Department of War (DoW), Department of Energy (DOE), for energy/physics/nuclear, DARPA, NASA. (Companies tend to invest in <em>applied</em> research and development, that leads directly to saleable products.)</p>
<p><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-attachment-id="32149" data-permalink="https://steveblank.com/2025/10/13/no-science-no-startups-the-unseen-engine-were-switching-off/govt-university-research-ecosystem/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Govt-University-Research-Ecosystem.jpg?fit=1543%2C1143&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="1543,1143" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Govt University Research Ecosystem" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Govt-University-Research-Ecosystem.jpg?fit=300%2C222&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Govt-University-Research-Ecosystem.jpg?fit=468%2C347&amp;ssl=1" src="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Govt-University-Research-Ecosystem.jpg?resize=468%2C347&amp;ssl=1" alt="" width="468" height="347" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Govt-University-Research-Ecosystem.jpg?w=1543&amp;ssl=1 1543w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Govt-University-Research-Ecosystem.jpg?resize=300%2C222&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Govt-University-Research-Ecosystem.jpg?resize=1024%2C759&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Govt-University-Research-Ecosystem.jpg?resize=150%2C111&amp;ssl=1 150w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Govt-University-Research-Ecosystem.jpg?resize=768%2C569&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Govt-University-Research-Ecosystem.jpg?resize=1536%2C1138&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Govt-University-Research-Ecosystem.jpg?w=936&amp;ssl=1 936w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Govt-University-Research-Ecosystem.jpg?w=1404&amp;ssl=1 1404w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 468px) 100vw, 468px">Professors (especially in Science, Technology, Engineering and Math) run labs that function like mini startups. They ask research questions, then hire grad students, postdocs, and staff and write grant proposals to fund their work, often spending 30–50% of their time writing and managing grants. When they get a grant the lead researcher (typically a faculty member/head of the lab) is called the Principal Investigator (PI).</p>
<p>The Labs are both workplaces and classrooms. Graduate students and Postdocs do the day-to-day science work as part of their training (often for a Ph.D.). Postdocs are full-time researchers gaining further specialization. Undergraduates may also assist in research, especially at top-tier schools.</p>
<p>(Up until 2025, U.S. science was deeply international with ~40–50% of U.S. basic research done by foreign-born researchers (graduate students, postdocs, and faculty). Immigration and student visas were a critical part of American research capacity.)</p>
<p>The results of this research are shared with the agencies that funded it, published in journals, presented at conferences and often patented or spun off into startups via technology transfer offices. A lot of commercial tech—from Google search to CRISPR—started in university labs.</p>
<p>Universities support their science researchers with basic administrative staff (for compliance, purchasing, and safety) but uniquely in the U.S., by providing the best research facilities (labs, cleanrooms, telescopes), and core scientific services: DNA sequencing centers, electron microscopes, access to cloud, data analysis hubs, etc. These were the best in the world – until the sweeping cuts in 2025.</p>
<p><strong>Engineers Build on the Work of Scientists<br>
</strong>Engineers design and build things <em>on top of the discoveries of scientists</em>. For example, seven years after scientists split the atom, it took 10s of thousands of <em>engineers</em> to build an atomic bomb. From the outset, the engineers knew what they wanted to build because of the basic and applied scientific research that came before them.</p>
<p><strong>Scientists Versus Engineers</strong><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-attachment-id="33138" data-permalink="https://steveblank.com/2025/10/13/no-science-no-startups-the-unseen-engine-were-switching-off/scientists-vs-engineer/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/scientists-vs-engineer.jpg?fit=771%2C416&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="771,416" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="scientists vs engineer" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/scientists-vs-engineer.jpg?fit=300%2C162&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/scientists-vs-engineer.jpg?fit=468%2C253&amp;ssl=1" src="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/scientists-vs-engineer.jpg?resize=468%2C253&amp;ssl=1" alt="" width="468" height="253" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/scientists-vs-engineer.jpg?w=771&amp;ssl=1 771w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/scientists-vs-engineer.jpg?resize=300%2C162&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/scientists-vs-engineer.jpg?resize=150%2C81&amp;ssl=1 150w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/scientists-vs-engineer.jpg?resize=768%2C414&amp;ssl=1 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 468px) 100vw, 468px"></p>
<p>Engineers create plans, use software to test their designs, then… cut sheet metal, build rocket engines, construct buildings and bridges, design chips, build equipment for experimentalists, design cars, etc.</p>
<p>As an example, at <a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/">Nvidia</a> their GPU chips are built in a chip factory (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TSMC" target="_blank" rel="noopener">TSMC</a>) using the <em>Applied</em> science done by companies like <a href="https://www.appliedmaterials.com/us/en" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Applied Materials</a> which in turn is based on <em>Basic</em> science of <a href="https://nano.stanford.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">semiconductor researchers</a>. And the massive data centers OpenAI, Microsoft, Google, et al that use Nvidia chips are being built by mechanical and other types of engineers. <img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-attachment-id="33128" data-permalink="https://steveblank.com/2025/10/13/no-science-no-startups-the-unseen-engine-were-switching-off/types-of-scientists-3/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Types-of-Scientists-1-e1760138797607.jpg?fit=581%2C288&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="581,288" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="Types of Scientists" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Types-of-Scientists-1-e1760138797607.jpg?fit=300%2C149&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Types-of-Scientists-1-e1760138797607.jpg?fit=468%2C232&amp;ssl=1" src="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Types-of-Scientists-1-e1760138797607.jpg?resize=307%2C152&amp;ssl=1" alt="" width="307" height="152" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Types-of-Scientists-1-e1760138797607.jpg?w=581&amp;ssl=1 581w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Types-of-Scientists-1-e1760138797607.jpg?resize=300%2C149&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Types-of-Scientists-1-e1760138797607.jpg?resize=150%2C74&amp;ssl=1 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 307px) 100vw, 307px"></p>
<p>My favorite example is that the reusable <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DOzVgPdBqM4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">SpaceX rocket landings</a> are made possible by the <em>Applied</em> Science research on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convex_optimization">Convex Optimization</a> frameworks and algorithms by Steven Boyd of Stanford. And Boyd’s work was based on the <em>Basic</em> science mathematical field of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convex_analysis" target="_blank" rel="noopener">convex analysis</a> (SpaceX, NASA, JPL, Blue Origin, Rocket Lab all use variations of Convex Optimization for guidance, control, and landing.)</p>
<p><strong>Startup Entrepreneurs Build Iteratively and Incrementally<br>
</strong>Entrepreneurs build companies to bring new products to market. <em>They hire engineers</em> to build, test and refine products.</p>
<p>Engineers and entrepreneurs operate with very different mindsets, goals, and tolerances for risk and failure. (Many great entrepreneurs start as engineers e.g., Musk, Gates, Page/Brin). An engineer’s goal is to design and deliver a solution to a <em>known</em> problem with a given set of specifications.</p>
<p>In contrast, entrepreneurs start with a series of <em>unknowns</em> about who are the customers, what are the wanted product features, pricing, etc. They retire each of these risks by building an iterative series of minimum viable products to find product/market fit and customer adoption. They pivot their solution as needed when they discover their initial assumptions are incorrect. (Treating each business unknown as a hypothesis is the entrepreneurs’ version of the Scientific Method.)</p>
<p><strong>Venture Capitalists Fund Entrepreneurs<br>
</strong>Venture capitalists (VCs) are the people who <em>fund entrepreneurs</em> who work with engineers who build things that applied scientists have proven from basic researchers.</p>
<p>Unlike banks which will give out loans for projects that have known specifications and outcomes, VCs invest <em>in a portfolio</em> of much riskier investments. While banks make money on the interest they charge on each loan, VCs take part ownership (equity) in the companies they invest in. While most VC investments fail, the ones that succeed make up for that.</p>
<p>Most VCs are not scientists. Few are engineers, some have been entrepreneurs. The best VCs understand technical trends and their investments help shape the future. <em>VCs do not invest in science/researchers</em>. VCs want to minimize the risk of their investment, so they mostly want to take engineering and manufacturing risk, but less so on applied science risk and rarely on basic research risk.&nbsp;Hence the role of government and Universities.</p>
<p>VCs invest in projects that can take advantage of science and deliver products within the time horizon of their funds (3–7 years). Science often needs decades before a killer app is visible.</p>
<p>As the flow of science-based technologies dries up, the opportunities for U.S. venture capital based on deep tech will decline, with its future in countries that are investing in science – China or Europe.</p>
<p><strong>Why Have Scientists? Why Not Just a Country of Engineers, Entrepreneurs and VCs (or AI)?<br>
</strong>If you’ve read so far, you might be scratching your head and asking, “Why do we have scientists at all? Why pay for people to sit around and think? Why spend money on people who run experiments when most of those experiments fail? Can’t we replace them with AI?”</p>
<p>The output of this university-industry-government science partnership became the foundation of Silicon Valley, the aerospace sector, the biotechnology industry, Quantum and AI. These investments gave us rockets, cures for cancer, medical devices, the Internet, Chat GPT, AI and more.</p>
<p>Investment in science is directly correlated with national power. Weaken science, you weaken the long-term growth of the economy, and national defense.</p>
<p>Tech firms’&nbsp;investments of $100s of billions in AI data centers is greater than the federal government’s R&amp;D expenditures. <em>But these investments are in <u>engineering</u> not in science</em>. The goal of making scientists redundant using artificial general intelligence misses the point that AI will (and is) making scientists more <em>productive – not replacing them.</em></p>
<p>Countries that neglect science become dependent on those that don’t. U.S. post-WWII dominance came from <em>basic science investments</em> (OSRD, NSF, NIH, DOE labs). After WWII ended, the UK slashed science investment which allowed the U.S. to commercialize the British inventions made during the war.</p>
<p>The Soviet Union’s collapse partly reflected failure to convert science into sustained innovation, during the same time that U.S. universities, startups and venture capital created Silicon Valley. Long-term military and economic advantage (nuclear weapons, GPS, AI) trace back to scientific research ecosystems.</p>
<p><strong>Lessons Learned</strong></p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li><em>Scientists</em> come in two categories
<ul>
<li>Theorists and experimentalists</li>
<li>Two types of experimentalists; Basic science (learn new things) or applied science (practical applications of the science)</li>
<li>Scientists train talent, create patentable inventions and solutions for national defense</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Engineers</em> design and <em>build things on top of the discoveries of scientists</em></li>
<li><em>Entrepreneurs</em> test and push the boundaries of what products could be built</li>
<li><em>Venture Capital</em> provides the money to startups</li>
<li>Scientists, engineers, entrepreneurs – these roles are complementary
<ul>
<li>Remove one and the system degrades</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Science won’t stop
<ul>
<li>Cut U.S. funding, then science will happen in other countries that understand its relationship to making a nation great – like China.</li>
<li>National power is derived from investments in Science</li>
<li>Reducing investment in basic and applied science makes America weak</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Appendix – How Does Science Work? – The Scientific Method</strong><br>
Whether you were a theorist or experimentalist, for the last 500 years the way to test science was by using <a href="https://www.khanacademy.org/science/biology/intro-to-biology/science-of-biology/a/the-science-of-biology">the scientific method.</a> This method starts by a scientist wondering and asking, “Here’s how I think this should work, let’s test the idea.”</p>
<p>The goal of the scientific method is to turn a guess (in science called a hypothesis) into actual evidence. Scientists do this by first designing an experiment to test their guess/hypothesis. They then run the experiment and collect and analyze the result and ask, “Did the result validate, invalidate the hypothesis? Or did it give us completely new ideas?” Scientists build instruments and run experiments not because of what they know, but because of what they don’t know.</p>
<p><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-attachment-id="33134" data-permalink="https://steveblank.com/2025/10/13/no-science-no-startups-the-unseen-engine-were-switching-off/scientific-method/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Scientific-Method.jpg?fit=1133%2C808&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="1133,808" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Scientific Method" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Scientific-Method.jpg?fit=300%2C214&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Scientific-Method.jpg?fit=468%2C334&amp;ssl=1" src="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Scientific-Method.jpg?resize=300%2C214&amp;ssl=1" alt="" width="300" height="214" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Scientific-Method.jpg?resize=300%2C214&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Scientific-Method.jpg?resize=1024%2C730&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Scientific-Method.jpg?resize=150%2C107&amp;ssl=1 150w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Scientific-Method.jpg?resize=768%2C548&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Scientific-Method.jpg?w=1133&amp;ssl=1 1133w, https://i0.wp.com/steveblank.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Scientific-Method.jpg?w=936&amp;ssl=1 936w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"></p>
<p>These experiments can be simple ones costing thousands of dollars that can be run in a university biology lab while others may require billions of dollars to build a satellite, particle accelerator or telescope. (The U.S. took the lead in Science after WWII when the government realized that funding scientists was good for the American economy and defense.)</p>
<p>Good science is reproducible. Scientists just don’t publish their results, but they also publish the details of how they ran their experiment. That allows other scientists to run the same experiment and see if they get the same result for themselves. That makes the scientific method self-correcting (you or others can see mistakes).</p>
<p>One other benefit of the scientific method is that scientists (and the people who fund them) expect most of the experiments to fail, but the failures are part of learning and discovery. They teach us what works and what doesn’t. Failure in science testing unknowns means learning and discovery.</p>
					
					<p>
						Filed under: <a href="https://steveblank.com/category/national-security/" rel="category tag">National Security</a>, <a href="https://steveblank.com/category/nih-national-institutes-of-health/" rel="category tag">NIH (National Institutes of Health)</a>, <a href="https://steveblank.com/category/nsf-national-science-foundation/" rel="category tag">NSF (National Science Foundation)</a> |					</p>

				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: SQLite Online – 11 years of solo development, 11K daily users (282 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://sqliteonline.com/</link>
            <guid>45567770</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 12:46:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://sqliteonline.com/">https://sqliteonline.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45567770">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main-row-bottom">
                <h4>Chart for Data Science</h4>
                <div>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>-- Change first word "SELECT" to "QLINE-SELECT"</span></pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>SELECT</span> <span></span> <span>QLINE-SELECT</span></pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span role="presentation"><span cm-text="">​</span></span></pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>-- Axis X:</span></pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>-- X - column name, axis: x1, x2, ..xn Value: Number</span></pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>-- L - column name, axis: l Value: Text</span></pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>-- T - column name, axis: t Value: UnixTime Number</span></pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>-- Axis Y:</span></pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>-- Y - column name, axis: y1, y2, ..yn Value: Number</span></pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>-- Y - color line: y_cFF00FF (HEX6)</span></pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>-- Option:</span></pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>-- C - color point: c  Value: FF00FF (HEX6)</span></pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>-- V - radius point: v  Value: Number</span></pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>-- Example : </span></pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>QLINE-SELECT</span> <a href="#sqltext=%23url-sqlite%3Ddb-sqlite%0D%0A%23tab-run%3DQLine%0D%0ACREATE%20VIRTUAL%20TABLE%20if%20NOT%20EXISTS%20happiness_csv%20USING%20ext_api(%0A%20%20%20%20'csv%3Bhttps%3A%2F%2Fraw.githubusercontent.com%2Fzirill%2Fdemo.sqliteonline.com%2Frefs%2Fheads%2Fmain%2Fhappiness_data.csv%3B1'%2C%0A%20%20%20%20'country%20text%2C%20region%20text%2C%20happiness_score%20real%2C%20gdp_per_capita%20int%2C%20population_millions%20real'%0A)%3B%0A%0AQLINE-SELECT%0A%20%20%20%20gdp_per_capita%20as%20x%2C%0A%20%20%20%20happiness_score%20as%20y%2C%0A%20%20%20%20population_millions%20as%20v%2C%0A%20%20%20%20CASE%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20WHEN%20region%20%3D%20'Asia'%20THEN%20'%23FF6B6B'%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20WHEN%20region%20%3D%20'Europe'%20THEN%20'%234ECDC4'%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20WHEN%20region%20%3D%20'Africa'%20THEN%20'%2345B7D1'%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20WHEN%20region%20%3D%20'Americas'%20THEN%20'%2396CEB4'%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20ELSE%20'%23FFEAA7'%0A%20%20%20%20END%20as%20c%2C%0A%20%20%20%20country%0AFROM%20happiness_csv%20%0AWHERE%20gdp_per_capita%20%3E%2012000%20AND%20happiness_score%20%3E%200%20AND%20population_millions%20%3E%200%20order%20by%20x%20asc%3B">example</a> </pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>-- Example : </span></pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>QAREA-SELECT</span> <a href="#sqltext=%23url-sqlite%3Ddb-sqlite%0D%0A%23tab-run%3DQArea%0D%0ACREATE%20VIRTUAL%20TABLE%20if%20NOT%20EXISTS%20happiness_csv%20USING%20ext_api(%0A%20%20%20%20'csv%3Bhttps%3A%2F%2Fraw.githubusercontent.com%2Fzirill%2Fdemo.sqliteonline.com%2Frefs%2Fheads%2Fmain%2Fhappiness_data.csv%3B1'%2C%0A%20%20%20%20'country%20text%2C%20region%20text%2C%20happiness_score%20real%2C%20gdp_per_capita%20int%2C%20population_millions%20real'%0A)%3B%0A%0AQAREA-SELECT%0A%20%20%20%20gdp_per_capita%20as%20x%2C%0A%20%20%20%20happiness_score%20as%20y%2C%0A%20%20%20%20population_millions%20as%20v%2C%0A%20%20%20%20CASE%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20WHEN%20region%20%3D%20'Asia'%20THEN%20'%23FF6B6B'%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20WHEN%20region%20%3D%20'Europe'%20THEN%20'%234ECDC4'%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20WHEN%20region%20%3D%20'Africa'%20THEN%20'%2345B7D1'%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20WHEN%20region%20%3D%20'Americas'%20THEN%20'%2396CEB4'%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20ELSE%20'%23FFEAA7'%0A%20%20%20%20END%20as%20c%2C%0A%20%20%20%20country%0AFROM%20happiness_csv%20%0AWHERE%20gdp_per_capita%20%3E%2012000%20AND%20happiness_score%20%3E%200%20AND%20population_millions%20%3E%200%20order%20by%20x%20asc%3B">example</a></pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>-- Example : </span></pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>QBAR-SELECT</span> <a href="#sqltext=%23url-sqlite%3Ddb-sqlite%0D%0A%23tab-run%3DQBar%0D%0ACREATE%20VIRTUAL%20TABLE%20if%20NOT%20EXISTS%20happiness_csv%20USING%20ext_api(%0A%20%20%20%20'csv%3Bhttps%3A%2F%2Fraw.githubusercontent.com%2Fzirill%2Fdemo.sqliteonline.com%2Frefs%2Fheads%2Fmain%2Fhappiness_data.csv%3B1'%2C%0A%20%20%20%20'country%20text%2C%20region%20text%2C%20happiness_score%20real%2C%20gdp_per_capita%20int%2C%20population_millions%20real'%0A)%3B%0A%0AQBAR-SELECT%0A%20%20%20%20country%20as%20l%2C%0A%20%20%20%20happiness_score%20as%20y%2C%20%20%20%20%0A%20%20%20%20CASE%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20WHEN%20region%20%3D%20'Asia'%20THEN%20'%23FF6B6B'%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20WHEN%20region%20%3D%20'Europe'%20THEN%20'%234ECDC4'%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20WHEN%20region%20%3D%20'Africa'%20THEN%20'%2345B7D1'%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20WHEN%20region%20%3D%20'Americas'%20THEN%20'%2396CEB4'%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20ELSE%20'%23FFEAA7'%0A%20%20%20%20END%20as%20c%20%20%20%20%0AFROM%20happiness_csv%20%0AWHERE%20gdp_per_capita%20%3E%2012000%20AND%20happiness_score%20%3E%200%20AND%20population_millions%20%3E%200%3B">example</a></pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>-- Example : </span></pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>QPIE-SELECT</span> <a href="#sqltext=%23url-sqlite%3Ddb-sqlite%0D%0A%23tab-run%3DQPie%0D%0ACREATE%20VIRTUAL%20TABLE%20if%20NOT%20EXISTS%20happiness_csv%20USING%20ext_api(%0A%20%20%20%20'csv%3Bhttps%3A%2F%2Fraw.githubusercontent.com%2Fzirill%2Fdemo.sqliteonline.com%2Frefs%2Fheads%2Fmain%2Fhappiness_data.csv%3B1'%2C%0A%20%20%20%20'country%20text%2C%20region%20text%2C%20happiness_score%20real%2C%20gdp_per_capita%20int%2C%20population_millions%20real'%0A)%3B%0A%0AQPIE-SELECT%0A%20%20%20%20population_millions%20as%20y%2C%0A%20%20%20%20country%20as%20l%2C%0A%20%20%20%20CASE%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20WHEN%20region%20%3D%20'Asia'%20THEN%20'%23FF6B6B'%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20WHEN%20region%20%3D%20'Europe'%20THEN%20'%234ECDC4'%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20WHEN%20region%20%3D%20'Africa'%20THEN%20'%2345B7D1'%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20WHEN%20region%20%3D%20'Americas'%20THEN%20'%2396CEB4'%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20ELSE%20'%23FFEAA7'%0A%20%20%20%20END%20as%20c%20%20%20%20%0AFROM%20happiness_csv%20%0AWHERE%20gdp_per_capita%20%3E%200%20AND%20happiness_score%20%3E%200%20AND%20population_millions%20%3E%200%3B">example</a></pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>-- Example : </span></pre>
                    <pre role="presentation"><span>QBUBBLE-SELECT</span> <a href="#sqltext=%23url-sqlite%3Ddb-sqlite%0D%0A%23tab-run%3DQBubble%0D%0ACREATE%20VIRTUAL%20TABLE%20if%20NOT%20EXISTS%20happiness_csv%20USING%20ext_api(%0A%20%20%20%20'csv%3Bhttps%3A%2F%2Fraw.githubusercontent.com%2Fzirill%2Fdemo.sqliteonline.com%2Frefs%2Fheads%2Fmain%2Fhappiness_data.csv%3B1'%2C%0A%20%20%20%20'country%20text%2C%20region%20text%2C%20happiness_score%20real%2C%20gdp_per_capita%20int%2C%20population_millions%20real'%0A)%3B%0A%0AQBUBBLE-SELECT%0A%20%20%20%20gdp_per_capita%20as%20x%2C%0A%20%20%20%20happiness_score%20as%20y%2C%0A%20%20%20%20population_millions%20as%20v%2C%0A%20%20%20%20CASE%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20WHEN%20region%20%3D%20'Asia'%20THEN%20'%23FF6B6B'%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20WHEN%20region%20%3D%20'Europe'%20THEN%20'%234ECDC4'%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20WHEN%20region%20%3D%20'Africa'%20THEN%20'%2345B7D1'%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20WHEN%20region%20%3D%20'Americas'%20THEN%20'%2396CEB4'%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20ELSE%20'%23FFEAA7'%0A%20%20%20%20END%20as%20c%2C%0A%20%20%20%20country%0AFROM%20happiness_csv%20%0AWHERE%20gdp_per_capita%20%3E%200%20AND%20happiness_score%20%3E%200%20AND%20population_millions%20%3E%200%3B">example</a></pre>
                </div>
            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[California Will Stop Using Coal as a Power Source Next Month (187 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://hardware.slashdot.org/story/25/10/13/032224/california-will-stop-using-coal-as-a-power-source-next-month</link>
            <guid>45567645</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 12:33:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://hardware.slashdot.org/story/25/10/13/032224/california-will-stop-using-coal-as-a-power-source-next-month">https://hardware.slashdot.org/story/25/10/13/032224/california-will-stop-using-coal-as-a-power-source-next-month</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45567645">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="fhbody-179766822">
	
		
	

	
		
		<p>
			
		 	
				An anonymous reader shared this excerpt from <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/newsletter/2025-10-08/essential-california-california-dumps-coal-power">a Los Angeles Times newsletter</a>:

<i>
One of the most consequential moments in California's drive to beat back climate change will take place next month. The state will stop receiving electricity from the Intermountain Power Plant in Central Utah, meaning our reliance on coal as a source of power will essentially be over...<p> 

[T]he U.S. got nearly half its electricity from coal-fired plants <a href="https://www.latimes.com/environment/newsletter/2025-10-02/boiling-point-california-quitting-coal">as recently as 2007</a>. By 2023, that figure had dropped to just 16.2%. California drove an even more dramatic shift, getting just 2.2% of its electricity from coal in 2024 — nearly all of it from the Intermountain plant.  Operators plan to cut off that final burst of ions next month. </p></i> <br>
"And with improved technology to store power, the change has been made without the power shortages that dogged the state up until 2020..."5<br>
		 	
		</p>

		

		

		
			
		
	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Sveriges Riksbank Prize in Economic Sciences in Memory of Alfred Nobel 2025 (108 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/economic-sciences/2025/summary/</link>
            <guid>45567153</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 11:23:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/economic-sciences/2025/summary/">https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/economic-sciences/2025/summary/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45567153">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content">

			<section>



<article>

	<header>
		
	</header>

	


			<div>
							<figure itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
											<a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/economic-sciences/2025/mokyr/facts/"><picture><source data-srcset="https://www.nobelprize.org/uploads/2025/10/1-2_3-68ecb29cb51af-scaled.jpg" media="(max-width: 479px)"><source data-srcset="https://www.nobelprize.org/uploads/2025/10/1-2_3-68ecb29cb51af-scaled.jpg" media="(max-width: 979px)"><source data-srcset="https://www.nobelprize.org/uploads/2025/10/1-2_3-68ecb29cb51af-scaled.jpg" media="(min-width: 980px)"><img src="https://www.nobelprize.org/uploads/2025/10/1-2_3-68ecb29cb51af-scaled.jpg" alt="Joel Mokyr" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAAAAACH5BAEKAAEALAAAAAABAAEAAAICTAEAOw=="></picture></a><figcaption><p>Ill. Niklas Elmehed © Nobel Prize Outreach</p></figcaption>										<figcaption>
						<h3 itemprop="name">
							<a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/economic-sciences/2025/mokyr/facts/" title="Title text" itemprop="url">
								Joel Mokyr							</a>
						</h3>
						<p itemprop="description">
							Prize share: 							1/2						</p>
					</figcaption>
				</figure>
							<figure itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
											<a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/economic-sciences/2025/aghion/facts/"><picture><source data-srcset="https://www.nobelprize.org/uploads/2025/10/2-2_3-68ecb2a3e3ddc-scaled.jpg" media="(max-width: 479px)"><source data-srcset="https://www.nobelprize.org/uploads/2025/10/2-2_3-68ecb2a3e3ddc-scaled.jpg" media="(max-width: 979px)"><source data-srcset="https://www.nobelprize.org/uploads/2025/10/2-2_3-68ecb2a3e3ddc-scaled.jpg" media="(min-width: 980px)"><img src="https://www.nobelprize.org/uploads/2025/10/2-2_3-68ecb2a3e3ddc-scaled.jpg" alt="Philippe Aghion" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAAAAACH5BAEKAAEALAAAAAABAAEAAAICTAEAOw=="></picture></a><figcaption><p>Ill. Niklas Elmehed © Nobel Prize Outreach</p></figcaption>										<figcaption>
						<h3 itemprop="name">
							<a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/economic-sciences/2025/aghion/facts/" title="Title text" itemprop="url">
								Philippe Aghion							</a>
						</h3>
						<p itemprop="description">
							Prize share: 							1/4						</p>
					</figcaption>
				</figure>
							<figure itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
											<a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/economic-sciences/2025/howitt/facts/"><picture><source data-srcset="https://www.nobelprize.org/uploads/2025/10/3-2_3-68ecb2915d101-scaled.jpg" media="(max-width: 479px)"><source data-srcset="https://www.nobelprize.org/uploads/2025/10/3-2_3-68ecb2915d101-scaled.jpg" media="(max-width: 979px)"><source data-srcset="https://www.nobelprize.org/uploads/2025/10/3-2_3-68ecb2915d101-scaled.jpg" media="(min-width: 980px)"><img src="https://www.nobelprize.org/uploads/2025/10/3-2_3-68ecb2915d101-scaled.jpg" alt="Peter Howitt" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAAAAACH5BAEKAAEALAAAAAABAAEAAAICTAEAOw=="></picture></a><figcaption><p>Ill. Niklas Elmehed © Nobel Prize Outreach</p></figcaption>										<figcaption>
						<h3 itemprop="name">
							<a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/economic-sciences/2025/howitt/facts/" title="Title text" itemprop="url">
								Peter Howitt							</a>
						</h3>
						<p itemprop="description">
							Prize share: 							1/4						</p>
					</figcaption>
				</figure>
					</div>

					<blockquote itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Quotation">
				<p>
					The Sveriges Riksbank Prize in Economic Sciences in Memory of Alfred Nobel 2025 was awarded "for having explained innovation-driven economic growth" with one half to Joel Mokyr "for having identified the prerequisites for sustained growth through technological progress" and the other half jointly to Philippe Aghion and Peter Howitt "for the theory of sustained growth through creative destruction"				</p>
			</blockquote>
		
		
	
	


	
<div>
	<p><a href="#content">
		Back to top	</a></p><svg width="18px" height="15px" viewBox="0 0 20 17" version="1.1" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" role="image" aria-labelledby="back-to-top-title  back-to-top-desc">
	<title id="back-to-top-title">Back To Top</title>
	<desc id="back-to-top-desc">Takes users back to the top of the page</desc>
	<g stroke="none" stroke-width="1" fill="none" fill-rule="evenodd">
		<g transform="translate(-474.000000, -9998.000000)" fill="#2E2A25">
			<g transform="translate(474.000000, 9998.000000)">
				<g transform="translate(10.000000, 10.000000) rotate(45.000000) translate(-10.000000, -10.000000) translate(3.000000, 3.000000)">
					<rect x="0" y="0" width="2" height="14"></rect>
					<rect x="0" y="0" width="14" height="2"></rect>
				</g>
				<rect x="9" y="3" width="2" height="14"></rect>
			</g>
		</g>
	</g>
</svg>
</div>

</article>


</section>

<section>

	


			<article>

			<div>
				<header>
					
					
				</header>

				
									<div>
						<p>Six prizes were awarded for achievements that have conferred the greatest benefit to humankind. The 14 laureates' work and discoveries range from quantum tunnelling to promoting democratic rights.</p>
<p>See them all presented here.</p>
					</div>
				
							</div>

							<figure>
					<a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/all-nobel-prizes-2025/"><picture><source data-srcset="https://www.nobelprize.org/uploads/2024/06/nobelprizes_2025-scaled.jpg" media="(max-width: 479px)"><source data-srcset="https://www.nobelprize.org/uploads/2024/06/nobelprizes_2025-scaled.jpg" media="(max-width: 979px)"><source data-srcset="https://www.nobelprize.org/uploads/2024/06/nobelprizes_2025-scaled.jpg" media="(min-width: 980px)"><img src="https://www.nobelprize.org/uploads/2024/06/nobelprizes_2025-scaled.jpg" alt="Illustration" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAAAAACH5BAEKAAEALAAAAAABAAEAAAICTAEAOw=="></picture></a>				</figure>
			
					</article>
	</section>

<section>

	

	<form id="68ed53080c5c4" method="GET" action="">

		<p><label for="mobile-dropdown">
				Select the category or categories you would like to filter by			</label>

			

		</p>

		<div>
			<p><label>Select the category or categories you would like to filter by</label></p><p><label for="physics">
						
						<span>
							Physics						</span>
					</label>
				</p>

			
				<p><label for="chemistry">
						
						<span>
							Chemistry						</span>
					</label>
				</p>

			
				<p><label for="medicine">
						
						<span>
							Medicine						</span>
					</label>
				</p>

			
				<p><label for="literature">
						
						<span>
							Literature						</span>
					</label>
				</p>

			
				<p><label for="peace">
						
						<span>
							Peace						</span>
					</label>
				</p>

			
				<p><label for="economic-sciences">
						
						<span>
							Economic Sciences						</span>
					</label>
				</p>

					</div>

		<p>

			<label for="increment-input">
				Choose a year you would like to search in			</label>

			

			
		</p>

		
	</form>

</section>






		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Matrices can be your Friends (110 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.sjbaker.org/steve/omniv/matrices_can_be_your_friends.html</link>
            <guid>45566766</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 10:23:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.sjbaker.org/steve/omniv/matrices_can_be_your_friends.html">https://www.sjbaker.org/steve/omniv/matrices_can_be_your_friends.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45566766">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">


<center>By Steve Baker</center>
What stops most novice graphics programmers from getting friendly with matrices
is that they look like 16 utterly random numbers. However,
a little mental picture that I have seems to help most people
to make sense of what's going on. Most programmers are visual
thinkers and don't take kindly to piles of abstract math.
<p>
Take an OpenGL matrix:
</p><pre>
  float m [ 16 ] ;

</pre>
Consider this as a 4x4 array with it's elements laid out into
four columns like this:
<pre>
   m[0]  m[4]  m[ 8]  m[12]
   m[1]  m[5]  m[ 9]  m[13]
   m[2]  m[6]  m[10]  m[14]
   m[3]  m[7]  m[11]  m[15]

</pre>
<b>
WARNING: Mathematicians like to see their matrices laid out on paper
this way (with the array indices increasing down the columns instead
of across the rows as a programmer would usually write them).
Look CAREFULLY at the order of the matrix elements in the layout above!
</b>
<p>
...but we are OpenGL programmers - not mathematicians - right?! The
reason OpenGL arrays are laid out in what some people would consider
to be the opposite direction to mathematical convention is somewhat
lost in the mists of time. However, it turns out to be a happy accident
as we will see later.
</p><p>
If you are dealing with a matrix which only deals with rigid
bodies (ie no scale, shear, squash, etc) then the last row
(array elements 3,7,11 and 15) are always 0,0,0 and 1 respectively
and so long as they always maintain those values, we can safely forget
about them for now.
</p><p>
The first three elements of the rightmost column of the matrix is
just the overall translation. If you imagine some kind of neat
little compact object (like a teapot), then array elements 12,13 and 14
tell you where it is in the world. It doesn't matter what combinations
of rotations and translations it took to produce the matrix, the
rightmost column tells you where the object basically is.  It is
often fortunate that the OpenGL matrix array is laid out the way it
is because it results in those three elements being consecutive in
memory.
</p><p>
OK, so now we are down to only nine random-looking numbers. These
are the top three elements of each of the first three columns - and
collectively they represent the rotation of the object.
</p><p>
The easy way to decode those numbers is to imagine what happens
to four points near to the origin after they are transformed by the
matrix:
</p><pre>
   (0,1,0)
        |  /(0,0,1)
        | /
        |/___(1,0,0)
   (0,0,0)

</pre>
These are four vertices on a 1x1x1 cube that has one corner
at the origin.
<p>
After the matrix has transformed this cube, where does it end up?
</p><p>
Well, if we neglect the translation part (the bottom row),
then the pure rotation part simply describes the new location
of the points on the cube:
</p><pre>
    (1,0,0)  ---&gt;  ( m[0], m[1], m[2] )
    (0,1,0)  ---&gt;  ( m[4], m[5], m[6] )
    (0,0,1)  ---&gt;  ( m[8], m[9], m[10])
    (0,0,0)  ---&gt;  ( 0, 0, 0 )

</pre>
<strong>After</strong> that, you just add the translation onto each point
so that:
<pre>
    (1,0,0)  ---&gt;  ( m[0], m[1], m[2] ) + ( m[12], m[13], m[14] )
    (0,1,0)  ---&gt;  ( m[4], m[5], m[6] ) + ( m[12], m[13], m[14] )
    (0,0,1)  ---&gt;  ( m[8], m[9], m[10]) + ( m[12], m[13], m[14] )
    (0,0,0)  ---&gt;  ( 0, 0, 0 ) + ( m[12], m[13], m[14] )

</pre>
Once you know this, it becomes quite easy to use matrices
to position objects exactly where you need them without
messing around with multiple calls to glRotate.
<p>
Just imagine a little cube at the origin - pretend it's
firmly attached to your model. Think about where the
cube ends up as the model moves - write down where
it's vertices would end up and there is your matrix.
</p><p>
So, if I gave you this matrix:
</p><pre>
   0.707, -0.707, 0, 10
   0.707,  0.707, 0, 10
   0    ,  0    , 1,  0
   0    ,  0    , 0,  1

</pre>
...you could <strong>easily</strong> see that the X axis of that little
cube is now pointing somewhere between the X and Y axes,
the Y axis is pointing somewhere between Y and negative X
and the Z axis is unchanged. The entire cube has been moved
10 units off in X and Y. This is a
45 degree rotation about Z and a 10,10,0 translation!
You didn't need any hard math - just a mental picture
of what the little cube did - and no concerns about the
order of operations or anything hard like that. What
would have happened to something out at 100,100,0? Well,
just imagine it was glued to the cube (on the end of a
long stick)...as the cube rotated, the thing at 100,100
would have moved quite a bit too - in fact, you can see
that the rotation would put it onto the Y axis and the
translation would have moved it 10 units up and to the
right.
<p>
With practice, you can figure out what that last row of
numbers does to the little cube too.
</p><p>
So, would you like to know how to use a matrix to squash,
stretch, shear, etc? Just think about where
the axes of that little cube end up - write them down and
you are done. What does a cube of jello look like when
there is a strong wind blowing from X=-infinity?
</p><pre>
  1, 0.3, 0, 0
  0, 0.9, 0, 0
  0, 0  , 1, 0
  0, 0  , 0, 1

</pre>
Look - the Y axis is leaning a third of a unit to the
right and the cube got a bit shorter.
<p>
Suppose your cartoon character is going to jump vertically,
and you want to do a bit of pre-squash before the jump...
and post-stretch during the jump. Just gradually vary the
matrix from:
</p><pre>
  1  , 0  , 0, 0         1  , 0  , 0, 0
  0  , 0.8, 0, 0         0  , 1.2, 0, 0
  0  , 0  , 1, 0   ===&gt;  0  , 0  , 1, 0
  0  , 0  , 0, 1         0  , 0  , 0, 1

</pre>
Not bad - he got shorter then longer - how about getting
a bit fatter too (conservation of cartoon volume) ?
<pre>
  1.2, 0  , 0  , 0      0.9,0  , 0 , 0
  0  , 0.8, 0  , 0      0  ,1.2, 0 , 0
  0  , 0  , 1.2, 0 ===&gt; 0  ,0  ,0.9, 0
  0  , 0  , 0  , 1      0  ,0  , 0 , 1

</pre>
Now the cube got smaller in Y and bigger in X and Z then
got bigger in Y and smaller in X/Z...easy!
<p>
Not only is it easier to think transforms out this way,
but it's invariably more efficient too. By seeing the
entire transformation as one whole operation on a unit
cube, you save a long sequence of glRotate/glTranslate/glScale
commands - which each imply a complicated set of multiply/add
steps to concatenate the new transform with whatever is
on the top of the stack.
</p><p>
Finally, there is one matrix that we all need to know - the "Identity"
matrix:
</p><pre>
  1, 0, 0, 0
  0, 1, 0, 0
  0, 0, 1, 0
  0, 0, 0, 1

</pre>
As you can see, this matrix leaves all the axes completely alone and
performs no translation. This is a "do nothing" matrix.
<p>
Matrices are really easy - it's just a matter of looking at
them pictorially.




</p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Dutch government takes control of Chinese-owned chipmaker Nexperia (172 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cnbc.com/2025/10/13/dutch-government-takes-control-of-chinese-owned-chipmaker-nexperia.html</link>
            <guid>45566644</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 10:03:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/10/13/dutch-government-takes-control-of-chinese-owned-chipmaker-nexperia.html">https://www.cnbc.com/2025/10/13/dutch-government-takes-control-of-chinese-owned-chipmaker-nexperia.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45566644">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="RegularArticle-ArticleBody-5" data-module="ArticleBody" data-test="articleBody-2" data-analytics="RegularArticle-articleBody-5-2"><div id="ArticleBody-InlineImage-108211030" data-test="InlineImage"><p>A close-up view of the Nexperia plant sign in Newport, Wales on April 1, 2022. </p><p>Matthew Horwood | Getty Images News | Getty Images</p></div><div><p>The Dutch government has taken control of Nexperia, a Chinese-owned semiconductor maker based in the Netherlands, in an extraordinary move to ensure a sufficient supply of its chips remains available in Europe amid rising global trade tensions.</p><p>Nexperia, a subsidiary of China's <span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="RegularArticle-QuoteInBody-1"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/745-SZ/">Wingtech Technology</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span>, specializes in the high-volume production of chips used in automotive, consumer electronics and other industries, making it vital for maintaining Europe's technological supply chains.&nbsp;</p><p>On Sunday evening, the Dutch Minister of Economic Affairs <a href="https://www.government.nl/latest/news/2025/10/12/minister-of-economic-affairs-invokes-goods-availability-act" target="_blank">revealed</a> that it had invoked the "Goods Availability Act" on the company in September in order "to prevent a situation in which the goods produced by Nexperia (finished and semi-finished products) would become unavailable in an emergency."</p><p>Following the announcement from The Hague, Wingtech plunged its maximum daily limit of 10% on the Shanghai Stock Exchange.</p><p>The Goods Availability Act allows The Hague to intervene in private companies to ensure the availability of critical goods in preparation for emergency situations, and its use comes amid escalation in the U.S.-China trade war.</p><p>The government statement said the "highly exceptional" move had been made after the ministry had observed "recent and acute signals of serious governance shortcomings and actions" within Nexperia.</p><p>"These signals posed a threat to the continuity and safeguarding on Dutch and European soil of crucial technological knowledge and capabilities. Losing these capabilities could pose a risk to Dutch and European economic security," it said, identifying the automotive industry as particularly vulnerable.</p><h3>Governance changes</h3><p>In a <a href="https://static.sse.com.cn/disclosure/listedinfo/announcement/c/new/2025-10-13/600745_20251013_YB5D.pdf" target="_blank">corporate filing</a> dated Oct.13, lodged with the Shanghai Stock Exchange, Wingtech confirmed Nexperia was under temporary external management and had been asked to suspend changes to the company's assets, business or personnel for up to a year, according to a Google translation.</p><p>Wingtech Chairman Zhang Xuezheng had been immediately suspended from his roles as executive director of Nexperia Holdings and nonexecutive director of Nexperia after the ministerial order, according to the filing.</p><p>The filing added that Nexperia's daily operations will continue, with the impact of the measures not yet quantifiable.</p><p>"The Dutch government's decision to freeze Nexperia's global operations under the pretext of 'national security' constitutes excessive intervention driven by geopolitical bias, rather than a fact-based risk assessment," Wingtech said in a deleted WeChat post, which was archived and translated by <a href="https://www.pekingnology.com/p/dutch-govt-accused-of-freezing-operations" target="_blank">Chinese policy blog Pekingnology.</a></p><p>It added that since it acquired Nexperia in 2019, Wingtech "has strictly abided by the laws and regulations of all jurisdictions where it operates, maintaining transparent operations and sound governance," and employs "thousands of local staff" through research and development and manufacturing sites in the Netherlands, Germany and Britain.</p><p>A spokesperson from Nexperia told CNBC that the company had no further comments, but that it "complies with all existing laws and regulations, export controls and sanctions regimes," and remained in regular contact with relevant authorities.</p><p>The Netherlands' move comes after Beijing <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/10/09/china-tightens-rare-earths-grip-stocks-surge.html">tightened</a> its restrictions on the export of rare earth elements and magnets Thursday, which could impact Europe's automotive industry.&nbsp;</p><p>The move could also further strain trade relations between China and the Netherlands, following years of <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/01/02/asml-blocked-from-exporting-some-critical-chipmaking-tools-to-china.html">restrictions</a> on Dutch company ASML's exports of advanced semiconductor manufacturing equipment to China.</p><p>In 2023, the Netherlands had also investigated Nexperia's proposed acquisition of chip firm startup Nowi, though the deal was <a href="https://www.reuters.com/markets/deals/netherlands-allow-takeover-chip-startup-nowi-by-chinese-owned-nexperia-2023-11-27/" target="_blank">later approved</a>.</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[American solar farms (178 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://tech.marksblogg.com/american-solar-farms.html</link>
            <guid>45566638</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 10:02:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://tech.marksblogg.com/american-solar-farms.html">https://tech.marksblogg.com/american-solar-farms.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45566638">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="article_text">
            <p>Last week, Jake Stid, a postdoctoral research associate at Michigan State University, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/jake-stid-38bb23131_solars-footprint-is-central-to-discussions-activity-7378531783019167744-CIlL/">announced</a> Ground-Mounted Solar Energy in the United States (GM-SEUS). This is a 15K-array, 2.9M-panel dataset of utility and commercial-grade solar farms across the lower 48 states plus the District of Columbia. This dataset was constructed by a team of researchers including alumni from NOAA, NASA and the USGS.</p>
<p>Below is a heatmap of the assets catalogued in this dataset.</p>
<p><a href="https://tech.marksblogg.com/theme/images/gmseus/45vpffTdeU.jpg">
<img alt="US Solar Farms" src="https://tech.marksblogg.com/theme/images/gmseus/45vpffTdeU.jpg">
</a></p><p>GM-SEUS is broken up into two datasets, one for arrays and another panels. Below you can see a solar farm with the array outlined in red and the panels covered purple.</p>
<p><a href="https://tech.marksblogg.com/theme/images/gmseus/qgis-bin_WjbnWSLWy8.jpg">
<img alt="US Solar Farms" src="https://tech.marksblogg.com/theme/images/gmseus/qgis-bin_WjbnWSLWy8.jpg">
</a></p><p>In this post, I'll explore GM-SEUS's Solar Farm dataset.</p>
<div id="my-workstation">
<h2>My Workstation</h2>
<p>I'm using a 5.7 GHz AMD Ryzen 9 9950X CPU. It has 16 cores and 32 threads and 1.2 MB of L1, 16 MB of L2 and 64 MB of L3 cache. It has a liquid cooler attached and is housed in a spacious, full-sized Cooler Master HAF 700 computer case.</p>
<p>The system has 96 GB of DDR5 RAM clocked at 4,800 MT/s and a 5th-generation, Crucial T700 4 TB NVMe M.2 SSD which can read at speeds up to 12,400 MB/s. There is a heatsink on the SSD to help keep its temperature down. This is my system's C drive.</p>
<p>The system is powered by a 1,200-watt, fully modular Corsair Power Supply and is sat on an ASRock X870E Nova 90 Motherboard.</p>
<p>I'm running Ubuntu 24 LTS via Microsoft's Ubuntu for Windows on Windows 11 Pro. In case you're wondering why I don't run a Linux-based desktop as my primary work environment, I'm still using an Nvidia GTX 1080 GPU which has better driver support on Windows and ArcGIS Pro only supports Windows natively.</p>
</div>
<div id="installing-prerequisites">
<h2>Installing Prerequisites</h2>
<p>I'll use GDAL 3.9.3 and a few other tools to help analyse the data in this post.</p>
<div><pre><span></span>$<span> </span>sudo<span> </span>add-apt-repository<span> </span>ppa:ubuntugis/ubuntugis-unstable
$<span> </span>sudo<span> </span>apt<span> </span>update
$<span> </span>sudo<span> </span>apt<span> </span>install<span> </span><span>\</span>
<span>    </span>gdal-bin<span> </span><span>\</span>
<span>    </span>jq
</pre></div>
<p>I'll use DuckDB v1.4.1, along with its <a href="https://github.com/isaacbrodsky/h3-duckdb">H3</a>, <a href="https://duckdb.org/docs/extensions/json">JSON</a>, <a href="https://community-extensions.duckdb.org/extensions/lindel.html">Lindel</a>, <a href="https://duckdb.org/docs/data/parquet/overview">Parquet</a> and <a href="https://duckdb.org/docs/extensions/spatial.html">Spatial</a> extensions, in this post.</p>
<div><pre><span></span>$<span> </span><span>cd</span><span> </span>~
$<span> </span>wget<span> </span>-c<span> </span>https://github.com/duckdb/duckdb/releases/download/v1.4.1/duckdb_cli-linux-amd64.zip
$<span> </span>unzip<span> </span>-j<span> </span>duckdb_cli-linux-amd64.zip
$<span> </span>chmod<span> </span>+x<span> </span>duckdb
$<span> </span>~/duckdb
</pre></div>
<div><pre><span></span><span>INSTALL</span><span> </span><span>h3</span><span> </span><span>FROM</span><span> </span><span>community</span><span>;</span>
<span>INSTALL</span><span> </span><span>lindel</span><span> </span><span>FROM</span><span> </span><span>community</span><span>;</span>
<span>INSTALL</span><span> </span><span>json</span><span>;</span>
<span>INSTALL</span><span> </span><span>parquet</span><span>;</span>
<span>INSTALL</span><span> </span><span>spatial</span><span>;</span>
</pre></div>
<p>I'll set up DuckDB to load every installed extension each time it launches.</p>

<div><pre><span></span>.timer on
.width 180
LOAD h3;
LOAD lindel;
LOAD json;
LOAD parquet;
LOAD spatial;
</pre></div>
<p>The maps in this post were mostly rendered with <a href="https://www.qgis.org/en/site/forusers/download.html">QGIS</a> version 3.44. QGIS is a desktop application that runs on Windows, macOS and Linux. The application has grown in popularity in recent years and has ~15M application launches from users all around the world each month.</p>
<p>I used QGIS' <a href="https://github.com/marklit/tile_plus">Tile+ plugin</a> to add basemaps from Esri to the maps in this post.</p>
</div>
<div id="analysis-ready-data">
<h2>Analysis-Ready Data</h2>
<p>I'll download a dataset containing the US CENSUS State codes. This will let me map the state ID in the arrays dataset to their state name.</p>
<div><pre><span></span>$<span> </span>wget<span> </span>https://gist.github.com/a8dx/2340f9527af64f8ef8439366de981168/raw/81d876daea10eab5c2675811c39bcd18a79a9212/US_State_Bounding_Boxes.csv
</pre></div>
<p>I'll download the ZIP file of deliverables for GM-SEUS.</p>
<div><pre><span></span>$<span> </span>wget<span> </span>-O<span> </span>GMSEUS_v1_0.zip<span> </span><span>\</span>
<span>    </span><span>'https://zenodo.org/records/14827819/files/GMSEUS_v1_0.zip?download=1'</span>
$<span> </span>unzip<span> </span>GMSEUS_v1_0.zip
</pre></div>
<p>I'll extract the projection used. This proj4 string will be used to below to re-project the data into EPSG:4326.</p>
<div><pre><span></span>$<span> </span>gdalsrsinfo<span> </span><span>\</span>
<span>    </span>-o<span> </span>proj4<span> </span><span>\</span>
<span>    </span>GMSEUS_v1_0/GPKG/GMSEUS_Arrays_Final.gpkg
</pre></div>
<div><pre><span></span>+proj=aea +lat_0=37.5 +lon_0=-96 +lat_1=29.5 +lat_2=45.5 +x_0=0 +y_0=0 +datum=NAD83 +units=m +no_defs
</pre></div>
<p>I'll use DuckDB to clean up the values and produce both a geometry field and a bounding box for each feature in this dataset. This will make working with this dataset remotely, such as from AWS S3, much easier.</p>

<p>This following produced a ZStandard-compressed, spatially-sorted Parquet file of the arrays dataset. I dropped the Z dimension as it was unused. The unknown values have been turned into NULLs. The original GPKG file was 108 MB and the resulting Parquet file is 37 MB.</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>COPY</span><span> </span><span>(</span>
<span>   </span><span>WITH</span><span> </span><span>a</span><span> </span><span>AS</span><span> </span><span>(</span>
<span>       </span><span>SELECT</span><span> </span><span>*</span><span> </span><span>EXCLUDE</span><span>(</span><span>geom</span><span>),</span>
<span>              </span><span>ST_FORCE2D</span><span>(</span>
<span>                </span><span>ST_FLIPCOORDINATES</span><span>(</span>
<span>                  </span><span>ST_TRANSFORM</span><span>(</span>
<span>                      </span><span>geom</span><span>,</span>
<span>                      </span><span>'+proj=aea +lat_0=37.5 +lon_0=-96 +lat_1=29.5 +lat_2=45.5 +x_0=0 +y_0=0 +datum=NAD83 +units=m +no_defs'</span><span>,</span>
<span>                      </span><span>'EPSG:4326'</span><span>)))</span><span> </span><span>geometry</span>
<span>       </span><span>FROM</span><span>   </span><span>ST_READ</span><span>(</span><span>'GMSEUS_v1_0/GPKG/GMSEUS_Arrays_Final.gpkg'</span><span>)</span>
<span>   </span><span>)</span>
<span>   </span><span>SELECT</span><span>   </span><span>a</span><span>.</span><span>*</span><span> </span><span>EXCLUDE</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>geometry</span><span>,</span>
<span>                         </span><span>tilt</span><span>,</span>
<span>                         </span><span>tiltEst</span><span>,</span>
<span>                         </span><span>instYr</span><span>,</span>
<span>                         </span><span>instYrLT</span><span>,</span>
<span>                         </span><span>effInit</span><span>,</span>
<span>                         </span><span>avgAzimuth</span><span>,</span>
<span>                         </span><span>avgLength</span><span>,</span>
<span>                         </span><span>avgSpace</span><span>,</span>
<span>                         </span><span>avgWidth</span><span>),</span>
<span>            </span><span>{</span><span>'xmin'</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>ST_XMIN</span><span>(</span><span>ST_EXTENT</span><span>(</span><span>geometry</span><span>)),</span>
<span>             </span><span>'ymin'</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>ST_YMIN</span><span>(</span><span>ST_EXTENT</span><span>(</span><span>geometry</span><span>)),</span>
<span>             </span><span>'xmax'</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>ST_XMAX</span><span>(</span><span>ST_EXTENT</span><span>(</span><span>geometry</span><span>)),</span>
<span>             </span><span>'ymax'</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>ST_YMAX</span><span>(</span><span>ST_EXTENT</span><span>(</span><span>geometry</span><span>))</span><span>}</span><span> </span><span>AS</span><span> </span><span>bbox</span><span>,</span>
<span>             </span><span>ST_ASWKB</span><span>(</span><span>geometry</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>geometry</span><span>,</span>
<span>             </span><span>CASE</span><span> </span><span>WHEN</span><span> </span><span>instYr</span><span>::</span><span>INT</span><span>     </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>-</span><span>9999</span><span> </span><span>THEN</span><span> </span><span>NULL</span><span> </span><span>ELSE</span><span> </span><span>instYr</span><span>::</span><span>INT</span><span>   </span><span>END</span><span> </span><span>AS</span><span> </span><span>instYr</span><span>,</span>
<span>             </span><span>CASE</span><span> </span><span>WHEN</span><span> </span><span>instYrLT</span><span>::</span><span>INT</span><span>   </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>-</span><span>9999</span><span> </span><span>THEN</span><span> </span><span>NULL</span><span> </span><span>ELSE</span><span> </span><span>instYrLT</span><span>::</span><span>INT</span><span> </span><span>END</span><span> </span><span>AS</span><span> </span><span>instYrLT</span><span>,</span>
<span>             </span><span>CASE</span><span> </span><span>WHEN</span><span> </span><span>numRow</span><span>::</span><span>INT</span><span>     </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>-</span><span>9999</span><span> </span><span>THEN</span><span> </span><span>NULL</span><span> </span><span>ELSE</span><span> </span><span>numRow</span><span>::</span><span>INT</span><span>   </span><span>END</span><span> </span><span>AS</span><span> </span><span>numRow</span><span>,</span>
<span>             </span><span>CASE</span><span> </span><span>WHEN</span><span> </span><span>tilt</span><span>::</span><span>INT</span><span>       </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>-</span><span>9999</span><span> </span><span>THEN</span><span> </span><span>NULL</span><span> </span><span>ELSE</span><span> </span><span>tilt</span><span>::</span><span>INT</span><span>     </span><span>END</span><span> </span><span>AS</span><span> </span><span>tilt</span><span>,</span>
<span>             </span><span>CASE</span><span> </span><span>WHEN</span><span> </span><span>tiltEst</span><span>::</span><span>INT</span><span>    </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>-</span><span>9999</span><span> </span><span>THEN</span><span> </span><span>NULL</span><span> </span><span>ELSE</span><span> </span><span>tiltEst</span><span>::</span><span>INT</span><span>  </span><span>END</span><span> </span><span>AS</span><span> </span><span>tiltEst</span><span>,</span>
<span>             </span><span>CASE</span><span> </span><span>WHEN</span><span> </span><span>effInit</span><span>::</span><span>INT</span><span>    </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>-</span><span>9999</span><span> </span><span>THEN</span><span> </span><span>NULL</span><span> </span><span>ELSE</span><span> </span><span>effInit</span><span>       </span><span>END</span><span> </span><span>AS</span><span> </span><span>effInit</span><span>,</span>
<span>             </span><span>CASE</span><span> </span><span>WHEN</span><span> </span><span>avgAzimuth</span><span>::</span><span>INT</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>-</span><span>9999</span><span> </span><span>THEN</span><span> </span><span>NULL</span><span> </span><span>ELSE</span><span> </span><span>avgAzimuth</span><span>    </span><span>END</span><span> </span><span>AS</span><span> </span><span>avgAzimuth</span><span>,</span>
<span>             </span><span>CASE</span><span> </span><span>WHEN</span><span> </span><span>avgLength</span><span>::</span><span>INT</span><span>  </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>-</span><span>9999</span><span> </span><span>THEN</span><span> </span><span>NULL</span><span> </span><span>ELSE</span><span> </span><span>avgLength</span><span>     </span><span>END</span><span> </span><span>AS</span><span> </span><span>avgLength</span><span>,</span>
<span>             </span><span>CASE</span><span> </span><span>WHEN</span><span> </span><span>avgSpace</span><span>::</span><span>INT</span><span>   </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>-</span><span>9999</span><span> </span><span>THEN</span><span> </span><span>NULL</span><span> </span><span>ELSE</span><span> </span><span>avgSpace</span><span>      </span><span>END</span><span> </span><span>AS</span><span> </span><span>avgSpace</span><span>,</span>
<span>             </span><span>CASE</span><span> </span><span>WHEN</span><span> </span><span>avgWidth</span><span>::</span><span>INT</span><span>   </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>-</span><span>9999</span><span> </span><span>THEN</span><span> </span><span>NULL</span><span> </span><span>ELSE</span><span> </span><span>avgWidth</span><span>      </span><span>END</span><span> </span><span>AS</span><span> </span><span>avgWidth</span><span>,</span>
<span>             </span><span>b</span><span>.</span><span>NAME</span><span> </span><span>state_name</span>
<span>   </span><span>FROM</span><span>     </span><span>a</span>
<span>   </span><span>JOIN</span><span>     </span><span>'US_State_Bounding_Boxes.csv'</span><span> </span><span>b</span><span> </span><span>ON</span><span> </span><span>a</span><span>.</span><span>STATEFP</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>b</span><span>.</span><span>STATEFP</span>
<span>   </span><span>ORDER</span><span> </span><span>BY</span><span> </span><span>HILBERT_ENCODE</span><span>([</span><span>ST_Y</span><span>(</span><span>ST_CENTROID</span><span>(</span><span>geometry</span><span>)),</span>
<span>                            </span><span>ST_X</span><span>(</span><span>ST_CENTROID</span><span>(</span><span>geometry</span><span>))]::</span><span>double</span><span>[</span><span>2</span><span>])</span>
<span>)</span><span> </span><span>TO</span><span> </span><span>'arrays.parquet'</span><span> </span><span>(</span>
<span>   </span><span>FORMAT</span><span>            </span><span>'PARQUET'</span><span>,</span>
<span>   </span><span>CODEC</span><span>             </span><span>'ZSTD'</span><span>,</span>
<span>   </span><span>COMPRESSION_LEVEL</span><span> </span><span>22</span><span>,</span>
<span>   </span><span>ROW_GROUP_SIZE</span><span>    </span><span>15000</span><span>);</span>
</pre></div>
<p>The original GPKG file for the panels dataset was 1.1 GB and the resulting Parquet file is 334 MB.</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>COPY</span><span> </span><span>(</span>
<span>   </span><span>WITH</span><span> </span><span>a</span><span> </span><span>AS</span><span> </span><span>(</span>
<span>       </span><span>SELECT</span><span> </span><span>*</span><span> </span><span>EXCLUDE</span><span>(</span><span>geom</span><span>),</span>
<span>              </span><span>ST_FORCE2D</span><span>(</span>
<span>                </span><span>ST_FLIPCOORDINATES</span><span>(</span>
<span>                  </span><span>ST_TRANSFORM</span><span>(</span>
<span>                      </span><span>geom</span><span>,</span>
<span>                      </span><span>'+proj=aea +lat_0=37.5 +lon_0=-96 +lat_1=29.5 +lat_2=45.5 +x_0=0 +y_0=0 +datum=NAD83 +units=m +no_defs'</span><span>,</span>
<span>                      </span><span>'EPSG:4326'</span><span>)))</span><span> </span><span>geometry</span>
<span>       </span><span>FROM</span><span>   </span><span>ST_READ</span><span>(</span><span>'GMSEUS_v1_0/GPKG/GMSEUS_Panels_Final.gpkg'</span><span>)</span>
<span>   </span><span>)</span>
<span>   </span><span>SELECT</span><span>   </span><span>*</span><span> </span><span>EXCLUDE</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>geometry</span><span>,</span>
<span>                       </span><span>rowSpace</span><span>),</span>
<span>            </span><span>{</span><span>'xmin'</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>ST_XMIN</span><span>(</span><span>ST_EXTENT</span><span>(</span><span>geometry</span><span>)),</span>
<span>             </span><span>'ymin'</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>ST_YMIN</span><span>(</span><span>ST_EXTENT</span><span>(</span><span>geometry</span><span>)),</span>
<span>             </span><span>'xmax'</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>ST_XMAX</span><span>(</span><span>ST_EXTENT</span><span>(</span><span>geometry</span><span>)),</span>
<span>             </span><span>'ymax'</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>ST_YMAX</span><span>(</span><span>ST_EXTENT</span><span>(</span><span>geometry</span><span>))</span><span>}</span><span> </span><span>AS</span><span> </span><span>bbox</span><span>,</span>
<span>             </span><span>ST_ASWKB</span><span>(</span><span>geometry</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>geometry</span><span>,</span>
<span>             </span><span>CASE</span><span> </span><span>WHEN</span><span> </span><span>rowSpace</span><span>::</span><span>INT</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>-</span><span>9999</span><span> </span><span>THEN</span><span> </span><span>NULL</span><span> </span><span>ELSE</span><span> </span><span>rowSpace</span><span> </span><span>END</span><span> </span><span>AS</span><span> </span><span>rowSpace</span>
<span>   </span><span>FROM</span><span>     </span><span>a</span>
<span>   </span><span>ORDER</span><span> </span><span>BY</span><span> </span><span>HILBERT_ENCODE</span><span>([</span><span>ST_Y</span><span>(</span><span>ST_CENTROID</span><span>(</span><span>geometry</span><span>)),</span>
<span>                            </span><span>ST_X</span><span>(</span><span>ST_CENTROID</span><span>(</span><span>geometry</span><span>))]::</span><span>double</span><span>[</span><span>2</span><span>])</span>
<span>)</span><span> </span><span>TO</span><span> </span><span>'panels.parquet'</span><span> </span><span>(</span>
<span>   </span><span>FORMAT</span><span>            </span><span>'PARQUET'</span><span>,</span>
<span>   </span><span>CODEC</span><span>             </span><span>'ZSTD'</span><span>,</span>
<span>   </span><span>COMPRESSION_LEVEL</span><span> </span><span>22</span><span>,</span>
<span>   </span><span>ROW_GROUP_SIZE</span><span>    </span><span>15000</span><span>);</span>
</pre></div>
</div>
<div id="solar-arrays">
<h2>Solar Arrays</h2>
<p>The arrays Parquet file has 15,017 rows. Below is an example record.</p>
<div><pre><span></span>$<span> </span><span>echo</span><span> </span><span>"SELECT * EXCLUDE(bbox,</span>
<span>                         geometry),</span>
<span>               bbox::JSON bbox</span>
<span>        FROM   'arrays.parquet'</span>
<span>        LIMIT  1"</span><span> </span><span>\</span>
<span>    </span><span>|</span><span> </span>~/duckdb<span> </span>-json<span> </span><span>\</span>
<span>    </span><span>|</span><span> </span>jq<span> </span>-S<span> </span>.
</pre></div>
<div><pre><span></span><span>[</span>
<span>  </span><span>{</span>
<span>    </span><span>"COUNTYFP"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"019"</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"GCR1"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0.6996</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"GCR2"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0.614</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"STATEFP"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"45"</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"Source"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"OSM"</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"arrayID"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>2807</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"avgAzimuth"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>170.63</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"avgLength"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>47.76166666666666</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"avgSpace"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>3.003333333333333</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"avgWidth"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>4.776666666666666</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"bbox"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>      </span><span>"xmax"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>-79.97229830431786</span><span>,</span>
<span>      </span><span>"xmin"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>-79.97325770533094</span><span>,</span>
<span>      </span><span>"ymax"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>32.87833627192598</span><span>,</span>
<span>      </span><span>"ymin"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>32.87808294640646</span>
<span>    </span><span>},</span>
<span>    </span><span>"capMW"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0.246</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"capMWest"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0.246</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"effInit"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0.197963503102977</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"instYr"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>2021</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"instYrLT"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>2021</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"latitude"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>32.87818725544087</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"longitude"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>-79.97276617375104</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"modType"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"c-si"</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"mount"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"fixed_axis"</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"nativeID"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"9324"</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"newBound"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>1</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"numRow"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>6.0</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"numRow_1"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>6</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"state_name"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"South Carolina"</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"tilt"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>30</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"tiltEst"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>30</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"totArea"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>1779.0</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"totRowArea"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>1244.93</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"version"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"v1.0"</span>
<span>  </span><span>}</span>
<span>]</span>
</pre></div>
<p>Below are the field names, data types, percentages of NULLs per column, number of unique values and minimum and maximum values for each column.</p>

<div><pre><span></span><span>SELECT</span><span>   </span><span>column_name</span><span>,</span>
<span>         </span><span>column_type</span><span>,</span>
<span>         </span><span>null_percentage</span><span>,</span>
<span>         </span><span>approx_unique</span><span>,</span>
<span>         </span><span>min</span><span>,</span>
<span>         </span><span>max</span>
<span>FROM</span><span>     </span><span>(</span><span>SUMMARIZE</span>
<span>          </span><span>FROM</span><span> </span><span>READ_PARQUET</span><span>(</span><span>'arrays.parquet'</span><span>))</span>
<span>WHERE</span><span>    </span><span>column_name</span><span> </span><span>!=</span><span> </span><span>'geometry'</span>
<span>AND</span><span>      </span><span>column_name</span><span> </span><span>!=</span><span> </span><span>'bbox'</span>
<span>ORDER</span><span> </span><span>BY</span><span> </span><span>1</span><span>;</span>
</pre></div>
<div><pre><span></span>┌─────────────┬─────────────┬─────────────────┬───────────────┬─────────────────────┬────────────────────┐
│ column_name │ column_type │ null_percentage │ approx_unique │         min         │        max         │
│   varchar   │   varchar   │  decimal(9,2)   │     int64     │       varchar       │      varchar       │
├─────────────┼─────────────┼─────────────────┼───────────────┼─────────────────────┼────────────────────┤
│ COUNTYFP    │ VARCHAR     │            0.00 │           235 │ 001                 │ 810                │
│ GCR1        │ DOUBLE      │            0.00 │          5057 │ 0.1047              │ 1.0                │
│ GCR2        │ DOUBLE      │            0.00 │          5013 │ 0.1245              │ 0.988              │
│ STATEFP     │ VARCHAR     │            0.00 │            49 │ 01                  │ 56                 │
│ Source      │ VARCHAR     │            0.00 │             6 │ CCVPV               │ USPVDB             │
│ arrayID     │ BIGINT      │            0.00 │         13155 │ 1                   │ 15017              │
│ avgAzimuth  │ DOUBLE      │           32.84 │          4295 │ 25.0                │ 269.27             │
│ avgLength   │ DOUBLE      │           39.79 │          8358 │ 4.02                │ 449.5004           │
│ avgSpace    │ DOUBLE      │           39.79 │          8623 │ 0.024               │ 20.0               │
│ avgWidth    │ DOUBLE      │           39.79 │          9185 │ 0.67625             │ 29.80222222222222  │
│ capMW       │ DOUBLE      │            0.00 │          5280 │ 0.001250225184651   │ 1051.703           │
│ capMWest    │ DOUBLE      │            0.00 │          7863 │ 0.004               │ 3170.1             │
│ effInit     │ DOUBLE      │            0.49 │            39 │ 0.132210289727273   │ 0.205484167047619  │
│ instYr      │ INTEGER     │            0.00 │            24 │ 1985                │ 2024               │
│ instYrLT    │ INTEGER     │            0.24 │            17 │ 2009                │ 2023               │
│ latitude    │ DOUBLE      │            0.00 │         16986 │ 25.53796582594631   │ 48.99547137225406  │
│ longitude   │ DOUBLE      │            0.00 │         15656 │ -124.10440474967092 │ -67.15066374183608 │
│ modType     │ VARCHAR     │            0.00 │             3 │ c-si                │ thin-film          │
│ mount       │ VARCHAR     │            0.00 │            10 │ dual_axis           │ unknown            │
│ nativeID    │ VARCHAR     │            0.00 │         15141 │ 1                   │ York Solar         │
│ newBound    │ BIGINT      │            0.00 │             2 │ 0                   │ 1                  │
│ numRow      │ DOUBLE      │            0.00 │          1461 │ 0.0                 │ 56782.0            │
│ numRow_1    │ INTEGER     │            0.00 │          1117 │ 0                   │ 56782              │
│ state_name  │ VARCHAR     │            0.00 │            57 │ Alabama             │ Wyoming            │
│ tilt        │ INTEGER     │           55.46 │            47 │ 0                   │ 83                 │
│ tiltEst     │ INTEGER     │           55.46 │            30 │ 10                  │ 43                 │
│ totArea     │ DOUBLE      │            0.00 │         13182 │ 54.0                │ 13735113.0         │
│ totRowArea  │ DOUBLE      │            0.00 │         15396 │ 44.97               │ 7223924.662        │
│ version     │ VARCHAR     │            0.00 │             1 │ v1.0                │ v1.0               │
├─────────────┴─────────────┴─────────────────┴───────────────┴─────────────────────┴────────────────────┤
│ 29 rows                                                                                      6 columns │
└────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────┘
</pre></div>
<p>I'll generate a heatmap of the asset locations in this dataset.</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>CREATE</span><span> </span><span>OR</span><span> </span><span>REPLACE</span><span> </span><span>TABLE</span><span> </span><span>h3_4_stats</span><span> </span><span>AS</span>
<span>    </span><span>SELECT</span><span>   </span><span>H3_LATLNG_TO_CELL</span><span>(</span>
<span>                </span><span>bbox</span><span>.</span><span>ymin</span><span>,</span>
<span>                </span><span>bbox</span><span>.</span><span>xmin</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>4</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>AS</span><span> </span><span>h3_4</span><span>,</span>
<span>             </span><span>COUNT</span><span>(</span><span>*</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>num_buildings</span>
<span>    </span><span>FROM</span><span>     </span><span>READ_PARQUET</span><span>(</span><span>'arrays.parquet'</span><span>)</span>
<span>    </span><span>WHERE</span><span>    </span><span>bbox</span><span>.</span><span>xmin</span><span> </span><span>BETWEEN</span><span> </span><span>-</span><span>178</span><span>.</span><span>5</span><span> </span><span>AND</span><span> </span><span>178</span><span>.</span><span>5</span>
<span>    </span><span>GROUP</span><span> </span><span>BY</span><span> </span><span>1</span><span>;</span>

<span>COPY</span><span> </span><span>(</span>
<span>    </span><span>SELECT</span><span> </span><span>ST_ASWKB</span><span>(</span><span>H3_CELL_TO_BOUNDARY_WKT</span><span>(</span><span>h3_4</span><span>)::</span><span>geometry</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>geometry</span><span>,</span>
<span>           </span><span>num_buildings</span>
<span>    </span><span>FROM</span><span>   </span><span>h3_4_stats</span>
<span>)</span><span> </span><span>TO</span><span> </span><span>'h3_4_stats.gpkg'</span>
<span>  </span><span>WITH</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>FORMAT</span><span> </span><span>GDAL</span><span>,</span>
<span>        </span><span>DRIVER</span><span> </span><span>'GPKG'</span><span>,</span>
<span>        </span><span>LAYER_CREATION_OPTIONS</span><span> </span><span>'WRITE_BBOX=YES'</span><span>);</span>
</pre></div>
<p><a href="https://tech.marksblogg.com/theme/images/gmseus/45vpffTdeU.jpg">
<img alt="US Solar Farms" src="https://tech.marksblogg.com/theme/images/gmseus/45vpffTdeU.jpg">
</a></p><p>Normally I would produce a Parquet file as even with 10s of thousands of records it'll generate in seconds versus a minute or so with GPKG. But ArcGIS Pro 3.5 didn't want to open the Parquet file I generated. QGIS 3.44 was fine with it but I wanted to use Esri's Nova basemap for the rendering below.</p>
<p>ArcGIS Pro 3.6 should be released sometime in the next few weeks so I'll re-examine this issue when it's out.</p>
<p>Below is the relationship between the sources of data and the installation year.</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>PIVOT</span><span>    </span><span>'arrays.parquet'</span>
<span>ON</span><span>       </span><span>Source</span>
<span>USING</span><span>    </span><span>COUNT</span><span>(</span><span>*</span><span>)</span>
<span>GROUP</span><span> </span><span>BY</span><span> </span><span>instYr</span>
<span>ORDER</span><span> </span><span>BY</span><span> </span><span>instYr</span><span>;</span>
</pre></div>
<div><pre><span></span>┌────────┬───────┬───────┬───────────────┬───────┬───────┬────────┐
│ instYr │ CCVPV │ CWSD  │ GMSEUSgeorect │  OSM  │  SAM  │ USPVDB │
│ int32  │ int64 │ int64 │     int64     │ int64 │ int64 │ int64  │
├────────┼───────┼───────┼───────────────┼───────┼───────┼────────┤
│   1985 │     0 │     0 │             0 │     0 │     0 │      1 │
│   1986 │     0 │     0 │             0 │     1 │     0 │      0 │
│   2002 │     0 │     0 │             0 │     0 │     0 │      1 │
│   2005 │     0 │     0 │             0 │    26 │     0 │      0 │
│   2006 │     0 │     0 │             0 │     2 │     0 │      1 │
│   2007 │     0 │     0 │             0 │    44 │     0 │      5 │
│   2008 │     0 │     0 │             0 │    58 │     1 │     11 │
│   2009 │     5 │     0 │             0 │    10 │     5 │     19 │
│   2010 │    20 │     0 │             0 │    71 │    20 │     37 │
│   2011 │    24 │     0 │             2 │   193 │    30 │    102 │
│   2012 │    59 │     0 │             2 │   267 │    88 │    157 │
│   2013 │    83 │     0 │             3 │   259 │    82 │    209 │
│   2014 │   102 │     0 │             1 │   335 │   119 │    291 │
│   2015 │   107 │     3 │             0 │   532 │   125 │    320 │
│   2016 │   145 │     1 │             2 │   564 │   170 │    412 │
│   2017 │   135 │     0 │             1 │   661 │   167 │    476 │
│   2018 │    66 │    34 │             4 │   644 │   210 │    414 │
│   2019 │    28 │    39 │             6 │   467 │   178 │    453 │
│   2020 │    10 │    75 │             1 │   437 │   186 │    496 │
│   2021 │     5 │    33 │             6 │   406 │   241 │    446 │
│   2022 │     1 │   173 │             3 │   231 │   354 │    166 │
│   2023 │     0 │     0 │             3 │   176 │   722 │    134 │
│   2024 │     0 │     0 │             0 │    31 │  1571 │      0 │
├────────┴───────┴───────┴───────────────┴───────┴───────┴────────┤
│ 23 rows                                               7 columns │
└─────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────┘
</pre></div>
<p>Below is the relationship between the mount and mod type.</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>PIVOT</span><span>    </span><span>'arrays.parquet'</span>
<span>ON</span><span>       </span><span>modType</span>
<span>USING</span><span>    </span><span>COUNT</span><span>(</span><span>*</span><span>)</span>
<span>GROUP</span><span> </span><span>BY</span><span> </span><span>mount</span>
<span>ORDER</span><span> </span><span>BY</span><span> </span><span>mount</span><span>;</span>
</pre></div>
<div><pre><span></span>┌─────────────┬───────┬───────┬───────────┐
│    mount    │ c-si  │  csp  │ thin-film │
│   varchar   │ int64 │ int64 │   int64   │
├─────────────┼───────┼───────┼───────────┤
│ dual_axis   │   301 │    18 │         1 │
│ fixed_axis  │  6057 │    32 │       208 │
│ mixed       │     2 │     0 │         0 │
│ mixed_df    │   189 │     7 │         0 │
│ mixed_dfs   │    94 │     0 │         0 │
│ mixed_ds    │    38 │     1 │         0 │
│ mixed_fs    │    60 │     0 │         1 │
│ single_axis │  2876 │    11 │       231 │
│ unknown     │  4885 │     5 │         0 │
└─────────────┴───────┴───────┴───────────┘
</pre></div>
<p>Below are the array capacity counts rounded to the neared 100 MW and broken down by source.</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>WITH</span><span> </span><span>a</span><span> </span><span>AS</span><span> </span><span>(</span>
<span>    </span><span>SELECT</span><span>   </span><span>Source</span><span>,</span>
<span>             </span><span>ROUND</span><span>(</span><span>capMW</span><span> </span><span>/</span><span> </span><span>100</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>*</span><span> </span><span>100</span><span> </span><span>AS</span><span> </span><span>capacity</span><span>,</span>
<span>             </span><span>COUNT</span><span>(</span><span>*</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>num_recs</span>
<span>    </span><span>FROM</span><span>     </span><span>'arrays.parquet'</span>
<span>    </span><span>GROUP</span><span> </span><span>BY</span><span> </span><span>1</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>2</span>
<span>)</span>
<span>PIVOT</span><span>    </span><span>a</span>
<span>ON</span><span>       </span><span>Source</span>
<span>USING</span><span>    </span><span>SUM</span><span>(</span><span>num_recs</span><span>)</span>
<span>GROUP</span><span> </span><span>BY</span><span> </span><span>capacity</span>
<span>ORDER</span><span> </span><span>BY</span><span> </span><span>capacity</span><span>;</span>
</pre></div>
<div><pre><span></span>┌──────────┬────────┬────────┬───────────────┬────────┬────────┬────────┐
│ capacity │ CCVPV  │  CWSD  │ GMSEUSgeorect │  OSM   │  SAM   │ USPVDB │
│  double  │ int128 │ int128 │    int128     │ int128 │ int128 │ int128 │
├──────────┼────────┼────────┼───────────────┼────────┼────────┼────────┤
│      0.0 │    790 │    356 │            33 │   5295 │   4022 │   3669 │
│    100.0 │   NULL │      2 │          NULL │     67 │    143 │    350 │
│    200.0 │   NULL │   NULL │             1 │     22 │     49 │     73 │
│    300.0 │   NULL │   NULL │          NULL │     17 │     21 │     49 │
│    400.0 │   NULL │   NULL │          NULL │      6 │     13 │      7 │
│    500.0 │   NULL │   NULL │          NULL │      4 │     11 │      2 │
│    600.0 │   NULL │   NULL │          NULL │      2 │      3 │   NULL │
│    700.0 │   NULL │   NULL │          NULL │      1 │      3 │   NULL │
│    800.0 │   NULL │   NULL │          NULL │   NULL │      2 │      1 │
│    900.0 │   NULL │   NULL │          NULL │   NULL │      1 │   NULL │
│   1000.0 │   NULL │   NULL │          NULL │   NULL │      1 │   NULL │
│   1100.0 │   NULL │   NULL │          NULL │      1 │   NULL │   NULL │
├──────────┴────────┴────────┴───────────────┴────────┴────────┴────────┤
│ 12 rows                                                     7 columns │
└───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────┘
</pre></div>
</div>
<div id="solar-panels">
<h2>Solar Panels</h2>
<p>The panels Parquet file has 2,917,782 rows. Below is an example record.</p>
<div><pre><span></span>$<span> </span><span>echo</span><span> </span><span>"SELECT * EXCLUDE(bbox,</span>
<span>                         geometry),</span>
<span>               bbox::JSON bbox</span>
<span>        FROM   'panels.parquet'</span>
<span>        LIMIT  1"</span><span> </span><span>\</span>
<span>    </span><span>|</span><span> </span>~/duckdb<span> </span>-json<span> </span><span>\</span>
<span>    </span><span>|</span><span> </span>jq<span> </span>-S<span> </span>.
</pre></div>
<div><pre><span></span><span>[</span>
<span>  </span><span>{</span>
<span>    </span><span>"Source"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"gmseus"</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"arrayID"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>2807.0</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"bbox"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>      </span><span>"xmax"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>-79.97312295800064</span><span>,</span>
<span>      </span><span>"xmin"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>-79.97325770533483</span><span>,</span>
<span>      </span><span>"ymax"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>32.87833627193374</span><span>,</span>
<span>      </span><span>"ymin"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>32.87830393275682</span>
<span>    </span><span>},</span>
<span>    </span><span>"panelID"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>2620732</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"rowArea"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>29.1</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"rowAzimuth"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>174.62</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"rowLength"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>12.77</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"rowMount"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"fixed_axis"</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"rowSpace"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>8.42</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"rowWidth"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>3.0</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>"version"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"v1.0"</span>
<span>  </span><span>}</span>
<span>]</span>
</pre></div>
<p>Below are the field names, data types, percentages of NULLs per column, number of unique values and minimum and maximum values for each column.</p>

<div><pre><span></span><span>SELECT</span><span>   </span><span>column_name</span><span>,</span>
<span>         </span><span>column_type</span><span>,</span>
<span>         </span><span>null_percentage</span><span>,</span>
<span>         </span><span>approx_unique</span><span>,</span>
<span>         </span><span>min</span><span>,</span>
<span>         </span><span>max</span>
<span>FROM</span><span>     </span><span>(</span><span>SUMMARIZE</span>
<span>          </span><span>FROM</span><span> </span><span>READ_PARQUET</span><span>(</span><span>'panels.parquet'</span><span>))</span>
<span>WHERE</span><span>    </span><span>column_name</span><span> </span><span>!=</span><span> </span><span>'geometry'</span>
<span>AND</span><span>      </span><span>column_name</span><span> </span><span>!=</span><span> </span><span>'bbox'</span>
<span>ORDER</span><span> </span><span>BY</span><span> </span><span>1</span><span>;</span>
</pre></div>
<div><pre><span></span>┌─────────────┬─────────────┬─────────────────┬───────────────┬───────────────┬─────────────┐
│ column_name │ column_type │ null_percentage │ approx_unique │      min      │     max     │
│   varchar   │   varchar   │  decimal(9,2)   │     int64     │    varchar    │   varchar   │
├─────────────┼─────────────┼─────────────────┼───────────────┼───────────────┼─────────────┤
│ Source      │ VARCHAR     │            0.00 │             3 │ CCVPV         │ gmseus      │
│ arrayID     │ DOUBLE      │            0.08 │          9451 │ 1.0           │ 15017.0     │
│ panelID     │ BIGINT      │            0.00 │       2703164 │ 1             │ 2917782     │
│ rowArea     │ DOUBLE      │            0.00 │         88974 │ 15.01         │ 1999.76     │
│ rowAzimuth  │ DOUBLE      │            0.00 │         14901 │ 90.0          │ 270.0       │
│ rowLength   │ DOUBLE      │            0.00 │         26759 │ 4.02          │ 530.05      │
│ rowMount    │ VARCHAR     │            0.00 │             3 │ dual_axis     │ single_axis │
│ rowSpace    │ DOUBLE      │            0.17 │         13376 │ 7.4765186e-08 │ 20.0        │
│ rowWidth    │ DOUBLE      │            0.00 │          1863 │ 0.45          │ 102.14      │
│ version     │ VARCHAR     │            0.00 │             1 │ v1.0          │ v1.0        │
├─────────────┴─────────────┴─────────────────┴───────────────┴───────────────┴─────────────┤
│ 10 rows                                                                         6 columns │
└───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────┘
</pre></div>
<p>Below is the relationship between the sources of data and the row mount.</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>PIVOT</span><span>    </span><span>'panels.parquet'</span>
<span>ON</span><span>       </span><span>Source</span>
<span>USING</span><span>    </span><span>COUNT</span><span>(</span><span>*</span><span>)</span>
<span>GROUP</span><span> </span><span>BY</span><span> </span><span>rowMount</span>
<span>ORDER</span><span> </span><span>BY</span><span> </span><span>rowMount</span><span>;</span>
</pre></div>
<div><pre><span></span>┌─────────────┬────────┬────────┬─────────┐
│  rowMount   │ CCVPV  │  OSM   │ gmseus  │
│   varchar   │ int64  │ int64  │  int64  │
├─────────────┼────────┼────────┼─────────┤
│ dual_axis   │     44 │   5975 │   80225 │
│ fixed_axis  │  13344 │ 118639 │  163512 │
│ single_axis │ 189699 │ 743371 │ 1602973 │
└─────────────┴────────┴────────┴─────────┘
</pre></div>
<p>Of the 15,017 arrays in this dataset, only 5,358 have any panels in them.</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>.</span><span>maxrows</span><span> </span><span>20</span>

<span>SELECT</span><span>   </span><span>a</span><span>.</span><span>arrayID</span><span>,</span>
<span>         </span><span>COUNT</span><span>(</span><span>DISTINCT</span><span> </span><span>b</span><span>.</span><span>panelID</span><span>)</span>
<span>FROM</span><span>     </span><span>READ_PARQUET</span><span>(</span><span>'arrays.parquet'</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>a</span>
<span>JOIN</span><span>     </span><span>READ_PARQUET</span><span>(</span><span>'panels.parquet'</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>b</span>
<span>ON</span><span>       </span><span>ST_COVERS</span><span>(</span><span>a</span><span>.</span><span>geometry</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>b</span><span>.</span><span>geometry</span><span>)</span>
<span>GROUP</span><span> </span><span>BY</span><span> </span><span>a</span><span>.</span><span>arrayID</span>
<span>ORDER</span><span> </span><span>BY</span><span> </span><span>2</span><span> </span><span>DESC</span><span>;</span>
</pre></div>
<div><pre><span></span>┌─────────┬───────────────────────────┐
│ arrayID │ count(DISTINCT b.panelID) │
│  int64  │           int64           │
├─────────┼───────────────────────────┤
│   11958 │                     56762 │
│   14225 │                     51140 │
│   12162 │                     43741 │
│   12433 │                     37304 │
│   14461 │                     31898 │
│   13229 │                     30093 │
│    6589 │                     27080 │
│   13329 │                     25120 │
│   12597 │                     24054 │
│   12224 │                     23449 │
│      ·  │                         · │
│      ·  │                         · │
│      ·  │                         · │
│    1792 │                         1 │
│    2286 │                         1 │
│     863 │                         1 │
│    1816 │                         1 │
│    8997 │                         1 │
│   12358 │                         1 │
│    6564 │                         1 │
│    3845 │                         1 │
│    6574 │                         1 │
│     991 │                         1 │
├─────────┴───────────────────────────┤
│ 5358 rows (20 shown)      2 columns │
└─────────────────────────────────────┘
</pre></div>
<p>Below is a solar farm in Nevada where some arrays have panels and others do not.</p>
<p><a href="https://tech.marksblogg.com/theme/images/gmseus/qgis-bin_qWE8hm28IE.jpg">
<img alt="US Solar Farms" src="https://tech.marksblogg.com/theme/images/gmseus/qgis-bin_qWE8hm28IE.jpg">
</a></p><p>I was interested in seeing the solar farm with 56K panels. Below are its coordinates.</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>SELECT</span><span> </span><span>ST_CENTROID</span><span>(</span><span>geometry</span><span>)</span>
<span>FROM</span><span>   </span><span>'arrays.parquet'</span>
<span>WHERE</span><span>  </span><span>arrayID</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>11958</span><span>;</span>
</pre></div>
<div><pre><span></span>┌────────────────────────────────────────────────┐
│             st_centroid(geometry)              │
│                    geometry                    │
├────────────────────────────────────────────────┤
│ POINT (-115.34248808114013 35.611919498003175) │
└────────────────────────────────────────────────┘
</pre></div>
<p>Even this has arrays without marked panels.</p>
<p><a href="https://tech.marksblogg.com/theme/images/gmseus/qgis-bin_9TpwvNOgbF.jpg">
<img alt="US Solar Farms" src="https://tech.marksblogg.com/theme/images/gmseus/qgis-bin_9TpwvNOgbF.jpg">
</a></p><p>I'm looking forward to v2 of this dataset with better panel detection. It'll be great to get a good approximation of how many are deployed in the US.</p>
</div>

        </div><p>
            Thank you for taking the time to read this post. I offer both consulting and hands-on development services to clients in North America and Europe. If you'd like to discuss how my offerings can help your business please contact me via <a href="https://uk.linkedin.com/in/marklitwintschik/">LinkedIn</a>.
        </p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Modern Linux tools (194 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ikrima.dev/dev-notes/linux/linux-modern-tools/</link>
            <guid>45566548</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 09:44:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ikrima.dev/dev-notes/linux/linux-modern-tools/">https://ikrima.dev/dev-notes/linux/linux-modern-tools/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45566548">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-md-component="main">
              <article>
                
                  

  
    <a href="https://github.com/ikrima/gamedevguide/blob/master/docs/dev-notes/linux/linux-modern-tools.md" title="Edit this page">
      
      <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 24 24"><path d="M10 20H6V4h7v5h5v3.1l2-2V8l-6-6H6c-1.1 0-2 .9-2 2v16c0 1.1.9 2 2 2h4zm10.2-7c.1 0 .3.1.4.2l1.3 1.3c.2.2.2.6 0 .8l-1 1-2.1-2.1 1-1c.1-.1.2-.2.4-.2m0 3.9L14.1 23H12v-2.1l6.1-6.1z"></path></svg>
    </a>
  
  
    
      
    
    <a href="https://github.com/ikrima/gamedevguide/raw/master/docs/dev-notes/linux/linux-modern-tools.md" title="View source of this page">
      
      <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 24 24"><path d="M17 18c.56 0 1 .44 1 1s-.44 1-1 1-1-.44-1-1 .44-1 1-1m0-3c-2.73 0-5.06 1.66-6 4 .94 2.34 3.27 4 6 4s5.06-1.66 6-4c-.94-2.34-3.27-4-6-4m0 6.5a2.5 2.5 0 0 1-2.5-2.5 2.5 2.5 0 0 1 2.5-2.5 2.5 2.5 0 0 1 2.5 2.5 2.5 2.5 0 0 1-2.5 2.5M9.27 20H6V4h7v5h5v4.07c.7.08 1.36.25 2 .49V8l-6-6H6a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4.5a8.2 8.2 0 0 1-1.23-2"></path></svg>
    </a>
  



<h2 id="other-resources">Other Resources<a href="#other-resources" title="Permanent link">#</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ibraheemdev/modern-unix">modern unix</a>: modern/faster/saner alternatives to common unix commands</li>
<li><a href="https://jvns.ca/blog/2022/04/12/a-list-of-new-ish--command-line-tools/">new(ish) command line tools</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/trimstray/the-book-of-secret-knowledge">book of secret knowledge</a>: various materials/cheatsheets/tools</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/luong-komorebi/Awesome-Linux-Software">awesome linux software</a>: awesome list of linux apps</li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/List_of_applications/Utilities">archlinux utilities</a>: comprehensive list with descriptions</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="cli-replacements">CLI Replacements<a href="#cli-replacements" title="Permanent link">#</a></h2>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/sharkdp/bat"><code>bat</code></a></td>
<td><code>cat</code> clone with syntax highlighting and <code>git</code> integration</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/ogham/exa"><code>exa</code></a></td>
<td>modern replacement for <code>ls</code>/<code>tree</code>, not maintained</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/eza-community/eza/"><code>eza</code></a></td>
<td>modern <code>ls</code>/<code>tree</code> based on <code>exa</code> fork</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/Peltoche/lsd"><code>lsd</code></a></td>
<td>next gen <code>ls</code>, backwards compatible</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/dandavison/delta"><code>delta</code></a></td>
<td>viewer for <code>git</code> and <code>diff</code> output</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://dev.yorhel.nl/ncdu"><code>ncdu</code></a></td>
<td>intuitive <code>du</code> with ncurses interface</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/bootandy/dust"><code>dust</code></a></td>
<td>more intuitive version of <code>du</code> written in rust</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/muesli/duf"><code>duf</code></a></td>
<td>better <code>df</code> alternative</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/Canop/broot"><code>broot</code></a></td>
<td>better <code>tree</code> with navigation support</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/sharkdp/fd"><code>fd</code></a></td>
<td>simple, fast and user-friendly alternative to <code>find</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/BurntSushi/ripgrep"><code>ripgrep</code></a></td>
<td>extremely fast alternative to <code>grep</code> that respects your gitignore</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/ggreer/the_silver_searcher"><code>ag</code></a></td>
<td>code searching tool similar to <code>ack</code>, but faster</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/junegunn/fzf"><code>fzf</code></a></td>
<td>general purpose command-line fuzzy <code>find</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/tavianator/bfs"><code>bfs</code></a></td>
<td>breadth-first <code>find</code> alternative</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/cantino/mcfly"><code>mcfly</code></a></td>
<td>fly through your shell <code>history</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/theryangeary/choose"><code>choose</code></a></td>
<td>human-friendly and fast alternative to <code>cut</code> and (sometimes) <code>awk</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/stedolan/jq"><code>jq</code></a></td>
<td><code>sed</code> for JSON data</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/chmln/sd"><code>sd</code></a></td>
<td>intuitive find/replace CLI. <code>sed</code> alternative</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/ClementTsang/bottom"><code>bottom</code></a></td>
<td>another cross-platform graphical process/system monitor</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/nicolargo/glances"><code>glances</code></a></td>
<td><code>top</code>/<code>htop</code> alternative</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/aksakalli/gtop"><code>gtop</code></a></td>
<td>System monitoring dashboard for terminal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/sharkdp/hyperfine"><code>hyperfine</code></a></td>
<td>command-line benchmarking tool</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/orf/gping"><code>gping</code></a></td>
<td><code>ping</code> with a graph</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/dalance/procs"><code>procs</code></a></td>
<td><code>ps</code> rust replacement</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/httpie/httpie"><code>httpie</code></a></td>
<td>modern, user-friendly command-line HTTP client for the API era</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/rs/curlie"><code>curlie</code></a></td>
<td>power of <code>curl</code>, the ease of use of <code>httpie</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/ducaale/xh"><code>xh</code></a></td>
<td>performance focused alternative of <code>httpie</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/ajeetdsouza/zoxide"><code>zoxide</code></a></td>
<td>smarter <code>cd</code> command inspired by <code>z</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/zyedidia/micro"><code>micro</code></a></td>
<td>modern terminal text editor</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/jarun/nnn"><code>nnn</code></a></td>
<td>fast lean terminal file manager</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/akavel/up"><code>up</code></a></td>
<td>pipes with instant live preview</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://www.mankier.com/"><code>ManKier</code></a></td>
<td>explain shell command with concise pretty man pages</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/tldr-pages/tldr"><code>tldr</code></a></td>
<td>concise <code>man</code> pages with practical examples</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/dbrgn/tealdeer"><code>tealdeer</code></a></td>
<td><code>tldr</code> fast rust implementation</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://explainshell.com/"><code>explainshell</code></a></td>
<td>match command-line arguments to their help text</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://cheat.sh/"><code>cheat.sh</code></a></td>
<td>unified <code>cheatsheets</code> with <code>tldr</code> pages</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/baobab"><code>baobab</code></a></td>
<td>gui disk usage analyzer</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/oguzhaninan/Stacer"><code>stacer</code></a></td>
<td>gui system optimizer/monitoring</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>







  
    
  
  
    
  


  


  




                
              </article>
            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Spotlight on pdfly, the Swiss Army knife for PDF files (287 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://chezsoi.org/lucas/blog/spotlight-on-pdfly.html</link>
            <guid>45566139</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 08:36:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://chezsoi.org/lucas/blog/spotlight-on-pdfly.html">https://chezsoi.org/lucas/blog/spotlight-on-pdfly.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45566139">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-uk-grid-margin="">

    <!-- With microformats2 support: -->
    <article>
        
        <p>
            <time datetime="2025-10-13" itemprop="datePublished">Mon 13 October 2025</time>
            <a title="permalink" href="https://chezsoi.org/lucas/blog/spotlight-on-pdfly.html">🔗</a>
            
        </p>


        
        <section itemprop="articleBody"><p><img alt="pdfly logo" src="https://chezsoi.org/lucas/blog/images/2025/10/pdfly-logo.png"></p>
<p>Project documentation: <a href="https://pdfly.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">pdfly.readthedocs.io</a></p>
<p><code>pdfly</code> is the youngest project of the <a href="https://py-pdf.github.io/"><code>py-pdf</code></a> organization.
It has been created by <a href="https://github.com/martinthoma">Martin Thoma</a> in 2022.</p>
<p>It's simply <strong>a CLI tool to manipulate PDF files</strong>, written in Python and based on the <a href="https://py-pdf.github.io/fpdf2/">fpdf2</a> &amp; <a href="https://pypdf.readthedocs.io/en/stable/">pypdf</a> libraries.</p>
<p>I'm a maintainer of the project 🙂</p>
<h2>What can it do?</h2>
<p>It has meany features, including:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>display PDF metadata</strong> using <a href="https://pdfly.readthedocs.io/en/latest/user/subcommand-meta.html"><code>pdfly meta</code></a> and <a href="https://pdfly.readthedocs.io/en/latest/user/subcommand-pagemeta.html"><code>pdfly pagemeta</code></a> commands.
Example:</li>
</ul>
<div><pre><span></span><code>$<span> </span>pdfly<span> </span>meta<span> </span>minimal-document.pdf
<span>                      </span>Operating<span> </span>System<span> </span>Data
┏━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━┳━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━┓
┃<span>         </span>Attribute<span> </span>┃<span> </span>Value<span>                     </span>┃
┡━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━╇━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━┩
│<span>         </span>File<span> </span>Name<span> </span>│<span> </span>/tmp/minimal-document.pdf<span> </span>│
│<span>  </span>File<span> </span>Permissions<span> </span>│<span> </span>-rw-r--r--<span>                </span>│
│<span>         </span>File<span> </span>Size<span> </span>│<span> </span><span>16</span>,978<span> </span>bytes<span>              </span>│
│<span>     </span>Creation<span> </span>Time<span> </span>│<span> </span><span>2025</span>-10-13<span> </span><span>09</span>:44:32<span>       </span>│
│<span> </span>Modification<span> </span>Time<span> </span>│<span> </span><span>2025</span>-10-13<span> </span><span>09</span>:44:32<span>       </span>│
│<span>       </span>Access<span> </span>Time<span> </span>│<span> </span><span>2025</span>-10-13<span> </span><span>09</span>:44:46<span>       </span>│
└───────────────────┴───────────────────────────┘
<span>                       </span>PDF<span> </span>Data
┏━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━┳━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━┓
┃<span>          </span>Attribute<span> </span>┃<span> </span>Value<span>                                                    </span>┃
┡━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━╇━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━┩
│<span>       </span>CreationDate<span> </span>│<span> </span><span>2022</span>-04-03<span> </span><span>18</span>:05:42+02:00<span>                                </span>│
│<span>            </span>Creator<span> </span>│<span> </span>TeX<span>                                                      </span>│
│<span>           </span>Producer<span> </span>│<span> </span>pdfTeX-1.40.23<span>                                           </span>│
│<span>              </span>Pages<span> </span>│<span> </span><span>1</span><span>                                                        </span>│
│<span>          </span>Encrypted<span> </span>│<span> </span>None<span>                                                     </span>│
│<span>   </span>PDF<span> </span>File<span> </span>Version<span> </span>│<span> </span>%PDF-1.5<span>                                                 </span>│
│<span>        </span>Page<span> </span>Layout<span> </span>│<span>                                                          </span>│
│<span>          </span>Page<span> </span>Mode<span> </span>│<span>                                                          </span>│
│<span>             </span>PDF<span> </span>ID<span> </span>│<span> </span><span>ID1</span><span>=</span>b<span>'q\x96\xc3\xe3U\xc1|\x9fS\xba\x9a\r\xcap\xcd\xd0'</span><span>   </span>│
│<span>                    </span>│<span> </span><span>ID2</span><span>=</span>b<span>'q\x96\xc3\xe3U\xc1|\x9fS\xba\x9a\r\xcap\xcd\xd0'</span><span>   </span>│
│<span> </span>Fonts<span> </span><span>(</span>embedded<span>)</span><span> </span>│<span>                                                          </span>│
│<span>   </span>Fonts<span> </span><span>(</span>embedded<span>)</span><span> </span>│<span> </span>/KNEUFH+CMR10<span>                                            </span>│
│<span>        </span>Attachments<span> </span>│<span> </span><span>[]</span><span>                                                       </span>│
│<span>             </span>Images<span> </span>│<span> </span><span>0</span><span> </span>images<span> </span><span>(</span><span>0</span><span> </span>bytes<span>)</span><span>                                       </span>│
└────────────────────┴──────────────────────────────────────────────────────────┘
</code></pre></div>

<ul>
<li>
<p><code>pdfly</code> can also combine files into new PDF documents: it can <strong>extract specific pages &amp; merge documents</strong> (<a href="https://pdfly.readthedocs.io/en/latest/user/subcommand-cat.html"><code>pdfly cat</code></a>); selectively <strong>remove pages</strong> (<a href="https://pdfly.readthedocs.io/en/latest/user/subcommand-rm.html"><code>pdfly rm</code></a>); <strong>convert images to PDF documents</strong> (<a href="https://pdfly.readthedocs.io/en/latest/user/subcommand-x2pdf.html"><code>pdfly x2pdf</code></a>); and even <strong>compress documents</strong> (<a href="https://pdfly.readthedocs.io/en/latest/user/subcommand-compress.html"><code>pdfly compress</code></a>) or <strong>build booklets</strong> (<a href="https://pdfly.readthedocs.io/en/latest/user/subcommand-2-up.html"><code>pdfly 2-up</code></a> &amp; <a href="https://pdfly.readthedocs.io/en/latest/user/subcommand-booklet.html"><code>pdfly booklet</code></a>).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><code>pdfly</code> includes some commands to <strong>pull out specific content from PDF files</strong>: <a href="https://pdfly.readthedocs.io/en/latest/user/subcommand-extract-images.html"><code>pdfly extract-images</code></a> &amp; <a href="https://pdfly.readthedocs.io/en/latest/user/subcommand-extract-text.html"><code>pdfly extract-annotated-text</code></a>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>sometimes you want to edit a PDF file manually, in a text editor.
But when you do so, you break its <code>xref</code> table, that is an index of byte offsets in the document. <a href="https://pdfly.readthedocs.io/en/latest/user/subcommand-update-offsets.html"><code>pdfly update-offsets</code></a> is there to save the day, <strong>fixing manually-edited PDF documents</strong>, so that they can be opened in a PDF viewer again!</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2>Release 0.5.0 &amp; new features</h2>
<p>Today we released a new version: <a href="https://github.com/py-pdf/pdfly/releases/tag/0.5.0"><code>pdfly release 0.5.0</code></a>.</p>
<p>Thanks to several contributors, including developers taking part in <a href="https://hacktoberfest.com/">Hacktoberfest</a>, new exciting features have been added:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://pdfly.readthedocs.io/en/latest/user/subcommand-sign.html"><code>pdfly sign</code></a> allows you to <strong>easily sign PDF documents</strong>, while <a href="https://pdfly.readthedocs.io/en/latest/user/subcommand-sign.html"><code>pdfly check-sign</code></a> makes it easy to check a PDF document signature. Thanks to <a href="https://github.com/moormaster">@moormaster</a> for implementing this in PRs <a href="https://github.com/py-pdf/pdfly/pull/165">#165</a> &amp; <a href="https://github.com/py-pdf/pdfly/pull/166">#166</a> 👍🙏.</li>
<li><a href="https://pdfly.readthedocs.io/en/latest/user/subcommand-extract-annotated-pages.html"><code>pdfly extract-annotated-pages</code></a> <strong>extract only annotated pages</strong> from a PDF, hence helping to review or rework pages from a large document iteratively. Thanks to <a href="https://github.com/hwine">Hal Wine (@hwine)</a> for implementing this in PR <a href="https://github.com/py-pdf/pdfly/pull/128">#128</a> 👍🙏.</li>
<li><a href="https://pdfly.readthedocs.io/en/latest/user/subcommand-rotate.html"><code>pdfly rotate</code></a> <strong>rotate specific pages</strong> of a document. Thanks to <a href="https://github.com/wolfram77">Subhajit Sahu (@wolfram77)</a> for implementing this in PR <a href="https://github.com/py-pdf/pdfly/pull/98">#98</a> 👍🙏.</li>
</ul>
<h2>What's next?</h2>
<p>We have a bunch of feature ideas: <a href="https://github.com/py-pdf/pdfly/issues?q=is%3Aissue%20state%3Aopen%20label%3Aup-for-grabs"><code>up-for-grabs</code> issues</a>, including some <a href="https://github.com/py-pdf/pdfly/issues?q=is%3Aissue%20state%3Aopen%20label%3A%22good%20first%20issue%22"><code>good first issues</code></a> aimed specially at <strong>new contributors</strong>, that are willing to help but new to open-source.</p>
<p>Personally, I think the <code>pdfly sign</code> &amp; <code>check-sign</code> could become handy to many end-users, and I think we should continue to extend those commands usage options, as described in <a href="https://github.com/py-pdf/pdfly/issues/71">issue #71</a>.</p>
<p>We would also be happy to get your feedbacks, bug reports &amp; feature suggestions! 🙂</p>
<!--
Com':
* [ ] https://dev.to/lucasc/
* [ ] https://news.ycombinator.com/
* [ ] https://www.reddit.com/r/hacktoberfest/
--></section>
        <hr>
    </article>

    


    
    

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HTTP3 Explained (168 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://http3-explained.haxx.se</link>
            <guid>45565646</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 07:15:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://http3-explained.haxx.se">https://http3-explained.haxx.se</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45565646">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><header id="site-header"><div><div><a href="https://http3-explained.haxx.se/"><img alt="" fetchpriority="high" src="https://http3-explained.haxx.se/~gitbook/image?url=https%3A%2F%2F3391341413-files.gitbook.io%2F%7E%2Ffiles%2Fv0%2Fb%2Fgitbook-legacy-files%2Fo%2Fspaces%252F-LvW30M9uwlSh6noqzxa%252Favatar.png%3Fgeneration%3D1578309610234856%26alt%3Dmedia&amp;width=32&amp;dpr=4&amp;quality=100&amp;sign=781f94f0&amp;sv=2" srcset="https://http3-explained.haxx.se/~gitbook/image?url=https%3A%2F%2F3391341413-files.gitbook.io%2F%7E%2Ffiles%2Fv0%2Fb%2Fgitbook-legacy-files%2Fo%2Fspaces%252F-LvW30M9uwlSh6noqzxa%252Favatar.png%3Fgeneration%3D1578309610234856%26alt%3Dmedia&amp;width=32&amp;dpr=1&amp;quality=100&amp;sign=781f94f0&amp;sv=2 32w, https://http3-explained.haxx.se/~gitbook/image?url=https%3A%2F%2F3391341413-files.gitbook.io%2F%7E%2Ffiles%2Fv0%2Fb%2Fgitbook-legacy-files%2Fo%2Fspaces%252F-LvW30M9uwlSh6noqzxa%252Favatar.png%3Fgeneration%3D1578309610234856%26alt%3Dmedia&amp;width=32&amp;dpr=2&amp;quality=100&amp;sign=781f94f0&amp;sv=2 64w, https://http3-explained.haxx.se/~gitbook/image?url=https%3A%2F%2F3391341413-files.gitbook.io%2F%7E%2Ffiles%2Fv0%2Fb%2Fgitbook-legacy-files%2Fo%2Fspaces%252F-LvW30M9uwlSh6noqzxa%252Favatar.png%3Fgeneration%3D1578309610234856%26alt%3Dmedia&amp;width=32&amp;dpr=3&amp;quality=100&amp;sign=781f94f0&amp;sv=2 96w, https://http3-explained.haxx.se/~gitbook/image?url=https%3A%2F%2F3391341413-files.gitbook.io%2F%7E%2Ffiles%2Fv0%2Fb%2Fgitbook-legacy-files%2Fo%2Fspaces%252F-LvW30M9uwlSh6noqzxa%252Favatar.png%3Fgeneration%3D1578309610234856%26alt%3Dmedia&amp;width=32&amp;dpr=4&amp;quality=100&amp;sign=781f94f0&amp;sv=2 128w" sizes="32px" width="256" height="256"><img alt="" loading="lazy" fetchpriority="high" src="https://http3-explained.haxx.se/~gitbook/image?url=https%3A%2F%2F3391341413-files.gitbook.io%2F%7E%2Ffiles%2Fv0%2Fb%2Fgitbook-legacy-files%2Fo%2Fspaces%252F-LvW30M9uwlSh6noqzxa%252Favatar.png%3Fgeneration%3D1578309610234856%26alt%3Dmedia&amp;width=32&amp;dpr=4&amp;quality=100&amp;sign=781f94f0&amp;sv=2" srcset="https://http3-explained.haxx.se/~gitbook/image?url=https%3A%2F%2F3391341413-files.gitbook.io%2F%7E%2Ffiles%2Fv0%2Fb%2Fgitbook-legacy-files%2Fo%2Fspaces%252F-LvW30M9uwlSh6noqzxa%252Favatar.png%3Fgeneration%3D1578309610234856%26alt%3Dmedia&amp;width=32&amp;dpr=1&amp;quality=100&amp;sign=781f94f0&amp;sv=2 32w, https://http3-explained.haxx.se/~gitbook/image?url=https%3A%2F%2F3391341413-files.gitbook.io%2F%7E%2Ffiles%2Fv0%2Fb%2Fgitbook-legacy-files%2Fo%2Fspaces%252F-LvW30M9uwlSh6noqzxa%252Favatar.png%3Fgeneration%3D1578309610234856%26alt%3Dmedia&amp;width=32&amp;dpr=2&amp;quality=100&amp;sign=781f94f0&amp;sv=2 64w, https://http3-explained.haxx.se/~gitbook/image?url=https%3A%2F%2F3391341413-files.gitbook.io%2F%7E%2Ffiles%2Fv0%2Fb%2Fgitbook-legacy-files%2Fo%2Fspaces%252F-LvW30M9uwlSh6noqzxa%252Favatar.png%3Fgeneration%3D1578309610234856%26alt%3Dmedia&amp;width=32&amp;dpr=3&amp;quality=100&amp;sign=781f94f0&amp;sv=2 96w, https://http3-explained.haxx.se/~gitbook/image?url=https%3A%2F%2F3391341413-files.gitbook.io%2F%7E%2Ffiles%2Fv0%2Fb%2Fgitbook-legacy-files%2Fo%2Fspaces%252F-LvW30M9uwlSh6noqzxa%252Favatar.png%3Fgeneration%3D1578309610234856%26alt%3Dmedia&amp;width=32&amp;dpr=4&amp;quality=100&amp;sign=781f94f0&amp;sv=2 128w" sizes="32px" width="256" height="256"><div>HTTP/3 explained</div></a></div><div><svg style="mask-image:url(https://ka-p.fontawesome.com/releases/v6.6.0/svgs/regular/magnifying-glass.svg?v=2&amp;token=a463935e93);-webkit-mask-image:url(https://ka-p.fontawesome.com/releases/v6.6.0/svgs/regular/magnifying-glass.svg?v=2&amp;token=a463935e93);mask-repeat:no-repeat;-webkit-mask-repeat:no-repeat;mask-position:center;-webkit-mask-position:center"></svg><div aria-busy="true"><kbd>Ctrl</kbd><kbd>K</kbd></div></div></div></header><div><main><header><h2>README</h2></header><!--$--><div><p><strong>HTTP/3 explained</strong> is a collaborative effort to document the HTTP/3 and the QUIC protocols. Join in and help!</p><p>Get the Web or PDF versions on <a href="https://http3-explained.haxx.se/">http3-explained.haxx.se<svg style="mask-image:url(https://ka-p.fontawesome.com/releases/v6.6.0/svgs/regular/arrow-up-right.svg?v=2&amp;token=a463935e93);-webkit-mask-image:url(https://ka-p.fontawesome.com/releases/v6.6.0/svgs/regular/arrow-up-right.svg?v=2&amp;token=a463935e93);mask-repeat:no-repeat;-webkit-mask-repeat:no-repeat;mask-position:center;-webkit-mask-position:center"></svg></a>.</p><p>The contents get updated automatically on every commit to this git repository.</p><div><picture><div><img data-testid="zoom-image" alt="" fetchpriority="high" src="https://http3-explained.haxx.se/~gitbook/image?url=https%3A%2F%2F3391341413-files.gitbook.io%2F%7E%2Ffiles%2Fv0%2Fb%2Fgitbook-legacy-files%2Fo%2Fassets%252F-LvW30M9uwlSh6noqzxa%252F-LvW31Pn1JTBepfnVcl_%252F-LvW3CUoDXkyB-gANFOO%252Fcover_small.jpg%3Fgeneration%3D1575734014557742%26alt%3Dmedia&amp;width=768&amp;dpr=4&amp;quality=100&amp;sign=e02eac3a&amp;sv=2" srcset="https://http3-explained.haxx.se/~gitbook/image?url=https%3A%2F%2F3391341413-files.gitbook.io%2F%7E%2Ffiles%2Fv0%2Fb%2Fgitbook-legacy-files%2Fo%2Fassets%252F-LvW30M9uwlSh6noqzxa%252F-LvW31Pn1JTBepfnVcl_%252F-LvW3CUoDXkyB-gANFOO%252Fcover_small.jpg%3Fgeneration%3D1575734014557742%26alt%3Dmedia&amp;width=400&amp;dpr=1&amp;quality=100&amp;sign=e02eac3a&amp;sv=2 400w, https://http3-explained.haxx.se/~gitbook/image?url=https%3A%2F%2F3391341413-files.gitbook.io%2F%7E%2Ffiles%2Fv0%2Fb%2Fgitbook-legacy-files%2Fo%2Fassets%252F-LvW30M9uwlSh6noqzxa%252F-LvW31Pn1JTBepfnVcl_%252F-LvW3CUoDXkyB-gANFOO%252Fcover_small.jpg%3Fgeneration%3D1575734014557742%26alt%3Dmedia&amp;width=400&amp;dpr=2&amp;quality=100&amp;sign=e02eac3a&amp;sv=2 800w, https://http3-explained.haxx.se/~gitbook/image?url=https%3A%2F%2F3391341413-files.gitbook.io%2F%7E%2Ffiles%2Fv0%2Fb%2Fgitbook-legacy-files%2Fo%2Fassets%252F-LvW30M9uwlSh6noqzxa%252F-LvW31Pn1JTBepfnVcl_%252F-LvW3CUoDXkyB-gANFOO%252Fcover_small.jpg%3Fgeneration%3D1575734014557742%26alt%3Dmedia&amp;width=400&amp;dpr=3&amp;quality=100&amp;sign=e02eac3a&amp;sv=2 1200w, https://http3-explained.haxx.se/~gitbook/image?url=https%3A%2F%2F3391341413-files.gitbook.io%2F%7E%2Ffiles%2Fv0%2Fb%2Fgitbook-legacy-files%2Fo%2Fassets%252F-LvW30M9uwlSh6noqzxa%252F-LvW31Pn1JTBepfnVcl_%252F-LvW3CUoDXkyB-gANFOO%252Fcover_small.jpg%3Fgeneration%3D1575734014557742%26alt%3Dmedia&amp;width=400&amp;dpr=4&amp;quality=100&amp;sign=e02eac3a&amp;sv=2 1600w, https://http3-explained.haxx.se/~gitbook/image?url=https%3A%2F%2F3391341413-files.gitbook.io%2F%7E%2Ffiles%2Fv0%2Fb%2Fgitbook-legacy-files%2Fo%2Fassets%252F-LvW30M9uwlSh6noqzxa%252F-LvW31Pn1JTBepfnVcl_%252F-LvW3CUoDXkyB-gANFOO%252Fcover_small.jpg%3Fgeneration%3D1575734014557742%26alt%3Dmedia&amp;width=768&amp;dpr=1&amp;quality=100&amp;sign=e02eac3a&amp;sv=2 768w, https://http3-explained.haxx.se/~gitbook/image?url=https%3A%2F%2F3391341413-files.gitbook.io%2F%7E%2Ffiles%2Fv0%2Fb%2Fgitbook-legacy-files%2Fo%2Fassets%252F-LvW30M9uwlSh6noqzxa%252F-LvW31Pn1JTBepfnVcl_%252F-LvW3CUoDXkyB-gANFOO%252Fcover_small.jpg%3Fgeneration%3D1575734014557742%26alt%3Dmedia&amp;width=768&amp;dpr=2&amp;quality=100&amp;sign=e02eac3a&amp;sv=2 1536w, https://http3-explained.haxx.se/~gitbook/image?url=https%3A%2F%2F3391341413-files.gitbook.io%2F%7E%2Ffiles%2Fv0%2Fb%2Fgitbook-legacy-files%2Fo%2Fassets%252F-LvW30M9uwlSh6noqzxa%252F-LvW31Pn1JTBepfnVcl_%252F-LvW3CUoDXkyB-gANFOO%252Fcover_small.jpg%3Fgeneration%3D1575734014557742%26alt%3Dmedia&amp;width=768&amp;dpr=3&amp;quality=100&amp;sign=e02eac3a&amp;sv=2 2304w, https://http3-explained.haxx.se/~gitbook/image?url=https%3A%2F%2F3391341413-files.gitbook.io%2F%7E%2Ffiles%2Fv0%2Fb%2Fgitbook-legacy-files%2Fo%2Fassets%252F-LvW30M9uwlSh6noqzxa%252F-LvW31Pn1JTBepfnVcl_%252F-LvW3CUoDXkyB-gANFOO%252Fcover_small.jpg%3Fgeneration%3D1575734014557742%26alt%3Dmedia&amp;width=768&amp;dpr=4&amp;quality=100&amp;sign=e02eac3a&amp;sv=2 3072w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 400px, 768px" width="200" height="262"></div><figcaption>HTTP/3 explained cover</figcaption></picture></div></div><!--/$--><div><a href="https://http3-explained.haxx.se/en"><span><span>Next</span><span>English</span></span><svg style="mask-image:url(https://ka-p.fontawesome.com/releases/v6.6.0/svgs/regular/chevron-right.svg?v=2&amp;token=a463935e93);-webkit-mask-image:url(https://ka-p.fontawesome.com/releases/v6.6.0/svgs/regular/chevron-right.svg?v=2&amp;token=a463935e93);mask-repeat:no-repeat;-webkit-mask-repeat:no-repeat;mask-position:center;-webkit-mask-position:center"></svg></a></div><div><p>Last updated <time data-visual-test="transparent" datetime="2023-10-24T06:06:49.592Z" data-state="closed">1 year ago</time></p><div><p>Was this helpful?</p></div></div></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Fastmail Desktop App (139 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.fastmail.com/blog/desktop-app/</link>
            <guid>45564619</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 04:14:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.fastmail.com/blog/desktop-app/">https://www.fastmail.com/blog/desktop-app/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45564619">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-pagefind-body="" data-cms-edit="content"> <p>Fastmail is now available as <a href="https://www.fastmail.com/download/">a dedicated desktop app for Mac, Windows, and Linux</a>. It’s the same Fastmail you know and love, now with the focus and convenience of a standalone app.</p> <p>With our desktop app you can:</p> <ul> <li>Launch Fastmail from your dock or taskbar and find it in your platform’s app switcher.</li> <li>Make Fastmail your default email client, so email links create a new message directly in Fastmail.</li> <li>Work whenever, wherever, with full offline support, just like our mobile apps. You can always read your mail, manage your calendar, and write replies — your changes sync back seamlessly when you reconnect.</li> </ul> <p><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://www.fastmail.com/assets/images/desktop-mac-screenshot-TFHw8lzi3I-375.webp 375w, https://www.fastmail.com/assets/images/desktop-mac-screenshot-TFHw8lzi3I-750.webp 750w, https://www.fastmail.com/assets/images/desktop-mac-screenshot-TFHw8lzi3I-1500.webp 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 425px) 375px, 750px"><img alt="Desktop app screenshot on a Mac" loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.fastmail.com/assets/images/desktop-mac-screenshot-TFHw8lzi3I-375.png" width="1500" height="989" srcset="https://www.fastmail.com/assets/images/desktop-mac-screenshot-TFHw8lzi3I-375.png 375w, https://www.fastmail.com/assets/images/desktop-mac-screenshot-TFHw8lzi3I-750.png 750w, https://www.fastmail.com/assets/images/desktop-mac-screenshot-TFHw8lzi3I-1500.png 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 425px) 375px, 750px"></picture></p> <p>Whether you’re on macOS, Windows, or your favourite Linux distribution, you’ll find the app feels right at home on your platform, with native notifications, menus, and system integrations.</p> <p>Getting started is simple. <a href="https://www.fastmail.com/download/">Download the app</a> for your platform, sign in with your Fastmail credentials, and you’re ready to go.</p> </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Despite what's happening in the USA, renewables are winning globally (156 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://thebulletin.org/2025/10/despite-whats-happening-in-the-usa-renewables-are-winning-globally/</link>
            <guid>45564077</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 02:15:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://thebulletin.org/2025/10/despite-whats-happening-in-the-usa-renewables-are-winning-globally/">https://thebulletin.org/2025/10/despite-whats-happening-in-the-usa-renewables-are-winning-globally/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45564077">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><em>Editor’s note: This story was originally published by </em><a href="https://grist.org/international/global-renewable-energy-report-2025-ember/">Grist</a>. <em>It appears here as part of the </em><a href="https://www.climatedesk.org/about-us/"><em>Climate Desk</em></a><em> collaboration. </em></p>
<p>If you live in the United States, you could be forgiven for thinking that renewable energy is on the outs. In July, <a href="https://grist.org/buildings/congress-is-killing-clean-energy-tax-credits-heres-how-to-use-them-before-they-disappear/">Congress voted to rapidly phase out longstanding tax credit support for wind and solar power</a>, and the Trump administration has taken seemingly every step in its power to halt the development of individual <a href="https://stateline.org/2025/09/16/trump-has-crushed-offshore-wind-plans-but-states-havent-quite-given-up-hope/">wind</a> and <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/climate-environment/2025/10/04/solar-energy-trump-trade-rules/">solar</a> projects—even as <a href="https://www.utilitydive.com/news/us-electricity-demand-to-grow-25-annually-thru-2035-bofa-institute/753911/">domestic electricity demand rises</a> and new sources of electricity become more important than ever.</p>
<p>But even as clean energy deployment hit roadblocks in the United States, the world overall set a new record for renewable energy investment over the first half of this year. Wind and solar power are meeting and even exceeding a global rise in energy demand. Indeed, electricity output from these sources is increasing faster than the world can use it, displacing some fossil fuel-generated power in the process. That’s according to a <a href="https://ember-energy.org/latest-insights/global-electricity-mid-year-insights-2025/">report published Tuesday by Ember</a>, a global energy think tank, which mapped this year’s global power supply by analyzing monthly data from 88 countries that are responsible for more than 90 percent of global electricity demand.</p>
<p>“Overall—we’re talking globally—renewables overtook coal,” said Malgorzata Wiatros-Motyka, a senior electricity analyst at Ember and a co-author of the company’s report. “And I expect this to hold.” This year marks the first time that renewable energy sources have outpowered coal in the global energy mix. In fact, <a href="https://apnews.com/article/climate-renewable-wind-solar-coal-electricity-demand-abf7b587b038bf7580de1baee6576bbc">global use of fossil fuels for electricity actually declined slightly</a>, compared to the same period in 2024.</p>
<p>Another <a href="https://www.iea.org/news/global-renewable-capacity-is-set-to-grow-strongly-driven-by-solar-pv">report published this week by the International Energy Agency</a>, or IEA, an intergovernmental energy research and policy organization, projects that the quantity of installed renewable power—meaning the maximum amount of energy that can be produced by systems like solar fields, hydroelectric dams, and wind turbines—will more than double by the end of this decade. National policies encouraging the development of green technology as well as astounding drops in the price of solar power—primarily driven by Chinese manufacturers, which <a href="https://www.iea.org/reports/solar-pv-global-supply-chains/executive-summary">build more than 80 percent of the world’s solar energy components</a>—are largely driving the transition.</p>
<p>And even that projection may be conservative.</p>
<p>“The IEA has, consistently over the last couple of decades, way underestimated how fast renewables are growing,” said Robert Brecha, a senior climate and energy adviser at Climate Analytics, a global climate science and policy institute, who was not involved in either the Ember or IEA report. “I don’t see any reason to believe that renewables won’t double by 2030.”</p>
<p>The vast majority of the renewable energy projected to go online in the coming years will come from solar, which already met more than 80 percent of new global energy demand in the first six months of 2025, according to the Ember report. In China, the largest renewable energy growth market in the world, and in India, which is on pace to become the second-largest market, a major uptick in solar energy output is responsible for a historic global decline in coal-generated power.</p>
<p>In the United States and the European Union, however, fossil fuel generation rose in the first half of this year. In Europe, poor wind conditions and drought, rather than state policies, took a bite out of the bloc’s wind and hydroelectric production, leading to a 14-percent rise in gas-fired power. Across the Atlantic, US coal-fired power generation rose 17 percent.</p>
<p>The policy outlook for renewables in the United States is so bleak that the IEA lowered the country’s renewable capacity growth expectations by 50 percent compared to last year’s projections. That US-driven dip drags down the agency’s global projections for renewable energy growth by 5 percent. Overall, however, the IEA still expects renewable energy capacity to grow even faster between 2025 and 2030 than it did between 2020 and 2025.</p>
<p>“They can slow it down; they can do a lot more damage than I thought they could,” said Brecha, referring to the <a href="https://www.hcn.org/articles/the-trump-administrations-war-on-wind/">Trump administration’s efforts to slow the growth of renewable energy</a>. “But they can’t stop it.”</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://thebulletin.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/ClimateDesk_logo-1-1.jpg.optimal.jpg" alt="" width="598" height="85" srcset="https://thebulletin.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/ClimateDesk_logo-1-1.jpg.optimal.jpg 598w, https://thebulletin.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/ClimateDesk_logo-1-1-300x43.jpg.optimal.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 598px) 100vw, 598px"></p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[For centuries massive meals amazed visitors to Korea (2019) (135 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.atlasobscura.com/articles/history-of-korean-food</link>
            <guid>45563900</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 01:46:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.atlasobscura.com/articles/history-of-korean-food">https://www.atlasobscura.com/articles/history-of-korean-food</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45563900">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.atlasobscura.com/articles/history-of-korean-food: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[John Searle has died (134 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/2025/10/12/books/john-searle-dead.html</link>
            <guid>45563627</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:57:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/10/12/books/john-searle-dead.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2025/10/12/books/john-searle-dead.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45563627">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nytimes.com/2025/10/12/books/john-searle-dead.html: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Wall Street is worried the private credit bubble will burst (101 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.thetimes.com/business-money/economics/article/wall-street-first-brands-private-credit-bubble-risk-363q2tcds</link>
            <guid>45562959</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2025 23:18:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.thetimes.com/business-money/economics/article/wall-street-first-brands-private-credit-bubble-risk-363q2tcds">https://www.thetimes.com/business-money/economics/article/wall-street-first-brands-private-credit-bubble-risk-363q2tcds</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45562959">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><p>We haven't been able to take payment</p><p>You must update your payment details via My Account or by clicking update payment details to keep your subscription.</p></div><div><p>Act now to keep your subscription</p><p>We've tried to contact you several times as we haven't been able to take payment. You must update your payment details via My Account or by clicking update payment details to keep your subscription.</p></div><div><p>Your subscription is due to terminate</p><p>We've tried to contact you several times as we haven't been able to take payment. You must update your payment details via My Account, otherwise your subscription will terminate.</p> </div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Free software hasn't won (345 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://dorotac.eu/posts/fosswon/</link>
            <guid>45562286</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2025 21:51:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://dorotac.eu/posts/fosswon/">https://dorotac.eu/posts/fosswon/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45562286">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

  <article>
    
      <p>This is a translated version of a talk I gave at <a href="https://piwo.sh/">P.I.W.O</a> in June, with cleanups and adjustments for the blog form.</p>

<p>…that doesn't sound right. I made the slides in <a href="https://inkscape.org/">Inkscape</a>, on a computer running <a href="https://kde.org/">KDE</a> and Linux, I use <a href="https://www.firefox.com/">Firefox</a> regularly. But maybe that's just me. What about you, are you using Free Software? Hands up! [hands go up in the audience] Of course! What nonsense, "Free Software hasn't won". Someone replaced my slides, hey conference staff!</p>
<p>**<strong>Staff:</strong>** *<em>The other folder.</em>*</p>
<p>[Browsing to a directory named "other folder", opening file called "your slides dimwit.pdf"]</p>
<p>Now, those are finally my slides.</p>
<p>Hello audience, my name is Dorota, and I'm going to talk about how</p>
<h2># Open Source has won.</h2>
<p>And that's not recent, the news has been out in 2008, and has been regularly repeated since by reputable press: <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/linux-and-open-source-have-won-get-over-it/">ZDNET</a>, <a href="https://www.linuxjournal.com/content/open-source-winning-and-now-its-time-people-win-too">Linux Journal</a>, <a href="https://www.wired.com/2016/08/open-source-won-now/">Wired</a>, and so on.</p>
<p>Those press articles list a multitude of examples to prove it.</p>
<p><img src="https://dorotac.eu/posts/fosswon/logos.svg" alt="Logos of businesses and project mentioned in the articles above"></p>
<p>Linux, Ruby, Red Hat, uh, GitHub? Does that mean I can download GitHub and run it on my own server? Microsoft? Come on, that's some kind of a joke. Those slides are manipulated! So what else do they contain? Oh, <a href="https://geoawesome.com/open-and-closed-source-who-wins-the-race/">this quote</a> is all right:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&gt; Open source won. It’s not that an enemy has been vanquished or that proprietary software is dead, there’s not much regarding adopting open source to argue about anymore. After more than a decade of the low-cost, lean startup culture successfully developing on open source tools, it’s clearly a legitimate, mainstream option for technology tools and innovation.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Oh, the name of the quoted person is wrong. Looks like an attack on my reputation! Anyways.</p>
<p>The point is, if we want to build something new, using Free Software is not a hindrance. And thats super important, because <a href="https://a16z.com/why-software-is-eating-the-world/">software is eating the world</a>. What does it mean? It means software keeps appearing in areas where there used to be no software before. That, in turn, means that we're slowly giving up control over more and more areas of life to those who made the software. After all, their software controls those areas of life from now on.</p>
<p>That's why it's great that there's always an alternative available, that we can select software that is free which grants control to us, and not just its manufacturer. So we have alternate <a href="https://fedoraproject.org/">operating systems</a> made with <a href="https://kernel.org/">Linux</a>. There are <a href="https://www.python.org/">very</a> <a href="https://rust-lang.org/">many</a> <a href="https://llvm.org/">programming</a> <a href="https://www.swi-prolog.org/">languages</a> <a href="https://isocpp.org/">to</a> <a href="https://www.scala-lang.org/">choose</a> <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript">from</a>. We can choose one of the <a href="https://zero-k.info/">open</a> <a href="http://openalchemist.free.fr/">games</a>, or <a href="https://krita.org/">graphics</a> or <a href="https://ardour.org/">audio creation</a> software without resorting to closed software.</p>
<p>Similarly, we don't need closed software to <a href="https://github.com/prusa3d/Prusa-Firmware-Buddy">print in 3D</a>, or to build a <a href="https://puri.sm/products/librem-5/">mobile computer</a> (also known as smartphone) or a <a href="https://github.com/InfiniTimeOrg/InfiniTime">smart watch</a>. There are graphics cards which run <a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Nouveau#Firmware">completely free of closed firmware</a> (Upon asking nouveau devs, they confirmed they wrote some firmware. Nvidia Kepler from 2012 is the last model where free firmware is allowed). There are such bicycles! Pretty much everyone owns one that rides without closed software. There are also sewing machines:</p>
<p><img src="https://dorotac.eu/posts/fosswon/sewing.png" alt="A fully mechanical sewing machine from the '90s"></p>
<p>There are comms systems:</p>
<p><img src="https://dorotac.eu/posts/fosswon/doorbell.png" alt="A doorbell/intercom for 20 flats like one you might remember from the '90s"></p>
<p>There are cars, and have been for a long time:</p>
<p><img src="https://dorotac.eu/posts/fosswon/beetle.jpg" alt="The classic half-century-old VW Beetle had no electronics inside"> <img src="https://dorotac.eu/posts/fosswon/lada.jpg" alt="So did some Lada models which were not impressive when they came out in the 1980s"></p>
<p>There are hard drives:</p>
<p>[the slides go blank]</p>
<p>There are wireless headphones, TVs... [slides remain blank] wait, something's wrong. There are phones! [Slides stay mockingly blank, noise of frantic clicking.]</p>
<p>[…]</p>
<p>[…]</p>
<p>[…]</p>
<p><img src="https://dorotac.eu/posts/fosswon/aster-72.jpg" alt="A pulse-dial Aster-72 rotary phone which belongs firmly in the 20th century"></p>
<p>Crap. This isn't right.</p>
<p><img src="https://dorotac.eu/posts/fosswon/schemat_Aster_RWT.jpg" alt="A yellow card showing the schematic of the Aster phone"></p>
<p>Oh, now I get it! The only kind of a phone that grants us openness is an analog phone. That reminds me of the time we were building the aforementioned Librem 5. There was a problem finding the modem for it. The reason is, one company controls the necessary patents necessary to connect to cellular networks. That company can and does impose arbitrary conditions on anyone using their integrated circuits. That made it very difficult to find modems that match our needs, and at the same time any reseller is willing to sell us. The resellers worried that by passing them on to us, they could break some distribution rule and not be able to get any modems in the future.</p>
<p>So that's a no. But I know what will be open for sure.</p>
<p><img src="https://dorotac.eu/posts/fosswon/GNU.png" alt="The stylized gnu logo of the GNU project"></p>
<p>Richard Stallman started an important project called <a href="https://www.gnu.org/">GNU</a> in 1983. In one of his <a href="https://en.linuxadictos.com/stallman-y-la-impresora-el-origen-de-las-licencias-libres-de-software.html">interviews</a>, as he describes how he started the project, he mentions a certain device that his university bought, but which didn't work very well. He wanted to improve it, but no one wanted to share the device's sources with him. That was an offense! Why wouldn't anyone share the code?</p>
<p>What was that device?</p>
<p>That was a printer. Considering that the GNU project started in 1983 and that the story's from 1981, it works out to over 40 years of fighting for printer freedom. So let's reveal our open alternative.</p>
<p><img src="https://dorotac.eu/posts/fosswon/Colored_pencils_chevre.jpg" alt="Colored pencils"></p>
<p>Oh come on. This cannot be. Have you ever used a printer? If you even manage to find a driver, if you even manage to connect to the printer, then it's still going to print single-sided black-and-white when you asked double-sided color. And despite having to put up with that, Free Software people still haven't gotten frustrated enough to solve the problem once and for all? Unbelievable.</p>
<p>I have a theory. People who say "Open Source has won" are only taking into account a small part of what software is out there. Take a look at this list: it's a map showing which kinds of software force you into running something closed (bold) and which have open options available (italics).</p>
<ul>
<li>Applications: *<em>Blender, Firefox, KiCAD</em>* – **<strong>Twitter, YouTube</strong>**</li>
<li>Operating System: *<em>GCC, Apache, OpenSSL</em>*</li>
<li>Kernel: *<em>Linux, Zephyr, FreeRTOS</em>*</li>
<li>Firmware: *<em><a href="https://coreboot.org/">Coreboot</a></em>* – **<strong>modem, GPU</strong>**</li>
<li>Appliances: *<em>Prusa 3D, <a href="https://github.com/airgradienthq/arduino">Airgradient</a></em>* – **<strong>washing machine, TV</strong>**</li>
</ul>
<p>What picture does this paint? Things programmers care about directly, like the OS and the kernel, are quite well covered. Whatever we need, there's an open version. Applications are also more or less fine. There's a Web browser, there's creativity software. The problem appears when you try to participate in social media. Sure, there are alternatives. But <a href="https://joinmastodon.org/">Mastodon</a>, or <a href="https://joinpeertube.org/">PeerTube</a> are separate networks from the closed ones, so they won't help much when trying to reach people who aren't yet using them.</p>
<p>Looking at the lower layers, like appliances or firmware, there seem to be options. But those options are limited to a couple niches, and with most things we buy, like a TV or a PC component – sorry, pal, there's simply no choice at all.</p>
<h2>## All the firmwares in the average laptop</h2>
<p>How many processors are there in a typical laptop? By "processor" I mean something that needs its own software. For example, a GPU has its own processor that needs software, or a hard drive, or a keyboard. Here's a diagram of my personal estimate of what separate components need software:</p>
<p><img src="https://dorotac.eu/posts/fosswon/firmwares.png" alt="A picture of a laptop with highlighted components: camera, touch screen, touchpad, Embedded Controller, SSD, battery, HDD, RAM, WiFi+Bluetooth card, sound card, BIOS, Intel ME."></p>
<p>I estimate there are 10 to 15 separate processors on a typical laptop. Just the graphics card may host five of them.</p>
<p>What does that mean for free software? Normally, all that's open – Linux, drivers, applications – all of this is confined to the main CPU. Now imagine you want to use this operating system through some human-friendly interface, like the touch screen or the keyboard. Those are running closed software, so if you want to enter any sort of data on your average laptop, it's game over: you can't make a move without dependence on closed software.</p>
<p>Same story with the graphics card. You won't display anything without closed software. What a fail. Okay, let's ditch keyboards and displays because this is a server. But that's a fail, too: to communicate over a network card, you still need software that it's running and that hasn't been opened. Suppose that we managed to somehow solve this problem. We hit the wall anyway when we try to store data: SSDs as well as HDDs are running their own closed software. I haven't heard of a single case of open software ever running on a storage device!</p>
<p>But that's not even the worst. The peak of lameness is <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170828150536/http://blog.ptsecurity.com/2017/08/disabling-intel-me.html">the processor inside the processor</a>. Have you already heard of Secure Boot? It's a piece of BIOS that is loaded onto the processor inside the main processor before the main operating system. Secure Boot allows the manufacturer choose which software the user can run. A similar system exists on Android phones to lock them to a particular system. Manufacturers of Android-based phones are not shy about restricting what the user can run on their devices.</p>
<h2>## That runs against user's freedom!</h2>
<p>User freedom exists only when the <a href="https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.en.html">Four Freedoms of Software</a> are upheld:</p>
<ul>
<li>0: freedom to run the program for any purpose,</li>
<li>1: to study and change it,</li>
<li>2: to share copies of it,</li>
<li>3: to improve it and share the improvements.</li>
</ul>
<p>…but those are just words. Who cares about that? This theory is only ever going to be relevant to us computer experts, right?</p>
<p>Except… could it be that you're the family's tech support expert? Does your uncle/mum/grandma come to you carrying their malfunctioning Android phone, hoping for you to make everything right again?</p>
<p>And have you ever disappointed them? Has it already happened that their phone was simply too old and unsupported to be useful any more? Have you already told someone they need to pay up to replace a phone that seems perfectly functional?</p>
<p>Sadly, that's what the Android manufacturer <a href="https://www.nextpit.com/how-tos/how-many-android-updates-manufactures-offer">support</a> <a href="https://forum.fairphone.com/t/what-kind-of-guarantee-is-there-regarding-updates/105832">timelines</a> say: typically after 4, exceptionally after 8 years, they will no longer release security updates. That makes devices too insecure to use, and turns them into e-waste.</p>
<p>What does Free Software have to do with it? I don't know, but my Lenovo laptop, 13 years since release of the hardware, the operating system is still receiving regular security updates. I suspect this has something to do with the lack of a boot loader lock and the openness of all the drivers. That's unlike Android. Even if there's no explicit lock, the drivers are so rarely open that the community rarely has the manpower to create a custom ROM for a given device.</p>
<h2>## Rug pulls</h2>
<p>The couple hundred bucks that your aunt might need to pony up to get a new phone pale in comparison to how much you need to pay for some cloud-only devices. Some cloud-enabled gadgets don't let the user choose an alternative provider for services the device requires. What happens when the company <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2024/12/startup-will-brick-800-emotional-support-robot-for-kids-without-refunds/">shuts down</a> the <a href="https://www.gamesradar.com/games/racing/210-days-after-nintendo-shut-down-the-3ds-and-wii-u-online-servers-the-last-connected-player-finally-signs-off-after-his-console-crashes-its-over/">online service</a>? Of course, the device <a href="https://www.pcmag.com/news/2300-magic-leap-1-headset-will-stop-working-after-2024">becomes an expensive brick</a>. Imagine someone setting your 2300 bucks on fire just like that.</p>
<p>That's still nothing compared to what some other people have to deal with. Imagine you're a farmer, and your harvest is on the field, ready to get cut and brought in. T here's a storm brewing, so you jump into the combine harvester, and start the work. Oh no! The machine broke down! Not to worry, you're a resourceful farmer and you have the necessary spare part. You install it and start the machine, except… it tells you: "Unauthorized component. Please contact customer service". Now you're in real trouble because it could take <a href="https://pirg.org/media-center/report-tractor-right-to-repair-would-save-u-s-farmers-4-2-billion/">9 months</a> for the customer service to solve the problem. You can't harvest the food worth tens of thousands of dollars, you're that much in the red. Game over, your farm is bankrupt. But that's not the end of the world, is it?</p>
<p><img src="https://dorotac.eu/posts/fosswon/pacemaker.jpg" alt="Two x-ray pictures of a human chest, with some wires and a chunky artificial shape visible"></p>
<p>This is what a pacemaker looks like. Why would I mention those in a talk about software freedom? You see, a pacemaker is a complex device which must examine and diagnose the patient continuously, in real time, in order to perform its function. Its task is to detect a dangerous condition and perform a medical procedure in response to it. It needs software to do this complicated task. But if the device isn't perfect at diagnosing, that's a big problem. I'm not a medical expert, but getting your heart shocked when it's not necessary sounds dangerous in its own right. When it runs closed software that does not grant us the freedom to modify it, we have to resort to begging the manufacturer to fix it. And when we get no freedom to study it, we can't even avoid the circumstances that make it misfire!</p>
<p>But don't take my word for it. I only know of this problem because of <a href="https://punkrocklawyer.com/">Karen Sandler</a>, whose <a href="https://sfconservancy.org/about/staff/">involvement with Free Software</a> is intertwined with this problem since the beginning.</p>
<p>The bottom line is, if we have people who have no other choice but to trust their own body to a <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/bionic-eye-obsolete">piece of closed software and a single manufacturer</a>, how could we possibly say that Open Source had won?</p>
<h2>## Appliances and copyleft</h2>
<p>Are you responsible for building an appliance? I bet you're using Open Source software in it, aren't you? Then licenses like the MIT require you to include a notice about the authors of the source code together with the software you distribute. There's a whole <a href="https://daniel.haxx.se/blog/2016/10/03/screenshotted-curl-credits/">gallery</a> of those on the curl website, ranging from cars to food processors. Are you feeling proud for releasing a device with Free Software in it? Not so quick! Can the user of your device study and modify the software you gave them? Have you actually granted them the Four Freedoms?</p>
<p>Permissive licenses <a href="https://www.gnu.org/licenses/license-list.html#Expat">like the MIT license are Free Software</a>, so they let you do all that the Four Freedoms promise. But they also allow you to do another thing: to close the software again by never granting those freedoms regarding your own modifications. If that's what happened, then freedom for me, not for thee. You, the manufacturer, reaped the benefits, the user can't, sucks to be the user.</p>
<p>The responsibility to prevent this falls on us, computer experts. When we create software, we have the choice of license we want to release it under. And we should be using what's called "copyleft": it's a term that applies to licenses which prevent code once released under that license from being closed again. The most widespread copyleft license is the <a href="https://www.gnu.org/licenses/quick-guide-gplv3.html">Gnu General Public License</a> (GPL), and I recommend that you all use that one.</p>
<h2>## Licenses and more</h2>
<p>Licenses are not the only thing relevant for Free Software. There are other things to fight:</p>
<ul>
<li>patents, like in the case of cellular modems,</li>
<li>hardware locks, like Android's,</li>
<li>project management.</li>
</ul>
<p>As for the last point, recently Google gave <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/03/google-makes-android-development-private-will-continue-open-source-releases/">an amazing example</a> by restricting access to sources in development to select manufacturers. Everyone else will not get continuous updates, but only once per major release. This illustrates how much influence over the practical usability of a project management decisions have. This is not a change in licensing, and it's also not a technical change, so it's not immediately visible under those lenses.</p>
<p>Instead, it's a consequence of who's in charge. In this case, it's not a community who controls the Android project, but a for-profit corporation. At the same time, it's regular people who are on the user side of the project. Is it any wonder that the goals of a corporation and those of regular people differ? Is it any wonder that the corporation is making changes that suit it even when they don't suit the community of users? When those are the conditions under which a project is developed, it can have deep consequences, even on an architectural level.</p>
<p>Take <a href="https://www.debian.org/">Debian</a> as a point of comparison. The first statement on the web page already says "Debian is a Community of People!". The software is being developed and used by the same people. They won't make it harder to use. They provide a complete operating system, publish all the sources, and <a href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=1099130">purge anything that isn't open enough</a>. On the other hand, Android has long been <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2018/07/googles-iron-grip-on-android-controlling-open-source-by-any-means-necessary/">replacing</a> open components by closed ones, making AOSP (the open part of android) all but <a href="https://www.esper.io/blog/aosp-missing-features-google-gms">unuseable on its own</a>.</p>
<h2>## Why?</h2>
<p>I suspect this situation has something to do with how computers and appliances have been developed historically. Computers have their roots in academia. When they were sold, they were always advertised as blank slates, general purpose devices, as opportunities to do what you choose to do with them. Not so much for appliances. Those have always had a single purpose. Except they kept getting complicated, until they entered a level of complexity where they needed to incorporate computers in order to perform their function. But they kept being manufactured as appliances, with only a handful of people being expected or allowed to exercise control over them. Incorporating computers didn't change the culture around them.</p>
<p>This is just a guess and I don't know how correct it is. For example Apple was always a computer manufacturer, but they are making computers now as if those were appliances.</p>
<h2>## What now?</h2>
<p>The responsibility is ours – computer nerds' – to make Free Software win. When we build a hardware device, we must publish the firmware sources. We must publish technical documentation – it often so happens that the device documentation needed to make open firmware is missing or incomplete (another war story from the Librem 5, camera sensors this time).</p>
<p>As users, or institutional customers, we should demand that the manufacturer provides open sources for any firmware they are shipping with their devices.</p>
<p>But there's one more way: political pressure. I expect this to be a more effective method than individual action. After all, EU managed to convince phone manufacturers to <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/technology-58665809">standardize on USB-C ports for charging</a>, as well as to <a href="https://www.androidcentral.com/phones/eu-repair-push-for-defective-consumer-goods">extend the warranty period</a>. Perhaps they could also force computer manufacturers to not install boot loader locks. It would fit nicely into the <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/EN/legal-content/summary/copyright-and-related-rights-in-the-information-society.html">Information Society Directive</a>. It says things like:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&gt; Member States must provide legal protection against any person knowingly performing without authority any of the following acts:</p>
<ul>
<li>&gt; the removal or alteration of any electronic rights-management information;</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>…oh. So instead of jailing people who put locks on devices they no longer own, it enforces the jailing of those who remove them from their own devices. Great.</p>
<p>Dear European Comission, please always have someone with a clue in the room who can explain the consequences of your ideas in a way you can understand. You can do it, already did a couple times, like above. But work on consistency, okay? Pinky promise?</p>
<p>Here are some people with a clue: <a href="https://fsfe.org/">Free Software Foundation Europe</a> with their <a href="https://publiccode.eu/">Public Money Public Code</a> open letter, the <a href="https://repair.eu/">Right to Repair</a> movement, as well as the <a href="https://european-pirateparty.eu/">European Pirate Party</a>.</p>
<p>I recommend anyone who cares to join forces with them. But if you don't want to engage politically, there are also financial way of support. And I don't even mean (although I do encourage) donating. I mean supporting Free Software friendly manufacturers! Buy the Librem 5 from <a href="https://puri.sm/">Purism</a>, or a 3D printer from <a href="https://www.prusa3d.com/">Prusa</a>, or a smartwatch running <a href="https://www.espruino.com/Bangle.js2">Espruino</a>. You see, it's expensive to manufacture any sort of hardware. It doesn't help that the markets are already saturated with closed products. Even if open source, hackable products are superior, it will take people at large a long time to realize that this is a superpower. Free Software thrived in culture of repair and modification. But this culture has been suffocated in the wider society with closed, throwaway items, so few people recognize its benefits. That unsustainable crowding out makes another obstacle for Open Source friendly products in the current markets.</p>
<p>There's a noble exception here. What makes it even more unusual is that it comes from Google. It's Chromebooks. Google has a set of requirements that all Chromebook manufacturers must fulfill, and one of them is having a completely open BIOS, together with the Embedded Controller firmware. All Chromebooks I'm aware of run Coreboot. They still contain some closed software, notably the RAM startup software, which, I believe, is present in all laptops, but! ARM-base Chromebooks are able to run with a completely open BIOS apart from that. So if anyone wants to take care of this together with me, I have this <a href="https://nlnet.nl/project/MT818x_MT819x-firmware/">NLNet project</a> to make it as easy as possible to run regular, mainline Linux on them. So please, contact me, if you're that person.</p>
<h2>## The world</h2>
<p>A short quiz: how many devices can you count around you which contain processors?</p>
<p>Some hints: TV, camera, toothbrush, oscilloscope, e-book reader, radio receiver, dishwasher, router, washing machine, vacuum cleaner, bathroom scales.</p>
<p>Now think wider. When I went to the supermarket, the vegetable section had a scales that printed labels with barcodes. They were equipped with touch screens. You bet there's a processor and a load of firmware in those. But shops are chock-full of processors in my part of the world. There are thousands of price labels in each of those stores, and they are all e-paper screens. I'm fairly sure you need software to drive those and receive wireless updates.</p>
<p>Keep going and you might realize that the software running in your car allows <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2016/sep/20/tesla-model-s-chinese-hack-remote-control-brakes">remote control</a>. Or <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/12/08/polish_trains_geofenced_allegation/">in your train</a>. That snafu wouldn't have occured if the railways had access to sources of the train software.</p>
<p>What about other business uses? Car diagnostic stations? Medical equipment? Accounting software?</p>
<p>Software is really eating the world, and it's closed software which is *<em>everywhere</em>* around us, without free options. What's the regular person's role in this? They give up control over entire areas of their lives to others, others who often can't be supervised or replaced.</p>
<p>You know, we messed up. There's no other way to put it. We even let closed software sneak into our own home field: computers. Sure, the interfaces are open. There's SATA, there's PCI. We can swap parts if we want to, we can run Linux there, all is fine. Except it's not, because peripherals are as important as the core, and we, software people, lost control of the peripherals of our darlings already.</p>
<h2>## Wasted potential</h2>
<p>In theory, it's possible that someone opens a piece of software regardless of the wishes of the original authors. The whole game modding scene is about that. Here's an example of someone running Tetris on a pocket camera:</p>
<p>ZX3 running Tetris with hacked firmware</p>


<p>But going against the manufacturer is just wasted work. Imagine the difference between hacking it in and modifying the official sources. The potential, things we could achieve if we didn't have to break doors that are open! So here's a silly example: I have an action camera. Due to some <a href="https://www.dpreview.com/articles/0794343949/wto-looking-at-moves-to-remove-30-minute-limit-from-digital-cameras">stupid law</a>, the camera breaks off every recording as soon as it reaches the 30 minutes mark. Now I have 20 years of coding experience. Having source code, I could have fixed the problem and went on with my life. Another example, another camera: I am making a time lapse from my window. Every day at 10:00, I take a picture from a camera that just sits there. But this camera has no time lapse feature, so I must go there in person every time. Why can't I fix this? Of course, no source code.</p>
<h2>## Epilogue</h2>
<p>There's now a <a href="https://www.crowdsupply.com/open-tools/open-printer">new printer</a> project that advertises itself as open source. But if you look at the details, it's actually not. Instead, it uses a <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">source-available license</a> which does not grant you Freedom 0 – you must not use the sources for commercial purposes. Better than nothing, I guess.</p>

    
    
    <section>
        <a href="https://comments.dorotac.eu/posts/fosswon">Comments</a>
        
    </section>
  </article>

    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>