<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 11:30:02 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Public static void main(String[] args) is dead (174 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://mccue.dev/pages/9-16-25-psvm</link>
            <guid>45258098</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 04:42:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://mccue.dev/pages/9-16-25-psvm">https://mccue.dev/pages/9-16-25-psvm</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45258098">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">

<p> by:  <b> Ethan McCue</b></p>

<p>As of September 16th, year of our lord 2025, this is no longer the first Java program you need to write.</p>
<div id="cb1"><pre><code><span id="cb1-1"><span>public</span> <span>class</span> Main <span>{</span></span>
<span id="cb1-2">    <span>public</span> <span>static</span> <span>void</span> <span>main</span><span>(</span><span>String</span><span>[]</span> args<span>)</span> <span>{</span></span>
<span id="cb1-3">        <span>Scanner</span> scanner <span>=</span> <span>new</span> <span>Scanner</span><span>(</span><span>System</span><span>.</span><span>in</span><span>);</span></span>
<span id="cb1-4">        <span>System</span><span>.</span><span>out</span><span>.</span><span>print</span><span>(</span><span>"What is your name? "</span><span>);</span></span>
<span id="cb1-5">        <span>String</span> name <span>=</span> scanner<span>.</span><span>nextLine</span><span>();</span></span>
<span id="cb1-6">        <span>System</span><span>.</span><span>out</span><span>.</span><span>println</span><span>(</span><span>"Hello, "</span> <span>+</span> name<span>);</span></span>
<span id="cb1-7">    <span>}</span></span>
<span id="cb1-8"><span>}</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>This is.</p>
<div id="cb2"><pre><code><span id="cb2-1"><span>void</span> <span>main</span><span>()</span> <span>{</span></span>
<span id="cb2-2">    var name <span>=</span> IO<span>.</span><span>readln</span><span>(</span><span>"What is your name? "</span><span>);</span></span>
<span id="cb2-3">    IO<span>.</span><span>println</span><span>(</span><span>"Hello, "</span> <span>+</span> name<span>);</span></span>
<span id="cb2-4"><span>}</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>Good Fucking Riddance.</p>
<p>I'll be nuanced later, we've all earned some catharsis now.</p>
<p>Holy fucking shit did this suck<sup><a href="#1">1</a></sup>. There is a comments section below. Give your eulogy for that piece of shit sorcerous incantation there or wherever else.</p>
<p><code>new Scanner(System.in)</code> and <code>System.out.println</code> too. Don't let your sense of dignity hold you back.</p>
<p>Just record yourself giving a guttural scream and post it. Sing a song, do a dance, cast aspersions.</p>
<p>Honestly just let it all out.</p>


<hr>
<h4 id="--index"><a href="https://mccue.dev/">&lt;- Index</a></h4>
</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA["Your" vs. "My" in user interfaces (222 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://adamsilver.io/blog/your-vs-my-in-user-interfaces/</link>
            <guid>45257627</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 03:05:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://adamsilver.io/blog/your-vs-my-in-user-interfaces/">https://adamsilver.io/blog/your-vs-my-in-user-interfaces/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45257627">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      
      <p>When referring to the user’s stuff, which is better out of these:</p>
<ul>
<li>“My account” or “Your account”?</li>
<li>“My orders” or “Your orders”?</li>
<li>“My cases” or “Your cases”?</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s a trick question because often you don’t need any prefix and can just use:</p>
<ul>
<li>Account</li>
<li>Orders</li>
<li>Cases</li>
</ul>
<p>Amazon is a good example of this in action because it’s obvious that it’s your account and your orders:</p>
<div>
	<figure><img src="https://adamsilver.io/assets/images/your-vs-my-in-user-interfaces/amazon.png" alt="Amazon’s header which does not use ‘your’ or ‘my’ for account and orders"></figure>
</div>
<p>But what if your product contains things that belong to you and to others – for example, a case working system that contains your cases and everyone else‘s?</p>
<h2>The problem with “my”</h2>
<p>You could use “My cases” in a navigation menu like this:</p>
<div>
	<figure><img src="https://adamsilver.io/assets/images/your-vs-my-in-user-interfaces/nav.png" alt="Navigation menu with options for ‘My cases’ and ‘All cases’"></figure>
</div>
<p>This seems fine on the face of it.</p>
<p>But screens are not only accessed or referred to through a menu.</p>
<p>For example, you might need to sign post users to their cases in an onboarding flow, email notification or help article.</p>
<p>Saying something like “Go to my cases” is awkward and unnatural – if I told you to go to my cases, you’d think I was telling you to go to my cases, not yours.</p>
<p>Similarly, a support agent might tell you to “Go to your cases” over webchat or a phone call. This is confusing if the UI says “My cases”.</p>
<p>These issues just don’t come up when you use “your” – I’ve used this approach in multiple products over the years, and seen exactly zero issues in user research.</p>
<p>So that’s good.</p>
<h2>“But what if the user is communicating to us using radio buttons, for example?”</h2>
<p>This is easy if we look at an example:</p>
<div>
	<figure><img src="https://adamsilver.io/assets/images/your-vs-my-in-user-interfaces/radios-your.png" alt="Radios where the legend is ‘Do you want to share your profile photo?’ and the options are ‘Yes, share your profile photo’ and ‘No, do not share your profile photo’"></figure>
</div>
<p>This doesn’t make sense because it sounds like you’re instructing the computer to share their profile, not yours.</p>
<p>But it’s clear if you use “my”:</p>
<div>
	<figure><img src="https://adamsilver.io/assets/images/your-vs-my-in-user-interfaces/radios-my.png" alt="Radios where the legend is ‘Do you want to share your profile photo?’ and the options are ‘Yes, share my profile photo’ and ‘No, do not share my profile photo’"></figure>
</div>
<p>In summary:</p>
<ul>
<li>Use “your” when communicating to the user</li>
<li>Use “my” when the user is communicating to us</li>
</ul>
<p>If you’d like to design forms that nail basic details like this, as well as complex problems found in enterprise systems, you might like my course, Form Design Mastery:</p>
<p><a href="https://formdesignmastery.com/">https://formdesignmastery.com</a></p>

      
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Linux phones are more important now than ever (540 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://feddit.org/post/18353777</link>
            <guid>45256651</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:33:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://feddit.org/post/18353777">https://feddit.org/post/18353777</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45256651">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="postContent"><div><h2 dir="auto">E: apparently it needs to be said that I am not suggesting you switch to Linux on your phone today; just that development needs to accelerate. Please don’t be one of the 34 people that replied to tell me Linux is not ready.</h2>
<p dir="auto">Android has always been a <em>fairly</em> open platform, especially if you were <em>deliberate</em> about getting it that way, but we’ve seen in recent months an <strong>extremely rapid</strong> devolution of the Android ecosystem:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://9to5google.com/2025/03/26/google-android-aosp-developement-private/" rel="noopener nofollow">The closing of development of an increasing number of components in AOSP.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://trendslife.in/samsung-one-ui-removed-bootloader-unlock/" rel="noopener nofollow">Samsung</a>, <a href="https://droidwin.com/xiaomi-might-no-longer-allow-bootloader-unlocking-on-miui/" rel="noopener nofollow">Xiaomi</a> and <a href="https://droidwin.com/now-oneplus-restricts-bootloader-unlocking/" rel="noopener nofollow">OnePlus</a> have removed the option of bootloader unlocking on all of their devices. I suspect Google is not far behind.</li>
<li>Google implementing Play Integrity API and encouraging developers to implement it. Notably the EU’s own identity verification wallet requires this, in stark contrast to their own laws and policies, despite the protest of hundreds on Github.</li>
<li>And finally, the mandatory implementation of developer verification across Android systems. Yes, if you’re running a 3rd-party OS like GOS you won’t be directly affected by this, but it will impact 99.9% of devices, and I foresee many open source developers just opting out of developing apps for Android entirely as a result. <a href="https://forum.syncthing.net/t/discontinuing-syncthing-android/23002" rel="noopener nofollow">We’ve already seen SyncThing simply discontinue development</a> for this reason, citing issues with Google Play Store. They’ve also repeatedly denied updates for NextCloud with no explanation, only restoring it after mass outcry. And we’ve already seen Google targeting any software intended to circumvent ads, labeling them in the system as “dangerous” and “untrusted”. This will most certainly carry into their new “verification” system.</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto">Google once competed with Apple for customers. But in a world where Google walks away from the biggest antitrust trial since 1998 with yet another slap on the wrist, competition is dead, and Google is taking notes from Apple about what they can legally get away with.</p>
<p dir="auto">Android as we know it is dead. And/or will be dead very soon. We need an open replacement.</p>
</div></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I feel Apple has lost its alignment with me and other long-time customers (359 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://morrick.me/archives/10137</link>
            <guid>45256577</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:20:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://morrick.me/archives/10137">https://morrick.me/archives/10137</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45256577">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
			<p>A first version of this piece was almost ready to be published two days ago, but after writing more than 2,000 words, I grew increasingly angry and exasperated, and that made the article become too meandering and rant-like, so I deleted everything, and started afresh several hours&nbsp;later.</p>
<p>This, of course, is about <em>Awe-dropping</em>, Apple’s September 9 event, where they presented the new iPhone lineup, the new AirPods Pro, and the new Apple Watches. And the honest truth here is that I’m becoming less and less inclined to talk about Apple, because it’s a company that I feel has lost its alignment with me and other long-time Apple users and customers.</p>
<p>The more Apple talks and moves like other big tech companies, the less special it gets; the less special and distinctive it gets, the less I’m interested in finding ways to talk about it. Yes, I have admitted that Apple makes me mad lately, so they still elicit a response that isn’t utter indifference on my part. And yes, you could argue that if Apple makes me mad, it means that in the end I still&nbsp;care.&nbsp;</p>
<p>But things aren’t this clear-cut. I currently don’t really care about Apple — I care that their bad software design decisions and their constant user-interface dumbing down may become trends and get picked up by other tech companies. So, what I still care about that’s related to Apple is essentially the consequences of their actions.</p>
<h2>The Steve Jobs&nbsp;quote</h2>
<p>The event kicked off with the famous Steve Jobs&nbsp;quote,</p>
<blockquote><p>
Design is not just what it looks like and feels like. Design is how it&nbsp;works.&nbsp;</p></blockquote>
<p>and I immediately felt the whiplash.</p>
<p>Why that quote? Why now, after months of criticism towards the new design æsthetic of Liquid Glass? I gave this choice three possible interpretations — I still may be missing something here; I’m sure my readers will let me&nbsp;know.</p>
<ol>
<li>It’s Apple’s way of trolling the critics, who have repeatedly resorted to Steve Jobs’s words to criticise the several misguided UI choices in Liquid Glass. It’s the same kind of response as Phil Schiller famously blurting, <em>Can’t innovate anymore, my ass!</em> in 2013 during the presentation of the then-redesigned Mac Pro. But it feels like a less genuine, more passive-aggressive response (if this is the way we’re supposed to read their use of that&nbsp;quote).</li>
<li>Apple used the quote in earnest. As in, they really believe that what they’re doing is in line with Jobs’s words. If that’s the case, this is utter self-deception. The quote doesn’t reflect at all what Apple is doing in the UI and software department — the Liquid Glass design is more ‘look <span>&amp;</span> feel’ than ‘work’. And the very introduction of the iPhone Air proves that Jobs’s words are falling on deaf ears on the hardware front as&nbsp;well.</li>
<li>Apple used the quote ‘for effect’. As if Meta started a keynote by saying, <em>Our mission is to connect people, no more no less.</em> You know, something that makes you sound great and noble, but not necessarily something you truly believe (or something that is actually true, for that matter).</li>
</ol>
<p>I can’t know for sure which of these might be the correct interpretation. I think it heavily depends on whose Apple executive came up with the idea. Whatever the case may be, the effect was the same — it felt really jarring and tone-deaf.</p>
<h2>AirPods and Watches</h2>
<p>If you’re not new here, you’ll know that these are the Apple products I care the least, together with HomePods and Apple TV. I always tune out when Apple presents these, so browse Apple’s website or go read the technical breakdown elsewhere. Personally, I’m too into traditional horology and therefore the design of the Apple Watch has always felt unimaginative at best, and plain ugly at&nbsp;worst.&nbsp;</p>
<p>From a UI standpoint, the Apple Watch continues to feel too complicated to use, and too overburdened with features. I wouldn’t say it’s design by committee, but more like designed to appeal to a whole committee. Apple wants the watch to appeal to a wide range of customers, therefore this little device comes stuffed with all kinds of bells and whistles. As I said more than once, the real feature I would love to see implemented is the ability to just turn off entire feature sets, so that if you only want to use it as a step counter and heart rate monitor, you can tell the watch to be just that; this would be more than just having a watchface that shows you time, steps, heart rate — it would be like having a watch that does <em>only that</em>. With all the features you deem unnecessary effectively disabled, imagine how simpler interacting with it would be, and imagine how longer its battery life would&nbsp;be.</p>
<p>What really got on my nerves during the Apple Watch segment of the event, though, is this: Apple always, <em>always</em> inserts a montage of sob stories about how the Apple Watch has saved lives, and what an indispensable life-saving device it is. Don’t get me wrong, I’m glad those lives were saved. But this kind of ‘showcase’ every year is made in such poor taste. It’s clear to me that it’s all marketing above everything else, that they just want to sell the product, and these people’s stories end up being used as a marketing tactic. It’s depressing.</p>
<p>As for the AirPods, and true wireless earbuds in general, I find this product category to be the most wasteful. Unless someone comes up with a type of earbuds that have easily replaceable batteries, I’m not interested in buying something that’s bound to become e‑waste in a relatively short period of&nbsp;time.</p>
<h2>The new iPhones</h2>
<p>Don’t buy them. Don’t waste your money, unless you have money to waste and don’t care about a company with this kind of leadership. Read <a href="https://www.anildash.com/2025/09/09/how-tim-cook-sold-out-steve-jobs/"><em>How Tim Cook sold out Steve Jobs</em></a> by Anil Dash to understand how I feel. I couldn’t have said it better myself.</p>
<p>I’d wrap up my article here, but then I’d receive a lot of emails asking me why I didn’t talk about the iPhones, so here are a few stray observations:</p>
<p>One, maybe involuntary, user-friendly move Apple did with this new iPhone lineup is that now we have three very distinct iPhone models, whose nature and price should really help people decide which to purchase.</p>
<p>The regular <strong>iPhone 17</strong> is the safe, iterative solution. It looks like an iPhone 16, it works like an iPhone 16 that has now better features. It’s the ideal phone for the average user (tech-savvy or not). It’s the safe choice and the best value iPhone overall.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The <strong>iPhone 17 Pro</strong> is possibly the most Pro iPhone to date. During its presentation, I felt like Apple wants you to consider this more like a pro camera for videographers and filmmakers rather than just a smartphone with a good camera array. People who have no use for all these pro video recording features shouldn’t waste their money on it. Unless they want a big chunky iPhone with the best camera array and/or have money to burn. In my country (Spain), the 6.3‑inch iPhone 17 Pro starts at €1,319 with 256GB of storage, and goes up to €1,819 with 1TB of storage. For the bigger iPhone 17 Pro, those prices become €1,469 and €1,969 respectively, and if you want the iPhone 17 Pro Max with 2TB of storage, it’ll cost you €2,469. You do you, but I think these are insane prices for phones (and&nbsp;SSDs).</p>
<p>The <strong> iPhone Air</strong> is just… odd. I was curious to know about other techies’ reactions, and of all the major tech YouTubers, I think the one I’m agreeing the most on their first impressions of the iPhone Air is Marques Brownlee. <a href="https://youtu.be/idEAABFzpfg?si=yS4-IoqZq1oFMiPs&amp;t=522">At this point</a> in his video, he&nbsp;says:&nbsp;</p>
<blockquote><p>
I really think this phone is gonna be a hard sell, because if you subtract emotions from it, it’s just… the worst one. This is gonna jump in the lineup at $999 — it replaces essentially the Plus phones in the lineup — and it is surrounded by other iPhones that are better than it in basically every way, other than being super thin and light. So it’s a fascinating gamble.&nbsp;</p>
<p>This phone has the same A19 Pro chip in it as the Pro phones, minus one GPU core. Interesting choice: apparently it’s a bit more efficient than the base A19, so that’s good for battery life. But we also just heard a whole long list of choices Apple made with the Pro phones to make them more thermally efficient to not overheat — switching from titanium to aluminium, and adding a vapour chamber to the back. But this phone is <em>still</em> titanium, and absolutely does not have room for an advanced thermal solution or any sort of vapour chamber, so it sounds like this phone could get much hotter and throttle performance much quicker. It’s a red&nbsp;flag.</p>
<p>Now we also know that ultra-thin phones have a tendency to be a little bit less durable. They’ve bent over the years. And I’m not gonna be the first one to point this out. […] And Apple of course has thought about this. They’ve for sure tested this, and they’re telling us it’s the most durable iPhone ever. But, I mean, I’m looking at the phone and I think it qualifies also as a red flag. And then we already know there is just no way battery life can be good on this phone, right? There’s just no way. I’ve been reviewing phones for more than a decade, and all signs point to it being&nbsp;trash.</p>
<p>There was a slide in the keynote today about how they were still proud to achieve ‘all-day battery life’. But, like, come on. Really? I mean they still do the thing where they rearranged the components up into the little plateau at the top to make room for more battery at the bottom. But there’s just absolutely not enough room in this phone for a large battery. And it doesn’t appear to be silicon-carbon, or any sort of a special ultra-high density battery.</p>
<p>And Apple also announced it alongside a special dedicated MagSafe battery accessory, just for this phone, that adds 3,149 mAh, and just barely, combined, will match the 17 Pro in terms of quoted video playback. So if that doesn’t scream red flag, I don’t know what to tell&nbsp;you.</p>
<p>It is also e‑SIM-only, globally, ’cause there’s no room in any version of this phone for a plastic SIM card. There’s also no millimeter-wave 5G. And like I said, it’s coming in at $1,000, which is more expensive than the base iPhone, which will have a better camera system, and better battery life, and may overheat less.</p>
<p>So look, I think there’s two ways to look at this phone. This is either Apple just throwing something new at the wall and seeing if it sticks. […] Or you can see this as a visionary, long-time-in-the-making preview at the future of all phones. Like, maybe someday in the future every phone will be this thin. And Apple is just now, today, getting the tech together with the battery and display and modem and Apple Silicon to make this phone possible. Maybe kind of like how the first MacBook Air sucked, and was underpowered, but then eventually all laptops became that thin. Maybe that’s also what’s gonna happen to smartphones. And maybe the same way Samsung made the ultra-thin S25 Edge, and then a few months later they came out with their super-thin foldable, the Z Fold7, and I felt like the Edge phone was one half of that foldable. Maybe that’s also what Apple’s doing. Maybe we’re gonna see an ultra-thin foldable iPhone next year.&nbsp;Maybe.&nbsp;</p></blockquote>
<p>Yeah, I’m firmly in the “Apple throwing something new at the wall and seeing if it sticks” camp. Because what’s that innovative in having thin smartphones? What’s the usefulness when the other two dimensions keep increasing? Making a thin and light and relatively compact MacBook and calling it ‘Air’ made sense back when virtually no other laptop was that thin and light. It was, and is, a great solution for when you’re out and about or travelling, and space is at a premium; and you also don’t want a bulky computer to lug around.</p>
<p>Then Apple applied the ‘Air’ moniker to the iPad, and that started to make less sense. It’s not that a regular or Pro iPad were and are that cumbersome to begin with. And then Apple felt the need to have MacBook Airs that are 13- and 15-inch in size, instead of 11- and 13-inch. A 15-inch MacBook Air makes little sense, too, as an ‘Air’ laptop. It may be somewhat thin, somewhat light, but it’s not exactly compact.&nbsp;</p>
<p>And now we have the iPhone Air — which is just thin for thinness’ sake. It’s still a big 6.5‑inch phone that’s hardly pocketable. I still happen to handle and use a few older iPhones in the household, and the dimensions of the iPhone 5/5S/SE make this iPhone more ‘Air’ than the iPhone Air. If you want a slightly more recent example, the iPhone 12 mini and 13 mini have the real <em>lightness</em> that could make sense in a phone. Perhaps you’ll once again remind me that the iPhone 12 mini and 13 mini weren’t a success, but I keep finding people telling me they would favour a more compact phone than a big-but-thin phone. I’ll be truly surprised if the iPhone Air turns out to be a bigger success than the ‘mini’ iPhones. It is a striking device in person, no doubt, but once this first impact is gone and you start thinking it over and making your decision, what Marques Brownlee said above is kind of hard to&nbsp;deny.&nbsp;</p>
<p>I find particularly hilarious the whole MagSafe battery accessory affair. Apple creates a super-thin, super-light phone, proudly showcases its striking design, and immediately neutralises this bold move and thin design by offering an accessory 1) that you’ll clearly need if you want to have a decently-lasting battery (thus admitting that that thinness certainly came with an important compromise); and 2) that instantly defeats the purpose of a thin design by returning the bulk that was shaved away in making the&nbsp;phone.</p>
<h2>What should I be in awe&nbsp;of?</h2>
<p>I found a lot of reactions to these products to be weirdly optimistic. Either I’m becoming more cynical with age and general tech fatigue, or certain people are easily impressed. What usually impresses me is some technological breakthrough I didn’t see coming, or a clever new device, or some clever system software features and applications that give new purposes to a device I’ve known well for a while. This event, and what was presented, didn’t show any of&nbsp;this.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Didn’t you expect Apple to be able to produce yet another iteration of Apple Watches and AirPods that were better than the previous one? Didn’t you expect Apple to be able to make a unibody iPhone after years of making unibody computers? Didn’t you expect Apple to be able to have iPhones with better cameras and recording capabilities than last year’s iPhones? Didn’t you expect Apple to be able to make a thinner iPhone? To come up with better chips? Or a vapour chamber to prevent overheating? Or a ‘centre stage’ feature for the selfie camera? Are these things I should be in awe&nbsp;of?</p>
<p>I will probably be genuinely amazed when Apple is finally able to come up with a solution that entirely removes the dynamic island from the front of the iPhone while still having a front-facing camera up&nbsp;there.</p>
<p>I’ll be similarly amazed when Apple finally gets rid of people who have shown to know very little about software design and user interfaces, and comes up with operating systems that are, once again, intuitive, discoverable, easy to use, and that both look and work well. Because the iOS, iPadOS, and Mac OS 26 releases are <em>not it</em> — and these new iPhones might be awe-inspiring all you want, but you’ll still have to deal with iOS 26 on them. These new iPhones may have a fantastic hardware and all, but what makes any hardware tick is the software. You’ve probably heard that famous quote by Alan Kay, <em> People who are really serious about software should make their own hardware</em>. Steve Jobs himself quoted it, adding that “this is how we feel about it” at his Apple. Today’s Apple needs to hear a revised version of that quote, something like, <em>People who are this serious about their hardware should make better software for it</em>.</p>
<p>The level of <em>good-enough-ism</em> Apple has reached today in software is downright baffling. This widening gap between their hardware and software competence is going to be really damaging if the course isn’t corrected. The tight integration between hardware and software has always been what made Apple platforms stand out. This integration is going to get lost if Apple keeps having wizards for hardware engineers on one side, and software and UI people producing amateurish results on the other side. Relying on legacy and unquestioning fanpeople, for whom everything Apple does is good and awesome and there’s nothing wrong with it, can only go so far. Steve Jobs always knew that software is comparatively more important than the hardware. In a 1994 interview with Jeff Goodell, published by <em>Rolling Stone</em> in 2010 (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20100325155945/http://www.rollingstone.com/news/story/31896381/from_the_archives_a_revealing_interview_with_steve_jobs/print">archived link</a>), Jobs&nbsp;said:&nbsp;</p>
<blockquote><p>
The problem is, in hardware you can’t build a computer that’s twice as good as anyone else’s anymore. Too many people know how to do it. You’re lucky if you can do one that’s one and a third times better or one and a half times better. And then it’s only six months before everybody else catches up. But you can do it in software.&nbsp;</p></blockquote>
<p>But not if you keep crippling it because you want to bring all your major platforms to the lowest common denominator.</p>
					</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why do we keep gravitating toward complexity? (104 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://kyrylo.org/software/2025/08/21/why-do-software-developers-love-complexity.html</link>
            <guid>45256043</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 23:02:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://kyrylo.org/software/2025/08/21/why-do-software-developers-love-complexity.html">https://kyrylo.org/software/2025/08/21/why-do-software-developers-love-complexity.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45256043">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
    <p>The Great Pyramids took decades to build. It was a monumental feat of human
ingenuity and collaboration. Today, we software developers erect our own
pyramids each day - not from stone, but from code. Yet despite far more advanced
tools, these systems don’t always make the experience better. So why, when KISS
(Keep It Simple, Stupid) is a well-known mantra, do we keep gravitating toward
complexity?</p>

<h2 id="marketing--simplicity">Marketing &gt; Simplicity</h2>

<p>Sell me this pen: ✎</p>

<p>What? You don’t know how? Okay, instead, sell me this <em>Penzilla</em> - a pen that
can erase, write in different colors, play music, dial 911, act as a radio
antenna, and even help you cheat on your homework.</p>

<p>In the software world, how would you sell a competitor to the <code>cat</code> command?
Sounds insane, right? It’s so simple - why would anyone compete with it, let
alone build an alternative? (Let’s pretend Rust coreutils don’t exist.)</p>

<p>But what if instead of a <code>cat</code> competitor, it was <em>catzilla</em> - a tool that could
watch your files, hop through portals, and jump across networks? Now that’s
marketable! Still, nobody would take you seriously. Why? Because <code>cat</code> just
works, and it’s highly unlikely anyone will ever need anything else (just like
Penzilla).</p>

<p>However, if <code>catzilla</code> were hyped from every corner of the internet, with a
CatConf coming next month, you’d at least be curious to try it. Social proof
makes you take it seriously. Even if it’s just a gimmick, it’s still a gimmick
with users.</p>

<p>Complexity also signals effort, expertise, and exclusivity. If you struggle to
understand it, your brain rewards you with awe: “Wow, this must be really
smart,” you think - even if a simpler solution would work just as well.</p>

<p>Marketers, engineers, and startups all exploit this trick. The more layers, the
fancier the terminology, the more “premium” it feels. Complexity turns into a
status symbol rather than a necessity.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-inside-the-great-pyramids">What is inside the Great Pyramids?</h2>

<p>Whatever you put inside, duh. Like the Pyramids, modern software is built layer
upon layer - dependencies, frameworks, and abstractions stacked high. But just
as the Pyramids’ inner chambers are often empty, these layers can hide a lack of
substance, making maintenance a nightmare.</p>

<p>When you look at a Pyramid, only a moment later you notice your mouth is open
wide in awe (close it now). Simplicity, on the other hand, doesn’t hold any
secrets inside. It’s invisible until you realize it’s genius.</p>

<p>Complexity shouts, “Look at me!”, while simplicity whispers “Did you notice?”.</p>

<p>One thing for sure, though, simplicity often wins in the long run. After the
initial amazement is gone, it’s the function that quietly does the job that most
people need.</p>

<h2 id="react-vs-vanilla-javascript">React vs. vanilla JavaScript</h2>

<p>This is a classic example I love to <a href="https://justfuckingusehtml.com/">rant about</a>.</p>

<p>React piles concepts into your mental backpack: rendering models, hooks, state
libraries, routing, and a build pipeline. Say no to it, and suddenly you’re the
“neckbeard stuck in the ’90s,” outside the cool-kids club.</p>

<p>The simple alternative is just around the corner: sprinkle vanilla JavaScript
where it’s needed and don’t build your identity around a framework. That mindset
is hard to swallow, though (especially when companies have spent millions
convincing developers their stack is the only way forward).</p>

<h2 id="beyond-marketing-why-we-embrace-complexity">Beyond marketing: why we embrace complexity</h2>

<p>While marketing glorifies and normalizes complexity, several deeper, more innate
forces draw us developers toward it:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The creative temptation:</strong> We are problem-solvers by nature. Building a
complex, intricate system is a rewarding intellectual challenge, akin to
solving a magnificent puzzle. The temptation to over-engineer is a powerful
siren song when we’re flexing our creative muscles.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Legacy systems and technical debt:</strong> Many projects inherit convoluted
codebases. Adding new features often means piling on more complexity rather
than simplifying, as time and budget constraints prioritize quick fixes over
elegant, simple solutions.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Team dynamics and collaboration:</strong> In large teams, developers add layers of
abstraction to make code “future-proof” or accommodate diverse requirements.
This can lead to over-engineered solutions as each contributor adds their own
signature, creating a complex whole that no single person fully understands.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Pressure to innovate:</strong> In a competitive tech landscape, there’s a constant
pressure to differentiate. Novelty and innovation are often expressed through
new features and intricate designs, making complexity an easy, if not always
effective, way to stand out.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="build-pyramids-with-purpose">Build pyramids with purpose</h2>

<p>Build pyramids if you must, but build them like the Egyptians did: with a clear
purpose, a solid foundation, and chambers that actually contain something of
value - not just hollow, maze-like passages that future archaeologists (or the
poor soul maintaining your code in two years) will curse.</p>

<p>So next time you find yourself coding a 500-line abstraction for something that
could be copy-pasted a few times and done in 50 lines, ask yourself: are you
solving a real problem for the users and maintainers… or just indulging in
intellectual masturbation?</p>

  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Massive Attack turns concert into facial recognition surveillance experiment (289 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.gadgetreview.com/massive-attack-turns-concert-into-facial-recognition-surveillance-experiment</link>
            <guid>45255400</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 21:51:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.gadgetreview.com/massive-attack-turns-concert-into-facial-recognition-surveillance-experiment">https://www.gadgetreview.com/massive-attack-turns-concert-into-facial-recognition-surveillance-experiment</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45255400">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>Bristol band uses live facial recognition on concertgoers to create uncomfortable art about surveillance culture</p><div><p>Imagine you’re vibing to “Teardrop” when suddenly your face appears on the massive LED screen behind the band. Not as a fun crowd shot—as processed data in <a href="https://massiveattack.co.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Massive Attack’s</a> real-time <a href="https://www.gadgetreview.com/why-you-should-never-give-your-phone-to-cops-even-with-digital-ids">facial recognition</a> system. Welcome to the most uncomfortable concert experience of <strong>2025</strong>.</p><h2>When Your Face Becomes the Show</h2><p>The band deployed live facial recognition technology that captured and analyzed attendees during their recent performance.</p><p>During their latest tour stop, Massive Attack shocked fans by integrating <a href="https://www.threads.com/@cyrus_in_the_i/post/DOghqyIEWMs/video-massive-attack-shocks-fans-with-live-facial-recognitionat-a-recent-concert-the-b" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>facial recognition</strong></a> into the show itself. Live video feeds captured audience faces, processing them through recognition software and projecting the results as part of the visual experience. This wasn’t subtle venue security—your biometric data became part of the artistic statement, whether you consented or not.</p><p>Social media erupted with bewildered reactions from attendees. Some praised the band for forcing a conversation about surveillance that most people avoid, while others expressed discomfort with the unexpected data capture. The split reactions confirmed the band’s provocative intent had landed exactly as designed.</p><figure></figure><h2>Art Meets Digital Resistance</h2><p>This stunt aligns with the band’s decades-long critique of surveillance culture and digital control systems.</p><p>This provocation fits Massive Attack’s DNA perfectly. The Bristol collective has spent years weaving <a href="https://www.thefader.com/2019/09/25/massive-attack-robert-del-naja-mezzanine-interview" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">political commentary</a> into their performances, particularly around themes of <a href="https://www.gadgetreview.com/top-10-spy-gadgets-you-can-buy-right-now">surveillance</a> and control. Their collaboration with filmmaker <a href="https://massiveattack.ie/articles/massive-attacks-political-voice-music-as-protest/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Adam Curtis</strong></a> and consistent engagement with privacy issues positioned them as natural provocateurs for this moment.</p><p>Unlike typical concert technology that enhances your experience, this facial recognition system explicitly confronted attendees with the reality of <strong>data capture</strong>. The band made visible what usually happens invisibly—your face being recorded, analyzed, and potentially stored by systems you never explicitly agreed to interact with.</p><h2>The Consent Question Nobody Asked</h2><p>Details about data storage and participant consent remain unclear, adding to both artistic ambiguity and ethical concerns.</p><p>Here’s where things get murky. Massive Attack hasn’t released official details about what happened to the captured biometric data or whether <a href="https://nenadgeorgievski.substack.com/p/massive-attack-live-in-skopje-music" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>permanent records</strong></a> were kept. This opacity intensifies the artistic statement while raising legitimate <a href="https://www.gadgetreview.com/evil-tech-scandals-failures-that-took-advantage-millions-people">privacy</a> questions about conducting surveillance to critique surveillance.</p><p>The audience split predictably along ideological lines. Privacy advocates called it a boundary violation disguised as art. Others viewed it as necessary shock therapy for our sleepwalking acceptance of facial recognition in everyday spaces. Both reactions prove the intervention achieved its disruptive goal.</p><p>Your relationship with facial recognition technology just got more complicated. Every venue, every event, every public space potentially captures your likeness. Massive Attack simply made the invisible visible—and deeply uncomfortable. The question now isn’t whether this was art or privacy violation, but whether you’re ready to confront how normalized surveillance has become in your daily life.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[William Gibson Reads Neuromancer (2004) (247 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://bearcave.com/bookrev/neuromancer/neuromancer_audio.html</link>
            <guid>45255137</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 21:28:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://bearcave.com/bookrev/neuromancer/neuromancer_audio.html">http://bearcave.com/bookrev/neuromancer/neuromancer_audio.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45255137">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">



<p>
The author <a href="http://www.raybradbury.com/">Ray Bradbury</a> is
one of the early science fiction authors that moved science fiction
into a literary form.  As a writer Bradbury constructs beautifully
written stories and novels.  Bradbury's writing is in stark contrast
to Bradbury as a speaker.  The first time I heard Ray Bradbury speak
was at the Association for Computing Machinery (ACM) yearly conference
in Los Angeles in the 1980s.  Hearing Bradbury speak is an almost
painful experience.  The pictures that Bradbury can paint with the
written word seem to be entirely missing when Bradbury speaks.  He is
halting, awkward and does not seem to know where he wants to go
in his talk.
</p>

<p>
In contrast to Bradbury, listenting to William Gibson has the feel of
his written work.  The same complex world view and sentence structure
is there, although not as finely edited.  An example of this can be
found in the documentary made about William Gibson, <a href="http://www.nomaps.com/"><i>No Maps for these Territories</i></a>.
This documentary includes extensive interviews with William Gibson.
<i>No Maps</i> also provides a glimpse of the way Gibson looks at the
interconnections and relationships in the world around us.  This view
of Gibson's mind shows us his genius.
</p>

<p>
The mirror between William Gibson's spoken voice and his written voice
gives special force to his readings of his work.  Early in his career
Gibson did an abridged reading of <i>Neuromancer</i>, his first novel
and the work that made him famous.  It was in this novel that Gibson
coined the term <i>cyberspace</i>.  This reading was only published on
audio-tape and is now out of print.
</p>

<p>
I hate the idea that Gibson's wonderful reading of <i>Neuromancer</i>
should be lost or inaccessable.  I was only able to hear it because
the Mountain View (California) Library had a copy.  Fortunately I've
been able to find an MP3 copy of these audio tapes.  They can be
downloaded below.
</p>

<p>
I am only providing these MP3s because the original has been out of
print for years.  As a software engineer I believe that I should be
paid for my work.  If I hold this view then it is only reasonable that
I should also believe that artist should be paid for their work.  All
of the software and music I own I have paid for (or is open source).
I would prefer that the publisher re-issue the audio-tape of William
Gibson's reading in a more modern format (perhaps CD) and that William
Gibson collect royalties on this work.  Gibson's reading has been out
of print so long that I can only assume that this is unlikely to
happen.
</p>

<p>
If you're a fan of William Gibson I hope that others will mirror these
files as well so that they will never be lost.
</p>
<p>
This reading was published on four magnetic tape audio cassetts.
These have been re-recorded in MP3 format:
</p>

<table>
<tbody><tr>
<th><b><i>Neuromancer</i></b> (abridged) read by William Gibson</th>
</tr>
  <tr><td><a href="http://www.bearcave.com/bookrev/neuromancer/Tape1a.mp3">Tape 1, side 1</a></td></tr>
  <tr><td><a href="http://www.bearcave.com/bookrev/neuromancer/Tape1b.mp3">Tape 1, side 2</a></td></tr>
  <tr><td><a href="http://www.bearcave.com/bookrev/neuromancer/Tape2a.mp3">Tape 2, side 1</a></td></tr>
  <tr><td><a href="http://www.bearcave.com/bookrev/neuromancer/Tape2b.mp3">Tape 2, side 2</a></td></tr>
  <tr><td><a href="http://www.bearcave.com/bookrev/neuromancer/Tape3a.mp3">Tape 3, side 1</a></td></tr>
  <tr><td><a href="http://www.bearcave.com/bookrev/neuromancer/Tape3b.mp3">Tape 3, side 2</a></td></tr>
  <tr><td><a href="http://www.bearcave.com/bookrev/neuromancer/Tape4a.mp3">Tape 4, side 1</a></td></tr>
  <tr><td><a href="http://www.bearcave.com/bookrev/neuromancer/Tape4b.mp3">Tape 4, side 2</a></td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<ul>
<li>
<p>
<a href="http://www.voidspace.org.uk/cyberpunk/neuromancer.shtml">An
on-line copy of William Gibson's <i>Neuromancer</i></a>
</p>
<p>
Neuromancer is one of the few books that I've read many times.  All of
Gibson's books are good (well, except for <i>The Difference
Engine</i>, but that's Bruce Sterling's fault).  <i>Neuromancer</i> is
still in print, so you should go out an buy a copy if you want to read
it.  Writers pay their bills from the royalties from book sales.  I've
included the link above in case you want to get a feel for the book
before you buy it (even paperback books are not cheap these days).
</p>
</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://www.bearcave.com/bookrev/revindex.htm">Book review table of contents</a></p>

<p><i><a href="http://www.bearcave.com/bear_contents.shtml">back to home page</a></i></p>

<address><a href="mailto:iank@bearcave.com">
<img src="http://www.bearcave.com/images/mailicon.gif" width="60" height="82">
</a></address>



</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Imperial Tyranny, Korean Humiliation (109 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://english.hani.co.kr/arti/english_edition/english_editorials/1218475.html</link>
            <guid>45255132</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 21:27:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://english.hani.co.kr/arti/english_edition/english_editorials/1218475.html">https://english.hani.co.kr/arti/english_edition/english_editorials/1218475.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45255132">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <div>
              <p><img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/894/604/imgdb/original/2025/0912/7617576652278449.webp" alt="A worker at a Hyundai-LG battery plant in Georgia is shackled by US authorities after an immigration raid on Sept. 4, 2025. US Immigration and Customs Enforcement later released video footage of the raid. (Yonhap)"></p><p>A worker at a Hyundai-LG battery plant in Georgia is shackled by US authorities after an immigration raid on Sept. 4, 2025. US Immigration and Customs Enforcement later released video footage of the raid. (Yonhap)</p>
            </div>
          <br>
            <div>
              <p><img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/151/181/imgdb/original/2025/0912/611757665227907.webp" alt=""></p>
            </div>
          <p><strong>By Park Hyun, editorial writer</strong></p><p>While many would have you believe that the fiasco involving over 300 Korean workers being arrested and detained by US immigration authorities has been resolved by allowing the workers to “voluntarily depart” back to Korea, this is far from the truth. Korea as a nation was deeply shocked to witness our workers, who had traveled to the US to work at the request of American investors, shackled at their hands and feet with chains. This barbaric incident will leave a lasting stain on Korea-US relations.</p><p>The mass arrests are undoubtedly a wake-up call, a major rupture that opens our eyes to what is happening in the US at this moment. We must heed this warning to close the loopholes and traps in our investment projects with the US. Otherwise, we may eventually face even greater calamity.</p><p>To understand what’s at the core of this situation, we must revisit the “Make America Great Again” movement championed by US President Donald Trump. MAGA represents a reactionary movement by white evangelical forces seeking to revert America to a time before the civil rights movement in the 1960s. Its core supporters are low-income, poorly educated white Americans and evangelical Protestants. Trump has become a voice amplifying the anxieties of these groups, whose societal status has been shaken by job losses due to globalization, deepening economic polarization, and a surge in immigration. Trump has incited them to channel their anger toward the established elite and “outsiders,” such as people of color, undocumented immigrants, and Muslims.</p><p>Trump is fundamentally a populist and white supremacist. His slogan of “Make America Great Again” would be phrased more accurately as “Make White America Great Again.” His insistence on imposing a 50% tariff specifically on steel and aluminum stems from the fact that white, Protestant populations are concentrated in the American Rust Belt.</p><p>The massive crackdown on allegedly undocumented immigrants at the Hyundai-LG Energy Solution plant in Georgia must also be understood within this context. The sight of our workers being led out in chains resembles images of African slaves in the 18th and 19th centuries being dragged out by their owners. The Department of Homeland Security boasted that the raid was “the largest single-site enforcement operation in [its] history,” and Immigration and Customs Enforcement even brazenly released footage of the operation — which clearly risks human rights violations — as if to flaunt these arrests as their achievement.</p><p>Far-right white Americans may have rejoiced inwardly at this incident. Even politicians like the governor of Georgia and local lawmakers, who had previously been enthusiastic about hosting the factory, have abruptly changed their stance and joined the chorus of discontent. This shift is likely because it’s difficult to ignore the anti-immigrant sentiment among Americans born into citizenship. The US is in the grip of an irrational frenzy, reminiscent of the McCarthyism that swept through American society in the 1950s. The US could have resolved this visa issue diplomatically by giving Korea advance notice as an ally. Yet, the crackdown — complete with helicopters and armored vehicles, as if to gleefully flaunt their power — can only be explained as a political performance.</p><p>The Trump administration’s plan to revive manufacturing in America is a strategy deeply influenced by political calculations rather than economic logic. Having stoked the discontent of the white working class in the Rust Belt to win his presidency, Trump has a strong motive to continue exploiting them politically. While he, as a political leader, may attempt to pursue such policies, these efforts amount to little more than wishful thinking. Historically, such attempts have rarely succeeded. If they had, why did the British Empire, once called a territory where the sun never sets, crumble over time?</p><p>Declining industries inevitably relocate to emerging nations over time. Even in Korea, we face difficulties in reviving such industries. How much more challenging would it be for the US, where production costs are at least 30% higher than ours, and over two decades of hollowing-out in manufacturing have collapsed the industrial ecosystem? Trump is dreaming a delusional fantasy of using imperial might to forcibly mobilize allies and reverse this trend. To make matters worse, treating allied workers who are trying their best to assist in realizing this pipe dream as if they are slaves of a vassal state will jeopardize even those projects that had some potential. We’re currently watching the US foolishly shoot itself in the foot.</p><p>This incident should prompt us in Korea to comprehensively reassess our investment projects in the US. We agreed to a tariff deal during a transitional period when President Lee Jae Myung had just taken office. Trump’s aggressive tactics forced us to follow Japan’s lead, but we must now take a cold, hard look at the specifics of what we agreed to. The US made outrageous demands on Japan: execute US$550 billion in investments within Trump’s term, provide funds within 45 days if Trump orders it, and hand over 50%-90% of profits to the US. Reports say the US is now making identical demands of us.</p><p>Following the footsteps of Japan, the world’s third-largest economy and a quasi-reserve currency nation, could poison our own economy. Rather than yielding to America’s unreasonable demands to avert an immediate crisis, the government must clearly distinguish what we can and cannot do and negotiate with the US. We must bear in mind that even if the manufacturing revival fails, the US, as the world’s largest economy and reserve currency holder, will likely suffer little harm. Our economy, on the other hand, could be severely shaken by a major shock.</p><p>Please direct questions or comments to [<a href="mailto:english@hani.co.kr">english@hani.co.kr</a>]</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ghost kitchens are dying (109 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://davidrmann3.substack.com/p/ghost-kitchens-are-dying-heres-the</link>
            <guid>45254505</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 20:25:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://davidrmann3.substack.com/p/ghost-kitchens-are-dying-heres-the">https://davidrmann3.substack.com/p/ghost-kitchens-are-dying-heres-the</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45254505">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Ucth!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff8c74335-d9a6-46da-bf26-25371c429f5f_1024x1024.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Ucth!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff8c74335-d9a6-46da-bf26-25371c429f5f_1024x1024.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Ucth!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff8c74335-d9a6-46da-bf26-25371c429f5f_1024x1024.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Ucth!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff8c74335-d9a6-46da-bf26-25371c429f5f_1024x1024.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Ucth!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff8c74335-d9a6-46da-bf26-25371c429f5f_1024x1024.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Ucth!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff8c74335-d9a6-46da-bf26-25371c429f5f_1024x1024.png" width="1024" height="1024" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/f8c74335-d9a6-46da-bf26-25371c429f5f_1024x1024.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1024,&quot;width&quot;:1024,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:1772728,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://davidrmann3.substack.com/i/173614060?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff8c74335-d9a6-46da-bf26-25371c429f5f_1024x1024.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Ucth!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff8c74335-d9a6-46da-bf26-25371c429f5f_1024x1024.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Ucth!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff8c74335-d9a6-46da-bf26-25371c429f5f_1024x1024.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Ucth!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff8c74335-d9a6-46da-bf26-25371c429f5f_1024x1024.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Ucth!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff8c74335-d9a6-46da-bf26-25371c429f5f_1024x1024.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><strong>Ghost Kitchens Are Dying. Here's the $15 Billion Lesson Every Restaurateur Must Learn.</strong></p><p>A ghost kitchen stripped away everything you think makes a restaurant a restaurant. No dining room. No servers. No storefront. No customers walking through the door. Just a kitchen. Four walls. Commercial equipment. And a phone that never stops ringing with delivery orders.</p><p>Ghost kitchens exist only in the digital world. Customers find them on DoorDash, Uber Eats, and Grubhub. They order through an app. Food gets cooked in a shared commercial space. A driver picks it up. 30 minutes later, it shows up at your door in a paper bag.</p><p>The kitchen itself operates like a factory assembly line. One space prepares food for multiple virtual restaurant brands³. The same cook making your "authentic" Italian pasta also flips burgers for a completely different brand name. Then switches to preparing tacos for a third virtual restaurant. All from the same kitchen. All with different logos on the delivery apps.</p><p>These facilities rent space in industrial areas where the rent costs less. No need for prime real estate. No foot traffic required. No parking spaces. No bathroom maintenance. No dining room cleaning.</p><p>The promise sounded perfect. Lower costs. Higher profits. Multiple revenue streams from one location.</p><p>The numbers, however, tell the brutal story of the Ghost kitchen. Companies raised over $3 billion in venture capital from 2020 to 2022¹. Today, their leaders are shutting down, pivoting away from physical operations, or laying off staff in waves.</p><p>You were sold efficiency. You got financial ruin.</p><p><strong>The Collapse of the Ghost Kitchen Giants</strong></p><p><span>Kitchen United raised $100 million in July 2022, including funding from grocery giant Kroger². Fifteen months later, the company shut down all eight of its Kroger locations². That represented 44% of Kitchen United's entire 18-unit footprint². The company then announced it would sell or close every remaining physical location and pivot to "software only"</span><sup>3</sup><span>.</span></p><p>Translation: We burned through $100 million and have nothing left to show for it.</p><p><span>CloudKitchens raised $850 million in November 2021 at a $15 billion valuation from investors including Microsoft</span><sup>4</sup><span>. By early 2023, the company's facilities were running at only 50% occupancy</span><sup>3</sup><span>. Internal data showed that 41 out of 71 restaurants at five CloudKitchens locations closed within one year</span><sup>3</sup><span>. That's a 58% failure rate.</span></p><p><span>The company responded with staff layoffs and location closures throughout 2023</span><sup>5</sup><span>.</span></p><p><span>Nextbite endured three rounds of layoffs within 14 months before selling to competitor Sam Nazarian</span><sup>4</sup><span>. Celebrity-backed brands like Hotbox by Wiz Khalifa and George Lopez Tacos generated terrible reviews and vanishing sales.</span></p><p><span>Reef lost its partnership with Wendy's after promising 700 delivery kitchen locations</span><sup>5</sup><span>. The deal that was supposed to define the industry's future collapsed completely.</span></p><p><strong>The Hidden Economics That Killed Profitability</strong></p><p><span>Ghost kitchens promised lower costs. The math never worked. Delivery apps charge restaurants up to 30% commission fees</span><sup>5</sup><span>. Ghost kitchen operators add rent plus percentage fees on top. Equipment repairs and maintenance create constant expenses. Marketing costs multiply when you have no storefront presence.</span></p><p>Layering these costs together, restaurants discovered a devastating truth: there wasn't enough money left for anyone to make a profit.</p><p>Quality control became impossible. Shared kitchen facilities meant that one staff member prepared food for multiple brands simultaneously. No ownership. No accountability. Just assembly-line cooking with zero connection to customers.</p><p>When food arrived cold or wrong, customers had no relationship with the brand to forgive mistakes. No loyal regulars. No servers to smooth over problems. Just angry reviews that destroyed virtual brands forever. No reason for repeat business.</p><p><strong>The Numbers Behind the Collapse</strong></p><p><span>The global ghost kitchen market was valued at $58.61 billion in 2022</span><sup>5</sup><span>. Industry projections show growth to $177.85 billion by 2032</span><sup>5</sup><span>. But these projections ignore the operational reality killing companies today.</span></p><p><span>Approximately 7,606 ghost kitchen operations remain active across the United States</span><sup>5</sup><span>. This sounds substantial until you realize how many have closed, pivoted, or failed in the past two years.</span></p><p><span>The highest-performing ghost kitchens report profit margins between 10-30%</span><sup>5</sup><span>. Traditional restaurants typically see margins of 3-5%</span><sup>5</sup><span>. But these numbers ignore the failure rates. When 58% of restaurants in your facility close within twelve months, your occupancy and revenue collapse.</span></p><p><strong>Quality Became the Fatal Flaw</strong></p><p>Food that travels well requires different recipes, different ingredients, different packaging. Most restaurants never figured this out. Ghost kitchens became synonymous with disappointing food experiences.</p><p><span>Virtual brands with celebrity names generated initial curiosity. But customers who ordered Packed Bowls by Wiz Khalifa once rarely reordered after experiencing cold food and small portions</span><sup>5</sup><span>. One Cincinnati operator threw away half his stock of Wiz Khalifa ingredients because customers wouldn't come back</span><sup>5</sup><span>.</span></p><p>The first lesson is that name recognition without quality execution equals business failure.</p><p><strong>There Is No Connection</strong></p><p>When you remove the human connection between restaurant and customer, you remove everything that makes people loyal to restaurants. When food travels twenty minutes in a bag, quality suffers. When customers have problems, there's no manager to smooth things over.</p><p>Ghost kitchens became digital fast food factories. Anonymous. Disposable. Forgettable.</p><p>The second lesson is that restaurants aren't just about food. They're about places. People. Experiences. Community.</p><p><strong>What Actually Works</strong></p><p>Focus on your core restaurant first. Make it profitable. Build loyal customers. Control your kitchen. Control your quality. Build a human connection.</p><p>If you want to expand, open a second location. Own or lease the space directly. Build your brand in the community. Skip the middleman operators. Skip the celebrity partnerships. Skip the virtual brands with made-up names.</p><p>The restaurant business has no shortcuts. It never did. It never will.</p><p>The $15 billion lesson is that real restaurants serve real customers in real locations, with real people. Everything else is just an expensive distraction.</p><p>Build something real instead.</p><p>#RestaurantBusiness #GhostKitchens #RestaurantStrategy #FoodDelivery #RestaurantManagement</p><p>Footnotes</p><p>1. Thomas, Barry. "Ghost kitchens are making a post-pandemic pivot to survive." Modern Retail, December 10, 2023.</p><p>2. "Kitchen United shuts down its Kroger food halls." Restaurant Business, November 27, 2023.</p><p>3. "Kitchen United will sell or close all physical units, pivot to software." Restaurant Dive, November 27, 2023.</p><p>4. "Kalanick's CloudKitchens Triples Valuation to $15 Billion, Hires CFO." Business Insider, January 4, 2022.</p><p>5. "The Troubles Continue for Uber Co-Founder's CloudKitchens." Eater, September 5, 2023.</p><p>6. Fantozzi, Joanna. "Nextbite's failures are a warning for the entire virtual restaurant industry." Nation's Restaurant News, June 14, 2023.</p><p>7. "Ghost kitchens are making a post-pandemic pivot to survive." Modern Retail, December 10, 2023.</p><p>8. Vidakovic, Sasha. "Ghost Kitchens: 2025 Statistics &amp; Facts." OysterLink, July 6, 2025.</p><p>9. "Nextbite's failures are a warning for the entire virtual restaurant industry." Nation's Restaurant News, June 14, 2023.</p><p>If you want more straight talk about what actually works in restaurants, follow me. No charge. No bullshit. Just the truth about running profitable food businesses from someone who has seen every mistake you're about to make.</p><p>I write for operators who want real answers. Not marketing speak. Not consultant double-talk. Just the hard-earned lessons that separate successful restaurants from expensive failures.</p><p>Your competition is reading industry magazines full of fluff. You'll get the unvarnished reality that keeps places profitable.</p><p>Follow for free. Unsubscribe anytime. Your call.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How People Use ChatGPT [pdf] (135 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://cdn.openai.com/pdf/a253471f-8260-40c6-a2cc-aa93fe9f142e/economic-research-chatgpt-usage-paper.pdf</link>
            <guid>45253775</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 19:14:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://cdn.openai.com/pdf/a253471f-8260-40c6-a2cc-aa93fe9f142e/economic-research-chatgpt-usage-paper.pdf">https://cdn.openai.com/pdf/a253471f-8260-40c6-a2cc-aa93fe9f142e/economic-research-chatgpt-usage-paper.pdf</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45253775">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Addendum to GPT-5 system card: GPT-5-Codex (230 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://openai.com/index/gpt-5-system-card-addendum-gpt-5-codex/</link>
            <guid>45253458</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 18:45:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://openai.com/index/gpt-5-system-card-addendum-gpt-5-codex/">https://openai.com/index/gpt-5-system-card-addendum-gpt-5-codex/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45253458">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://openai.com/index/gpt-5-system-card-addendum-gpt-5-codex/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hosting a website on a disposable vape (1152 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://bogdanthegeek.github.io/blog/projects/vapeserver/</link>
            <guid>45252817</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 17:53:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://bogdanthegeek.github.io/blog/projects/vapeserver/">https://bogdanthegeek.github.io/blog/projects/vapeserver/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45252817">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><h2 id="preface">Preface<a href="#preface" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>This article is <em>NOT</em> served from a web server running on a disposable vape. If you want to see the real deal, click <a href="http://ewaste.fka.wtf/">here</a>. The content is otherwise identical.</p><h2 id="background">Background<a href="#background" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>For a couple of years now, I have been collecting disposable vapes from friends and family. Initially, I only salvaged the batteries for “future” projects (It’s not hoarding, I promise), but recently, disposable vapes have gotten more advanced. I wouldn’t want to be the lawyer who one day will have to argue how a device with USB C and a rechargeable battery can be classified as “disposable”. Thankfully, I don’t plan on pursuing law anytime soon.</p><p>Last year, I was tearing apart some of these fancier pacifiers for adults when I noticed something that caught my eye, instead of the expected black blob of goo hiding some ASIC (Application Specific Integrated Circuit) I see a little integrated circuit inscribed “PUYA”.
I don’t blame you if this name doesn’t excite you as much it does me, most people have never heard of them. They are most well known for their flash chips, but I first came across them after reading Jay Carlson’s blog post about <a href="https://jaycarlson.net/2023/02/04/the-cheapest-flash-microcontroller-you-can-buy-is-actually-an-arm-cortex-m0/">the cheapest flash microcontroller you can buy</a>. They are quite capable little ARM Cortex-M0+ micros.</p><p>Over the past year I have collected quite a few of these PY32 based vapes, all of them from different models of vape from the same manufacturer. It’s not my place to do free advertising for big tobacco, so I won’t mention the brand I got it from, but if anyone who worked on designing them reads this, thanks for labeling the debug pins!</p><h2 id="what-are-we-working-with">What are we working with<a href="#what-are-we-working-with" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>The chip is marked <code>PUYA C642F15</code>, which wasn’t very helpful. I was pretty sure it was a <code>PY32F002A</code>, but after poking around with <a href="http://pyocd.io/">pyOCD</a>, I noticed that the flash was 24k and we have 3k of RAM. The extra flash meant that it was more likely a <code>PY32F002B</code>, which is actually a very different chip.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p><p>So here are the specs of a microcontroller so <em>bad</em>, it’s basically disposable:</p><ul><li>24MHz Coretex M0+</li><li>24KiB of Flash Storage</li><li>3KiB of Static RAM</li><li>a few peripherals, none of which we will use.</li></ul><p>You may look at those specs and think that it’s not much to work with. I don’t blame you, a 10y old phone can barely load google, and this is about 100x slower. I on the other hand see a <em>blazingly</em> fast web server.</p><h2 id="getting-online">Getting online<a href="#getting-online" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>The idea of hosting a web server on a vape didn’t come to me instantly. In fact, I have been playing around with them for a while, but after writing my post on <a href="https://bogdanthegeek.github.io/blog/insights/jlink-rtt-for-the-masses/">semihosting</a>, the penny dropped.</p><p>If you don’t feel like reading that article, semihosting is basically syscalls for embedded ARM microcontrollers. You throw some values/pointers into some registers and call a breakpoint instruction. An attached debugger interprets the values in the registers and performs certain actions. Most people just use this to get some logs printed from the microcontroller, but they are actually bi-directional.</p><p>If you are older than me, you might remember a time before Wi-Fi and Ethernet, the dark ages, when you had to use dial-up modems to get online. You might also know that the ghosts of those modems still linger all around us. Almost all USB serial devices actually emulate those modems: a 56k modem is just 57600 baud serial device. Data between some of these modems was transmitted using a protocol called SLIP (Serial Line Internet Protocol).<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup></p><p>This may not come as a surprise, but Linux (and with some tweaking even macOS) supports SLIP. The <code>slattach</code> utility can make any <code>/dev/tty*</code> send and receive IP packets. All we have to do is put the data down the wire in the right format and provide a virtual tty.
This is actually easier than you might imagine, pyOCD can forward all semihosting though a telnet port. Then, we use <code>socat</code> to link that port to a virtual tty:</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="sh"><span><span>pyocd gdb -S -O semihost_console_type<span>=</span>telnet -T <span>$(</span>PORT<span>)</span> <span>$(</span>PYOCDFLAGS<span>)</span> &amp;
</span></span><span><span>socat PTY,link<span>=</span><span>$(</span>TTY<span>)</span>,raw,echo<span>=</span><span>0</span> TCP:localhost:<span>$(</span>PORT<span>)</span>,nodelay &amp;
</span></span><span><span>sudo slattach -L -p slip -s <span>115200</span> <span>$(</span>TTY<span>)</span> &amp;
</span></span><span><span>sudo ip addr add 192.168.190.1 peer 192.168.190.2/24 dev sl0
</span></span><span><span>sudo ip link set mtu <span>1500</span> up dev sl0
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Ok, so we have a “modem”, but that’s hardly a web server. To actually talk TCP/IP, we need an IP stack. There are many choices, but I went with <a href="https://github.com/adamdunkels/uip/tree/uip-0-9">uIP</a> because it’s pretty small, doesn’t require an RTOS, and it’s easy to port to other platforms.
It also, helpfully, comes with a very minimal HTTP server example.</p><p>After porting the SLIP code to use semihosting, I had a working web server…half of the time.
As with most highly optimised libraries, uIP was designed for 8 and 16-bit machines, which rarely have memory alignment requirements. On ARM however, if you dereference a <code>u16 *</code>, you better hope that address is even, or you’ll get an exception. The <code>uip_chksum</code> assumed <code>u16</code> alignment, but the script that creates the filesystem didn’t.
I actually decided to modify a bit the structure of the filesystem to make it a bit more portable.
This was my first time working with <code>perl</code> and I have to say, it’s quite well suited to this kind of task.</p><h2 id="blazingly-fast">Blazingly fast<a href="#blazingly-fast" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>So how fast is a web server running on a disposable microcontroller. Well, initially, not very fast. Pings took ~1.5s with 50% packet loss and a simple page took over 20s to load. That’s so bad, it’s actually funny, and I kind of wanted to leave it there.</p><p>However, the problem was actually between the seat and the steering wheel the whole time. The first implementation read and wrote a single character at a time, which had a massive overhead associated with it. I previously benchmarked semihosting on this device, and I was getting ~20KiB/s, but uIP’s SLIP implementation was designed for very low memory devices, so it was serialising the data byte by byte.
We have a whopping 3kiB of RAM to play with, so I added a ring buffer to cache reads from the host and feed them into the SLIP poll function. I also split writes in batches to allow for escaping.</p><p>Now this is what I call blazingly fast! Pings now take 20ms, no packet loss and a full page loads in about 160ms. This was using using almost all of the RAM, but I could also dial down the sizes of the buffer to have more than enough headroom to run other tasks. The project repo has everything set to a nice balance latency and RAM usage:</p><pre tabindex="0"><code>Memory region         Used Size  Region Size  %age Used
           FLASH:        5116 B        24 KB     20.82%
             RAM:        1380 B         3 KB     44.92%
</code></pre><p>For this blog however, I paid for none of the RAM, so I’ll use all of the RAM.</p><p>As you may have noticed, we have just under 20kiB (80%) of storage space. That may not be enough to ship all of React, but as you can see, it’s more than enough to host this entire blog post.
And this is not just a static page server, you can run any server-side code you want, if you know C that is.</p><p>Just for fun, I added a json api endpoint to get the number of requests to the main page (since the last crash) and the unique ID of the microcontroller.</p><h2 id="resources">Resources<a href="#resources" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><ul><li><a href="https://github.com/BogdanTheGeek/semihost-ip">Code for this project</a></li></ul></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[React is winning by default and slowing innovation (535 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.lorenstew.art/blog/react-won-by-default/</link>
            <guid>45252715</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 17:46:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.lorenstew.art/blog/react-won-by-default/">https://www.lorenstew.art/blog/react-won-by-default/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45252715">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-astro-cid-dmqsi53g="">  <article data-astro-cid-7jjqptxk="">  <div data-astro-cid-7jjqptxk=""> 
<p>React is no longer winning by technical merit. Today it is winning by default. That default is now slowing innovation across the frontend ecosystem.</p>
<p>When teams need a new frontend, the conversation rarely starts with “What are the constraints and which tool best fits them?” It often starts with “Let’s use React; everyone knows React.” That reflex creates a self-perpetuating cycle where network effects, rather than technical fit, decide architecture.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, frameworks with real innovations struggle for adoption. Svelte compiles away framework overhead. Solid delivers fine-grained reactivity without virtual-DOM tax. Qwik achieves instant startup via resumability. These approaches can outperform React’s model in common scenarios, but they rarely get a fair evaluation because React is chosen by default.</p>
<p>React is excellent at many things. The problem isn’t React itself, it’s the React-by-default mindset.</p>
<h2 id="the-innovation-ceiling">The Innovation Ceiling</h2>
<p>React’s technical foundations explain some of today’s friction. The virtual DOM was a clever solution for 2013’s problems, but as Rich Harris outlined in <a href="https://svelte.dev/blog/virtual-dom-is-pure-overhead">“Virtual DOM is pure overhead”</a>, it introduces work modern compilers can often avoid.</p>
<p>Hooks addressed class component pain but introduced new kinds of complexity: dependency arrays, stale closures, and misused effects. Even React’s own docs emphasize restraint: <a href="https://react.dev/learn/you-might-not-need-an-effect">“You Might Not Need an Effect”</a>. Server Components improve time-to-first-byte, but add architectural complexity and new failure modes.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://react.dev/learn/react-compiler">React Compiler</a> is a smart solution that automates patterns like <code>useMemo</code>/<code>useCallback</code>. Its existence is also a signal: we’re optimizing around constraints baked into the model.</p>
<p>Contrast this with alternative approaches: Svelte 5’s <a href="https://svelte.dev/blog/runes">Runes</a> simplify reactivity at compile time; Solid’s <a href="https://www.solidjs.com/docs/latest#reactivity">fine-grained reactivity</a> updates exactly what changed; Qwik’s <a href="https://qwik.builder.io/docs/concepts/resumable/">resumability</a> eliminates traditional hydration. These aren’t incremental tweaks to React’s model—they’re different models with different ceilings.</p>
<p>Innovation without adoption doesn’t change outcomes. Adoption can’t happen when the choice is made by reflex.</p>
<h2 id="the-technical-debt-were-all-carrying">The Technical Debt We’re All Carrying</h2>
<p>Defaulting to React often ships a runtime and reconciliation cost we no longer question. Even when it’s fast enough, the ceiling is lower than compile-time or fine-grained models. Developer time is spent managing re-renders, effect dependencies, and hydration boundaries instead of shipping value. The broader lesson from performance research is consistent: JavaScript is expensive on the critical path (<a href="https://medium.com/dev-channel/the-cost-of-javascript-84009f51e99e">The Cost of JavaScript</a>).</p>
<p>We’ve centered mental models around “React patterns” instead of web fundamentals, reducing portability of skills and making architectural inertia more likely.</p>
<p>The loss isn’t just performance, it’s opportunity cost when better-fit alternatives are never evaluated. For instance, benchmarks like the <a href="https://krausest.github.io/js-framework-benchmark/">JS Framework Benchmark</a> show alternatives like Solid achieving up to 2-3x faster updates in reactivity-heavy scenarios compared to React.</p>
<h2 id="the-frameworks-being-suffocated">The Frameworks Being Suffocated</h2>
<h3 id="svelte-the-compiler-revolution">Svelte: The Compiler Revolution</h3>
<p>Svelte shifts work to compile time: no virtual DOM, minimal runtime. Components become targeted DOM operations. The mental model aligns with web fundamentals.</p>
<p>But “not enough jobs” keeps Svelte adoption artificially low despite its technical superiority for most use cases. Real-world examples, like The Guardian’s adoption of Svelte for their frontend, demonstrate measurable gains in performance and developer productivity, with reported reductions in bundle sizes and faster load times. For instance, as detailed in <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/javascript-framework-puts-web-pages-diet/">Wired’s article on Svelte</a>, developer Shawn Wang (<a href="https://x.com/swyx">@swyx</a> on X/Twitter) reduced his site’s size from 187KB in React to just 9KB in Svelte by leveraging its compile-time optimizations, which shift framework overhead away from runtime. This leads to faster, more efficient apps especially on slow connections.</p>
<h3 id="solid-the-reactive-primitive-approach">Solid: The Reactive Primitive Approach</h3>
<p>Solid delivers fine-grained reactivity with JSX familiarity. Updates flow through signals directly to affected DOM nodes, bypassing reconciliation bottlenecks. Strong performance characteristics, limited mindshare. As outlined in Solid’s <a href="https://www.solidjs.com/guides/comparison">comparison guide</a>, this approach enables more efficient updates than React’s virtual DOM, with precise reactivity that minimizes unnecessary work and improves developer experience through simpler state management.</p>
<p>While prominent case studies are scarcer than for more established frameworks, this is largely due to Solid’s lower adoption. Yet anecdotal reports from early adopters suggest similar transformative gains in update efficiency and code simplicity, waiting to be scaled and shared as more teams experiment.</p>
<h3 id="qwik-the-resumability-innovation">Qwik: The Resumability Innovation</h3>
<p>Qwik uses resumability instead of hydration, enabling instant startup by loading only what the current interaction needs. Ideal for large sites, long sessions, or slow networks. According to Qwik’s <a href="https://qwik.dev/docs/concepts/think-qwik/">Think Qwik guide</a>, this is achieved through progressive loading and serializing both state and code. Apps can thus resume execution instantly without heavy client-side bootstrapping, resulting in superior scalability and reduced initial load times compared to traditional frameworks.</p>
<p>Success stories for Qwik may be less visible simply because fewer teams have broken from defaults to try it. But those who have report dramatic improvements in startup times and resource efficiency, indicating a wealth of untapped potential if adoption grows.</p>
<p>All three under-adopted not for lack of merit, but because the default choice blocks trying them out.</p>
<p>Furthermore, React’s API surface area is notably larger and more complex than its alternatives, encompassing concepts like hooks, context, reducers, and memoization patterns that require careful management to avoid pitfalls. This expansive API contributes to higher cognitive load for developers, often leading to bugs from misunderstood dependencies or over-engineering. For example, in Cloudflare’s <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/deep-dive-into-cloudflares-sept-12-dashboard-and-api-outage/">September 12, 2025 outage</a>, a useEffect hook with a problematic dependency array triggered repeated API calls, overwhelming their Tenant Service and causing widespread failures. In contrast, frameworks like Svelte, Solid, and Qwik feature smaller, more focused APIs that emphasize simplicity and web fundamentals, reducing the mental overhead and making them easier to master and maintain.</p>
<h2 id="the-network-effect-prison">The Network Effect Prison</h2>
<p>React’s dominance creates self-reinforcing barriers. Job postings ask for “React developers” rather than “frontend engineers,” limiting skill diversity. Component libraries and team muscle memory create institutional inertia.</p>
<p>Risk-averse leaders choose the “safe” option. Schools teach what jobs ask for. The cycle continues independent of technical merit.</p>
<p>That’s not healthy competition; it’s ecosystem capture by default.</p>
<h2 id="breaking-the-network-effect">Breaking the Network Effect</h2>
<p>Escaping requires deliberate action at multiple levels. Technical leaders should choose based on constraints and merits, not momentum. Companies can allocate a small innovation budget to trying alternatives. Developers can upskill beyond a single mental model.</p>
<p>Educators can teach framework-agnostic concepts alongside specific tools. Open source contributors can help alternative ecosystems mature.</p>
<p>Change won’t happen automatically. It requires conscious choice.</p>
<h2 id="framework-evaluation-checklist">Framework Evaluation Checklist</h2>
<p>To make deliberate choices, use this simple checklist when starting a new project:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Assess Performance Needs</strong>: Evaluate metrics like startup time, update efficiency, and bundle size. Prioritize frameworks with compile-time optimizations if speed is critical.</li>
<li><strong>Team Skills and Learning Curve</strong>: Consider existing expertise but factor in migration paths; many alternatives offer gentle ramps (e.g., Solid’s JSX compatibility with React).</li>
<li><strong>Scaling and Cost of Ownership</strong>: Calculate long-term costs, including maintenance, dependency management, and tech debt. Alternatives often reduce runtime overhead, lowering hosting costs and improving scalability.</li>
<li><strong>Ecosystem Fit</strong>: Balance maturity with innovation; pilot in non-critical areas to test migration feasibility and ROI.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="the-standard-counterarguments">The Standard Counter‑Arguments</h2>
<p><strong>“But ecosystem maturity!”</strong> Maturity is valuable, and can also entrench inertia. Age isn’t the same as fitness for today’s constraints.</p>
<p>Additionally, a mature ecosystem often means heavy reliance on third-party packages, which can introduce maintenance burdens like keeping dependencies up-to-date, dealing with security vulnerabilities, and bloating bundles with unused code. While essential in some cases, this flexibility can lead to over-dependence; custom solutions tailored to specific needs are often leaner and more maintainable in the long run. Smaller ecosystems in alternative frameworks encourage building from fundamentals, fostering deeper understanding and less technical debt. Moreover, with AI coding assistants now able to generate precise, custom functions on demand, the barrier to creating bespoke utilities has lowered dramatically. This makes it feasible to avoid generic libraries like lodash or date libraries like Moment or date-fns entirely in favor of lightweight, app-specific implementations.</p>
<p><strong>“But hiring!”</strong> Hiring follows demand. You can de‑risk by piloting alternatives in non‑critical paths, then hiring for fundamentals plus on‑the‑job training.</p>
<p><strong>“But component libraries!”</strong> Framework‑agnostic design systems and Web Components reduce lock-in while preserving velocity.</p>
<p><strong>“But stability!”</strong> React’s evolution from classes to hooks to Server Components demonstrates constant churn, not stability.
Alternative frameworks often provide more consistent APIs.</p>
<p><strong>“But proven at scale!”</strong> jQuery was proven at scale too. Past
success doesn’t guarantee future relevance.</p>
<h2 id="the-broader-ecosystem-harm">The Broader Ecosystem Harm</h2>
<p>Monoculture slows web evolution when one framework’s constraints become de facto limits. Talent spends cycles solving framework-specific issues rather than pushing the platform forward. Investment follows incumbents regardless of technical merit.</p>
<p>Curricula optimize for immediate employability over fundamentals, creating framework-specific rather than transferable skills. Platform improvements get delayed because “React can handle it” becomes a default answer.</p>
<p>The entire ecosystem suffers when diversity disappears.</p>
<h2 id="the-garden-we-could-grow">The Garden We Could Grow</h2>
<p>Healthy ecosystems require diversity, not monocultures. Innovation emerges when different approaches compete and cross-pollinate. Developers grow by learning multiple mental models. The platform improves when several frameworks push different boundaries.</p>
<p>Betting everything on one model creates a single point of failure. What happens if it hits hard limits? What opportunities are we missing by not exploring alternatives?</p>
<p>It’s time to choose frameworks based on constraints and merit rather than momentum. Your next project deserves better than React-by-default. The ecosystem deserves the innovation only diversity can provide.</p>
<p>Stop planting the same seed by default. The garden we could cultivate through diverse framework exploration would be more resilient and more innovative than the monoculture we’ve drifted into.</p>
<p>The choice is ours to make.</p> </div>  </article>  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[macOS Tahoe (482 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.apple.com/os/macos/</link>
            <guid>45252378</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 17:16:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.apple.com/os/macos/">https://www.apple.com/os/macos/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45252378">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main" role="main" data-page-type="macos">
		
		
		
		
		
		
		<div data-anim-scroll-group="More" data-analytics-section-engagement="name:more features" data-component-list="StaggeredFadeIn">
					<div data-staggered-item="">
						<picture id="shared-more-icon-accessibility-3" data-lazy="">
							<source data-empty="" srcset="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAHAAACH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAICRAEAOw==" media="(min-width:0px)">
							<img src="https://www.apple.com/v/os/c/images/shared/more/icon_accessibility__ey38qgbdpiuu_large.png" onload="window.__lp?.(event)" alt="">
						</picture>
						
						<div>
							<h3>Accessibility.</h3><p> Magnifier lets you zoom in on your surroundings using a connected camera. Accessibility Reader provides a systemwide, customized reading and listening experience. Braille Access creates an all-new interface for braille displays.<sup><a href="#footnote-9" aria-label="Footnote 9" data-modal-close="">9</a></sup> And Vehicle Motion Cues help reduce motion sickness in moving&nbsp;vehicles.</p></div>
					</div>
					<div data-staggered-item="">
						<picture id="shared-more-icon-family-sharing-3" data-lazy="">
							<source data-empty="" srcset="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAHAAACH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAICRAEAOw==" media="(min-width:0px)">
							<img src="https://www.apple.com/v/os/c/images/shared/more/icon_family_sharing__etze23t93rwy_large.png" onload="window.__lp?.(event)" alt="">
						</picture>
						
						<div>
							<h3>Family.</h3><p> Parents can take advantage of a wide set of parental controls designed to keep children safe. These include new enhancements across Communication Limits, Communication Safety, and the App&nbsp;Store.</p></div>
					</div>
					<div data-staggered-item="">
						<picture id="shared-more-icon-journal-3" data-lazy="">
							<source data-empty="" srcset="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAHAAACH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAICRAEAOw==" media="(min-width:0px)">
							<img src="https://www.apple.com/v/os/c/images/shared/more/icon_journal__c2vx8vx6e0eq_large.png" onload="window.__lp?.(event)" alt="">
						</picture>
						
						<div>
							<h3>Journal.</h3><p> Now on Mac for the most comfortable writing experience, Journal makes it easy to capture and write about everyday moments and special events using photos, videos, audio recordings, places, and&nbsp;more.</p></div>
					</div>
					<div data-staggered-item="">
						<picture id="shared-more-icon-photos-3" data-lazy="">
							<source data-empty="" srcset="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAHAAACH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAICRAEAOw==" media="(min-width:0px)">
							<img src="https://www.apple.com/v/os/c/images/shared/more/icon_photos__c1mo1v0dm1ci_large.png" onload="window.__lp?.(event)" alt="">
						</picture>
						
						<div>
							<h3>Photos.</h3><p> An updated design lets you quickly access filtering and sorting options and customize the size of Collections tiles so you can view your library just how you like. And with Pinned Collections, you can keep your most-visited ones right at your&nbsp;fingertips.</p></div>
					</div>
					<div data-staggered-item="">
						<picture id="macos-more-icon-facetime-1" data-lazy="">
							<source data-empty="" srcset="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAHAAACH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAICRAEAOw==" media="(min-width:0px)">
							<img src="https://www.apple.com/v/os/c/images/macos/more/icon_facetime__feotyd7la8i2_large.png" onload="window.__lp?.(event)" alt="">
						</picture>
						
						<div>
							<h3>FaceTime.</h3><p> Celebrate the people who matter most with a new tiled design that features beautiful and personalized Contact&nbsp;Posters.</p></div>
					</div>
					<div data-staggered-item="">
						<picture id="shared-more-icon-reminders-2" data-lazy="">
							<source data-empty="" srcset="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAHAAACH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAICRAEAOw==" media="(min-width:0px)">
							<img src="https://www.apple.com/v/os/c/images/shared/more/icon_reminders__cts245t4xcsy_large.png" onload="window.__lp?.(event)" alt="">
						</picture>
						
						<div>
							<h3>Reminders.</h3><p> With Apple&nbsp;Intelligence, Reminders can suggest tasks, grocery items, and follow-ups based on emails or other text on your device. It can also automatically categorize related reminders into sections within a list.</p></div>
					</div>
					<div data-staggered-item="">
						<picture id="shared-more-icon-gaming-2" data-lazy="">
							<source data-empty="" srcset="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAHAAACH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAICRAEAOw==" media="(min-width:0px)">
							<img src="https://www.apple.com/v/os/c/images/shared/more/icon_gaming__faqjmo0zhvu6_large.png" onload="window.__lp?.(event)" alt="">
						</picture>
						
						<div>
							<h3>Games.</h3><p> The new Games&nbsp;app brings together all the games you have on your Mac. In the Game Overlay, you can adjust system settings, chat with friends, or invite them to play — all without leaving the game. And for developers, Metal&nbsp;4 brings even more advanced graphics and rendering technologies, like MetalFX Frame Interpolation and&nbsp;Denoising.</p></div>
					</div>
					<div data-staggered-item="">
						<picture id="macos-more-icon-messages-1" data-lazy="">
							<source data-empty="" srcset="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAHAAACH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAICRAEAOw==" media="(min-width:0px)">
							<img src="https://www.apple.com/v/os/c/images/macos/more/icon_messages__c75oi8dpw4gi_large.png" onload="window.__lp?.(event)" alt="">
						</picture>
						
						<div>
							<h3>Messages.</h3><p> Create polls and personalize conversations with backgrounds. Redesigned conversation details feature designated sections for contact info, photos, links, location, and more. Typing indicators in groups let you know exactly who is about to chime in. Screening tools detect spam and give you control. And the Add Contact button now appears next to an unknown number in a&nbsp;group.</p></div>
					</div>
					<div data-staggered-item="">
						<picture id="macos-more-icon-passwords-1" data-lazy="">
							<source data-empty="" srcset="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAHAAACH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAICRAEAOw==" media="(min-width:0px)">
							<img src="https://www.apple.com/v/os/c/images/macos/more/icon_passwords__c7rqhn941eoi_large.png" onload="window.__lp?.(event)" alt="">
						</picture>
						
						<div>
							<h3>Passwords.</h3><p> Easily refer to changes you’ve made to your accounts. Find previous versions of passwords, along with when they were&nbsp;changed.</p></div>
					</div>
					<div data-staggered-item="">
						<picture id="shared-more-icon-notes-2" data-lazy="">
							<source data-empty="" srcset="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAHAAACH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAICRAEAOw==" media="(min-width:0px)">
							<img src="https://www.apple.com/v/os/c/images/shared/more/icon_notes__b48ojk6xh7py_large.png" onload="window.__lp?.(event)" alt="">
						</picture>
						
						<div>
							<h3>Notes.</h3><p> Capture conversations in the Phone app as audio recordings with transcriptions.<sup><a href="#footnote-10" aria-label="Footnote 10" data-modal-close="">10</a></sup> You can also export a note into a Markdown&nbsp;file.</p></div>
					</div>
				</div>
		
	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[GPT-5-Codex (317 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://openai.com/index/introducing-upgrades-to-codex/</link>
            <guid>45252301</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 17:10:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-upgrades-to-codex/">https://openai.com/index/introducing-upgrades-to-codex/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45252301">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://openai.com/index/introducing-upgrades-to-codex/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Wanted to spy on my dog, ended up spying on TP-Link (457 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://kennedn.com/blog/posts/tapo/</link>
            <guid>45251690</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 16:28:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://kennedn.com/blog/posts/tapo/">https://kennedn.com/blog/posts/tapo/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45251690">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><p><img src="https://kennedn.com/blog/posts/tapo/cover.png" alt=""></p>
<p>I recently bought a cheap Tapo indoor camera to see what my dog gets up to when I am out of the house.</p>
<p>What actually followed? I ended up reverse-engineering onboarding flows, decompiling an APK, MITMing TLS sessions, and writing cryptographic scripts.</p>
<p>My main motivation for this project really stemmed from the fact that the camera annoyed me from day one. Setting the camera up in frigate was quite painful, no one really seemed to know how these cameras worked online.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>SIDENOTE: If you want 2 way audio to work in frigate you must use the <code>tapo://</code> go2rtc configuration for your main stream instead of the usual <code>rtsp://</code>. TP-Link are lazy and only implement 2 way audio on their own proprietary API.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>One undocumented behavior that tripped me up was that the device’s API is supposed to accept credentials <code>admin</code>:<code>&lt;your-tapo-cloud-password&gt;</code> after onboarding. However after banging my head against a wall for a few hours I later discovered that if you change your cloud password after onboarding, paired devices don’t get the memo 🙂.</p>
<p>This implied a few things to me that started the cogs turning:</p>
<ul>
<li>There must be a call made during on-boarding that syncs the device password with the cloud password</li>
<li>The device must either allow unauthenticated calls before this step or have some sort of default password.</li>
</ul>
<p>So considering my onboarding woes and the fact that I was starting to recoil every time the tapo app tried to jam a “Tapo Care” subscription down my throat, a cloudless onboarding solution for the device was beginning to look more and more desirable.</p>
<p>The first step to cracking this egg was to be be able to snoop on what the app and the camera are saying to each other during onboarding. E.g, establish a man in the middle.</p>
<h2 id="man-in-the-middle">Man in the middle</h2>
<p>To man in the middle a phone app, you must be able to route all http(s) traffic via a proxy server you control. Historically this has been quite simple to achieve, simply spin up a proxy on a computer, add the proxy’s self-signed certificate to the phone’s truststore, and configure the phone to point at the proxy.</p>
<p>However, modern phone apps can use a few nasty tricks to render this approach ineffective. Namely they will blatantly ignore proxies, throw the system truststore to the wind and make liberal use of certificate pinning.</p>
<p>The most full-proof technique for generically MITMing an app has therefore become dynamic instrumentation via tools like <code>frida</code>. What this allows us to do is force an app to use the proxies and certificates that we tell it to whilst batting aside it’s attempts to do things like certificate pinning.</p>
<p>So the setup ended up looking like this (full setup guide <a href="https://github.com/kennedn/tapo-onboarding?tab=readme-ov-file#capturing-onboarding-calls-from-tapo-app" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a>
):</p>
<pre>  ---
config:
  theme: 'base'
  themeVariables:
    primaryColor: '#00000000'
    primaryTextColor: '#fff'
    primaryBorderColor: '#ffffff8e'
    lineColor: '#fff'
    secondaryColor: '#fff'
    tertiaryColor: '#fff'
---
sequenceDiagram
    participant A as Tapo App &lt;br&gt;(with frida hooks)
    participant L as Laptop &lt;br&gt;(mitmproxy)
    participant C as Tapo Camera

    A-&gt;&gt;L: Request
    L-&gt;&gt;L: Record request
    L-&gt;&gt;C: Forward request
    C--&gt;&gt;L: Response
    L-&gt;&gt;L: Record response
    L--&gt;&gt;A: Forward response
</pre>

<p>After spinning up <code>mitmproxy</code>, injecting the <a href="https://github.com/httptoolkit/frida-interception-and-unpinning" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">frida scripts</a>
, and onboarding the camera, we finally see an initial login flow — before the admin password ever gets changed:</p>

<p>However, subsequent requests look like this:</p>
<div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="json"><span><span><span>{</span>
</span></span><span><span>  <span>"method"</span><span>:</span> <span>"securePassthrough"</span><span>,</span>
</span></span><span><span>  <span>"params"</span><span>:</span> <span>{</span>
</span></span><span><span>    <span>"request"</span><span>:</span> <span>"bAhdgihJ9j6PrrknnbXWATBohGTZK5llv3MEzRcmoAmcxexmlVNz3OUX2r0h9a9EG/3X0tBpPi654T2+BjqVEOn2D178kokBpf8RQj01AvBZLYD5S5sFeaCXWiRXA7MgQUppROV4AbrU4f+GOM37KgPqT59qgLVja2slw6CzrKjPzOrG4Ho6Mu6wBa1xepcj"</span>
</span></span><span><span>  <span>}</span>
</span></span><span><span><span>}</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>And responses look like this:</p>
<div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="json"><span><span><span>{</span>
</span></span><span><span>  <span>"seq"</span><span>:</span> <span>584</span><span>,</span>
</span></span><span><span>  <span>"result"</span><span>:</span> <span>{</span>
</span></span><span><span>    <span>"response"</span><span>:</span> <span>"Gqz1wbXAig/3wL+kXzY2Ig3hq+JSYasYI7FXdMNZR5PyH8bpLX+GJqQbImUtby9IEj5HQDhxqcTa+dUqQjI0GaGCxuGHqmrgQ0FeyCTQjBiW5gslAPQG33wj44OOkAep"</span>
</span></span><span><span>  <span>},</span>
</span></span><span><span>  <span>"error_code"</span><span>:</span> <span>0</span>
</span></span><span><span><span>}</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>So from this initial dive we have learned that:</p>
<ul>
<li>Tapo 100% has a default password due to the fact that it performs a full login before it knows anything about the cloud password.</li>
<li>Tapo has an encrypted <code>securePassthrough</code> channel for its API calls to prevent peeping toms such as myself from spilling the beans.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="the-jadx-dive">The JADX dive</h2>
<p>The next logical step is to decompile the apk in JADX and start rummaging around for a default password.</p>
<p>The initial login call that we captured references an <code>admin</code> username:</p>

<div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="json"><span><span><span>{</span>
</span></span><span><span>  <span>"method"</span><span>:</span> <span>"login"</span><span>,</span>
</span></span><span><span>  <span>"params"</span><span>:</span> <span>{</span>
</span></span><span><span>    <span>"cnonce"</span><span>:</span> <span>"AD0E189F6E1BA335"</span><span>,</span>
</span></span><span><span>    <span>"encrypt_type"</span><span>:</span> <span>"3"</span><span>,</span>
</span></span><span><span>    <span>"username"</span><span>:</span> <span>"admin"</span>
</span></span><span><span>  <span>}</span>
</span></span><span><span><span>}</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Searching for <code>"admin"</code> in JADX gives us many hits but there are a few concentrated in a <code>CameraOnboardingViewModel</code> class that look interesting:</p>
<p><img src="https://kennedn.com/blog/posts/tapo/jadx1.png" alt=""></p>
<p>The function <code>m98131y2</code> appears to be returning a password that is then passed to the <code>new Account()</code> call. Following this function up the chain, we hit gold:</p>

<p><a href="#loginrequest">We already know</a>
 that the device is using <code>encrypt_type: 3</code>, so that means our default password is:</p>
<p><code>TPL075526460603</code></p>
<h2 id="teaching-mitmproxy-new-tricks">Teaching mitmproxy new tricks</h2>
<p>With the default password now revealed, we have the cards in our hand to derive session keys and decode the <code>securePassthrough</code> messages.</p>
<p>The only thing that would help us further is if we had a reference implementation for the authentication flow. This is where <a href="https://github.com/JurajNyiri/pytapo" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">PyTapo</a>
 really came in handy.</p>
<p>Using PyTapo as a reference, we could dump the session state and encrypted messages from mitmproxy and write a script to do some static analysis on the decrypted requests and responses, but a really cool feature of <code>mitmproxy</code> is that it supports scripting itself.</p>
<p>What this means is that we can pass a python script to mitmproxy, and have it directly decrypt request and response payloads inline whilst running a capture.</p>
<p>So I wrote <code>tapo_decrypt_pretty.py</code> which:</p>
<ul>
<li>Watches for the login handshake (<code>cnonce</code>, <code>nonce</code>, <code>device_confirm</code>)</li>
<li>Derives <code>lsk</code>/<code>ivb</code> session keys from it</li>
<li>Transparently decrypts subsequent API calls</li>
<li>Pretty-prints them inline in mitmproxy’s UI in <code>request_decrypted</code> and <code>response_decrypted</code> fields</li>
<li>Dumps them to JSON files for later analysis</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="analysing-the-results">Analysing the results</h2>
<p>The complete list of calls made by the Tapo app during onboarding were:</p>
<div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="bash"><span><span>getAppComponentList
</span></span><span><span>setLanguage
</span></span><span><span>scanApList
</span></span><span><span>bindToCloud
</span></span><span><span>changeAdminPassword
</span></span><span><span>setTimezone
</span></span><span><span>setRecordPlan
</span></span><span><span>setDeviceLocation
</span></span><span><span>connectAp
</span></span><span><span>getConnectStatus
</span></span><span><span>setAccountEnabled
</span></span><span><span>changeThirdAccount
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>This boiled down to just four important calls:</p>
<ol>
<li><code>scanApList</code> — list Wi-Fi access points</li>
<li><code>setAccountEnabled</code> + <code>changeThirdAccount</code> — enable RTSP/ONVIF account</li>
<li><code>changeAdminPassword</code> — change from default password to the cloud password</li>
<li><code>connectAp</code> — join the selected Wi-Fi access point</li>
</ol>
<p>Everything else was fluff: timezones, record plans, binding to cloud.</p>
<h2 id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h2>
<p>In the end, the prize for all this nonsense was a scrappy little Bash script, <a href="https://github.com/kennedn/tapo-onboarding/blob/main/tapo_onboard.sh" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><code>tapo_onboard.sh</code></a>
, which:</p>
<ul>
<li>Logs in with the default admin password,</li>
<li>Scans and selects a Wifi access point</li>
<li>Switches off the obnoxious OSD logo on the camera feed,</li>
<li>Enables RTSP/ONVIF capabilities</li>
<li>Changes the admin password,</li>
<li>And finally joins the Wi-Fi.</li>
</ul>

<p>Peeling this onion left me with a few observations on Tapo’s firmware.</p>
<ul>
<li>Some endpoints use SHA-256 for hashing, while others cling to MD5 like it’s 2003.</li>
<li>There are <em>two</em> public keys used to send passwords to the device — one that is shared with the client and another super secret one that’s hardcoded in the app. The easiest way to figure out which one to use is to flip a coin.</li>
<li>Password syncing between the app and its managed devices is strictly vibe-based.</li>
</ul>
<p>The whole thing feels like it was cobbled together by a consortium of couch-cryptographers. But then again, it was the cheapest indoor camera on amazon, so what did I expect?</p>
<p>And with all this said I did finally manage to figure out what the dog does when I am away.</p>
<p>She sleeps. On the sofa. Sometimes even in her bed.</p>

</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Microsoft to force install the Microsoft 365 Copilot app in October (186 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/microsoft/microsoft-to-force-install-the-microsoft-365-copilot-app-in-october/</link>
            <guid>45251593</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 16:22:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/microsoft/microsoft-to-force-install-the-microsoft-365-copilot-app-in-october/">https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/microsoft/microsoft-to-force-install-the-microsoft-365-copilot-app-in-october/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45251593">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
	   
<p><img alt="Microsoft 365" height="900" src="https://www.bleepstatic.com/content/hl-images/2025/09/05/Microsoft-365.jpg" width="1600"></p>

<p>Next month, Microsoft will begin automatically installing the Microsoft 365 Copilot app on Windows devices outside of the EEA region that have the Microsoft 365 desktop client apps.</p>

<p>The Microsoft 365 Copilot app integrates the AI-powered Copilot assistant with Microsoft 365 suite apps, including Word, Excel, and PowerPoint, as well as other features like Notebooks and AI agents.</p>

<ol data-border="0" data-indent="0" data-list-tree="true" data-stringify-type="ordered-list"></ol><p>Redmond also advised admins to notify their organizations' helpdesk teams and users before the app is forcibly installed on their devices "to reduce confusion and support requests."</p>

<p>The rollout will start in early October and be completed by mid-November; however,&nbsp;the Microsoft 365 Copilot app will not be installed on systems within the European Economic Area (EEA).</p>

<p>"Starting in October 2025, Microsoft will begin automatically installing the Microsoft 365 Copilot app on Windows devices that have Microsoft 365 desktop client apps," the company said in a <a href="https://admin.microsoft.com/#/MessageCenter/:/messages/MC1152323" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">Microsoft 365 message center update</a> on Friday.</p>

<p>"This app provides a centralized entry point for accessing Copilot experiences and AI-powered capabilities across Microsoft 365. This change simplifies access to Copilot and ensures users can easily discover and engage with productivity-enhancing features."</p>

<p>While the newly installed app will be added to the Windows Start Menu and enabled by default, IT administrators responsible for managing Microsoft 365 app deployments <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/copilot/microsoft-365/deploy-microsoft-365-copilot-app#deploy-the-app-with-microsoft-365-apps" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">will be able to opt out</a> in the Apps Admin Center:</p>

<ol data-border="0" data-indent="0" data-list-tree="true" data-stringify-type="ordered-list"><li>Sign in to the <a data-linktype="external" href="https://config.office.com/deploymentsettings" rel="nofollow noopener">Microsoft 365 Apps admin center</a> with an admin account.</li>
	<li>Go to <em>Customization &gt; Device Configuration &gt; Modern App Settings</em>.</li>
	<li>Select <em>Microsoft 365 Copilot app</em>, then clear the <em>Enable automatic installation of Microsoft 365 Copilot app</em> check box.</li>
</ol><p>Although&nbsp;many users may notice a new&nbsp;Microsoft 365 Copilot app icon in the Start menu, the application may have already been installed, resulting in no apparent change.</p>

<p>Last month, as part of the same effort to make Copilot more easily available, Microsoft <a href="https://admin.microsoft.com/#/MessageCenter/:/messages/MC1073071" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">announced</a> that it will integrate Microsoft 365 Copilot agents into the Edge sidebar starting in late September 2025, allowing users to access them while using Copilot.</p>

<p>Weeks earlier, it <a href="https://admin.microsoft.com/#/MessageCenter/:/messages/MC1115982" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">added a new setting</a> that allows Microsoft 365 admins to pin the Microsoft 365 Copilot app to the Windows taskbar.</p>

	   
<div>
    <p><a href="https://hubs.li/Q03B5Kw_0" target="_blank" rel="noopener sponsored">
            <img src="https://www.bleepstatic.com/c/p/picus/blue-report-2025.jpg" alt="Picus Blue Report 2025"></a>
    </p>
    
</div>

           
          
 
	  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Asciinema CLI 3.0 rewritten in Rust, adds live streaming, upgrades file format (325 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.asciinema.org/post/three-point-o/</link>
            <guid>45251375</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 16:06:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.asciinema.org/post/three-point-o/">https://blog.asciinema.org/post/three-point-o/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45251375">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
  <h2>
    <a href="https://blog.asciinema.org/post/three-point-o/">3.0</a>
    <span>Published on 15 Sep 2025 by Marcin Kulik</span>
  </h2>
  <p>I’m happy to announce the release of asciinema CLI 3.0!</p>
<p>This is a complete rewrite of asciinema in Rust, upgrading the recording file
format, introducing terminal live streaming, and bringing numerous improvements
across the board.</p>
<p>In this post, I’ll go over the highlights of the release. For a deeper overview
of new features and improvements, see the <a href="https://github.com/asciinema/asciinema/releases/tag/v3.0.0">release
notes</a> and the
detailed
<a href="https://github.com/asciinema/asciinema/blob/develop/CHANGELOG.md">changelog</a>.</p>
<p>First, let’s get the Rust rewrite topic out of the way. I did it because I felt
like it. But seriously, I felt like it because I prefer working with Rust 100x
more than with Python these days. And this type of code, with syscalls and
concurrency, is way easier to deal with in Rust than in Python. That’s my
experience, YMMV. Anyway, in addition to making me enjoy working with this
component of asciinema again, the rewrite resulted in faster startup, easier
installation (a static binary), and made many new features possible by
integrating <a href="https://github.com/asciinema/avt">asciinema virtual terminal</a>
(also Rust) into the CLI.</p>
<p>Let’s look at what’s cool and new now.</p>
<h2 id="asciicast-v3-file-format">asciicast v3 file format</h2>
<p>The new <a href="https://docs.asciinema.org/manual/asciicast/v3/">asciicast v3</a> file
format is an evolution of the good old asciicast v2. It addresses several
shortcomings of the previous format that were discovered over the years.</p>
<p>The major change in the new format is the use of intervals (deltas) for timing
session events. v2 used absolute timestamps (measured since session start),
which had its own pros and cons. One often-brought-up issue was the difficulty
of editing the recordings - timestamps of all following events had to be
adjusted when adding/removing/updating events.</p>
<p>Other than timing, the header has been restructured, grouping related things
together, e.g. all terminal-related metadata is now under <code>term</code>. There’s also
support for the new <code>"x"</code> (exit) event type, for storing the session exit
status. Finally, line comments are allowed by using the <code>#</code> character as the
first character on a line.</p>
<p>Here’s an example of a short recording in asciicast v3 format:</p>
<div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="json"><span><span>{<span>"version"</span>: <span>3</span>, <span>"term"</span>: {<span>"cols"</span>: <span>80</span>, <span>"rows"</span>: <span>24</span>, <span>"type"</span>: <span>"xterm-256color"</span>}, <span>"timestamp"</span>: <span>1504467315</span>, <span>"title"</span>: <span>"Demo"</span>, <span>"env"</span>: {<span>"SHELL"</span>: <span>"/bin/zsh"</span>}}
</span></span><span><span># event stream follows the header
</span></span><span><span>[<span>0.248848</span>, <span>"o"</span>, <span>"Hey Dougal...\n"</span>]
</span></span><span><span>[<span>0.248848</span>, <span>"o"</span>, <span>"Yes Ted?\n"</span>]
</span></span><span><span>[<span>1.001376</span>, <span>"o"</span>, <span>"Is there anything on your mind?\n"</span>]
</span></span><span><span>[<span>3.500000</span>, <span>"m"</span>, <span>""</span>]
</span></span><span><span>[<span>0.143733</span>, <span>"o"</span>, <span>"No."</span>]
</span></span><span><span># terminal window resized to <span>90</span> cols and <span>30</span> rows
</span></span><span><span>[<span>2.050000</span>, <span>"r"</span>, <span>"90x30"</span>]
</span></span><span><span>[<span>1.541828</span>, <span>"o"</span>, <span>"Bye!"</span>]
</span></span><span><span>[<span>0.8870</span>, <span>"x"</span>, <span>"0"</span>]
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>The new format is already supported by <a href="https://docs.asciinema.org/manual/server/">asciinema
server</a> and <a href="https://docs.asciinema.org/manual/player/">asciinema
player</a>.</p>
<h2 id="live-terminal-streaming">Live terminal streaming</h2>
<p>The new CLI allows for live streaming of terminal sessions, and provides two
modes for doing so.</p>
<p>Local mode uses built-in HTTP server, allowing people to view the stream on
trusted networks (e.g. a LAN). In this mode no data is sent anywhere, except to
the viewers’ browsers, which may require opening a firewall port. The CLI
bundles the latest version of asciinema player, and uses it to connect to the
stream from the page served by the built-in server.</p>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>$ asciinema stream --local
::: asciinema session started
::: Live streaming at http://127.0.0.1:37881
::: Press &lt;ctrl+d&gt; or type 'exit' to end
$ _
</code></pre><p>Remote mode publishes the stream through an asciinema server (either
asciinema.org or a self-hosted one), which acts as a relay, delivering the
stream to the viewers at a shareable URL.</p>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>$ asciinema stream --remote
::: asciinema session started
::: Live streaming at https://asciinema.org/s/TQGS82DwiBS1bYAY
::: Press &lt;ctrl+d&gt; or type 'exit' to end
$ _
</code></pre><p>The two modes can be used together as well.</p>
<p>Here’s a live stream of <code>btop</code> running on one of the asciinema.org servers:</p>

<p>You can also watch it directly on asciinema.org at
<a href="https://asciinema.org/s/olesiD03BIFH6Yz1">asciinema.org/s/olesiD03BIFH6Yz1</a>.</p>
<p>Read more about the streaming architecture and supported protocols
<a href="https://docs.asciinema.org/manual/server/streaming/">here</a>.</p>
<p>asciinema player (seen above) supports all the described protocols. To make the
viewing experience smooth and glitch-free, it implements an adaptive buffering
mechanism. It measures network latency in real-time and adjusts the buffer size
constantly, aiming for a good balance between low latency and buffer-underrun
protection.</p>
<p>asciinema server can now record every live stream and turn it into a regular
recording. At the moment, asciinema server running at asciinema.org has stream
recording disabled and a concurrent live stream limit of 1, but you can
self-host the server where recording is enabled and there’s no concurrent
stream limit by default. The limits on asciinema.org may change. I’d like to
first see how the streaming feature affects resource usage (btw, shout-out to
<a href="https://www.brightbox.com/">Brightbox</a>, which provides cloud services for
asciinema.org).</p>
<h2 id="local-first">Local-first</h2>
<p>In the early versions of asciinema, <code>asciinema rec</code> didn’t support saving to a
file - the recording was saved to a tmp file, uploaded to asciinema.org, and
the tmp file was removed. Later on, the CLI got the ability to specify a
filename, which allowed you to save the result of a recording session to a file
in asciicast v1 format and decide whether you want to keep it local only or
publish.</p>
<p>Although optional, the filename argument had long been available. However,
many, many tutorials on the internet (probably including asciinema’s own docs)
showed examples of recording and publishing in one go with <code>asciinema rec</code>.
That was fine - many people loved this short path from recording to sharing.</p>
<p>Over the years, I started seeing two problems with this. The first one is that
lots of people still think you must upload to asciinema.org, which is not true.
You can save locally and nothing leaves your machine. The second one is that
the optionality of the filename made it possible to unintentionally publish a
recording, and potentially leak sensitive data. And it’s a completely valid
concern!</p>
<p>Because of that, on several occasions I’ve seen negative comments saying
“asciinema is shady” /m\. It was never shady. It’s just a historical thing. I
just kept the original behavior for backward compatibility. asciinema.org is
not a commercial product - it’s <em>an</em> instance of asciinema server, which is
meant to give users an easy way to share, and to give a taste of what you get
when you self-host the server. In fact, I encourage everyone to self-host it,
as the recordings uploaded to asciinema.org are a liability for me (while being
a good promotion of the project :)).</p>
<p>I hope this clears up any confusion and suspicion.</p>
<p>Anyway, many things have changed since the original behavior of <code>asciinema rec</code> was implemented, including my approach to sharing my data with cloud
services. These days I self-host lots of services on a server at home, and I
try to avoid cloud services if I can (I’m pragmatic about it though).</p>
<p>The streaming feature was built from the ground up to support the local mode,
which came first, and the remote mode followed.</p>
<p>In asciinema CLI 2.4, released 2 years ago, I made the <code>upload</code> command show a
prompt where you have to explicitly make a decision on what to do with the
recording. It looked like this:</p>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>$ asciinema rec
asciinema: recording asciicast to /tmp/tmpo8_612f8-ascii.cast
asciinema: press &lt;ctrl-d&gt; or type "exit" when you're done
$ echo hello
hello
$ exit 
asciinema: recording finished
(s)ave locally, (u)pload to asciinema.org, (d)iscard
[s,u,d]? _
</code></pre><p>It was a stopgap and a way to prepare users for further changes that are coming
now.</p>
<p>In 3.0, the filename is always required, and the <code>rec</code> command no longer has
upload capability. To publish a recording to asciinema.org or a self-hosted
asciinema server, use the explicit <code>asciinema upload &lt;filename&gt;</code>.</p>
<h2 id="more-self-hosting-friendly">More self-hosting-friendly</h2>
<p>A related improvement introduced in this release is the new server URL prompt.</p>
<p>When using a command that integrates with asciinema server (<code>upload</code>, <code>stream</code>,
<code>auth</code>) for the first time, a prompt is shown, pre-filled with
<a href="https://asciinema.org/">https://asciinema.org</a> (for convenience). This lets you choose an asciinema
server instance explicitly and intentionally. The choice is saved for future
invocations.</p>
<p>It was always possible to <a href="https://docs.asciinema.org/manual/cli/configuration/">point the CLI to another asciinema
server</a> with a config
file or environment variable, but this new prompt should come in handy
especially when running the CLI in a non-workstation/non-laptop yet interactive
environment, such as a fresh VM or a dev container.</p>
<p>This change should make it easier to use the CLI with your own asciinema
server, and at the same time it doubles as an additional guard preventing
unintended data leaks (to asciinema.org).</p>
<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>I’m really excited about this release. It’s been in the making for a while, but
it’s out now, and I’m looking forward to seeing what new use-cases and
workflows people will discover with it.</p>
<p>It’s going to take a moment until 3.0 shows up in package repositories for all
supported platforms/distros. Meanwhile, you can download prebuilt binaries for
GNU/Linux and macOS from the <a href="https://github.com/asciinema/asciinema/releases/tag/v3.0.0">GitHub
release</a>, or <a href="https://github.com/asciinema/asciinema#building">build
it from source</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading to this point!</p>


</article><p>
  Did you like it? Feel free to send me an email with your feedback to

  <span></span>. You can also reach me on Mastodon at <a href="https://hachyderm.io/@ku1ik">@ku1ik@hachyderm.io</a>.

  Thanks!
</p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Thought police bill introduced to revoke US passport for criticism of Israel (173 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://thecradle.co/articles-id/33135</link>
            <guid>45251124</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 15:47:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://thecradle.co/articles-id/33135">https://thecradle.co/articles-id/33135</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45251124">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Boring work needs tension (123 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://iaziz786.com/blog/boring-work-needs-tension/</link>
            <guid>45251093</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 15:44:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://iaziz786.com/blog/boring-work-needs-tension/">https://iaziz786.com/blog/boring-work-needs-tension/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45251093">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<article>
   

  <div><p>We are all moved by great movies, cinematography, and stories. Watching them is fun because you can imagine yourself resonating with a character. You are thrilled by the tension the story creates and curious how it will be resolved.</p>
<p>Many find software development a dull job where you have to write exactly what your PM or client asks for. It’s exciting at first, but it can become boring after a few iterations.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Whatever doesn’t excite you, change it.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>When we, as developers, push ourselves to be protagonists, we discover many problems to solve — a lot of tension to resolve. Here are a few good problems for everyday devs:</p>
<ul>
<li>Your CI/CD takes a huge amount of time because you forgot to leverage caching.</li>
<li>You forgot to add connection pooling and your service bombarded the database, causing too many open connections.</li>
<li>You misconfigured the garbage collector and now you have a memory leak that keeps growing.</li>
<li>If it takes you more than 3 seconds to understand what you wrote last week, it’s poorly written.</li>
<li>Latency is high for your users in Mumbai because your servers are in Singapore.</li>
<li>The database becomes very slow when you start dumping data in batches.</li>
<li>You want consistent API responses for read operations for users in both Mumbai and Singapore.</li>
</ul>
<p>These are not trivial problems; they happen every day. These are our villains — irritating, unwanted, and surprising. We should eliminate them.</p>
<p>Pick your fight. This is one way to make your day exciting. If you can’t tackle these at work, do it in your personal projects.</p>
<p>If you chase the right tension, a story will follow.</p>


  </div>

  
</article>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Launch HN: Trigger.dev (YC W23) – Open-source platform to build reliable AI apps (142 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45250720</link>
            <guid>45250720</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 15:20:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45250720">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="bigbox"><td><table><tbody><tr id="45250720"><td><span></span></td><td><center><a id="up_45250720" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=45250720&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D45250720"></a></center></td><td><span><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45250720">Launch HN: Trigger.dev (YC W23) – Open-source platform to build reliable AI apps</a></span></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><span><span id="score_45250720">104 points</span> by <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=eallam">eallam</a> <span title="2025-09-15T15:20:18 1757949618"><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45250720">5 hours ago</a></span> <span id="unv_45250720"></span> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/hide?id=45250720&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D45250720">hide</a> | <a href="https://hn.algolia.com/?query=Launch%20HN%3A%20Trigger.dev%20%28YC%20W23%29%20%E2%80%93%20Open-source%20platform%20to%20build%20reliable%20AI%20apps&amp;type=story&amp;dateRange=all&amp;sort=byDate&amp;storyText=false&amp;prefix&amp;page=0">past</a> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/fave?id=45250720&amp;auth=69e8b16747f008a8937f512469fc6120465e3faa">favorite</a> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45250720">42&nbsp;comments</a></span></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><div><p>Hi HN, I’m Eric, CTO at Trigger.dev (<a href="https://trigger.dev/">https://trigger.dev</a>). We’re a developer platform for building and running AI agents and workflows, open-source under the Apache 2.0 license (<a href="https://github.com/triggerdotdev/trigger.dev" rel="nofollow">https://github.com/triggerdotdev/trigger.dev</a>).</p><p>We provide everything needed to create production-grade agents in your codebase and deploy, run, monitor, and debug them. You can use just our primitives or combine with tools like Mastra, LangChain and Vercel AI SDK. You can self-host or use our cloud, where we take care of scaling for you. Here’s a quick demo: (<a href="https://youtu.be/kFCzKE89LD8" rel="nofollow">https://youtu.be/kFCzKE89LD8</a>).</p><p>We started in 2023 as a way to reliably run async background jobs/workflows in TypeScript (<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=34610686">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=34610686</a>). Initially we didn’t deploy your code, we just orchestrated it. But we found that most developers struggled to write reliable code with implicit determinism, found breaking their work into small “steps” tricky, and they wanted to install any system packages they needed. Serverless timeouts made this even more painful.</p><p>We also wanted to allow you to wait for things to happen: on external events, other tasks finishing, or just time passing. Those waits can take minutes, hours, or forever in the case of events, so you can’t just keep a server running.</p><p>The solution was to build and operate our own serverless cloud infrastructure. The key breakthrough that enabled this was realizing we could snapshot the CPU and memory state. This allowed us to pause running code, store the snapshot, then restore it later on a different physical server. We currently use Checkpoint Restore In Userspace (CRIU) which Google has been using at scale inside Borg since 2018.</p><p>Since then, our adoption has really taken off especially because of AI agents/workflows. This has opened up a ton of new use cases like compute-heavy tasks such as generating videos using AI (Icon.com), real-time computer use (Scrapybara), AI enrichment pipelines (Pallet, Centralize), and vibe coding tools (Hero UI, Magic Patterns, Capy.ai).</p><p>You can get started with Trigger.dev cloud (<a href="https://cloud.trigger.dev/">https://cloud.trigger.dev</a>), self-hosting (<a href="https://trigger.dev/docs/self-hosting/overview">https://trigger.dev/docs/self-hosting/overview</a>), or read the docs (<a href="https://trigger.dev/docs">https://trigger.dev/docs</a>).</p><p>Here’s a sneak peek at some upcoming changes: 1) warm starts for self-hosting 2) switching to MicroVMs for execution – this will be open source, self-hostable, and will include checkpoint/restoring.</p><p>We’re excited to be sharing this with HN and are open to all feedback!</p></div></td></tr><tr></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><form action="comment" method="post"></form></td></tr></tbody></table><br>
</td></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Paid $2400 to Cloudflare, support refuses to help (121 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45250553</link>
            <guid>45250553</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 15:05:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45250553">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="bigbox"><td><table><tbody><tr id="45250553"><td><span></span></td><td><center><a id="up_45250553" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=45250553&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D45250553"></a></center></td><td><span><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45250553">Paid $2400 to Cloudflare, support refuses to help</a></span></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><span><span id="score_45250553">106 points</span> by <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=thekonqueror">thekonqueror</a> <span title="2025-09-15T15:05:12 1757948712"><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45250553">9 hours ago</a></span> <span id="unv_45250553"></span> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/hide?id=45250553&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D45250553">hide</a> | <a href="https://hn.algolia.com/?query=Paid%20%242400%20to%20Cloudflare%2C%20support%20refuses%20to%20help&amp;type=story&amp;dateRange=all&amp;sort=byDate&amp;storyText=false&amp;prefix&amp;page=0">past</a> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/fave?id=45250553&amp;auth=d1b288916d85a74e30d3a861fda5f3545628cba5">favorite</a> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45250553">20&nbsp;comments</a></span></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><div><p>I signed up for Cloudflare's Business plan and paid for a year in advance. While adding a new domain I made a typo and now the subscription is stuck in a limbo.</p><p>I can't change the domain without contacting their support or paying another $2400. When I open a support ticket, their portal shows 'Unable to find your account' and tells me to open another support request for it.</p><p>All support tickets are closed automatically by their "AI" which points to the same article that says open a ticket.</p><p>Is shaming them on Twitter my only option left?</p></div></td></tr><tr></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><form action="comment" method="post"></form></td></tr></tbody></table><br>
</td></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Meta bypassed Apple privacy protections, claims former employee (156 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://9to5mac.com/2025/08/21/meta-allegedly-bypassed-apple-privacy-measure-and-fired-employee-who-flagged-it/</link>
            <guid>45250500</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 14:59:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/08/21/meta-allegedly-bypassed-apple-privacy-measure-and-fired-employee-who-flagged-it/">https://9to5mac.com/2025/08/21/meta-allegedly-bypassed-apple-privacy-measure-and-fired-employee-who-flagged-it/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45250500">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
					
<figure>
	<img width="1600" height="800" src="https://9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2025/08/Meta-bypassed-Apple-privacy-protections-and-fired-employee-who-flagged-it-%E2%80%93-FT.jpg?quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;w=1600" alt="Meta bypassed Apple privacy protections, and fired employee who flagged it – FT | Photo of an eye looking through a spy-hole" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2025/08/Meta-bypassed-Apple-privacy-protections-and-fired-employee-who-flagged-it-%E2%80%93-FT.jpg?w=320&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 320w, https://i0.wp.com/9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2025/08/Meta-bypassed-Apple-privacy-protections-and-fired-employee-who-flagged-it-%E2%80%93-FT.jpg?w=640&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 640w, https://i0.wp.com/9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2025/08/Meta-bypassed-Apple-privacy-protections-and-fired-employee-who-flagged-it-%E2%80%93-FT.jpg?w=1024&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2025/08/Meta-bypassed-Apple-privacy-protections-and-fired-employee-who-flagged-it-%E2%80%93-FT.jpg?w=1500&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 1500w" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high"></figure>

<p>A former <a href="https://9to5mac.com/guides/meta/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Meta</a> product manager has claimed that the social network circumvented Apple’s <a href="https://9to5mac.com/guides/privacy/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">privacy</a> protections, as well as cheating advertisers, and fired him when he repeatedly raised the issue internally.</p>



<p>Meta is said to have found ways to identify Apple users even after they refused consent for app tracking, in order to avoid an estimated <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2021/11/01/apples-app-privacy-policy/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">$10 billion loss of revenue</a> …</p>







<p>Meta relied heavily on selling personalized advertising, which required it to be able to target particular demographics and interest groups. This was achieved by tracking individual users across different apps.</p>



<p>Apple’s <a href="https://9to5mac.com/guides/app-tracking-transparency/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">App Tracking Transparency</a> (ATT) was introduced in 2021 and meant that companies required user permission in order to carry out this tracking. Unsurprisingly, the vast majority of users declined.</p>



<p>It was estimated at the time that this would cost social media companies many billions of dollars, and Meta’s CFO warned investors that its own loss would be around $10B per year</p>







<p>It was quickly alleged that <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2022/09/22/app-tracking-transparency-workaround/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Meta was using workarounds</a> to continue to track users who had denied permission, alongside <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2022/08/24/facebook-privacy-3/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">other privacy violations</a>. A class action lawsuit followed.</p>



<p>A fired product manager at the company, Samujjal Purkayastha, has now taken his case to an employment tribunal claiming he was unlawfully dismissed for raising concerns about the practice, reports the <em><a href="https://www.ft.com/content/be6a99d2-22de-48ec-9afa-1d2e2f709afc" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Financial Times</a></em>.</p>



<blockquote>
<p>Meta secretly linked user data with other information to track users’ activity on other websites without their permission — despite Apple in 2021 introducing measures explicitly requiring consent, according to Purkayastha’s filings […]</p>



<p>A “closed and secretive” team at Meta is alleged to have used “deterministic matching” — gathering identifiable information that could then be used to connect data across multiple platforms in violation of Apple’s new privacy policies.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>He also accuses Meta of inflating the value of sales achieved by advertising on its platforms.</p>



<p>Meta denies any wrongdoing, and claims that Purkayastha was dismissed for unrelated reasons. The tribunal was unable to rule immediately, and said a full hearing will be held later in the year.</p>



<h4 id="h-highlighted-accessories">Highlighted accessories</h4>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/3UaJjDn" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Official Apple Store on Amazon</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Anker-Charger-Compact-Technology-Included/dp/B0CP7NWH6L?tag=blovejoy-20" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Anker 511 Nano Pro ultra-compact iPhone charger</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Spigen-Compatible-Accessories-Anti-Yellowing-Military-Grade/dp/B0DKGBTVHW?tag=blovejoy-20" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Spigen MagFit case for iPhone 16e – adds MagSafe support</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Apple-MagSafe-Charger-Capability-Compatible/dp/B0DGJ4QQ5W?tag=blovejoy-20" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Apple MagSafe Charger with 25w power for iPhone 16 models</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Apple-30W-USB-C-Power-Adapter/dp/B0CX23PHFD?tag=blovejoy-20" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Apple 30W charger for above</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/B0C4FDJ8F7?tag=blovejoy-20" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Anker 240W braided USB-C to USB-C cable</a></li>
</ul>



<p><em>Photo by&nbsp;<a href="https://unsplash.com/@heller_mario?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">Mario Heller</a>&nbsp;on&nbsp;<a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/a-mans-eye-is-seen-through-a-pipe-DZoOkd3Tbak?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">Unsplash</a></em></p>
	<p>
				<a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://news.google.com/publications/CAAqBggKMLOFATDAGg?hl=en-US&amp;gl=US&amp;ceid=US:en">
			<em>Add 9to5Mac to your Google News feed.</em>&nbsp;
					</a>
			</p>
	<div><p><em>FTC: We use income earning auto affiliate links.</em> <a href="https://9to5mac.com/about/#affiliate">More.</a></p><p><a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/bmx/solidsafe-safer-solid-state-battery-for-iphone-wireless-usb?ref=gka71h"><img src="https://9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2025/08/BMX-Mac-925-banner-1.png" alt="" width="750" height="150"></a></p></div>				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Apple has a private CSS property to add Liquid Glass effects to web content (330 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://alastair.is/apple-has-a-private-css-property-to-add-liquid-glass-effects-to-web-content/</link>
            <guid>45250370</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 14:49:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://alastair.is/apple-has-a-private-css-property-to-add-liquid-glass-effects-to-web-content/">https://alastair.is/apple-has-a-private-css-property-to-add-liquid-glass-effects-to-web-content/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45250370">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>

    

    <div>
        <p>I have an incredibly boring summer hobby: looking at the changelog for the <a href="https://github.com/WebKit/WebKit?ref=alastair.is" rel="noreferrer">WebKit Github repo</a>. Why? Because I spend a chunk of my professional life working with webviews inside mobile apps and I like to get an early peek into what's coming in the next version of iOS. Since Tim Cook has yet to stand up at WWDC and announce "one more thing... Service Worker support in WKWebView, provided you add the correct entry to the <code>WKAppBoundDomains</code> array in your <code>Info.plist</code>" (and you know what, he <em>should</em>) manual research is the order of the day.</p><p>So I was really interested to see, the day after WWDC finished, a pull request named:</p><blockquote><a href="https://github.com/WebKit/WebKit/pull/46754/files?ref=alastair.is" rel="noreferrer">[Materials] Rename "hosted blur" materials to reference "glass"</a></blockquote><p><a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/06/apple-introduces-a-delightful-and-elegant-new-software-design/?ref=alastair.is" rel="noreferrer">Liquid Glass</a> was one of the big takeaways from 2025's WWDC. Probably the biggest change in iOS UI since iOS 7 ditched the skeuomorphic look of the past. But that's all native UI, what does any of that have to do with webviews?</p><p>A poke around the context of the PR revealed something really interesting: Apple has a custom CSS property named <code>-apple-visual-effect</code> . Not only does it allow the use of Liquid Glass in iOS 26 (via values like <code>-apple-system-glass-material</code>) but all versions support using <a href="https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/materials?ref=alastair.is#Standard-materials" rel="noreferrer">standard materials</a> with values like <code>-apple-system-blur-material-thin</code>.</p><h3 id="yes-it-works-and-no-we-cant">Yes it works and no, we can't</h3><p>Before you, like me, fire up Safari and start editing some CSS, I have bad news: no, it doesn't work on the web. As well it shouldn't. But it <em>also</em> doesn't work by default in an app using WKWebView, you have to toggle a setting in WKPreferences called <code>useSystemAppearance</code>... and it's <a href="https://github.com/WebKit/WebKit/blob/613c42873c56e2b2073f91b2983eec825be6a791/Source/WebKit/UIProcess/API/Cocoa/WKPreferencesInternal.h?ref=alastair.is#L59" rel="noreferrer">private</a>. So if you use it, say goodbye to App Store approval.</p><p>I wanted to try it out all the same so I hacked around to set <code>useSystemAppearance</code> to true, set my CSS to:</p><pre><code>.toolbar {
  border-radius: 50%;
  -apple-visual-effect: -apple-system-glass-material;
  height: 75px;
  width: 450px;
}</code></pre><p>lo and behold, it works!</p><figure data-kg-thumbnail="https://alastair.is/content/media/2025/09/glass_with_ipad_new_frame_thumb.jpg" data-kg-custom-thumbnail="">
            <div>
                <video src="https://alastair.is/content/media/2025/09/glass_with_ipad_new_frame.mp4" poster="https://img.spacergif.org/v1/2266x1488/0a/spacer.png" width="2266" height="1488" loop="" autoplay="" muted="" playsinline="" preload="metadata"></video>
                
                <div>
                        <p>
                        
                        <span>0:00</span></p><p>
                            /<span>0:09</span>
                        </p>
                        </div>
            </div>
            <figcaption><p><span>With thanks to MapboxGL JS for the beautiful background</span></p></figcaption>
        <img src="https://alastair.is/content/media/2025/09/glass_with_ipad_new_frame_thumb.jpg"></figure><p>Whoever it was at Apple that decided to make this a CSS property is a genius because it makes it incredibly easy to provide different rules based on Liquid Glass support:</p><pre><code>.toolbar {
  border-radius: 50%;
  height: 75px;
  width: 450px;
  background: rgba(204, 204, 204, 0.7);
}

@supports (-apple-visual-effect: -apple-system-glass-material) {
  background: transparent;
  -apple-visual-effect: -apple-system-glass-material
}</code></pre><h2 id="who-cares">Who cares?</h2><p>It's an interesting piece of trivia but no-one outside of Apple can use it. So what does it matter? It doesn't. Except for the implication for what I'll call Alastair's Grand Theory of In-App Webviews. Industry wide they don't have a great reputation. But my suggestion is this: <strong>the main reason webviews in apps have such a bad reputation is because you don't notice the webviews that are integrated seamlessly.</strong></p><p>It stands to reason that Apple wouldn't have developed this feature if they weren't using it. Where? We have no idea. But they must be using it <em>somewhere</em>. The fact that none of us have noticed exactly where suggests that we're interacting with webviews in our daily use of iOS without ever even realising it.</p><p>Food for thought!</p>
    </div>

    

</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to self-host a web font from Google Fonts (128 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.velocifyer.com/Posts/3,0,0,2025-8-13,+how+to+self+host+a+font+from+google+fonts.html</link>
            <guid>45250202</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 14:33:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.velocifyer.com/Posts/3,0,0,2025-8-13,+how+to+self+host+a+font+from+google+fonts.html">https://blog.velocifyer.com/Posts/3,0,0,2025-8-13,+how+to+self+host+a+font+from+google+fonts.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45250202">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
        <a href="https://blog.velocifyer.com/"><h2>Blog-𝕚𝕗𝕪𝕖𝕣</h2></a>
        
        <h3>2025-8-13 (September 14th, 2025)..= 2025-8-14 (september 15th 2025)</h3>
            <!-- TODO: fix line spacing -->
            A common place to get a web font is <a href="https://fonts.google.com/" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">Google Fonts</a><br>
            If you want to use a font from Google Fonts, you should not just paste the code they give you so you don't leak visitor IP adresses to google.<br>
            Instead, you should download the font files and put them on your webserver.<br>
            The Download button in Google Fonts gives TTF files and not WOFF2 files<br>
            If you want a font used it this website(like Noto Sans and Fira Code), copy the relevant files from here <a href="https://codeberg.org/Velocifyer/Blog-ifyer/src/branch/main/Assets/Fonts/" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" ping="https://blog.velocifyer.com/clicked+link+to+codeberg+fonts">
            here
        </a> and skip steps 0 and 1.<br>
        <strong>THIS IS NOT LEGAL ADVICE</strong><br>
        <strong>I AM NOT YOUR LAWYER</strong>
        <ol start="-1">
            <li><strong>ENSURE THAT YOUR USE OF THE FONT WILL COMPLY WITH THE LICENSE</strong></li>
            <li>
                Download the font
                <ol start="0">
                    <li>
                        Go to <a href="https://fonts.google.com/" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">Google Fonts</a> and search for the font you want.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Select "Get font".
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Select "Get embed code" (don't paste the code it gives you).
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Select which options you want included.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        In the HTML code it gives you, it should have something like <code>&lt;link href="https://fonts.googleapis.com/css2?family=Fira+Code&amp;display=swap" rel="stylesheet"&gt;</code>.<br>
                        Download the file using the URL after the href (<code>https://fonts.googleapis.com/css2?family=Fira+Code&amp;display=swap</code> in this case).
                        Download each font referenced in the CSS file you just downloaded.<br>
                        Put all of the font you just downloaded in a folder, ideally with a something that will change each update and a long cache time (like /Assets/Fira/Code/2025-8-13/).<br>
                        Copy the CSS file into that folder.
                        Change the CSS to use relative links.<br> (eg change <code>src: url(https://fonts.gstatic.com/s/firacode/v26/uU9eCBsR6Z2vfE9aq3bL0fxyUs4tcw4W_D1sJVD7Ng.woff2) format('woff2');</code> into <code>src: url(uU9eCBsR6Z2vfE9aq3bL0fxyUs4tcw4W_D1sJVD7Ng.woff2) format('woff2');</code>)
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </li>
            <li>
                Paste the license of the font into a file. To find the license of a google font do:
                <ol start="0">
                    <li>Search for the font on <a href="https://fonts.google.com/" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">Google Fonts</a></li>
                    <li>Select the font</li>
                    <li>Select "License"</li>
                </ol>
            </li>
            <li>
                Add html to use the CSS like:
                <pre><code>&lt;link href="/Assets/Fonts/Fira/Code/2025-8-13/fira-code.css" rel="preload"&gt;
&lt;link href="/Assets/Fonts/Fira/Code/2025-8-13/fira-code.css" rel="stylesheet"&gt;</code></pre>
            </li>
            <li>
                Add css to use the font like:
<pre><code>code {
    font-family: "Fira Code", monospace;
    font-optical-sizing: auto;
    font-weight: 400;
    font-style: normal;
}</code></pre>
            </li>
            <li>
                Add a link to the font LICENSE and <strong>ensure that your usage of the font follows the license of the font</strong>.
            </li>
        </ol>
        If you can't understand these steps, <a href="https://codeberg.org/Velocifyer/Blog-ifyer/src/branch/main/Assets/Fonts/Noto/Sans/2025-8-3" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" ping="https://blog.velocifyer.com/clicked+other+link+to+codeberg+fonts">
            see how it was done here.
        </a>
        <hr>
            <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45250202">View/Comment/Upvote on Hacker News</a>
        <hr>
        <small>
            <a href="https://blog.velocifyer.com/Posts/Posts/feed.atom">Atom Feed</a><br>
            To contact Velocifyer, email velocifyer at (the domain of this blog). <br>
            Velocifyer's OpenPGP Certificate is <a href="https://blog.velocifyer.com/Posts/pgp-certificate.asc">1BA0 FC4B 80E0 F21B 0269 8CEE 634E BF87 40C7 48BE</a>
            Except for the favicon and javascript and the fonts, this is licensed CC-BY-SA 4.0 𝕍𝕖𝕝𝕠𝕔𝕚𝕗𝕪𝕖𝕣.<br>
            One of the fonts used on this website is Fira Code, which uses <a href="https://blog.velocifyer.com/Assets/Fonts/Fira/Code/2025-8-13/LICENSE.TXT">this</a> license.
            One of the fonts used on this website is Noto Sans, which uses <a href="https://blog.velocifyer.com/Assets/Fonts/Noto/Sans/2025-8-3/License.txt">this license</a>.<br>
            This blog is available on <a href="https://codeberg.org/Velocifyer/Blog-ifyer">Codeberg</a>. Make an issue or merge request if it would be useful.<br>
            View warrant canaries <a href="https://files.velocifyer.com/Warant%20canaries/" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade">here</a>.
            
        </small>
    

</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Programming Deflation (103 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://tidyfirst.substack.com/p/programming-deflation</link>
            <guid>45249985</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 14:11:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://tidyfirst.substack.com/p/programming-deflation">https://tidyfirst.substack.com/p/programming-deflation</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45249985">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><p>The genies are out of the bottle. Let’s take as a given that augmented coding is steadily reducing the cost, skill barriers, and time needed to develop software. (Interesting debate to be had—another day.)</p><p>Will this lead to fewer programmers or more programmers?</p><p>Economics gives us two contradictory answers simultaneously.</p><ul><li><p><strong>Substitution</strong><span>. The substitution effect says we'll need fewer programmers—machines are replacing human labor.</span></p></li><li><p><strong>Jevons’. </strong><span>Jevons’ paradox predicts that when something becomes cheaper, demand </span><em>increases</em><span> as the cheaper good is economically viable in a wider variety of cases.</span></p></li></ul><p>Both can't be right. Or can they?</p><p><span>Another way of looking at the contradiction—if programs are cheaper to write today than they were yesterday, then we should be more likely to write them today. </span><em>But</em><span>, if programs are going to be cheaper to write tomorrow, then why not just wait until the cost goes to zero? This is the deflationary spiral, the urge to defer investment leading to less economic activity leading to lower prices leading to the urge to defer investment.</span></p><p>What’s a software executive to do? A programmer? What we’d like is a strategy that:</p><ul><li><p>Let’s us act today.</p></li><li><p>Doesn’t rely on information that just not available.</p></li><li><p>Leads to reasonable outcomes regardless of which way the rock tumbles.</p></li></ul><p>Traditional deflation is destructive because it reflects economic weakness—falling demand, broken confidence, shrinking money supply. Programming deflation is different. It's driven by genuine productivity gains. AI isn't just redistributing the same pie; it's making the pie-making process fundamentally cheaper.</p><p>This creates some interesting paradoxes:</p><p><strong>Delay vs. Experiment</strong><span>: Yes, you might wait for better tools. But when experimentation costs approach zero, the urge to try something </span><em>right now</em><span> often wins. How many of us have spun up a quick prototype just because we could?</span></p><p><strong>Quality Bifurcation</strong><span>: Cheap code floods the market. Most of it is terrible. But the gap between commodity code and carefully crafted software widens. The middle disappears.</span></p><p><strong>Value Migration</strong><span>: Writing code becomes like typing—a basic skill, not a career. Value moves to understanding what to build, how systems fit together, and navigating the complexity of infinite cheap software pieces.</span></p><p><span>Here's where programming deflation breaks the traditional model entirely. In economic deflation, the spiral is self-reinforcing and destructive. In programming deflation, cheaper tools might actually </span><em>accelerate</em><span> innovation—when programming accelerates programming. Better tools. Better models. The reinforcing loop kicks in.</span></p><p>Every small business becomes a software company. Every individual becomes a developer. The cost of "what if we tried..." approaches zero.</p><p>Publishing was expensive in 1995, exclusive. Then it became free. Did we get less publishing? Quite the opposite. We got an explosion of content, most of it terrible, some of it revolutionary.</p><p>So what do we do while we're in this deflation? A few thoughts:</p><p><strong>Embrace the Commodity</strong><span>: Use the cheap tools. Build the obvious stuff with AI. Save your energy for the hard problems.</span></p><p><strong>Focus on Integration</strong><span>: The bottleneck isn't writing code anymore. It's making all these cheap software pieces work together coherently.</span></p><p><strong>Develop Taste</strong><span>: When anyone can build anything, knowing what's worth building becomes the skill.</span></p><p><strong>Think in Systems</strong><span>: Individual programs are commoditized. Complex, adaptive systems are not.</span></p><p>In a world of abundant cheap code, what becomes scarce? Understanding. Judgment. The ability to see how pieces fit together. The wisdom to know what not to build.</p><p>We're not just experiencing technological change. We're watching the basic economics of software development transform in real time. The question isn't whether programming deflation will happen—it's already happening. The question is how we adapt to abundance.</p><p>Here's the beautiful thing about focusing on understanding, integration, and judgment: these skills matter whether we end up with fewer programmers or more programmers. If automation replaces routine coding, these human skills become the differentiator. If cheap tools create an explosion of new programmers, these skills separate signal from noise even more than they did a year ago.</p><p><span>Cultivating judgement also improves one’s competitive position </span><em>vis a vis</em><span> those who use the tools simply to churn out the same features faster.</span></p><p>Don’t bother predicting which future we'll get. Build capabilities that thrive in either scenario.</p><p><em>Interested in a private, custom talk for your organization on the effects of AI on software development &amp; how y’all can navigate them? Contact me! I still have some slots open in the last quarter of the year.</em></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PayPal to support Ethereum and Bitcoin (373 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://newsroom.paypal-corp.com/2025-09-15-PayPal-Ushers-in-a-New-Era-of-Peer-to-Peer-Payments,-Reimagining-How-Money-Moves-to-Anyone,-Anywhere</link>
            <guid>45249915</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 14:04:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://newsroom.paypal-corp.com/2025-09-15-PayPal-Ushers-in-a-New-Era-of-Peer-to-Peer-Payments,-Reimagining-How-Money-Moves-to-Anyone,-Anywhere">https://newsroom.paypal-corp.com/2025-09-15-PayPal-Ushers-in-a-New-Era-of-Peer-to-Peer-Payments,-Reimagining-How-Money-Moves-to-Anyone,-Anywhere</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45249915">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>PayPal Ushers in a New Era of Peer-to-Peer Payments, Reimagining How Money Moves to Anyone, Anywhere</p><p>Send and receive money as easily as sending a text, across apps, borders, and currencies

</p><div wd_resize="formatNews" wd_print_url="https://newsroom.paypal-corp.com/2025-09-15-PayPal-Ushers-in-a-New-Era-of-Peer-to-Peer-Payments,-Reimagining-How-Money-Moves-to-Anyone,-Anywhere?printable=1"><p>,  /<a href="http://www.prnewswire.com/" target="_blank">PRNewswire</a>/ --&nbsp;On the heels of the PayPal World announcement, a global platform connecting the world's largest digital payment systems and wallets, PayPal today introduced <a href="https://www.paypal.com/us/digital-wallet/send-receive-money/paypal-link">PayPal links</a>, a new way to send and receive money through a personalized, one-time link that can be shared in any conversation.</p>

<p><img alt="PayPal app flow to create a personalized payment link" src="https://newsroom.paypal-corp.com/image/Links_16x7.jpg"><br>
<sub><em>Creating personalized payment links&nbsp; |&nbsp;&nbsp;<a href="https://newsroom.paypal-corp.com/2025-09-15-PayPal-Ushers-in-a-New-Era-of-Peer-to-Peer-Payments,-Reimagining-How-Money-Moves-to-Anyone,-Anywhere#assets_117:19733">Click to Enlarge</a></em></sub></p>

<p>PayPal users in the U.S. can begin creating personalized payment links today, with international expansion to the UK, <span>Italy</span>, and other markets starting later this month. By making payments this simple and universal, PayPal links helps drive new customer acquisition and brings more users into the PayPal ecosystem.</p>

<p>The peer-to-peer (P2P) experience is about to go even further. <span>Crypto</span> will soon be directly integrated into PayPal's new P2P payment flow in the app. This will make it more convenient for PayPal users in the U.S. to send <span>Bitcoin</span>, <span>Ethereum</span>, PYUSD, and more, to PayPal, Venmo, as well a rapidly growing number of digital wallets across the world that support <span>crypto</span> and stablecoins.</p>

<p>Expanding what people can do with PayPal also comes with reassurance around how personal payments are handled. As always, friends-and-family transfers through Venmo and PayPal are exempt from 1099-K reporting. Users won't receive tax forms for gifts, reimbursements, or splitting expenses, helping ensure that personal payments stay personal.</p>

<p>"For 25 years, PayPal has revolutionized how money moves between people. Now, we're taking the next major step," said <span>Diego Scotti</span>, General Manager, Consumer Group at PayPal. "Whether you're texting, messaging, or emailing, now your money follows your conversations. Combined with PayPal World, it's an unbeatable value proposition, showing up where people connect, making it effortless to pay your friends and family, no matter where they are or what app they're using."</p>

<p>P2P is a cornerstone of PayPal's consumer experience, driving engagement and bringing more users into the ecosystem. P2P and other consumer total payment volume saw solid growth in the second quarter, increasing 10% year-over-year as the company focused on improving the experience and increasing user discoverability to make it easier than ever to move money globally. Plus, Venmo saw its highest TPV growth in three years. With PayPal World unlocking seamless interoperability, P2P is poised for even greater momentum in the future as PayPal and Venmo connect to billions of wallets worldwide.</p>

<p><b><i>How PayPal links work:</i></b></p>

<ul type="disc">
	<li><b>Create a personalized link</b> – Open the PayPal app, enter the details of your payment or request, and generate a unique, one-time link to share.</li>
	<li><b>Always the right person</b> – Each link is private, one-time use, and created for a specific transaction.</li>
	<li><b>Drop it anywhere</b> – Send your link in a text, DM, email, or chat. Add a note, emoji, or payment note.</li>
	<li><b>Manage payment activity:</b> Unclaimed links expire after 10 days. Users can send a reminder or even cancel the payment or request before the link is claimed with the PayPal app.</li>
	<li><b>Tap and done</b> – The recipient taps the link and either completes or accepts the payment within the PayPal App with their PayPal account.</li>
	<li><b>Funds are instant </b>– the recipient will get immediate access to their funds with a PayPal Balance account once accepted.<br>
	&nbsp;</li>
</ul>

<p><b>About PayPal</b><br>
<span>PayPal has been revolutionizing commerce globally for more than 25 years. Creating innovative experiences that make moving money, selling, and shopping simple, personalized, and secure, PayPal empowers consumers and businesses in approximately 200 markets to join and thrive in the global economy. For more information, visit&nbsp;</span><a href="https://edge.prnewswire.com/c/link/?t=0&amp;l=en&amp;o=4508758-1&amp;h=3058181002&amp;u=https%3A%2F%2Fc212.net%2Fc%2Flink%2F%3Ft%3D0%26l%3Den%26o%3D4457610-1%26h%3D4001781295%26u%3Dhttps%253A%252F%252Fwww.paypal.com%252Fus%252Fhome%26a%3Dhttps%253A%252F%252Fwww.paypal.com&amp;a=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.paypal.com" rel="nofollow" target="_blank">https://www.paypal.com</a><span>,&nbsp;</span><a href="https://edge.prnewswire.com/c/link/?t=0&amp;l=en&amp;o=4508758-1&amp;h=2013349456&amp;u=https%3A%2F%2Fc212.net%2Fc%2Flink%2F%3Ft%3D0%26l%3Den%26o%3D4457610-1%26h%3D222604361%26u%3Dhttps%253A%252F%252Fabout.pypl.com%252Fabout-us%252Fdefault.aspx%26a%3Dhttps%253A%252F%252Fabout.pypl.com%252F&amp;a=https%3A%2F%2Fabout.pypl.com%2F" rel="nofollow" target="_blank">https://about.pypl.com/</a><span>&nbsp;and&nbsp;</span><a href="https://edge.prnewswire.com/c/link/?t=0&amp;l=en&amp;o=4508758-1&amp;h=1969862495&amp;u=https%3A%2F%2Fc212.net%2Fc%2Flink%2F%3Ft%3D0%26l%3Den%26o%3D4457610-1%26h%3D793990610%26u%3Dhttps%253A%252F%252Finvestor.pypl.com%252Fhome%252F%26a%3Dhttps%253A%252F%252Finvestor.pypl.com%252F&amp;a=https%3A%2F%2Finvestor.pypl.com%2F" rel="nofollow" target="_blank">https://investor.pypl.com/</a><span>.</span></p>

<p><b>About PayPal USD (PYUSD)</b> &nbsp;&nbsp;<br>
PayPal USD is issued by Paxos Trust Company, LLC, a fully chartered limited purpose trust company. Paxos is licensed to engage in Virtual Currency Business Activity by the <span>New York State</span> Department of Financial Services. Reserves for PayPal USD are fully backed by U.S. dollar deposits, U.S. Treasuries and similar cash equivalents, and PayPal USD can be bought or sold through PayPal and Venmo at a rate of <span>$1.00</span> per PayPal USD.&nbsp;&nbsp;<br>
PayPal, Inc. (NMLS ID #: 910457) is licensed to engage in Virtual Currency Business Activity by the <span>New York State</span> Department of Financial Services.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>

<p><b>Media contact</b><br>
<span>Gideon Anstey</span><br>
<a href="mailto:gbanstey@paypal.com" rel="nofollow" target="_blank">gbanstey@paypal.com</a></p>

<div>
<h4>Related Articles</h4>




</div>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[CubeSats are fascinating learning tools for space (166 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/cubesats-are-fascinating-learning-tools-space</link>
            <guid>45249878</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 14:02:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/cubesats-are-fascinating-learning-tools-space">https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/cubesats-are-fascinating-learning-tools-space</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45249878">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/four-cubesats-together.jpeg" width="700" height="394" data-insert-type="image" data-entity-type="file" data-entity-uuid="insert-image-fbd23249-1ddc-40cf-a157-77b2ea4f0c6e" data-insert-attach="{&quot;id&quot;:&quot;fbd23249-1ddc-40cf-a157-77b2ea4f0c6e&quot;,&quot;attributes&quot;:{&quot;alt&quot;:[&quot;alt&quot;,&quot;description&quot;],&quot;title&quot;:[&quot;title&quot;]}}" alt="Cubesats together"></p>

<p>These are CubeSats. Satellites that are going to space—or at least, the ones I have here are <em>prototypes</em>. But these have one thing in common: they're all powered by either a Raspberry Pi, or a microcontroller.</p>

<p>There are already Pis in space, like on Mark Rober's <a href="https://space.crunchlabs.com/">SatGus</a>, on <a href="https://www.raspberrypi.com/news/worlds-first-raspberry-pi-powered-cubesat-celebrates-record-making-orbit/">GASPACS</a>, and the <a href="https://astro-pi.org/">Astro Pis on the Space station</a>. Another Pi is going up <em>this weekend</em>, which is why I'm posting <em>this</em> today. I'll get to that one, but I wanted to spend some time talking about two things that fascinate me: Raspberry Pis, and putting them space!</p>

<p>In this post, I'll cover:</p>

<ul>
<li>What is a CubeSat</li>
<li>Who builds and launches CubeSats</li>
<li>How <em>you</em> can build your own CubeSat</li>
</ul>

<p>Then for a bonus, in today's video, I interviewed two people helping students launch SilverSat into space (this weekend!), and a YouTuber who I've learned a lot from about track satellites (including CubeSats) from your own backyard!</p>

<div>
<p><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qvN3sE2Nv4U" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>
</div>

<p>The rest of this post contains a lightly-edited transcript of the video above.</p>

<p>So let's dive in.</p>

<h2>What's a CubeSat?</h2>

<p>What's a CubeSat? Well, it's in the name—it's a satellite that's a cube!</p>

<p>But they don't have to be a cube, these smallest ones are '1U', or 10 x 10 x 10 centimeters. You can also find 2U CubeSats, like the taller Build a CubeSat, which is <em>20</em> centimeters tall. (Well, technically the current prototype is 1.5U).</p>

<p><a href="https://isstracker.pl/en/satellites/62713">SatGus</a>, Mark Rober's satellite taking space selfies, is a whopping <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6KcV1C1Ui5s">12U</a>! They needed all that extra space to fit a phone, a mechanism to <em>deploy</em> the phone, a camera to take the selfie, a Raspberry Pi to control the phone, and redundant systems for <em>everything</em>. They've already taken <em>thousands</em> of selfies, and SatGus has me beat. My best Pi might get to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OXXKi-J0gs4">3.4 Gigahertz</a>, but the Pi on SatGus is whizzing through space at almost <a href="https://www.pulsesat.com/satellites/s/302a5e31-68b8-422a-86fd-cfe32474ef6e/"><em>17,000 miles per hour</em></a>. That's <em>7,570 meters per second</em> for everyone else in the world.</p>

<p>But back to CubeSats. Having standards means you can build off existing work for the hard things, like a space-rated Aluminum frame, or the complex EPS, or Electrical Power System board.</p>

<p>Then you can add in custom parts, like a Pi to run experiments, a communications board with antennas and radios, cameras, sensors, and more!</p>

<p><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/cubesat-build-a-cubesat-antennas.jpeg" width="700" height="394" data-insert-type="image" data-entity-type="file" data-entity-uuid="insert-image-6c8bc5c8-7585-48d8-a06c-f10d1140d008" data-insert-attach="{&quot;id&quot;:&quot;6c8bc5c8-7585-48d8-a06c-f10d1140d008&quot;,&quot;attributes&quot;:{&quot;alt&quot;:[&quot;alt&quot;,&quot;description&quot;],&quot;title&quot;:[&quot;title&quot;]}}" alt="Build a CubeSat Antennas"></p>

<p>And <em>these</em> cubesats have normal screw-on antennas, but the way these things are deployed, you only get 10x10x10 centimeters—you can't have an antenna poking out the top. So they use cool things like <a href="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-981-19-7474-8_15">flexible tape antennas</a> that pop out once your CubeSat deploys.</p>

<p>What else makes CubeSats cool?</p>

<p>Well, how about price? In the old days, you had to have like $10 million to build a satellite, and $60+ million to launch it into space.</p>

<p>Today, you can build a space-ready CubeSat using a few <em>thousand</em> dollars of parts. Then you can launch it on a rideshare for... well, <a href="https://nanoracks.com/wp-content/uploads/Cubesat-Services.pdf">$85 grand</a>. Which is a <em>lot</em>, but it's not <em>$60 million-a-lot</em>.</p>

<p>So most of us won't be launching one of these things into space, unless maybe you can get a grant. But that doesn't mean they're not useful to us.</p>

<h2>Who builds CubeSats?</h2>

<p>Like with many projects, I love these things for the challenge, the way they break some of my assumptions, like working with Raspberry Pis.</p>

<p>If you're building a device that's less than 2 kilograms, has 1.8W of maximum continuous power draw, and needs to be operated remotely—even for just a month—you're immediately going to change your assumptions about how you build things.</p>

<p>I would hack Home Assistant onto a mini PC to monitor some sensors if I was feeling lazy—but that Mini PC would use an order of magnitude too much power for a CubeSat (much less the internal volume it would occupy).</p>

<p>On CubeSats, every millimeter, and every milliAmp has to be accounted for.</p>

<p>So to me, CubeSats are like Swiss watches of modern electronics. How many sensors can you fit in one? How much throughput can you get on a tiny radio with a small antenna? Can you get enough power out of tiny solar cells to keep the main flight computer working? How do you control thermals without air? How do you design it so it can recover from a complete power loss?</p>

<p>Every step of the way there are challenges; and that's before we even launch one! Someone who I think illustrates this best is Manuel, with his <a href="https://codeberg.org/buildacubesat-project">Build a CubeSat</a> project. He's working on this Cubesat:</p>

<p><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/cubesat-build-a-cubesat.jpeg" width="700" height="394" data-insert-type="image" data-entity-type="file" data-entity-uuid="insert-image-e8f931dd-27ae-47b2-8834-4ee4dde6d557" data-insert-attach="{&quot;id&quot;:&quot;e8f931dd-27ae-47b2-8834-4ee4dde6d557&quot;,&quot;attributes&quot;:{&quot;alt&quot;:[&quot;alt&quot;,&quot;description&quot;],&quot;title&quot;:[&quot;title&quot;]}}" alt="Build a CubeSat"></p>

<p>He did a weather balloon launch this year, and he's <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@buildacubesat">documenting everything on YouTube</a>.</p>

<p>His first launch had many small problems. But also great learning, especially around redundancy and how to get the thing off the <em>launch</em> stand without problems.</p>

<p>And you're not only dealing with hardware, but also with <em>software</em>. And software that, at its core, <em>has</em> to be remotely accessed. And not only remote, but also <em>wireless</em>, meaning anyone <em>else</em> on earth within range can access it too.</p>

<p>So how do you keep it secure? That's something Tim from <a href="https://ethoslabs.space/">Ethos Labs</a> is also dealing with with <em>this</em>, his T.E.M.P.E.S.T. CubeSat:</p>

<p><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/cubesat-tempest-with-ground-station.jpeg" width="700" height="394" data-insert-type="image" data-entity-type="file" data-entity-uuid="insert-image-d7c3fe9a-3901-4cca-8a05-cc8ee81a2027" data-insert-attach="{&quot;id&quot;:&quot;d7c3fe9a-3901-4cca-8a05-cc8ee81a2027&quot;,&quot;attributes&quot;:{&quot;alt&quot;:[&quot;alt&quot;,&quot;description&quot;],&quot;title&quot;:[&quot;title&quot;]}}" alt="CubeSat TEMPEST"></p>

<p>This thing is actually made to be <em>not</em> secure. It has intentional vulnerabilities, and he uses those to teach people different ways to make <em>their</em> CubeSats <em>more</em> secure.</p>

<p>You have complex hardware, running in limited space, with limited power and communications, and you want cram in as much functionality as possible.</p>

<p>Do you see where I'm going with this? That kind of problem is perfect for the microcontrollers and low-power SBCs that I love testing and playing with every day.</p>

<p>Except instead of me worrying about something consuming 10 watts, these guys are looking at a power budget of <em>one</em> watt. Or less!</p>

<p>These problems are <em>hard</em>. And not everyone has the patience for a completely custom project like Build a CubeSat, so there are also some small companies building <em>kits</em> to help you learn all these lessons with a little less stress.</p>

<p>Like what hardware do you need for a 100% self-contained CubeSat? And how do you get it certified for flight on a SpaceX rocket?</p>

<h2>Your own CubeSat</h2>

<p>Well, I'll quickly cover two products that are meant for like STEM classroom education, one from the lower end, and one that's based on a CubeSat that just flew this summer.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/cubesat-mysat.jpeg" width="700" height="394" data-insert-type="image" data-entity-type="file" data-entity-uuid="insert-image-65a69da8-2129-4089-9ead-f44b1a2c459c" data-insert-attach="{&quot;id&quot;:&quot;65a69da8-2129-4089-9ead-f44b1a2c459c&quot;,&quot;attributes&quot;:{&quot;alt&quot;:[&quot;alt&quot;,&quot;description&quot;],&quot;title&quot;:[&quot;title&quot;]}}" alt="MySat CubeSat"></p>

<p>The first one is the <a href="https://www.mysatkit.com/">MySat Kit</a>, that you can buy from MySat in Ukraine. It comes with a board powered by an ESP32 with a camera, light sensors, an LED, gyroscope, accelerometer, barometer, clock, and a few other boards. And these are all off-the-shelf components you can buy replacements for or use 'em with other hardware, like a Raspberry Pi.</p>

<p>The way it's put together won't hold up on a rocket launch, but it's not meant for that. It's meant to show you how it's built, how you can communicate with it, and that sort of thing.</p>

<p>It took like an hour to build, and once I put it together I tried flashing the flight control firmware with my Mac... but I ran into some issues with Arduino IDE, and that's a <em>me</em> problem and not so much a MySat problem. Plus the team behind it has a whole war going on that they've been dealing with, so I'll be patient and try getting it going later.</p>

<p>The MySat goes from like $130 for a basic kit where you 3D print your own frame, or up to $300 for a full kit including deployable solar panels.</p>

<p>On the higher end, there's <a href="https://www.robinson-aerospace.com/cubesat">RASCube</a>, and Edward Robinson, the 21 year old founder of Robinson Space, sent it over after he saw me posting about CubeSats online.</p>

<p>The RASCube comes from Australia, and Edward's mission is to teach students about space through hands-on building.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/rascube-lb-rbf-tag.jpeg" width="700" height="394" data-insert-type="image" data-entity-type="file" data-entity-uuid="insert-image-e33d0cda-b427-49c5-9378-1f723f535040" data-insert-attach="{&quot;id&quot;:&quot;e33d0cda-b427-49c5-9378-1f723f535040&quot;,&quot;attributes&quot;:{&quot;alt&quot;:[&quot;alt&quot;,&quot;description&quot;],&quot;title&quot;:[&quot;title&quot;]}}" alt="RASCube LB CubeSat"></p>

<p>I just built this LS version of the cube last week; it's the little brother to their V2 design, which <em>flew in space</em> on a Falcon 9 rocket earlier this year.</p>

<p>Like MySat, you build the kit with an EPS board for power, a computer board with all the controls, and a radio board that ties in GPS and radio comms.</p>

<p>The RASCubes are a bit more expensive, coming in at around $430 each for the LB, and $600 each for the full aluminum V2s. But the price tag on that also covers full lesson plans and resources for teachers.</p>

<p>I love these things—all the people I've talked to on this journey are motivated by the same thing: learning about space, electronics, and integrating hardware in a new way, and sharing what they learn with others, especially students.</p>

<h2>CubeSat T.E.M.P.E.S.T. and Build a CubeSat</h2>

<p>Like take Build a Cubesat. For that project, <a href="https://codeberg.org/buildacubesat-project/bac-hardware"><em>everything</em> is open source hardware</a>, and every part of the journey is being documented on YouTube.</p>

<p>One thing I learned from the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bDQ_N9Gvzqs">first flight test</a> was how weird it is to have your Pi go from like overheating on the ground, to getting really cold as it goes higher, but then overheating again in the upper atmosphere because there's not enough air to dissipate heat!</p>

<p>You start to realize some of the crazy physical conditions you'll deal with on orbit.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/cubesat-tempest-ground-station-pico.jpeg" width="700" height="394" data-insert-type="image" data-entity-type="file" data-entity-uuid="insert-image-ee5aabae-0658-476e-89bf-29164500901a" data-insert-attach="{&quot;id&quot;:&quot;ee5aabae-0658-476e-89bf-29164500901a&quot;,&quot;attributes&quot;:{&quot;alt&quot;:[&quot;alt&quot;,&quot;description&quot;],&quot;title&quot;:[&quot;title&quot;]}}" alt="CubeSat TEMPEST Ground Station Raspberry Pi Pico"></p>

<p>Back down to earth, though, for CubeSat Tempest: the whole reason this exists is to help people learn why security is important, even for a tiny CubeSat. More importantly, <a href="https://www.antisyphontraining.com/product/foundations-in-space-cybersecurity-hardware-edition-with-tim-fowler/">Tim Fowler's course</a> teaches people <em>how</em> to secure things like uplinks (see: the ground station pictured above) and flight control systems.</p>

<p>There are so many people like Tim, who work in their free time to try to teach about space, or engineering, or just small slices of things like security, using these tactile little cubes you can build and put next to your laptop on a desk.</p>

<p>It's crazy to think we're to a point where <em>students</em> can build these things, write flight control software, and even <em>launch 'em into space</em>!</p>

<p>And that brings me to <a href="https://silversat.org/">SilverSat</a>.</p>

<h2>SilverSat</h2>

<p>There's another CubeSat with a Raspberry Pi onboard, and it's launching NET <em>Sunday</em>, at 6:11 p.m. Eastern time, aboard a Falcon 9 rocket. What does NET mean? Well, as I found out when I visited Florida this summer, that means "No Earlier Than", and in spaceflight, many things delay launches.</p>

<p>The students who built SilverSat are no strangers to delays—they were originally supposed to see their CubeSat launch earlier this year, but the cargo module they were on got <a href="https://arstechnica.com/space/2025/03/nasa-sidelines-cygnus-spacecraft-after-damage-in-transit-to-launch-site/">damaged during transport</a>, and that delayed them for <em>months</em>.</p>

<p>I got to talk to two of the adults guiding the students on their first space launch, and I discussed the history of the project (it started up in <em>2017</em>), how they are supported by NASA's <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/cubesat-launch-initiative-introduction/">CubeSat Launch Initiative</a>, the importance of amateur radio for CubeSats, and why they chose a Raspberry Pi Zero for their onboard computer.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/raspberry-pi-zero-2w-rbf-tag.jpeg" width="700" height="394" data-insert-type="image" data-entity-type="file" data-entity-uuid="insert-image-1e5acf9b-eb16-4bb9-a0ff-c34d10da66d1" data-insert-attach="{&quot;id&quot;:&quot;1e5acf9b-eb16-4bb9-a0ff-c34d10da66d1&quot;,&quot;attributes&quot;:{&quot;alt&quot;:[&quot;alt&quot;,&quot;description&quot;],&quot;title&quot;:[&quot;title&quot;]}}" alt="Raspberry Pi with CubeSats"></p>

<p>That interview is tucked away in the last half of the video at the top of this post.</p>

<h2>Tracking Satellites from your backyard</h2>

<p>Also in that video, I spoke to Gabe from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@saveitforparts">saveitforparts</a>, and he mentioned it's not that difficult to listen in on satellites on orbit—including amateur CubeSats!</p>

<p>SilverSat will be broadcasting <a href="https://github.com/silver-sat/systems/wiki/SSDV">SSDV</a> (Slow-Scan Digital Video) at set times, and the <a href="https://silversat.org/mission-status/">schedule for that</a> should be posted on their website.</p>

<p>Check out the video embedded in this post (near the top), or Gabe's own channel for ideas for tracking satellites. It can be done with under $100 of equipment (usually just an SDR and a cheap antenna).</p>

<h2>Infectious Enthusiasm for Learning (and Teaching)</h2>

<p>I feel like a broken record, but one thing I love, talking to <em>anyone</em> in the CubeSat community is this sense of infectious enthusiasm. And I was going to cut this video out for time, but watching it back, I realized other people would probably enjoy Tim showing off some neat CubeSats in his personal collection as much as I did. So I put up some bonus content on my second channel, Level 2 Jeff; you can watch another 8 minutes of CubeSat hardware below:</p>

<div>
<p><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/woO0w92YuC0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>
</div>

<p>Thank you to <em>everyone</em> who taught me about CubeSats for this video and blog post.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hosting a WebSite on a Disposable Vape (651 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://bogdanthegeek.github.io/blog/projects/vapeserver/</link>
            <guid>45249287</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 13:13:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://bogdanthegeek.github.io/blog/projects/vapeserver/">https://bogdanthegeek.github.io/blog/projects/vapeserver/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45249287">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><h2 id="preface">Preface<a href="#preface" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>This article is <em>NOT</em> served from a web server running on a disposable vape. If you want to see the real deal, click <a href="http://ewaste.fka.wtf/">here</a>. The content is otherwise identical.</p><h2 id="background">Background<a href="#background" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>For a couple of years now, I have been collecting disposable vapes from friends and family. Initially, I only salvaged the batteries for “future” projects (It’s not hoarding, I promise), but recently, disposable vapes have gotten more advanced. I wouldn’t want to be the lawyer who one day will have to argue how a device with USB C and a rechargeable battery can be classified as “disposable”. Thankfully, I don’t plan on pursuing law anytime soon.</p><p>Last year, I was tearing apart some of these fancier pacifiers for adults when I noticed something that caught my eye, instead of the expected black blob of goo hiding some ASIC (Application Specific Integrated Circuit) I see a little integrated circuit inscribed “PUYA”.
I don’t blame you if this name doesn’t excite you as much it does me, most people have never heard of them. They are most well known for their flash chips, but I first came across them after reading Jay Carlson’s blog post about <a href="https://jaycarlson.net/2023/02/04/the-cheapest-flash-microcontroller-you-can-buy-is-actually-an-arm-cortex-m0/">the cheapest flash microcontroller you can buy</a>. They are quite capable little ARM Cortex-M0+ micros.</p><p>Over the past year I have collected quite a few of these PY32 based vapes, all of them from different models of vape from the same manufacturer. It’s not my place to do free advertising for big tobacco, so I won’t mention the brand I got it from, but if anyone who worked on designing them reads this, thanks for labeling the debug pins!</p><h2 id="what-are-we-working-with">What are we working with<a href="#what-are-we-working-with" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>The chip is marked <code>PUYA C642F15</code>, which wasn’t very helpful. I was pretty sure it was a <code>PY32F002A</code>, but after poking around with <a href="http://pyocd.io/">pyOCD</a>, I noticed that the flash was 24k and we have 3k of RAM. The extra flash meant that it was more likely a <code>PY32F002B</code>, which is actually a very different chip.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p><p>So here are the specs of a microcontroller so <em>bad</em>, it’s basically disposable:</p><ul><li>24MHz Coretex M0+</li><li>24KiB of Flash Storage</li><li>3KiB of Static RAM</li><li>a few peripherals, none of which we will use.</li></ul><p>You may look at those specs and think that it’s not much to work with. I don’t blame you, a 10y old phone can barely load google, and this is about 100x slower. I on the other hand see a <em>blazingly</em> fast web server.</p><h2 id="getting-online">Getting online<a href="#getting-online" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>The idea of hosting a web server on a vape didn’t come to me instantly. In fact, I have been playing around with them for a while, but after writing my post on <a href="https://bogdanthegeek.github.io/blog/insights/jlink-rtt-for-the-masses/">semihosting</a>, the penny dropped.</p><p>If you don’t feel like reading that article, semihosting is basically syscalls for embedded ARM microcontrollers. You throw some values/pointers into some registers and call a breakpoint instruction. An attached debugger interprets the values in the registers and performs certain actions. Most people just use this to get some logs printed from the microcontroller, but they are actually bi-directional.</p><p>If you are older than me, you might remember a time before Wi-Fi and Ethernet, the dark ages, when you had to use dial-up modems to get online. You might also know that the ghosts of those modems still linger all around us. Almost all USB serial devices actually emulate those modems: a 56k modem is just 57600 baud serial device. Data between some of these modems was transmitted using a protocol called SLIP (Serial Line Internet Protocol).<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup></p><p>This may not come as a surprise, but Linux (and with some tweaking even macOS) supports SLIP. The <code>slattach</code> utility can make any <code>/dev/tty*</code> send and receive IP packets. All we have to do is put the data down the wire in the right format and provide a virtual tty.
This is actually easier than you might imagine, pyOCD can forward all semihosting though a telnet port. Then, we use <code>socat</code> to link that port to a virtual tty:</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="sh"><span><span>pyocd gdb -S -O semihost_console_type<span>=</span>telnet -T <span>$(</span>PORT<span>)</span> <span>$(</span>PYOCDFLAGS<span>)</span> &amp;
</span></span><span><span>socat PTY,link<span>=</span><span>$(</span>TTY<span>)</span>,raw,echo<span>=</span><span>0</span> TCP:localhost:<span>$(</span>PORT<span>)</span>,nodelay &amp;
</span></span><span><span>sudo slattach -L -p slip -s <span>115200</span> <span>$(</span>TTY<span>)</span> &amp;
</span></span><span><span>sudo ip addr add 192.168.190.1 peer 192.168.190.2/24 dev sl0
</span></span><span><span>sudo ip link set mtu <span>1500</span> up dev sl0
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Ok, so we have a “modem”, but that’s hardly a web server. To actually talk TCP/IP, we need an IP stack. There are many choices, but I went with <a href="https://github.com/adamdunkels/uip/tree/uip-0-9">uIP</a> because it’s pretty small, doesn’t require an RTOS, and it’s easy to port to other platforms.
It also, helpfully, comes with a very minimal HTTP server example.</p><p>After porting the SLIP code to use semihosting, I had a working web server…half of the time.
As with most highly optimised libraries, uIP was designed for 8 and 16-bit machines, which rarely have memory alignment requirements. On ARM however, if you dereference a <code>u16 *</code>, you better hope that address is even, or you’ll get an exception. The <code>uip_chksum</code> assumed <code>u16</code> alignment, but the script that creates the filesystem didn’t.
I actually decided to modify a bit the structure of the filesystem to make it a bit more portable.
This was my first time working with <code>perl</code> and I have to say, it’s quite well suited to this kind of task.</p><h2 id="blazingly-fast">Blazingly fast<a href="#blazingly-fast" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>So how fast is a web server running on a disposable microcontroller. Well, initially, not very fast. Pings took ~1.5s with 50% packet loss and a simple page took over 20s to load. That’s so bad, it’s actually funny, and I kind of wanted to leave it there.</p><p>However, the problem was actually between the seat and the steering wheel the whole time. The first implementation read and wrote a single character at a time, which had a massive overhead associated with it. I previously benchmarked semihosting on this device, and I was getting ~20KiB/s, but uIP’s SLIP implementation was designed for very low memory devices, so it was serialising the data byte by byte.
We have a whopping 3kiB of RAM to play with, so I added a ring buffer to cache reads from the host and feed them into the SLIP poll function. I also split writes in batches to allow for escaping.</p><p>Now this is what I call blazingly fast! Pings now take 20ms, no packet loss and a full page loads in about 160ms. This was using using almost all of the RAM, but I could also dial down the sizes of the buffer to have more than enough headroom to run other tasks. The project repo has everything set to a nice balance latency and RAM usage:</p><pre tabindex="0"><code>Memory region         Used Size  Region Size  %age Used
           FLASH:        5116 B        24 KB     20.82%
             RAM:        1380 B         3 KB     44.92%
</code></pre><p>For this blog however, I paid for none of the RAM, so I’ll use all of the RAM.</p><p>As you may have noticed, we have just under 20kiB (80%) of storage space. That may not be enough to ship all of React, but as you can see, it’s more than enough to host this entire blog post.
And this is not just a static page server, you can run any server-side code you want, if you know C that is.</p><p>Just for fun, I added a json api endpoint to get the number of requests to the main page (since the last crash) and the unique ID of the microcontroller.</p><h2 id="resources">Resources<a href="#resources" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><ul><li><a href="https://github.com/BogdanTheGeek/semihost-ip">Code for this project</a></li></ul></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How big a solar battery do I need to store all my home's electricity? (248 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://shkspr.mobi/blog/2025/09/how-big-a-solar-battery-do-i-need-to-store-all-my-homes-electricity/</link>
            <guid>45248899</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 12:33:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://shkspr.mobi/blog/2025/09/how-big-a-solar-battery-do-i-need-to-store-all-my-homes-electricity/">https://shkspr.mobi/blog/2025/09/how-big-a-solar-battery-do-i-need-to-store-all-my-homes-electricity/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45248899">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Denmark's Justice Minister calls encrypted messaging a false civil liberty (407 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://mastodon.social/@chatcontrol/115204439983078498</link>
            <guid>45248802</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 12:21:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://mastodon.social/@chatcontrol/115204439983078498">https://mastodon.social/@chatcontrol/115204439983078498</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45248802">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>