<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 22:30:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Nearly half of Nvidia's revenue comes from four mystery whales each buying $3B+ (190 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fortune.com/2024/08/29/nvidia-jensen-huang-ai-customers/</link>
            <guid>41410450</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 17:42:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fortune.com/2024/08/29/nvidia-jensen-huang-ai-customers/">https://fortune.com/2024/08/29/nvidia-jensen-huang-ai-customers/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41410450">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>Microchip designer <a href="https://fortune.com/company/nvidia/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/nvidia/">Nvidia</a> more than doubled its second-quarter revenue thanks to just a handful of whales that accounted for nearly one out of every two dollars in sales the company booked.</p><div>



<p>Four customers, whose identities were kept anonymous for competitive reasons, directly purchased goods and services collectively worth 46% of Nvidia’s $30 billion in turnover. That amounts to roughly $13.8 billion, according to the company’s&nbsp;<a href="https://d18rn0p25nwr6d.cloudfront.net/CIK-0001045810/78501ce3-7816-4c4d-8688-53dd140df456.pdf" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://d18rn0p25nwr6d.cloudfront.net/CIK-0001045810/78501ce3-7816-4c4d-8688-53dd140df456.pdf" rel="noopener">10-Q regulatory filing</a>&nbsp;published alongside its&nbsp;<a href="https://fortune.com/2024/08/23/nvidia-jensen-huang-quarterly-earnings-tech-bull-market-ai/?utm_source=search&amp;utm_medium=suggested_search&amp;utm_campaign=search_link_clicks" target="_self" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/2024/08/23/nvidia-jensen-huang-quarterly-earnings-tech-bull-market-ai/?utm_source=search&amp;utm_medium=suggested_search&amp;utm_campaign=search_link_clicks">hotly anticipated</a>&nbsp;quarterly investor update.</p>



<p>Each was responsible for more than a tenth of overall top line, and their purchases were all related to its booming business selling chips to data centers, the likes of which entrepreneurs such as&nbsp;<a href="https://fortune.com/2024/04/29/elon-musk-tesla-ai-fsd-china-ev-sales/?utm_source=search&amp;utm_medium=suggested_search&amp;utm_campaign=search_link_clicks" target="_self" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/2024/04/29/elon-musk-tesla-ai-fsd-china-ev-sales/?utm_source=search&amp;utm_medium=suggested_search&amp;utm_campaign=search_link_clicks">Elon Musk</a>&nbsp;are in a&nbsp;<a href="https://fortune.com/2024/06/18/elon-musk-xai-memphis-supercomputer-site/" target="_self" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/2024/06/18/elon-musk-xai-memphis-supercomputer-site/">rush to build</a>&nbsp;amid the gold rush in artificial intelligence.&nbsp;</p>



<p>To put that into perspective, this quartet of customers contributed more in sales than Nvidia reported for the prior year’s period as a whole.&nbsp;</p>



<blockquote><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Video of the inside of Cortex today, the giant new AI training supercluster being built at <a href="https://fortune.com/company/tesla/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/tesla/">Tesla</a> HQ in Austin to solve real-world AI <a href="https://t.co/DwJVUWUrb5" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://t.co/DwJVUWUrb5" rel="noopener">pic.twitter.com/DwJVUWUrb5</a></p>— Elon Musk (@elonmusk) <a href="https://twitter.com/elonmusk/status/1827981493924155796?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://twitter.com/elonmusk/status/1827981493924155796?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" rel="noopener">August 26, 2024</a></blockquote>



<p>Although the names of the mystery AI whales are not known, <a href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/nvidias-largest-customers-201900375.html?" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://finance.yahoo.com/news/nvidias-largest-customers-201900375.html?" rel="noopener">they are likely to include</a> Amazon, Meta, Microsoft, Alphabet, OpenAI, or Tesla.</p>



<p>Nvidia’s hottest products are AI chips like the H200. These are needed to train large language models like OpenAI’s GPT-4. They are also used to power inference, the process that ChatGPT or&nbsp;<a href="https://fortune.com/2024/02/16/sora-openai-sam-altman-text-to-video-generative-ai/" target="_self" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/2024/02/16/sora-openai-sam-altman-text-to-video-generative-ai/">Sora</a>&nbsp;uses to generate answers to text-based prompts.</p>



<p>This dependency on a handful of major customers also highlights a rising concern in the market over just how sustainable this abrupt, exponential growth from just one corner of its business can be. Some investors like&nbsp;<a href="https://fortune.com/2024/08/02/ai-nvidia-intel-arm-stock-bubble-elliott/" target="_self" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/2024/08/02/ai-nvidia-intel-arm-stock-bubble-elliott/">Elliott Management</a>&nbsp;and Citadel have&nbsp;<a href="https://fortune.com/2024/07/02/ken-griffin-citadel-generative-ai-hype-openai-mira-murati-nvidia-jobs/?utm_source=search&amp;utm_medium=suggested_search&amp;utm_campaign=search_link_clicks" target="_self" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/2024/07/02/ken-griffin-citadel-generative-ai-hype-openai-mira-murati-nvidia-jobs/?utm_source=search&amp;utm_medium=suggested_search&amp;utm_campaign=search_link_clicks">voiced skepticism</a>&nbsp;over how long this can be maintained.</p>



<p>History does give reason for concern. The semiconductor industry is known for its boom-and-bust cycles.</p>



<p>Shares in Nvidia are expected to open lower on Thursday, underperforming the broader equity market.</p>



<h2>One customer provided revenue greater than Nvidia’s second-largest business</h2>



<p>In fact Nvidia’s business ties with these whales are so significant the company flags them in a section of its quarterly reports titled “concentration of revenue,” which is dedicated to cluster risks.</p>



<p>“We have experienced periods where we receive a significant amount of our revenue from a limited number of customers,” it stated in its 10-Q regulatory filing, “and this trend may continue.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>It’s a trend that is staggeringly profitable. Nvidia pocketed $5.60 out of every $10 of revenue it made over the entire first half as net income—margins most companies can only dream of.&nbsp;</p>



<p>That explains why profit after tax nearly quadrupled to $31.5 billion during this six-month period over the previous year. Whether revenue, and therefore earnings, can continue to grow at this blistering pace is crucial to its investment story.</p>



<p>Take “Customer B” cited in the filing, for example: Its direct purchases represented 11% of Nvidia’s $30 billion in revenue. That means a single company contributed more in business than the group’s second largest division—gaming, with $2.9 billion—did as a whole.</p>



<p>Customer B, however, remained below the 10% threshold for the entire first half, which suggests it significantly ramped up spending during the past quarter seemingly out of the blue. The exact same could be said about “Customer C”; the numbers provided by Nvidia are identical.&nbsp;</p>



<blockquote><p lang="qme" dir="ltr"><a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%24NVDA&amp;src=ctag&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://twitter.com/search?q=%24NVDA&amp;src=ctag&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" rel="noopener">$NVDA</a> <a href="https://t.co/Lym4uHBCXs" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://t.co/Lym4uHBCXs" rel="noopener">pic.twitter.com/Lym4uHBCXs</a></p>— Jesse Cohen (@JesseCohenInv) <a href="https://twitter.com/JesseCohenInv/status/1828404561867923571?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://twitter.com/JesseCohenInv/status/1828404561867923571?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" rel="noopener">August 27, 2024</a></blockquote>



<p>Speaking to Bloomberg TV on Wednesday, CEO Jensen Huang answered a question on where demand is coming from, beyond the handful of hyperscalers like <a href="https://fortune.com/company/microsoft/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/microsoft/">Microsoft</a>, <a href="https://fortune.com/company/alphabet/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/alphabet/">Google</a>, and <a href="https://fortune.com/company/amazon-com/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/amazon-com/">Amazon</a>.</p>



<p>“We’re relatively diversified today,” he&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NC5NZPrxbHk&amp;t=99s" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NC5NZPrxbHk&amp;t=99s" rel="noopener">claimed</a>, citing a range of different customer groups.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Yet his own company’s numbers appear to dispute that conclusion. This time last year, for example, there were no direct customers whose business made up 10% or more of total revenue—neither for the first nor the second quarter.</p>



<p>Nvidia didn’t immediately respond to a request from&nbsp;<em>Fortune</em>&nbsp;for comment.</p></div><div data-cy="subscriptionPlea"><p><strong>Recommended reading:</strong><br>In our new special issue, a Wall Street legend gets a radical makeover, a tale of crypto iniquity, misbehaving poultry royalty, and more.<br><a href="https://fortune.com/packages/digital-issue-kkr/?&amp;itm_source=fortune&amp;itm_medium=article_tout&amp;itm_campaign=kkr_issue" target="_self" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/packages/digital-issue-kkr/?&amp;itm_source=fortune&amp;itm_medium=article_tout&amp;itm_campaign=kkr_issue">Read the stories.</a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Did your car witness a crime? Bay Area police may be coming for your Tesla (126 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.sfchronicle.com/crime/article/tesla-sentry-mode-police-evidence-19731000.php</link>
            <guid>41409882</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 16:21:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/crime/article/tesla-sentry-mode-police-evidence-19731000.php">https://www.sfchronicle.com/crime/article/tesla-sentry-mode-police-evidence-19731000.php</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41409882">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.sfchronicle.com/crime/article/tesla-sentry-mode-police-evidence-19731000.php: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Harder Drive: hard drives we didn't want, or need [video] (2022) (230 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://tom7.org/harder/</link>
            <guid>41409503</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 15:21:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://tom7.org/harder/">http://tom7.org/harder/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41409503">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p><span>Harder</span>
  <span>Drive</span>:<br> Hard drives we didn't want or need
</p>

<h2>Read words</h2>
Consider reading the paper, <b><a href="http://tom7.org/papers/murphy2022harder.pdf">Harder Drive: Hard drives we didn't want or need</a></b>, which appears in
<a href="http://sigbovik.org/2022/">SIGBOVIK 2022</a>. (<a href="http://tom7.org/papers/murphy2022harder.bib">bibtex</a>)


<h2>Watch draws and hear words</h2>

<iframe width="853" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/JcJSW7Rprio" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
	 
Of course, there are multiple irksome videos on my YouTube channel <a href="https://youtube.com/suckerpinch">Suckerpinch</a>!

<img src="http://tom7.org/harder/titlescreen1080.png" alt="screenshot for thumbnails">

<h2>Browse the internet</h2>
If you have a 64-bit Windows machine and enough RAM (32 GB?) and want to try out the app I used in the video for exploring the
IPv4 address space, you can try this torrent:
<a href="http://tom7.org/harder/harder-drive-internet-map.torrent">harder-drive-internet-map.torrent</a>. I'll shoot to keep this working through the end
of April 2022, but no promises.

<h2>Ringtones</h2>
Enhance your mobile calling experience with the ringtone audio from
the video, available with my other songs at <a href="http://mp3.tom7.org/t7es">Tom 7 Entertainment System</a>.

<h2>Have your own Harder Drive</h2>
Good luck trying to use the impenetrable <a href="https://sourceforge.net/p/tom7misc/svn/HEAD/tree/trunk/pingu/">source code</a>.

<p>Please leave a comment <a href="http://radar.spacebar.org/">on my blog</a> or on Twitter at <a href="http://twitter.com/tom7">@tom7</a>!
</p><p>Get all Tom 7 thingos at → [<a href="http://tom7.org/">tom7.org</a>]</p>




</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Rust solves the problem of incomplete Kernel Linux API docs (165 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://vt.social/@lina/113056457969145576</link>
            <guid>41409475</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 15:16:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://vt.social/@lina/113056457969145576">https://vt.social/@lina/113056457969145576</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41409475">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Buy, Borrow, Die – Explained (225 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://old.reddit.com/r/BuyBorrowDieExplained/comments/1f26rsf/buy_borrow_die_explained/</link>
            <guid>41408772</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 13:35:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/BuyBorrowDieExplained/comments/1f26rsf/buy_borrow_die_explained/">https://old.reddit.com/r/BuyBorrowDieExplained/comments/1f26rsf/buy_borrow_die_explained/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41408772">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>So, you’ve read about “buy, borrow, die” but you’re left with more questions than answers about how - and why - it works. Maybe you’re skeptical that it works at all. Is it just a concept journalists have manufactured that sounds good on paper but falls apart under closer scrutiny? </p>

<p>I’m a private wealth attorney at an international law firm headquartered in the U.S. and I implement “buy, borrow, die” for a living. The short answer is, yes, “buy, borrow, die” works, and it’s a devastatingly effective tax elimination strategy. </p>

<p>Let's dive into the planning a little bit and use some concrete examples to illustrate. In the comments below I will answer some of the frequently asked questions I see in discussions about “buy, borrow, die,” and address some of the misconceptions people have about it. </p>

<p><strong>Step 1A. Buy.</strong> </p>

<p>This stage of the planning really is that simple. Peter will purchase an asset for $50M. His "basis" in the asset is therefore $50M. Let's assume the asset appreciates at an annual rate of 8 percent. After 10 years, the asset now has a fair market value of $108M and Peter has a "built-in" (or "unrealized") capital gain of $58M.</p>

<p>If Peter sells the asset, it's a "realization" event and he'll be subject to income tax. The asset is a capital asset, and since Peter has owned the asset for more than 1 year, he'd receive long-term capital gain treatment and pay income tax at preferential rates if he sold it. Nevertheless, Peter's long-term capital gain rate would be 20 percent, he'd be subject to the net investment income tax of 3.8 percent, and Peter lives in Quahog which has a 5 percent income tax rate. </p>

<p>So, if Peter were to sell the asset and cash in on his gain, he'd have a total tax liability of around $17M, and his after-tax proceeds would be $91M. </p>

<p>Peter's buddy Joe overheard some of his cop buddies talking about how the ultrawealthy never pay taxes because they implement "buy, borrow, die," and he shares the idea with Peter. Peter decides to look into it.</p>

<p><strong>Step 2A. Borrow.</strong> </p>

<p>Peter goes to the big city and hires a private wealth attorney, who connects him with an investment banker at Quahog Sachs. The investment bank might give Peter a loan or line of credit of up to $97M (a "loan to value" ratio of 90 percent) based on several conditions, including that the loan/line of credit is secured by the asset. Now Peter has $97M of cash to use as he pleases, and he's paid no taxes.</p>

<p><strong>Step 3A. Die.</strong> </p>

<p>Peter has been living off these asset-backed loans/lines of credits and his asset has continued appreciating in value. Let's say 35 years have passed. With an annual rate of return of 8 percent, the asset now has a fair market value of $740M.</p>

<p>Then Peter dies. When Peter dies, the basis of the asset is "adjusted" to the asset's fair market value on Peter's date of death. In other words, Peter's basis of $50M in the asset is adjusted to $740M.</p>

<p>Peter's estate can now sell the asset tax free, because "gain" is computed by subtracting adjusted basis from the sales proceeds ($740M sales proceeds less $740M adjusted basis equals $0 gain). </p>

<p>Peter's estate can use the cash to pay back the loans/lines of credits. He's paid no income tax and his beneficiaries can now use the cash to buy assets and begin the "buy, borrow, die" cycle themselves. </p>

<p><strong>BUY, BORROW, DIE IN THE REAL WORLD:</strong></p>

<p>Actual “buy, borrow, die” planning is enormously complicated. If that weren't the case, the ultrawealthy wouldn’t have to pay private wealth attorneys like me upwards of $2,500 an hour for their tax, asset protection, and estate planning needs. </p>

<p>First, this type of planning is generally not economically feasible unless the taxpayer has a net worth exceeding around <strong>$300M</strong>. If you’re worth less than that, you’re not going to be able to command attractive loan/line of credit terms from investment banks. You’re going to have to get a plain vanilla product from a retail lender which is going to have relatively high interest rates (typically the Secured Overnight Financing Rate plus some amount of spread) and other terms that make implementing “buy, borrow, die” expensive enough that you aren’t much better off (or you’re much worse off) than you would have been had you sold the asset and taken the after-tax proceeds. (Caveat: even loans/lines of credit at retail interest rates can still be very useful for short-term borrowing needs.) Clients with a net worth exceeding around $300M, however, can obtain bespoke products from the handful of lenders that specialize in this market, and the terms and conditions of these products make “buy, borrow, die” a no-brainer for virtually everyone who has this level of wealth. </p>

<p><strong>These types of loans/lines of credit will typically be interest-only and mature on the borrower’s death. The interest rates can be ultra-low based on numerous factors—I’ve seen anywhere from 0.5 percent to 3 percent, even in the current interest rate environment.</strong> But again, these types of loans/lines of credit are highly customized and the terms depend on the facts and circumstances. </p>

<p>Generally, in exchange for such favorable terms (i.e., interest-only, matures on death), the bank will ask for a share of the collateral’s appreciation (essentially, "stock appreciation rights"), and this obligation will be settled upon the borrower’s death along with the loan. The amount of the bank’s share of the collateral’s appreciation depends on many factors and it is fundamentally a matter of the bank’s underwriting process. </p>

<p>Ultimately, when the debt is settled, the taxpayer is going to pay a large sum to the investment bank, taking into consideration the risk involved and the time value of money. But by structuring the loan/line of credit in this way, the taxpayer has deferred the vast majority of their debt repayment until their death – at which point, as explained above, they can sell their assets tax-free and use the cash to satisfy those obligations. When faced with the alternatives of (i) paying the investment bank and attorneys $X or (ii) paying the government $1,000X, it’s a pretty easy choice for the taxpayer. </p>

<p><strong>The simple explanation described above, and as described in most media accounts of "buy, borrow, die," totally ignores wealth transfer taxes (in particular, gift and estate taxes).</strong> This is a very unusual oversight because “buy, borrow, die,” as it exists in the real world at least, is very much an integrated tax and estate planning strategy. </p>

<p>The unified estate and gift tax exemption for 2024 is $13.61M per taxpayer, or $27.22M per married couple. That means you can give up to $13.61M to anybody you want, either during your lifetime or upon your death, without paying any wealth transfer tax. Amounts you give away above that are generally subject to wealth transfer tax at a rate of 40 percent. So, if Peter gifts (or bequests) $15M to Meg, the first $13.61M is tax free, and the remaining $1.39M is subject to a 40 percent gift (or estate) tax, creating a tax liability of $556,000.</p>

<p>In the above example, when Peter dies with an asset worth $740M – assuming he has no other assets or liabilities and he has not used any of his wealth transfer tax exemption – he is going to be subject to an estate tax of $290.5M ($740M less $13.61M then multiplied by 40 percent) (assuming Peter does not make any gifts to his spouse, Lois, that qualify for the marital deduction, or any gifts to charitable organizations that qualify for the charitable deduction). Peter has avoided income tax by virtue of the basis adjustment that occurs at death, but he's subject to a substantial estate tax that in theory serves as a backstop to make sure he pays some taxes eventually (even if it’s not until his death).</p>

<p>The conventional wisdom is that you can avoid income tax (via the basis adjustment at death) <em>or</em> you can avoid estate tax (via lifetime gifting and estate freezing strategies) but you can’t do both. This conventional wisdom is wrong, and I’ll explain why below.</p>

<p><strong>What a well-advised taxpayer would do is implement an estate freezing technique early on in the “buy, borrow, die” game.</strong> This will involve transferring assets to an irrevocable trust. </p>

<p>Importantly, the trust agreement is going to provide Peter with a retained power of substitution (i.e., a power to remove assets from the irrevocable trust and title them in his own name so long as he replaces the removed assets with assets having the same fair market value) and the right to borrow from the trust without providing adequate security. These powers serve two principal purposes. First, they cause the trust to be treated as a “grantor” trust for federal income tax purposes (which, among other things, allows Peter to transact with the trust without any adverse tax consequences). And second, they allow Peter to pull appreciated properly and/or cash out of the trust to perfect the techniques described below. </p>

<p>Now, let’s revisit “buy, borrow, die,” but instead of the oversimplified concept we see in the news that seems (i) totally ineffective in a moderate to high interest rate environment and (ii) exposes the taxpayer to an enormous estate tax, let’s look at how “buy, borrow, die” is actually carried out by private wealth attorneys in the real world.</p>

<p><strong>Step 1B. Buy.</strong></p>

<p>Peter buys an asset worth $50M and transfers it to the PLG 2024 Irrevocable Trust (the "Trust"). To eliminate gift tax on that transfer, he'll use his $13.61M exemption amount and a variety of sophisticated techniques we don’t really need to get into here which might involve preferred freeze partnerships, zeroed-out grantor retained annuity trusts, and installment sales to intentionally defective grantor trusts. Suffice to say, we move the $50M asset out of Peter's ownership and all appreciation thereafter occurs outside of his estate for wealth transfer tax purposes. </p>

<p>After 10 years of appreciating at an annual rate of 8 percent, the asset is worth $108M. </p>

<p><strong>Step 2B. Borrow.</strong></p>

<p>Peter goes to the bank to get a loan. But now Peter doesn't have the asset to use as collateral because he transferred it to the Trust! Not a problem. The trustee of the Trust is going to guarantee the loan, using the Trust asset as collateral. In return, Peter will pay the Trust a guaranty fee (typically, around 1 percent of the assets serving as collateral, annually, which will be cumulative and payable upon Peter’s death). Peter can transact with the Trust like this without any adverse consequences because it’s a grantor trust. </p>

<p>Prior to Peter's death, he's going to use a loan/line of credit to obtain cash. Then, he’s going to exercise his power of substitution to swap the highly appreciated asset out of the Trust and swap the cash into the Trust. </p>

<p>So, immediately before the loan, Peter might have $0 assets and $0 liabilities. The trust will have an asset worth $780M and no liabilities. Immediately after the loan, Peter will have perhaps $700M cash (90 percent loan-to-value collateralized by the Trust assets) and $700M liabilities. The Trust will still have $780M assets and no liabilities. </p>

<p>Then Peter will exercise his power of substitution. He’ll swap $700M worth of cash into the trust in exchange for $700M worth of interests in the asset and he'll “buy” the remaining interest - $80M - from the Trust pursuant to a promissory note.</p>

<p>Immediately after the swap, Peter has the $780M asset and $780M liabilities ($700M owed to the bank and $80M owed to the Trust). The Trust has $780M assets ($700M cash and an $80M note) and no liabilities.  </p>

<p>Then Peter dies. </p>

<p><strong>Step 3B. Die.</strong> </p>

<p>Peter's gross estate includes the $780M asset. His estate receives an indebtedness deduction for $780M (the $700M he owes to the lender plus the $80M he owes to the Trust under the promissory note). <strong>Peter's taxable estate is $0 and he pays no estate tax.</strong> </p>

<p>Because the $780M asset is includible Peter's gross estate, it receives a basis adjustment to FMV upon his death. It can now be sold for $780M cash. His personal representative will use $700M to pay off the debt to the bank, and he'll use $80M to pay off the promissory note owed to the Trust. <strong>The Trust now has $780M in cash. All of the built-in (unrealized) capital gain has been eliminated, and Peter and his estate have paid no income tax.</strong> </p>

<p>(But recall that some share of the asset’s appreciation during Peter's lifetime is going to go the bank pursuant to the stock appreciation rights Peter granted them under the terms of the “buy, borrow, die” loan. Peter can’t avoid all costs, he can only avoid all taxes. But the costs are a <em>tiny</em> fraction of the taxes saved, so that’s okay.) </p>

<p>Peter's descendants/beneficiaries can now continue the “buy, borrow, die” cycle, avoiding all wealth transfer taxes and all income taxes in perpetuity, generation after generation after generation. </p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Orphaning bcachefs-tools in Debian (163 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://jonathancarter.org/2024/08/29/orphaning-bcachefs-tools-in-debian/</link>
            <guid>41407768</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 10:22:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://jonathancarter.org/2024/08/29/orphaning-bcachefs-tools-in-debian/">https://jonathancarter.org/2024/08/29/orphaning-bcachefs-tools-in-debian/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41407768">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><div><p>Around a decade ago, I was happy to learn about bcache – a Linux block cache system that implements tiered storage (like a pool of hard disks with SSDs for cache) on Linux. At that stage, ZFS on Linux was nowhere close to where it is today, so any progress on gaining more ZFS features in general Linux systems was very welcome. These days we care a bit less about tiered storage, since any cost benefit in using anything else than nvme tends to quickly evaporate compared to time you eventually lose on it.</p><p>In 2015, it was announced that bcache would grow into its own filesystem. This was particularly exciting and it caused quite a buzz in the Linux community, because it brought along with it more features that compare with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ZFS">ZFS</a> (and also <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Btrfs">btrfs</a>), including built-in compression, built-in encryption, check-summing and RAID implementations.</p><p>Unlike ZFS, it didn’t have a dkms module, so if you wanted to test bcachefs back then, you’d have to pull the entire upstream bcachefs kernel source tree and compile it. Not ideal, but for a promise of a new, shiny, full-featured filesystem, it was worth it.</p><p>In 2019, it seemed that the <a href="https://lkml.org/lkml/2019/6/10/762">time has come for bcachefs to be merged into Linux</a>, so I thought that it’s about time we have the userspace tools (bcachefs-tools) packaged in Debian. Even if the Debian kernel wouldn’t have it yet by the time the bullseye (Debian 11) release happened, it might still have been useful for a future backported kernel or users who roll their own.</p><p>By total coincidence, the first git snapshot that I got into Debian (version 0.1+git20190829.aa2a42b) was committed exactly 5 years ago today.</p><p>It was quite easy to package it, since it was written in C and shipped with a makefile that just worked, and it made it past NEW into unstable in 19 January 2020, just as I <a href="https://jonathancarter.org/2020/02/07/random-bits-from-fosdem-2020/">was about to head off to FOSDEM</a> as the pandemic started, but that’s of course a whole other story.</p><p>Fast-forwarding towards the end of 2023, version 1.2 shipped with some utilities written in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rust_(programming_language)">Rust</a>, this caused a little delay, since I wasn’t at all familiar with Rust packaging yet, so I shipped an update that didn’t yet include those utilities, and saw this as an opportunity to learn more about how the Rust eco-system worked and Rust in Debian.</p><p>So, back in April the Rust dependencies for bcachefs-tools in Debian didn’t at all match the build requirements. I got some help from the Rust team who says that the common practice is to relax the dependencies of Rust software so that it builds in Debian. So errno, which needed the exact version 0.2, was relaxed so that it could build with version 0.4 in Debian, udev 0.7 was relaxed for 0.8 in Debian, memoffset from 0.8.5 to 0.6.5, paste from 1.0.11 to 1.08 and bindgen from 0.69.9 to 0.66.</p><p>I found this a bit disturbing, but it seems that some Rust people have lots of confidence that if something builds, it will run fine. And at least it did build, and the resulting binaries did work, although I’m personally still not very comfortable or confident about this approach (<em>perhaps</em> that might change as I learn more about Rust).</p><p>With that in mind, at this point you may wonder how any distribution could sanely package this. The problem is that they can’t. Fedora and other distributions with stable releases take a similar approach to what we’ve done in Debian, while distributions with much more relaxed policies (like Arch) include all the dependencies as they are vendored upstream.</p><p>As it stands now, bcachefs-tools is impossible to maintain in Debian stable. While my primary concerns when packaging, are for Debian unstable and the next stable release, I also keep in mind people who have to support these packages long after I stopped caring about them (like <a href="https://www.freexian.com/lts/debian/details/">Freexian who does LTS support for Debian</a> or <a href="https://ubuntu.com/about/release-cycle">Canonical who has long-term Ubuntu support</a>, and probably other organisations that I’ve never even heard of yet). And of course, if bcachfs-tools don’t have any usable stable releases, it doesn’t have any LTS releases either, so anyone who needs to support bcachefs-tools long-term has to carry the support burden on their own, and if they bundle it’s dependencies, then those as well.</p><p>I’ll admit that I don’t have any solution for fixing this. I suppose if I were upstream I might look into the possibility of at least supporting a larger range of recent dependencies (<em>usually</em> easy enough if you don’t hop onto the newest features right away) so that distributions with stable releases only need to concern themselves with providing some minimum recent versions, but even if that could work, the upstream author is 100% against any solution other than vendoring all its dependencies with the utility and insisting that it must only be built using these bundled dependencies. I’ve made 6 uploads for this package so far this year, but still I constantly get complaints that it’s out of date and that it’s ancient. If a piece of software is considered so old that it’s useless by the time it’s been published for two or three months, then there’s no way it can survive even a usual stable release cycle, nevermind any kind of long-term support.</p><p>With this in mind (not even considering some hostile emails that I recently received from the upstream developer or his public rants on lkml and reddit), I decided to remove bcachefs-tools from Debian completely. Although after discussing this with another DD, I was convinced to <a href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=1078599" data-type="link" data-id="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=1078599">orphan it instead, which I have now done</a>. I made an upload to experimental so that it’s still available if someone wants to work on it (without having to go through NEW again), it’s been <a href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=1079375">removed from unstable</a> so that it doesn’t migrate to testing, and the ancient (especially by bcachefs-tools standards) versions that are in <a href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=1078543">stable and oldstable will be removed too</a>, since they are very likely to cause damage with any recent kernel versions that support bcachefs.</p><p>And so, my adventure with bcachefs-tools comes to an end. I’d advise that if you consider using bcachefs for any kind of production use in the near future, you first consider how supportable it is long-term, and whether there’s really anyone at all that is succeeding in providing stable support for it.</p></div></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[EU ChatControl is back on the agenda (269 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://digitalcourage.social/@echo_pbreyer/113055345076289453</link>
            <guid>41407562</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 09:25:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://digitalcourage.social/@echo_pbreyer/113055345076289453">https://digitalcourage.social/@echo_pbreyer/113055345076289453</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41407562">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[This month in Servo: tabbed browsing, Windows buffs, devtools, and more (256 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://servo.org/blog/2024/08/31/this-month-in-servo/</link>
            <guid>41406799</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 05:45:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://servo.org/blog/2024/08/31/this-month-in-servo/">https://servo.org/blog/2024/08/31/this-month-in-servo/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41406799">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p><span>2024-08-31</span> Flexbox and WebXR are now enabled by default.</p><div>
  <figure><a href="https://servo.org/img/blog/features-august-2024.png"><img src="https://servo.org/img/blog/features-august-2024.png" alt="Servo nightly with a flexbox-based table of new features including textarea text, ‘border-image’, structuredClone(), crypto.randomUUID(), ‘clip-path’, and flexbox properties themselves"></a>
<figcaption>A flexbox-based table showcasing some of Servo’s new features this month.</figcaption></figure>
<p><span></span>Servo has had several new features land in our nightly builds over the last month:</p>
<ul>
<li>as of 2024-07-27, basic support for <strong>show() on HTMLDialogElement</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/lukewarlow">@lukewarlow</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32681">#32681</a>)</li>
<li>as of 2024-07-29, the <strong>type property on HTMLFieldSetElement</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/shanehandley">@shanehandley</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32869">#32869</a>)</li>
<li>as of 2024-07-31, we now support <strong>rendering text typed in &lt;textarea&gt;</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/mrobinson">@mrobinson</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32886">#32886</a>)</li>
<li>as of 2024-07-31, we now support the <strong>‘border-image’</strong> property (<a href="https://github.com/mrobinson">@mrobinson</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32874">#32874</a>)</li>
<li>as of 2024-08-02, <strong>unsafe-eval</strong> and <strong>wasm-unsafe-eval</strong> CSP <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTTP/Headers/Content-Security-Policy/Sources">sources</a> (<a href="https://github.com/chocolate-pie">@chocolate-pie</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32893">#32893</a>)</li>
<li>as of 2024-08-04, we now support playback of <strong>WAV audio files</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/Melchizedek6809">@Melchizedek6809</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32924">#32924</a>)</li>
<li>as of 2024-08-09, we now support the <strong>structuredClone()</strong> API (<a href="https://github.com/Taym95">@Taym95</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32960">#32960</a>)</li>
<li>as of 2024-08-12, we now support <strong>IIRFilterNode</strong> in Web Audio (<a href="https://github.com/msub2">@msub2</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33001">#33001</a>)</li>
<li>as of 2024-08-13, we now support navigating through <strong>cross-origin redirects</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/jdm">@jdm</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32996">#32996</a>)</li>
<li>as of 2024-08-23, we now support the <strong>crypto.randomUUID()</strong> API (<a href="https://github.com/webbeef">@webbeef</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33158">#33158</a>)</li>
<li>as of 2024-08-29, the <strong>‘clip-path’</strong> property, except path(), polygon(), shape(), or url() values (<a href="https://github.com/chocolate-pie">@chocolate-pie</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33107">#33107</a>)</li>
</ul>
<p>We’ve upgraded Servo to <strong>SpiderMonkey 128</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/sagudev">@sagudev</a>, <a href="https://github.com/jschwe">@jschwe</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32769">#32769</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32882">#32882</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32951">#32951</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33048">#33048</a>), <strong>WebRender 0.65</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/mrobinson">@mrobinson</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32930">#32930</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33073">#33073</a>), <strong>wgpu 22.0</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/sagudev">@sagudev</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32827">#32827</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32873">#32873</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32981">#32981</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33209">#33209</a>), and <strong>Rust 1.80.1</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/Hmikihiro">@Hmikihiro</a>, <a href="https://github.com/sagudev">@sagudev</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32896">#32896</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33008">#33008</a>).</p>
<p><strong>WebXR</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/msub2">@msub2</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33245">#33245</a>) and <strong>flexbox</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/mrobinson">@mrobinson</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33186">#33186</a>) are now <strong>enabled by default</strong>, and web APIs that return promises now correctly <strong>reject the promise on failure</strong>, rather than throwing an exception (<a href="https://github.com/sagudev">@sagudev</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32923">#32923</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32950">#32950</a>).</p>
<p>To get there, we revamped our <strong>WebXR API</strong>, landing support for <strong>Gamepad</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/msub2">@msub2</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32860">#32860</a>), and updates to <strong>hand input</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/msub2">@msub2</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32958">#32958</a>), XRBoundedReferenceSpace (<a href="https://github.com/msub2">@msub2</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33176">#33176</a>), XRFrame (<a href="https://github.com/msub2">@msub2</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33102">#33102</a>), XRInputSource (<a href="https://github.com/msub2">@msub2</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33155">#33155</a>), XRPose (<a href="https://github.com/msub2">@msub2</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33146">#33146</a>), XRSession (<a href="https://github.com/msub2">@msub2</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33007">#33007</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33059">#33059</a>), XRTargetRayMode (#33155), XRView (<a href="https://github.com/msub2">@msub2</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33007">#33007</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33145">#33145</a>), and XRWebGLLayer (<a href="https://github.com/msub2">@msub2</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33157">#33157</a>).</p>
<p>And to top it all off, you can now call <strong>makeXRCompatible() on WebGL2RenderingContext</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/msub2">@msub2</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33097">#33097</a>), not just on WebGLRenderingContext.</p>
<p>The biggest flexbox features that landed this month are the <strong>‘gap’ property</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/Loirooriol">@Loirooriol</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32891">#32891</a>), <strong>‘align-content: stretch’</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/mrobinson">@mrobinson</a>, <a href="https://github.com/Loirooriol">@Loirooriol</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32906">#32906</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32913">#32913</a>), and the <strong>‘start’</strong> and <strong>‘end’</strong> values on <strong>‘align-items’</strong> and <strong>‘align-self’</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/mrobinson">@mrobinson</a>, <a href="https://github.com/Loirooriol">@Loirooriol</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33032">#33032</a>), as well as basic support for <strong>‘flex-direction: column’</strong> and <strong>‘column-reverse’</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/mrobinson">@mrobinson</a>, <a href="https://github.com/Loirooriol">@Loirooriol</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33031">#33031</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33068">#33068</a>).</p>
<p><strong>‘position: relative’</strong> is now supported on flex items (<a href="https://github.com/mrobinson">@mrobinson</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33151">#33151</a>), <strong>‘z-index’ always creates stacking contexts</strong> for flex items (<a href="https://github.com/mrobinson">@mrobinson</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32961">#32961</a>), and we now give flex items and flex containers their correct <strong>intrinsic sizes</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/delan">@delan</a>, <a href="https://github.com/mrobinson">@mrobinson</a>, <a href="https://github.com/mukilan">@mukilan</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32854">#32854</a>).</p>
<p>We’re now working on support for <strong>bidirectional text</strong>, with architectural changes to the fragment tree (<a href="https://github.com/mrobinson">@mrobinson</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33030">#33030</a>) and ‘writing-mode’ interfaces (<a href="https://github.com/mrobinson">@mrobinson</a>, <a href="https://github.com/atbrakhi">@atbrakhi</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33082">#33082</a>), and now partial support for the <strong>‘unicode-bidi’ property</strong> and the <strong>dir attribute</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/mrobinson">@mrobinson</a>, <a href="https://github.com/atbrakhi">@atbrakhi</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33148">#33148</a>).
Note that the <code>dir=auto</code> value is not yet supported.</p>
<figure><a href="https://servo.org/img/blog/servoshell-august-2024.png"><img src="https://servo.org/img/blog/servoshell-august-2024.png" alt="Servo nightly showing a toolbar with icons on the buttons, one tab open with the title “Servo - New Tab”, and a location bar that reads “servo:newtab”"></a>
<figcaption>servoshell now has a more elegant toolbar, tabbed browsing, and a clean but useful “new tab” page.</figcaption></figure>
<h2 id="beyond-the-engine" tabindex="-1"><span></span>Beyond the engine <a href="#beyond-the-engine">
        <span><i></i></span>
      </a></h2>
<p><a href="https://book.servo.org/running-servoshell.html">Servo-the-browser</a> now has a <strong>redesigned toolbar</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/Melchizedek6809">@Melchizedek6809</a>, 33179) and <strong>tabbed browsing</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/webbeef">@webbeef</a>, <a href="https://github.com/Wuelle">@Wuelle</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33100">#33100</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33229">#33229</a>)!
This includes a slick <strong>new tab page</strong>, taking advantage of a new API that lets Servo embedders register <strong>custom protocol handlers</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/webbeef">@webbeef</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33104">#33104</a>).</p>
<p>Servo now runs better on Windows, with keyboard navigation now fixed (<a href="https://github.com/crbrz">@crbrz</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33252">#33252</a>), <code>--output</code> to PNG also fixed (<a href="https://github.com/crbrz">@crbrz</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32914">#32914</a>), and fixes for some font- and GPU-related bugs (<a href="https://github.com/crbrz">@crbrz</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33045">#33045</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33177">#33177</a>), which were causing misaligned glyphs with incorrect colors on servo<!-- no link -->.org (<a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/issues/32459">#32459</a>) and duckduckgo<!-- no link -->.com (<a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/issues/33094">#33094</a>), and corrupted images on wikipedia<!-- no link -->.org (<a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/issues/33170">#33170</a>).</p>
<p>Our <strong>devtools support</strong> is becoming very capable after <a href="https://github.com/eerii">@eerii</a>’s final month of work on their internship project, with Servo now supporting the <strong>HTML tree</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/eerii">@eerii</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32655">#32655</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32884">#32884</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32888">#32888</a>) and the <strong>Styles and Computed panels</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/eerii">@eerii</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33025">#33025</a>).
Stay tuned for a more in-depth post about the Servo devtools!</p>
<h2 id="changes-for-servo-developers" tabindex="-1">Changes for Servo developers <a href="#changes-for-servo-developers">
        <span><i></i></span>
      </a></h2>
<p>Running servoshell immediately after building it is now <strong>several seconds faster on macOS</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/mrobinson">@mrobinson</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32928">#32928</a>).</p>
<p>We now <strong>run clippy in CI</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/sagudev">@sagudev</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33150">#33150</a>), together with the existing tidy checks in a dedicated linting job.</p>
<p>Servo now has <strong>new CI runners</strong> for Windows builds (<a href="https://github.com/delan">@delan</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33081">#33081</a>), thanks to your donations, <strong>cutting Windows-only build times by 70%</strong>!
We’re not stopping at Windows though, and with new runners for Linux builds just around the corner, your WPT try builds will soon be a lot faster.</p>
<p>We’ve been running some <strong>triage meetings</strong> to investigate GitHub issues and coordinate our work on them.
The next Servo issue triage meeting is on <strong>2 September at 10:00 UTC</strong>.
For more details, see <a href="https://github.com/servo/project/issues/99">project#99</a>.</p>
<h2 id="engine-reliability" tabindex="-1">Engine reliability <a href="#engine-reliability">
        <span><i></i></span>
      </a></h2>
<p>August has been a huge month for squashing <strong>crash bugs</strong> in Servo, including on real-world websites.</p>
<p>We’ve fixed crashes when rendering <strong>floats near tables</strong> in <a href="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/">the HTML spec</a> (<a href="https://github.com/Wuelle">@Wuelle</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33098">#33098</a>), <strong>removed unnecessary explicit reflows</strong> that were causing crashes on w3schools<!-- no link -->.com (<a href="https://github.com/jdm">@jdm</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33067">#33067</a>), and <strong>made the HTML parser re-entrant</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/jdm">@jdm</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32820">#32820</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33056">#33056</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/html5ever/pull/548">html5ever#548</a>), fixing crashes on kilonova<!-- no link -->.ro (<a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/issues/32454">#32454</a>), tweakers<!-- no link -->.net (<a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/issues/32744">#32744</a>), and many other sites.
Several other crashes have also been fixed:</p>
<ul>
<li>crashes when <strong>resizing windows with WebGL</strong> on macOS (<a href="https://github.com/jdm">@jdm</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33124">#33124</a>)</li>
<li>crashes when rendering text with <strong>extremely long grapheme clusters</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/crbrz">@crbrz</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33074">#33074</a>)</li>
<li>crashes when rendering text with <strong>tabs in certain fonts</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/mrobinson">@mrobinson</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32979">#32979</a>)</li>
<li>crashes in the parser <strong>after calling window.stop()</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/Taym95">@Taym95</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33173">#33173</a>)</li>
<li>crashes when <strong>passing some values to console.log()</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/jdm">@jdm</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33085">#33085</a>)</li>
<li>crashes when <strong>parsing some &lt;img srcset&gt; values</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/NotnaKO">@NotnaKO</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32980">#32980</a>)</li>
<li>crashes when <strong>parsing some HTTP header values</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/ToBinio">@ToBinio</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32973">#32973</a>)</li>
<li>crashes when <strong>setting window.opener</strong> in certain situations (<a href="https://github.com/Taym95">@Taym95</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33002">#33002</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33122">#33122</a>)</li>
<li>crashes when <strong>removing iframes</strong> from documents (<a href="https://github.com/newmoneybigbucks">@newmoneybigbucks</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32782">#32782</a>)</li>
<li>crashes when <strong>calling new AudioContext()</strong> with unsupported options (<a href="https://github.com/Taym95">@Taym95</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33023">#33023</a>)</li>
<li>intermittent crashes in WRSceneBuilder <strong>when exiting Servo</strong> (<a href="https://github.com/Taym95">@Taym95</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32897">#32897</a>)</li>
</ul>
<p>We’ve fixed a bunch of <strong>BorrowError</strong> crashes under SpiderMonkey GC (<a href="https://github.com/jdm">@jdm</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33133">#33133</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/issues/24115">#24115</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/issues/32646">#32646</a>), and we’re now working towards preventing this class of bugs with static analysis (<a href="https://github.com/jdm">@jdm</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/33144">#33144</a>).</p>
<p>Servo no longer <strong>leaks the DOM Window object</strong> when navigating (<a href="https://github.com/ede1998">@ede1998</a>, <a href="https://github.com/rhetenor">@rhetenor</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32773">#32773</a>), and servoshell now <strong><a href="https://pubs.opengroup.org/onlinepubs/9799919799/functions/V2_chap02.html#tag_16_04_03_01">terminates abnormally</a> when panicking</strong> on Unix (<a href="https://github.com/mrobinson">@mrobinson</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/pull/32947">#32947</a>), ensuring <a href="https://book.servo.org/hacking/testing.html">web tests</a> correctly record their test results as “CRASH”.</p>
<h2 id="donations" tabindex="-1">Donations <a href="#donations">
        <span><i></i></span>
      </a></h2>
<p>Thanks again for your generous support!
We are now receiving <strong>3077 USD/month</strong> (+4.1% over July) in recurring donations.
This includes donations from <strong>12 people</strong> on LFX, but we will stop accepting donations there soon — <strong>please move your recurring donations to <a href="https://github.com/sponsors/servo">GitHub</a> or <a href="https://opencollective.com/servo">Open Collective</a></strong>.</p>
<p>Servo is also on <a href="https://thanks.dev/">thanks.dev</a>, and already <strong>three GitHub orgs</strong> that depend on Servo are sponsoring us there.
If you use Servo libraries like <a href="https://crates.io/crates/url/reverse_dependencies">url</a>, <a href="https://crates.io/crates/html5ever/reverse_dependencies">html5ever</a>, <a href="https://crates.io/crates/selectors/reverse_dependencies">selectors</a>, or <a href="https://crates.io/crates/cssparser/reverse_dependencies">cssparser</a>, signing up for <a href="https://thanks.dev/">thanks.dev</a> could be a good way for you (or your employer) to give back to the community.</p>
<figure><div>
        <p><strong>3077</strong> USD/month</p>
        
        
        <p><strong>10000</strong></p>
    </div></figure>
<p>As always, use of these funds will be decided transparently in the Technical Steering Committee.
For more details, head to our <a href="https://servo.org/sponsorship/">Sponsorship page</a>.</p>


</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Iron as an inexpensive storage medium for hydrogen (133 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ethz.ch/en/news-and-events/eth-news/news/2024/08/iron-as-an-inexpensive-storage-medium-for-hydrogen.html</link>
            <guid>41406669</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 05:03:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ethz.ch/en/news-and-events/eth-news/news/2024/08/iron-as-an-inexpensive-storage-medium-for-hydrogen.html">https://ethz.ch/en/news-and-events/eth-news/news/2024/08/iron-as-an-inexpensive-storage-medium-for-hydrogen.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41406669">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section id="content">
                
                    
    
    <!-- Panorama header -->
    

    <!-- Blog header -->
    
    <!-- Tags when not blog -->
    
        
    

    <!-- Articleheader -->
    <div>
    <p>
            Researchers at ETH Zurich are using iron to store hydrogen safely and for long periods. In the future, this technology could be used for seasonal energy storage.
        </p>
    

</div>

    <!-- Nav & News images -->
    

    <!-- Details -->
    <div>
        <p><span>
            <time datetime="2024-08-28T00:00:00Z">28.08.2024</time>
            
                by
                
                    <a href="https://ethz.ch/en/news-and-events/eth-news/news.html?AUTHOR=Q2hyaXN0b3BoIEVsaGFyZHQ&amp;path=L2NvbnRlbnQvbWFpbi9lbi9uZXdzLXVuZC12ZXJhbnN0YWx0dW5nZW4vZXRoLW5ld3MvbmV3cy9qY3I6Y29udGVudA" title="Christoph Elhardt">
                
                Christoph Elhardt
                
                    </a>
                
            
            
            
        </span></p><ul> 
            <!-- ReadSpeaker --> 
            <li id="news_rs_play">
                <a href="https://app-eu.readspeaker.com/cgi-bin/rsent?customerid=14392&amp;lang=en&amp;voice=Max&amp;readid=contentMain" onclick="readpage(this.href, 'eth-readspeaker'); return false;" data-target="eth-readspeaker">
                    Read
                </a>
            </li>
            <li>
                <a id="newsCommentsLink" href="#comment-system">
                    
                    <span>Number of comments</span>
                </a>
            </li>
            <!-- Socialsharing (configurable) -->
            
    
        
            
                <li>
            
            
            
                </li>
            
        
        
    

        </ul>
    </div>

    <!-- ArticleLeadImage -->
    
        <div>
            <figure>
            <img alt="ETH researchers Samuel Heiniger (left, with a glass of iron ore) and Professor Wendelin Stark in front of the three iron reactors on the Hönggerberg campus of ETH Zurich. " src="https://ethz.ch/en/news-and-events/eth-news/news/2024/08/iron-as-an-inexpensive-storage-medium-for-hydrogen/_jcr_content/articleLeadImage/image.imageformat.carousel.940179852.jpg">
			<figcaption>
			    <p>
			      ETH researchers Samuel Heiniger (left, with a jar of iron ore) and Professor Wendelin Stark in front of the three iron reactors on ETH Zurich’s Hönggerberg campus.&nbsp;(Image: ETH Zurich)</p>
			  </figcaption>
			</figure>
    
          </div>
    

    <!-- Parsys 1 --> 
    <div>

<div>
                
                	<h2>In brief</h2>
                
                
                <ul> 
 <li>Storing hydrogen is expensive and inefficient. In a pilot plant on ETH Zurich’s Hönggerberg campus, ETH researchers are showing how this could soon change.</li> 
 <li>The researchers react the hydrogen with iron oxide in three reactors. The resulting iron is easy to store and convert back into hydrogen and iron oxide.</li> 
 <li>The pilot plant is to be expanded such that by 2026, one-fifth of the Hönggerberg campus’s winter electricity requirements can be met with solar power.</li> 
</ul>
            </div>
<div>
                
                
                <p>Photovoltaics are set to meet over 40 percent of Switzerland’s electricity needs by 2050. But solar power isn’t always available when it’s needed: there’s too much of it in summer and too little in winter, when the sun shines less often and heat pumps are running at full tilt. According to the Swiss federal government’s Energy Strategy, Switzerland wants to close the winter electricity gap with a combination of imports, wind and hydropower as well as alpine solar plants and gas-fired power plants.</p>
<p>One way to minimise the need for imports and gas-fired power plants in winter is to produce hydrogen from cheap solar power in summer, which could then be converted into electricity in winter. However, hydrogen is highly flammable, extremely volatile and makes many materials brittle. Storing the gas from summer until winter calls for special pressurised containers and cooling technology. These require a lot of energy, while the many safety precautions that must be followed make building such storage facilities very expensive. What’s more, hydrogen tanks are never completely leak-proof, which harms the environment and adds to the costs.</p>
<p>Now researchers at ETH Zurich led by Wendelin Stark, Professor of Functional Materials at the Department of Chemistry and Applied Biosciences, have developed a new technology for the seasonal storage of hydrogen that is much safer and cheaper than existing solutions. The researchers are using a well-known technology and the fourth most abundant element on Earth: iron.</p>
<h2>Chemical storage</h2>
<p>To store hydrogen better, Stark and his team are relying on the steam-iron process, which has been understood since the 19th century. If there is a surplus of solar power available in the summer months, it can be used to split water to produce hydrogen. This hydrogen is then fed into a stainless steel reactor filled with natural iron ore at 400 degrees Celsius. There, the hydrogen extracts the oxygen from the iron ore – which in chemical terms is simply iron oxide – resulting in elemental iron and water.</p>
<p>“This chemical process is similar to charging a battery.&nbsp; It means that the energy in the hydrogen can be stored as iron and water for long periods with almost no losses,” Stark says. When the energy is needed again in winter, the researchers reverse the process: they feed hot steam into the reactor to turn the iron and water back into iron oxide and hydrogen. The hydrogen can then be converted into electricity or heat in a gas turbine or fuel cell. To keep the energy required for the discharging process to a minimum, the steam is generated using waste heat from the discharging reaction.</p>

            </div>
<div>
                        <figure>
            <a href="https://ethz.ch/en/news-and-events/eth-news/news/2024/08/iron-as-an-inexpensive-storage-medium-for-hydrogen/_jcr_content/wide_content/image/image.imageformat.lightbox.408338324.png" data-caption="The charging and discharging process for the storage technology." data-size="1450x748" aria-label="Enlarged view: Representation of the charging and discharging process">
	<img alt="Enlarged view: Representation of the charging and discharging process" src="https://ethz.ch/en/news-and-events/eth-news/news/2024/08/iron-as-an-inexpensive-storage-medium-for-hydrogen/_jcr_content/wide_content/image/image.imageformat.1286.408338324.png">
			<span></span>
                        </a>
                <figcaption>
			    <p>
			      The charging and discharging process for the storage technology.&nbsp;(Visualisations: ETH Zurich)</p>
			  </figcaption>
			</figure>
    
                    </div>
<div>
                
                	<h2>Cheap iron ore meets expensive hydrogen</h2>
                
                
                <p>“The big advantage of this technology is that the raw material, iron ore, is easy to procure in large quantities. Plus it doesn’t even need processing before we put it in the reactor,” Stark says. Moreover, the researchers assume that large iron ore storage facilities could be built worldwide without substantially influencing the global market price of iron.</p>
<p>The reactor in which the reaction takes place doesn’t have to fulfil any special safety requirements either. It consists of stainless steel walls just 6 millimetres thick. The reaction takes place at normal pressure and the storage capacity increases with each cycle. Once filled with iron oxide, the reactor can be reused for any number of storage cycles without having to replace its contents. Another advantage of the technology is that the researchers can easily expand the storage capacity. It’s simply a case of building bigger reactors and filling them with more iron ore. All these advantages make this storage technology an estimated ten times cheaper than existing methods.</p>
<p>However, there’s also a downside to using hydrogen: its production and conversion are inefficient compared to other sources of energy, as up to 60 percent of its energy is lost in the process. This means that as a storage medium, hydrogen is most attractive when sufficient wind or solar power is available and other options are off the table. That is especially the case with industrial processes that can’t be electrified.</p>
<h2>Pilot plant on the Hönggerberg campus</h2>
<p>The researchers have demonstrated the technical feasibility of their storage technology using a pilot plant on the Hönggerberg campus. This consists of three stainless steel reactors with a capacity of 1.4 cubic metres, each of which the researchers have filled with 2–3 tonnes of untreated iron ore available on the market.</p>
            </div>
<div>
                        <figure>
            <img alt="Stainless steel boiler in a shed." src="https://ethz.ch/en/news-and-events/eth-news/news/2024/08/iron-as-an-inexpensive-storage-medium-for-hydrogen/_jcr_content/wide_content/image_1397025554/image.imageformat.1286.858633795.jpg">
			<figcaption>
			    <p>
			      This 1.4-cubic-metre stainless steel reactor at the Hönggerberg campus holds 2–3 tonnes of untreated iron ore.&nbsp;(Image: ETH Zurich)</p>
			  </figcaption>
			</figure>
    
                    </div>
<div>
                
                
                <p>“The pilot plant can store around 10 megawatt hours of hydrogen over long periods. Depending on how you convert the hydrogen into electricity, that’ll give you somewhere between 4 and 6 megawatt hours of power,” explains Samuel Heiniger, a doctoral student in Stark’s research group. This corresponds to the electricity demand from three to five Swiss single-family homes in the winter months. At present, the system is still running on electricity from the grid and not on the solar power generated on the Hönggerberg campus.</p> 
<p>This is soon set to change: the researchers want to expand the system such that by 2026, the ETH Hönggerberg campus can meet one-fifth of its winter electricity requirements using its own solar power from the summer. This would require reactors with a volume of 2,000 cubic metres, which could store around 4 gigawatt hours (GWh) of green hydrogen. Once converted into electricity, the stored hydrogen would supply around 2 GWh of power. “This plant could replace a small reservoir in the Alps as a seasonal energy storage facility. To put that in perspective, it equates to around one-tenth of the capacity of the Nate de Drance pumped storage power plant,” Stark says. In addition, the discharging process would generate 2 GWh of heat, which the researchers want to integrate into the campus’s heating system.</p>
            </div>

<div>
                
                	<h2>Good scalability</h2>
                
                
                <p>But could this technology be harnessed to provide seasonal energy storage for Switzerland as a whole? The researchers have made some initial calculations: providing Switzerland with around 10 terawatt hours (TWh) of electricity from seasonal hydrogen storage systems every year in the future – which would admittedly be a lot – would require some 15–20 TWh of green hydrogen and roughly 10,000,000 cubic metres of iron ore. “That’s about 2 percent of what Australia, the largest producer of iron ore, mines every year,” Stark says. By way of comparison, in its <a>Energy Perspectives 2050+</a>, the Swiss Federal Office of Energy anticipates total electricity consumption of around 84 TWh in 2050.</p>
<p>If reactors were built that could store around 1 GWh of electricity each, they would have a volume of roughly 1,000 cubic metres. This calls for around 100 square metres of building land. Switzerland would have to build some 10,000 of these storage systems to obtain 10 TWh of electricity in winter, which corresponds to an area of around 1 square metre per inhabitant.</p>
            </div>
<div>
                
                	<h2>Coalition for Green Energy and Storage (CGES)</h2>
                
                
                <p>This project is part of the <a href="https://ethz.ch/en/news-and-events/eth-news/news/2023/06/eth-zurich-and-epfl-launch-a-green-energy-coalition.html">Coalition for Green Energy and Storage</a>, which ETH Zurich launched in 2023 together with EPFL, PSI and Empa and is driving forward together with industrial partners - including major Swiss energy suppliers and authorities. The coalition has set itself the goal of rapidly bringing innovative technologies for the production and storage of carbon-neutral gases and fuels and for CO2 capture to market maturity. As part of CGES, larger pilot plants (‘catapults’) are to be built to test these technologies and make important contributions to the climate-neutral transformation of the energy system and security of supply. The next step will be to establish an association that will network interested stakeholders, provide them with scientific support and guidance and facilitate the implementation of projects.</p>
            </div>
<div>
                
                	<h2>Reference</h2>
                
                
                <p>Literature: Heiniger, SP; Fan Z; Lustenberger UB, Stark WJ: Safe seasonal energy and hydrogen storage in a 1 : 10 single-household-sized pilot reactor based on the steam-iron process. Sustainable Energy &amp; Fuels 2024, 8 (1), 125-132.&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.1039/D3SE01228J"><span>external page</span>https://doi.org/10.1039/D3SE01228J</a></p>
            </div>

</div>
    <!-- Socialsharing (display only) -->
    
    
        
            
            
            
        
        
    


    <!-- Parsys 2 -->
    
    <!-- Taglist -->
    
        
            
        
    

    <!-- Comments -->
    
    	
	    
    

                
                
            </section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Is my vision that bad? No, it's just a bug in Apple's Calculator (534 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://martin.wojtczyk.de/2024/08/31/is-my-vision-that-bad-no-its-just-a-bug-in-apples-calculator/</link>
            <guid>41406550</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 04:29:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/2024/08/31/is-my-vision-that-bad-no-its-just-a-bug-in-apples-calculator/">https://martin.wojtczyk.de/2024/08/31/is-my-vision-that-bad-no-its-just-a-bug-in-apples-calculator/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41406550">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="post-838">
				<!-- .entry-header -->

				<div>
			
<p>While programming on my Mac and converting decimal numbers to hex and binary and using Apple’s Calculator for it – because it is built-in and works decent – I thought, I saw some wobbly lines of numbers.</p>



<figure><a href="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/1_calculator.png"><img decoding="async" width="510" height="587" data-attachment-id="839" data-permalink="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/2024/08/31/is-my-vision-that-bad-no-its-just-a-bug-in-apples-calculator/1_calculator/" data-orig-file="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/1_calculator.png" data-orig-size="510,587" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="1_calculator" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/1_calculator-261x300.png" data-large-file="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/1_calculator.png" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/1_calculator.png" alt="" srcset="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/1_calculator.png 510w, https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/1_calculator-261x300.png 261w" sizes="(max-width: 510px) 100vw, 510px"></a></figure>



<p>My first thought was: my eyes are getting tired. But it looked annoyingly wobbly and there went my focus on the task. I had to investigate, what was going on. I took a screenshot. Can you see it in the image above?</p>



<p>Let me highlight the annoying detail in the image below.</p>



<figure><a href="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/2_calculator.png"><img decoding="async" width="510" height="587" data-attachment-id="840" data-permalink="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/2024/08/31/is-my-vision-that-bad-no-its-just-a-bug-in-apples-calculator/2_calculator/" data-orig-file="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/2_calculator.png" data-orig-size="510,587" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="2_calculator" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/2_calculator-261x300.png" data-large-file="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/2_calculator.png" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/2_calculator.png" alt="" srcset="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/2_calculator.png 510w, https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/2_calculator-261x300.png 261w" sizes="(max-width: 510px) 100vw, 510px"></a></figure>



<p>Maybe you are reading this on a tiny screen, or your eyes are tired, but also… I had to see it for myself. Here is a zoomed in version below:</p>



<figure><a href="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/3_calculator.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="820" height="751" data-attachment-id="841" data-permalink="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/2024/08/31/is-my-vision-that-bad-no-its-just-a-bug-in-apples-calculator/3_calculator/" data-orig-file="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/3_calculator.png" data-orig-size="820,751" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="3_calculator" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/3_calculator-300x275.png" data-large-file="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/3_calculator.png" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/3_calculator.png" alt="" srcset="https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/3_calculator.png 820w, https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/3_calculator-300x275.png 300w, https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/3_calculator-768x703.png 768w, https://martin.wojtczyk.de/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/3_calculator-624x571.png 624w" sizes="(max-width: 820px) 100vw, 820px"></a></figure>



<p>Yes, indeed! Some digits in the binary display section are off by one pixel. Nice anti-aliased rendering by the way, but still, why are some digits misplaced by a pixel? </p>



<p>How did this happen? I should add, the calculator app has been open for many days. Maybe the UI coordinate system is using floats and a rounding error aggregated over many days… I’d love to find out, but I guess I won’t. Anyways, at least my vision is not that bad.</p>



<p>I would contact Apple, if there was a feedback option, but there isn’t, so I won’t. Instead I’ll just share the bug on the Internet. Enjoy!</p>
					</div><!-- .entry-content -->
		
		<!-- .entry-meta -->
	</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Rediscovering the Small Web (2020) (218 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/</link>
            <guid>41406453</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 03:56:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/">https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41406453">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
		<header>
		
		<p>Most websites today are built like commercial products by professionals and marketers, optimised to draw the largest audience, generate engagement and 'convert'. But there is also a smaller, less-visible web designed by regular people to simply to share their interests and hobbies with the world. A web that is unpolished, often quirky but often also fun, creative and interesting.</p>
		<p>- <a href="https://neustadt.fr/index.html">Parimal Satyal</a>, 25 May 2020</p>
		</header>
		        
		<p>Every website redesign begins with inspiration. </p>

		<p>For this one, there were two: Anders' <a href="https://anders.unix.se/">clean, readable website</a>, which inspired the homepage, and <a href="https://marijn.uk/index.html">Marijn's site</a>, which reminded me just how <em>fun</em> the web can be. The colours, graphics, <a href="https://marijn.uk/music/">creative navigation</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holocene_calendar">interesting ideas</a>... the simple fact of clicking through the pages of someone's personal website in 2020 made me nostalgic of the web of the late 90s and early 2000s that I grew up with.</p>

		<p>Some of you might have read my previous article, <a href="https://neustadt.fr/essays/against-a-user-hostile-web/">Against an Increasingly User Hostile Web</a>. In it, I argue that we are replacing an open web that connects and empowers with one that restricts and commoditises people. I talk about how the modern web of surveillance, bloat and walled gardens is at odds with the open web that I love. I was pleasantly surprised by how much the sentiment seemed to be shared by so many other people who emailed me, <a href="https://www.eduardomorais.com/stream/id/3519">wrote responses on their own blog</a> and <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=15611122">discussed it</a> on <a href="https://lobste.rs/s/5bi46y/against_increasingly_user_hostile_web">online forums</a>. Despite being two and a half years old, that article rather disappointingly still reflects the state of the web today. </p>

		<p>But stumbling upon Marijn’s site gave me hope. It led me down a rabbit hole of many other small websites made by people with all kinds of interests: movies, aviation, music, art, computers. It reminded me that the creative, personal, fun web I grew up with is not a thing of the past. It’s still here in 2020. You just have to know where to look.</p>

		<p>My aim is not to convince you that everything was better in the past; it wasn't. You had trojans, malware, endless pop-ups, terrible security practices, browser incompatibility, slow Java applets. No, technically, the modern web is more secure and more usable.</p> 

		<p>This essay is my attempt to show you what the small and independent web can look like, why it’s different from the the sites that dominate web traffic today, why it's worth exploring and how easy it is for anyone to be a part of it.</p>

		<p>This essay is somewhat long; you might find this table of contents handy:</p>


		<ol>
			<li><a href="#retro-redesign">Retro Redesign</a></li>
			<li><a href="#first-webpages">The First Webpages</a></li>
			<li><a href="#masters-navigators">Masters and Navigators</a></li>
			<li><a href="#modern-gatekeepers">Modern Gatekeepers</a></li>
			<li><a href="#commercial-web-of-marketing">The Commercial Web (of Marketing)</a></li>
			<li><a href="#product-oriented-website">The Product-Oriented Website</a></li>
			<li><a href="#web-as-creative-space">The Web as a Creative Space</a></li>
			<li><a href="#highlights-from-the-past">Highlights: From the Past</a></li>
			<li><a href="#highlights-from-the-present">Highlights: From the Present</a></li>
			<li><a href="#your-own-corner">Your Own Corner of the Web</a></li>
		</ol>

		<h2 id="retro-redesign">Retro Redesign</h2>

		<p>On my <a href="https://neustadt.fr/">homepage</a>, I mention that this website is “a tribute to the creative web of the 90s”. This is not simply because this website has animated gifs and a <a href="https://users2.smartgb.com/g/g.php?a=s&amp;i=g26-37520-60">guestbook</a>. The <em>way</em> I built it is also inspired by how I built my earliest websites: everything is written in <strong>plain HTML</strong>.</p>

		<p>No content management systems, no generators, no templates, no themes, no plugins. Just plain markup and styling, the most basic of the basic building blocks of the web. </p>

		<p>I didn’t originally plan to do it like this. I previously <a href="https://neustadt.fr/essays/crafting-a-simple-blog-with-metalsmith">used a static site generator</a> to output plain HTML and was simply working on a new design template for that. But my three-year-old node.js setup was now spewing error messages, telling me some dependencies had to be updated and that a plugin was no longer compatible. Because I'm lazy and didn't want to fix any of that, I wondered if I couldn’t just do it all manually instead and save myself the trouble. </p>

		<p>So I did. I decided to hand-code everything in plain HTML and CSS, manually link all the pages and even hand-write the RSS feed. And to be honest, I haven’t had this much fun making a website since when I first started playing around with <a href="https://www.webdesignmuseum.org/old-software/html-editors/microsoft-frontpage-97">Microsoft Frontpage</a> and <a href="https://www.webdesignmuseum.org/old-software/graphic-software/adobe-photoshop-4-0">Adobe Photoshop 4.0</a> in the late 90s and early 2000s.</p>

		<p>This approach wouldn't work for a bigger website. But for a small one like mine with about 10 total pages, it has many obvious benefits: next to no dependencies, easy to maintain, reasonably future proof, easily portable and most important of all, terribly fun to work on. I stayed up till six in the morning for two straight days working on the redesign, not because I couldn’t sleep but because I didn’t want to stop. Admittedly, about 30% of that time was spent scouring <a href="https://gifcities.org/">GifCities.org</a> and the <a href="https://archive.org/web/">Internet Archive</a> for animated GIFs and backgrounds. (You might notice that each page of the website has a different background, including some with <a href="https://neustadt.fr/essays/china-one-nation-how-many-languages/">original art</a> by my friend).</p>

		<p>Redesigning my website this way inspired me to scour archives of old websites for interesting relics from the early web. This in turned led me to the fun, creative websites that are actively maintained even today. </p>

		<p>To understand what these small websites represent and why I think they are important, we need to start in the past.</p>

		<h2 id="first-webpages">The First Webpages</h2>

		<p>The web was still in its infancy in the early 90s. You probably know the story.</p>

		<p>It had only just been <a href="https://home.cern/science/computing/birth-web/short-history-web">invented by Sir Tim Berners-Lee</a> in 1991 and released into the <a href="https://home.cern/science/computing/birth-web/licensing-web">public domain</a> in 1993, making it available for free to anyone in the world to use and build on. In its very early days, it was really only accessible to the more technical crowd, much like <em>Gopher</em>, <em>FTP</em>, <em>Usenet</em> and other internet protocols at the time. It wasn't until the first easy-to-use graphical browser <a href="http://www.ncsa.illinois.edu/enabling/mosaic">Mosaic</a> was released for free in 1993 that regular computer users would discover the web for the first time. Others like myself discovered it later still when the Mosaic-spinoff <a href="http://sillydog.org/netscape/">Netscape Navigator</a> (the foundation of today's <a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-GB/firefox/new/">Firefox</a>) and Internet Explorer became commonplace. </p>

		<p>It was all terribly exciting. Unlike traditional media, you could now speak back and participate. It was the first interplanetary communication system where anyone, anywhere in the world, could make a page and share their thoughts and ideas with the world. Netscape would later even include <a href="https://www.ccsf.edu/Pub/Fac/composer.html">an editor</a> that let users make webpages visually, the same as using a word-processor ("WYSIWYG", as it was called back then: <em>what you see is what you get</em>). The goal was to enable anyone, even those without the technical skills, to put a page up.</p>

		<p>But if you wanted your web page to be "on the web", where would you put it? </p>

		<p>You needed a web host of some sort to store the pages and share a public address so other people could visit. It would ideally also be free so you could try things for fun without having to think about it too much. That's where <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/19980704165228/http://www20.geocities.com/join/freehp.html">Geocities</a> came in, along with other free web hosts like <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20000815052634/http://www.tripod.lycos.com/">Tripod</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20000229235048/http://www.fortunecity.com/build/index.html">Fortunecity</a> and <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20000815053429/http://www.freeservers.com/">Freeservers</a>. They were perhaps the biggest catalysts to democratising the web. </p>

		<figure>
			<img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/Geocities-1998.jpg" alt="Geocities introduction page from February 1998">
			<figcaption>Geocities introduction page from February 1998, accessed via <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/19980213154923/http://www13.geocities.com:80/main/info/">Internet Archive</a></figcaption> 
		</figure>

		<p>It was so simple, anyone who wanted to could create a free account and build a website to share their hobbies and ideas. And share they did! People made websites about virtually everything: music, philosophy, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20011004132631/http://www.geocities.com/~intransit1/home/home_frm.html">art projects</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20010424064639/http://www.geocities.com/spunk1111/">ASCII art</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20000815075236/http://www.pezcentral.com/pezmenu.html">candy</a>, and <a href="https://geocities.restorativland.org/Athens/Olympus/1406/main.html">about their lives</a>. </p>

		<p>A key detail was that most people who made these websites were neither professionals nor companies; they were simply people who wanted to share their interests. Like I did back in 2001 with my <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20020103123131/http://www.geocities.com:80/gammarayfan">unofficial fansite for German metal band Gamma Ray</a>: </p>

		<figure>
			<img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/gammarayfansite-2001.jpg" alt="My Geocities-hosted Gamma Ray fansite from January 2001">
			<figcaption>My Geocities-hosted Gamma Ray fansite from January 2001, accessed via <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20020103123131/http://www.geocities.com:80/gammarayfan/">Internet Archive</a></figcaption> 
		</figure>

		<p>But how would someone go about finding these pages? We didn't have Google in the early days. Other search engines like <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/19980214192548/http://www.lycos.com/">Lycos</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/19970630113649/http://www06.excite.com/">Excite</a> and <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/19980206192654/http://www.northernlight.com/">Northern Lights</a> did exist but were nowhere near as efficient as modern search engines. Finding something you were interested in was not as simple as typing a few words and getting to that information in one click.</p>

		<p>No, the web was much more of an adventure. It was a <em>place</em> that you wandered to discover new areas, like exploring the vast open seas. A new virtual space that lead to all kinds of strange, interesting, exciting places. This is what the web was like, at least, in our collective imagination.</p>


		<h2 id="masters-navigators">Masters and Navigators</h2>

		<p>The web was a different kind of place in those early years, and we had different words to talk about it. In an article titled <a href="https://rhizome.org/editorial/2015/nov/30/oldweb-today/">Cyberspace, the old-fashioned way</a>, authors at the Rhizome project make a very important point:</p>

		<blockquote>Today's web browsers want to be invisible, merging with the visual environment of the desktop in an effort to convince users to treat "the cloud" as just an extension of their hard drive. <strong>In the 1990s, browser design took nearly the opposite approach, using iconography associated with travel to convey the feeling of going on a journey.</strong> Netscape Navigator, which used a ship's helm as its logo, made a very direct link with the nautical origins of the prefix cyber-, while Internet Explorer’s logo promised to take the user around the whole globe. </blockquote>

		<figure>
			<img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/navigator-explorer.jpg" alt="Old logos of Netscape Navigator and Internet Explorer">
			<figcaption>Old logos of Netscape Navigator and Internet Explorer</figcaption> 
		</figure>

		<p>Navigation. Exploration. Browsing. Surfing.  The web was akin to a virtual manifestation of physical space. We even had a word for it: <em>webspace</em>. In Geocities, this was expressed with the notion of <em><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/19980704165140/http://www20.geocities.com/neighborhoods/">neighborhoods</a></em>, creatively-named categories like <em>Area51</em> for sci-fi, <em>Heartland</em> for families and pets, <em>RainForest</em> for the environment, <em>Vienna</em> for classical music, <em>CapeCanaveral</em> for science and mathematics.</p>

		<figure>
			<img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/geocities-neighbourhoods-1998.png" alt="A partial list of neighborhoods avialable on Geocities in 1998">
			<figcaption>Neighborhoods avialable on Geocities in 1998, accessed via <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/19980703151237/http://www11.geocities.com/neighborhoods/">Internet Archive</a></figcaption> 
		</figure>

		<p>Another word that was very common back in the Geocities days that has since died out is the word "webmaster" (mostly gender-neutral, although sometimes declined to the feminine "webmistress"). The idea was that you created a <em>space</em> on the web, of which you were the <em>master</em>. You welcomed visitors (sometimes with a splash screen), guided them around by explaining what the site was about and the different spaces available to them (usually on the home page) and reminded them to leave a word on the guestbook on their way out.</p>

		<p>But the semantics of the web of yore made sense in the context of how you <em>practically</em> interacted with it. You very rarely just came in for one specific thing and then immediately left like you might today; you usually <em>entered</em> a website and looked around. You browsed.</p>

		<p>Which takes us back to the original question of how other <em>internautes</em> found your website in the first place. You were lucky if your small site showed up in pre-Google search engines, but even if it did, it would mean that somebody was actively looking for it. But not everybody who visited your website <em>was</em> looking for anything specific. They might simply have wanted to find other websites about a topic they were interested it.</p>

		<p>One way of doing so was by browsing directories, like the Geocities neighbourhoods: lists of websites often arranged by categories and sub-categories. In fact, most search engines were also directories, or <em>portals</em> as some were called back then.
		</p>

		<figure>
			<img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/excite-channels.jpg" alt="In 1997, Excite was both a search engine and a directory, organised into channels.">
			<figcaption>In 1997, Excite was both a search engine and a directory, organised into channels, accessed via <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/19970601223506/http://www10.excite.com/">Internet Archive</a></figcaption> 
		</figure>

		<p>One of the biggest ones was the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20010206123038/http://www.dmoz.org/about.html">DMOZ open-directory project</a>, based on the original Mozilla directories, whose goal it was to <em>"produce the most comprehensive directory of the web, by relying on a vast army of volunteer editors"</em>. You can still browse <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20010224172816/http://www.dmoz.org/">a 2001 archive of the old directory</a> to get a sense of how it worked.</p>
		
		<figure>
			<img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/dmoz-2000.jpg" alt="About DMOZ page from 2001">
			<figcaption>About DMOZ page from 2000, accessed via <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20000408141943/http://dmoz.org/about.html">Internet Archive</a></figcaption> 
		</figure>

		<p>The other way to discover new websites relied on a key feature of the web: hyperlinks. You would go to one website and find your way to many others, much like if you go to my "<a href="https://neustadt.fr/retro-stuff">Retro Stuff</a>" page and follow one of the links to something interesting elsewhere on the web. This idea of linking to things <em>elsewhere</em> was particularly common; most websites had a "links" page with their own personal collection of interesting webpages.</p>

		<p>This cross-linking was the main way I personally discovered my favourite websites, which I would then add to my bookmarks to be able to find them again later. In fact, the practice of cross-linking had an intersting cultural element: <em>webrings</em>. </p>

		<figure>
			<img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/example-webring.jpg" alt="An example of a webring, about European History">
			<figcaption>An example of a webring (about European History) from <a href="http://brisray.com/web/webrings.htm">Ray's Miscellany</a></figcaption> 
		</figure>

		<p><a href="http://brisray.com/web/webrings.htm">Webrings</a> were "circular" collections of websites, often around a topic or a theme. The idea was that you could go from one website to another by clicking on the "next" or "previous" buttons usually placed on the bottom of each member's homepage. These have also largely disappeared.</p>

		<h2 id="modern-gatekeepers">Modern Gatekeepers</h2>

		<p>Today, most of the time spent on the web is either <em>on</em> a small number of very dominant platforms like Facebook and LinkedIn, or mediated <em>through</em> them. </p>

		<p>There is so much "content" that is constantly pushed at you as a user that very few of us actually venture out to browse and explore anymore. We simply don't need to. But these platforms thrive on "user engagement"—likes, comments, clicks and shares—and their algorithms are more likely to give visibility to content that generates this behavior. Instead of browsing, the web is for many an endless and often overwhelming stream of content and commentary picked out by algorithms based on what they think you already like and will <em>engage</em> with. It's the opposite of exploration. </p>

		<p>When you're not <em>receiving</em> information passively and instead actually actively looking for something, you most likely have the same singular point of entry as about <a href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/216573/worldwide-market-share-of-search-engines/">87% of all web users</a>: Google.</p>

		<p>Google has become the de facto gatekeeper of the web, an arbiter of what is useful and what should get visibility. Except, most websites that appear on the first page, the links that you are most likely to click on—<a href="https://backlinko.com/google-ctr-stats">less than 1% of searchers click on something in the second page</a>—are designed to be there by optimising for Google's algorithms. One consequence of this  is that most of the websites that people get to "organically" are created by professionals and marketers who "position" themselves on those keywords. This means that the smaller, amateur web gets hidden in the shadows of web professionals who design around specific keywords and audiences.</p>
		
		<figure>
			<img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/google-bartending-recipes.jpg" alt="Google's results for 'bartending recipes' won't take you to the small web">
			<figcaption>Google's results for "bartending recipes" won't take you to the small web</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>Not only is Google largely a monopoly in search— other search engines like Bing, DuckDuckGo and Qwant are <a href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/216573/worldwide-market-share-of-search-engines/">still far behind in adoption</a>—it is also the biggest ad selling platform. Last year, it represented "31,1% of worldwide ad spending, or $103,73 billion" (<a href="https://www.emarketer.com/content/global-digital-ad-spending-2019">source</a>). The power that comes from being in such a position, along with being present in almost all major websites (through their widely-used analytics platform, despite the <a href="https://www.emerald.com/insight/content/doi/10.1108/OIR-02-2018-0056/full/pdf?title=protecting-privacy-on-the-web-a-study-of-https-and-google-analytics-implementation-in-academic-library-websites">numerous privacy concerns</a>) means it can actively push its own vision of the web.</p>

		<p>And this web is quite different from the kind of "small web" crafted by webmasters of the 90s and early 2000s. Google's web has a <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20190214003848/https://marketingplatform.google.com/about/analytics/">different set of values and vocabulary</a> that come with it: personalisation, insights, engagement, conversion, performance, optimisation. </p>


		<h2 id="commercial-web-of-marketing">The Commercial Web (of Marketing)</h2>

		<p>There has always been a place for commerce and marketing on the web.</p>

		<p><a href="https://www.webdesignmuseum.org/web-design-history/amazon-com-1995">Amazon</a> was already selling books online back in 1995, <a href="https://www.webdesignmuseum.org/web-design-history/ebay-1997">eBay</a> was launched in 1997 and <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/19970605120422/http://www.dell.com/">Dell</a> sold over a million dollars worth of equipment by the end of the same year. By the 2000s, despite the <a href="https://ideas.ted.com/an-eye-opening-look-at-the-dot-com-bubble-of-2000-and-how-it-shapes-our-lives-today/">dot com bust</a>, online commerce was growing. This development was natural; the web enabled sellers to reach more distant clients without having to rely on phone orders, fax or the postal system. The commercial web co-existed and grew with the personal, amateur one. The open nature of the web meant that all kinds of websites could thrive.</p>
	
		<p>But today's web is <em>mostly</em> commercial. The smaller web of individuals has neither the resources nor the will to compete for visibility and audience the way the commercial web does.</p>

		<p>Companies and marketers understood that the web presented new opportunities to sell more and <em>target</em> users based on their online activity. They started pouring money into digital ad strategies, analysing how people used the web, what they talk about, what they search for and what they click on. Marketing companies convinced brands that you had to be online and produce content to be more relevant because that's where their customers already were. They invented words like "native advertising" and "sponsored content" (content made to look like a regular articles but are really paid advertising). Companies started pouring money into their digital strategies to understand and alter influence the behavior of internet users to their advantage.</p>
		
		<figure>
			<a href="https://www.quantcast.com/products/measure-audience-insights/"><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/quantcast.jpg" alt="Companies like Quantcast offer detailed behavioral/psychographic data on us web users, including our actions across different websites, to marketers to track and influence us"></a>
			<figcaption>Companies like <a href="https://www.quantcast.com/products/measure-audience-insights/">Quantcast</a> offer detailed behavioral/<em>psychographic</em> data on us web users, including our actions across different websites, to marketers to track and influence us.</figcaption>
		</figure>

		<p>With its content strategy, analytics (the surveillance infrastructure that I <a href="https://neustadt.fr/essays/against-a-user-hostile-web">spoke about in my previous article</a>) and search engine optimisation, the commercial web brought a completely different set of priorities: to <em>engage</em> their "audience", <em>convert</em> them and <em>retain</em> them for as long as possible.</p>

		<p>For them, the web was just another marketing channel.</p>

		<p>Compared to the small web, this commercial web is tactical and predatory. It can dynamically generate hundreds of pages around common search queries. It can follow web users across different websites, analyse their interactions, and use that information to target them more precisely. It also has serious resources. Just last year, companies spent <a href="https://www.emarketer.com/content/global-digital-ad-spending-2019">over 300 billion euros</a> in online digital advertising, most of this money going to the same platforms and gatekeepers—Google and Facebook—that sell their ability to better target you based on the information you give them. </p>

		<p><strong>What this means is that web users end up interacting and spending most of their time on the visible, predatory commercial web, while the very long tail of smaller, amateur websites remains hidden in the noise.</strong></p>

		<h2 id="product-oriented-website">The Product-oriented Website</h2>

		<p>The design of the modern commercial web is also "sanitised": it is polished, follows conventions and is optimised for efficiency. This is one of the reasons so many websites you go to today look and feel the same. The codes of the commercial web have become so dominant that we have forgotten that the small web still exists and has a completely different priorities.</p>

		<p>Modern web design principles are very rarely directed at regular people looking to make a website on something they are interested in. Instead, the focus is on creating websites that perform well:</p>

		<p><em>Don't use too many colours.  Write short, catchy headlines. Don't let content be too long. Optimise for SEO. Produce video content, attention span is decreasing. Have a an obvious call to action. Push your newsletter. Keep important information above the fold. Don't make users think. Follow conventions.</em></p>
		
		<figure>
			<img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/neil-patel-design.jpg" alt="An SEO person's idea of good design for better conversions">
			<figcaption>An SEO person's idea of <em><a href="https://neilpatel.com/blog/web-design-conversions/">Universal Web Design Principles That Improve Usability And Conversion</a></em></figcaption> 
		</figure>

		<p>Modern websites are designed to direct user behavior towards certain goals: a purchase, a click, a share or a sign-up. The words, the colours, the message are tailored to these goals, much like packaging on products in the super market. </p>

		<p>A 2008 article called by Smashing Magazine called <a href="https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2008/01/10-principles-of-effective-web-design/">10 Principles Of Good Website Design</a> was the top result when I searched for "<a href="https://startpage.com/do/metasearch.pl?query=good%20web%20design">good web design</a>" whilst writing this essay. There are many others, some more recent, but they all pretty much say the same thing. The author of this one even clearly begins by stating that <em>"[...] user-centric design has established as a standard approach for successful and profit-oriented web design</em>".</p>

		<p>But the web is not always "profit-oriented" and it certainly does not need to be "user-centric" (and I say this as a UX consultant). If it were, there would be very little creativity and self-expression left. The rich diversity of the web would be reduced to the online equivalent of a massive, orderly, clinical shopping mall meant to drive sales. No, the web can just as well be "author-centered", hobby-centered or even be <a href="https://blog.geocities.institute/archives/6551">dog-centered</a>!</p>

		<p>It is worth remembering a website does not have to be a product; it can also be art. <strong>The web is also a creative and cultural space that need not confine itself to the conventions defined by commercial product design and marketing</strong>.</p>

		<h2 id="web-as-creative-space">The Web as a Creative Space</h2>

		<p>With the dominance of the commercial web and the normalisation of its code and techniques, it is easy for most people to think that the web is a complex machine. Most websites today are built with sophisticated content management systems, SEO and social media strategies, multiple plugins, detailed analytics and audience tracking, optimized for different breakpoints and served via a global CDN.</p> 

		<p>But the web is really a lot simpler than that. You really only need two things: a web host and HTML (and basic CSS for formatting). And you don't need to make it "user-centered"; much like the early webmasters on Geocities carving out their own corner of the web, you can express yourself any way you want. It’s the difference between product and art.</p>

		<p><strong>A painter wouldn’t add more red to her painting or change the composition because market data showed that people liked it better. It’s her creative vision; some people might like it, others might not. But it is her creation, with her own rules. The question of "performance" is simply irrelevant. It's the same thing with the small web.</strong></p>

		<p>If the commercial web is "industrial", you could say that the small web is "artisanal". One is not better than the other. They serve different needs and both can co-exist in an open web. It would nevertheless be a shame if we only spent time on the commercial web and never got the opportunity to experience the creativity, passion and quirkiness of the small web.</p>

		<p>To show you what the it can look like and how different it can be from modern websites, I have collected a few examples that I think illustrate the richness of the small web.</p>

		<h2 id="highlights-from-the-past">Highlights: From the Past</h2>

		<p>We will first look at small websites from the past and then move on to ones that are up and running today. </p>

		<p>To be able to dig up these websites and give you access to them, I am grateful to the wonderful and important archival work done by: </p>

		<ul>
			<li><a href="https://archive.org/web/">Internet Archive</a>, which, thanks to the 439 billion web pages saved since the mid 90s, lets you travel back in time and see how a website looked in the past.</li>
			<li><a href="https://restorativland.org/">Restorativland</a>, a "restored visual gallery of the archived Geocities sites, sorted by neighborhood".</li>
		</ul>
		
		<p>On to the examples.</p>
		
		
				<h3>A Laurel &amp; Hardy Fansite</h3>
				<p>A fan-made site from 1998 about comedy duo Stan Laurel and Oliver Norville Hardy. The author has this to say about the website:</p>
				<blockquote>
					On this website you will find: over one hundred pictures, a small collection of sound files, the complete movie list - from the silent eara to the talkies. Ever wondered what they were singing? Go to the lyrics page and read the text. Laurel &amp; Hardy were the stars but they couldn't have done it without the help of others. You can see who they were on the Supporting Cast page.
				</blockquote>
				<p>If you go to the <a href="https://geocities.restorativland.org/Hollywood/Studio/5352/siteinfo.html">siteinfo</a> page, you’ll notice that the “why” of the website is simply “why not!!”. Why not indeed!
		</p>
				<figure>
					<a href="https://geocities.restorativland.org/Hollywood/Studio/5352/index.html"><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/laurel-hardy-fansite.jpg" alt="A screenshot of the home page of A Laurel and Hardy Fansite"></a>
					<figcaption>A screenshot of the home page of <em>A Laurel and Hardy Fansite</em></figcaption> 
				</figure>
				<p><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/link.png" alt="" height="25">  <a href="https://geocities.restorativland.org/Hollywood/Studio/5352/index.html">Visit A Laurel &amp; Hardy Fansite</a> on Restorativland</p>
				

		<h3>Fractal Explorer</h3>
		<p>A complete website about fractals by Fabio Cesari, (then) a 24 year old student of computer engineering at the University of Bologna, Italy. Includes very clear explanations, image galleries and step-by-step guided tours:</p>
		<blockquote>
			Many people have probably been fascinated by the infinite complexity and beauty of fractals. I wrote this brief tutorial to explain, in simple terms, how the Mandelbrot set and Julia sets are generated. This document provides an informal introduction to these subjects, and is only intended to be a starting point to learn more about fractals and fractal geometry.
		</blockquote>
		<figure>
			<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20020223163039fw_/http://www.geocities.com/fabioc/"><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/fractal-explorer.jpg" alt="A screenshot of the homepage of On to Mars!"></a>
			<figcaption>A screenshot of the guided tour of a Mandelbrot set in <em>Fractal Explorer</em></figcaption> 
		</figure>
		<p><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/link.png" alt="" height="25"> <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20020223163039fw_/http://www.geocities.com/fabioc/">Visit Fractal Explorer</a> on Internet Archive</p>


		<h3>The National Coca-Cola Bottle Clearing House</h3>
		<p>This website is almost certainly a definitive list of every single commemorative Coca-Cola bottle since the 70s. There are some surprising entries. For example, did you know there was an 8oz (~240ml) <em>Dominos Pizza International Expo 1991</em> edition, or that such an expo existed at all? Or a 10oz (~300ml) <em>English Royal Wedding</em> one in 1982?</p>
		<figure>
			<a href="https://geocities.restorativland.org/Heartland/2983/"><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/coca-cola-clearinghouse.jpg" alt="A screenshot of the homepage of The National Coca Cola Bottle Clearing House"></a>
			<figcaption>A screenshot of the homepage of <em>The National Coca Cola Bottle Clearing House</em></figcaption> 
		</figure>
		<p><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/link.png" alt="" height="25"> <a href="https://geocities.restorativland.org/Heartland/2983/">Visit The National Coca-Cola Bottle Clearing House</a> on Restorativland</p>


		<h3>NetHistory</h3>		
		<p>Before the Internet existed, BITNET was “<em>an early world leader in network communications for the research and education communities, and helped lay the groundwork for the subsequent introduction of the internet, especially outside the US</em>". (<a href="https://www.livinginternet.com/u/ui_bitnet.htm">LivingInternet.com</a>).</p> 	
		<p>This website is an “informal history of BITNET and the Internet”:</p>	
		<blockquote>
			If you're looking for a dry, formal history of the Internet, look elsewhere. The purpose of NetHistory is to give you a feeling for what it was like in the pioneering days of BITNET and the Internet. Hopefully, you will gain some perspective and come to understand the early Internet experience (although one could argue that the experience in question is a lot like sitting in front of a mainframe terminal in the middle of the night with a Twinkie-and-Jolt buzz). At worst, you should find it entertaining. 
		</blockquote>		
		<p>NetHistory has extensive archives of early network publications (VM/COM, NetMonth, FSFNet, DargonZine, Nutworks, The Gilding Byte among others) and “personal insights of the people who were there while BITNET and Internet history was being made”.</p>
		<figure>
			<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20010516205238/http://nethistory.dumbentia.com/"><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/nethistory.jpg" alt="A screenshot of NetHistory's Archive page"></a>
			<figcaption>A screenshot of <em>NetHistory</em>'s Archive page</figcaption> 
		</figure>
		
		<p><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/link.png" alt="" height="25"> <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20010516205238/http://nethistory.dumbentia.com/">Visit NetHistory</a> on Internet Archive</p>
		
		
		<h3>joan stark's ASCII Art Gallery </h3>
		<p>Think text art is dull? This artist has something to tell you:</p>
		<blockquote>
			You might not think so after visiting this website. There is much more to these low bandwidth graphics than smileys and emoticons. ASCII Art has progressed beyond being a simple computer graphics technique and has become a popular art form. You'll be amazed at what can be created by only using ASCII (American Standard Code of Information Interchange) characters. Some of the text graphics at this site are html-colorized, some are JavaScript-animated, others are simply text. All are unique, created by hand, and certainly not the same ol' boring text art that you might be expecting!
		</blockquote>
		<figure>
			<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20010420182629/http://www.geocities.com/spunk1111/indexjava.htm"><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/joanstark-ascii.jpg" alt="A screenshot of joan stark's ASCII Art Gallery"></a>
			<figcaption>A screenshot of <em>joan stark's ASCII Art Gallery</em></figcaption> 
		</figure>
		<p><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/link.png" alt="" height="25"> <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20010420182629/http://www.geocities.com/spunk1111/indexjava.htm">Visit joan stark's ASCII Art Gallery</a>on Internet Archive</p>
		
		
	
		<h2 id="highlights-from-the-present">Highlights: From the Present</h2>

		<p>As excited as I was to find these wonderful relics, I was even more excited to learn that the small web exists today just as it did back when I was a kid. It's just less visible. Among the projects contributing to keeping the small web alive, three are particularly exciting to me:  </p>

		<ul>
			<li><a href="https://wiby.me/">Wiby.me</a> is a search engine for old-school, interesting and informative webpages, with a useful "<a href="https://wiby.me/surprise/">surprise me</a>" button that takes you to a random result. </li>
			<li><a href="https://neocities.org/">Neocities.org</a> is a modern web host that lets anyone create a basic website for free and be a part of a community where you can follow other webmasters. </li>
			<li><a href="https://curlie.org/">Curlie</a> is "<em>the largest human-edited directory of the Web. It is constructed and maintained by a passionate, global community of volunteer editors</em>".</li>
		</ul>

		<h3>Ottaviana's Kitchen</h3>
		<p>This website from 1996 is still up today and features a family's Italian recipes passed down from generation to generation:</p>
		<blockquote>My Grandparents were immigrants from Italy. They came to Ellis Island, in search of the great American dream. This was where my mother was born in Newark, NJ. The recipes were passed to her from her mother, and then passed to me from mine. Since I have no	children of my own, what better way to pass on these recipes but	on my web page so everyone can enjoy them, and maybe start their	own tradition with them. So for now, Buon Appetito.</blockquote>
		<p>You can read the <a href="http://ottavianaskitchen.com/menu.htm">entire menu</a> and find authentic recipes to <a href="http://ottavianaskitchen.com/sauces.htm">sauces</a>, <a href="http://ottavianaskitchen.com/soups.htm">soups</a>, <a href="http://ottavianaskitchen.com/risotto.htm">risotti</a>, <a href="http://ottavianaskitchen.com/cookies.htm">cookies and dessert</a>, and much much more.</p>	
		<figure>
			<a href="http://ottavianaskitchen.com/sauces.htm"><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/ottavianas-kitchen.jpg" alt="A screenshot of a recipe page from Ottaviana's Kitchen"></a>
			<figcaption>A screenshot of a recipe page from <em>Ottaviana's Kitchen</em></figcaption> 
		</figure>	
		<p><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/link.png" alt="" height="25"> <a href="http://ottavianaskitchen.com/intro.htm">Visit Ottaviana's Kitchen</a></p>

		<h3>Europäische Schmetterlinge</h3>
		<p>This is a German website about European butterflies created in 1998 and maintained until 2005 by Mario Maier. But it isn't just <em>any</em> old website about butterflies; this one is a near-exhaustive collection of almost all butterflies in Europe organised by genus/species, each with a description, an indication of its "flight time" and the corresponding caterpillar's plants of choice, along with photos (most taken by the author himself).</p>
		<figure>
			<a href="http://www.butterflies.de/"><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/europaeische-schmetterlinge.jpg" alt="A screenshot of the page on Melitae didyma butterflies on Europäische Schmetterlinge"></a>
			<figcaption>A screenshot of the page on <em>Melitae didyma</em> butterflies on <em>Europäische Schmetterlinge</em></figcaption> 
		</figure>
		<p>Some of the pages like <a href="http://www.butterflies.de/Deutsch/ainsae.htm">this one on <em>Agrodiaetus ainsae</em></a> seem to have more information than currently <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyommatus_fulgens">available on Wikipedia</a>! I originally found the <a href="https://geocities.restorativland.org/Paris/Cafe/1508/">Geocities version</a> on Restorativland and then found this version that is currently up.</p>
		<p><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/link.png" alt="" height="25"> <a href="http://www.butterflies.de/">Visit Europäische Schmetterlinge</a></p>
		<p>It looks like the same author had a larger website for <em>all</em> butterflies on Earth that was up until 2018. You can visit <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180421072253/http://www.butterflycorner.net/Schmetterlinge-aus-aller-Welt.1.0.html">an archived copy of Butterfly Corner</a>.</p>
		
		
		<h3>Marseillaise.org</h3>		
		<p>Everything you wanted to know about the French national anthem <em>La Marseillaise</em>, from Ian Patterson’s website that’s been up “in one form or another since 1996”.</p>		
		<blockquote>
			Welcome. No doubt you've come here to see what all the fuss is about on the 14th of July. I think you'll find all you want to know here. La Marseillaise is the national anthem of France, believed by many to be the most stirring of all anthems. Here you will find a transcription of its score, complete sound clips in various formats and a translation into English. 
		</blockquote>
		<figure>
			<a href="http://www.marseillaise.org/english/"><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/marseillaise-org.jpg" alt="A screenshot of Marsaillaise.org"></a>
			<figcaption>A screenshot of <em>Marsaillaise.org</em></figcaption> 
		</figure>		
		<p><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/link.png" alt="" height="25"> <a href="http://www.marseillaise.org/english/">Visit Marseillaise.org</a></p>

		<h3>The Webtender</h3>		
		<p>Interested in mixing your own drinks? The Webtender, which has been online since 1995, features over 6000 recipes, a handbook with information on bar glassware, tools, measurements and ingredients, a forum, a wiki and even lets you search for recipes based on what you have in your bar!</p>		
		<figure>
			<a href="https://www.webtender.com/info/"><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/webtender.jpg" alt="A screenshot of the home page of Webtender"></a>
			<figcaption>A screenshot of the home page of Webtender</figcaption> 
		</figure>	
		<blockquote>
			<p>I got the idea to this database when I saw a program called Bartender for the Amiga. I wanted to create a useful web-service, and decided to make something similar for the World Wide Web. Remember that this was just at the same time as the Web (I prefer to call it that) became popular with not only students and people connected to the Internet at work, but also to people at home.</p>
			<p>So, during spring 1995 I started to collect drink recipes from various Internet sources, including the mentioned program. One of the main sources was The (Un)Official Internet Bartender's Guide and postings to the newsgroup <code>rec.food.drink</code>.</p>
			<p>Then I decided to let my visitors help building the database. A lot of people make their own drinks, or have their own favourite, so why not let them add it to the database? I created a simple web form that visitors could use to add their drinks. It bacame a success!</p>
		<p>Today, about 1500 of the drinks have been added by me, and the rest have been contributed by visitors.</p>
		</blockquote>
		<p><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/link.png" alt="" height="25"> <a href="https://www.webtender.com/info/">Visit The Webtender</a></p>
		
		<h3>Distant Skies - A Crystalis Fansite</h3>		
		<p>A fan-made website about an action-RPG game called Crystalis:</p>		
		<blockquote>
			'Crystalis' is an Action-RPG for the Nintendo Entertainment System. It was released in Japan in April of 1990 and in the United States the following July. It was praised by critics at the time for its graphics and gameplay and it inspired a devout, if somewhat small, fan following. In Japan the game was called ゴッド・スレイヤー はるか天空のソナタ or God Slayer: Sonata of the Distant Sky. 
		</blockquote>
		<p>Built in the visual style of the game itself, the site provides detailed information about the story, characters, game world, spells and items in the game. Even though I don’t know the game, it’s fun to browse around.</p>
		<figure>
			<a href="https://distantskies.neocities.org/"><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/distant-skies.jpg" alt="A screenshot of the home page of Distant Skies"></a>
			<figcaption>A screenshot of the home page of <em>Distant Skies</em></figcaption> 
		</figure>		
		<p><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/link.png" alt="" height="25"> <a href="https://distantskies.neocities.org/">Visit Distant Skies - A Crystalis Fansite</a></p>
		
		
		<h2 id="your-own-corner">Your Own Corner of the Web</h2>
		<p>So the small web still exists, and is still giving us all kinds of websites to browse through and discover. 
		</p>
		<p>As fun as it is to explore what's out there, the best part is really to join in and make your own website. Not on closed platforms or on social media mediated by ad companies, but simply in your own little corner of the web. It's the best way to see how simple and open the web really is.</p>
		<p>You could easily put up those drawings you've been making, share your thoughts and ideas, or reviews of your favourite whiskies. Make a website to share your writing tips or your best recipes. Or a list of your favourite addresses in your city for travelers who might be visiting.</p>
		<p>All you would need is to learn basic markup (HTML) and styling (CSS), set up a site on a free host like <a href="https://neocities.org/">Neocities.org</a> and start playing. As you can imagine, Neocities is a Geocities-like free web host (minus the ads) whose mission it is to "<em>make the web fun again by giving you back control of how you express yourself online</em>". Discovering and joining Neocities was one of the reasons I got so excited about the small web. You can spend hours and hours <a href="https://neocities.org/browse?sort_by=last_updated">browsing through</a> the many sites hosted there, or just get a free account to play with.</p>		
		<figure>
			<a href="https://neocities.org/"><img src="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/neocities-home.jpg" alt="A screenshot of the home page of Neocities"></a>
			<figcaption>A screenshot of the home page of Neocities</figcaption> 
		</figure>
		<p>If you don't know how to make websites, HTMLDog has excellent tutorials to learn <a href="https://htmldog.com/guides/html/beginner/">basic HTML</a> and <a href="https://htmldog.com/guides/css/beginner/">basic CSS</a>. If you prefer video, Khan Academy has an excellent free course for beginners called "<a href="https://www.khanacademy.org/computing/computer-programming/html-css">Making Webpages</a>" that looks very complete.</p>
		<p>If you have no prior experience, it might take you a while to get a hang of how to change text sizes and colours, add images and link between pages, but I think that’s part of the fun. </p>
		<p>You could of course always just get a pre-made template or a theme and use that, but it's a different exercise. It’s the difference between buying art and learning how to paint or sculpt. The end result might be the same but the exercise is very different. It might be more practical but is nothing like creating an HTML page from scratch and putting it up on the web for the world to see. </p>
		<p>Another great thing about the web is that you can always view the source of any public website to take inspiration and learn. Make sure you pick simple, basic ones; the modern web is full of bloated websites that make HTML unreadable. This website, for example, only uses basic HTML and CSS and I invite you to play with <a href="https://github.com/parimalsatyal/neu/blob/master/essays/the-small-web/index.html">the code</a> to your heart’s content. It’s all in the <a href="https://neustadt.fr/license.txt">public domain</a>, so you can even copy all of it and modify it (and you don’t have to credit me or even link back, it’s all free).</p>
		<p>If you do end up making a website after reading this, I’d love to see it (and perhaps even add it on here): send me an email at <a href="mailto:webmaster@neustadt.fr">webmaster@neustadt.fr</a>. </p>


		<h2 id="thoughts-and-feedback">Thoughts and Feedback</h2>

		<p>The small web still exists and has a lot to offer.</p> 
			
		<p>It might not be as polished as the commercial web we're used to, but I hope I have, at the very least, piqued your curiosity and made you want to explore it too.</p>

		<p>I would love to hear from you if you have thoughts and comments about the essay, or if you have other interesting examples, or corrections. You can email me at <a href="mailto:webmaster@neustadt.fr">webmaster@neustadt.fr</a>. This essay along with everything else on this website is also on <a href="https://github.com/parimalsatyal/neu/blob/master/essays/the-small-web/index.html">GitHub</a>; if you find errors or have suggestions for an edit, you can simply send me a pull request.</p>

		<p>I hope you enjoyed your stay on my website. Feel free to browse around; the <a href="https://neustadt.fr/retro-stuff">Retro Stuff</a> has other relics from the 90s and the 2000s that you might enjoy. And of course, you can <a href="https://users2.smartgb.com/g/g.php?a=s&amp;i=g26-37520-60">sign my guestbook</a> on your way out if you'd like.</p>
		
		<p><strong>Elsewhere:</strong> The <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=23326329">discussion on Hacker News</a> around this essay has plenty of other interesting links and ideas that you might also enjoy. <em>(Updated 28 May).</em></p>
		
		<p><strong>Merci:</strong> Thanks to Mario, Zach and Alex for <a href="https://github.com/parimalsatyal/neu/pulls?q=is%3Apr+is%3Aclosed">pointing out and fixing</a> some typos.</p>
—
		<span>← <a href="https://neustadt.fr/">back home</a></span>
	</article><p>
		<a href="https://neustadt.fr/license.txt"><img src="https://neustadt.fr/img/publicdomain.png" alt="CC0 Public Domain Logo"></a><br> <a href="https://neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/">Rediscovering the Small Web</a>, written by Parimal Satyal on 25 May 2020 and published on <a href="https://neustadt.fr/">Neustadt.fr</a>. This text is in the public domain with a <a href="https://neustadt.fr/license.txt">CC0 1.0 Universal license</a>; you are free to do whatever you want with it (obviously doesn't apply to the websites and resources I've linked to, or the logos and graphics in the background). A link back is nice but not required. </p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Five Most Productive Years: What Happened and What's Next (117 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2024/08/five-most-productive-years-what-happened-and-whats-next/</link>
            <guid>41406256</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 02:49:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2024/08/five-most-productive-years-what-happened-and-whats-next/">https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2024/08/five-most-productive-years-what-happened-and-whats-next/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41406256">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <p><img src="https://content.wolfram.com/sites/43/2024/08/sw-5-years-hero-v6.png" max-width="650px" height="auto" alt="Five Most Productive Years: What Happened and What's Next" title="Five Most Productive Years: What Happened and What's Next"></p>
<h2 id="so--what-happened">So… What Happened?</h2>

<p><img src="https://content.wolfram.com/sites/43/2024/08/blog-image-strip-v2.png" id="sideStripe"></p>
<p><a href="https://www.wolframalpha.com/input?i=how+old+is+stephen+wolfram">Today is my birthday</a>—for the 65th time. Five years ago, on my 60th birthday, I did a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2-aAi6QXsl0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">livestream where I talked about some of my plans</a>. So… what happened? Well, what happened was great. And in fact I’ve just had the most productive five years of my life. Nine <a href="https://www.amazon.com/stores/Stephen-Wolfram/author/B01HTZP7PQ?ref=sr_ntt%20_srch%20_lnk%20_%201&amp;qid=1724798966&amp;sr=8-1&amp;isDramIntegrated=true&amp;shoppingPortalEnabled=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">books</a>. 3939 pages of <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/">writings</a> (1,283,267 words). 499 hours of <a href="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/stephenwolfram" target="_blank" rel="noopener">podcasts</a> and 1369 hours of <a href="https://livestreams.stephenwolfram.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">livestreams</a>. 14 <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/category/new-technology/">software product releases</a> (with our great team). Oh, and a bunch of big—and beautiful—ideas and results.</p>
<p>It’s been wonderful. And unexpected. I’ve spent my life alternating between technology and basic science, progressively building a taller and taller tower of practical capabilities and intellectual concepts (and sharing what I’ve done with the world). Five years ago everything was going well, and making steady progress. But then there were the questions I never got to. Over the years I’d come up with a certain number of big questions. And some of them, within a few years, I’d answered. But others I never managed to get around to. </p>
<p>And five years ago, as I explained in my birthday livestream, I began to think “it’s now or never”. I had no idea how hard the questions were. Yes, I’d spent a lifetime building up tools and knowledge. But would they be enough? Or were the questions just not for our time, but only perhaps for some future century?<span id="more-62482"></span></p>
<p>At several points before in my life I’d faced such issues—and things had worked out well (<em><a href="https://www.wolframscience.com/nks/">A New Kind of Science</a></em>, <a href="https://www.wolframalpha.com/">Wolfram|Alpha</a>, etc.). And from this, I had gotten a certain confidence about what might be possible. In addition, as a serious <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/category/historical-perspectives">student of intellectual history</a>, I had a sense of what kind of boldness was needed. Five years ago there wasn’t really anything that made me need to do something big and new. But I thought: “What the heck. I might as well try. I’ll never know what’s possible unless I try.”</p>
<p>A major theme of my work since the early 1980s had been <a href="https://www.wolframscience.com/nksonline/toc.html">exploring the consequences of simple computational rules</a>. And I had found the surprising result that even extremely simple rules could lead to immensely complex behavior. So what about the universe? Could it be that at a fundamental level <a href="https://www.wolframscience.com/nks/chap-9--fundamental-physics/">our whole universe is just following some simple computational rule</a>? </p>
<p>I had begun my career in the 1970s as a teenager <a href="https://www.stephenwolfram.com/publications/academic/">studying the frontiers of existing physics</a>. And at <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2020/04/how-we-got-here-the-backstory-of-the-wolfram-physics-project/#maybe-it-could-apply-to-physics">first I couldn’t see</a> how computational rules could connect to what is known in physics. But in the early 1990s I had an idea, and by the late 1990s I had developed it and gotten some very suggestive results. But when I published these in <em>A New Kind of Science</em> in 2002, even my friends in the physics community <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2020/04/how-we-got-here-the-backstory-of-the-wolfram-physics-project/#please-dont-do-that-project">didn’t seem to care</a>—and I decided to concentrate my efforts elsewhere (e.g. building Wolfram|Alpha, <a href="https://reference.wolfram.com/language/">Wolfram Language</a>, etc.).</p>
<p>But I didn’t stop thinking “one day I need to get back to my physics project”. And in 2019 I decided: “What the heck. Let’s try it now.” It helped that I’d made a piece of technical progress the year before, and that <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2020/04/how-we-got-here-the-backstory-of-the-wolfram-physics-project/#two-young-physicists-and-a-little-idea">now two young physicists</a> were enthusiastic to work with me on the project. </p>
<p>And so it was, soon after <a href="https://x.com/stephen_wolfram/status/1167118524537610240" target="_blank" rel="noopener">my birthday in 2019</a>, that we embarked on our <a href="https://www.wolframphysics.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Physics Project</a>. It was a mixture of computer experiments and big concepts. But before the end of 2019 it was clear: <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2020/04/how-we-got-here-the-backstory-of-the-wolfram-physics-project/#oh-my-gosh-its-actually-going-to-work">it was going to work</a>! It was an amazing experience. Thing after thing in physics that had always been mysterious I suddenly understood. And it was beautiful—a theory of such strength built on a structure of such incredible simplicity and elegance. </p>
<p><a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2020/04/finally-we-may-have-a-path-to-the-fundamental-theory-of-physics-and-its-beautiful/">We announced</a> what we’d figured out in April 2020, right when the pandemic was in full swing. There was still much to do (and there still is today). But the overall picture was clear. I later learned that a century earlier many well-known physicists were beginning to think in a similar direction (matter is discrete, light is discrete; space must be too) but back then they hadn’t had the computational paradigm or the other tools needed to move this forward. And now the responsibility had fallen on us to do this. (Pleasantly enough, given our framework, many modern areas of mathematical physics seemed to fit right in.)</p>
<p>And, yes, figuring out the basic “machine code” for our universe was of course pretty exciting. But seeing an old idea of mine blossom like this had another very big effect on me. It made me think: “OK, what about all those other projects I’ve been meaning to do? Maybe it’s time to do those too.”</p>
<p>And something else had happened as well. In doing the Physics Project we’d developed a new way of thinking about things—not just computational, <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2021/09/multicomputation-a-fourth-paradigm-for-theoretical-science/">but “multicomputational”</a>. And actually, the <a href="https://www.wolframscience.com/nks/chap-5--two-dimensions-and-beyond#sect-5-6--multiway-systems">core ideas behind this</a> were in <em>A New Kind of Science</em> too. But somehow I’d never taken them seriously enough before, and never extended my intuition to encompass them. But now with the Physics Project I was doing this. And I could see that the ideas could also go much further. </p>
<p>So, yes, I had a new and powerful conceptual framework for doing science. And I had all the technology of the modern <a href="https://www.wolfram.com/language/">Wolfram Language</a>. But in 2020 I had another thing too—in effect, a new distribution channel for my ideas and efforts. Early in my career I had used <a href="https://www.stephenwolfram.com/publications/academic/">academic papers</a> as my “channel” (at one point in 1979 even averaging a paper every few weeks). But in the late 1980s I had a very different kind of channel: embodying my ideas in the design and implementation of <a href="https://www.wolfram.com/mathematica/">Mathematica</a> and what’s now the Wolfram Language. Then in the 1990s I had another channel: putting everything together into what became my book <em>A New Kind of Science</em>. </p>
<p>After that was published in 2002 I would occasionally write small posts—for the <a href="https://community.wolfram.com/content?curTag=wolfram%20science">community site</a> around the science in my book, for our <a href="https://blog.wolfram.com/">corporate blog</a>, etc. And in 2010 I <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2010/09/welcome-to-the-blog/">started my own blog</a>. At first I mostly just wrote small, fun pieces. But by 2015—partly driven by telling historical stories (<a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2015/11/george-boole-a-200-year-view/">200th anniversary of George Boole</a>, <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2015/12/untangling-the-tale-of-ada-lovelace/">200th anniversary of Ada Lovelace</a>, …)—the things I was writing were getting ever meatier. (There’d actually already been some <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2012/03/the-personal-analytics-of-my-life/">meaty ones</a> about <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/category/personal-analytics/">personal analytics</a> in 2012.)</p>
<p>And by 2020 my pattern was set and I would routinely write 50+ -page pieces, full of pictures (all with immediately runnable “<a href="https://reference.wolfram.com/language/ref/ClickToCopy.html">click-to-copy</a>” code) and intended for anyone who cared to read them. Finally I had a good channel again. And I started using it. As I’d found over the years—whether with <a href="https://reference.wolfram.com/language/">language documentation</a> or with <em>A New Kind of Science</em>—the very act of exposition was a critical part of organizing and developing my ideas. </p>
<p>And now I started producing pieces. Some were directly about specific topics around the Physics Project. But within two months I was already writing about a “spinoff”: “<a href="https://www.wolframphysics.org/bulletins/2020/06/exploring-rulial-space-the-case-of-turing-machines/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Exploring Rulial Space: The Case of Turing Machines</a>”. I had realized that one of the places the ideas of the Physics Project should apply was to the foundations of mathematics, and to metamathematics. In a footnote to <em>A New Kind of Science</em> I had introduced the idea of “<a href="https://www.wolframscience.com/nks/notes-12-9--empirical-metamathematics/">empirical metamathematics</a>”. And in the summer of 2020, fuelled by my newfound “finish those old projects” mindset, I ended up writing an 80-page piece on “<a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2020/09/the-empirical-metamathematics-of-euclid-and-beyond/">The Empirical Metamathematics of Euclid and Beyond</a>”. </p>
<p>December 7, 1920 was the date a certain <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2021/03/a-little-closer-to-finding-what-became-of-moses-schonfinkel-inventor-of-combinators/">Moses Schönfinkel introduced</a> what we <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2020/12/combinators-and-the-story-of-computation/">now call combinators</a>: the very first clear foundations for universal computation. I had always found combinators interesting (if hard to understand). I had used ideas from them back around 1980 in <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2013/06/there-was-a-time-before-mathematica/">the predecessor of what’s now the Wolfram Language</a>. And I had <a href="https://www.wolframscience.com/nks/chap-3--the-world-of-simple-programs#sect-3-10--symbolic-systems">talked about them a bit</a> in <em>A New Kind of Science</em>. But as the centenary approached, I decided to make a <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2020/12/combinators-a-centennial-view/">more definitive study</a>, in particular using methods from the Physics Project. And, for good measure, even in the middle of the pandemic I tracked down the <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2021/03/a-little-closer-to-finding-what-became-of-moses-schonfinkel-inventor-of-combinators/">mysterious history of Moses Schönfinkel</a>.</p>
<p>In March 2021, there was <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ultMxODJE7o" target="_blank" rel="noopener">another centenary</a>, this time of <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2021/03/after-100-years-can-we-finally-crack-posts-problem-of-tag-a-story-of-computational-irreducibility-and-more/#more-about-the-history">Emil Post’s tag system</a>, and again I decided to finish <a href="https://www.wolframscience.com/nks/chap-3--the-world-of-simple-programs#sect-3-7--tag-systems">what I’d started</a> in <em>A New Kind of Science</em>, and write <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2021/03/after-100-years-can-we-finally-crack-posts-problem-of-tag-a-story-of-computational-irreducibility-and-more/">a definitive piece</a>, this time running to about 75 pages.</p>
<p>One might have thought that the excursions into <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2020/09/the-empirical-metamathematics-of-euclid-and-beyond/">empirical metamathematics</a>, <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2020/12/combinators-a-centennial-view/">combinators</a>, <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2021/03/after-100-years-can-we-finally-crack-posts-problem-of-tag-a-story-of-computational-irreducibility-and-more/">tag systems</a>, <a href="https://www.wolframphysics.org/bulletins/2020/06/exploring-rulial-space-the-case-of-turing-machines/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">rulial</a> and <a href="https://www.wolframphysics.org/bulletins/2021/02/multiway-turing-machines/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">multiway Turing machines</a> would be distractions. But they were not. Instead, they just deepened my understanding and intuition for the new ideas and methods that had come out of the Physics Project. As well as finishing projects that I’d wondered about for decades (and the world had had open for a century). </p>
<p>Perhaps not surprisingly given its fundamental nature, the Physics Project also engaged with some deep <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/category/philosophy/">philosophical issues</a>. People would ask me about them with some regularity. And in March 2021 I started writing a bit about them, beginning with <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2021/03/what-is-consciousness-some-new-perspectives-from-our-physics-project/">a piece on consciousness</a>. The next month I wrote “<a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2021/04/why-does-the-universe-exist-some-perspectives-from-our-physics-project/">Why Does the Universe Exist? Some Perspectives from Our Physics Project</a>”. (This piece of writing happened to coincide with the few days in my life when I’ve needed to do active cryptocurrency trading—so I was in the amusing position of thinking about a philosophical question about as deep as they come, interspersed with making cryptocurrency trades.)</p>
<p>Everything kept weaving together. These philosophical questions made me internalize just how important the nature of the observer is in our Physics Project. Meanwhile I started thinking about the relationship of methods from the Physics Project to distributed computing, and to economics. And in May 2021 that intersected with practical <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=h94VrSuPFJc" target="_blank" rel="noopener">blockchain questions</a>, which caused me to write about “<a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2021/05/the-problem-of-distributed-consensus/">The Problem of Distributed Consensus</a>”—which would soon show up again in the <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/12/observer-theory/">science and philosophy of observers</a>. </p>
<p>The fall of 2021 involved really leaning into the new <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2021/09/multicomputation-a-fourth-paradigm-for-theoretical-science/">multicomputational paradigm</a>, among other things giving a <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2021/09/multicomputation-a-fourth-paradigm-for-theoretical-science/#potential-application-areas">long list of where it might apply</a>: metamathematics, chemistry, molecular biology, evolutionary biology, neuroscience, immunology, linguistics, economics, machine learning, distributed computing. And, yes, in a sense this was my “to do” list. In many ways, half the battle was just defining this. And I’m happy to say that just three years later, we’ve already made a big dent in it. </p>
<p>While all of this was going on, I was also energetically pursuing my “day job” as CEO of Wolfram Research. <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2020/03/in-less-than-a-year-so-much-new-launching-version-12-1-of-wolfram-language-mathematica/">Version 12.1</a> of the Wolfram Language had come out less than a month before the Physics Project was announced. <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2020/12/launching-version-12-2-of-wolfram-language-mathematica-228-new-functions-and-much-more/">Version 12.2</a> right after the combinator centenary. And in 2021 there were two new versions. In all 635 new functions, all of which <a href="https://livestreams.stephenwolfram.com/category/live-ceoing/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">I had carefully reviewed</a>, and many of which I’d been deeply involved in designing. </p>
<p>It’s a pattern in the history of science (as well as technology): some new methodology or some new paradigm is introduced. And suddenly vast new areas are opened up. And there’s lots of juicy “low-hanging fruit” to be picked. Well, that’s what had happened with the ideas from our Physics Project, and the concept of multicomputation. There were many directions to go, and many people wanting to get involved. And in 2021 it was becoming clear that something organizational had to be done: this wasn’t a job for a company (even for one as terrific and innovative as ours is), it was <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2022/04/weve-got-a-science-opportunity-overload-its-time-to-launch-the-wolfram-institute/">a job for something like an institute</a>. (And, yes, in 2022, we indeed launched what’s now the <a href="https://www.wolframinstitute.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wolfram Institute for Computational Foundations of Science</a>.)</p>
<p>But back in 1986, I had started the <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2021/09/charting-a-course-for-complexity-metamodeling-ruliology-and-more/#theres-a-whole-new-field-to-build">very first institute concentrating on complexity</a> and how it could arise from simple rules. Running it hadn’t been a good fit for me back then, and <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2016/04/my-life-in-technology-as-told-at-the-computer-history-museum/">very quickly I started our company</a>. In 2002, when <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2022/05/the-making-of-a-new-kind-of-science/"><em>A New Kind of Science</em> was published</a>, I’d thought again about starting an institute. But it didn’t happen. But now there really seemed to be no choice. I started reflecting on what had happened to “complexity”, and whether there was something to leverage from the institutional structure that had grown up around it. Nearly 20 years after the publication of <em>A New Kind of Science</em>, what should “complexity” be now?</p>
<p>I wrote “<a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2021/09/charting-a-course-for-complexity-metamodeling-ruliology-and-more/">Charting a Course for ‘Complexity’: Metamodeling, Ruliology and More</a>”—and in doing so, finally invented a word for the “pure basic science of what simple rules do”: <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2021/09/charting-a-course-for-complexity-metamodeling-ruliology-and-more/#the-pure-basic-science-of-ruliology">ruliology</a>. </p>
<p>My original framing of what became our Physics Project had been to try to “find a computational rule that gives our universe”. But I’d always found this unsatisfying. Because even if we had the rule, we’d still be left asking “why this one, and not another?” But in 2020 there’d been a dawning awareness of a possible answer.</p>
<p>Our Physics Project is based on the idea of <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2020/04/finally-we-may-have-a-path-to-the-fundamental-theory-of-physics-and-its-beautiful/#how-it-works">applying rules to abstract hypergraphs</a> that represent space and everything in it. But given a particular rule, there are in general many ways it can be applied. And a key idea in our Physics Project is that somehow it’s always <a href="https://www.wolframphysics.org/technical-introduction/the-updating-process-for-string-substitution-systems/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">applied in all these ways</a>—leading to many separate threads of history, that branch and merge—and, importantly, giving us a way to <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2020/04/finally-we-may-have-a-path-to-the-fundamental-theory-of-physics-and-its-beautiful/#the-inevitability-of-quantum-mechanics">understand quantum mechanics</a>.</p>
<p>We talked about these different threads of history corresponding to different places in <a href="https://www.wolframphysics.org/technical-introduction/the-updating-process-for-string-substitution-systems/the-concept-of-branchial-graphs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">branchial space</a>—and about how the laws of quantum mechanics are <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2020/04/finally-we-may-have-a-path-to-the-fundamental-theory-of-physics-and-its-beautiful/#general-relativity-and-quantum-mechanics-are-the-same-idea">the direct analogs in branchial space</a> (or branchtime) of the laws of classical mechanics (and gravity) in physical space (or spacetime). But what if instead of just applying a given rule in all possible ways, we applied all possible rules in all possible ways?</p>
<p>What would one get? In November 2021 I came up with a name for it: <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2021/11/the-concept-of-the-ruliad/">the ruliad</a>. A year and a half earlier I’d already been <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2020/04/finally-we-may-have-a-path-to-the-fundamental-theory-of-physics-and-its-beautiful/#why-this-universe-the-relativity-of-rules">starting to talk about rulial space</a>—and the idea of us as observers perceiving the universe in terms of our particular sampling of rulial space. But naming the ruliad really helped to crystallize the concept. And I began to realize that I had come upon a breathtakingly broad intellectual arc. </p>
<p>The ruliad is the biggest computational thing there can be: it’s the entangled limit of all possible computations. It’s abstract and it’s unique—and it’s as inevitable in its structure as 2 + 2 = 4. It encompasses everything computational—including us. So what then is physics? Well, it’s a description of how <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2021/11/the-concept-of-the-ruliad/#experiencing-the-ruliad">observers like us embedded in the ruliad</a> perceive the ruliad.</p>
<p><a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/02/a-50-year-quest-my-personal-journey-with-the-second-law-of-thermodynamics/#computational-irreducibility-and-rule-30">Back in 1984 I’d introduced</a> what<a href="https://www.wolframscience.com/nks/notes-12-6--history-of-computational-irreducibility/"> I saw as being the very central concept</a> of <a href="https://www.wolframscience.com/nks/chap-12--the-principle-of-computational-equivalence#sect-12-6--computational-irreducibility">computational irreducibility</a>: the idea that there are many computational processes whose outcomes can be found only by following them step by step—with no possibility of doing what mathematical science was used to, and being able to “jump ahead” and make predictions without going through each step. At the beginning of the 1990s, when I began to work on <em>A New Kind of Science</em>, I’d invented the <a href="https://www.wolframscience.com/nks/chap-12--the-principle-of-computational-equivalence/">Principle of Computational Equivalence</a>—the idea that systems whose behavior isn’t obviously simple will always tend to be equivalent in the sophistication of the computations they do. </p>
<p>Given the Principle of Computational Equivalence, computational irreducibility was inevitable. It followed from the fact that the observer could only be as computationally sophisticated as the system they were observing, and so would never be able to “jump ahead” and shortcut the computation. There’d come to be a belief that eventually science would always let one predict (and control) things. But here—from inside science—was a fundamental limitation on the power of science. All these things I’d known in some form since the 1980s, and with clarity since the 1990s. </p>
<p>But the ruliad took things to another level. For now I could see that the very laws of physics we know were determined by the way we are as observers. I’d always imagined that the laws of physics just are the way they are. But now I realized that we could potentially derive them from the inevitable structure of the ruliad, and very basic features of what we’re like as observers. </p>
<p>I hadn’t seen this philosophical twist coming. But somehow it immediately made sense. We weren’t getting our laws of physics from nothing; we were getting them from being the way we are. Two things seemed to be critical: that as observers we are computationally bounded, and that (somewhat relatedly) we believe we are persistent in time (i.e. we have a continuing thread of experience through time). </p>
<p>But even as I was homing in on the idea of the ruliad as it applied to physics, I was also thinking about another application: the <a href="https://www.wolframscience.com/metamathematics/">foundations of mathematics</a>. I’d been interested in the foundations of mathematics for a very long time; in fact, in the design of Mathematica (and what’s now the Wolfram Language) and <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2013/06/there-was-a-time-before-mathematica/">its predecessor SMP</a>, I’d made central use of ideas that I’d developed from thinking about the foundations of mathematics. And in <em>A New Kind of Science</em>, I’d included <a href="https://www.wolframscience.com/nks/chap-12--the-principle-of-computational-equivalence#sect-12-9--implications-for-mathematics-and-its-foundations">a long section on the foundations of mathematics</a>, discussing things like the network of all possible theorems, and the space of all possible axiom systems.</p>
<p>But now I was developing a clearer picture. The ruliad represented not only all possible physics, but also all possible mathematics. And the actual mathematics that we perceive—like the actual physics—would be determined by our nature as observers, in this case mathematical observers. There were lots of technical details, and it wasn’t until March 2022 that I published “<a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2022/03/the-physicalization-of-metamathematics-and-its-implications-for-the-foundations-of-mathematics/">The Physicalization of Metamathematics and Its Implications for the Foundations of Mathematics</a>”. </p>
<p>In some ways this finished what I’d started in the mid-1990s. But it went much further than I expected, in particular in providing a sweeping unification of the foundations of physics and mathematics. It talked about what the ultimate limit of mathematics would be like. And it talked about how “human-level mathematics”—where we can discuss things like the Pythagorean theorem rather than just the microdetails of underlying axioms—emerges for observers like us just like our human-level impression of physical space emerges from the underlying network of atoms of space. </p>
<p>One of the things I’d discovered in computational systems is how common computational irreducibility is, along with undecidability. And I had always wondered why undecidability wasn’t more common in typical mathematics. But now I had an answer: it just isn’t what mathematical observers like us “see” in the ruliad. At some level, this was a very philosophical result. But for me it also had <a href="https://www.wolframscience.com/metamathematics/implications-for-the-future-of-mathematics/">practical implications</a>, notably greatly validating the idea of using higher-level computational language to represent useful human-level mathematics, rather than trying to drill down to “axiomatic machine code”. </p>
<p>October 22, 2021 had marked <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2021/10/celebrating-a-third-of-a-century-of-mathematica-and-looking-forward/">a third of a century of Mathematica</a>. And May 14, 2022 was the <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2022/05/twenty-years-later-the-surprising-greater-implications-of-a-new-kind-of-science/">20th anniversary of <em>A New Kind of Science</em></a>. And in contextualizing my activities, and planning for the future, I’ve increasingly found it useful to reflect on what I’ve done before, and how it’s worked out. And in both these cases I could see that seeds I’d planted many years earlier had blossomed, sometimes in ways I’d suspected they might, and sometimes in ways that far exceeded what I’d imagined. </p>
<p>What had I done right? The key, it seemed, was drilling down to find the essence of things, and then developing that. Even if I hadn’t been able to imagine quite what could be built on them, I’d been able to construct solid foundations, that successfully encapsulated things in the cleanest and simplest ways. </p>
<p>In talking about observers and the ruliad—and in fact our Physics Project in general—I kept on making analogies to the way that the gas laws and fluid dynamics emerge from the complicated underlying dynamics of molecules. And at the core of this is the <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/02/computational-foundations-for-the-second-law-of-thermodynamics/">Second Law of thermodynamics</a>. </p>
<p>Well, as it happens, the very first foundational question in physics that I ever seriously studied was the origin of the Second Law. But that was <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/02/a-50-year-quest-my-personal-journey-with-the-second-law-of-thermodynamics/">when I was 12 years old</a>, in 1972. For more than a century the Second Law <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/01/how-did-we-get-here-the-tangled-history-of-the-second-law-of-thermodynamics/">had been quite mysterious</a>. But when I discovered computational irreducibility in 1984 I soon realized that it <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/02/a-50-year-quest-my-personal-journey-with-the-second-law-of-thermodynamics/#computational-irreducibility-and-rule-30">might be the key to the Second Law</a>. And in the summer of 2022—armed with a new perspective on the importance of observers—I decided I’d better once and for all write down how the Second Law works.</p>
<p>Once again, there were lots of <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/02/computational-foundations-for-the-second-law-of-thermodynamics/">technical details</a>. And as a way to check my ideas I decided to go back and try to untangle the rather confused <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/01/how-did-we-get-here-the-tangled-history-of-the-second-law-of-thermodynamics/">150-year history of the Second Law</a>. It was an interesting exercise, satisfying for seeing how my new ways of thinking clarified things, but cautionary in seeing how wrong turns had been taken—and solidified—in the past. But in the end, there it was: the Second Law was a consequence of the interplay between underlying computational irreducibility, and our limitations as observers.</p>
<p>It had taken half a century, but finally I had finished the project I’d started when I was 12 years old. I was on a roll finishing things. But I was also realizing that a bigger structure than I’d ever imagined was emerging. The Second Law project completed what I think is the most beautiful thing I’ve ever discovered. That all three of the core theories of twentieth century physics—general relativity, quantum mechanics and the Second Law (statistical mechanics)—have the same origin: the interplay between the underlying computational structure of the ruliad, and our characteristics and limitations as observers. </p>
<p>And I knew it didn’t stop there. I’d already applied the same kind of thinking to the foundations of mathematics. And I was ready to start applying it to all sorts of deep questions in science, in philosophy, and beyond. But at the end of 2022, just as I was finishing my pieces about the Second Law, there was a surprise: <a href="https://openai.com/index/chatgpt/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ChatGPT</a>.</p>
<p>I’d been <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2015/05/wolfram-language-artificial-intelligence-the-image-identification-project/#personal-backstory">following AI and neural nets</a> for decades. I first simulated a neural net in 1981. <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2016/04/my-life-in-technology-as-told-at-the-computer-history-museum/">My first company, started in 1981</a>, had, to my chagrin, been labeled an “AI company”. And from the early 2010s we’d integrated neural nets into the Wolfram Language. But—like the creators of ChatGPT—I didn’t expect the capabilities that emerged in ChatGPT. And as soon as I saw ChatGPT I started trying to understand it. What was it really doing? What would its capabilities be?</p>
<p>In the world at large, there was a sense of shock: if AI can do this now, soon it’ll be able to do everything. But I immediately thought about computational irreducibility. And it gave us limitations. But those limitations would inevitably apply to AIs as well. There would be things that couldn’t be “quickly figured out by pure thought”—by humans and AIs alike. And, by the way, I’d just spent four decades building a way to represent things computationally, and actually do systematic computations on them—because that was the point of the Wolfram Language. </p>
<p>So immediately I could see <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/01/wolframalpha-as-the-way-to-bring-computational-knowledge-superpowers-to-chatgpt/">we were in a very interesting position</a>. The Wolfram Language had the completely unique mission of creating a full-scale computational language. And now this was a crucial tool for AIs. The AIs could provide a very interesting and useful broad linguistic interface. But when it came to solid computation, they were—like humans—going to need a tool. Conveniently, Wolfram|Alpha already communicated in natural language. And it took only a few weeks to hook up Wolfram|Alpha—and Wolfram Language—to ChatGPT. We’d <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/03/chatgpt-gets-its-wolfram-superpowers/">given “computational superpowers” to the AI</a>. </p>
<p>ChatGPT was everywhere. And people kept asking me about it. And over and over again I ended up explaining things about it. So at the beginning of February 2023 I decided it’d be better for me just to write down once and for all what I knew. It took a little over a week (yes, I’m a fast writer)—and then I had an “<a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/02/what-is-chatgpt-doing-and-why-does-it-work/">explainer</a>” (that ran altogether to 76 pages) of ChatGPT. </p>
<p>Partly it talked in general about how machine learning and neural nets work, and how ChatGPT in particular works. But what a lot of people wanted to know was not “how” but “why” ChatGPT works. Why was something like that possible? Well, in effect ChatGPT was <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/02/what-is-chatgpt-doing-and-why-does-it-work/#what-really-lets-chatgpt-work">showing us a new science discovery</a>—about language. Everyone knows that there’s a certain syntactic grammar of language—like that, in English, sentences typically have the form noun-verb-noun. But what ChatGPT was showing us is that there’s also a <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/02/what-is-chatgpt-doing-and-why-does-it-work/#semantic-grammar-and-the-power-of-computational-language">semantic grammar</a>—some pattern of rules for what words can be put together and make sense. </p>
<p>I’ve thought about the <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/category/language-and-communication">foundations of language</a> for a long time (which isn’t too surprising, given the four decades I’ve spent as a computational language designer). So in effect I was well primed to think about its interaction with ChatGPT. And it also helped that—as I’ll talk about below—one of my long-unfinished projects is precisely on a formal framework for capturing meaning that I call “<a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2016/10/computational-law-symbolic-discourse-and-the-ai-constitution/">symbolic discourse language</a>”.</p>
<p>In technology and other things I always like best situations where basically nothing is known, and one has to invent everything from scratch. And that’s what was happening for functionality based on LLMs in the middle of 2023. How would <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/05/the-new-world-of-llm-functions-integrating-llm-technology-into-the-wolfram-language/">LLM-based Wolfram Language functions</a> work? How would a <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/06/prompts-for-work-play-launching-the-wolfram-prompt-repository/">prompt repository</a> work? How would <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/06/introducing-chat-notebooks-integrating-llms-into-the-notebook-paradigm/">LLMs interact with notebooks</a>?</p>
<p>Meanwhile, there was still lots of foment in the world about the “AI shock”. Before the arrival of the Physics Project in 2019—I’d been <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2019/06/testifying-at-the-senate-about-a-i-selected-content-on-the-internet/">quite involved</a> in <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2016/10/a-short-talk-on-ai-ethics/">AI philosophy</a>, AI ethics, etc. And in March 2023 I wrote a piece on “<a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/03/will-ais-take-all-our-jobs-and-end-human-history-or-not-well-its-complicated/">Will AIs Take All Our Jobs and End Human History—or Not?</a>” In the end—after all sorts of philosophical arguments, and an <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/03/will-ais-take-all-our-jobs-and-end-human-history-or-not-well-its-complicated/#afterword-looking-at-some-actual-data">analysis of actual historical data</a>—the answer was: “It’s Complicated”. But along the way computational irreducibility and the ruliad were central elements: limiting the controllability of AIs, allowing for an infinite frontier of invention, and highlighting the inevitable meaninglessness of everything in the absence of human choice. </p>
<p>By this point (and actually, with remarkable speed) my explainer on ChatGPT had turned into a <a href="https://www.wolfram-media.com/products/what-is-chatgpt-doing-and-why-does-it-work/">book</a>—that proved extremely popular (and now, for example, exists in over 10 languages). It was nice that people found the book useful—and perhaps it helped remove some of the alarming mystique of AI. But I couldn’t help noticing that of all the many things I’d written, this had been one of the fastest to write, yet it was garnering one of the largest readerships.</p>
<p>One might have imagined that AI was pretty far from our Physics Project, the ruliad, etc. But actually it soon became clear that there were close connections, and that there were things to learn in both directions. In particular, I’d come to think of minds that work in different ways as occupying different positions in the ruliad. But how could one get intuition about what such minds would experience—or observe? Well, I realized, one could just look at generative AI. In July I wrote “<a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/07/generative-ai-space-and-the-mental-imagery-of-alien-minds/">Generative AI Space and the Mental Imagery of Alien Minds</a>”. I called this the “cats in hats piece”, because, yes, it has lots of pictures of (often bizarrely distorted) cats (in hats)—used as examples of what happens if one moves a mind around in rulial space. But despite the whimsy of the cats, this piece provided a surprisingly useful window into what for me has been a very longstanding question of how <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2018/01/showing-off-to-the-universe-beacons-for-the-afterlife-of-our-civilization/">other minds might perceive things</a>. </p>
<p>And this fed quite directly into my piece on “<a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/12/observer-theory/">Observer Theory</a>” in December 2023. Ever since things like Turing machines we’ve had a formal model for the process of computation. My goal was to do the same kind of thing for the process of observation. In a sense, computation constructs sequences of new things, say with time. Observation, on the other hand, equivalences things together, so they fit in finite minds. And just what equivalencing is done—by our senses, our measuring devices, our thinking—determines what our ultimate perceptions will be. Or, put another way, if we can characterize well enough what we’re like as observers, it’ll show us how we sample the ruliad, and what we’ll perceive the laws of physics to be.</p>
<p>When I started the Physics Project I wasn’t counting on it having any applications for hundreds of years. But quite soon it became clear that actually there were going to be all sorts of near-term applications, particularly of the formalism of multicomputation. And every time one used that formalism one could get more intuition about features of the Physics Project, particularly related to quantum mechanics. I ended up writing a variety of “ruliological” pieces, all, as it happens, expanding on footnotes in <em>A New Kind of Science</em>. There was “<a href="https://www.wolframphysics.org/bulletins/2021/10/multicomputation-with-numbers-the-case-of-simple-multiway-systems/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Multicomputation with Numbers</a>” (October 2021), “<a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2022/06/games-and-puzzles-as-multicomputational-systems/">Games and Puzzles as Multicomputational Systems</a>” (June 2022) and “<a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/11/aggregation-and-tiling-as-multicomputational-processes/">Aggregation and Tiling as Multicomputational Processes</a>” (November 2023). And in September 2023 there was also “<a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/09/expression-evaluation-and-fundamental-physics/">Expression Evaluation and Fundamental Physics</a>”. </p>
<p>Back around 1980—when I was working on SMP—I’d become interested in the theory of expression evaluation. And finally, now, with the Physics Project—and my work on combinators and metamathematics—four decades later I had a principled way to study it (potentially with immediate application in distributed computing and computational language design around that). And I could check off progress on another long-pending project.</p>
<p>I give many talks, and do many podcasts and livestreams—essentially all unprepared. But in October 2023 I agreed to give a TED talk. And I just didn’t see any way to fit a reasonable snapshot of my activities into 18 minutes without preparation. How was I to coherently explain the Physics Project, the ruliad and computational language in such a short time? I called the talk “<a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/10/how-to-think-computationally-about-ai-the-universe-and-everything/">How to Think Computationally about AI, the Universe and Everything</a>”. And I began with what for me was a new condensation: “Human language. Mathematics. Logic. These are all ways to formalize the world. And in our century there’s a new and yet more powerful one: computation.” </p>
<p>Over the years I’d done all sorts of seemingly very different projects in science and in technology. But somehow it seemed like they were now all converging. Back in 1979, for example, I’d invented the idea of transformations for symbolic expressions as a foundation for computational language. But now—more than four decades later—our Physics Project was saying that those kinds of transformations (specifically on hypergraphs) were just what the “machine code of the universe” was made of. </p>
<p>Since the 1980s I’d thought that computation was a useful paradigm with which to think about the world. But now our Physics Project and the ruliad were saying that it wasn’t just useful; it was the underlying paradigm of the world. For some time I’d been viewing our whole Wolfram Language effort as a way to provide a way to formalize computation for the purposes of both humans and machines. Four hundred years ago mathematical notation had streamlined mathematical thinking, allowing what became the mathematical sciences to develop. I saw what we were doing with our <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2019/05/what-weve-built-is-a-computational-language-and-thats-very-important/">computational language</a> as a way to streamline computational thinking, and allow “computational X” for all fields “X” to develop. </p>
<p>I began to see computational thinking as a way to “humanize” the ruliad; to pick out those parts that are meaningful to humans. And I began to see computational language as the bridge between the power of raw computation, and the kinds of things we humans think about. </p>
<p>But how did AI fit in? At the beginning of 2024, lots of people were still asking in effect “Can AI Solve Science?” So I <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2024/03/can-ai-solve-science/">decided to analyze that</a>. I certainly didn’t expect AI to be able to “break computational irreducibility”. And it didn’t. Yes, it could automate much of what humans could do in a quick look. But formalized, irreducible computation: that was going to need computational language, not AI. </p>
<p>It’s easy to be original in the computational universe: if you pick a rule at random, it’s overwhelmingly likely <a href="https://x.com/stephen_wolfram/status/1420206573096513539/photo/1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">nobody’s ever looked at it before</a>. But will anyone care? They’ll care if in effect that part of the ruliad has been “colonized”; if there’s already a human connection to it. But what if you define some attribute that you want, then just “search out there” for a rule that exhibits it? That’s basically what biological evolution—or machine learning training—seems to do.</p>
<p>And as a kind of <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2024/03/can-ai-solve-science/#exploring-spaces-of-systems">off-hand note</a> I decided to just see if I could make a minimal model for that. <a href="https://content.wolfram.com/sw-publications/2020/07/approaches-complexity-engineering.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">I’d tried before—in the mid-1980s</a>. And in the 1990s when I was writing <em>A New Kind of Science</em> I’d become convinced that computational irreducibility was in a sense a <a href="https://www.wolframscience.com/nks/chap-8--implications-for-everyday-systems#sect-8-5--fundamental-issues-in-biology">stronger force than adaptive evolution</a>, and that when complex behavior was seen in biology, it was computational irreducibility that should take most of the credit.</p>
<p>But I decided to just do the experiment and see. And although computational irreducibility in a sense tells one to always “expect the unexpected”, in all these years I’ve never fully come to terms with that—and I’m still regularly surprised by what simple systems somehow “cleverly” manage to do. And so it was with <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2024/05/why-does-biological-evolution-work-a-minimal-model-for-biological-evolution-and-other-adaptive-processes/">my minimal model of biological evolution</a>.</p>
<p>I’d always wondered why biological evolution managed to work at all, why it didn’t “get stuck”, and how it managed to come up with the ornate “solutions” it did. Well, now I knew: and it turned out it was, once again, a story of computational irreducibility. And I’d managed to finish another project that I started in the 1980s.</p>
<p>But then there was machine learning. And despite all the energy around it—as well as <a href="https://www.wolfram.com/language/core-areas/machine-learning/">practical experience with it</a>—it didn’t seem like there was a good foundational understanding of what it was doing or why it worked. For a couple of years I’d been asking all the machine learning experts I ran into what they knew. But mostly they confirmed that, yes, it wasn’t well understood. And in fact several of them suggested that I’d be the best person to figure it out. </p>
<p>So just a few weeks ago, starting with ideas from the biological evolution project, and mixing in some things I tried back in 1985, I decided to embark on exploring minimal models of machine learning. I just <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2024/08/whats-really-going-on-in-machine-learning-some-minimal-models/">posted the results last week</a>. And, yes, one seems to be able to see the essence of machine learning in systems vastly simpler than neural nets. In these systems one can visualize what’s going on—and it’s basically a story of finding ways to put together lumps of irreducible computation to do the tasks we want. Like stones one might pick up off the ground to put together into a stone wall, one gets something that works, but there’s no reason for there to be any understandable structure to it. </p>
<p>Like so many of the projects I’ve done in the past five years, I could in principle have done this project much earlier—even in the 1980s. But back then I didn’t have the intuition, the tools or the intellectual confidence to actually dive in and get the project done. And what’s been particularly exciting over the past five years is that I can feel—and even very tangibly see—how what I can do has grown. With every project I’ve done I’ve further honed my intuition, developed more tools (both conceptual and practical), and built my intellectual confidence. Could I have gotten here earlier in my life? I don’t think so. I think to get to where I am now required the kind of journey I’ve taken through science, technology and the other things I’ve done. A living example of the phenomenon of computational irreducibility. </p>
<h2 id="the-process-of-getting-things-done">The Process of Getting Things Done</h2>
<p>I started my career young—and usually found myself the “youngest person in the room”. But shockingly fast all those years whizzed by, and now I’m usually the “oldest person in the room”. But somehow I always still seem to feel like a young whippersnapper—not settled into some expected pattern, and “pushing for the future”. </p>
<p>I’ve always done projects that are hard. Projects that many people thought were impossible. Projects that stretched my capabilities to the limit. And to do this has required a certain mixture of confidence and humility. Confidence that it’s worth me trying the project. Humility in not assuming that it’ll be easy for me. </p>
<p>I’ve learned a lot of fields by now, and with them a lot of different ways of thinking. But somehow it’s never enough to make the projects I do easy. Somehow the projects are always far enough out on the frontier that I have to learn new things and new ways of thinking to succeed at them. And so there I am, often the only person in the room whose project isn’t somehow easy for them. And who still has to be pushing, whippersnapper style.</p>
<p>At this point, a fair fraction of the projects I do are ones that I’ve thought about for a long time; a smaller fraction are opportunistic—coming into scope just now as a result of something I’ve done, or something that’s happened in the world at large. Before the past five years I had a lot of projects that had languished, often for decades. Yes, I thought they would be interesting, and I gradually collected information about them. But somehow I wasn’t quite in a place to tackle them.</p>
<p>But now I feel quite differently. In the past five years, I’ve gone back and finished a fair fraction of all those languishing projects. And it’s been great. Without exception, the projects turned out to be richer and more interesting than I expected. Often I realized I really couldn’t have done them without the tools and ideas (and infrastructure) I now have. And—often to my great surprise—the projects turned out to have very direct connections to big themes around the ruliad, the Physics Project and, for that matter, computational language. </p>
<p>Why was this happening? Partly it’s a tribute to the breadth of the computational (and now multicomputational) paradigm. But partly it has to do with the specific character of projects I was choosing—always seeking what seemed like the simplest, most foundational versions of things. </p>
<p>I’ve done quite a few big projects in my life, many seemingly very different. But as I look back, I realize that all my projects have a certain overall pattern to them. They’re all about taking something that seems complicated, then drilling down to find the foundations of what’s going on, and then building up from these—often with considerable engineering-style effort. And the methods and tools I’ve developed have in a sense implicitly been optimized for this pattern of work. </p>
<p>I suppose one gets used to the rhythm of it all. The time when one’s drilling down, slowly trying to understand things. The time when one’s doing all the work to build the big structure up. And yes, it’s all hard. But by now I know the signs of progress, and they’re always energizing to see. </p>
<p>At any given time, I’ll have many projects gestating—often for years or decades. But once a project becomes active, it’s usually the only one I’m working on. And I’ll work on it with great intensity, pushing hard to keep going until it’s done. Often I’ll be working with other people, usually much younger than me. And I think it’s always a surprise that I’ll routinely be the one who works with the greatest intensity—every day, at all hours. </p>
<p>I think I’m <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2019/02/seeking-the-productive-life-some-details-of-my-personal-infrastructure/">pretty efficient too</a>. Of course, it helps that I have a tool—Wolfram Language—that I’ve been building for decades to support me. And it helps that I’ve developed all kinds of practices around how I organize code and notebooks I create, and how I set up my process of writing about things. Of course, it also helps that I have very capable people around me to make suggestions, explore additional directions, fill in details, check things, and get my write-ups produced and published.</p>
<p>As I have <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2019/02/seeking-the-productive-life-some-details-of-my-personal-infrastructure/">written about elsewhere</a>, my life is in many ways set up to be quite simple and routine. I get up at the same time every day, eat the same thing for breakfast, and so on. But in a sense this frees me to concentrate on the intellectual things I’m doing—which are different every day, often in unexpected ways. </p>
<p>But how is it that I even get the time to do all these intellectual things? After all, I am—as I have been for the past 38 years—the CEO of a <a href="https://www.wolfram.com/">very active tech company</a>. Two things I think help (in addition, of course, to the fact that I have such a great long-term team at the company). First, organization. And second, resolve. Every day I’ll have <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2012/03/the-personal-analytics-of-my-life/">tightly scheduled meetings</a> over the course of the working day. (And there are lots of details to this. I get up in the late morning, then do my first two meetings while walking, and so on.) But somehow—mostly on evenings and weekends—I find time to work intensely on my intellectual projects.</p>
<p>It’s not as if I ignore everything else in the world. But I do have a certain drive—and resolve—that fills any time available with my projects, and somehow seems to succeed in getting them done. (And, yes, there are many optimizations in the details of my life, saving me all sorts of time. And it probably helps that I’ve been a work-from-home CEO now for 33 years.)</p>
<p>One might have thought that CEOing would greatly detract from being able to do intellectual work. But I find the exact opposite. Because in my experience the discipline of strategy and decision making (as well as communicating thoughts and ideas to other people) that comes with CEOing is critical to being able to do incisive intellectual work. And, by the way, the kind of thinking that goes with intellectual work is also incredibly valuable in being an effective CEO. </p>
<p>There’s another critical part to my “formula”. And that has to do with exposition. For me, the exposition of a project is an integral part of the project. Part of it is that the very definition of the question is often one of the most important parts of a project. But more than that, it’s through exposition that I find I really understand things. It takes a certain discipline. It can be easy enough to make some highfalutin technical statement. But can one grind it down into truly simple pieces that one can immediately understand? Yes, that means other people will be able to understand it too. But for me, what’s critical is that that’s the way I can tell if I’m getting things right. And for me the exposition is what in the end defines the backbone of a project. </p>
<p>Normally I write quickly, and basically without revision. But whenever there’s a piece I’m finding unduly hard to write I know that’s where I’m muddled, and need to go back and understand what’s going on. Some of my projects (like creating this piece, for example) end up being essentially “pure writing”. But most are deeply computational—and full of computer experiments. And just as I put a lot of effort into making written exposition clear, I do the same for computational language, and for pictures. Indeed, many of my projects are in large measure driven by pictures. Usually these are what one can think of as “algorithmic diagrams”—created automatically with a <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2017/11/what-is-a-computational-essay/">structure optimized for exposition</a>.</p>
<p>And the pictures aren’t just useful for presenting what I’ve done; they’re also critical to my own efforts to figure things out. And I’ve learned that it’s important to get the presentational details of pictures right as early as possible in a project—to give myself the best chance to notice things. </p>
<p>Often the projects I do require exploring large numbers of possible systems. And somehow with great regularity this leads to me ending up looking at <a href="https://www.wolframscience.com/nks/p55--more-cellular-automata/">large arrays of little pictures</a>. Yes, there’s a lot of “looking” <a href="https://www.wolframphysics.org/technical-introduction/typical-behaviors/random-rules-and-overall-classification-of-behavior/#p-144" target="_blank" rel="noopener">that can be automated</a>. But in the end computational irreducibility means there’ll always be the unexpected, that I basically have to see for myself. </p>
<p>A great thing about the Wolfram Language is that it’s been very stable ever since it was first released. And that means that I can take notebooks even from the 1980s and immediately run them today. And, yes, given all the “old” projects I’ve worked on in the past five years, that’s been very important. </p>
<p>But in addition to being very stable, the Wolfram Language is also very self contained—and very much <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2019/05/what-weve-built-is-a-computational-language-and-thats-very-important/">intended to be readable by humans</a>. And the result is something that I’ve found increasingly important: every computational picture in everything I write has Wolfram Language code “behind it”, that you can get by clicking. All the time I find myself going back to previous things I’ve written, and picking up <a href="https://reference.wolfram.com/language/ref/ClickToCopy.html">click-to-copy</a> code to run for some new case, or use as the basis for something new I’m doing. </p>
<p>And of course that click-to-copy code is open for anyone to use. Not only for its “computational content”, but also for the often-elaborate visuals it implements.</p>
<p>Most of my writings over the past five years have been about new basic science. But interspersed with this—along with pieces about technology and about philosophy—are <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/category/historical-perspectives/">pieces about history</a>. And in fact many of my scientific pieces have had extensive historical sections as well. </p>
<p>Why do I put such effort into history? Partly I just find it fun to figure out. But mostly it’s to contextualize my understanding of things. Particularly in the past five years I’ve ended up working on a whole sequence of projects that are in a sense about changing longstanding directions in science. And to feel confident about making such changes, one has to know why people went in those directions in the first place. And that requires studying history.</p>
<p>Make no mistake: history—or at least good history—is hard. Often there’ll be a standard simple story about how some discovery was suddenly made, or how some direction was immediately defined. But the real story is usually much more complicated—and much more revealing of the true intellectual foundations of what was figured out. Almost never did someone discover something “one day”; almost always it took many years to build up the conceptual framework so that “one day” the key thing could even be noticed. </p>
<p>When I do history I always make a big effort to look at the original documents. And often I realize that’s critical—because it’s only with whatever new understanding I’ve developed that one would stand a chance of correctly interpreting what’s in the documents. And even if one’s mainly interested in the history of ideas, I’ve always found it’s crucial to also understand the people who were involved with them. What was their motivation? What was their practical situation? What kinds of things did they know about? What was their intellectual style in thinking about things?</p>
<p>It has helped me greatly that I’ve had my own experiences in making discoveries—that gives me an intuition for how the process of discovery works. And it also helps that I’ve had my fair share of “worldly” experiences. Still, often it’s at first a mystery how some idea developed or some discovery got made. But my consistent experience is that with enough effort one can almost always solve it. </p>
<p>Particularly for the projects I’ve done in recent years, it often leaves me with a strange feeling of connection. For in many cases I find out that the things I’ve now done can be viewed as direct follow-ons to ideas that were thought about a century or more ago, and for one reason or another ignored or abandoned since. </p>
<p>And I’m then usually left with a strong sense of responsibility. An idea that was someone’s great achievement had been buried and lost to the world. But now I have found it again, and it rests on me to bring it into the future.</p>
<p>In addition to writing about “other people’s history”, I’ve also been writing quite a bit about my own history. And in the last few years I’ve made a point of explaining my personal history around the science—and technology—I describe. In doing this, it helps a lot that I have <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2019/02/seeking-the-productive-life-some-details-of-my-personal-infrastructure/#archiving-and-searching">excellent personal archives</a>—that routinely let me track to within minutes <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2024/06/ruliology-of-the-forgotten-code-10/">discoveries I made even four decades ago</a>. </p>
<p>My goal in describing my own history is to help other people contextualize things I write about. But I have to say that time and time again I’ve found the effort to piece together my own history extremely valuable just for me. As I go through life, I try to build up a repertoire of patterns for how things I do fit together. But often those patterns aren’t visible at the time. And it takes going back—often years later—to see them. </p>
<p>I do the projects I do first and foremost for myself. But I’ve always liked the idea that other people can get their own pleasure and benefit from my projects. And—basically starting with the Physics Project—I’ve tried to open to the world not just the results of my projects, but the process by which they’re done. </p>
<p>I post my <a href="https://www.wolframphysics.org/archives/index/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">working notebooks</a>. Whenever practical I <a href="https://livestreams.stephenwolfram.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">livestream</a> my working meetings. And, perhaps taking things to an extreme, I record even my own solitary work, posting it in “<a href="https://livestreams.stephenwolfram.com/category/personal-video-worklogs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">video work logs</a>”. (Except I just realized I forgot to record the writing I’m doing right now!) </p>
<p>A couple of years before the Physics Project I actually also <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2017/12/what-do-i-do-all-day-livestreamed-technology-ceoing/">opened up my technology development activities</a>—livestreaming our <a href="https://livestreams.stephenwolfram.com/category/live-ceoing/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">software design reviews</a>, in the past five years 692 hours of them. (And, yes, I put a lot of work and effort into designing the Wolfram Language!)</p>
<p>At the beginning of the pandemic I thought: “There are all these kids out of school. Let me try to do a little bit of public service and livestream something about science and technology for them.” And that’s how I started my “<a href="https://livestreams.stephenwolfram.com/category/science-technology-qa-for-kids-and-others" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Science &amp; Technology Q&amp;A for Kids &amp; Others</a>” livestreams, that I’ve now been doing for four and a half years. Along the way, I’ve added “<a href="https://livestreams.stephenwolfram.com/category/history-of-science-and-technology-qa" target="_blank" rel="noopener">History of Science &amp; Technology Q&amp;A</a>”, “<a href="https://livestreams.stephenwolfram.com/category/future-of-science-technology-qa/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Future of Science &amp; Technology Q&amp;A</a>”, and “<a href="https://livestreams.stephenwolfram.com/category/business-innovation-and-managing-life-qa" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Business, Innovation &amp; Managing Life Q&amp;A</a>”. Altogether I’ve done 272 hours of these, that have generated 376 <a href="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/stephenwolfram" target="_blank" rel="noopener">podcast episodes</a>.</p>
<p>Twice a week I sit down in front of a camera, watch the feed of questions, and try to answer them. It’s always off the cuff, completely unprepared. And I find it a great experience. I can tell that over the time I’ve been doing this, I’ve become a better and more fluent explainer, which no doubt helps my written exposition too. Often in answering questions I’ll come up with a new way to explain something, that I’ve never thought of before. And often there’ll be questions that make me think about things I’ve never thought about at all before. Indeed, several of my recent projects actually got started as a result of questions people asked. </p>
<p>When I was younger I always just wanted to get on with research, create things, and so on; I wasn’t interested in education. But as I’ve gotten older I’ve come to really like education. Partly it’s because I feel I learn a lot myself from it, but mostly it’s because I find it fulfilling to use what I know and try to help people develop. </p>
<p>I’ve always been interested in people—a useful attribute in running a talent-rich company for four decades. (I’m particularly interested in how people develop through their lives—leading me recently, for example, to organize a 50-year reunion for my elementary school class.) I’ve had a <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2019/08/fifty-years-of-mentoring/">long-time “hobby” of mentoring CEOs and kids</a> (both being categories of people who tend to believe that anything is possible). </p>
<p>But my main educational efforts are concentrated in a few weeks of the year when we do our <a href="https://education.wolfram.com/summer-school">Wolfram Summer School</a> (started in 2003) and our <a href="https://education.wolfram.com/summer-research-high-school/">Wolfram High School Summer Research Program</a> (started in 2012). All the students in these programs (775 of them over the past five years) do an original project, and one of my jobs is to come up with what all these projects should be. Over the course of the year I’ll accumulate ideas—though rather often when I actually meet a student I’ll invent something new. </p>
<p>I obviously do plenty of projects myself. But it’s always an interesting—and invigorating—experience to see so many projects get done with such intensity at our summer programs. Plus, I get lots of extra practice in framing projects that helps when I come to frame my own projects.</p>
<p>At this point, I’ve spent years trying to organize my life to optimize it for what I want to get out of it. I need long stretches of time when I can concentrate coherently. But I like having a diversity of activities, and I’m pretty sure I wouldn’t have the energy and effectiveness I do without that. Over the years, I’ve added in little pieces. Like my weekly virtual sessions where I “do my homework” with a group of kids, working on something that I need to get done, but that doesn’t quite fit elsewhere. Or my weekly sessions with local kids, talking about things that make me and them think. Or, for that matter, my “call while driving” list of calls it’s good to make, but wouldn’t usually quite get the priority to happen. </p>
<p>Doing all the things I do is hard work. But it’s what I want to do. Yes, things can drag from time to time. But at this point I’m so used to the rhythm of projects that I don’t think I notice much. And, yes, I work basically every hour of every day I can. Do I have hobbies? Well, back when I was an academic, business was my main “hobby”. When I started CEOing, science became a “hobby”. Writing. Education. Livestreaming. These were all “hobbies” too. But somehow one of the patterns of my life is that nothing really stays quite as a “true hobby”.</p>
<h2 id="whats-next">What’s Next?</h2>
<p>The past five years have not only been my most productive ever, but they’ve also built more “productivity momentum” than I’ve had before. So, what’s next? I have a lot of projects currently “in motion”, or ready to “get into motion”. Then I have many more that are in gestation, for which the time may finally have come. But I know there’ll also be surprises: projects that suddenly occur to me, or that I suddenly realize are possible. And one of the great challenges is to be in a position to actually jump into such things. </p>
<p>It has to be said that there’s always a potentially complicated tradeoff. To what extent should one “tend” the things one’s already done, and to what extent should one do new things? Of course, there are some things that are never “done”—like the Wolfram Language, which I started building 38 years ago, and still (energetically) work on every day. Or the Physics Project, where there’s just so much to figure out. But one of the things that’s worked well in most of the basic science projects I’ve done in the past five years or is that once I’ve written my piece about the project, I can usually consider the project “done for now”. It always takes a lot of effort to get a project to the point where I can write about it. But I work hard to make sure I only have to do it once; that I’ve “picked the low-hanging fruit”, so I don’t feel I have to come back “to add a little more”.</p>
<p>I put a lot of effort into the pieces I write about my projects. And I also give talks, do interviews, etc. (about 500 altogether in the past five years). But I certainly don’t “market” my efforts as much as I could. It’s a decision I’ve made: that at this point in my life—particularly with the burst of productivity I’m experiencing—I want to spend as much of my time as possible doing new things. And so I need to count on others to follow up and spread knowledge about what I’ve done, whether in the academic world, on Wikipedia, the web, etc. (And, yes, pieces I write and the pictures they contain are <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/terms/">set up to be immediately reproducible wherever appropriate</a>.)</p>
<p>OK, so what specific new things are currently in my pipeline? Well, there’s lots of science (and related intellectual things). And there’s also lots of technology. But let’s talk about science first. </p>
<p>A big story is the Physics Project—where there’s a lot to be done, in many different directions. There’s foundational theory to be developed. And there are experimental implications to be found.</p>
<p>It’d be great if we could find experimental evidence of the discreteness of space, or maximum entanglement speed, or a host of other unexpected phenomena in our models. A century or so ago it was something of a stroke of luck that atoms were big enough that they could be detected. And we don’t know if the discreteness of space is something we’ll be able to detect now—or only centuries from now. </p>
<p>There are phenomena—particularly associated with black holes—that might effectively serve as powerful “spacetime microscopes”. And there are phenomena like dimension fluctuations that could potentially show up in a variety of astrophysical settings. But one direction I’m particularly interested in exploring is what one might call “spacetime heat”—the effect of detailed microscopic dynamics in the hypergraph that makes up spacetime. Could “dark matter”, for example, not be “matter” at all, but instead be associated with spacetime heat?</p>
<p>Part of investigating this involves building practical simulation software to investigate our models on as large a scale as possible. And part of it involves “good, old-fashioned physics”, figuring out how to go from underlying foundational effects to observable phenomena. </p>
<p>And there’s a foundational piece to this too. How does one set up mathematics—and mathematical physics—when one’s starting from a hypergraph? A traditional manifold is ultimately built up from Euclidean space. But what kind of object is the limit of a hypergraph? To understand this, we need to construct what I’m calling infrageometry—and infracalculus alongside it. Infrageometry—as its name suggests—starts from something lower level than traditional geometry. And the challenge is in effect to build a “21st century Euclid”, then Newton, etc.—eventually finding generalizations of things like differential geometry and algebraic topology that answer questions like what 3<img title="" src="https://content.wolfram.com/sites/43/2024/08/one-quarter-fraction.png" alt="" width="9" height="24">-dimensional curvature tensors are like, or how we might distinguish local gauge degrees of freedom from spatial ones in a limiting hypergraph.</p>
<p>Another direction has to do with particles—like electrons. The fact is that existing quantum field theory in a sense only really deals with particles indirectly, by thinking of them as perturbations in a field—which in turn is full of (usually unobservable) zero-point fluctuations. In our models, the structure of everything—from spacetime up—is determined by the “fluctuating” structure of the underlying hypergraph (or, more accurately, by the whole multiway graph of “possible fluctuations”). And what this suggests is that there’s in a sense a much lower level version of the Feynman diagrams we use in quantum field theory and where we can discuss the “effect of particles” without ever having to say exactly what a particle “is”.</p>
<p>I must say that I expected we’d have to know what particles were even to talk about energy. But it turned out there was a “bulk” way to do that. And maybe similarly there’s an indirect way to talk about interactions between particles. My guess is that in our model particles are structures a bit like black holes—but we may be able to go a very long way without having to know the details.</p>
<p>One of the important features of our models is that quantum mechanics is “inevitable” in them. And one of the projects I’m hoping to do is to finally “really understand quantum mechanics”. In general terms, it’s connected to the way branching observers (like us) perceive branching universes. But how do we get intuition for this, and what effects can we expect? Several projects over the past years (like <a href="https://www.wolframphysics.org/bulletins/2021/02/multiway-turing-machines/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">multiway Turing machines</a>, <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2022/06/games-and-puzzles-as-multicomputational-systems/">multiway games</a>, <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/11/aggregation-and-tiling-as-multicomputational-processes/">multiway aggregation</a>, etc.) I’ve done in large part to bolster my intuition about branchial space and quantum mechanics. </p>
<p>I first <a href="https://x.com/stephen_wolfram/status/1370144700003463168" target="_blank" rel="noopener">worked on quantum computers back in 1980</a>. And at the time, I thought that the measurement process (whose mechanism isn’t described in the standard formalism of quantum mechanics) would be a big problem for them. Years have gone by, and enthusiasm for quantum computers has skyrocketed. In our models there’s a rather clear picture that inside a quantum computer there are “many threads of history” that can in effect do computations in parallel. But for an observer like us to “know what the answer is” we have to knit those threads together. And in our models (particularly with my observer theory efforts) we start to be able to see how that might happen, and what the limitations might be.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, in the world at large there are all sorts of experimental quantum computers being built. But what are their limitations? I have a suspicion that there’s some as-yet-unknown fundamental physics associated with these limitations. It’s like building telescopes: you polish the mirror, and keep on making engineering tweaks. But unless you know about diffraction, you won’t understand why your resolution is limited. And I have a slight hope that even existing results on quantum computers may be enough to see limitations perhaps associated with <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2020/04/finally-we-may-have-a-path-to-the-fundamental-theory-of-physics-and-its-beautiful/#branchial-motion-and-the-entanglement-horizon">maximum entanglement speed</a> in our models. And the way our models work, knowing this speed, you can for example <a href="https://www.wolframphysics.org/technical-introduction/potential-relation-to-physics/units-and-scales/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">immediately deduce</a> the discreteness scale of space. </p>
<p>Back in 1982, I and another physicist wrote two papers on “Properties of the Vacuum”. <a href="https://content.wolfram.com/sw-publications/2020/07/properties-vacuum-mechanical-thermodynamic.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Part 1 was mechanical properties</a>. <a href="https://content.wolfram.com/sw-publications/2020/07/properties-vacuum-electrodynamic.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Part 2 was electrodynamic</a>. We announced a part 3, on gravitational properties. But we never wrote it. Well, finally, it looks as if our Physics Project shows us how to think about such properties. So perhaps it’s time to finally write “Part 3”, and respond to all those people who sent preprint request cards for it four decades ago. </p>
<p>One of the great conclusions of our Physics Project—and the concept of the ruliad—is that we have the laws of physics we do because we are observers of the kind we are. And just knowing very coarsely about us as observers seems to already imply the major laws of twentieth century physics. And to be able to say more, I think we need more characterization of us as observers. And my guess is, for example, that some feature of us that we probably consider completely obvious is what leads us to perceive space as (roughly) three dimensional. And indeed I increasingly suspect that the whole structure of our Physics Project can be derived—a bit like early derivations of special relativity—from certain axiomatic assumptions about our nature as observers, and fundamental features of computation.</p>
<p>There’s plenty to do on our Physics Project, and I’m looking forward to making progress with all of it. But the ideas of the Physics Project—and multicomputation in general—<a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2021/09/multicomputation-a-fourth-paradigm-for-theoretical-science/#potential-application-areas">apply to lots of other fields too</a>. And I have many projects planned on these.</p>
<p>Let’s talk first about chemistry. I never found chemistry interesting as a kid. But as we’ve added <a href="https://www.wolfram.com/language/core-areas/chemistry/">chemistry functionality in the Wolfram Language</a>, I’ve understood more about it, and why it’s interesting. And I’ve also followed molecular computing since the 1980s. And now, largely inspired by thinking about multicomputation, I’ve become very interested in what one might call the foundations of chemistry. Actually, what I’m most interested in is what I’m calling “subchemistry”. I suppose one can think of it as having a similar kind of relation to chemistry as infrageometry has to geometry. </p>
<p>In ordinary chemistry, one thinks about reactions between different species of molecules. And to calculate rates of reactions, one multiplies concentrations of different species, implicitly assuming that there’s perfect randomness in which specific molecules interact. But what if one goes to a lower level, and starts talking about the interactions not of species of molecules, but individual molecules? From our Physics Project we get the idea of making causal graphs that represent the causal relations between different specific interaction events. </p>
<p>In a gas the assumption of molecular-level randomness will probably be pretty good. But even in a liquid it’ll be more questionable. And in more exotic materials it’ll be a completely different story. And I suspect that there are “subchemical” processes that can potentially be important, perhaps in a sense finding a new “slice of computational reducibility” within the general computational irreducibility associated with the Second Law.</p>
<p>But the most important potential application of subchemistry is in biology. If we look at biological tissue, a basic question might be: “What phase of matter is it?” One of the major takeaways from molecular biology in the last few decades has been that in biological systems, molecules (or at least large ones) are basically never just “bouncing around randomly”. Instead, their motion is typically carefully orchestrated. </p>
<p>So when we look at biological tissue—or a biological system—we’re basically seeing the result of “bulk orchestration”. But what are the laws of bulk orchestration? We don’t know. But I want to find out. I think the “<a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/02/computational-foundations-for-the-second-law-of-thermodynamics/#class-4-and-the-mechanoidal-phase">mechanoidal phase</a>” that I identified in studying the Second Law is potentially a good test case. </p>
<p>If we look at a microprocessor, it’s not very useful to describe it as “containing a gas of electrons”. And similarly, it’s not useful to describe a biological cell as “being liquid inside”. But just what kind of theory is needed to have a more useful description we don’t know. And my guess is that there’ll be some new level of abstraction that’s needed to think about this (perhaps a bit like the new abstraction that was needed to formulate information theory).</p>
<p>Biology is not big on theory. Yes, there’s natural selection. And there’s the digital nature of biomolecules. But mostly biology has ended up just accumulating vast amounts of data (using ever better instrumentation) without any overarching theory. But I suspect that in fact there’s another foundational theory to be found in biology. And if we find it, a lot of the data that’s been collected will suddenly fall into place.</p>
<p>There’s the “frankly molecular” level of biology. And there’s the more “functional” level. And I was surprised recently to be able to find a very minimal model that seems to capture <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2024/05/why-does-biological-evolution-work-a-minimal-model-for-biological-evolution-and-other-adaptive-processes/">“functional” aspects of biological evolution</a>. It’s a surprisingly rich model, and there’s much more to explore with it, notably about how different “ideas” get propagated and developed in the process of adaptive evolution—and what kinds of tree-of-life-style branchings occur. </p>
<p>And then there’s the question of <a href="https://www.wolframscience.com/nks/notes-12-10--self-reproduction/">self replication</a>—a core feature of biology. Just how simple a system can exhibit it in a “biologically relevant way”? I had thought that self replication was “just relevant for biology”. But in thinking about the problem of observers in the ruliad, I’ve come to realize that it’s also relevant at a foundational level there. It’s no good to just have one observer; you have to have a whole “rulial flock” of similar ones. And to get similar ones you need something like self replication. </p>
<p>Talking of “societies of observers” brings me to another area I want to study: economics. How does a coherent economic system emerge from all the microscopic transactions and other events in a society? I suspect it’s a story that’s in the end similar to the theories we’ve studied in physics—from the emergence of bulk properties in fluids, to the emergence of continuum spacetime, and so on. But now in economics we’re dealing not with fluid density or metric, but instead with things like price. I don’t yet know how it will work out. Maybe computational reducibility will be associated with value. Maybe computational irreducibility will be what determines robustness of value. But I suspect that there’s a way of thinking about “economic observers” in the ruliad—and figuring out what “natural laws” they’ll “inevitably observe”. And maybe some of those natural laws will be relevant in thinking about the kind of questions we humans care about in economics.</p>
<p>It’s rather amazing in how many different areas one seems to be able to apply the kind of approach that’s emerged from the Physics Project, the ruliad, etc. One that I’ve very <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2024/08/whats-really-going-on-in-machine-learning-some-minimal-models/">recently tackled is machine learning</a>. And in my effort to understand its foundations, I’ve ended up coming up with some very minimal models. My purpose was to understand the essence of machine learning. But—somewhat to my surprise—it looks as if these minimal models can actually be practical ways to do machine learning. Their hardware-level tradeoffs are somewhat different. But—given my interest in practical technology—I want to see if one can build out a practical machine-learning framework that’s based on these (fundamentally discrete) models. </p>
<p>And while I’m not currently planning to investigate this myself, I suspect that the approach I’ve used to study machine learning can also be applied to neuroscience, and perhaps to linguistics. And, yes, there’ll probably be a lot of computational irreducibility in evidence. And once again one has to hope that the pockets of computational reducibility that exist will give rise to “natural laws” that are useful for what we care about in these fields. </p>
<p>In addition to these “big” projects, I’m also hoping to do a variety of “smaller” projects. Many I started decades ago, and in fact mentioned in <em>A New Kind of Science</em>. But now I feel I have the tools, intuition and intellectual momentum to finally finish them. <a href="https://www.wolframscience.com/nks/p130--recursive-sequences/">Nestedly recursive functions</a>. <a href="https://www.wolframscience.com/nks/p221--systems-based-on-constraints/">Deterministic random tilings</a>. <a href="https://www.wolframscience.com/nks/notes-12-8--undecidability-in-natural-systems/">Undecidability in the three-body problem</a>. <a href="https://www.wolframscience.com/nks/notes-6-8--structures-in-the-game-of-life/">“Meta-engineering” in the Game of Life</a>. These might on their own seem esoteric. But my repeated experience—particularly in the past five years—is that by solving problems like these one builds examples and intuition that have surprisingly broad application.</p>
<p>And then there are history projects. Just what did happen to theories of discrete space in the early twentieth century (and how close did people like Einstein get to the ideas of our Physics Project)? What was “ancient history” of neural nets, and why did people come to assume they should be based on continuous real numbers? I fully expect that as I investigate these things, I’ll encounter all sorts of “if only” situations—where for example some unpublished note languishing in an archive (or attic) would have changed the course of science if it had seen the light of day long ago. And when I find something like this, it’s yet more motivation to actually finish those projects of mine that have been languishing so long in the filesystem of my computer. </p>
<p>There’s a lot I want to do “down in the computational trenches”, in physics, chemistry, biology, economics, etc. But there are also things at a more abstract level in the ruliad. There’s more to study about metamathematics, and about how mathematics that we humans care about can emerge from the ruliad. And there are also foundational questions in computer science. P vs. NP, for example, can be formulated as an essentially geometric problem in the ruliad—and conceivably there are mathematical methods (say from higher category theory) that might give insight into it. </p>
<p>Then there are questions about hyperruliads and hyporuliads. In a hyperruliad that’s based on hypercomputation, there will be hyperobservers. But is there a kind of “rulial relativity” that makes their perception of things just the same as “ordinary observers” in the ordinary ruliad? A way to get some insight into this may be to study hyporuliads—versions of the ruliad in which there are only limited levels of computation possible. A bit like the way a spacelike singularity associated with a black hole supports only limited time histories, or a decidable axiomatic theory supports only proofs of limited length, there will be limitations in the hyporuliad. And by studying them, there’s a possibility that we’ll be able to see more about issues like what kinds of mathematical axioms can be compatible with observers like us. </p>
<p>It’s worth commenting that our Physics Project—and the ruliad—have all sorts of connections and resonances with long-studied ideas in philosophy. “Didn’t Kant talk about that? Isn’t that similar to Leibniz?”, etc. I’ve wanted to try to understand these historical connections. But while I’ve done a lot of work on the historical development of ideas, the ideas in question have tended to be more focused, and more tied to concrete formalism than they usually are in philosophy. “Did Kant actually mean that, or something completely different?” You might have to understand all his works to know. And that’s more than I think I can do.</p>
<p>I invented the concept of the ruliad as a matter of science. But it’s now clear that the ruliad has all sorts of connections and resonances not only with philosophy but also with theology. Indeed, in a great many belief systems there’s always been the idea that somehow in the end “everything is one”. In cases where this gets slightly more formalized, there’s often some kind of combinatorial enumeration involved (think: <em>I Ching</em>, or various versions of “counting the names of God”). </p>
<p>There are all sorts of examples where long-surviving “ancient beliefs” end up having something to them, even if the specific methods of post-1600s science don’t have much to say about them. One example is the notion of a soul, which we might now see as an ancient premonition of the modern notion of abstract computation. And whenever there’s a belief that’s ancient, there’s likely to have been lots of thinking done around it over the millennia. So if we can, for example, see a connection to the ruliad, we can expect to leverage that thinking. And perhaps also be able to provide new input that can refine the belief system in interesting and valuable ways. </p>
<p>I’m always interested in different viewpoints about things—whether from science, philosophy, theology, wherever. And an extreme version of this is to think about how other “alien” minds might view things. Nowadays I think of different minds as effectively being at different places in the ruliad. Humans with similar backgrounds have minds that are close in rulial space. Cats and dogs have minds that are further away. And the weather (with <a href="https://www.wolframscience.com/nks/p845--historical-perspectives/">its “mind of its own”</a>) is still further. </p>
<p>Now that we have AIs we potentially have a way to study the correspondence—and communication—between “different minds”. I looked at one aspect of this in my <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/07/generative-ai-space-and-the-mental-imagery-of-alien-minds/">“cats” piece</a>. But my <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2024/08/whats-really-going-on-in-machine-learning-some-minimal-models/">recent work on the foundations of machine learning</a> suggests a broader approach, that can also potentially tell us things about the fundamental character of language, and about how it serves as a medium that can “<a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2021/11/the-concept-of-the-ruliad/#communicating-across-rulial-space">transport thoughts</a>” from one mind to another.</p>
<p>Many non-human animals seem to have at least some form of language—though mostly in effect just a few standalone words. But pretty unquestionably the greatest single invention of our species is language—and particularly compositional language where words and phrases can fit together in an infinite number of ways. But is there something beyond compositional language? And, for example, where might we get if our brains were bigger?</p>
<p>With the 100 billion neurons in our brains, we seem to be able to handle about 50,000 words. If we had a trillion neurons we’d probably be able to handle more words (though perhaps more slowly), in effect letting us describe more things more easily. But what about something fundamentally beyond compositional language? Something perhaps “higher order”? </p>
<p>With a word we are in effect conflating all instances of a certain concept into a single object that we can then work with. But typically with ordinary words we’re dealing with what we might call “static concepts”. So what about “ways of thinking”, or paradigms? They’re more like active, functional concepts. And it’s a bit like dogs versus us: dogs deal with a few standalone words; we “package” those together into whole sentences and beyond. And at the next level, we could imagine in effect packaging things like generators of meaningful sentences.</p>
<p>Interestingly enough, we have something of a preview of ideas like this—in computational language. And this is one of those places where my efforts in science—and philosophy—start to directly intersect with my efforts in technology.</p>
<p>The foundation of the Wolfram Language is the idea of representing everything in computational terms, and in particular in symbolic computational terms. And one feature of such a representation is that it can encompass both “data” and “code”—i.e. both things one might think about, and ways one might think about them. </p>
<p>I first started building Wolfram Language as a practical tool—though one very much informed by my foundational ideas. And now, four decades later, the Wolfram Language has emerged as the largest single project of my life, and something that, yes, I expect to always put immense effort into. It wasn’t long ago that we finally finished my 1991 to-do list for Wolfram Language—and we have many projects running now that will take years to complete. But the <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2020/10/our-mission-and-the-opportunity-of-artifacts-from-the-future/">mission has always remained the same</a>: to take the concept of computation and apply it as broadly as possible, through the medium of computational language. </p>
<p>Now, however, I have some additional context for that—viewing computational language as a bridge from what we humans think about to what’s possible in the computational universe. And this helps in framing some of the ways to expand the foundations of our computational language, for example to multicomputation, or to hypergraph-based representations. It also helps in understanding the character of current AI, and how it needs to interact with computational language.</p>
<p>In the Wolfram Language we’ve been steadily trying to create a representation for everything. And when it comes to definitive, objective things we’ve gotten a long way. But there’s more than that in everyday discourse. For example, I might say “I’m going to drink a glass of orange juice.” Well, we do just fine at <a href="https://www.wolfram.com/language/12/food-and-nutrition-entities/">representing “a glass of orange juice”</a> in the Wolfram Language, and we can compute lots of things—like nutrition content—about it. But what about “I’m going to drink…”? For that we need something different. </p>
<p>And, actually, I’ve been thinking for a shockingly long time about what one might need. I first considered the question in the early 1980s, in connection with “extending SMP to AI”. I learned about the attempts to make “philosophical languages” in the 1600s, and about some of the thinking around modern conlangs (constructed languages). Something that always held me back, though, was use cases. Yes, I could see how one could use things like this for tasks like customer service. But I wasn’t too excited about that. </p>
<p>But finally there was blockchain, and with it, smart contracts. And around 2015 I started thinking about how one might represent contracts in general not in legalese but in some precise computational way. And the result was that I began to <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2016/10/computational-law-symbolic-discourse-and-the-ai-constitution/">crispen my ideas about what I called “symbolic discourse language”</a>. I thought about how this might relate to questions like a “constitution for AIs” and so on. But I never quite got around to actually starting to design the specifics of the symbolic discourse language.</p>
<p>But then along came LLMs, together with my theory that their success had to do with a “semantic grammar” of language. And finally now we’ve launched a serious project to build a symbolic discourse language. And, yes, it’s a difficult language design problem, deeply entangled with a whole range of foundational issues in philosophy. But as, by now at least, the world’s most experienced language designer (for better or worse), I feel a responsibility to try to do it. </p>
<p>In addition to language design, there’s also the question of making all the various “symbolic calculi” that describe in appropriately coarse terms the operation of the world. Calculi of motion. Calculi of life (eating, dying, etc.). Calculi of human desires. Etc. As well as calculi that are directly supported by the computation and knowledge in the Wolfram Language.</p>
<p>And just as LLMs can provide a kind of conversational linguistic interface to the Wolfram Language, one can expect them also to do this to our symbolic discourse language. So the pattern will be similar to what it is for Wolfram Language: the symbolic discourse language will provide a formal and (at least within its purview) correct underpinning for the LLM. It may lose the poetry of language that the LLM handles. But from the outset it’ll get its reasoning straight.</p>
<p>The symbolic discourse language is a broad project. But in some sense breadth is what I have specialized in. Because that’s what’s needed to build out the Wolfram Language, and that’s what’s needed in my efforts to pull together the foundations of so many fields. </p>
<p>And in maintaining a broad range of interests there are some where I imagine that someday there’ll be a project I can do, but there may for example be many years of “ambient technology” that are needed before that project will be feasible. Usually, though, I have some “conceptual idea” of what the project might be. For example, I’ve followed robotics, imagining that one day there’ll be a way to do “general-purpose robotics”, perhaps constructing everything out of modular elements. I’ve followed biomedicine, partly out of personal self interest, and partly because I think it’ll relate to some of the foundational questions I’m asking in biology. </p>
<p>But in addition to all the projects where the goal is basic research, or technology development, I’m also hoping to pursue my interests in education. Much of what I hope to do relates to content, but some of it relates to access and motivation. I don’t have perfect evidence, but I strongly believe there’s a lot of young talent out there in the world that never manages to connect for example with things like the educational programs we put on. We–and I—have tried quite hard over the years to “bridge the gap”. But with the world as it is, it’s proved remarkably difficult. But it’s still a problem I’d like to solve, and I’ll keep picking away at it, hoping to change for the better some kids’ “trajectories”. </p>
<p>But about content I believe my path is clearer. With the modern Wolfram Language I think we’ve gone a long way towards being able to take computational thinking about almost anything, and being able to represent it in a formalized way, and compute from it. But how do people manage to do the computational thinking in the first place? Well, like mathematical thinking and other formalized kinds of thinking, they <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2016/09/how-to-teach-computational-thinking/">have to learn how to do it</a>. </p>
<p>For years people have been telling me I should “write the book” to teach this. And finally in January of this year I started. I’m not sure how long it will take, but I’ll soon be starting to post sections I’ve written so far.</p>
<p>My goal is to create a general book—and course—that’s an introduction to computational thinking at a level suitable for typical first-year college students. Lots of college students these days say they want to study “computer science”. But really it’s computational X for some field X that they’re ultimately interested in. And neither the theoretical nor the engineering aspects of typical “computer science” are what’s most relevant to them. What they need to know is computational thinking as it might be applied to computational X—not “CS” but what one might call “CX”. </p>
<p>So what will CX101 be like? In some ways more like a philosophy course than a CS one. Because in the end it’s about generally learning to think, albeit in the new paradigm of computation. And the point is that once someone has a clear computational conceptualization of something, then it’s our job in the Wolfram Language to make sure that <a href="https://www.wolfram.com/language/elementary-introduction/3rd-ed/">it’s easy for them to concretely implement it</a>. </p>
<p>But how does one teach computational conceptualization? What I’ve concluded is that one needs to anchor it in actual things in the world. Geography. Video. Genomics. Yes, there are principles to explain. But they need practical context to make them useful, or even understandable. And what I’m finding is that framing everything computationally makes things incredibly much easier to explain than before. (A test example coming soon is whether I can easily explain math ideas like algebra and calculus this way.)</p>
<p>OK, so that’s a lot of projects. But I’m excited about all of them, and can’t wait to make them happen. At an age when many of my contemporaries are retiring, I feel like I’m just getting started. And somehow the way my projects keep on connecting back to things I did decades ago makes me feel—in a computational irreducibility kind of way—that there’s something necessary about all the steps I’ve taken. I feel like the things I’ve done have let me climb some hills. But now there are many more hills that have come into view. And I look forward to being able to climb those too. For myself and for the world.</p>
        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cassette Tape Archive (130 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://www.tapedeck.org/index.php</link>
            <guid>41405961</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 01:18:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://www.tapedeck.org/index.php">http://www.tapedeck.org/index.php</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41405961">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <p id="intro"><img src="http://www.tapedeck.org/img/hl_about-tapedeck.gif" alt="about tapedeck">
        <br>
        Tapedeck.org is a project of <a href="http://www.neckcns.com/" target="_blank">neckcns.com</a>, built to showcase the amazing beauty and (sometimes) weirdness found in the <strong>designs of the common <a href="#" onclick="MM_showHideLayers('intro','','hide','about','','hide','audiotape','','show','sendusyourtapes','','hide'); return false">audio tape cassette</a></strong>. There's an amazing range of designs, starting from the early 60's functional cassette designs, moving through the colourful playfulness of the 70's audio tapes to amazing shape variations during the 80's and 90's. We hope you enjoy these tapes as much as we do!</p>
        <div id="audiotape"><p><img src="http://www.tapedeck.org/img/hl_about-audio-tapes.gif" alt="about audio tapes">
        <br>
        The <strong>compact audio cassette medium</strong> for audio storage was introduced by Philips in 1963 under the name <strong>Compact Cassette</strong>. Although there were other magnetic tape cartridge systems at the time, the Compact Cassette became dominant as a result of Philips' decision (in the face of pressure from Sony) to license the format free of charge. It went on to become a popular (and re-recordable) alternative to the vinyl record deck during the 1970s. During the 1980s, its popularity grew further as a result of the <strong>Sony Walkman</strong>, with cassette sales overtaking those of LPs. (Vinyl overall remained ahead due to greater sales of singles, although cassette singles achieved popularity for a period in the 1990s).
        </p><p>
        
        The mass production of compact audio cassettes <strong>began in 1965</strong> in Hannover, Germany, as did commercial sales of prerecorded music cassettes (also known as musicassettes; MC for short). The system had been initially designed for dictation and portable use, thus the audio quality of early recorders was not well suited for music. Some early models also had unreliable mechanical design. As time went on, various improvements (in particular, the introduction of <strong>Dolby noise reduction</strong>) resulted in the format being taken seriously for musical use.
        </p><p>
        
        Although its use in the West has declined as a result of more advanced technologies, it remains widespread, and is still the dominant medium for listening to music in many third world countries.
        </p><p>
        
        In essence, the audio cassette is simply a cassette-based (and smaller) version of the older reel-to-reel tape format. It consists of two miniature reels, between which an oxide-coated plastic tape, or magnetic tape, is passed and wound. These reels (along with some other mechanical parts) are held inside a protective plastic shell.
        </p><p>
        
        Four single audio tracks are available on the tape. These are paired to produce two stereophonic tracks – one played when the cassette is inserted with its 'A' side facing up, and the other when it is turned over (with the 'B' side up), thus mimicking gramophone records.
        </p><p>
        
        <span>(Source: Wikipedia, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Compact_cassette" target="_blank">right here</a>. Wikipedia <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Copyrights" target="_blank">Copyright</a> stipulations apply.)</span></p></div>
        <div id="sendusyourtapes"><p><img src="http://www.tapedeck.org/img/hl_send-us-your-tapes.gif" alt="send us your tapes">
        <br>
        <strong>Have you got some cool audio tapes lying around?</strong> Send us a picture then, we'd love to get e-mail from you!
        </p><p>
        
        Please take a picture of your tape on white background from straight above without using a flash. The tape should measure about 800x600 pixels on the image. Please try to use as little JPG compression as possible (quality 10 or better when saving from Photoshop) and send the files to <a href="mailto:tapes@tapedeck.org">tapes@tapedeck.org</a></p><p>
        
        Thanks you all so much for the contributions tapedeck.org has already received - without your input this site would be impossible. Thank you very much: Alexandru, Diego, Ahmed, George, Dominik, Marcello, Jouse, Pascal, Niko, Jaromir, Tim, Paul, Luciano, Marc, Andreas, Colin, Alexander, Roland, Maurice, Sven, Radu, Daniel, Scott, Reinhard and Ronny!</p></div>
    </div><div id="news"> <!-- ################################# -->
<div>
<h2>tapedeck.org responsive layout</h2>
<p>after changing the ad layout (which only supports the site and does NOT make me rich, by the way) on <a href="http://tapedeck.org/">tapedeck</a> to inline, tape-sized ads i was finally able to make tapedeck even more responsive: sizing your browser now gives you 1, 3, 4, 5 or 6 columns of tapes, depending on the space available. go ahead and try it! a few pics are on <a href="http://on.fb.me/V8da8z">facebook</a></p>
</div><div>
<h2>Isolating Tapes 101</h2>
<p>[photo album] <a href="http://on.fb.me/MX2BHS">http://on.fb.me/MX2BHS</a> — isolating this <a href="http://tapedeck.org/denon/">denon</a> tape was a real piece of work. Still, properly isolated tapes make better tees! Remember that. New Stuff coming soon to <a href="http://tapedeck.org/tapewear/">Tapewear</a>!</p>
</div><div>
<h2>Updates first on Facebook</h2>
<p>to stay up to date with the tapes we post, be a fan of <a href="http://www.facebook.com/tapedeck.org">tapedeck on Facebook</a> — all updates are posted there first, sometimes days before officially appearing on the site! on Facebook, you'll also get updates on the tapes we're going to post in the future: <a href="http://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.245367002165067.51553.207335379301563&amp;type=3">the shape of tapes to come</a>.</p>
</div>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Expect – Linux tool for automating interactive programs (158 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://linux.die.net/man/1/expect</link>
            <guid>41405364</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 23:17:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://linux.die.net/man/1/expect">https://linux.die.net/man/1/expect</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41405364">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://linux.die.net/man/1/expect: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Crows are even smarter than we thought (465 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nautil.us/crows-are-even-smarter-than-we-thought-820066/</link>
            <guid>41405195</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 22:46:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nautil.us/crows-are-even-smarter-than-we-thought-820066/">https://nautil.us/crows-are-even-smarter-than-we-thought-820066/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41405195">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
  <div>
    <p>Sign up for the free <i>Nautilus</i> newsletter:</p>
    <p>science and culture for people who love beautiful writing.</p>
    
  </div>
  <p><img src="https://nautil.us/wp-content/themes/nautilus-block-theme/blocks/speedbump/assets/icon.svg">
  </p>
</div><div>
                        
            <p><span>C</span>rows and ravens, which belong to the corvid family, are known for their high intelligence, playful natures, and strong personalities. They hold grudges against each other, do basic statistics, perform acrobatics, and even host funerals for deceased family members. But we keep <a href="https://nautil.us/why-neuroscientists-need-to-study-the-crow-235845/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">learning new things</a> about the savvy of these birds, and how widespread that savvy is among the corvid family.</p><p>Earlier this year, a team of researchers from Lomonosov Moscow State University in Russia and the University of Bristol <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10071-024-01874-6" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">found that</a> a species of crow called the hooded crow—which has a gray bust and black tail and head feathers, making it look like it is wearing a “hood”—is able to manage a mental feat we once thought was unique to humans: to memorize the shape and size of an object after it is taken away—in this case a small piece of colored paper—and to reproduce one like it.</p>
      
    <p>This kind of feat, according to animal behavior researchers, requires the ability to form “mental templates.”<strong> </strong>Essentially, a mental template is an image in the mind of what a particular object looks like, even when that object is not present. <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-018-27405-1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mental templates</a> allow animals to <a href="https://academic.oup.com/icb/article/61/3/825/6273191?login=true" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">create tools</a>, which can be used to get food or make a stronger nest, both ultimately leading to a better chance of survival. They might also make it possible for individuals to learn about tool making from other members of their species—and to pass along improvements in tool making over time, often called “cumulative culture,” which so far seems rare among non-human animals.</p><blockquote>
<p>Young crows learn how to make different types of tools by stealing their parent’s tools.</p>
</blockquote>
          <p>We have been looking for evidence that different corvid and other bird species can create mental templates since at least 2002. That year, researchers published <a href="https://www.bioteach.ubc.ca/TeachingResources/GeneralScience/CrowsToolPaper.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">findings</a> showing that Betty, a captive New Caledonian crow, was able to spontaneously bend a piece of wire to create a hook that she could use to grab a hard-to-reach treat. Betty had successfully used a pre-made hook to obtain the treat in earlier trials but in follow-up tasks didn’t seem to fully understand how hooks work.&nbsp; The researchers decided she must have formed a mental template of the hook, which she then reproduced. So far, researchers have found that<strong> </strong>Goffin cockatoos, a kind of parrot, can also create tools spontaneously, which could indicate similar mental agility.</p><p>But the new hooded crow findings suggest that the ability to learn this way could be more widespread than we thought, says Sarah Jelbert, a comparative psychologist who studies animal behavior at the University of Bristol and is one of the authors of the study. Creating and using mental templates might be a skill that evolved in the ancestor of all corvids, the “Corvida” branch of songbirds<strong>,</strong> or perhaps it is even shared more broadly across the animal kingdom, she says.</p><p>For their study, Jelbert and her colleagues first trained three hooded crows—Glaz (15 years old), Rodya (4 years old), and Joe (3 years old)—to recognize pieces of paper of different sizes and colors. To do this, they exposed the birds to “template” pieces of paper in different colors and sizes for several minutes before removing them—and then rewarded the birds for dropping scraps that matched these templates into a small slit.</p><figure><img width="800" height="536" alt="In Body Image" src="https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/Castleberry_BREAKER.png?auto=compress&amp;fit=scale&amp;fm=png&amp;h=686&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;w=1024&amp;wpsize=large" srcset="https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/Castleberry_BREAKER.png?q=65&amp;auto=format&amp;w=1600 800w,https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/Castleberry_BREAKER.png?q=65&amp;auto=format&amp;w=1200 600w,https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/Castleberry_BREAKER.png?q=65&amp;auto=format&amp;w=800 400w" loading="lazy"><figcaption><strong>BIRD BRAINS: </strong>A New Caledonian crow creating a scrap of colored paper that matches the template with which it was trained. <em>Photo by Sarah Jelbert, University of Bristol.</em></figcaption></figure>
          <p>The crows were next given the opportunity to manufacture versions of these objects in exchange for a reward. The researchers found that all three crows manufactured objects that matched the original template object they had been rewarded for in both color and size—even though the treats in this second stage of the experiment were awarded at random. The researchers also observed that Glaz, the oldest of the three hooded crows, seemed to be the most proficient at making scraps that looked like the ones the bird was trained on. This finding suggested to them that mental templates may be linked to experience garnered with age.</p><p>“Unlike humans, who regularly copy each other’s behavior … we don’t have much evidence that crows will watch each other and deliberately copy what another crow is doing,” Jelbert says. However, they will steal each other’s tools—in particular, juvenile crows often steal their parents’ tools when they are young. So it’s possible that young crows learn how to make different types of tools from experience stealing their parent’s tools, using them, remembering what these tools look like, and then trying to create something similar, Jelbert says.</p><p>What qualifies as a mental template, and how flexible these templates are, seems to be up for some debate. Research suggests birdsong and mating practices may rely on certain kinds of mental templates, which can backfire if a bird memorizes behavior from the wrong species. “For example, if a song sparrow gets imprinted on the song of a swamp sparrow and sings a song from a different species rather than its own, it will have difficulty finding mating partners,” explains Andreas Nieder, a professor of animal psychology at the University of Tübingen and a lead researcher on corvid neuroscience, who was not involved in this study. “Similarly, if one finch species gets sexually imprinted on another, it may show courtship displays to the <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0065345408600091?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">wrong species</a> in adulthood.”</p><p>Nieder says this kind of imprinting can become fixed in the bird’s brain, and is not changeable even in new environments. “In this case, templates may no longer represent intelligence but rather the opposite,” he adds. Researchers have not yet determined whether mental templates related to tool making remain flexible, though there is some evidence in New Caledonian crows that they may evolve.</p>
          <p>For biologists and comparative psychologists, understanding the ways corvids use mental templates can help to illuminate not just the nature of bird intelligence, but of intelligence across the animal kingdom and evolutionary time. <img decoding="async" src="https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/nautilus-favicon-14.png?fm=png" alt=""></p><p><em>Lead image: RuqayaMai / Shutterstock</em></p>              
                            <ul>
                                      <li>
                      <div>
                        <h6>
                          Kenna Hughes-Castleberry                        </h6>
                        <p>
                          Posted on <time datetime="2024-08-28T15:44:36-05:00">August 28, 2024</time>
                        </p>
                      </div>
                                                <p>
                            Kenna Hughes-Castleberry is freelance science journalist who covers quantum technology, AI, diversity within the tech industries, animal intelligence, corvids, and cephalopods. Her work has been featured in various publications, including <i>National Geographic, Scientific American, New Scientist, Discover Magazine, Ars Technica,</i> and <i>Hakai Magazine</i>, among others.                          </p>
                                            </li>
                                  </ul>
            <div>
  <p><img src="https://nautil.us/wp-content/themes/nautilus-block-theme/images/icons/logo-icon.svg" alt="new_letter"></p><div>
    <h4>Get the Nautilus newsletter</h4>
    <p>Cutting-edge science, unraveled by the very brightest living thinkers.</p>
  </div>

  
</div>        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>