<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2024 00:30:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[LLMs aren't "trained on the internet" anymore (121 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://allenpike.com/2024/llms-trained-on-internet</link>
            <guid>40549021</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 20:59:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://allenpike.com/2024/llms-trained-on-internet">https://allenpike.com/2024/llms-trained-on-internet</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40549021">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>A path to continued model improvement.</p><div>
<p>I often see a misconception when people try to reason about the capability of LLMs, and in particular how much future improvement to expect.</p>

<p>It’s frequently said that that LLMs are “trained on the internet,” and so they’ll always be bad at producing content that is rare on the web. A recent <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40333672">example from Hacker News</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>LLMs are mostly trained on Internet posts, so they are Internet simulators.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Wikipedia also <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Large_language_model">frames LLM training this way</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>LLMs are trained on increasingly large corpora of text largely scraped from the web.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Even former Apple SVP of Engineering – and famously sharp computer scientist – Bertrand Serlet explains them thus, in his recent video <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QwtyIDmhxh4">Why AI Works</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>[An LLM has] been trained on the entire internet, so it has packed all this knowledge that’s in the internet, but also all the reasoning patterns that can be found [there.]</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Admittedly, this used to be true! And is still <em>mostly</em> true. But it’s increasingly becoming less true.</p>

<p>Because it’s becoming less true, the idea of an “internet simulator” is not a useful way to predict how GPT-5 and beyond will work. New models are already exceeding this definition, and the shift is only beginning.</p>

<h2 id="the-data-wall">The Data Wall</h2>

<p>Way back in 2020, OpenAI’s <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2005.14165">GPT-3 paper</a> described their training dataset in some detail. GPT-3 was, basically, trained on the internet.</p>

<div>
<p><img src="https://allenpike.com/images/2024/gpt3-data.png"></p><p>An artifact from a bygone era, when frontier AI was open.</p>
</div>

<p>By 2022, LLMs were being <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.02155">trained to follow instructions</a> using custom human feedback. Since then, frontier model labs like OpenAI have gotten very cagey about what they’re adding to their training datasets. We don’t know what GPT-4o was trained on, let alone Sora or GPT-5.</p>

<p>But we do know <strong>it’s not just the internet</strong>.</p>

<p>Recently, LLM trainers have hit a “<a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/4/1/24117828/the-internet-may-not-be-big-enough-for-the-llms">data wall</a>”. More data generally improves model training, but OpenAI already has roughly all the data on the web – even inconvenient-to-access data like <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/4/6/24122915/openai-youtube-transcripts-gpt-4-training-data-google">Youtube video transcriptions</a>. So other than training ever-larger models on the same internet data, how can they make better LLMs?</p>

<p>The answer, for labs with money, is acquiring and creating non-public data. At first, their focus was making existing training data more useful, or adding existing non-public data to the training pool. For example:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Annotation and filtering</strong>: Researchers have been creating annotations for their training data for years. Good annotations let them focus LLM training on the highest value data, which allows for better (or smaller) models.</li>
  <li><strong>RLHF</strong>: Labs also have humans rate model outputs. They use this data to fine-tune the models, and encourage useful behaviours like instruction-following and refusing to say naughty things.</li>
  <li><strong>Usage data</strong>: ChatGPT is <a href="https://www.interconnects.ai/p/the-data-wall">said to</a> generate on the order of 10 billion tokens of data per day – even before they opened their more compelling GPT-4o model to free users.</li>
  <li><strong>Data acquisition</strong>: While a lot of humanity’s data is on the internet, much of it is not. Emails, chat logs, proprietary manuals and procedures, JIRA tickets, phone recordings, internal reports, and contracts are all useful data. While examples exist on the internet, model trainers can cut deals to add more of these to their training data.</li>
</ol>

<p>So that’s all helpful.</p>

<p>But none of these techniques are a complete solution to a famous weakness of current models: the “<strong>LLMs suck at producing outputs that don’t look like existing data</strong>” problem.</p>

<p>Here are some of the many things that LLMs are bad at doing, in part because there isn’t a lot of text online that demonstrates them:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Expressing doubt or uncertainty in one’s answer</li>
  <li>Having long conversations without repeating phrasings or looping</li>
  <li>Making high-level plans for LLM agents to pursue</li>
  <li>Reasoning like a Principal Engineer about a massive legacy codebase</li>
  <li>Reliably following extremely long or complex prompts</li>
</ol>

<p>While improved architectures and more parameters might help with these limitations, you can bet your butt that OpenAI, Meta, Google, and/or Microsoft are paying big money to fill some of these gaps in a simpler way: <strong>creating novel examples to train on</strong>.</p>

<h2 id="llms-are-now-being-trained-on-custom-data">LLMs are now being trained on custom data</h2>

<p>A recent example of the rise of custom data is Microsoft’s <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14219">Phi-3 Technical Report</a>, published in April. phi-3-mini is only 3.8 billion parameters – a waif in LLM terms – but claims performance competitive with the impressive but much-heavier Mixtral model. The paper credits some of this improvement to including high-quality synthetic data, generated by larger LLMs, in the training data. Synthetic data allows them to fill gaps in the internet-sourced data, and improves model performance for a given size.</p>

<p>Now, synthetic data is a hot topic in LLM research. It’s not yet clear how far you can go with training LLMs on their own output before things <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01413">go horribly wrong</a>, like a giant neural snake eating its own tail.</p>

<p>At the minimum, though, synthetic data will help fill the kind of gaps that arise simply from LLMs behaving like “internet simulators.” For example, if your model is hallucinating because you don’t have enough training examples of people expressing uncertainty, or biased because it has unrepresentative data, then generate some better examples!</p>

<p>Still, creating great synthetic data with LLMs is a challenging problem, and will have its limits. That’s why there’s one last huge source of non-internet data inbound: Humans.</p>

<h2 id="how-much-data-can-you-create-for-1byr">How much data can you create for $1B/yr?</h2>

<p>It turns out that if you pay people money, they’re willing to make data for you. <a href="https://scale.ai/">Scale.ai</a>, which bills itself as “the data foundry for AI,” operates a service where labs pay humans to do just this. Reportedly, AI companies are paying more than $1B a year for Scale’s services already. While some of this is for annotation and ratings on data that came from the web or LLMs, they also <a href="https://fortune.com/2024/05/21/scale-ai-funding-valuation-ceo-alexandr-wang-profitability/">create new training data whole-hog</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The company has shifted its focus to more highly-specialized workers such as Ph.D-level academics, lawyers, accountants, poets, authors, and those fluent in specific languages. These workers, who help train and test models for companies from OpenAI and Cohere to Anthropic and&nbsp;Google, also work through a third-party, often another Scale subsidiary called Outlier, but are paid higher hourly wages.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Not only can companies like OpenAI pay to have professionals create new, good data that fills holes in the internet-sourced data, they then keep that data to train subsequent models. A dataset like “50,000 examples of Ph.Ds expressing thoughtful uncertainty when asked questions they don’t know the answer to” could be worth a lot more than it costs to produce.</p>

<p>So yes, LLMs were originally trained on the internet. Yes, we can understand a lot of their early weaknesses as stemming from the foibles of whatever crap people post on the web.</p>

<p>However. As the size and impact of custom training data increases, we should expect LLMs to markedly exceed “internet simulation”. In particular, they’ll continue to get better at things that aren’t on the internet, but can be demonstrated in $1B+ of custom data creation.</p>

<p>That is to say: this train will keep rollin’ for a while yet.</p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Loss of nearly a full decade of information from early days of Chinese internet (178 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://chinamediaproject.org/2024/05/27/goldfish-memories/</link>
            <guid>40546920</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 16:13:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://chinamediaproject.org/2024/05/27/goldfish-memories/">https://chinamediaproject.org/2024/05/27/goldfish-memories/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40546920">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p>In a fitting illustration last week of the Chinese leadership’s unrelenting efforts to manipulate collective memory, an online essay with a shocking revelation about the wholesale disappearance of Chinese internet content spanning the 2000s was deleted by content monitors. But the post, quickly <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20240523001943/https:/mp.weixin.qq.com/s/afg3zHPpEyRzSfOR1Aeh3w">archived</a> and <a href="https://chinadigitaltimes.net/chinese/708143.html">shared</a>, reverberated in platforms beyond PRC-managed cyberspace.</p>



<p>Written by He Jiayan (何加盐), an internet influencer active since 2018, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20240523001943/https:/mp.weixin.qq.com/s/afg3zHPpEyRzSfOR1Aeh3w">the essay</a> concluded, based on a wide range of searches of various entertainment and cultural figures from the late 1990s through the mid-2000s, that nearly 100 percent of content from major internet portals and private websites from the first decade of China’s internet has now been obliterated. “No one has recognized a serious problem,” wrote He. “The Chinese-language internet is rapidly collapsing, and Chinese-language internet content predating the emergence of the mobile internet has almost entirely disappeared.”</p>



<p>Simple searches through the Baidu search engine for public figures such as Alibaba founder Jack Ma and Xiaomi CEO Lei Jun (雷军), who would have yielded perhaps millions of unique posts during the period of the “traditional internet” from the late 1990s through the end of the 2000s, turned up few if any results, He Jiayan revealed. These wholesale absences in Chinese-language content from inside China were repeated when He used non-Chinese search engines, including Google and Bing.</p>



<p>The post cited several reasons for this mass vanishing, including the phasing out of private websites and blog platforms as technologies developed, the shuttering of old and unprofitable platforms by commercial providers who have no commercial incentive to maintain archives, and a lack of social resources in China that might handle archiving as a preservation initiative (like <a href="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</a> in the United States). But as others <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fNQ6r-qSymw">commented outside</a> the Great Firewall, the most decisive factor in the loss of content and the failure to archive has been the Chinese Communist Party and its mandate for political and ideological control of history and public opinion.</p>



<p>Posted on Wednesday, May 22, He’s post had been removed from WeChat by the following day, yielding a 404 message that read: “This content violates regulations and cannot be viewed.”</p>



<div><figure><p><img loading="lazy" src="https://chinamediaproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/404-missing-internet-1024x439.jpg" alt="" width="548" height="235" srcset="https://chinamediaproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/404-missing-internet-1024x439.jpg 1024w, https://chinamediaproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/404-missing-internet-300x129.jpg 300w, https://chinamediaproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/404-missing-internet-768x329.jpg 768w, https://chinamediaproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/404-missing-internet.jpg 1438w" sizes="(max-width: 548px) 100vw, 548px"></p></figure></div>



<p>Acknowledging the various reasons for the widespread outage of content from the period of China’s traditional internet, the fact of this mass vanishing raises huge questions about the role of the internet in the formation of collective identity — and what it will mean for entire landscapes of history to be simply gone. “In the internet era to come, as people look back on the first two decades of the 21st century, it will be a 20-year period absent from the historical record,” He wrote. “If you still glimpse old information right now on the Chinese internet, these are just the last rays of the setting sun.”</p>



<p>___________</p>



<p>[A partial translation of He Jiayan’s post follows]</p>



<p><strong><em>“The Chinese Internet is Collapsing” (中文互联网正在加速崩塌)</em></strong></p>



<p><em>Let me ask you a small question:</em></p>



<p><em>If we search for the name “Jack Ma” (马云) on Baidu, and then set our search parameters from 1998 to 2005, how many pieces of information do you suppose we’ll turn up? 100 million? 10 million? One million?</em></p>



<p><em>I have asked in several groups, and most feel it should be somewhere in the neighborhood of millions or tens of millions. After all, the internet is such a vast reservoir of information. Jack Ma, as the stormy entrepreneur of that era, must have left a lot of traces on the Internet.</em></p>



<p><em>The full search results, in fact, are as follows:</em></p>



<div><figure><p><img loading="lazy" src="https://chinamediaproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Ma-Yun-2-1024x502.jpg" alt="" width="555" height="271" srcset="https://chinamediaproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Ma-Yun-2-1024x502.jpg 1024w, https://chinamediaproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Ma-Yun-2-300x147.jpg 300w, https://chinamediaproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Ma-Yun-2-768x377.jpg 768w, https://chinamediaproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Ma-Yun-2.jpg 1252w" sizes="(max-width: 555px) 100vw, 555px"></p></figure></div>



<p><em>Within the selected date range of “May 22, 1998 to May 22, 2005” on Baidu, there is just one positive result for “Jack Ma” (dated May 22, 2024).</em></p>



<p><em>This piece of information is also false. Click on the result and you’ll find it is an article posted in 2021, which does not fall within the specified time frame but is somehow, inexplicably, returned</em>.</p>



<p><em>This means that if we set out to understand Jack Ma’s experience over this particular time period — </em>i<em>ncluding news reports, public discussions, his speeches, company developments, and so on — the sum total of the material we derive from this search is zero.</em></p>



<p><em>You may imagine this is a problem unique to Baidu. But if you switch to Bing or Google, can you obtain search results?</em></p>



<p><em>I tested, these two sites to search for valid information, and both were not much different from Baidu. They had slightly more, but only in the single digits still. There were also more cases again of invalid information out of order [within the time frame], results that were wrongly pulled out of the search for some unspecified technical reason.</em></p>



<p><em>You might wonder if this could happen because Jack Ma is one of the more controversial people out there — that for some indescribable reason, his information is unsearchable.</em></p>



<p><em>But Jack Ma is in fact not an isolated case. If we search for [Tencent founder] Pony Ma (马化腾), [Xiaomi CEO] Lei Jun (雷军), [Huawei CEO] Ren Zhengfei (任正非), and so on, or even for figures like [Chinese entrepreneur and internet celebrity] Luo Yonghao (罗永浩) and Sister Fu Rong (芙蓉姐姐) who were hot topics at that time, and even if we search for internet stars like [Taiwanese singer and musician] Jay Chou (周杰伦) or [Super Girl contest winner] Li Yuchun (李宇春), we still get the same results.</em></p>



<p>W<em>hen we search for information about Lei Jun for the period, here are the results we get:</em></p>



<div><figure><p><img loading="lazy" src="https://chinamediaproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Lei-Jun-2-1024x424.jpg" alt="" width="753" height="311" srcset="https://chinamediaproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Lei-Jun-2-1024x424.jpg 1024w, https://chinamediaproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Lei-Jun-2-300x124.jpg 300w, https://chinamediaproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Lei-Jun-2-768x318.jpg 768w, https://chinamediaproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Lei-Jun-2-1536x636.jpg 1536w, https://chinamediaproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Lei-Jun-2.jpg 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 753px) 100vw, 753px"></p><figcaption>A search by He Jiayuan for Xiaomi CEO Lei Jun on Baidu turns up no results. </figcaption></figure></div>



<p><em>After testing various websites and people’s names, over varying time periods, I discovered a shocking phenomenon:</em></p>



<p><em>Nearly all of the Chinese websites that were popular back in those days — the likes of NetEase (网易), Sohu (搜狐), Campus BBS (校园BBS, Xici Hutong (西祠胡同), Kaidi Maoyan (凯迪猫眼), Tianya Forum (天涯论坛), SchoolNet (校内网), Sina blogs (新浪博客), Baidu Post (百度贴吧), and a massive number of personal websites — have completely vanished before a certain date, or in most cases have disappeared altogether. The only apparent exception is Sina.com, where you can still find some information from more than ten years ago, but still very little. More than 99.9999 percent of the other content from that time has disappeared.</em></p>



<p><em>No one has recognized a serious problem: the Chinese-language internet is rapidly collapsing, and Chinese-language internet content predating the emergence of the mobile Internet has almost entirely disappeared.</em></p>



<p><em>We once believed that the internet had a memory. We failed to realize that this memory was like the memory of a goldfish.</em></p>



<figure><p>
<iframe loading="lazy" title="互聯網是有記憶的？「中文互聯網正在加速崩塌」⋯⋯" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fNQ6r-qSymw?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</p><figcaption>A Chinese YouTube influencer reads He Jiayan’s deleted essay aloud, and comments on the case. </figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>[2</strong>]</p>



<p><em>This problem came to my attention because the subject of the He Jiayan public account is the research of leading lights in society. For this reason, I routinely need to research material about such figures.</em>&nbsp;</p>



<p><em>Over the past two years, I had a very distinct feeling: the amount of original material I could find online was declining in a sharp, cliff-like manner. Some of the original reports I had seen in the past were later slowly vanishing. The speeches that my target subjects had made in the past, or the articles they had written, were also becoming impossible to find. Video interviews and discussions I had seen before were also slowly disappearing.&nbsp;</em></p>



<p><strong><em>Perhaps there was a monster devouring webpages, and it was following the historical timeline — swallowing pages starting in the past and moving on toward the present, first in nibbles and then in great bites, chomping away the Chinese internet in five and ten-year chunks.</em>&nbsp;</strong></p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Frances Hesselbein's leadership story (2022) (115 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://davidepstein.substack.com/p/year-end-remembrances-part-3-the</link>
            <guid>40546415</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 15:14:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://davidepstein.substack.com/p/year-end-remembrances-part-3-the">https://davidepstein.substack.com/p/year-end-remembrances-part-3-the</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40546415">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe2dffd5b-1f62-449e-9eec-2f53446a8163_712x710.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe2dffd5b-1f62-449e-9eec-2f53446a8163_712x710.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe2dffd5b-1f62-449e-9eec-2f53446a8163_712x710.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe2dffd5b-1f62-449e-9eec-2f53446a8163_712x710.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe2dffd5b-1f62-449e-9eec-2f53446a8163_712x710.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe2dffd5b-1f62-449e-9eec-2f53446a8163_712x710.png" width="712" height="710" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/e2dffd5b-1f62-449e-9eec-2f53446a8163_712x710.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:710,&quot;width&quot;:712,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:923975,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe2dffd5b-1f62-449e-9eec-2f53446a8163_712x710.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe2dffd5b-1f62-449e-9eec-2f53446a8163_712x710.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe2dffd5b-1f62-449e-9eec-2f53446a8163_712x710.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe2dffd5b-1f62-449e-9eec-2f53446a8163_712x710.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a><figcaption>Frances Hesselbein’s Presidential Medal of Freedom. She was told to “come forward” rather than “up” to receive it, because she didn’t like hierarchical language.</figcaption></figure></div><p><span>This is the third and final part of my three-part series of remembrances. You can read parts 1 and 2 </span><a href="https://davidepstein.substack.com/p/year-end-remembrances-and-what-i" rel="">here</a><span> and </span><a href="https://davidepstein.substack.com/p/year-end-remembrances-part-2-lance" rel="">here</a><span>. This is also the last </span><em>Range Widely</em><span> post of the year. </span></p><p>I want to end this post with words from the woman featured in it. So I wish you a wonderful start to the new year, and I’m going to get the housekeeping out of the way up top. </p><p>If you appreciate this post, please share it: </p><p data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://davidepstein.substack.com/p/year-end-remembrances-part-3-the?utm_source=substack&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_content=share&amp;action=share&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Share&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:null,&quot;class&quot;:null}" data-component-name="ButtonCreateButton"><a href="https://davidepstein.substack.com/p/year-end-remembrances-part-3-the?utm_source=substack&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_content=share&amp;action=share" rel=""><span>Share</span></a></p><p>If you want to support Range Widely as a free or paid subscriber:</p><p>Let’s get to it…</p><p><span>If you read my book, </span><em>Range</em><span>, then you know Frances — who passed away on December 11 at the age of 107. But I want to keep telling parts of her story, because I think she was the kind of leader who over-performed and under-self-promoted. And I want to share a personal anecdote at the end that I didn’t share in the book.</span></p><p>But first, Frances’s story. (If you know it already, you can skip to the bottom section for the personal anecdote, and the quote I want to end the year with.):&nbsp;</p><p>Frances grew up in Johnstown, Pennsylvania. When she arrived at the University of Pittsburgh’s junior college (“Junior Pitt”), she dreamed of a bookish life as a playwright — until her father died her freshman year. She was 17, the oldest of three, and was stroking his cheek when he passed, promising to care for the family. So she dropped out.&nbsp;</p><p>She worked as an “adman’s assistant” at the Penn Traffic Company department store, until she got married. Just in time for her husband, John, to report to the Navy during World War II. John was a combat aircrew photographer, and when he came back, he set up a studio. Frances was the studio’s jack-of-all-trades, helping with anything from high school portraits, to documentary films, to weird customer requests — like the time a customer wanted a photo of a dog to look like a painting, so Frances grabbed oil paints and got it done.&nbsp;</p><p>Frances adored Johnstown’s diversity, but it afforded her some ugly lessons. John was on the new Pennsylvania Human Rights Commission. When a barber claimed he didn’t have the tools to serve Black customers, John said he’d better buy them. Frances decided then that a community that valued inclusiveness should answer “yes” to the question: “When they look at us, can they find themselves?”&nbsp;</p><p>Frances was 34 when a prominent woman in the community stopped by her home to ask if she would volunteer to lead Girl Scout Troop 17. The previous leader had left to be a missionary in India, and other neighbors had turned down the request. So did Frances, three times. She had an eight-year-old boy and professed to know nothing about little girls. Finally, the woman told her that the group of ten-year-old girls from modest families who met in a church basement would just have to be disbanded. Frances agreed to fill in for six weeks, until a real leader was found.&nbsp;</p><p>To prepare, she read up on the Girl Scouts. She learned that the organization was founded eight years before women could vote in the U.S., and that the founder had reminded girls that they could be “a doctor, a lawyer, an aviatrix, or a hot-air balloonist.” Frances thought back to second grade, when she announced that she wanted to be a pilot and her classmates laughed. She ended up sticking with Troop 17 for eight years, until they graduated high school.&nbsp;</p><p>Afterward, she kept picking up Girl Scout roles she didn’t seek out, often declined initially, and then ended up sticking with. She later described her life philosophy as: “doing what’s needed at the time.” She chaired a local United Way campaign at a time when that role was as foreign for women as aviatrix had once been.&nbsp;</p><p>In 1970, she declined a request to run the local Girl Scout council. She’d never take a “professional” job, she said. Then the businessmen entreating her said that the council would lose the United Way partnership if the finances weren’t fixed in a hurry. Frances agreed to fill in for six months, and then step aside for an experienced professional. At 54, she began what she called her first professional job. She stayed for four years, and fell in love with learning about management. Unfortunately, the overall picture for Girl Scouts was bleak.&nbsp;</p><p>Society had changed dramatically in the late 1960s and early 1970s. The Girl Scouts had not. Girls needed info on thorny topics like sex and drugs, and preparation for careers. Membership fell off a cliff. The national CEO position went vacant for nearly an entire year. In 1976, Frances was invited to interview for the position. She declined.&nbsp;</p><p>Previous CEOs had staggering leadership credentials. One had been founding director of the U.S. Coast Guard Women’s Reserve. Another had a PhD from MIT and worked with wartime technology. Frances was one of 335 local council leaders. But John told her that if she wanted to say “no,” he would drive her to New York City so she could do it in person.&nbsp;</p><p>With nothing to lose, she plainly told the committee everything that needed to change. They needed more math and science. They needed to lose the one hallowed handbook and get material that appealed to different demographics. They needed to dismantle the hierarchical leadership structure in favor of her “circular management,” where staff members are like beads on concentric circles, with many contacts at adjacent levels through whom they could get and give feedback. And when girls of all backgrounds looked at Girl Scouts, they needed to see themselves.&nbsp;</p><p>Frances arrived in Manhattan on July 4, 1976, as CEO of a 3 million member organization. Out went the lone handbook in favor of multiple handbooks targeted at different ages. She commissioned research on effective messaging that led to poetic marketing. A poster that targeted Native American girls read: “Your names are on the rivers.”&nbsp;</p><p><span>Diversity was great, Frances was told, but it was too much too soon. Fix the organizational problems first, then worry about diversity. But she decided that diversity </span><em>was </em><span>the organizational problem, so she kept going. Ultimately, she tripled minority membership. She also added 130,000 new volunteers — people she paid in a sense of mission — and grew the cookie business to $300 million a year. She added badges for math and science. One had binary code, for girls learning about computers.&nbsp;</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5ad5b96-fbff-437c-b4f6-a243a7ffa89c_1815x1883.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5ad5b96-fbff-437c-b4f6-a243a7ffa89c_1815x1883.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5ad5b96-fbff-437c-b4f6-a243a7ffa89c_1815x1883.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5ad5b96-fbff-437c-b4f6-a243a7ffa89c_1815x1883.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5ad5b96-fbff-437c-b4f6-a243a7ffa89c_1815x1883.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5ad5b96-fbff-437c-b4f6-a243a7ffa89c_1815x1883.jpeg" width="1456" height="1511" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/d5ad5b96-fbff-437c-b4f6-a243a7ffa89c_1815x1883.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1511,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:782142,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5ad5b96-fbff-437c-b4f6-a243a7ffa89c_1815x1883.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5ad5b96-fbff-437c-b4f6-a243a7ffa89c_1815x1883.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5ad5b96-fbff-437c-b4f6-a243a7ffa89c_1815x1883.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5ad5b96-fbff-437c-b4f6-a243a7ffa89c_1815x1883.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><span>Frances made tough decisions, like selling campgrounds that volunteers and staff loved from their childhoods but that were no longer getting enough use. Ultimately, she remained CEO for 13 years. Revered management expert Peter Drucker called her the best CEO in the country. When the head of General Motors retired a few months after her, </span><em>Business Week </em><span>asked Drucker who should take over. “I would pick Frances,” he told them.&nbsp;</span></p><p>---</p><p>Frances’s leadership story didn’t end there. She had been retired for all of a day when the chairman of Mutual of America offered her an office to do whatever she wanted with. An odd proposition, but by that point she realized none of her contributions grew out of long-term plans, but rather from doing what’s needed at the time. So she took it, and started a leadership institute, where she continued working through the age of 107. She also taught at the United States Military Academy at West Point.&nbsp;</p><p>Frances never did graduate from college, but the second time I visited her at her office, I counted 23 honorary doctorates. Not to mention a Presidential Medal of Freedom, the highest civilian award in the U.S. (When President Bill Clinton conferred it, he jokingly asked Frances to “come forward,” rather than “up,” because she didn’t like hierarchical language.)&nbsp;</p><p>But for all the honors and awards, it was just being around Frances that left the biggest impression on me. One day, she invited me to lunch at a cafeteria, and someone in front of us was rude to the cashier. When it was Frances’s turn to talk to the cashier, she said something to the effect of: “It’s so busy here at lunch hour! You’re doing a fantastic job. You must be great at handling pressure. I’m not sure everyone could do that. We’re lucky to have you here. Thank you.”&nbsp;</p><p><span>I’m pretty sure everyone behind us in line was suddenly extremely polite to the cashier. Being around Frances, I just couldn’t help but be a better person, and compliment people more. It feels to me like that kind of leader doesn’t get enough attention these days. Frances wasn’t a big self-promoter, which is one reason I feel obliged to keep promoting her and her brand of leadership. So thank you for joining me in 2022, and I want to give Frances the last </span><em>Range Widely </em><span>words of the year:</span></p><p>“Leadership is a matter of how to be, not how to do.”&nbsp;</p><p><span>-</span><strong>Frances Hesselbein (1915-2022)</strong></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7edf1054-35e7-49e7-94b1-e057a5afc762_3024x4032.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7edf1054-35e7-49e7-94b1-e057a5afc762_3024x4032.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7edf1054-35e7-49e7-94b1-e057a5afc762_3024x4032.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7edf1054-35e7-49e7-94b1-e057a5afc762_3024x4032.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7edf1054-35e7-49e7-94b1-e057a5afc762_3024x4032.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7edf1054-35e7-49e7-94b1-e057a5afc762_3024x4032.jpeg" width="1456" height="1941" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/7edf1054-35e7-49e7-94b1-e057a5afc762_3024x4032.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1941,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:1726787,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7edf1054-35e7-49e7-94b1-e057a5afc762_3024x4032.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7edf1054-35e7-49e7-94b1-e057a5afc762_3024x4032.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7edf1054-35e7-49e7-94b1-e057a5afc762_3024x4032.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7edf1054-35e7-49e7-94b1-e057a5afc762_3024x4032.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Napster sparked a file-sharing revolution 25 years ago (292 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://torrentfreak.com/napster-sparked-a-file-sharing-revolution-25-years-ago-250601/</link>
            <guid>40545436</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 13:08:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://torrentfreak.com/napster-sparked-a-file-sharing-revolution-25-years-ago-250601/">https://torrentfreak.com/napster-sparked-a-file-sharing-revolution-25-years-ago-250601/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40545436">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://torrentfreak.com/images/napster-logo-old.jpg" alt="napster logo" width="300" height="167" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/napster-logo-old.jpg 540w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/napster-logo-old-300x167.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px">The <a href="https://torrentfreak.com/how-the-mp3-pirates-and-apple-changed-the-music-industry-210117/">invention of the MP3</a> format in 1993 didn’t make any mainstream news headlines. In hindsight, however, it was a pivotal moment that would revolutionize music consumption, and more. </p>
<p>Invented by the German engineer Karlheinz Brandenburg and colleagues at the Fraunhofer Society, the coding format made it possible to reduce the size of music files without any significant loss of audible sound quality.</p>
<p>Due to the size reductions, these digital files could be stored on flash-memory devices. This led to the invention of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portable_media_player">dedicated MP3 players</a> capable of playing music ripped from CDs. Many considered this a more compact and shock-resistant alternative to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Discman">Discman</a>. </p>
<p>At the time, music industry insiders were already fantasizing about the ‘celestial jukebox’; a tool or service that would make it possible to play any track on demand. The MP3 helped to bring this concept a step closer too, as Napster would soon prove. </p>
<h2>Napster: June 1, 1999</h2>
<p>At the end of the nineties, technology and the Internet were a playground for young engineers and ‘hackers’. Some of them regularly gathered in the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201222012204/http://www.w00w00.org/">w00w00</a> IRC chatroom on the EFnet network. This tech-think-tank had many notable members, including WhatsApp founder Jan Koum and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shawn_Fanning">Shawn Fanning</a>, who logged on with the nickname Napster. </p>
<p>In 1998, 17-year-old Fanning shared an idea with the group. ‘Napster’ wanted to create a network of computers that could share files with each other. More specifically, a central music database that everyone in the world could access.</p>
<p>This idea never left the mind of the young developer. Fanning stopped going to school and flanked by his friend <a href="http://Sean Parker">Sean Parker</a>, devoted the following months to making his vision a reality. That moment came on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Napster">June 1, 1999</a>, when the first public release of Napster was released online. Soon after, the software went viral.</p>
<center><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://torrentfreak.com/images/fanning-1.jpg" alt="fanning" width="600" height="423"></center>
<p>Napster was quickly embraced by millions of users, who saw the software as something magical. It was a gateway for musical exploration, one that dwarfed even the largest record stores in town. And all for free. It sounds mundane today, but some equated it to pure technological sorcery.</p>
<p>For many top players in the music industry, Napster’s sorcery was pure witchcraft. At the time, manufacturing CDs with high profit margins felt like printing money and Napster’s appearance threatened to ruin the party.</p>
<h2>Music Industry Shocked</h2>
<p>According to the RIAA’s former CEO, Hilary Rosen, a few months after Napster’s release, the music industry shifted into full panic mode. In February 2000, all major label executives discussed the threat during an RIAA board meeting at the Four Seasons Hotel in Los Angeles.</p>
<p>“I will never forget this day. All of the heads of the labels, literally the titans of the music business, were in that room. I had somebody wheel in a PC and put some speakers up and I started doing a name that tune,” Rosen <a href="https://torrentfreak.com/how-the-mp3-pirates-and-apple-changed-the-music-industry-210117/">later recalled</a>.</p>
<p>The major music bosses started to name tracks, including some that weren’t even released yet, and time and again Napster would come up with results. Needless to say, the board was terrified.</p>
<p>Within a year, the RIAA sued Napster Inc. and soon after artists including Metallica and Dr. Dre followed. These high profile cases only raised the popularity of Napster and MP3 players began to sell like hotcakes.</p>
<h2>Peak Napster</h2>
<p>At the start of 2001, Napster’s user base reached a peak of more than 26.4 million worldwide. Yet, despite huge growth and backing from investors, the small file-sharing empire couldn’t overcome the legal challenges.</p>
<p>The RIAA lawsuit resulted in an injunction from the Ninth Circuit Court, which ordered the network to shut down. This happened during July 2001, little more than two years after Napster launched. By September that year, the case had been settled for millions of dollars.</p>
<center><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://torrentfreak.com/images/benefit.jpg" alt="benefit" width="600" height="344" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/benefit.jpg 1613w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/benefit-1536x882.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px"></center>
<p>While the Napster craze was over, file-sharing had mesmerized the masses and the genie was out of the bottle. Grokster, KaZaa, Morpheus, LimeWire, and many others popped up and provided sharing alternatives, for as long as they lasted. Meanwhile, BitTorrent was also knocking on the door. </p>
<h2>Ripple Effect</h2>
<p>Today, 25 years later, music piracy certainly hasn’t disappeared, but it has changed. When Napster came out, there simply weren’t any legal options to buy digital music online; let alone one that offered ‘unlimited access’. </p>
<p>Napster paved the way for Apple’s iTunes store, to serve the demand that was clearly there. The boom in digital download sales never came close to mimicking the ‘all you can play’ experience and was soon marginalized.</p>
<p>The current music industry generates the bulk of its revenues from online streaming subscriptions, while CDs have been downgraded to rare artifacts. This music streaming landscape was largely pioneered by a <a href="https://torrentfreak.com/how-the-pirate-bay-helped-spotify-become-a-success-180319/">Napster ‘fan’ from Sweden</a>, Daniel Ek.</p>
<p>Like many others, Ek was fascinated by the ‘all you can play’ experience offered by file-sharing software, and that planted the seeds for the music streaming startup Spotify, where he still serves as CEO today. In fact, Spotify itself used file-sharing technology under the hood to ensure swift playback. </p>
<p>Spotify is just one of the many examples of the Napster ripple effect, which reaches far beyond technology. The entire music industry has changed, for better and worse, depending on one’s perspective. And the ripples that started 25 years ago will still be felt in the decades to come.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Space secrets leak disclosure (181 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://huggingface.co/blog/space-secrets-disclosure</link>
            <guid>40544875</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 11:38:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://huggingface.co/blog/space-secrets-disclosure">https://huggingface.co/blog/space-secrets-disclosure</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40544875">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
				<p><a href="https://huggingface.co/blog">
						Back to Articles</a></p>

				<h2><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->
	<a id="space-secrets-leak-disclosure" href="#space-secrets-leak-disclosure">
		<span></span>
	</a>
	<span>
		Space secrets leak disclosure
	</span>
<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></h2>
				
				
				<div data-target="BlogAuthorsByline" data-props="{&quot;authors&quot;:[{&quot;author&quot;:{&quot;avatarUrl&quot;:&quot;https://cdn-avatars.huggingface.co/v1/production/uploads/1583856921041-5dd96eb166059660ed1ee413.png&quot;,&quot;fullname&quot;:&quot;Hugging Face&quot;,&quot;name&quot;:&quot;huggingface&quot;,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;org&quot;,&quot;isHf&quot;:true,&quot;isEnterprise&quot;:true}}],&quot;translators&quot;:[],&quot;proofreaders&quot;:[],&quot;lang&quot;:&quot;en&quot;}">

<p><span><span><a href="https://huggingface.co/huggingface"><img alt="Hugging Face's avatar" src="https://cdn-avatars.huggingface.co/v1/production/uploads/1583856921041-5dd96eb166059660ed1ee413.png">
					</a>
			</span>

	</span></p></div>
				

				<!-- HTML_TAG_START -->
<p>

Earlier this week our team detected unauthorized access to our Spaces platform, specifically related to Spaces secrets. As a consequence, we have suspicions that a subset of Spaces’ secrets could have been accessed without authorization.</p>
<p>As a first step of remediation, we have revoked a number of HF tokens present in those secrets. Users whose tokens have been revoked already received an email notice. <strong>We recommend you refresh any key or token and consider switching your HF tokens to fine-grained access tokens which are the new default.</strong></p>
<p>We are working with outside cyber security forensic specialists, to investigate the issue as well as review our security policies and procedures.</p>
<p>Over the past few days, we have made other significant improvements to the security of the Spaces infrastructure, including completely removing org tokens (resulting in increased traceability and audit capabilities), implementing key management service (KMS) for Spaces secrets, robustifying and expanding our system’s ability to identify leaked tokens and proactively invalidate them, and more generally improving our security across the board. We also plan on completely deprecating “classic” read and write tokens in the near future, as soon as fine-grained access tokens reach feature parity. We will continue to investigate any possible related incident.</p>
<p>Finally, we have also reported this incident to law enforcement agencies and Data protection authorities.</p>
<p>We deeply regret the disruption this incident may have caused and understand the inconvenience it may have posed to you. We pledge to use this as an opportunity to strengthen the security of our entire infrastructure. For any question, please contact us at <a href="mailto:security@huggingface.co">security@huggingface.co</a>.</p>
<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Einstein went to his office just so he could walk home with Gödel (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.futilitycloset.com/2024/05/31/footwork-10/</link>
            <guid>40544407</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 10:18:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.futilitycloset.com/2024/05/31/footwork-10/">https://www.futilitycloset.com/2024/05/31/footwork-10/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40544407">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="page">
		<main id="main" role="main">

		
			
<article id="post-67543">
	
	<div>
			<p>Albert Einstein used to say that he went to his office at the Institute for Advanced Study “just to have the privilege of walking home with Kurt Gödel.” The two would meet at Einstein’s home each day between 10 and 11 and undertake the half-hour walk to the institute. At 1 or 2 in the afternoon they’d walk back, discussing politics, philosophy, and physics. Biographer Palle Yourgrau estimates that these walks consumed 30 percent of Einstein’s workday.</p>
<p>Einstein’s secretary, Helen Dukas, wrote in 1946, “I know of one occasion when a car hit a tree after its driver suddenly recognized the face of the beautiful old man walking along the street.”</p>
<p>Gödel caused no such problems. “I have so far not found my ‘fame’ burdensome in any way,” he wrote to his mother. “That begins only when one becomes so famous that one is known to every child in the street, as is the case of Einstein.” </p>
<p>(From <a href="https://archive.org/details/AWorldWithoutTime"><em>A World Without Time: The Forgotten Legacy of Godel and Einstein</em></a>, 2009.)</p>

					</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</article><!-- #post-## -->
				<!-- .navigation -->
	
			
		
		</main><!-- #main -->
	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Arthur Whitney releases an open-source K with MIT license (268 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://shakti.com/k</link>
            <guid>40544283</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 09:47:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://shakti.com/k">https://shakti.com/k</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40544283">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><header></header><list><e d="0" f="about"><t f="" onclick="t(1,'about')"><a k="p">about</a></t><n onclick="event.stopPropagation()">k: fast fun universal database and language

for: hedgefunds banks manufacturers formula1 ..

why: 100 times faster than polars datatable biqquery redshift databricks snowflake ..

who: arthur whitney+  thanks to
 e.l. whitney[1920-1966] dad:multiple putnam winner(beat john nash every time)
 k.e. iverson[1920-2004] advisor:APL turing award'79
 john cocke  [1925-2002] advisor:RISC turing award'87

benchmarks: same machine. same data. same queries. (apples-to-apples)

h20:     1Billion rows  k is about 100 times faster than polars datatable ..
taxi:    1Billion rows  k is about 100 times faster than biggie shifty sparky ..
taq:  1000Billion rows  only k (incl. kx.com) can do the asof joins in our lifetime.
stac: 2000Billion rows  only k (incl. kx.com) can do these queries.

time - user and machine - is expensive. pandas and polars are free - god bless them - so

            1,000 rows: use excel
        1,000,000 rows: use polars
    1,000,000,000 rows: use k
1,000,000,000,000 rows: only k
</n></e><e d="0" f="benchmark"><t onclick="t(0,'benchmark')"><a k="p">benchmark</a></t><l f="benchmark"><e d="1" f="benchmark/about"><t f="" onclick="t(1,'benchmark/about')"><a k="p">about</a></t><n onclick="event.stopPropagation()">real-sql(k) is consistently 100 times faster (or more) than
 redshift, bigquery, snowflake, spark, mongodb, postgres, ..

same data. same queries. same hardware. anyone can run the scripts.

benchmarks:
 h2o     1Billion rows
 taxi    1Billion rows
 taq  1000Billion trades and quotes
 stac 2000Billion trades and quotes                             

Taq 1.1T  https://www.nyse.com/publicdocs/nyse/data/Daily_TAQ_Client_Spec_v2.2a.pdf

 q1:select max price by sym,ex from trade where sym in S
 q2:select sum size by sym,time.hour from trade where sym in S
 q3:do(100)select last bid by sym from quote where sym in S    / point select
 q4:select from trade[s],quote[s] where price&lt;bid              / asof join
 S is top 100 (10%)

 time(ms) 16core 100 days
                q1     q2       q3       q4
 k              44     72       63       20
 spark       80000  70000      DNF      DNF - can't do it
 postgres    20000  80000      DNF      DNF - can't do it
 ..

Taxi 1.1B  https://tech.marksblogg.com/benchmarks.html

 q1:select count by type from trips
 q2:select avg amount by pcount from trips
 q3:select count by year,pcount from trips
 q4:select count by year,pcount,_ distance from trips

           cpu  cost core/ram  elapsed         machines
 k           4 .0004    4/16    1            1*i3.2xlarge(8v/32/$.62+$.93)
 redshift  864 .0900  108/1464  8(1 2 2 3)   6*ds2.8xlarge(36v/244/$6.80)
 bigquery 1600 .3200  200/3200  8(2 2 1 3)
 db/spark 1260 .0900   42/336  30(2 4 4 20) 21*m5.xlarge(4v/16/$.20+$.30)

Stac https://www.stacresearch.com/
..</n></e><e d="1" f="benchmark/h2o.k"><t f="" onclick="t(1,'benchmark/h2o.k')"><a k="c">h2o.k</a></t><n onclick="event.stopPropagation()">t:.`9.csv
\t select sum v1 by id1 from t
\t select sum v1 by id1,id2 from t
\t select sum v1,avg v3 by id3 from t
\t select avg v1,avg v2,avg v3 by id1 from t
\t select sum v1,sum v2,sum v3 by id3 from t
\t select med v3,dev v3 by id1,id2 from t
\t select min v1,max v1 by id3 from t;
\t select 2 max v3 by id3 from t
\t select v1 dev v2 by id1,id2 from t
\\

https://h2oai.github.io/db-benchmark

data: 50GB csv: 1e9 rows[id1 id2 id3 id4 id5 id6 v1 v2 v3]
query: 9 multi-column aggregations[sum avg var dev correlation median 2max]
machine: amd epyc 9374f
code: k p/polars r/datatable [and much slower:clickhouse spark pandas arrow duckdb ..]

     query    csvload  (milliseconds)
k      950      1,600
*   97,000    606,000
p  258,000    265,000
r  257,000   1250,000

detail for the 9 queries
k      42   76   25  117    16   293    33    15   330
*     616 1509 6499  693  6260 20655  5817 51161  4231
p    1366 2401 42054 943 47177  5093 90847 29360 38500
r    3364 4494 7307 10008 7466 49770 63584 76673 31024

similar results for the 1e7 and 1e8. *(k4) is an old/1999 version of k.
</n></e></l></e><e d="0" f="document"><t onclick="t(0,'document')"><a k="p">document</a></t><l f="document"><e d="1" f="document/k.d"><t f="" onclick="t(1,'document/k.d')"><a k="c">k.d</a></t><n onclick="event.stopPropagation()">fast universal database and language.
connect to everything. depend on nothing.
select min e,max e,avg e by n from`t.csv (billion row challenge)

`t 2'`t.csv  [&gt;&gt;&gt;k.k("2'","t",pandas.read_csv("t.csv"))]
select [count first last min max sum avg var dev med ..] by from where ..
while(..)if(..)else .. in .. exp log sqrt sin cos ..
flip flop list sort asc desc unique group key val .. 

Verb    (monad)      Adverb              Noun
+ +                  ' each              char    " ab"          
- -                  / over right        name    ``ab
* *      sqr         \ scan left         int     2 3 4
% div    sqrt                            float   2 3.4
&amp; and    flip        \l load            
| or     flop        \t time
&lt; &lt;      asc         \v vars         z.d date    2001.01.01  
&gt; &gt;      desc        \w work         z.t time    12:34:56.789
= =      group       \\ exit        
~ ~      ~
. .      value
! mod    index                          
@ @      first       I/O                 Class
? find   unique      0' line             List    (2;3.4)
# take   count       1' char             Dict    {a:2 3}
_ drop   floor       2' data             Table   [a:2 3]
^ cut    order       3' set*             Expr    :2+a
, ,      ,           4' get*             Func    {[a]2+a}    

rosetta        Atom         List   atom   list        Ddd Mm
k      ()[].;: +-*%&amp;|&lt;&gt;=~$! @?#_^, ~-*%_$ @,#!!|^&lt;&gt;?= ..! @&amp;  f'       F'        while(a)if(b)c else d
python ()[].;= +-*/&amp;|&lt;&gt; ^ %  isssa ~- sfs   lrwrsa u  dvk @t [f(x)..] [F(x,y)..] while a:if b:c else:d 
(index slices split append;sqrt floor str;len range where reverse sort argsort unique;dict key value;transpose)

Type   int float complex boolean char name date time
Class  List Dict Array Table Expression Function(* immutable)

             ifgbcndt  LDATEF*       devs
k      1992  833...88  ++++++*    300spartans
sql    1992  32 . .22     -  *     20million
python 1991  .... .    --          10million
 numpy 2005  433   99    +   *      5million
go     2009  422..                  2million
nodejs 1995  . . .     --          15million
excel  1982  . . .         + *     80million
c      1972  42                     5million
apl    1962  . ..        +   *</n></e><e d="1" f="document/sql.d"><t f="" onclick="t(1,'document/sql.d')"><a k="c">sql.d</a></t><n onclick="event.stopPropagation()">shakti universal database includes:

ansi-sql [1992..2011] ok for row/col select.
real-sql [1974..2021] atw@ipsa does it better.

join:  real-easy ansi-ok
 real: select from T,U
 ansi: select from T left outer join U

group: real-easy ansi-annoy
 real: select A by B from T
 ansi: select B, A from T group by B order by B

simple: real-easy ansi-easy
 real: select A from T where C or D, E
 ansi: select A from T where (C or D)and E

complex: real-easy ansi-awful
 asof/joins      select from t,q where price&lt;bid
 first/last      select last bid from quote where sym=`A
 deltas/sums     select from t where 0&lt;deltas price
 foreignkeys     select order.cust.nation.region ..
 arithmetic      x+y e.g. combine markets through time

example: TPC-H National Market Share Query 8 http://www.qdpma.com/tpch/TPCH100_Query_plans.html
what market share does supplier.nation BRAZIL have by order.year for order.customer.nation.region AMERICA and part.type STEEL?

 real: select revenue avg supplier.nation=`BRAZIL by order.year from t where order.customer.nation.region=`AMERICA, part.type=`STEEL

 ansi: select o_year,sum(case when nation = 'BRAZIL' then revenue else 0 end) / sum(revenue) as mkt_share from (
  select extract(year from o_orderdate) as o_year, revenue, n2.n_name as nation 
  from t,part,supplier,orders,customer,nation n1,nation n2,region
  where p_partkey = l_partkey and s_suppkey = l_suppkey and l_orderkey = o_orderkey and o_custkey = c_custkey and 
   c_nationkey = n1.n_nationkey and n1.n_regionkey = r_regionkey and r_name = 'AMERICA' and 
   s_nationkey = n2.n_nationkey and o_orderdate between date '1995-01-01' and date '1996-12-31' and p_type = 'STEEL') as all_nations 
 group by o_year order by o_year;

Comparison:     real                  ansi(sqlserver/oracle/db2/sap/teradata/..)
 install           1 second        100,000 second
 hardware          1 milliwatt     100,000 milliwatt
 software        160 kilobyte    8,000,000 kilobyte  (+ 10,000,000kilobyte O/S)
 mediandb  1,000,000 megarow            10 megarow

https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/sql/database-engine/install-windows/install-sql-server?view=sql-server-ver15

shakti is essential for analyzing big (trillion row+) and/or complex data.</n></e></l></e><e d="0" f="k"><t onclick="t(0,'k')"><a k="p">k</a></t><l f="k"><e d="1" f="k/a"><t f="" onclick="t(0,'k/a')"><a href="https://shakti.com/k/a" k="p">a</a></t></e><e d="1" f="k/k.d"><t f="" onclick="t(1,'k/k.d')"><a k="c">k.d</a></t><n onclick="event.stopPropagation()">  F      f       f 2+x
+ +      +       F'each   [fF]'each
- -      -       F/right [cfF]/over
* *      sqr     F\left  [cfF]\scan
% div    sqrt
&amp; and    flip    
| or     flop    
&lt; &lt;      asc
&gt; &gt;      desc
= =      group
~ ~      ~
. .      value
! mod    index    I/O
@ @      first    0'line
? find   nub      1'char
# take   count
_ drop   floor   \l load
^ cut    order   \t time
, ,      ,       \w work
$ cast   string  \\ exit
"23";23;2.3;2:3

nyi
{a:2 3} [a:2 3] while(a)if(b)c else d 
x[.@?]y [&amp;^?&lt;&gt;=]x</n></e><e d="1" f="k/k.zip"><t f="" onclick="t(0,'k/k.zip')"><a href="https://shakti.com/k/k.zip" k="c">k.zip</a></t></e></l></e></list></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ticketmaster confirms data hack which could affect 560M globally (129 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/articles/cw99ql0239wo</link>
            <guid>40544219</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 09:33:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/articles/cw99ql0239wo">https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/articles/cw99ql0239wo</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40544219">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-component="text-block"><p><b>Ticketmaster owner Live Nation confirmed "unauthorised activity" on its database after a group of hackers said they had stolen the personal details of 560 million  customers.</b></p><p>ShinyHunters, the group claiming responsibility, says the stolen data includes names, addresses, phone numbers and partial credit card details from Ticketmaster users worldwide.</p><p>The hacking group is <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/articles/c899pz84d8zo">reportedly demanding a $500,000 (£400,000</a>) ransom payment to prevent the data from being sold to other parties.</p><p>In a filing to the US Securities and Exchange Commission, Live Nation said that on 27 May "a criminal threat actor offered what it alleged to be Company user data for sale via the dark web", and that it was investigating.</p><p>The number of customers affected by the data breach has not been confirmed by Live Nation.</p><p>The Ticketmaster breach was first revealed by hackers who posted an advert for the data on Wednesday evening. Ticketmaster refused to confirm it to reporters or customers and instead notified shareholders late on Friday.</p><p>The Australian government said it is working with Ticketmaster to address the issue. The FBI has also offered to assist, a spokesperson for the US Embassy in Canberra told Agence France-Presse.</p><p>A spokesperson for the FBI told the BBC it "has no comment on this matter".</p><p>In its filing, Live Nation said it was working to "mitigate risk" to its customers and that it was notifying users about the unauthorised access to their personal information.</p><p>"As of the date of this filing, the incident has not had, and we do not believe it is reasonably likely to have, a material impact on our overall business operations or on our financial condition or results of operations. We continue to evaluate the risks and our remediation efforts are ongoing", it added.</p><p>American website Ticketmaster is one of the largest online ticket sales platforms in the world.   This hack is one of the biggest in history in terms of global victims but it’s not yet clear how sensitive the data is that is in the hands of cyber criminals.</p><p>Researchers are also warning that it’s part of a larger ongoing hack involving a cloud service provider called Snowflake which is used by many large firms to store data in the cloud. Snowflake notified customers that it has been breached but would not say which firms are impacted. On Friday Santander confirmed it had data from an estimated 30m customers stolen which was being sold by the same hacking group as the Ticketmaster hackers. It’s thought these hacks are all linked and many others could become public.</p><p>An advert with some data samples allegedly obtained in the breach have been posted on the website BreachForums - a newly relaunched hacking forum on the dark web where other hackers buy and sell stolen material, and information to enable hacks to take place.</p><p>ShinyHunters has been linked to a string of high-profile data breaches resulting in millions of dollars in losses to the companies involved.</p><p>In 2021 the group sold a genuine database of stolen information from 70 million customers of US telecoms firm AT&amp;T.</p><p>In September last year, almost 200,000 Pizza Hut customers in Australia had their data breached.</p><p>The FBI cracked down on the domain in March 2023, arresting its administrator Conor Brian Fitzpatrick, but it has reappeared, according to tech media.</p><p>Users of hacking forums often inflate the scale of their hacking to attract attention from other hackers.</p><p>They are often where large stolen databases first appear but can also feature false allegations and claims.</p><p>Individuals declaring large batches of data in the past have proven to be duplicates of previous hacks rather than newly stolen information.</p><p>If the data hack is as large as claimed by ShinyHunters, the hack could be the most significant breach ever in terms of numbers and the extent of the data stolen.</p><p>This is not the first time Ticketmaster has been hit with security issues.</p><p>In 2020 it admitted it hacked into one of its competitors and agreed to pay a $10m fine.</p><p>In November it was allegedly hit by a cyber attack which led to problems selling tickets for Taylor Swift's Era's tour.</p><p>Earlier this month, US regulators sued Live Nation accusing the entertainment giant of using illegal tactics to maintain a monopoly over the live music industry.</p><p>The lawsuit from the Department of Justice said the firm's practices had kept out competitors, and led to higher ticket prices and worse service for customers.</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Experts say it’s important not to panic but to be alert, if you think you may be a victim.</p><p>Watch out for bogus emails, messages and phone calls - hackers can sometimes use the details they have to trick victims into revealing more information.</p><p>In some cases scammers may try and exploit the fear caused by the hack as a way of trying to persuade you to share information.</p><p>Be especially suspicious of:</p><div><ul role="list"><li><p>official-sounding messages about "resetting passwords", "receiving compensation", "scanning devices" or "missed deliveries"</p></li></ul></div><div><ul role="list"><li><p>emails full of "tech speak", designed to sound more convincing</p></li></ul></div><div><ul role="list"><li><p>being urged to act immediately or within a limited timeframe</p></li></ul></div><p>In 2018 when a hack put some Ticketmaster customer information at risk, UK officials <a href="https://www.ncsc.gov.uk/guidance/ncsc-advice-ticketmaster-customers">also suggested users<span>, <!-- -->external</span></a> kept an eye on their financial accounts for suspicious activity. They also advised changing your password for Ticketmaster and on any other sites using the same password.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Lessons learned from 6 months of operating a tiny news archive (114 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://hiandrewquinn.github.io/til-site/posts/lessons-learned-from-6-months-of-operating-a-teensy-tiny-news-archive/</link>
            <guid>40544043</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 08:55:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://hiandrewquinn.github.io/til-site/posts/lessons-learned-from-6-months-of-operating-a-teensy-tiny-news-archive/">https://hiandrewquinn.github.io/til-site/posts/lessons-learned-from-6-months-of-operating-a-teensy-tiny-news-archive/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40544043">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div><ol><li><p><strong>The best websites are <a href="https://www.robinsloan.com/notes/home-cooked-app/">home-cooked meals</a>.</strong> <a href="https://hiandrewquinn.github.io/selkouutiset-archive/">Andrew’s Selkouutiset Archive</a> was birthed after I realized there was no obvious way to fetch the <em>previous</em> articles of the “Easy Finnish” daily news broadcast. This annoyed me as a student of the language. “Here we have a stream”, I thought, “of high-quality, human-written, interesting practice material, and no easy way to access it!” So I went out of my way to create such a way, and me and my language skills have been profiting off of it ever since. A very small website, for a very specific need, just leaves a delightful aftertaste in the mouth.</p></li><li><p><strong>Cronjobs and Git complement each other nicely.</strong> ASA runs off of 3 Git repos, each submoduling and iterating upon the last. The first repo archives the page as-is with a cronjob. The second repo turns the first repo into cleaned-up Markdown with an English translation with another cronjob. The third repo turns the cleaned-up Markdown into a Hugo website with a third cronjob. If at any point an issue appears, with e.g. the shell scripts that do the actual cleaning, I always have the option to simply revert to a previous commit and work fresh.</p></li><li><p><strong>Simplicity is underrated.</strong> Everything about this website is done as simply as I could stand. For example, notice how there’s no database at all. In essence we are using Git itself as our database, specifically that very first repo. That means this site is <em>entirely static</em>, and can be deployed directly to Github Pages without any complications. I don’t think I’ve had to tweak anything about that flow in the last 3 months.</p></li><li><p><strong>Working locally is <em>hella</em> underrated.</strong> Originally I started this because I got tired of spending 15 minutes every morning copying and pasting that day’s news, along with its Google Translation to English, into Anki. Later I got tired of spending 5 minutes per article copying and pasting the actual archive, even though the whole translation was right there as well. Because I made sure to make the intermediate repo as easy to work with as possible, I later found it very straightforward to write <a href="https://github.com/Selkouutiset-Archive/selkokortti/tree/main">a little Python program</a> that could process <em>all</em> of the news into a flashcard format. Crucially, because all of the Git repos are things anyone else can pull down, this program <em>clones its own local copy</em> of Repo #2 and creates flashcards on that copy on the local filesystem, making it probably an order of magnitude faster than even the fastest response-request cycle could get (and much more deterministic too).</p></li><li><p><strong>Bare HTML never goes out of style.</strong> My archive doesn’t use any JavaScript at all, it’s just HTML with the smallest amount of classless CSS I could get away with to make it easy to read the Finnish and English side-by-side. At one point I thought perhaps I should add in some code to help people find the dictionary forms of the rarer words, but it turns out <a href="https://github.com/hiAndrewQuinn/finstem">I already wrote a command line tool to solve that general case</a>. Adding JavaScript in to a non-JS website to solve that task felt like way more complexity than it was worth.</p></li><li><p><strong><a href="https://pandoc.org/">pandoc</a> is the bee’s knees!</strong></p></li></ol></div></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Stealing everything you've ever typed on your Windows Recall PC is now possible (161 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/1/stealing-everything-youve-ever-typed/#atom-everything</link>
            <guid>40543990</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 08:43:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/1/stealing-everything-youve-ever-typed/#atom-everything">https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/1/stealing-everything-youve-ever-typed/#atom-everything</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40543990">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>


<p><a href="https://doublepulsar.com/recall-stealing-everything-youve-ever-typed-or-viewed-on-your-own-windows-pc-is-now-possible-da3e12e9465e">Stealing everything you’ve ever typed or viewed on your own Windows PC is now possible with two lines of code — inside the Copilot+ Recall disaster</a> (<a href="https://cyberplace.social/@GossiTheDog/112537206611365804" title="@GossiTheDog">via</a>) Recall is a new feature in Windows 11 which takes a screenshot every few seconds, runs local device OCR on it and stores the resulting text in a SQLite database. This means you can search back through your previous activity, against local data that has remained on your device.</p>
<p>The security and privacy implications here are still enormous because malware can now target a single file with huge amounts of valuable information:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>During testing this with an off the shelf infostealer, I used Microsoft Defender for Endpoint — which detected the off the shelve infostealer — but by the time the automated remediation kicked in (which took over ten minutes) my Recall data was already long gone.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I like Kevin Beaumont's argument here about the subset of users this feature is appropriate for:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>At a surface level, it is great if you are a manager at a company with too much to do and too little time as you can instantly search what you were doing about a subject a month ago.</p>
<p>In practice, that audience’s needs are a very small (tiny, in fact) portion of Windows userbase — and frankly talking about screenshotting the things people in the <em>real world</em>, not executive world, is basically like punching customers in the face.</p>
</blockquote>



</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[CERN Root (312 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://root.cern/</link>
            <guid>40543651</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 07:25:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://root.cern/">https://root.cern/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40543651">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main" role="main">
  <article itemscope="" itemtype="https://schema.org/CreativeWork">
    <meta itemprop="headline" content="ROOT: analyzing petabytes of data, scientifically.">
    <meta itemprop="description" content="An open-source data analysis framework used by high energy physics and others.">
    
    

    <section itemprop="text">
      <div>
    <center>
    <div>
        <p><a href="https://root.cern/get_started"><img width="128" src="https://root.cern/assets/images/start.svg"></a></p>
        <p><span color="#346295" size="3">Start</span></p>
    </div><!--
    --><div>
        <p><a href="https://root.cern/doc/v632"><img width="128" src="https://root.cern/assets/images/doc.svg"></a></p>
        <p><span color="#346295" size="3">Reference</span></p>
    </div><!--
    --><div>
        <p><a href="https://root-forum.cern.ch/"><img width="128" src="https://root.cern/assets/images/forum.svg"></a></p>
        <p><span color="#346295" size="3">Forum</span></p>
    </div><!--
    --><div>
        <p><a href="https://root.cern/gallery"><img width="128" src="https://root.cern/assets/images/gallery.svg"></a></p>
        <p><span color="#346295" size="3">Gallery</span></p>
    </div>
    </center>
</div>






<div>

  
    <div>
          
            <h2>√-1</h2>
          

          
            <p>ROOT enables <i>statistically sound</i> scientific analyses and visualization of large amounts of data: today, more than 1 exabyte (1,000,000,000 gigabyte) are stored in ROOT files. <a href="https://root.cern/gallery#higgs-plots">The Higgs was found with ROOT!</a></p>
          

          
        </div>
  
    <div>
          
            <h2><img src="https://root.cern/assets/images/globe_with_meridians.svg" alt="*.*"></h2>
          

          
            <p>As <i>high-performance</i> software, ROOT is written mainly in C++. You can use it on Linux, macOS, or Windows; it works out of the box. ROOT is <a href="https://root.cern/about/license">open source</a>: use it freely, <a href="https://root.cern/install/build_from_source">modify it</a>, <a href="https://root.cern/contribute">contribute to it</a>!</p>
          

          
        </div>
  
    <div>
          
            <h2>$ _</h2>
          

          
            
          

          
        </div>
  

</div>



<table>
   <tbody>
      <tr>
         <td>
            <p><span size="4"><b><a href="https://root.cern/blog/rntuple-update/">RNTuple: Where are we now and what's next?</a></b></span> <span size="1">(26 Jan 2024)</span>
               <span size="2"><p>Hello, this is Florine from the ROOT team! Over the past year, I’ve been working
as a technical student funded by ATLAS to evaluate and help further develop
RNTuple. As you may already be aware, RNTuple <a href="#rntuple-evolution">[1]</a> is
currently being developed as the successor to TTree, and is projected to be
used in Run 4. I imagine you might be wondering why there is a need for a
completely new (TTree-incompatible) system, and what this looks like. That’s why
in this blog post, I will try to answer this question, as well as give you an
overview of the current status of RNTuple, what we’re still working on before
its first production release (and what we will work on beyond this), and
finally how you can already try it out!</p>
</span>
               
               <span size="4"><b><a href="https://root.cern/blog/web-based-graphics-default/">Interactive, web-based canvas is now the default in ROOT</a></b></span> <span size="1">(05 Jun 2023)</span>
               <span size="2"><p>After a long period of development and testing we decided to switch to the web-based <code>TCanvas</code>
implementation by default in the ROOT master version. It has been present in the ROOT for a
while (since 2017) and used already in the web-based TBrowser, which you have probably seen already.</p>
</span>
               
               <span size="4"><b><a href="https://root.cern/blog/new-class-tscatter/">New class TScatter</a></b></span> <span size="1">(30 May 2023)</span>
               <span size="2"><center>
   <img src="https://root.cern/assets/images/scatter.png" alt="TScatter" width="1600" height="749">
</center>
</span>
               
               <span size="4"><b><a href="https://root.cern/blog/code-horsepower-f1/">Coding in ROOT with the horsepower of an <kbd>F1</kbd></a></b></span> <span size="1">(01 Mar 2022)</span>
               <span size="2"><p>If you’ve ever rubbed your eyes trying to decrypt <em>C++</em> compilation errors from a terminal, or even have faced with your bare eye the intimidating logs of valgrind output for memory leak detection, or manually deployed <em>gdb</em>, you should definitely keep reading. With this post, I believe you’ll improve your productivity and experience with <em>ROOT</em> by using QtCreator as a development and troubleshooting environment.</p>
</span>
               
               <span size="4"><b><a href="https://root.cern/blog/debuging-root-scripts-in-eclipse/">Debugging CERN ROOT scripts and ROOT-based programs in Eclipse IDE</a></b></span> <span size="1">(30 Oct 2021)</span>
               <span size="2"><center>
   <img src="https://root.cern/assets/images/setup-eclipse-ide-with-cern-root.jpg" alt="Eclipse IDE dependencies" width="1600" height="749">
</center>
</span>
               
               <b><a href="https://root.cern/blog"> More ...</a></b>
            </p>
         </td>
         <td>
         </td>
         <td>
            <h2>Latest Releases</h2>
            <br>
            <div>
               <p><span size="2">
               









<ul>




<li> <a href="https://root.cern/releases/release-63200/"> Release 6.32/00 - 


28th

of May, 2024 </a></li>

<li> <a href="https://root.cern/releases/release-63006/"> Release 6.30.06 - 


3rd
  
of April, 2024 </a></li>

<li> <a href="https://root.cern/releases/release-63004/"> Release 6.30.04 - 


31st
  
of January, 2024 </a></li>

<li> <a href="https://root.cern/releases/release-63002/"> Release 6.30/02 - 


28th

of November, 2023 </a></li>

<li> <a href="https://root.cern/releases/release-63000/"> Release 6.30/00 - 


7th

of November, 2023 </a></li>







</ul>

               <br>
               <b><a href="https://root.cern/install/all_releases"> More ...</a></b>
               </span>
            </p></div>
            <br>
         </td>
      </tr>
   </tbody>
</table>

    </section>
  </article>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ticketmaster confirms data breach with a SEC filing (129 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://stackdiary.com/ticketmaster-confirms-data-breach-with-a-sec-filing/</link>
            <guid>40543408</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 06:34:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://stackdiary.com/ticketmaster-confirms-data-breach-with-a-sec-filing/">https://stackdiary.com/ticketmaster-confirms-data-breach-with-a-sec-filing/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40543408">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content">

	
	
		
			
<div>
				
<p>Live Nation Entertainment, also known as Ticketmaster, has submitted an official <strong>Form 8-K</strong> with the U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC), acknowledging and confirming that <a href="https://stackdiary.com/ticketmaster-breached-a-reputable-source-says-yes/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">the recently rumored data breach</a> is real.</p>



<p>In the filing (<a href="https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1335258/000133525824000081/lyv-20240520.htm" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">which can be seen here</a>), Ticketmaster says that on May 20, 2024, Live Nation Entertainment, Inc. <strong>discovered unauthorized activity within a third-party cloud database environment that contained company data</strong>, primarily from its Ticketmaster L.L.C. subsidiary. The company immediately launched an investigation with the help of leading forensic experts to understand the extent and nature of the breach.</p>



<p>On May 27, 2024, a criminal actor claimed to have company user data for sale on the dark web. Live Nation is actively working to mitigate the risk to its users and the company. They have notified and are cooperating with law enforcement agencies. Additionally, they are informing regulatory authorities and affected users about unauthorized access to personal information.</p>



<p>The company says they continue to assess the risks and are working on remediation efforts.</p>



<h2>What happened? A timeline.</h2>



<p>Starting May 29th, when a group called <em>ShinyHunters</em> published the initial data for sale on dark web forums, numerous key events were associated with this breach. As such, here is a complete timeline of the events as they happened:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>May 27, 2024</strong> — A dark web user with no previous breach reputation published a forum post saying they have 560 million Ticketmaster user data for sale: name, address, email, phone numbers, order details, etc.</li>



<li><strong>May 29, 2024</strong> — The dark web threat group ShinyHunters reposted the sale of this data themselves on BreachForums, which gave this story immediate credibility. ShinyHunters has a history of high-level data breaches. Following this, major news media immediately picked up the story and began publishing articles saying Ticketmaster had been hacked.</li>



<li><strong>May 30, 2024</strong> — A reputable cybersecurity group called <a href="https://x.com/vxunderground/status/1796063116574314642" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">vx-underground was given sample data</a> from the Ticketmaster breach. They said, “Based on data provided to us by the Threat Group responsible for the compromise, we can assert with a high degree of confidence that the data is legitimate.”</li>



<li><strong>May 31, 2024</strong> — The <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c6ppv06e3n8o" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">BBC published a news article</a> saying that Santander, a major financial organization, had been breached, and all customer data was offered for sale: the price was $2 million. At the time, there was no connection between this story and Ticketmaster’s. Until…</li>



<li><strong>May 31, 2024</strong> — The security research group at Hudson Rock <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20240531225301/https://www.hudsonrock.com/blog/snowflake-massive-breach-access-through-infostealer-infection" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">publishes a story</a> (✤) about a conversation with the threat actor responsible for the Ticketmaster and Santander breaches. According to the perpetrator, these breaches were made possible by breaching Snowflake, a cloud provider of data solutions. Both Santander and Live Nation are Snowflake customers.</li>



<li><strong>May 31, 2024</strong> — Snowflake published <a href="https://community.snowflake.com/s/question/0D5VI00000Emyl00AB/detecting-and-preventing-unauthorized-user-access" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">a security bulletin acknowledging the breach</a>. They don’t acknowledge the exact method of breach implied by the perpetrator, but they don’t deny it either. What matters here is that there is a connection with everything that happened before.</li>



<li><strong>May 31, 2024</strong> — The Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) publishes <a href="https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1335258/000133525824000081/lyv-20240520.htm" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">the Live Nation filing</a> disclosing the Ticketmaster breach. Details are very sparse at this time, and we should expect more updates in the coming days or weeks.</li>
</ul>



<p>According to the Hudson Rock story with the perpetrator, he had initially wanted to get $20 million from Snowflake to never publish the data, neither from Ticketmaster or Santander nor the other 400 companies he alleges he had access to.</p>



<figure><blockquote><p>To put it bluntly, a single credential resulted in the exfiltration of potentially hundreds of companies that stored their data using Snowflake, with the threat actor himself suggesting&nbsp;<strong>400 companies</strong>&nbsp;are impacted. The goal of the threat actor, as in most cases, was to blackmail Snowflake into buying their own data back for $20,000,000.</p><cite>Hudson Rock</cite></blockquote></figure>



<p>It’s important to note that the language used by all the parties involved in this situation has been extremely obscure. For example, at the time of this publication, Snowflake has not explicitly stated that the threat actor did not gain access to extremely sensitive data. Snowflake has also declined to comment on the situation when asked about it.</p>



<p>Likewise, at the time of this publication, Ticketmaster has not yet begun notifying its users of the data breach. The entire timeline suggests that this could potentially be the largest data breach ever (all things considered), yet there is very little direct confirmation outside of Live Nation’s SEC filing.</p>



<p><em>✤: Stack Diary is aware that Hudson Rock has removed its blog post showcasing the perpetrator’s conversation. This was likely done because Hudson Rock unknowingly/knowingly doxxed (revealed personal details) an employee whose account was breached at Snowflake. We’ve reached out for comment.</em></p>

			</div>

		
	
			<section>
			<p>
				<h2>
					Read more				</h2>
			</p>

			
		</section>
		
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Nginx Unit: open-source, lightweight and versatile application runtime (150 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://unit.nginx.org/</link>
            <guid>40543330</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 06:18:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://unit.nginx.org/">https://unit.nginx.org/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40543330">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content">

<p>NGINX Unit is a lightweight and versatile application runtime
that provides the essential components for your web application
as a single open-source server:
running application code
(including WebAssembly),
serving static assets,
handling TLS and request routing.</p>
<p>Unit was created by
<a href="https://nginx.org/en/">nginx</a>
team members from scratch
to be highly efficient
and fully configurable at runtime.
The latest version is 1.32.1,
released on Mar 26, 2024.</p>
<ul>
<li>See a quickstart
<a href="https://github.com/nginx/unit/">guide</a>
on our GitHub page.</li>
<li>Browse the
<a href="https://unit.nginx.org/CHANGES.txt">changelog</a>,
see the release notes in the
<a href="https://unit.nginx.org/news/"><span>news</span></a>
archive,
or subscribe to
our RSS
<a href="https://unit.nginx.org/rss.xml">feed</a>.</li>
<li>Check out the discussion of our
<a href="https://unit.nginx.org/keyfeatures/"><span>key features</span></a>
for further details.</li>
<li>Peek at our future plans
with a GitHub-based
<a href="https://github.com/orgs/nginx/projects/1">roadmap</a>.</li>
</ul>
<div>
  <p>
    <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/NaaS1qOBnuw" allowfullscreen="">
    </iframe>
  </p>

  <p>
    <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/thEX-oQHfDA?start=545" allowfullscreen="">
    </iframe>
  </p>
</div><p>Watch the entire NGINX Unit tutorial course
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLGz_X9w9raXdV3vuPUu0kKBSBjG9rPaUf">here</a>.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tiny number of 'supersharers' spread the majority of fake news (287 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.science.org/content/article/tiny-number-supersharers-spread-vast-majority-fake-news</link>
            <guid>40542321</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 02:16:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.science.org/content/article/tiny-number-supersharers-spread-vast-majority-fake-news">https://www.science.org/content/article/tiny-number-supersharers-spread-vast-majority-fake-news</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40542321">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.science.org/content/article/tiny-number-supersharers-spread-vast-majority-fake-news: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>