<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2024 01:00:05 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google has no visionary leaders and a pervasive sense of nihilism (105 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.linkedin.com/posts/dhtheriault_my-hot-take-google-does-not-have-one-single-activity-7153269568893775872-9xzp/</link>
            <guid>39082599</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 20:18:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/dhtheriault_my-hot-take-google-does-not-have-one-single-activity-7153269568893775872-9xzp/">https://www.linkedin.com/posts/dhtheriault_my-hot-take-google-does-not-have-one-single-activity-7153269568893775872-9xzp/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39082599">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main-content" role="main">
      <section>
                

                
    

    
      

    <article data-activity-urn="urn:li:activity:7153269568893775872" data-featured-activity-urn="urn:li:activity:7153269568893775872" data-attributed-urn="urn:li:share:7153255739082309632">
      
              
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    

    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    

    
    

<!---->  
        

      
            

    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    

    
  
        

      
              

    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    

      
  
        

        
            
            
  <p dir="ltr" data-test-id="main-feed-activity-card__commentary">My hot take: Google does not have one single visionary leader. Not a one. From the C-suite to the SVPs to the VPs, they are all profoundly boring and glassy-eyed. 

Google has not launched one single successful executive-driven thing in years. Sometimes, VPs try to decree "we need a new chat app or AI-first demo for I/O!" There's a boondoggle slog, and in the end, the thing is half-baked and roundly derided. If it doesn't get 100 million users in six months, they give up and shut it down. It's like that joke algorithm I learned about in college -- BogoSort. In each iteration of the algorithm, you reorder everything randomly and if the elements happen to land in order, you are done. 

Some of Google's executives are competent referees. I couldn't name which, but I feel like I've seen it done in my 8+ years. They point in a direction, their subordinates swarm the area, try a bunch of stuff, and sometimes something sticks and is cool. 

Right now, all of these boring, glassy-eyed leaders are trying to point in a vague direction (AI) while at the same time killing their golden goose. Given that they have no real vision of their own, they really need their subordinates to come up with cool stuff for them. And at the same time, there have been rolling layoffs for the past 6-12 months throughout the company, including engineering, sales, support, UX, product, data science, SRE, everything. Just randomly firing people, torching institutional knowledge, and blowing up perfectly functional teams. 

Maybe it's not random. But they refuse to describe their reasons except as "we are excited to focus our resources on our highest priorities," so it might as well be random. I think they don't know what the priorities are. Not durably. They are waiting for their subordinates to propose concrete stuff in the direction they are waving their arms. Meanwhile, all of the mid-level leaders are scrambling to protect their teams (and themselves) by guessing what their VPs might find appealing. If you are a leader and you guess wrong, you and your team get cut.

There is a pervasive sense of nihilism that has taken hold. "Well, I guess I will just do the job until they fire me." A lot of people have golden handcuffs situations and aren't going to walk away from the salary, but nobody works late anymore. The buildings are half empty at 4:30. I know a lot of people, myself included, who used to happily do extra work evenings and weekends to get the demo done or just out of boredom.&nbsp;That's gone. 

Google really was a magical place, not very long ago. And for some reason, executives are cashing out their human capital at the very moment it seems to me like they really need it. Who can be dawn-of-a-new-era-of-humanity creative in this environment of fear? It's really sad. I have no way to align myself with any unspoken VP strategy or do good enough work to save myself if my whole team is cut. So I guess I will just hang around and do my job until Google no longer wants me.</p>



        

      
            
      
    
    
    

    
      <div>
        
      
      <p>
          Content type not supported
        </p>
    
      </div>
  
  
      
                  

<!---->
      
          
        

      
          
        

      
          
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    

      
  
  
        

      
              
    
    
    

    
  
                    

      
            
              

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    

      
  
  
              

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    

      
  
  
              

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    

      
  
  
              

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    

      
  
  
              

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    

      
  
  
              

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    

      
  
  
              

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    

      
  
  
              

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    

      
  
  
              

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    

      
  
  
              

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    

      
  
  
              <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/signup/cold-join?session_redirect=https%3A%2F%2Fwww%2Elinkedin%2Ecom%2Fposts%2Fdhtheriault_my-hot-take-google-does-not-have-one-single-activity-7153269568893775872-9xzp&amp;trk=public_post_see-more-comments" data-test-id="main-feed-activity-card-with-comments__see-more-comments" data-tracking-control-name="public_post_see-more-comments" data-tracking-will-navigate="">
                See more comments
              </a>
      
        

      
            

    
    

    
  
        
    </article>
  
      
  
  
            </section>
        <section>

            <h2>
              Explore topics
            </h2>

<!---->
        
      </section>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[C23: A Slightly Better C (178 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lemire.me/blog/2024/01/21/c23-a-slightly-better-c/</link>
            <guid>39081948</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 19:23:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lemire.me/blog/2024/01/21/c23-a-slightly-better-c/">https://lemire.me/blog/2024/01/21/c23-a-slightly-better-c/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39081948">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="page">
<p><a href="#content">
Skip to content </a></p>
<div id="content">
<main id="main">
<article id="post-21097">

<div>
<p>One of the established and most popular programming languages is the C programming language. It is relatively easy to learn, and highly practical.</p>
<p>Maybe surprisingly, the C programming language keeps evolving, slowly and carefully. If you have GCC 23 or LLVM (Clang) 16, you already have a compiler with some of the features from the latest standard (C23).</p>
<pre><span>// Only include stdio.h if it exists</span>
<span>#</span><span>if</span><span> __has_include </span><span>(</span><span>&lt;</span><span>stdio</span><span>.</span><span>h</span><span>&gt;</span><span>)</span>
<span>  #</span><span>include </span><span>&lt;</span><span>stdio.h</span><span>&gt;</span>
<span>#</span><span>endif</span>
<span>
#</span><span>include </span><span>&lt;</span><span>stdlib.h</span><span>&gt;</span>
<span>
[</span><span>[</span>deprecated<span>]</span><span>]</span>
<span>void</span> f<span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span><span>}</span>
<span>
[</span><span>[</span>nodiscard<span>]</span><span>]</span>
<span>int</span> g<span>(</span><span>int</span> x<span>)</span> <span>{</span>
<span>  return</span> x <span>+</span> <span>1</span><span>;</span>
<span>}
</span>
int main() <span>{</span>
  f<span>(</span><span>)</span><span>;</span> <span>// compile-time warning: 'f' is deprecated</span>
  g<span>(</span><span>1</span><span>)</span><span>;</span> <span>// compile-time warning</span>
  auto x <span>=</span> <span>0</span><span>b</span><span>1111</span><span>;</span>
  typeof<span>(</span>x<span>)</span> y <span>=</span> <span>1</span><span>'000'</span><span>000</span><span>;</span> <span>// type of y is the same as x</span>
  printf<span>(</span><span>"%d</span><span>\n</span><span>"</span><span>,</span> x<span>)</span><span>;</span> <span>// prints 15</span>
  printf<span>(</span><span>"%d</span><span>\n</span><span>"</span><span>,</span> y<span>)</span><span>;</span> <span>// prints 1000000</span>
  constexpr <span>int</span> N <span>=</span> <span>10</span><span>;</span>
<span>  // compile-time asserts using static_assert</span>
  static_assert <span>(</span>N <span>=</span><span>=</span> <span>10</span><span>,</span> <span>"N must be 10"</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
  bool a<span>[</span>N<span>]</span><span>;</span> <span>// array of N booleans</span>
<span>  for</span> <span>(</span><span>int</span> i <span>=</span> <span>0</span><span>;</span> i <span>&lt;</span> N<span>;</span> <span>+</span><span>+</span>i<span>)</span> <span>{</span>
    a<span>[</span>i<span>]</span> <span>=</span> <span>true</span><span>;</span>
<span>  }</span>
  printf<span>(</span><span>"%d</span><span>\n</span><span>"</span><span>,</span> a<span>[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span>)</span><span>;</span> <span>// prints 1</span>
<span>}</span>

</pre>
<ol>
<li>The first part of the code contains some preprocessor directives, which are instructions for the compiler to process the source code before compiling it. The <tt>#if</tt> directive checks a condition at compile time and includes the following code only if the condition is true. The <tt>__has_include</tt> macro is a feature of C++17 adopted by C23 that checks if a header file exists and can be included. In this instance, it is not useful because we know that <tt>stdio.h</tt> is present, but in other instances, this can prove useful to determine what headers are available.</li>
<li>The next part of the code defines two functions with attributes, which are annotations that provide additional information to the compiler about the behavior or usage of a function, variable, type, etc.
<ul>
<li>The [[deprecated]] attribute is a feature of C++14 adopted by C23 that marks a function as obsolete and discourages its use. The compiler will issue a warning if the function is called or referenced.</li>
<li>The [[nodiscard]] attribute is a feature of C++17 adopted by C23 that indicates that the return value of a function should not be ignored or discarded. The compiler will issue a warning if the function is called from a discarded-value expression.</li>
</ul>
<p>In this case, the function f is deprecated and does nothing, while the function g returns the input value plus one and should not be ignored. The first two lines of the main function call the functions f and g and trigger the warnings.</p></li>
<li>The third line of the main function declares a variable x with the auto keyword, which is a feature of C++11 that lets the compiler deduce the type of the variable from its initializer. In this case, the initializer is a binary literal, which is a feature of C++14 and adopted by C23 that allows writing integer constants in binary notation using the prefix 0b. The value of x is 0b1111, which is equivalent to 15 in decimal.</li>
<li>The fourth line declares another variable y with the typeof operator that returns the type of an expression. In this case, the expression is x, so the type of y is the same as the type of x. The initializer of y is a digit separator, which is a feature of C++14 adopted by C23 that allows inserting single quotes between digits in numeric literals to improve readability. The value of y is 1’000’000, which is equivalent to 1000000 in decimal.</li>
<li>The seventh line declares a constant variable N with the constexpr keyword, which is a feature of C++11 adopted by C23 that indicates that the value of the variable can be evaluated at compile time. The value of N is 10. Previously, one would often use a macro to define a compile-time constant (e.g., <tt>#define N 10</tt>).</li>
<li>The eighth line uses the static_assert keyword, which is a feature of C++11 adopted by C23 that performs a compile-time assertion check. The keyword takes a boolean expression and an optional string message as arguments. If the expression is false, the compiler will emit an error and stop the compilation, displaying the message. If the expression is true, the compiler will do nothing. In this case, the expression is N == 10, which is true, so the compilation continues.</li>
<li>The ninth line declares an array of N booleans named a. An array is a collection of elements of the same type that are stored in contiguous memory locations. The size of the array must be a constant expression, which is why N is declared with constexpr. We also use the keywords true and false which become standard in C23.</li>
</ol>
<p>There are many more features in C23, but it will take some time for compilers and system librairies to catch up.</p>
<p>My thoughts so far:</p>
<ul>
<li>The introduction of consexpr in C will probably help reduce the dependency on macros, which is a good idea generally. Macros work well in C, but when a bug is introduced, it can be difficult get meaningful error messages. It does not happen too often, but in large code bases, it can be a problem.</li>
<li>I personally rarely use auto and typeof in other languages, so I don’t expect to use them very much in C. In some specific cases, it can greatly simply one’s code, however. It is likely going to help reduce the reliance on macros.</li>
<li>The idea behind static_assert is great. You run a check that has no impact on the performance of the software, and may even help it. It is cheap and it can catch nasty bugs. It is not new to C, but adopting the C++ syntax is a good idea.</li>
<li>The <tt>__has_include</tt> feature can simplify supporting diverse compilers. It is good idea.</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div>

<p><img alt="" src="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/2ca999bef9535950f5b84281a4dab006?s=56&amp;d=mm&amp;r=g" srcset="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/2ca999bef9535950f5b84281a4dab006?s=112&amp;d=mm&amp;r=g 2x" height="56" width="56" decoding="async"> </p>

</div>

</article>

<nav aria-label="Posts">
<h2>Post navigation</h2>

</nav>
</main>
</div>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[FreeBSD evaluating Rust's adoption into base system (166 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://mail-archive.freebsd.org/cgi/getmsg.cgi?fetch=414797+0+current/freebsd-hackers</link>
            <guid>39081166</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 18:27:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://mail-archive.freebsd.org/cgi/getmsg.cgi?fetch=414797+0+current/freebsd-hackers">https://mail-archive.freebsd.org/cgi/getmsg.cgi?fetch=414797+0+current/freebsd-hackers</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39081166">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content">

<pre><strong>Date: </strong>     Sat, 20 Jan 2024 09:51:25 -0700
<strong>From: </strong>     Alan Somers &lt;asomers@freebsd.org&gt;
<strong>To: </strong>       FreeBSD Hackers &lt;freebsd-hackers@freebsd.org&gt;
<strong>Cc: </strong>       Warner Losh &lt;imp@bsdimp.com&gt;, Scott Long &lt;scottl@freebsd.org&gt;, meka@tilda.center
<strong>Subject: </strong>  The Case for Rust (in the base system)
<strong>Message-ID: </strong> &lt;<a href="https://mail-archive.freebsd.org/cgi/mid.cgi?db=irt&amp;id=CAOtMX2hAUiWdGPtpaCJLPZB%2Bj2yzNw5DSjUmkwTi%2B%2BmyemehCA@mail.gmail.com">CAOtMX2hAUiWdGPtpaCJLPZB%2Bj2yzNw5DSjUmkwTi%2B%2BmyemehCA@mail.gmail.com</a>&gt;
</pre>
<hr noshade="noshade">
<p><a href="https://mail-archive.freebsd.org/cgi/mid.cgi?db=irt&amp;id=CAOtMX2hAUiWdGPtpaCJLPZB%2Bj2yzNw5DSjUmkwTi%2B%2BmyemehCA@mail.gmail.com">next in thread</a>
| <a href="https://mail-archive.freebsd.org/cgi/getmsg.cgi?fetch=414797+0+current/freebsd-hackers+raw">raw e-mail</a>
| <a href="https://mail-archive.freebsd.org/mail/current/freebsd-hackers.html">index</a>
| <a href="https://mail-archive.freebsd.org/cgi/getmsg.cgi?fetch=0+0+current/freebsd-hackers+archive">archive</a>
| <a href="https://mail-archive.freebsd.org/search/search-mid/">help</a></p><hr noshade="noshade">
<pre>In a recent thread on src-committers, we discussed the costs and
benefits of including Rust code in the FreeBSD base system.  To
summarize, the cost is that it would double our build times.  imp
suggested adding an additional step after buildworld for stuff that
requires an external toolchain.  That would ease the build time pain.
The benefit is that some tools would become easier to write, or even
become possible.  Here is a list of actual and potential Rust projects
that could benefit from being in-tree.  If anybody else has items to
add, I suggest moving this into the project wiki:

Stuff that could only be written in Rust if it were in base
===========================================================

* ctl-exporter (I started this, but discovered that the CTL stats API is
  unstable, so it can't live in ports.  Instead, I had to do it in C).
  <a href="https://github.com/freebsd/freebsd-src/commit/1a7f22d9c211f504f6c48a86401469181a67ec34">https://github.com/freebsd/freebsd-src/commit/1a7f22d9c211f504f6c48a86401469181a67ec34</a>

* fusefs tests.  Absolutely impossible to do in C.  I considered Rust, but went
  with C++ so they could live in base.  They are too closely coupled to
  fusefs(5) to live out-of-tree.
  <a href="https://github.com/freebsd/freebsd-src/tree/main/tests/sys/fs/fusefs">https://github.com/freebsd/freebsd-src/tree/main/tests/sys/fs/fusefs</a>

* devd.  Currently C++, but imp suggested a rewrite.
  <a href="https://github.com/freebsd/freebsd-src/tree/main/sbin/devd">https://github.com/freebsd/freebsd-src/tree/main/sbin/devd</a>

* zfsd.  Currently C++, but I've long pondered a rewrite.  Using Rust would
  make it more testable.
  <a href="https://github.com/freebsd/freebsd-src/tree/main/cddl/usr.sbin/zfsd">https://github.com/freebsd/freebsd-src/tree/main/cddl/usr.sbin/zfsd</a>

* nscd.  Currently C, but confusing and with no test coverage.  I've
  contemplated a rewrite myself, but I don't want to do it in C.
  <a href="https://github.com/freebsd/freebsd-src/tree/main/usr.sbin/nscd">https://github.com/freebsd/freebsd-src/tree/main/usr.sbin/nscd</a>

* The userland portion of the 802.11ac and Lightning stacks.  scottl suggested
  that these were good candidates for Rust.

* freebsd-kpi-r14-0 .  <a href="https://crates.io/crates/freebsd-kpi-r14-0">https://crates.io/crates/freebsd-kpi-r14-0</a>

Stuff that can live in ports, but would be nicer in base
========================================================

* gstat-rs <a href="https://crates.io/crates/gstat">https://crates.io/crates/gstat</a>

* geom-exporter (I've started this, but haven't published it)

* nfs-exporter <a href="https://crates.io/crates/freebsd-nfs-exporter">https://crates.io/crates/freebsd-nfs-exporter</a>

* virtiofsd-rs .  Nobody has yet tried to port it to FreeBSD.  But if the
  connection to bhyve(8) is too intimate, it might be hard to do in ports.
  <a href="https://gitlab.com/virtio-fs/virtiofsd">https://gitlab.com/virtio-fs/virtiofsd</a>

* jail-exporter <a href="https://crates.io/crates/jail_exporter">https://crates.io/crates/jail_exporter</a>

* Various jail managers have been attempted in Rust.  I think these are fine in
  ports, but others like Goran Mekic have opined that they should be moved to
  base instead.

* musikid's pjdfstest rewrite.  I think it would be great to start using this
  to test the base system's file systems.  If the tests themselves lived in
  base, they would be easier to sync with file system development.
  <a href="https://github.com/musikid/pjdfstest">https://github.com/musikid/pjdfstest</a>

* pf-rs.  I suspect that the API isn't very stable.
  <a href="https://crates.io/crates/pf-rs">https://crates.io/crates/pf-rs</a>

* benchpmc.  The pmc counter names changes between releases.
  <a href="https://crates.io/crates/benchpmc">https://crates.io/crates/benchpmc</a>

FreeBSD-related applications that are just fine in ports
=========================================================

* fsx-rs.  Unlike pjdfstest, this only tests datapath APIs.  Those are usually
  more stable than control path APIs, so I think there's little to be gained by
  moving this into base. <a href="https://crates.io/crates/fsx">https://crates.io/crates/fsx</a>

* ztop.  It uses ZFS's kstats sysctl interface, which is pretty stable.
  <a href="https://crates.io/crates/ztop">https://crates.io/crates/ztop</a>

* iocage-provision  <a href="https://crates.io/crates/iocage-provision">https://crates.io/crates/iocage-provision</a>

* rsblk <a href="https://crates.io/crates/rsblk">https://crates.io/crates/rsblk</a>

* xfuse  <a href="https://github.com/KhaledEmaraDev/xfuse">https://github.com/KhaledEmaraDev/xfuse</a>

Other FreeBSD-related libraries in Rust
=======================================
Just see the list at <a href="https://crates.io/keywords/freebsd">https://crates.io/keywords/freebsd</a>


</pre>
<hr>
<p>Want to link to this message? Use this URL: &lt;<a href="https://mail-archive.freebsd.org/cgi/mid.cgi?CAOtMX2hAUiWdGPtpaCJLPZB%2Bj2yzNw5DSjUmkwTi%2B%2BmyemehCA">https://mail-archive.FreeBSD.org/cgi/mid.cgi?CAOtMX2hAUiWdGPtpaCJLPZB%2Bj2yzNw5DSjUmkwTi%2B%2BmyemehCA</a>&gt;</p>
	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA['Cozy' relationship between Boeing and U.S. draws scrutiny amid 737 MAX 9 mess (123 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.npr.org/2024/01/19/1225466035/boeing-737-max-faa-door-plug-alaska-crashes-ntsb</link>
            <guid>39080954</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 18:11:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.npr.org/2024/01/19/1225466035/boeing-737-max-faa-door-plug-alaska-crashes-ntsb">https://www.npr.org/2024/01/19/1225466035/boeing-737-max-faa-door-plug-alaska-crashes-ntsb</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39080954">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="storytext">
      <div id="res1225475606">
            <div data-crop-type="">
        <picture>
            <source srcset="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-139198177-fcb7088c16c87dc2bd7e7950f656e522d222a965-s400-c85.webp 400w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-139198177-fcb7088c16c87dc2bd7e7950f656e522d222a965-s600-c85.webp 600w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-139198177-fcb7088c16c87dc2bd7e7950f656e522d222a965-s800-c85.webp 800w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-139198177-fcb7088c16c87dc2bd7e7950f656e522d222a965-s900-c85.webp 900w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-139198177-fcb7088c16c87dc2bd7e7950f656e522d222a965-s1200-c85.webp 1200w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-139198177-fcb7088c16c87dc2bd7e7950f656e522d222a965-s1600-c85.webp 1600w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-139198177-fcb7088c16c87dc2bd7e7950f656e522d222a965-s1800-c85.webp 1800w" sizes="(min-width: 1300px) 763px, (min-width: 1025px) calc(100vw - 496px), (min-width: 768px) calc(100vw - 171px), calc(100vw - 30px)" type="image/webp">
            <source srcset="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-139198177-fcb7088c16c87dc2bd7e7950f656e522d222a965-s400-c85.jpg 400w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-139198177-fcb7088c16c87dc2bd7e7950f656e522d222a965-s600-c85.jpg 600w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-139198177-fcb7088c16c87dc2bd7e7950f656e522d222a965-s800-c85.jpg 800w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-139198177-fcb7088c16c87dc2bd7e7950f656e522d222a965-s900-c85.jpg 900w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-139198177-fcb7088c16c87dc2bd7e7950f656e522d222a965-s1200-c85.jpg 1200w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-139198177-fcb7088c16c87dc2bd7e7950f656e522d222a965-s1600-c85.jpg 1600w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-139198177-fcb7088c16c87dc2bd7e7950f656e522d222a965-s1800-c85.jpg 1800w" sizes="(min-width: 1300px) 763px, (min-width: 1025px) calc(100vw - 496px), (min-width: 768px) calc(100vw - 171px), calc(100vw - 30px)" type="image/jpeg">
            <img src="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-139198177-fcb7088c16c87dc2bd7e7950f656e522d222a965-s1100-c50.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy">
        </picture>
        
</div>
<div>
    <div>
        <p>
                Then-President Barack Obama walks down the stairs of a Boeing 787 Dreamliner at the company's production facility in Everett, Wash., in 2012.
                <b aria-label="Image credit">
                    
                    Saul Loeb/AFP via Getty Images
                    
                </b>
                <b><b>hide caption</b></b>
            </p>


            <p><b><b>toggle caption</b></b>
    </p></div>

    <p><span aria-label="Image credit">
        
        Saul Loeb/AFP via Getty Images
        
    </span>
</p></div>
<div>
        <picture>
            <source data-original="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-139198177-fcb7088c16c87dc2bd7e7950f656e522d222a965-s1200.webp" type="image/webp">
            <source data-original="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-139198177-fcb7088c16c87dc2bd7e7950f656e522d222a965-s1200.jpg" type="image/jpeg">
            <img data-original="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-139198177-fcb7088c16c87dc2bd7e7950f656e522d222a965-s1200.jpg" alt="" src="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-139198177-fcb7088c16c87dc2bd7e7950f656e522d222a965-s1200.jpg">
        </picture>
    </div>
<div>
        <p>Then-President Barack Obama walks down the stairs of a Boeing 787 Dreamliner at the company's production facility in Everett, Wash., in 2012.</p>
        <p><span aria-label="Image credit">
            
            Saul Loeb/AFP via Getty Images
            
        </span>
    </p></div>
   </div>
   <p>When he was still the president of the United States, Barack Obama joked about having another job on the side: salesman in chief.</p>   <p>"I'm expecting a gold watch from Boeing at the end of my presidency, because I know that I'm on the list of top salesmen at Boeing," Obama deadpanned in 2013.</p>   <p>Boeing is no ordinary company. It's a pillar of the U.S. economy, both as a military contractor and in civil aviation. It claims to be the country's largest exporter.</p>   <p>But the longstanding special relationship between the U.S. government and Boeing has come under growing scrutiny, particularly after two crashes involving Boeing's 737 Max 8 plane, in 2018 and 2019. Those tragedies prompted significant changes, with a new CEO at Boeing and revamped oversight rules at the Federal Aviation Administration.</p>   
   <p>Now the latest safety incident involving a Boeing jet, the 737 Max 9, is raising difficult questions about <a href="https://www.npr.org/2024/01/17/1224998393/boeing-737-max-9-downfall-documentary">whether that response went far enough</a>.</p>   
   
<!-- END ID="RES1225468504" CLASS="BUCKETWRAP INTERNALLINK INSETTWOCOLUMN INSET2COL " -->
   <p>Investigators are still trying to determine why a panel blew off an Alaska Airlines jet in midair earlier this month. Federal regulators have grounded 171 Max 9 planes with similar configurations, while launching a review of Boeing's manufacturing and production lines.</p>   <p>The head of the FAA says it's time to reexamine the longtime practice of delegating some of the agency's oversight responsibilities to Boeing employees, raising the possibility of moving some of those duties to a third party.</p>   <p>That would be a remarkable shift in how the federal government regulates a company that is an icon of American industry and innovation.</p>   <h3>The U.S. helps Boeing sell planes overseas</h3>   <p>Boeing's importance to the economy extends far beyond the more than 140,000 people that it employs directly. The company also supports a network of suppliers and contractors that reaches across the country.</p>   <p>"Small businesses are up and down the supply chain," Obama said <a href="https://youtu.be/v7vn3VdqsIk?si=3ews34EDez3npV1o&amp;t=6700">at the same meeting</a> of the President's Export Council where he joked about earning a gold watch from Boeing. "And when we sell a bunch of airplanes, a lot of small businesses and medium-sized businesses are benefiting from that as well."</p>   
   <p>Obama isn't the only president to act as a cheerleader for Boeing.</p>   <p>"God bless you, may God bless the United States of America, and God bless Boeing," then-President Donald Trump said during a 2017 visit to a plant in South Carolina where the company builds its 787 Dreamliner.</p>   <p>When it comes to civil aviation, Boeing has no rivals based in the U.S. Its primary competitor, Airbus, is headquartered in Europe, though it does build some planes here.</p>   <div id="res1225478476">
            <div data-crop-type="">
        <picture>
            <source srcset="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-1910140521-ad5bc0bdd1e31fa581971e3413bead358c85d3ad-s400-c85.webp 400w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-1910140521-ad5bc0bdd1e31fa581971e3413bead358c85d3ad-s600-c85.webp 600w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-1910140521-ad5bc0bdd1e31fa581971e3413bead358c85d3ad-s800-c85.webp 800w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-1910140521-ad5bc0bdd1e31fa581971e3413bead358c85d3ad-s900-c85.webp 900w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-1910140521-ad5bc0bdd1e31fa581971e3413bead358c85d3ad-s1200-c85.webp 1200w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-1910140521-ad5bc0bdd1e31fa581971e3413bead358c85d3ad-s1600-c85.webp 1600w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-1910140521-ad5bc0bdd1e31fa581971e3413bead358c85d3ad-s1800-c85.webp 1800w" sizes="(min-width: 1300px) 763px, (min-width: 1025px) calc(100vw - 496px), (min-width: 768px) calc(100vw - 171px), calc(100vw - 30px)" type="image/webp">
            <source srcset="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-1910140521-ad5bc0bdd1e31fa581971e3413bead358c85d3ad-s400-c85.jpg 400w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-1910140521-ad5bc0bdd1e31fa581971e3413bead358c85d3ad-s600-c85.jpg 600w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-1910140521-ad5bc0bdd1e31fa581971e3413bead358c85d3ad-s800-c85.jpg 800w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-1910140521-ad5bc0bdd1e31fa581971e3413bead358c85d3ad-s900-c85.jpg 900w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-1910140521-ad5bc0bdd1e31fa581971e3413bead358c85d3ad-s1200-c85.jpg 1200w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-1910140521-ad5bc0bdd1e31fa581971e3413bead358c85d3ad-s1600-c85.jpg 1600w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-1910140521-ad5bc0bdd1e31fa581971e3413bead358c85d3ad-s1800-c85.jpg 1800w" sizes="(min-width: 1300px) 763px, (min-width: 1025px) calc(100vw - 496px), (min-width: 768px) calc(100vw - 171px), calc(100vw - 30px)" type="image/jpeg">
            <img src="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-1910140521-ad5bc0bdd1e31fa581971e3413bead358c85d3ad-s1100-c50.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy">
        </picture>
        
</div>
<div>
    <div>
        <p>
                Investigators are still trying to determine why a panel known as a door plug blew off this Boeing 737 Max 9 jet earlier this month.
                <b aria-label="Image credit">
                    
                    National Transportation Safety Board via Getty Images
                    
                </b>
                <b><b>hide caption</b></b>
            </p>


            <p><b><b>toggle caption</b></b>
    </p></div>

    <p><span aria-label="Image credit">
        
        National Transportation Safety Board via Getty Images
        
    </span>
</p></div>
<div>
        <picture>
            <source data-original="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-1910140521-ad5bc0bdd1e31fa581971e3413bead358c85d3ad-s1200.webp" type="image/webp">
            <source data-original="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-1910140521-ad5bc0bdd1e31fa581971e3413bead358c85d3ad-s1200.jpg" type="image/jpeg">
            <img data-original="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-1910140521-ad5bc0bdd1e31fa581971e3413bead358c85d3ad-s1200.jpg" alt="" src="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/gettyimages-1910140521-ad5bc0bdd1e31fa581971e3413bead358c85d3ad-s1200.jpg">
        </picture>
    </div>
<div>
        <p>Investigators are still trying to determine why a panel known as a door plug blew off this Boeing 737 Max 9 jet earlier this month.</p>
        <p><span aria-label="Image credit">
            
            National Transportation Safety Board via Getty Images
            
        </span>
    </p></div>
   </div>
   <p>Still, U.S. leaders are willing to put a finger on the scale in Boeing's favor.</p>   <p>The federal government has an official credit agency, the Export-Import Bank of the United States, that extends financing for overseas buyers. It's sometimes described as "Boeing's bank," because the company is such a big beneficiary.</p>   <p>The U.S. government is, in a literal sense, helping Boeing sell planes overseas — and these days, that largely means the 737 Max series. It is <a href="https://www.npr.org/2019/04/29/718394234/boeing-ceo-defends-737-max-jets-against-angry-shareholders">the company's best-selling plane</a>, with thousands of pending orders, and is seen as crucial to Boeing's financial future.</p>   <p>None of this is supposed to affect how regulators at the FAA treat the company. But in the real world, Boeing wields a lot of power and influence in Washington.</p>   <p>"Boeing evidently does think it's too big to fail," Jim Hall, a former chairman of the National Transportation Safety Board, said in a recent interview.</p>   <p>"It's not complicated. In Washington, D.C., as everyone knows, there is a great deal of influence exercised through fundraising to members of Congress," Hall said. "There's a great coziness or familiarity between all of the parties. And so, who's the bad cop?"</p>   <h3>737 Max 8 crashes reveal systemic problems</h3>   <div id="res1225535281">
            <div data-crop-type="">
        <picture>
            <source srcset="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/lionair_custom-992db4ac8dfba6074ea8af2d25a3adedee96cdda-s400-c85.webp 400w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/lionair_custom-992db4ac8dfba6074ea8af2d25a3adedee96cdda-s600-c85.webp 600w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/lionair_custom-992db4ac8dfba6074ea8af2d25a3adedee96cdda-s800-c85.webp 800w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/lionair_custom-992db4ac8dfba6074ea8af2d25a3adedee96cdda-s900-c85.webp 900w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/lionair_custom-992db4ac8dfba6074ea8af2d25a3adedee96cdda-s1200-c85.webp 1200w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/lionair_custom-992db4ac8dfba6074ea8af2d25a3adedee96cdda-s1600-c85.webp 1600w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/lionair_custom-992db4ac8dfba6074ea8af2d25a3adedee96cdda-s1800-c85.webp 1800w" sizes="(min-width: 1300px) 763px, (min-width: 1025px) calc(100vw - 496px), (min-width: 768px) calc(100vw - 171px), calc(100vw - 30px)" type="image/webp">
            <source srcset="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/lionair_custom-992db4ac8dfba6074ea8af2d25a3adedee96cdda-s400-c85.jpg 400w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/lionair_custom-992db4ac8dfba6074ea8af2d25a3adedee96cdda-s600-c85.jpg 600w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/lionair_custom-992db4ac8dfba6074ea8af2d25a3adedee96cdda-s800-c85.jpg 800w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/lionair_custom-992db4ac8dfba6074ea8af2d25a3adedee96cdda-s900-c85.jpg 900w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/lionair_custom-992db4ac8dfba6074ea8af2d25a3adedee96cdda-s1200-c85.jpg 1200w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/lionair_custom-992db4ac8dfba6074ea8af2d25a3adedee96cdda-s1600-c85.jpg 1600w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/lionair_custom-992db4ac8dfba6074ea8af2d25a3adedee96cdda-s1800-c85.jpg 1800w" sizes="(min-width: 1300px) 763px, (min-width: 1025px) calc(100vw - 496px), (min-width: 768px) calc(100vw - 171px), calc(100vw - 30px)" type="image/jpeg">
            <img src="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/lionair_custom-992db4ac8dfba6074ea8af2d25a3adedee96cdda-s1100-c50.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy">
        </picture>
        
</div>
<div>
    <div>
        <p>
                Officials in Jakarta, Indonesia, inspect an engine recovered in November 2018 from a Boeing 737 Max 8 flown by Indonesia's Lion Air that crashed.
                <b aria-label="Image credit">
                    
                    Achmad Ibrahim/AP
                    
                </b>
                <b><b>hide caption</b></b>
            </p>


            <p><b><b>toggle caption</b></b>
    </p></div>

    <p><span aria-label="Image credit">
        
        Achmad Ibrahim/AP
        
    </span>
</p></div>
<div>
        <picture>
            <source data-original="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/lionair_custom-992db4ac8dfba6074ea8af2d25a3adedee96cdda-s1200.webp" type="image/webp">
            <source data-original="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/lionair_custom-992db4ac8dfba6074ea8af2d25a3adedee96cdda-s1200.jpg" type="image/jpeg">
            <img data-original="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/lionair_custom-992db4ac8dfba6074ea8af2d25a3adedee96cdda-s1200.jpg" alt="" src="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/lionair_custom-992db4ac8dfba6074ea8af2d25a3adedee96cdda-s1200.jpg">
        </picture>
    </div>
<div>
        <p>Officials in Jakarta, Indonesia, inspect an engine recovered in November 2018 from a Boeing 737 Max 8 flown by Indonesia's Lion Air that crashed.</p>
        <p><span aria-label="Image credit">
            
            Achmad Ibrahim/AP
            
        </span>
    </p></div>
   </div>
   <p>Ties between the U.S. government and Boeing came under intense criticism after the 2018 and 2019 crashes involving the company's 737 Max 8 planes. A total of 346 people were killed.</p>   
   <p>After the first crash, of a Lion Air jet in Indonesia, Boeing maintained that the pilots were mostly to blame. Five months later, an Ethiopian Airlines plane went down under very similar circumstances.</p>   <p>Regulators in many other countries immediately moved to ground the Boeing Max 8. But the Federal Aviation Administration waited several days, making it one of the last agencies to take that step.</p>   
   
<!-- END ID="RES1225468929" CLASS="BUCKETWRAP INTERNALLINK INSETTWOCOLUMN INSET2COL " -->
   <p>When congressional investigators started digging into what caused the crashes, they found <a href="https://www.npr.org/2020/09/16/913426448/congressional-inquiry-faults-boeing-and-faa-failures-for-deadly-737-max-plane-cr">a range of problems at Boeing</a> — both with the design of the Max 8's flight control systems, and with pilot training — and they found insufficient oversight by the FAA.</p>   <p>At a dramatic hearing in October 2019, family members held up photographs of the crash victims while Boeing CEO Dennis Muilenburg testified.</p>   <p>"We can and must do better. We've been challenged and changed by these accidents," Muilenburg told members of Congress.</p>   <p>One of the parents in the hearing room that day was Nadia Milleron, whose daughter Samya Stumo was killed in the second crash. Milleron confronted Boeing's CEO after the hearing.</p>   <p>"I asked him to resign, because I said that he made decisions which killed people, and then he refused to acknowledge it," she told NPR's <em>Morning Edition </em>in an <a href="https://www.npr.org/2019/10/30/774646279/victims-family-responds-to-boeing-ceos-testimony">interview at the time</a>.</p>   <p>"Our daughter got on the plane completely trusting," Milleron said. "And she never dreamed that there would be any problem with the plane itself, and there was a huge problem."</p>   <p>Muilenburg was pushed out of his job just a few months later.</p>   <div id="res1225535583">
            <div data-crop-type="">
        <picture>
            <source srcset="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/muilenburg_custom-2540c7a9d3d9bd7fb195802ff2eccba477075801-s400-c85.webp 400w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/muilenburg_custom-2540c7a9d3d9bd7fb195802ff2eccba477075801-s600-c85.webp 600w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/muilenburg_custom-2540c7a9d3d9bd7fb195802ff2eccba477075801-s800-c85.webp 800w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/muilenburg_custom-2540c7a9d3d9bd7fb195802ff2eccba477075801-s900-c85.webp 900w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/muilenburg_custom-2540c7a9d3d9bd7fb195802ff2eccba477075801-s1200-c85.webp 1200w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/muilenburg_custom-2540c7a9d3d9bd7fb195802ff2eccba477075801-s1600-c85.webp 1600w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/muilenburg_custom-2540c7a9d3d9bd7fb195802ff2eccba477075801-s1800-c85.webp 1800w" sizes="(min-width: 1300px) 763px, (min-width: 1025px) calc(100vw - 496px), (min-width: 768px) calc(100vw - 171px), calc(100vw - 30px)" type="image/webp">
            <source srcset="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/muilenburg_custom-2540c7a9d3d9bd7fb195802ff2eccba477075801-s400-c85.jpg 400w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/muilenburg_custom-2540c7a9d3d9bd7fb195802ff2eccba477075801-s600-c85.jpg 600w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/muilenburg_custom-2540c7a9d3d9bd7fb195802ff2eccba477075801-s800-c85.jpg 800w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/muilenburg_custom-2540c7a9d3d9bd7fb195802ff2eccba477075801-s900-c85.jpg 900w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/muilenburg_custom-2540c7a9d3d9bd7fb195802ff2eccba477075801-s1200-c85.jpg 1200w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/muilenburg_custom-2540c7a9d3d9bd7fb195802ff2eccba477075801-s1600-c85.jpg 1600w,
https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/muilenburg_custom-2540c7a9d3d9bd7fb195802ff2eccba477075801-s1800-c85.jpg 1800w" sizes="(min-width: 1300px) 763px, (min-width: 1025px) calc(100vw - 496px), (min-width: 768px) calc(100vw - 171px), calc(100vw - 30px)" type="image/jpeg">
            <img src="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/muilenburg_custom-2540c7a9d3d9bd7fb195802ff2eccba477075801-s1100-c50.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy">
        </picture>
        
</div>
<div>
    <div>
        <p>
                Then-Boeing CEO Dennis Muilenburg (center foreground) prepares to testify during an Oct. 29, 2019, hearing on Capitol Hill as family members hold up photographs of those killed in the Ethiopian Airlines Flight 302 and Lion Air Flight 610 crashes.
                <b aria-label="Image credit">
                    
                    Andrew Harnik/AP
                    
                </b>
                <b><b>hide caption</b></b>
            </p>


            <p><b><b>toggle caption</b></b>
    </p></div>

    <p><span aria-label="Image credit">
        
        Andrew Harnik/AP
        
    </span>
</p></div>
<div>
        <picture>
            <source data-original="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/muilenburg_custom-2540c7a9d3d9bd7fb195802ff2eccba477075801-s1200.webp" type="image/webp">
            <source data-original="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/muilenburg_custom-2540c7a9d3d9bd7fb195802ff2eccba477075801-s1200.jpg" type="image/jpeg">
            <img data-original="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/muilenburg_custom-2540c7a9d3d9bd7fb195802ff2eccba477075801-s1200.jpg" alt="" src="https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2024/01/18/muilenburg_custom-2540c7a9d3d9bd7fb195802ff2eccba477075801-s1200.jpg">
        </picture>
    </div>
<div>
        <p>Then-Boeing CEO Dennis Muilenburg (center foreground) prepares to testify during an Oct. 29, 2019, hearing on Capitol Hill as family members hold up photographs of those killed in the Ethiopian Airlines Flight 302 and Lion Air Flight 610 crashes.</p>
        <p><span aria-label="Image credit">
            
            Andrew Harnik/AP
            
        </span>
    </p></div>
   </div>
   <h3>"A case study of the complete and total failure of self-regulation"</h3>   <p>Congressional hearings on the design and certification of the 737 Max 8 also brought to light some <a href="https://www.npr.org/2020/01/09/795123158/boeing-employees-mocked-faa-in-internal-messages-before-737-max-disasters">troubling internal emails</a> from Boeing employees, who mocked their colleagues as well as regulators at the FAA.</p>   <p>"This airplane is designed by clowns who in turn are supervised by monkeys," one employee wrote.</p>   
   <p>Another Boeing employee wrote that a presentation for regulators was "like dogs watching TV," because the regulators didn't understand what they were seeing.</p>   
   
<!-- END ID="RES1225479190" CLASS="BUCKETWRAP INTERNALLINK INSETTWOCOLUMN INSET2COL " -->
   <p>Investigators learned that Boeing had hidden key details about the 737 Max 8's flight control systems from regulators before they signed off on the plane's design.</p>   <p>They also found that FAA regulators had determined after the first crash that the Max 8 was likely to have the same problem again, but did not make those calculations public at the time.</p>   <p>That brought harsh criticism from safety advocates and Democrats on Capitol Hill.</p>   <p>"We must reexamine the current system that allowed for a much too cozy relationship between regulators and companies, including Boeing," then-Sen. Tom Udall, D-N.M., said at a hearing in 2020.</p>   <p>"This continues to be a case study of the complete and total failure of self-regulation," Udall said. "And I think this will go down as one of the big mistakes in history in this area."</p>   <h3><strong>A long history of delegating oversight to industry </strong></h3>   <p>The FAA has delegated some of its oversight authority to manufacturers since the 1950s. But regulators have come to rely more and more on Boeing over time, as its planes have gotten more complex and supply chains have grown longer.</p>   <p>This pattern accelerated in the early 2000s, says Peter Robison, an investigative reporter for Bloomberg News and the author of <em>Flying Blind: The 737 MAX Tragedy and the Fall of Boeing</em>.</p>   <p>Regulators at the FAA were pushed by the bosses to hand off more work to Boeing, Robison says — partly because they trusted that Boeing engineers knew the planes best and partly because it was cheaper for the FAA.</p>   
   
<!-- END ID="RES1225470911" CLASS="BUCKETWRAP INTERNALLINK INSETTWOCOLUMN INSET2COL " -->
   <p>"What I traced was a distortion in the relationship where the regulator came to feel almost that it worked for Boeing," Robison told NPR's <em>Here and Now</em> <a href="https://www.wbur.org/hereandnow/2024/01/09/boeing-737-max-9-culture">earlier this month</a>. "The managers worked very closely with Boeing to speed production of planes. And the managers at the FAA really came to treat Boeing as its customer rather than the flying public as the people it was serving."</p>   <p>At the same time, Robison says, the corporate culture at Boeing was changing too, becoming more focused on profit and less on quality.</p>   
   <h3><strong>Max 8 crashes prompt sweeping changes </strong></h3>   <p>After the Max 8 tragedies, Congress passed bipartisan legislation aimed at preventing the company or the FAA from repeating the mistakes that led to the deadly crashes. The FAA made changes that were supposed to tighten up how its authority is delegated.</p>   <p>A new CEO took over at Boeing, pledging to restore the company's commitment to quality and safety.</p>   <p>After nearly two years, regulators cleared the Max 8 to begin flying again, and Boeing began trying to rebuild its reputation with airlines and the flying public.</p>   
   
<!-- END ID="RES1225481110" CLASS="BUCKETWRAP INTERNALLINK INSETTWOCOLUMN INSET2COL " -->
   <p>Then came Jan. 5, 2024, when a panel known as a door plug blew off a Boeing jet — this time a 737 Max 9 — at 16,000 feet, raising troubling questions for the company and the FAA once again.</p>   <p>There are several key differences between the Alaska Airlines incident and the Max 8 crashes.</p>   <p>No one was killed or seriously injured last month, although NTSB investigators said the incident could have been much worse had it had occurred at a higher altitude. And while the cause of the latest incident is still under investigation, it appears to be a problem in the manufacturing process, not a design flaw.</p>   <p>Still, Boeing's critics see a troubling similarity between the events. The company once again appears to be putting the bottom line ahead of safety, they say, by rushing planes off the factory floor at the rate of more than one per day.</p>   <p>This time, however, Boeing has moved quickly to own up to its mistake.</p>   <p>"This event can never happen again," CEO Dave Calhoun said at an all-hands meeting last week at a factory near Seattle. He told employees: "We're gonna approach this — No. 1 — acknowledging our mistake. We are gonna approach it with 100% and complete transparency every step of the way."</p>   <p>The reaction of the FAA has been different, too. This time, regulators moved quickly to ground all 737 Max 9 jets with door plugs. And they seem to be in no rush to recertify those planes to fly again.</p>   
   <h3><strong>Another look at how oversight is delegated</strong></h3>   <p>The FAA says it's now considering even bigger changes to the way it regulates Boeing.</p>   <p>"It is time to reexamine the delegation of authority and assess any associated safety risks," FAA Administrator Mike Whitaker <a href="https://www.npr.org/2024/01/12/1224444590/boeing-faa-737-max-9-alaska-airlines-door-plug">said last week</a>. "The grounding of the 737-9 and the multiple production-related issues identified in recent years require us to look at every option to reduce risk."</p>   
   
<!-- END ID="RES1225469145" CLASS="BUCKETWRAP INTERNALLINK INSETTWOCOLUMN INSET2COL " -->
   <p>Regulators say they will consider whether to move quality oversight and inspections to an independent third party.</p>   <p>That would be a major shift in the relationship between the FAA and Boeing — one that some safety advocates say is long overdue.</p>   <p>"This is a very smart move by the FAA," said David Soucie, a former FAA safety inspector and the author of the book <em>Why Planes Crash</em>. "The drive for profitability may just be overriding this ability to have an independent delegation within the organization."</p>   <p>It's a difficult moment for the FAA and Whitaker, who took over as administrator <a href="https://www.npr.org/2023/10/18/1206607841/senate-committee-michael-whitaker-faa-administrator">just a few months ago</a>. FAA safety inspectors cannot inspect every bolt on every plane that leaves the Boeing factory. But business as usual at the agency no longer seems like a good option either.</p>   <p>What's at stake is how the FAA regulates one of the biggest companies in the aviation industry — and in the entire U.S. economy.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[On the dimensionality of spacetime (1997) [pdf] (112 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://space.mit.edu/home/tegmark/dimensions.pdf</link>
            <guid>39080201</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 16:59:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://space.mit.edu/home/tegmark/dimensions.pdf">https://space.mit.edu/home/tegmark/dimensions.pdf</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39080201">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://space.mit.edu/home/tegmark/dimensions.pdf: Error: unable to verify the first certificate]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Learn Datalog Today (138 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.learndatalogtoday.org/</link>
            <guid>39080003</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 16:38:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.learndatalogtoday.org/">https://www.learndatalogtoday.org/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39080003">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><strong>Learn Datalog Today</strong> is an interactive tutorial designed to teach you the <a href="https://datomic.com/">Datomic</a> dialect of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Datalog">Datalog</a>. Datalog is a declarative <strong>database query language</strong> with roots in logic programming. Datalog has similar expressive power as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sql">SQL</a>.</p><p>Datomic is a database with an interesting and novel architecture, giving its users a unique set of features. You can read more about Datomic at <a href="http://datomic.com/">https://datomic.com</a> and the architecture is described in some detail <a href="https://www.infoq.com/articles/Architecture-Datomic">in this InfoQ article</a>.</p><h2>Table of Contents</h2><ul><li><a href="https://www.learndatalogtoday.org/chapter/0">Extensible Data Notation</a></li><li><a href="https://www.learndatalogtoday.org/chapter/1">Basic Queries</a></li><li><a href="https://www.learndatalogtoday.org/chapter/2">Data Patterns</a></li><li><a href="https://www.learndatalogtoday.org/chapter/3">Parameterized Queries</a></li><li><a href="https://www.learndatalogtoday.org/chapter/4">More Queries</a></li><li><a href="https://www.learndatalogtoday.org/chapter/5">Predicates</a></li><li><a href="https://www.learndatalogtoday.org/chapter/6">Transformation Functions</a></li><li><a href="https://www.learndatalogtoday.org/chapter/7">Aggregates</a></li><li><a href="https://www.learndatalogtoday.org/chapter/8">Rules</a></li></ul><p>This tutorial was written on rainy days for the <a href="http://lispinsummerprojects.org/">Lisp In Summer Projects</a> 2013. If you find bugs, or have suggestions on how to improve the tutorial, please visit the project on <a href="https://github.com/jonase/learndatalogtoday">github</a>.</p><p>Many thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/RobStuttaford">Robert Stuttaford</a> for his careful proof reading/editing. I'd also like to thank everyone who has <a href="https://github.com/jonase/learndatalogtoday/graphs/contributors">contributed</a> by fixing bugs and spelling mistakes.</p><p>If you learn datalog today, you can consider <a href="https://github.com/sponsors/jonase">sponsoring</a> the maintenance and running costs of this website.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Free and Open Source Alternative to Airdrop (210 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.sharedrop.io/</link>
            <guid>39079256</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 15:26:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.sharedrop.io/">https://www.sharedrop.io/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39079256">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
    <p><span>Loading...</span></p>

    

    
    
    

    
  

</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[NASA regains contact with mini-helicopter on Mars (314 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://phys.org/news/2024-01-nasa-regains-contact-mini-helicopter.amp</link>
            <guid>39078669</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 14:23:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://phys.org/news/2024-01-nasa-regains-contact-mini-helicopter.amp">https://phys.org/news/2024-01-nasa-regains-contact-mini-helicopter.amp</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39078669">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
    

    
    

    <div id="popover">
            <p>
             This article has been reviewed according to Science&nbsp;X's <a href="https://sciencex.com/help/editorial-process/" target="_blank">editorial process</a>
                and <a href="https://sciencex.com/help/editorial-standards/" target="_blank"> policies</a>. 
                <a href="https://sciencex.com/help/editorial-team/" target="_blank">Editors</a> have highlighted the following attributes while ensuring the content's credibility: 
            </p>
            <div>
                                            <p><span></span> fact-checked
                </p>
                                                                                                                                                <p><span></span> reputable news agency
                </p>
                                                                                        <p><span></span> proofread
                </p>
                                          
            </div>
            </div>

    

    

    
    
<div>
    <figure itemprop="image" itemscope="" itemtype="https://schema.org/ImageObject" id="i1131629">
        <amp-img on="tap:lbx1131629" role="button" tabindex="0" src="https://scx2.b-cdn.net/gfx/news/2024/nasas-tiny-ingenuity-h.jpg" srcset="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/800w/2024/nasas-tiny-ingenuity-h.jpg?f=webp 800w" layout="responsive" width="1280" height="936" alt="NASA's tiny Ingenuity helicopter is seen sitting on the surface of Mars in a photograph taken by the rover Perseverance">
        </amp-img>
                    <figcaption itemprop="description" on="tap:AMP.setState({expanded: !expanded})" tabindex="0" role="button" [class]="expanded ? 'desc expanded' : 'desc'">
                NASA's tiny Ingenuity helicopter is seen sitting on the surface of Mars in a photograph taken by the rover Perseverance.
            </figcaption>
            </figure>
    <amp-lightbox id="lbx1131629" layout="nodisplay" animate-in="fly-in-bottom">
        <div>
            <p><span>× </span> close
            </p>
            <amp-img on="tap:lbx1131629" role="button" tabindex="0" src="https://scx2.b-cdn.net/gfx/news/2024/nasas-tiny-ingenuity-h.jpg" layout="fill" alt="NASA's tiny Ingenuity helicopter is seen sitting on the surface of Mars in a photograph taken by the rover Perseverance">
            </amp-img>
            <figcaption on="tap:AMP.setState({collapsed: !collapsed})" role="button" tabindex="0" [class]="!collapsed ? 'expanded' : ''">
                NASA's tiny Ingenuity helicopter is seen sitting on the surface of Mars in a photograph taken by the rover Perseverance.
            </figcaption>
        </div>
    </amp-lightbox>
</div><p>NASA has re-established contact with its tiny helicopter on Mars, the US space agency said Saturday, after an unexpected outage prompted fears that the hard-working craft had finally met its end.</p>


		    <!-- Phys.org - News - AMP -->
		

                    <p>Ingenuity, a drone about 1.6 feet (0.5 meters) tall, arrived on Mars in 2021 aboard the rover Perseverance and became the first motorized craft to fly autonomously on another planet.</p>
<p>Data from the helicopter are transmitted via Perseverance back to Earth, but communications were suddenly lost during a test flight on Thursday, Ingenuity's 72nd lift-off on Mars.</p>
<p>"Good news today," NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory (JPL) wrote on X, formerly Twitter, late Saturday.</p>
<p>The agency said that contact had finally been made with the helicopter by commanding Perseverance to "perform long-duration listening sessions for Ingenuity's signal."</p>
<p>"The team is reviewing the new data to better understand the unexpected comms dropout during Flight 72," it added.</p>
<p>NASA previously said that Ingenuity had attained an altitude of 40 feet (12 meters) on Flight 72, which was a "quick pop-up vertical flight to check out the helicopter's systems, following an unplanned early landing during its previous flight."</p>
<p>But during its descent, "communications between the helicopter and rover terminated early, prior to touchdown," the agency said.</p>
<p>JPL had noted on Friday that Perseverance was temporarily "out of line-of-sight with Ingenuity, but the team could consider driving closer for a visual inspection."</p>
<p>In a response to a post on X asking if Ingenuity would be able to fly again, JPL said Saturday that "the team needs to assess the new data before that can be determined."</p>
<p>NASA has lost contact with the helicopter before, including for an agonizing two months last year.</p>
<p>The mini rotorcraft, which weighs just four pounds (1.8 kilograms), has far exceeded its original goal of undertaking five flights over 30 days on the red planet.</p>
<p>In all, it has covered just over 10 miles (17 kilometers) and reached altitudes of up to 79 feet (24 meters).</p>
<p>Its longevity has proved remarkable, particularly considering that it must survive glacially cold Martian nights, kept warm by the <a href="https://phys.org/tags/solar+panels/" rel="tag">solar panels</a> that recharge its batteries during daylight hours.</p>
<p>Working with Perseverance, it has acted as an aerial scout to assist its wheeled companion in searching for possible signs of ancient microbial life.</p>

		 

            <!-- Phys.org - News - AMP -->
		
		
													
				
        

                    <p>© 2024 AFP</p>
        
        
	</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google Is Tracking You Even in Incognito Mode, New Disclaimer Is Up (200 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.abplive.com/technology/google-incognito-new-disclaimer-canary-version-you-are-being-tracked-even-in-google-incognito-mode-new-disclaimer-is-up-privacy-lawsuit-1658159</link>
            <guid>39078417</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 13:53:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://news.abplive.com/technology/google-incognito-new-disclaimer-canary-version-you-are-being-tracked-even-in-google-incognito-mode-new-disclaimer-is-up-privacy-lawsuit-1658159">https://news.abplive.com/technology/google-incognito-new-disclaimer-canary-version-you-are-being-tracked-even-in-google-incognito-mode-new-disclaimer-is-up-privacy-lawsuit-1658159</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39078417">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section>
              <!-- Start Middle Page -->
              

<section>   
        
    <h2>The new disclaimer of Google's incognito mode reads, "This won’t change how data is collected by websites you visit and the services they use, including Google."</h2>    
    <!--ad-->

<!--ad-->   
    <div>
     
                
        <div id="featured_image_container">
            <div><p><img title="Google Is Tracking You Even In Incognito Mode, New Disclaimer Is Up" src="https://news.abplive.com/technology/this.onerror=null;this.src='https://cdn.abplive.com/imagebank/default_16x9.png';" data-src="https://feeds.abplive.com/onecms/images/uploaded-images/2024/01/21/43937a1e75dae5f0292fff79825414101705815201999555_original.png?impolicy=abp_cdn&amp;imwidth=720" alt="Google Incognito New Disclaimer Canary Version You Are Being Tracked Even In Google Incognito Mode New Disclaimer Is Up Privacy Lawsuit Google Is Tracking You Even In Incognito Mode, New Disclaimer Is Up" onerror="this.onerror=null;this.src='https://cdn.abplive.com/imagebank/default_16x9.png';"></p></div><div><p>Google releases new disclaimer in incognito to let you know that you are being tracked ( Image Source :Getty )</p></div>                    </div>

        <div id="article-hfix">
            <div id="article-hstick-inner">
                                <p>Google has finally admitted that it tracks your search history, activities, the websites you visit and the services they use even in Incognito mode. Following the search engine's agreement to settle a $5 billion USD privacy lawsuit that accused it of tracking users illegally in incognito mode, it has now updated the disclaimer to reflect the transparency. In its Canary version (Early-access version which allows users and developers to test new features and updates before they are rolled out for everyone), Google now states that data will still be collected even in Incognito mode.</p>
<p>The normal disclaimer which you can see in Incognito mode at the moment is- "Now you can browse privately, and other people who use this device won’t see your activity. However, downloads, bookmarks and reading list items will be saved." However, in the Canary version, the disclaimer reads, "Others who use this device won’t see your activity, so you can browse more privately. This won’t change how data is collected by websites you visit and the services they use, including Google. Downloads, bookmarks and reading list items will be saved."</p>
<h2><span>Why Does It Make A Difference?</span></h2>
<p>Speculations of the search engine tracking users in the incognito mode were always there but Google never confirmed that it continues to track users despite them being in incognito mode. However, now, after putting up this disclaimer, it has clarified that indeed does track your activities. Notably, this does not mean that Google is now starting to track your activities and was not doing so before. It means that they were doing that earlier as well but now they have admitted to it finally.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
<p>Users must be cautious about using Google even in incognito mode as it is not just the search engine that tracks you but the websites also do. Are you one of the people who used to open the incognito mode to book flight tickets so that you could avoid surge prices? You might encounter that surge now as both Google as well as the ticket-selling website will be tracking your activity.</p>

                                                                                              
               
            </div>
           
            <div>
                    <p>Published at : 21 Jan 2024 11:05 AM (IST)</p>
                                    </div>
            
            
        </div>
    </div>

        

</section>

<section>
    <div>
                        <h2>Technology Videos</h2>        </div>
    <section>
        <a href="https://news.abplive.com/videos/news/india-chandrayaan-3-launch-14-july-will-be-written-in-golden-words-pm-narendra-modi-abp-news-1615884" title="Chandrayaan 3 launch: '14 July will be written in golden words': PM Narendra Modi | Abp News">
                
                <p><img src="https://news.abplive.com/technology/this.onerror=null;this.src='https://cdn.abplive.com/imagebank/default_16x9.png';" data-src="https://feeds.abplive.com/onecms/images/uploaded-images/2023/07/14/5490a86500085ec3d642181e04d8c1fc1689324615704326_original.jpg?impolicy=abp_cdn&amp;imwidth=470" alt="Chandrayaan 3 launch: '14 July will be written in golden words': PM Narendra Modi | Abp News" onerror="this.onerror=null;this.src='https://cdn.abplive.com/imagebank/default_16x9.png';" data-rel="https://images.abplive.in/transcoding-videos/64b0ec9aee2b1d0ba3e4d929/hover_gif_64b0ec9aee2b1d0ba3e4d929.gif" onmouseenter="changeImage(this);" onmouseout="resetImage(this)">
                    <span><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="32" height="32" viewBox="0 0 32 32" fill="none">
                            <use xlink:href="https://news.abplive.com/abp-web/assets/images/desktop/sprite.svg#vid-icon"></use>
                        </svg></span>
                </p>
                <p>Chandrayaan 3 launch: '14 July will be written in golden words': PM Narendra Modi | Abp News
                </p>
            </a>        
        
    </section>
</section>


<section>
    <div>
                        <h2>Technology Photo Gallery</h2>        </div>



    
    
</section>

              <!-- End Middle Page -->
              

            </section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Password may not contain: select, insert, update, delete, drop (289 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://id.uni-lj.si/DigitalnaIdentiteta/PonastavitevGesla?culture=en-GB</link>
            <guid>39078372</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 13:46:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://id.uni-lj.si/DigitalnaIdentiteta/PonastavitevGesla?culture=en-GB">https://id.uni-lj.si/DigitalnaIdentiteta/PonastavitevGesla?culture=en-GB</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39078372">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Your password protects your digital identity.
Please select a strong password that you will be able to remember.
Avoid passwords that are easy to guess such as your first name, your last name, the name of your partner, your date of birth, etc.
Your password needs to be <strong>at least 10 characters</strong> long and it must not include your first or last name and has to fulfill at least 3 of the given criteria:</p>
<ul>
<li> uppercase letters of the English alphabet, </li>
<li> lowercase letters of the English alphabet, </li>
<li> numbers, </li>
<li> symbols: <strong><code>-_.+@</code></strong>.</li> 
</ul>
<p>Your password must also not contain the following character combinations:
<code>script</code>, <code>select</code>, <code>insert</code>, <code>update</code>, <code>delete</code>, <code>drop</code>, <code>--</code>, <code>'</code>, <code>/*</code>, <code>*/</code>.</p></div><p>Please enter the password twice in order to avoid typos.</p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Some fish live beyond 100 and get healthier as they age (174 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nationalgeographic.com/premium/article/buffalofish-oldest-hundred-years-mystery</link>
            <guid>39078061</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 13:01:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/premium/article/buffalofish-oldest-hundred-years-mystery">https://www.nationalgeographic.com/premium/article/buffalofish-oldest-hundred-years-mystery</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39078061">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section><article><div><header><ul><li><a tabindex="0" href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/animals"><span>Animals</span></a></li></ul><div><p>Buffalofish have surprisingly long life spans, a new study shows—and live their best lives into their 80s and 90s. What can humans learn from them?</p></div></header></div><div><p>Angler Stuart Black has caught a lot of fish in his days, but when he landed his first buffalofish in <a href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/travel/destination/arizona" target="_blank">Arizona</a>’s Apache Lake in 2019, he had a hunch something was special about it.</p><p>“I didn’t even know why at the time,” he says. At 13 pounds, it wasn’t even that big—he’s caught bigger.</p><p>Turns out, his intuition was right. Scientists recently confirmed that the majority of the buffalofish swimming around this remote desert lake in eastern Arizona are older than a hundred.</p><p>The discovery builds on other recent research that has upended beliefs about the little-studied buffalofish, a genus of five <a href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/animals/fish/facts/freshwater-fish" target="_blank">freshwater fish</a> species native to North America.</p><p>Just a few years ago, scientists thought that these fish, which come in an array of colors from chestnut brown to bluish, only lived into their mid-20s. However, a <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s42003-019-0452-0" target="_blank">2019 study</a> revealed that <a href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/animals/article/oldest-freshwater-fish-discovered-radiocarbon-dating" target="_blank">bigmouth buffalofish could live up to 112 years old</a>, making it the oldest known freshwater teleost, a group of about 12,000 ray-finned fish species found worldwide. Then in January, researchers <a href="https://cdnsciencepub.com/doi/abs/10.1139/cjfas-2022-0122" target="_blank">announced the discovery of a 127-year-old bigmouth</a> in Saskatchewan, Canada.</p><p>Now, the new study, <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-023-44328-8" target="_blank">published recently in <i>Scientific Reports</i></a><i>,</i> confirmed that two more buffalofish species—the smallmouth buffalo and the black buffalo—can live more than a hundred years, making it the only known genus of animal besides the marine rockfish, <i>Sebastes,&nbsp;</i>that has three centenarian species.<b>&nbsp;</b></p><p>This is not to say that other animals can’t achieve remarkably long life spans. <a href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/animals/article/greenland-sharks-animals-science-age" target="_blank">Greenland sharks have the greatest longevity of any living vertebrate</a>, reaching at least 250 years old.</p><p>What’s more, research has revealed that buffalofish continue to live their best lives into their upper 80s and 90s, with better stress response and immune function relative to younger individuals. <a href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/animals/article/flamingo-albatross-longevity-clam" target="_blank"><i>(See six of the world’s longest-lived animals.)</i></a></p><p>“The one takeaway is that buffalofishes do not conform to preconceived notions,” says study leader <a href="https://scse.d.umn.edu/faculty-staff/alec-lackmann" target="_blank">Alec Lackmann</a>, a fish expert at the University of Minnesota. “They defy expectations.”</p><h2><b>Desert discovery</b></h2><p>For the Arizona study, a few dozen anglers, including Black, caught 222 buffalofish at Apache Lake from July 2018 to July 2023. Twenty three were humanely euthanized and donated to the research team, who estimated the fishes’ ages by removing and analyzing tiny ear stones called otoliths. These calcium carbonate structures, which allow fish to hear and sense vibrations in the water, form a new layer each year that can be read somewhat like tree rings.</p><p>The otolith analysis revealed that about 90 percent of Apache Lake’s buffalofishes were more than 85 years old. Researchers aged individuals of all three species studied there—smallmouth buffalo, bigmouth buffalo, and black buffalo—past a hundred years old.</p><p>For the other 199 fish, the anglers used a technique called catch-photo-release, in which they reeled in fish with tiny barbed or no-barbed hooks that avoid hurting the animal. All were photographed, and 129 were weighed before releasing them back into the lake. Researchers estimated live fishes’ ages by studying orange and black spots in the anglers’ photographs.</p><p>“Several species of large riverine fishes like sturgeon and alligator gar are known to live more than 50 years,” says Nathan Farnau, curator of fishes and invertebrates at the <a href="http://www.georgiaaquarium.org/" target="_blank">Georgia Aquarium</a> in Atlanta, who wasn’t involved in the study.</p><p>“But it’s always really exciting when researchers can find physical evidence of fish that are more than a hundred years old."</p><h2><b>Hardy non-natives</b></h2><p>What makes these findings even more remarkable, Lackmann says, is that these fish aren’t even native to the state. About 400 of them arrived to Arizona by rail in 1918 as part of a U.S. Bureau of Fisheries plan to establish a commercial fishery in Roosevelt Lake, a dammed reservoir on the Salt River. Apache Lake, part of the same river system, was later established and some of the fish eventually migrated there by swimming downstream.</p><p>The bigmouth buffalo’s native range spans from southern Saskatchewan down into Texas and Louisiana, with smallmouth and black buffalo sharing similar ranges that also include parts of Ontario, New Mexico, and Mexico. The fish in Apache Lake likely came from a hatchery in Iowa, Lackmann says.</p><p>He adds that the new findings indicate that some of the original stockfish still live in the Salt River system. <a href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/animals/article/110609-coelacanths-long-lived-fish-science-animals" target="_blank"><i>(Read about coelacanths, an ancient fish that can reach a hundred years.)</i></a></p><p>“It's like a rugged desert environment in that reservoir, yet they still are able to persist across a century,” Lackmann says. “Just imagine taking a wild animal and putting it in a novel habitat like that. If anything, you would expect they wouldn't live as long.”</p><h2><b>Fountain of youth?</b></h2><p>Buffalofish can go decades between successful reproductions because they require very specific environmental conditions—most of which are still unknown—to procreate. That’s why the fish evolved to live so long: It’s an evolutionary adaptation to account for long periods without breeding, according to Lackmann.</p><p>In Saskatchewan, where buffalofish can go up to 50 years without producing offspring, the fish only attempt to spawn within a narrow range of water-level fluctuations that may rarely occur.</p><p>Lackmann says further studies into buffalofish longevity could provide insight into how vertebrates, including humans, can live longer. <a href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/magazine/article/aging-cure-longevity-science-technology-feature" target="_blank"><i>(Read: “Can aging be cured? Scientists are giving it a try.”)</i></a></p><p>“One of the major outstanding questions about the buffalofishes is how they do it in terms of their amazing longevity. What is their fountain of youth?”</p><p>One strategy may be understanding why older buffalofish are less stressed and have stronger immunity than younger fish, which was <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-021-88626-5" target="_blank">confirmed in a 2021 study on bigmouth buffalofish</a>.</p><p>Older individuals could fight off bacteria better than younger animals. Not only that, the elderly fish had a lower ratio of neutrophils to lymphocytes in the blood, an indication of lower stress levels.</p><p>“They are still advancing into prime condition at a century old, which is astonishing,” Lackmann says.</p><p>Meanwhile, conservation is a priority, he says. Buffalofish are a prized sportfish in the upper Midwest, and while their numbers are declining, harvest is virtually unregulated—including in Arizona.</p><p>“Right now, you can go to Apache Lake, catch a buffalofish, and just take it home,” Black says. “So for me, getting them protected now is probably the most important thing.”</p></div></article></section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Remembering Bell Labs as legendary idea factory prepares to leave N.J. home (164 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nj.com/essex/2024/01/remembering-bell-labs-as-legendary-idea-factory-prepares-to-leave-nj-home.html</link>
            <guid>39077867</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 12:31:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nj.com/essex/2024/01/remembering-bell-labs-as-legendary-idea-factory-prepares-to-leave-nj-home.html">https://www.nj.com/essex/2024/01/remembering-bell-labs-as-legendary-idea-factory-prepares-to-leave-nj-home.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39077867">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p id="U2BF3LEFJ5CV5EDWJGQ6SP3ATE">Mario Romero worked at one of the busiest, most high-profile research laboratories in the world for 30 years. But, if you ask him, it never felt much like a job.</p><p id="KLTBN3KOS5CIXAJFBOOVGPUTRM">“Let me tell you, I never felt I was going to work, never,” said Romero, who retired as a corporate accountant in 2009 from the famed <a href="https://www.nj.com/middlesex/2023/12/famed-bell-labs-leaving-historic-headquarters-to-move-to-new-brunswick.html" target="_blank">Bell Labs headquarters in Murray Hill</a>.</p><p id="WIAQ7IXZ2RARHN63KTKBUJMBCA">“I felt that I was going to school, I felt that I was going to learn something, that I was going to contribute to something,” said Romero, 64. “I didn’t ever drag my feet going into work, it didn’t feel that way.”</p><p id="U2GEPTIBFNEZNB4PCUJWHUDYUI">Romero and other former employees of Bell Labs talk about their time working at the research company’s historic New Jersey headquarters with the same fondness college graduates describe their alma maters.</p><p id="HPG5NLOVMRBRVLUMJIJULBONKI">The sprawling Murray Hill campus on Mountain Avenue was a bustling center for innovation in suburban Union County for decades. It served as the headquarters for a 90-year-old company whose researchers helped earn 10 Nobel Prizes, five Turing Awards for computer science breakthroughs and more than 20,000 patents.</p><p id="VTOIJHI3KRB5HITBBICRACSQVU">At its height, Bell Labs employed nearly 15,000 people in New Jersey, including some of the world’s top scientists and innovators. Many worked in the more than a half-dozen buildings spread throughout 240 acres at the country club-like Murray Hill headquarters on the border of Berkeley Heights and New Providence.</p><p id="T2N6T7R6MFBYDOI4MZHFUGF4UA">When Nokia’s research arm, Nokia <a href="https://www.nj.com/education/2021/03/two-ex-bell-labs-scientists-changed-computer-programming-forever-now-theyll-split-a-1m-prize.html">Bell Labs</a>, said in early December the company will move out of the Murray Hill campus over the next five years to relocate to a new tech hub being built in <a href="https://www.nj.com/topic/new-brunswick/posts.html">New Brunswick</a>, the announcement spurred an <a href="https://www.nj.com/opinion/2023/12/please-dont-let-bell-labs-and-murray-hill-fade-from-history-opinion.html" target="_blank">outpouring of memories</a> online from current and former employees.</p><figure><div><p><img srcset="https://www.nj.com/resizer/7HMVIJTn24jEZBkpJ56XVmbjzd4=/500x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/SIG7TH57EVDXVM3RSSWGWZWBTY.png 500w, https://www.nj.com/resizer/B9QZiYyViIspUSBf4-mp799sWDo=/800x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/SIG7TH57EVDXVM3RSSWGWZWBTY.png 800w, https://www.nj.com/resizer/J82ejHXR38pDjUBVpgcH0RzeT0I=/1280x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/SIG7TH57EVDXVM3RSSWGWZWBTY.png 1280w" sizes="50vw" src="https://www.nj.com/resizer/J82ejHXR38pDjUBVpgcH0RzeT0I=/1280x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/SIG7TH57EVDXVM3RSSWGWZWBTY.png" loading="lazy" alt="Remembering Bell Labs as legendary ‘factory for ideas’ prepares to leave N.J. home" height="600" width="300"></p><figcaption><p>Bell Labs in Murray Hill, seen here in 1960, was home to giants of the science world and Nobel Prize winners. <span>Nokia</span></p></figcaption></div></figure><p id="CNLH6Y3YHNHXZOVELMBGGTJZWY">“It was an honor to work there,” one former employee wrote on Facebook. “I’ll never forget what a great place it was to work at,” said another.</p><p id="KUBCU7AQXBAK7MDYPTOEST6HWM">Some of the world’s most important breakthroughs have come out of Bell Labs, including the first transistor, the laser, radio astronomy, the dawn of cellular and satellite communications and the beginnings of artificial intelligence. Bell Labs was also the birthplace of the UNIX computer operating system, C++  and numerous programming languages.</p><p id="2G5T2JAVDJH3NOAVWYP4LY2UOU">Bell Labs began in 1925 as the Bell Telephone Laboratories, a science and communication research arm of the Bell system with ownership evenly split between AT&amp;T and Western Electric. At its prime, the lab produced Nobel Prize-winning discoveries and even helped the United States win World War II.</p><p id="5IWWQ3V7CVAOBI3HFR5EV56HTI">In the 1980s, AT&amp;T Technologies took over the company, according to the <a href="https://www.bell-labs.com/about/history/#gref">Nokia Bell Labs website</a>. In 1996, AT&amp;T spun off most of Bell Laboratories and its equipment manufacturing business into Lucent Technologies, leading to a series of ownership changes.</p><p id="3AGIOFD6QZFPVKIN6TDFDJ4DYA">Following a merger in 2007, Bell Laboratories and the former research and innovations division of Alcatel were combined into a single organization. And in 2016, Nokia acquired Alctael-Lucent, merging Bell Labs and Nokia’s research arm FutureWorks.</p><p id="GMVTFBNVQZBNHDP27Y2L7AU4HY">Bell Labs’ new headquarters will be located at <a href="https://www.nj.com/politics/2021/10/the-hub-is-coming-to-nj-the-research-center-will-have-no-rival-murphy-says.html">the HELIX innovation center</a> in New Brunswick. Originally known as <a href="https://www.nj.com/politics/2018/03/its_called_the_hub_and_murphy_swears_it_will_help_make_us_a_tech_magnet.html">“The Hub,”</a> the HELIX innovation center will be a large complex in the city’s downtown on the site of the former Ferren Mall.</p><p id="QKY6RFHHDBEWTKZTJPBBUJVZAU">Nokia said the change in location will help Nokia Bell Labs to adapt and evolve to remain at the forefront of cutting-edge technology.</p><p id="XFHF7UHFQBCFBL2RXON4UCGJ6Y">It is a major change for Bell Labs, which has been a fixture in Murray Hill and has had numerous satellite locations around New Jersey.</p><p id="HHK6HSGLFFGT7IVFKOYK3IOXY4">Bell Labs’ research center in Holmdel in Monmouth County was a center for major scientific developments, including cellular technology and <a href="https://www.nj.com/news/2023/10/nj-community-to-buy-the-antenna-used-to-confirm-the-big-bang-theory.html" target="_blank">the Horn Antenna </a>used to confirm the Big Bang theory.</p><p id="IO6YWKCJRNGPZGSO3MFQA2TRPY">But the company closed the location in 2006 and it was eventually purchased and redeveloped into a 2-million-square-foot “work, live, play” campus called <a href="https://www.nj.com/entertainment/2018/05/inside_bell_works_holmdel_nj_former_bell_labs.html" target="_blank">Bell Works</a>, which includes entertainment, dining and fitness amenities. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L_-UQr5HKvg" target="_blank">Bell Works </a>was dubbed the most iconic building in New Jersey in 2018 by Architectural Digest.</p><p id="5XQBDMRGTJCP3J57FSSSXYOQQ4">It is unclear what will happen to the Murray Hill site once Bell Labs leaves. The mayors of New Providence and Berkeley Heights have both said they are working with each other, as well as state and local officials, to find a new use for the property.</p><p id="XTVNS2MSYBAY3M3COEMWC62SKM">“Our priority will be preserving open space, exploring recreation opportunities, protecting environmentally sensitive areas, ensuring that we meet our affordable requirements, and attracting commercial businesses that will support our community,” New Providence Mayor Al Morgan said in a statement.</p><figure><div><p><img srcset="https://www.nj.com/resizer/a1BViRNO6WiObr1rHH4yVZiWn24=/500x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/J2FXFBUCOVGKLHZUYQ2W3PMSEQ.jpg 500w, https://www.nj.com/resizer/oT_Be0vIs5_i2kW3ivujPAWKQDM=/800x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/J2FXFBUCOVGKLHZUYQ2W3PMSEQ.jpg 800w, https://www.nj.com/resizer/4f_mq-0DjmTO4EQKrwTw6dcZ5jo=/1280x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/J2FXFBUCOVGKLHZUYQ2W3PMSEQ.jpg 1280w" sizes="50vw" src="https://www.nj.com/resizer/4f_mq-0DjmTO4EQKrwTw6dcZ5jo=/1280x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/J2FXFBUCOVGKLHZUYQ2W3PMSEQ.jpg" loading="lazy" alt="Two suited scientists at Bell Laboratories stand in front of the first full-length motion picture technology with synchronized sound in a black and white photograph from 1927." height="600" width="300"></p><figcaption><p>In 1927, scientists at Bell Labs developed equipment for the first full-length motion picture with synchronized sound, as opposed to silent film. The discovery changed motion pictures. <span>Nokia</span></p></figcaption></div></figure><h2>‘A factory for ideas’</h2><p id="MRIGSOHTLNHWTJM4JBBMN72BRE">Science fiction author and futurist Arthur C. Clarke described Bell Labs as “a factory for ideas” when he visited the Murray Hill headquarters in the late 1950s.</p><p id="UITURIGC2JF3LMSDLFS5HDNS6I">“At first sight, when one comes upon it in its surprisingly rural setting, the Bell Telephone Laboratories’ main New Jersey site looks like a large and up-to-date factory, which in a sense it is. But it is a factory for ideas, and so its production lines are invisible,” Clarke wrote in the 1958 book “Voice Across the Sea” on the history of intercontinental communication.</p><p id="IC6Z6ENFDVDXBPE3ZXDLFRIIJU">Bell Labs opened its Murray Hill headquarters in 1942, just as the United States was engulfed in World War II.</p><p id="A5RH76SPE5DQNK2EM6DD2ERHJE">The laboratory was essential to the war effort, conducting wartime research projects, according to newspaper articles from the time. Researchers worked on finding alternatives for scarce resources, including copper and quartz, which were difficult to get at the time.</p><p id="43CGGXXMFVAVXCDIVTRJT33BLI">Bell Labs helped develop synthetic crystals for the U.S. Navy’s sonar equipment, according to news articles. Sonar was instrumental in foiling the Nazi submarine campaign and enabled American subs to destroy Japanese shipping.</p><p id="SSGLAJNONNDBLN24WJ5BBFMDRU">The physicists at Bell Laboratories in Murray Hill were also responsible for creating the transistor in 1947, which transformed telecommunication and sparked a revolution in electronics. The transistor would later be a key component in the <a href="https://www.nj.com/news/2012/08/njit_physicist_takes_part_in_n.html" target="_blank">Telstar 1 satellite,</a> the first active orbiting communication satellite to relay live television transmissions and phone signals between the United States and Europe.</p><p id="WSCPZZZMZBCFXJZFCAWFZMNEZE">“The satellite was built at a special Bell Laboratories plant in Hillsdale, New Jersey — underwent testing at Bell Labs in Murray Hill and Whippany — and the signals transmitted via Telstar from the ground station at Andover, Maine were picked up by <a href="https://www.nj.com/news/2023/10/nj-community-to-buy-the-antenna-used-to-confirm-the-big-bang-theory.html" target="_blank">the huge horn antenna at Bell Laboratories in Holmdel,</a>” according to a July 1962 article in the Bridgeton Evening News.</p><figure><div><p><img srcset="https://www.nj.com/resizer/nQTSK6GZb6xoG3trZEngXmJ-5xM=/500x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/XVOY5JXR2RCZ3B63CTR3VBZ3RA.jpg 500w, https://www.nj.com/resizer/-Cr3TreEoUd3bmN28xoDONYK76Q=/800x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/XVOY5JXR2RCZ3B63CTR3VBZ3RA.jpg 800w, https://www.nj.com/resizer/Yl-vu4JiDybuwA5rNAK7By9K2nA=/1280x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/XVOY5JXR2RCZ3B63CTR3VBZ3RA.jpg 1280w" sizes="50vw" src="https://www.nj.com/resizer/Yl-vu4JiDybuwA5rNAK7By9K2nA=/1280x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/XVOY5JXR2RCZ3B63CTR3VBZ3RA.jpg" loading="lazy" alt="Remembering Bell Labs as legendary ‘factory for ideas’ prepares to leave N.J. home" height="600" width="300"></p><figcaption><p>Bell Labs Murray Hill researchers George Smith and Willard Boyle in 1969. They later won the Nobel Prize for pioneering an image sensor known as the charge-coupled device, which revolutionized photography.<span>Nokia</span></p></figcaption></div></figure><p id="QGTBSDNUDRHFVMIJEROFNC77N4">Some of the inventors who spent time in Murray Hill won the Nobel Prize for their discoveries.</p><p id="7ZOMFZRFGBBFNMIK63DPJO56NA">In 2009, <a href="https://www.nj.com/news/2009/10/three_us_scientists_share_nobe.html" target="_blank">two Bell Labs scientists who created the technology behind digital photography received the Nobel Prize </a>in physics.</p><p id="N6EMXELJ6FDRDPCUOYMJNOVPIY">Willard S. Boyle, then 85, and George E. Smith, then 79, were honored for inventing the eye of the digital camera, a sensor able to transform light into a large number of pixels, the tiny points of color that are the building blocks of every digital image. The technology is found in devices ranging from the cheapest point-and-shoot digital camera to robotic medical instruments that let surgeons perform delicate operations deep inside the human body.</p><p id="3XEGUPDV3JAK7PZOTYI2YNF3AQ">Bell Labs has also been the site of extraordinary achievements by pioneering <a href="https://mosaic.nj.com/news/2023/11/exhibit-showcasing-the-impact-of-black-inventors-is-coming-to-new-jersey.html" target="_blank">Black scientists and engineers</a>, according to research published by the <a href="https://www.aip.org/sites/default/files/history/teaching-guides/bell-laboratories/African%20American%20Scientists%20at%20Bell%20Laboratories_Bell%20Laboratories%20Handout.pdf" target="_blank">American Institute of Physics</a>.</p><p id="5FBMPN56NVDRBH4TZMU73OJJVI"><b>READ MORE: </b><a href="https://mosaic.nj.com/news/2023/11/a-plan-to-open-a-27m-black-inventors-museum-in-new-jersey.html" target="_blank"><b>A plan to open a $27M Black inventors museum in New Jersey</b></a></p><p id="UFYI5ZGQ6BENJNDYN3WOOBJ6IA"><a href="https://www.nj.com/insidejersey/2010/09/how_new_jersey_saved_civilizat_19.html" target="_blank">Physicist and inventor James West</a> created the foil electret microphone — a small microphone that did not require a battery — which revolutionized the communications industry. Today, around 90% of microphone technology is based on the electret microphone and the invention has been used in hearing aids and space technology, according to the American Institute of Physics.</p><p id="67HVVRMNMJACHA575S2DVKWLEI">When West arrived at Bell Labs in 1957, there were just seven Black technical workers.</p><p id="DVSV4OEDWJGHJPGLG4GJEBVHHA">West and a small number of Black professionals at Bell Labs formed the Association of Black Laboratory Employees in 1970 to promote diversity in the STEM world. At the group’s urging, Bell Labs agreed to fund a first-of-its-kind fellowship program that recruited promising scientists of color, funded their PhD research, and paired them with a mentor already on Bell Labs’ staff.</p><p id="ENQSAC3LPRD4PH5TWAQ773CSAA">The fellowship program went on to support alumni including James Hunt, who co-invented the Hunt-Szymanski algorithm which is widely employed in computer science and mathematics.</p><figure><div><p><img srcset="https://www.nj.com/resizer/12i_2lxYeXLjI3PqqGah3e_JbqA=/500x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/XZTHGHH4MNB5RDEZYGS2KFG3RY.jpg 500w, https://www.nj.com/resizer/kCq632RvA2r91zyvd1RaEi_OvyQ=/800x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/XZTHGHH4MNB5RDEZYGS2KFG3RY.jpg 800w, https://www.nj.com/resizer/Q3jx3YDD_zY9AmDeOIdm2qrRT3s=/1280x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/XZTHGHH4MNB5RDEZYGS2KFG3RY.jpg 1280w" sizes="50vw" src="https://www.nj.com/resizer/Q3jx3YDD_zY9AmDeOIdm2qrRT3s=/1280x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/XZTHGHH4MNB5RDEZYGS2KFG3RY.jpg" loading="lazy" alt="Remembering Bell Labs as legendary ‘factory for ideas’ prepares to leave N.J. home" height="600" width="300"></p><figcaption><p>The scientists at Bell Labs in Murray Hill included inventor James West, creator of the electret microphone, which has become the standard microphone used in products ranging from recording equipment to hearing aids. <span>Photo courtesy of Nokia</span></p></figcaption></div></figure><p id="RHJ2STD2MBDHVOC6KXGWBSAYKE">Even as the company began to change ownership, it continued to churn out new innovations.</p><p id="TUPJGY366VEWTMYQVWCGHSOO4Y">In 1989, researchers at AT&amp;T Bell Laboratories devised a new computer chip, called a photonic integrated circuit, capable of handling 2,048 transactions simultaneously, according to a story in The Star-Ledger.</p><p id="KVUB4BJPZRAMJORTUCR6U5PT64">The following year, scientists in Murray Hill confirmed the existence of a third state of matter, known as “quasicrystals,” according to a 1990 article in The Star-Ledger.</p><p id="R5P3SRITNNAEFG5OKFQOGQJJQI">Bell Labs’ new home at the Helix in New Brunswick will break ground in 2025. The state-of-the-art facility will be developed by SJP Properties with support from the New Brunswick Development Corporation, the New Jersey Economic Development Authority and the city of New Brunswick.</p><figure><div><p><img srcset="https://www.nj.com/resizer/qTU1yHSTxdfFbsjrWIvd8BmZgbU=/500x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/RMKIS3WCGBGH7C4EMVDOG6CVZU.png 500w, https://www.nj.com/resizer/3qfkMZx0cjQqabn9vA_zLtmPhwo=/800x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/RMKIS3WCGBGH7C4EMVDOG6CVZU.png 800w, https://www.nj.com/resizer/oX0F7HVlp0bIpjA2dxBfHbQZDeQ=/1280x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/RMKIS3WCGBGH7C4EMVDOG6CVZU.png 1280w" sizes="50vw" src="https://www.nj.com/resizer/oX0F7HVlp0bIpjA2dxBfHbQZDeQ=/1280x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/RMKIS3WCGBGH7C4EMVDOG6CVZU.png" loading="lazy" alt="Fames Bell Labs to move from historic headquarters to New Brunswick" height="600" width="300"></p><figcaption><p>Nokia Bell Labs will relocate by 2028 to a state-of-the-art research and development facility in New Brunswick, pictured here in an artist's rendering.<span>Nokia</span></p></figcaption></div></figure><p id="2OVGFUUF5RH3FNFLRDPP22AI2Y">Bell Labs does not expect to reduce its staff due to the move, a Nokia spokeswoman said.</p><p id="ZVYZHBPBUVETJM22QAQPZDTD4U">The new building in New Brunswick will have “bespoke” laboratories build specifically for the needs of the Bell Labs researchers and their areas of focus, the company said.</p><p id="2Z6FN7MGVFEMHGO5A5AYNK75WY">“Ultimately, we want a facility that feels right for the next 100 years of Nokia Bell Labs,” Nishant Batra, chief strategy and technology officer at Nokia, said last month when the move was announced.</p><figure><div><p><img srcset="https://www.nj.com/resizer/qCIMV8thPp1AjzX_2ESWi2pJUk4=/500x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/E5GZRLSHFRE5RPUAOELUQGAFTU.jpg 500w, https://www.nj.com/resizer/KwKX_Ft_0wwsNFJrzRE40H9PkjQ=/800x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/E5GZRLSHFRE5RPUAOELUQGAFTU.jpg 800w, https://www.nj.com/resizer/nTn6QYun4CkohXUmB6IPKw9KEBw=/1280x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/E5GZRLSHFRE5RPUAOELUQGAFTU.jpg 1280w" sizes="50vw" src="https://www.nj.com/resizer/nTn6QYun4CkohXUmB6IPKw9KEBw=/1280x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/E5GZRLSHFRE5RPUAOELUQGAFTU.jpg" loading="lazy" alt="Remembering Bell Labs as legendary ‘factory for ideas’ prepares to leave N.J. home" height="600" width="300"></p><figcaption><p>In 1969, Dennis Ritchie and Ken Thompson developed UNIX, a computer programming language. <span>Nokia</span></p></figcaption></div></figure><figure><div><p><img srcset="https://www.nj.com/resizer/9Ly7GvI0xtdq9BPkO3CAZwOSoTs=/500x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/CCTKGXXM5FG5FHJMW6GGM7P34I.jpg 500w, https://www.nj.com/resizer/S7SUB86OKiljv_KMteN2tZo3Dnc=/800x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/CCTKGXXM5FG5FHJMW6GGM7P34I.jpg 800w, https://www.nj.com/resizer/jcs1s83ufVmbK2Ph8VvT2eKzfmE=/1280x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/CCTKGXXM5FG5FHJMW6GGM7P34I.jpg 1280w" sizes="50vw" src="https://www.nj.com/resizer/jcs1s83ufVmbK2Ph8VvT2eKzfmE=/1280x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/CCTKGXXM5FG5FHJMW6GGM7P34I.jpg" loading="lazy" alt="Remembering Bell Labs as legendary ‘factory for ideas’ prepares to leave N.J. home" height="600" width="300"></p><figcaption><p>In 1958, Bell Labs invented the optical maser, the beginnings of the modern-day laser.<span>Nokia</span></p></figcaption></div></figure><figure><div><p><img srcset="https://www.nj.com/resizer/s03BvIru4E9X_nVXZxwSlI2Uo78=/500x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/E2UGZWEPBRGPDGKD65LZFBV4TE.jpg 500w, https://www.nj.com/resizer/Kuj9PxBzn1DFBc4rGocek4hEZkQ=/800x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/E2UGZWEPBRGPDGKD65LZFBV4TE.jpg 800w, https://www.nj.com/resizer/PGCMXsp7bBEYpE39Yf_bGFFoiLU=/1280x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/E2UGZWEPBRGPDGKD65LZFBV4TE.jpg 1280w" sizes="50vw" src="https://www.nj.com/resizer/PGCMXsp7bBEYpE39Yf_bGFFoiLU=/1280x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/E2UGZWEPBRGPDGKD65LZFBV4TE.jpg" loading="lazy" alt="Remembering Bell Labs as legendary ‘factory for ideas’ prepares to leave N.J. home" height="600" width="300"></p><figcaption><p>In 1948, Bell Labs researcher Claude Shannon developed the fundamentals of information theory, the mathematical study of the quantification, storage and communication of information.<span>Nokia</span></p></figcaption></div></figure><figure><div><p><img srcset="https://www.nj.com/resizer/kiaAMrbTvyTMkwlj76TXk36uF0s=/500x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/AWIUA7263ZD37IZDVHCCD62NYY.jpg 500w, https://www.nj.com/resizer/4IVIB50oabwidbaB-JmEVuqQ4HY=/800x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/AWIUA7263ZD37IZDVHCCD62NYY.jpg 800w, https://www.nj.com/resizer/UpnuRguj2oDUcwuwcfCh7_mLo2M=/1280x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/AWIUA7263ZD37IZDVHCCD62NYY.jpg 1280w" sizes="50vw" src="https://www.nj.com/resizer/UpnuRguj2oDUcwuwcfCh7_mLo2M=/1280x0/smart/cloudfront-us-east-1.images.arcpublishing.com/advancelocal/AWIUA7263ZD37IZDVHCCD62NYY.jpg" loading="lazy" alt="A man stands next to a large screen representing the first public long-distance television transmission in the United States in a black and white photograph from 1927." height="600" width="300"></p><figcaption><p>In 1927, Bell Labs demonstrated the first public long-distance television transmission in the United States. <span>Nokia</span></p></figcaption></div></figure><section><ul data-testid="list"><li><a href="https://www.nj.com/lottery/2024/01/mega-millions-ticket-worth-1m-bought-in-nj-as-jackpot-climbs.html">Mega Millions ticket worth $1M bought in N.J. as jackpot climbs</a></li><li><a href="https://www.nj.com/news/2024/01/donations-sought-to-bury-family-killed-in-nj-murder-suicide.html">Donations sought to bury family killed in N.J. murder-suicide</a></li><li><a href="https://www.nj.com/weather/2024/01/fridays-winter-storm-could-be-deceiving-work-from-home-if-you-can-state-officials-say.html">Friday’s winter storm could be ‘deceiving.’ Work from home if you can, state officials say.</a></li></ul></section><p id="XJGLQWB7U5EATPYRZVLIFZZW2E"><i>Our journalism needs your support. Please subscribe today to </i><a href="https://www.nj.com/"><i>NJ.com</i></a><i>.</i></p><p id="QQ4423CSQ5D4BNCN7INAB23O4M"><a href="https://www.nj.com/staff/jroman/posts.html"><i>Jackie Roman</i></a><i> may be reached at </i><a href="mailto:jroman@njadvancemedia.com"><i>jroman@njadvancemedia.com</i></a><i>.</i></p></div><p>If you purchase a product or register for an account through a link on our site, we may receive compensation.<span> By using this site, you consent to our <a href="https://www.advancelocal.com/advancelocalUserAgreement/user-agreement.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">User Agreement</a> and agree that your clicks, interactions, and personal information may be collected, recorded, and/or stored by us and social media and other third-party partners in accordance with our <a href="https://www.advancelocal.com/advancelocalUserAgreement/privacy-policy.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Privacy Policy.</a></span></p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why is everything so ugly? (141 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nplusonemag.com/issue-44/the-intellectual-situation/why-is-everything-so-ugly/</link>
            <guid>39077622</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 11:46:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nplusonemag.com/issue-44/the-intellectual-situation/why-is-everything-so-ugly/">https://www.nplusonemag.com/issue-44/the-intellectual-situation/why-is-everything-so-ugly/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39077622">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><span><span>We live in undeniably ugly times.</span> Architecture, industrial design, cinematography, probiotic soda branding — many of the defining features of the visual field aren’t sending their best. Despite more advanced manufacturing and design technologies than have existed in human history, our built environment tends overwhelmingly toward the insubstantial, the flat, and the gray, punctuated here and there by the occasional childish squiggle. This drab sublime unites flat-pack furniture and home electronics, municipal infrastructure and commercial graphic design: an ocean of stuff so homogenous and underthought that the world it has inundated can feel like a digital rendering — of a slightly duller, worse world.</span></p><p><span>If the Situationists drifted through Paris looking to get defamiliarized, today a scholar of the new ugliness can conduct their research in any contemporary American city — or upzoned American Main Street, or exurban American parking lot, or, if they’re really desperate, on the empty avenues of Meta’s Horizon Worlds. Our own walk begins across the street from our apartment, where, following the recent demolition of a perfectly serviceable hundred-year-old building, a monument to ugliness has recently besieged the block. Our new neighbor is a classic 5-over-1: retail on the ground floor, topped with several stories of apartments one wouldn’t want to be able to afford. The words <span>THE JOSH</span> have been appended to the canopy above the main entrance in a passionless font.</span></p><p><span>We spent the summer certain that the caution tape–yellow panels on The Josh’s south side were insulation, to be eventually supplanted by an actual facade. Alas, in its finished form The Josh really is yellow, and also burgundy, gray, and brown. Each of these colors corresponds to a different material — plastic, concrete, rolled-on brick, an obscure wood-like substance — and the overall effect is of an overactive spreadsheet. Trims, surfaces, and patterns compete for attention with shifty black windows, but there’s nothing bedazzling or flamboyant about all this chaos. Somehow the building’s plane feels flatter than it is, despite the profusion of arbitrary outcroppings and angular balconies. The lineage isn’t Bauhaus so much as a sketch of the Bauhaus that’s been xeroxed half a dozen times.</span></p><p><span>The Josh is aging rapidly for a 5-month-old. There are gaps between the panels, which have a taped-on look to them, and cracks in the concrete. Rust has bloomed on surfaces one would typically imagine to be rustproof. Every time it rains, The Josh gets conspicuously . . . wet. Attempts have been made to classify structures like this one and the ethos behind their appearance: SimCityist, McCentury Modern, fast-casual architecture. We prefer cardboard modernism, in part because The Josh looks like it might turn to pulp at the first sign of a hundred-year flood.</span></p><p><span>Writing a century ago, H. L. Mencken bemoaned America’s “libido for the ugly.” There exists, he wrote, a “love of ugliness for its own sake, the lust to make the world intolerable. Its habitat is the United States.” However mystical and psychosexual his era’s intolerability might have felt in its origins, by the 1940s the explanations were more prosaic. With the wartime rationing of steel and sudden dearth of skilled labor, concrete structural systems quickly gained appeal — as did buildings that could be made piecemeal in a factory, put on a trailer, and nailed together anywhere in the country. And as the postwar baby boom took hold, such buildings were soon in high demand, fulfilling modernism’s wildest dreams of standardization with little of the glamour. A few Levittowns later, the promise of salvation-by-mass-production would come to seem elusive: new manufacturing techniques were transforming both the buildings and the builders building them. In </span><i><span>Prisoners of the American Dream</span></i><span>, Mike Davis describes how, in the 1970s, “the adoption of new building technologies involving extensive use of prefabricated structures, like precast concrete, eroded the boundaries of traditional skills and introduced a larger semi-skilled component into the labor force.” If it’s cheaper to assemble concrete panels than to hire bricklayers, cityscapes will eventually contain fewer bricks.</span></p><p><span>A construction industry with newly decadent profit margins was ready to spring into action in the 1990s, when — after a violent, decades-long process of urban renewal and white flight — real estate developers, brokers, and local politicians started luring predominantly white homeowners and renters back to the cities they’d abandoned. By the 2000s, infill housing began to crop up in American cities that had for decades been defined by their plentiful surface parking. These residential developments were ugly, but not yet inescapable. Like the fresh-faced presidential candidate with whom it’s hard not to associate them (did every wood-and-concrete complex feature a knockoff Shepard Fairey mural, or have we been blinded by the mists of memory?), the buildings spoke to an upwardly mobile, progressive, even post-racial demographic that didn’t share its parents’ all-consuming fear of city life. Then came the ultimate stop-work order: the 2008 financial crisis.</span></p><blockquote><p>The ruling class seized cities and chose to turn them into . . . this? To our right is a place that sells wiggly candles.</p> <a onclick="return popitup('https://twitter.com/share?text=The+ruling+class+seized+cities+and+chose+to+turn+them+into%E2%80%AF.%E2%80%AF.%E2%80%AF.+this%3F+To+our+right+is+a+place+that+sells+wiggly+candles.+%7C+n%2B1+%7C&amp;lang=en&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.nplusonemag.com%2F%3Fp%3D34098')" href="https://twitter.com/share?text=The+ruling+class+seized+cities+and+chose+to+turn+them+into%E2%80%AF.%E2%80%AF.%E2%80%AF.+this%3F+To+our+right+is+a+place+that+sells+wiggly+candles.+%7C+n%2B1+%7C&amp;lang=en&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.nplusonemag.com%2F%3Fp%3D34098">Tweet</a></blockquote><p><span>The urban building boom that picked up in the wake of the Great Recession wasn’t a boom at all, at least not by previous booming standards: in the early 2010s, multifamily housing construction was at its lowest in decades. But low interest rates worked in developers’ favor, and what had begun as an archipelago of scattered development had coalesced, by the end of the Obama years, into a visual monoculture. At the global scale, supply chains narrowed the range of building materials to a generic minimum (hence The Josh’s pileup of imitation teak accents and synthetic stucco antiflourishes). At the local level, increasingly stringent design standards imposed by ever-more-cumbersome community approval processes compelled developers to copy designs that had already been rubber-stamped elsewhere (hence that same fake teak and stucco in identical boxy buildings across the country). The environment this concatenation of forces has produced is at once totalizing and meek — an architecture embarrassed by its barely architected-ness, a building style that cuts corners and then covers them with rainscreen cladding. For all the air these buildings have sucked up in the overstated conflict between YIMBYs (who recognize that new housing is ultimately better than no housing) and NIMBYs (who don’t), the unmistakable fact of cardboard modernism is that its buildings are less ambitious, less humane, and uglier than anyone deserves.</span></p><p><span>They’re also really gray. The Josh’s steel railings are gray, and its plastic window sashes are a slightly clashing shade of gray. Inside, the floors are made of gray TimberCore, and the walls are painted an abject post-beige that interior designers call greige but is in fact just gray. Gray suffuses life beyond architecture: television, corporate logos, product packaging, clothes for babies, direct-to-consumer toothbrushes. What incentives — material, libidinal, or otherwise — could possibly account for all this gray? In 2020, a study by London’s Science Museum Group’s Digital Lab used image processing to analyze photographs of consumer objects manufactured between 1800 and the present. They found that things have become less colorful over time, converging on a spectrum between steel and charcoal, as though consumers want their gadgets to resemble the raw materials of the industries that produce them. If </span><i><span>The Man in the Gray Flannel Suit </span></i><span>once offered a warning about conformity, he is now an inspiration, although the outfit has gotten an upgrade. Today he is </span><i><span>The Man in the Gray Bonobos</span></i><span>,</span> <span>or </span><i><span>The Man in the</span></i> <i><span>Gray Buck Mason Crew Neck</span></i><span>, or </span><i><span>The Man in the Gray Mack Weldon Sweatpants</span></i><span> — all delivered via gray Amazon van. The imagined color of life under communism, gray has revealed itself to be the actual hue of globalized capital. “The distinct national colors of the imperialist map of the world have merged and blended in the imperial global rainbow,” wrote Hardt and Negri. What color does a blended rainbow produce? Greige, evidently.</span></p><hr><p><span><span>A lot of ugliness</span> accretes privately, in the form of household goods, which can make it hard to see — except on the first of the month. Today’s perma-class of renters moves more frequently than ever before (inevitably to smaller apartments), and on moving day the sidewalks are transformed into a rich bazaar of objects significant for ugliness studies. We stroll past discarded pottery from wild sip ’n’ spin nights; heaps of shrunken fast fashion from Shein; dead Strategist-approved houseplants; broken Wirecutter-approved humidifiers; an ergonomic gaming chair; endless Ikea BILLYs, MALMs, LACKs, SKUBBs, BARENs, SLOGGs, JUNQQs, and FGHSKISs. Perhaps this shelf is salvageable — ? No, just another mass of peeling veneer and squishy particleboard. On one stoop sits a package from a direct-to-consumer eyewear company, and we briefly fantasize about a pair of glasses that would illuminate, </span><i><span>They Live</span></i><span>–style, the precise number of children involved in manufacturing each of these trashed items, or maybe the acreage of Eastern European old-growth trees.</span></p><p><span>It occurs to us, strolling past a pair of broken BuzzFeed Shopping–approved AirPods, that the new ugliness has beset us from both above and below. Many of the aesthetic qualities pioneered by low-interest-rate-era construction — genericism, non-ornamentation, shoddy reproducibility — have trickled down into other realms, even as other principles, unleashed concurrently by Apple’s slick industrial-design hegemon, have trickled up. In the middle, all that is solid melts into sameness, such that smart home devices resemble the buildings they surveil, which in turn look like the computers on which they were algorithmically engineered, which resemble the desks on which they sit, which, like the sofas at the coworking space around the corner, put the </span><i><span>mid</span></i><span> in </span><i><span>fake midcentury modern</span></i><span>. And all of it is bound by the commandment of planned obsolescence, which decays buildings even as it turns phones into bricks.</span></p><p><span>Beyond the sidewalk, the street — which is mostly for cars, key technology of the 20th-century assault on the city. Barthes wrote that the 1955 Citroën DS marked a welcome shift in the appearance in cars toward the “homely,” meaning that they’d begun to carry the comfortable livability of kitchens and household equipment. Today’s automobiles, far from being “the supreme creation of an era,” are homely in the other sense of the word. A contemporary mythologist could sort them into either hamsters or monoliths. Hamster cars (the Honda Fit, the Toyota Prius) are undoubtedly ugly, but in a virtuous way. The monolith cars (the Cadillac Escalade, the Infiniti QX80) possess a militaristic cast, as if to get to Costco one must first stop off at the local black site.<sup id="rf1-34098"><a href="#fn1-34098" title="See also the increasing dominance of cars with opaque and foreboding matte paint jobs, described by the newsletter Blackbird Spyplane as “putty-lookin’ ass whips.”">1</a></sup> <span>No brand has embraced the ethos more than Tesla, with its tanklike Cybertruck. Even Musk’s more domesticated offerings feel like they’re in the surveillance business: sitting inside a Tesla is not unlike sitting inside a smartphone, while also staring at a giant smartphone.</span></span></p><blockquote><p>Shittiness is a big tent — and the tent is falling apart.</p> <a onclick="return popitup('https://twitter.com/share?text=Shittiness+is+a+big+tent%E2%80%8A%E2%80%94%E2%80%8Aand+the+tent+is+falling+apart.+%7C+n%2B1+%7C&amp;lang=en&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.nplusonemag.com%2F%3Fp%3D34098')" href="https://twitter.com/share?text=Shittiness+is+a+big+tent%E2%80%8A%E2%80%94%E2%80%8Aand+the+tent+is+falling+apart.+%7C+n%2B1+%7C&amp;lang=en&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.nplusonemag.com%2F%3Fp%3D34098">Tweet</a></blockquote><p><span>Dodging huge grilles we walk on, pulled by ugliness toward a gentrified retail strip. Here the violence of the new ugliness comes more fully into focus. The ruling class seized cities and chose to turn them into . . . this? To our right is a place that sells wiggly candles. Past that is a boutique liquor store whose chalkboard sign proclaims, in cheerleader handwriting, that the time is Wine O’Clock, and past that is a Bank of America. Across the street, a row of fast-casual chains, whose names and visual identities insist on modesty and anonymity: Just Salad, Just Food For Dogs, Blank Street Coffee. (This raft of normcore brands finds its opposite in the ghost kitchens down the block, which all for some reason are called things like Fuck Your Little Bitch Burrito.) Up ahead is an axe throwing “experience,” and another Bank of America.</span></p><p><span>Who asked for all of this? Numerous critics — self-hating and otherwise — have argued that the mallification of the American city is the fault of the same millennials for whom all the new construction was built, who couldn’t quite bear to abandon the creature comforts of home even as they reurbanized. The story goes that millennials lived, laughed, and loved their way into an unprecedentedly insipid environment, turning once-gritty cities into Instagram-friendly dispensaries of baroque ice cream cones that call back, madeleine-style, to the enfolding warmth of their suburban childhoods. But the contemporary built environment is not the millennials’ legacy; it is their inheritance. They didn’t ask for cardboard modernism — they simply capitulate to its infantilizing aesthetic paradigm because there is no alternative. Or if there is an alternative, it’s between an $8 ice cream cone or an $11 ice cream cone (or a $49 ticket to the Museum of Ice Cream).</span></p><p><span>Our ugliness tour is leading us toward the $11 ice cream cone zone. On the waterfront, the spatial logic of The Josh persists, only at four times the cost per square foot. There is less random yellow, the concrete is glossier, and the view through the precarious glass is a little more ennobling. Too bad about the build quality. One paradox of the new ugliness is that it flattens the distinction between the rich, the very rich, the superrich, and the merely fortunate by ripping them all off in turn. These days housing at the most elite strata sucks nearly as much as the simply bourgeois kind. According to a parade of entertaining </span><i><span>New York Times</span></i><span> stories, residents of the toothpick-like towers on Manhattan’s Billionaires’ Row complain of elevator breakdowns, “catastrophic” flooding from poor plumbing, and “metal partitions [that] groan as buildings sway” in the wind. Shittiness is a big tent — and the tent is falling apart.</span></p><hr><p><span><span>Our dérive has</span> deposited us near a subway stop. We swipe in with a trusty MetroCard, soon to be replaced by the privately owned data-tracking behemoth OMNY, whose neon-on-black logo recalls the chilly visual identity of another threat to transit, Uber.<sup id="rf2-34098"><a href="#fn2-34098" title="Along with Molly Fischer’s 2020 study of the “millennial aesthetic” in New York, Jesse Barron’s 2016 essay in Real Life remains an authoritative critique of neoliberal startup semiotics, from Uber to Seamless. “In 2012, Uber stood alone. Black, sinister, efficient. The logo like devil’s horns. The invisible umlaut. In the place of cuteness, Uber offered a fantasy of minimalist sadism, with the user holding the whip.”">2</a></sup> But at least as far as branding goes, OMNY is no uglier than other offenders. Our train car is covered in ads, all curiously alike despite marketing a staggering variety of superfluous stuff. How did workplace management systems, body-positive nutritional supplements, bean-forward meal kits, woman-owned sex toys, and woman-owned day-trading services all converge on the same three fonts? Everywhere we look there are little pool noodle–shaped squiggles, and where the squiggles end, there is muted flash photography that makes even otherworldly models look matter-of-fact. With the exception of the food delivery apps, which flaunt their violent takeover of the city in a meaningless word salad designed for shouting about salad —<span> WHEN YOU’RE SO HANGRY, YOU’D TRASH TALK ANY SLOW WALKER BETWEEN YOU AND YOUR BEC</span>, goes one GrubHub ad — the advertising all seems sheepish about being caught in the act of selling something.</span></p><p><span>But no single ad is as emblematically ugly as the digital screens that have appeared across the city’s train cars since 2017. Public transit has pivoted to video, and the function of its new giant iPads mystifies: their purpose is neither civic nor fully commercial. Instead, they’re given over to a bewildering set of images for the TikTokified city, the worst of which belong to a marketing campaign called “Moments in Food.” We watch, a little nauseated, as the Moments loop by: video tutorials for Homemade Pesto Hack, Homemade Chipotle Chicken Cutlet Hack, Homemade Three-Ingredient Oven-Free Blondie Hack. Why are there no measurements? Would this even seem edible, in the distinctly non-subwaylike atmosphere of an actual kitchen? Like The Josh’s synthetic not-quite-surfaces, it all seems gesturally foodlike, a step removed from the real thing. Above us, pesto glistens.</span></p><p><span>Speaking of moments in food, it’s lunchtime. Exiting the train, we pass a food hall, where, again, the theoretical possibility of endless variety manifests as lackluster sameness. Dozens of restaurants’ satellite stalls all feature the same signage, the same subway tile backdrop, the same impression of having been shrunk to diorama size and turned into IP. We turn instead to the outdoor dining sheds. After sprouting with uncharacteristic speed in the first chaotic spring of the pandemic, the sheds have performed a sort of guerilla Haussmannization of the city — in a good way, clawing back public space from cars. The ugliness they’ve introduced to the built environment diverges, happily, from the usual kind. Unruly and old-school, the sheds have pissed off deranged community boards and their mouthpieces in the media. “The shanty outside Dumpling Man on St. Marks is unspeakably hideous,” declared a recent </span><i><span>New York</span></i><span> article, “its colorless wood fragments hammered together so arbitrarily that you would rather eat in a pile of Lincoln Logs.” Yeah — just the way we like it!</span></p><p><span>Around the corner is a movie theater, one of those places where they bring snacks or cocktails right to your seat. Filmmaking today is supposed to be more powerful than it’s ever been, capable of representing everything everywhere all at once. As the world offscreen recedes into sameness, movies can and should look great — but onscreen there is more ugly sameness. The thing we wander into is at first indistinguishable from any other blockbuster of the late green-screen era: only after Ryan Reynolds cocks his signature “terror gun” do we recognize this as </span><i><span>Army Soldier II</span></i><span>,</span> <span>a digitally shot Netflix-financed production based on a TV show based on a comic book. Can a movie be a remake of itself? This is the depleted vibe </span><i><span>Army Soldier II</span></i><span> and its ilk are giving off. The easy recourse to postproduction — “we’ll fix it in post” — has resulted in a mise-en-scène so underlit as to be literally invisible. Despite its $275 million budget, the movie looks like it was filmed underwater in a polluted lake. The action scenes are nearly monochromatic, the color palette ranging from Tentative Black to what looks like Apple’s proprietary Space Gray. Lighting isn’t a lost art, but subsumed in all that murk, we’re having trouble finding it.</span></p><blockquote><p>Our neighbor to the right tells us she was hit by a Tesla while e-biking to Roosevelt Island to deliver a single unicorn latte.</p> <a onclick="return popitup('https://twitter.com/share?text=Our+neighbor+to+the+right+tells+us+she+was+hit+by+a+Tesla+while+e-biking+to+Roosevelt+Island+to+deliver+a+single+unicorn+latte.+%7C+n%2B1+%7C&amp;lang=en&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.nplusonemag.com%2F%3Fp%3D34098')" href="https://twitter.com/share?text=Our+neighbor+to+the+right+tells+us+she+was+hit+by+a+Tesla+while+e-biking+to+Roosevelt+Island+to+deliver+a+single+unicorn+latte.+%7C+n%2B1+%7C&amp;lang=en&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.nplusonemag.com%2F%3Fp%3D34098">Tweet</a></blockquote><p><span>Two and a half hours in, </span><i><span>Army Soldier II </span></i><span>suddenly becomes a comedy, with Reynolds vamping his way through long, flat takes designed to accommodate his “riffs.” Now everything is </span><i><span>over</span></i><span>lit, as if the gaffers were only available for the second half of the shoot.</span></p><p><span>Such bad lighting</span><span> — and such large portions! We exit the movie theater to a bright realization: our films are exactly as overlit as our reality. As our environment has become blander, it has also become more legible — too legible. That’s a shame, because many products of the new ugliness could benefit from a little chiaroscuroed ambiguity: if the world has to fill itself up with smart teapots, app-operated vacuum cleaners, and creepily huge menswear, we’d prefer it all to be shrouded in darkness. For thousands of years, this was the principle of illumination that triumphed over all others. Louis XIV’s Versailles and Louis the Tavern Owner’s tavern had this in common: the recognition that some details are worth keeping hidden. But now blinding illumination is the default condition of every apartment, office, pharmacy, laundromat, print shop, sandwich shop, train station, airport, grocery store, UPS Store, tattoo parlor, bank, and this vape shop we’ve just walked into.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>Surveying a suite of candy-colored bongs, we reflect on the primacy of LEDs. (One of the bongs is bedecked with LEDs.) The shift to cold lighting in recent years was borne of urgent environmental necessity, and we accept that climate change requires concessions. We’re prepared to make those: we will eat crickets and endorse, if necessary, the blockage of the waterfront park around the corner by a giant seawall. We will even help build the seawall! Change is inevitable. But LEDs can appear in many colors, as demonstrated by our new light-up bong. So why this atomic, lobotomizing white?</span></p><p><span>Outdoors, the situation is depressingly similar. After New York replaced the sodium-vapor lights in the city’s 250,000 streetlamps with shiny new LEDs in 2017, the experience of walking through the city at night transformed, almost . . . overnight. Forgiving, romantic, shadowy orange gave way to cold, all-seeing bluish white. Again environmental concerns necessitate this scale of change, and again we wonder why, when it comes to its light bulbs, New York has chosen to back the blue. Inertia, disinterest, thoughtlessness, yes, but also the promise of increased police vigilance. Still, what is most striking about New York’s ominous glow-up is the sense that the city has been estranged from itself: the hyperprecise shadows of every leaf and every branch set against every brick wall deliver a Hollywood unreality. New York after hours now looks less like it did in Scorsese’s </span><i><span>After Hours </span></i><span>and more like an excessive set-bound ’60s production. The new ugliness is defined in part by an abandonment of function </span><i><span>and </span></i><span>form: buildings afraid to look like buildings, cars that look like renderings, restaurants that look like the apps that control them. New York City is a city increasingly in quotation marks, a detailed facsimile of a place.</span></p><p><span>Gah! Blinded by the intense glare of an LED streetlamp, we bump right into said streetlamp. Fortunately there’s an urgent care across the street, still open in the dwindling dusk. We’re no doctor — at least not until they start giving out PhDs in walking around — but we can tell that our knee is bleeding. If anything is broken, the CityMD’s MD will take care of it. We stumble inside, into the intersection of exploitative private insurance and inadequate public options. Here, like everywhere else, a clash of patterns and surfaces — gray tile, gray bricks, greige wood paneling — enfolds us in a numbing palliative aura. We try to check in at the front, but the iPad doesn’t react to the tap of our index finger. Are we a ghost? Is this the afterlife? The lighting is giving gates of heaven, but as with the supertall buildings and their elevators that never work, our problem is technical: the iPad is frozen. Another one is wheeled out and we make our way through a questionnaire. Allergic reactions? None. History of medical litigation? Huh, weird.</span></p><p><span>Our estimated wait time is three and a half hours, which gives us ample opportunity to reflect on our surroundings. Is there a more contemporary urban form than the urgent care facility? How did the entire world come to look like this nonplace, flimsy and artificial and built unsuccessfully to stave off emergency? Above our heads, the original </span><i><span>Army Soldier</span></i><span> plays on a flatscreen, Ryan Reynolds’s leaden features motion-smoothed into alarming definition. Our phone buzzes with a push notification from Zillow: a 0.5-bedroom studio is now available for $4,775 a month in the sub-basement of The Josh. We examine our fellow patients, because nobody else is. The bleeding young man to our left looks to have been the victim of an axe throw gone very wrong. Our neighbor to the right tells us she was hit by a Tesla while e-biking to Roosevelt Island to deliver a single unicorn latte. We overhear someone behind us describe a harrowing food poisoning incident involving a Homemade Chipotle Chicken Cutlet Hack.</span></p><p><span>In the end we pay $75 for a Band-Aid, two Advils, a Blank Street Coffee gift card, and a branded pen we have no plans to return. After a long day of digital encounters we’re asked to sign a paper receipt, and we click the pen. It looks like a pen and works the way a pen ought to work. Our eyes fill with tears at this satisfying tactile experience. Maybe it’s just the bruising.</span></p><ol><li id="fn1-34098"><p>See also the increasing dominance of cars with opaque and foreboding matte paint jobs, described by the newsletter Blackbird Spyplane as “putty-lookin’ ass whips.”&nbsp;<a href="#rf1-34098" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">↩</a></p></li><li id="fn2-34098"><p>Along with Molly Fischer’s 2020 study of the “millennial aesthetic” in <em>New York</em>, Jesse Barron’s 2016 essay in Real Life remains an authoritative critique of neoliberal startup semiotics, from Uber to Seamless. “In 2012, Uber stood alone. Black, sinister, efficient. The logo like devil’s horns. The invisible umlaut. In the place of cuteness, Uber offered a fantasy of minimalist sadism, with the user holding the whip.”&nbsp;<a href="#rf2-34098" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text.">↩</a></p></li></ol></div><p>If you like this article, please <a href="https://www.nplusonemag.com/subscribe/?affid=article">subscribe</a> or leave a tax-deductible tip below to support n+1.</p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Boehm-Demers-Weiser conservative C/C++ Garbage Collector (119 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://hboehm.info/gc/</link>
            <guid>39077535</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 11:30:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/">https://hboehm.info/gc/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39077535">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
<table>
  <tbody><tr>
  <td><a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/gcinterface.html">Interface Overview</a></td>
  <td><a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/04tutorial.pdf">Tutorial Slides</a></td>
  <td><a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/faq.html">FAQ</a></td>
  <td><a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/simple_example.html">Example</a></td>
  <td><a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/gc_source">Download</a></td>
  <td><a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/license.txt">License</a></td>
  </tr>
</tbody></table>

<ul>
<li><a href="#where">Where to get the collector</a>
</li><li><a href="#platforms">Platforms</a>
</li><li><a href="#multiprocessors">Scalable multiprocessor versions</a>
</li><li><a href="#details">Some collector details</a>
</li><li><a href="#further">Further reading</a>
</li><li><a href="#users">Current users</a>
</li><li><a href="#collector">Local links for this collector</a>
</li><li><a href="#background">Local background Links</a>
</li><li><a href="#contacts">Contacts, Updates, and Reporting Issues</a><a>
</a></li><li><a href="#translations">Translations of this page</a>
</li></ul>
[ This is an updated version of the page formerly at
<tt>http://www.hpl.hp.com/personal/Hans_Boehm/gc</tt>,
and before that at
<tt>http://reality.sgi.com/boehm/gc.html</tt>
and before that at
<tt>ftp://parcftp.xerox.com/pub/gc/gc.html</tt>. ]
<p>
The <a href="http://www.hboehm.info/">Boehm</a>-<a href="http://www.cs.cornell.edu/annual_report/00-01/bios.htm#demers">Demers</a>-<a href="http://www-sul.stanford.edu/weiser/">Weiser</a>
conservative garbage collector can
be used as a garbage collecting
replacement for C <tt>malloc</tt> or C++ <tt>new</tt>.
It allows you to allocate memory basically as you normally would,
without explicitly deallocating memory that is no longer useful.
The collector automatically recycles memory when it determines
that it can no longer be otherwise accessed.
A simple example of such a use is given
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/simple_example.html">here</a>.
</p><p>
The collector is also used by a number of programming language
implementations that either use C as intermediate code, want
to facilitate easier interoperation with C libraries, or
just prefer the simple collector interface.
For a more detailed description of the interface, see
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/gcinterface.html">here</a>.
</p><p>
Alternatively, the garbage collector  may be used as
a <a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/leak.html">leak detector</a>
for C or C++ programs, though that is not its primary goal.
</p><p>
The arguments for and against conservative garbage collection
in C and C++ are briefly
discussed in
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/issues.html">issues.html</a>.  The beginnings of
a frequently-asked-questions list are <a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/faq.html">here</a>.
</p><p>
Empirically, this collector works with most unmodified C programs,
simply by replacing
<tt>malloc</tt> with <tt>GC_malloc</tt> calls,
replacing <tt>realloc</tt> with <tt>GC_realloc</tt> calls, and removing
free calls.  Exceptions are discussed
in <a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/issues.html">issues.html</a>. 
</p><h2><a name="where">Where to get the collector</a></h2>
<p>
Many versions are available in the
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/gc_source">
<tt>gc_source</tt></a> subdirectory.
Currently a recent stable version is
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/gc_source/gc-8.2.4.tar.gz"><tt>gc-8.2.4.tar.gz</tt></a>.
Note that this uses the new version numbering scheme
and may occasionally require a separate <tt>libatomic_ops</tt> download (see below).
</p><p>
If that fails, try the latest explicitly numbered version
in <a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/gc_source">
<tt>gc_source</tt></a>.
Later versions may contain additional features, platform support,
or bug fixes, but are likely to be less well tested.
</p><p>
Version 7.3 and later require that you download a corresponding
version of libatomic_ops, which should be available
in <a href="https://github.com/ivmai/libatomic_ops/wiki/Download">
<tt>https://github.com/ivmai/libatomic_ops/wiki/Download</tt></a>.
The current (stable) version is also available as
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/gc_source/libatomic_ops-7.8.0.tar.gz">
<tt>gc_source/libatomic_ops-7.8.0.tar.gz</tt></a>.
You will need to place that in a <tt>libatomic_ops</tt>
subdirectory.
</p><p>
Previously it was best to use corresponding versions of gc
and libatomic_ops, but for recent versions, it should be OK to
mix and match them.
</p><p>
Starting with 8.0, libatomic_ops is only required if the compiler does
not understand gcc's C atomic intrinsics.
</p><p>
The development version of the GC source code now resides on github,
along with the downloadable packages.
The GC tree itself is at
<a href="https://github.com/ivmai/bdwgc/"><tt>https://github.com/ivmai/bdwgc/</tt></a>.
The <tt>libatomic_ops</tt> tree required by the GC is at
<a href="https://github.com/ivmai/libatomic_ops/"><tt>https://github.com/ivmai/libatomic_ops/</tt></a>.
</p><p>
To build a working version of the collector, you will need to do
something like the following, where <tt>D</tt> is the absolute
path to an installation directory:
</p><pre>cd D
git clone https://github.com/ivmai/libatomic_ops
git clone https://github.com/ivmai/bdwgc
ln -s  D/libatomic_ops D/bdwgc/libatomic_ops
cd bdwgc
autoreconf -vif
automake --add-missing
./configure
make
</pre>
This will require that you have C and C++ toolchains, <tt>git</tt>,
<tt>automake</tt>, <tt>autoconf</tt>, and <tt>libtool</tt> already
installed.
<p>
Historical versions of the source can still be found
on the SourceForge site (project "bdwgc")
<a href="http://bdwgc.cvs.sourceforge.net/bdwgc/">here</a>.
</p><p>
The garbage collector code is copyrighted by
<a href="http://hboehm.info/">Hans-J. Boehm</a>,
Alan J. Demers,
<a href="http://www.xerox.com/">Xerox Corporation</a>,
<a href="http://www.sgi.com/">Silicon Graphics</a>,
and
<a href="http://www.hp.com/">Hewlett-Packard Company</a>.
It may be used and copied without payment of a fee under minimal restrictions.
See the README file in the distribution or the
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/license.txt">license</a> for more details.
<b>IT IS PROVIDED AS IS,
WITH ABSOLUTELY NO WARRANTY EXPRESSED OR IMPLIED.  ANY USE IS AT YOUR OWN RISK</b>.
</p><h2><a name="platforms">Platforms</a></h2>
The collector is not completely portable, but the distribution
includes ports to most standard PC and UNIX/Linux platforms.
The collector should work on Linux, *BSD, recent Windows versions,
MacOS X, HP/UX, Solaris,
Tru64, Irix and a few other operating systems.
Some ports are more polished than others.
There are <a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/porting.html">instructions</a> for porting the collector
to a new platform.
<p>
Irix pthreads, Linux threads, Win32 threads, Solaris threads
(old style and pthreads),
HP/UX 11 pthreads, Tru64 pthreads, and MacOS X threads are supported
in recent versions.
</p><h3>Separately distributed ports</h3>
For MacOS 9/Classic use, Patrick Beard's latest port were once available from
<tt>http://homepage.mac.com/pcbeard/gc/</tt>.
<p>
Several Linux and BSD versions provide prepacked versions of the collector.
The Debian port can be found at
<a href="https://packages.debian.org/sid/libgc-dev">
https://packages.debian.org/sid/libgc-dev</a>.
</p><h2><a name="multiprocessors">Scalable multiprocessor versions</a></h2>
Kenjiro Taura, Toshio Endo, and Akinori Yonezawa developed a parallel collector
based on this one.  It was once available from <tt>http://www.yl.is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp/gc/</tt>
Their collector takes advantage of multiple processors
during a collection.  Starting with collector version 6.0alpha1
we also do this, though with more modest processor scalability goals.
Our approach is discussed briefly in
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/scale.html"><tt>scale.html</tt></a>.
<h2><a name="details">Some Collector Details</a></h2>
The collector uses a <a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/complexity.html">mark-sweep</a> algorithm.
It provides incremental and generational
collection under operating systems which provide the right kind of
virtual memory support.  (Currently this includes SunOS[45], IRIX,
OSF/1, Linux, and Windows, with varying restrictions.)
It allows <a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/finalization.html"><i>finalization</i></a> code
to be invoked when an object is collected.
It can take advantage of type information to locate pointers if such
information is provided, but it is usually used without such information.
ee the README and
<tt>gc.h</tt> files in the distribution for more details.
<p>
For an overview of the implementation, see <a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/gcdescr.html">here</a>.
</p><p>
The garbage collector distribution includes a C string
(<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/gc_source/cordh.txt"><i>cord</i></a>) package that provides
for fast concatenation and substring operations on long strings.
A simple curses- and win32-based editor that represents the entire file
as a cord is included as a
sample application.
</p><p>
Performance of the nonincremental collector is typically competitive
with malloc/free implementations.  Both space and time overhead are
likely to be only slightly higher
for programs written for malloc/free
(see Detlefs, Dosser and Zorn's
<a href="ftp://ftp.cs.colorado.edu/pub/techreports/zorn/CU-CS-665-93.ps.Z">Memory Allocation Costs in Large C and C++ Programs</a>.)
For programs allocating primarily very small objects, the collector
may be faster; for programs allocating primarily large objects it will
be slower.  If the collector is used in a multithreaded environment
and configured for thread-local allocation, it may in some cases
significantly outperform malloc/free allocation in time.
</p><p>
We also expect that in many cases any additional overhead
will be more than compensated for by decreased copying etc.
if programs are written
and tuned for garbage collection.
</p><h2><a name="further">Further Reading:</a></h2>
<b>The beginnings of a frequently asked questions list for this
collector are <a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/faq.html">here</a></b>.
<p>
<b>The following provide information on garbage collection in general</b>:
</p><p>
Paul Wilson's <a href="ftp://ftp.cs.utexas.edu/pub/garbage">garbage collection ftp archive</a> and <a href="ftp://ftp.cs.utexas.edu/pub/garbage/gcsurvey.ps">GC survey</a>.
</p><p>
The Ravenbrook <a href="http://www.memorymanagement.org/">
Memory Management Reference</a>.
</p><p>
David Chase's
<a href="http://www.iecc.com/gclist/GC-faq.html">GC FAQ</a>.
</p><p>
Richard Jones'
<a href="http://www.ukc.ac.uk/computer_science/Html/Jones/gc.html">
GC page</a> and
<a href="https://www.cs.kent.ac.uk/people/staff/rej/gcbook/gcbook.html">
his book</a>.
</p><p>
<b>The following papers describe the collector algorithms we use
and the underlying design decisions at
a higher level.</b>
</p><p>
(Some of the lower level details can be found
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/gcdescr.html">here</a>.)
</p><p>
The first one is not available
electronically due to copyright considerations.  Most of the others are
subject to ACM copyright.
</p><p>
Boehm, H., "Dynamic Memory Allocation and Garbage Collection", <i>Computers in Physics
9</i>, 3, May/June 1995, pp. 297-303.  This is directed at an otherwise sophisticated
audience unfamiliar with memory allocation issues.  The algorithmic details differ
from those in the implementation.  There is a related letter to the editor and a minor
correction in the next issue.
</p><p>
Boehm, H., and <a href="http://www.ubiq.com/hypertext/weiser/weiser.html">M. Weiser</a>,
<a href="https://hboehm.info/spe_gc_paper">"Garbage Collection in an Uncooperative Environment"</a>,
<i>Software Practice &amp; Experience</i>, September 1988, pp. 807-820.
</p><p>
Boehm, H., A. Demers, and S. Shenker, <a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/papers/pldi91.ps.Z">"Mostly Parallel Garbage Collection"</a>, Proceedings
of the ACM SIGPLAN '91 Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation,
<i>SIGPLAN Notices 26</i>, 6 (June 1991), pp. 157-164.
</p><p>
Boehm, H., <a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/papers/pldi93.ps.Z">"Space Efficient Conservative Garbage Collection"</a>, Proceedings of the ACM
SIGPLAN '93 Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation, <i>SIGPLAN
Notices 28</i>, 6 (June 1993), pp. 197-206.
</p><p>
Boehm, H., "Reducing Garbage Collector Cache Misses",
<i> Proceedings of the 2000 International Symposium on Memory Management </i>.
<a href="http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?doid=362422.362438">
Official version.</a>
<a href="http://www.hpl.hp.com/techreports/2000/HPL-2000-99.html">
Technical report version.</a>  Describes the prefetch strategy
incorporated into the collector for some platforms.  Explains why
the sweep phase of a "mark-sweep" collector should not really be
a distinct phase.
</p><p>
M. Serrano, H. Boehm,
"Understanding Memory Allocation of Scheme Programs",
<i>Proceedings of the Fifth ACM SIGPLAN International Conference on
Functional Programming</i>, 2000, Montreal, Canada, pp. 245-256.
<a href="http://www.acm.org/pubs/citations/proceedings/fp/351240/p245-serrano/">
Official version.</a>
<a href="http://www.hpl.hp.com/techreports/2000/HPL-2000-62.html">
Earlier Technical Report version.</a>  Includes some discussion of the
collector debugging facilities for identifying causes of memory retention.
</p><p>
Boehm, H.,
"Fast Multiprocessor Memory Allocation and Garbage Collection",
<a href="http://www.hpl.hp.com/techreports/2000/HPL-2000-165.html">
HP Labs Technical Report HPL 2000-165</a>.  Discusses the parallel
collection algorithms, and presents some performance results.
</p><p>
Boehm, H., "Bounding Space Usage of Conservative Garbage Collectors",
<i>Proceeedings of the 2002 ACM SIGPLAN-SIGACT Symposium on Principles of
Programming Languages</i>, Jan. 2002, pp. 93-100.
<a href="http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?doid=503272.503282">
Official version.</a>
<a href="http://www.hpl.hp.com/techreports/2001/HPL-2001-251.html">
Technical report version.</a>
Includes a discussion of a collector facility to much more reliably test for
the potential of unbounded heap growth.
</p><p>
<b>The following papers discuss language and compiler restrictions necessary to guaranteed
safety of conservative garbage collection.</b>
</p><p>
We thank John Levine and JCLT for allowing
us to make the second paper available electronically, and providing PostScript for the final
version.
</p><p>
Boehm, H., <a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/papers/pldi96.ps.gz">``Simple
Garbage-Collector-Safety''</a>, Proceedings
of the ACM SIGPLAN '96 Conference on Programming Language Design
and Implementation.
</p><p>
Boehm, H., and D. Chase,  <a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/papers/boecha.ps.gz">
``A Proposal for Garbage-Collector-Safe C Compilation''</a>,
<i>Journal of C  Language Translation 4</i>, 2 (Decemeber 1992), pp. 126-141.
</p><p>
<b>Other related information: </b>
</p><p>
The Detlefs, Dosser and Zorn's <a href="ftp://ftp.cs.colorado.edu/pub/techreports/zorn/CU-CS-665-93.ps.Z">Memory Allocation Costs in Large C and C++ Programs</a>.
 This is a performance comparison of the Boehm-Demers-Weiser collector to malloc/free,
using programs written for malloc/free.
</p><p>
Joel Bartlett's <a href="ftp://ftp.digital.com/pub/DEC/CCgc">mostly copying conservative garbage collector for C++</a>.
</p><p>
John Ellis and David Detlef's <a href="ftp://parcftp.xerox.com/pub/ellis/gc/gc.ps">Safe Efficient Garbage Collection for C++</a> proposal.
</p><p>
Henry Baker's <a href="http://home.pipeline.com/~hbaker1/">paper collection</a>.
</p><p>
Slides for Hans Boehm's <a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/myths.ps">Allocation and GC Myths</a> talk.
</p><h2><a name="users">Current users:</a></h2>
<p>
<b>This section has not been updated recently.</b>
</p><p>
Known current users of some variant of this collector include:
</p><p>
The runtime system for <a href="http://gcc.gnu.org/java">GCJ</a>,
the static GNU java compiler.
</p><p>
<a href="http://w3m.sourceforge.net/">W3m</a>, a text-based web browser.
</p><p>
Some versions of the Xerox DocuPrint printer software.
</p><p>
The <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/">Mozilla</a> project, as leak
detector.
</p><p>
The <a href="http://www.go-mono.com/">Mono</a> project,
an open source implementation of the .NET development framework.
</p><p>
The <a href="http://www.gnu.org/projects/dotgnu/">DotGNU Portable.NET
project</a>, another open source .NET implementation.
</p><p>
The <a href="http://irssi.org/">Irssi IRC client</a>.
</p><p>
<a href="http://titanium.cs.berkeley.edu/">The Berkeley Titanium project</a>.
</p><p>
<a href="http://www.nag.co.uk/nagware_fortran_compilers.asp">The NAGWare f90 Fortran 90 compiler</a>.
</p><p>
Elwood Corporation's <a href="http://www.elwood.com/eclipse-info/index.htm">
Eclipse</a> Common Lisp system, C library, and translator.
</p><p>
The <a href="http://www-sop.inria.fr/mimosa/fp/Bigloo/">Bigloo
Scheme</a>
and <a href="http://kaolin.unice.fr/~serrano/camloo.html">Camloo ML
compilers</a>
written by Manuel Serrano and others.
</p><p>
Brent Benson's <a href="http://ftp.cs.indiana.edu/pub/scheme-repository/imp/">libscheme</a>.
</p><p>
The <a href="http://www.cs.rice.edu/CS/PLT/packages/mzscheme/index.html">MzScheme</a> scheme implementation.
</p><p>
The <a href="http://www.cs.washington.edu/research/projects/cecil/www/cecil-home.html">University of Washington Cecil Implementation</a>.
</p><p>
<a href="http://www.icsi.berkeley.edu/Sather/">The Berkeley Sather implementation</a>.
</p><p>
<a href="http://www.cs.berkeley.edu/~harmonia/">The Berkeley Harmonia Project</a>.
</p><p>
The <a href="http://www.cs.arizona.edu/sumatra/toba/">Toba</a> Java Virtual
Machine to C translator.
</p><p>
The <a href="http://www.gwydiondylan.org/">Gwydion Dylan compiler</a>.
</p><p>
The <a href="http://gcc.gnu.org/onlinedocs/gcc/Objective-C.html">
GNU Objective C runtime</a>.
</p><p>
<a href="http://www.math.uiuc.edu/Macaulay2">Macaulay 2</a>, a system to support
research in algebraic geometry and commutative algebra.
</p><p>
The <a href="http://www.vestasys.org/">Vesta</a> configuration management
system.
</p><p>
<a href="http://www.visual-prolog.com/vip6">Visual Prolog 6</a>.
</p><p>
<a href="http://asymptote.sf.net/">Asymptote LaTeX-compatible
vector graphics language.</a>

</p><h2><a name="collector">More collector information at this site</a></h2>
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/simple_example.html">A simple illustration of how to build and
use the collector.</a>.
<p>
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/gcinterface.html">Description of alternate interfaces to the
garbage collector.</a>
</p><p>
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/04tutorial.pdf">Slides from an ISMM 2004  tutorial about the GC.</a>
</p><p>
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/faq.html">A FAQ (frequently asked questions) list.</a>
</p><p>
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/leak.html">How to use the garbage collector as a leak detector.</a>
</p><p>
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/debugging.html">Some hints on debugging garbage collected
applications.</a>
</p><p>
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/gcdescr.html">An overview of the implementation of the
garbage collector.</a>
</p><p>
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/porting.html">Instructions for porting the collector to new
platforms.</a>
</p><p>
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/tree.html">The data structure used for fast pointer lookups.</a>
</p><p>
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/scale.html">Scalability of the collector to multiprocessors.</a>
</p><p>
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/gc_source">Directory containing garbage collector source.</a>

</p><h2><a name="background">More background information at this site</a></h2>
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/bounds.html">An attempt to establish a bound on space usage of
conservative garbage collectors.</a>
<p>
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/complexity.html">Mark-sweep versus copying garbage collectors
and their complexity.</a>
</p><p>
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/conservative.html">Pros and cons of conservative garbage collectors,
in comparison to other collectors.
</a>
</p><p>
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/issues.html">Issues related to garbage collection vs.
manual memory management in C/C++.</a>
</p><p>
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/example.html">An example of a case in which garbage collection
results in a much faster implementation as a result of reduced
synchronization.</a>
</p><p>
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/nonmoving">Slide set discussing performance of nonmoving
garbage collectors.</a>
</p><p>
<a href="http://hboehm.info/popl03/web">
Slide set discussing <i>Destructors, Finalizers, and Synchronization</i>
(POPL 2003).</a>
</p><p>
<a href="http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?doid=604131.604153">
Paper corresponding to above slide set.</a>
(<a href="http://www.hpl.hp.com/techreports/2002/HPL-2002-335.html">
Technical Report version</a>.)
</p><p>
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/gc_bench.html">A Java/Scheme/C/C++ garbage collection benchmark.</a>
</p><p>
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/myths.ps">Slides for talk on memory allocation myths.</a>
</p><p>
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/gctalk.ps">Slides for OOPSLA 98 garbage collection talk.</a>
</p><p>
<a href="https://hboehm.info/gc/papers">Related papers.</a>
</p><h2><a name="contacts">Contacts, Updates, and Reporting Issues</a><a></a></h2><a>
</a><p><a>
For current updates on the collector and information on reporting issues,
please see the </a><a href="https://github.com/ivmai/bdwgc#feedback-contribution-questions-and-notifications">
bdwgc github page</a>.
</p><p>
There used to be a pair of mailing lists for GC discussions. Those are no longer active.
Please see the above page for pointers to the archives.
</p><p>
Some now ancient discussion of the collector took place on the gcc
java mailing list, whose archives appear
<a href="http://gcc.gnu.org/ml/java/">here</a>, and also on
<a href="http://lists.tunes.org/mailman/listinfo/gclist">gclist@iecc.com</a>.
</p><p>
Comments and bug reports may also be sent to
(<a href="mailto:boehm@acm.org">boehm@acm.org</a>), but reporting issues on
<a href="https://github.com/ivmai/bdwgc/issues">github</a> is strongly preferred.
 


</p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Nutrient insights through your grocery receipts (131 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nutri.adrianstobbe.com/</link>
            <guid>39077428</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 11:07:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nutri.adrianstobbe.com/">https://nutri.adrianstobbe.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39077428">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>  <p>Click for a demo without receipt upload!</p> <main> <h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-1lvi74z">Nutrient insights on your groceries</h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-hg1fum">Upload your grocery receipts for veggie tips to make your diet complete in nutrients!</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1ww4jn8">Insights are powered by AI and may be inaccurate. The nutrient content classification only serves as rough estimate.</p> <div role="alert">    <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M21 15v4a2 2 0 0 1-2 2H5a2 2 0 0 1-2-2v-4"></path><polyline points="7 10 12 15 17 10"></polyline><line x1="12" x2="12" y1="15" y2="3"></line></svg> <h5>Stored for later</h5> <p>All data is stored locally, so you can come back later and upload new receipts for the week.</p></div> <div><h3>Add items</h3> <p>Manually add items you don't buy every week.</p></div> <div><div><h3>Choose receipts</h3> <p>Add photos of your receipts here.</p></div> <div><h3>Generate insights</h3> <p>Get nutrient information on your items.</p></div></div> <p><h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-175ukci">No receipts uploaded yet</h3></p>    </main> 
			
			
		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I believe bestselling author Mark Dawson is a serial plagiarist (186 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://old.reddit.com/r/books/comments/18n30jn/i_believe_bestselling_author_mark_dawson_is_a/</link>
            <guid>39077223</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 10:22:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/books/comments/18n30jn/i_believe_bestselling_author_mark_dawson_is_a/">https://old.reddit.com/r/books/comments/18n30jn/i_believe_bestselling_author_mark_dawson_is_a/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39077223">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>If you don’t know who Mark Dawson is, he’s a self-published author who has 203,722 ratings on Goodreads. He says himself that his books have had over 6 million downloads (including both paid and free promotional copies). He runs the Self Publishing Formula course and podcast, he talks at the 20BooksTo50K conference in Vegas, and he’s part of a new initiative called Fuse Publishing. He’s a pretty big deal in self-publishing, so what he does reflects on self-publishing as a whole.</p>

<p>I was wondering how this guy published so many books in so little time and I found my answer: he stole a lot of his material.</p>

<ul>
<li>[2013 William Boyd interviews James Bond by William Boyd from the Guardian] “the gaudy harlequinade of youth much in evidence”</li>
<li>[2014 The Driver by Mark Dawson] “The harlequinade of youth much in evidence”</li>
</ul>

<p>​</p>

<ul>
<li>[2013 William Boyd interviews James Bond by William Boyd from the Guardian] “the dark-eyed girls in their short dresses and the long-haired young men in crushed velvet and fur-trimmed Afghans"</li>
<li>[2014 The Driver by Mark Dawson] “Long-haired young men in vintage suits and fur-trimmed Afghans, and girls in short dresses”</li>
</ul>

<p>​</p>

<ul>
<li>[2012 <em>Annecy shootings: On a steep forest road, few signs of the horror that was</em> by John Lichfield for the Independent] “The misty slopes of the massif of the Montagne de Charbon tower above the treeline”</li>
<li>[2013 The Cleaner by Mark Dawson] “The misty slopes of the massif of the Montagne de Charbon stretched above the treeline”</li>
</ul>

<p>​</p>

<ul>
<li>[2009 I, Sniper: A Bob Lee Swagger Novel by Stephen Hunter] “He settled in, feeling the tension in the trigger, finding his stock weld, sliding to the eyepiece, and seeing the world through the mil-dot-rich reticle…”</li>
<li>[2014 Tarantula by Mark Dawson] “The man settled behind the rifle. He felt the tension in the trigger, found his stockweld and slid up to the eyepiece, staring into it and seeing the ridge and the trees and the vegetation through the mil-dot-rich reticle.”</li>
</ul>

<p>​</p>

<ul>
<li>[2009 I, Sniper: A Bob Lee Swagger Novel by Stephen Hunter] ”Then pulling out his Kestral 4000 weather station and noting the wind, humidity, and temperature.”</li>
<li>[2014 Tarantula by Mark Dawson] “Took out a small weather station and noted the wind, the humidity, and temperature.”</li>
</ul>

<p>​</p>

<ul>
<li>[2009 I, Sniper: A Bob Lee Swagger Novel by Stephen Hunter] “He dialed the first into the scope of the rifle, clicking mostly elevation but some windage, for there was a drift of light wind that rustled undulations in the grass.</li>
<li>[2014 Tarantula by Mark Dawson] “The trees were rustling a little in a light breeze that was running in off the sea […] He dialled the first into the scope of the rifle, making adjustments for windage.”</li>
</ul>

<p>​</p>

<ul>
<li>[2009 I, Sniper: A Bob Lee Swagger Novel by Stephen Hunter]  “… the smell of the cleaning fluid, the touch of hand to comb, cheek to fiberglass, finger to trigger”</li>
<li>[2014 Tarantula by Mark Dawson] “… the smell of the cleaning fluid that had been used on its metallic parts, the cold touch of the aluminum eyepiece against his eye socket. He felt the chill of the fibreglass stock against his cheek.”</li>
</ul>

<p>​</p>

<ul>
<li>[2010 Amexica: War Along the Borderline by Ed Vulliamy] “We pass the iron girder skeleton of a building that never seems to get finished”</li>
<li>[2013 Saint Death Mark Dawson] “Milton passed the iron girder skeleton of a building”</li>
</ul>

<p>​</p>

<ul>
<li>[2010 Amexica: War Along the Borderline by Ed Vulliamy] “little shops, outlets for cocaine, marijuana, synthetic drugs, and heroin—which in Juarez are called picaderos, usually marked by a shoe tied to a nearby telegraph wire”</li>
<li>[2013 Saint Death Mark Dawson] “Milton knew about Juarez […] Illicit outlets—picaderos—were marked out by shoes slung over nearby telegraph wires, and their shifty proprietors sold whatever illicit substance you needed to get high”</li>
</ul>

<p>​</p>

<ul>
<li>An older version of Saint Death said “Illicit outlets––picaderos––were marked out by shoes slung over nearby telegraph wires and their shifty proprietors sold cocaine, marijuana, synthetic drugs and heroin. The legitimate marketplace at Cerrajeros was busy with custom, a broad sweep of unwanted bric-a-brac for sale: discarded furniture, soda fountains, hair curlers, Kelvinator fridges.” but he changed it. So it was even more plagiarized before. You can look it up in Google and it’ll show up, though it leads to a weird scam site which will try to convince you that you have a virus on your computer but I still think that counts as proof as I’m assuming the scam site simply copied an older version of his book verbatim before he sent out an update through Kindle to cover up his more blatant plagiarism.</li>
<li>This also matches up to another passage from Amexica: “… lines the streets in overload quantities: sixties furniture, soda fountains, hair curlers, Kelvinator cookers and Osterizer blenders…” So Mark changed sixties furniture to discarded furniture and Kelvinator cookers to Kelvinator fridges. Nice.</li>
</ul>

<p>And I found all this in an hour or two, just looking at a few of his books, and only looking at the first few pages which were available for free in the Kindle sample and typing suspicious sentences into Google. He’s probably plagiarized a lot more and hidden it with after-the-fact edits and rearranging words in a way that’s harder to check using a search engine.</p>

<p>Basic rule: read through one of his books and type any phrase that seems either interesting and profound or technical about matters he’s not familiar with like guns into Google in quotes. You’ll probably find that he took it from somewhere else.</p>

<p>“Harlequins of youth much in evidence?” Never heard that sentence before. Oh, he didn’t write it.</p>

<p>“Fur-trimmed Afghans?” What are those? Oh, he probably doesn’t know either. Because he didn’t write it.</p>

<p>“Misty slopes of the massif” “Mil-dot-rich reticle” “iron girder skeleton of a building” etc.</p>

<p>For original prose you get clunky purple prose like “the sun glared down, a myriad of shafts that lanced into his eyes.” I mean, a myriad of shafts sounds like you’re talking about golf clubs or genitals. I would HOPE neither of those are lancing you in the eye.</p>

<p>It seems unfair that he’s reportedly sold 6 million books and is so involved in these groups while heavily plagiarizing when books like <em>How Opal Mehta Got Kissed, Got Wild, and Got a Life</em> get cancelled entirely for plagiarism. But maybe in self-publishing things just work differently. But I feel like an author who sells 6 million books should be held to a higher standard whether they’re self-published or not.</p>

<p>(If this was not the right sub to post something like this, then I apologize and I'll take it down. I just thought more people should know about this because it seems like most of his fans have no idea he plagiarizes.)</p>

<p>​</p>

<p>EDIT: A previous of this version incorrectly stated that Mark Dawson wrote 20 books in 2 years. This was based on a cursory look of his Wikipedia page, where it seems to suggest he published 20 books (meaning both novels and novellas) from 2013 to 2015. However, it has been brought to my attention that many people took 'book' to mean full-length novel, not novella, and that a lot of these books had either been written previously and were just now being published, or had listed co-authors. So 20 novels and novellas with his name on them were published between 2013 and 2015 according to his Wikipedia bibliography, but that doesn't mean he necessarily wrote 20 books in 2 years. Apologies for any misinformation.</p>

<p>Hopefully after that blunder I still have some credibility.</p>

<p>EDIT 2: I’ve now reached out to Vox, Forbes, the New York Times, the Guardian, and CBS News with tips.</p>

<p>Some people were also telling me to reach out to various YouTubers and internet personalities to see if they were interested in tweeting about it or investigating it further, but many of them have their Twitter DMs closed and only have brand emails for emailing about sponsorships and such which are only read by a third party. So if you would like to see them talk about this and you know better ways to contact them, feel free to send it their way.</p>

<p>But for now I’m going to focus less on getting the word out and more on finding new examples of plagiarism within Mark Dawson’s other books.</p>

<p>Cheers.</p>

<p>EDIT 3: It seems I've found another source of inspiration.</p>

<ul>
<li>“tree allees, expansive lawns, follies, knot gardens, boxwood parterres” [<a href="http://www.marxdesign.com/TheMorganEstate/exterior.html">http://www.marxdesign.com/TheMorganEstate/exterior.html</a>]</li>
<li>“tree allées, expansive lawns, follies, knot gardens, and boxwood parterres” [The Driver by Mark Dawson (62% of sample on Kindle)]</li>
</ul>

<p>If you look up even the shortened form “tree allées, expansive lawns” only the article and The Driver appear. Doesn't seem like a coincidence to me. The website is copyrighted for 2013, while The Driver came out in January 4, 2014, according to Goodreads. Mark does noticeably fix the spelling of allées though, so that’s nice.</p>

<p>EDIT 4: He really likes the Morgan Estate apparently.</p>

<ul>
<li>“A majestic wrought iron gate brought in from a Southern plantation” [<a href="http://www.marxdesign.com/TheMorganEstate/">http://www.marxdesign.com/TheMorganEstate/</a>] (again copyrighted for 2013)</li>
<li>“a majestic wrought-iron gate that looked like it belonged on a Southern plantation” [The Driver by Mark Dawson (60% of sample)]</li>
</ul>

<p>EDIT 5:</p>

<ul>
<li>[A quote by Stephen Thomas Erlewine which is available from many sources including the All Music Guide: The Definitive Guide to Popular Music from 2001, page 396; notably, this is also the bio for the band on iHeart] “Suede kick-started the Brit pop revolution of the '90s, bringing English indie pop/rock music away from the swirling layers of shoegazing and dance-pop fusions of Madchester, and reinstating such conventions of British pop as mystique and the three-minute single.”</li>
<li>[The Driver by Mark Dawson, 2014, 69% of sample (nice)] “He liked the swirling layers of shoegazing and dance-pop fusions from the Madchester era and the sharp, clean three-minute singles that had evolved out of it. Suede and Sleeper and Blur.”</li>
</ul>

<p>“Swirling layers of shoegazing and dance-pop fusions” is a pretty generic phrase though, don’t you think? Could definitely just be a coincidence.</p>

<p>EDIT 6:</p>

<ul>
<li>[Page 169 of Mayfair Magazine October 2013] “oak parquetry floor, inlaid with ebony wood, with a gilded fireplace from a palazzo near Florence, Italy, no less.”</li>
<li>[77% of sample of The Driver, published in 2014] “oak parquetry floor inlaid with ebony, a gilded fireplace that belonged in a palazzo as the focal point of the wall”</li>
</ul>

<p>EDIT 7:</p>

<ul>
<li>[ <a href="http://www.marxdesign.com/TheMorganEstate/upper.html">http://www.marxdesign.com/TheMorganEstate/upper.html</a> ] (2013) “The upper silk fabric walls that blend with the original wainscoting painted by Dutch painter Van Amstel set the unique intimately warm tone of this office that includes a private powder room and a large wood burning fireplace.”</li>
<li>[79% of sample of The Driver from 2014] “Silk fabric walls blended with painted wainscoting. There was a private powder room and a large wood-burning fireplace.”</li>
</ul>

<p>Again, it may seem like it’s not plagiarism, but think about the elements of the sentence. The word order is the same: silk fabric walls, then wainscoting, then the powder room, then the fireplace. And the powder room is specifically private, and the fireplace is specifically large and fire-burning, and the walls specifically blend with the wainscoting. Though the sentences look different, the structure and verbiage is pretty much identical. It doesn’t even seem like Mark read this once and recalled it from memory. It seems like he wrote the first quote down word for word, then looked for a way to edit it so it might not show up on an automated plagiarism checker.</p>

<p>There’s also another similarity with I, Sniper and Tarantula. They both contain this phrase: “in a steady two-hand grip, trigger finger indexed above the trigger guard.” Both halves of that phrase seem somewhat commonplace, but the combined phrase is unique to those two.</p>

<p>Also a lot of people were saying “That’s just how snipers operate,” and I agree that technical jargon and actions are going to be described similarly in different works. There aren’t that many ways to say someone shot a gun or slammed a door shut. But the larger context is the similarity of both scenes overall:</p>

<p>In I, Sniper, (1 through 5 are in the span of three paragraphs):</p>

<ol>
<li>The protagonist Bob settles behind his rifle (feels the tension in the trigger, finds the stockweld, slides to the eyepiece, and sees the world through the the mil-dot-rich reticle)</li>
<li>He diddles with the focus ring until it declares the world pristine and hard-edged at five to eight hundred yards</li>
<li>He uses a Leica laser</li>
<li>He pulls out a Kestral 4000 weather station (and notes wind, humidity, and temperature)</li>
<li>He runs the data through his Palm Pilot, dials them into the scope of his rifle, then adjusts for windage</li>
<li>Then a few paragraphs later, he is alone in the world of scope, home in the feel of the rifle, the smell of the cleaning fluid, fiberglass on his cheek, his finger on the trigger</li>
</ol>

<p>In Tarantula, (1 through 5 are in the span of two paragraphs):</p>

<ol>
<li>A character called Tarantula settles behind his rifle (feels the tension in the trigger, finds the stockweld, slides to the eyepiece, stares into it and sees the trees and vegetation through the mil-dot-rich reticle)</li>
<li>He makes a minute adjustment to the focus ring until the last remnant of blur is gone</li>
<li>He uses his handheld laser</li>
<li>He takes out a small weather station (and notes wind, humidity, and temperature)</li>
<li>He notes the data in a small notebook and calculates the solutions and dials those calculations into his rifle, then adjusts for windage</li>
<li>Then a few paragraphs later, he shuts out everything except for the scope, concentrating on the feel of the rifle, the smell of the cleaning fluid, fiberglass on his cheek, and… an aluminum eyepiece against his eye socket? Definitely sounds like something a real gun buff would write...</li>
</ol>

<p>Also he seems to have taken information from a gun website basically verbatim:</p>

<ul>
<li>[ <a href="https://hermannsguns.com.au/dsr-1/">https://hermannsguns.com.au/dsr-1/</a> ] “The folding bipod is mounted onto upper rails (above the barrel), and the adjustable horizontal front grip is mounted on the lower rails (under the barrel). The rifle features fully adjustable buttstock and cheekpiece. […] The barrel is protected by ventilated aluminum handguard and is fitted with muzzle brake (very useful when firing full-power magnum loads).”</li>
<li>[Tarantula, 43% of sample] “The folding bipod was mounted onto upper rails above the barrel and the adjustable horizontal front grip was mounted on the lower rails, under the barrel. The rifle had an adjustable stock and cheekpiece. The barrel was protected by a ventilated aluminium hand guard and was fitted with a muzzle brake, useful when firing full-power magnum loads like this.”</li>
</ul>

<p>I mean, is this what we’re calling research these days? Just dumping an encyclopedia article into your novel with minimal editing?</p>

<p>EDIT 8:</p>

<p>Fixed the part where I said he had sold 6 million books. Someone in the comments said the 6 million figure is for downloads which includes freebies, so the actual sales figure may be a bit different. His latest John Milton book which isn't out yet says "Five Million Copies Sold" on the cover, though that might just be for the John Milton series specifically. His site says, "6 million books downloaded worldwide," not sold. Though his Twitter bio says "over 6m copies sold worldwide," so it could be that his website just hasn't been updated as recently. I'm just going to be safe and say "over 6 million downloads."</p>

<p>Also, somebody noticed that in his newer books, Mark is using a new tactic:</p>

<ul>
<li>[Never Let Me Down Again, 89% sample] "He opened Wikipedia and skimmed the details. It was a small resort on the coast with the locals relying on tourism to help them make their way. It was set on the edge of the Firth of Lorn, the bay reaching out in a horseshoe shape and shielded by the island of Kerrera and, beyond that, the larger Isle of Mull"</li>
<li>[Wikipedia article on Oban] "Oban occupies a setting in the Firth of Lorn. The bay forms a near perfect horseshoe, protected by the island of Kerrera; and beyond Kerrera, the Isle of Mull."</li>
</ul>

<p>All you have to do is have your character read Wikipedia in-universe so that you automatically cite your sources. Pretty good strategy, I must say. (This definitely isn't the most offensive of the evidence, I just found it funny that he just has his characters reading Wikipedia on their phones now.)</p>

<p>EDIT 9:</p>

<p>It looks like Mark Dawson has removed the Kindle version of Tarantula from Amazon, leaving only the Audible version up. He notably also did this with his novel The Black Mile, which some reviews on Amazon and Goodreads have accused of being extremely similar to LA Confidential.</p>

<p>I probably won't be updating this post too much, as I am pretty busy in my personal life, but I encourage people to share the information with newspapers and literary influencers and the like, and I'd also like to point out some common errors I see in articles being written on Substack and Medium:</p>

<ol>
<li>Mark Dawson did not write 20 books in 2 years. (I take full responsibility for this one. Despite correcting this claim in my post, the thumbnail for this post still says it on other platforms, forever reminding me of my mistake. Ugh). Also, generally I'd say don't mention prolificness at all. It makes other prolific authors feel like you're insulting their craft.</li>
<li>Mark Dawson does not run 20BooksTo50K. Michael Anderle started it, and Craig Martelle runs it. Mark Dawson has talked at their Vegas conference as a guest speaker, but that seems to be the extent of his involvement. Generally, don't mention 20BooksTo50K at all other than to say that he's a pretty well-connected, popular author who gets invited to guest speak at conferences. The group has a lot of fans who will defend it, and obviously saying he runs it when he doesn't isn't great for your case.</li>
<li>No conspiracy theories about ChatGPT. He wrote these books 10 years ago.</li>
<li>And obviously, no insulting self-publishing as a whole, or saying that any author who finds success is a sellout. For some reason, I see a lot of people doing this. When you write about a popular self-published author, you're going to attract people who are interested in the self-publishing space. Those people are not going to want to be told that most bestselling self-published books are worthless trash. That should be obvious.</li>
</ol>

<p>So if you'd like to help spread the story, please try not to repeat any of the misinformation listed above. It weakens our case and makes it easy for someone to dismiss an entire article based on a singular factual mistake.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Colorado pastor charged for cryptocurrency scam he perpetrated at God's command (139 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://web3isgoinggreat.com/single/indxcoin</link>
            <guid>39077151</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 10:04:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://web3isgoinggreat.com/single/indxcoin">https://web3isgoinggreat.com/single/indxcoin</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39077151">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><span>A Colorado-based pastor for an online ministry sold INDXcoin to his followers and others in the Christian faith. However, there was no way for buyers to cash out the tokens. Meanwhile, Regalado and his wife spent the money on a Rolls Royce, jewelry, and designer handbags — and, according to Regalado, "a home renovation the Lord told us to do."<p>Regalado posted a video to his supporters explaining that he had been sued by the Colorado state securities regulator. "So the charges are that Kaitlyn and I pocketed $1.3 million, and I just want to come out and say that those uh charges are true," said Regalado in the video, presumably causing a cold chill to run down the spine of his defense attorney in the middle of whatever he was doing.</p><p>According to Regalado, God told them to first invest in a separate coin, which turned out to be a scam. Then, says Regalado, God told him to make his own currency, which Regalado called INDXcoin, "but also give them a 10x". Who knew God was a <a href="https://web3isgoinggreat.com/glossary#degen" target="_blank">degen</a>! Regalado had told investors that the funds would be going to "widows and orphans", but spent most of it on himself and his wife.</p></span></p><ul><li><a href="https://securities.colorado.gov/press-release/press-release-colorado-securities-commissioner-files-complaint-against-alleged" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer"><span>"Colorado Securities Commissioner Files Complaint Against Alleged Cryptocurrency Fraud Scheme"</span></a><span>, Colorado Division of Securities press release</span><span> <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20240121025545/https://securities.colorado.gov/press-release/press-release-colorado-securities-commissioner-files-complaint-against-alleged" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">[archive]</a></span></li><li><a href="https://businessden.com/2024/01/18/pastor-pocketed-1-3m-selling-worthless-cryptocurrency-state-says/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer"><span>"Pastor pocketed $1.3M selling worthless cryptocurrency, state says"</span></a><span>, <i>BusinessDen</i></span><span> <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20240118132215/https://businessden.com/2024/01/18/pastor-pocketed-1-3m-selling-worthless-cryptocurrency-state-says/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">[archive]</a></span></li></ul></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How a baker survived the Titanic by getting drunk (2022) (125 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nationalpost.com/news/canada/how-a-baker-survived-the-titanic-by-getting-spectacularly-drunk</link>
            <guid>39077133</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 10:00:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nationalpost.com/news/canada/how-a-baker-survived-the-titanic-by-getting-spectacularly-drunk">https://nationalpost.com/news/canada/how-a-baker-survived-the-titanic-by-getting-spectacularly-drunk</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39077133">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://nationalpost.com/news/canada/how-a-baker-survived-the-titanic-by-getting-spectacularly-drunk: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Keeping a long shell history (165 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://registerspill.thorstenball.com/p/which-command-did-you-run-1731-days</link>
            <guid>39076573</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 08:02:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://registerspill.thorstenball.com/p/which-command-did-you-run-1731-days">https://registerspill.thorstenball.com/p/which-command-did-you-run-1731-days</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39076573">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><blockquote><p><em>Professor Henry Jones</em><span>: Well, he who finds the Grail must face the final challenge.</span></p><p><em>Indiana Jones</em><span>: What final challenge?</span></p><p><em>Professor Henry Jones</em><span>: Three devices of such lethal cunning.</span></p><p><em>Indiana Jones</em><span>: Booby traps?</span></p><p><em>Professor Henry Jones</em><span>: Oh, yes. But I found the clues that will safely take us through them in the Chronicles of St.&nbsp;Anselm.</span></p><p><em>Indiana Jones</em><span>: [pleased] Well, what are they?</span></p><p>[short pause as Henry tries to recall]</p><p><em>Indiana Jones</em><span>: Can’t you remember?</span></p><p><em>Professor Henry Jones</em><span>: I wrote them down in my diary so that I wouldn’t </span><em>have</em><span> to remember.</span></p></blockquote><p><span>                </span><strong>***</strong></p><p>Recipe for living a good life in the shell:</p><ol><li><p>Make sure it’s fast.</p></li><li><p>Make sure its history can grow nearly infinitely and you can fuzzy-search through it.</p></li></ol><p><span>The first one–fast shells–</span><a href="https://registerspill.thorstenball.com/p/how-fast-is-your-shell" rel="">we talked about last week</a><span>, so this time, let’s talk about shell history.</span></p><p><span>On one of my machines the </span><code>~/.zsh_history</code><span> file contains 26278 commands. Its oldest entry was recorded on April 25, 2019. When I hit </span><code>Ctrl-r</code><span> in ZSH </span><a href="https://github.com/junegunn/fzf" rel="">fzf</a><span> pops up and lets me fuzzy-search through all 26278 commands, through the last 5 years of my shell history. It’s glorious.</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F01532c09-5727-4ac5-8536-e20522bb90d4_800x518.gif" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F01532c09-5727-4ac5-8536-e20522bb90d4_800x518.gif 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F01532c09-5727-4ac5-8536-e20522bb90d4_800x518.gif 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F01532c09-5727-4ac5-8536-e20522bb90d4_800x518.gif 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F01532c09-5727-4ac5-8536-e20522bb90d4_800x518.gif 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F01532c09-5727-4ac5-8536-e20522bb90d4_800x518.gif" width="800" height="518" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/01532c09-5727-4ac5-8536-e20522bb90d4_800x518.gif&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:518,&quot;width&quot;:800,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:2388737,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/gif&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F01532c09-5727-4ac5-8536-e20522bb90d4_800x518.gif 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F01532c09-5727-4ac5-8536-e20522bb90d4_800x518.gif 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F01532c09-5727-4ac5-8536-e20522bb90d4_800x518.gif 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F01532c09-5727-4ac5-8536-e20522bb90d4_800x518.gif 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><span>That one </span><code>curl</code><span> command with these four strange HTTP headers that I had to send to make sure I could talk to my local dev env correctly through the reverse-proxy – that’s in there, a few keystrokes and some hazy memories away. That one </span><code>rsync</code><span> that uses the correct SSH client binary on the other side and that preserves timestamps and permission – also in there. The ugly bastard of a command that combined </span><code>git grep</code><span> with </span><code>find</code><span> and 8 ugly incantations of AWK chained together – locked in there too. The test command I ran yesterday is as reachable as the one command with 12 </span><code>&amp;&amp;</code><span> in it that I ran 3 years ago, all thanks to a long shell history file.</span></p><p><span>Truly: </span><code>~/.zsh_history</code><span> is one of the most important files on my machine. I make use of it tens of times every day, whenever I hit </span><code>Ctrl-r</code><span>. If I wasn’t such a doofus it would contain even more than 26278 commands, because I’ve been keeping a long shell history for nearly a decade. But since I </span><em>am</em><span> such a doofus, I forgot to back it up (or deleted the backup too early) a few times and hence the </span><code>~/.zsh_history</code><span> on the machine I’m typing this only contains 1034 commands.</span></p><p>Someone might say: “well, if the command was that important, why don’t you save it to a script?” And to that I say: look, man, if I knew in advance which command would turn out to be important, then we wouldn’t be here, because I’d already have ascended to the astral realm.</p><p><span>Also: why </span><em>would</em><span> I record it in a script if I can just configure my shell to keep track of all of those commands for me? It’s cheap, it’s fast, there’s essentially no downsides to it: the largest </span><code>~/.zsh_history</code><span> I have is 2MB and I can fuzzy-search through it in </span><em>milliseconds</em><span>.</span></p><p><span>                </span><strong>***</strong></p><p>So, to repeat: your shell – ZSH, Bash, Fish, or others – can record every command you execute in it and I’m begging you to make sure it is configured to do that.</p><p><span>Make sure it keeps track of </span><em>a lot</em><span> of commands. So many commands that when you put the number in your rc-file you think: that’s ridiculous, why would I need to record that many commands? Double that number. As the next and final step you need to get a fuzzy-finder fuzzy-finder to search through it.</span></p><p><span>Here’s </span><a href="https://github.com/mrnugget/dotfiles/blob/2bdf21b659cbf34f21a0716bfac1f90914426a87/zshrc#L18-L35" rel="">the ZSH configuration</a><span> I used for many, many years:</span></p><pre><code><code>##########
# HISTORY
##########

HISTFILE=$HOME/.zsh_history
HISTSIZE=50000
SAVEHIST=50000

# Immediately append to history file:
setopt INC_APPEND_HISTORY

# Record timestamp in history:
setopt EXTENDED_HISTORY

# Expire duplicate entries first when trimming history:
setopt HIST_EXPIRE_DUPS_FIRST

# Dont record an entry that was just recorded again:
setopt HIST_IGNORE_DUPS

# Delete old recorded entry if new entry is a duplicate:
setopt HIST_IGNORE_ALL_DUPS

# Do not display a line previously found:
setopt HIST_FIND_NO_DUPS

# Dont record an entry starting with a space:
setopt HIST_IGNORE_SPACE

# Dont write duplicate entries in the history file:
setopt HIST_SAVE_NO_DUPS

# Share history between all sessions:
setopt SHARE_HISTORY

# Execute commands using history (e.g.: using !$) immediatel:
unsetopt HIST_VERIFY
</code></code></pre><p><span>That was combined with </span><a href="https://github.com/junegunn/fzf" rel="">fzf</a><span> to fuzzy-search through the history on </span><code>ctrl-r</code><span>.</span></p><p>Configure your shell roughly like that and there you are: living the good shell life.</p><p><span>Or you can use </span><a href="https://github.com/atuinsh/atuin" rel="">Atuin</a><span>, which I’ve been trying out for the last few weeks and have come to love. It’s a drop-in enhancement of your shell’s history functionality and not only gives you everything I described above – incredibly long shell history and fuzzy-search through it – but also syncing and backup (yup, need that) of shell history across multiple machines, filtering commands by machine, working-directory-specific history and probably 13 other things I forgot. It’s </span><em>very</em><span> nice. Highly recommend it.</span></p><p>Whatever you use: make sure your shell history is recorded, make sure your shell history can grow ridiculously long, and get a fuzzy-search for it.</p></div></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The growing inequality of who gets to work from home (107 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://hbr.org/2023/12/research-the-growing-inequality-of-who-gets-to-work-from-home</link>
            <guid>39076168</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 06:30:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://hbr.org/2023/12/research-the-growing-inequality-of-who-gets-to-work-from-home">https://hbr.org/2023/12/research-the-growing-inequality-of-who-gets-to-work-from-home</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39076168">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>



<hero-image>
	<div>
				<p><img src="https://hbr.org/resources/images/article_assets/2023/11/Dec23_14_2683499.jpg" alt="" title="" aria-label="" sizes="(min-width: 64em) 84vw, 100vw" srcset="https://hbr.org/resources/images/article_assets/2023/11/Dec23_14_2683499.jpg 1200w, https://hbr.org/resources/images/article_assets/2023/11/Dec23_14_2683499-300x169.jpg 300w, https://hbr.org/resources/images/article_assets/2023/11/Dec23_14_2683499-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://hbr.org/resources/images/article_assets/2023/11/Dec23_14_2683499-768x432.jpg 768w, https://hbr.org/resources/images/article_assets/2023/11/Dec23_14_2683499-500x281.jpg 500w, https://hbr.org/resources/images/article_assets/2023/11/Dec23_14_2683499-383x215.jpg 383w, https://hbr.org/resources/images/article_assets/2023/11/Dec23_14_2683499-700x394.jpg 700w, https://hbr.org/resources/images/article_assets/2023/11/Dec23_14_2683499-850x478.jpg 850w"></p><p><span>Synchro Shoot/Stocksy</span>
		</p>


	</div>
</hero-image>



	<page-utils data-js-target="page-utils" data-id="tag:blogs.harvardbusiness.org,2007-03-31:999.369583" data-title="Research: The Growing Inequality of Who Gets to Work from Home" data-url="/2023/12/research-the-growing-inequality-of-who-gets-to-work-from-home" data-topic="Hybrid work" data-authors="Peter John Lambert; Nicholas Bloom; Steven Davis; Stephen Hansen; Yabra Muvdi; Raffaella Sadun; Bledi Taska" data-content-type="Digital Article" data-content-image="/resources/images/article_assets/2023/11/Dec23_14_2683499-383x215.jpg" data-summary="<p>An analysis of online job postings found that remote-work opportunities increasingly skew toward the highly paid and highly educated.</p>
">
		<ul>
			<li>
				<a href="http://twitter.com/HarvardBiz" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" js-target="twitter-share">
					<i></i>
					<p>Tweet</p>
				</a>
			</li>
			<li>
				<a href="http://www.facebook.com/HBR" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" js-target="facebook-share">
					<i></i>
					<p>Post</p>
				</a>
			</li>
			<li>
				<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/harvard-business-review?trk=biz-companies-cym" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" js-target="linkedin-share">
					<i></i>
					<p>Share</p>
				</a>
			</li>
			<li js-target="annotate-icon">
				<a js-target="handle-mindstone-click">
					<i js-target="mindstone-icon-black">	<svg alt="" aria-labelledby="title">
	<title></title>
	<use xlink:href="/resources/css/images/hbr-icons.svg#mindstone-icon-black"></use></svg>
</i>
					<p>Annotate</p>
				</a>
			</li><li>
				<a href="#" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" js-target="save-flyout">
					<i></i>
					<p>Save</p>
				</a>
			</li>
				<li>
					<a rel="noopener noreferrer" href="#" js-target="pdf-download-link" data-reprint-product-id="H07X67-PDF-ENG">
						<i></i>
						<p>Get PDF</p>
					</a>
				</li>
				<li>
					<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://hbr.org/product/research-the-growing-inequality-of-who-gets-to-work-from-home/H07X67-PDF-ENG" js-target="buy-reprint-link" data-reprint-product-id="H07X67-PDF-ENG">
						<i>	<svg alt="" aria-labelledby="title">
	<title></title>
	<use xlink:href="/resources/css/images/hbr-icons.svg#buy-copies-thicker"></use></svg>
</i>
						<p>Buy Copies</p>
					</a>
				</li>
			<li>
				<span>
					<i></i>
					<p>Print</p>
				</span>
			</li>
		</ul>
	</page-utils>




	<p>
		<span><p>There is a large and growing divide in terms of who gets to work from home. Research on job postings found that remote work is far more common for higher paid roles, for roles that require more experience, for full-time work, and for roles that require more education. Managers should be aware of this divide, as it has the potential to create toxic dynamics within teams and to sap morale.</p>
</span>
	</p>

					<div>
						<div>
	<page-utils data-js-target="page-utils" data-id="tag:blogs.harvardbusiness.org,2007-03-31:999.369583" data-title="Research: The Growing Inequality of Who Gets to Work from Home" data-url="/2023/12/research-the-growing-inequality-of-who-gets-to-work-from-home" data-topic="Hybrid work" data-authors="Peter John Lambert; Nicholas Bloom; Steven Davis; Stephen Hansen; Yabra Muvdi; Raffaella Sadun; Bledi Taska" data-content-type="Digital Article" data-content-image="/resources/images/article_assets/2023/11/Dec23_14_2683499-383x215.jpg" data-summary="<p>An analysis of online job postings found that remote-work opportunities increasingly skew toward the highly paid and highly educated.</p>
">
		<ul>
			<li>
				<a href="http://twitter.com/HarvardBiz" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" js-target="twitter-share">
					<i></i>
					<p>Tweet</p>
				</a>
			</li>
			<li>
				<a href="http://www.facebook.com/HBR" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" js-target="facebook-share">
					<i></i>
					<p>Post</p>
				</a>
			</li>
			<li>
				<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/harvard-business-review?trk=biz-companies-cym" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" js-target="linkedin-share">
					<i></i>
					<p>Share</p>
				</a>
			</li>
			<li js-target="annotate-icon">
				<a js-target="handle-mindstone-click">
					<i js-target="mindstone-icon-black">	<svg alt="" aria-labelledby="title">
	<title></title>
	<use xlink:href="/resources/css/images/hbr-icons.svg#mindstone-icon-black"></use></svg>
</i>
					<p>Annotate</p>
				</a>
			</li><li>
				<a href="#" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" js-target="save-flyout">
					<i></i>
					<p>Save</p>
				</a>
			</li>
				<li>
					<a rel="noopener noreferrer" href="#" js-target="pdf-download-link" data-reprint-product-id="H07X67-PDF-ENG">
						<i></i>
						<p>Get PDF</p>
					</a>
				</li>
				<li>
					<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://hbr.org/product/research-the-growing-inequality-of-who-gets-to-work-from-home/H07X67-PDF-ENG" js-target="buy-reprint-link" data-reprint-product-id="H07X67-PDF-ENG">
						<i>	<svg alt="" aria-labelledby="title">
	<title></title>
	<use xlink:href="/resources/css/images/hbr-icons.svg#buy-copies-thicker"></use></svg>
</i>
						<p>Buy Copies</p>
					</a>
				</li>
			<li>
				<span>
					<i></i>
					<p>Print</p>
				</span>
			</li>
		</ul>
	</page-utils>
						</div>

						<content js-target="article-content" data-key="DLWvS+SOUi7RaTenW6tSPwOWwvqosZC4i7nFy2zvsFF4GYOtHTYIBJdoe7h4cg/G" data-index="BM5l29iJY6Ee+8B2yfNlrdgbvN4VLOJhHh/T44P8lW5E79C1aEAUC2JC22eLVUK3+E6CE4FanSeVoJtpnFz2kQ==" data-waiver="false" data-page-year="2023" data-page-month="12" data-page-seo-title="research-the-growing-inequality-of-who-gets-to-work-from-home" data-page-adunit-locations="" data-page-slug="article" data-piano-verified="false">
								<p>Remote work has exploded since the pandemic struck, and employees like it. In speaking to hundreds of managers about this development, one concern crops up again and again: The shift to remote work is highly unequal. Front-line staff with modest paychecks rarely enjoy the benefits of working from home. Instead, they commute every workday to engage customers and coworkers, operate machinery, and look after facilities. In contrast, highly paid professionals and managers often work from home two or three days a week — saving time, money, and aggravation. Business leaders rightly worry that this divide could hurt morale among front-line staff, undermine perceived fairness, and create new rifts in the workforce.</p>
						</content>
<!-- citation -->
					</div>
				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Collision Detection (2015) (186 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.jeffreythompson.org/collision-detection/index.php</link>
            <guid>39075804</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 05:17:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.jeffreythompson.org/collision-detection/index.php">https://www.jeffreythompson.org/collision-detection/index.php</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39075804">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="wrapper">
		
		
		<canvas id="Introduction" data-processing-sources="code/Introduction/web-export/Introduction.pde"><p>[ your browser does not support the canvas tag ]</p></canvas>


<h4>Jeff Thompson</h4>

<p>The collision of objects underlies most game experiences and user-interfaces. Baseball bats collide with balls, zombies bump into walls, and Mario lands on platforms and stomps turtles. Even something as simple as clicking a button (a rectangle) with your mouse (a point) is a collision.</p>

<p>This book explains the algorithms behind those collisions using basic shapes like circles, rectangles, and lines so you can implement them into your own projects.</p>

<p><strong>UPDATE!</strong> This site has been getting lots of visits which is awesome. I've made some changes so it will look better on mobile devices, make navigation easier, and tried to look over everything for mistakes. If you have any problems or suggestions, please <a href="https://github.com/jeffThompson/CollisionDetection/issues">post an issue on the project repository</a>. Thanks!</p>

<p>Ready to get started? Skip ahead to the <a href="https://www.jeffreythompson.org/collision-detection/table_of_contents.php">Table of Contents...</a></p>
<!-- <a href="table_of_contents.php"><p class="nextPage">Skip ahead to the Table of Contents</p></a> -->

<h2>WHAT'S COVERED HERE?</h2>
<p>This book covers collisions between points, circles, rectangles, lines, polygons, and triangles. These examples are meant to be as readable and easily understood as possible. There are definitely faster, more efficient ways to detect these collisions, but this book is intended to be friendly and teach the principles with minimal math.</p>

<p>Each section include a description of the collision algorithm and an interactive example built using <code>processing.js</code>. You can <a href="https://github.com/jeffThompson/CollisionDetection">view the source code for all the examples (and this book!) on GitHub.</a></p>

<p><strong>NOTE!</strong> If you're on a mobile device, the examples might not work super well for you. They are designed for mouse input, so if you're getting frustrated or your finger is in the way, try the site on a computer.</p>

<h2>WHAT'S NOT?</h2>
<p>As with any book, there's a lot more useful material than could be covered here. Things that aren't discussed are mostly left out because the math gets too complicated. Three-dimensional space isn't touched on. Ellipses, which seem like they should be pretty easy, are actually very difficult.</p>

<p>If there's a specific collision not covered that would be helpful, please please <a href="https://github.com/jeffThompson/CollisionDetection/issues"> submit an issue with a request</a> or, better yet, submit a working example that you've built!</p>

<h2>ISSUES?</h2>
<p>If you find code that doesn't run correctly, an algorithm that isn't explained quite right, or a typo, please <a href="https://github.com/jeffThompson/CollisionDetection/issues">report them at this project's GitHub repository</a>. Thanks for your help!</p>

<h2>NAVIGATION</h2>
<p>OK, let's write some code! Click the link at the bottom the page, or the arrows at the top, to move to the next chapter. The <code>Collision Detection</code> link at the top will take you back to the <a href="https://www.jeffreythompson.org/collision-detection/table_of_contents.php">Table of Contents</a>.</p>


	<!-- link to the next page -->
	<a href="https://www.jeffreythompson.org/collision-detection/table_of_contents.php"><p>NEXT: Table Of Contents</p></a>
	

	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Use Midnight Commander like a pro (2015) (150 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://klimer.eu/2015/05/01/use-midnight-commander-like-a-pro/</link>
            <guid>39075316</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 03:43:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://klimer.eu/2015/05/01/use-midnight-commander-like-a-pro/">https://klimer.eu/2015/05/01/use-midnight-commander-like-a-pro/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39075316">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content-wrapper">
		<main id="main" role="main">

		
			
<article id="post-37">
			<!-- .entry-header -->		<div>
			<p>
							<span>
					<a href="https://klimer.eu/category/linux/" rel="category tag">Linux</a>				</span></p><!-- .cat-links -->
			
			
			<p><span>
				<time datetime="2015-05-01T17:11:00+00:00">May 1, 2015</time><time datetime="2021-01-01T17:12:59+00:00">January 1, 2021</time>			</span>

			<span>6 Minutes</span>		</p></div><!-- .entry-meta -->
	
	<div>
		
<p>If you’ve used an <code>*nix</code> system, at some point you’ve stumbled upon <a href="http://www.midnight-commander.org/">Midnight Commander</a>, a file manager based on the venerable Norton Commander. You’re probably familiar with the basic operations (<code>F5</code> for copying, <code>F6</code> for moving, <code>F8</code> for deleting, etc.) and how to switch panels (ummm, the <code>Tab</code> key). But <code>mc</code> offers so much more than that. This article aims to show all the useful (YMMV) shortcuts and functionalities that are often overlooked. Most of them can be accessed using the menu (<code>F9</code>), but who has the time to do that?</p>



<p>Before we get started, let’s establish some facts. This article was written and tested on the following software:</p>



<ul><li>Midnight Commander 4.8.13</li><li>GNU bash 4.2.53</li></ul>



<p>Oh, and make sure you’re running a modern and UTF-8 friendly terminal – for example, rxvt-unicode.</p>



<h2 id="hold-your-horses">Hold your horses</h2>



<p>There’s actually one thing I’d recommend doing before you run <code>mc</code>. <code>mc</code> has the ability to exit to its current directory. Meaning, you can navigate the filesystem using <code>mc</code> (sometimes it’s easier than <code>cd</code>ing into that one directory buried deep down <em>somewhere</em>) and when you quit <code>mc</code> (<code>F10</code>), your shell will automagically <code>cd</code> to that directory. This is done thanks to the <code>mc-wrapper</code> script that should be bundled with your installation of <code>mc</code>. The exact location is dependent on your distribution – in mine (Gentoo) it’s <code>/usr/libexec/mc/</code>, in Ubuntu supposedly it’s in <code>/usr/share/mc/bin/</code>. Once found, modify your <code>~/.bashrc</code>:</p>


<div><pre title="">alias mc='. /usr/libexec/mc/mc-wrapper.sh'

</pre></div>


<p>Restart your shell, launch <code>mc</code>, change to another directory, exit and your shell should be set to that new directory.</p>



<h2 id="selecting-files">Selecting files</h2>



<ul><li><code>Insert</code> (<code>Ctrl + t</code> alternatively) – select files (for example, for copying, moving or deleting).</li><li><code>+</code> – select files based on a pattern.</li><li><code>\</code> –<em>un</em>select files based on a pattern.</li><li><code>*</code> – reverse selection. If nothing was selected, all files will get selected.</li></ul>



<h2 id="accessing-the-shell">Accessing the shell</h2>



<ul><li>There’s a shell awaiting your command at the bottom of the screen – just start typing (when no other command dialog is open, of course).</li><li>Since <code>Tab</code> is bound to switching panels (or moving the focus in dialogs), you have to use <code>Esc Tab</code> to use autocompletion. Hit it twice to get all the possible completions (just like in a shell). This works in dialogs too.</li><li>If you want inspect the output of the command, do some input or just prefer a bigger console, no need to quit <code>mc</code>. Just hit <code>Ctrl + o</code> – the effect will be similar to putting <code>mc</code> in the background but with a nice perk. Your current working directory from <code>mc</code> will be passed on to the shell… and vice versa! Hit <code>Ctrl + o</code> again to return to <code>mc</code>.</li><li><code>Ctrl + Enter</code> or <code>Alt + Enter</code> – copy the currently selected file’s name to the shell.</li><li><code>Ctrl + Shift + Enter</code> – same as above, but the full path is copied.</li></ul>



<h2 id="internal-viewer-f3-and-editor-f4">Internal viewer (<code>F3</code>) and editor (<code>F4</code>)</h2>



<ul><li>The internal viewer has many built in modes for “previewing” the content of the file. Try “viewing” a binary, an archive, a DOC document or an image. In some cases, external programs are needed in order for this “previewing” to work.</li><li>If you want to preview the “raw” contents of the file, hit <code>Shift + F3</code>.</li><li>While the internal viewer and editor are powerful, sometimes you want to use your preferred software (<em>cough</em>vim<em>cough</em>). You can do so by setting the <code>PAGER</code> (for viewer) and <code>EDITOR</code> (for editor) variables (for example, in your <code>~/.bashrc</code> file). Then toggle the <code>Options -&gt; Configuration -&gt; Use interal edit/view</code> option (access the top menu by pressing <code>F9</code>).</li></ul>



<h2 id="panels">Panels</h2>



<ul><li><code>Alt + ,</code> – switch <code>mc</code>’s layout from left-right to top-bottom. Mind = blown. Useful for operating on files with long names.</li><li><code>Alt + t</code> – switch the panel’s listing mode in a loop: default, brief, long, user-defined. “long” is especially useful, because it maximises one panel so that it takes full width of the window and longer filenames fit on screen.</li><li><code>Alt + i</code> – synchronize the active panel with the other panel. That is, show the current directory in the other panel.</li><li><code>Ctrl + u</code> – swap panels.</li><li><code>Alt + o</code> – if the currently selected file is a directory, load that directory on the other panel and move the selection to the next file. If the currently selected file is not a directory, load the parent directory on the other panel and moves the selection to the next file. This is useful for quick checking the contents of a list of directories.</li><li><code>Ctrl + PgUp</code> (or just left arrow, if you’ve enabled <code>Lynx-like motion</code>, see later) – move to the parent directory.</li><li><code>Alt + Shift + h</code> – show the directory history. Might be easier to navigate than going back one entry at a time.</li><li><code>Alt + y</code> – move to the previous directory in history.</li><li><code>Alt + u</code> – move to the next directory in history.</li></ul>



<h2 id="searching-files">Searching files</h2>



<ul><li><code>Alt + ?</code> – shows the full Find dialog.</li><li><code>Alt + s</code> or <code>Ctrl + s</code> – quick search mode. Start typing and the selection will move to the first matching file. Press the shortcut again to jump to another match. Use wildcards (<code>*</code>, <code>?</code>) for easier matching.</li></ul>



<h2 id="common-actions">Common actions</h2>



<ul><li><code>Ctrl + Space</code> – calculate the size of the selected directories. Press this shortcut when the selection is on <code>..</code> to calculate the size of all the directories in the current directory.</li><li><code>Ctrl + x s</code> (that is press <code>Ctrl + x</code>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L0MK7qz13bU">let it go</a> and then press <code>s</code>) – create a symbolic link (change <code>s</code> to <code>l</code> for a hardlink). I find it very useful and intuitive – the link will, of course, be created in the other panel. You can change it’s destination and name, like with any other file operation.</li><li><code>Ctrl + x c</code> – open the <code>chmod</code> dialog.</li><li><code>Ctrl + x o</code> – open the <code>chown</code> dialog.</li></ul>



<h2 id="virtual-file-system-vfs">Virtual File System (VFS)</h2>



<p><code>mc</code> has a concept known as Virtual File System. Try “entering” an archive (<code>*.tar.gz</code>, <code>*.rpm</code> or even <code>*.jar</code>) – you’ll be able to browse the contents of the archive like a normal folder, without unpacking it first. You extract selected files from the archive by just copying them to the other panel. Bonus points: try “entering” a… <code>*.patch</code> file.</p>



<p>This concept is even more powerful when you realize that remote locations can be viewed the same way. A quick way to browse an FTP location is to just <code>cd</code> to it: <code>cd ftp://mirrors.tera-byte.com/pub/gentoo</code> (first Gentoo FTP mirror I found). You’ll be able to interact with files as you normally do. To exit this remote location, <code>cd</code> to a local directory. Just typing <code>cd</code> will suffice as it will take you to your home directory.</p>



<p>VFS works for SFTP and Samba shares too. Check the manpages for more information on how to specify user/pass, etc.</p>



<h2 id="useful-options">Useful options</h2>



<ul><li><strong>Configuration</strong><ul><li><code>Verbose operation</code> and <code>Compute totals</code> – so that operations like copy/move have a more detailed progress dialogs.</li></ul></li><li><strong>Layout</strong><ul><li><code>Equal split</code> – uncheck to define your own ratio for panels. Maybe you prefer one panel bigger than the other? Useful especially if you keep one of the panels in tree mode (or maybe info/quick view, too).</li><li>Uncheck <code>Hintbar visible</code> – one more line available, one less line of noise.</li></ul></li><li><strong>Panel options</strong><ul><li><code>Show backup files</code> and <code>Show hidden files</code> – I keep both enabled, as I often work with configuration files, etc.</li><li><code>Lynx-like motion</code> – mentioned above, makes left arrow go to parent directory, while the right arrow enters the directory under selection. Faster than <code>Home</code>, <code>Enter</code>, <code>Home</code>, <code>Enter</code>, etc. This options is quite smart, that is if the shell command line is not empty, the arrows work as usual and allow moving the cursor in the command line.</li><li><code>File highlight</code> -&gt; <code>File types</code> is useful, as it uses a different color for example for executable files. <code>Permissions</code>, for me, is not that useful, but I can definitely see it’s use, for example, for sysadmins.</li></ul></li><li><strong>Appearance</strong><ul><li>Only one option here, <code>Skins</code>. You can check out different skins shipped with <code>mc</code> – just select one from the list. I prefer <code>gotar</code>, because it plays well with my <a href="http://ethanschoonover.com/solarized">solarized</a> terminal colors.</li><li>Useful tip – set up a different skin when logged in as the <code>root</code> user. It’ll be easier to differentiate between root’s and normal user’s session, when you’re swapping between them (as is often the case).</li></ul></li></ul>



<h2 id="bonus-assignments">Bonus assignments</h2>



<ul><li>Define your own listing mode (<code>Right/Left</code> -&gt; <code>Listing mode...</code> -&gt; <code>User defined</code>). Hit <code>F1</code> to see available columns and options.</li><li>Play around in tree mode: <code>Right/Left</code> -&gt; <code>Tree</code> or <code>Command</code> -&gt; <code>Directory tree</code>.</li><li>Compare directories (<code>Ctrl + x d</code>)</li><li>Fill up the directory hotlist (<code>Ctrl + \</code>)</li></ul>



<p>Well, that was a lot to take in. Of course, this list is not complete (that’s what <code>man mc</code> is there for), but I’ve selected the commands and functionalities that are the most useful to <em>me</em>. Embrace the ones you find useful, forget the rest and learn about the other ones I’ve missed!</p>



<p>Happy browsing!</p>
	</div><!-- .entry-content -->

	<!-- .entry-footer -->

	<div>
				<p><strong>Published</strong>
			<time datetime="2015-05-01T17:11:00+00:00">May 1, 2015</time><time datetime="2021-01-01T17:12:59+00:00">January 1, 2021</time>		</p><!-- .site-posted-on -->
	</div>
</article><!-- #post-## -->

			
	<nav aria-label="Posts">
		<h2>Post navigation</h2>
		
	</nav>
			
<!-- #comments -->

		
		</main><!-- #main -->
	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Vistex CEO Sanjay Shah dies on stage after freak accident (105 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.news.com.au/finance/work/leaders/tech-boss-sanjay-shah-plunges-to-his-death-after-freak-accident-on-stage/news-story/751f3f155fb58a9c349974bbcf0f9764</link>
            <guid>39075266</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 03:30:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.news.com.au/finance/work/leaders/tech-boss-sanjay-shah-plunges-to-his-death-after-freak-accident-on-stage/news-story/751f3f155fb58a9c349974bbcf0f9764">https://www.news.com.au/finance/work/leaders/tech-boss-sanjay-shah-plunges-to-his-death-after-freak-accident-on-stage/news-story/751f3f155fb58a9c349974bbcf0f9764</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39075266">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="story-primary" data-area="story-primary"><p>A tech boss has plunged to his death during his firm’s celebrations as horror footage captured his final moments alive.</p><p>Sanjay Shah, CEO of US-based company Vistex, was making a grand performance in an iron cage before part of the chain supporting the structure snapped.</p><p>The freak accident took place at Ramoji Film City in Hyderabad, India, during the company’s silver jubilee on Thursday evening, <i><a href="https://www.thesun.co.uk/news/25429964/horror-moment-death-sanjay-shah-vistex/" title="www.thesun.co.uk">The Sun</a></i> reports.</p><p>Sanjay, accompanied by his colleague Raju Datla, entered an iron cage on stage intended to be lowered from a height.</p><p>But one side of the iron chain supporting the cage broke, dropping both men over 4.5 metres to the concrete ground.</p><p>The collapsing cage, pulled by a rolling machine, had iron wires and grills.</p><p>“Suddenly, one of the two wires attached to the cage snapped. Both plunged more than 15 feet and landed on the concrete dais. This caused multiple injuries,” cops said.</p><p>Sanjay and Raju were rushed to the hospital, but the CEO succumbed to his injuries while undergoing treatment.</p><p>His colleague remains in a serious condition.</p><p>“Shah and Raju being lowered from the cage onto the dais was a planned event to kickstart the celebrations,” a company official told <i><a href="https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/videos/city/hyderabad/tragedy-strikes-vistex-silver-jubilee-ceo-sanjay-shah-dies-president-injured-as-iron-cage-collapses-at-celebrations/videoshow/107012522.cms" title="timesofindia.indiatimes.com">The Times of India</a></i>.</p><p>Police added that a case was registered against the Film City event management authorities based on a complaint made by another company official.</p><p>Vistex, an Illinois-based firm, had arranged accommodations for its staff at Ramoji Film City and had planned a two-day celebration for its silver jubilee.</p><p>The company specialises in revenue management solutions and services, with 20 global offices and more than 2,000 employees.</p><p>Vistex serves leading brands such as GM, Barilla, and Bayer.</p><p>Originally from Mumbai, Sanjay Shah was a tech entrepreneur who played a pivotal role in leading Vistex to become a prominent player in the industry.</p><div><h4>More Coverage</h4></div><p>Shah was also active in philanthropy through the establishment of the Vistex Foundation which provides grants to non-profits focusing on health, education, and basic needs.</p><p>Raju Datla has been with Vistex since 2000, and played a key role in shaping and expanding the firm’s Solution Delivery capabilities, the company’s website reads.</p><p><i>This story was published by <a href="https://www.thesun.co.uk/news/25429964/horror-moment-death-sanjay-shah-vistex/" title="www.thesun.co.uk">The Sun</a> and was reproduced with permission</i></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Common Lisp's block / return-from and unwind-protect (105 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://axisofeval.blogspot.com/2024/01/common-lisps-block-return-from-and.html</link>
            <guid>39074568</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 01:37:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://axisofeval.blogspot.com/2024/01/common-lisps-block-return-from-and.html">http://axisofeval.blogspot.com/2024/01/common-lisps-block-return-from-and.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39074568">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post-body-3640259933044464038" itemprop="description articleBody">
<p>I was just&nbsp;<a href="https://twitter.com/TitzerBL/status/1743775279485452497">chatting with Ben Titzer on Twitter</a>&nbsp;about control flow in his&nbsp;<a href="https://github.com/titzer/virgil">Virgil language</a>&nbsp;(which is cool and you should definitely check out), when I felt the need to&nbsp;<b>once more promote&nbsp;how Common Lisp does non-local control flow</b>&nbsp;(stuff like returning early from a function or breaking from a loop), because I think it's a very nice solution.</p><p>So in Common Lisp we have BLOCK&nbsp;/ RETURN-FROM&nbsp;(which work as a pair) and UNWIND-PROTECT.</p><h3>BLOCK / RETURN-FROM</h3><p><a href="http://clhs.lisp.se/Body/s_block.htm">BLOCK</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="http://clhs.lisp.se/Body/s_ret_fr.htm">RETURN-FROM</a>&nbsp;effectively offer the same functionality as C's&nbsp;<b>setjmp/longjmp</b>&nbsp;-- non-local exits -- but nicely wrapped as we expect it in a lexically-scoped, expression-oriented language.</p><p>BLOCK / RETURN-FROM lets you do:</p><ul><li><b>Early returns</b>&nbsp;from functions or arbitrary code blocks</li><li><b>Breaking</b>&nbsp;from loops, including any number of nested loops</li><li><b>Continuing</b>&nbsp;in loops, including any number of nested loops</li><li>Even&nbsp;<b>arbitrary GOTOs</b>&nbsp;in a code block (with some macrology &amp; trampolining, see&nbsp;<a href="https://www.plover.com/~mjd/misc/hbaker-archive/MetaCircular.html">Baker's TAGBODY</a>)</li></ul><p><b>(block name forms*)</b>&nbsp;lexically binds name within the forms as a non-local exit from which you can return a value with&nbsp;<b>(return-from name value)</b>. Just&nbsp;<b>(return-from name)</b>&nbsp;without a value uses nil as the value.</p><p>A BLOCK without any RETURN-FROM just returns the last value:&nbsp;</p><p><b>(block b 1 2 3)</b>&nbsp;returns 3.</p><p>This prints 1 and returns 2:</p><p><b>(block b (print 1) (return-from b 2) (print 3))</b></p><p>You can have any number of&nbsp;<b>nested blocks</b>:</p><p><b>(block b1 ... (block b2 ... (return-from b1) ...) ...)</b></p><p>To do an&nbsp;<b>early return</b>&nbsp;from a function, place a block at its beginning:</p><p><b>(defun foo ()</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp; (block b&nbsp;</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</b><b>&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</b><b>...</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</b><b>&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</b><b>(return-from b)</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</b><b>...))</b></p><p>(Common Lisp automatically places an anonymous block around every function body, so you don't need to do this in practice, but my hobby Lisp doesn't, and I'm using this explicit approach, and I like it.)</p><p>To&nbsp;<b>break from a loop</b>, place a block around it:</p><p><b>(block break</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp; (loop</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</b><b>&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</b><b>...</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; (return-from break)</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</b><b>...))</b></p><p>To&nbsp;<b>continue in a loop</b>, place a block inside it:</p><p><b>(loop</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp; (block continue</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; ...</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; (return-from continue)</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; ...))</b></p><p>You can have&nbsp;<b>multiple nested loops</b>, like in Java:</p><p><b>(block break-outer</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp; (loop</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; (block break-inner</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</b><b>&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</b><b>&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</b><b>(loop</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</b><b>&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</b><b>...</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; (return-from break-inner)</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; ...))))</b></p><h3>UNWIND-PROTECT</h3><p><a href="http://clhs.lisp.se/Body/s_unwind.htm">UNWIND-PROTECT</a>&nbsp;is effectively a try/finally block (without a catch).</p><p><b>(unwind-protect protected-form cleanup-forms*)</b>&nbsp;evaluates the protected form, and regardless of whether it returns normally or does a non-local exit with RETURN-FROM, the cleanup forms are evaluated.</p><p><b>(unwind-protect (foo)</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp;(bar)</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp;</b><b>(quux))</b></p><p>is analogous to</p><p><b>try {</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp;return foo();</b></p><p><b>} finally {</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp;bar();</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp;quux();</b></p><p><b>}</b></p><p>Both of the following expressions print 2 and return 1:</p><p><b>(unwind-protect 1</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp;(print 2))</b></p><p><b>(block exit</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp;</b><b>(unwind-protect (return-from exit 1)</b></p><p><b>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; (print 2)))</b></p><h3>Conclusion</h3><p>Common Lisp's BLOCK / RETURN-FROM and UNWIND-PROTECT offer a minimalistic and expressive system for non-local control flow.</p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>