<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 May 2024 00:00:04 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Pi-C.A.R.D, a Raspberry Pi Voice Assistant (148 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/nkasmanoff/pi-card</link>
            <guid>40346995</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 19:03:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/nkasmanoff/pi-card">https://github.com/nkasmanoff/pi-card</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40346995">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Pi-C.A.R.D</h2><a id="user-content-pi-card" aria-label="Permalink: Pi-C.A.R.D" href="#pi-card"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/nkasmanoff/pi-card/blob/main/assets/assistant.png"><img src="https://github.com/nkasmanoff/pi-card/raw/main/assets/assistant.png" height="300"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Table of Contents</h2><a id="user-content-table-of-contents" aria-label="Permalink: Table of Contents" href="#table-of-contents"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="#introduction">Introduction</a></li>
<li><a href="#usage">Usage</a></li>
<li><a href="#hardware">Hardware</a></li>
<li><a href="#setup">Setup</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Introduction</h2><a id="user-content-introduction" aria-label="Permalink: Introduction" href="#introduction"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Pi-card is an AI powered voice assistant running entirely on a Raspberry Pi. It is capable of doing anything a standard LLM (like ChatGPT) can do in a conversational setting.
In addition, if there is a camera equipped, you can also ask Pi-card to take a photo, describe what it sees, and then ask questions about that image.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Why Pi-card?</h3><a id="user-content-why-pi-card" aria-label="Permalink: Why Pi-card?" href="#why-pi-card"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Raspberry <strong>Pi</strong> - <strong>C</strong>amera <strong>A</strong>udio <strong>R</strong>ecognition <strong>D</strong>evice.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/nkasmanoff/pi-card/blob/main/assets/picard-facepalm.jpg"><img src="https://github.com/nkasmanoff/pi-card/raw/main/assets/picard-facepalm.jpg" height="300"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Please submit an issue or pull request if you can think of a better way to force this ackronym.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How does it work?</h3><a id="user-content-how-does-it-work" aria-label="Permalink: How does it work?" href="#how-does-it-work"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Pi-card runs entirely on your Raspberry Pi. Once the main program is run, the system will listen for your wake word. Once your wake word has been said, you are officially in a conversation. Within this conversation you do not need to constantly repeat the wake word. The system will continue to listen for your commands until you say something like "stop", "exit", or "goodbye".</p>
<p dir="auto">The system has a memory of the conversation while you have it, meaning if you want the assistant to repeat something it said, or elaborate on a previous topic, you can do so.</p>
<p dir="auto">While the system is designed to be entirely local, it is also possible to easily connect it to some external APIs or services if you want to enhance the conversation, or give it control to some external devices. To do so is something I am open to improving, but for now it will be done based on specific keywords to trigger the external service. A good example of this is that for camera purposes, the system will activate the camera if you say "take a photo" or "what do you see".</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How useful is it?</h3><a id="user-content-how-useful-is-it" aria-label="Permalink: How useful is it?" href="#how-useful-is-it"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The system is designed to be a fun project that can be a <em>somewhat</em> helpful AI assistant. Since everything is done locally, the system will not be as capable, or as fast, as cloud based systems. However, the system is still capable of a lot of improvements to be made.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Why isn't this an app?</h3><a id="user-content-why-isnt-this-an-app" aria-label="Permalink: Why isn't this an app?" href="#why-isnt-this-an-app"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The main reason for this is that I wanted to create a voice assistant that is completely offline and doesn't require any internet connection. This is because I wanted to ensure that the user's privacy is protected and that the user's data is not being sent to any third party servers.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h2><a id="user-content-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Usage" href="#usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">After downloading the repository, installing the requirements, and following the other setup instructions, you can run the main program by running the following command:</p>

<p dir="auto">Once the program is running, you can start a conversation with the assistant by saying the wake word. The default wake word is "hey assistant", but you can change this in the <code>config.py</code> file.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Hardware</h2><a id="user-content-hardware" aria-label="Permalink: Hardware" href="#hardware"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Raspberry Pi 5 Model B</li>
<li>USB Microphone</li>
<li>Speaker</li>
<li>Camera</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Setup</h2><a id="user-content-setup" aria-label="Permalink: Setup" href="#setup"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Software</h3><a id="user-content-software" aria-label="Permalink: Software" href="#software"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To keep this system as fast and lean as possible, we use cpp implementations of the audio transcription and vision language models. These are done with the wonderful libraries <a href="https://github.com/ggerganov/whisper.cpp">whipser.cpp</a> for the audio transcription and <a href="https://github.com/ggerganov/llama.cpp">llama.cpp</a> for the vision language model.</p>
<p dir="auto">In both cases, please clone these repositories wherever you like, and add their paths to the <code>config.py</code> file.</p>
<p dir="auto">Once cloned, please go to each repository, and follow the setup instructions to get the models running. Some pointers are given below:</p>
<p dir="auto">For llama.cpp, we are using the vision language model capabilities, which are slightly different from the standard setup. You will need to follow the setup instructions for <a href="https://github.com/ggerganov/llama.cpp/blob/master/examples/llava/README.md">LlaVA</a>, but update the model to be used to be one better suited for this device, <a href="https://github.com/nkasmanoff/pi-card/blob/main/moondream.ai">Moondream2</a></p>
<p dir="auto">To install Moondream, you'll need to go to HuggingFace model hub, and download the model. I did so using python, with the following commands. Once again, make sure the vision model path is added to the <code>config.py</code> file.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="from huggingface_hub import snapshot_download
model_id=&quot;vikhyatk/moondream2&quot;
snapshot_download(repo_id=model_id, local_dir=your/local/path, local_dir_use_symlinks=False, revision=&quot;main&quot;)"><pre><span>from</span> <span>huggingface_hub</span> <span>import</span> <span>snapshot_download</span>
<span>model_id</span><span>=</span><span>"vikhyatk/moondream2"</span>
<span>snapshot_download</span>(<span>repo_id</span><span>=</span><span>model_id</span>, <span>local_dir</span><span>=</span><span>your</span><span>/</span><span>local</span><span>/</span><span>path</span>, <span>local_dir_use_symlinks</span><span>=</span><span>False</span>, <span>revision</span><span>=</span><span>"main"</span>)</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">For whisper.cpp, you will need to follow the quick-start guide in the <a href="https://github.com/ggerganov/whisper.cpp?tab=readme-ov-file#quick-start">README</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Hardware</h3><a id="user-content-hardware-1" aria-label="Permalink: Hardware" href="#hardware-1"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The hardware setup is quite simple. You will need a Raspberry Pi 5 Model B, a USB microphone, a speaker, and a camera.</p>
<p dir="auto">The USB microphone and speaker can be plugged into the Raspberry Pi's USB ports. The camera can be connected to the camera port on the Raspberry Pi.</p>
<p dir="auto">I used the following hardware for my setup:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0CRSNCJ6Y?psc=1&amp;ref=ppx_yo2ov_dt_b_product_details" rel="nofollow">Raspberry Pi 5 Kit</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B087PTH787?psc=1&amp;ref=ppx_yo2ov_dt_b_product_details" rel="nofollow">USB Microphone</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B075M7FHM1?ref=ppx_yo2ov_dt_b_product_details&amp;th=1" rel="nofollow">Speaker</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B012V1HEP4?ref=ppx_yo2ov_dt_b_product_details&amp;th=1" rel="nofollow">Camera</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0716TB6X3?psc=1&amp;ref=ppx_yo2ov_dt_b_product_details" rel="nofollow">Camera Connector</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Please note Pi 5's have a new camera port, hence the new camera connector.</p>
<p dir="auto">Feel free to use your own, this is what worked for me.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[mRNA cancer vaccine triggers fierce immune response to fight brain tumors (187 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ufhealth.org/news/2024/uf-developed-mrna-vaccine-triggers-fierce-immune-response-to-fight-malignant-brain-tumor</link>
            <guid>40346675</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 18:36:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ufhealth.org/news/2024/uf-developed-mrna-vaccine-triggers-fierce-immune-response-to-fight-malignant-brain-tumor">https://ufhealth.org/news/2024/uf-developed-mrna-vaccine-triggers-fierce-immune-response-to-fight-malignant-brain-tumor</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40346675">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      



    


<main id="maincontent" data-gtm-scope="Content">
  
<div>
      <header data-gtm-scope="ContentHeader">
        



    <div>
            
            

                  <figure>

                  
  
        <picture>
    <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://ufhealth.org/assets/images/stories/_640x426_crop_center-center_line/Brain-Cancer-Vaccine_Feature.jpg.webp 640w, https://ufhealth.org/assets/images/stories/_860x573_crop_center-center_line/Brain-Cancer-Vaccine_Feature.jpg.webp 860w, https://ufhealth.org/assets/images/stories/_1500x1000_crop_center-center_line/Brain-Cancer-Vaccine_Feature.jpg.webp 1500w, https://ufhealth.org/assets/images/stories/_2432x1621_crop_center-center_line/Brain-Cancer-Vaccine_Feature.jpg.webp 2432w" sizes="100vw">
    <img alt="Researchers discussing the mRNA brain cancer vaccine" width="640" height="426" src="https://ufhealth.org/assets/images/stories/_640x426_crop_center-center_line/Brain-Cancer-Vaccine_Feature.jpg" srcset="https://ufhealth.org/assets/images/stories/_640x426_crop_center-center_line/Brain-Cancer-Vaccine_Feature.jpg 640w, https://ufhealth.org/assets/images/stories/_860x573_crop_center-center_line/Brain-Cancer-Vaccine_Feature.jpg 860w, https://ufhealth.org/assets/images/stories/_1500x1000_crop_center-center_line/Brain-Cancer-Vaccine_Feature.jpg 1500w, https://ufhealth.org/assets/images/stories/_2432x1621_crop_center-center_line/Brain-Cancer-Vaccine_Feature.jpg 2432w" sizes="100vw">
  </picture>
  

                        <figcaption>
          <p>Dr. Elias Sayour, Chong Zhao and Arnav Barpujari discuss the mRNA cancer vaccine developed at the University of Florida.</p>
        </figcaption>
        
                
      </figure>
          </div>
  </header>
</div>


        
    
  
  
  
<section>
                    




<div data-module="InlineVideo">
  <figure data-target="InlineVideo__Preview">
        <img data-lazy="" src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/mgEIofnZTe8/maxresdefault.jpg" data-src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/mgEIofnZTe8/maxresdefault.jpg" width="768" height="432" alt="In a first-ever human clinical trial of four adult patients, an mRNA cancer vaccine developed at UF quickly reprogrammed the immune system to attack glioblastoma, the most aggressive and lethal brain tumor.">

    
  </figure>

    <iframe data-target="InlineVideo__Video" width="768" height="432" data-src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mgEIofnZTe8?autoplay=1&amp;rel=0&amp;modestbranding=1&amp;enablejsapi=1" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="">
  </iframe>
</div>


    
          
<div data-gtm-component="GenericContent">
  <p>In a first-ever human clinical trial of four adult patients, an mRNA cancer vaccine developed at the <a href="https://www.ufl.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">University of Florida</a> quickly reprogrammed the immune system to attack glioblastoma, the most aggressive and lethal brain tumor.<br></p>
<p>The results mirror those in 10 pet dog patients suffering from naturally occurring brain tumors whose owners approved of their participation, as they had no other treatment options, as well as results from preclinical mouse models. The breakthrough now will be tested in a Phase 1 pediatric clinical trial for brain cancer.</p>
<p> <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0092867424003982?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Reported May 1 in the journal Cell</a>, the discovery represents a potential new way to recruit the immune system to fight notoriously treatment-resistant cancers using an iteration of mRNA technology and lipid nanoparticles, similar to COVID-19 vaccines, but with two key differences: use of a patient’s own tumor cells to create a personalized vaccine, and a newly engineered complex delivery mechanism within the vaccine.</p>
<p>“Instead of us injecting single particles, we’re injecting clusters of particles that are wrapping around each other like onions, like a bag full of onions,” said senior author <a href="https://ufhealth.org/doctors/elias-sayour" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Elias Sayour</a>, M.D., Ph.D., a UF Health pediatric oncologist who pioneered the new vaccine, which like other immunotherapies attempts to “educate” the immune system that a tumor is foreign. “And the reason we’ve done that in the context of cancer is these clusters alert the immune system in a much more profound way than single particles would.”<br></p>
</div>


    
          
 
      


  





  

  

    
          
<div data-gtm-component="GenericContent">
  <p>Among the most impressive findings was how quickly the new method, delivered intravenously, spurred a vigorous immune-system response to reject the tumor, said Sayour, principal investigator of the RNA Engineering Laboratory within UF’s <a href="https://braintumors.ufhealth.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Preston A. Wells Jr. Center for Brain Tumor Therapy</a> and a <a href="https://cancer.ufl.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">UF Health Cancer Center</a> and <a href="https://mbi.ufl.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">McKnight Brain Institute</a> investigator who led the multi-institution research team.</p>
<p>“In less than 48 hours, we could see these tumors shifting from what we refer to as ‘cold’ — immune cold, very few immune cells, very silenced immune response — to ‘hot,’ very active immune response,” he said. “That was very surprising given how quick this happened, and what that told us is we were able to activate the early part of the immune system very rapidly against these cancers, and that’s critical to unlock the later effects of the immune response.”</p>
<p>Glioblastoma is among the most devastating diagnoses, with median survival around 15 months. Current standard of care involves surgery, radiation and some combination of chemotherapy.</p>
<p>The new publication is the culmination of promising translational results over seven years of studies, starting in preclinical mouse models and then in a clinical trial of 10 pet dogs that had spontaneously developed terminal brain cancer and had no other treatment options. That trial was conducted with owners’ consent in collaboration with the <a href="https://www.vetmed.ufl.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">UF College of Veterinary Medicine</a>. Dogs offer a naturally occurring model for malignant glioma because they are the only other species that develops spontaneous brain tumors with some frequency, said <a href="https://www.vetmed.ufl.edu/profile/carrera-justiz-sheila/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sheila Carrera-Justiz</a>, D.V.M., a veterinary neurologist at the UF College of Veterinary Medicine who is partnering with Sayour on the clinical trials. Gliomas in dogs are universally terminal, she said.</p>
<p>After treating pet dogs that had spontaneously developed brain cancer with personalized mRNA vaccines, Sayour’s team advanced the research to a small Food and Drug Administration-approved clinical trial designed to ensure safety and test feasibility before expanding to a larger trial.</p>
<p>In a cohort of four patients, genetic material called RNA was extracted from each patient’s own surgically removed tumor, and then messenger RNA, or mRNA — the blueprint of what is inside every cell, including tumor cells — was amplified and wrapped in the newly designed high-tech packaging of biocompatible lipid nanoparticles, to make tumor cells “look” like a dangerous virus when reinjected into the bloodstream and prompt an immune-system response. The vaccine was personalized to each patient with a goal of getting the most out of their unique immune system.</p>
<p>“The demonstration that making an mRNA cancer vaccine in this fashion generates similar and strong responses across mice, pet dogs that have developed cancer spontaneously and human patients with brain cancer is a really important finding, because oftentimes we don’t know how well the preclinical studies in animals are going to translate into similar responses in patients,” said <a href="https://neurosurgery.ufl.edu/faculty-staff/research-faculty/mitchell/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Duane Mitchell</a>, M.D., Ph.D., director of the UF Clinical and Translational Science Institute and the <a href="https://neurosurgery.ufl.edu/research/laboratories/ufbtip-lab/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">UF Brain Tumor Immunotherapy Program</a> and a co-author of the paper. “And while mRNA vaccines and therapeutics are certainly a hot topic since the COVID pandemic, this is a novel and unique way of delivering the mRNA to generate these really significant and rapid immune responses that we’re seeing across animals and humans.”<br></p>
</div>


    
          
 
      


  





  

  

    
          
<div data-gtm-component="GenericContent">
  <p>While too early in the trial to assess the clinical effects of the vaccine, the patients either lived disease-free longer than expected or survived longer than expected.</p>
<p>The 10 pet dogs lived a median of 139 days, compared with a median survival of 30 to 60 days typical for dogs with the condition.</p>
<p>The next step, through support from the Food and Drug Administration and the <a href="https://curesearch.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CureSearch for Children’s Cancer foundation</a>, will be an expanded Phase I clinical trial to include up to 24 adult and pediatric patients to validate the findings. Once an optimal and safe dose is confirmed, an estimated 25 children would participate in Phase 2, said Sayour, an associate professor in the <a href="https://neurosurgery.ufl.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lillian S. Wells Department of Neurosurgery</a> and the department of pediatrics in the <a href="https://med.ufl.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">UF College of Medicine</a>, part of UF Health.</p>
<p>For the new clinical trial, Sayour’s lab will partner with a multi-institution consortium, the <a href="https://pnoc.us/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pediatric Neuro-Oncology Consortium</a>, to send the immunotherapy treatment to children’s hospitals across the country. They will do this by receiving an individual patient’s tumor, manufacturing the personalized vaccine at UF and sending it back to the patient’s medical team, said Sayour, co-leader of the Immuno-Oncology and Microbiome research program at the UF Health Cancer Center.</p>
<p>Despite the promising results, the authors said one limitation is continued uncertainty about how best to harness the immune system while minimizing the potential for adverse side effects.</p>
<p>“I am hopeful that this could be a new paradigm for how we treat patients, a new platform technology for how we can modulate the immune system,” said Sayour, the Stop Children's Cancer/Bonnie R. Freeman Professor for Pediatric Oncology Research. “I am hopeful for how this could now synergize with other immunotherapies and perhaps unlock those immunotherapies. We showed in this paper that you actually can have synergy with other types of immunotherapies, so maybe now we can have a combination approach of immunotherapy.”</p>
<p>Sayour and Mitchell hold patents related to the vaccine which are under option to license by iOncologi Inc., a biotech company born as a “spin out” from UF in which Mitchell holds interest.</p>
</div>


    
  

      </section>

        
  
    
    
    



    
<div>

      <section>
    <h2>
      About the author
    </h2>

    
  </section>
  
      <section id="for-the-media">
    <h2>For the media</h2>
    <div>
        <h3>
          Media contact
        </h3>

                          


        
                      </div>
  </section>
</div>

</main>

  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Amazon S3 will no longer charge for several HTTP error codes (242 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://aws.amazon.com/about-aws/whats-new/2024/05/amazon-s3-no-charge-http-error-codes/</link>
            <guid>40346597</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/about-aws/whats-new/2024/05/amazon-s3-no-charge-http-error-codes/">https://aws.amazon.com/about-aws/whats-new/2024/05/amazon-s3-no-charge-http-error-codes/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40346597">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="aws-page-content"> 
     <main id="aws-page-content-main" role="main" tabindex="-1"> 
      <section data-page-alert-target="true"> 
        
       <p> Posted On: <span> May 13, 2024</span> </p> 
       <div> 
        <p>Amazon S3 will make a change so unauthorized requests that customers did not initiate are free of charge. With this change, bucket owners will never incur request or bandwidth charges for requests that return an HTTP 403 (Access Denied) error response if initiated from outside their individual AWS account or AWS Organization. To see the full list of error codes that are free of&nbsp;charge, visit <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/userguide/ErrorCodeBilling.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Billing for Amazon S3 error responses</a>. This billing change requires no changes to customer applications and applies to all S3 buckets.</p> 
       </div> 
       <div> 
        <p>These billing changes will apply in all AWS Regions, including the AWS GovCloud Regions and the AWS China Regions. This deployment is starting today and we will post another update in a few weeks when it is completed. To learn more,&nbsp;visit <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/userguide/ErrorCodeBilling.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Billing for Amazon S3 error responses</a> and <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/API/ErrorResponses.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Error Responses</a> in the S3 User Guide.</p> 
       </div> 
        
      </section> 
     </main> 
    </div><div data-lb-comp="modal" data-lb-modal-id="ie-deprecation-msg" data-ie10-deprecation-msg="You are using an outdated browser. Please upgrade to a modern browser to improve your experience."> 
      
     <p>
       AWS support for Internet Explorer ends on 07/31/2022. Supported browsers are Chrome, Firefox, Edge, and Safari. 
      <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/aws/heads-up-aws-support-for-internet-explorer-11-is-ending/" rel="noopener">Learn more »</a> 
     </p> 
      
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Apple and Google deliver support for unwanted tracking alerts in iOS and Android (191 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.apple.com/ca/newsroom/2024/05/apple-and-google-deliver-support-for-unwanted-tracking-alerts-in-ios-and-android/</link>
            <guid>40346024</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 17:46:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.apple.com/ca/newsroom/2024/05/apple-and-google-deliver-support-for-unwanted-tracking-alerts-in-ios-and-android/">https://www.apple.com/ca/newsroom/2024/05/apple-and-google-deliver-support-for-unwanted-tracking-alerts-in-ios-and-android/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40346024">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">


	
    







 
<nav id="ac-localnav" lang="en-CA" role="navigation" aria-label="Newsroom" data-analytics-region="local nav" data-sticky="">
	
    
        




    
    
    

</nav>



<main id="main" role="main"> 



<span id="opens-in-new-window">opens in new window</span>
<section>
<article data-analytics-activitymap-region-id="article">









    
    
    









    





    <div>
                
                
                
                    <h2>
                        
    
        Apple and Google deliver support for unwanted tracking alerts in iOS and Android
    

                    </h2>
                
            </div>







    
    
    


    
        
        
        
        
            <figure aria-label="Media, Logos representing Apple and Google.">
                <div>
                        
                         
                            
                        
                        
                        
                        <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/images/2024/05/apple-and-google-deliver-support-for-unwanted-tracking-alerts-in-ios-and-android/article/Apple-Google-partner-tracking-detection-hero.zip" download="" data-analytics-title="download image - Apple-Google-partner-tracking-detection-hero_inline" aria-label="Download media, Logos representing Apple and Google."></a>
                    </div>
            </figure>
        
    










    
    
    


     
     
    
    
        <div>
             
                 <div>
Apple and Google have worked together to create an industry specification — <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-detecting-unwanted-location-trackers/01/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" data-analytics-exit-link="">Detecting Unwanted Location Trackers</a> — for Bluetooth tracking devices that makes it possible to alert users across both iOS and Android if such a device is unknowingly being used to track them. This will help mitigate the misuse of devices designed to help keep track of belongings. Today Apple is implementing this capability in iOS 17.5, and Google is now launching this capability on Android 6.0+ devices.</div>
                 
             
                 <div>
With this new capability, users will now get an “[Item] Found Moving With You” alert on their device if an unknown Bluetooth tracking device is seen moving with them over time, regardless of the platform the device is paired with.</div>
                 
             
                 <div>If a user gets such an alert on their iOS device, it means that someone else’s AirTag, Find My accessory, or other industry specification-compatible Bluetooth tracker is moving with them. It’s possible the tracker is attached to an item the user is borrowing, but if not, iPhone can view the tracker’s identifier, have the tracker play a sound to help locate it, and access instructions to disable it.&nbsp;Bluetooth tag manufacturers including Chipolo, eufy, Jio, Motorola, and Pebblebee have committed that future tags will be compatible.
</div>
                 
             
                 <div>
AirTag and third-party Find My network accessories were designed from the beginning with industry-first privacy and safety protections, and Apple has remained committed to innovating and supplementing these protections to keep consumers safe. This cross-platform collaboration — also an industry first, involving community and industry input — offers instructions and best practices for manufacturers, should they choose to build unwanted tracking alert capabilities into their products. Apple and Google will continue to work with the <a href="https://www.ietf.org/about/introduction/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" data-analytics-exit-link="">Internet Engineering Task Force</a> via the Detecting Unwanted Location Trackers working group to develop the official standard for this technology.</div>
                 
             
         </div>
 

    
    
    




    
    
        
    


    
    
    



    
    
    






    
















	
	
		















	
	
	

</article>



</section>
</main>


	

</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[GPT-4o (1561 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://openai.com/index/hello-gpt-4o/</link>
            <guid>40345775</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 17:28:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://openai.com/index/hello-gpt-4o/">https://openai.com/index/hello-gpt-4o/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40345775">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://openai.com/index/hello-gpt-4o/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: An open source framework for voice assistants (186 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/pipecat-ai/pipecat</link>
            <guid>40345696</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 17:21:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/pipecat-ai/pipecat">https://github.com/pipecat-ai/pipecat</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40345696">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/pipecat-ai/pipecat/blob/main/pipecat.png"><img alt="pipecat" width="300px" height="auto" src="https://github.com/pipecat-ai/pipecat/raw/main/pipecat.png"></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Pipecat</h2><a id="user-content-pipecat" aria-label="Permalink: Pipecat" href="#pipecat"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://pypi.org/project/pipecat-ai" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/e44c7b97b713ead1309d49f5930eaf97f7045880e0f508d21570d49f607485df/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f707970692f762f706970656361742d6169" alt="PyPI" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/pypi/v/pipecat-ai"></a> <a href="https://discord.gg/pipecat" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/884b6fbc9b12772324a7011eaee4cc25bc81d85225e7cf866f74b007051511e6/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f646973636f72642f31323339323834363737313635303536303231" alt="Discord" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/discord/1239284677165056021"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><code>pipecat</code> is a framework for building voice (and multimodal) conversational agents. Things like personal coaches, meeting assistants, <a href="https://storytelling-chatbot.fly.dev/" rel="nofollow">story-telling toys for kids</a>, customer support bots, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lDevgsp9vn0" rel="nofollow">intake flows</a>, and snarky social companions.</p>
<p dir="auto">Take a look at some example apps:</p>
<p dir="auto">
    <a href="https://github.com/pipecat-ai/pipecat/tree/main/examples/simple-chatbot"><img src="https://github.com/pipecat-ai/pipecat/raw/main/examples/simple-chatbot/image.png" width="280"></a>&nbsp;
    <a href="https://github.com/pipecat-ai/pipecat/tree/main/examples/storytelling-chatbot"><img src="https://github.com/pipecat-ai/pipecat/raw/main/examples/storytelling-chatbot/image.png" width="280"></a>
    <br>
    <a href="https://github.com/pipecat-ai/pipecat/tree/main/examples/translation-chatbot"><img src="https://github.com/pipecat-ai/pipecat/raw/main/examples/translation-chatbot/image.png" width="280"></a>&nbsp;
    <a href="https://github.com/pipecat-ai/pipecat/tree/main/examples/moondream-chatbot"><img src="https://github.com/pipecat-ai/pipecat/raw/main/examples/moondream-chatbot/image.png" width="280"></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Getting started with voice agents</h2><a id="user-content-getting-started-with-voice-agents" aria-label="Permalink: Getting started with voice agents" href="#getting-started-with-voice-agents"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">You can get started with Pipecat running on your local machine, then move your agent processes to the cloud when you’re ready. You can also add a 📞 telephone number, 🖼️ image output, 📺 video input, use different LLMs, and more.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# install the module
pip install pipecat-ai

# set up an .env file with API keys
cp dot-env.template .env"><pre><span><span>#</span> install the module</span>
pip install pipecat-ai

<span><span>#</span> set up an .env file with API keys</span>
cp dot-env.template .env</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">By default, in order to minimize dependencies, only the basic framework functionality is available. Some third-party AI services require additional dependencies that you can install with:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="pip install &quot;pipecat-ai[option,...]&quot;"><pre>pip install <span><span>"</span>pipecat-ai[option,...]<span>"</span></span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Your project may or may not need these, so they're made available as optional requirements. Here is a list:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>AI services</strong>: <code>anthropic</code>, <code>azure</code>, <code>fal</code>, <code>moondream</code>, <code>openai</code>, <code>playht</code>, <code>silero</code>, <code>whisper</code></li>
<li><strong>Transports</strong>: <code>local</code>, <code>websocket</code>, <code>daily</code></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Code examples</h2><a id="user-content-code-examples" aria-label="Permalink: Code examples" href="#code-examples"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/pipecat-ai/pipecat/tree/main/examples/foundational">foundational</a> — small snippets that build on each other, introducing one or two concepts at a time</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/pipecat-ai/pipecat/tree/main/examples/">example apps</a> — complete applications that you can use as starting points for development</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">A simple voice agent running locally</h2><a id="user-content-a-simple-voice-agent-running-locally" aria-label="Permalink: A simple voice agent running locally" href="#a-simple-voice-agent-running-locally"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Here is a very basic Pipecat bot that greets a user when they join a real-time session. We'll use <a href="https://daily.co/" rel="nofollow">Daily</a> for real-time media transport, and <a href="https://elevenlabs.io/" rel="nofollow">ElevenLabs</a> for text-to-speech.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="#app.py

import asyncio
import aiohttp

from pipecat.frames.frames import EndFrame, TextFrame
from pipecat.pipeline.pipeline import Pipeline
from pipecat.pipeline.task import PipelineTask
from pipecat.pipeline.runner import PipelineRunner
from pipecat.services.elevenlabs import ElevenLabsTTSService
from pipecat.transports.services.daily import DailyParams, DailyTransport

async def main():
  async with aiohttp.ClientSession() as session:
    # Use Daily as a real-time media transport (WebRTC)
    transport = DailyTransport(
      room_url=...,
      token=...,
      &quot;Bot Name&quot;,
      DailyParams(audio_out_enabled=True))

    # Use Eleven Labs for Text-to-Speech
    tts = ElevenLabsTTSService(
      aiohttp_session=session,
      api_key=...,
      voice_id=...,
      )

    # Simple pipeline that will process text to speech and output the result
    pipeline = Pipeline([tts, transport.output()])

    # Create Pipecat processor that can run one or more pipelines tasks
    runner = PipelineRunner()

    # Assign the task callable to run the pipeline
    task = PipelineTask(pipeline)

    # Register an event handler to play audio when a
    # participant joins the transport WebRTC session
    @transport.event_handler(&quot;on_participant_joined&quot;)
    async def on_new_participant_joined(transport, participant):
      participant_name = participant[&quot;info&quot;][&quot;userName&quot;] or ''
      # Queue a TextFrame that will get spoken by the TTS service (Eleven Labs)
      await task.queue_frames([TextFrame(f&quot;Hello there, {participant_name}!&quot;), EndFrame()])

    # Run the pipeline task
    await runner.run(task)

if __name__ == &quot;__main__&quot;:
  asyncio.run(main())"><pre><span>#app.py</span>

<span>import</span> <span>asyncio</span>
<span>import</span> <span>aiohttp</span>

<span>from</span> <span>pipecat</span>.<span>frames</span>.<span>frames</span> <span>import</span> <span>EndFrame</span>, <span>TextFrame</span>
<span>from</span> <span>pipecat</span>.<span>pipeline</span>.<span>pipeline</span> <span>import</span> <span>Pipeline</span>
<span>from</span> <span>pipecat</span>.<span>pipeline</span>.<span>task</span> <span>import</span> <span>PipelineTask</span>
<span>from</span> <span>pipecat</span>.<span>pipeline</span>.<span>runner</span> <span>import</span> <span>PipelineRunner</span>
<span>from</span> <span>pipecat</span>.<span>services</span>.<span>elevenlabs</span> <span>import</span> <span>ElevenLabsTTSService</span>
<span>from</span> <span>pipecat</span>.<span>transports</span>.<span>services</span>.<span>daily</span> <span>import</span> <span>DailyParams</span>, <span>DailyTransport</span>

<span>async</span> <span>def</span> <span>main</span>():
  <span>async</span> <span>with</span> <span>aiohttp</span>.<span>ClientSession</span>() <span>as</span> <span>session</span>:
    <span># Use Daily as a real-time media transport (WebRTC)</span>
    <span>transport</span> <span>=</span> <span>DailyTransport</span>(
      <span>room_url</span><span>=</span>...,
      <span>token</span><span>=</span>...,
      <span>"Bot Name"</span>,
      <span>DailyParams</span>(<span>audio_out_enabled</span><span>=</span><span>True</span>))

    <span># Use Eleven Labs for Text-to-Speech</span>
    <span>tts</span> <span>=</span> <span>ElevenLabsTTSService</span>(
      <span>aiohttp_session</span><span>=</span><span>session</span>,
      <span>api_key</span><span>=</span>...,
      <span>voice_id</span><span>=</span>...,
      )

    <span># Simple pipeline that will process text to speech and output the result</span>
    <span>pipeline</span> <span>=</span> <span>Pipeline</span>([<span>tts</span>, <span>transport</span>.<span>output</span>()])

    <span># Create Pipecat processor that can run one or more pipelines tasks</span>
    <span>runner</span> <span>=</span> <span>PipelineRunner</span>()

    <span># Assign the task callable to run the pipeline</span>
    <span>task</span> <span>=</span> <span>PipelineTask</span>(<span>pipeline</span>)

    <span># Register an event handler to play audio when a</span>
    <span># participant joins the transport WebRTC session</span>
    <span>@<span>transport</span>.<span>event_handler</span>(<span>"on_participant_joined"</span>)</span>
    <span>async</span> <span>def</span> <span>on_new_participant_joined</span>(<span>transport</span>, <span>participant</span>):
      <span>participant_name</span> <span>=</span> <span>participant</span>[<span>"info"</span>][<span>"userName"</span>] <span>or</span> <span>''</span>
      <span># Queue a TextFrame that will get spoken by the TTS service (Eleven Labs)</span>
      <span>await</span> <span>task</span>.<span>queue_frames</span>([<span>TextFrame</span>(<span>f"Hello there, <span><span>{</span><span>participant_name</span><span>}</span></span>!"</span>), <span>EndFrame</span>()])

    <span># Run the pipeline task</span>
    <span>await</span> <span>runner</span>.<span>run</span>(<span>task</span>)

<span>if</span> <span>__name__</span> <span>==</span> <span>"__main__"</span>:
  <span>asyncio</span>.<span>run</span>(<span>main</span>())</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Run it with:</p>

<p dir="auto">Daily provides a prebuilt WebRTC user interface. Whilst the app is running, you can visit at <code>https://&lt;yourdomain&gt;.daily.co/&lt;room_url&gt;</code> and listen to the bot say hello!</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">WebRTC for production use</h2><a id="user-content-webrtc-for-production-use" aria-label="Permalink: WebRTC for production use" href="#webrtc-for-production-use"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">WebSockets are fine for server-to-server communication or for initial development. But for production use, you’ll need client-server audio to use a protocol designed for real-time media transport. (For an explanation of the difference between WebSockets and WebRTC, see <a href="https://www.daily.co/blog/how-to-talk-to-an-llm-with-your-voice/#webrtc" rel="nofollow">this post.</a>)</p>
<p dir="auto">One way to get up and running quickly with WebRTC is to sign up for a Daily developer account. Daily gives you SDKs and global infrastructure for audio (and video) routing. Every account gets 10,000 audio/video/transcription minutes free each month.</p>
<p dir="auto">Sign up <a href="https://dashboard.daily.co/u/signup" rel="nofollow">here</a> and <a href="https://docs.daily.co/reference/rest-api/rooms" rel="nofollow">create a room</a> in the developer Dashboard.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What is VAD?</h2><a id="user-content-what-is-vad" aria-label="Permalink: What is VAD?" href="#what-is-vad"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Voice Activity Detection — very important for knowing when a user has finished speaking to your bot. If you are not using press-to-talk, and want Pipecat to detect when the user has finished talking, VAD is an essential component for a natural feeling conversation.</p>
<p dir="auto">Pipecast makes use of WebRTC VAD by default when using a WebRTC transport layer. Optionally, you can use Silero VAD for improved accuracy at the cost of higher CPU usage.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="pip install pipecat-ai[silero]"><pre>pip install pipecat-ai[silero]</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">The first time your run your bot with Silero, startup may take a while whilst it downloads and caches the model in the background. You can check the progress of this in the console.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Hacking on the framework itself</h2><a id="user-content-hacking-on-the-framework-itself" aria-label="Permalink: Hacking on the framework itself" href="#hacking-on-the-framework-itself"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><em>Note that you may need to set up a virtual environment before following the instructions below. For instance, you might need to run the following from the root of the repo:</em></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="python3 -m venv venv
source venv/bin/activate"><pre>python3 -m venv venv
<span>source</span> venv/bin/activate</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">From the root of this repo, run the following:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="pip install -r dev-requirements.txt -r {env}-requirements.txt
python -m build"><pre>pip install -r dev-requirements.txt -r {env}-requirements.txt
python -m build</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">This builds the package. To use the package locally (eg to run sample files), run</p>

<p dir="auto">If you want to use this package from another directory, you can run:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="pip install path_to_this_repo"><pre>pip install path_to_this_repo</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Running tests</h3><a id="user-content-running-tests" aria-label="Permalink: Running tests" href="#running-tests"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">From the root directory, run:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="pytest --doctest-modules --ignore-glob=&quot;*to_be_updated*&quot; src tests"><pre>pytest --doctest-modules --ignore-glob=<span><span>"</span>*to_be_updated*<span>"</span></span> src tests</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Setting up your editor</h2><a id="user-content-setting-up-your-editor" aria-label="Permalink: Setting up your editor" href="#setting-up-your-editor"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This project uses strict <a href="https://peps.python.org/pep-0008/" rel="nofollow">PEP 8</a> formatting.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Emacs</h3><a id="user-content-emacs" aria-label="Permalink: Emacs" href="#emacs"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">You can use <a href="https://github.com/jwiegley/use-package">use-package</a> to install <a href="https://codeberg.org/ideasman42/emacs-py-autopep8" rel="nofollow">py-autopep8</a> package and configure <code>autopep8</code> arguments:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="(use-package py-autopep8
  :ensure t
  :defer t
  :hook ((python-mode . py-autopep8-mode))
  :config
  (setq py-autopep8-options '(&quot;-a&quot; &quot;-a&quot;, &quot;--max-line-length=100&quot;)))"><pre>(<span>use-package</span> py-autopep8
  <span>:ensure</span> <span>t</span>
  <span>:defer</span> <span>t</span>
  <span>:hook</span> ((<span>python-mode</span> <span>.</span> py-autopep8-mode))
  <span>:config</span>
  (<span>setq</span> py-autopep8-options '(<span><span>"</span>-a<span>"</span></span> <span><span>"</span>-a<span>"</span></span>, <span><span>"</span>--max-line-length=100<span>"</span></span>)))</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><code>autopep8</code> was installed in the <code>venv</code> environment described before, so you should be able to use <a href="https://github.com/ryotaro612/pyvenv-auto">pyvenv-auto</a> to automatically load that environment inside Emacs.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="(use-package pyvenv-auto
  :ensure t
  :defer t
  :hook ((python-mode . pyvenv-auto-run)))
"><pre>(<span>use-package</span> pyvenv-auto
  <span>:ensure</span> <span>t</span>
  <span>:defer</span> <span>t</span>
  <span>:hook</span> ((<span>python-mode</span> <span>.</span> pyvenv-auto-run)))
</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Visual Studio Code</h3><a id="user-content-visual-studio-code" aria-label="Permalink: Visual Studio Code" href="#visual-studio-code"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Install the
<a href="https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=ms-python.autopep8" rel="nofollow">autopep8</a> extension. Then edit the user settings (<em>Ctrl-Shift-P</em> <code>Open User Settings (JSON)</code>) and set it as the default Python formatter, enable formatting on save and configure <code>autopep8</code> arguments:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="&quot;[python]&quot;: {
    &quot;editor.defaultFormatter&quot;: &quot;ms-python.autopep8&quot;,
    &quot;editor.formatOnSave&quot;: true
},
&quot;autopep8.args&quot;: [
    &quot;-a&quot;,
    &quot;-a&quot;,
    &quot;--max-line-length=100&quot;
],"><pre><span>"[python]"</span>: {
    <span>"editor.defaultFormatter"</span>: <span><span>"</span>ms-python.autopep8<span>"</span></span>,
    <span>"editor.formatOnSave"</span>: <span>true</span>
},
<span>"autopep8.args"</span>: [
    <span><span>"</span>-a<span>"</span></span>,
    <span><span>"</span>-a<span>"</span></span>,
    <span><span>"</span>--max-line-length=100<span>"</span></span>
],</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Getting help</h2><a id="user-content-getting-help" aria-label="Permalink: Getting help" href="#getting-help"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">➡️ <a href="https://discord.gg/pipecat" rel="nofollow">Join our Discord</a></p>
<p dir="auto">➡️ <a href="https://x.com/pipecat_ai" rel="nofollow">Reach us on Twitter</a></p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Discord has been using ML to determine the gender and age of some of its users (109 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/DiscordPreviews/status/1790065494432608432</link>
            <guid>40345627</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 17:14:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/DiscordPreviews/status/1790065494432608432">https://twitter.com/DiscordPreviews/status/1790065494432608432</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40345627">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://twitter.com/DiscordPreviews/status/1790065494432608432: Error: Request failed with status code 400]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Good, Kind, Caring People Became the Bad Guys (119 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.okdoomer.io/thebadguys/</link>
            <guid>40345552</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 17:09:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.okdoomer.io/thebadguys/">https://www.okdoomer.io/thebadguys/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40345552">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
              <p>There's a story about Zig Ziglar, the motivational speaker and author. Apparently, a woman approached Ziglar at one of his seminars, begging him for help. She said she hated her job. Her boss was horrible. Her coworkers were so mean to her.</p><p>What should she do?</p><p>Well, Zig told her to shut up and stop complaining. He said <em>she </em>sounded like the negative one. He told her to chant aphorisms into a mirror. Low and behold, she was cured.</p><p>I've got bad news for everyone. Zig didn't help this woman. In fact, all he did was reinforce a cognitive bias that psychologists have been studying for decades now.</p><p>This bias explains a lot about the state of the world today.</p><p>But first, a personal story:</p><p>I don't know if you've ever been trapped in a small space with a severe, violent schizophrenic relative.</p><p>It's not fun.</p><p>When I was a teen, my mom started having delusions and hallucinations. She thought the CIA was spying on my dad. She thought a Category 4 Hurricane was going to hit the house. She thought I was a space alien. She thought dinosaurs were real. She tried to make bombs out of old electronics and threw them in our rooms in the middle of the night. And, she tried to seduce my brother.</p><p>All of that happened in the span of ten years.</p><p>I got pretty good at spotting the early red flags. My mom said and did little things that didn't make sense. She started dropping incredibly pessimistic observations or insults into the middle of small talk. She hid things in weird places. She stayed up even later than usual, not watching television, just smoking and drinking black coffee, staring off into the midnight void. The tone of her voice changed.</p><p>So did her body language.</p><p>I tried to warn my dad and brother. Every single time, they ignored me until it was too late. My dad usually got angry at me. He thought I was trying to wreck the family vacation or whatever. More than once, he piled us into the car and drove us to a beach, where my mom's health completely unraveled and I got stuck following her around and trying to keep her from drowning herself.</p><p>So I got used to quietly watching things devolve, until one night she'd get so violent my dad had to call the police.</p><p>The police wouldn't come.</p><p>(At first.)</p><p>They frequently told us they couldn't do anything until <em>after </em>she hurt someone. It didn't matter if she implied she was going to do us harm. It didn't matter if she made us feel unsafe. It didn't matter if a court had ordered her to take medication.</p><p>In the end, she wound wind up hurting one of us. Then the police would arrest her. Then the doctors would evaluate her and determine that, yes, she belonged in a mental health facility, but only for as long as our health insurance provider allowed.</p><p>Social workers started visiting my house. They came to my school. I was called out of class to answer their questions. They asked me if I felt safe in my home. They asked if I was okay.</p><p>I lied.</p><p>I lied because I'd been taught a valuable lesson, one that I didn't truly understand for years. When you complain, people judge you. It doesn't matter what you're complaining about. It doesn't matter what you're protesting or whistle-blowing. It doesn't matter if your life is at stake. It doesn't matter if thousands of lives are at stake. It doesn't matter if the fate of humanity is at stake. Someone's first instinct is to suspect you. It's to accuse you of lying. It's to label you a troublemaker.</p><p>They hear negative words coming out of your mouth. They associate those negative things with you, because you're the person saying them. That's how our primate brains operate. It takes a lot of self-awareness to overcome that, and many people lack it.</p><p>A lot has changed since then.</p><p>Now I'm an adult, watching this kind of thing play out on a global scale every single day with the collapse of public health, the collapse of our democracies, the collapse of global industrial civilization, and the collapse of our ecosystems.</p><p>Now it occurs to me.</p><p>I've already lived through collapse. I've watched the collapse of my mom's mental and physical health. I've watched the collapse of my family. And I've watched the collapse of at least one university.</p><p>You could call me a connoisseur of collapse.</p><p>Over the last few years, I've studied the psychology of denial and cognitive dissonance. There are so many bugs and glitches in the human psyche to explain what's happening and why it takes so much patience, and so much effort, to ever get anyone to take threats seriously or to change their behavior, for any reason.</p><p>Here's one of the most fascinating ones:</p><p>Spontaneous trait transference.</p><p>In the 1990s, psychologists John Skowronski and Donal Carlston began noticing something strange when someone tried to raise concerns about someone else. Instead of believing them, people tended to <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/9569648/?ref=okdoomer.io" rel="noreferrer">transfer those negative traits</a> to the person trying to warn them. They confirmed the behavior in four different studies. They defined spontaneous trait transference as when "communicators are perceived as possessing the very traits they describe in others."</p><p>He who smelt it dealt it.</p><p>Am I right?</p><p>As Skowronsky explains, "politicians who allege corruption by their opponents may themselves be perceived as dishonest" and "critics who praise artists may themselves be perceived as talented." If you describe someone as negative, unreliable, or dangerous, people tend to misremember it as a self-description. Yes, they really think you were talking about yourself.</p><p>This tendency reinforces our worst behaviors, ensuring we never criticize those who deserve it while the ones who deserve praise never actually get it. All those fake compliments flying around? These people have probably never heard of spontaneous trait transference, but they've observed it. They've learned that if you pass out worthless attagirls all day long, people mistakenly assume you're a great person.</p><p>And it works.</p><p>Because humans are kind of gullible...</p><p>Rick Brown and John Bassili even found that people can transfer personality traits <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022103101914866?ref=okdoomer.io" rel="noreferrer">to inanimate objects</a> like bananas. They do it without even thinking. Yes, you can condition someone to believe that bananas are evil.</p><p>It gets worse.</p><p>You know the phrase, don't shoot the messenger?</p><p>That actually happens.</p><p>In 2019, a team of psychologists at Harvard led by Leslie John reviewed hundreds of studies and conducted <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2019-19962-004?ref=okdoomer.io" rel="noreferrer">eleven different experiments</a> to explain why people punish someone for giving them bad news. They learned that the human brain often reaches for the quickest, easiest explanations for negative events in their lives, especially ones that preserve their self-image and group harmony. As Leslie John and her colleagues write, "people are especially prone to attributing agency to others for negative outcomes." They also "attribute agency to those proximal to the event."</p><p>There's nothing more proximal to an event than the first person to tell you what's going on. Once again, our shared psychology discourages us from warning each other about threats.</p><p>And so:</p><p>"Bad news messengers may be prime candidates in recipients' search for antagonists to cast in accounts of unwanted outcomes." Bad news also motivates people to come up with "fallacious" causal explanations "often generated effortlessly, seemingly automatically." They generate these fallacious explanations through poor reasoning "characterized by shallow, unconscious thought."</p><p>That's how we wind up with so many conspiracy theories. They're easier to swallow than the truth.</p><p>They gratify us. </p><p>To sum things up, people tend to attribute the bad news and negative events in their lives to those around them, often their friends and family. They don't do a good job of distinguishing between a threat and someone trying to warn them.</p><p>They get them mixed up.</p><p>That's hardly a useful evolutionary trait, is it?</p><p>And yet, this trait explains so much of what's going on now. It explains why the public gets angry at climate protestors instead of the oil executives who've ruined their future. It explains how university students have somehow wound up as the villains in so many people's eyes, instead of the governments sponsoring and committing genocide. It explains why you can't criticize billionaires or super rich influencers without that incredibly annoying counter claim:</p><p>"You're just jealous."</p><p>It explains why you get pathologized and called everything from a doomer to a snowflake for caring about anything but yourself. It explains why pretending to care looks better.</p><p>It explains why my family didn't listen to me about my mom's mental health. It explains why Zig Ziglar was such an asshole to a woman who begged him for help.</p><p>I've tried to come up with little strategies and workarounds for all of humanity's psychological shortcomings.</p><p>It comes down to this:</p><p>You have to find a way to be the smart, positive, compassionate, mature, respectful, charming one. You have to do that even if everyone around you is acting like a complete idiot.</p><p>You have to achieve a fine balance between sugar coating and blunt honesty. Above all, you have to anticipate that all of your hard work won't achieve the results you want in the short term. It takes a long time. A lot of people won't listen at first.</p><p>You often have to trick people into doing the right thing.</p><p>It's exhausting.</p><p>It takes a lot out of you to be respectful to idiots all day long, especially when many of them go out of their way to do you harm. Despite the audacious tone of my writing (my dry humor is often mistaken for bitterness or anger), I try to remain calm and compassionate when dealing with people right in front of me.</p><p>And of course, a lot of people will call you rude or disrespectful, simply because you don't smile when you talk.</p><p>It's a lot to deal with.</p><p>It's all hard, because every single minute matters now. We don't have decades to change public thought. The plagues are getting worse and more frequent. The climate collapse is accelerating. The weather is getting more extreme. People are dying from heatstroke in the thousands now. They're getting swept away in crash floods. They're getting blown out of their apartments by typhoon-strength winds in the middle of the night. Every disease we ever dealt with is now converging on our weakened immune systems.</p><p>Our politicians spent the last year whining about TikTok while letting yet another zoonotic disease run rampant. The last threads of democracy are unraveling right in front of us.</p><p>It's hard to sound optimistic.</p><p>What's my point?</p><p>I guess, this:</p><p>When I was dealing with my mom's mental health, the worst part wasn't the fear or the violence. It was the solitude. It was lying to social workers. It was pretending everything was fine around my friends. It was waiting for my family to finally see what I saw.</p><p>Those days when my mom was in the mental health facility, those were the best. She was getting the help she needed. My family stopped being angry at me. It was when she came home, when she stopped taking her medicine, and things went back to "normal."</p><p>Those were the worst days.</p><p>It was lonely.</p><p>I hated those long stretches of "normal," when we were all waiting for the next schizophrenic break but wouldn't do anything about it. When I moved out, I was relieved. My mom suffered from schizophrenia for almost 20 more years before she died. At least I didn't have to live in that state of paralysis anymore.</p><p>I could have a life.</p><p>Know this:</p><p>You are seen. You are not working in vain. Millions of people out there are listening to your warnings, even if it often doesn't feel that way. Maybe it's not enough to stop the worst of everything.</p><p>But you're not alone.</p><p>It's something, at least.</p><hr><p><em>Thank you to all the readers who </em><a href="https://www.okdoomer.io/support/" rel="noreferrer"><em>support</em></a><em> this site.</em></p><p><em>It makes a difference.</em></p>
            </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OpenAI launches new AI model and desktop version of ChatGPT (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cnbc.com/2024/05/13/openai-launches-new-ai-model-and-desktop-version-of-chatgpt.html</link>
            <guid>40345526</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 17:08:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/05/13/openai-launches-new-ai-model-and-desktop-version-of-chatgpt.html">https://www.cnbc.com/2024/05/13/openai-launches-new-ai-model-and-desktop-version-of-chatgpt.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40345526">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="SpecialReportArticle-ArticleBody-6" data-module="ArticleBody" data-test="articleBody-2" data-analytics="SpecialReportArticle-articleBody-6-2"><div id="Placeholder-ArticleBody-Video-107414178" data-test="VideoPlaceHolder" role="region" tabindex="0" data-vilynx-id="7000340046" aria-labelledby="Placeholder-ArticleBody-Video-107414178"><p><img src="https://image.cnbcfm.com/api/v1/image/107414179-17156232921715623289-34511329350-1080pnbcnews.jpg?v=1715623291&amp;w=750&amp;h=422&amp;vtcrop=y" alt="OpenAI unveils new AI model and desktop version of ChatGPT"><span></span><span></span></p></div><div><p><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/05/09/openai-disruptor-50.html">OpenAI</a> on Monday launched a new AI model and desktop version of ChatGPT, along with an updated user interface, the company's latest effort to expand use of its popular chatbot.</p><p>The update brings GPT-4 to everyone, including OpenAI's free users, technology chief Mira Murati said in a livestreamed event. She added that the new model, GPT-4o, is "much faster," with improved capabilities in text, video and audio. OpenAI said it eventually plans to allow users to video chat with ChatGPT.</p><p>"This is the first time that we are really making a huge step forward when it comes to the ease of use," Murati said.</p><p>OpenAI, backed by <span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="SpecialReportArticle-QuoteInBody-2"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/MSFT/">Microsoft</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span>, has been valued by more than $80 billion by investors. The company, founded in 2015, is under pressure to stay on top of the generative AI market while finding ways to make money as it spends massive sums on processors and infrastructure to build and train its models.</p></div><div id="ArticleBody-InlineImage-107346332" data-test="InlineImage"><p>Sam Altman, CEO of OpenAI, at the Hope Global Forums annual meeting in Atlanta on Dec. 11, 2023.</p><p>Dustin Chambers | Bloomberg | Getty Images</p></div><div><p>The o in GPT-4o stands for omni. The new model allows ChatGPT to handle 50 different languages with improved speed and quality, and it will also be available via OpenAI's API making it possible for developers to begin building applications using the new model today, Murati said.</p><p>She added that GPT-4o is twice as fast as, and half the cost of, GPT-4 Turbo.</p><p>OpenAI team members demonstrated the new model's audio capabilities, for example, asking it to help calm someone down ahead of a public speech. OpenAI researcher Mark Chen said the model is able to "perceive your emotion," adding the model can also handle users interrupting it. The team also asked it to analyze a user's facial expression to comment on the emotions the person may be experiencing.</p><p>"Hey there, what's up? How can I brighten your day today?" ChatGPT's audio mode said when a user greeted it.</p><p>The company plans to test Voice Mode in the coming weeks, with early access for paid subscribers to ChatGPT Plus, according to a <a href="https://openai.com/index/hello-gpt-4o/" target="_blank">blog post</a>. OpenAI also said the new model can respond to users' audio prompts "in as little as 232 milliseconds, with an average of 320 milliseconds, which is similar to&nbsp;human response time&nbsp;in a conversation."</p><p>Chen demonstrated the model's ability to tell a bedtime story and asked it to change the tone of its voice to be more dramatic or robotic. He even asked it to sing the story.</p><p>In addition, OpenAI's new model can function as a translator, even in audio mode, the company said. Chen demonstrated the tool's ability to listen to Murati speaking Italian while he spoke English and to translate into their respective languages as they conversed.</p><p>Team members also demonstrated the model's ability to solve math equations and help write code, positioning it as a stronger competitor to Microsoft's own GitHub Copilot.</p><p>For OpenAI, the launch was one of the company's biggest announcements since the August kickoff of ChatGPT Enterprise, the AI chatbot's business tier. That tool was in development for "under a year" and had the help of more than 20 companies of varying sizes and industries, OpenAI Chief Operating Officer Brad Lightcap told CNBC at the time.</p><p>OpenAI, Microsoft and <span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="SpecialReportArticle-QuoteInBody-4"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/GOOGL/">Google</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span> are at the helm of a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cnbc.com/ai-artificial-intelligence/">generative AI</a>&nbsp;gold rush as companies in seemingly every industry race to add AI-powered chatbots and agents to key services to avoid <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/03/30/fomo-drives-tech-heavyweights-to-invest-billions-in-generative-ai-.html">being left behind</a> by competitors. Earlier this month, OpenAI rival Anthropic announced its <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/05/01/anthropic-iphone-ai-app-business-plan-to-compete-with-openai-announced.html">first-ever enterprise offering</a> and a free iPhone app.</p><p>A record $29.1 billion was invested across nearly 700 generative AI deals in 2023, an increase of more than 260% from the prior year, according to PitchBook. The market is&nbsp;predicted to<a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/professional/insights/data/generative-ai-races-toward-1-3-trillion-in-revenue-by-2032/#:~:text=Generative%20AI%20is%20poised%20to,our%20proprietary%20market%2Dsizing%20model." target="_blank">&nbsp;top $1 trillion</a>&nbsp;in revenue within a decade.</p><p>Some in the industry have raised concerns about the speed at which untested new services are coming to market, and academics and ethicists are&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/03/29/elon-musk-other-tech-leaders-pause-training-ai-beyond-gpt-4.html">distressed</a>&nbsp;about the technology's tendency to propagate bias.</p><p>After ChatGPT's launch in November 2022, it broke records at the time as the fastest-growing consumer app in history, and now has about 100 million weekly active users. OpenAI says that&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/11/06/openai-announces-more-powerful-gpt-4-turbo-and-cuts-prices.html">more than 92%</a>&nbsp;of Fortune 500 companies are using the platform.</p><p>Murati said during the Monday event that OpenAI wants to "remove some of the mysticism from the technology."</p><p>"Over the next few weeks, we'll be rolling out these capabilities to everyone," she said.</p><p>The new model will first roll out on Tuesday to customers of ChatGPT Plus and Team, and then to Enterprise later, a <a href="https://openai.com/index/gpt-4o-and-more-tools-to-chatgpt-free/" target="_blank">blog post</a> on Monday said. It will also be available to free users of ChatGPT starting Monday, with usage limits. Users of ChatGPT Plus will have five times more message capacity than free users, and clients of ChatGPT Team and Enterprise will have even greater usage limits.</p><p>Murati concluded the livestreamed event by thanking Nvidia CEO Jensen Huang and his company for providing the necessary graphics processing units (GPUs) to power OpenAI's technology.</p><p>"I just want to thank the incredible OpenAI team, and also thanks to Jensen and the Nvidia team for bringing us the most advanced GPUs to make this demo possible today," she said.</p></div><div id="SpecialReportArticle-RelatedContent-1"><h2>Don’t miss these exclusives from CNBC PRO</h2><div><ul><li><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/05/04/most-of-warren-buffetts-stock-portfolio-is-tied-up-in-just-5-stocks-heres-what-they-are.html"><em>Most of Warren Buffett's stock portfolio is tied up in just 5 stocks. Here's what they are</em></a>&nbsp;</li><li><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/05/02/bank-of-america-says-you-should-buy-this-shoe-stock-before-earnings.html"><em>Bank of America says this shoe stock is an inflation winner and you should buy it before earnings</em></a><em>&nbsp;</em></li><li><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/04/17/-these-are-morgan-stanleys-top-picks-into-quarterly-earnings.html"><em>These are Morgan Stanley's top picks into quarterly earnings</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/05/02/tesla-to-face-a-huge-demand-problem-over-price-cuts-says-investor.html"><em>Tesla price cuts could backfire, fund manager says, warning of a 'huge demand problem' on the horizon</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/05/01/doublelines-gundlach-sees-one-rate-cut-this-year-as-fed-keeps-up-inflation-fight.html"><em>Gundlach sees one rate cut this year as Fed keeps up inflation fight</em></a></li></ul></div></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Falcon 2 (216 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.tii.ae/news/falcon-2-uaes-technology-innovation-institute-releases-new-ai-model-series-outperforming-metas</link>
            <guid>40344302</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 15:17:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.tii.ae/news/falcon-2-uaes-technology-innovation-institute-releases-new-ai-model-series-outperforming-metas">https://www.tii.ae/news/falcon-2-uaes-technology-innovation-institute-releases-new-ai-model-series-outperforming-metas</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40344302">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="block-mainpagecontent"> <main>  <div> <article><div><ul><li><strong>Next-Gen Falcon 2 Series launches AI Model that is Open-Source, Multilingual, and Multimodal – and is only AI Model with Vision-to-Language Capabilities</strong></li><li><strong>New Falcon 2 11B Outperforms Meta’s Llama 3 8B, and Performs on par with leading Google Gemma 7B Model, as Independently Verified by Hugging Face Leaderboard</strong></li><li><strong>Immediate Plans Include Exploring 'Mixture of Experts' for Enhanced Machine Learning Capabilities</strong></li></ul></div><p><strong>Abu Dhabi-UAE: 13 May, 2024</strong> - <a href="https://www.tii.ae/news/tii.ae">The Technology Innovation Institute</a> (TII), a leading global scientific research center and the applied research pillar of Abu Dhabi’s <a href="https://www.atrc.gov.ae/">Advanced Technology Research Council</a> (ATRC), today launched a second iteration of its renowned large language model (LLM) – Falcon 2. Within this series, it has unveiled two groundbreaking versions: Falcon 2 11B, a more efficient and accessible LLM trained on 5.5 trillion tokens with 11 billion parameters, and Falcon 2 11B VLM, distinguished by its vision-to-language model (VLM) capabilities, which enable seamless conversion of visual inputs into textual outputs. While both models are multilingual, notably, Falcon 2 11B VLM stands out as TII's first multimodal model – and the only one currently in the top tier market that has this image-to-text conversion capability, marking a significant advancement in AI innovation.</p><p>Tested against several prominent AI models in its class among pre-trained models, Falcon 2 11B surpasses the performance of Meta’s newly launched Llama 3 with 8 billion parameters(8B), and performs on par with Google’s Gemma 7B at first place (Falcon 2 11B: 64.28 vs Gemma 7B: 64.29), as independently verified by Hugging Face, a US-based platform hosting an objective evaluation tool and global leaderboard for open LLMs. More importantly, Falcon 2 11B and 11B VLM are both open-source, empowering developers worldwide with unrestricted access. In the near future, there are plans to broaden the Falcon 2 next-generation models, introducing a range of sizes. These models will be further enhanced with advanced machine learning capabilities like 'Mixture of Experts' (MoE), aimed at pushing their performance to even more sophisticated levels.</p><p>All of TII’s AI models released to date have consistently ranked in the top tier globally, as the most powerful open-source LLMs. The new scaled-down and versatile Falcon 2 11B models are set to give TII greater market adoption in the ever-evolving world of generative AI.</p><p>Falcon 2 11B models, equipped with multilingual capabilities, seamlessly tackle tasks in English, French, Spanish, German, Portuguese, and various other languages, enriching their versatility and magnifying their effectiveness across diverse scenarios. Falcon 2 11B VLM, a 2 vision-to-language model, has the capability to identify and interpret images and visuals from the environment, providing a wide range of applications across industries such as healthcare, finance, e-commerce, education, and legal sectors. These applications range from document management, digital archiving, and context indexing to supporting individuals with visual impairments. Furthermore, these models can run efficiently on just one graphics processing unit (GPU), making them highly scalable, and easy to deploy and integrate into lighter infrastructures like laptops and other devices.</p><p><strong>H.E. Faisal Al Bannai</strong>, Secretary General of ATRC and Strategic Research and Advanced Technology Affairs Advisor to the UAE President, said: "With the release of Falcon 2 11B, we've introduced the first model in the Falcon 2 series. While Falcon 2 11B has demonstrated outstanding performance, we reaffirm our commitment to the open-source movement with it, and to the Falcon Foundation. With other multimodal models soon coming to the market in various sizes, our aim is to ensure that developers and entities that value their privacy, have access to one of the best AI models to enable their AI journey."</p><p>Speaking on the model, <strong>Dr. Hakim Hacid</strong>, Executive Director and Acting Chief Researcher of the AI Cross-Center Unit at TII, said: “AI is continually evolving, and developers are recognizing the myriad benefits of smaller, more efficient models. In addition to reducing computing power requirements and meeting sustainability criteria, these models offer enhanced flexibility, seamlessly integrating into edge AI infrastructure, the next emerging megatrend. Furthermore, the vision-to-language capabilities of Falcon 2 open new horizons for accessibility in AI, empowering users with transformative image to text interactions.”</p><p>The versatility of Falcon 2 11B has also led TII to consider working on more exciting GenAI innovations. Among these, will be the adoption of a new type of machine learning capability known as the aforementioned ‘Mixture of Experts’. This method involves amalgamating smaller networks with distinct specializations, ensuring that the most knowledgeable domains collaborate to deliver highly sophisticated and customized responses – almost like having a team of smart helpers who each know something different and work together to predict or make decisions when needed. This approach not only improves accuracy, but it also accelerates decision-making, paving the way for more intelligent and efficient AI systems</p><p>Falcon 2 11B is licenced under TII Falcon License 2.0, the permissive Apache 2.0-based software license which includes an acceptable use policy that promotes the responsible use of AI. More information on the new model can be found at <a href="https://falconllm.tii.ae/">FalconLLM.TII.ae</a></p> </article></div> </main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Pg_lakehouse: Query Any Data Lake from Postgres (107 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/paradedb/paradedb/tree/dev/pg_lakehouse</link>
            <guid>40343131</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 13:29:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/paradedb/paradedb/tree/dev/pg_lakehouse">https://github.com/paradedb/paradedb/tree/dev/pg_lakehouse</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40343131">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><div dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/paradedb/paradedb/blob/dev/docs/logo/pg_lakehouse.svg"><img src="https://github.com/paradedb/paradedb/raw/dev/docs/logo/pg_lakehouse.svg" alt="pg_lakehouse" width="500px"></a>
<br>
</h2><a id="user-content---" aria-label="Permalink: " href="#--"></a></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Overview</h2><a id="user-content-overview" aria-label="Permalink: Overview" href="#overview"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><code>pg_lakehouse</code> is an extension that transforms Postgres into an analytical query engine over object stores like S3 and table formats like Delta Lake. Queries are pushed down to <a href="https://github.com/apache/datafusion">Apache DataFusion</a>, which delivers excellent analytical performance. Combinations of the following object stores, table formats, and file formats are supported.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Object Stores</h3><a id="user-content-object-stores" aria-label="Permalink: Object Stores" href="#object-stores"></a></p>
<ul>
<li> Amazon S3</li>
<li> S3-compatible object stores (e.g. MinIO)</li>
<li> Local file system</li>
<li> Google Cloud Storage (coming soon)</li>
<li> Azure Blob Storage (coming soon)</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">...and potentially any service supported by <a href="https://opendal.apache.org/docs/category/services" rel="nofollow">Apache OpenDAL</a>. See the Development section for instructions on how to <a href="#adding-a-service">add a service</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">File Formats</h3><a id="user-content-file-formats" aria-label="Permalink: File Formats" href="#file-formats"></a></p>
<ul>
<li> Parquet</li>
<li> CSV</li>
<li> JSON</li>
<li> Avro</li>
<li> ORC (coming soon)</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Table Formats</h3><a id="user-content-table-formats" aria-label="Permalink: Table Formats" href="#table-formats"></a></p>
<ul>
<li> Delta Lake</li>
<li> Apache Iceberg (coming soon)</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><code>pg_lakehouse</code> is supported on Postgres 14, 15, and 16. Support for Postgres 12 and 13 is coming soon.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Motivation</h2><a id="user-content-motivation" aria-label="Permalink: Motivation" href="#motivation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Today, a vast amount of non-operational data — events, metrics, historical snapshots, vendor data, etc. — is ingested into data lakes like S3. Querying this data by moving it into a cloud data warehouse or operating a new query engine is expensive and time consuming. The goal of <code>pg_lakehouse</code> is to enable this data to be queried directly from Postgres. This eliminates the need for new infrastructure, loss of data freshness, data movement, and non-Postgres dialects of other query engines.</p>
<p dir="auto"><code>pg_lakehouse</code> uses the foreign data wrapper (FDW) API to connect to any object store or table format and the executor hook API to push queries to DataFusion. While other FDWs like <code>aws_s3</code> have existed in the Postgres extension ecosystem, these FDWs suffer from two limitations:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Lack of support for most object stores, file, and table formats</li>
<li>Too slow over large datasets to be a viable analytical engine</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto"><code>pg_lakehouse</code> differentiates itself by supporting a wide breadth of stores and formats (thanks to <a href="https://github.com/apache/opendal">OpenDAL</a>) and by being very fast (thanks to <a href="https://github.com/apache/datafusion">DataFusion</a>).</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Getting Started</h2><a id="user-content-getting-started" aria-label="Permalink: Getting Started" href="#getting-started"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The following example uses <code>pg_lakehouse</code> to query an example dataset of 3 million NYC taxi trips from January 2024, hosted in a public S3 bucket provided by ParadeDB.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="CREATE EXTENSION pg_lakehouse;
CREATE FOREIGN DATA WRAPPER s3_wrapper HANDLER s3_fdw_handler VALIDATOR s3_fdw_validator;

-- Provide S3 credentials
CREATE SERVER s3_server FOREIGN DATA WRAPPER s3_wrapper
OPTIONS (bucket 'paradedb-benchmarks', region 'us-east-1', allow_anonymous 'true');

-- Create foreign table
CREATE FOREIGN TABLE trips (
    &quot;VendorID&quot;              INT,
    &quot;tpep_pickup_datetime&quot;  TIMESTAMP,
    &quot;tpep_dropoff_datetime&quot; TIMESTAMP,
    &quot;passenger_count&quot;       BIGINT,
    &quot;trip_distance&quot;         DOUBLE PRECISION,
    &quot;RatecodeID&quot;            DOUBLE PRECISION,
    &quot;store_and_fwd_flag&quot;    TEXT,
    &quot;PULocationID&quot;          REAL,
    &quot;DOLocationID&quot;          REAL,
    &quot;payment_type&quot;          DOUBLE PRECISION,
    &quot;fare_amount&quot;           DOUBLE PRECISION,
    &quot;extra&quot;                 DOUBLE PRECISION,
    &quot;mta_tax&quot;               DOUBLE PRECISION,
    &quot;tip_amount&quot;            DOUBLE PRECISION,
    &quot;tolls_amount&quot;          DOUBLE PRECISION,
    &quot;improvement_surcharge&quot; DOUBLE PRECISION,
    &quot;total_amount&quot;          DOUBLE PRECISION
)
SERVER s3_server
OPTIONS (path 's3://paradedb-benchmarks/yellow_tripdata_2024-01.parquet', extension 'parquet');

-- Success! Now you can query the remote Parquet file like a regular Postgres table
SELECT COUNT(*) FROM trips;
  count
---------
 2964624
(1 row)"><pre>CREATE EXTENSION pg_lakehouse;
CREATE FOREIGN DATA WRAPPER s3_wrapper HANDLER s3_fdw_handler VALIDATOR s3_fdw_validator;

<span><span>--</span> Provide S3 credentials</span>
CREATE SERVER s3_server FOREIGN DATA WRAPPER s3_wrapper
OPTIONS (bucket <span><span>'</span>paradedb-benchmarks<span>'</span></span>, region <span><span>'</span>us-east-1<span>'</span></span>, allow_anonymous <span><span>'</span>true<span>'</span></span>);

<span><span>--</span> Create foreign table</span>
CREATE FOREIGN TABLE trips (
    <span><span>"</span>VendorID<span>"</span></span>              <span>INT</span>,
    <span><span>"</span>tpep_pickup_datetime<span>"</span></span>  <span>TIMESTAMP</span>,
    <span><span>"</span>tpep_dropoff_datetime<span>"</span></span> <span>TIMESTAMP</span>,
    <span><span>"</span>passenger_count<span>"</span></span>       <span>BIGINT</span>,
    <span><span>"</span>trip_distance<span>"</span></span>         <span>DOUBLE PRECISION</span>,
    <span><span>"</span>RatecodeID<span>"</span></span>            <span>DOUBLE PRECISION</span>,
    <span><span>"</span>store_and_fwd_flag<span>"</span></span>    <span>TEXT</span>,
    <span><span>"</span>PULocationID<span>"</span></span>          <span>REAL</span>,
    <span><span>"</span>DOLocationID<span>"</span></span>          <span>REAL</span>,
    <span><span>"</span>payment_type<span>"</span></span>          <span>DOUBLE PRECISION</span>,
    <span><span>"</span>fare_amount<span>"</span></span>           <span>DOUBLE PRECISION</span>,
    <span><span>"</span>extra<span>"</span></span>                 <span>DOUBLE PRECISION</span>,
    <span><span>"</span>mta_tax<span>"</span></span>               <span>DOUBLE PRECISION</span>,
    <span><span>"</span>tip_amount<span>"</span></span>            <span>DOUBLE PRECISION</span>,
    <span><span>"</span>tolls_amount<span>"</span></span>          <span>DOUBLE PRECISION</span>,
    <span><span>"</span>improvement_surcharge<span>"</span></span> <span>DOUBLE PRECISION</span>,
    <span><span>"</span>total_amount<span>"</span></span>          <span>DOUBLE PRECISION</span>
)
SERVER s3_server
OPTIONS (<span>path</span> <span><span>'</span>s3://paradedb-benchmarks/yellow_tripdata_2024-01.parquet<span>'</span></span>, extension <span><span>'</span>parquet<span>'</span></span>);

<span><span>--</span> Success! Now you can query the remote Parquet file like a regular Postgres table</span>
<span>SELECT</span> <span>COUNT</span>(<span>*</span>) <span>FROM</span> trips;
  count
<span><span>--</span>-------</span>
 <span>2964624</span>
(<span>1</span> row)</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Note that column names must be wrapped in double quotes to preserve uppercase letters. This is because DataFusion is case-sensitive and Postgres' foreign table column names must match the foreign table's column names exactly.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Query Acceleration</h2><a id="user-content-query-acceleration" aria-label="Permalink: Query Acceleration" href="#query-acceleration"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This extension uses Postgres hooks to intercept and push queries down to DataFusion. In order to enable these hooks, the extension must be added to <code>shared_preload_libraries</code> inside <code>postgresql.conf</code>.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# Inside postgresql.conf
shared_preload_libraries = 'pg_lakehouse'"><pre><span><span>#</span> Inside postgresql.conf</span>
shared_preload_libraries = <span><span>'</span>pg_lakehouse<span>'</span></span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Inspecting the Foreign Schema</h2><a id="user-content-inspecting-the-foreign-schema" aria-label="Permalink: Inspecting the Foreign Schema" href="#inspecting-the-foreign-schema"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The <code>arrow_schema</code> function displays the schema of a foreign table. This function is useful for verifying that the server and table credentials you've provided are valid. If the connection is successful and <code>pg_lakehouse</code> is able to read the foreign data, a table will be returned with the <a href="https://docs.rs/datafusion/latest/datafusion/common/arrow/datatypes/enum.DataType.html" rel="nofollow">Arrow schema</a> of the foreign table. Otherwise, an empty table will be returned or an error will be thrown.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="SELECT * FROM arrow_schema(
  server => 's3_server',
  path => 's3://paradedb-benchmarks/yellow_tripdata_2024-01.parquet',
  extension => 'parquet'
);"><pre><span>SELECT</span> <span>*</span> <span>FROM</span> arrow_schema(
  server <span>=&gt;</span> <span><span>'</span>s3_server<span>'</span></span>,
  <span>path</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span><span>'</span>s3://paradedb-benchmarks/yellow_tripdata_2024-01.parquet<span>'</span></span>,
  extension <span>=&gt;</span> <span><span>'</span>parquet<span>'</span></span>
);</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">You can also use this function to decide what Postgres types to assign to each column of the foreign table. For instance, an Arrow <code>Utf8</code> datatype should map to a Postgres <code>TEXT</code>, <code>VARCHAR</code>, or <code>BPCHAR</code> column. If an incompatible Postgres type is chosen, querying the table will fail.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Connect an Object Store</h2><a id="user-content-connect-an-object-store" aria-label="Permalink: Connect an Object Store" href="#connect-an-object-store"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To connect your own object store, please refer to the <a href="https://docs.paradedb.com/analytics/object_stores" rel="nofollow">documentation</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Types</h2><a id="user-content-types" aria-label="Permalink: Types" href="#types"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Some types like <code>date</code>, <code>timestamp</code>, and <code>timestamptz</code> must be handled carefully. Please refer to the <a href="https://docs.paradedb.com/analytics/schema#datetime-types" rel="nofollow">documentation</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Development</h2><a id="user-content-development" aria-label="Permalink: Development" href="#development"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Install Rust</h3><a id="user-content-install-rust" aria-label="Permalink: Install Rust" href="#install-rust"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To develop the extension, first install Rust via <code>rustup</code>.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="curl --proto '=https' --tlsv1.2 -sSf https://sh.rustup.rs | sh
rustup install <version>

rustup default <version>"><pre>curl --proto <span><span>'</span>=https<span>'</span></span> --tlsv1.2 -sSf https://sh.rustup.rs <span>|</span> sh
rustup install <span>&lt;</span>version<span>&gt;</span>

rustup default <span>&lt;</span>version<span>&gt;</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Note: While it is possible to install Rust via your package manager, we recommend using <code>rustup</code> as we've observed inconcistencies with Homebrew's Rust installation on macOS.</p>
<p dir="auto">Then, install the PostgreSQL version of your choice using your system package manager. Here we provide the commands for the default PostgreSQL version used by this project:</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Install Postgres</h3><a id="user-content-install-postgres" aria-label="Permalink: Install Postgres" href="#install-postgres"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# macOS
brew install postgresql@16

# Ubuntu
wget --quiet -O - https://www.postgresql.org/media/keys/ACCC4CF8.asc | sudo apt-key add -
sudo sh -c 'echo &quot;deb http://apt.postgresql.org/pub/repos/apt/ $(lsb_release -cs)-pgdg main&quot; > /etc/apt/sources.list.d/pgdg.list'
sudo apt-get update &amp;&amp; sudo apt-get install -y postgresql-16 postgresql-server-dev-16"><pre><span><span>#</span> macOS</span>
brew install postgresql@16

<span><span>#</span> Ubuntu</span>
wget --quiet -O - https://www.postgresql.org/media/keys/ACCC4CF8.asc <span>|</span> sudo apt-key add -
sudo sh -c <span><span>'</span>echo "deb http://apt.postgresql.org/pub/repos/apt/ $(lsb_release -cs)-pgdg main" &gt; /etc/apt/sources.list.d/pgdg.list<span>'</span></span>
sudo apt-get update <span>&amp;&amp;</span> sudo apt-get install -y postgresql-16 postgresql-server-dev-16</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">If you are using Postgres.app to manage your macOS PostgreSQL, you'll need to add the <code>pg_config</code> binary to your path before continuing:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="export PATH=&quot;$PATH:/Applications/Postgres.app/Contents/Versions/latest/bin&quot;"><pre><span>export</span> PATH=<span><span>"</span><span>$PATH</span>:/Applications/Postgres.app/Contents/Versions/latest/bin<span>"</span></span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Install pgrx</h3><a id="user-content-install-pgrx" aria-label="Permalink: Install pgrx" href="#install-pgrx"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Then, install and initialize <code>pgrx</code>:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# Note: Replace --pg16 with your version of Postgres, if different (i.e. --pg15, --pg14, etc.)
cargo install --locked cargo-pgrx --version 0.11.3

# macOS arm64
cargo pgrx init --pg16=/opt/homebrew/opt/postgresql@16/bin/pg_config

# macOS amd64
cargo pgrx init --pg16=/usr/local/opt/postgresql@16/bin/pg_config

# Ubuntu
cargo pgrx init --pg16=/usr/lib/postgresql/16/bin/pg_config"><pre><span><span>#</span> Note: Replace --pg16 with your version of Postgres, if different (i.e. --pg15, --pg14, etc.)</span>
cargo install --locked cargo-pgrx --version 0.11.3

<span><span>#</span> macOS arm64</span>
cargo pgrx init --pg16=/opt/homebrew/opt/postgresql@16/bin/pg_config

<span><span>#</span> macOS amd64</span>
cargo pgrx init --pg16=/usr/local/opt/postgresql@16/bin/pg_config

<span><span>#</span> Ubuntu</span>
cargo pgrx init --pg16=/usr/lib/postgresql/16/bin/pg_config</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">If you prefer to use a different version of Postgres, update the <code>--pg</code> flag accordingly.</p>
<p dir="auto">Note: While it is possible to develop using pgrx's own Postgres installation(s), via <code>cargo pgrx init</code> without specifying a <code>pg_config</code> path, we recommend using your system package manager's Postgres as we've observed inconsistent behaviours when using pgrx's.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Adding a Service</h3><a id="user-content-adding-a-service" aria-label="Permalink: Adding a Service" href="#adding-a-service"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><code>pg_lakehouse</code> uses OpenDAL to integrate with various object stores. As of the time of writing, some — but not all — of the object stores supported by OpenDAL have been integrated.</p>
<p dir="auto">Adding support for a new object store is as straightforward as</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Adding the service feature to <code>opendal</code> in <code>Cargo.toml</code>. For instance, S3 requires <code>services-s3</code>.</li>
<li>Creating a file in the <code>fdw/</code> folder that implements the <code>BaseFdw</code> trait. For instance, <code>fdw/s3.rs</code> implements the S3 FDW.</li>
<li>Registering the FDW in <code>fdw/handler.rs</code>.</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Running Tests</h3><a id="user-content-running-tests" aria-label="Permalink: Running Tests" href="#running-tests"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">We use <code>cargo test</code> as our runner for <code>pg_lakehouse</code> tests. Tests are conducted using <a href="https://github.com/testcontainers/testcontainers-rs">testcontainers</a> to manage testing containers like <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/localstack/localstack" rel="nofollow">LocalStack</a>. <code>testcontainers</code> will pull any Docker images that it requires to perform the test.</p>
<p dir="auto">You also need a running Postgres instance to run the tests. The test suite will look for a connection string on the <code>DATABASE_URL</code> environment variable. You can set this variable manually, or use <code>.env</code> file with contents like this:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="DATABASE_URL=postgres://<username>@<host>:<port>/<database>"><pre lang="text"><code>DATABASE_URL=postgres://&lt;username&gt;@&lt;host&gt;:&lt;port&gt;/&lt;database&gt;
</code></pre></div>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Squarespace to Go Private in $6.9B All-Cash Transaction with Permira (249 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://investors.squarespace.com/news-events-financials/investor-news/news-details/2024/Squarespace-to-Go-Private-in-6.9B-All-Cash-Transaction-with-Permira/default.aspx</link>
            <guid>40343006</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 13:17:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://investors.squarespace.com/news-events-financials/investor-news/news-details/2024/Squarespace-to-Go-Private-in-6.9B-All-Cash-Transaction-with-Permira/default.aspx">https://investors.squarespace.com/news-events-financials/investor-news/news-details/2024/Squarespace-to-Go-Private-in-6.9B-All-Cash-Transaction-with-Permira/default.aspx</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40343006">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://investors.squarespace.com/news-events-financials/investor-news/news-details/2024/Squarespace-to-Go-Private-in-6.9B-All-Cash-Transaction-with-Permira/default.aspx: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Static Chess (240 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.val.town/v/maxm/staticChess</link>
            <guid>40342803</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 12:56:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.val.town/v/maxm/staticChess">https://www.val.town/v/maxm/staticChess</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40342803">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><span></span><span>import</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span> </span><span>Chess</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>Move</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>Square</span><span> </span><span>}</span><span> </span><span>from</span><span> </span><span>"npm:chess.js"</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span></span><span>import</span><span> </span><span>minify</span><span> </span><span>from</span><span> </span><span>"npm:css-simple-minifier"</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span></span><span>import</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span> </span><span>renderToString</span><span> </span><span>}</span><span> </span><span>from</span><span> </span><span>"npm:react-dom/server"</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span></span><span>class</span><span> </span><span>StaticChess</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>size</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>8</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>rows</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>Array</span><span>.</span><span>from</span><span>(</span><span>{</span><span> </span><span>length</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>size</span><span> </span><span>}</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>_</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>i</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>=&gt;</span><span> </span><span>i</span><span>)</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>squares</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>Array</span><span>.</span><span>from</span><span>(</span><span>{</span><span> </span><span>length</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>size</span><span> </span><span>}</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>_</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>i</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>=&gt;</span><span> </span><span>i</span><span>)</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>constructor</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>}</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>async</span><span> </span><span>fetch</span><span>(</span><span>req</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>Request</span><span>)</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>Promise</span><span>&lt;</span><span>Response</span><span>&gt; </span><span>{</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>gameInfo</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>parseURL</span><span>(</span><span>req</span><span>.</span><span>url</span><span>)</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>if</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>gameInfo</span><span> </span><span>===</span><span> </span><span>undefined</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>return</span><span> </span><span>new</span><span> </span><span>Response</span><span>(</span><span>"Not Found"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span> </span><span>status</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>404</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>headers</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span> </span><span>"cache-control"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"max-age=86400, public"</span><span> </span><span>}</span><span> </span><span>}</span><span>)</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>}</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>game</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>new</span><span> </span><span>Game</span><span>(</span><span>gameInfo</span><span>.</span><span>game</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>gameInfo</span><span>.</span><span>selected</span><span>)</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>return</span><span> </span><span>new</span><span> </span><span>Response</span><span>(</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>renderToString</span><span>(</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>&lt;</span><span>html</span><span>&gt;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>&lt;</span><span>head</span><span>&gt;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>&lt;</span><span>title</span><span>&gt;</span><span>Static Chess</span><span>&lt;/</span><span>title</span><span>&gt;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>&lt;</span><span>meta</span><span> </span><span>name</span><span>=</span><span>"viewport"</span><span> </span><span>content</span><span>=</span><span>"width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0"</span><span> </span><span>/&gt;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>&lt;</span><span>link</span><span> </span><span>rel</span><span>=</span><span>"icon"</span><span> </span><span>href</span><span>=</span><span>"https://fav.farm/♟️"</span><span> </span><span>/&gt;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>&lt;</span><span>style</span><span>&gt;</span><span>{</span><span>minify</span><span>(</span><span>CSS</span><span>)</span><span>}</span><span>&lt;/</span><span>style</span><span>&gt;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>&lt;/</span><span>head</span><span>&gt;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>&lt;</span><span>body</span><span>&gt;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>&lt;</span><span>h1</span><span>&gt;</span><span>Static Chess</span><span>&lt;/</span><span>h1</span><span>&gt;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>&lt;</span><span>div</span><span>&gt;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>&lt;</span><span>a</span><span> </span><span>href</span><span>=</span><span>"https://www.val.town/v/maxm/staticChess"</span><span>&gt;</span><span>info</span><span>&lt;/</span><span>a</span><span>&gt;</span><span> - </span><span>&lt;</span><span>a</span><span> </span><span>href</span><span>=</span><span>"/"</span><span>&gt;</span><span>reset</span><span>&lt;/</span><span>a</span><span>&gt;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>&lt;/</span><span>div</span><span>&gt;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>&lt;</span><span>div</span><span> </span><span>className</span><span>=</span><span>"board"</span><span>&gt;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>{</span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>rows</span><span>.</span><span>map</span><span>(</span><span>row</span><span> </span><span>=&gt;</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>&lt;</span><span>div</span><span> </span><span>key</span><span>=</span><span>{</span><span>row</span><span>}</span><span> </span><span>className</span><span>=</span><span>"row"</span><span>&gt;</span><span>{</span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>squares</span><span>.</span><span>map</span><span>(</span><span>square</span><span> </span><span>=&gt;</span><span> </span><span>game</span><span>.</span><span>squareContent</span><span>(</span><span>row</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>square</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>}</span><span>&lt;/</span><span>div</span><span>&gt;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>}</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>&lt;/</span><span>div</span><span>&gt;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>&lt;</span><span>div</span><span> </span><span>className</span><span>=</span><span>"info"</span><span>&gt;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>{</span><span>game</span><span>.</span><span>selected</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>?</span><span> </span><span>"Click a highted square to move the selected piece, or select a different piece."</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>`It is </span><span>${</span><span>{</span><span> </span><span>w</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"white"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>b</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"black"</span><span> </span><span>}</span><span>[</span><span>game</span><span>.</span><span>game</span><span>.</span><span>turn</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>]</span><span>}</span><span>'s turn. Click a piece to make a move.`</span><span>}</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>&lt;/</span><span>div</span><span>&gt;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>&lt;/</span><span>body</span><span>&gt;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>&lt;/</span><span>html</span><span>&gt;</span><span>,</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>)</span><span>,</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>{</span><span> </span><span>headers</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span> </span><span>"content-type"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"text/html"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>"cache-control"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"max-age=86400, public"</span><span> </span><span>}</span><span> </span><span>}</span><span>,</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>)</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>}</span><span></span></p><p><span></span><span>}</span><span></span></p><p><span></span><span>class</span><span> </span><span>Game</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>game</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>Chess</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>selected</span><span>?</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>string</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>selectable</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>string</span><span>[</span><span>]</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>board</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>nextMoves</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>key</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>string</span><span>]</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>Move</span><span> </span><span>}</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>fen</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>string</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>constructor</span><span>(</span><span>game</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>Chess</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>selected</span><span>?</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>string</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>game</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>game</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>selected</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>selected</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>board</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>game</span><span>.</span><span>board</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>fen</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>game</span><span>.</span><span>fen</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>.</span><span>replaceAll</span><span>(</span><span>" "</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>"_"</span><span>)</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>nextMoves</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>}</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>selectable</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>game</span><span>.</span><span>moves</span><span>(</span><span>{</span><span> </span><span>verbose</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>true</span><span> </span><span>}</span><span>)</span><span>.</span><span>map</span><span>(</span><span>(</span><span>m</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>=&gt;</span><span> </span><span>m</span><span>.</span><span>from</span><span>.</span><span>toString</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>if</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>selected</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>var</span><span> </span><span>moves</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>game</span><span>.</span><span>moves</span><span>(</span><span>{</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>square</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>selected</span><span> </span><span>as</span><span> </span><span>Square</span><span>,</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>verbose</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>true</span><span>,</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>}</span><span>)</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>for</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>move</span><span> </span><span>of</span><span> </span><span>moves</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>nextMoves</span><span>[</span><span>move</span><span>.</span><span>to</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>move</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>}</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>}</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>}</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>squareContent</span><span>(</span><span>row</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>number</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>square</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>number</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>pos</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>indexToPos</span><span>(</span><span>row</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>square</span><span>)</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>color</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>board</span><span>[</span><span>row</span><span>]</span><span>[</span><span>square</span><span>]</span><span>?.</span><span>color</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>let</span><span> </span><span>className</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>"square"</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>if</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>color</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>className</span><span> </span><span>+=</span><span> </span><span>" "</span><span> </span><span>+</span><span> </span><span>color</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>if</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>selected</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>if</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>nextMoves</span><span>[</span><span>pos</span><span>]</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>className</span><span> </span><span>+=</span><span> </span><span>" highlight"</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>if</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>selected</span><span> </span><span>==</span><span> </span><span>pos</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>className</span><span> </span><span>+=</span><span> </span><span>" selected highlight"</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>}</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>squareContent</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>=&gt;</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>if</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>selectable</span><span>.</span><span>includes</span><span>(</span><span>pos</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>return</span><span> </span><span>&lt;</span><span>a</span><span> </span><span>href</span><span>=</span><span>{</span><span>`/</span><span>${</span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>fen</span><span>}</span><span>/</span><span>${</span><span>pos</span><span>}</span><span>`</span><span>}</span><span>&gt;</span><span>{</span><span>pieces</span><span>[</span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>board</span><span>[</span><span>row</span><span>]</span><span>[</span><span>square</span><span>]</span><span>?.</span><span>type</span><span>]</span><span>}</span><span>&lt;/</span><span>a</span><span>&gt;</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>}</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>nextMove</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>nextMoves</span><span>[</span><span>pos</span><span>]</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>if</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>nextMove</span><span> </span><span>!==</span><span> </span><span>undefined</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>return</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>&lt;</span><span>a</span><span> </span><span>href</span><span>=</span><span>{</span><span>`/</span><span>${</span><span>nextMove</span><span>.</span><span>after</span><span>.</span><span>replaceAll</span><span>(</span><span>" "</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>"_"</span><span>)</span><span>}</span><span>/`</span><span>}</span><span>&gt;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>{</span><span>pieces</span><span>[</span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>board</span><span>[</span><span>row</span><span>]</span><span>[</span><span>square</span><span>]</span><span>?.</span><span>type</span><span>]</span><span>}</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>&lt;/</span><span>a</span><span>&gt;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>)</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>}</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>return</span><span> </span><span>&lt;</span><span>span</span><span>&gt;</span><span>{</span><span>pieces</span><span>[</span><span>this</span><span>.</span><span>board</span><span>[</span><span>row</span><span>]</span><span>[</span><span>square</span><span>]</span><span>?.</span><span>type</span><span>]</span><span>}</span><span>&lt;/</span><span>span</span><span>&gt;</span><span>;</span><span></span></p><p><span> </span><span>}</span><span>)</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>;</span></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The USDA's gardening zones shifted, this map shows you what's changed (404 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://apps.npr.org/plant-hardiness-garden-map/</link>
            <guid>40342578</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 12:32:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://apps.npr.org/plant-hardiness-garden-map/">https://apps.npr.org/plant-hardiness-garden-map/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40342578">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      <p><img alt="walking pot" src="https://apps.npr.org/plant-hardiness-garden-map/assets/synced/illo/resized/walker.gif">            
      </p>      
      
            
      <div id="sticky-nav">
          <p>2023 USDA map</p>
          <p>2012 USDA map</p>
          
        </div>
      <div id="debugger">
        <h3>Initial Load</h3><p>
          Speed for transfer:<span id="Speedfortransfer"></span>s<br>
          Speed for paint:<span id="Speedforpaint"></span>s<br>
          Total map load:<span id="loadSpeed"></span>s<br>
          Initial tiles transfered:<span id="initTiles"></span></p><h3>Cumulative</h3><p>
          Total tiles requested:   <span id="Totaltilesrequested"></span></p><h3>current slide ID: <span id="slideID"></span></h3>
        <h3>Layers Loaded</h3>
          
      </div>
      

<div id="titlecard" data-type="image">

    <p><img data-src="./assets/synced/illo/resized/walker-title.gif" alt="Animation of a cute azalea plant walking in front of the hardiness map"></p>
    
    

    <div>

      
        
      

      <hr>

      <div>
        <p>Recently, the USDA updated its plant hardiness map for the first time in 11<span>&nbsp;</span>years.</p>
<p>If you’re a gardener — and everybody can be a gardener, even on a balcony or a stoop — this is a big<span>&nbsp;</span>deal!</p>
<p>The updated map opens up new possibilities for home gardeners, but there are limits. Let’s explore how the map has changed and what this means for your<span>&nbsp;</span>garden.</p>

      </div>
    </div>
  
    

    
  </div>

<div id="intro-1" data-type="map" data-maplayer="2012_zones" data-center="[-98.04, 39.507]" data-zoom="3.8">
    

    <p>Enter your city and<span>&nbsp;</span>state:</p>

    

    

    

    
      

    
    
  </div>
<div id="zoomIn" data-type="map" data-maplayer="2012_zones"><p>In 2012, the USDA classified <span data-item="yourPlace"></span>, as Zone <span data-item="oldZone"></span>.
</p><p>Back then, <span data-item="yourPlaceShortPoss"></span> coldest winter temperature was somewhere <span data-item="tempRange-2012"></span> degrees Fahrenheit on average.</p></div>
<div id="intro-3" data-type="map" data-maplayer="2023_zones"> 
  <p>
    In 2023, <span data-item="yourPlaceShort"></span> is still rated as Zone <span data-item="newZone"></span>.
  </p>
  <div><p>
    In 2023, the USDA reclassified <span data-item="yourPlaceShort"></span> as Zone <span data-item="newZone">8a</span>. 
</p><p>Now, the lowest winter temperature is <span data-item="tempRange-2023"></span> degrees Fahrenheit on<span>&nbsp;</span>average.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div id="intro-4" data-type="map" data-maplayer="temp_diff_layer">
    

    <div> 
  <div><p>
    Even though <span data-item="yourPlaceShortPoss">your area’s</span> zone didn’t change, that doesn’t mean the area hasn’t experienced some change in winter lows. 
</p><p>The new 30-year minimum temperature average was <span data-item="tempDiff"> 3.3 degrees F warmer</span> than the previous average, which spanned 1976 to<span>&nbsp;</span>2005.</p>
  </div>
  <p>
    That’s because the new average minimum temperature in <span data-item="yourPlaceShort"></span> is <span data-item="tempDiff"> 3.3 degrees Fahrenheit  warmer</span> than the previous average, from an earlier period.
  </p>
</div>

    

    

    
      <div>
  
    <h3>Change in lowest winter temperature</h3>
  
  <ul>
    <li data-range="-8"></li>
    <li data-range="-7"></li>
    <li data-range="-6"></li>
    <li data-range="-5"></li>
    <li data-range="-4"></li>
    <li data-range="-3"></li>
    <li data-range="-2"></li>
    <li data-range="-1"></li>
    <li data-range="0"></li>
    <li data-range="1"></li>
    <li data-range="2"></li>
    <li data-range="3"></li>
    <li data-range="4"></li>
    <li data-range="5"></li>
    <li data-range="6"></li>
    <li data-range="7"></li>
    <li data-range="8"></li>
  </ul>
  <div>
    <p>-8</p>
    
    <p>-6</p>
    
    <p>-4</p>
    
    <p>-2</p>
    
    <p>0</p>
    
    <p>+2</p>
    
    <p>+4</p>
    
    <p>+6</p>
    
    <p>+8°&nbsp;F</p>
    <!-- <p class="max">+9&deg;&nbsp;C</p> -->
  </div>

  
    <details>
      <summary>About this data</summary>
      <p>The 2012 USDA hardiness zones were calculated using the average lowest winter temperature for the observation period of 1976-2005. The new zones are calculated using the years 1991-2020. These two observation windows overlap. Colors show the difference between the two 30-year averages for each place on the<span>&nbsp;</span>map.</p>

    </details>
  
  
</div>
    

    
    
  </div>
<div id="intro-5" data-type="map" data-maplayer="temp_diff_layer">
      
      <p>Most of the changes across the country are due to the warming<span>&nbsp;</span>climate.</p>
<p>Winters are warming at a faster pace than other seasons, according to Deke Arndt, director of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration’s National Centers for Environmental<span>&nbsp;</span>Information.</p>
<p>At the same time, an increase in the amount and quality of data collected at weather stations across the country helped to improve the overall accuracy of temperature readings in recent<span>&nbsp;</span>years.</p>

    </div>
<div id="transition-1">
      <p><img data-src="./assets/synced/illo/resized/rake-final.png" width="”600”" height="”400”" alt="””" src="https://apps.npr.org/plant-hardiness-garden-map/assets/synced/illo/resized/rake-final.png">
</p>
<h3>What does your hardiness zone tell<span>&nbsp;</span>you?</h3>
<p>Some people might think their hardiness zone tells them which plants they can grow. In reality, it’s a little more<span>&nbsp;</span>complicated.</p>
<p>Your zone measurement is an average of the coldest yearly temperature in your area over the past 30<span>&nbsp;</span>years.</p>

    </div>
<section id="temperature-chart" data-type="chart">  
  
  


  <div id="chart-1"><p>Here are the coldest temperatures from each winter between 1991 and 2020 in <span data-item="chartPlaceShort"></span>. 
</p><p>Though these temperature estimates differ slightly from the data the USDA used to create the zone map, we’re using them to illustrate how zones are calculated.</p></div>

  <div id="chart-2"><p>The <span>average coldest night</span> over the past 30 years was about <span data-item="avg"></span>.</p></div>

  <div id="chart-3"> 
  <div><p>
    With this average temperature, <span data-item="chartPlace"></span> might be classified as Zone <span data-item="wrongZone"></span>.	
</p><p>However, the temperatures we’re showing here are based on estimates, and in this case they do not align with the more accurate, granular data that the USDA used. The USDA map classifies this area as <span data-item="newZone"></span>.</p>
  </div>
  <p>
    With this average coldest temperature, <span data-item="chartPlaceShort"></span> is classified as Zone <span data-item="chartNewZone"></span>.
  </p>
</div>

</section>
<div id="how-to" data-type="text">
        <p>This measurement, which predicts an area’s coldest temperatures, is only useful for plants that have to survive the<span>&nbsp;</span>winter.</p>
<p>They’re called <b>perennials:</b> You plant them once and they come back after each winter if they’re given the right environment to survive. Think things like trees, shrubs and woody<span>&nbsp;</span>plants.</p>


        

        <p>And for predicting winter plant survival, knowing an area’s hardiness zone is a big help to gardeners, says Todd Rounsaville, a horticulturist with the USDA who was involved with creating the new map. He explains that the hardiness zone “is really one of the best predictors of winter survival and plant survival in general in the<span>&nbsp;</span>landscape.”</p>
<p>He advises gardeners to use the map as one very important tool of many in their risk assessment<span>&nbsp;</span>toolbox.</p>
<p>“Because the USDA map has really become the industry standard for rating things, it’s pretty rare that you will not see a zone rating on a plant, either on the tag or on a website,” he<span>&nbsp;</span>says.</p>
<p>Knowing what your average coldest temperature is helps rightsize your expectations about what might grow in your area. Live in Chicago’s <span>Zone 6a</span>? You can be assured that no citrus plants will survive your winter. Instead, try an apple tree. The apple tree is that kid you grew up with who wore shorts all winter. It needs the cold temperatures to set<span>&nbsp;</span>fruit.</p>
<p>Live in Miami’s <span>Zone 11a</span>? No apples for you. Instead, grow dragon<span>&nbsp;</span>fruit!</p>
<p><img data-src="./assets/synced/illo/resized/plant-tag.png" width="1200" height="674" alt="" src="https://apps.npr.org/plant-hardiness-garden-map/assets/synced/illo/resized/plant-tag.png">
</p>
<h3>What does your hardiness zone <u>not</u> tell you?</h3>
<p>On its own, your hardiness zone can’t tell you exactly what to grow in your<span>&nbsp;</span>area.</p>
<p>For example, parts of these three areas — Juneau, Alaska; Boston, Mass.; and Santa Fe, N.M. — are all in USDA’s <span>Zone<span>&nbsp;</span>7a</span>.</p>


        

        <p>“We know intuitively that the same plants can’t grow in these places,” Rounsaville<span>&nbsp;</span>says.</p>
<p>While Juneau may have relatively temperate winters, it also is extremely wet, averaging over 80 inches of snow a year. Santa Fe, on the other hand, is extremely dry, with much hotter summer temperatures than Juneau. Boston has both temperate winters and summers. It gets a good amount of rain but not nearly enough to sustain Juneau’s rainforest plants. It gets plenty of heat but is colder and wetter in the winter, making it inhospitable for desert dwellers, like cactuses and other<span>&nbsp;</span>succulents.</p>
<p>But all three cities rarely get below zero degrees each winter, so they are classified as the same<span>&nbsp;</span>zone.</p>
<p>So when you hear that your zone has changed, here are some things to keep in<span>&nbsp;</span>mind:</p>
<h4><span><b>1</b> The hardiness map says nothing about your <u>extreme</u> lowest temperature</span></h4>
<p>Just because your average lowest winter temperature has changed, doesn’t mean the temperature will never dip below your hardiness<span>&nbsp;</span>zone.</p>

      </div><section id="temperature-chart-return" data-type="chart" data-center="[-90.244582,38.635699]">  
  
  


  <div id="return-1">
    <p>For example, the average coldest night of the year in <u>St. Louis, Mo.,</u> tends to be around 2º F, meaning that it’s in Zone <span>7a</span>. Because St. Louis has warmed, it moved up from its <span>previous zone rating</span> of <span>6b</span>.</p>

    

    

    
  </div>

  <div id="return-2">

      <p>But notice that this is an <b><u>average</u></b> of the coldest temperature St. Louis gets each<span>&nbsp;</span>winter.</p>
<p>In the past 30 years, the temperature dropped below <span>Zone 7a</span> in at least 11 different<span>&nbsp;</span>years.</p>

    </div>

  <div id="return-3">

      <p>In 2014, the temperature dipped <span><b>three</b> half zones</span> below St. Louis’ hardiness zone, to -10º F.<span>&nbsp;</span>Brrrr!</p>
<p>Many common&nbsp;plants that are hardy down to Zone <span>7</span>, like rosemary, canna lilies or agave, would suffer significant damage or death from those temperatures, especially during a long cold<span>&nbsp;</span>snap.</p>

    </div>

</section>
<div id="limits-of-hardiness" data-type="text">
        <h4><span><b>2</b> The hardiness map says nothing about the <u>frequency</u> of extreme cold<span>&nbsp;</span>weather</span></h4>
<p>Your poor plants have to stay outside all winter, so the duration and frequency of cold weather matters for plant<span>&nbsp;</span>survival.</p>
<p>“If you’re naked and you run through a freezer, it’s not going to kill you,” says Andrew Bunting, vice president of horticulture at the Pennsylvania Horticultural Society. “If you run into the freezer and have to stay there for an extended period of time, it’s probably going to kill<span>&nbsp;</span>you.”</p>
<p><img data-src="./assets/synced/illo/resized/fig.png" width="1200" height="674" alt="" src="https://apps.npr.org/plant-hardiness-garden-map/assets/synced/illo/resized/fig.png">
</p>
<p>If extreme, out-of-zone weather occurs during a quick cold snap, steps can be taken to protect your plants with temporary blankets or other shelters. Pots can be brought<span>&nbsp;</span>inside.</p>
<p>But if the extreme lows persist, tender plants will struggle to survive. Your hardiness zone does not take any of this into<span>&nbsp;</span>account.</p>
<h4><span><b>3</b> The hardiness map can’t tell you if your plants will survive the<span>&nbsp;</span>summer</span></h4>
<p>Summer temperature extremes matter a great deal but are not reflected in the USDA hardiness<span>&nbsp;</span>map.</p>
<p>Let’s look again at <u>Juneau</u> and <u>Santa Fe,</u> much of which are in <span>Zone 7a</span>. Juneau’s all-time high temperature was 90º F in 1975. Summer days in Santa Fe routinely reach the 90s. Some shade- and cool-weather-loving plants like ferns and hostas will thrive in Juneau but struggle mightily in a place like Santa Fe. Likewise, a cactus accustomed to high temperatures would struggle to thrive in the cooler summer temperatures of Juneau, to say nothing of the overwhelming<span>&nbsp;</span>rainfall.</p>
<p>Because of this tricky problem, there have been attempts to create a corresponding map that helps gardeners know which plants might survive summer in their<span>&nbsp;</span>area.</p>
<p>In 1997, the American Horticultural Society released a heat zone map that measured the average number of times per year that the temperature of an area exceeds 86º<span>&nbsp;</span>F.</p>
<p><img data-src="./assets/synced/images/ahs-heat-map.jpg" alt="AHS Heat Zone Map (1997)" src="https://apps.npr.org/plant-hardiness-garden-map/assets/synced/images/ahs-heat-map.jpg">
<span>American Horticultural Society</span> 
</p>
<p>But this map didn’t become well known among gardeners. On a recent visit to a plant nursery outside Washington, D.C., nearly every plant tag had a USDA hardiness zone, but only one, out of the several dozen checked, had the AHS heat zone<span>&nbsp;</span>listed.</p>
<p>Above 86º F, plants from cooler climates rapidly become<span>&nbsp;</span>stressed.</p>
<p>Because of these complexities, more plant survival factors should be included in the 2023 map, says Tony Avent, who runs Juniper Level Botanic Garden and Plant Delights Nursery in Raleigh,<span>&nbsp;</span>N.C.</p>
<p>“If [these metrics] had been factored in, that would have given you a much more applicable map,” says Avent, who was a member of the committee that put together the 2012 version of the<span>&nbsp;</span>map.</p>
<p>“And that’s the part that’s a little<span>&nbsp;</span>disappointing.”</p>
<p><img data-src="./assets/synced/illo/resized/wilting.png" width="1200" height="674" alt="" src="https://apps.npr.org/plant-hardiness-garden-map/assets/synced/illo/resized/wilting.png">
</p>
<p>But including more plant survival factors in the USDA hardiness map runs the risk of creating an overly complicated map and muddying its intended use, Rounsaville<span>&nbsp;</span>says.</p>
<p>“In a perfect world, we could infinitely break down where plants will grow well, but that’s very hard to do and produce a map that is, you know, coherent but at a local resolution,” Rounsaville<span>&nbsp;</span>says.</p>
<p><img data-src="./assets/synced/illo/resized/shovel.png" width="”600”" height="”400”" alt="””" src="https://apps.npr.org/plant-hardiness-garden-map/assets/synced/illo/resized/shovel.png">
</p>
<p>Since the USDA plant hardiness zone can’t tell you everything about how a plant will fare in your garden, it’s a good idea to turn to local plant experts for guidance. Local nurseries and botanical gardens can be great resources for in-depth knowledge of the area and recent warming or cooling<span>&nbsp;</span>trends.</p>
<p>New plant varieties are constantly being bred with improvements such as increased hardiness, bloom count, bloom length or color<span>&nbsp;</span>combinations.</p>
<p>Some nursery owners like Avent enjoy experimenting with these plants.  He and his team grow many varieties of plants — both typical and unconventional — to figure out which plants they can bring to market in<span>&nbsp;</span>Raleigh.</p>
<p>“We live to kill plants,” Avent says. He estimates that they’ve killed over 50,000 plant varieties in his career. Every one they kill, they record in a<span>&nbsp;</span>database.</p>
<p><img data-src="./assets/synced/illo/resized/hose.png" width="”600”" height="”400”" alt="””" src="https://apps.npr.org/plant-hardiness-garden-map/assets/synced/illo/resized/hose.png">
</p>
<h3>If my zone changed, can I plant new things<span>&nbsp;</span>now?</h3>
<p>Maybe, and maybe you already did! It’s possible you or your neighbors may have already noticed some of these climatic changes and have been experimenting with plant varieties that were once unusual for your<span>&nbsp;</span>area.</p>
<p>Keep in mind that the new USDA map is backward looking; it represents changes that have already taken place over the past 30<span>&nbsp;</span>years.</p>
<p>In the <span>7a</span>-<span>7b</span> Philadelphia suburbs, Bunting notes two perennials that he has noticed surviving Philadelphia winters in recent<span>&nbsp;</span>years.</p>
<p>“It used to be [that] if you had a camellia, it was in a little courtyard with lots of protection, maybe even wrapped [in protective cloth] for the winter.” But now, “It’s perfectly hardy. Same with figs. People used to wrap figs. You don’t have to do that<span>&nbsp;</span>anymore.”</p>
<p>Of course, your mileage may vary. As Bunting notes, <i>where</i> you plant a perennial in your yard — whether sheltered or in the open — matters. Some areas get southern exposure and lots of sun, others are behind a house, or under a tree. Every yard has many distinct microclimates, and learning how to harness these subtle differences in your yard can help you plant more ambitious varieties with more<span>&nbsp;</span>confidence.</p>
<p>“Gardeners know that if they’re near paved surfaces or brick and mortar structures, that there’s a lot of radiant heat that those absorb during the day,” Rounsaville says. “And they can really push hardiness zones through the winter to help with plant<span>&nbsp;</span>survival.”</p>
<p><img data-src="./assets/synced/illo/resized/walking-final.png" width="1200" height="674" alt="" src="https://apps.npr.org/plant-hardiness-garden-map/assets/synced/illo/resized/walking-final.png">
</p>

      </div>

<section id="cooperative-extensions" data-type="waterfall">
  <!-- <img
    class="backdrop"
    data-src="./assets/synced/images/"
    alt=""
    style=""
  > -->

  
  <div>
    <p>Aside from local nurseries and botanic gardens, cooperative extension services can be a great place to find local gardening advice. The extension services are <a href="https://www.nifa.usda.gov/land-grant-colleges-and-universities-partner-website-directory">part of a national network</a> of local experts who provide advice on everything from agriculture to<span>&nbsp;</span>gardening.</p>
<p>NPR reached out to services in over 30 areas across the country, and many told us about changes they’ve seen in what they can and can’t plant over the past 15<span>&nbsp;</span>years.</p>

  </div>
  

<div>
    
      <div>
        <p>Phoenix</p>
        <div><p><span>Aleppo pines</span> and <span>Arizona ash</span> have shown increased issues in urban environments.
</p><p>
[Meanwhile,] plants which are strongly limited by freeze events have benefited from over a decade without severe freezes in some parts of the region.</p></div>
        <p>– Michael Chamberland, assistant agent for urban horticulture, University of Arizona, Maricopa County Cooperative Extension</p>
      </div>
    
      <div>
        <p>Amherst, Mass.</p>
        <p>Nurseries in western Massachusetts rarely carried <span>Leyland cypress</span> and <span>Japanese cryptomeria</span> but now offer them. There's nothing that I know of that can no longer be grown here due to the warming trend.</p>
        <p>– Nicholas J. Brazee, extension plant pathologist, University of Massachusetts Amherst</p>
      </div>
    
      <div>
        <p>Omaha, Neb.</p>
        <p>Because [the hardiness map]'s based on averages and we live in a part of the country that <span>experiences significant fluctuations</span> in both temperature and precipitation, we’re advising gardeners not to buy more plants for the increased hardiness zone than they can afford to lose. </p>
        <p>– Dana Freeman, horticulture program coordinator, University of Nebraska Extension, Douglas-Sarpy Counties</p>
      </div>
    
      <div>
        <p>Denver</p>
        <p>One thing I’ve noticed in my horticulture career is that <span>“global weirding”</span> — the continental climate variability we have here — does quite a bit to negate the USDA zone changes. I always want what I can’t have and persistently have things perform well even for a few years, only to be killed in late spring freezes. A plant’s ability to prosper somewhere is based upon more than the average winter temperature (i.e., USDA zone).</p>
        <p>– John Murgel, extension specialist for Douglas County, Colorado State University </p>
      </div>
    
      <div>
        <p>Minneapolis</p>
        <p>With the new USDA Plant Hardiness map, our state now recognizes larger areas of Zone 5A, particularly in urban and southwestern areas, supporting a broader palette of plants such as <span>oakleaf hydrangea</span> and <span>Japanese maple</span> that can be grown in these areas. </p>
        <p>– Brandon Miller, assistant professor; 
Julie Weisenhorn, extension horticulture educator and associate extension professor, University of Minnesota</p>
      </div>
    
      <div>
        <p>San Francisco</p>
        <p>Since our climate is more moderate in climate extremes (highs and lows) vs. say the Midwest or East Coast, these extremes have not necessarily increased significantly other than in duration and period of occurrence. We have noticed that some plants such as <span>Bougainvillea</span>, which might go into winter dormancy and be in jeopardy of damage in a freeze or cold night, no longer go into dormancy and keep many of their leaves throughout the winter.</p>
        <p>– University of California Cooperative Extension Master Gardeners, San Mateo and San Francisco Counties</p>
      </div>
    
      <div>
        <p>Dallas</p>
        <div><p>The climate change as indicated by the new zone map will have an impact in the South, especially if the area continues to experience droughts. This will result in a <span>shorter growing season.</span></p><p>
A greater impact may be noticed as you go north, where the area may experience more insect and disease pressure due to mild winters, and a shift in vegetable crops that can be grown. For example, <span>okra</span> is not common in Michigan but may be easily grown with warmer temperatures. This change may also have more impact on <span>fruiting trees such as apples</span> with a minimum chilling hours requirement that will not be met if temperatures continue to stay warmer in the winters.</p></div>
        <p>– Joe Masabni, extension vegetable specialist, Texas A&amp;M AgriLife Research and Extension Center</p>
      </div>
    
  </div>

</section>
<div id="explore" data-type="map" data-maplayer="2023_zones">
    

    <div>
      
      <p>With that, you have what you need to start a garden. Big or<span>&nbsp;</span>small.</p>
<p>Happy planting!</p>
<p><img data-src="./assets/synced/illo/planted-final.png" width="1200" height="674" alt="" src="https://apps.npr.org/plant-hardiness-garden-map/assets/synced/illo/planted-final.png">
</p>

    </div>

    

    

    

    
    

      <div>
        <p>
          Explore the map
      </p>
      <p>
        Start over with a new location
      </p>

      </div>

    
  </div>


    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[It’s an age of marvels (303 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.plover.com/tech/its-an-age-of-marvels.html</link>
            <guid>40342188</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 11:49:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.plover.com/tech/its-an-age-of-marvels.html">https://blog.plover.com/tech/its-an-age-of-marvels.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40342188">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

   <br>

<span>Sun, 12 May 2024</span>
<p>
<a name="its-an-age-of-marvels" href="https://blog.plover.com/tech/its-an-age-of-marvels.html">It's an age of marvels</a>
<br>
</p><p>As I walk around Philadelphia I often converse with Benjamin Franklin,
to see what he thinks about how things have changed since 1790.
Sometimes he's astounded, other times less so. The things that
astound Franklin aren't always what you might think at first.
Electric streetlamps are a superb invention, and while I think
Franklin would be very pleased to see them, I don't think he would be
surprised.  Better street lighting was something everyone wanted in
Franklin's time, and
<a href="https://www.ushistory.org/franklin/autobiography/page60.htm">this was something very much on Franklin's mind</a>.
It was certainly clear that electricity could be turned into light.
Franklin could have and might have thought up the basic
mechanism of an incandescent bulb himself, although he wouldn't have
been able to make one.</p>

<p>The Internet?  Well, again yes, but no.  The complicated engineering
details are complicated engineering, but again the basic idea is
easily within the reach of the 18th century and is not all that
astounding.  They hadn't figured out Oersted's law yet, which was
crucial, but they certainly knew that you could do something at one
end of a long wire and it would have an effect at the other end, and
had an idea that that might be a way to send messages from one place
to another.  Wikipedia says that as early as 1753 people were thinking
that an electric signal could deflect a ping-pong ball at the
receiving end.  It might have worked!  If you look into the history of
transatlantic telegraph cables you will learn that the earliest
methods were almost as clunky.</p>

<p>Wikipedia itself is more impressive.  The universal encyclopedia has
long been a dream, and now we have one.  It's not always reliable,
but you know what?  Not all of <em>anything</em> is reliable.</p>

<p>An obvious winner, something sure to blow Franklin's mind is “yeah,
we've sent people to the Moon to see what it was like, they left
scientific instruments there and then they came back with rocks and
stuff.”  But that's no everyday thing, it blew everyone's mind when it
happened and it still does.  Some things I tell Franklin make him
goggle and say “We did <em>what</em>?” and I shrug modestly and say yeah,
it's pretty impressive, isn't it.  The Moon thing makes me goggle
right
back. <a href="https://store.theonion.com/products/man-walks-on-moon-front-page-poster-from-the-onions-our-dumb-century"><em>The Onion</em> nailed it</a>.</p>

<p>The really interesting stuff is the <em>everyday</em> stuff that makes
Franklin goggle.  CAT scans, for example.  Ordinary endoscopy will
interest and perhaps impress Franklin, but it won't boggle his mind.
(“Yeah, the doctor sticks a tube up your butt with an electric light
so they can see if your bowel is healthy.”  Franklin nods right
along.)  X-rays are more impressive.  (I wrote a while back about
<a href="https://blog.plover.com/tech/dental-x-rays.html">how long it took dentists to start adopting X-ray technology</a>:
about two weeks.)  But CAT scans are mind-boggling.  Oh yeah, we send
invisible rays at you from all directions, and measure how much each
one was attenuated from passing through your body, and then infer from
that exactly what must be inside and how it is all arranged.  We do
<em>what</em>?  And that's without getting into any of the details of whether
this is done by positron emission or nuclear magnetic resonance
(whatever those are, I have no idea) or something else equally
incomprehensible.  Apparently there really is something to this
quantum physics nonsense.</p>

<p>So far though the most Franklin-astounding thing I've found has been GPS.  The
explanation starts with “well, first we put 32 artificial satellites
in orbit around the Earth…”, which is already astounding, and can
derail the conversation all by itself.  But it just
goes on from there getting more and more astounding:</p>

<p>“…and each one has a  clock on board, accurate to within 40 nanoseconds…”</p>

<p>“…and can communicate the exact time wirelessly to the entire half of
the Earth that it can see…”</p>

<p>“… and because the GPS device <em>also</em> has a perfect clock, it can
compute how far it is from the satellite by comparing the two times
and multiplying by the speed of light…”</p>

<p>“… and because the satellite also tells the GPS device exactly where
it is, the device can determine that it lies on the surface of a sphere
with the satellite at the center, so with messages from three or four
satellites the device can compute its exact location, up to the error
in the clocks and other measurements…”</p>

<p>“…and it fits in my pocket.”</p>

<p>And that's not even getting into the hair-raising complications
introduced by general relativity.  “It's a bit fiddly because time
isn't passing at the same rate for the device as it is for the
satellites, but we were able to work it out.”  What.  The.  Fuck.</p>

<p>Of course not all marvels are good ones.  I sometimes explain to
Franklin that we have gotten so good at fishing&nbsp;— <em>too</em> good&nbsp;— that we
are in real danger of fishing out the oceans.  A marvel,
nevertheless.</p>

<p>A past what-the-fuck was that we know exactly how many cells
there are (959) in a particular little worm, <em>C. elegans</em>, and
<a href="https://www.wormatlas.org/celllineages.html">how each of those cells arises from the division of previous cells</a>,
as the grows from a fertilized egg, and we know what each cell does
and how they are connected, and we know that 302 of those cells are
nerve cells, and how the nerve cells are connected together.  (There
are 6,720 connections.)  The big science news on Friday was that for
the first time
<a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.add9330">we have done this for an insect brain</a>.
It was the <em>drosophila</em> larva, and it has 3016 neurons and 548,000
synapses.</p>

<p>Today I was reading somewhere about how most meteorites are
asteroidal, but some are from the Moon and a few are from Mars.  I
wondered “how do we know that they are from Mars?” but then I couldn't
understand
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martian_meteorite">the explanation</a>.
Someday maybe.</p>

<p>And by the way, there are only 277 known Martian meteorites.  So
today's what-the-fuck is: “Yeah, we looked at all the rocks we could
find all over the Earth and we noticed a couple hundred we found lying
around various places looked funny and we figured out they must have
come from Mars.  And when.  And how long they were on Mars before
that.”</p>

<p>Obviously, It's amazing that we know enough about Mars to
be able to say that these rocks are like the ones on Mars. (“Yeah, we
sent some devices there to look around and send back messages about
what it was like.”)  But to me, the deeper and more amazing thing is,
from looking at billions of rocks, we have learned <em>so</em> much about what
rocks are like that we can pick out, from these billions, a couple of
hundred that came to the Earth not merely from elsewhere but
<em>specifically</em> from Mars.</p>

<p>What. The. Fuck.</p>




<p>
<i>[<a href="https://blog.plover.com/tech">Other articles in category /tech</a>] 
<a href="https://blog.plover.com/tech/its-an-age-of-marvels.html">permanent link</a></i>
</p>

<br>

  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The danger of the mediocre success when testing startup hypotheses (2023) (145 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://pivotal.substack.com/p/the-worst-outcome-is-a-mediocre-success</link>
            <guid>40342075</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 11:38:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://pivotal.substack.com/p/the-worst-outcome-is-a-mediocre-success">https://pivotal.substack.com/p/the-worst-outcome-is-a-mediocre-success</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40342075">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><p>One of the wisest and most important pieces of advice I received as a startup founder was this: “The worst outcome is a mediocre success”.</p><p>Now, this is not a simplistic exhortation to go big or go home, hit a home run or strike out, be blindly ambitious, any of those things. It's subtler than that. Let me explain.</p><p>Startups are defined by uncertainty. As a founder, you have to discover almost everything about your business: What is the product? Who are your customers? How will you reach them? How much will they pay? Who are your competitors? How is the industry evolving? The list goes on.</p><p>One common way to answer these questions is, essentially, the scientific method, applied to tech startups. Frame a hypothesis; run an experiment to test the hypothesis; confirm or disprove the hypothesis; learn and iterate and learn and iterate.</p><p>For example, your hypothesis could be that ‘Cold-calling customers will lead to sales’. So you hire a couple of sales reps and tell them to cold-call 100 customers. If you get 30 new sales out of that (a terrific hit rate) — great, the hypothesis is true! You can hire more sales reps and double down on this tactic. And if you get 0 new sales — that’s also great, the hypothesis is false! You can move on to other acquisition tactics like FB ads or SEO or events or whatever. Either way, your experiment worked in confirming or disproving the hypothesis.</p><p><span>The </span><em>worst</em><span> outcome, the very worst outcome, is to get a small but non-zero number of sales — say 1 or 2. Because now you're in a bind. Do you double down or pull the plug? Does cold-calling work or not? Could it be that the method works, but the sales reps aren’t hustling enough, or they’re not following the right script, or they’re not calling the right people? Or maybe the method is flawed and your reps just got lucky? You just don't know!</span></p><p>That’s the danger of the mediocre success. The point of startup experimentation isn't the success itself; it’s the learning that comes with clear-cut success or failure. You don't really care about the sales revenue generated by your first two reps; you care about whether this is a strategy you can scale to dozens and then hundreds of reps, or whether you need to use a completely different strategy. It’s all about the learning. And mediocre successes don’t give you any learning.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff391cd33-db65-4f91-be4a-49311c477d7b_1513x811.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff391cd33-db65-4f91-be4a-49311c477d7b_1513x811.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff391cd33-db65-4f91-be4a-49311c477d7b_1513x811.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff391cd33-db65-4f91-be4a-49311c477d7b_1513x811.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff391cd33-db65-4f91-be4a-49311c477d7b_1513x811.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff391cd33-db65-4f91-be4a-49311c477d7b_1513x811.jpeg" width="460" height="246.42857142857142" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/f391cd33-db65-4f91-be4a-49311c477d7b_1513x811.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:780,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:460,&quot;bytes&quot;:151282,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff391cd33-db65-4f91-be4a-49311c477d7b_1513x811.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff391cd33-db65-4f91-be4a-49311c477d7b_1513x811.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff391cd33-db65-4f91-be4a-49311c477d7b_1513x811.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff391cd33-db65-4f91-be4a-49311c477d7b_1513x811.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Unfortunately, there’s a natural human tendency to hedge our bets — to make design choices in our experiments such that a mediocre success is the most likely outcome. There’s also a tendency to only do experiments that you know in advance will work — but such experiments are not useful: the delta in information is close to zero. For example, and continuing the sales experiment: as a founder, you could do the calls yourself; reach out only to the very best, most qualified prospects; create custom collateral; offer sweetheart pricing. All those actions will increase the chances of closing any one deal, and as a result they’re very tempting, but do they tell you if cold-calling is a viable sales strategy at scale? Nope.</p><p>Making it worse is that we’re all heavily socialized to aim for mediocre success. Schools, universities, large organizations — they don’t want big swings and big misses; they want safety and consistency. A steady 7 is better than 10s interspersed with 0s. This might work well in structured, predictable environments, but in startup-land it’s anathema.</p><p>So when a startup comes to me with an idea for an experiment, the one thing I tell them is: make sure that there’s a well-defined distinction between success and failure. Don't fall in the messy middle. If the hypothesis fails, make sure it fails clearly and unambiguously; if it succeeds, make sure it succeeds equally clearly and unambiguously. And remember that a hypothesis failing means the experiment succeeded; you learned something. That’s what it's all about.</p><p>The worst outcome is a mediocre success!</p><p><em>Toronto, Sep 2023.</em></p><ul><li><p><span>This essay is about </span><em>tactics</em><span>, and specifically about how mediocre successes hamper your learning. There’s a whole separate essay to be written about mediocre success in the realm of </span><em>strategy</em><span>, which is largely about opportunity cost.</span></p></li><li><p>I’m experimenting with the content and form factor of this newsletter. In addition to the long-form, deep-dive pieces that I’ve written so far, I’m going to write some shorter single-topic pieces like this one, hopefully at a higher cadence. I’ll also widen the scope to include more personal anecdotes, tactical nuggets and random riffs. Let’s see how it goes!</p></li><li><p>If you enjoyed this article, please subscribe, and share it with 2-3 other folks who you think might enjoy it as well. I’d like to get more subscribers, and Twitter/X is no longer the reader-content discovery engine it once was.</p></li></ul></div></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Telegram has launched a pretty intense campaign to malign Signal as insecure (446 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/matthew_d_green/status/1789687898863792453</link>
            <guid>40341716</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 10:49:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/matthew_d_green/status/1789687898863792453">https://twitter.com/matthew_d_green/status/1789687898863792453</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40341716">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://twitter.com/matthew_d_green/status/1789687898863792453: Error: Request failed with status code 400]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Great Flattening (129 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://stratechery.com/2024/the-great-flattening/?access_token=eyJhbGciOiJSUzI1NiIsImtpZCI6InN0cmF0ZWNoZXJ5LnBhc3Nwb3J0Lm9ubGluZSIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJhdWQiOiJzdHJhdGVjaGVyeS5wYXNzcG9ydC5vbmxpbmUiLCJhenAiOiJIS0xjUzREd1Nod1AyWURLYmZQV00xIiwiZW50Ijp7InVyaSI6WyJodHRwczovL3N0cmF0ZWNoZXJ5LmNvbS8yMDI0L3RoZS1ncmVhdC1mbGF0dGVuaW5nLyJdfSwiZXhwIjoxNzE4MTg4NzMyLCJpYXQiOjE3MTU1OTY3MzIsImlzcyI6Imh0dHBzOi8vYXBpLnBhc3Nwb3J0Lm9ubGluZS9vYXV0aCIsInNjb3BlIjoiZmVlZDpyZWFkIGFydGljbGU6cmVhZCBhc3NldDpyZWFkIGNhdGVnb3J5OnJlYWQgZW50aXRsZW1lbnRzIiwic3ViIjoiV3NyTHlycjZxZW1WQWdFR0NqTW0zNCIsInVzZSI6ImFjY2VzcyJ9.NgkSZcz_OwkjW7TH6FNBKp7iHS1K6VPyf-xlU6tk1kEXbTuBZzP7kwYsU4WIEpXM4Ab-1DZxZhIus-1-1OtQ6HMi5DdJZqKYcCoARikBeSSkWFtPNGAVpBeOnWzYan2eSUrpGXeuKVq7g5aXv6zNDHoMqHuScb9jE7gFMIa4E3BdafrvjIQ0020M6tUQrm5jinP31XBSQrLUUU2cY_M6QjTn5Hh0CjLUUfNbrJz2yBuvC-egYBpyVersqGIHphD7ZDetF225mvWhhSMbpjeVPqXunJ__GjyFjB_Azlwy_k1exgM4wT0auYJe3jI7KGxWPu2gYm2ZlT8A5itGD0npgQ</link>
            <guid>40341687</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 10:45:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://stratechery.com/2024/the-great-flattening/?access_token=eyJhbGciOiJSUzI1NiIsImtpZCI6InN0cmF0ZWNoZXJ5LnBhc3Nwb3J0Lm9ubGluZSIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJhdWQiOiJzdHJhdGVjaGVyeS5wYXNzcG9ydC5vbmxpbmUiLCJhenAiOiJIS0xjUzREd1Nod1AyWURLYmZQV00xIiwiZW50Ijp7InVyaSI6WyJodHRwczovL3N0cmF0ZWNoZXJ5LmNvbS8yMDI0L3RoZS1ncmVhdC1mbGF0dGVuaW5nLyJdfSwiZXhwIjoxNzE4MTg4NzMyLCJpYXQiOjE3MTU1OTY3MzIsImlzcyI6Imh0dHBzOi8vYXBpLnBhc3Nwb3J0Lm9ubGluZS9vYXV0aCIsInNjb3BlIjoiZmVlZDpyZWFkIGFydGljbGU6cmVhZCBhc3NldDpyZWFkIGNhdGVnb3J5OnJlYWQgZW50aXRsZW1lbnRzIiwic3ViIjoiV3NyTHlycjZxZW1WQWdFR0NqTW0zNCIsInVzZSI6ImFjY2VzcyJ9.NgkSZcz_OwkjW7TH6FNBKp7iHS1K6VPyf-xlU6tk1kEXbTuBZzP7kwYsU4WIEpXM4Ab-1DZxZhIus-1-1OtQ6HMi5DdJZqKYcCoARikBeSSkWFtPNGAVpBeOnWzYan2eSUrpGXeuKVq7g5aXv6zNDHoMqHuScb9jE7gFMIa4E3BdafrvjIQ0020M6tUQrm5jinP31XBSQrLUUU2cY_M6QjTn5Hh0CjLUUfNbrJz2yBuvC-egYBpyVersqGIHphD7ZDetF225mvWhhSMbpjeVPqXunJ__GjyFjB_Azlwy_k1exgM4wT0auYJe3jI7KGxWPu2gYm2ZlT8A5itGD0npgQ">https://stratechery.com/2024/the-great-flattening/?access_token=eyJhbGciOiJSUzI1NiIsImtpZCI6InN0cmF0ZWNoZXJ5LnBhc3Nwb3J0Lm9ubGluZSIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJhdWQiOiJzdHJhdGVjaGVyeS5wYXNzcG9ydC5vbmxpbmUiLCJhenAiOiJIS0xjUzREd1Nod1AyWURLYmZQV00xIiwiZW50Ijp7InVyaSI6WyJodHRwczovL3N0cmF0ZWNoZXJ5LmNvbS8yMDI0L3RoZS1ncmVhdC1mbGF0dGVuaW5nLyJdfSwiZXhwIjoxNzE4MTg4NzMyLCJpYXQiOjE3MTU1OTY3MzIsImlzcyI6Imh0dHBzOi8vYXBpLnBhc3Nwb3J0Lm9ubGluZS9vYXV0aCIsInNjb3BlIjoiZmVlZDpyZWFkIGFydGljbGU6cmVhZCBhc3NldDpyZWFkIGNhdGVnb3J5OnJlYWQgZW50aXRsZW1lbnRzIiwic3ViIjoiV3NyTHlycjZxZW1WQWdFR0NqTW0zNCIsInVzZSI6ImFjY2VzcyJ9.NgkSZcz_OwkjW7TH6FNBKp7iHS1K6VPyf-xlU6tk1kEXbTuBZzP7kwYsU4WIEpXM4Ab-1DZxZhIus-1-1OtQ6HMi5DdJZqKYcCoARikBeSSkWFtPNGAVpBeOnWzYan2eSUrpGXeuKVq7g5aXv6zNDHoMqHuScb9jE7gFMIa4E3BdafrvjIQ0020M6tUQrm5jinP31XBSQrLUUU2cY_M6QjTn5Hh0CjLUUfNbrJz2yBuvC-egYBpyVersqGIHphD7ZDetF225mvWhhSMbpjeVPqXunJ__GjyFjB_Azlwy_k1exgM4wT0auYJe3jI7KGxWPu2gYm2ZlT8A5itGD0npgQ</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40341687">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="post-12943">
	<!-- .entry-header -->

	<div>
		<p>Apple did what needed to be done to get that unfortunate iPad ad out of the news; you know, the one that somehow found the crushing of musical instruments and bottles of paint to be inspirational:</p>

<p>The ad was released as a part of <a href="https://stratechery.com/2024/apples-ipad-event-the-peaceful-ipad-disney-earnings/">the company’s iPad event</a>, and was originally scheduled to run on TV; Tor Myhren, Apple’s vice-president of marketing communications, <a href="https://adage.com/article/digital-marketing-ad-tech-news/apple-apologizes-ipad-pro-crushed-ad-it-missed-mark/2559321">told AdAge</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>
  Creativity is in our DNA at Apple, and it’s incredibly important to us to design products that empower creatives all over the world…Our goal is to always celebrate the myriad of ways users express themselves and bring their ideas to life through iPad. We missed the mark with this video, and we’re sorry.
</p></blockquote>
<p>The apology comes across as heartfelt — accentuated by the fact that <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2024/05/09/apple-crush-apology">an Apple executive put his name to it</a> — but I disagree with Myhren: the reason why people reacted so strongly to the ad is that it couldn’t have hit the mark more squarely.</p>
<h3>Aggregation Theory</h3>
<p>The Internet, birthed as it was in the idealism of California tech in the latter parts of the 20th century, was expected to be a force for decentralization; one of the central conceits of this blog has been to explain why reality has been so different. From 2015’s <a href="https://stratechery.com/2015/aggregation-theory/">Aggregation Theory</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>
  The fundamental disruption of the Internet has been to turn this dynamic on its head. First, the Internet has made distribution (of digital goods) free, neutralizing the advantage that pre-Internet distributors leveraged to integrate with suppliers. Secondly, the Internet has made transaction costs zero, making it viable for a distributor to integrate forward with end users/consumers at scale.</p>
<p>  <a href="https://stratechery.com/2015/aggregation-theory/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/stratechery.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Screen-Shot-2018-03-27-at-12.47.09-PM.png?resize=640%2C275&amp;ssl=1" alt="Aggregation Theory" width="640" height="275" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/stratechery.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Screen-Shot-2018-03-27-at-12.47.09-PM.png?w=1816&amp;ssl=1 1816w, https://i0.wp.com/stratechery.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Screen-Shot-2018-03-27-at-12.47.09-PM.png?resize=300%2C129&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/stratechery.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Screen-Shot-2018-03-27-at-12.47.09-PM.png?resize=768%2C330&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/stratechery.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Screen-Shot-2018-03-27-at-12.47.09-PM.png?resize=1024%2C440&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/stratechery.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Screen-Shot-2018-03-27-at-12.47.09-PM.png?resize=1200%2C515&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/stratechery.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Screen-Shot-2018-03-27-at-12.47.09-PM.png?w=1280&amp;ssl=1 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" data-recalc-dims="1"></a></p>
<p>  This has fundamentally changed the plane of competition: no longer do distributors compete based upon exclusive supplier relationships, with consumers/users an afterthought. Instead, suppliers can be commoditized leaving consumers/users as a first order priority. By extension, this means that the most important factor determining success is the user experience: the best distributors/aggregators/market-makers win by providing the best experience, which earns them the most consumers/users, which attracts the most suppliers, which enhances the user experience in a virtuous cycle.
</p></blockquote>
<p>In short, the analog world was defined by scarcity, which meant distribution of scarce goods was the locus of power; the digital world is defined by abundance, which means discovery of what you actually want to see is the locus of power. The result is that consumers have access to anything, which is to say that nothing is special; everything has been flattened.</p>
<ul>
<li>Google broke down every publication in the world into individual pages; search results didn’t deliver you to the front page of a newspaper or magazine, but rather dropped you onto individual articles.</li>
<li>Facebook promoted user-generated content to the same level of the hierarchy as articles from professional publications; your feed might have a picture of your niece followed by a link to a deeply-reported investigative report followed by a meme.</li>
<li>Amazon created the “Everything Store” with practically every item on earth and the capability to deliver it to your doorstep; instead of runnings errands you could simply check-out</li>
<li>Netflix transformed “What’s on?” to “What do you want to watch?”. Everything from high-brow movies to budget flicks to prestige TV to reality TV was on equal footing, ready to be streamed whenever and wherever you wanted.</li>
<li>Sites like Expedia and Booking changed travel from an adventure mediated by a travel agent or long-standing brands to search results organized by price and amenities.</li>
</ul>
<p>Moreover, this was only v1; it turns out that the flattening can go even further:</p>
<ul>
<li>LLMs are breaking down all written text ever into massive models that don’t even bother with pages: they simply give you the answer.</li>
<li>TikTok disabused Meta of the notion that your relationships were a useful constraint on the content you wanted to see; now all short-form video apps surface content from across the entire network based on their understanding of what you individually are interested in.</li>
<li>Amazon is transforming into a logistics powerhouse befitting the fact that Amazon.com is increasingly dominated by 3rd-party merchant sales, and extending that capability throughout the economy.</li>
<li>All of Hollywood, convinced that content was what mattered, jointly killed the linear TV model to ensure that all professionally-produced content was available on-demand, even as the YouTube became the biggest streamer of all with user-generated content that is delivered through the exact same distribution channel (apps on a smart device) as the biggest blockbusters.</li>
<li>Services like Uber and Airbnb commoditized transportation and lodging to the individual driver or homeowner.</li>
</ul>
<p>Apple is absent from this list, although the App Store has had an Aggregator effect on developers; the reason the company belongs, though, and why they were the only company that could make an ad that so perfectly captures this great flattening, is because they created the device on which all of these services operate. The prerequisite to the commoditization of everything is access to anything, thanks to the smartphone. “There’s an app for that” indeed:</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/szrsfeyLzyg?si=wot79Q9zFOfjC-Vw&amp;controls=0" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>
<p>This is what I mean when I say that Apple’s iPad ad hit the mark: the reason why I think the ad resonated so deeply is that it captured something deep in the gestalt that actually has very little to do with trumpets or guitars or bottles of paint; rather, thanks to the Internet — particularly the smartphone-denominated Internet — everything is an app.</p>
<h3>The Bicycle for the Mind</h3>
<p>The more tangible way to see in which that iPad ad hit the mark it to play it in reverse:</p>

<p>This is without question the message that Apple was going for: this one device, thin as can be, contains musical instruments, an artist’s studio, an arcade machine, and more. It brings relationships without borders to life, complete with cute emoji. And it’s not wrong!</p>
<p>Indeed, it harkens back to one of Steve Jobs’ last keynotes, when he introduced the iPad 2. My favorite moment in that keynote — one of my favorite Steve Jobs’ keynote moments ever, in fact — was the introduction of GarageBand. You can <a href="https://videos.files.wordpress.com/pyENUudf/garageband-introduction.mp4">watch the entire introduction and demo</a>, but the part that stands out in my memory is Jobs — clearly sick, in retrospect — moved by what the company had just produced:</p>

<blockquote><p>
  I’m blown away with this stuff. Playing your own instruments, or using the smart instruments, anyone can make music now, in something that’s this thick and weighs 1.3 pounds. It’s unbelievable. GarageBand for iPad. Great set of features — again, this is no toy. This is something you can really use for real work. This is something that, I cannot tell you, how many hours teenagers are going to spend making music with this, and teaching themselves about music with this.
</p></blockquote>
<p>Jobs wasn’t wrong: <a href="https://medium.com/@certifiedmish/artists-who-made-global-hits-with-garageband-32314c0861e1">global hits have originated on GarageBand</a>, and undoubtedly many more hours of (mostly terrible, if my personal experience is any indication) amateur experimentation. Why I think this demo was so personally meaningful for Jobs, though, is that not only was GarageBand about music, one of his deepest passions, but it was also a manifestation of his life’s work: creating a bicycle for the mind.</p>

<blockquote><p>
  I remember reading an Article when I was about 12 years old, I think it might have been in <em>Scientific American</em>, where they measured the efficiency of locomotion for all these species on planet earth. How many kilocalories did they expend to get from point A to point B, and the condor won: it came in at the top of the list, surpassed everything else. And humans came in about a third of the way down the list, which was not such a great showing for the crown of creation.</p>
<p>  But somebody there had the imagination to test the efficiency of a human riding a bicycle. Human riding a bicycle blew away the condor, all the way off the top of the list. And it made a really big impression on me that we humans are tool builders, and that we can fashion tools that amplify these inherent abilities that we have to spectacular magnitudes, and so for me a computer has always been a bicycle of the mind, something that takes us far beyond our inherent abilities.</p>
<p>  I think we’re just at the early stages of this tool, very early stages, and we’ve come only a very short distance, and it’s still in its formation, but already we’ve seen enormous changes, but I think that’s nothing compared to what’s coming in the next 100 years.
</p></blockquote>
<p>In Jobs view of the world, teenagers the world over are potential musicians, who might not be able to afford a piano or guitar or trumpet; if, though, they can get an iPad — now even thinner and lighter! — they can have access to everything they need. In this view “There’s an app for that” is profoundly empowering.</p>
<h3>After the Flattening</h3>
<p>The duality of Apple’s ad speaks to the reality of technology: its impact is structural, and amoral. When I first started Stratechery I wrote a piece called <a href="https://stratechery.com/2013/friction/">Friction</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>
  If there is a single phrase that describes the effect of the Internet, it is the elimination of friction. With the loss of friction, there is necessarily the loss of everything built on friction, including value, privacy, and livelihoods. And that’s only three examples! The Internet is pulling out the foundations of nearly every institution and social more that our society is built upon.</p>
<p>  Count me with those who believe the Internet is on par with the industrial revolution, the full impact of which stretched over centuries. And it wasn’t all good. Like today, the industrial revolution included a period of time that saw many lose their jobs and a massive surge in inequality. It also lifted millions of others out of sustenance farming. Then again, it also propagated slavery, particularly in North America. The industrial revolution led to new monetary systems, and it created robber barons. Modern democracies sprouted from the industrial revolution, and so did fascism and communism. The quality of life of millions and millions was unimaginably improved, and millions and millions died in two unimaginably terrible wars.</p>
<p>  Change is guaranteed, but the type of change is not; never is that more true than today. See, friction makes everything harder, both the good we can do, but also the unimaginably terrible. In our zeal to reduce friction and our eagerness to celebrate the good, we ought not lose sight of the potential bad.
</p></blockquote>
<p>Today that exhortation might run in the opposite direction: in our angst about the removal of specialness and our eagerness to criticize the bad, we ought not lose sight of the potential good.</p>
<p>Start with this site that you are reading: yes, the Internet commoditized content that was previously granted value by virtue of being bundled with a light manufacturing business (i.e. printing presses and delivery trucks), but it also created the opportunity for entirely new kinds of content predicated on reaching niche audiences that are only sustainable when the entire world is your market.</p>
<p>The same principle applies to every other form of content, from music to video to books to art; the extent to which being “special” meant being scarce is the extent to which the existence of “special” meant a constriction of opportunity. Moreover, that opportunity is not a function of privilege but rather consumer demand: the old powers may decry that their content is competing with everyone on the Internet, but they are only losing to the extent that consumers actually prefer to read or watch or listen to something else. Is this supposed to be a bad thing?</p>
<p>Moreover, this is just as much a feather in Apple’s cap as the commoditization of everything is a black mark: Apple creates devices — tools — that let everyone be a creator. Indeed, that is why the ad works in both directions: the flattening of everything means there has been a loss; the flattening of everything also means there is entirely new opportunity.</p>
<h3>The AI Choice</h3>
<p>One thing I do credit Apple for is not trying to erase the ad from the Internet — it’s still posted on <a href="https://twitter.com/tim_cook/status/1787864325258162239">CEO Tim Cook’s X account</a> — because I think it’s important not just as a marker of what has happened over the last several years, but also the choices facing us in the years ahead.</p>
<p>The last time I referenced Steve Jobs’ “Bicycle of the Mind” analogy was in <a href="https://stratechery.com/2018/techs-two-philosophies/">2018’s Tech’s Two Philosophies</a>, where I contrasted Google and Facebook on one side, and Microsoft and Apple on the other: the former wanted to create products that did things for you; the latter products that let you do more things. This was a simplified characterization, to be sure, but, as I noted in that Article, was also related to their traditional positions as Aggregators and platforms, respectively.</p>
<p>What is increasingly clear, though, is that Jobs’ prediction that future changes would be even more profound raise questions about the “bicycle for the mind” analogy itself: specifically, will AI be a bicycle that we control, or an unstoppable train to destinations unknown? To put it in the same terms as the ad, will human will and initiative be flattened, or expanded?</p>
<p>The route to the former seems clear, and maybe even the default: this is a world where a small number of entities “own” AI, and we use it — or are used by it — on their terms. This is the outcome being pushed by those obsessed with “safety”, and demanding regulation and reporting; that those advocates also seem to have a stake in today’s leading models <a href="https://stratechery.com/2023/attenuating-innovation-ai/">seems strangely ignored</a>.</p>
<p>The alternative — <a href="https://stratechery.com/2024/mkbhds-for-everything/">MKBHDs For Everything</a> — means openness and commoditization. Yes, those words have downsides: they mean that the powers that be are not special, and sometimes that is something we lament, as I noted at the beginning of this Article. Our alternative, though, is not the <a href="https://stratechery.com/2017/goodbye-gatekeepers/">gatekept world</a> of the 20th century — <a href="https://stratechery.com/2023/regretful-accelerationism/">we can’t go backwards</a> — but one where the flattening is not the elimination of vitality but the tilling of the ground so that something — many things — new can be created.</p>

	</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Protecting your email address via SVG instead of JavaScript (259 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://rouninmedia.github.io/protecting-your-email-address-via-svg-instead-of-js/</link>
            <guid>40340642</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 07:33:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://rouninmedia.github.io/protecting-your-email-address-via-svg-instead-of-js/">https://rouninmedia.github.io/protecting-your-email-address-via-svg-instead-of-js/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40340642">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      
      
      

      <h2 id="protecting-your-email-address-via-svg-instead-of-js">Protecting your email address via SVG instead of JS</h2>

<p><em>For a live demo of this accessible, no-javascript technique, see:</em></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://rouninmedia.github.io/protecting-your-email-address-via-svg-instead-of-js/svg-email-protection.html"><em>SVG-based Email Protection</em></a></li>
</ul>

<hr>

<p>Email addresses published on webpages usually need to be protected from email-harvesting spambots.</p>

<p>Conventionally, email protection techniques utilise a combination of <strong>HTML</strong>, <strong>CSS</strong> and <strong>JS</strong> - though each approach is subject to its own pros and cons.</p>

<p>In general, approaches involving <strong>JS</strong> tend to be more sophisticated than alternatives based on <strong>HTML</strong> and / or <strong>CSS</strong>.</p>

<p>But the downside is that <strong>JS</strong> then becomes an unavoidable dependency of that page.</p>

<p>There is always benefit in considering the school of thought which advocates that while JS may <em>enhance</em> pages, ideally we should want all the essential functionality on those pages to work even while JavaScript is turned off.</p>

<hr>

<p>The technique detailed on this page utilises an an approach entirely different from conventional email protection techniques, based on <strong>CSS</strong>, <strong>JS</strong>, <strong>CSS + JS</strong> etc.</p>

<p>Because <em>this</em> technique is based on <strong>SVG</strong>.</p>

<p><strong>N.B.</strong> <em>This technique - and any other email-protection technique utilising front-end-technologies - <strong>won’t</strong> protect your published email address from being harvested by the most determined and sophisticated spambots. But, as with many JS-based email-protection techniques, it <strong>will</strong> protect you nevertheless from a great many unsophisticated harvesters and keep your email successfully hidden from any simple or amateurish scripts trawling the web, seeking to copy any unprotected email addresses they find.</em></p>

<hr>

<h2 id="three-advantages-of-an-svg-based-approach-to-protecting-email-addresses">Three advantages of an SVG-based approach to protecting email addresses</h2>

<h3 id="1-works-with-javascript-turned-off">1. Works with JavaScript turned off</h3>
<p>The main advantage of this <strong>SVG-based approach</strong> to protecting emails, is that it involves <strong>no JavaScript</strong>.</p>

<p>As such, even when a human visitor has their JavaScript turned off, the email address displayed on the page remains usable, accessible and protected, while remaining secure and hidden from spambots.</p>

<h3 id="2-permits-a-standard-mailto-link">2. Permits a standard <code>mailto:</code> link</h3>
<p>Unlike other <em>no-JavaScript-required</em> approaches (e.g. obfuscating email addresses by inserting non-visible HTML Comments or inserting visible elements and subsequently hiding them via CSS), this <strong>SVG-based approach</strong> allows for standard <code>mailto:</code> links. The twist is: the <code>mailto:</code> link exists inside the external <strong>SVG document</strong>, <em>not</em> inside the referring <strong>HTML document</strong>.</p>

<h3 id="3-conceals-content-like-an-image-copyable-like-text">3. Conceals content like an image; Copyable like text</h3>

<p>A third advantage is that embedded <strong>SVGs</strong> are <em>image-like</em> but <em>not</em> images.</p>

<p>As replaced elements embedded within a hypertext document, <strong>SVGs</strong> may conceal an email address from spambots nearly as effectively as an image might.</p>

<p>But, strictly, <strong>SVGs</strong> are <em>graphics documents</em> rather than actual images.</p>

<p>Consequently, <em>unlike with an image</em>, a human visitor may still copy the email address by <strong>right-clicking</strong> on the <code>&lt;text&gt;</code> element in the embedded <strong>SVG</strong>.</p>

<p>This would not be possible with a conventional image.</p>

<hr>

<h2 id="implementing-the-code">Implementing the Code</h2>

<p>In the example below there are two files.</p>

<p>The SVG graphics document is embedded in the HTML hypertext document via:</p>

<div><pre><code>&lt;object data="svg-email-protection.svg" type="image/svg+xml" /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;
</code></pre></div>

<p>Note that the same SVG graphics document may be embedded in hypertext once - or multiple times.</p>

<h3 id="html-file">HTML File</h3>

<div><pre><code><span>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;</span>
<span>&lt;html</span> <span>lang=</span><span>"en-GB"</span><span>&gt;</span>
<span>&lt;head&gt;</span>
<span>&lt;meta</span> <span>charset=</span><span>"utf-8"</span><span>&gt;</span>
<span>&lt;title&gt;</span>SVG Email Protection<span>&lt;/title&gt;</span>
    
<span>&lt;style&gt;</span>
    
<span>.svg-email-protection</span> <span>{</span>
  <span>width</span><span>:</span> <span>180px</span><span>;</span>
  <span>height</span><span>:</span> <span>24px</span><span>;</span>
  <span>vertical-align</span><span>:</span> <span>middle</span><span>;</span>
<span>}</span>
    
<span>&lt;/style&gt;</span>
<span>&lt;/head&gt;</span>

<span>&lt;body&gt;</span>

<span>&lt;p&gt;</span>This is my email: <span>&lt;object</span> <span>class=</span><span>"svg-email-protection"</span> <span>data=</span><span>"svg-email-protection.svg"</span> <span>type=</span><span>"image/svg+xml"</span><span>&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</span>

<span>&lt;/body&gt;</span>
<span>&lt;/html&gt;</span>
</code></pre></div>

<h3 id="svg-file">SVG File</h3>
<pre><code>&lt;svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
     lang="en-GB"
     aria-labelledby="title"
     viewBox="0 0 200 24"&gt;

  &lt;title id="title"&gt;Email Us!&lt;/title&gt;

  &lt;defs&gt;

  &lt;style type="text/css"&gt;&lt;![CDATA[

  rect {
    width: 200px;
    height: 24px;
    fill: rgb(255, 255, 255);
  }

  a:focus rect,
  rect:hover {
    rx: 4px;
    ry: 4px;
    fill: rgb(0, 0, 255);
  }

  text {
    font-size: 16px;
    fill: rgb(0, 0, 255);
    pointer-events: none;
  }

  a:focus text,
  rect:hover + text {
    fill: rgb(255, 255, 255);
    font-weight: 900;
    text-shadow: 1px 1px 1px rgba(0, 0, 0, 0.2);
    text-decoration: underline 1px solid rgb(255, 255, 255);
    text-underline-offset: 5px;
  }

  ]]&gt;&lt;/style&gt;

  &lt;/defs&gt;

  &lt;a href="mailto:myemail@mydomain.tld" aria-label="Email Us!"&gt;
    &lt;rect /&gt;
    &lt;text x="50%" y="50%" text-anchor="middle" dominant-baseline="middle"&gt;myemail@mydomain.tld&lt;/text&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/svg&gt;
</code></pre>

<hr>

<h2 id="accessibility">Accessibility</h2>

<p>As ever, it’s important to ensure that this setup remains as <strong><em>accessible</em></strong> as possible.</p>

<p>On this basis, note the following in the SVG graphics document:</p>

<ul>
  <li>the entire SVG document is <code>aria-labelledby</code> the SVG document <code>&lt;title&gt;</code>, indicating a call-to-action</li>
  <li>the anchor element (<code>&lt;a&gt;</code>) inside the SVG has an <code>aria-label</code> which has the same call-to-action</li>
  <li>the SVG is styled such that when the <em>tab-focus</em> falls on the anchor element (<code>&lt;a&gt;</code>), the child-elements, <code>&lt;rect /&gt;</code> and the <code>&lt;text /&gt;</code>, are both highlighted</li>
</ul>

<hr>

<p><em>To see a live demo of this accessible, no-javascript technique, go to:</em></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://rouninmedia.github.io/protecting-your-email-address-via-svg-instead-of-js/svg-email-protection.html"><em>SVG-based Email Protection</em></a></li>
</ul>


      
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ordered back to the office, top tech talent left instead, study finds (117 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/2024/05/12/rto-microsoft-apple-spacex/</link>
            <guid>40339852</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 04:43:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/2024/05/12/rto-microsoft-apple-spacex/">https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/2024/05/12/rto-microsoft-apple-spacex/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40339852">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/2024/05/12/rto-microsoft-apple-spacex/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Fort Worth's tallest building sells for $12.3M, bought for $137.5M in 2021 (101 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.foxbusiness.com/real-estate/fort-worths-tallest-building-sells-just-12-3m-auction-stunning-price-drop</link>
            <guid>40339415</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 03:00:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.foxbusiness.com/real-estate/fort-worths-tallest-building-sells-just-12-3m-auction-stunning-price-drop">https://www.foxbusiness.com/real-estate/fort-worths-tallest-building-sells-just-12-3m-auction-stunning-price-drop</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40339415">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><!----> <!---->  <p>Bargain buy?</p> <p>Burnett Plaza, the tallest building in <a href="https://www.foxbusiness.com/category/fox-news-dallas-fort-worth" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fort Worth, Texas</a>, has been purchased via foreclosure auction for $12.3 million just three years after it was sold for more than $137.5 million, according to the Dallas Business Journal.</p><p>The 40-story behemoth was bought back by Pinnacle Bank Texas in the auction held on the steps of the Tarrant County courthouse on Tuesday.&nbsp;</p> <p>Pinnacle had claimed in public filings that the tower's former owner, Burnett Cherry Street LLC, an affiliate of New York-based Opal Holdings LLC, defaulted on a $13 million loan used to purchase the building in 2021.</p> <p><a href="https://www.foxbusiness.com/economy/cost-buying-house-hit-another-record-high-mortgage-rates-spike-again"><strong>THE COST OF BUYING A HOUSE HIT ANOTHER RECORD HIGH AS MORTGAGE RATES SPIKE AGAIN</strong></a></p><div><div><picture><source media="(max-width: 767px)" srcset="https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2024/05/343/192/Burnett-Plaza-Fort-Worth-Texas-2.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1, https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2024/05/686/384/Burnett-Plaza-Fort-Worth-Texas-2.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1 2x"> <source media="(min-width: 768px) and (max-width: 1023px)" srcset="https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2024/05/672/378/Burnett-Plaza-Fort-Worth-Texas-2.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1, https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2024/05/1344/756/Burnett-Plaza-Fort-Worth-Texas-2.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1 2x"> <source media="(min-width: 1024px) and (max-width: 1279px)" srcset="https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2024/05/931/523/Burnett-Plaza-Fort-Worth-Texas-2.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1, https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2024/05/1862/1046/Burnett-Plaza-Fort-Worth-Texas-2.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1 2x"> <source media="(min-width: 1280px)" srcset="https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2024/05/720/405/Burnett-Plaza-Fort-Worth-Texas-2.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1, https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2024/05/1440/810/Burnett-Plaza-Fort-Worth-Texas-2.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1 2x"> <img src="https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2024/05/931/523/Burnett-Plaza-Fort-Worth-Texas-2.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1" alt="Burnett Plaza, in Fort Worth, Texas."></picture></div> <p><span>Burnett Plaza, the tallest building in Fort Worth, Texas, has been bought for $12.3 million, three years after it sold $137.5 million.</span><span> (Google Maps)</span></p></div><p>The bank bought it back with a roughly $12.3 million credit bid, just&nbsp;$12.30 per square foot.</p><p>As well as being the tallest in Fort Worth, Burnett Plaza is also considered the largest, with over one million square feet of commercial office and <a href="https://www.foxbusiness.com/real-estate" target="_blank" rel="noopener">retail space</a>, according to its website.&nbsp;</p><p><a href="https://www.foxbusiness.com/real-estate/martha-stewart-nabs-12-million-nyc-pad-building-featured-hulus-hit-show"><strong>MARTHA STEWART NABS $12 MILLION NYC PAD IN BUILDING FEATURED IN HULU'S HIT SHOW</strong></a></p><div><div><picture><source media="(max-width: 767px)" srcset="https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2023/05/343/192/Fort-Worth-Texas-skyline.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1, https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2023/05/686/384/Fort-Worth-Texas-skyline.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1 2x"> <source media="(min-width: 768px) and (max-width: 1023px)" srcset="https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2023/05/672/378/Fort-Worth-Texas-skyline.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1, https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2023/05/1344/756/Fort-Worth-Texas-skyline.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1 2x"> <source media="(min-width: 1024px) and (max-width: 1279px)" srcset="https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2023/05/931/523/Fort-Worth-Texas-skyline.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1, https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2023/05/1862/1046/Fort-Worth-Texas-skyline.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1 2x"> <source media="(min-width: 1280px)" srcset="https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2023/05/720/405/Fort-Worth-Texas-skyline.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1, https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2023/05/1440/810/Fort-Worth-Texas-skyline.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1 2x"> <img src="https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2023/05/931/523/Fort-Worth-Texas-skyline.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1" alt="Fort Worth Texas skyline"></picture></div> <p><span>A view of downtown Fort Worth, Texas.</span><span> (iStock / iStock)</span></p></div><p>Constructed in 1983, the distinctive block-sized complex stands at 567 feet tall at 801 Cherry St. and is surrounded by a public urban park.</p><p>It was most recently appraised at $104.5 million by Tarrant Appraisal District, according to the Dallas Business Journal. Tenants include <a href="https://www.foxbusiness.com/category/gm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">General Motors Financial</a>, Kimley-Horn and Associates, Huckabee, as well as Freese and Nichols.</p><p>The Dallas Business Journal reports that contractors filed 10&nbsp;mechanic’s liens&nbsp;totaling more than $1.6 million against Opal, alleging unpaid renovation work at the site. The largest, amounting to nearly $1 million, was filed by Tarrant Construction Services for renovations of two suites and the 19th-floor bathrooms.&nbsp;</p><p><a href="https://foxbusiness.onelink.me/Zkcx?pid=AppArticleLink&amp;af_dp=foxbusinesssaf%3A%2F%2F&amp;af_web_dp=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.foxbusiness.com%2Fapps-products" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong>GET FOX BUSINESS ON THE GO BY CLICKING HERE</strong></a></p><div><div><picture><source media="(max-width: 767px)" srcset="https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2024/05/343/192/Burnett-Plaza-Fort-Worth-Texas.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1, https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2024/05/686/384/Burnett-Plaza-Fort-Worth-Texas.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1 2x"> <source media="(min-width: 768px) and (max-width: 1023px)" srcset="https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2024/05/672/378/Burnett-Plaza-Fort-Worth-Texas.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1, https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2024/05/1344/756/Burnett-Plaza-Fort-Worth-Texas.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1 2x"> <source media="(min-width: 1024px) and (max-width: 1279px)" srcset="https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2024/05/931/523/Burnett-Plaza-Fort-Worth-Texas.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1, https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2024/05/1862/1046/Burnett-Plaza-Fort-Worth-Texas.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1 2x"> <source media="(min-width: 1280px)" srcset="https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2024/05/720/405/Burnett-Plaza-Fort-Worth-Texas.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1, https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2024/05/1440/810/Burnett-Plaza-Fort-Worth-Texas.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1 2x"> <img src="https://a57.foxnews.com/static.foxbusiness.com/foxbusiness.com/content/uploads/2024/05/931/523/Burnett-Plaza-Fort-Worth-Texas.jpg?ve=1&amp;tl=1" alt="Burnett Plaza, in Fort Worth, Texas."></picture></div> <p><span>The 40-story behemoth was bought back by Pinnacle Bank Texas in an auction after it claimed the previous owners defaulted</span><span> (Google Maps / Google Maps)</span></p></div><p>Opal sued Pinnacle on April 2, alleging the lender pushed the building into default, the outlet reported.</p><p>Burnett Plaza’s vacancy was at 22 percent last quarter, The Real Deal reports, citing Cushman &amp; Wakefield, with vacancy in Downtown Fort Worth&nbsp;much lower at 11.5 percent.</p><p>Pinnacle also bought back a four-building Centerpoint office park in Arlington from the firm at the auction for $30 million, according to&nbsp;the Dallas Business Journal.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: CarCheck – Car Buying Checklist App (156 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://usefulchecklists.com/</link>
            <guid>40339405</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 02:56:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://usefulchecklists.com/">https://usefulchecklists.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40339405">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-astro-cid-j7pv25f6=""> <div> <div>  <p>
Checklists for everyday things.
</p> </div> <div> <p>Available Now!</p> <p><img src="https://usefulchecklists.com/images/carcheck-icon.png" alt="Car Check" width="80" height="80" loading="lazy" decoding="async"></p><p>CarCheck</p> <p>Your Car Pre-Purchase Checklist Partner.</p> <div> <p><a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/carcheck-useful-checklists/id6478466680"> <img src="https://usefulchecklists.com/images/AppleBlack.svg" alt="AppStoreImage" width="150" height="100" loading="lazy" decoding="async"> </a> </p> <p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.usefulchecklists.carcheck"> <img src="https://usefulchecklists.com/images/PlayStore.png" alt="AppStoreImage" width="150" height="100" loading="lazy" decoding="async"> </a> </p> </div> </div> </div> <div id="features"> <p> <h2>
CarCheck Features
</h2> </p>  </div> <section id="roadmap"> <div>  <h2>
Roadmap
</h2> </div> <div> <div>  <p><img src="https://usefulchecklists.com/images/custom.png" alt="Car Check" width="80" height="80" loading="lazy" decoding="async"></p><p>Custom Checklists</p> <ul> <li>Basic TODO</li> <li>Pass/Fail</li> <li>Percentage slider</li> </ul> </div> <div>  <p><img src="https://usefulchecklists.com/images/unified.png" alt="Car Check" width="80" height="80" loading="lazy" decoding="async"></p><p>Unified App</p> <ul> <li>Create a Useful Checklists app</li> <li>CarCheck added into generic branded app</li> <li>Begin adding other checklists (HouseCheck, BoatCheck)</li> </ul> </div>  </div> <div> <div>  <p><img src="https://usefulchecklists.com/images/server.png" alt="Car Check" width="80" height="80" loading="lazy" decoding="async"></p><p>Backend Infratructure</p> <ul> <li>User Accounts</li> <li>Cloud Sync</li> </ul> </div> <div>  <p><img src="https://usefulchecklists.com/images/web.png" alt="Car Check" width="80" height="80" loading="lazy" decoding="async"></p><p>Access on Web</p> <ul> <li>Login on web</li> <li>Online dashboard</li> </ul> </div>  </div> <div>  <p><img src="https://usefulchecklists.com/images/share.png" alt="Car Check" width="80" height="80" loading="lazy" decoding="async"></p><p>Sharable Checklists</p> <ul> <li>Create and share unique checklists</li> </ul> </div> </section> <div data-astro-cid-j7pv25f6="" id="signup"> <p data-astro-cid-j7pv25f6=""> <h3 data-astro-cid-j7pv25f6="">
Sign up to our mailing list!
</h3> </p> <p data-astro-cid-j7pv25f6="">
Get updates on new checklists and features.
</p>  </div> </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Open Source YouTube to MP3 Downloader (118 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/PackJC/YoutubeToMP3</link>
            <guid>40338967</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 01:22:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/PackJC/YoutubeToMP3">https://github.com/PackJC/YoutubeToMP3</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40338967">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">YoutubeToMP3</h2><a id="user-content-youtubetomp3" aria-label="Permalink: YoutubeToMP3" href="#youtubetomp3"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/34726562/329894214-d363050e-b42e-4c16-8edf-ab1f6574faa6.gif?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MTU1OTQ3MDQsIm5iZiI6MTcxNTU5NDQwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii8zNDcyNjU2Mi8zMjk4OTQyMTQtZDM2MzA1MGUtYjQyZS00YzE2LThlZGYtYWIxZjY1NzRmYWE2LmdpZj9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDA1MTMlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQwNTEzVDEwMDAwNFomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPWRiNDA1NjliZDVkNTAyZTE2Mjc5MTkyODVmYTdkYjBmN2VjMDI2YWIwMTE3NTQ3NjhiZDRhMjdkZGI2YTYyMDEmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0JmFjdG9yX2lkPTAma2V5X2lkPTAmcmVwb19pZD0wIn0.XibTjFXntxIYGBBi818EhXKHn-1Rsvz_K8q7GA3UM9g"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/34726562/329894214-d363050e-b42e-4c16-8edf-ab1f6574faa6.gif?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MTU1OTQ3MDQsIm5iZiI6MTcxNTU5NDQwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii8zNDcyNjU2Mi8zMjk4OTQyMTQtZDM2MzA1MGUtYjQyZS00YzE2LThlZGYtYWIxZjY1NzRmYWE2LmdpZj9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDA1MTMlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQwNTEzVDEwMDAwNFomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPWRiNDA1NjliZDVkNTAyZTE2Mjc5MTkyODVmYTdkYjBmN2VjMDI2YWIwMTE3NTQ3NjhiZDRhMjdkZGI2YTYyMDEmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0JmFjdG9yX2lkPTAma2V5X2lkPTAmcmVwb19pZD0wIn0.XibTjFXntxIYGBBi818EhXKHn-1Rsvz_K8q7GA3UM9g" alt="Animation" data-animated-image=""></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This Windows Forms application in C# allows users to download YouTube videos as MP3 files. Users can enter a YouTube URL, and upon clicking the download button, the app uses YoutubeExplode to fetch and download the video. A progress bar updates in real-time, showing the download progress. After downloading, the app converts the video to MP3 using MediaToolkit. Users choose the save location for the MP3 file via a SaveFileDialog. A completion notification pops up once the process is complete. This app provides a user-friendly way to convert YouTube videos into MP3s directly from the desktop.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Scott Galloway: How the US is destroying young people's future [video] (104 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ted.com/talks/scott_galloway_how_the_us_is_destroying_young_people_s_future</link>
            <guid>40338619</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 00:24:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/scott_galloway_how_the_us_is_destroying_young_people_s_future">https://www.ted.com/talks/scott_galloway_how_the_us_is_destroying_young_people_s_future</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40338619">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-testid="talk-description"><p><span data-testid="talk-description-text" dir="ltr">In a scorching talk, marketing professor and podcaster Scott Galloway dissects the data showing that, by many measures, young people in the US are worse off financially than ever before. He unpacks the root causes and effects of this "great intergenerational theft," asking why we let it continue and showing how we could make it end. (Note: This talk contains mature language.)</span></p><ul><li><a href="https://www.ted.com/topics/politics">politics</a></li><li><a href="https://www.ted.com/topics/technology">technology</a></li><li><a href="https://www.ted.com/topics/business">business</a></li><li><a href="https://www.ted.com/topics/economics">economics</a></li><li><a href="https://www.ted.com/topics/future">future</a></li><li><a href="https://www.ted.com/topics/united+states">United States</a></li><li><a href="https://www.ted.com/topics/society">society</a></li><li><a href="https://www.ted.com/topics/government">government</a></li><li><a href="https://www.ted.com/topics/youth">youth</a></li><li><a href="https://www.ted.com/topics/policy">policy</a></li><li><a href="https://www.ted.com/topics/kids">kids</a></li></ul></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Star Destroyer and Imperial Military Doctrine (129 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://acoup.blog/2024/05/10/fireside-friday-may-10-2024/</link>
            <guid>40338517</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 00:04:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://acoup.blog/2024/05/10/fireside-friday-may-10-2024/">https://acoup.blog/2024/05/10/fireside-friday-may-10-2024/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40338517">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
		
<p>Fireside this week!  Next week, with luck, I’ll have my ‘On the Reign of Alexander III of Macedon’ up as an addendum to our discussion of Hellenistic armies.  But in the meantime, it is a fireside, and I thought, since it was just recently May the Fourth, we might talk some Star Wars (and history).  So this is going to be a bit silly this week.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" data-attachment-id="23981" data-permalink="https://acoup.blog/2024/05/10/fireside-friday-may-10-2024/pxl_20240505_171735432-mp_/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171735432.MP_.jpg?fit=4032%2C3024&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="4032,3024" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Pixel 3a&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1714915055&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;4.44&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;419&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.041667&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="PXL_20240505_171735432.MP_" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171735432.MP_.jpg?fit=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171735432.MP_.jpg?fit=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1" src="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171735432.MP_.jpg?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171735432.MP_.jpg?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171735432.MP_.jpg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171735432.MP_.jpg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171735432.MP_.jpg?resize=1536%2C1152&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171735432.MP_.jpg?resize=2048%2C1536&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171735432.MP_.jpg?resize=1200%2C900&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171735432.MP_.jpg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171735432.MP_.jpg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171735432.MP_.jpg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171735432.MP_.jpg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171735432.MP_.jpg?resize=1100%2C825&amp;ssl=1 1100w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171735432.MP_.jpg?w=2200&amp;ssl=1 2200w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171735432.MP_.jpg?w=3300&amp;ssl=1 3300w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" data-recalc-dims="1"><figcaption>The completed Lego Star Destroyer.</figcaption></figure>



<p>For this week’s <strong>musing</strong>, over the last week, as part of my May the Fourth celebration (and some enforced post-semester relaxation), I went and built the Lego Star Destroyer my better half bought for me (about a year ago – the space for building it got consumed by other things in the intervening time).  This is not the <em>very old</em> (2002) Star Destroyer kit, nor the very newest (2024) kit, but the finely aged (2019) ‘Ultimate Collector’ set, coming in at a massive 4,700 pieces.  It was fun to build and there’s actually a lot of kind of neat engineering and design that clearly went in to making it work.  With so many pieces, the set is so <em>heavy</em> that it needs a whole reinforcing frame (also made of legos) to hold it together internally.</p>



<p>But that got me thinking about Star Destroyers (<a href="https://acoup.blog/2019/12/20/collections-starships-in-silhouette/" data-type="post" data-id="1960">not the first time</a>) and Star Wars, so I figured I’d muse a bit at you both about the odd place of Star Destroyers in imperial military doctrine and also the nature of the Old Republic and the Empire as polities.</p>



<p>So let’s star with the obvious about the design of the Imperial Star Destroyer (ISD), which is that it was designed (for the screen) to <em>look</em> a certain way, rather than as a function fighting machine.  And as that sort of design, the ISD is brilliant.  The lower hull seems to have been planned out for that massive opening shot: the long, flat sections make it feel like the ship goes on <em>forever</em>, while the three breaks in the shape (the two docking hangers and the bulge over the reactor) break up the monotony.  The <em>two</em> docking bays, a smaller one first and then a much larger one, also stress the ship’s gargantuan size: the viewer see’s what they think is the primary hanger, and then, wait, no, <em>there’s another, much bigger one</em> and then the ship <em>doesn’t end</em>.  The rear of the ship, with its massive brace of engines, also manages to communicate that this behemoth might also be <em>fast</em> as well as large.  And then when we see the thing from the front, the presence of its raised superstructure immediately communicates its primary role as a battleship, because it has a similar sort of superstructure to WWII-era battleships, with that raised command tower looming over a superstructure above the main structure.  It is simultaneously different enough from any real vehicle to be immediately memorable – not merely a battleship stuck in space – but at the same time, shares enough design language for the audience to intuit its role immediately.</p>



<p>As an aside, I think this is something the ISD design does a lot better than many more recent similar efforts.  Both new Star Wars (particularly the sequel films) and new Star Trek (particularly <em>Discovery </em>and <em>Picard</em>) have a problem with villain ships which are wildly out of scale with the existing designs in the setting, but which are essentially just blown-up versions of existing visual language (<em>Discovery</em>‘s <em>Dreadnought</em> and <em>The Rise of Skywalker</em>‘s <em>Xyston</em>-class both come to mind).  Even the First Order Star Destroyers often felt like they had to be massively <em>bigger</em> than the ISD because they otherwise lacked new ideas.  But the ISD itself was pretty fresh as a concept and delivers on it extremely well (and the SSD is a better, “that, but bigger, scarier and in Vadar’s theme colors” variant than anything in the sequel trilogy).</p>



<p>Of course, the ISD initially existed without any context – it is the <em>second</em> thing we see on screen after the crawl (not counting planets) – but it eventually got one, a design lineage from the Republic-era <em>Venator</em>.  And this creates a bit of an oddity, because in the Clone Wars, the Republic fleet is essentially built around fast carriers – the <em>Venators</em> – and their fighters, whereas it is the CIS fleet which has specialized gunboats (along with the slower Lucrehulks that function as carriers), but by the time we get to the Empire, the doctrine has switched: the ISD is clearly a gun platform first and foremost, which carries its own fighter screen, but expects to win with its primary battery, not its (flimsy) TIE-Fighters, while it is the Rebellion that eventually adopts a fast-carrier kind of doctrine.</p>



<p>Now, the out-of-universe reason for this is that George Lucas thinks it is cool to have the protagonists flying fighters against big enemy battleships and so that is the doctrine he gives to the ‘good guys’ in each films.  I wonder if that is itself an influence from the Second World War (and the war films Lucas studied to block out his space battle sequences), where the early phases (particularly 1942) in the Pacific were the plucky efforts of a few American fast carriers and cruisers against fleets loaded with imposing-looking battleships.  It also, of course, makes storytelling sense: the characters we care about can be in the fighters, while the bad guys in their big Death Stars and Star Destroyers are distant, powerful and imposing.</p>



<p>But it creates a lore problem, which is, ‘why did the Galactic Empire entirely change its doctrine <em>after</em> winning the Clone Wars?’  ‘Legends’ canon – that is, the pre-Disney canon – had its answer, which is that ‘it didn’t.’  Instead, there was a longer progression of ship designs late in the Clone Wars, from the carrier-oriented <em>Venator</em> and <em>Accalamator</em> to the up-gunned version, the <em>Victory</em>-class Star Destroyer (VSD), which was supposed to be a late-Clone Wars design which serves as the bridge from to the ISD.  With the VSD in the design lineage, the ISD makes sense: the Empire deployed, late in the war, a more gun-based platform, then won the war and continued development along that ‘successful’ design lineage, producing an extreme version of the VSD in the ISD.</p>



<p>The Canon (‘Disney-Canon’) <em>technically</em> has the same narrative (the <a href="https://starwars.fandom.com/wiki/Victory-class_Star_Destroyer" data-type="link" data-id="https://starwars.fandom.com/wiki/Victory-class_Star_Destroyer">VSD is technically still canon, according to Wookiepedia</a>), but has never put the VSD on screen. In the scenes where we <em>ought</em> to see a transitional VSD, we instead see an ISD, and the new canon has also removed one of the main ‘Legends’ advantages the VSD had: in legends, the VSD was capable of atmospheric flight, but the ISD was not, but in canon, the ISD now can do that. The reason here, I have to assume is that brand new models are expensive and Disney would rather keep reusing and modifying <em>Rogue One</em>‘s very high-quality ISD-I model <em>forever</em> if necessary, even in places where it makes no sense, like for the <em>Xyston</em>-class or in games set after the Battle of Endor. If Disney can’t be bothered to make a high-detail ISD-II model, they surely can’t be bothered to work up a new VSD model.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" data-attachment-id="23983" data-permalink="https://acoup.blog/2024/05/10/fireside-friday-may-10-2024/pxl_20240505_171251219-mp_/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171251219.MP_-rotated.jpg?fit=4032%2C3024&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="4032,3024" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Pixel 3a&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1714914771&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;4.44&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;825&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.041667&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="PXL_20240505_171251219.MP_" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171251219.MP_-rotated.jpg?fit=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171251219.MP_-rotated.jpg?fit=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1" src="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171251219.MP_.jpg?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171251219.MP_-rotated.jpg?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171251219.MP_-rotated.jpg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171251219.MP_-rotated.jpg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171251219.MP_-rotated.jpg?resize=1536%2C1152&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171251219.MP_-rotated.jpg?resize=2048%2C1536&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171251219.MP_-rotated.jpg?resize=1200%2C900&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171251219.MP_-rotated.jpg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171251219.MP_-rotated.jpg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171251219.MP_-rotated.jpg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171251219.MP_-rotated.jpg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171251219.MP_-rotated.jpg?resize=1100%2C825&amp;ssl=1 1100w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171251219.MP_-rotated.jpg?w=2200&amp;ssl=1 2200w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240505_171251219.MP_-rotated.jpg?w=3300&amp;ssl=1 3300w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" data-recalc-dims="1"><figcaption>Front view of the set, where you can see that it comes with a Tantive IV CR90 Corvette to scale (it fits neatly into the docking bay).<span id="easy-footnote-1-23926"></span><span><a href="#easy-footnote-bottom-1-23926" title="As an aside, one of the silliest things in the sequel trilogy lore was bringing back not just <em>a</em> CR90, but insisting that the Resistance&amp;#8217;s CR90 was a <a href=&quot;https://starwars.fandom.com/wiki/Tantive_IV#Return_and_destruction.&quot; data-type=&quot;link&quot; data-id=&quot;https://starwars.fandom.com/wiki/Tantive_IV#Return_and_destruction.&quot;>recovered Tantive IV</a>.  The &amp;#8216;Legends&amp;#8217; canon has Vader do the obvious thing to complete the ruse of sending a distress signal and then reporting the ship destroyed in an accident, which was, of course, <strong>to destroy the ship and kill the crew</strong>, thereby leaving no evidence behind, a thing <strong>Darth Vader</strong> is obviously ruthless enough to do."><sup>1</sup></a></span></figcaption></figure>



<p>But I think I can actually puzzle out a ‘history of the Galactic Empire’ which makes a bit of sense and into which the ISD has an understandable – if not <em>sound</em> – doctrinal place.  First, we need to understand what kind of polity the Old Republic – and thus the Empire – <em>is</em>.  And here, the phrasing I go to (somewhat imprecise) is that the Republic was a ‘Republic of Princes’ in the same sense that the Holy Roman Empire was an empire of ‘princes’ or more technically ‘imperial states.’<span id="easy-footnote-2-23926"></span><span><a href="#easy-footnote-bottom-2-23926" title="As I understand it in technical terms, a &amp;#8216;prince&amp;#8217; of the HRE was a direct vassal of the emperor; many imperial states were &amp;#8216;princes&amp;#8217; &amp;#8211; including some archbishoprics &amp;#8211; but not all were.  However, I find when explaining this to folks, the idea of a &amp;#8216;government of princes&amp;#8217; makes a lot more sense than &amp;#8216;a government of states.&amp;#8217;"><sup>2</sup></a></span>  I promise we will get back to Star Destroyers here eventually.</p>



<p>In short, the Republic was not a democracy of <em>people</em> but a republic of <em>states</em>, the ‘princes’ which in turn governed their own territory internally.  These ‘princes’ could be any form of government.  And indeed, the imperial states of the Holy Roman Empire could be noble rulers, but also bishops ruling cities (the ‘prince-archbishops’), monks running abbeys (Imperial prelates), grandmasters running holy orders, and even cities governing themselves (free and imperial cities).  So too with the Republic, which is why the Trade Federation can sit on the Senate alongside democratic Naboo and monarchic Alderaan.</p>



<p>Crucially, each of these ‘princes’ is internally self-governing, but also has its own military, some large and some small, and its own resource base with which to <em>develop</em> such a military.</p>



<p>Given that, what I think a historian of this period, looking back would conclude about the Star Wars story would be this: the Clone Wars were essentially a civil war between the princes of the Rim territories against the princes of the core regions (as the later effectively ruled the senate).  That civil war produced political momentum among some of the core princes towards centralization, which fuels the career of Palpatine.  Palpatine’s reign and the Empire in general is thus understood as a reaction to the Clone Wars primarily aimed at centralizing power at the expense of the princes.</p>



<p>That in turn produced two related reactions.  On the one hand, it produces obvious discontent among the ‘princes’ themselves – the ruling classes of these planets.  The Bail Organas and Mon Mothmas.  But the centralization also begins to disintermediate the princely governments themselves, suddenly exposing their citizens to <em>direct</em> rule by the empire (we see this quite clearly in <em>Andor</em>) and it turns out, they don’t like it.  After all, you have to imagine generations of local government means all of these planets have different assumptions about their rights and customs, and now here comes the Stormtroopers attempting to institute <em>one</em> law and <em>one</em> custom.  That creates a separate but symbiotic <em>popular</em> movement against the empire, which the princes are able to co-opt into their rebel alliance, promising that a return to princely government will mean a return to the traditional liberties and customs.</p>



<p>As this is happening, the Imperial Navy is in a state of change.  During the Clone Wars, it was fighting a peer adversary using a fast-carrier doctrine aiming to win a war that was already raging.  But now there are <em>simmering</em> tensions which the Imperial Navy is supposed to tamp down.  As a result, imperial designers reach for <strong>escalation dominance</strong> in their designs, aiming to build ships which can, on their own, <em>intimidate</em> the militaries of the princes – because remember, the ‘princes’ (planetary governments of whatever form) <em>all have their own</em> <em>small navies</em> – in order to avoid a conflict.  The ISD is the end result of that design philosophy: a gun-platform powerful enough to be effectively beyond the ability of any planetary princely navy to fight effectively.</p>



<p>Those same designers are <em>also</em>, of course, dealing with a bubbling hit-and-run insurgency, which manifests as popular insurgents whose weapons and resources clearly suggest they are being funded and supplied, in secret, by some of the princes.  Those same imperial designers respond by emphasizing <strong>force protection</strong>, to try to keep the key imperial assets well-enough armored and defended so as to limit the damage of ambush and hit-and-run.  In this sense, an ISD is a gigantic MRAP (Mine-Resistant Ambush-Protected vehicle; a kind of vehicle designed for the Global War on Terror).  Sure, it’s less <em>practical</em> than the more Humvee-like <em>Venators</em>, but its size and firepower places it beyond the capability of rebel hit-and-run attacks, allowing it to deliver its troops and firepower in safety.</p>



<p>Of course, it risks exactly the same problem that MRAPs do: troops buttoned up on their force-protection-oriented vehicles may be safe (though they may not be), but they’re not <em>accomplishing the mission</em>.  But what the ISD avoids is getting weekly reports about losing a few ships here and there as these irritatingly well-funded rebels pick off this or that small force.  Instead, imperial force is concentrated in a handful of mega-platforms that are effectively beyond attack.</p>



<p>The immediate problem, though, is that building a huge navy of brand new massive Space-MRAP-Battleships is probably really expensive, with the massive cost increasing dissatisfaction among the princes and the people, fueling the discontent already simmering in frustrations about this centralizing government.  Finally in 0BBY, the Empire makes its disastrous move: deciding that the best course of action would be to intimidate the princes by beheading one of them (Alderaan) as an example to the others, while disbanding the senate and essentially abolishing princely rule.  But like Ferdinand II marching into Bohemia and the Palatinate in 1618-9, this assertion of direct imperial power ends up triggering a more general revolt of the princes (intensified, of course, by the fact that the Empire <em>loses the Death Star</em> almost immediately, meaning the threat meant to keep the princes in line while their administrations were dismantled had vanished).</p>



<p>From that point, the Empire actually unravels quite quickly: slow, grinding centralization had taken two decades from the end of the Clone Wars to the Battle of Yavin, but from the Battle of Yavin to Endor is just five years.  The problem is a classic feature of military-tributary empires: an army can intimidate many enemies, but it can only fight one, so once the state has to turn potential force into deployed violence, the intimidation value of those armies collapses in the absence of bedrock legitimacy to keep people in line without force, <a href="https://acoup.blog/2023/07/07/collections-the-status-quo-coalition/" data-type="post" data-id="19921">as every actor in the systems’ interests suddenly recalculate against hegemony and towards balancing</a>.</p>



<p>The Rebel Alliance, constructing a navy from scratch, builds one to the doctrine of the last peer-conflict, the Clone Wars, thus a fast-carrier oriented force, while the Empire, saddled with high costs is stuck with the ships it has: giant Space-MRAPs designed to intimidation and counter-insurgency.  But with the princes broadly in revolt, what the Empire increasingly has on its hands is actually a peer, conventional conflict.  The issue comes to a head at Endor, where the Emperor tries a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Dien_Bien_Phu" data-type="link" data-id="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Dien_Bien_Phu">Dien Bien Phu</a>-gambit with the same historical results: thinking he can lure the rebels into a conventional battle and win, he does so but finds to his dismay that the balance of conventional forces is not so lopsided as he hoped.</p>



<p>Naturally a later historian is going to be unaware of the personal elements of the story, but “the emperor, having clearly bungled the strategy and unwilling to change course – I mean, he built a <em>second</em> Death Star – is assassinated by his close associates (Darth Vader) who remain loyal <em>to the empire, just not the emperor</em> and hope to change strategy” is a pretty standard way for dynasties to end.  And what we get after Endor is a pretty standard way that gambit often plays out, with imperial forces fragmenting instead of congealing around a new strategy.  Unable to coalesce around a new strategy or a new leader, the remains of the emperor’s half-built centralized government are dismantled by the princes who then reestablish the old Republic of Princes, albeit with some more centralized components (a central military, for instance) kept.  Restoring the intermediate layer between the Galactic government and the regular people perhaps does calm popular anger as well, as local rulers are better able to handle local issues (in a <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cuius_regio,_eius_religio" data-type="link" data-id="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cuius_regio,_eius_religio">cuius regio, eius religio</a></em> sort of way).</p>



<p>As a coda, one of the things I liked in the old Legends canon that we haven’t seen on-screen, at least, in the new Disney-canon was that the New Republic’s centralized military – something they keep from the Clone Wars experience, evidently – ended up having lots of imperial ships, including ISDs and even SSDs.  Which makes a lot of sense: having reasserted control, one of the things the princes want both for themselves and to deliver to their newly-quite-well-armed populations is lower taxes and thus less naval spending.  But less naval spending doesn’t mean that you build smaller, cheaper ships: <em><strong>it means you keep the old ships</strong></em>.  So the New Republic isn’t going to build a new, cheaper navy, but look for ways to repurpose this pile of giant Space-MRAPs they’ve inherited from the defunct empire, alongside their Ferix-Junkyard collection of ships from the war.  I’d absolutely expect, then, to see some newly blue-trimmed Star Destroyers, employed as the flagships for Republic Navy task forces, even as New Republic officers complain about how poorly suited they are for the role and New Republic designers draw up endless new plans for high-tech, highly capable fast-carrier designs that they can never get funding to build at scale.</p>



<p>And then, of course, fortunately, the story just sort of trails off, because the notion that some insurgent power in the outer rim would conjure into existence not one but <em>two</em> fleets of Star Destroyers out of nothing with no one noticing and casually overthrow this entire system <em>off-screen</em> between movies is the daft sort of thing which would only have been excusable if paired with really good character work, <a href="https://acoup.blog/2019/12/29/miscellanea-the-latest-jedi/" data-type="post" data-id="1956">if anyone had bothered to do any</a>.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="768" height="1024" data-attachment-id="23985" data-permalink="https://acoup.blog/2024/05/10/fireside-friday-may-10-2024/pxl_20240509_154232603/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240509_154232603.jpg?fit=3024%2C4032&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="3024,4032" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Pixel 3a&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1715254952&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;4.44&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;443&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.041667&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="PXL_20240509_154232603" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240509_154232603.jpg?fit=225%2C300&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240509_154232603.jpg?fit=768%2C1024&amp;ssl=1" src="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240509_154232603.jpg?resize=768%2C1024&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240509_154232603.jpg?resize=768%2C1024&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240509_154232603.jpg?resize=225%2C300&amp;ssl=1 225w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240509_154232603.jpg?resize=1152%2C1536&amp;ssl=1 1152w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240509_154232603.jpg?resize=1536%2C2048&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240509_154232603.jpg?resize=900%2C1200&amp;ssl=1 900w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240509_154232603.jpg?resize=600%2C800&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240509_154232603.jpg?resize=450%2C600&amp;ssl=1 450w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240509_154232603.jpg?resize=300%2C400&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240509_154232603.jpg?resize=150%2C200&amp;ssl=1 150w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240509_154232603.jpg?resize=1200%2C1600&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240509_154232603.jpg?resize=1100%2C1467&amp;ssl=1 1100w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/PXL_20240509_154232603.jpg?w=2200&amp;ssl=1 2200w" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" data-recalc-dims="1"><figcaption>Of course I can’t leave you without a cat picture, so here is Ollie helping me manage my research filing system, also known as “a giant mess in at least four languages.”</figcaption></figure>



<p>On to <strong>recommendations</strong>!</p>



<p>Excavations in Pompeii turned up some <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/science-environment-68777741" data-type="link" data-id="https://www.bbc.com/news/science-environment-68777741">remarkable new frescoes of mythological scenes</a> earlier this month, which you can see in this BBC report.  I am always struck by the focus in domestic Greek and Roman artwork on mythological scenes which are often, at least to my mind, deeply fraught; Apollo and Cassandra (where the former is about the curse the latter for her chastity) is hardly what I would want in my dining room, but the ancients seem to have preferred scenes of high emotional and moral tension, even if it was unpleasant tension.  CUNY Professor in Classics and History Liv Yarrow offers some <a href="https://livyarrow.org/2024/04/12/new-pompeii-images/" data-type="link" data-id="https://livyarrow.org/2024/04/12/new-pompeii-images/">additional thoughts on the frescoes on her blog</a>, which I’ll also recommend generally for her musings about ancient material culture objects, their mysteries and what we can understand from them.</p>



<p>Meanwhile, Cardiff University’s Flint Dibble wrote in <em>The Guardian</em> about<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2024/apr/28/lost-civilisations-make-good-tv-ancient-apocalypse-but-archaeology-real-stories-hold-far-more-wonder" data-type="link" data-id="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2024/apr/28/lost-civilisations-make-good-tv-ancient-apocalypse-but-archaeology-real-stories-hold-far-more-wonder"> his experiences as an <em>actual</em> archaeology taking on pseudo-archaeological nonsense</a>.  I agree with Dibble that the <em>actual</em> past that archaeology reveals to us is more interesting and wondrous than the wild fantasies that pseudo-archaeologists project on it, in no small part because the real past can surprise and challenge us in a way that psuedo-archaeology cannot, as it is always just a distorted mirror of our own biases and assumptions.  It is, however, profoundly frustrating how major outlets, like Netflix, continue to present nonsense peddlers as if they are asking unanswered questions, rather than asking <em>extensively</em> answered questions, the answers of which they steadfastly refuse to read.</p>



<p>Over at the <em>Partial Historians</em>, I want to pick out a really neat special guest episode from about a month ago on the <a href="https://partialhistorians.com/2024/03/28/special-episode-augustus-mausoleum-with-dr-victoria-austen/" data-type="link" data-id="https://partialhistorians.com/2024/03/28/special-episode-augustus-mausoleum-with-dr-victoria-austen/">Mausoleum of Augustus</a>, with Dr. Victoria Austen.  The mausoleum is one of those monuments in Rome that gets a bit less attention from tourists, and has been undergoing preservation work (and thus not open to the public) for quite a while now.  But the conversation between Drs. Radform, Greenfield and Austen, I think, is a really useful way to think about how the mausoleum fits in with Augustus’ building program, but also his use of space generally on the Campus Martius (the area of Rome it was in), as well as discussing the way that monuments like that get reused, repurposed and re-imagined by subsequent generations.</p>



<p>Finally, on a gaming note, I just wanted to point out game-analysis YouTuber Rosencreutz has <a href="https://youtu.be/LkCWeYsGA8g?si=ts7TcTeoAFunE7g-" data-type="link" data-id="https://youtu.be/LkCWeYsGA8g?si=ts7TcTeoAFunE7g-">a long video-essay putting the cult-classic <em>Vampire the Masquerade: Bloodlines</em> in the context of the broader genre of ‘vampire games’ </a>that I found quite interesting.  Rosencreutz videos are an interesting sort because they tend to be ruminations on a theme rather than focused deep-dives of a single game (the more common format), but they are often insightful.  I’ll also shout out his take a few months ago on “Valkyria Chronicles, Persecution, and Atrocity” for making an argument I’ve thought for some time: that it is strange and also quite interesting that one of the more <a href="https://youtu.be/Xo0uoG7FgxM?si=UEIg0_BjsV0YMjSh" data-type="link" data-id="https://youtu.be/Xo0uoG7FgxM?si=UEIg0_BjsV0YMjSh">serious takes on the holocaust in gaming is to be found in an alternate-universe anime-WWII tactics game</a>.  His channel is well worth if you are interested in thoughtful analysis of the themes and ideas in video games.</p>



<p>For this week’s <strong>book recommendation</strong>, I want to recommend J. Lyall, <em><a href="https://amzn.to/4dCRxwE" data-type="link" data-id="https://amzn.to/4dCRxwE">Divided Armies: Inequality &amp; Battlefield Performance in Modern War</a></em> (2020), a book I am legitimately surprised I have not already recommended and which is well on its way to becoming one of those modern classics of military history scholarship.  The central argument of the book is actually quite easy to state and fairly intuitive: armies with a high degree of inequality – specifically inequality of membership in the political community – suffer recognizable pathologies that cause them to perform more poorly than they might otherwise have done on the battlefield.  Alert readers will pick up from our series on Hellenistic and Roman armies that I have been noodling around my own version of this argument for those ancient armies (indeed, since before this book was published; you can see the foundations of my ideas on this back in my 2018 dissertation), so Lyall’s book came like a bolt of deliverance: here was a sustained, focused study of the modern instantiation of a phenomenon I thought I could detect in ancient armies.</p>



<p>Of course it is easy to make the observation that it <em>seems</em> like high levels of inequality negatively impact combat performance, but it is another thing to <em>prove</em> it.  Lyall comes at this problem with a political science methodology, which is to say that the foundation of the book is a quantitative approach which seeks to measure – in numbers – inequality (a ‘military inequality coefficient’) and battlefield performance (a ‘battlefield performance index’) and then compare the two.  These sorts of quantitative approaches almost invariably lead historians to cry foul and I will admit I have some <em>concerns</em> about the quite subjective foundations of these apparently objective, quantitative coefficients and indexes.   If that was all there was, I’d be concerned.  But that isn’t all there is.  Indeed, Lyall spends relatively few of his pages on the quantitative aspects of the study and instead buttresses the validity of his figures with a series of detailed, well-developed case studies running from 1800 to 1942.  That said, I also think Lyall’s definition of inequality is actually a really good one, focusing in not on economic inequality or even political representation but on inequality of membership in a political community: who is considered a full member of the polity, who <em>belongs</em> even in polities where belonging doesn’t bring a certain economic standard of living or set of political rights.  As Lyall, I think, demonstrates well, when it comes to military effectiveness, this is the question that matters.</p>



<p>Lyall makes a strong effort (noted in a forward) to try to make the book approachable and consequently confined much of the technical matter to appendices available online.  But I think for the reader looking for the <em>general</em> insight of the negative impact of inequality within armies (rather than the particular, quantitative relationship), the case studies carry the necessary weight.  These are delivered in plain language and with enough context for the reader to follow, and with a historian’s granularity in following the course of specific key moments.  The result is a book that, as long as one kind of skims the quantitative sections (or, as one of my mentors once quipped, of a different political science work’s quantitative chapter, “don’t read it, but don’t skip it”), is very readable and even quite engaging.  More to the point, its a very valuable working, taking something I think many of us kind of knew in a general sense (‘inequality damages army performance’) and providing a focused, in-depth study of the phenomenon in both particular cases and in general that puts substance behind that general sense.</p>
<ol><li><span id="easy-footnote-bottom-1-23926"></span>As an aside, one of the silliest things in the sequel trilogy lore was bringing back not just <em>a</em> CR90, but insisting that the Resistance’s CR90 was a <a href="https://starwars.fandom.com/wiki/Tantive_IV#Return_and_destruction." data-type="link" data-id="https://starwars.fandom.com/wiki/Tantive_IV#Return_and_destruction.">recovered Tantive IV</a>.  The ‘Legends’ canon has Vader do the obvious thing to complete the ruse of sending a distress signal and then reporting the ship destroyed in an accident, which was, of course, <strong>to destroy the ship and kill the crew</strong>, thereby leaving no evidence behind, a thing <strong>Darth Vader</strong> is obviously ruthless enough to do.<a href="#easy-footnote-1-23926"></a></li><li><span id="easy-footnote-bottom-2-23926"></span>As I understand it in technical terms, a ‘prince’ of the HRE was a direct vassal of the emperor; many imperial states were ‘princes’ – including some archbishoprics – but not all were.  However, I find when explaining this to folks, the idea of a ‘government of princes’ makes a lot more sense than ‘a government of states.’<a href="#easy-footnote-2-23926"></a></li></ol>	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>