<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 18:30:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Chaos in the Cloudflare Lisbon Office (146 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.cloudflare.com/chaos-in-cloudflare-lisbon-office-securing-the-internet-with-wave-motion/</link>
            <guid>43389064</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 14:38:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/chaos-in-cloudflare-lisbon-office-securing-the-internet-with-wave-motion/">https://blog.cloudflare.com/chaos-in-cloudflare-lisbon-office-securing-the-internet-with-wave-motion/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43389064">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post"><article><h2>Chaos in Cloudflare’s Lisbon office: securing the Internet with wave motion</h2><p>2025-03-17</p><section><p>7 min read</p><img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/2J0BiaLyDMtbEcZrETkdWu/26d0ae2c2dd564138723922bd9612dec/image1.png" alt=""><div><p>Over the years, Cloudflare has gained fame for many things, including our technical blog, but also as <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/cloudflare-lava-lamps-protect-from-hackers/"><u>a tech company securing the Internet using </u><b><u>lava lamps</u></b></a>, a story that began as a research/science project almost 10 years ago. In March 2025, we added another layer to its legacy: a "wall of entropy" made of 50 <b>wave machines </b>in constant motion at our Lisbon office, the company's European HQ.&nbsp;</p><p>These wave machines are a new source of entropy, joining <b>lava lamps</b> in San Francisco, <b>suspended rainbows</b> in Austin, and <b>double chaotic pendulums </b>in London. The entropy they generate contributes to securing the Internet <a href="#lavarand-origins-and-walls-of-entropy"><u>through LavaRand</u></a>.</p>
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/6sp4ZXYnpwUGAabVB0fRKW/f56edd916efeb49173c623e99b87bc70/DSC00336.JPG" alt="" width="3104" height="2064" loading="lazy">
          </figure>
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/1D1cayhBpPyuUNKV4JCcvF/e6d493a71e41c3622dd4f895505a3f43/DSC00450.JPG" alt="" width="3104" height="2064" loading="lazy">
          </figure>
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/EE2gOFRrXCGM5ASh3uCl7/b282e0ed651cb5c354b183bc33aff116/image4.jpg" alt="" width="1999" height="1330" loading="lazy">
          </figure><p><sup><i>The new waves wall at Cloudflare’s Lisbon office sits beside the Radar Display of global Internet insights, with the 25th of April Bridge overlooking the Tagus River in the background.</i></sup></p><p>It’s exciting to see waves in Portugal now playing a role in keeping the Internet secure, especially given Portugal’s deep maritime history.</p><p>The installation honors Portugal’s passion for the sea and exploration of the unknown, famously beginning over 600 years ago, in 1415, with pioneering vessels like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caravel"><u>caravels</u></a> and naus/carracks, precursors to galleons and other ships. Portuguese sea exploration was driven by navigation schools and historic voyages <i>“through seas never sailed before”</i> (<i>“Por mares nunca dantes navegados” </i>in Portuguese), as described by Portugal’s famous poet, Luís Vaz de Camões, born 500 years ago (1524).</p><p>Anyone familiar with Portugal knows the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_Portugal#Naval_exploration_and_Portuguese_Empire_(15th%E2%80%9316th_centuries)"><u>sea is central</u></a> to its identity. The small country has 980 km of coastline, where most of its main cities are located. Maritime areas make up 90% of its territory, including the mid-Atlantic Azores. In 1998, Lisbon’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expo_%2798"><u>Expo 98</u></a> celebrated the oceans and this maritime heritage. Since 2011, the small town of Nazaré also became globally <a href="https://allwaves.surf/waves-explained-nazare/"><u>famous among the surfing community</u></a> for its <a href="https://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/149486/monster-waves-of-nazare"><u>giant waves</u></a>.</p>
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/2zN2XfhmWnjbFmkXfTiYGw/fa321c61b54e676136f93d050364ee8b/image6.jpg" alt="" width="1916" height="639" loading="lazy">
          </figure>
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/Tyu4Wlgn1NMihceYSCUvI/45905ee3820880371b508dc13c32f11b/image2.jpg" alt="" width="1999" height="692" loading="lazy">
          </figure><p><sup><i>Nazaré’s waves, famous since Garrett McNamara’s 23.8&nbsp;m (78 ft) ride in 2011, hold </i></sup><a href="https://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/world-records/78115-largest-wave-surfed-unlimited"><sup><i><u>Guinness World Records</u></i></sup></a><sup><i> for the biggest waves ever surfed. Photos: Sam Khawasé &amp; Beatriz Paula, from Cloudflare.</i></sup></p><p>Portugal’s maritime culture also inspired literature and music, including poet Fernando Pessoa, who referenced it in his 1934 book <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mensagem"><u>Mensagem</u></a>, and musician Rui Veloso, who dedicated his 1990s album <a href="https://open.spotify.com/album/2mzMuD3bxwFaFgfjU2vigY"><u>Auto da Pimenta</u></a> to Portugal’s historic connection to the sea.</p>
          <p>
            <h3 id="how-this-chaos-came-to-be">How this chaos came to be</h3>
            
          </p>
        <p>As Cloudflare’s CEO, Matthew Prince, <a href="https://x.com/eastdakota/status/1899226252956827846"><u>said</u></a> recently, this new wall of entropy began with an idea back in 2023: “What could we use for randomness that was like our lava lamp wall in San Francisco but represented our team in Portugal?”</p><p>The original inspiration came from wave motion machine desk toys, which were popular among some of our team members. Waves and the ocean not only provide a source of movement and randomness, but also align with Portugal’s maritime history and the office’s scenic view.</p><p>However, this was easier said than done. It turns out that making a wave machine wall is a real challenge, given that these toys are not as popular as they were in the past,&nbsp; and aren’t being manufactured in the size we needed any more. We scoured eBay and other sources but couldn't find enough, consistent in style and in working order wave machines. We also discovered that off-the-shelf models weren’t designed to run 24/7, which was a critical requirement for our use.</p><h4>Artistry to create wave machines</h4><p>Undaunted, <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/cloudflare-top-100-most-loved-workplaces-in-2022"><u>Cloudflare’s Places team</u></a>, which ensures our offices reflect our values and culture, found a <a href="https://wavemotionmachines.com/"><u>U.S.-based artisan</u></a> that specializes in ocean wave displays to create the wave machines for us. Since 2009, his one-person business, <a href="https://wavemotionmachines.com/"><u>Hughes Wave Motion Machines</u></a>, has blended artistry, engineering, and research, following his transition from Lockheed Martin Space Systems, where he designed military and commercial satellites.</p>
<p><sup><i>Timelapse of the mesmerizing office waves, set to the tune of an AI-generated song.</i></sup></p><p>Collaborating closely, we developed a custom rectangular wave machine (18 inches/45 cm long) that runs nonstop — not an easy task — which required hundreds of hours of testing and many iterations. Featuring rotating wheels, continuous motors, and a unique fluid formula, these machines create realistic ocean-like waves in green, blue, and Cloudflare’s signature orange.&nbsp;</p><p>Here’s a quote from the artist himself about these wave machines:</p><blockquote><p><i>“The machine’s design is a balancing act of matching components and their placement to how the fluid responds in a given configuration. There is a complex yet delicate relationship between viscosity, specific gravity, the size and design of the vessel, and the placement of each mechanical interface. Everything must be precisely aligned, centered around the fluid like a mathematical function. I like to say it’s akin to ’balancing a checkerboard on a beach ball in the wind.’”</i></p></blockquote>
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/3K9fpTU0D0xi831MHFOFBj/570b8c307fea1078f3c0262e13447bf6/image7.jpg" alt="" width="1500" height="1999" loading="lazy">
          </figure><p><sup><i>The Cloudflare Places Team with Lisbon office architects and contractor testing wave machine placement, shelves, lighting, and mirrors to enhance movement and reflection, March 2024.</i></sup></p><p>Despite delays, the Lisbon wave machines finally debuted on March 10, 2025 — an incredibly exciting moment for the Places team.</p><p><b>Some numbers about our wave-machine entropy wall:</b></p><ul><li><p>50 wave machines, 50 motion wheels &amp; motors, 50 acrylic containers filled with Hughes Wave Fluid Formula (two <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/topics/engineering/immiscible-liquid"><u>immiscible liquids</u></a>)</p></li><li><p>3 liquid colors: blue, green, and orange</p></li><li><p>15 months from concept to completion</p></li><li><p>14 flips (side-to-side balancing movements) per minute — over 20,000 per day</p></li><li><p>Over 15 waves per minute</p></li><li><p>~0.5 liters of liquid per machine</p></li></ul>
          <p>
            <h3 id="lavarand-origins-and-walls-of-entropy">LavaRand origins and walls of entropy</h3>
            
          </p>
        <p>Cloudflare’s servers handle 71 million HTTP requests per second on average, with 100 million HTTP requests per second at peak. <a href="https://radar.cloudflare.com/adoption-and-usage#http-vs-https"><u>Most of these requests are secured via TLS</u></a>, which relies on secure randomness for cryptographic integrity. A Cryptographically Secure Pseudorandom Number Generator (<a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/ssl/lava-lamp-encryption/"><u>CSPRNG</u></a>) ensures unpredictability, but only when seeded with high-quality entropy. Since chaotic movement in the real world is truly random, Cloudflare designed a system to harness it. Our <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/harnessing-office-chaos/"><u>2024 blog post</u></a> expands on this topic in a more technical way, but here’s a quick summary.</p><p>In <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/randomness-101-lavarand-in-production/"><u>2017</u></a>, Cloudflare launched LavaRand, inspired by <a href="https://www.wired.com/1997/03/lava-lites-easy-to-break-hard-to-crack/"><u>Silicon Graphics’ 1997 concept</u></a> However, the need for randomness in security was already a hot topic on our blog before that, such as in our discussions of <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/why-randomness-matters/"><u>securing systems</u></a> and <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/a-relatively-easy-to-understand-primer-on-elliptic-curve-cryptography/"><u>cryptography</u></a>. Originally, LavaRand collected entropy from a wall of lava lamps in our San Francisco office, feeding an internal API that servers periodically query to include in their entropy pools. Over time, we expanded LavaRand beyond lava lamps, incorporating <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/harnessing-office-chaos/#londons-unpredictable-pendulums"><u>new sources of office chaos</u></a> while maintaining the same core method.</p>
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/2v6Wvde8j8R7482QjBsSrV/89b37c652654e27c13d328e9acac6489/image9.png" alt="" width="1612" height="381" loading="lazy">
          </figure><p>A camera captures images of dynamic, unpredictable randomness displays. Shadows, lighting changes, and even sensor noise contribute entropy. Each image is then processed into a compact hash, converting it into a sequence of random bytes. These, combined with the previous seed and local system entropy, serve as input for a Key Derivation Function (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Key_derivation_function"><u>KDF</u></a>), which generates a new seed for a CSPRNG — capable of producing virtually unlimited random bytes upon request. The waves in our Lisbon office are now contributing to this pool of randomness.</p>
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/1XFFjr4jhRMQlz6akHKZm4/44759c4e879de3792cd21b4ce2525c90/image5.png" alt="" width="1491" height="400" loading="lazy">
          </figure><p>Cloudflare’s LavaRand API makes this randomness accessible internally, strengthening cryptographic security across our global infrastructure. For example, when you use <i>Math.random()</i> in <a href="https://workers.cloudflare.com/"><u>Cloudflare Workers</u></a>, part of that randomness comes from LavaRand. Similarly, querying our <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/harnessing-office-chaos/#drand-distributed-and-verifiable-public-randomness"><u>drand API</u></a> taps into LavaRand as well. Cloudflare offers this API to enable anyone to generate random numbers and even seed their own systems.</p>
          <p>
            <h3 id="our-new-lisbon-office-space">Our new Lisbon office space</h3>
            
          </p>
        
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/5ivPkCfTkGxfo6Swt6p9qY/e7414a14b88bef7ac7e0ef6f737b58c6/image8.jpg" alt="" width="1999" height="1330" loading="lazy">
          </figure><p><sup><i>Photo of the view from our Lisbon office, featuring ceiling lights arranged in a wave-like pattern.</i></sup></p><p>Entropy also inspired the design ethos of our new Lisbon office, given that the wall of waves and the office are part of the same project. As soon as you enter, you're greeted not only by the motion of the entropy wall but also by the constant movement of planet Earth on our Cloudflare Radar Display screen that stands next to it. But the waves don’t stop there — more elements throughout the space mimic the dynamic flow of the Internet itself. Unlike ocean tides, however, Internet traffic ebbs and flows with the motion of the Sun, not the Moon.</p><p>As you walk through the office, waves are everywhere — in the ceiling lights, the architectural contours, and even the floor plan, thoughtfully designed by our architect to reflect the fluid movement of water. The visual elements create a cohesive experience, reinforcing a sense of motion. Each meeting room embraces this maritime theme, named after famous Portuguese beaches — including, naturally, Nazaré.</p><p>We partnered with an incredible group of local Portuguese vendors for this construction project, where all the leads were women — something incredibly rare for the industry. The local teams worked with passion, proudly wore Cloudflare t-shirts, and fostered a warm, family-like atmosphere. They openly expressed pride in the project, sharing how it stood out from anything they had worked on before.</p>
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/7lpuurEtWfpIPKvHVqmD0L/0b0561097859f286d6b5e98db82f1e0f/image3.jpg" alt="" width="1999" height="1125" loading="lazy">
          </figure><p><sup><i>Our amazing third-party team and internal Places team, proudly rocking Cloudflare shirts after bringing this project to life.</i></sup></p>
          <p>
            <h3 id="help-us-select-a-name-for-our-new-wall-of-entropy">Help us select a name for our new wall of entropy</h3>
            
          </p>
        <p>Next, we have several name options for this new wall of entropy. Help us decide the best one, and register your vote using <a href="https://forms.gle/L2gAqoJTwQmJFkmy8"><u>this form</u></a>.</p><blockquote><p><b>The Surf Board</b></p><p><b>Chaos Reef</b></p><p><b>Waves of Entropy</b></p><p><b>Wall of Waves</b></p><p><b>Whirling Wave Wall</b></p><p><b>Chaotic Wave Wall</b></p><p><b>Waves of Chaos</b></p></blockquote><p>If you’re interested in working in Cloudflare’s Lisbon office, we’re hiring! Our <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/careers/jobs/"><b><u>career page</u></b></a> lists our open roles in Lisbon, as well as our other locations in the U.S., Mexico, Europe and Asia.</p><p><sup><i>Acknowledgements: This project was only possible with the effort, vision and help of John Graham-Cumming, Caroline Quick, Jen Preston, Laura Atwall, Carolina Beja, Hughes Wave Motion Machines, P4 Planning and Project Management, Gensler Europe, Openbook Architecture, and Vector Mais.</i></sup></p></div></section><div><p>Cloudflare's connectivity cloud protects <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/network-services/" rel="noreferrer">entire corporate networks</a>, helps customers build <a target="_blank" href="https://workers.cloudflare.com/" rel="noreferrer">Internet-scale applications efficiently</a>, accelerates any <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/performance/accelerate-internet-applications/" rel="noreferrer">website or Internet application</a>, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/ddos/" rel="noreferrer">wards off DDoS attacks</a>, keeps <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/application-security/" rel="noreferrer">hackers at bay</a>, and can help you on <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/products/zero-trust/" rel="noreferrer">your journey to Zero Trust</a>.</p><p>Visit <a target="_blank" href="https://one.one.one.one/" rel="noreferrer">1.1.1.1</a> from any device to get started with our free app that makes your Internet faster and safer.</p><p>To learn more about our mission to help build a better Internet, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/what-is-cloudflare/" rel="noreferrer">start here</a>. If you're looking for a new career direction, check out <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/careers" rel="noreferrer">our open positions</a>.</p></div><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/lavarand/">LavaRand</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/entropy/">Entropy</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/security/">Security</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/randomness/">Randomness</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/cryptography/">Cryptography</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/portugal/">Portugal</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/life-at-cloudflare/">Life at Cloudflare</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/lisbon/">Lisbon</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/offices/">Offices</a></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Undergraduate Disproves 40-Year-Old Conjecture, Invents New Kind of Hash Table (133 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wired.com/story/undergraduate-upends-a-40-year-old-data-science-conjecture/</link>
            <guid>43388296</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 13:19:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/undergraduate-upends-a-40-year-old-data-science-conjecture/">https://www.wired.com/story/undergraduate-upends-a-40-year-old-data-science-conjecture/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43388296">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-testid="ArticlePageChunks"><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p><em><span>The original version</span> of</em> <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/undergraduate-upends-a-40-year-old-data-science-conjecture-20250210/"><em>this story</em></a> <em>appeared in <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/">Quanta Magazine</a>.</em></p><p>Sometime in the fall of 2021, Andrew Krapivin, an undergraduate at Rutgers University, encountered a paper that would change his life. At the time, Krapivin didn’t give it much thought. But two years later, when he finally set aside time to go through the paper (“just for fun,” as he put it), his efforts would lead to a rethinking of a widely used tool in computer science.</p><p>The paper’s title, “<a data-offer-url="https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.12800" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.12800&quot;}" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.12800" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Tiny Pointers</a>,” referred to arrowlike entities that can direct you to a piece of information, or element, in a computer’s memory. Krapivin soon came up with a potential way to further miniaturize the pointers so they consumed less memory. However, to achieve that, he needed a better way of organizing the data that the pointers would point to.</p><p>He turned to a common approach for storing data known as a hash table. But in the midst of his tinkering, Krapivin realized that he had invented a new kind of hash table, one that worked faster than expected—taking less time and fewer steps to find specific elements.</p><p><a href="https://engineering.nyu.edu/faculty/martin-farach-colton" target="_blank">Martín Farach-Colton</a>, a coauthor of the “Tiny Pointers” paper and Krapivin’s former professor at Rutgers, was initially skeptical of Krapivin’s new design. Hash tables are among the most thoroughly studied data structures in all of computer science; the advance sounded too good to be true. But just to be sure, he asked a frequent collaborator (and a “Tiny Pointers” coauthor), <a data-offer-url="https://csd.cmu.edu/people/faculty/william-kuszmaul" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://csd.cmu.edu/people/faculty/william-kuszmaul&quot;}" href="https://csd.cmu.edu/people/faculty/william-kuszmaul" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">William Kuszmaul</a> of Carnegie Mellon University, to check out his student’s invention. Kuszmaul had a different reaction. “You didn’t just come up with a cool hash table,” he remembers telling Krapivin. “You’ve actually completely wiped out a 40-year-old conjecture!”</p><figure><p><span><p>Without setting out to do so, Andrew Krapivin upended the common thinking around hash tables—one of the best-studied tools in computer science.</p>
</span><span>Photograph: Phillip Ammon for Quanta Magazine</span></p></figure><p>Together, Krapivin (now a graduate student at the University of Cambridge), Farach-Colton (now at New York University), and Kuszmaul demonstrated in a <a data-offer-url="https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02305" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02305&quot;}" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02305" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">January 2025 paper</a> that this new hash table can indeed find elements faster than was considered possible. ln so doing, they had disproved a conjecture long held to be true.</p></div><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>“It’s an important paper,” said <a data-offer-url="https://ajhconway.com/" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://ajhconway.com/&quot;}" href="https://ajhconway.com/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Alex Conway</a> of Cornell Tech in New York City. “Hash tables are among the oldest data structures we have. And they’re still one of the most efficient ways to store data.” Yet open questions remain about how they work, he said. “This paper answers a couple of them in surprising ways.”</p><p>Hash tables have become ubiquitous in computing, partly because of their simplicity and ease of use. They’re designed to allow users to do exactly three things: “query” (search for) an element, delete an element, or insert one into an empty slot. The first hash tables date back to the early 1950s, and computer scientists have studied and used them ever since. Among other things, researchers wanted to figure out the speed limits for some of these operations. How fast, for example, could a new search or insertion possibly be?</p><figure><p><span><p>Martín Farach-Colton helped Krapivin prove that his new hash table contradicted a long-standing conjecture.</p>
</span><span>Photograph: Andrew Farach-Colton</span></p></figure><p>The answer generally depends on the amount of time it takes to find an empty spot in a hash table. This, in turn, typically depends on how full the hash table is. Fullness can be described in terms of an overall percentage—this table is 50 percent full, that one’s 90 percent—but researchers often deal with much fuller tables. So instead, they may use a whole number, denoted by <em>x</em>, to specify how close the hash table is to 100 percent full. If <em>x</em> is 100, then the table is 99 percent full. If <em>x</em> is 1,000, the table is 99.9 percent full. This measure of fullness offers a convenient way to evaluate how long it should take to perform actions like queries or insertions.</p><p>Researchers have long known that for certain common hash tables, the expected time required to make the worst possible insertion—putting an item into, say, the last remaining open spot—is proportional to <em>x</em>. “If your hash table is 99 percent full,” Kuszmaul said, “it makes sense that you would have to look at around 100 different positions to find a free slot.”</p></div><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>In a <a data-offer-url="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3828.3836" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3828.3836&quot;}" href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3828.3836" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">1985 paper</a>, the computer scientist <a data-offer-url="https://amturing.acm.org/award_winners/yao_1611524.cfm" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://amturing.acm.org/award_winners/yao_1611524.cfm&quot;}" href="https://amturing.acm.org/award_winners/yao_1611524.cfm" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Andrew Yao</a>, who would go on to win the A.M. Turing Award, asserted that among hash tables with a specific set of properties, the best way to find an individual element or an empty spot is to just go through potential spots randomly—an approach known as uniform probing. He also stated that, in the worst-case scenario, where you’re searching for the last remaining open spot, you can never do better than <em>x</em>. For 40 years, most computer scientists assumed that Yao’s conjecture was true.</p><p>Krapivin was not held back by the conventional wisdom for the simple reason that he was unaware of it. “I did this without knowing about Yao’s conjecture,” he said. His explorations with tiny pointers led to a new kind of hash table—one that did not rely on uniform probing. And for this new hash table, the time required for worst-case queries and insertions is proportional to (log <em>x</em>)<sup>2</sup>—far faster than <em>x</em>. This result directly contradicted Yao’s conjecture. Farach-Colton and Kuszmaul helped Krapivin show that (log <em>x</em>)<sup>2</sup> is the optimal, unbeatable bound for the popular class of hash tables Yao had written about.</p><p>“This result is beautiful in that it addresses and solves such a classic problem,” said <a data-offer-url="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~guyb/" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~guyb/&quot;}" href="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~guyb/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Guy Blelloch</a> of Carnegie Mellon.</p><p>“It’s not just that they disproved [Yao’s conjecture], they also found the best possible answer to his question,” said <a data-offer-url="https://cs.uwaterloo.ca/about/people/sassadi" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://cs.uwaterloo.ca/about/people/sassadi&quot;}" href="https://cs.uwaterloo.ca/about/people/sassadi" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Sepehr Assadi</a> of the University of Waterloo. “We could have gone another 40 years before we knew the right answer.”</p><figure><p><span><p>Krapivin on the King’s College Bridge at the University of Cambridge. His new hash table can find and store data faster than researchers ever thought possible.</p>
</span><span>Photoraph: Phillip Ammon for Quanta Magazine</span></p></figure><p>In addition to refuting Yao’s conjecture, the new paper also contains what many consider an even more astonishing result. It pertains to a related, though slightly different, situation: In 1985, Yao looked not only at the worst-case times for queries, but also at the average time taken across all possible queries. He proved that hash tables with certain properties—including those that are labeled “greedy,” which means that new elements must be placed in the first available spot—could never achieve an average time better than log <em>x</em>.</p><p>Farach-Colton, Krapivin, and Kuszmaul wanted to see if that same limit also applied to non-greedy hash tables. They showed that it did not by providing a counterexample, a non-greedy hash table with an average query time that’s much, much better than log <em>x</em>. In fact, it doesn’t depend on <em>x</em> at all. “You get a number,” Farach-Colton said, “something that is just a constant and doesn’t depend on how full the hash table is.” The fact that you can achieve a constant average query time, regardless of the hash table’s fullness, was wholly unexpected—even to the authors themselves.</p><p>The team’s results may not lead to any immediate applications, but that’s not all that matters, Conway said. “It’s important to understand these kinds of data structures better. You don’t know when a result like this will unlock something that lets you do better in practice.”</p><hr><p><a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/undergraduate-upends-a-40-year-old-data-science-conjecture-20250210/"><em>Original story</em></a> <em>reprinted with permission from <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/">Quanta Magazine</a>, an editorially independent publication of the</em> <a href="https://www.simonsfoundation.org/"><em>Simons Foundation</em></a> <em>whose mission is to enhance public understanding of science by covering research developments and trends in mathematics and the physical and life sciences.</em></p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Raspberry Pi RP2350 Now Available for Purchase, Stacked Memory Variant Coming (112 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Raspberry-Pi-RP2350-Buy</link>
            <guid>43388221</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 13:11:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/news/Raspberry-Pi-RP2350-Buy">https://www.phoronix.com/news/Raspberry-Pi-RP2350-Buy</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43388221">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p><img alt="RASPBERRY PI" src="https://www.phoronix.com/assets/categories/raspberrypi.webp" width="100" height="100"></p><p>
Raspberry Pi last year announced the RP2350 second-generation micro-controller that debuted within their $5 Raspberry Pi Pico 2 single board computer. Today they announced the RP2350 micro-controller is now available to purchase for your own micro-controller needs.
</p><p>
The Raspberry Pi RP2350 features two Arm Cortex-M33 processors at 150MHz and with floating point and DSP support. The RP2350A 7×7 QFN60 is priced at $1.10 USD per unit or the RP2350B 10×10 QFN80 is priced at $1.20 per unit when purchasing individually. Or if buying the RP2350A on a 13" reel for 3400 units it comes down to just $0.80 USD per unit or $0.90 for the RP2350B. There are also 7" reel 500 unit options for $0.90 or $1.00 as well.
</p><p><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=2025&amp;image=rp2350" alt="Raspberry Pi RP2350"></p>
<p>Raspberry Pi is also working on RP2354A and RP2354B variants that will feature 2MB of stacked flash memory. Those Raspberry Pi micro-controllers with stacked memory should be in mass production later this year and available via approved resellers.
</p><p>
Those wishing to learn more about the Raspberry Pi RP2350 micro-controller can do so via <a href="https://www.raspberrypi.com/news/rp2350-now-available-to-buy-a-high-performance-secure-microcontroller-for-your-next-project/">RaspberryPi.com</a>.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Meta puts stop on promotion of tell-all book by former employee (170 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2025/mar/13/meta-careless-people-book-former-employee</link>
            <guid>43387325</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 11:27:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2025/mar/13/meta-careless-people-book-former-employee">https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2025/mar/13/meta-careless-people-book-former-employee</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43387325">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/meta" data-link-name="in body link">Meta</a> on Wednesday won an emergency arbitration ruling to temporarily stop promotion of the tell-all book Careless People by a former employee, according to a copy of the ruling published by the social media company.</p><p>The book, written by a former director of global public policy at Meta, Sarah Wynn-Williams, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/03/10/books/review/careless-people-sarah-wynn-williams.html" data-link-name="in body link">was called by the New York Times</a> book review “an ugly, detailed portrait of one of the most powerful companies in the world”, and its leading executives, including CEO Mark Zuckerberg, former chief operating officer Sheryl Sandberg and chief global affairs officer Joel Kaplan.</p><p>Meta will suffer “immediate and irreparable loss” in the absence of an emergency relief, the American Arbitration Association’s emergency arbitrator, Nicholas Gowen, said in a ruling after a hearing, which Wynn-Williams did not attend.</p><p>Book publisher Macmillan attended and argued it was not bound by the arbitration agreement, which was part of a severance agreement between the employee and company.</p><p>The ruling says that Wynn-Williams should stop promoting the book and, to the extent she could, stop further publication. It did not order any action by the publisher.</p><p>A Meta spokesperson, Andy Stone, said in a post on Threads: “This ruling affirms that Sarah Wynn Williams’ false and defamatory book should never have been published”. Wynn-Williams and Macmillan did not immediately respond to a request for comment on the ruling.</p><figure data-spacefinder-role="inline" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.NewsletterSignupBlockElement"><a data-ignore="global-link-styling" href="#EmailSignup-skip-link-6">skip past newsletter promotion</a><p id="EmailSignup-skip-link-6" tabindex="0" aria-label="after newsletter promotion" role="note">after newsletter promotion</p></figure><p>A spokesperson for Pan Macmillan gave the Guardian this statement on Thursday: “Careless People is a first person narrative account of what the author herself, Sarah Wynn Williams, witnessed during seven years at Meta (formerly Facebook). As publishers, we are committed to upholding freedom of speech and her right to tell her story. Due to legal process instituted by Meta, the author has been prevented from continuing to participate in the book’s publicity.”</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[uv downloads overtake Poetry for Wagtail users (207 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://wagtail.org/blog/uv-overtakes-poetry/</link>
            <guid>43386357</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 08:49:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://wagtail.org/blog/uv-overtakes-poetry/">https://wagtail.org/blog/uv-overtakes-poetry/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43386357">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <p data-block-key="wj9wf">The data ^ seems pretty clear – <a href="https://docs.astral.sh/uv/"><b>uv</b></a><b> is now the second most popular package installer for Wagtail users</b>, after pip, taking over from <a href="https://python-poetry.org/docs/">Poetry</a>.</p><p data-block-key="flrn5">Poetry is still pretty popular – and so is pip. But the growth in uv usage likely isn’t just from new users of Wagtail like the data might convey at a glance (see <a href="https://github.com/thibaudcolas/wagtail-tooling/blob/main/downloads-analysis/installers-stats.sql">the query</a> - PyPI download statistics in BigQuery).</p><p data-block-key="bcgc1">Note the chart above has July-August 2024 numbers manually adjusted – it looks like someone did an oopsie around that time, perhaps a uv early adopter letting CI go wild? (❤️ happens to the best of us) Or a version resolution gotcha for people testing Django pre-releases? Hmm.</p><p><img alt="pip and uv monthly downloads of Wagtail" height="371" src="https://media.wagtail.org/images/pip_and_uv_monthly_downloads_of_Wagtail.width-800.png" width="600"></p><h2 data-block-key="8mu50">What it means for Wagtail</h2><p data-block-key="4ure9">We need to make sure it works well with uv, in addition to other tools! Possibly update some of our docs. uv as a first-class citizen for <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/bakerydemo">bakerydemo site</a>? Updating the <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/news-template">news template</a>? We want to be careful that usage instructions make sense for all package managers, but also adapt to Python developers’ shifting expectations.</p><p data-block-key="evtgu">This is our <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail#-getting-started">current recommended</a> install steps for first-time users:</p>
    </div><div>
    <p data-block-key="3g8ar">There’s ways we could go further here, perhaps have more of a one-liner "uvx wagtail@latest start mysite --autorun" scaffolding experience (rare in the Django world). Tooling evolutions like those in uv this are a great opportunity for us to revisit those developer experience fundamentals.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Alexa feature "Do Not Send Voice Recordings" you enabled no longer available (786 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://discuss.systems/@dev/114161826926246661</link>
            <guid>43385268</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 04:41:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://discuss.systems/@dev/114161826926246661">https://discuss.systems/@dev/114161826926246661</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43385268">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://discuss.systems/@dev/114161826926246661: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Conducting forensics of mobile devices to find signs of a potential compromise (124 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/mvt-project/mvt</link>
            <guid>43384894</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 03:25:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/mvt-project/mvt">https://github.com/mvt-project/mvt</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43384894">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto">
     <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/a545b05395270e4383838329a58589a89b2476f217e8eb3bba22afdf0177a809/68747470733a2f2f646f63732e6d76742e72652f656e2f6c61746573742f6d76742e706e67"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/a545b05395270e4383838329a58589a89b2476f217e8eb3bba22afdf0177a809/68747470733a2f2f646f63732e6d76742e72652f656e2f6c61746573742f6d76742e706e67" width="200" data-canonical-src="https://docs.mvt.re/en/latest/mvt.png"></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Mobile Verification Toolkit</h2><a id="user-content-mobile-verification-toolkit" aria-label="Permalink: Mobile Verification Toolkit" href="#mobile-verification-toolkit"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://pypi.org/project/mvt/" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/d47f0f4ef327bd2cb2d9bf1d1b0bcb0a05560dfe0b3fd72e62f7051ef57db449/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f707970692f762f6d7674" alt="" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/pypi/v/mvt"></a>
<a href="https://docs.mvt.re/en/latest/?badge=latest" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/506cc619196a2076aa7c7a616b1814389d9ed8f6cae1516d64067d62a96c6668/68747470733a2f2f72656164746865646f63732e6f72672f70726f6a656374732f6d76742f62616467652f3f76657273696f6e3d6c6174657374" alt="Documentation Status" data-canonical-src="https://readthedocs.org/projects/mvt/badge/?version=latest"></a>
<a href="https://github.com/mvt-project/mvt/actions/workflows/tests.yml"><img src="https://github.com/mvt-project/mvt/actions/workflows/tests.yml/badge.svg" alt="CI"></a>
<a href="https://pepy.tech/project/mvt" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/559f2ada7ecf46681346f7bc5e7927952662545f870476a24aaeb6ac959122b5/68747470733a2f2f706570792e746563682f62616467652f6d7674" alt="Downloads" data-canonical-src="https://pepy.tech/badge/mvt"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Mobile Verification Toolkit (MVT) is a collection of utilities to simplify and automate the process of gathering forensic traces helpful to identify a potential compromise of Android and iOS devices.</p>
<p dir="auto">It has been developed and released by the <a href="https://securitylab.amnesty.org/" rel="nofollow">Amnesty International Security Lab</a> in July 2021 in the context of the <a href="https://forbiddenstories.org/about-the-pegasus-project/" rel="nofollow">Pegasus Project</a> along with <a href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/research/2021/07/forensic-methodology-report-how-to-catch-nso-groups-pegasus/" rel="nofollow">a technical forensic methodology</a>. It continues to be maintained by Amnesty International and other contributors.</p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Note</strong>
MVT is a forensic research tool intended for technologists and investigators. It requires understanding digital forensics and using command-line tools. This is not intended for end-user self-assessment. If you are concerned with the security of your device please seek reputable expert assistance.</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Indicators of Compromise</h3><a id="user-content-indicators-of-compromise" aria-label="Permalink: Indicators of Compromise" href="#indicators-of-compromise"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">MVT supports using public <a href="https://github.com/mvt-project/mvt-indicators">indicators of compromise (IOCs)</a> to scan mobile devices for potential traces of targeting or infection by known spyware campaigns. This includes IOCs published by <a href="https://github.com/AmnestyTech/investigations/">Amnesty International</a> and other  research groups.</p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Warning</strong>
Public indicators of compromise are insufficient to determine that a device is "clean", and not targeted with a particular spyware tool. Reliance on public indicators alone can miss recent forensic traces and give a false sense of security.</p>
<p dir="auto">Reliable and comprehensive digital forensic support and triage requires access to non-public indicators, research and threat intelligence.</p>
<p dir="auto">Such support is available to civil society through <a href="https://securitylab.amnesty.org/get-help/?c=mvt_docs" rel="nofollow">Amnesty International's Security Lab</a> or through our forensic partnership with <a href="https://www.accessnow.org/help/" rel="nofollow">Access Now’s Digital Security Helpline</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto">More information about using indicators of compromise with MVT is available in the <a href="https://docs.mvt.re/en/latest/iocs/" rel="nofollow">documentation</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h2><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">MVT can be installed from sources or from <a href="https://pypi.org/project/mvt/" rel="nofollow">PyPI</a> (you will need some dependencies, check the <a href="https://docs.mvt.re/en/latest/install/" rel="nofollow">documentation</a>):</p>

<p dir="auto">For alternative installation options and known issues, please refer to the <a href="https://docs.mvt.re/en/latest/install/" rel="nofollow">documentation</a> as well as <a href="https://github.com/mvt-project/mvt/issues">GitHub Issues</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h2><a id="user-content-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Usage" href="#usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">MVT provides two commands <code>mvt-ios</code> and <code>mvt-android</code>. <a href="https://docs.mvt.re/" rel="nofollow">Check out the documentation to learn how to use them!</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The purpose of MVT is to facilitate the <em><strong>consensual forensic analysis</strong></em> of devices of those who might be targets of sophisticated mobile spyware attacks, especially members of civil society and marginalized communities. We do not want MVT to enable privacy violations of non-consenting individuals.  In order to achieve this, MVT is released under its own license. <a href="https://docs.mvt.re/en/latest/license/" rel="nofollow">Read more here.</a></p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Let's knock down social media's walled gardens – Tim Berners-Lee (104 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ft.com/content/79d2d19a-08df-48fc-9a6f-a9dbef58f642</link>
            <guid>43384786</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 03:00:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/79d2d19a-08df-48fc-9a6f-a9dbef58f642">https://www.ft.com/content/79d2d19a-08df-48fc-9a6f-a9dbef58f642</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43384786">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-o-grid-colspan="12 L6"><p><h2><span>Join FT Edit</span></h2><h2><strong><span>Only </span><span>CHF5</span><span> per month</span></strong></h2></p><p><span>Access to eight surprising articles a day, hand-picked by FT editors. For seamless reading, access content via the FT Edit page on FT.com, receive the FT Edit newsletter or download our award winning FT Edit app on iOS devices.</span></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Brown University Professor Is Deported Despite a Judge's Order (121 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/2025/03/16/us/brown-university-rasha-alawieh-professor-deported.html</link>
            <guid>43384730</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 02:48:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/03/16/us/brown-university-rasha-alawieh-professor-deported.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2025/03/16/us/brown-university-rasha-alawieh-professor-deported.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43384730">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nytimes.com/2025/03/16/us/brown-university-rasha-alawieh-professor-deported.html: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Sunsetting Whois (777 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.icann.org/en/announcements/details/icann-update-launching-rdap-sunsetting-whois-27-01-2025-en</link>
            <guid>43384069</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:48:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.icann.org/en/announcements/details/icann-update-launching-rdap-sunsetting-whois-27-01-2025-en">https://www.icann.org/en/announcements/details/icann-update-launching-rdap-sunsetting-whois-27-01-2025-en</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43384069">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.icann.org/en/announcements/details/icann-update-launching-rdap-sunsetting-whois-27-01-2025-en: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tesla drives into Wile E. Coyote fake road wall in camera vs. Lidar test (139 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://electrek.co/2025/03/16/tesla-autopilot-drives-into-wall-camera-vs-lidar-test/</link>
            <guid>43382230</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 20:55:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://electrek.co/2025/03/16/tesla-autopilot-drives-into-wall-camera-vs-lidar-test/">https://electrek.co/2025/03/16/tesla-autopilot-drives-into-wall-camera-vs-lidar-test/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43382230">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
					
<figure>
	<img width="1600" height="834" src="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/03/Tesla-cameras-vs-radar-wall.png?w=1600" alt="Tesla cameras vs radar wall" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/03/Tesla-cameras-vs-radar-wall.png?w=320&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 320w, https://i0.wp.com/electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/03/Tesla-cameras-vs-radar-wall.png?w=640&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 640w, https://i0.wp.com/electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/03/Tesla-cameras-vs-radar-wall.png?w=1024&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/03/Tesla-cameras-vs-radar-wall.png?w=1500&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 1500w" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high"></figure>

<p>Tesla Autopilot drove into Wile E. Coyote-style fake road wall in the middle of the road in a camera versus lidar test.</p>



<p>While most companies developing self-driving technologies have been using a mix of sensors (cameras, radar, lidar, and ultrasonic), Tesla insists on only using cameras.</p>



<p>The automaker removed radars from its vehicle lineup and even deactivated radars already installed in existing vehicles.</p>



<p>The strategy has yet to pay off as Tesla’s systems are still stuck at level 2 driver assist systems.</p>	
	



<p>CEO Elon Musk claims that Tesla’s advantage is that once it solves autonomy, it will be able to scale faster than competitors because its vision plus neural net system is designed to work like a human driver and, therefore, will be able to adapt to any road.</p>



<p>Critics have pushed back against those claims, especially since Musk mentioned Tesla achieving “level 5 autonomy”, which means “in any conditions,” and cameras have limitations on that front that are fixed by lidar sensors.</p>



<p>A new video by engineering Youtuber Mark Rober has provided a very interesting demonstration of that very problem:</p>



<figure><p>
<iframe id="post-youtube-video-1" title="Can You Fool A Self Driving Car?" width="500" height="281" data-src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/IQJL3htsDyQ?feature=oembed&amp;rel=0&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</p></figure>



<p>In the video, Rober puts a Tesla Model Y on Autopilot against a vehicle using a lidar system in a series of tests in different conditions.</p>



<p>The Tesla on Autopilot managed to stop for a kid mannequin in the middle of the road when statics, moving, and blinded by lights, but it couldn’t stop in fog or heavy rain:</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" src="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-16-at-12.25.18%E2%80%AFPM.png?w=1024" alt=""></figure>



<p>It’s not surprising that the lidar, a laser-based system, is capable of detecting better in heavy fog than a camera system.</p>



<p>The heavy rain was a bit more surprising, but to be fair, the level of rain was quite spectacular.</p>



<p>The last scenario of a Wile E. Coyote-style wall with a fake road painted on it was obviously not realistic, but it serves to illustrate the issue with cameras versus radar or lidar sensors: they rely on the perception of potential obstacles rather than hard data about potential obstacles.</p>



<p>In simple words, the lidar sensors didn’t care what was painted on the wall, they only cared that it was a wall, while cameras can be tricked.</p>



<h2 id="h-electrek-s-take">Electrek’s Take</h2>



<p>I think it’s clear that no Tesla vehicle currently available will be capable of level 5 autonomy as Elon claimed.</p>




	<p>Level 4 is also questionable.</p>



<p>I think you can accomplish a lot with cameras, but I think it’s undeniable that adding radars and lidars can make systems safer.</p>



<p>In DMs with us during Tesla’s transition to vision only, Elon even admitted that “very high-resolution radars would be better than pure vision”, but he claimed that “such a radar does not exist”: </p>



<blockquote>
<p>“A very high-resolution radar would be better than pure vision, but such a radar does not exist.”</p>
</blockquote>



<p>When we pointed one out to him, he didn’t respond. Also, while they use light rather than radio waves, lidars are basically high-resolution radars, but the problem is that Musk has taken such a strong stance against them for so long that now that they have improved immensely and reduced in prices, he still can’t admit that he was wrong and use them.</p>
	<p>
		<a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://news.google.com/publications/CAAqBwgKMKqD-Qow6c_gAg?hl=en-US&amp;gl=US&amp;ceid=US:en">
			<em>Add Electrek to your Google News feed.</em>&nbsp;
					</a>
	</p>
	<p><em>FTC: We use income earning auto affiliate links.</em> <a href="https://electrek.co/about/#affiliate">More.</a></p>				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Military grade sonic weapon is used against protesters in Serbia (516 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/nexta_tv/status/1901244199220982213</link>
            <guid>43382093</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 20:40:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/nexta_tv/status/1901244199220982213">https://twitter.com/nexta_tv/status/1901244199220982213</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43382093">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://twitter.com/nexta_tv/status/1901244199220982213: Error: Request failed with status code 400]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Zlib-rs is faster than C (308 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://trifectatech.org/blog/zlib-rs-is-faster-than-c/</link>
            <guid>43381512</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 19:35:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://trifectatech.org/blog/zlib-rs-is-faster-than-c/">https://trifectatech.org/blog/zlib-rs-is-faster-than-c/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43381512">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://trifectatech.org/blog/zlib-rs-is-faster-than-c/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AI Is Making Developers Dumb (170 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://eli.cx/blog/ai-is-making-developers-dumb</link>
            <guid>43381215</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 18:51:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://eli.cx/blog/ai-is-making-developers-dumb">https://eli.cx/blog/ai-is-making-developers-dumb</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43381215">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://eli.cx/blog/ai-is-making-developers-dumb: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tcl Tutorial (157 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.tcl-lang.org/man/tcl8.5/tutorial/tcltutorial.html</link>
            <guid>43381195</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 18:48:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.tcl-lang.org/man/tcl8.5/tutorial/tcltutorial.html">https://www.tcl-lang.org/man/tcl8.5/tutorial/tcltutorial.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43381195">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.tcl-lang.org/man/tcl8.5/tutorial/tcltutorial.html: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Microsoft's 1986 IPO (109 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://dfarq.homeip.net/microsofts-1986-ipo/</link>
            <guid>43381141</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 18:41:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://dfarq.homeip.net/microsofts-1986-ipo/">https://dfarq.homeip.net/microsofts-1986-ipo/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43381141">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>On March 13, 1986, Microsoft shook up the financial world, and to some degree, we are still feeling the reverberations from that 40 years later. That was the day of Microsoft’s very successful IPO. The hunt for the next Microsoft began immediately, leading directly to the <a href="https://dfarq.homeip.net/when-the-dotcom-bubble-burst/">dotcom bubble</a> of the turn of the century.</p><h2>How big was Microsoft’s IPO?</h2><figure id="attachment_37141" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-37141"><a href="https://dfarq.homeip.net/?attachment_id=37141" rel="attachment wp-att-37141"><img data-recalc-dims="1" fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/dfarq.homeip.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Microsoft_Dubai.jpg?resize=225%2C300&amp;ssl=1" alt="Microsoft standing tall" width="225" height="300" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/dfarq.homeip.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Microsoft_Dubai.jpg?resize=225%2C300&amp;ssl=1 225w, https://i0.wp.com/dfarq.homeip.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Microsoft_Dubai.jpg?w=450&amp;ssl=1 450w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px"></a><figcaption id="caption-attachment-37141">Microsoft stood so tall after its 1986 IPO that the search for a repeat was a major contributor to a recession.</figcaption></figure><p>Microsoft’s IPO initially valued company at $21.00 per share. It raised $61 million for the company, and put its market capitalization at $777 million. The price peaked at $35.50 per share before settling to $27.75 at the end of the day. Microsoft expected it to take weeks to reach $27.75. Bill Gates owned 45% of the company’s stock, which meant on March 14, 1986, he was worth almost $350 million. He had not yet turned 31. The next year, he became the youngest person to become a billionaire, before he had turned 32.</p><h2>Why Microsoft waited so long</h2><p>Founded in 1975, Microsoft was an 11-year-old company at the time it went public. They waited so long because Bill Gates wanted to maintain control over the company as long as he could. By 1986, Microsoft had to go public. This wasn’t because they needed money. Their profit margins were enviable, at 34% of their pre tax revenue. Microsoft didn’t need the $61 million the IPO raised.</p><p>The reason Microsoft had to go public in 1986 was because Bill Gates had been using stock to attract talent. Microsoft projected that by sometime in 1987, they would have 500 shareholders, which would require Microsoft to register with the Securities and Exchange Commission, effectively turning them into a publicly traded company, but without the benefits of going public in the conventional way.</p><p>Backed into this corner, Gates agreed in late 1985 to pursue an IPO.</p><h2>Why was Microsoft so profitable?</h2><p>Motley Fool greatly oversimplifies Microsoft’s early years, as do others. They’re better at SEO than analysis. Microsoft’s best known products in 1986 were PC DOS and MS-DOS, the text-based operating systems for IBM and IBM-compatible PCs. In 1986, <a href="https://dfarq.homeip.net/microsoft-windows-first-announced-nov-10-1983/">Microsoft Windows existed</a>, barely, but wasn’t yet successful.</p><p>Microsoft’s secret was that virtually every computer on the market was running some Microsoft product. Its operating system powered the booming PC market. But Excel was the most popular spreadsheet on the Macintosh. Its predecessor, Multiplan, was a reasonably popular spreadsheet on other platforms. Microsoft Word was an up and coming word processor. Microsoft Basic was one of the most popular programming languages, and ran on virtually every platform.</p><p>Sometimes Microsoft licensed software on a royalty basis and sometimes for a flat rate up front. Getting the flat rate up front shielded Microsoft from losing profits to piracy early on. But once Microsoft could afford to risk some loss to piracy, it was more profitable to take a royalty per unit sold. There were <a href="https://dfarq.homeip.net/how-many-ibm-pcs-sold/">60 million IBM and IBM-compatible PCs</a> sold in the 1980s, and Microsoft collected a royalty on virtually every single one. Then in 1991, it discovered it could sell new versions of MS-DOS as upgrades and make money on each unit sold a second time.</p><p>When Windows 3.0 hit the market in May 1990, the game was essentially over. Microsoft could sell you an operating system, a graphical environment, and versions of Word and Excel that ran in that environment, all running on commodity hardware that was getting cheaper by the quarter, if not the month. Although it would be a few years before other companies would give up, a monopoly in operating systems and office suites was inevitable before 1990 was over.</p><p>The more successful Microsoft became, the more afraid of failure and anticompetitive it became. This led to legal issues in the late 1990s. Microsoft reformed to a degree and is more tolerant of certain competing products continuing to exist than it was in the 90s.</p><p>Today, Apple, Amazon, and Alphabet (formerly Google) are larger than Microsoft, but the four companies are the only technology firms in the 2024 Fortune 20 list. The fifth largest technology firm is Meta, the social media company everyone loves to hate, at #30.</p><h2>The legacy of Microsoft’s IPO</h2><p>To this day, young ambitious people enroll in school to get technical degrees in hopes of becoming the next Bill Gates, and venture capitalists like <a href="https://dfarq.homeip.net/how-shark-tanks-kevin-oleary-became-rich/">Kevin O’Leary</a> and Marc Andreessen (himself a cofounder of a <a href="https://dfarq.homeip.net/netscape-the-ipo-that-went-boom-on-its-way-up-and-down/">failed dotcom</a>) prey on them. These ambitious programmer/entrepreneurs rarely get rich, but the venture capitalists have figured out how to make money even as the businesses they fund fail.</p><p>Today’s entrepreneurs would do well to note that Microsoft made minimal use of venture capital. Microsoft’s only VC only owned 6.2 percent of the company. Gates didn’t trust them.</p><p>If you’re thinking of trying your hand at being the next Bill Gates, keep that in mind.</p><p>Another direct consequence of the Microsoft IPO was the dotcom bubble of the late 1990s and the subsequent recession. Fear of missing out on the next Microsoft drove up the value of anything tech- or Internet-related. Investors believed the next Microsoft would come out of that generation of companies. In the end they were kind of right. Two companies from that wave ended up matching and eventually eclipsing Microsoft. But it wasn’t exactly clear until a few years after the dotcom bust that Amazon and Google would be the ones to do it. Short-lived randos like <a href="https://dfarq.homeip.net/va-linux-the-biggest-dotcom-ipo/">VA Linux</a>, Geocities, Cyberrebate, and <a href="https://dfarq.homeip.net/the-most-excessive-dotcom-internet-america/">Internet America</a> were able to come along for the ride while the market shook out.</p><div itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope="" itemprop="author"><p><img data-recalc-dims="1" decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/dfarq.homeip.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/dave_farquhar_181px.jpg?resize=100%2C100&amp;ssl=1" data-src="https://i0.wp.com/dfarq.homeip.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/dave_farquhar_181px.jpg?resize=100%2C100&amp;ssl=1" width="100" height="100" alt="" itemprop="image"></p><div><p>David Farquhar is a computer security professional, entrepreneur, and author. He has written professionally about computers since 1991, so he was writing about retro computers when they were still new. He has been working in IT professionally since 1994 and has specialized in vulnerability management since 2013. He holds Security+ and CISSP certifications. Today he blogs five times a week, mostly about retro computers and retro gaming covering the time period from 1975 to 2000.</p></div></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>