<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 07:30:17 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[FDA declines to review Moderna's mRNA flu shot (109 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nbcnews.com/health/health-news/fda-declines-review-modernas-mrna-flu-shot-rcna258436</link>
            <guid>46968424</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 23:16:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/health/health-news/fda-declines-review-modernas-mrna-flu-shot-rcna258436">https://www.nbcnews.com/health/health-news/fda-declines-review-modernas-mrna-flu-shot-rcna258436</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46968424">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-testid="decibel-player"><p><span>Listen to this article with a </span><span>free account</span></p></div><div><p id="anchor-f723cc">The Food and Drug Administration rejected Moderna’s application for its mRNA-based flu vaccine, the drugmaker said Tuesday.</p><p id="anchor-140ab9">The move is the latest sign that the FDA, under Health Secretary Robert F. Kennedy Jr., is slow-walking vaccine approvals and taking a harder line on shots that use messenger RNA technology.</p><p id="anchor-dcf81b">Moderna’s vaccine uses the same mRNA technology as its Covid shot. </p><p id="anchor-a6cea3">In a release Tuesday, Moderna said the FDA did not identify any safety or efficacy concerns with the vaccine. Instead, it said the FDA took issue with the “comparator” in its clinical trial — the vaccine the company used as a benchmark to evaluate its own shot. </p><p id="anchor-41f779">The FDA said the use of the standard flu shot as a comparator “does not reflect the best-available standard of care.” The standard flu shot is FDA-approved.</p><p id="anchor-901d02">However, Moderna said that the agency’s stated reason is “inconsistent” with what regulators had told the company in 2024 and 2025. </p><p id="anchor-d112e7">“It should not be controversial to conduct a comprehensive review of a flu vaccine submission that uses an FDA-approved vaccine as a comparator in a study that was discussed and agreed on with CBER prior to starting,” Moderna CEO Stéphane Bancel said in the release,<strong> </strong>referring to the FDA’s Centers for Biologics Evaluation and Research, which reviews and approves vaccines, as well as other treatments such as gene therapies.</p><p id="anchor-a087df"><a href="https://feeds.issuerdirect.com/news-release.html?newsid=4899326521164266&amp;symbol=MRNA" target="_blank">Moderna said last year</a> that its mRNA flu shot was 26.6% more effective than the standard flu shot, based on a Phase 3 clinical trial. </p><p id="anchor-55a797">In an emailed statement, Andrew Nixon, a spokesperson for the Department of Health and Human Services, which oversees the FDA, said: “The FDA generally does not comment on regulatory communications to individual sponsors.”</p><p id="anchor-d8b1de">Last year, <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/health/health-news/updated-covid-vaccines-fall-may-jeopardy-rfk-jrs-new-rules-rcna204242" target="_blank">Kennedy ordered</a> that all new vaccines go through placebo-controlled clinical trials.</p><p id="anchor-c79a9c">When vaccines are already available for a disease, it's considered unethical to give clinical trial participants a placebo, rather than compare the new vaccine to the existing one. Giving a placebo would leave people who would be otherwise protected vulnerable to infection.</p><p id="anchor-c33254">Last May, Moderna withdrew its application seeking approval for its combination flu and Covid mRNA shot after the FDA <a href="https://www.biopharmadive.com/news/moderna-flu-covid-vaccine-fda-delay/746857/">asked for more data</a>.</p><p id="anchor-e4922e">Kennedy, an anti-vaccine activist, has <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/health/health-news/kennedy-draws-misinformation-playbook-touting-inhaled-steroid-treat-me-rcna200085">downplayed the benefits of vaccines</a> and has singled out vaccines made with mRNA as particularly dangerous, calling <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/health/health-news/covid-vaccine-kids-pregnant-women-cdc-recommendation-rfk-jr-rcna207312">the mRNA Covid vaccine</a> “the deadliest vaccine ever made.” </p><p id="anchor-65eede">Numerous studies have shown the mRNA vaccines are safe and effective. A <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC9871947/" target="_blank">2023 analysis in JAMA Pediatrics </a>reviewed 17 studies covering more than 10 million children ages 5 to 11 who got Pfizer’s or Moderna’s Covid vaccines. Vaccinated kids had a lower risk of infection and hospitalization compared to those who weren’t vaccinated. </p><p id="anchor-0ec4aa">In August, the Department of Health and Human Services <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/health/health-news/rfk-jr-cuts-500-million-mrna-vaccine-contracts-dealing-major-blow-prom-rcna223281">canceled nearly $500 million</a> in funding into mRNA vaccine research. </p><p id="anchor-9cd6a6">Several states have introduced legislation to ban mRNA vaccines.</p><p id="anchor-0c939d">Regulators in the European Union, Canada and Australia have accepted Moderna's mRNA flu vaccine application, the company said.</p></div><div data-activity-map="expanded-byline-article-bottom"><div data-testid="byline-thumbnail"><a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/author/berkeley-lovelace-jr-ncpn1284341" tabindex="-1"><picture data-testid="picture" data-flavor="focal" data-original-height="48" data-original-width="48"><source media="(min-width: 320px)" srcset="https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_focal-60x60,f_avif,q_auto:eco,dpr_2/newscms/2023_08/3595665/berkeley-lovelace-byline-jm-1.jpg 2x, https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_focal-60x60,f_auto,q_auto:best/newscms/2023_08/3595665/berkeley-lovelace-byline-jm-1.jpg 1x"><img loading="lazy" src="https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_focal-60x60,f_auto,q_auto:best/newscms/2023_08/3595665/berkeley-lovelace-byline-jm-1.jpg" alt="" height="48" width="48"></picture></a></div><p>Berkeley Lovelace Jr. is a health and medical reporter for NBC News. He covers the Food and Drug Administration, with a special focus on Covid vaccines, prescription drug pricing and health care. He previously covered the biotech and pharmaceutical industry with CNBC.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Day the Telnet Died (306 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.labs.greynoise.io/grimoire/2026-02-10-telnet-falls-silent/</link>
            <guid>46967772</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 22:20:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.labs.greynoise.io/grimoire/2026-02-10-telnet-falls-silent/">https://www.labs.greynoise.io/grimoire/2026-02-10-telnet-falls-silent/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46967772">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="quarto-content">
<!-- sidebar -->
<!-- margin-sidebar -->
    
<!-- main -->
<main id="quarto-document-content">

<!-- Google Tag Manager (noscript) -->

<!-- End Google Tag Manager (noscript) -->





<pre><code>A long, long time ago
I can still remember how a protocol
used to make me smile
And I knew if I had my chance
That I could make those botnets dance
And maybe they'd be happy for a while

But January made me shiver
With every packet I tried to deliver
Bad news on the backbone
I couldn't scan a single ASN

I can't remember if I cried
When my -f root hit an ACL line
But something touched me deep inside
The day the telnet died

So bye, bye mass spreading Mirai
Drove my SYNs down on the fiber line
But the fiber line was dry
And good old bots were passing creds in the clear and dry
Singin' this'll be the day that I die
This'll be the day that I die</code></pre>
<p>On January 14, 2026, at approximately 21:00 UTC, something changed in the internet’s plumbing. The GreyNoise Global Observation Grid recorded a sudden, sustained collapse in global telnet traffic — not a gradual decline, not scanner attrition, not a data pipeline problem, but a step function. One hour, ~74,000 sessions. The next, ~22,000. By the following hour, we were down to ~11,000 and the floor held.</p>
<p>Six days later, on <a href="https://seclists.org/oss-sec/2026/q1/89">January 20</a>, the security advisory for CVE-2026-24061 hit oss-security. By <a href="https://www.cisa.gov/news-events/alerts/2026/01/26/cisa-adds-five-known-exploited-vulnerabilities-catalog">January 26</a>, CISA had added it to the KEV catalog.</p>
<p>We wrote about the <a href="https://www.labs.greynoise.io/grimoire/2026-01-22-f-around-and-find-out-18-hours-of-unsolicited-houseguests/index.html">first 18 hours of exploitation activity</a> back on January 22. This post is about something different: the structural change in global telnet traffic that preceded the CVE, and why we think the two events may not be independent.</p>
<section id="the-drop">
<h2 data-anchor-id="the-drop">The Drop</h2>
<p><img src="https://www.labs.greynoise.io/grimoire/2026-02-10-telnet-falls-silent/media/asn-heatmap.png"></p>
<p>From December 1, 2025 through January 14, 2026, GreyNoise observed an average of ~914,000 non-spoofable telnet sessions per day across 51.2 million total sessions — let’s call that the “baseline”.</p>
<p>On January 14 at 21:00 UTC, hourly volume dropped 65% in a single tick. Within two hours it had fallen 83% below baseline. The new average settled around ~373,000 sessions/day — a <strong>59% sustained reduction</strong> that persists through the time of writing (February 10).</p>
<p>This wasn’t a taper. The hourly data around the inflection point tells the story:</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Time (UTC)</th>
<th>Sessions/Hour</th>
<th>Notes</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Jan 14, 19:00</td>
<td>73,900</td>
<td>Normal baseline</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Jan 14, 20:00</td>
<td>64,722</td>
<td>Normal baseline</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Jan 14, 21:00</strong></td>
<td><strong>22,460</strong></td>
<td><strong>65% drop in one hour</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Jan 14, 22:00</td>
<td>11,325</td>
<td>83% below baseline</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Jan 14, 23:00</td>
<td>11,147</td>
<td>New floor established</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Jan 15, 00:00</td>
<td>12,089</td>
<td>Sustained at reduced level</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>That kind of step function — propagating within a single hour window — reads as a configuration change on routing infrastructure, not behavioral drift in scanning populations.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-went-silent">
<h2 data-anchor-id="what-went-silent">What Went Silent</h2>
<p>Eighteen ASNs with significant pre-drop telnet volume (&gt;50K sessions each) went to absolute zero after January 15. Some of the names that stand out:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Vultr</strong> (AS20473) — 382K pre-drop sessions, then nothing</li>
<li><strong>Cox Communications</strong> (AS22773) — 150K sessions, gone</li>
<li><strong>Charter/Spectrum</strong> (AS20115) — 141K sessions, gone</li>
<li><strong>BT/British Telecom</strong> (AS2856) — 127K sessions, gone</li>
</ul>
<p>Five entire countries vanished from GreyNoise telnet data: Zimbabwe, Ukraine, Canada, Poland, and Egypt. Not reduced — <em>zero</em>.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the major cloud providers were largely unaffected or even increased. AWS went <em>up</em> 78%. Contabo <em>up</em> 90%. DigitalOcean essentially flat at +3%. Cloud providers have extensive private peering at major IXPs that bypasses traditional transit backbone paths. Residential and enterprise ISPs typically don’t.</p>
</section>
<section id="wheres-the-filter">
<h2 data-anchor-id="wheres-the-filter">Where’s the Filter?</h2>
<p>The pattern points toward one or more North American Tier 1 transit providers implementing port 23 filtering:</p>
<p>The timing — 21:00 UTC, which is 16:00 EST — is consistent with a US-based maintenance window. US residential ISPs (Cox, Charter, Comcast at -74%) were devastated while cloud providers on the same continent peered around whatever changed. Verizon/UUNET (AS701) dropped 79%, and as a major Tier 1 backbone, that’s consistent with it either being the filtering entity or sitting directly upstream of one. The 21% residual traffic on AS701 would represent paths that don’t transit the filtered links.</p>
<p>Countries that rely on transatlantic or transpacific backbone routes to reach US-hosted infrastructure got hit hardest. Countries with strong direct European peering (France at +18%, Germany at -1%) were essentially unaffected.</p>
<p>The Chinese backbone providers (China Telecom and China Unicom) both dropped ~59%, uniformly. That uniformity suggests the filter sits on the US side of transpacific links rather than within China. If this were a Chinese firewall action, we’d expect asymmetric impact across Chinese carriers and a harder cutoff.</p>
</section>
<section id="then-came-the-cve">
<h2 data-anchor-id="then-came-the-cve">Then Came the CVE</h2>
<p>CVE-2026-24061 is a critical (CVSS 9.8) authentication bypass in GNU Inetutils telnetd. The flaw is an argument injection in how telnetd handles the <code>USER</code> environment variable during telnet option negotiation. An attacker sends <code>-f root</code> as the username value, and <code>login(1)</code> obediently skips authentication, handing over a root shell. No credentials required. No user interaction. The vulnerable code was introduced in a 2015 commit and sat undiscovered for nearly 11 years.</p>
<p>The timeline:</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Date</th>
<th>Event</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Jan 14, 21:00 UTC</td>
<td>Telnet backbone drop begins</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Jan 20</td>
<td>CVE-2026-24061 advisory posted to oss-security</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Jan 21</td>
<td>NVD entry published; GreyNoise tag deployed; first exploitation observed</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Jan 22</td>
<td><a href="https://www.labs.greynoise.io/grimoire/2026-01-22-f-around-and-find-out-18-hours-of-unsolicited-houseguests/index.html">GreyNoise Grimoire post</a> on initial 18 hours of exploitation</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Jan 26</td>
<td>CISA adds CVE-2026-24061 to KEV catalog</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The six-day gap between the telnet drop and the public CVE disclosure is the interesting part. On its face, the drop can’t have been <em>caused</em> by the CVE disclosure, because the drop happened first. But “caused by” isn’t the only relationship worth considering.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-supposition">
<h2 data-anchor-id="the-supposition">The Supposition</h2>
<p>Responsible disclosure timelines don’t start at publication. The researcher who found this (<a href="https://thehackernews.com/2026/01/critical-gnu-inetutils-telnetd-flaw.html">credited as Kyu Neushwaistein / Carlos Cortes Alvarez</a>) reported the flaw on January 19, per public sources. But the coordination that leads to patches being ready, advisories being drafted, and CISA being prepared to add something to the KEV within six days of publication typically starts earlier than the day before disclosure.</p>
<p>Here’s what we think may have happened: advance notification of a trivially exploitable, unauthenticated root-access vulnerability affecting telnet daemons reached parties with the ability to act on it at the infrastructure level. A backbone or transit provider — possibly responding to a coordinated request, possibly acting on their own assessment — implemented port 23 filtering on transit links. The filtering went live on January 14. The public disclosure followed on January 20.</p>
<p>This would explain:</p>
<ul>
<li>The timing gap (advance notification → infrastructure response → public disclosure)</li>
<li>The specificity of the filtering (port 23/TCP, not a general routing change)</li>
<li>The topology of impact (transit-dependent paths affected, direct-peering paths not)</li>
<li>The sustained nature (the filter is still in place weeks later)</li>
</ul>
<p>We can’t prove this. The backbone drop could be entirely coincidental — ISPs have been slowly moving toward filtering legacy insecure protocols for years (ref: Wannacry), and January 14 could simply have been when someone’s change control ticket finally got executed. Correlation, temporal proximity, and a plausible mechanism <em>absolutely do not</em> equal causation.</p>
<p>But the combination of a Tier 1 backbone implementing what appears to be port 23 filtering, followed six days later by the disclosure of a trivially exploitable root-access telnet vulnerability, followed four days after <em>that</em> by a CISA KEV listing, is worth documenting and considering.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-the-post-drop-world-looks-like">
<h2 data-anchor-id="what-the-post-drop-world-looks-like">What the Post-Drop World Looks Like</h2>
<p>The telnet landscape after January 14 shows a recurring sawtooth pattern — periodic spikes followed by troughs (e.g., January 28 at 806K sessions, then January 30 at 191K). This could indicate intermittent filter application, routing flaps around the filtering infrastructure, or scanner campaigns that happen to use paths not affected by the filter.</p>
<p>The weekly averages tell the sustained story:</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Week Starting</th>
<th>Avg Daily Sessions</th>
<th>% of Baseline</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Dec 01</td>
<td>1,086,744</td>
<td>119%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Jan 05</td>
<td>985,699</td>
<td>108%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Jan 19</td>
<td>363,184</td>
<td>40%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Jan 26</td>
<td>407,182</td>
<td>45%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Feb 02</td>
<td>322,606</td>
<td>35%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>We’re now operating at roughly a third of the pre-drop baseline, and the trend is still slightly downward.</p>
</section>
<section id="practical-implications">
<h2 data-anchor-id="practical-implications">Practical Implications</h2>
<p>If you’re running GNU Inetutils telnetd anywhere — and given the 11-year window, there are plenty of embedded systems, network appliances, and legacy Linux installations where it’s still likely present — patch to version 2.7-2 or later, or disable the service entirely. The CISA KEV remediation deadline for federal agencies is February 16, 2026. As noted, GreyNoise observed exploitation attempts <a href="https://www.labs.greynoise.io/grimoire/2026-01-22-f-around-and-find-out-18-hours-of-unsolicited-houseguests/index.html">within hours of disclosure</a> and the campaign peaked at ~2,600 sessions/day in early February before tapering off.</p>
<p>If you’re a network operator and you haven’t already filtered port 23 at your border, the backbone-level filtering we’ve documented here suggests the industry is moving in that direction regardless. Someone upstream of a significant chunk of the internet’s transit infrastructure apparently decided telnet traffic isn’t worth carrying anymore. That’s probably the right call.</p>
<p>If you know anything about this (or was the brave soul who implemented it), drop us a line at <a href="mailto:research@greynoise.io?subject=I-broke-telnet"><code>research@greynoise.io</code></a>.</p>


</section>

</main> <!-- /main -->





</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How did Windows 95 get permission to put the Weezer video Buddy Holly on the CD? (162 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://devblogs.microsoft.com/oldnewthing/20260210-00/?p=112052</link>
            <guid>46965440</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 19:25:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/oldnewthing/20260210-00/?p=112052">https://devblogs.microsoft.com/oldnewthing/20260210-00/?p=112052</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46965440">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div> <!-- page container -->
  <div>
        <header>
            <div>
                <p><span>February 10th, 2026</span>
                                    </p>
                <p><span><img alt="like" src="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/oldnewthing/wp-content/themes/devblogs-evo/images/emojis/like.svg"><img alt="mind blown" src="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/oldnewthing/wp-content/themes/devblogs-evo/images/emojis/mind-blown.svg"></span><span>3 reactions</span>                </p>
            </div>
                    </header><!-- .entry-header -->
                <div>
                    <p><img src="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/oldnewthing/wp-content/uploads/sites/38/2019/02/RaymondChen_5in-150x150.jpg" alt="Raymond Chen">
                    </p>
                    
                </div>
    </div><!-- container-sidebar-left-post - top heading -->
<div id="single-wrapper">
    
    <article data-clarity-region="article" id="post-112052">
        <div data-bi-area="body_article" data-bi-id="post_page_body_article">
            <p>Some time ago, I noted that <a title="Why did the Windows 95 CD have extra fun stuff?" href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/oldnewthing/20060103-52/?p=32853"> the Windows 95 CD contained a variety of multimedia extras</a>, partly because they were fun, and partly to show off Windows 95’s multimedia capabilities.</p>
<p>One of those multimedia extras was the music video for the song <i><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buddy_Holly_(song)">Buddy Holly</a></i> by the band <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weezer">Weezer</a>. Acquiring permission to redistribute the video took multiple steps.</p>
<p>First, Microsoft had to secure the rights to the song itself, which was negotiated directly with Weezer’s publisher Geffen Records, and apparently <a title="Knowledge Drop: Weezer Had No Idea The Music Video For " href="https://genius.com/a/weezer-had-no-idea-the-music-video-for-buddy-holly-would-be-included-with-windows-95"> without the knowledge of the band members themselves</a>. They were reportedly upset that they weren’t consulted but later realized that it was “one of the greatest things that could have happened to us. Can you imagine that happening today? It’s like, there’s one video on YouTube, and it’s your video.”</p>
<p>But that only secured the rights to the music. What about the video?</p>
<p>The video takes place in a reconstruction of a location from the <i>Happy Days</i> television program, and clips from that show were spliced into the music video to create the illusion that many of the characters from the show were part of the video. The lawyer responsible for securing the rights to the video had to contact all of the actors from <i>Happy Days</i> to get their permission. That lawyer thoroughly enjoyed the assignment. I don’t know whether he got to talk to the actors directly, or only to their agents, but I can imagine it being an interesting experience trying to find Henry Winkler’s telephone number (or his agent’s telephone number) with a chance of talking to The Fonz himself.</p>
        </div><!-- .entry-content -->

        <!-- AI Disclaimer -->
            </article>
    
</div><!-- This is the end of main section three column -->
<div><!-- Author section -->
            <h2>Author</h2>
            <div><div><p><img src="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/oldnewthing/wp-content/uploads/sites/38/2019/02/RaymondChen_5in-150x150.jpg" alt="Raymond Chen"></p></div><p>Raymond has been involved in the evolution of Windows for more than 30 years. In 2003, he began a Web site known as The Old New Thing which has grown in popularity far beyond his wildest imagination, a development which still gives him the heebie-jeebies. The Web site spawned a book, coincidentally also titled The Old New Thing (Addison Wesley 2007). He occasionally appears on the Windows Dev Docs Twitter account to tell stories which convey no useful information.</p></div>        </div>  <div><!-- start max-width bottom section -->
      <!-- Comments section -->
      
      <div>
          <!-- Read Next Section -->
    <h2>Read next</h2>
    
            </div>
      <!-- Stay Informed Section -->
      
<div>
    <div id="subscribe_form" data-bi-area="body_newsletter" data-bi-id="post_page_body_newsletter">
        <h2 id="stayInformed">Stay informed</h2>
        <p>Get notified when new posts are published.</p>
            
        </div>        <div>
        <p>Follow this blog</p>
        <div data-bi-area="body_blog_follow">
            <a title="twitter" data-bi-id="post_page_body_blog_follow" data-bi-name="The Old New Thing-twitter" aria-label="Follow Us on Twitter" target="_blank" href="https://twitter.com/ChenCravat"><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24"><path d="M14.4821 10.6218L21.0389 3H19.4852L13.7919 9.61788L9.24467 3H4L10.8763 13.0074L4 21H5.55384L11.5661 14.0113L16.3683 21H21.613L14.4817 10.6218H14.4821ZM12.3539 13.0956L11.6572 12.0991L6.11372 4.16971H8.50033L12.974 10.5689L13.6707 11.5655L19.4859 19.8835H17.0993L12.3539 13.096V13.0956Z"></path></svg></a><p><a title="youtube" data-bi-id="post_page_body_blog_follow" data-bi-name="The Old New Thing-youtube" aria-label="Follow Us on YouTube" target="_blank" href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLlrxD0HtieHge3_8Dm48C0Ns61I6bHThc"><img src="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/oldnewthing/wp-content/themes/devblogs-evo/images/social-icons/youtube.svg" alt="youtube"></a></p><a title="GitHub" data-bi-id="post_page_body_blog_follow" data-bi-name="The Old New Thing-github" aria-label="Follow Us on GitHub" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/oldnewthing"><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="22" height="24" viewBox="0 0 25 24"><g clip-path="url(#clip0_4234_38739)"><path fill-rule="evenodd" clip-rule="evenodd" d="M13.2989 0C6.67328 0 0.5 5.37254 0.5 12.0004C0.5 17.3022 3.93804 21.7996 8.70651 23.3864C9.3069 23.4969 9.52569 23.1263 9.52569 22.8081C9.52569 22.5237 9.51538 21.7686 9.50949 20.7675C6.17163 21.4924 5.46737 19.1586 5.46737 19.1586C4.9215 17.7722 4.13473 17.4031 4.13473 17.4031C3.0452 16.6591 4.21724 16.6738 4.21724 16.6738C5.4217 16.7585 6.05523 17.9107 6.05523 17.9107C7.12562 19.7443 8.86416 19.2146 9.54779 18.9074C9.65682 18.1324 9.96696 17.6035 10.3095 17.3037C7.64497 17.0009 4.84341 15.971 4.84341 11.3727C4.84341 10.0629 5.3112 8.99107 6.07881 8.15274C5.95505 7.84923 5.54325 6.62856 6.19668 4.97695C6.19668 4.97695 7.2037 4.65429 9.49623 6.20719C10.4532 5.94051 11.4801 5.80791 12.5004 5.80276C13.5199 5.80791 14.5461 5.94051 15.5045 6.20719C17.7956 4.65429 18.8011 4.97695 18.8011 4.97695C19.456 6.62856 19.0442 7.84923 18.9212 8.15274C19.6903 8.99107 20.1544 10.0629 20.1544 11.3727C20.1544 15.9828 17.3484 16.9972 14.6758 17.2941C15.106 17.6646 15.4898 18.3969 15.4898 19.5166C15.4898 21.1204 15.475 22.4147 15.475 22.8081C15.475 23.1293 15.6916 23.5027 16.3001 23.3856C21.0649 21.7951 24.5 17.3007 24.5 12.0004C24.5 5.37254 19.1267 0 12.4989 0"></path></g><defs><clipPath id="clip0_4234_38739"><rect width="24" height="24" fill="white" transform="translate(0.5)"></rect></clipPath></defs></svg></a><a title="RSS Feed" data-bi-id="post_page_body_blog_follow" data-bi-name="The Old New Thing-rss-feed" aria-label="Subscribe to Our RSS Feed" target="_blank" href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/oldnewthing/feed/"><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none"><path d="M6.25 3C4.45507 3 3 4.45507 3 6.25V17.75C3 19.5449 4.45507 21 6.25 21H17.75C19.5449 21 21 19.5449 21 17.75V6.25C21 4.45507 19.5449 3 17.75 3H6.25ZM6.75 7.5C6.34494 7.5 6 7.18276 6 6.7777V6.7233C6 6.33021 6.30507 6.00189 6.69816 6.00012L6.75 6C12.9632 6 18 11.0368 18 17.25L17.9999 17.3018C17.9981 17.6949 17.6698 18 17.2767 18H17.2223C16.8172 18 16.5 17.6551 16.5 17.25C16.5 11.8652 12.1348 7.5 6.75 7.5ZM13.294 18H13.2036C12.805 18 12.5 17.6486 12.5 17.25C12.5 14.0744 9.92564 11.5 6.75 11.5C6.35135 11.5 6 11.195 6 10.7964V10.706C6 10.3267 6.2871 10.0048 6.66639 10.0005C6.69422 10.0002 6.72209 10 6.75 10C10.7541 10 14 13.2459 14 17.25C14 17.2779 13.9998 17.3058 13.9995 17.3336C13.9952 17.7129 13.6733 18 13.294 18ZM7.5 18C6.67157 18 6 17.3284 6 16.5C6 15.6716 6.67157 15 7.5 15C8.32843 15 9 15.6716 9 16.5C9 17.3284 8.32843 18 7.5 18Z" fill="#DA3B01"></path></svg></a>        </div>
    </div>
</div>
    </div><!-- end comments bottom full-width section -->
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The switch to Linux and the beginning of my self-hosting journey (111 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://hazemkrimi.tech/blog/linux-self-hosting-journey/</link>
            <guid>46964159</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 18:09:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://hazemkrimi.tech/blog/linux-self-hosting-journey/">https://hazemkrimi.tech/blog/linux-self-hosting-journey/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46964159">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content"><p>I made the full switch into Linux in 2023 since I started following YouTubers like <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@LukeSmithxyz" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Luke Smith</a>
and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/MentalOutlaw" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mental Outlaw</a>
to name a few and then got into the rabbit hole of self-hosting on a budget therefore it is safe for me to say that I am somewhat experienced in this practice so I will walk you in this post on my setups over those 3 years, what I learned and what are my plans for the future.</p><h2 id="linux-as-my-main-os">Linux As My Main OS</h2><p>Back then I only had a desktop that I bought the year before and was using Windows 10 on it for gaming and work since at that time I was working with Microsoft software. Here are its specs (the only thing that remained till now is the GPU and case as I replaced everything else):</p><ul><li>Intel Core i5 10400.</li><li>16 GB DDR4 RAM.</li><li>NVIDIA GeForce RTX 3050 8GB VRAM.</li><li>1 TB NVMe.</li></ul><p>Here is a picture of my desktop where I first bought it (apologies for the image quality):</p><p><img src="https://hazemkrimi.tech/blog/linux-self-hosting-journey/desktop.webp" alt="Picture of my desktop in 2023"></p><p>For me the main reason for making the switch to Linux is that I wanted to learn it hands on and dedicate my computer for software development, I started out with Debian 11 as my first distro.
I wasn’t doing too much gaming but I came up with a solution for some of the games I was playing with friends that had Anti-Cheat and that was a VM with GPU passthrough thanks to QEMU/KVM which was built in and allowed me to have a config in such a way that Windows and the Anti-Cheat software can’t figure that they are running in a VM.</p><p>Here are guides I used back in 2024 when I updated my VM to use Windows 11 through Qemu/KVM and GPU Passthrough:</p><ul><li><a href="https://sysguides.com/install-kvm-on-linux" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Installing KVM And QEMU</a></li><li><a href="https://sysguides.com/install-a-windows-11-virtual-machine-on-kvm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Installing Windows 11 On VMs</a></li></ul><p>Other reasons that are still as important are ownership and privacy: I get to use my OS without having to have an account tied to the developers and customize it to my heart’s content all with minimal resource consumption. There are still issues with driver and software compatibility but it is getting better in the recent years thanks to projects like <a href="https://www.winehq.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wine</a>
and <a href="https://github.com/ValveSoftware/Proton" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Proton</a>
.</p><h2 id="self-hosting">Self-Hosting</h2><p>Previously, I had my website deployed on Vercel since back then I made it using Next.js but as I got deeper into the optimization meme I recreated my website in <a href="https://gohugo.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hugo</a>
which worked out pretty well and I am now more satisfied with its performance. Naturally, since I migrated away from Next.js I decided to get my own VPS and deploy the website there. I would say I got an overpowered one for my uses but I gained the capability to have more stuff in there like some of my personal projects and my own email through open source tools (check Luke Smith’s <a href="https://github.com/LukeSmithxyz/emailwiz" target="_blank" rel="noopener">emailwiz</a>
repo). Here is the VPS specs which I got from Hostinger through a YouTuber’s affiliate link:</p><ul><li>AMD EPYC 9354P 8 Cores.</li><li>32 GB DDR4 RAM.</li><li>400 GB NVMe.</li><li>32 TB Bandwidth.</li></ul><p>Having to manage a server comes with learning more tools related to System Administration like Nginx, Certbot, GitHub Actions, Systemd services, setting up SSH and firewall rules, blocking unwanted traffic through <a href="https://github.com/crowdsecurity/crowdsec" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Crowdsec</a>
. This made me get a better hands on understanding on how different components work in Linux since nothing is abstracted away like it was with Vercel and had to configure almost everything by hand. Here are some guides that helped me setup my website on my VPS:</p><ul><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DmbBgXK8M5M" target="_blank" rel="noopener">VPS Setup And Website Deployment</a></li><li><a href="https://curiouscoding.nl/posts/goaccess-setup/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Based Website Analytics Written In C</a></li></ul><p>And here is a sneak peek at my latest analytics stats:</p><video autoplay="" muted="" playsinline="" loop="" preload="metadata">
<source src="https://hazemkrimi.tech/blog/linux-self-hosting-journey/analytics.webm" type="video/webm">Your browser does not support the video tag.</video><h2 id="my-home-server">My Home Server</h2><p>The next thing I did was to get some sort of personal cloud that is hosted locally mainly to sync and backup files between my devices and block ads in my local network. For that I started out with a Raspberry Pi 4 that had 8 GB of RAM in which I connected a 500 GB SSD external drive and for cooling I got heatsinks and a cpu fan and kept it running 24/7 and it worked surprisingly well for a good amount of time. I used <a href="https://syncthing.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Syncthing</a>
for file synchronization and <a href="https://pi-hole.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PiHole</a>
as my local network DNS server to block unwanted incoming traffic. Here are pictures of my Raspberry Pi and how I mounted it to my old desk in 2024:</p><p><img src="https://hazemkrimi.tech/blog/linux-self-hosting-journey/pi.webp" alt="Picture of my RPi"></p><p><img src="https://hazemkrimi.tech/blog/linux-self-hosting-journey/pi-boxed-ssd.webp" alt="Picture of my RPi mounted to my old desk"></p><p>Then in 2025 I got a new desktop so I used the old one as my home server. I upgraded the RAM to 32 GB and the CPU to an i5 12400 and got an SSD on which I installed <a href="https://pve.proxmox.com/wiki/Main_Page" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Proxmox VE</a>
. Thanks to the <a href="https://community-scripts.github.io/ProxmoxVE/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">community scripts</a>
I was able to get the stuff I had on the Pi migrated to my home server with ease into separate LXCs and VMs. I also added the ability to connect to my home server remotely through VPN using <a href="https://www.wireguard.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wireguard</a>
and since my ip at home is dynamic I registered a subdomain as a DDNS record and used <a href="https://ddclient.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ddclient</a>
on the server to automatically send the new ip every time it changes. Here are some guides I used to configure PCIe passthrough both to VMs and LXCs to pass my GPU for better performance:</p><ul><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_hOBAGKLQkI" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Proxmox PCIe Passthrough</a></li><li><a href="https://digitalspaceport.com/proxmox-lxc-docker-gpu-passthrough-setup-guide/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Proxmox LXC GPU Passthrough Written Guide</a></li></ul><p>Here is my home server running 24/7 and connected to a UPS to stay up for a while in case of a power outage (the other UPS is connected to other devices like the router):</p><p><img src="https://hazemkrimi.tech/blog/linux-self-hosting-journey/home-server.webp" alt="Picture of my home server"></p><p>And here is its proxmox dashboard from where I can access LXCs and VMs or monitor and manage resources:</p><p><img src="https://hazemkrimi.tech/blog/linux-self-hosting-journey/proxmox.webp" alt="Proxmox dashboard"></p><h2 id="next-steps">Next Steps</h2><p>Getting into Linux and self-hosting made me better at system administration and got me excited and hopeful about having as much autonomy as possible with the tools I use especially with the current times where almost every commercial software dedicated to normal consumers hoards and sells data to be used for ads even in paid products. Although it is not for everyone since it involves a lot of configuration which requires patience but for me it is so I will continue to incoporate free and open source tools into my “personal cloud” to keep learning as a software engineer and to keep control of my digital footprint.</p><p>One step I recently took in that direction is installing my own search engine using <a href="https://docs.searxng.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">SearXNG</a>
on my VPS which I can use on all of my devices. Other steps I plan to take is to get into more Linux distros (I tried debian based, Arch and Nix) and most importantly contribute back to the open source tools in any way I can whether financially or through assistance in development.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google Handed ICE Student Journalist's Bank and Credit Card Numbers (737 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://theintercept.com/2026/02/10/google-ice-subpoena-student-journalist/</link>
            <guid>46963804</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 17:48:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://theintercept.com/2026/02/10/google-ice-subpoena-student-journalist/">https://theintercept.com/2026/02/10/google-ice-subpoena-student-journalist/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46963804">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    
    <p><span>Google provided</span> Immigration and Customs Enforcement with a wide array of personal data on a student activist and journalist, including his credit card and bank account numbers, according to a copy of an ICE subpoena obtained by The Intercept.</p>
<p><a href="https://theintercept.com/2025/09/16/google-facebook-subpoena-ice-students-gaza/">Amandla Thomas-Johnson</a> had attended a protest targeting companies that supplied weapons to Israel at a Cornell University job fair in 2024 for all of five minutes, but the action got him banned from campus. When President Donald Trump assumed office and issued a series of executive orders targeting students who protested in support of Palestinians, Thomas-Johnson and his friend Momodou Taal went into hiding.</p>
<p>Google informed Thomas-Johnson via a brief email in April that it had already shared his metadata with the Department of Homeland Security, as The Intercept <a href="https://theintercept.com/2025/09/16/google-facebook-subpoena-ice-students-gaza/">previously reported</a>. But the full extent of the information the tech giant provided —&nbsp;including usernames, addresses, itemized list of services, including any IP masking services, telephone or instrument numbers, subscriber numbers or identities, and credit card and bank account numbers — was not previously known.</p>
<p>“I’d already seen the subpoena request that Google and Meta had sent to Momodou [Taal], and I knew that he had gotten in touch with a lawyer and the lawyer successfully challenged that,” Thomas-Johnson said. “I was quite surprised to see that I didn’t have that opportunity.”<ins></ins></p>
<!-- BLOCK(cta)[0](%7B%22componentName%22%3A%22CTA%22%2C%22entityType%22%3A%22SHORTCODE%22%2C%22optional%22%3Atrue%7D)(%7B%7D) --><!-- END-BLOCK(cta)[0] -->
<p>The subpoena provides no justification for why ICE is asking for this information, except that it’s required “in connection with an investigation or inquiry relating to the enforcement of U.S. immigration laws.” In the subpoena, ICE requests that Google not “disclose the existence of this summons for indefinite period of time.”</p>
<p>Thomas-Johnson, who is British, believes that ICE requested that information to track and eventually detain him — but he had already fled to Geneva, Switzerland, and is now in Dakar, Senegal.&nbsp;</p>

<p>The Electronic Frontier Foundation, which is representing Thomas-Johnson, and the ACLU of Northern California sent a letter to Google, Amazon, Apple, Discord, Meta, Microsoft, and Reddit last week calling on tech companies to resist similar subpoenas in the future from DHS without court intervention. The letter asks the companies to provide users with as much notice as possible before complying with a subpoena to give them the opportunity to fight it, and to resist gag orders that would prevent the tech companies from informing targets that a subpoena was issued.</p>
<p>“Your promises to protect the privacy of users are being tested right now. As part of the federal government’s unprecedented campaign to target critics of its conduct and policies, agencies like DHS have repeatedly demanded access to the identities and information of people on your services,” the letter reads. “Based on our own contact with targeted users, we are deeply concerned your companies are failing to challenge unlawful surveillance and defend user privacy and speech.”</p>
<p>In addition to Thomas-Johnson’s case, the letter refers to other instances in which technology companies provided user data to DHS, including a subpoena sent to Meta to “unmask” the identities of users who documented immigration raids in California. Unlike Thomas-Johnson, users in that case were given the chance to fight the subpoena because they were made aware of it before Meta complied.</p>
<p>Lindsay Nash, a professor at Cardozo Law and a former staff attorney with ACLU Immigrants’ Rights Project, said that by not giving prior notice, Google deprived Thomas-Johnson of his ability to protect his information.</p>
<figure>
<blockquote>
<p>“Your promises to protect the privacy of users are being tested right now.”</p>
</blockquote>
</figure>
<p>“The problem is that it doesn’t allow the person whose personal information is on the line and whose privacy may be being invaded to raise challenges to the disclosure of that potentially private information,” Nash said. “And I think that’s important to protect rights that they may have to their own information.”</p>
<p>Google did not respond to a request for comment.</p>
<p>Tech companies’ data sharing practices are primarily governed by two federal laws, the Stored Communications Act, which protects the privacy of digital communications, including emails, and Section 5 of the Federal Trade Commission Act, which prohibits unfair or deceptive trade practices.</p>
<p>“Under both federal law and the law of every state, you cannot deceive consumers,” said Neil Richards, a law professor at Washington University St. Louis who specializes in privacy, the internet, and civil liberties. “And if you make a material misrepresentation about your data practices, that’s a deceptive trade practice.”</p>
<p>Whether or not corporations are clear enough with consumers about how they collect and share their <a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2019/07/ftc-sues-cambridge-analytica-settles-former-ceo-app-developer">data has been litigated for decades</a>, Richards said, referencing the infamous Cambridge Analytica lawsuit brought by the Federal Trade Commission, alleging that the company misled Facebook users about data collection and sharing.</p>
<!-- BLOCK(newsletter)[0](%7B%22componentName%22%3A%22NEWSLETTER%22%2C%22entityType%22%3A%22SHORTCODE%22%2C%22optional%22%3Atrue%7D)(%7B%7D) --><!-- END-BLOCK(newsletter)[0] -->
<p>Google’s <a href="https://policies.google.com/privacy#infosharing">public privacy policy acknowledges</a> that it will share personal information in response to an “enforceable governmental request,” adding that its legal team will “frequently push back when a request appears to be overly broad or doesn’t follow the correct process.”</p>
<p>According to Google, the <a href="https://transparencyreport.google.com/user-data/overview">company overwhelmingly complied with the millions of requests</a> made by the government for user information over the last decade. Its data also shows that those requests have spiked over the last five years. It’s unclear how many of those users were given notice of those requests ahead of time or after.</p>
<p>Richards said that cases like these emphasize the need for legal reforms around data privacy and urged Congress to amend the Stored Communications Act to require a higher standard before the government can access our digital data. He also said the federal government needs to regulate Big Tech and place “substantive restrictions on their ability to share information with the government.”</p>
<p>It’s hard to know exactly how tech companies are handling our personal data in relation to the government, but there seems to have been a shift in optics, Richards said. “What we have seen in the 12 months since the leaders of Big Tech were there on the podium at the inauguration,” Richards said, “is much more friendliness of Big Tech towards the government and towards state power.”</p>
<p>From Dakar, Thomas-Johnson said that understanding the extent of the subpoena was terrifying but had not changed his commitment to his <a>work</a>.</p>
<p>“As a journalist, what’s weird is that you’re so used to seeing things from the outside,” said Thomas-Johnson, whose work has appeared in outlets including Al Jazeera and The Guardian. “We need to think very hard about what resistance looks like under these conditions… where government and Big Tech know so much about us, can track us, can imprison, can destroy us in a variety of ways.”</p>
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Singularity will occur on a Tuesday (986 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://campedersen.com/singularity</link>
            <guid>46962996</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 17:04:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://campedersen.com/singularity">https://campedersen.com/singularity</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46962996">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><main><article><figure><img src="https://campedersen.com/_next/static/media/always-has-been.7ceff529.jpg" alt="Always has been astronaut meme"><figcaption><p>"Wait, the singularity is just humans freaking out?" "Always has been."</p></figcaption></figure>
<p>Everyone in <span>San Francisco</span> is talking about the singularity. At dinner parties, at coffee shops, at the OpenClaw meetup where Ashton Kutcher showed up for some reason. The conversations all have the same shape: someone says it's coming, someone says it's hype, and nobody has a number.</p>
<p>This seems like the wrong question. If things are accelerating (and they measurably are) the interesting question isn't <em>whether</em>. It's <em>when</em>. And if it's accelerating, we can calculate <span>exactly when</span>.</p>
<p>I collected five real metrics of AI progress, fit a hyperbolic model to each one independently, and found the one with genuine curvature toward a <span>pole</span>. The date has <span>millisecond precision</span>. There is a countdown.</p>
<p>(I am aware this is <span>unhinged</span>. We're doing it anyway.)</p>
<!-- -->
<h2>The Data</h2>
<p>Five metrics, chosen for what I'm calling their <em>anthropic significance</em> (anthropic here in the Greek sense ("pertaining to humans"), not the company, though they appear in the dataset with suspicious frequency):</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>MMLU scores</strong>: the SAT for language models</li>
<li><strong>Tokens per dollar</strong>: cost collapse of intelligence (log-transformed, because the Gemini Flash outlier spans 150× the range otherwise)</li>
<li><strong>Frontier release intervals</strong>: shrinking gap between <span>"holy shit"</span> moments</li>
<li><strong>arXiv "emergent" papers</strong> (<span>trailing 12mo</span>): field excitement, measured <span>memetically</span></li>
<li><strong>Copilot code share</strong>: fraction of code written by AI</li>
</ol>
<!--$!--><template data-dgst="BAILOUT_TO_CLIENT_SIDE_RENDERING"></template><p>Calibrating instruments...</p><!--/$-->
<p>Each metric <span>normalized</span> to <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><mo stretchy="false">[</mo><mn>0</mn><mo separator="true">,</mo><mn>1</mn><mo stretchy="false">]</mo></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">[0, 1]</annotation></semantics></math></span></span>. Release intervals inverted (shorter = better). Tokens per dollar log-transformed before normalizing (the raw values span <span>five orders of magnitude</span>; without the log, Gemini Flash at 2.5M tokens/$ dominates the fit and everything else is noise). Each series keeps its own scale, no merging into a single ensemble.</p>
<!-- -->
<h2>Why Hyperbolic</h2>
<p>Most people extrapolate AI with <span>exponentials</span>. Wrong move!</p>
<p>An exponential <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><mi>f</mi><mo stretchy="false">(</mo><mi>t</mi><mo stretchy="false">)</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>a</mi><msup><mi>e</mi><mrow><mi>b</mi><mi>t</mi></mrow></msup></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">f(t) = ae^{bt}</annotation></semantics></math></span></span> approaches infinity only as <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><mi>t</mi><mo>→</mo><mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mi></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t \to \infty</annotation></semantics></math></span></span>. You'd be waiting forever. Literally.</p>
<p>We need a function that hits infinity at a <em>finite</em> time. That's the whole point of a singularity: a pole, a <span>vertical asymptote</span>, <span>the math breaking</span>:</p>
<p><span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><mi>x</mi><mo stretchy="false">(</mo><mi>t</mi><mo stretchy="false">)</mo><mo>=</mo><mfrac><mi>k</mi><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub><mo>−</mo><mi>t</mi></mrow></mfrac><mo>+</mo><mi>c</mi></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">x(t) = \frac{k}{t_s - t} + c</annotation></semantics></math></span></span></p>
<p>As <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><mi>t</mi><mo>→</mo><msubsup><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi><mo>−</mo></msubsup></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t \to t_s^-</annotation></semantics></math></span></span>, the denominator goes to zero. <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><mi>x</mi><mo stretchy="false">(</mo><mi>t</mi><mo stretchy="false">)</mo><mo>→</mo><mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mi></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">x(t) \to \infty</annotation></semantics></math></span></span>. Not a bug. <span><em>The</em> feature.</span></p>
<!--$!--><template data-dgst="BAILOUT_TO_CLIENT_SIDE_RENDERING"></template><p>Calibrating instruments...</p><!--/$-->
<p><strong>Polynomial</strong> growth (<span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msup><mi>t</mi><mi>n</mi></msup></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t^n</annotation></semantics></math></span></span>) never reaches infinity at finite time. You could wait until <span>heat death</span> and <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msup><mi>t</mi><mn>47</mn></msup></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t^{47}</annotation></semantics></math></span></span> would still be finite. Polynomials are for people who think AGI is "decades away."</p>
<p><strong>Exponential</strong> growth reaches infinity at <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><mi>t</mi><mo>=</mo><mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mi></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t = \infty</annotation></semantics></math></span></span>. Technically a singularity, but an infinitely patient one. Moore's Law was exponential. We are no longer on Moore's Law.</p>
<p><strong>Hyperbolic</strong> growth is what happens when the thing that's growing <em>accelerates its own growth</em>. Better AI → better AI research tools → better AI → better tools. Positive feedback with <span>supralinear dynamics</span>. The singularity is real and finite.</p>
<!-- -->
<h2>The Fit</h2>
<p>The procedure is straightforward, which should concern you.</p>
<p>The model fits a separate hyperbola to each metric:</p>
<p><span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msubsup><mi>y</mi><mi>i</mi><mrow><mo stretchy="false">(</mo><mi>j</mi><mo stretchy="false">)</mo></mrow></msubsup><mo>=</mo><mfrac><msub><mi>k</mi><mi>j</mi></msub><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub><mo>−</mo><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>i</mi></msub></mrow></mfrac><mo>+</mo><msub><mi>c</mi><mi>j</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">y_i^{(j)} = \frac{k_j}{t_s - t_i} + c_j</annotation></semantics></math></span></span></p>
<p>Each series <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><mi>j</mi></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">j</annotation></semantics></math></span></span> gets its own <span>scale <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>k</mi><mi>j</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">k_j</annotation></semantics></math></span></span></span> and <span>offset <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>c</mi><mi>j</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">c_j</annotation></semantics></math></span></span></span>. The singularity time <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t_s</annotation></semantics></math></span></span> is shared. MMLU scores and tokens-per-dollar have no business being on the same y-axis, but they can agree on when the pole is.</p>
<p>For each candidate <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t_s</annotation></semantics></math></span></span>, the per-series fits are <span>linear in <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>k</mi><mi>j</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">k_j</annotation></semantics></math></span></span> and <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>c</mi><mi>j</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">c_j</annotation></semantics></math></span></span></span>. The question is: which <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t_s</annotation></semantics></math></span></span> makes the hyperbola fit best?</p>
<p>Here's the thing nobody tells you about fitting singularities: most metrics don't actually have one. If you minimize total <span>RSS</span> across all series, the best <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t_s</annotation></semantics></math></span></span> is always at infinity. A distant hyperbola <span>degenerates</span> into a line, and lines fit noisy data just fine. The "singularity date" ends up being whatever you set as the search boundary. You're finding the edge of your search grid, not a singularity.</p>
<p>So instead, we look for the real signal. For each series independently, <span>grid search</span> <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t_s</annotation></semantics></math></span></span> and find the <span>R²</span> peak: the date where hyperbolic fits <em>better</em> than any nearby alternative. If a series genuinely curves toward a pole, its R² will peak at some finite <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t_s</annotation></semantics></math></span></span> and then decline. If it's really just linear, R² will keep increasing as <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub><mo>→</mo><mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mi></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t_s \to \infty</annotation></semantics></math></span></span> and never peak. No peak, no signal, no vote!</p>
<p><span>One series peaks!</span> arXiv "emergent" (the count of AI papers about emergence) has a clear, unambiguous R² maximum. The other four are <span>monotonically</span> better fit by a line. The singularity date comes from the one metric that's actually going hyperbolic.</p>
<p>This is more honest than forcing five metrics to average out to a date that none of them individually support.</p>
<p>Same inputs → same date. <span>Deterministic</span>. The <span>stochasticity</span> is in the universe, not the model.</p>
<!-- -->
<h2>The Date</h2>
<!--$!--><template data-dgst="BAILOUT_TO_CLIENT_SIDE_RENDERING"></template><p>Calibrating instruments...</p><!--/$-->
<p>The fit <span>converged</span>! Each series has its own <span>R²</span> at the shared <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t_s</annotation></semantics></math></span></span>, so you can see exactly which metrics the hyperbola captures well and which it doesn't. arXiv's R² is the one that matters. It's the series that actually peaked.</p>
<p>The 95% confidence interval comes from <span>profile likelihood</span> on <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t_s</annotation></semantics></math></span></span>. We slide the singularity date forward and backward until the fit degrades past an <span>F-threshold</span>.</p>
<!-- -->
<h2>The Countdown</h2>
<!--$!--><template data-dgst="BAILOUT_TO_CLIENT_SIDE_RENDERING"></template><p>Calibrating instruments...</p><!--/$-->
<!-- -->
<h2>Sensitivity</h2>
<p>How much does the date move if we drop one metric entirely?</p>
<!--$!--><template data-dgst="BAILOUT_TO_CLIENT_SIDE_RENDERING"></template><p>Calibrating instruments...</p><!--/$-->
<p>If dropping a single series shifts <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t_s</annotation></semantics></math></span></span> by years, that series was doing all the work. If the shifts are zero, the dropped series never had a signal in the first place.</p>
<p>The table tells the story plainly: arXiv is doing all the work. Drop it and the date jumps to the search boundary (no remaining series has a finite peak). Drop anything else and nothing moves. They were never contributing to the date, only providing context curves at the shared <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t_s</annotation></semantics></math></span></span>.</p>
<p>Note: Copilot has exactly 2 data points and 2 parameters (<span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><mi>k</mi></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">k</annotation></semantics></math></span></span> and <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><mi>c</mi></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">c</annotation></semantics></math></span></span>), so it fits any hyperbola perfectly. Zero RSS, zero influence on <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t_s</annotation></semantics></math></span></span>. It's along for the ride!</p>
<!-- -->
<h2>What <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t_s</annotation></semantics></math></span></span> Actually Means</h2>
<p>The model says <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><mi>y</mi><mo>→</mo><mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mi></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">y \to \infty</annotation></semantics></math></span></span> at <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t_s</annotation></semantics></math></span></span>. But what does "infinity" mean for arXiv papers about emergence? It doesn't mean infinitely many papers get published on a Tuesday in 2034.</p>
<p>It means the model breaks. <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t_s</annotation></semantics></math></span></span> is the point where the current trajectory's curvature can no longer be sustained. The system either breaks through into something qualitatively new, or it saturates and the hyperbola was wrong. A <span>phase transition marker</span>, not a physical prediction.</p>
<figure><img src="https://campedersen.com/_next/static/media/wile-e-coyote.817e5484.jpg" alt="Wile E. Coyote holding a BYE sign as he falls off a cliff"><figcaption><p><span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t_s</annotation></semantics></math></span></span> is the moment he looks down.</p></figcaption></figure>
<p>But here's the part that should unsettle you: <strong>the metric that's actually going hyperbolic is human attention, not machine capability.</strong></p>
<p>MMLU, tokens per dollar, release intervals. The actual capability and infrastructure metrics. All linear. No pole. No singularity signal. The only curve pointing at a finite date is the count of papers about emergence. Researchers noticing and naming new behaviors. <em>Field excitement, measured memetically.</em></p>
<p>The data says: machines are improving at a constant rate. Humans are freaking out about it at an accelerating rate that accelerates its own acceleration.</p>
<p>That's a very different singularity than the one people argue about.</p>
<!-- -->
<h2>The Social Singularity</h2>
<p>If <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t_s</annotation></semantics></math></span></span> marks when the rate of AI surprises exceeds human capacity to process them, the interesting question isn't what happens to the machines. It's what happens to us.</p>
<p>And the uncomfortable answer is: <span>it's already happening.</span></p>
<figure><img src="https://campedersen.com/_next/static/media/this-is-fine.4256436c.jpg" alt="This is fine dog sitting in a burning room"></figure>
<p><strong>The labor market isn't adjusting. It's snapping.</strong> In 2025, <a href="https://fortune.com/2025/12/09/forever-layoffs-job-security-k-shaped-economy-white-collar-recession-challenger-glassdoor/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">1.1 million layoffs were announced</a>. Only the sixth time that threshold has been breached since 1993. Over <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/11/04/white-collar-layoffs-ai-cost-cutting-tariffs.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">55,000 explicitly cited AI</a>. But <a href="https://hbr.org/2026/01/companies-are-laying-off-workers-because-of-ais-potential-not-its-performance" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">HBR found</a> that companies are cutting based on AI's <em>potential</em>, not its performance. The displacement is anticipatory. The curve doesn't need to reach the pole. It just needs to <span><em>look like it will</em></span>.</p>
<p><strong>Institutions can't keep up.</strong> The EU AI Act's high-risk rules have <a href="https://artificialintelligenceact.eu/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">already been delayed to 2027</a>. The US <a href="https://www.metricstream.com/blog/ai-regulation-trends-ai-policies-us-uk-eu.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">revoked its own 2023 AI executive order</a> in January 2025, then issued a new one in December trying to preempt state laws. California and Colorado are <a href="https://www.softwareimprovementgroup.com/blog/us-ai-legislation-overview/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">going their own way anyway</a>. The laws being written today regulate 2023's problems. By the time legislation catches up to GPT-4, we're on GPT-7. When governments visibly can't keep up, trust doesn't erode. It <a href="https://phys.org/news/2025-10-falters-weak-digital-misinformation.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">collapses</a>. Global trust in AI has dropped to 56%.</p>
<p><strong>Capital is concentrating at dot-com levels.</strong> The top 10 S&amp;P 500 stocks (almost all AI-adjacent) hit <a href="https://www.apolloacademy.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/ExtremeAIConcentration-090825.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">40.7% of index weight</a> in 2025, surpassing the dot-com peak. Since ChatGPT launched, AI-related stocks have captured <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/10/22/your-portfolio-may-be-more-tech-heavy-than-you-think.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">75% of S&amp;P 500 returns, 80% of earnings growth, and 90% of capital spending growth</a>. The <span>Shiller CAPE</span> is at <a href="https://www.ainvest.com/news/market-concentration-500-record-year-history-warns-2026-2512/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">39.4</a>. The last time it was this high was <span>1999</span>. The money flooding in doesn't require AI to actually reach superintelligence. It just requires enough people to believe the curve keeps going up.</p>
<p><strong>People are losing the thread.</strong> Therapists are <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2026/01/24/ai-artificial-intelligence-worries-therapy.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">reporting a surge</a> in what they're calling <span>FOBO</span> (Fear of Becoming Obsolete). The clinical language is striking: patients describe it as <em>"the universe saying, 'You are no longer needed.'"</em> <a href="https://allwork.space/2026/01/long-term-fears-build-as-60-of-u-s-workers-say-ai-will-cut-more-jobs-than-it-adds-in-2026/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">60% of US workers</a> believe AI will cut more jobs than it creates. AI usage is up 13% year-over-year, but confidence in it has <a href="https://fortune.com/2026/01/21/ai-workers-toxic-relationship-trust-confidence-collapses-training-manpower-group/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">dropped 18%</a>. <span>The more people use it, the less they trust it.</span></p>
<p><strong>The epistemics are cracking.</strong> Less than <a href="https://research.aimultiple.com/reproducible-ai/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">a third of AI research is reproducible</a>. Under 5% of researchers share their code. Corporate labs are publishing less. The gap between what frontier labs know and what the public knows is growing, and the people making policy are operating on information that's <a href="https://www.cfr.org/articles/how-2026-could-decide-future-artificial-intelligence" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">already obsolete</a>. The experts who testify before Congress contradict each other, because the field is moving <span>faster than expertise can form.</span></p>
<p><strong>The politics are realigning.</strong> <a href="https://time.com/7371825/trump-data-center-ai-backlash-ai-america-china/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">TIME</a> is writing about populist AI backlash. <a href="https://www.foreignaffairs.com/united-states/coming-ai-backlash" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Foreign Affairs</a> published "The Coming AI Backlash: How the Anger Economy Will Supercharge Populism." <a href="https://www.huffpost.com/entry/the-coming-war-over-ai-will-define-the-2026-midterms_n_6953f7fbe4b06a970133dfb7" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">HuffPost</a> says AI will define the 2026 midterms. MAGA is <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2026/02/02/politics/artificial-intelligence-maga-divide-trump" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">splitting</a> over whether AI is pro-business or anti-worker. Sanders proposed a data center moratorium. The old left-right axis is buckling under the weight of a question it wasn't built to answer.</p>
<p>All of this is happening <strong><span>eight years before <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t_s</annotation></semantics></math></span></span></span></strong>. The social singularity is <span>front-running</span> the technical one. The institutional and psychological disruption doesn't wait for capabilities to go vertical. It starts as soon as the <em>trajectory</em> becomes legible.</p>
<p>The pole at <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t_s</annotation></semantics></math></span></span> isn't when machines become superintelligent. It's when humans lose the ability to make coherent collective decisions about machines. The actual capabilities are almost beside the point. The social fabric frays at the seams of attention and institutional response time, not at the frontier of model performance.</p>
<!-- -->
<h2>Caveats</h2>
<p><strong>The date comes from one series.</strong> arXiv "emergent" is the only metric with genuine hyperbolic curvature. The other four are better fit by straight lines. The singularity date is really "the date when AI emergence research goes vertical." Whether field excitement is a <span>leading indicator</span> or a <span>lagging one</span> is the crux of whether this means anything.</p>
<figure><img src="https://campedersen.com/_next/static/media/honest-work.9594c4e9.jpg" alt="It ain't much, but it's honest work"></figure>
<p><strong>The model assumes <span>stationarity</span>.</strong> Like assuming the weather will continue to be "changing." The curve will bend, either into a <span>logistic</span> (the hype saturates) or into something the model can't represent (genuine phase transition). <span><span><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>t</mi><mi>s</mi></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">t_s</annotation></semantics></math></span></span> marks where the current regime can't continue, not what comes after.</p>
<p><strong>MMLU is hitting its ceiling.</strong> Benchmark saturation introduces a <span>leptokurtic compression artifact</span>. MMLU's low R² reflects this. The hyperbola is <span>the wrong shape</span> for saturating data.</p>
<p><strong>Tokens per dollar is <span>log-transformed</span></strong> (values span five orders of magnitude) <strong>and <span>non-monotonic</span></strong> (GPT-4 cost more than 3.5; Opus 4.5 costs more than DeepSeek-R1). The cost curve isn't smooth: it's <span>Pareto advances</span> interspersed with <span>"we spent more on this one."</span></p>
<p><strong>Five metrics isn't enough.</strong> More series with genuine hyperbolic curvature would make the date less dependent on arXiv alone. A proper study would add SWE-bench, ARC, GPQA, compute purchases, talent salaries. I used five because <span>five fits in a table</span>.</p>
<p><strong>Copilot has two data points.</strong> Two parameters, two points, zero <span>degrees of freedom</span>, zero RSS contribution. The sensitivity analysis confirms it doesn't matter.</p>
<!-- -->
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>Real data. Real model. Real date!</p>
<p>The math found one metric curving toward a pole on a specific day at a specific millisecond: the rate at which humans are discovering emergent AI behaviors. The other four metrics are linear. The machines are improving steadily. <span>We are the ones accelerating!</span></p>
<p>The social consequences of that acceleration (labor displacement, institutional failure, capital concentration, epistemic collapse, political realignment) are not predictions for 2034. They are descriptions of 2026. The singularity in the data is a singularity in human attention, and it is already exerting gravitational force on everything it touches.</p>
<p>I see no reason to let <span>epistemological humility</span> interfere with a <span>perfectly good timer</span>.</p>
<span>See you on the other side!</span></article><!--$--><!--/$--></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA["Hate brings views": Confessions of a London fake news TikToker (161 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.londoncentric.media/p/london-tiktok-fake-news-creator-hate-immigrants</link>
            <guid>46962924</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 17:00:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.londoncentric.media/p/london-tiktok-fake-news-creator-hate-immigrants">https://www.londoncentric.media/p/london-tiktok-fake-news-creator-hate-immigrants</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46962924">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EHJR!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7dd2a1c7-a179-4daa-b9a2-8f12eb9a4900_1500x1000.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EHJR!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7dd2a1c7-a179-4daa-b9a2-8f12eb9a4900_1500x1000.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EHJR!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7dd2a1c7-a179-4daa-b9a2-8f12eb9a4900_1500x1000.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EHJR!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7dd2a1c7-a179-4daa-b9a2-8f12eb9a4900_1500x1000.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EHJR!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7dd2a1c7-a179-4daa-b9a2-8f12eb9a4900_1500x1000.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EHJR!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7dd2a1c7-a179-4daa-b9a2-8f12eb9a4900_1500x1000.png" width="1456" height="971" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/7dd2a1c7-a179-4daa-b9a2-8f12eb9a4900_1500x1000.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:971,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:752556,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.londoncentric.media/i/187071963?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7dd2a1c7-a179-4daa-b9a2-8f12eb9a4900_1500x1000.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EHJR!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7dd2a1c7-a179-4daa-b9a2-8f12eb9a4900_1500x1000.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EHJR!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7dd2a1c7-a179-4daa-b9a2-8f12eb9a4900_1500x1000.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EHJR!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7dd2a1c7-a179-4daa-b9a2-8f12eb9a4900_1500x1000.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EHJR!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7dd2a1c7-a179-4daa-b9a2-8f12eb9a4900_1500x1000.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><span>London Centric’s investigation into the </span><a href="https://www.londoncentric.media/p/tiktok-london-immigrants-fake-news-house-tours" rel="">TikToker secretly filming fake anti-immigrant videos inside Londoners’ homes</a><span> generated a huge public response. </span></p><p>Amid the hundreds of comments two major questions remained: Who was the individual behind the TikTok account and what motivated them to make the videos? </p><p>Today, we have an extraordinary confession from someone purporting to be the TikToker in question. They are just one person in a sea of online hate content. But their explanation of their actions helps shed light on the motivations behind a wider online trend. </p><p>London is being used as the backdrop for inaccurate viral videos that reach enormous audiences around the world by playing into the worst stereotypes about the capital. </p><p><strong>See that story – and what Sadiq Khan has to say about our reporting – below. </strong></p><p><em>Read to the end for Taylor Swift’s visit to a forthcoming Croydon mixed-used redevelopment, the growing number of freemasons in the Met police, and what we missed about Jeffrey Epstein’s London.</em></p><p><strong>By Katherine Denkinson and Jim Waterson</strong></p><p>The man on the recording is baffled. He can’t understand how London Centric traced his anonymous hate-filled London TikTok account back to his employer by geolocating the wheelie bins in his videos.</p><p>“I thought no one’s gonna notice that,” he says. “Why would someone?”</p><p>Last summer, the man says, he found himself sitting in his car, analysing trends on TikTok. His day job was conducting viewings for an estate agency but he was trying to come up with an idea for a viral video account that could be run as a money-making side-hustle.</p><p>“I was thinking of unique videos I can do for people,” he says on the tape. </p><p>That’s when he had a brainwave: “Hate brings views.” </p><p>At that time protests outside asylum hotels were spreading across the country. The man says he noticed “far-right people” were among the most engaged on TikTok. They were easy to rile up: “They hate such videos of illegal migrants. I was like, why not?”</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EuSS!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbae4353c-8b38-46a0-95eb-557b393eb3fc_1236x1088.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EuSS!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbae4353c-8b38-46a0-95eb-557b393eb3fc_1236x1088.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EuSS!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbae4353c-8b38-46a0-95eb-557b393eb3fc_1236x1088.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EuSS!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbae4353c-8b38-46a0-95eb-557b393eb3fc_1236x1088.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EuSS!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbae4353c-8b38-46a0-95eb-557b393eb3fc_1236x1088.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EuSS!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbae4353c-8b38-46a0-95eb-557b393eb3fc_1236x1088.jpeg" width="1236" height="1088" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/bae4353c-8b38-46a0-95eb-557b393eb3fc_1236x1088.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1088,&quot;width&quot;:1236,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:452687,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.londoncentric.media/i/187071963?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbae4353c-8b38-46a0-95eb-557b393eb3fc_1236x1088.jpeg&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EuSS!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbae4353c-8b38-46a0-95eb-557b393eb3fc_1236x1088.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EuSS!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbae4353c-8b38-46a0-95eb-557b393eb3fc_1236x1088.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EuSS!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbae4353c-8b38-46a0-95eb-557b393eb3fc_1236x1088.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EuSS!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbae4353c-8b38-46a0-95eb-557b393eb3fc_1236x1088.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>Typical screengrabs of videos from the viral TikTok account.</figcaption></figure></div><p>The result was the account Reform_UK_2025, which co-opted the logo and name of Nigel Farage’s political movement without permission from the party. It posted video tours of Londoners’ homes accompanied by an AI-generated voice claiming properties in Knightsbridge and Chelsea had been handed over to illegal immigrants for free. It smeared residents, who were visible in some of the videos, as rapists and said that others proclaimed their hatred of the UK while collecting the keys.</p><p>It was an instant hit, attracting millions of views. It was also, the man confesses, all lies.</p><p><strong>“Dangerous and divisive”</strong></p><p>You don’t have to believe London is anywhere near perfect to recognise the increasing divergence between the way the city is portrayed online and the reality on the streets.</p><p>Sadiq Khan told London Centric that our latest investigation into this anonymous TikTok account reveals part of a “dangerous and divisive” trend that sees “bad faith actors spreading hate for clicks”.</p><p>“Accounts are talking London down because the algorithms reward them for doing so,” said the mayor.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!n136!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5cbd0ba6-ae1b-47b2-8158-5febab9a9d03_1238x936.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!n136!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5cbd0ba6-ae1b-47b2-8158-5febab9a9d03_1238x936.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!n136!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5cbd0ba6-ae1b-47b2-8158-5febab9a9d03_1238x936.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!n136!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5cbd0ba6-ae1b-47b2-8158-5febab9a9d03_1238x936.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!n136!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5cbd0ba6-ae1b-47b2-8158-5febab9a9d03_1238x936.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!n136!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5cbd0ba6-ae1b-47b2-8158-5febab9a9d03_1238x936.jpeg" width="1238" height="936" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/5cbd0ba6-ae1b-47b2-8158-5febab9a9d03_1238x936.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:936,&quot;width&quot;:1238,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:373708,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.londoncentric.media/i/187071963?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5cbd0ba6-ae1b-47b2-8158-5febab9a9d03_1238x936.jpeg&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" title="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!n136!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5cbd0ba6-ae1b-47b2-8158-5febab9a9d03_1238x936.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!n136!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5cbd0ba6-ae1b-47b2-8158-5febab9a9d03_1238x936.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!n136!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5cbd0ba6-ae1b-47b2-8158-5febab9a9d03_1238x936.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!n136!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5cbd0ba6-ae1b-47b2-8158-5febab9a9d03_1238x936.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>How legitimate private tenants were described on the viral TikTok account.</figcaption></figure></div><p><strong>The “one rogue contractor” defence</strong></p><p>When London Centric tried to work out who was running the Reform_UK_2025 account, our investigation led us to SmartLet Estates, a north London estate agency. </p><p>When we confronted company director Sam Wasserstrum, he said he knew who was running the TikTok account but wasn’t willing to share their name with us. He claimed they were a member of the public who had been looking to rent a flat from his company.</p><p>He now accepts that was a lie – and he knew it was a lie when he told us. </p><p>Now, Wasserstrum wants to set out a different version of events. He says the person behind the camera was really a “rogue” contractor he employed for two years as a viewings agent to show potential residents around the properties. Wasserstrum says he had no idea that his employee had been running the hate-filled TikTok account until we first approached his company in November. He says the employee was sacked soon afterwards and he regrets ever telling us that a client was responsible.</p><p>To back up his case, Wasserstrum provided London Centric with multiple lengthy audio recordings of what he says is him confronting the anonymous employee. One of these tapes, he says, was recorded before he told London Centric he would not reveal the name of the culprit. The other was recorded after we published our article.</p><p>Wasserstrum did not provide the name of employee and we have not been able to independently verify the veracity of his story. However, metadata associated the audio files suggests the conversations took place around the dates that London Centric began asking questions.</p><p>The extraordinary taped confession is a rare insight into what motivates people to run fake news accounts on TikTok – and how monetising engagement can also effectively monetise hate, with little concern for its real-world impact.</p><p><strong>“One day I might make some money.”</strong></p><p>The audio on the tape is clear, with Wasserstrum’s voice asking questions in what sounds like an HR-style meeting.</p><p>The employee explains his motivation for setting up the anti-migrant fake news account was simple: “One day I might make some money.”</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!347C!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0a4f6cd-1ea3-4846-9ce1-9f902a66bb74_1030x1500.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!347C!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0a4f6cd-1ea3-4846-9ce1-9f902a66bb74_1030x1500.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!347C!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0a4f6cd-1ea3-4846-9ce1-9f902a66bb74_1030x1500.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!347C!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0a4f6cd-1ea3-4846-9ce1-9f902a66bb74_1030x1500.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!347C!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0a4f6cd-1ea3-4846-9ce1-9f902a66bb74_1030x1500.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!347C!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0a4f6cd-1ea3-4846-9ce1-9f902a66bb74_1030x1500.jpeg" width="432" height="629.1262135922331" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/f0a4f6cd-1ea3-4846-9ce1-9f902a66bb74_1030x1500.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1500,&quot;width&quot;:1030,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:432,&quot;bytes&quot;:195041,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.londoncentric.media/i/187071963?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0a4f6cd-1ea3-4846-9ce1-9f902a66bb74_1030x1500.jpeg&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!347C!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0a4f6cd-1ea3-4846-9ce1-9f902a66bb74_1030x1500.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!347C!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0a4f6cd-1ea3-4846-9ce1-9f902a66bb74_1030x1500.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!347C!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0a4f6cd-1ea3-4846-9ce1-9f902a66bb74_1030x1500.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!347C!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0a4f6cd-1ea3-4846-9ce1-9f902a66bb74_1030x1500.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>Another video supposedly showing a house given to illegal immigrants. When London Centric visited the London property we found legal residents renting privately.</figcaption></figure></div><p>The aim, he explains, was to build an audience and then make cash through TikTok, which allows people to monetise content once they reach a certain number of views and followers on the platform.</p><p>He’d previously run a TikTok account that had amassed 24,000 followers. One night, he was astonished to find, he received his first payout from TikTok’s creator scheme.</p><p>His head was turned by the substantial sum of money: “I told my wife, wow, it’s £1,000.”</p><p>Then, to his annoyance, TikTok immediately deleted his account because he was just stealing other people’s videos and reposting them.</p><p>Hooked on the income and in search for a new source of original content, he decided to start filming videos of homes across London while he was hosting viewings.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!GIdl!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbee6fc16-6b08-4277-9ef3-ea77a9e39b11_1116x952.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!GIdl!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbee6fc16-6b08-4277-9ef3-ea77a9e39b11_1116x952.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!GIdl!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbee6fc16-6b08-4277-9ef3-ea77a9e39b11_1116x952.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!GIdl!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbee6fc16-6b08-4277-9ef3-ea77a9e39b11_1116x952.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!GIdl!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbee6fc16-6b08-4277-9ef3-ea77a9e39b11_1116x952.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!GIdl!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbee6fc16-6b08-4277-9ef3-ea77a9e39b11_1116x952.jpeg" width="1116" height="952" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/bee6fc16-6b08-4277-9ef3-ea77a9e39b11_1116x952.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:952,&quot;width&quot;:1116,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:342385,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.londoncentric.media/i/187071963?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbee6fc16-6b08-4277-9ef3-ea77a9e39b11_1116x952.jpeg&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" title="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!GIdl!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbee6fc16-6b08-4277-9ef3-ea77a9e39b11_1116x952.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!GIdl!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbee6fc16-6b08-4277-9ef3-ea77a9e39b11_1116x952.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!GIdl!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbee6fc16-6b08-4277-9ef3-ea77a9e39b11_1116x952.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!GIdl!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbee6fc16-6b08-4277-9ef3-ea77a9e39b11_1116x952.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>Furious comments on the TikTok account about the houses being handed to “illegal immigrants”.</figcaption></figure></div><p>He added an AI-generated voiceover about asylum seekers, rapists, and illegal immigrants then pressed upload. The audience response was instant and enormous, and TikTok’s algorithm responded by pushing it into the feeds of hundreds of thousands of people. Irate Londoners drove up engagement by complaining they couldn’t afford such properties while illegal immigrants were supposedly getting them for free.</p><p><em>London Centric doesn’t have a marketing team – if you found this article interesting, please forward it to a friend, post it in your WhatsApp group, or recommend it on social platforms.</em></p><p><span>Last year a </span><a href="https://www.thebureauinvestigates.com/stories/2025-10-16/new-ai-video-tools-are-fuelling-racism-on-tiktok" rel="">report</a><span> by The Bureau of Investigative Journalism showed AI-generated racist videos amassing millions of views despite breaching TikTok’s guidelines on hate-speech. </span></p><p>A spokesperson for TikTok told London Centric that “hate has no place” on its platform: “Of the content we’ve removed for breaking these rules, more than 94% was taken down before being reported to us, and we work with experts to keep ahead of evolving trends and continually strengthen our safeguards against hate.”</p><p>The man on the tape seems to feel otherwise.</p><p>“My first video got one million [views],” he says. “Most of the videos got over 10,000… so I thought, one day I might make some money.”</p><p>TikTok told us: “This article is based on the opinion of one unnamed individual, and it is not representative of the positive and creative experience that millions enjoy every day on TikTok.”</p><p><strong>“I wrote down ‘illegal migrants’.”</strong></p><p><span>The TikToker appears to have no concept of the potential real-world impact of his uploads, instead considering everything in terms of view counts and pieces of content. He even suggests that Wasserstrum should not be concerned by London Centric’s reporting because </span><a href="https://www.tiktok.com/@jimwaterson/video/7599207225571233046?lang=en" rel="">our own video</a><span> didn’t attract anything like as many viewers as his original hate-filled fake uploads. </span></p><p>“Their video didn’t even go that viral,” he offers by way of defence, arguing it could therefore be ignored. “They only got like 200,000 views on TikTok. It’s probably gonna die. It’s not gonna last long.”</p><p>The man tells Wasserstrum that he does not want to own up to running the account because “it’s going to make it much worse” and could “ruin [his] life”. In any case, he says, journalists would simply think he was a “paid actor”.</p><p>Wasserstrum can be heard on the recordings spelling out to the man how London Centric had approached the business. “They came to the office... they had every single fact you can think about,” he says. “They’ve cross referenced everything… We’ve had management companies calling us, councils calling us up, saying you’re putting our clients in danger.”</p><p>The man appears confused by the fuss his actions have caused. He gives the impression that he considered TikTok’s algorithm and the site’s content regulation policies to be the ultimate arbiter of whether a video crossed a line. </p><p>He insists the impact on tenants whose faces are visible in some of the videos was limited because they “didn’t get a lot of views” compared to his other content.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!9sZR!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff200f2f0-5de3-46cd-9621-9ee531cdccce_494x229.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!9sZR!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff200f2f0-5de3-46cd-9621-9ee531cdccce_494x229.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!9sZR!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff200f2f0-5de3-46cd-9621-9ee531cdccce_494x229.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!9sZR!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff200f2f0-5de3-46cd-9621-9ee531cdccce_494x229.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!9sZR!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff200f2f0-5de3-46cd-9621-9ee531cdccce_494x229.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!9sZR!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff200f2f0-5de3-46cd-9621-9ee531cdccce_494x229.jpeg" width="494" height="229" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/f200f2f0-5de3-46cd-9621-9ee531cdccce_494x229.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:229,&quot;width&quot;:494,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:10844,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.londoncentric.media/i/187071963?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff200f2f0-5de3-46cd-9621-9ee531cdccce_494x229.jpeg&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!9sZR!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff200f2f0-5de3-46cd-9621-9ee531cdccce_494x229.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!9sZR!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff200f2f0-5de3-46cd-9621-9ee531cdccce_494x229.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!9sZR!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff200f2f0-5de3-46cd-9621-9ee531cdccce_494x229.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!9sZR!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff200f2f0-5de3-46cd-9621-9ee531cdccce_494x229.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>A comment left by the account creator on one of his videos.</figcaption></figure></div><p>“It wasn’t racist,” the man says of his account. He argues that if the videos had really been racist, TikTok’s algorithm would have downgraded the content. Instead, he was rewarded with millions of views. He was just an entrepreneur following a simple content strategy: “Every single video I would basically copy paste the same thing. I wrote down ‘illegal migrants’.”</p><p><strong>“Spreading hate for clicks”</strong></p><p>London Centric took our findings to the mayor of London, Sadiq Khan, who recently raised concerns about the growing impact of dubious viral videos on global perceptions of the city. </p><p>“While the social media revolution has come with extraordinary benefits, we’re also seeing a surge in misinformation and online abuse, due to a lack of sufficient guardrails,” the mayor told us.</p><p>“The large social media companies and regulators need to do much more to prevent algorithms pushing hate and violence and promoting misinformation and disinformation into people’s feeds.</p><p>“Our democracies are being undermined by those bad faith actors spreading hate for clicks.” </p><p><strong>“We have reported the matter to the police”</strong></p><p>On Friday Wasserstrum said that he has asked the police to investigate his former employee.</p><p>In a statement issued to London Centric the estate agency boss said: “We are aware of the vile and extremely dangerous TikTok videos that were filmed inside properties let by SmartLet Estates. We recognise the very real threat that these videos posed to the individuals filmed and to whom false views were attributed. We have reported the matter to the police.</p><p>“We conducted a thorough investigation as soon as the matter was brought to our attention. We established that the videos were created by a third-party contractor who acted without the authority, knowledge, or consent of the company. We severed all ties with the contractor immediately. We are appalled by his actions and condemn them in the strongest possible terms.</p><p>“We are committed to acting transparently and rebuilding trust with our partners and the communities we serve. We are fully prepared to cooperate with the authorities and to assist with any investigation.”</p><p>Despite fostering online hatred, the man recorded by Wasserstrum insists he doesn’t personally share the views expressed on his TikTok account. Instead, he suggests his fake anti-migrant house tour videos were just a way to game the algorithm, build an audience, and hopefully make money.</p><p>”I didn’t do anything because of hate,” he says on the tape. “I didn’t care. It’s just I wanted the clicks.”</p><p data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.londoncentric.media/p/london-tiktok-fake-news-creator-hate-immigrants/comments&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Leave a comment&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:null,&quot;class&quot;:null}" data-component-name="ButtonCreateButton"><a href="https://www.londoncentric.media/p/london-tiktok-fake-news-creator-hate-immigrants/comments" rel=""><span>Leave a comment</span></a></p><p><em>All our reporting is funded by our paying subscribers, who receive exclusive investigations. Your support for original investigative local journalism is very much appreciated.</em></p><p><em><span>Click </span><a href="https://www.londoncentric.media/p/tiktok-london-immigrants-fake-news-house-tours" rel="">here</a><span> to read our original investigation into the account, including a film by Jonah Sealey Braverman. </span></em></p><p><em><span>Want to get in touch with London Centric? Send us a </span><a href="https://wa.me/447760993558" rel="">WhatsApp</a><span> or send an </span><a href="mailto:hello@londoncentric.media" rel="">email</a><span> or leave a comment on this piece.  </span></em></p><p>In November Taylor Swift flew 3,500 miles in her private jet to film the music video to her song ‘Opalite’ at one of London’s leading attractions: Whitgift shopping centre in Croydon. </p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!VH9a!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5b1c3f1-9595-4c95-8f9b-9a4af4fdfea2_2002x1502.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!VH9a!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5b1c3f1-9595-4c95-8f9b-9a4af4fdfea2_2002x1502.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!VH9a!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5b1c3f1-9595-4c95-8f9b-9a4af4fdfea2_2002x1502.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!VH9a!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5b1c3f1-9595-4c95-8f9b-9a4af4fdfea2_2002x1502.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!VH9a!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5b1c3f1-9595-4c95-8f9b-9a4af4fdfea2_2002x1502.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!VH9a!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5b1c3f1-9595-4c95-8f9b-9a4af4fdfea2_2002x1502.png" width="1456" height="1092" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/c5b1c3f1-9595-4c95-8f9b-9a4af4fdfea2_2002x1502.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1092,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:3690864,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.londoncentric.media/i/187071963?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5b1c3f1-9595-4c95-8f9b-9a4af4fdfea2_2002x1502.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" title="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!VH9a!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5b1c3f1-9595-4c95-8f9b-9a4af4fdfea2_2002x1502.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!VH9a!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5b1c3f1-9595-4c95-8f9b-9a4af4fdfea2_2002x1502.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!VH9a!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5b1c3f1-9595-4c95-8f9b-9a4af4fdfea2_2002x1502.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!VH9a!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5b1c3f1-9595-4c95-8f9b-9a4af4fdfea2_2002x1502.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>This week the finished video was released, introducing hundreds of millions of Swift fans around the world to Croydon’s forever-awaiting-development mall. </p><p>It is not known whether Swift took any time off from filming to examine the long-delayed plans for redeveloping the site,  nor whether she has any views on the council-backed proposals which will see her filming location become part of a mixed-used construction project featuring homes and retail.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!RfnM!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34eebe17-f993-4e9b-9f8a-bd4b092fed68_2374x3312.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!RfnM!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34eebe17-f993-4e9b-9f8a-bd4b092fed68_2374x3312.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!RfnM!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34eebe17-f993-4e9b-9f8a-bd4b092fed68_2374x3312.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!RfnM!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34eebe17-f993-4e9b-9f8a-bd4b092fed68_2374x3312.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!RfnM!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34eebe17-f993-4e9b-9f8a-bd4b092fed68_2374x3312.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!RfnM!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34eebe17-f993-4e9b-9f8a-bd4b092fed68_2374x3312.png" width="1456" height="2031" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/34eebe17-f993-4e9b-9f8a-bd4b092fed68_2374x3312.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:2031,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:11272728,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.londoncentric.media/i/187071963?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34eebe17-f993-4e9b-9f8a-bd4b092fed68_2374x3312.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" title="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!RfnM!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34eebe17-f993-4e9b-9f8a-bd4b092fed68_2374x3312.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!RfnM!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34eebe17-f993-4e9b-9f8a-bd4b092fed68_2374x3312.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!RfnM!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34eebe17-f993-4e9b-9f8a-bd4b092fed68_2374x3312.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!RfnM!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34eebe17-f993-4e9b-9f8a-bd4b092fed68_2374x3312.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>Top: Taylor Swift and Domhnall Gleeson descend Whitgift shopping centre’s escalators. Bottom: Taylor Swift and Domhall Gleeson strangely not in Whitgift shopping centre when London Centric visited on Friday afternoon.</figcaption></figure></div><p>Her team were able to secure the location for a weekend of filming due to the increasing number of empty units as shops increasingly desert the shopping centre. </p><div><p><span>When London Centric visited on Friday afternoon locals seemed more interested in restoring pride to their local high street rather than Swift. Passerby Darryl, 34, from Croydon asked: “Why the Whitgift? Is her video supposed to represent a dystopian future?”</span></p><p><span>When the pop star featured Kentish Delight, a kebab shop in Camden, in her 2018 music video for End Game, the owner said it boosted business. Whether Swifties will descend on the Whitgift – or Stoke Newington’s Mildmay club, which also features in the new video – with the same enthusiasm remains to be seen.</span></p></div><p>The Met police’s battle to force its employees to register their membership of freemasonry lodges continues. London Centric’s latest Freedom of Information request found that 386 police officers and Met staff have now declared “they are or have been a member of the Freemasonry Organisation” since the rule came into effect at the end of last year. That’s up from the 300 made public last month. </p><p><span>Our story on Jeffrey Epstein’s discussions about buying a central London hotel to host his London “playroom” was followed up in most of the national newspapers. Some of them even kindly remembered to credit London Centric. If you want to read the original, </span><a href="https://www.londoncentric.media/p/jeffrey-epsteins-london-hotel-property-houses" rel="">it’s here</a><span>. As one reader pointed out, we’d failed to note that Dukes hotel has a side entrance onto a narrow road called Little St James’s – which shares its name with the deceased sex offender’s private Caribbean island.</span></p><p><em>We’ll be back next week with more exclusive original reporting on London.</em></p><p data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.londoncentric.media/p/london-tiktok-fake-news-creator-hate-immigrants/comments&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Leave a comment&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:null,&quot;class&quot;:null}" data-component-name="ButtonCreateButton"><a href="https://www.londoncentric.media/p/london-tiktok-fake-news-creator-hate-immigrants/comments" rel=""><span>Leave a comment</span></a></p><p>. </p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Semaglutide improves knee osteoarthritis independant of weight loss (179 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cell.com/cell-metabolism/abstract/S1550-4131(26)00008-2</link>
            <guid>46962801</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 16:55:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cell.com/cell-metabolism/abstract/S1550-4131(26)00008-2">https://www.cell.com/cell-metabolism/abstract/S1550-4131(26)00008-2</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46962801">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.cell.com/cell-metabolism/abstract/S1550-4131(26)00008-2: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Rowboat – AI coworker that turns your work into a knowledge graph (OSS) (152 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/rowboatlabs/rowboat</link>
            <guid>46962641</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 16:47:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/rowboatlabs/rowboat">https://github.com/rowboatlabs/rowboat</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46962641">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5AWoGo-L16I" rel="nofollow">
  <img width="1339" height="607" alt="rowboat-github-2" src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/6592213/547591215-fc463b99-01b3-401c-b4a4-044dad480901.png?jwt=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3NzA3NzAxMDQsIm5iZiI6MTc3MDc2OTgwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii82NTkyMjEzLzU0NzU5MTIxNS1mYzQ2M2I5OS0wMWIzLTQwMWMtYjRhNC0wNDRkYWQ0ODA5MDEucG5nP1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI2MDIxMSUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNjAyMTFUMDAzMDA0WiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9ZmQzNzg3ZTk0MDk4YjVjYjZmOGZmMzAyM2MzYThiZmNjNjU2MjFjMGI5MTFiM2E0OWNjNmFjMzc2ZTQ0ZjkwMSZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QifQ.G3nM7QpHt-FTLkImMhEiTuYiDg8EN5ACEmNaGg-Y6A4" secured-asset-link="">
</a>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Rowboat</h2><a id="user-content-rowboat" aria-label="Permalink: Rowboat" href="#rowboat"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Open-source AI coworker that turns work into a knowledge graph and acts on it</strong></p>

<p dir="auto">Rowboat connects to your email and meeting notes, builds a long-lived knowledge graph, and uses that context to help you get work done - privately, on your machine.</p>
<p dir="auto">You can do things like:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>Build me a deck about our next quarter roadmap</code> → generates a PDF using context from your knowledge graph</li>
<li><code>Prep me for my meeting with Alex</code> → pulls past decisions, open questions, and relevant threads into a crisp brief (or a voice note)</li>
<li>Visualize, edit, and update your knowledge graph anytime (it’s just Markdown)</li>
<li>Record voice memos that automatically capture and update key takeaways in the graph</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Download latest for Mac/Windows/Linux: <a href="https://www.rowboatlabs.com/downloads" rel="nofollow">Download</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Demo</h2><a id="user-content-demo" aria-label="Permalink: Demo" href="#demo"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5AWoGo-L16I" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/6592213/547586875-3f560bcf-d93c-4064-81eb-75a9fae31742.gif?jwt=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3NzA3NzAxMDQsIm5iZiI6MTc3MDc2OTgwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii82NTkyMjEzLzU0NzU4Njg3NS0zZjU2MGJjZi1kOTNjLTQwNjQtODFlYi03NWE5ZmFlMzE3NDIuZ2lmP1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI2MDIxMSUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNjAyMTFUMDAzMDA0WiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9YTAxZTk0ZjNhMGM0YjQ1NjViNjZjMmU1ODEwMzhiNTE4ZWU0MjZjODhmYmI0ODI2YWY5NzhlNDhlMDU4NGZkZiZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QifQ.6aHzXndSwYPZmCMiKxpBjjhw1X8ZTkfBmOQUeH1Lor4" alt="Demo" secured-asset-link="" data-animated-image=""></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5AWoGo-L16I" rel="nofollow">Watch the full video</a></p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h2><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Download latest for Mac/Windows/Linux:</strong> <a href="https://www.rowboatlabs.com/downloads" rel="nofollow">Download</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>All release files:</strong>   <a href="https://github.com/rowboatlabs/rowboat/releases/latest">https://github.com/rowboatlabs/rowboat/releases/latest</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Google setup</h3><a id="user-content-google-setup" aria-label="Permalink: Google setup" href="#google-setup"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To connect Google services (Gmail, Calendar, and Drive), follow <a href="https://github.com/rowboatlabs/rowboat/blob/main/google-setup.md">Google setup</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Voice notes</h3><a id="user-content-voice-notes" aria-label="Permalink: Voice notes" href="#voice-notes"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To enable voice notes (optional), add a Deepgram API key in ~/.rowboat/config/deepgram.json:</p>

<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What it does</h2><a id="user-content-what-it-does" aria-label="Permalink: What it does" href="#what-it-does"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Rowboat is a <strong>local-first AI coworker</strong> that can:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>Remember</strong> the important context you don’t want to re-explain (people, projects, decisions, commitments)</li>
<li><strong>Understand</strong> what’s relevant right now (before a meeting, while replying to an email, when writing a doc)</li>
<li><strong>Help you act</strong> by drafting, summarizing, planning, and producing real artifacts (briefs, emails, docs, PDF slides)</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Under the hood, Rowboat maintains an <strong>Obsidian-compatible vault</strong> of plain Markdown notes with backlinks — a transparent “working memory” you can inspect and edit.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Integrations</h2><a id="user-content-integrations" aria-label="Permalink: Integrations" href="#integrations"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Rowboat builds memory from the work you already do, including:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>Gmail</strong> (email)</li>
<li><strong>Granola</strong> (meeting notes)</li>
<li><strong>Fireflies</strong> (meeting notes)</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How it’s different</h2><a id="user-content-how-its-different" aria-label="Permalink: How it’s different" href="#how-its-different"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Most AI tools reconstruct context on demand by searching transcripts or documents.</p>
<p dir="auto">Rowboat maintains <strong>long-lived knowledge</strong> instead:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>context accumulates over time</li>
<li>relationships are explicit and inspectable</li>
<li>notes are editable by you, not hidden inside a model</li>
<li>everything lives on your machine as plain Markdown</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">The result is memory that compounds, rather than retrieval that starts cold every time.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What you can do with it</h2><a id="user-content-what-you-can-do-with-it" aria-label="Permalink: What you can do with it" href="#what-you-can-do-with-it"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>Meeting prep</strong> from prior decisions, threads, and open questions</li>
<li><strong>Email drafting</strong> grounded in history and commitments</li>
<li><strong>Docs &amp; decks</strong> generated from your ongoing context (including PDF slides)</li>
<li><strong>Follow-ups</strong>: capture decisions, action items, and owners so nothing gets dropped</li>
<li><strong>On-your-machine help</strong>: create files, summarize into notes, and run workflows using local tools (with explicit, reviewable actions)</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Background agents</h2><a id="user-content-background-agents" aria-label="Permalink: Background agents" href="#background-agents"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Rowboat can spin up <strong>background agents</strong> to do repeatable work automatically - so routine tasks happen without you having to ask every time.</p>
<p dir="auto">Examples:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Draft email replies in the background (grounded in your past context and commitments)</li>
<li>Generate a daily voice note each morning (agenda, priorities, upcoming meetings)</li>
<li>Create recurring project updates from the latest emails/notes</li>
<li>Keep your knowledge graph up to date as new information comes in</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">You control what runs, when it runs, and what gets written back into your local Markdown vault.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Bring your own model</h2><a id="user-content-bring-your-own-model" aria-label="Permalink: Bring your own model" href="#bring-your-own-model"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Rowboat works with the model setup you prefer:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>Local models</strong> via Ollama or LM Studio</li>
<li><strong>Hosted models</strong> (bring your own API key/provider)</li>
<li>Swap models anytime — your data stays in your local Markdown vault</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Extend Rowboat with tools (MCP)</h2><a id="user-content-extend-rowboat-with-tools-mcp" aria-label="Permalink: Extend Rowboat with tools (MCP)" href="#extend-rowboat-with-tools-mcp"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Rowboat can connect to external tools and services via <strong>Model Context Protocol (MCP)</strong>.
That means you can plug in (for example) search, databases, CRMs, support tools, and automations - or your own internal tools.</p>
<p dir="auto">Examples: Exa (web search), Twitter/X, ElevenLabs (voice), Slack, Linear/Jira, GitHub, and more.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Local-first by design</h2><a id="user-content-local-first-by-design" aria-label="Permalink: Local-first by design" href="#local-first-by-design"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>All data is stored locally as plain Markdown</li>
<li>No proprietary formats or hosted lock-in</li>
<li>You can inspect, edit, back up, or delete everything at any time</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Looking for Rowboat Web Studio?</h2><a id="user-content-looking-for-rowboat-web-studio" aria-label="Permalink: Looking for Rowboat Web Studio?" href="#looking-for-rowboat-web-studio"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If you’re looking for Rowboat web Studio, start <a href="https://docs.rowboatlabs.com/" rel="nofollow">here</a>.</p>
<hr>

</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mathematicians disagree on the essential structure of the complex numbers (2024) (195 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.infinitelymore.xyz/p/complex-numbers-essential-structure</link>
            <guid>46962402</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 16:36:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.infinitelymore.xyz/p/complex-numbers-essential-structure">https://www.infinitelymore.xyz/p/complex-numbers-essential-structure</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46962402">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><p><strong>Introduction</strong></p><p>How are we to think of the complex numbers? What I mean is, with what fundamental structure at bottom do we take the complex numbers to be endowed? In short, what is the essential structure of the complex numbers? They form the complex field, of course, with the corresponding algebraic structure, but do we think of the complex numbers necessarily also with their smooth topological structure? Is the real field necessarily distinguished as a fixed particular subfield of the complex numbers? Do we understand the complex numbers necessarily to come with their rigid coordinate structure of real and imaginary parts?</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!LLOP!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbfa08af5-c9c1-47dc-b75b-73edff9ba33f_1792x1024.webp" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!LLOP!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbfa08af5-c9c1-47dc-b75b-73edff9ba33f_1792x1024.webp 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!LLOP!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbfa08af5-c9c1-47dc-b75b-73edff9ba33f_1792x1024.webp 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!LLOP!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbfa08af5-c9c1-47dc-b75b-73edff9ba33f_1792x1024.webp 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!LLOP!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbfa08af5-c9c1-47dc-b75b-73edff9ba33f_1792x1024.webp 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!LLOP!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbfa08af5-c9c1-47dc-b75b-73edff9ba33f_1792x1024.webp" width="671" height="383.42857142857144" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/bfa08af5-c9c1-47dc-b75b-73edff9ba33f_1792x1024.webp&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:832,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:671,&quot;bytes&quot;:515928,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/webp&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!LLOP!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbfa08af5-c9c1-47dc-b75b-73edff9ba33f_1792x1024.webp 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!LLOP!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbfa08af5-c9c1-47dc-b75b-73edff9ba33f_1792x1024.webp 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!LLOP!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbfa08af5-c9c1-47dc-b75b-73edff9ba33f_1792x1024.webp 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!LLOP!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbfa08af5-c9c1-47dc-b75b-73edff9ba33f_1792x1024.webp 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>These different perspectives ultimately amount, I argue, to mathematically inequivalent structural conceptions of the complex numbers, conceptions exhibiting different symmetries and thus also different automorphism groups. The additional structural features of the richer conceptions, after all, with the topology, the particular copy of ℝ as a distinguished subfield, or with the coordinate structure, are not determined uniquely by the algebraic field structure alone, and the coordinate structure is not determined uniquely by the topology. The automorphism groups of the conceptions are vastly different—the complex field admits crazy wild automorphisms, while the complex field over ℝ has only complex conjugation as a nontrivial automorphism, and the complex plane is rigid, having no nontrivial automorphisms at all. Which of these mathematical structural conceptions do we regard ultimately as the essential structure of the complex numbers? Indeed is there any one such essential structure?</p><p>It turns out that mathematicians do not agree—they do not all have the same conception of the complex numbers. Discussing the issue in various mathematical venues, I found a range of views, split roughly equally amongst the perspectives I discuss in this paper. I should like to discuss these various conceptions and then explain how they engage with several aspects of the philosophy of structuralism in the philosophy of mathematics.</p><p><strong>Different perspectives on the complex numbers</strong></p><p>To my way of thinking, there are at least four natural perspectives to take on the essential structure of the complex numbers, which I shall refer to under the following slogans.</p><ul><li><p><strong>Analytic</strong><span>: The complex field ℂ over ℝ</span></p></li><li><p><strong>Smooth</strong><span>: The topological complex field</span></p></li><li><p><strong>Rigid</strong><span>: The complex plane</span></p></li><li><p><strong>Algebraic</strong><span>: The complex field</span></p></li></ul><p>Two of these perspectives, it will turn out, arise from what amounts to the same underlying structural conception of the complex numbers (do you see which two?), and so those two perspectives are equivalent in this sense. Ultimately, therefore, we have here only three different perspectives in play. Let me elaborate on them.</p><div><p>Please enjoy this extended essay on the topic of the complex numbers. We shall see how  our different various conceptions of them ultimately engage with several issues concerning the philosophy of structuralism in the philosophy of mathematics.  </p><p>Toward the end of the essay we shall see how the complex numbers once made a key appearance in the midst of a contentious philosophical dispute, with many philosophers ultimately taking it decisively to refute what had seemed a promising position in the philosophy of mathematics.</p></div><p><strong>The analytic conception</strong></p><p><span>Many mathematicians like to consider the complex numbers ℂ as a field over ℝ, a view I refer to as the </span><em>analytic</em><span> conception, because it considers the structure of the complex field ℂ as it relates to and extends the real numbers ℝ, sitting with its analytic structure of the real line as a fixed distinguished subfield of ℂ. In particular, on the analytic view the complex field ℂ is conceived as the algebraic closure of ℝ—it is a degree-two extension of ℝ.</span></p><p><span>One common method to introduce the complex numbers as a field over ℝ is to introduce a symbol </span><em>i</em><span> for the imaginary unit and then present the complex numbers as formal sums </span><em>a</em><span> + </span><em>bi</em><span> with real numbers </span><em>a</em><span>, </span><em>b</em><span> ∈ ℝ. The sums obey the expected rules for addition and multiplication, subject to the rule </span><em>i</em><span>² = −1.</span></p><p><span>Since </span><em>i</em><span>² = −1, the complex field thus provides a system of numbers giving sense to expressions like √–1, while obeying the familiar algebraic rules of a field. One may easily observe in the complex numbers, however, that –</span><em>i</em><span> is also a square root of –1, because </span></p><div data-component-name="Latex"><p><span>\((–i)\cdot(–i)=(–1)^2\cdot i^2=i^2=-1.\)</span></p></div><p><span>Thus, both </span><em>i</em><span> and –</span><em>i</em><span> have the property of being square roots of –1, and indeed, these are the only square roots of –1 in the complex field.</span></p><p><span>A small conundrum may arise when one realizes that –</span><em>i</em><span> therefore also fulfills what might naively have been taken as the “defining” property of the imaginary unit </span><em>i</em><span>, namely, that it squares to –1. So this property doesn't actually define </span><em>i</em><span>, in light of the fact that there is another distinct object –</span><em>i</em><span> that also has this property. Can we tell </span><em>i</em><span> and –</span><em>i</em><span> apart?</span></p><p><span>Not in the complex field, no, we cannot. The basic fact is that </span><em>i</em><span> and –</span><em>i</em><span> are indiscernible as complex numbers with respect to the algebraic structure of ℂ—any property that </span><em>i</em><span> has in the complex field ℂ over ℝ will also hold of –</span><em>i</em><span>. One way to see this is to observe that complex conjugation, the map </span></p><p><span>is an automorphism of the complex number field over ℝ, an isomorphism of the field structure with itself that fixes every real number. Since this automorphism swaps </span><em>i</em><span> with –</span><em>i</em><span>, it follows that any statement true of </span><em>i</em><span> in the complex numbers, expressible in the language of fields with a predicate for the real subfield ℝ, will also hold of –</span><em>i</em><span>. In short, they are indiscernible in ℂ over ℝ.</span></p><p><span>Thus, the analytic conception admits complex conjugation as a fundamental symmetry of ℂ over ℝ. Even though we have introduced </span><em>i</em><span> as a formal symbol, we do not consider the choice between </span><em>i</em><span> and –</span><em>i</em><span> as part of the underlying structure. To make this precise in the language of first-order logic, we might therefore present the analytic perspective of ℂ over ℝ as embodied by the structure ⟨ℂ, +, ·, 0, 1, ℝ⟩, where the language signature includes the field structure, as well as a predicate ℝ that explicitly picks out the intended copy of ℝ in ℂ. We do not have </span><em>i</em><span> available as a constant symbol or singular term in this language.</span></p><p><span>It is not difficult to see that conjugation is the only nontrivial automorphism of ℂ over ℝ, since if a field automorphism of ℂ fixes every real number, then it will be completely determined by whether it sends </span><em>i</em><span> to itself or to –</span><em>i</em><span>, meaning either that it is the identity automorphism or complex conjugation, respectively.</span></p><p><span>Another common way to present the complex field ℂ as a field over ℝ is as the quotient field ℝ[</span><em>x</em><span>]/(</span><em>x</em><span>² + 1), where we first form the polynomial ring ℝ[</span><em>x</em><span>], consisting of formal polynomial expressions in the indeterminate symbol </span><em>x</em><span>, and then take the quotient by the ideal generated by the irreducible polynomial </span><em>x</em><span>² + 1, thereby in effect treating this polynomial as 0, which means </span><em>x</em><span>² = −1. It follows that every polynomial in the quotient can be represented as </span><em>a</em><span> + </span><em>bx</em><span>, where </span><em>a</em><span>, </span><em>b</em><span> ∈ ℝ. And so ultimately this quotient construction amounts to the same as the </span><em>a</em><span> + </span><em>bi</em><span> conception.</span></p><p>With either presentation of ℂ over ℝ, one proceeds to prove the fundamental theorem of algebra, asserting that the resulting field ℂ is algebraically closed. And we may easily provide a categorical characterization of ℂ over ℝ, which determines it uniquely up to isomorphism, building on the categorical characterization of the real field up to isomorphism as the unique complete ordered field. Namely, the complex field ℂ is simply the algebraic closure of the real field ℝ, a degree-two extension of the complete ordered field ℝ, and any two such extensions are isomorphic by an isomorphism furthermore respecting the real numbers and hence respecting the “over ℝ” aspect of the characterization. Indeed, an alternative characterization of ℂ over ℝ is that ℂ is a nontrivial algebraic extension of ℝ—such an extension must have degree two, since the degree two extension is already algebraically closed.</p><p>At bottom the analytic conception of ℂ is that of an algebraically closed field with a single nontrivial automorphic symmetry, complex conjugation, whose fixed points constitute the distinguished real subfield.</p><p><strong>The smooth conception</strong></p><p><span>Many mathematicians prefer to emphasize what I call the </span><em>smooth</em><span> conception of the complex numbers, viewing the complex field as carrying also its familiar topological structure. On this account, ℂ is a certain topological field, a field that is also a topological space, in which addition and multiplication are continuous operations. With the familiar intended topology of the complex plane, we see easily that ℝ is the closure of the set ℚ of rational numbers. Since the rational numbers are inherent to the algebraic structure, it follows that in the topological complex field we can recover the real subfield ℝ as a distinguished subfield, the closure of ℚ. In this sense, the smooth conception of the complex numbers subsumes the analytic conception.</span></p><p><span>But in fact, I claim, the smooth conception and the analytic conception are equivalent—they arise from the same underlying structure. We have already seen how the topology reveals the distinguished copy of ℝ in ℂ as the closure of ℚ. Conversely, if we have fixed a copy of the real subfield ℝ in ℂ for the analytic conception, then even though we cannot distinguish </span><em>i</em><span> from –</span><em>i</em><span>, we can nevertheless still define the complex norm |</span><em>z</em><span>| of any complex number </span><em>z</em><span>, which is √(</span><em>a</em><span>² + </span><em>b</em><span>²), if </span><em>z</em><span> = </span><em>a</em><span> ± </span><em>bi</em><span> and </span><em>a</em><span>, </span><em>b</em><span> ∈ ℝ. The norm simply does not require us to have chosen between </span><em>i</em><span> and –</span><em>i</em><span>. Using the norm, we can then define the distance between any two complex numbers, and so we can realize the topology by viewing ℂ as a metric space. In short, identifying the real subfield enables us to specify the unique intended topology and vice versa, and so the analytic conception and the smooth conception of the complex numbers amount to having the same underlying structure for the complex field.</span></p><p>When considering automorphisms of the complex numbers under the smooth conception, we should of course require that they also respect the topology. But since any continuous automorphism of ℂ must fix every real number, since it must fix the rational numbers, it follows that the only continuous automorphisms of ℂ are the identity automorphism and complex conjugation, which are indeed homeomorphisms of the topology.</p><p><strong>The rigid conception</strong></p><p><span>Another common conception of the complex numbers is what I call the </span><em>rigid</em><span> conception, which incorporates into the field structure also the full coordinate structure of the complex plane. One elementary approach to this conception of ℂ is simply to identify complex numbers with points (</span><em>a</em><span>, </span><em>b</em><span>) in the plane ℝ × ℝ and define the algebraic operations by reference to the coordinates, like this:</span></p><div data-component-name="Latex"><p><span>\((a,b)+(c,d)=(a+c,b+d)\qquad (a,b)\cdot(c,d)=(ac-bd,ad+bc).\)</span></p></div><p><span>Such definitions were presented by </span><a href="https://mathshistory.st-andrews.ac.uk/Biographies/Hamilton/" rel="">Hamilton to the Royal Irish Academy</a><span> in 1833, and are designed simply to implement the intended arithmetic of complex numbers, with </span></p><div data-component-name="Latex"><p><span>\((a+bi)+(c+di)=(a+c)+(b+d)i\)</span></p></div><p>and </p><div data-component-name="Latex"><p><span>\((a+bi)(c+di)=ac+adi+bci+bdi^2=(ac-bd)+(ad+bc)i.\)</span></p></div><p><span>With the structure of the complex plane, one can proceed furthermore to define the polar representation </span><em><span>re</span><sup>i</sup></em><sup>θ</sup><span>, with modulus </span><em>r</em><span> and argument θ, and one can translate back and forth definably between cartesian and polar coordinates.</span></p><p><span>In my experience, the complex plane construction is often successful for the pedagogical task of explaining how it could be that there is a field exhibiting the properties claimed of the complex numbers, how it could be, for example, that there is a number </span><em>z</em><span> with </span><em>z</em><span>² = −1. This amounts to the simple calculation with the number </span><em>z</em><span> = (0, 1), of course, following the rule we gave above, since </span></p><div data-component-name="Latex"><p><span>\((0,1)\cdot(0,1)=(0\cdot0-1\cdot 1,0\cdot 1+1\cdot 0)=(-1,0),\)</span></p></div><p>and the point (1, 0) is the multiplicative unit, so this is −1 as a complex number. For many mathematical beginners, it is the complex plane construction that de-mystifies the complex numbers.</p><p>The ordered-pair account of the complex field, if one regards the pair information as part of the underlying structure, amounts to viewing the complex field together with the real and imaginary part operators, defined by</p><div data-component-name="Latex"><p><span>\(\text{Re}(a+bi)=a\qquad \text{Im}(a+bi)=b.\)</span></p></div><p>So we are considering the complex numbers in effect as the structure ⟨ℂ,+,·,0,1,Re,Im⟩ with the two additional operators.</p><p><span>The coordinate structure carries more information than just the algebraic structure of the complex field, of course, for we can define the intended copy of ℝ in ℂ as those numbers whose imaginary part is zero. From the real field we can define the norm and hence also the topology, as we explained earlier. And we can naturally distinguish </span><em>i</em><span> from –</span><em>i</em><span> in the coordinate conception, since </span><em>i</em><span> has imaginary part 1, while –</span><em>i</em><span> has imaginary part −1. So in this conception we block the symmetry between </span><em>i</em><span> and –</span><em>i</em><span>. Indeed, in this conception the complex plane is rigid—it has no nontrivial automorphisms at all.</span></p><p><span>An equivalent presentation of the rigid conception of the complex plane arises from the </span><em>a</em><span> + </span><em>bi</em><span> presentation of ℂ over ℝ, but where we now fix the imaginary unit </span><em>i</em><span> as part of the structure ⟨ℂ, +, ·, 0, 1, </span><em>i</em><span>, ℝ⟩. In this language we can define the real and imaginary parts of any complex number. Indeed, to my way of thinking, the complex plane understanding of the </span><em>a</em><span> + </span><em>bi</em><span> presentation of ℂ is a more direct reading of that construction, since we take the imaginary constant </span><em>i</em><span> at face value as a distinguished constant, having made a particular choice of orientation, thus blocking the symmetry between </span><em>i</em><span> and –</span><em>i</em><span>.</span></p><p><strong>The algebraic conception</strong></p><p><span>Finally, many mathematicians find it natural to regard the complex numbers at bottom as a field, that is, endowed with its field operations as the (only) essential structure. This is a purely </span><em>algebraic</em><span> conception of the complex numbers, in which they are endowed with the algebraic operations of addition and multiplication to form the familiar complex field ⟨ℂ, +, ·, 0, 1⟩.</span></p><p>Indeed the complex field admits a categorical characterization in terms of this algebraic structure, a characterization determining it uniquely up to isomorphism. Namely, the complex field is, up to isomorphism, the unique algebraically closed field of characteristic zero and size continuum. Any two algebraically closed fields of characteristic zero (which just means that 1 + 1 + ⋯ + 1 is never 0) and size continuum are isomorphic. Equivalently, the complex field arises as the unique algebraically closed field of transcendence degree continuum over the rational field ℚ.</p><p><span>In fact, the first-order theory of algebraically closed fields of characteristic zero, a theory commonly denoted ACF₀ by the model theorists, is categorical in every uncountable power, which is the technical term expressing the fact that for every uncountable cardinality κ, there is up to isomorphism a unique such field of size κ. (An analogous result holds for ACFₚ in any prime characteristic </span><em>p</em><span>.) The reason is that the isomorphism type of an algebraically closed field of characteristic zero is determined by its transcendence degree over the prime subfield ℚ. The theory is not categorical for countable models, since we can form algebraically closed fields exhibiting any desired finite transcendence degree over ℚ, as well as the countably infinite transcendence degree, and these fields are nonisomorphic distinct countable models of the theory. But in the uncountable case, the transcendence degree will have to be the same as the size of the field itself, and thus we get the categoricity result. In this way, the complex numbers are characterized as the unique algebraically closed field of characteristic zero and size continuum.</span></p><p><strong>Summary of the conceptions</strong></p><p>So we have in the end three distinct conceptions of the complex numbers. First, the analytic account, for which we regard ℂ as a field extension of ℝ, specifically, the degree-two algebraic extension of ℝ, which is also the algebraic closure of ℝ, and which admits complex conjugation as the only nontrivial automorphism. That view, it turns out, is structurally equivalent to the smooth account, which endows the complex field ℂ with its familiar topology, since from the topology we can define the intended real subfield ℝ as the closure of the rationals, and conversely from ℝ we can define the topology. Next, we have the rigid account of the complex plane, which gives ℂ its coordinate structure of the real and imaginary parts, and which admits no nontrivial automorphisms. Finally, there is the algebraic conception of the complex field, with a rich, chaotic automorphism group that includes many wild automorphisms. The various conceptions are thereby distinguished from one another by their account of the extent to which the complex numbers exhibit a self-symmetric nature.</p><p><strong>Google AI and ChatGPT weigh in</strong></p><p>I was astounded to see that the Google AI overview in effect takes a stand amongst three conceptions of the complex numbers we have been discussing. Namely, while I was searching for references online, this is what it had told me:</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!9w_x!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F12697d47-08a6-46e0-8907-f7ab608fdf35_1983x1593.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!9w_x!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F12697d47-08a6-46e0-8907-f7ab608fdf35_1983x1593.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!9w_x!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F12697d47-08a6-46e0-8907-f7ab608fdf35_1983x1593.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!9w_x!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F12697d47-08a6-46e0-8907-f7ab608fdf35_1983x1593.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!9w_x!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F12697d47-08a6-46e0-8907-f7ab608fdf35_1983x1593.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!9w_x!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F12697d47-08a6-46e0-8907-f7ab608fdf35_1983x1593.jpeg" width="1456" height="1170" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/12697d47-08a6-46e0-8907-f7ab608fdf35_1983x1593.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1170,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:418089,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!9w_x!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F12697d47-08a6-46e0-8907-f7ab608fdf35_1983x1593.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!9w_x!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F12697d47-08a6-46e0-8907-f7ab608fdf35_1983x1593.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!9w_x!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F12697d47-08a6-46e0-8907-f7ab608fdf35_1983x1593.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!9w_x!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F12697d47-08a6-46e0-8907-f7ab608fdf35_1983x1593.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>ChatGPT takes the same stand.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!l7q0!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F00a822d4-7425-47c3-a249-f509399ecb01_2127x1305.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!l7q0!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F00a822d4-7425-47c3-a249-f509399ecb01_2127x1305.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!l7q0!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F00a822d4-7425-47c3-a249-f509399ecb01_2127x1305.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!l7q0!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F00a822d4-7425-47c3-a249-f509399ecb01_2127x1305.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!l7q0!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F00a822d4-7425-47c3-a249-f509399ecb01_2127x1305.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!l7q0!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F00a822d4-7425-47c3-a249-f509399ecb01_2127x1305.jpeg" width="1456" height="893" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/00a822d4-7425-47c3-a249-f509399ecb01_2127x1305.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:893,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:362252,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!l7q0!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F00a822d4-7425-47c3-a249-f509399ecb01_2127x1305.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!l7q0!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F00a822d4-7425-47c3-a249-f509399ecb01_2127x1305.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!l7q0!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F00a822d4-7425-47c3-a249-f509399ecb01_2127x1305.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!l7q0!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F00a822d4-7425-47c3-a249-f509399ecb01_2127x1305.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>The assertions made by these AI summaries are not mathematically correct, of course, since we have already discussed that the complex field admits innumerable wild automorphisms, not just the two continuous automorphisms. There are </p><p>many automorphisms of the complex field ℂ when it is considered with only its algebraic structure.</p><p>Nevertheless, perhaps it would be a charitable reading of the AI position to regard them as considering only automorphisms of ℂ over ℝ, that is, automorphisms fixing the real subfield, and this is the same as considering only continuous automorphisms. In this case, as we mentioned, there are only the two automorphisms of the identity and complex conjugation. On this charitable reading, therefore, the AI systems seem to be adopting the analytic/smooth conception of the complex numbers.</p><p>Nevertheless, they have not done so properly, since they do both refer to automorphisms of the complex field, rather than automorphisms of the complex field over ℝ. For this reason, in my view their precise claims are not ultimately correct mathematically, and this is a matter that would seem to require attention from the AI overseers.</p><p><strong>Strongly held mathematical views</strong></p><p>I ran an unscientific poll on Twitter that revealed a dispersed range of views in the mathematical/philosophical community for how to conceive of the complex numbers.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!CEO-!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb1bb17b-26ae-42cf-8a9a-77cb9ea357a3_1428x1032.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!CEO-!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb1bb17b-26ae-42cf-8a9a-77cb9ea357a3_1428x1032.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!CEO-!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb1bb17b-26ae-42cf-8a9a-77cb9ea357a3_1428x1032.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!CEO-!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb1bb17b-26ae-42cf-8a9a-77cb9ea357a3_1428x1032.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!CEO-!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb1bb17b-26ae-42cf-8a9a-77cb9ea357a3_1428x1032.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!CEO-!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb1bb17b-26ae-42cf-8a9a-77cb9ea357a3_1428x1032.jpeg" width="1428" height="1032" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/bb1bb17b-26ae-42cf-8a9a-77cb9ea357a3_1428x1032.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1032,&quot;width&quot;:1428,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:201266,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!CEO-!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb1bb17b-26ae-42cf-8a9a-77cb9ea357a3_1428x1032.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!CEO-!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb1bb17b-26ae-42cf-8a9a-77cb9ea357a3_1428x1032.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!CEO-!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb1bb17b-26ae-42cf-8a9a-77cb9ea357a3_1428x1032.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!CEO-!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb1bb17b-26ae-42cf-8a9a-77cb9ea357a3_1428x1032.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>And yet, despite the variation in views, many mathematicians are quite passionate about their favored answer, viewing those with the opposing view as making a fundamental mistake.</p><p><span>For example, </span><a href="https://x.com/tailcalled/status/1851195451527119154" rel="">one respondent</a><span> expressed the view that the algebraic conception is “definitely wrong,” and </span><a href="https://x.com/okularab/status/1851385279816610228" rel="">another user</a><span> says, “the coordinate view of [the complex plane] is what lives in my spine.” Mathematician </span><a href="https://x.com/littmath/status/1851095546993271238" rel="">Daniel Litt</a><span> (algebraic geometry, number theory) mentions that the complex plane conception “is tantamount to choosing a square root of −1, I guess, which I think of as immoral.” He adds that “At the very least making such a choice often leads to confusion later on.” Mathematician </span><a href="https://x.com/BarbaraFantechi/status/1852264198908076492" rel="">Barbara Fantechi</a><span> (algebraic geometry) states, “I was taught that choosing a square root of (−1) is wrong.” The view is that somehow it is a kind of mathematical sin to break the symmetry between </span><em>i</em><span> and −</span><em>i</em><span> in ℂ over ℝ and thus wrong to adopt the rigid perspective of the complex plane conception of ℂ. Nevertheless, mathematician </span><a href="https://x.com/RogierBrussee/status/1851165390270824623" rel="">Rogier Brussee</a><span> responds that, “Immoral sure, but, well, you know, the snake and the apple things; it can be a bloody convenient immorality at times.” Mathematician </span><a href="https://x.com/gro_tsen/status/1851164297436492000" rel="">David Madore</a><span> writes:</span></p><blockquote><p>People who study algebraic stacks and such questions are always careful to speak of “an” algebraic closure of a field (or even “a” field with 8 elements) because they are unique up to isomorphism but the isomorphism is non-unique. BUT even these people say “the” field of complex numbers, never “a” field of complex numbers, which suggests that they rigidify ℂ so as not to have any automorphism, so probably as per the complex plane conception in your poll.</p></blockquote><p>So mathematicians hold different conceptions of the complex numbers, and many of them even look upon the alternative conceptions as fundamentally wrong or misguided.</p><p><strong>Interpreting ℝ in the complex field ℂ</strong></p><p>We have seen that the real field ℝ is not definable in the complex field ℂ if one has only the algebraic field structure of ℂ, as with the algebraic conception. I should like to observe, further, that we cannot even interpret ℝ in the field ℂ. To interpret ℝ in ℂ is a much weaker way of finding a copy of ℝ in ℂ, after all, where we find it not necessarily as a subfield, but rather as a definable structure built using whatever algebraic resources are available in ℂ.</p><p><span>What does it mean exactly to interpret one mathematical structure in another? This is a technical term used in model theory and mathematical logic to refer to the situation when one can provide a definable copy of the first structure in the second, by specifying a definable domain of </span><em>k</em><span>-tuples (not necessarily just a domain of individuals) and definable interpretations of the atomic operations and relations, as well as a definable equivalence relation, a congruence with respect to the operations and relations, such that the first structure is isomorphic to the quotient of this definable structure by that equivalence relation. All these definitions should be expressible in the language of the host structure. One may proceed recursively to translate any assertion in the language of the interpreted structure into the language of the host structure, thereby enabling a complete discussion of the first structure purely in the language of the second.</span></p><p><span>For example, we can define a copy of the integer ring ⟨ℤ, +, ·⟩ inside the semi-ring of natural numbers ⟨ℕ, +, ·⟩ by considering every integer as the equivalence class of a pair of natural numbers (</span><em>n</em><span>, </span><em>m</em><span>) under the same-difference relation, by which</span></p><div data-component-name="Latex"><p><span>\((n,m)\equiv(u,v)\ \iff\ n-m=u-v\ \iff\ n+v=u+m.\)</span></p></div><p><span>Integer addition and multiplication can be defined on these pairs, well-defined with respect to same difference, and so we have interpreted the integers in the natural numbers. Similarly, the rational field ℚ can be interpreted in the integers as the quotient field, whose elements can be thought of as integer pairs (</span><em>p</em><span>, </span><em>q</em><span>) written more conveniently as fractions </span><em>p</em><span>/</span><em>q</em><span>, where </span><em>q</em><span> ≠ 0, considered under the same-ratio relation </span></p><div data-component-name="Latex"><p><span>\(\frac pq\equiv\frac rs\qquad\iff\qquad ps=rq.\)</span></p></div><p>The field structure is now easy to define on these pairs by the familiar fractional arithmetic, which is well-defined with respect to that equivalence. Thus, we have provided a definable copy of the rational numbers inside the integers, an interpretation of ℚ in ℤ.</p><p><span>We can also similarly interpret the complex field ℂ in the real field ℝ by considering the complex number </span><em>a</em><span> + </span><em>bi</em><span> as represented by the real number pair (</span><em>a</em><span>,</span><em>b</em><span>) as in the rigid conception of ℂ we discussed above. By keeping only the field structure on these pairs, we have an interpretation of the complex field in ℝ, but we can also interpret the structures corresponding to the analytic/smooth and rigid conceptions of ℂ as well.</span></p><p><span>Meanwhile, what I claim is that it is not possible conversely to interpret the real field ℝ inside the complex field ℂ with only its algebraic structure. The proof of this is grounded in the fact that the complex field admits only countably many different types of elements up to automorphism, even with respect to finitely many parameters </span><em>p</em><span>. Namely, either an element is algebraic over ℚ(</span><em>p</em><span>), in which case it is determined up to automorphism by its minimal polynomial, or it is transcendental over ℚ(</span><em>p</em><span>), and all transcendental elements are automorphic by an automorphism fixing the parameters. By applying this idea successively, it follows also that there are only countably many types of </span><em>k</em><span>-tuples of elements of ℂ. That is, if two </span><em>k</em><span>-tuples </span><em>a</em><span> and </span><em>b</em><span> from ℂ obey the same minimal-polynomial algebraic relations in ℂ over ℚ(</span><em>p</em><span>), then there is an automorphism of ℂ moving </span><em>a</em><span> to </span><em>b</em><span> and fixing </span><em>p</em><span>. In short, the complex field ℂ with only the algebraic structure makes distinctions amongst only countably many types of </span><em>k</em><span>-tuples with respect to expressible properties.</span></p><p><span>This is enough to see that we cannot interpret ℝ, since any copy of ℝ will exhibit its corresponding rational numbers that arise within it, and these numbers admit uncountably many cuts as realized by points in the interpreted copy of ℝ. But the problem is that these cuts thereby realize different, discernible types of elements in the interpreted copy of ℝ, which are therefore discernible in the host structure ℂ. In short, any interpreted copy of ℝ will require us to have distinguished uncountably many different kinds of </span><em>k</em><span>-tuples, but we have said this is impossible in the complex field. So there is no interpretation of ℝ in ℂ.</span></p><p><strong>Set-theoretic indiscernibility of </strong><em><strong>i</strong></em><strong> and –</strong><em><strong>i</strong></em></p><p><span>The analytic/smooth conception of the complex field ℂ over ℝ highlights the fundamental symmetry between the imaginary unit </span><em>i</em><span> and its negation –</span><em>i</em><span>. It is not possible to distinguish these two complex numbers by any property expressible in the complex field, even when we have fixed the canonical subfield of the real subfield ℝ in ℂ, because complex conjugation swaps these two elements, while preserving all the expressible properties of ℂ as a field extension of ℝ.</span></p><p><span>A few years ago (Hamkins 2022), I realized that it is relatively consistent with ZFC that we can definably construct a copy of the complex numbers ℂ over ℝ in such a way that </span><em>i</em><span> and –</span><em>i</em><span> are not only indiscernible in the field structure of this copy of ℂ, but also the particular set-theoretic objects </span><em>i</em><span> and –</span><em>i</em><span> that are used in this structure are indiscernible in the larger set-theoretic background in which the construction is undertaken.</span></p><p><strong>Goal. </strong><span>A definable copy of the complex field in which the two square roots of −1 are indiscernible not only in the field structure but also in the set-theoretic background in which the construction of the field takes place.</span></p><p>These two aims are in tension, for we want the particular copy of ℂ to be set-theoretically definable (defined with respect to the set-theoretic background as a particular set-theoretic object, not just defined up to isomorphism), but the individual square roots of −1 are to be set-theoretically indiscernible.</p><p><span>The goal is not always possible in ZFC. For example, some models of ZFC are pointwise definable, meaning that every individual set is definable in them by some distinguishing set-theoretic property—see further discussion in (Hamkins, Linetsky, Reitz 2013). More generally, if the </span><em>V</em><span> = HOD axiom holds, then there is a definable global well-order of the set-theoretic universe, and with any such order we could define a linear order on {</span><em>i</em><span>, –</span><em>i</em><span>} in any definable copy of ℂ, which would allow us to define each of the roots. For these reasons, in some models of ZFC, it is not possible to achieve the goal, and the most we can hope for is a consistency result.</span></p><p>But indeed, the goal is achievable, as I shall now explain.</p><p><strong>Theorem. </strong><span>If ZFC is consistent, then there is a model of ZFC that has a definable complete ordered field ℝ with a definable algebraic closure ℂ, such that the two square roots of −1 in ℂ are set-theoretically indiscernible, even with ordinal parameters.</span></p><p><strong>Proof. </strong><span>The proof makes use of what are known as Groszek-Laver pairs, definable pair sets having no ordinal-definable element. See (Groszek, Laver 1987) for a very general version of this. The result also appears as theorem 4.6 in my 2018 paper with Gunter Fuchs and Victoria Gitman. The arguments provide a model of set theory with a definable pair set </span><em>A</em><span> = {</span><em>i</em><span>, </span><em>j</em><span>}, such that neither element </span><em>i</em><span> nor </span><em>j</em><span> is definable from ordinal parameters. The pair set is definable, but neither element is definable.</span></p><p>To undertake the construction, we start with one of the standard definable constructions of the real field ℝ. For example, we could use Dedekind cuts in ℚ, where ℚ is constructed explicitly as the quotient field of the integer ring ℤ in some canonical definable manner, and where the integers are definably constructed from a definable copy of the natural numbers ℕ, such as the finite von Neumann ordinals. So we have a set-theoretically definable complete ordered field, the real field ℝ.</p><p><span>Given this and the set </span><em>A</em><span> = {</span><em>i</em><span>, </span><em>j</em><span>}, we follow a suggestion of Timothy Gowers in the discussion of this problem </span><a href="https://x.com/JDHamkins/status/1589018820777488384" rel="">on Twitter</a><span>. Namely, we use the elements of </span><em>A</em><span> as variables to form the polynomial ring ℝ[</span><em>A</em><span>], meaning ℝ[</span><em>i</em><span>, </span><em>j</em><span>], where </span><em>i</em><span> and </span><em>j</em><span> are the two elements of </span><em>A</em><span>. It is not necessary to distinguish the elements of </span><em>A</em><span> to form this ring of polynomials, since we take all finite polynomial expressions using real coefficients and elements of </span><em>A</em><span> raised to a power. (In particular, although I have referred to the elements as </span><em>i</em><span> and </span><em>j</em><span>, there is to be no suggestion that I am somehow saying </span><em>i</em><span> is the “real” </span><em>i</em><span>; I am not, for I could have called them </span><em>j</em><span>, </span><em>i</em><span> or </span><em>j</em><span>, </span><em>k</em><span> or </span><em>a</em><span>, </span><em>a</em><span>′, and so on.) Then we quotient by the ideal (</span><em>i</em><span>² + 1, </span><em>j</em><span>² + 1, </span><em>i</em><span> + </span><em>j</em><span>), which is defined symmetrically in the elements of </span><em>A</em><span>. Let ℂ be the quotient ℝ[</span><em>i</em><span>, </span><em>j</em><span>]/(</span><em>i</em><span>² + 1, </span><em>j</em><span>² + 1, </span><em>i</em><span> + </span><em>j</em><span>), which will make </span><em>i</em><span> and </span><em>j</em><span> the two square roots of −1, and so by the fundamental theorem of algebra this is a copy of the complex numbers.</span></p><p><span>Since ℝ and </span><em>A</em><span> were definable, and we didn’t need ever to choose a particular element of </span><em>A</em><span> in the construction to define the polynomial ring or the ideal, this copy of ℂ is definable without parameters. But since </span><em>i</em><span> and </span><em>j</em><span> are set-theoretically indiscernible in the model of set theory in which we are undertaking the construction, it follows that their equivalence classes in the quotient are also indiscernible. And so we have a definable copy of the complex field ℂ, extending a definable copy of ℝ, in which the two square roots of −1 are indiscernible not just in the field structure, but fully in the set-theoretic background in which the fields were constructed. □</span></p><p>In particular, in this model of set theory, there will be absolutely no way to distinguish the two roots by any further definable structure, whether using second-order or higher-order definitions of the field ℂ or using any definable set-theoretic property whatsoever. (However, we clearly can distinguish them if we allow parameters, since we can just choose one of them and use it to define the rigid complex plane.)</p><p>The analysis suggests a natural further inquiry. Namely,</p><p><strong>Question. </strong><span>Is there a model of set theory with a definable copy of the complex field ℂ, such that the hierarchy of relative definability and indiscernibility in ℂ matches the set-theoretic relative definability and indiscernibility of the objects?</span></p><p><span>That is, we would want to mimic the phenomenon of </span><em>i</em><span> and –</span><em>i</em><span> in the above construction with all complex numbers, so that √2 and −√2 were also indiscernible, not just in this copy of ℂ but also in the set-theoretic background, and the 4th roots of 2 would be set-theoretically indiscernible, but each can set-theoretically define both √2 and −√2. In other words, I would want the set-theoretic definability hierarchy to match the complex-number-theoretic definability hierarchy.</span></p><p><span>This question remains open, although I believe that perhaps it might be answerable via iterated Sacks forcing in a manner similar to that used in many papers by Marcia Groszek, and in particular, in my 2019 paper with her, </span><em>The Implicitly constructible universe</em><span>.</span></p><p><strong>The complex field as a problem for singular terms</strong></p><p>I should like briefly to relate the story of how the complex field ℂ came to play a decisive role in a certain philosophical dispute in the philosophy of mathematics—many philosophers took it ultimately to refute a certain otherwise tempting position regarding the philosophy of structuralism.</p><p>To be sure, one finds diverse and often incompatible accounts of structuralism in the philosophy of mathematics, for we have abstract structuralism, ante-rem structuralism, eliminative structuralism, in-re structuralism, post-rem structuralism, modal structuralism, structuralism in mathematical practice, the structuralist imperative, and more—see my overview in (Hamkins 2021, p.27-36).</p><p>I have emphasized what I see as two parallel threads of structuralism, developing largely independently in mathematics and philosophy. Namely, the philosophical treatment of structuralism is often seen as growing out of Benacerraf's influential work (1965, 1973), and it is concerned with core philosophical issues, such as the ontology of mathematics and the problem of reference to abstract mathematical objects. Meanwhile, structuralism in mathematics, as I see it, grows mainly out of the much-earlier categoricity results of Dedekind and others in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, leading to the idea currently pervasive in mathematical practice that a mathematician rightly considers mathematical objects only up to isomorphism—this is perhaps the single most widely held philosophical position in mathematics held by mathematicians. The philosophical treatment of structuralism, by my lights, has often been little connected with actual mathematics, and likewise mathematicians talking even at length about structuralism rarely mention Benacerraf or the other philosophical literature on structuralism. In my experience, the two threads of structuralism are thus often focused on fundamentally different matters. However, the situation is improving in recent years.</p><p>On the mathematical side of structuralism, I state the structuralist imperative as follows:</p><p><strong>The structuralist imperative. </strong><span>For mathematical insight, investigate mathematical structure, the relations among entities in a mathematical system, and consider mathematical concepts only as being invariant under isomorphism. Therefore, do not concern yourself with the substance of individual mathematical objects, for this is mathematically fruitless as structure arises with any kind of object. (Hamkins 2021)</span></p><p><span>We might say that an object </span><em>a</em><span> in structure </span><em>A</em><span> plays the same </span><em>structural role</em><span> as object </span><em>b</em><span> in structure </span><em>B</em><span> exactly when there is an isomorphism of </span><em>A</em><span> with </span><em>B</em><span> carrying </span><em>a</em><span> to </span><em>b</em><span>.</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!UP4r!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdbf7306a-25c2-4029-a5f1-dc34bcbea765_2016x708.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!UP4r!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdbf7306a-25c2-4029-a5f1-dc34bcbea765_2016x708.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!UP4r!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdbf7306a-25c2-4029-a5f1-dc34bcbea765_2016x708.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!UP4r!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdbf7306a-25c2-4029-a5f1-dc34bcbea765_2016x708.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!UP4r!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdbf7306a-25c2-4029-a5f1-dc34bcbea765_2016x708.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!UP4r!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdbf7306a-25c2-4029-a5f1-dc34bcbea765_2016x708.jpeg" width="687" height="241.11057692307693" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/dbf7306a-25c2-4029-a5f1-dc34bcbea765_2016x708.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:511,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:687,&quot;bytes&quot;:91467,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!UP4r!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdbf7306a-25c2-4029-a5f1-dc34bcbea765_2016x708.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!UP4r!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdbf7306a-25c2-4029-a5f1-dc34bcbea765_2016x708.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!UP4r!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdbf7306a-25c2-4029-a5f1-dc34bcbea765_2016x708.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!UP4r!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdbf7306a-25c2-4029-a5f1-dc34bcbea765_2016x708.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><span>It seems natural to consider the </span><em>isomorphism orbit</em><span> of an object in a structure, the equivalence class of the object/structure pair (</span><em>a</em><span>, </span><em>A</em><span>) with respect to the same-structural-role-as relation. </span></p><div data-component-name="Latex"><p><span>\((a,A)\equiv(b,B)
\qquad\iff\qquad\exists\,\pi:A\cong B\quad \pi(a)=b.\)</span></p></div><p><span>This orbit tracks how </span><em>a</em><span> is copied to all its various isomorphic images in all the various structures isomorphic to </span><em>A</em><span>. And whether or not these objects are definable or discernible in their structures, it is precisely the objects appearing in the isomorphism orbit that play the same structural role in those structures that </span><em>a</em><span> plays in </span><em>A</em><span>.</span></p><p>Meanwhile, according to Shapiro (1996, 1997), the slogan of structuralism is that “mathematics is the science of structure.” This view leads ultimately to the position of ante-rem or abstract structuralism, the view that what mathematical objects are, at bottom, is the structural roles that those objects play in a mathematical system. Thus, what the real number 1 is, at bottom, is the structural role of being the multiplicative identity. What the number √2 is, is the structural role played by a number that is positive and whose square is 1 + 1, where 1 is the multiplicative identity. And so forth.</p><p><span>The position may be initially attractive. But I have criticized it on the grounds that it is ultimately anti-structuralist. Yes, I argue that abstract structuralism is anti-structuralist. The reason is that it is preoccupied with answering the question of what the mathematical objects really are at bottom. But the structuralist imperative implores us specifically against that—it is not a structuralist undertaking. According to the structuralist imperative, to try to find out what mathematical objects </span><em>really</em><span> are is an anti-structuralist endeavor, a fruitless quest, as well as mathematically irrelevant. It just doesn’t matter what the objects really are, as structure can arise with any kind of object, and so it is anti-structuralist to provide an answer, even if the answer that is provided is that the objects are at bottom purely structural. (Hamkins 2021, p. 35-36)</span></p><p><span>And now let us observe how the complex field made its entrance into the philosophical dispute (see Shapiro 2012). The main observation to make is that the structural role played by </span><em>i</em><span> in the complex field ℂ is identical to the structural role played by –</span><em>i</em><span> in ℂ, precisely because complex conjugation is an automorphism that swaps them. In short, the numbers are distinct, but the role played by them in the relevant structure ℂ is exactly the same. So we cannot coherently identify the mathematical objects with the structural role that they play in a mathematical system, because </span><em>i</em><span> and –</span><em>i</em><span> play exactly the same role in the complex field ℂ, and yet they are not the same object. Isn’t this a clear refutation of that philosophical position?</span></p><p><span>Furthermore, there was nothing special about </span><em>i</em><span> and –</span><em>i</em><span> in the argument, since if we are considering ℂ under the algebraic conception, then every single irrational complex number admits distinct automorphic images. The number √2 plays the same role in the complex field ℂ as does −√2, and </span><em>e</em><span> and π play the same role, and so forth. We have mentioned that indeed there are only countably many structural roles played by numbers in ℂ, since there are the roles played by specific algebraic numbers, while all transcendental numbers are automorphic with each other. But there are uncountably many complex numbers.</span></p><p><strong>The problem of nonrigid structuralist existence</strong></p><p>Let me conclude this essay by turning to another related philosophical problem concerning the complex field and the philosophy of structuralism.</p><p>In my view, in light of the categoricity results characterizing all our familiar mathematical structures, the structuralist practice is what enables a direct structuralist reference to abstract mathematical objects. Namely, in structuralist mathematics, when referring to the real field ℝ, we don’t point at a particular field, kept like the iron rod in a cabinet in Paris, to serve as the canonical instance of this structure. Rather, we simply say, “take any complete ordered field.” Since we only care about ℝ up to isomorphism and any such field is isomorphic to any other, any such field will serve in our argument. Our structuralist argument will not depend on the underlying substance out of which that field had been formed. In this way, the structuralist practice in mathematics relies on our having categorical characterizations for all our core mathematical structures in the first place, since the categorical characterizations are what enable the direct structuralist reference to them.</p><p>In regard to the complex numbers, since we have categorical characterizations of the complex field ℂ under each of the several conceptions—the analytic/smooth conception, the rigid conception, and the algebraic conception—we can thus make direct structuralist reference to the complex numbers under any of the three conceptions, whichever is desired.</p><p>But now a certain problem arises. Suppose we want to make structuralist reference to the complex field under the analytic conception, say, as the field ℂ over ℝ. The categorical characterization is that ℂ is the algebraic closure of ℝ, and so we make structuralist reference to it by saying, “take the algebraic closure ℂ of a complete ordered field ℝ.” That is fine.</p><p><span>But in order for this to work in mathematical proof, we must earlier have proved that indeed there is such a structure, that there is an algebraic closure of a complete ordered field. But now we come to the crux of the issue. Namely, all the constructions of ℂ over ℝ of which I am aware break the symmetry between </span><em>i</em><span> and –</span><em>i</em><span> during the course of the construction—the constructions themselves provide a way of choosing between </span><em>i</em><span> and –</span><em>i</em><span> at an early stage of the process, even if this extra structure is eventually omitted in the end.</span></p><p><span>Take the presentation of ℂ over ℝ using formal sums of the form </span><em>a</em><span> + </span><em>bi</em><span>, say, where </span><em>i</em><span> was introduced as a purely formal symbol. Obviously, this construction enables us to choose that this symbol represents </span><em>i</em><span> and not –</span><em>i</em><span>. We specifically had to forget this constant term in the final field in order to reintroduce the symmetry between </span><em>i</em><span> and –</span><em>i</em><span>.</span></p><p><span>Similarly, in the quotient construction ℝ[</span><em>x</em><span>]/(</span><em>x</em><span>² + 1), the polynomial construction itself obviously distinguishes </span><em>x</em><span> from –</span><em>x</em><span> and thus ultimately distinguishes </span><em>i</em><span> from –</span><em>i</em><span>. We cast that extra structure aside at the end by keeping only the field structure over ℝ and not the distinction between </span><em>x</em><span> and –</span><em>x</em><span>.</span></p><p>When we construct ℂ over ℝ from the complex plane, with the coordinate structure, it is just the same. We construct the rigid complex plane, but then keep only the real-part operator Re, while forgetting the imaginary part operator Im. Our field ℂ over ℝ arises from a process of forgetting from what was the rigid structure of the complex plane.</p><p>In every case, therefore, when proving that there is such a thing as the complex field ℂ over ℝ, what we actually do first is construct a rigid structure, in effect the complex plane, and then take a suitable reduct to forget some of the structure in order to admit the symmetry of complex conjugation.</p><p><span>Earlier I had quoted Daniel Litt, who described it as mathematically immoral to break the symmetry between </span><em>i</em><span> and –</span><em>i</em><span>. My problem with this is that I don’t know any construction of ℂ over ℝ that doesn’t break this symmetry during the course of the construction. In order to build such a field in the first place, we first build a rigid structure and then afterward drop the extra structure in order to recover the desired symmetry. Must we be immoral?</span></p><p><span>Indeed, I claim that this structure-forgetting step is inherent to the process, and I don’t believe we can provide (in ZFC set theory, say) a construction of the complex field ℂ over ℝ that does not during the course of the construction introduce a symmetry-breaking choice between </span><em>i</em><span> and –</span><em>i</em><span>. The final steps of the construction will invariably apply a forgetful operation to remove this extra structure and thereby reintroduce the desired symmetry.</span></p><p>I have argued  that this phenomenon is inherent in mathematic practice, by which nonrigid structure invariably arises always as a reduct substructure of a previously constructed rigid structure. It is simply too difficult ever to specify or refer directly to a nonrigid structure, in which objects of the conception are indiscernible, without first being able to discern them in a richer structural context.</p><blockquote><p><span>We don't start with a naked copy of ℂ and then seek to impose an orientation on it that will enable us to resolve </span><em>i</em><span> from -</span><em>i</em><span>. Rather, we proceed oppositely: instances of mathematical structures are obtained from richer contexts where the objects were already individuated. We might build a copy of ℂ from ordered pairs of real numbers, for example, where we can discern (0,1) from (0,-1) and therefore </span><em>i</em><span> from -</span><em>i</em><span> in this particular copy of ℂ. Every particular copy of ℂ and indeed every particular mathematical structure of any kind arises similarly from a context in which the objects are individuated. (Hamkins 2021, p. 46-47)</span></p></blockquote><p>And then I point out how this philosophical observation becomes a mathematical theorem in set-theoretic foundations. </p><blockquote><p>When using ZFC set theory as a foundation of mathematics, this philosophical observation becomes a mathematical theorem: every set is a reduct substructure of a rigid structure, a structure in which every individual plays a distinct structural role. The reason is that every set is a subset of a transitive set, and every transitive set is rigid with respect to the ∈-membership relation. Indeed, the set-theoretic universe ⟨V,∈⟩ as a whole is rigid—any two objects in the set-theoretic universe are therefore distinguishable as sets and play different set-theoretic roles… Therefore, every mathematical structure that can be realized in set theory at all can be realized as a reduct substructure of a rigid structure. We can refer to distinct individuals in the original structure by the distinct structural roles they play in the larger context.  (Hamkins 2021, p. 47)</p></blockquote><p><span>The earlier results on set-theoretic indiscernibility, however, can be seen as pushing back against the inherency argument above, by showing that it is at least consistent with ZFC that one can definably undertake a construction of ℂ over ℝ without having any set-theoretically definable method of discerning </span><em>i</em><span> from -</span><em>i</em><span>. Nevertheless, although the sets used in the Groszek-Laver pair set {</span><em>i</em><span>, </span><em>j</em><span>} in that construction are set-theoretically indiscernible, they do play different structural roles in the set-theoretic universe, which is rigid, and so in this sense we can still view the polynomial ring ℝ[</span><em>i</em><span>,</span><em>j</em><span>] used in the construction as rigid.</span></p><p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p><p>I began with the question, how shall we view the complex numbers? With which fundamental structure is it to be endowed? Ultimately, my answer to this question is that the complex field exhibits all three of the structural conceptions I have discussed, each considered on its own for a purpose, and although these structures are different and inequivalent, it is wrong to insist on only one conception.</p><p>In particular, the rigid conception plays an important seminal role for the other conceptions of the complex field. Even though the rigid conception is rejected as misguided by many mathematicians, sometimes strongly so, nevertheless all the usual constructions of the structures instantiating the other conceptions have at their heart a rigid presentation of the complex plane, with the symmetries reintroduced only afterward by forgetting the extra structure used in the construction.</p><p data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.infinitelymore.xyz/p/complex-numbers-essential-structure?utm_source=substack&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_content=share&amp;action=share&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Share&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:null,&quot;class&quot;:null}" data-component-name="ButtonCreateButton"><a href="https://www.infinitelymore.xyz/p/complex-numbers-essential-structure?utm_source=substack&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_content=share&amp;action=share" rel=""><span>Share</span></a></p><p><span>Paul Benacerraf. “What Numbers Could not Be”. The Philosophical Review 74.1 (1965), pp. 47–73. issn: 00318108, 15581470. </span><a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/2183530" rel="">http://www.jstor.org/stable/2183530</a><span>.</span></p><p>Paul Benacerraf. “Mathematical Truth”. Journal of Philosophy 70 (1973), pp. 661–679.</p><p><span>Gunter Fuchs, Victoria Gitman, and Joel David Hamkins. “Ehrenfeucht’s Lemma in Set Theory”. Notre Dame Journal of Formal Logic 59.3 (2018), pp. 355–370. doi: </span><a href="https://doi.org/10.1215/00294527-2018-0007" rel="">10.1215/00294527-2018-0007</a><span>. arXiv:</span><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1501.01918" rel="">1501.01918</a><span>. </span></p><p><span>Marcia J. Groszek and Joel David Hamkins. “The implicitly constructible universe”. Journal of Symbolic Logic 84.4 (2019), pp. 1403–1421. doi:</span><a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/jsl.2018.57" rel="">10.1017/jsl.2018.57</a><span>. arXiv:</span><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1702.07947" rel="">1702.07947</a><span>.</span></p><p><span>M. Groszek and R. Laver. “Finite groups of OD-conjugates”. Period. Math. Hungar. 18.2 (1987), pp. 87–97. doi: </span><a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/BF01896284" rel="">10.1007/BF01896284</a><span>.</span></p><p><span>Joel David Hamkins. The real numbers are not interpretable in the complex field. Mathematics and Philosophy of the Infinite. 2020. </span><a href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/the-real-numbers-are-not-interpretable-in-the-complex-field/" rel="">http://jdh.hamkins.org/the-real-numbers-are-not-interpretable-in-the-complex-field/</a><span>.</span></p><p><span>Joel David Hamkins. Lectures on the Philosophy of Mathematics. MIT Press, 2021. isbn: 9780262542234. </span><a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262542234/lectures-on-the-philosophy-of-mathematics/" rel="">https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262542234/lectures-on-the-philosophy-of-mathematics/</a><span> </span></p><p><span>Joel David Hamkins. A model of set theory with a definable copy of the complex field in which the two roots of −1 are set-theoretically indiscernible. Mathematics and Philosophy of the Infinite. 2022. </span><a href="https://jdh.hamkins.org/a-model-of-set-theory-with-a-definable-copy-of-the-complex-field-in-which-the-two-roots-of-1-are-set-theoretically-indiscernible/" rel="">https://jdh.hamkins.org/a-model-of-set-theory-with-a-definable-copy-of-the-complex-field-in-which-the-two-roots-of-1-are-set-theoretically-indiscernible/</a></p><p><span>Joel David Hamkins, David Linetsky, and Jonas Reitz. “Pointwise definable models of set theory”. Journal of Symbolic Logic 78.1 (2013), pp. 139–156. doi: </span><a href="https://doi.org/10.2178/jsl.7801090" rel="">10.2178/jsl.7801090</a><span>. arXiv:</span><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1105.4597" rel="">1105.4597</a><span>. </span></p><p>Stewart Shapiro. “An “i” for an i: Singular Terms, Uniqueness, and Reference”. Review of Symbolic Logic 5.3 (2012), pp. 380–415.</p><p><span>Stewart Shapiro. “Mathematical Structuralism”. Philosophia Mathematica 4.2 (May 1996), pp. 81–82. issn: 1744-6406. doi: </span><a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/philmat/4.2.81" rel="">10.1093/philmat/4.2.81</a><span>.</span></p><p>Stewart Shapiro. Philosophy of Mathematics: Structure and Ontology. Oxford University Press, 1997.</p><p>Parts of this essay were adapted from my blog posts in 2020, 2022, as well as my book 2021.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ex-GitHub CEO launches a new developer platform for AI agents (450 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://entire.io/blog/hello-entire-world/</link>
            <guid>46961345</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 15:44:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://entire.io/blog/hello-entire-world/">https://entire.io/blog/hello-entire-world/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46961345">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Bazzite Post-Mortem (114 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ba.antheas.dev/bazzite-postmortem.html</link>
            <guid>46961261</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 15:40:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ba.antheas.dev/bazzite-postmortem.html">https://ba.antheas.dev/bazzite-postmortem.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46961261">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I started programming when I was 7. I'm 50 now and the thing I loved has changed (715 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.jamesdrandall.com/posts/the_thing_i_loved_has_changed/</link>
            <guid>46960675</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 15:08:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.jamesdrandall.com/posts/the_thing_i_loved_has_changed/">https://www.jamesdrandall.com/posts/the_thing_i_loved_has_changed/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46960675">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>I Started Programming When I Was 7. I'm 50 Now, and the Thing I Loved Has Changed</p><div><p>I wrote my first line of code in 1983. I was seven years old, typing BASIC into a machine that had less processing power than the chip in your washing machine. I understood that machine completely. Every byte of RAM had a purpose I could trace. Every pixel on screen was there because I’d put it there. The path from intention to result was direct, visible, and mine.</p>
<p>Forty-two years later, I’m sitting in front of hardware that would have seemed like science fiction to that kid, and I’m trying to figure out what “building things” even means anymore.</p>
<p>This isn’t a rant about AI. It’s not a “back in my day” piece. It’s something I’ve been circling for months, and I think a lot of experienced developers are circling it too, even if they haven’t said it out loud yet.</p>
<h2 id="the-era-that-made-me">The era that made me</h2>
<p>My favourite period of computing runs from the 8-bits through to about the 486DX2-66. Every machine in that era had character. The Sinclair Spectrum with its attribute clash. The Commodore 64 with its SID chip doing things the designers never intended. The NES with its 8-sprite-per-scanline limit that made developers invent flickering tricks to cheat the hardware. And the PC — starting life as a boring beige box for spreadsheets, then evolving at breakneck pace through the 286, 386, and 486 until it became a gaming powerhouse that could run Doom. You could feel each generation leap. Upgrading your CPU wasn’t a spec sheet exercise — it was transformative.</p>
<p>These weren’t just products. They were engineering adventures with visible tradeoffs. You had to understand the machine to use it. IRQ conflicts, DMA channels, CONFIG.SYS and AUTOEXEC.BAT optimisation, memory managers — getting a game to run <em>was</em> the game. You weren’t just a user. You were a systems engineer by necessity.</p>
<p>And the software side matched. Small teams like id Software were going their own way, making bold technical decisions because nobody had written the rules yet. Carmack’s raycasting in Wolfenstein, the VGA Mode X tricks in Doom — these were people pushing against real constraints and producing something genuinely new. Creative constraints bred creativity.</p>
<p>Then it professionalised. Plug and Play arrived. Windows abstracted everything. The Wild West closed. Computers stopped being fascinating, cantankerous machines that demanded respect and understanding, and became appliances. The craft became invisible.</p>
<p>But it wasn’t just the craft that changed. The promise changed.</p>
<p>When I started, there was a genuine optimism about what computers could be. A kid with a Spectrum could teach themselves to build anything. The early web felt like the greatest levelling force in human history. Small teams made bold decisions because nobody had written the rules yet.</p>
<p>That hope gave way to something I find genuinely distasteful. The machines I fell in love with became instruments of surveillance and extraction. The platforms that promised to connect us were really built to monetise us. The tinkerer spirit didn’t die of natural causes — it was bought out and put to work optimising ad clicks.</p>
<p>The thing I loved changed, and then it was put to work doing things I’m not proud to be associated with. That’s a different kind of loss than just “the tools moved on.”</p>
<p>But I adapted. That’s what experienced developers, human beings, do.</p>
<h2 id="the-shifts-i-rode">The shifts I rode</h2>
<p>Over four decades I’ve been through more technology transitions than I can count. New languages, new platforms, new paradigms. CLI to GUI. Desktop to web. Web to mobile. Monoliths to microservices. Tapes, floppy discs, hard drives, SSDs. JavaScript frameworks arriving and dying like mayflies.</p>
<p>Each wave required learning new things, but the core skill transferred. You learned the new platform, you applied your existing understanding of how systems work, and you kept building. The tool changed; the craft didn’t. You were still the person who understood why things broke, how systems composed, where today’s shortcut became next month’s mess.</p>
<p>I’ve written production code in more languages than some developers have heard of. I’ve shipped software on platforms that no longer exist. I’ve chased C-beams off the shoulder of Orion. And every time the industry lurched in a new direction, the experience compounded. You didn’t start over. You brought everything with you and applied it somewhere new.</p>
<p>That’s the deal experienced developers made with the industry: things change, but understanding endures.</p>
<h2 id="this-time-is-different">This time is different</h2>
<p>I say that knowing how often those words have been wrong throughout history. But hear me out.</p>
<p>Previous technology shifts were “learn the new thing, apply existing skills.” AI isn’t that. It’s not a new platform or a new language or a new paradigm. It’s a shift in what it <em>means</em> to be good at this.</p>
<p>I noticed it gradually. I’d be working on something — building a feature, designing an architecture — and I’d realise I was still doing the same thing I’d always done, just with the interesting bits hollowed out. The part where you figure out the elegant solution, where you wrestle with the constraints, where you feel the satisfaction of something clicking into place — that was increasingly being handled by a model that doesn’t care about elegance and has never felt satisfaction.</p>
<p>Cheaper. Faster. But hollowed out.</p>
<p>I’m not typing the code anymore. I’m reviewing it, directing it, correcting it. And I’m good at that — 42 years of accumulated judgment about what works and what doesn’t, what’s elegant versus what’s expedient, how systems compose and where they fracture. That’s valuable. I know it’s valuable. But it’s a different kind of work, and it doesn’t feel the same.</p>
<p>The feedback loop has changed. The intimacy has gone. The thing that kept me up at night for decades — the puzzle, the chase, the moment where you finally understand why something isn’t working — that’s been compressed into a prompt and a response. And I’m watching people with a fraction of my experience produce superficially similar output. The craft distinction is real, but it’s harder to see from the outside. Harder to value. Maybe harder to feel internally.</p>
<h2 id="the-abstraction-tower">The abstraction tower</h2>
<p>Here’s the part that makes me laugh, darkly.</p>
<p>I saw someone on LinkedIn recently — early twenties, a few years into their career — lamenting that with AI they “didn’t really know what was going on anymore.” And I thought: mate, you were <em>already</em> so far up the abstraction chain you didn’t even realise you were teetering on top of a wobbly Jenga tower.</p>
<p>They’re writing TypeScript that compiles to JavaScript that runs in a V8 engine written in C++ that’s making system calls to an OS kernel that’s scheduling threads across cores they’ve never thought about, hitting RAM through a memory controller with caching layers they couldn’t diagram, all while npm pulls in 400 packages they’ve never read a line of.</p>
<p>But sure. <em>AI</em> is the moment they lost track of what’s happening.</p>
<p>The abstraction ship sailed decades ago. We just didn’t notice because each layer arrived gradually enough that we could pretend we still understood the whole stack. AI is just the layer that made the pretence impossible to maintain.</p>
<p>The difference is: I remember what it felt like to understand the whole machine. I’ve <em>had</em> that experience. And losing it — even acknowledging that it was lost long before AI arrived — is a kind of grief that someone who never had it can’t fully feel.</p>
<h2 id="what-remains">What remains</h2>
<p>I don’t want to be dishonest about this. There’s a version of this post where I tell you that experience is more valuable than ever, that systems thinking and architectural judgment are the things AI can’t replace, that the craft endures in a different form.</p>
<p>And that’s true. When I’m working on something complex — juggling system-level dependencies, holding a mental model across multiple interacting specifications, making the thousand small decisions that determine whether something feels coherent or just <em>works</em> — I can see how I still bring something AI doesn’t. The taste. The judgment. The pattern recognition from decades of seeing things go wrong.</p>
<p>AI tools actually make that kind of thinking <em>more</em> valuable, not less. When code generation is cheap, the bottleneck shifts to the person who knows what to ask for, can spot when the output is subtly wrong, and can hold the whole picture together. Typing was never the hard part.</p>
<p>But I’d be lying if I said it felt the same. It doesn’t. The wonder is harder to access. The sense of discovery, of figuring something out through sheer persistence and ingenuity — that’s been compressed. Not eliminated, but compressed. And something is lost in the compression, even if something is gained.</p>
<h2 id="the-fallow-period">The fallow period</h2>
<p>I turned 50 recently. Four decades of intensity, of crafting and finding satisfaction and identity in the building.</p>
<p>And now I’m in what I’ve started calling a fallow period. Not burnout exactly. More like the ground shifting under a building you thought that although ever changing also had a permanence, and trying to figure out where the new foundation is.</p>
<p>I don’t have a neat conclusion. I’m not going to tell you that experienced developers just need to “push themselves up the stack” or “embrace the tools” or “focus on what AI can’t do.” All of that is probably right, and none of it addresses the feeling.</p>
<p>The feeling is: I gave 42 years to this thing, and the thing changed into something I’m not sure I recognise anymore. Not worse, necessarily. Just different. And different in a way that challenges the identity I built around it and doesn’t satisfy in the way it did.</p>
<p>I suspect a lot of developers over 40 are feeling something similar and not saying it, because the industry worships youth and adaptability and saying “this doesn’t feel like it used to” sounds like you’re falling behind.</p>
<p>I’m not falling behind. I’m moving ahead, taking advantage of the new tools, building faster than ever, and using these tools to help others accelerate their own work. I’m creating products I could only have dreamt of a few years ago. But at the same time I’m looking at the landscape, trying to figure out what building means to me now. The world’s still figuring out its shape too. Maybe that’s okay.</p>
<p>Maybe the fallow period is the point. Not something to push through, but something to be in for a while.</p>
<p>I started programming when I was seven because a machine did exactly what I told it to, felt like something I could explore and ultimately know, and that felt like magic. I’m fifty now, and the magic is different, and I’m learning to sit with that.</p>
<hr>
<p>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@soymeraki?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Javier Allegue Barros</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/silhouette-of-road-signage-during-golden-hour-C7B-ExXpOIE?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The US is flirting with its first-ever population decline (283 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2026-01-30/trump-immigration-crackdown-could-shrink-us-population-for-first-time</link>
            <guid>46960624</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 15:05:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2026-01-30/trump-immigration-crackdown-could-shrink-us-population-for-first-time">https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2026-01-30/trump-immigration-crackdown-could-shrink-us-population-for-first-time</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46960624">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2026-01-30/trump-immigration-crackdown-could-shrink-us-population-for-first-time: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Vercel's CEO offers to cover expenses of 'Jmail' (274 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.threads.com/@qa_test_hq/post/DUkC_zjiGQh</link>
            <guid>46960517</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 14:58:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.threads.com/@qa_test_hq/post/DUkC_zjiGQh">https://www.threads.com/@qa_test_hq/post/DUkC_zjiGQh</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46960517">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Parse, Don't Validate (2019) (229 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lexi-lambda.github.io/blog/2019/11/05/parse-don-t-validate/</link>
            <guid>46960392</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 14:49:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lexi-lambda.github.io/blog/2019/11/05/parse-don-t-validate/">https://lexi-lambda.github.io/blog/2019/11/05/parse-don-t-validate/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46960392">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div role="main"><article><header></header><p>Historically, I’ve struggled to find a concise, simple way to explain what it means to practice type-driven design. Too often, when someone asks me “How did you come up with this approach?” I find I can’t give them a satisfying answer. I know it didn’t just come to me in a vision—I have an iterative design process that doesn’t require plucking the “right” approach out of thin air—yet I haven’t been very successful in communicating that process to others.</p><p>However, about a month ago, <a href="https://twitter.com/lexi_lambda/status/1182242561655746560">I was reflecting on Twitter</a> about the differences I experienced parsing JSON in statically- and dynamically-typed languages, and finally, I realized what I was looking for. Now I have a single, snappy slogan that encapsulates what type-driven design means to me, and better yet, it’s only three words long:</p><p><strong>Parse, don’t validate.</strong></p><h2><a name="the-essence-of-type-driven-design"></a>The essence of type-driven design</h2><p>Alright, I’ll confess: unless you already know what type-driven design is, my catchy slogan probably doesn’t mean all that much to you. Fortunately, that’s what the remainder of this blog post is for. I’m going to explain precisely what I mean in gory detail—but first, we need to practice a little wishful thinking.</p><h3><a name="the-realm-of-possibility"></a>The realm of possibility</h3><p>One of the wonderful things about static type systems is that they can make it possible, and sometimes even easy, to answer questions like “is it possible to write this function?” For an extreme example, consider the following Haskell type signature:</p><pre><code><span>foo</span><span> </span><span>::</span><span> </span><span>Integer</span><span> </span><span>-&gt;</span><span> </span><span>Void</span></code></pre><p>Is it possible to implement <code>foo</code>? Trivially, the answer is <em>no</em>, as <code>Void</code> is a type that contains no values, so it’s impossible for <em>any</em> function to produce a value of type <code>Void</code>.<sup><a href="#footnote-1" id="footnote-ref-1-1">1</a></sup> That example is pretty boring, but the question gets much more interesting if we choose a more realistic example:</p><pre><code><span>head</span><span> </span><span>::</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>a</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>-&gt;</span><span> </span><span>a</span></code></pre><p>This function returns the first element from a list. Is it possible to implement? It certainly doesn’t sound like it does anything very complicated, but if we attempt to implement it, the compiler won’t be satisfied:</p><pre><code><span>head</span><span> </span><span>::</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>a</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>-&gt;</span><span> </span><span>a</span>
<span>head</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>x</span><span>:</span><span>_</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>x</span></code></pre><pre><code>warning: [-Wincomplete-patterns]
    Pattern match(es) are non-exhaustive
    In an equation for ‘head’: Patterns not matched: []
</code></pre><p>This message is helpfully pointing out that our function is <em>partial</em>, which is to say it is not defined for all possible inputs. Specifically, it is not defined when the input is <code>[]</code>, the empty list. This makes sense, as it isn’t possible to return the first element of a list if the list is empty—there’s no element to return! So, remarkably, we learn this function isn’t possible to implement, either.</p><h3><a name="turning-partial-functions-total"></a>Turning partial functions total</h3><p>To someone coming from a dynamically-typed background, this might seem perplexing. If we have a list, we might very well want to get the first element in it. And indeed, the operation of “getting the first element of a list” isn’t impossible in Haskell, it just requires a little extra ceremony. There are two different ways to fix the <code>head</code> function, and we’ll start with the simplest one.</p><h4><a name="managing-expectations"></a>Managing expectations</h4><p>As established, <code>head</code> is partial because there is no element to return if the list is empty: we’ve made a promise we cannot possibly fulfill. Fortunately, there’s an easy solution to that dilemma: we can weaken our promise. Since we cannot guarantee the caller an element of the list, we’ll have to practice a little expectation management: we’ll do our best return an element if we can, but we reserve the right to return nothing at all. In Haskell, we express this possibility using the <code>Maybe</code> type:</p><pre><code><span>head</span><span> </span><span>::</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>a</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>-&gt;</span><span> </span><span>Maybe</span><span> </span><span>a</span></code></pre><p>This buys us the freedom we need to implement <code>head</code>—it allows us to return <code>Nothing</code> when we discover we can’t produce a value of type <code>a</code> after all:</p><pre><code><span>head</span><span> </span><span>::</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>a</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>-&gt;</span><span> </span><span>Maybe</span><span> </span><span>a</span>
<span>head</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>x</span><span>:</span><span>_</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>Just</span><span> </span><span>x</span>
<span>head</span><span> </span><span>[]</span><span>    </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>Nothing</span></code></pre><p>Problem solved, right? For the moment, yes… but this solution has a hidden cost.</p><p>Returning <code>Maybe</code> is undoubtably convenient when we’re <em>implementing</em>  <code>head</code>. However, it becomes significantly less convenient when we want to actually use it! Since <code>head</code> always has the potential to return <code>Nothing</code>, the burden falls upon its callers to handle that possibility, and sometimes that passing of the buck can be incredibly frustrating. To see why, consider the following code:</p><pre><code><span>getConfigurationDirectories</span><span> </span><span>::</span><span> </span><span>IO</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>FilePath</span><span>]</span>
<span>getConfigurationDirectories</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>do</span>
<span>  </span><span>configDirsString</span><span> </span><span>&lt;-</span><span> </span><span>getEnv</span><span> </span><span>"CONFIG_DIRS"</span>
<span>  </span><span>let</span><span> </span><span>configDirsList</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>split</span><span> </span><span>','</span><span> </span><span>configDirsString</span>
<span>  </span><span>when</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>null</span><span> </span><span>configDirsList</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>$</span>
<span>    </span><span>throwIO</span><span> </span><span>$</span><span> </span><span>userError</span><span> </span><span>"CONFIG_DIRS cannot be empty"</span>
<span>  </span><span>pure</span><span> </span><span>configDirsList</span>

<span>main</span><span> </span><span>::</span><span> </span><span>IO</span><span> </span><span>()</span>
<span>main</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>do</span>
<span>  </span><span>configDirs</span><span> </span><span>&lt;-</span><span> </span><span>getConfigurationDirectories</span>
<span>  </span><span>case</span><span> </span><span>head</span><span> </span><span>configDirs</span><span> </span><span>of</span>
<span>    </span><span>Just</span><span> </span><span>cacheDir</span><span> </span><span>-&gt;</span><span> </span><span>initializeCache</span><span> </span><span>cacheDir</span>
<span>    </span><span>Nothing</span><span> </span><span>-&gt;</span><span> </span><span>error</span><span> </span><span>"should never happen; already checked configDirs is non-empty"</span></code></pre><p>When <code>getConfigurationDirectories</code> retrieves a list of file paths from the environment, it proactively checks that the list is non-empty. However, when we use <code>head</code> in <code>main</code> to get the first element of the list, the <code>Maybe FilePath</code> result still requires us to handle a <code>Nothing</code> case that we know will never happen! This is terribly bad for several reasons:</p><ol><li><p>First, it’s just annoying. We already checked that the list is non-empty, why do we have to clutter our code with another redundant check?</p></li><li><p>Second, it has a potential performance cost. Although the cost of the redundant check is trivial in this particular example, one could imagine a more complex scenario where the redundant checks could add up, such as if they were happening in a tight loop.</p></li><li><p>Finally, and worst of all, this code is a bug waiting to happen! What if <code>getConfigurationDirectories</code> were modified to stop checking that the list is empty, intentionally or unintentionally? The programmer might not remember to update <code>main</code>, and suddenly the “impossible” error becomes not only possible, but probable.</p></li></ol><p>The need for this redundant check has essentially forced us to punch a hole in our type system. If we could statically <em>prove</em> the <code>Nothing</code> case impossible, then a modification to <code>getConfigurationDirectories</code> that stopped checking if the list was empty would invalidate the proof and trigger a compile-time failure. However, as-written, we’re forced to rely on a test suite or manual inspection to catch the bug.</p><h4><a name="paying-it-forward"></a>Paying it forward</h4><p>Clearly, our modified version of <code>head</code> leaves some things to be desired. Somehow, we’d like it to be smarter: if we already checked that the list was non-empty, <code>head</code> should unconditionally return the first element without forcing us to handle the case we know is impossible. How can we do that?</p><p>Let’s look at the original (partial) type signature for <code>head</code> again:</p><pre><code><span>head</span><span> </span><span>::</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>a</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>-&gt;</span><span> </span><span>a</span></code></pre><p>The previous section illustrated that we can turn that partial type signature into a total one by weakening the promise made in the return type. However, since we don’t want to do that, there’s only one thing left that can be changed: the argument type (in this case, <code>[a]</code>). Instead of weakening the return type, we can <em>strengthen</em> the argument type, eliminating the possibility of <code>head</code> ever being called on an empty list in the first place.</p><p>To do this, we need a type that represents non-empty lists. Fortunately, the existing <code>NonEmpty</code> type from <code>Data.List.NonEmpty</code> is exactly that. It has the following definition:</p><pre><code><span>data</span><span> </span><span>NonEmpty</span><span> </span><span>a</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>a</span><span> </span><span>:|</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>a</span><span>]</span></code></pre><p>Note that <code>NonEmpty a</code> is really just a tuple of an <code>a</code> and an ordinary, possibly-empty <code>[a]</code>. This conveniently models a non-empty list by storing the first element of the list separately from the list’s tail: even if the <code>[a]</code> component is <code>[]</code>, the <code>a</code> component must always be present. This makes <code>head</code> completely trivial to implement:<sup><a href="#footnote-2" id="footnote-ref-2-1">2</a></sup></p><pre><code><span>head</span><span> </span><span>::</span><span> </span><span>NonEmpty</span><span> </span><span>a</span><span> </span><span>-&gt;</span><span> </span><span>a</span>
<span>head</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>x</span><span>:|</span><span>_</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>x</span></code></pre><p>Unlike before, GHC accepts this definition without complaint—this definition is <em>total</em>, not partial. We can update our program to use the new implementation:</p><pre><code><span>getConfigurationDirectories</span><span> </span><span>::</span><span> </span><span>IO</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>NonEmpty</span><span> </span><span>FilePath</span><span>)</span>
<span>getConfigurationDirectories</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>do</span>
<span>  </span><span>configDirsString</span><span> </span><span>&lt;-</span><span> </span><span>getEnv</span><span> </span><span>"CONFIG_DIRS"</span>
<span>  </span><span>let</span><span> </span><span>configDirsList</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>split</span><span> </span><span>','</span><span> </span><span>configDirsString</span>
<span>  </span><span>case</span><span> </span><span>nonEmpty</span><span> </span><span>configDirsList</span><span> </span><span>of</span>
<span>    </span><span>Just</span><span> </span><span>nonEmptyConfigDirsList</span><span> </span><span>-&gt;</span><span> </span><span>pure</span><span> </span><span>nonEmptyConfigDirsList</span>
<span>    </span><span>Nothing</span><span> </span><span>-&gt;</span><span> </span><span>throwIO</span><span> </span><span>$</span><span> </span><span>userError</span><span> </span><span>"CONFIG_DIRS cannot be empty"</span>

<span>main</span><span> </span><span>::</span><span> </span><span>IO</span><span> </span><span>()</span>
<span>main</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>do</span>
<span>  </span><span>configDirs</span><span> </span><span>&lt;-</span><span> </span><span>getConfigurationDirectories</span>
<span>  </span><span>initializeCache</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>head</span><span> </span><span>configDirs</span><span>)</span></code></pre><p>Note that the redundant check in <code>main</code> is now completely gone! Instead, we perform the check exactly once, in <code>getConfigurationDirectories</code>. It constructs a <code>NonEmpty a</code> from a <code>[a]</code> using the <code>nonEmpty</code> function from <code>Data.List.NonEmpty</code>, which has the following type:</p><pre><code><span>nonEmpty</span><span> </span><span>::</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>a</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>-&gt;</span><span> </span><span>Maybe</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>NonEmpty</span><span> </span><span>a</span><span>)</span></code></pre><p>The <code>Maybe</code> is still there, but this time, we handle the <code>Nothing</code> case very early in our program: right in the same place we were already doing the input validation. Once that check has passed, we now have a <code>NonEmpty FilePath</code> value, which preserves (in the type system!) the knowledge that the list really is non-empty. Put another way, you can think of a value of type <code>NonEmpty a</code> as being like a value of type <code>[a]</code>, plus a <em>proof</em> that the list is non-empty.</p><p>By strengthening the type of the argument to <code>head</code> instead of weakening the type of its result, we’ve completely eliminated all the problems from the previous section:</p><ul><li><p>The code has no redundant checks, so there can’t be any performance overhead.</p></li><li><p>Furthermore, if <code>getConfigurationDirectories</code> changes to stop checking that the list is non-empty, its return type must change, too. Consequently, <code>main</code> will fail to typecheck, alerting us to the problem before we even run the program!</p></li></ul><p>What’s more, it’s trivial to recover the old behavior of <code>head</code> from the new one by composing <code>head</code> with <code>nonEmpty</code>:</p><pre><code><span>head'</span><span> </span><span>::</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>a</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>-&gt;</span><span> </span><span>Maybe</span><span> </span><span>a</span>
<span>head'</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>fmap</span><span> </span><span>head</span><span> </span><span>.</span><span> </span><span>nonEmpty</span></code></pre><p>Note that the inverse is <em>not</em> true: there is no way to obtain the new version of <code>head</code> from the old one. All in all, the second approach is superior on all axes.</p><h3><a name="the-power-of-parsing"></a>The power of parsing</h3><p>You may be wondering what the above example has to do with the title of this blog post. After all, we only examined two different ways to validate that a list was non-empty—no parsing in sight. That interpretation isn’t wrong, but I’d like to propose another perspective: in my mind, the difference between validation and parsing lies almost entirely in how information is preserved. Consider the following pair of functions:</p><pre><code><span>validateNonEmpty</span><span> </span><span>::</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>a</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>-&gt;</span><span> </span><span>IO</span><span> </span><span>()</span>
<span>validateNonEmpty</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>_</span><span>:</span><span>_</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>pure</span><span> </span><span>()</span>
<span>validateNonEmpty</span><span> </span><span>[]</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>throwIO</span><span> </span><span>$</span><span> </span><span>userError</span><span> </span><span>"list cannot be empty"</span>

<span>parseNonEmpty</span><span> </span><span>::</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>a</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>-&gt;</span><span> </span><span>IO</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>NonEmpty</span><span> </span><span>a</span><span>)</span>
<span>parseNonEmpty</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>x</span><span>:</span><span>xs</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>pure</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>x</span><span>:|</span><span>xs</span><span>)</span>
<span>parseNonEmpty</span><span> </span><span>[]</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>throwIO</span><span> </span><span>$</span><span> </span><span>userError</span><span> </span><span>"list cannot be empty"</span></code></pre><p>These two functions are nearly identical: they check if the provided list is empty, and if it is, they abort the program with an error message. The difference lies entirely in the return type: <code>validateNonEmpty</code> always returns <code>()</code>, the type that contains no information, but <code>parseNonEmpty</code> returns <code>NonEmpty a</code>, a refinement of the input type that preserves the knowledge gained in the type system. Both of these functions check the same thing, but <code>parseNonEmpty</code> gives the caller access to the information it learned, while <code>validateNonEmpty</code> just throws it away.</p><p>These two functions elegantly illustrate two different perspectives on the role of a static type system: <code>validateNonEmpty</code> obeys the typechecker well enough, but only <code>parseNonEmpty</code> takes full advantage of it. If you see why <code>parseNonEmpty</code> is preferable, you understand what I mean by the mantra “parse, don’t validate.” Still, perhaps you are skeptical of <code>parseNonEmpty</code>’s name. Is it really <em>parsing</em> anything, or is it merely validating its input and returning a result? While the precise definition of what it means to parse or validate something is debatable, I believe <code>parseNonEmpty</code> is a bona-fide parser (albeit a particularly simple one).</p><p>Consider: what is a parser? Really, a parser is just a function that consumes less-structured input and produces more-structured output. By its very nature, a parser is a partial function—some values in the domain do not correspond to any value in the range—so all parsers must have some notion of failure. Often, the input to a parser is text, but this is by no means a requirement, and <code>parseNonEmpty</code> is a perfectly cromulent parser: it parses lists into non-empty lists, signaling failure by terminating the program with an error message.</p><p>Under this flexible definition, parsers are an incredibly powerful tool: they allow discharging checks on input up-front, right on the boundary between a program and the outside world, and once those checks have been performed, they never need to be checked again! Haskellers are well-aware of this power, and they use many different types of parsers on a regular basis:</p><ul><li><p>The <a href="https://hackage.haskell.org/package/aeson">aeson</a> library provides a <code>Parser</code> type that can be used to parse JSON data into domain types.</p></li><li><p>Likewise, <a href="https://hackage.haskell.org/package/optparse-applicative">optparse-applicative</a> provides a set of parser combinators for parsing command-line arguments.</p></li><li><p>Database libraries like <a href="https://hackage.haskell.org/package/persistent">persistent</a> and <a href="https://hackage.haskell.org/package/postgresql-simple">postgresql-simple</a> have a mechanism for parsing values held in an external data store.</p></li><li><p>The <a href="https://hackage.haskell.org/package/servant">servant</a> ecosystem is built around parsing Haskell datatypes from path components, query parameters, HTTP headers, and more.</p></li></ul><p>The common theme between all these libraries is that they sit on the boundary between your Haskell application and the external world. That world doesn’t speak in product and sum types, but in streams of bytes, so there’s no getting around a need to do some parsing. Doing that parsing up front, before acting on the data, can go a long way toward avoiding many classes of bugs, some of which might even be security vulnerabilities.</p><p>One drawback to this approach of parsing everything up front is that it sometimes requires values be parsed long before they are actually used. In a dynamically-typed language, this can make keeping the parsing and processing logic in sync a little tricky without extensive test coverage, much of which can be laborious to maintain. However, with a static type system, the problem becomes marvelously simple, as demonstrated by the <code>NonEmpty</code> example above: if the parsing and processing logic go out of sync, the program will fail to even compile.</p><h3><a name="the-danger-of-validation"></a>The danger of validation</h3><p>Hopefully, by this point, you are at least somewhat sold on the idea that parsing is preferable to validation, but you may have lingering doubts. Is validation really so bad if the type system is going to force you to do the necessary checks eventually anyway? Maybe the error reporting will be a little bit worse, but a bit of redundant checking can’t hurt, right?</p><p>Unfortunately, it isn’t so simple. Ad-hoc validation leads to a phenomenon that the <a href="http://langsec.org/">language-theoretic security</a> field calls <em>shotgun parsing</em>. In the 2016 paper, <a href="http://langsec.org/papers/langsec-cwes-secdev2016.pdf">The Seven Turrets of Babel: A Taxonomy of LangSec Errors and How to Expunge Them</a>, its authors provide the following definition:</p><blockquote><p>Shotgun parsing is a programming antipattern whereby parsing and input-validating code is mixed with and spread across processing code—throwing a cloud of checks at the input, and hoping, without any systematic justification, that one or another would catch all the “bad” cases.</p></blockquote><p>They go on to explain the problems inherent to such validation techniques:</p><blockquote><p>Shotgun parsing necessarily deprives the program of the ability to reject invalid input instead of processing it. Late-discovered errors in an input stream will result in some portion of invalid input having been processed, with the consequence that program state is difficult to accurately predict.</p></blockquote><p>In other words, a program that does not parse all of its input up front runs the risk of acting upon a valid portion of the input, discovering a different portion is invalid, and suddenly needing to roll back whatever modifications it already executed in order to maintain consistency. Sometimes this is possible—such as rolling back a transaction in an RDBMS—but in general it may not be.</p><p>It may not be immediately apparent what shotgun parsing has to do with validation—after all, if you do all your validation up front, you mitigate the risk of shotgun parsing. The problem is that validation-based approaches make it extremely difficult or impossible to determine if everything was actually validated up front or if some of those so-called “impossible” cases might actually happen. The entire program must assume that raising an exception anywhere is not only possible, it’s regularly necessary.</p><p>Parsing avoids this problem by stratifying the program into two phases—parsing and execution—where failure due to invalid input can only happen in the first phase. The set of remaining failure modes during execution is minimal by comparison, and they can be handled with the tender care they require.</p><h2><a name="parsing-not-validating-in-practice"></a>Parsing, not validating, in practice</h2><p>So far, this blog post has been something of a sales pitch. “You, dear reader, ought to be parsing!” it says, and if I’ve done my job properly, at least some of you are sold. However, even if you understand the “what” and the “why,” you might not feel especially confident about the “how.”</p><p>My advice: focus on the datatypes.</p><p>Suppose you are writing a function that accepts a list of tuples representing key-value pairs, and you suddenly realize you aren’t sure what to do if the list has duplicate keys. One solution would be to write a function that asserts there aren’t any duplicates in the list:</p><pre><code><span>checkNoDuplicateKeys</span><span> </span><span>::</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>MonadError</span><span> </span><span>AppError</span><span> </span><span>m</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>Eq</span><span> </span><span>k</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>=&gt;</span><span> </span><span>[(</span><span>k</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>v</span><span>)]</span><span> </span><span>-&gt;</span><span> </span><span>m</span><span> </span><span>()</span></code></pre><p>However, this check is fragile: it’s extremely easy to forget. Because its return value is unused, it can always be omitted, and the code that needs it would still typecheck. A better solution is to choose a data structure that disallows duplicate keys by construction, such as a <code>Map</code>. Adjust your function’s type signature to accept a <code>Map</code> instead of a list of tuples, and implement it as you normally would.</p><p>Once you’ve done that, the call site of your new function will likely fail to typecheck, since it is still being passed a list of tuples. If the caller was given the value via one of its arguments, or if it received it from the result of some other function, you can continue updating the type from list to <code>Map</code>, all the way up the call chain. Eventually, you will either reach the location the value is created, or you’ll find a place where duplicates actually ought to be allowed. At that point, you can insert a call to a modified version of <code>checkNoDuplicateKeys</code>:</p><pre><code><span>checkNoDuplicateKeys</span><span> </span><span>::</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>MonadError</span><span> </span><span>AppError</span><span> </span><span>m</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>Eq</span><span> </span><span>k</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>=&gt;</span><span> </span><span>[(</span><span>k</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>v</span><span>)]</span><span> </span><span>-&gt;</span><span> </span><span>m</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>Map</span><span> </span><span>k</span><span> </span><span>v</span><span>)</span></code></pre><p>Now the check <em>cannot</em> be omitted, since its result is actually necessary for the program to proceed!</p><p>This hypothetical scenario highlights two simple ideas:</p><ol><li><p><strong>Use a data structure that makes illegal states unrepresentable.</strong> Model your data using the most precise data structure you reasonably can. If ruling out a particular possibility is too hard using the encoding you are currently using, consider alternate encodings that can express the property you care about more easily. Don’t be afraid to refactor.</p></li><li><p><strong>Push the burden of proof upward as far as possible, but no further.</strong> Get your data into the most precise representation you need as quickly as you can. Ideally, this should happen at the boundary of your system, before <em>any</em> of the data is acted upon.<sup><a href="#footnote-3" id="footnote-ref-3-1">3</a></sup></p><p>If one particular code branch eventually requires a more precise representation of a piece of data, parse the data into the more precise representation as soon as the branch is selected. Use sum types judiciously to allow your datatypes to reflect and adapt to control flow.</p></li></ol><p>In other words, write functions on the data representation you <em>wish</em> you had, not the data representation you are given. The design process then becomes an exercise in bridging the gap, often by working from both ends until they meet somewhere in the middle. Don’t be afraid to iteratively adjust parts of the design as you go, since you may learn something new during the refactoring process!</p><p>Here are a handful of additional points of advice, arranged in no particular order:</p><ul><li><p><strong>Let your datatypes inform your code, don’t let your code control your datatypes.</strong> Avoid the temptation to just stick a <code>Bool</code> in a record somewhere because it’s needed by the function you’re currently writing. Don’t be afraid to refactor code to use the right data representation—the type system will ensure you’ve covered all the places that need changing, and it will likely save you a headache later.</p></li><li><p><strong>Treat functions that return <code>m ()</code> with deep suspicion.</strong> Sometimes these are genuinely necessary, as they may perform an imperative effect with no meaningful result, but if the primary purpose of that effect is raising an error, it’s likely there’s a better way.</p></li><li><p><strong>Don’t be afraid to parse data in multiple passes.</strong> Avoiding shotgun parsing just means you shouldn’t act on the input data before it’s fully parsed, not that you can’t use some of the input data to decide how to parse other input data. Plenty of useful parsers are context-sensitive.</p></li><li><p><strong>Avoid denormalized representations of data, <em>especially</em> if it’s mutable.</strong> Duplicating the same data in multiple places introduces a trivially representable illegal state: the places getting out of sync. Strive for a single source of truth.</p><ul><li><p><strong>Keep denormalized representations of data behind abstraction boundaries.</strong> If denormalization is absolutely necessary, use encapsulation to ensure a small, trusted module holds sole responsibility for keeping the representations in sync.</p></li></ul></li><li><p><strong>Use abstract datatypes to make validators “look like” parsers.</strong> Sometimes, making an illegal state truly unrepresentable is just plain impractical given the tools Haskell provides, such as ensuring an integer is in a particular range. In that case, use an abstract <code>newtype</code> with a smart constructor to “fake” a parser from a validator.</p></li></ul><p>As always, use your best judgement. It probably isn’t worth breaking out <a href="https://hackage.haskell.org/package/singletons">singletons</a> and refactoring your entire application just to get rid of a single <code>error "impossible"</code> call somewhere—just make sure to treat those situations like the radioactive substance they are, and handle them with the appropriate care. If all else fails, at least leave a comment to document the invariant for whoever needs to modify the code next.</p><h2><a name="recap-reflection-and-related-reading"></a>Recap, reflection, and related reading</h2><p>That’s all, really. Hopefully this blog post proves that taking advantage of the Haskell type system doesn’t require a PhD, and it doesn’t even require using the latest and greatest of GHC’s shiny new language extensions—though they can certainly sometimes help! Sometimes the biggest obstacle to using Haskell to its fullest is simply being aware what options are available, and unfortunately, one downside of Haskell’s small community is a relative dearth of resources that document design patterns and techniques that have become tribal knowledge.</p><p>None of the ideas in this blog post are new. In fact, the core idea—“write total functions”—is conceptually quite simple. Despite that, I find it remarkably challenging to communicate actionable, practicable details about the way I write Haskell code. It’s easy to spend lots of time talking about abstract concepts—many of which are quite valuable!—without communicating anything useful about <em>process</em>. My hope is that this is a small step in that direction.</p><p>Sadly, I don’t know very many other resources on this particular topic, but I do know of one: I never hesitate to recommend Matt Parson’s fantastic blog post <a href="https://www.parsonsmatt.org/2017/10/11/type_safety_back_and_forth.html">Type Safety Back and Forth</a>. If you want another accessible perspective on these ideas, including another worked example, I’d highly encourage giving it a read. For a significantly more advanced take on many of these ideas, I can also recommend Matt Noonan’s 2018 paper <a href="https://kataskeue.com/gdp.pdf">Ghosts of Departed Proofs</a>, which outlines a handful of techniques for capturing more complex invariants in the type system than I have described here.</p><p>As a closing note, I want to say that doing the kind of refactoring described in this blog post is not always easy. The examples I’ve given are simple, but real life is often much less straightforward. Even for those experienced in type-driven design, it can be genuinely difficult to capture certain invariants in the type system, so do not consider it a personal failing if you cannot solve something the way you’d like! Consider the principles in this blog post ideals to strive for, not strict requirements to meet. All that matters is to try.</p><ol><li id="footnote-1"><p>Technically, in Haskell, this ignores “bottoms,” constructions that can inhabit <em>any</em> value. These aren’t “real” values (unlike <code>null</code> in some other languages)—they’re things like infinite loops or computations that raise exceptions—and in idiomatic Haskell, we usually try to avoid them, so reasoning that pretends they don’t exist still has value. But don’t take my word for it—I’ll let Danielsson et al. convince you that <a href="https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/jeremy.gibbons/publications/fast+loose.pdf">Fast and Loose Reasoning is Morally Correct</a>. <a href="#footnote-ref-1-1">↩</a></p></li><li id="footnote-2"><p>In fact, <code>Data.List.NonEmpty</code> already provides a <code>head</code> function with this type, but just for the sake of illustration, we’ll reimplement it ourselves. <a href="#footnote-ref-2-1">↩</a></p></li><li id="footnote-3"><p>Sometimes it is necessary to perform some kind of authorization before parsing user input to avoid denial of service attacks, but that’s okay: authorization should have a relatively small surface area, and it shouldn’t cause any significant modifications to the state of your system. <a href="#footnote-ref-3-1">↩</a></p></li></ol></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Oxide raises $200M Series C (563 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://oxide.computer/blog/our-200m-series-c</link>
            <guid>46960036</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 14:20:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://oxide.computer/blog/our-200m-series-c">https://oxide.computer/blog/our-200m-series-c</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46960036">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content"><p>We have raised a $200M Series C, and yes, you are permitted a double take:
didn’t we <em>just</em> raise a
<a href="https://oxide.computer/blog/our-100m-series-b">$100M Series B</a>?
And aren’t we the ones that are especially candid about the
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8ZgfTarNxdY">perils of raising too much money</a>?</p><p>Well, yes, on both fronts, so let us explain a little.</p><p>First, we have the luxury of having achieved real product-market fit:  we are
making <a href="https://oxide.computer/">a product</a> that people want to buy.  This takes
on additional dimensions when making something physical: with complexities like
manufacturing, inventory, cash-conversion, and shifting supply chains,
product-market fit implies getting the unit economics of the business right.
All of this is a long way of saying: we did not (and do not) need to raise
capital to support the business.</p><p>So if we didn’t need to raise, why seek the capital?  Well, we weren’t seeking
it, really.  But our
investors, seeing the business take off, were eager to support it.  And we, in
turn, were eager to have them:  they were the ones, after all, who joined us in
taking a real leap when it felt like there was a lot more risk on the table.
They understood our vision for the company and shared our love for customers
and our desire to build a singular team.  They had been with us in some
difficult moments; they know and trust us, as do we them.  So being able to raise
a Series C purely from our existing investors presented a real opportunity.</p><p>Still, even from investors that we trust and with a quick close, if the business
doesn’t need the money, does it make sense to raise?  We have always believed
that our biggest challenge at Oxide was time — and therefore capital.  We
spelled this out in our initial pitch deck from 2019:</p><div><p><img srcset="https://oxide-computer.imgix.net//img/blog/series-c/oxide-pitch-2019.png?w=700 700w, https://oxide-computer.imgix.net//img/blog/series-c/oxide-pitch-2019.png?w=1400 1400w, https://oxide-computer.imgix.net//img/blog/series-c/oxide-pitch-2019.png?w=2100 2100w" sizes="(min-width: 600px) 700px, 1400px, 2100px" src="https://oxide.computer/img/blog/series-c/oxide-pitch-2019.png" alt="Oxide pitch deck"></p><p>Challenges slide from Oxide original pitch deck ca. 2019</p></div><p>Six years later, we stand by this, which is not to minimize any of those
challenges: the technical challenges were indeed hard; we feel fortunate to have
attracted an extraordinary team; and we certainly caught some
<a href="https://www.networkworld.com/article/4053783/broadcoms-vmware-strategy-pays-off-financially-but-customers-not-as-keen-as-wall-street.html">lucky breaks</a>
with respect to the market.  With this large Series C, we have entirely
de-risked capital going forward, which in turn assures our independence.</p><p>This last bit is really important, because any buyer of infrastructure has
had their heart broken countless times by promising startups that succumbed to
acquisition by one of the established players that they were seeking to
disrupt.  The serial disappointments leave a refreshing bluntness in their
wake, and it’s not uncommon for us to be asked directly: "How do I know you
won’t be bought?"</p><p>Our intent in starting Oxide was not to be an
acquisition target but rather build a generational company; this is our life’s
work, not a means to an end.  With our Series C, customers
don’t have to merely take our word for it:  we have the capital to assure our
survival into the indefinite future.  If our Series B left us with confidence
in achieving <a href="https://rfd.shared.oxide.computer/rfd/0002">our mission</a>, our
Series C leaves us with certainty: we’re going to kick butt, have fun, not
cheat (of course!), love our customers — and <strong>change computing forever</strong>.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Jury told that Meta, Google 'engineered addiction' at landmark US trial (468 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://techxplore.com/news/2026-02-jury-told-meta-google-addiction.html</link>
            <guid>46959832</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 14:02:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://techxplore.com/news/2026-02-jury-told-meta-google-addiction.html">https://techxplore.com/news/2026-02-jury-told-meta-google-addiction.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46959832">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
									    
<div data-thumb="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2026/meta-co-founder-and-ch-2.jpg" data-src="https://scx2.b-cdn.net/gfx/news/2026/meta-co-founder-and-ch-2.jpg" data-sub-html="Meta co-founder and chief executive Mark Zuckerberg is scheduled to testify as the parent company of Facebook and Instagram stands trial in a civil suit accusing the social media giant of putting profit over the mental health of young users.">
        <figure>
            <img src="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/800a/2026/meta-co-founder-and-ch-2.jpg" alt="Meta co-founder and chief executive Mark Zuckerberg is scheduled to testify as the parent company of Facebook and Instagram stands trial in a civil suit accusing the social media giant of putting profit over the mental health of young users" title="Meta co-founder and chief executive Mark Zuckerberg is scheduled to testify as the parent company of Facebook and Instagram stands trial in a civil suit accusing the social media giant of putting profit over the mental health of young users." width="800" height="530">
             <figcaption>
                Meta co-founder and chief executive Mark Zuckerberg is scheduled to testify as the parent company of Facebook and Instagram stands trial in a civil suit accusing the social media giant of putting profit over the mental health of young users.
            </figcaption>        </figure>
    </div><p>Meta and Google-owned YouTube were accused Monday of pushing highly addictive apps on children as a landmark social media trial began in earnest in a California court.</p>

                                        
                                          

                                        
                                                                                                                                                                                <p>The blockbuster trial in front of a Los Angeles jury could establish a legal precedent on whether the social media juggernauts deliberately designed their platforms to lead to addiction in children.</p>
<p>The proceedings are expected to see Meta chief Mark Zuckerberg on the stand next week and Instagram boss Adam Mosseri in the courtroom as early as Wednesday. In addition to Instagram, Meta's platforms include Facebook and WhatsApp.</p>
<p>"This case is about two of the richest corporations in history who have engineered addiction in children's brains," plaintiffs' attorney Mark Lanier told the jury in his opening statement.</p>
<p>"This case is as easy as A-B-C," Lanier said as he stacked children's toy blocks bearing the letters.</p>
<p>He contended the A was for addicting, the B for brains and the C for children.</p>

<div data-thumb="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2026/parents-mariano-janin-1.jpg" data-src="https://scx2.b-cdn.net/gfx/news/2026/parents-mariano-janin-1.jpg" data-sub-html="Parents Mariano Janin and George Nicolaou hold photos of their children outside the Los Angeles County Superior Court in Los Angeles.">
        <figure>
            <img src="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/800a/2026/parents-mariano-janin-1.jpg" alt="Parents Mariano Janin and George Nicolaou hold photos of their children outside the Los Angeles County Superior Court in Los Angeles" title="Parents Mariano Janin and George Nicolaou hold photos of their children outside the Los Angeles County Superior Court in Los Angeles.">
             <figcaption>
                Parents Mariano Janin and George Nicolaou hold photos of their children outside the Los Angeles County Superior Court in Los Angeles.
            </figcaption>        </figure>
    </div>
<p>"They don't only build apps; they build traps," Lanier said, saying Meta and YouTube pursued "<a href="https://techxplore.com/news/2023-10-meta-struggle-defend-state-lawsuits.html?utm_source=embeddings&amp;utm_medium=related&amp;utm_campaign=internal" rel="related">addiction by design</a>," making his arguments using props like a toy Ferrari and a mini slot machine.</p>
<p>Meta attorney Paul Schmidt countered in opening remarks to the jury that evidence will show problems with the plaintiff's family and real-world bullying took a toll on her self-esteem, body image and happiness rather than Instagram.</p>
<p>"If you took Instagram away and everything else was the same in Kaley's life, would her life be completely different, or would she still be struggling with the same things she is today?" Schmidt asked, pointing out an Instagram addiction is never mentioned in medical records included in the evidence.</p>

                                                                                                    
													                                                            
                                                                                                                                            <p>The trial before Judge Carolyn Kuhl focuses on allegations that a 20-year-old woman identified as Kaley G.M. suffered severe mental harm because she became addicted to social media as a child.</p>
<p>The case is being treated as a bellwether proceeding because its outcome could set the tone, and the level of payouts to successful plaintiffs, for a tidal wave of similar litigation across the United States.</p>
<p>Social media firms are accused in hundreds of lawsuits of leading young users to become addicted to content and suffer from <a href="https://phys.org/news/2024-11-reliable-evidence-social-media-young.html?utm_source=embeddings&amp;utm_medium=related&amp;utm_campaign=internal" rel="related" target="_blank">depression</a>, eating disorders, psychiatric hospitalization and even suicide.</p>
<p>Lawyers for the plaintiffs are borrowing strategies used in the 1990s and 2000s against the tobacco industry, which faced a similar onslaught of lawsuits arguing that companies knowingly sold a harmful product.</p>
<p>Lanier told the jurors that Kaley began watching YouTube at six years old because the company never told her mother "the goal was viewer addiction," or that toddlers as young as two were being targeted despite "critical" risk of addiction.</p>
<p>"This is the first time that a social media company has ever had to face a jury for harming kids," Social Media Victims Law Center founder Matthew Bergman, whose team is involved in more than 1,000 such cases, told AFP.</p>

                                                                                                                                            <h2>"Strongly disagree"</h2>
<p>Internet titans have argued that they are shielded by <a href="https://techxplore.com/news/2022-10-supreme-court-cases-tech-firm.html?utm_source=embeddings&amp;utm_medium=related&amp;utm_campaign=internal" rel="related">Section 230</a> of the US Communications Decency Act, which frees them from responsibility for what social media users post.</p>
<p>However, this case argues that those firms are culpable for business models designed to hold people's attention and to promote content that can harm their mental health.</p>
<p>The plaintiffs said they would call expert witnesses that will argue that <a href="https://techxplore.com/news/2026-01-social-media-giants-landmark-trial.html?utm_source=embeddings&amp;utm_medium=related&amp;utm_campaign=internal" rel="related">young people's brains</a> are not yet developed to withstand the powers of the algorithms being flung at them on Instagram and YouTube.</p>
<p>The company pointed to recent efforts to provide more safeguards for young people, adding that "we're always working to do better."</p>
<p>Jose Castaneda, a YouTube spokesperson, said "the allegations in these complaints are simply not true."</p>
<p>Lawyers for YouTube are to present opening remarks to the jury on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Snapchat and TikTok were named as defendants in the suit, but struck settlement deals before the start of the trial. The terms were not disclosed.</p>
<p>Lawsuits, including some brought by school districts, accusing social media platforms of practices endangering young users are making their way through federal court in northern California and state courts across the country.</p>
<p>A separate lawsuit accusing Meta of putting profit over the well-being of young users was also getting underway in New Mexico on Monday.</p>

                                                                                                                                    
                                                                                
                                        											
										                                                                                    <p>
                                                © 2026 AFP
                                            </p>
                                                                                
                                        <!-- print only -->
                                        <div>
                                            <p><strong>Citation</strong>:
                                                Jury told that Meta, Google 'engineered addiction' at landmark US trial (2026, February 10)
                                                retrieved 10 February 2026
                                                from https://techxplore.com/news/2026-02-jury-told-meta-google-addiction.html
                                            </p>
                                            <p>
                                            This document is subject to copyright. Apart from any fair dealing for the purpose of private study or research, no
                                            part may be reproduced without the written permission. The content is provided for information purposes only.
                                            </p>
                                        </div>
                                        
									</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Simplifying Vulkan One Subsystem at a Time (239 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.khronos.org/blog/simplifying-vulkan-one-subsystem-at-a-time</link>
            <guid>46959418</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 13:26:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.khronos.org/blog/simplifying-vulkan-one-subsystem-at-a-time">https://www.khronos.org/blog/simplifying-vulkan-one-subsystem-at-a-time</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46959418">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="description">
    <p>When those of us in the Vulkan® working group want to modify the API—whether it’s a new hardware feature to expose, a new use case we want to address, or even just a gap in the spec we want to address—we have one invaluable tool that we make heavy use of: extensions!</p>
<p>Extensions are a wonderful way for us to get improvements to the Vulkan API out to developers without waiting for a new core version. They let vendors expose novel functionality and enable us to gather community feedback on new features before we firm them up into a core specification.</p>
<p>Amazing! So we get new functionality out to developers quickly—what’s not to love!? Well…</p>
<h2>The Extension Explosion Problem 💥</h2>
<p>Having access to this much extensibility comes at a cost. As we add more extensions to the API, we sometimes inadvertently obscure the simplest way to use it. What functionality can you rely on always being there? How many ways are there to do what you want to do? Which of those ways will give the best performance? How many paths through the API can you reasonably support in one application?</p>
<p>We sometimes <em>lovingly</em> refer to this as the “extension explosion problem” due to the <a href="https://docs.vulkan.org/spec/latest/appendices/extensions.html#_list_of_current_extensions">number of extensions we have now</a>—and <a href="https://registry.khronos.org/OpenGL/index_gl.php">how many existed in OpenGL</a>/<a href="https://registry.khronos.org/OpenGL/index_es.php">ES</a>™ beforehand. The more we add, the more they chain off of and interact with each other, adding combinatorically to the decision space for developers.</p>
<p>This is a persistent challenge that we’ve heard loud and clear from Vulkan’s developer base, but until now we haven’t had a good solution.</p>
<p>When we produced Vulkan 1.0, it gave us a clean slate moving from OpenGL® , but now 10 years into Vulkan we are facing the same problem again. So, what’s the answer? Should we rebuild the entire API from scratch every few years?</p>
<p>No—believe it or not, <strong>we add more extensions</strong>!</p>
<p>…🤨?</p>
<h2>Subsystem Replacement</h2>
<p>Counterintuitive as it may seem, adding more extensions is one way we can improve the situation. However, this <strong>cannot</strong> just be business as usual. We <strong>have</strong> to take a different approach.</p>
<p>Rather than incrementally adding or changing the API and increasing complexity, we want to revise whole API subsystems, producing whole-cloth replacements that let you ignore whatever came before, with supporting tooling and industry backing to make sure the new approach ships everywhere.</p>
<p><a href="https://docs.vulkan.org/refpages/latest/refpages/source/VK_EXT_descriptor_heap.html">VK_EXT_descriptor_heap</a> is the first concrete attempt at this approach, <strong>totally replacing</strong> the existing descriptor set subsystem in Vulkan. Members of the Vulkan working group have poured everything into this, and it’s had the kind of attention we’ve only historically seen with major API revisions (e.g. Vulkan 1.0). While it’s shipping as an EXT for now, it’s very much on a path to becoming future core functionality.</p>
<p>We previously attempted to fix up the descriptor model with <a href="https://docs.vulkan.org/features/latest/features/proposals/VK_EXT_descriptor_buffer.html">VK_EXT_descriptor_buffer</a>, which developers have had some success with, but we used incremental (if large!) improvements to the existing descriptor set functionality, making it necessary to check for a variety of descriptor set extensions. This incremental approach also didn’t attract wide industry backing, resulting in cross-vendor portability issues. We knew we had the core of something important, but it needed a rethink to make it stick. So we took the lessons learned from VK_EXT_descriptor_buffer, and designed a completely new subsystem.</p>
<p>The new VK_EXT_descriptor_heap extension does not interact with the previous descriptor set API, including layouts, push descriptors, or descriptor buffers in <em>any way</em>—<a href="https://docs.vulkan.org/spec/latest/appendices/legacy.html#legacy-descriptor-sets">it fully replaces it all</a>. Instead of just trying to tidy up the API a little, this extension fundamentally changes how Vulkan applications interact with descriptors. Descriptors are no longer some opaque thing that you manage through a series of awkward API commands and restrictive shader bindings. Descriptor heaps are just memory, descriptors are just data, and you can do <em>more or less</em> whatever you want with them. There are <em>some</em> restrictions, but it’s a lot closer to what you might expect on a console than in a portable API.</p>
<p>This extension has also had contributions from a huge swathe of the industry, much more than our typical extensions. Feel free to look at the <a href="https://docs.vulkan.org/refpages/latest/refpages/source/VK_EXT_descriptor_heap.html#_other_extension_metadata">contributor list</a>—it’s <strong>extensive</strong>. This extension has had meaningful input from virtually everyone in the Vulkan Working Group. Together we’ve spent the better part of the past three years iterating on and refining this, ensuring it not only works but works <strong>well</strong>.</p>
<h2>If this has so much buy-in, why isn’t it a KHR?</h2>
<p><strong>We want to make sure we have buy-in from you, too.</strong></p>
<p>With something this big, we want to make sure we get it right. We’re confident that what we’ve built is already a huge improvement and an excellent feature, but by releasing it as an EXT, we’re giving the wider community a chance to try it out, figure out its intricacies, and perhaps suggest ways it can be even better.</p>
<p>The EXT is not going to change, so you can use it in shipping apps today; when we do eventually ship a KHR version, we’re aiming for the transition to be as straightforward as possible if you choose to use it.</p>
<p>If you do find anything in the new extension that you think could be simpler or improved, we will consider any feedback as we finalize the KHR specification. By doing so, we will work to get everything as polished as possible and avoid additional extensions to fix things later.</p>
<p>While we can’t make any guarantees about when the eventual KHR will materialize, getting feedback within the next 9 months will give us the best opportunity to incorporate your input.</p>
<p>Please <strong>use this extension and</strong> <a href="https://github.com/KhronosGroup/Vulkan-Docs/"><strong>let us know how it goes</strong></a>!</p>
<h2>Cool. You did something about descriptors. What about &lt;insert feature&gt;?</h2>
<p>Developer needs are at the center of our roadmap planning, and we're committed to addressing the requests we've been hearing. <strong>There’s a very good chance <a href="https://youtu.be/-OQsVwOJjQ4?t=1360">we’re already working on the thing you are after</a></strong>.</p>
<p>If we don’t have your problem logged somewhere, or if you think it’s not getting enough attention, we encourage you to <a href="https://discord.com/invite/vulkan">jump on our Discord</a> or <a href="https://github.com/KhronosGroup/Vulkan-Docs/">file an issue on GitHub</a> to let us know about it!</p>
<p>In order to replace subsystems like this, we have a lot of considerations to balance - developer needs, ecosystem needs, vendor roadmaps, future direction, and upcoming hardware and software releases, among other things. Taking care of all of those needs takes care to try and get it right the first time. That doesn’t mean any of this needs to be slow though! We are actively working on how to use this methodology to upgrade key parts of the Vulkan API, with strong industry buy-in.</p>
<p>One of our top priorities right now is to make the Vulkan API a joy to use. We know we still have a long way to go, but we hope that well-considered subsystem replacements like this are a major positive step in that direction. Please do let us know what you think of this approach—we’d love to hear from you!</p>

    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Europe's $24T Breakup with Visa and Mastercard Has Begun (819 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://europeanbusinessmagazine.com/business/europes-24-trillion-breakup-with-visa-and-mastercard-has-begun/</link>
            <guid>46958399</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 11:42:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://europeanbusinessmagazine.com/business/europes-24-trillion-breakup-with-visa-and-mastercard-has-begun/">https://europeanbusinessmagazine.com/business/europes-24-trillion-breakup-with-visa-and-mastercard-has-begun/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46958399">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <p><em>ECB President Christine Lagarde has called for Europe to break its dependence on American payment infrastructure, warning that every card transaction sends European consumer data to the United States. A coalition of 16 banks thinks it has the answer.</em></p>
<p><strong>QUICK ANSWER</strong></p>
<p><strong>What’s happening?</strong> ECB President Christine Lagarde told Irish radio that Europe needs its own digital payment system “urgently,” warning that virtually all European card and mobile payments currently run through <a href="https://davekeating.substack.com/p/can-europe-free-itself-from-visamastercard" target="_blank" rel="noopener">non-European infrastructure controlled by Visa, Mastercard, PayPal or Alipay</a>. Days later, on 2 February, the European Payments Initiative (EPI) and the <a href="https://news.europawire.eu/european-payment-leaders-sign-mou-to-create-a-sovereign-pan-european-interoperable-payments-network/eu-press-release/2026/02/02/15/34/11/168858/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">EuroPA Alliance signed a landmark agreement</a> to build a pan-European interoperable payment network covering 130 million users across 13 countries. The system, built around the digital wallet Wero, aims to let Europeans pay and transfer money across borders without touching a single American network.</p><div>
  <h3>Join The European Business Briefing</h3>
  <p>The daily email on markets, technology, power and money across Europe. Join 10,000+ founders, investors and executives who read EBM every morning.</p>
  <p><a href="https://mailchi.mp/europeanbusinessmagazine/european-business-briefing" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Subscribe</a>
</p></div>
<hr>
<h2>The Problem No One Thinks About</h2>
<p>Every time a European taps a card, pays online or splits a bill with friends, the transaction flows through infrastructure owned and operated by American companies. Visa and Mastercard together <a href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/europe-banks-launching-product-break-101215642.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">process approximately $24 trillion in transactions annually</a>. Card payments account for 56% of all cashless transactions in the EU. And the data — who bought what, where, when and for how much — leaves European jurisdiction every time.</p>
<p>“It’s important for us to have digital payment under our control,” Lagarde <a href="https://davekeating.substack.com/p/can-europe-free-itself-from-visamastercard" target="_blank" rel="noopener">told The Pat Kenny Show</a>. “Whether you use a card or whether you use a phone, typically it goes through Visa, Mastercard, PayPal, Alipay. Where are all those coming from? Well, either the US or China.”</p>
<p>The host’s response — “I didn’t realise this” — captured the broader European blind spot. Most consumers have no idea that their payment data routinely exits the EU. In a <a href="https://europeanbusinessmagazine.com/business/european-stocks-at-a-tipping-point-why-2026-could-decide-the-continents-economic-future/">geopolitical environment</a> where Europe is scrambling to reduce dependence on the United States across defence, energy and trade, payments remain an overlooked vulnerability.</p>
<p>The lesson of Russia sharpened the urgency. When Western sanctions cut Russia off from Visa and Mastercard in 2022, the country’s domestic payments were immediately disrupted. European policymakers asked the obvious question: what would happen if the US decided — or was pressured — to restrict European access to those same networks?</p>
<h2>Enter Wero</h2>
<p>The European Payments Initiative, a consortium of 16 major banks and payment processors including <a href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/europe-banks-launching-product-break-101215642.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">BNP Paribas, Deutsche Bank and Worldline</a>, launched Wero in July 2024 as Europe’s answer. Built on SEPA instant credit transfers, Wero lets users send money using just a phone number — no IBAN, no card, no intermediary.</p>
<p>The numbers so far are encouraging. <a href="https://empsa.org/news/bancomat-bizum-epi-sibs-and-vipps-mobilepay-sign-mou-to-accelerate-the-rollout-of-sovereign-pan-european-payment-solutions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wero already has over 47 million registered users</a> in Belgium, France and Germany, has processed over €7.5 billion in transfers, and counts more than 1,100 member institutions. Retail payments went live in Germany at the end of 2025, with merchants including Lidl, Decathlon, Rossmann and Air Europa already accepting Wero online. France and Belgium follow in 2026.</p>
<p>But the real breakthrough came on 2 February, when EPI signed a memorandum of understanding with the <a href="https://empsa.org/news/bancomat-bizum-epi-sibs-and-vipps-mobilepay-sign-mou-to-accelerate-the-rollout-of-sovereign-pan-european-payment-solutions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">EuroPA Alliance</a> — a coalition of national payment systems including Italy’s Bancomat, Spain’s Bizum, Portugal’s MB WAY and the Nordics’ Vipps MobilePay. The deal instantly connects approximately 130 million users across 13 countries, covering roughly 72% of the EU and Norway population. Cross-border peer-to-peer payments launch this year, with e-commerce and point-of-sale payments following in 2027.</p>
<p>“European payment sovereignty is not a vision, but a reality in the making,” said Martina Weimert, CEO of EPI.</p>
<h2>Why Previous Attempts Failed</h2>
<p>Europe has tried this before. The Monnet Project, launched in 2008 by twenty European banks, collapsed in 2012. The original EPI vision itself was scaled back after several founding members withdrew, forcing a pivot from a full card-replacement scheme to a narrower account-to-account model.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://thepaypers.com/payments/expert-views/breaking-the-visa-and-mastercard-duopoly-europes-path-to-innovation" target="_blank" rel="noopener">core problem has always been fragmentation</a>. Each EU country developed its own domestic payment solution — Bizum in Spain, iDEAL in the Netherlands, Payconiq in Belgium, Girocard in Germany — but none could work across borders. A Belgian consumer buying from a Dutch retailer still needed Visa or Mastercard. National pride and competing banking interests repeatedly sabotaged attempts at unification.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://europeanbusinessmagazine.com/business/10-cultural-differences-between-asia-and-europe/">network effect</a> compounds the challenge. Merchants accept Visa and Mastercard because consumers carry them. Consumers carry them because merchants accept them. Breaking that loop requires either regulatory force or a critical mass of users large enough to make merchants care — which is precisely what the EuroPA deal attempts to deliver by connecting existing national user bases rather than building from scratch.</p>
<h2>The Digital Euro Question</h2>
<p>Running in parallel is the ECB’s digital euro project, which would create a central bank-backed digital currency usable across the eurozone. EU finance ministers have <a href="https://moderndiplomacy.eu/2025/09/19/eu-aims-to-rival-visa-mastercard-with-digital-euro/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">accelerated discussions</a> on the initiative, though the European Parliament has not yet passed the required legislation. Once approved, the ECB estimates it would need a further two to three years to launch.</p>
<p>EPI is careful to distinguish Wero from the digital euro. Wero is a private-sector initiative; the digital euro is public money. They are designed to complement rather than compete — though the overlap in ambition is obvious. Both exist because Europe’s political establishment has finally accepted that payments sovereignty is as strategically important as energy independence or <a href="https://europeanbusinessmagazine.com/business/why-is-europes-ipo-market-surging-in-2026-record-start-sparks-revival-hope/">defence autonomy</a>.</p>
<h2>Can It Actually Work?</h2>
<p>Sceptics have good reasons for doubt. Creating a viable alternative to Visa and Mastercard requires “several billion euros” in investment, according to EPI’s own estimates. Low interchange fees under EU regulation make profitability difficult. Consumer habits are deeply entrenched — and neither Visa nor Mastercard will sit idle while Europe tries to dismantle their most profitable market.</p>
<p>Weimert herself concedes that calling Wero a “challenger” may be premature, <a href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/europe-banks-launching-product-break-101215642.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">describing it as functioning like a startup</a> — albeit one with €500 million in backing and 47 million users already on board.</p>
<p>But the political tailwinds are stronger than they have ever been. The EU’s instant payments regulation, the Capital Markets Union push, the <a href="https://europeanbusinessmagazine.com/business/indias-mother-of-all-deals-the-winners-the-losers-and-the-33-trillion-bet/">broader drive for European strategic autonomy</a> in a world of tariff wars and great power rivalry — all point in the same direction. The question is no longer whether Europe wants its own payment infrastructure. It is whether it can execute fast enough to matter.</p>
<p>As Lagarde put it: “We have the assets and opportunities to do that ourselves. And if we were to remove the internal barriers that we have set for ourselves in Europe, our economic wealth would increase significantly.”</p>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Feynman Lectures on Physics (1961-1964) (239 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.feynmanlectures.caltech.edu/</link>
            <guid>46958345</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 11:36:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.feynmanlectures.caltech.edu/">https://www.feynmanlectures.caltech.edu/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46958345">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.feynmanlectures.caltech.edu/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Clean-room implementation of Half-Life 2 on the Quake 1 engine (326 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://code.idtech.space/fn/hl2</link>
            <guid>46958231</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 11:21:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://code.idtech.space/fn/hl2">https://code.idtech.space/fn/hl2</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46958231">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="readme">
			
				<h2 id="user-content-img-rt2-png-rad-therapy-ii" dir="auto"><a href="https://code.idtech.space/fn/hl2/media/branch/current/img/rt2.png" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener"><img src="https://code.idtech.space/fn/hl2/media/branch/current/img/rt2.png" alt=""></a> Rad-Therapy II</h2>
<p dir="auto">The original port of <strong>Half-Life 2</strong> (2004) to Quake(World).</p>
<p dir="auto">The game is <strong>not</strong> playable from start to finish. <em>You can play deathmatch and other odd modes.</em></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://code.idtech.space/fn/hl2/media/branch/current/img/preview1.jpg" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener"><img src="https://code.idtech.space/fn/hl2/media/branch/current/img/preview1.jpg" alt="Preview 1"></a>
<a href="https://code.idtech.space/fn/hl2/media/branch/current/img/preview2.jpg" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener"><img src="https://code.idtech.space/fn/hl2/media/branch/current/img/preview2.jpg" alt="Preview 2"></a>
<a href="https://code.idtech.space/fn/hl2/media/branch/current/img/preview3.jpg" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener"><img src="https://code.idtech.space/fn/hl2/media/branch/current/img/preview3.jpg" alt="Preview 3"></a>
<a href="https://code.idtech.space/fn/hl2/media/branch/current/img/preview4.jpg" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener"><img src="https://code.idtech.space/fn/hl2/media/branch/current/img/preview4.jpg" alt="Preview 4"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Requires both <code>hl2</code> and <code>hl2dm</code> directories in order to function. Any copy will do fine. If you're on a case-insensitive filesystem and you're running pre .vpk data files you might want to put them in a .zip and name it 'pak0.pk3'. It's generally easier to just use the latest data from Steam.</p>
<h2 id="user-content-playing-installing" dir="auto">Playing/Installing</h2>
<p dir="auto">Run <a href="https://www.fteqw.org/" rel="nofollow">FTE</a> like so:</p>
<p dir="auto"><code>fteqw.exe -halflife2</code></p>
<p dir="auto">It will then automatically attempt to install <strong>Rad-Therapy II</strong> - when run from within your <strong>Half-Life 2: Deathmatch</strong> directory.</p>
<h2 id="user-content-building" dir="auto">Building</h2>
<p dir="auto">Git clone <a href="https://code.idtech.space/vera/nuclide" rel="nofollow">Nuclide</a> first, run <code>make update</code> and <code>make fteqcc</code>, then clone the repository inside the Nuclide-SDK:</p>
<pre><code>git clone https://code.idtech.space/fn/hl2 hl2
make game GAME=hl2
make plugins GAME=hl2
</code></pre><p dir="auto">The last command will build the plugins required for the engine to load the data files. The one before it will build the game-logic.
Make sure that Nuclide-SDK has <code>fteqcc</code> and <code>fteqw</code> present for building and running, respectively.
It will also respect versions installed by the package manager, just make sure it's up to date.</p>
<h2 id="user-content-community" dir="auto">Community</h2>
<h3 id="user-content-matrix" dir="auto">Matrix</h3>
<p dir="auto">If you're a fellow Matrix user, join the Nuclide Space. Where you can ask questions, or prod devs about what they're up to.
<a href="https://matrix.to/#/%23nuclide:matrix.org" rel="nofollow">https://matrix.to/#/#nuclide:matrix.org</a></p>
<h3 id="user-content-irc" dir="auto">IRC</h3>
<p dir="auto">You can also join us on #nuclide via irc.libera.chat.
It's bridged with the main room of the Matrix space.</p>
<h2 id="user-content-license" dir="auto">License</h2>
<p dir="auto">ISC License</p>
<p dir="auto">Copyright (c) 2019-2025 Marco "eukara" Cawthorne <a href="mailto:marco@icculus.org" rel="nofollow">marco@icculus.org</a></p>
<p dir="auto">Permission to use, copy, modify, and distribute this software for any
purpose with or without fee is hereby granted, provided that the above
copyright notice and this permission notice appear in all copies.</p>
<p dir="auto">THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS" AND THE AUTHOR DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES
WITH REGARD TO THIS SOFTWARE INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHOR BE LIABLE FOR
ANY SPECIAL, DIRECT, INDIRECT, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF MIND, USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER
IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION, ARISING
OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF THIS SOFTWARE.</p>
<h2 id="user-content-content-copyright-notice" dir="auto">Content Copyright Notice</h2>
<p dir="auto">Half-Life 2 and Half-Life 2: Deathmatch belong to Valve Corporation.
Original licensed assets from Steam or a disc are required in order to experience <strong>Rad-Therapy II</strong>.</p>

			
		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Qwen-Image-2.0: Professional infographics, exquisite photorealism (373 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://qwen.ai/blog?id=qwen-image-2.0</link>
            <guid>46957198</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 09:19:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://qwen.ai/blog?id=qwen-image-2.0">https://qwen.ai/blog?id=qwen-image-2.0</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46957198">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>