<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Aug 2023 01:00:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[90% of “eco-friendly” paper straws contain traces of toxic forever chemicals (245 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://scienceswitch.com/2023/08/27/90-of-eco-friendly-paper-straws-contain-traces-of-toxic-forever-chemicals/</link>
            <guid>37275856</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 19:03:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://scienceswitch.com/2023/08/27/90-of-eco-friendly-paper-straws-contain-traces-of-toxic-forever-chemicals/">https://scienceswitch.com/2023/08/27/90-of-eco-friendly-paper-straws-contain-traces-of-toxic-forever-chemicals/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37275856">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

							<p>The growing movement against single-use plastics has led many bars and restaurants to swap plastic straws for paper ones. On the surface, this seems like an easy win – we get to sip our drinks through an eco-friendly alternative while keeping tons of plastic out of landfills and oceans. But the truth about paper straws is more complicated.</p>
<p>A <a href="https://www.scimex.org/newsfeed/paper-straws-contain-forever-chemicals-which-mean-they-might-not-be-better-than-plastic-ones">study conducted</a> at the University of Antwerp found that a shocking 90% of so-called eco-friendly paper straws actually contain traces of “forever chemicals.” Forever chemicals, more formally known as <a href="https://chemtrust.org/pfas/">per-and polyfluoroalkyl substances</a>&nbsp;(PFAS), are compounds that don’t break down once released into the environment or our bodies. They stick around virtually forever, which is how they got their ominous nickname.</p>
<p>PFAS have been linked to concerning health effects including high cholesterol, reduced immune response, thyroid disease, and increased risk of certain cancers. So why are they turning up in paper straws? The researchers tested 39 different brands of straws made from various materials like paper, bamboo, glass, stainless steel, and plastic. PFAS were detected in the majority – 69% overall.</p>
<p>But paper straws were by far the worst offenders, with PFAS identified in a whopping 90% of brands tested. The concentrations varied quite a bit, but the frequent presence of the chemicals suggests they were likely intentionally added in some cases. PFAS are sometimes used as a <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2022/jan/26/water-resistant-products-toxic-pfas-study">water-resistant coating</a> – not something you want leaching into your daily iced tea.</p>
<p>Among the PFAS found in paper straws was <a href="https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/compound/Perfluorooctanoic-acid">perfluorooctanoic acid</a> (PFOA), which has actually been <a href="https://chemicalwatch.com/189390/global-ban-on-pfoa-enters-into-force-for-most-countries">globally banned since 2020</a> due to health risks including cancer and organ damage. Also frequently detected were other concerning PFAS chemicals <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trifluoroacetic_acid">trifluoroacetic acid</a>&nbsp;(TFA) and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triflic_acid">trifluoromethanesulfonic acid</a> (TFMS). While bamboo straws fared slightly better than paper ones, <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0045653521007074?via%3Dihub">PFAS was still found in 80%</a> of the bamboo brands tested. Plastic and glass straws also occasionally contained PFAS, though less commonly than plant-based options.</p>
<p>The one material that seems safest is stainless steel – the researchers did not detect any PFAS compounds in the steel straws analyzed. While the PFAS levels measured in this study were fairly low, these chemicals have the ominous ability to accumulate in the human body and the environment over time. The findings raise the question – if paper straws leach PFAS into our drinks over months and years of use, could they be harming our health?</p>
<p>Unfortunately the current research didn’t examine whether the chemicals transfer into liquids. But previous studies have shown PFAS can migrate from food packaging materials into actual food and drinks. More research is critically needed to determine if PFAS leach out of paper straws during typical use.</p>
<p>In the meantime, it’s clear we need to rethink the assumption that paper and other plant-based products are inherently better for health and sustainability compared to plastic. The revelation about paper straws casts doubt on the idea that swapping plastic for paper is a foolproof eco-friendly solution. After all, PFAS spreading from straws into waterways and landfills still contribute to environmental contamination – regardless of that paper label.</p>
<p>The study was published in the journal&nbsp;<i><a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/19440049.2023.2240908" rel="noopener">Food Additives and Contaminants</a></i>.</p>
			
			
			
							
						</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A video of the transformation of a single cell into a salamander (142 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://pmdvod.nationalgeographic.com/NG_Video/772/995/1442844739770_1550184269599_1442865731523_mp4_video_1024x576_1632000_primary_audio_eng_3.mp4</link>
            <guid>37275401</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 18:17:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://pmdvod.nationalgeographic.com/NG_Video/772/995/1442844739770_1550184269599_1442865731523_mp4_video_1024x576_1632000_primary_audio_eng_3.mp4">https://pmdvod.nationalgeographic.com/NG_Video/772/995/1442844739770_1550184269599_1442865731523_mp4_video_1024x576_1632000_primary_audio_eng_3.mp4</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37275401">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Slack’s Migration to a Cellular Architecture (234 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://slack.engineering/slacks-migration-to-a-cellular-architecture/</link>
            <guid>37274871</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 17:27:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://slack.engineering/slacks-migration-to-a-cellular-architecture/">https://slack.engineering/slacks-migration-to-a-cellular-architecture/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37274871">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content-area">
		<main id="primary">
			<article id="post-16208">
				<!-- .entry__header -->

									<div>
						<h2>Summary</h2>
<p><span>In recent years, </span><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/solutions/guidance/cell-based-architecture-on-aws/"><span>cellular architectures</span></a><span> have become increasingly popular for large online services as a way to increase redundancy and limit the blast radius of site failures. In pursuit of these goals, we have migrated the most critical user-facing services at Slack from a monolithic to a cell-based architecture over the last 1.5 years. In this series of blog posts, we’ll discuss our reasons for embarking on this massive migration, illustrate the design of our cellular topology along with the engineering trade-offs we made along the way, and talk about our strategies for successfully shipping deep changes across many connected services.</span></p>
<h2><b>Background: the incident</b></h2>
<figure id="attachment_16211" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-16211"><img decoding="async" src="https://slack.engineering/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2023/08/image1.jpg?w=640" alt="Graph of TCP retransmits by AZ, with one AZ worse than the others" width="640" height="188" srcset="https://slack.engineering/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2023/08/image1.jpg 1600w, https://slack.engineering/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2023/08/image1.jpg?resize=640,188 640w, https://slack.engineering/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2023/08/image1.jpg?resize=768,226 768w, https://slack.engineering/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2023/08/image1.jpg?resize=1280,376 1280w, https://slack.engineering/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2023/08/image1.jpg?resize=1536,451 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 479px) 90vw, (max-width: 599px) 432px, 536px"><figcaption id="caption-attachment-16211">TCP retransmits by AZ, 2021-06-30 outage</figcaption></figure>
<p><span>At Slack, we conduct an incident review after each notable service outage. Below is an excerpt from our internal report summarizing one such incident and our findings:&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><i><span>At 11:45am PDT on 2021-06-30, our cloud provider experienced a network disruption in one of several availability zones in our U.S. East Coast region, where the majority of Slack is hosted. A network link that connects one availability zone with several other availability zones containing Slack servers experienced intermittent faults, causing slowness and degraded connections between Slack servers and degrading service for Slack customers.</span></i></p>
<p><i><span>At 12:33pm PDT on 2021-06-30, the network link was automatically removed from service by our cloud provider, restoring full service to Slack customers. After a series of automated checks by our cloud provider, the network link entered service again.</span></i></p>
<p><i><span>At 5:22pm PDT on 2021-06-30, the same network link experienced the same intermittent faults. At 5:31pm PDT on 2021-06-30, the cloud provider permanently removed the network link from service, restoring full service to our customers.</span></i></p>
<p><span>At first glance, this appears to be pretty unremarkable; a piece of physical hardware upon which we were reliant failed, so we served some errors until it was removed from service. However, as we went through the reflective process of incident review, we were led to wonder why, in fact, this outage was visible to our users </span><i><span>at all</span></i><span>.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>Slack operates a global, multi-regional edge network, but most of our core computational infrastructure resides in multiple Availability Zones within a single region, us-east-1. Availability Zones (AZs) are isolated datacenters within a single region; in addition to the physical isolation they offer, components of cloud services upon which we rely (virtualization, storage, networking, etc.) are blast-radius limited such that they should not fail simultaneously across multiple AZs. This enables builders of services hosted in the cloud (such as Slack) to architect services in such a way that the availability of the entire service in a region is greater than the availability of any one underlying AZ. So to restate the question above — why didn’t this strategy work out for us on June 30? Why did one failed AZ result in user-visible errors?</span></p>
<p><span>As it turns out, detecting failure in distributed systems is a hard problem. A single Slack API request from a user (for example, loading messages in a channel) may fan out into hundreds of RPCs to service backends, each of which must complete to return a correct response to the user. Our service frontends are continuously attempting to detect and exclude failed backends, but we’ve got to record some failures before we can exclude a failed server! To make things even harder, some of our key datastores (including </span><a href="https://slack.engineering/scaling-datastores-at-slack-with-vitess/"><span>our main datastore Vitess</span></a><span>) offer strongly consistent semantics. This is enormously useful to us as application developers but also requires that there be a single backend available for any given write. If a shard primary is unavailable to an application frontend, writes to that shard will fail until the primary returns or a secondary is promoted to take its place.</span></p>
<p><span>We might class the outage above as a </span><a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/paper-1.pdf"><i><span>gray failure</span></i></a><span>. In a gray failure, different components have different views of the availability of the system. In our incident, systems within the impacted AZ saw complete availability of backends within their AZ, but backends outside the AZ were unavailable, and vice versa systems in unimpacted AZs saw the impacted AZ as unavailable. Even clients within the same AZ would have different views of backends in the impacted AZ, depending on whether their network flows happened to traverse the failed equipment. Informally, it seems that this is quite a lot of complexity to ask a distributed system to deal with along the way to doing its real job of serving messages and cat GIFs to our customers.</span></p>
<p><span>Rather than try to solve automatic remediation of gray failures, our solution to this conundrum was to make the computers’ job easier by tapping the power of human judgment. During the outage, it was quite clear to engineers responding that the impact was largely due to one AZ being unreachable — nearly every graph we had aggregated by target AZ looked similar to the retransmits graph above. If we had a button that told all our systems “This AZ is bad; avoid it.” we would absolutely have smashed it! So we set out to build a button that would drain traffic from an AZ.</span></p>
<h2><b>Our solution: AZs are cells, and cells may be drained</b></h2>
<p><span>Like a lot of satisfying infrastructure work, an AZ drain button is conceptually simple yet complicated in practice. The design goals we chose are:</span></p>
<ol>
<li><span>Remove as much traffic as possible from an AZ within 5 minutes. Slack’s </span><a href="https://slack.com/terms/service-level-agreement"><span>99.99% availability SLA</span></a><span>&nbsp;allows us less than 1 hour per year of total unavailability, and so to support it effectively we need tools that work quickly.</span></li>
<li><span>Drains must not result in user-visible errors. An important quality of draining is that it is a </span><a href="https://www.oreilly.com/content/generic-mitigations/"><span>generic mitigation</span></a><span>: as long as a failure is contained within a single AZ, a drain may be effectively used to mitigate even if the root cause is not yet understood. This lends itself to an experimental approach wherein, during in an incident, an operator may try draining an AZ to see if it enables recovery, then undrain if it does not. If draining results in additional errors this approach is not useful.</span></li>
<li><span>Drains and undrains must be incremental. When undraining, an operator should be able to assign as little as 1% of traffic to an AZ to test whether it has truly recovered.</span></li>
<li><span>The draining mechanism must not rely on resources in the AZ being drained. For example, it’s not OK to activate a drain by just SSHing to every server and forcing it to healthcheck down. This ensures that drains may be put in place even if an AZ is completely offline.</span></li>
</ol>
<p><span>A naive implementation that fits these requirements would have us plumb a signal into each of our RPC clients that, when received, causes them to fail a specified percentage of traffic away from a particular AZ. This turns out to have a lot of complexity lurking within. Slack does not share a common codebase or even runtime; services in the user-facing request path are written in Hack, Go, Java, and C++. This would necessitate a separate implementation in each language. Beyond that concern, we support a number of internal service discovery interfaces including the Envoy xDS API, the Consul API, and even DNS. Notably, DNS does not offer an abstraction for something like an AZ or partial draining; clients expect to resolve a DNS address and receive a list of IPs and no more. Finally, we rely heavily on open-source systems like Vitess, for which code-level changes present an unpleasant choice between maintaining an internal fork and doing the additional work to get changes merged into upstream.</span></p>
<p><span>The main strategy we settled on is called </span><i><span>siloing</span></i><span>. Services may be said to be </span><i><span>siloed</span></i><span>&nbsp;if they only receive traffic from within their AZ and only send traffic upstream to servers in their AZ. The overall architectural effect of this is that each service appears to be N virtual services, one per AZ. Importantly, we may effectively remove traffic from all siloed services in an AZ simply by redirecting user requests away from that AZ. If no new requests from users are arriving in a siloed AZ, internal services in that AZ will naturally quiesce as they have no new work to do.</span></p>
<figure id="attachment_16212" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-16212"><img decoding="async" src="https://slack.engineering/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2023/08/image2.jpg?w=640" alt="A digram showing request failures across multiple AZs caused by a failure in a single AZ." width="640" height="434" srcset="https://slack.engineering/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2023/08/image2.jpg 1160w, https://slack.engineering/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2023/08/image2.jpg?resize=640,435 640w, https://slack.engineering/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2023/08/image2.jpg?resize=768,522 768w" sizes="(max-width: 479px) 90vw, (max-width: 599px) 432px, 536px"><figcaption id="caption-attachment-16212">Our original architecture. Backends are spread across AZs, so errors present in frontends in all AZs.</figcaption></figure>
<p><span>And so we finally arrive at our cellular architecture. All services are present in all AZs, but each service only communicates with services within its AZ. Failure of a system within one AZ is contained within that AZ, and we may dynamically route traffic away to avoid those failures simply by redirecting at the frontend.</span></p>
<figure id="attachment_16213" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-16213"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://slack.engineering/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2023/08/image3.jpg?w=640" alt="A digram showing client requests siloed within AZs, routing around a failed AZ." width="640" height="424" srcset="https://slack.engineering/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2023/08/image3.jpg 1160w, https://slack.engineering/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2023/08/image3.jpg?resize=640,424 640w, https://slack.engineering/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2023/08/image3.jpg?resize=768,508 768w" sizes="(max-width: 479px) 90vw, (max-width: 599px) 432px, 536px"><figcaption id="caption-attachment-16213">Siloed architecture. Failure in one AZ is contained to that AZ; traffic may be routed away.</figcaption></figure>
<p><span>Siloing allows us to concentrate our efforts on the traffic-shifting implementation in one place: the systems that route queries from users into the core services in us-east-1. Over the last several years we have invested heavily in </span><a href="https://slack.engineering/migrating-millions-of-concurrent-websockets-to-envoy/"><span>migrating from HAProxy to the Envoy / xDS ecosystem,</span></a><span>&nbsp;and so all our edge load balancers are now running Envoy and receive configuration from Rotor, our in-house xDS control plane. This enabled us to power AZ draining by simply using two out-of-the-box Envoy features: weighted clusters and dynamic weight assignment via RTDS. When we drain an AZ, we simply send a signal through Rotor to the edge Envoy load balancers instructing them to reweight their per-AZ target clusters at us-east-1. If an AZ at us-east-1 is reweighted to zero, Envoy will continue handling in-flight requests but assign all new requests to another AZ, and thus the AZ is drained. Let’s see how this satisfies our goals:</span></p>
<ol>
<li><span>Propagation through the control plane is on the order of seconds; Envoy load balancers will apply new weights immediately.</span></li>
<li><span>Drains are graceful; no queries to a drained AZ will be abandoned by the load balancing layer.</span></li>
<li><span>Weights provide gradual drains with a granularity of 1%.</span></li>
<li><span>Edge load balancers are located in different regions entirely, and the control plane is replicated regionally and resilient against the failure of any single AZ.</span></li>
</ol>
<p><span>Here is a graph showing bandwidth per AZ as we gradually drain traffic from one AZ into two others. Note how pronounced the “knees” in the graph are; this reflects the low propagation time and high granularity afforded us by the Envoy/xDS implementation.</span></p>
<figure id="attachment_16214" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-16214"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://slack.engineering/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2023/08/image4.jpg?w=640" alt="Graph showing queries per second per AZ. One AZ's rate drops while the others rise at 3 distinct points in time and then the rates re-converge at an even split." width="640" height="416" srcset="https://slack.engineering/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2023/08/image4.jpg 1999w, https://slack.engineering/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2023/08/image4.jpg?resize=640,416 640w, https://slack.engineering/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2023/08/image4.jpg?resize=768,499 768w, https://slack.engineering/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2023/08/image4.jpg?resize=1280,832 1280w, https://slack.engineering/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2023/08/image4.jpg?resize=1536,999 1536w, https://slack.engineering/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2023/08/image4.jpg?resize=1920,1249 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 479px) 90vw, (max-width: 599px) 432px, 536px"><figcaption id="caption-attachment-16214">Queries per second, by AZ.</figcaption></figure>
<p><span>In our next post we’ll dive deeper into the details of our technical implementation. We’ll discuss how siloing is implemented for internal services, and which services can’t be siloed and what we do about them. We’ll also discuss how we’ve changed the way we operate and build services at Slack now that we have this powerful new tool at our disposal. Stay tuned!</span></p>
					</div><!-- .entry__content -->
				<!-- .entry__footer -->
			</article><!-- #post-16208 -->

		
		</main><!-- #primary -->

		
<!-- #secondary -->
	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[n8n.io - A powerful workflow automation tool (154 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://n8n.io</link>
            <guid>37274052</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 16:06:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://n8n.io">https://n8n.io</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37274052">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-v-691fb278="" id="__nuxt" data-server-rendered="true"><div data-v-43b42ddf="" data-v-691fb278=""><div data-v-43b42ddf=""><p data-v-43b42ddf="">
        Workflow automation for technical people
      </p> <h2 data-v-43b42ddf="">
        Build complex automations 10x faster, without fighting APIs
      </h2> <p data-v-43b42ddf="">Your days spent slogging through a spaghetti of scripts are over. <br>Use JavaScript when you need flexibility and UI for everything else.</p> <div data-v-0e3fb934="" data-v-43b42ddf=""><a href="https://github.com/n8n-io/n8n" data-v-0e3fb934=""><div data-v-0e3fb934="" data-v-43b42ddf=""><p><img src="https://n8n.io/_nuxt/image/87df9a.svg" width="32" height="32" alt="GitHub logo" loading="lazy" srcset="https://n8niostorageaccount.blob.core.windows.net/n8nio-strapi-blobs-prod/assets/github_white_3112efbe15_d6f929e422.svg" data-v-43b42ddf=""></p> </div></a></div></div> <div data-v-43b42ddf=""><p><img src="https://n8n.io/_nuxt/image/a57c32.svg" alt="" loading="lazy" data-v-43b42ddf=""> <span data-v-43b42ddf="">Full source code available</span></p><p><img src="https://n8n.io/_nuxt/image/a57c32.svg" alt="" loading="lazy" data-v-43b42ddf=""> <span data-v-43b42ddf="">Self host-able</span></p><p><img src="https://n8n.io/_nuxt/image/a57c32.svg" alt="" loading="lazy" data-v-43b42ddf=""> <span data-v-43b42ddf="">55,385 community members</span></p></div> <p><img src="https://n8n.io/_nuxt/image/f4908d.svg" alt="homepage bg mobile" srcset="https://n8niostorageaccount.blob.core.windows.net/n8nio-strapi-blobs-stage/assets/Group_491_1_3966733d3a.svg" format="webp" fetchpriority="high" data-v-43b42ddf=""> <img src="https://n8n.io/_nuxt/image/f07ac5.svg" alt="n8n_image" srcset="https://n8niostorageaccount.blob.core.windows.net/n8nio-strapi-blobs-stage/assets/Frame_1035_bf4f8a8954.svg" fetchpriority="high" format="webp" data-v-43b42ddf=""></p></div><div data-v-53511fec="" data-v-691fb278=""><div data-index="0" data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><h3 data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec="">
          Code when you need, no code when you don’t&nbsp;
        </h3> <p><span data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><p>Connect APIs with no code to automate basic tasks. Or write vanilla Javascript when you need to manipulate complex data.</p>
</span></p></div><div data-index="1" data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><h3 data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec="">
          Build custom scenarios at speed
        </h3> <p><span data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><p>You can implement multiple triggers. Branch and merge your workflows. And even pause flows to wait for external events.</p>
</span></p></div><div data-index="2" data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><h3 data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec="">
          Integrate with any app
        </h3> <p><span data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><p>Interface easily with any API or service with custom HTTP requests.</p>
</span></p></div><div data-index="3" data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><h3 data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec="">
          Independent instances for each environment
        </h3> <p><span data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><p>Avoid breaking live workflows by separating dev and prod environments with unique sets of auth data.</p>
</span></p></div><div data-index="4" data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><h3 data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec="">
          Bulk operations&nbsp;
        </h3> <p><span data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><p>n8n nodes let you process data at scale with a built-in iteration functionality in every node.</p>
</span></p></div><div data-index="5" data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><h3 data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec="">
          Painless debugging
        </h3> <p><span data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><p>See the execution data of every workflow. Integrate error nodes into workflows to catch errors. And rerun individual nodes to test fixes fast.</p>
</span></p></div><div data-index="6" data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><h3 data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec="">
          Host on your own infrastructure
        </h3> <p><span data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><p>Fully on-prem for those that need the security</p>
</span></p></div></div><div data-v-4aa551c5="" data-v-691fb278=""> <div data-v-4aa551c5=""><ul data-v-4aa551c5=""><li role="presentation" data-v-4aa551c5=""><span role="tab" data-v-4aa551c5="">
          Customer integrations
        </span></li><li role="presentation" data-v-4aa551c5=""><span role="tab" data-v-4aa551c5="">
          SaaS backend prototyping
        </span></li><li role="presentation" data-v-4aa551c5=""><span role="tab" data-v-4aa551c5="">
          Lead automation
        </span></li><li role="presentation" data-v-4aa551c5=""><span role="tab" data-v-4aa551c5="">
          CRM customization
        </span></li></ul></div> <div data-v-4aa551c5=""><div data-v-4aa551c5=""><div data-v-4aa551c5=""><h3>Optimize engineering resources</h3>
<p>Save time building customer integrations. Engineer faster POCs. And keep your customer-specific functionality separate from product. All without writing a single line of code.</p>
</div> <div data-v-4aa551c5=""><p><img src="https://n8n.io/_nuxt/image/736d75.png" alt="eng-resources" loading="lazy" srcset="https://n8niostorageaccount.blob.core.windows.net/n8nio-strapi-blobs-stage/assets/common_uses_cases_engineering_resources_96ca4f3e48.png" format="webp" data-v-4aa551c5=""></p> </div></div><div data-v-4aa551c5=""><div data-v-4aa551c5=""><h3>Build and test new features faster</h3>
<p>Avoid throwing away features that took forever to build. With n8n, you can quickly set up end points to test what works. And easily debug to fix what doesn’t.</p>
</div> <div data-v-4aa551c5=""><p><img src="https://n8n.io/_nuxt/image/0ebf9c.png" alt="common_uses_cases_newFeatures" loading="lazy" srcset="https://n8niostorageaccount.blob.core.windows.net/n8nio-strapi-blobs-stage/assets/common_uses_cases_new_Features_bd1ae37b46.png" format="webp" data-v-4aa551c5=""></p> </div></div><div data-v-4aa551c5=""><div data-v-4aa551c5=""><h3>Save time&nbsp;managing leads</h3>
<p>Take the stress out of managing your leads by connecting all your marketing tools to run on autopilot.</p>
</div> <div data-v-4aa551c5=""><p><img src="https://n8n.io/_nuxt/image/b0bef3.png" alt="common_uses_cases_leads" loading="lazy" srcset="https://n8niostorageaccount.blob.core.windows.net/n8nio-strapi-blobs-stage/assets/common_uses_cases_leads_ae5eddfdbf.png" format="webp" data-v-4aa551c5=""></p> </div></div><div data-v-4aa551c5=""><div data-v-4aa551c5=""><h3>CRM customization</h3>
<p>Push past the limitations of your CRM by building custom integrations to move any data you want between your apps and systems.</p>
</div> <div data-v-4aa551c5=""><p><img src="https://n8n.io/_nuxt/image/d6a2ea.png" alt="common_uses_cases_CRM" loading="lazy" srcset="https://n8niostorageaccount.blob.core.windows.net/n8nio-strapi-blobs-stage/assets/common_uses_cases_CRM_085a831754.png" format="webp" data-v-4aa551c5=""></p> </div></div></div></div><div data-v-53511fec="" data-v-691fb278=""><div data-index="0" data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><h3 data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec="">
          Scalable performance
        </h3> <p><span data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><p>220 workflow executions per sec on a single instance, and add more instances if required. <a href="https://docs.n8n.io/hosting/scaling/performance-benchmarking/">More info</a></p>
</span></p></div><div data-index="1" data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><h3 data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec="">
          Customizable error handling
        </h3> <p><span data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><p>Get notified whenever a workflow fails — be it via email, Slack or a log aggregator</p>
</span></p></div><div data-index="2" data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><h3 data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec="">
          Share workflows with a click
        </h3> <p><span data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><p>Reuse, export to JSON, or import workflows with a single copy/paste.</p>
</span></p></div><div data-index="3" data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><h3 data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec="">
          Use 600+ templates to move faster
        </h3> <p><span data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><p>Get a head start on your workflows with templates developed by our core team and community.</p>
</span></p></div><div data-index="4" data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><h3 data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec="">
          350+ native integrations
        </h3> <p><span data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><p>Connect to all your favorite apps. Or write your own integration with a general connector to the rest.</p>
</span></p></div><div data-index="5" data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><h3 data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec="">
          Automated API auth
        </h3> <p><span data-v-5efc53c4="" data-v-53511fec=""><p>All you have to do is enter the API key. n8n handles the rest of the auth. No reading through docs required.</p>
</span></p></div></div><div data-v-59da2cda="" data-v-691fb278=""><div data-v-4dc91236="" data-v-59da2cda=""><p><img src="https://n8n.io/_nuxt/image/502eb8.svg" alt="how-it-works-1" loading="lazy" srcset="https://n8niostorageaccount.blob.core.windows.net/n8nio-strapi-blobs-prod/assets/how_It_Works_1_db22134a11.svg" data-v-4dc91236=""></p> <div data-v-4dc91236=""><h3 data-v-4dc91236="">Pull in data</h3> <p data-v-4dc91236="">Set up triggers for app events or specific times to fetch data across your app stack</p></div> <p><img src="https://n8n.io/_nuxt/image/579b4a.svg" width="64" height="73" alt="arrow_primary" loading="lazy" data-v-4dc91236=""> <img src="https://n8n.io/_nuxt/image/fe7f83.svg" width="105" height="116" alt="arrow_secondary" loading="lazy" data-v-4dc91236=""></p></div><div data-v-4dc91236="" data-v-59da2cda=""><p><img src="https://n8n.io/_nuxt/image/8fd21a.svg" alt="how-it-works-2" loading="lazy" srcset="https://n8niostorageaccount.blob.core.windows.net/n8nio-strapi-blobs-prod/assets/how_It_Works_2_dd2c4fc758.svg" data-v-4dc91236=""></p> <div data-v-4dc91236=""><h3 data-v-4dc91236="">Set up steps</h3> <p data-v-4dc91236="">Use 220+ app nodes to create, read, and update the valuable data across your apps</p></div> <p><img src="https://n8n.io/_nuxt/image/579b4a.svg" width="64" height="73" alt="arrow_primary" loading="lazy" data-v-4dc91236=""> <img src="https://n8n.io/_nuxt/image/fe7f83.svg" width="105" height="116" alt="arrow_secondary" loading="lazy" data-v-4dc91236=""></p></div><div data-v-4dc91236="" data-v-59da2cda=""><p><img src="https://n8n.io/_nuxt/image/1f8301.svg" alt="how-it-works-3" loading="lazy" srcset="https://n8niostorageaccount.blob.core.windows.net/n8nio-strapi-blobs-prod/assets/how_It_Works_3_7a4b095a4b.svg" data-v-4dc91236=""></p> <div data-v-4dc91236=""><h3 data-v-4dc91236="">Save time - every day</h3> <p data-v-4dc91236="">From monthly syncs to millions of executions, sit back as your workflow does the heavy lifting</p></div> <!----> <!----></div></div><div data-v-7442cf86="" data-v-691fb278=""><div data-v-67dbc12e="" data-v-7442cf86=""> <p>Your workflows<br>
Your way</p> <ul data-v-67dbc12e=""><li data-v-67dbc12e=""><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="16" fill="none" style="color:#8287eb" data-v-67dbc12e=""><path fill="currentColor" d="m23.472 6.728-6-6a1.8 1.8 0 0 0-2.544 2.544L17.854 6.2H1.8a1.8 1.8 0 0 0 0 3.6h16.054l-2.926 2.928a1.801 1.801 0 1 0 2.544 2.544l6-6a1.797 1.797 0 0 0 0-2.544Z" data-v-67dbc12e=""></path></svg> <p><strong>Full source code available:</strong><br>
Audit, tweak, and fork our codebase to suit your needs.</p></li><li data-v-67dbc12e=""><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="16" fill="none" style="color:#8287eb" data-v-67dbc12e=""><path fill="currentColor" d="m23.472 6.728-6-6a1.8 1.8 0 0 0-2.544 2.544L17.854 6.2H1.8a1.8 1.8 0 0 0 0 3.6h16.054l-2.926 2.928a1.801 1.801 0 1 0 2.544 2.544l6-6a1.797 1.797 0 0 0 0-2.544Z" data-v-67dbc12e=""></path></svg> <p><strong>Self-hostable:</strong> Easily keep your data secure. And ensure compliance with data privacy laws.</p></li><li data-v-67dbc12e=""><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="16" fill="none" style="color:#8287eb" data-v-67dbc12e=""><path fill="currentColor" d="m23.472 6.728-6-6a1.8 1.8 0 0 0-2.544 2.544L17.854 6.2H1.8a1.8 1.8 0 0 0 0 3.6h16.054l-2.926 2.928a1.801 1.801 0 1 0 2.544 2.544l6-6a1.797 1.797 0 0 0 0-2.544Z" data-v-67dbc12e=""></path></svg> <p><strong>Embeddable:</strong> White label our UI to give your customers access to 220+ native integrations.</p></li></ul> </div><div data-v-67dbc12e="" data-v-7442cf86=""> <p>Build without blowing your budget</p> <ul data-v-67dbc12e=""><li data-v-67dbc12e=""><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="16" fill="none" style="color:#8287eb" data-v-67dbc12e=""><path fill="currentColor" d="m23.472 6.728-6-6a1.8 1.8 0 0 0-2.544 2.544L17.854 6.2H1.8a1.8 1.8 0 0 0 0 3.6h16.054l-2.926 2.928a1.801 1.801 0 1 0 2.544 2.544l6-6a1.797 1.797 0 0 0 0-2.544Z" data-v-67dbc12e=""></path></svg> <p>Other platforms’ per-execution pricing can eat up your budget insanely fast.</p></li><li data-v-67dbc12e=""><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="16" fill="none" style="color:#8287eb" data-v-67dbc12e=""><path fill="currentColor" d="m23.472 6.728-6-6a1.8 1.8 0 0 0-2.544 2.544L17.854 6.2H1.8a1.8 1.8 0 0 0 0 3.6h16.054l-2.926 2.928a1.801 1.801 0 1 0 2.544 2.544l6-6a1.797 1.797 0 0 0 0-2.544Z" data-v-67dbc12e=""></path></svg> <p>With n8n, you can self-host for free. Or <strong>pay for a package of workflows</strong> in the cloud.</p></li><li data-v-67dbc12e=""><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="16" fill="none" style="color:#8287eb" data-v-67dbc12e=""><path fill="currentColor" d="m23.472 6.728-6-6a1.8 1.8 0 0 0-2.544 2.544L17.854 6.2H1.8a1.8 1.8 0 0 0 0 3.6h16.054l-2.926 2.928a1.801 1.801 0 1 0 2.544 2.544l6-6a1.797 1.797 0 0 0 0-2.544Z" data-v-67dbc12e=""></path></svg> <p>So you can make your flows as complex as you like — at no extra cost.</p></li></ul> </div><div data-v-67dbc12e="" data-v-7442cf86=""> <p>Resolve 99% of issues&nbsp;in hours, not months</p> <ul data-v-67dbc12e=""><li data-v-67dbc12e=""><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="16" fill="none" style="color:#8287eb" data-v-67dbc12e=""><path fill="currentColor" d="m23.472 6.728-6-6a1.8 1.8 0 0 0-2.544 2.544L17.854 6.2H1.8a1.8 1.8 0 0 0 0 3.6h16.054l-2.926 2.928a1.801 1.801 0 1 0 2.544 2.544l6-6a1.797 1.797 0 0 0 0-2.544Z" data-v-67dbc12e=""></path></svg> <p>You don’t have to wait weeks for someone on your vendor’s team to fix your issue. (If they can fix it at all.)</p></li><li data-v-67dbc12e=""><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="16" fill="none" style="color:#8287eb" data-v-67dbc12e=""><path fill="currentColor" d="m23.472 6.728-6-6a1.8 1.8 0 0 0-2.544 2.544L17.854 6.2H1.8a1.8 1.8 0 0 0 0 3.6h16.054l-2.926 2.928a1.801 1.801 0 1 0 2.544 2.544l6-6a1.797 1.797 0 0 0 0-2.544Z" data-v-67dbc12e=""></path></svg> <p>Get access to a <strong>6K-strong forum</strong> of n8n engineers and community experts available 24/7 to answer your questions.</p></li><li data-v-67dbc12e=""><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="16" fill="none" style="color:#8287eb" data-v-67dbc12e=""><path fill="currentColor" d="m23.472 6.728-6-6a1.8 1.8 0 0 0-2.544 2.544L17.854 6.2H1.8a1.8 1.8 0 0 0 0 3.6h16.054l-2.926 2.928a1.801 1.801 0 1 0 2.544 2.544l6-6a1.797 1.797 0 0 0 0-2.544Z" data-v-67dbc12e=""></path></svg> <p>You can expect same-day responses (almost) every time.</p></li></ul> </div></div><div data-v-2dd2ed8c="" data-v-691fb278=""><p data-v-2dd2ed8c="">
        Scale your company's operations with our advanced on-prem or cloud automation
      </p>  <!----></div><div data-v-17ea5a8e="" data-v-691fb278=""><p>Stop struggling with your scripts<br>
Start creating workflows 10X faster — with n8n</p> </div> <p><a href="https://www.producthunt.com/posts/n8n-1-0?utm_source=badge-featured&amp;utm_medium=badge&amp;utm_souce=badge-n8n-1-0" target="_blank" data-v-691fb278=""><img src="https://api.producthunt.com/widgets/embed-image/v1/featured.svg?post_id=406015&amp;theme=dark" alt="n8n 1.0 - Workflow automation for technical people | Product Hunt" width="250" height="54" data-v-691fb278=""></a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google Maps is a critical dependency for nutrition facts on mcdonalds.com (107 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://mastodon.social/@simevidas/110956696765338181</link>
            <guid>37273907</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 15:49:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://mastodon.social/@simevidas/110956696765338181">https://mastodon.social/@simevidas/110956696765338181</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37273907">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Let Maintainers Be Maintainers (152 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://graydon2.dreamwidth.org/306832.html</link>
            <guid>37272929</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 13:52:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://graydon2.dreamwidth.org/306832.html">https://graydon2.dreamwidth.org/306832.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37272929">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>A short note about corporate free / open source software (FOSS), and corporate-employed maintainers. Or specifically "corporate-employed maintainers .. with bad incentives". I tried to come up with a pithy name, but that's the best I could do: CEMBIs.</p><p>I've worked professionally in FOSS for a long time. I've seen a lot of corporate approaches to FOSS participation over that time, and seen the FOSS community develop a fairly nuanced understanding of what sorts of corporate strategies are welcome or unwelcome, healthy or harmful to a project. We have articulated a lot of thoughts about (say) open core and dual licensing business models, or (say) which forms of corporate "embrace" represent a step on an "extend/extinguish" path, or (say) which forms of telemetry are appropriate and which put users at risk of surveillance.</p><p>What I haven't seen a lot of discussion of, and wish I did see, is the structure and content of relationships that exist between corporate-employed FOSS maintainers and their employers. And I think this matters because the people doing corporate FOSS aren't soul-less automata executing corporate strategy. They are people with their own motivations, incentives, a certain amount of autonomy, but (most relevant to my concerns) a set of performance-evaluation criteria they have to satisfy to remain employed and/or get promoted.</p><p>Companies incentivize lots of things, but I worry (and in many cases I either know first hand or have heard second hand) that companies often have an incentive structure that rewards <em>novelty</em>, especially in the form of <em>features</em> if not entire <em>products</em>. There's a good reason for this when the company is "making products to sell": this year's new-and-improved is always sellable over last year's tired old model. But it's also just a reflection of the "growth orientation" or capitalism in general: whatever activity the company accomplished last year, a common measure of health and vitality isn't consistent execution but <em>growth of the business</em>. Failure to grow is treated as stagnation which is treated as equivalent to death. This orientation can be embedded so deep in a company's DNA that it's the incentive structure given to <em>everyone</em> who works there, regardless of whether they're making products, auditing the accounts, or <em>maintaining corporate infrastructure</em>.</p><p>And to a large measure, that's what FOSS is. Not always, but usually: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Infrastructure">infrastructure</a>. It's stuff that's supposed to work the same way from one day to the next. Stuff that's not supposed to be noticed because it just works. Reliably, efficiently, silently. Stuff that has a massive installed base of users relying on it, massive social and institutional inertia, and thereby massive (and sensible) built-in resistance to novelty. You don't actually want novelty in the electrical grid, the drinking water system, sewers, roads, bridges, rail lines, telecoms .. you want this stuff to be <em>absolutely rock solid</em> and not novel in the least. That's what maybe 90 or 95% of FOSS is like, certainly the stuff that <em>needs</em> reliable corporate maintainers.</p><p>For corporate-employed FOSS maintainers working at a firm with these "growth and novelty" incentives -- CEMBIs -- this leads to a real quandry. They're in a position where their job performance is very likely to be evaluated in terms of visible growth and novelty (it might be dressed up in more abstract terms like "real-world impact" or "visibility" but it still means the same thing) even though that is exactly the wrong thing for the health of the project they're maintaining. The incentives are bad. If they do the <em>best</em> thing for the project <em>as infrastructure</em> -- triage and fix bugs from the backlog, optimize performance, increase security and reliability, pay down tech debt, simplify and automate ongoing maintenance -- the bias of their organization is likely to view them as "doing nothing", or at best doing "low-value work" that only counts as "reducing fixed costs", not leading the way towards new growth. To be seen in a positive light by their employer, the CEMBI winds uphaving to do essentially <em>anti-maintenance work</em>: make the program "do something new and exciting", that it didn't do yesterday. Ignore maintenance of "what is", focus on "what's next".</p><p>Seeing this over and over in FOSS makes me a bit sad. I guess I've maybe been watching too many re-runs of The West Wing lately, but while I've been thinking about this subject, I keep thinking of the "<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Let_Bartlet_Be_Bartlet">Let Bartlet Be Bartlet</a>" episode near the end of the first season, where the characters come around to the idea that maybe it'd be best to just do what they were elected to do. I keep thinking it'd be nice if employers could incentivize their employees to do what they were hired to do. To "<b>Let Maintainers Be Maintainers</b>". Maintaining FOSS isn't low-value work. It's <em>essential</em> work, stuff that you ignore at your medium and long-term peril. As a new homeowner I will make more salient analogies: it's testing the wiring for faults, testing the walls for mould, replacing the roof before it leaks. It's work that <em>has to be done</em> in order for FOSS to keep functioning over the long term. Software actually does "break down and wear out": requirements change; upstream and downstream platforms and libraries change incompatibly; patterns of usage change; hardware changes; new subsystems become performance bottlenecks; new bugs are discovered, some of which will be high severity security vulnerabilities, others will merely grow in importance as they're encountered more often. Software maintenance is <em>real and important work</em>, and if a company hires a maintainer of a project "in order to support the project", it's what that company should be incentivizing and evaluating those maintainers in terms of.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[E-ink is so Retropunk (506 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://rmkit.dev/eink-is-so-retropunk/</link>
            <guid>37272652</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 13:21:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://rmkit.dev/eink-is-so-retropunk/">https://rmkit.dev/eink-is-so-retropunk/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37272652">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/BlogPosting">

  

  <div itemprop="articleBody">
    <p>I’ve long been struggling to describe why e-ink is so much fun for me, but I
think I’ve finally realized what it is: <strong>e-ink is just so so so retropunk</strong>.</p>

<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/8760cI9.jpg" alt=""></p>

<p>An e-ink device is a hacker’s dream - or at least, this hacker’s dream.  They
are a return to the magical feeling of computers of the 80s and 90s. It’s a
world where Microsoft and Apple never existed and we don’t have to suffer with
abstractions on top of abstractions.  It’s DOS for the 2020s. It’s graphing
calculators for grown-ups.</p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>The e-ink devices I favor are low powered ARM devices running linux without a
display server or gigabytes of RAM. Let’s break down why that’s so awesome:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Low Powered: They can last for weeks on a single charge</li>
  <li>ARM is a simple architecture with a low instruction count and even lower cost</li>
  <li>Linux: as much as I like it, Android is a complicated mess</li>
  <li>Apps are simple: they talk to the kernel to read input and draw directly to the framebuffer</li>
  <li>Low RAM and slow CPUs: There’s no room to build complicated stacks of software, which means no window managers, no browsers and definitely no electron apps</li>
</ul>

<p>As similar as they are to the computers of the early 90s, they are different in
some tangible ways:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The resolution is much higher than an old computer - The PPI is between 200 - 300</li>
  <li>All devices supports touch events, some even support a pen stylus</li>
  <li>They are super portable, weighing between 200 - 400 grams, with displays ranging from 6” to 10”</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-software">The Software</h2>

<p>Since the devices are niche, the software ecosystem is way more
<strong>homebrew</strong> (as in the Homebrew Computing Club): people write and share their
apps and the community is tight knit. The people who use eink devices are
enthusiasts: they’ve given up the joys of color displays to work on these
under-powered devices that are devoid of app stores, tracking pixels, pay to
play features and constant distractions. There’s no email on these devices,
there’s no chat or social networks, there’s only simple applications.</p>

<p>Don’t be fooled though: the device constraints lead to interesting and quirky
software. In the <a href="https://toltec-dev.org/">reMarkable eco-system</a>, there’s dozens of
applications, including:</p>

<ul>
  <li>multi-tasking application launchers like <a href="https://github.com/Eeems/oxide/">oxide</a> and <a href="https://github.com/rmkit-dev/rmkit/tree/master/src/remux">remux</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/timower/rM2-stuff">terminal emulators</a></li>
  <li>an <a href="https://github.com/bkirwi/folly">interactive fiction interpreter</a></li>
  <li>an <a href="https://github.com/bkirwi/sill">experimental shell that you can write into</a></li>
  <li>alternative ebook readers like <a href="https://github.com/koreader/koreader/">koreader</a> and <a href="https://github.com/LinusCDE/plato/">plato</a></li>
  <li>a <a href="https://rmkit.dev/apps/sas">simple app script that follows the unix philosphy</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/LinusCDE/chessmarkable">a chess board</a></li>
  <li>even a <a href="https://github.com/LinusCDE/doomarkable">port of doom</a></li>
  <li>and so <a href="https://rmkit.dev/">much more</a> - like <a href="https://toltec-dev.org/stable/">much, much, more</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Since eink is currently niche, it also means green fields: there are lots of
opportunities to write applications that fills out the ecosystem. In short, a
hacker’s playground.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-get-started">How to get started</h2>

<p>Convinced that you should hack on eink devices? Grab a reMarkable or Kobo and
get hacking ;) Join the <a href="https://discord.gg/hAKFTcuu">reMarkable discord
server</a> or browse the <a href="https://www.mobileread.com/forums/forumdisplay.php?f=247">Mobile Read Kobo
Forums</a>.</p>

<p>For reMarkable, the toltec repository is a good place to get started - one of
the maintainers, Eeems, <a href="https://eeems.website/toltec/">has written a great
tutorial</a>.</p>

<p>If you want more specific advice, feel free to directly <a href="https://rmkit.dev/about">get in touch</a></p>

<h2 id="why-write-a-post-now">Why write a post now?</h2>

<p>Several years ago, I started hacking on e-ink devices and had an enormous
amount of fun writing applications and seeing what others have built.
Unfortunately, I’ve had several false starts with writing about e-ink: whether
it was about what I’ve actually done, or the lessons learned along the way or
even a set of things to consider when developing e-ink apps, the posts would
lay half finished because they just never felt compelling - my enthusiasm for
e-ink just wasn’t coming through.</p>

<p>Instead of trying to push any of those posts to completion, I’ve decided to try
to articulate what is so cool about e-ink to me.</p>

<h2 id="appendix-hacker-unfriendly-devices">Appendix: Hacker unfriendly devices</h2>

<h4 id="kindles">Kindles</h4>

<p>The Kindle requires a jailbreak to use and is running a modified version of
Kindle Fire. The Kindle Scribe is still secured, though. For this reason, I don’t
particularly recommend the Kindle devices.</p>

<h4 id="onyx">Onyx</h4>

<p>In every eink thread that comes up, the Onyx is brought up as not following the
GPL: <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Onyx_Boox/comments/p9ztru/lets_help_onyx_become_a_better_company/">they use a modified linux kernel and haven’t published the source for it</a>.</p>

<h4 id="pine">Pine</h4>

<p>The Pine Note is cool and open, but it’s software is still in development. Use
only if you are willing to take on an <a href="https://wiki.pine64.org/wiki/PineNote#State_of_the_software">early product aimed at early adopters and
developers</a> - In other words,
maybe the Pine Note is too hacker friendly.</p>

  </div>

</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Fish – A friendly interactive shell (221 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell</link>
            <guid>37272611</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 13:17:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell">https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37272611">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-target="readme-toc.content">
            <article itemprop="text"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><a href="https://fishshell.com/" rel="nofollow">fish</a> - the friendly interactive shell <a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/actions"><img alt="Build Status" src="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/workflows/make%20test/badge.svg">
</a> <a href="https://cirrus-ci.com/github/fish-shell/fish-shell" rel="nofollow"><img alt="Cirrus CI Build Status" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/a3f090242fed30c7af9884c39e814e1e0ab15cecf6beb4797da42cbe6e4d4815/68747470733a2f2f6170692e6369727275732d63692e636f6d2f6769746875622f666973682d7368656c6c2f666973682d7368656c6c2e7376673f6272616e63683d6d6173746572" data-canonical-src="https://api.cirrus-ci.com/github/fish-shell/fish-shell.svg?branch=master"></a></h2>
<p dir="auto">fish is a smart and user-friendly command line shell for macOS, Linux,
and the rest of the family. fish includes features like syntax
highlighting, autosuggest-as-you-type, and fancy tab completions that
just work, with no configuration required.</p>
<p dir="auto">For downloads, screenshots and more, go to <a href="https://fishshell.com/" rel="nofollow">https://fishshell.com/</a>.</p>
<a name="user-content-quick-start"></a>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Quick Start</h2>
<p dir="auto">fish generally works like other shells, like bash or zsh. A few
important differences can be found at
<a href="https://fishshell.com/docs/current/tutorial.html" rel="nofollow">https://fishshell.com/docs/current/tutorial.html</a> by searching for the
magic phrase “unlike other shells”.</p>
<p dir="auto">Detailed user documentation is available by running <code>help</code> within
fish, and also at <a href="https://fishshell.com/docs/current/index.html" rel="nofollow">https://fishshell.com/docs/current/index.html</a></p>
<a name="user-content-getting-fish"></a>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Getting fish</h2>
<a name="user-content-macos"></a>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">macOS</h3>
<p dir="auto">fish can be installed:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>using <a href="http://brew.sh/" rel="nofollow">Homebrew</a>: <code>brew install fish</code></li>
<li>using <a href="https://www.macports.org/" rel="nofollow">MacPorts</a>:
<code>sudo port install fish</code></li>
<li>using the <a href="https://fishshell.com/" rel="nofollow">installer from fishshell.com</a></li>
<li>as a <a href="https://fishshell.com/" rel="nofollow">standalone app from fishshell.com</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Note: The minimum supported macOS version is 10.10 "Yosemite".</p>
<a name="user-content-packages-for-linux"></a>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Packages for Linux</h3>
<p dir="auto">Packages for Debian, Fedora, openSUSE, and Red Hat Enterprise
Linux/CentOS are available from the <a href="https://software.opensuse.org/download.html?project=shells%3Afish&amp;package=fish" rel="nofollow">openSUSE Build
Service</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Packages for Ubuntu are available from the <a href="https://launchpad.net/~fish-shell/+archive/ubuntu/release-3" rel="nofollow">fish
PPA</a>,
and can be installed using the following commands:</p>
<pre>sudo apt-add-repository ppa:fish-shell/release-3
sudo apt update
sudo apt install fish
</pre>
<p dir="auto">Instructions for other distributions may be found at
<a href="https://fishshell.com/" rel="nofollow">fishshell.com</a>.</p>
<a name="user-content-windows"></a>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Windows</h3>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>On Windows 10, fish can be installed under the WSL Windows Subsystem
for Linux with the instructions for the appropriate distribution
listed above under “Packages for Linux”, or from source with the
instructions below.</li>
<li>Fish can also be installed on all versions of Windows using
<a href="https://cygwin.com/" rel="nofollow">Cygwin</a> (from the <strong>Shells</strong> category).</li>
</ul>
<a name="user-content-building-from-source"></a>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Building from source</h3>
<p dir="auto">If packages are not available for your platform, GPG-signed tarballs are
available from <a href="https://fishshell.com/" rel="nofollow">fishshell.com</a> and
<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/releases">fish-shell on
GitHub</a>. See the
<a href="#building">Building</a> section for instructions.</p>
<a name="user-content-running-fish"></a>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Running fish</h2>
<p dir="auto">Once installed, run <code>fish</code> from your current shell to try fish out!</p>
<a name="user-content-dependencies"></a>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Dependencies</h3>
<p dir="auto">Running fish requires:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>curses or ncurses (preinstalled on most *nix systems)</li>
<li>some common *nix system utilities (currently <code>mktemp</code>), in
addition to the basic POSIX utilities (<code>cat</code>, <code>cut</code>, <code>dirname</code>,
<code>ls</code>, <code>mkdir</code>, <code>mkfifo</code>, <code>rm</code>, <code>sort</code>, <code>tee</code>, <code>tr</code>,
<code>uname</code> and <code>sed</code> at least, but the full coreutils plus <code>find</code> and
<code>awk</code> is preferred)</li>
<li>The gettext library, if compiled with
translation support</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">The following optional features also have specific requirements:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>builtin commands that have the <code>--help</code> option or print usage
messages require <code>nroff</code> or <code>mandoc</code> for
display</li>
<li>automated completion generation from manual pages requires Python 3.5+</li>
<li>the <code>fish_config</code> web configuration tool requires Python 3.5+ and a web browser</li>
<li>system clipboard integration (with the default Ctrl-V and Ctrl-X
bindings) require either the <code>xsel</code>, <code>xclip</code>,
<code>wl-copy</code>/<code>wl-paste</code> or <code>pbcopy</code>/<code>pbpaste</code> utilities</li>
<li>full completions for <code>yarn</code> and <code>npm</code> require the
<code>all-the-package-names</code> NPM module</li>
<li><code>colorls</code> is used, if installed, to add color when running <code>ls</code> on platforms
that do not have color support (such as OpenBSD)</li>
</ul>
<a name="user-content-switching-to-fish"></a>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Switching to fish</h3>
<p dir="auto">If you wish to use fish as your default shell, use the following
command:</p>
<pre>chsh -s /usr/local/bin/fish
</pre>
<p dir="auto"><code>chsh</code> will prompt you for your password and change your default
shell. (Substitute <code>/usr/local/bin/fish</code> with whatever path fish was
installed to, if it differs.) Log out, then log in again for the changes
to take effect.</p>
<p dir="auto">Use the following command if fish isn’t already added to <code>/etc/shells</code>
to permit fish to be your login shell:</p>
<pre>echo /usr/local/bin/fish | sudo tee -a /etc/shells
</pre>
<p dir="auto">To switch your default shell back, you can run <code>chsh -s /bin/bash</code>
(substituting <code>/bin/bash</code> with <code>/bin/tcsh</code> or <code>/bin/zsh</code> as
appropriate).</p>
<a name="user-content-building"></a>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Building</h2>
<a name="user-content-id1"></a>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Dependencies</h3>
<p dir="auto">Compiling fish from a tarball requires:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>a C++11 compiler (g++ 4.8 or later, or clang 3.3 or later)</li>
<li>CMake (version 3.5 or later)</li>
<li>a curses implementation such as ncurses (headers and libraries)</li>
<li>PCRE2 (headers and libraries) - optional, this will be downloaded if missing</li>
<li>gettext (headers and libraries) - optional, for translation support</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Sphinx is also optionally required to build the documentation from a
cloned git repository.</p>
<p dir="auto">Additionally, running the test suite requires Python 3.5+ and the pexpect package.</p>
<a name="user-content-dependencies-git-master"></a>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Dependencies, git master</h3>
<p dir="auto">Building from git master currently requires, in addition to the dependencies for a tarball:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Rust (version 1.67 or later)</li>
<li>libclang, even if you are compiling with GCC</li>
<li>an Internet connection</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">fish is in the process of being ported to Rust, replacing all C++ code, and as such these dependencies are a bit awkward and in flux.</p>
<p dir="auto">In general, we would currently not recommend running from git master if you just want to <em>use</em> fish.
Given the nature of the port, what is currently there is mostly a slower and buggier version of the last C++-based release.</p>
<a name="user-content-building-from-source-all-platforms-makefile-generator"></a>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Building from source (all platforms) - Makefile generator</h3>
<p dir="auto">To install into <code>/usr/local</code>, run:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="mkdir build; cd build
cmake ..
make
sudo make install"><pre>mkdir build<span>;</span> <span>cd</span> build
cmake ..
make
sudo make install</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">The install directory can be changed using the
<code>-DCMAKE_INSTALL_PREFIX</code> parameter for <code>cmake</code>.</p>
<a name="user-content-build-options"></a>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Build options</h3>
<p dir="auto">In addition to the normal CMake build options (like <code>CMAKE_INSTALL_PREFIX</code>), fish has some other options available to customize it.</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>BUILD_DOCS=ON|OFF - whether to build the documentation. This is automatically set to OFF when Sphinx isn't installed.</li>
<li>INSTALL_DOCS=ON|OFF - whether to install the docs. This is automatically set to on when BUILD_DOCS is or prebuilt documentation is available (like when building in-tree from a tarball).</li>
<li>FISH_USE_SYSTEM_PCRE2=ON|OFF - whether to use an installed pcre2. This is normally autodetected.</li>
<li>MAC_CODESIGN_ID=String|OFF - the codesign ID to use on Mac, or "OFF" to disable codesigning.</li>
<li>WITH_GETTEXT=ON|OFF - whether to build with gettext support for translations.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Note that fish does <em>not</em> support static linking and will attempt to error out if it detects it.</p>
<a name="user-content-help-it-didnt-build"></a>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Help, it didn’t build!</h3>
<p dir="auto">If fish reports that it could not find curses, try installing a curses
development package and build again.</p>
<p dir="auto">On Debian or Ubuntu you want:</p>
<pre>sudo apt install build-essential cmake ncurses-dev libncurses5-dev libpcre2-dev gettext
</pre>
<p dir="auto">On RedHat, CentOS, or Amazon EC2:</p>
<pre>sudo yum install ncurses-devel
</pre>
<a name="user-content-contributing-changes-to-the-code"></a>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing Changes to the Code</h2>
<p dir="auto">See the <a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/blob/master/CONTRIBUTING.rst">Guide for Developers</a>.</p>
<a name="user-content-contact-us"></a>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contact Us</h2>
<p dir="auto">Questions, comments, rants and raves can be posted to the official fish
mailing list at <a href="https://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/fish-users" rel="nofollow">https://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/fish-users</a>
or join us on our <a href="https://gitter.im/fish-shell/fish-shell" rel="nofollow">gitter.im
channel</a>. Or use the <a href="https://unix.stackexchange.com/questions/tagged/fish" rel="nofollow">fish tag
on Unix &amp; Linux Stackexchange</a>.
There is also a fish tag on Stackoverflow, but it is typically a poor fit.</p>
<p dir="auto">Found a bug? Have an awesome idea? Please <a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/new">open an
issue</a>.</p>

</article>
          </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[This venture-backed startup has quietly bought more than 80 mom-and-pop shops (191 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/08/24/this-venture-backed-startup-has-quietly-bought-more-than-80-mom-and-pop-shops/</link>
            <guid>37272298</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 12:37:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/08/24/this-venture-backed-startup-has-quietly-bought-more-than-80-mom-and-pop-shops/">https://techcrunch.com/2023/08/24/this-venture-backed-startup-has-quietly-bought-more-than-80-mom-and-pop-shops/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37272298">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
				<p id="speakable-summary"><a href="https://www.teamshares.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Teamshares</a> is a low-flying, New York-based startup with big ambitions to capitalize on an opportunity in plain sight: that of small businesses without a succession plan.</p>
<p>It’s not a small market. According to the U.S. Small Business Administration, small businesses represent 99.7% of U.S. employer firms and 64% of private-sector jobs. Meanwhile, just 15% or so of small business owners pass along their company to a family member, with many others simply closing up shop at some point.</p>
<p>With an aging population in the U.S., Teamshares is betting this market will grow even bigger, which is why since 2018, it has snapped up 84 small businesses from retiring owners. These owners like its pitch. Though Teamshares says that it sometimes pays below market price for a company, it installs a new president that it trains and grants 10% of the business’s stock to its employees. <span>Moreover</span>, it promises to increase those employees’ ownership to 80% within 20 years. It sounds almost valiant, like when KKR bought out a door company in 2015 and promised every employee a payout of at least $15,000 if the company met its targets when sold. When in 2022, KKR sold the company for 10 times what it paid, its 800 employees saw a payout of <a href="https://hbswk.hbs.edu/item/how-kkr-got-more-by-giving-ownership-to-the-factory-floor" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$360 million</a>.</p>
<p>But Teamshares isn’t in the private equity business. It’s a fintech company that has raised $245 million in venture capital to date, including from QED Investors, Spark Capital, Union Square Ventures, Inspired Capital, Khosla Ventures and Slow Ventures. It has also secured another $150 million in debt.</p>
<p>Those backers aren’t funding Teamshares so that it can grow and resell the businesses it acquires. In fact, according to co-founder and CEO Michael Brown, Teamshares doesn’t want to sell the companies it is buying — ever. The plan instead is to generate revenue from a growing array of fintech products that it sells to the businesses it buys. Think insurance, think credit cards. If everything goes as planned, Teamshares will eventually replace the majority of vendors these companies use — and become a brand known to many others outside of its immediate sphere. Certainly, it’s among the more unique fintech models this reporter can recall. More below, edited for length.</p>
<p><strong>TC: Other than some exceptions like KKR, which is focused in part on employee ownership because owners tend to be better employees, I don’t know of another venture-backed company doing what you’re doing. How did you settle on this broader idea?</strong></p>
<p>MB:&nbsp; I spent the first seven years of my career in investment banking. And that’s where I met <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/alexeu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Alex Eu</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/kevinshiiba/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kevin Shiiba</a>, the other two founders. Kevin decided he wanted to join the tech industry very early [and joined the] coding bootcamp General Assembly; Alex and I went and bought one, and then eventually eight, small businesses. We transitioned from being financial spreadsheet people to being operators and later entrepreneurs; learning how to operate a businesses informs [our work] today.</p>
<p><strong>How did you exit those businesses?</strong></p>
<p>We still own the ones in Canada; they’re running themselves today. There’s a president, a vice president. They’re just sort of like a dormant legacy business, but they’ve started the employee ownership journey, too, and that’s continuing on.</p>
<p><strong>You make money off those businesses through dividends? Is this how you’ll make money at Teamshares?</strong></p>
<p>How Teamshares makes money is we buy businesses, we dilute ourselves voluntarily to get employee ownership jump-started. We [carve out] 10% for all the employees and an additional 5% for [a president who we hire to run each business], and that stock is a gift — it’s earned over time through service.</p>
<p>From a financial standpoint, we’re [structured] just like Berkshire Hathaway, so if we buy a business with $5 million in revenue, then that becomes our revenue the next day. We profit from the profits of the business that was acquired, proportionate to our ownership, and we sell our stock back over time to the companies until it becomes 80% employee owned. We also have new revenue streams that we’ve just started launching. We built a neobank, we’re soon to launch credit cards, and we’re building an insurance business as well, so there’s a secondary layer of financial products that will basically replace the vendors that the companies used to use.</p>
<p><strong>These products are going to be available exclusively to Teamshares companies or you start there and expand out?</strong></p>
<p>The hope is the latter. We only build something if a product doesn’t exist for our exact use case, which is some combination of really traditional small business or employee ownership. And there’s not a lot of stuff [out there]. When we set out, we didn’t think we’d build a neobank, but there just wasn’t something that existed to our satisfaction, in part because small businesses still unfortunately receive a lot of checks. But the hope would be that in the future — let’s call it in the next five years — we could scale up and open these products up and have small businesses generally get to know Teamshares.</p>
<p><strong>What do the companies you’ve acquired so far have in common?</strong></p>
<p>Where <em>we</em> have commonality in the companies is around employee ownership, financial education, the president program and financial infrastructure. So, we’re audited by KPMG, for example, and we help these companies go from mom-and-pop accounting to having real financial infrastructure and being able to produce statement financials every month that are in accordance with GAAP. But we really believe in the companies [operating as] independently as possible. We provide support, and we work closely with the presidents. But we don’t think that it’s a good idea to try and integrate all the companies.</p>
<p><strong>So you aren’t trying to roll up similar companies, or swaths of similar companies?</strong></p>
<p>There are some exceptions where, for example, we’ve been buying pizza shops in a state back East, and those are being integrated to create one larger company that’s going to create more employee ownership wealth than could a stand-alone set of pizza shops. We’re doing this again in pool maintenance, where a lot of the businesses are really [small] and actually [buying] a first one that’s small but big enough to support the cost of a president, and then you can add smaller ones. So there’s a roll-up-esque element of certain companies we work with, but in general, we think these are really high-quality businesses that can operate fairly independently and we actually make a very devout customer promise that the companies are going to become 80% employee owned, or never for sale again.</p>
<p><strong>What’s your investing criteria?</strong></p>
<p>There are over 40 specific industries [represented in Teamshares’ current portfolio], but they really fall into about six categories, which are business services, consumer services, distribution, manufacturing, restaurants, and retail. So they’re all traditional businesses that are, on average, 30 years old, with annual revenue of between $2 million and $10 million generally.</p>
<p>We have a belief that employee ownership works in every industry, and our actual final decision — amongst the 70,000 leads we get every year — is all done on a case-by-case basis. But we start off by filtering the companies on what we call our structural criteria. So is it a true retirement sale? Are the owners of that age? Are there two or more managers? Is there low customer concentration? Do the earnings show up on the tax returns?</p>
<p><strong>You’re planning to sell these companies your products. Are there other ways the companies in the Teamshares ecosystem can work together?</strong></p>
<p>Absolutely. We’re now getting to the size where we’re starting to organize the companies, around industry groups. So there’s talk of the restaurant companies all kind of banding together [toward the goal of] common purchasing. The presidents [sometimes] share knowledge about what’s the best sort of ERP system and other software to use? Then there’s other things that don’t make sense for us to build but we can arrange large, corporate vendor partnerships. So, for example, you know, lots of these companies need vehicles, so having a national account with one of the major vehicle lessors is going to make sense.</p>
<p><strong>You mentioned Berkshire Hathaway early on. Is that what you aspire to build? Do you want Teamshares to go public?</strong></p>
<p>The most probable outcome is we go public, but there are ways to stay private, too. We do not plan to ever sell Teamshares; we would want it to be independent.</p>
<p>In terms of the Berkshire Hathaway piece, we subscribe to a lot of their philosophy about being very long-term minded and being pretty efficient in our underwriting and keeping things simple. But we’re not a one-for-one translation of the model. Their model is to have the permanent ownership forever, whereas our model has employee ownership as a twist, so we’re actually forgoing some amount of future growth by making employee ownership happen. And we believe that’s the right thing to do. And we believe the companies will be bigger and better for it.</p>
<p>Also Berkshire Hathaway can only buy companies that already have a CEO in place, whereas that’s not a luxury you can have in small business. We realized we had to build up a new generation of people, generally in their 30s and 40s, who were ready for something more entrepreneurial and ready for something really mission aligned. And so we recruit people from some really great companies — McKinsey, USAA, Tesla and Amazon — and train them to run these small businesses.</p>
<p><strong>How many employees do you have, and how big is your tech team?</strong></p>
<p>We have about 140 people altogether, and a 70-person tech team, so we’ve closed seven companies a month with two people. We’ve created a lot of leverage through building a lot of software for ourselves and for the companies.</p>
			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The EU’s Digital Services Act is now in effect (105 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theverge.com/23845672/eu-digital-services-act-explained</link>
            <guid>37271653</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 11:01:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theverge.com/23845672/eu-digital-services-act-explained">https://www.theverge.com/23845672/eu-digital-services-act-explained</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37271653">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>The European Union’s Digital Services Act (DSA) has officially gone into effect. Starting on August 25th, 2023, tech giants like Google, Facebook, Amazon, and more must comply with sweeping legislation that holds online platforms legally accountable for the content posted to them.</p><p>Even though this new law was passed in the EU, we’ll likely see far-reaching global effects as companies adjust their policies to comply. Here’s what exactly the DSA does and how the EU plans on enforcing it.</p><p><h3>What is the Digital Services Act?</h3></p><p>The overarching goal of the DSA is to foster safer online environments. Under the new rules, online platforms must implement ways to prevent and remove posts containing illegal goods, services, or content while simultaneously giving users the means to report this type of content.</p><p>Additionally, the DSA bans targeted advertising based on a person’s sexual orientation, religion, ethnicity, or political beliefs and puts restrictions on targeting ads to children. It also requires online platforms to provide more transparency on how their algorithms work. </p><p>The DSA carves out additional rules for what it considers “very large online platforms,” forcing them to give users the right to opt out of recommendation systems and profiling, share key data with researchers and authorities, cooperate with crisis response requirements, and perform external and independent auditing. </p><p>The European Parliament <a href="https://www.europarl.europa.eu/news/en/press-room/20220701IPR34364/digital-services-landmark-rules-adopted-for-a-safer-open-online-environment">passed the DSA in July 2022</a>. While the EU doesn’t require smaller companies to comply with the DSA just yet, it asked very large online platforms to comply four months after their designation as such, <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/commission/presscorner/detail/en/ip_23_2413">which occurred in April</a>.</p><p><h3>Which online platforms are affected?</h3></p><p>The EU considers very large online platforms (or very large online search engines) as those with over 45 million monthly users in the EU. So far, the EU has designed 19 platforms and search engines that fall into that category, including the following:</p><div><ul><li>Alibaba AliExpress</li><li>Amazon Store</li><li>Apple App Store</li><li>Booking.com</li><li>Facebook</li><li>Google Play</li><li>Google Maps</li><li>Google Shopping</li><li>Instagram</li><li>LinkedIn</li><li>Pinterest</li><li>Snapchat</li><li>TikTok</li><li>Twitter</li><li>Wikipedia</li><li>YouTube</li><li>Zalando</li><li>Bing</li><li>Google Search</li></ul></div><p>The EU will require each of these platforms to update their user numbers at least every six months. If a platform has less than 45 million monthly users for an entire year, they’ll be removed from the list.</p><p><h3>What are online platforms doing to comply?</h3></p><p>Many of these companies have already outlined the ways in which they’re going to comply with the DSA. Here’s a brief overview of the most notable ones.</p><p><h4>Google</h4></p><p>While Google says it already complies with some of the policies envisioned by the DSA, including the ability to give YouTube creators to appeal video removals and restrictions, <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/8/24/23845117/google-expanding-ads-transparency-center-comply-eu-dsa">Google announced that it’s expanding</a> its Ads Transparency Center to meet the requirements outlined by the legislation.</p><p>The company also committed to expanding data access to researchers to provide more information about “how Google Search, YouTube, Google Maps, Google Play and Shopping work in practice.” It will also improve its transparency reporting and analyze potential “risks of illegal content dissemination, or risks to fundamental rights, public health or civic discourse.”</p><p><h4>Meta</h4></p><p>Meta, the parent company of Facebook and Instagram, is working to expand its Ad Library, which currently compiles the ads shown on its platforms. The company will soon start displaying and archiving all the ads that target users in the EU while also including the parameters used to target the ads, as well as who was served the ad.</p><div><p>In June, Meta released <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/6/29/23778068/meta-facebook-instagram-social-media-algorithms-ai-transparency">a lengthy report about how its algorithm works</a> across Facebook and Instagram as part of its push toward transparency. It will also start <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/8/22/23841173/instagram-facebook-meta-chronological-feed-stories-reels-european-union-digital-services-act">allowing European users to view content chronologically on Reels</a>, Stories, and Search on both Facebook and Instagram — without being subject to its personalization engine.</p></div><p><h4>TikTok</h4></p><p>Similar to the measures Meta is rolling out, TikTok has also announced that it’s making its algorithm optional for users in the EU. When the algorithm is disabled, users will see videos from “both the places where they live and around the world” in their For You and Live feeds instead of videos based on personal interests. </p><p>It will also enable users to view content chronologically on their Following and Friends feeds. TikTok is making some changes to its advertising policies as well. For European users aged 13 to 17, TikTok will stop showing personalized ads based on their activity in the app.</p><p><h4>Snap</h4></p><p>Snapchat will also give users in the EU the option to opt out of personalized feeds on its Discover and Spotlight pages and <a href="https://help.snapchat.com/hc/en-us/articles/17338132910484-Personalisation-on-Snapchat?_ga=2.55027560.2100881955.1692971960-1974149196.1692971960">has also published reports</a> on how it ranks the posts on these feeds. The company has committed to providing users with more information about why their posts or account has been removed and will give them the tools they need to appeal the decision.</p><p>In addition, Snapchat will no longer serve personalized ads to European Snapchat users aged 13 to 17. It will also create an archive of targeted advertisements it shows in the EU and will give European Snapchat users over the age of 18 more control over the ads they see.</p><p><h3>What happens if these platforms don't comply?</h3></p><p>Online platforms that don’t comply with the DSA’s rules could see fines of up to 6 percent of their global turnover. <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/commission/presscorner/detail/en/QANDA_20_2348">According to the EU Commission</a>, the Digital Services Coordinator and the Commission&nbsp;will have the power to “require immediate actions where necessary to address very serious harms.” A platform continually refusing to comply could result in a temporary suspension in the EU.</p><p>The EU is already seeing some companies push back on the DSA. In July, Amazon filed a petition that asks the EU to reevaluate its classification as a very large online platform, claiming that it’s getting “unfairly singled out.” <a href="https://www.reuters.com/business/retail-consumer/zalando-sues-eu-commission-over-landmark-online-content-rules-2023-06-27/">German retailer Zalando also filed a lawsuit</a> against the EU Commission, similarly claiming that it doesn’t meet the definition of a very large online platform.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Clean mount lists in Linux (166 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://dbohdan.com/clean-mount-lists</link>
            <guid>37271611</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 10:54:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://dbohdan.com/clean-mount-lists">https://dbohdan.com/clean-mount-lists</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37271611">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<p>Default installations of Linux distributions mount more filesystems than they used to. This is because of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loop_device">loop devices</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cgroups">cgroups</a>, and, in Ubuntu, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snap_(software)">snaps</a>. As a result, the output from GNU df(1) as well as from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Util-linux">lsblk(8) and mount(8)</a> is more difficult to understand at a glance.</p>
<p>It is possible to make the output of these commands more readable by removing some of the “noise” devices. The following is a list of command arguments that remove irrelevant devices. After the list, I show how to replace the default commands in <a href="https://fishshell.com/">fish</a>. You can adapt the replacement script for other shells.</p>
<h2 id="contents">Contents</h2>
<nav id="TOC" role="doc-toc">
<ul>
<li>
<a href="#df">df</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href="#lsblk">lsblk</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href="#mount">mount</a>
<ul>
<li>
<a href="#include-list">Include list</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href="#exclude-list">Exclude list</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href="#fish">fish configuration</a>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<a href="#findmnt">findmnt instead of df and mount</a>
</li>
</ul>
</nav>
<h2 id="df">df</h2>
<p>GNU df(1) allows you to exclude <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tmpfs">tmpfs</a> with a simple option. In Ubuntu 22.04, this removes <code>/dev/shm</code>, <code>/run</code>, <code>/run/user/*</code>, and other mount points from its output. In an improvement from Ubuntu 20.04, df(1) is already <a href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/ubuntu/+source/apt/+bug/1756595">patched</a> to exclude <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SquashFS">Squashfs</a> (snaps).</p>
<p>Command:</p>
<pre><code>df -x tmpfs</code></pre>
<p>The improvement on my system is as follows:</p>
<pre><code>&gt; df | wc -l
25
&gt; df -x tmpfs | wc -l
19</code></pre>
<h2 id="lsblk">lsblk</h2>
<p>The command lsblk(8) can exclude devices by major device type. Snaps are loopback devices. According to <a href="https://www.kernel.org/doc/Documentation/admin-guide/devices.txt"><code>devices.txt</code></a> in the Linux kernel admin guide, the device type for loopback devices is 7.</p>
<p>Command:</p>
<pre><code>lsblk -e 7</code></pre>
<p>Improvement:</p>
<pre><code>&gt; lsblk | wc -l
56
&gt; lsblk -e 7 | wc -l
28</code></pre>
<h2 id="mount">mount</h2>
<p>We can simplify the output of GNU mount(8) by either excluding certain filesystem types or only including certain filesystem types.</p>
<h3 id="include-list">Include list</h3>
<p>Example command:</p>
<pre><code>mount -l -t btrfs,fat,exfat,ext2,ext4,iso9660,ntfs3,ufs,vfat,xfs,zfs</code></pre>
<p>Choose the type based on what filesystems you work with. For a list of supported filesystem type, look in <code>/proc/filesystems</code> and <code>/lib/modules/"$(uname -r)"/kernel/fs/</code>.</p>
<h3 id="exclude-list">Exclude list</h3>
<p>This is a little more involved, since mount(8) seems to lack a built-in “exclude” option. We can filter the output by the type column with awk.</p>
<p>Example command:</p>
<pre><code>mount | awk '$5 !~ /(autofs|binfmt_misc|bpf|cgroup2|configfs|debugfs|devpts|devtmpfs|fuse|hugetlbfs|mqueue|nfsd|nsfs|proc|pstore|ramfs|rpc_pipefs|securityfs|squashfs|sysfs|tmpfs|tracefs)/'</code></pre>
<p>The improvement with the exclude list is,</p>
<pre><code>&gt; mount | wc -l
77
&gt; mount | awk '...' | wc -l
19</code></pre>
<h3 id="fish">fish configuration</h3>
<p>This configuration script replaces commands with wrappers that use arguments from the previous sections by default. They only use the arguments if you do not give arguments of your own. To ignore the wrapper and run, for example, <code>mount</code> without any arguments, use <code>command mount</code> or <code>mount --</code>.</p>
<h4 id="installation">Installation</h4>
<pre><code>cd ~/.config/fish/conf.d/
curl -O https://dbohdan.com/clean-mount-lists.fish
less clean-mount-lists.fish  # Examine the code.</code></pre>
<h4 id="source">Source</h4>
<pre><code># clean-mount-lists 0.2.0
# Wrap commands to show cleaner mount lists in Linux.
# See https://dbohdan.com/clean-mount-lists
# License: MIT.
# https://dbohdan.mit-license.org/@2023

if status is-interactive; and test "$(uname)" = Linux
    if not set --query clean_mount_lists_exclude
        set --universal clean_mount_lists_exclude \
            autofs binfmt_misc bpf cgroup2 configfs debugfs devpts \
            devtmpfs fuse hugetlbfs mqueue nfsd nsfs proc pstore ramfs \
            rpc_pipefs securityfs squashfs sysfs tmpfs tracefs
    end

    function df --wraps df
        if test (count $argv) -eq 0
            # `-x` requires GNU df(1).
            command df -h -x tmpfs
        else
            command df $argv
        end
    end

    function mount --wraps mount
        if test (count $argv) -eq 0
            set --local re (string join '|' $clean_mount_lists_exclude)

            command mount | awk -v re=$re '$5 !~ re'
        else
            command mount $argv
        end
    end

    function lsblk --wraps lsblk
        if test (count $argv) -eq 0
            command lsblk -e 7
        else
            command lsblk $argv
        end
    end
end
</code></pre>
<h2 id="findmnt">findmnt instead of df and mount</h2>
<p><a href="https://linux.die.net/man/8/findmnt">findmnt(8)</a> from util-linux is an alternative to df(1) and mount(8) with better options for filtering. For example,</p>
<pre><code>findmnt --df --options rw --real</code></pre>
<p>produces output like <code>df -h</code>, but only for real and read-write filesystems.</p>
<p>Thanks to the <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37271611">HN discussion thread</a> for suggesting findmnt(8) and the <code>--options rw --real</code> invocation.</p>


          </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[As I get older, I just don't care about new technology (158 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://old.reddit.com/r/webdev/comments/1613yqj/as_i_get_older_i_just_dont_care_about_new/</link>
            <guid>37271401</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 10:19:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/webdev/comments/1613yqj/as_i_get_older_i_just_dont_care_about_new/">https://old.reddit.com/r/webdev/comments/1613yqj/as_i_get_older_i_just_dont_care_about_new/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37271401">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Maybe it's just the depressive phase I'm currently in, or if I'm just getting older and have less and less patience for things, but I just don't care about new technology.</p>

<p>Trying to do this Next 12 -&gt; Next 13 upgrade is not fun work for a production app, and on top of that there is this whole new "app" concept in Next... and I just don't care. I adopted Turborepo and regret that 10x over.</p>

<p>I want to build things for people. Not constantly update my tools because other developers are bored.</p>

<p>(please take this all with a grain of salt. I'm tired and depressed and my coworkers are useless)</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[NES Emulator in Common Lisp (2016) (126 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/samanthadoran/potential-disco</link>
            <guid>37271269</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 10:01:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/samanthadoran/potential-disco">https://github.com/samanthadoran/potential-disco</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37271269">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-target="readme-toc.content">
            <article itemprop="text"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">potential-disco</h2>
<p dir="auto">Trying to emulate the NES again in Common Lisp</p>
<p dir="auto">TODO: Other mapppers besides NROM<br>
TODO: Audio<br>
TODO: Run at proper speed instead of just letting it go however fast it pleases.<br>
TODO: Write more idiomatic Lisp</p>
<h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Examples</h4>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/44db2860bd2f8ad6ab26a51e4bf860a822f4e85ab3e9077f1168e520a2e60c6a/68747470733a2f2f692e6779617a6f2e636f6d2f35623862313631626537343238313235356534386236336462343561373238352e676966"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/44db2860bd2f8ad6ab26a51e4bf860a822f4e85ab3e9077f1168e520a2e60c6a/68747470733a2f2f692e6779617a6f2e636f6d2f35623862313631626537343238313235356534386236336462343561373238352e676966" alt="Super Mario Bros" data-animated-image="" data-canonical-src="https://i.gyazo.com/5b8b161be74281255e48b63db45a7285.gif"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/2d3447d9e5b3ad4174558df1047905c4c0558694704cd9e015e9a5f123d09e4c/68747470733a2f2f692e6779617a6f2e636f6d2f64396166346236663332613162363739306265343636323763323033353330362e676966"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/2d3447d9e5b3ad4174558df1047905c4c0558694704cd9e015e9a5f123d09e4c/68747470733a2f2f692e6779617a6f2e636f6d2f64396166346236663332613162363739306265343636323763323033353330362e676966" alt="Galaga" data-animated-image="" data-canonical-src="https://i.gyazo.com/d9af4b6f32a1b6790be46627c2035306.gif"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/ed8c3793ee37feefbef576d326c9d5d29edcd59846609841a43a2de90cf7c474/68747470733a2f2f692e6779617a6f2e636f6d2f65646663316463343234356365306266626266393961663865383438373065302e676966"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/ed8c3793ee37feefbef576d326c9d5d29edcd59846609841a43a2de90cf7c474/68747470733a2f2f692e6779617a6f2e636f6d2f65646663316463343234356365306266626266393961663865383438373065302e676966" alt="Donkey Kong" data-animated-image="" data-canonical-src="https://i.gyazo.com/edfc1dc4245ce0bfbbf99af8e84870e0.gif"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/1ae921f93fa87a01b0ef491f96a4f881f2110f8df0f784b412f9324768d80fb2/68747470733a2f2f692e6779617a6f2e636f6d2f65663231636436356466373236373636323633376337333561613430366264652e676966"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/1ae921f93fa87a01b0ef491f96a4f881f2110f8df0f784b412f9324768d80fb2/68747470733a2f2f692e6779617a6f2e636f6d2f65663231636436356466373236373636323633376337333561613430366264652e676966" alt="Volley Ball" data-animated-image="" data-canonical-src="https://i.gyazo.com/ef21cd65df7267662637c735aa406bde.gif"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/5b102ced9fb1c697db6b3c919ece21454a21445396600a911a2c572cd72929a8/68747470733a2f2f692e6779617a6f2e636f6d2f66366630373637663338303633383862393966623334333139303430366237312e706e67"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/5b102ced9fb1c697db6b3c919ece21454a21445396600a911a2c572cd72929a8/68747470733a2f2f692e6779617a6f2e636f6d2f66366630373637663338303633383862393966623334333139303430366237312e706e67" alt="NesTest" data-canonical-src="https://i.gyazo.com/f6f0767f3806388b99fb343190406b71.png"></a></p>
<h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h4>
<p dir="auto">In your favorite common lisp repl (I haven't tested outside of
sbcl), just run</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="(asdf:load-system :console)
(nes:setup-and-emulate path-to-rom)"><pre><code>(asdf:load-system :console)
(nes:setup-and-emulate path-to-rom)
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Where path to rom is a string<br>
The controls map to..
Start: Tab<br>
Select: Grave<br>
Left, Down, Right, Up: W, A, S, D<br>
A, B: Left Arrow, Down Arrow<br>
I'm sorry, they aren't re-mappable yet. =(</p>
</article>
          </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[66% of Americans say they want extended European-style vacation policies at work (129 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cnbc.com/2023/08/25/66percent-of-americans-say-they-want-extended-european-style-vacation-policies-at-work.html</link>
            <guid>37270881</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 08:47:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/08/25/66percent-of-americans-say-they-want-extended-european-style-vacation-policies-at-work.html">https://www.cnbc.com/2023/08/25/66percent-of-americans-say-they-want-extended-european-style-vacation-policies-at-work.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37270881">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="MakeItRegularArticle-ArticleBody-5" data-module="ArticleBody" data-test="articleBody-1" data-analytics="MakeItRegularArticle-articleBody-5-1"><div><p>In many parts of Europe, it's common for workers to <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/08/18/9-european-countries-where-workers-get-more-than-a-month-of-vacation.html">take off weeks at a time</a>, especially during the summer. Envious Americans say it's time for the U.S. to follow suit.</p><p>Some 66% of U.S. workers say companies should adopt extended vacation policies, like a month off in August, in their workplaces, according to a <a href="https://pro.morningconsult.com/analysis/us-sentiment-four-day-work-week" target="_blank">Morning Consult survey</a> of 1,047 U.S. adults.</p><p>While the average American is lucky to get <a href="https://www.bls.gov/charts/employee-benefits/paid-leave-sick-vacation-days-by-service-requirement.htm" target="_blank">11 vacation days</a> from their employer each year, workers in the European Union are guaranteed&nbsp;at least<a href="https://cepr.net/images/stories/reports/no-vacation-nation-2019-05.pdf#page=5" target="_blank">&nbsp;20 working days of paid vacation</a> due to the European Union Working Time Directive, which passed in the early 1990s. Several countries offer even more by law before paid public holidays come into play, which can add up to more than a month of business days in vacation time per year.</p><p>But not all U.S. workers say they'd welcome longer vacation policies: 21% of Americans say companies should not adopt extended PTO policies in their workplace, while the remaining respondents say they don't know or don't have an opinion.</p><p>The survey didn't specifically address the concerns of those against extended time off work, says Ellyn Briggs, brands analyst at Morning Consult. However, in responses to a separate question about people's attitudes toward a four-day workweek, roughly half of American workers say they'd use their extra time to catch up on work or learn a work-related skill.</p><p>Separately, 41% of U.S. workers report being more satisfied in their career today than before, which is nearly double the share of those who feel less satisfied in their career today, according to Morning Consult data. "These data points suggest a portion of employed U.S. adults generally enjoy their work and seek new opportunities to improve upon it," Briggs says. "Extended periods off may hold little appeal for this group."</p><p>That being said, generous vacations aren't the only European practice that Americans say should become the norm here: 65% of U.S. workers would like to see extended lunch breaks, 62% want workweeks shorter than 40 hours, and 51% support slower employee response time outside of work hours, similar to many labor laws common throughout Europe.</p><p><em><strong>Want to be smarter and more successful with your money, work &amp; life?&nbsp;</strong></em><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/makeitnewsletter/?__source=makeit%7Cnlarticleteaser"><em><strong>Sign up for our new newsletter</strong></em></a><em><strong>!</strong></em></p><p><em>Get CNBC's free&nbsp;</em><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/buffett-whitepaper/">Warren Buffett Guide to Investing</a><em>, which distills the billionaire's No. 1 best piece of advice for regular investors, do's and don'ts, and three key investing principles into a clear and simple guidebook.</em></p><p><em><strong>Check out: </strong></em><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/07/09/how-a-norway-28-year-old-prepares-for-required-3-week-summer-vacation.html"><em><strong>28-year-old social media manager in Norway is required to take 3 weeks of vacation in summer</strong></em></a></p></div><div id="Placeholder-ArticleBody-Video-107268190" data-test="VideoPlaceHolder" role="region" tabindex="0" data-vilynx-id="7000306846" aria-labelledby="Placeholder-ArticleBody-Video-107268190"><p><img src="https://image.cnbcfm.com/api/v1/image/107268257-mm-torres-still.jpg?v=1688993102&amp;w=750&amp;h=422&amp;vtcrop=y" alt="How a Gen Z couple earning $43,000 in Nashville, Tennessee spends their money"><span></span><span><span data-test="PlayButton"></span></span></p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Uncle Sam accuses SpaceX of not considering asylees and refugees for employment (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theregister.com/2023/08/25/spacex_discrimination_lawsuit/</link>
            <guid>37270634</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 07:41:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/08/25/spacex_discrimination_lawsuit/">https://www.theregister.com/2023/08/25/spacex_discrimination_lawsuit/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37270634">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="body">
<p>Fresh from blowing up a small portion of Texas with Starship, SpaceX is once again being forced to focus on more earthly matters, like discriminatory hiring practices, in a lawsuit brought by the US Department of Justice.</p>
<p>The <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.justice.gov/media/1311656/dl?inline">complaint</a> [PDF] filed Wednesday through the Office of the Chief Administrative Hearing Officer, part of the department's Executive Office for Immigration Review, accuses SpaceX of discriminating against asylees and refugees and "routinely" discouraging people with this citizenship status against even applying for roles at the company.</p>
<p>We're all used to CEO Elon Musk saying things of dubious veracity as the owner of <span>Twitter</span> X, but in this case the DoJ claims that statements from both SpaceX and its boss were so wrong they broke federal law, specifically the Immigration and Nationality Act (INA). The rules stipulate that asylees and refugees cannot be discriminated against for their citizenship status in the process of applying for job.</p>

    

<p>SpaceX fell foul of the law, the DoJ alleges, because it repeatedly and incorrectly claimed it could only hire US citizens and lawful permanent residents, thereby discouraging asylees and refugees from even bothering. Between September 2018 and May 2022, it was accused of tracking applicants by citizen status and marking asylees and refugees as ineligible for employment under the International Traffic in Arms Regulations (ITAR).</p>

        


        

<p>Explaining why this was way off-piste, the DoJ said in a <a target="_blank" href="https://www.justice.gov/opa/pr/justice-department-sues-spacex-discriminating-against-asylees-and-refugees-hiring">statement</a> yesterday: "Under these regulations, asylees, refugees, lawful permanent residents, US citizens and US nationals working at US companies can access export-controlled items without authorization from the US government. Therefore, these laws do not require SpaceX to treat asylees and refugees differently than US citizens or green card holders."</p>
<p>The DoJ added that asylees and refugees "undergo thorough vetting by the United States government. Under the INA, employers cannot discriminate against them in hiring, unless a law, regulation, executive order or government contract requires the employer to do so. In this instance, no law, regulation, executive order or government contract required or permitted SpaceX to engage in the widespread discrimination against asylees or refugees that the department's investigation found."</p>

        

<p>The complaint alleges that SpaceX's incorrect stance went right to the top, highlighting a number of times where Musk said that the working at the company was off-limits to anyone who wasn't a US citizen or lacked a green card.</p>
<p>On June 16, 2020, Musk posted on Twitter: "US law requires at least a green card to be hired at SpaceX, as rockets are considered advanced weapons technology."</p>
<p>It also said that during an international space conference in September 2016, "SpaceX's CEO stated the SpaceX had to comply with ITAR, which meant that a normal work visa is insufficient to work at SpaceX unless the company can obtain 'special permission from the Secretary of Defense or Secretary of State.' He then added that SpaceX is 'not allowed' to hire people who don't have a 'green card' and that 'unless [you] can somehow get a green card, we are legally prevented from hiring anyone.'"</p>
<ul>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/08/23/spacex_counter_omnispace/">SpaceX, T-Mobile US phone service will interfere with ours, claims rival</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/07/06/spacex_denies_environmental_lawsuit/">SpaceX says, sure, Starship blew up but you can forget about the rest of that lawsuit</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/05/10/vast_trip_space_station/">This upstart is selling tickets for a SpaceX trip to the world's first private space station</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/04/26/us_faa_starship/">US watchdog grounds SpaceX Starship after that explosion</a></li>
</ul>
<p>In an online video dating all the way back to 2012, the complaint quoted Musk as saying: "It's quite difficult for us to employ people that don't have a green card because of US ITAR rules." He added that his "first advice" to non-US citizens hoping for a job at SpaceX would be: "Do anything you can to get a green card."</p>
<p>The complaint also claimed that SpaceX's Vice President of Human Resources said on an online chat forum in 2016: "To comply with US government space technology export regulations including ITAR, applicants must generally be US citizens or lawful permanent residents."</p>

        

<p>The DoJ points out that not everyone working at SpaceX is a rocket scientist, also employing "welders, cooks, crane operators, baristas and dishwashers... The jobs at issue in the lawsuit are not limited to those that require advanced degrees."</p>
<p>Assistant Attorney General Kristen Clarke of the Justice Department's Civil Rights Division said: "Our investigation found that SpaceX failed to fairly consider or hire asylees and refugees because of their citizenship status and imposed what amounted to a ban on their hire regardless of their qualification, in violation of federal law.</p>
<p>"Our investigation also found that SpaceX recruiters and high-level officials took actions that actively discouraged asylees and refugees from seeking work opportunities at the company.</p>
<p>"Asylees and refugees have overcome many obstacles in their lives, and unlawful employment discrimination based on their citizenship status should not be one of them. Through this lawsuit we will hold SpaceX accountable for its illegal employment practices and seek relief that allows asylees and refugees to fairly compete for job opportunities and contribute their talents to SpaceX's workforce."</p>
<p>The suit seeks "fair consideration and back pay for asylees and refugees who were deterred or denied employment at SpaceX due to the alleged discrimination," civil penalties to be determined in court, and policy changes to ensure the company does not flout the INA again.</p>
<p>It could be that SpaceX has been erring on the side caution when it comes to ITAR because it has a number of lucrative contracts with NASA and the US Department of Defense. Accidental violation of export control laws and regulations could indeed put such contracts at risk.</p>
<p>However, by law, asylees and refugees should never fall under these restrictions, thus the DoJ believes SpaceX has, for lack of a better term, done goofed.</p>
<p><em>The Register</em> has asked SpaceX to comment. ®</p>                                
                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Companies That Union-Bust Must Now Automatically Recognize Union, NLRB Rules (147 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.vice.com/en/article/dy3xej/companies-that-union-bust-must-now-automatically-recognize-union-nlrb-rules</link>
            <guid>37269909</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 04:18:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.vice.com/en/article/dy3xej/companies-that-union-bust-must-now-automatically-recognize-union-nlrb-rules">https://www.vice.com/en/article/dy3xej/companies-that-union-bust-must-now-automatically-recognize-union-nlrb-rules</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37269909">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>NLRB sign. Image Credit: Getty Images</p></div><div data-component="BodyComponentRenderer"><p><span data-component="TextBlock"><p>The National Labor Relations Board issued a ruling on Friday that <a href="https://www.nlrb.gov/news-outreach/news-story/board-issues-decision-announcing-new-framework-for-union-representation" target="_blank"><span>changes the framework</span></a> for unionizations, making it easier for workers to organize and harder for companies to fight back against them.&nbsp;</p></span><span data-component="TextBlock"><p>The new process comes as part of a decision in the case between Cemex Construction Materials Pacific, LLC and the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, where the Board found that the employer had committed over 20 “instances of objectionable or unlawful misconduct” between the filing of the union election petition and the election itself, intending to dissuade workers from organizing.&nbsp;</p></span></p><p><span data-component="TextBlock"><p>The decision requires that if a majority of workers ask a company for voluntary recognition of their union, the company must either immediately recognize them or promptly file a petition asking the Board to hold a union election.&nbsp;</p></span><span data-component="TextBlock"><p>“However, if an employer who seeks an election commits any unfair labor practice that would require setting aside the election, the petition will be dismissed, and—rather than re-running the election—the Board will order the employer to recognize and bargain with the union,” an <a href="https://www.nlrb.gov/news-outreach/news-story/board-issues-decision-announcing-new-framework-for-union-representation" target="_blank"><span>NLRB press release stated</span></a>. If the company neither recognizes the union nor files a petition, the Board will issue a bargaining order forcing the company to come to the table.&nbsp;</p></span></p><p><span data-component="TextBlock"><p>“This is a very important ruling that will help workers to be able to unionize free of coercion, especially at companies like Trader Joe's, Starbucks and Amazon,” said Seth Goldstein, a partner at Julien, Mirer, Singla and Goldstein, who has represented workers at those companies attempting to unionize and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/07/21/opinion/starbucks-union-strikes-labor-movement.html" target="_blank"><span>facing union-busting efforts</span></a>. “This has been the law of the land for 80 years, so it really goes back to what should have been all along.”&nbsp;</p></span><span></span><span data-component="TextBlock"><p>Goldstein was referring to a 1949 Supreme Court decision known as <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2022/06/07/the-lie-that-helped-kill-the-labor-movement-00037459" target="_blank"><span>Joy Silk</span></a>, which stated that an employer had to voluntarily recognize and bargain with a majority of workers who wanted a union, and could only contest the unionization if it had “good faith doubt” about the union’s majority status. Joy Silk was <a href="https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/395/575/" target="_blank"><span>abandoned in 1969</span></a> in favor of giving companies more leverage in the unionization process.&nbsp;</p></span><span data-component="TextBlock"><p>But NLRB General Counsel Jennifer Abruzzo issued a memo earlier this year <a href="https://www.jdsupra.com/legalnews/nlrb-general-counsel-calls-for-4375993/" target="_blank"><span>demanding that the Board revive Joy Silk</span></a>, something that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2022/06/07/the-lie-that-helped-kill-the-labor-movement-00037459" target="_blank"><span>labor activists have been fighting</span></a> for since it was overturned. The Cemex decision issued on Friday is a partial step in that direction.&nbsp;</p></span><span data-component="TextBlock"><p>“What this new decision does is, it's a compromise,” said Eric Blanc, an assistant professor of labor studies at Rutgers University. “It's not a return to ‘card check,’” the unionization process in the 1930s and ‘40s that said if a majority of workers signed cards stating they wanted a union, the company was obligated to recognize and bargain with them—which Joy Silk had upheld.&nbsp;</p></span><span data-component="TextBlock"><p>“If there's intense illegal union busting, as is very often the case, the NLRB can force the employers to immediately recognize the union rather than have to go through another union election,” Blanc said. “But it's far short of what many union organizers were hoping for. By not making ‘card check’ the norm, [it] still opens up the process to all sorts of legal appeals and delays, which is ultimately one of the main tactics of employers—to delay the union first and then hold things up in endless appeals. This unfortunately doesn't avoid that dynamic, but it does get the NLRB more powers to require employers to recognize unions, and that should be at least a partial deterrent on employers’ willingness to break the law.”&nbsp;</p></span><span data-component="TextBlock"><p>Goldstein said that despite the incomplete return to Joy Silk, he thought it was a “big step forward.”&nbsp;</p></span><span data-component="TextBlock"><p>“The Board is taking a proactive stance, that unfair labor violations are going to be challenged,” he said. “We haven’t seen this kind of activism from the Board since the 1940s. I think this is going to really help workers.”</p></span></p></div><div><p><h3>ORIGINAL REPORTING ON EVERYTHING THAT MATTERS IN YOUR INBOX.</h3></p><p>By signing up, you agree to the<!-- --> <a href="https://vice-web-statics-cdn.vice.com/privacy-policy/en_us/page/terms-of-use.html">Terms of Use</a> <!-- -->and<!-- --> <a href="https://vice-web-statics-cdn.vice.com/privacy-policy/en_us/page/privacy-policy.html">Privacy Policy</a> <!-- -->&amp; to receive electronic communications from Vice Media Group, which may include marketing promotions, advertisements and sponsored content.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[FFmpeg Explorer (189 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ffmpeg.lav.io</link>
            <guid>37269425</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 02:33:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ffmpeg.lav.io">https://ffmpeg.lav.io</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37269425">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>