<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 12:30:30 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I want to wash my car. The car wash is 50 meters away. Should I walk or drive? (653 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://mastodon.world/@knowmadd/116072773118828295</link>
            <guid>47031580</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 06:31:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://mastodon.world/@knowmadd/116072773118828295">https://mastodon.world/@knowmadd/116072773118828295</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47031580">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[JavaScript-heavy approaches are not compatible with long-term performance goals (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://sgom.es/posts/2026-02-13-js-heavy-approaches-are-not-compatible-with-long-term-performance-goals/</link>
            <guid>47029339</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 00:26:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://sgom.es/posts/2026-02-13-js-heavy-approaches-are-not-compatible-with-long-term-performance-goals/">https://sgom.es/posts/2026-02-13-js-heavy-approaches-are-not-compatible-with-long-term-performance-goals/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47029339">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
    
<p>This post is a (very long) opinion piece, albeit one that I hope is somewhat substantiated by the accompanying anecdotes. The TL;DR is that in my experience the title is a correct statement the vast majority of the time, and we should favour more server-centric approaches instead, when possible.</p>
<details>
<summary>What I mean by “JS-heavy approaches“</summary>

<p>I use this term to refer to any approach that relies on shipping large quantities of JS to the browser, for the browser to execute as an intrinsic part of using the web app, often in the critical path. These sorts of approaches are usually associated with Single-page Applications (SPAs), but do unfortunately pop up in Multi-page Applications (MPAs) as well.</p>
</details>

<h2 id="background">Background</h2>
<h3 id="my-experience">My experience</h3>
<p>In case you don’t know me, hi! 👋 I work full-time on web performance at <a href="https://automattic.com/">Automattic</a>, as part of a small PerfOps team whose mission is to improve performance across the various things we build or work on as a company. Our team also builds and maintains our company’s performance monitoring infrastructure, but the majority of our time is spent finding and fixing performance issues across our various stacks, all the way from optimising DB queries to fixing janky CSS animations.</p>
<p>Personally, I specialize on the browser side of things. As part of this work, I have had more than my share of debugging sessions for loading performance issues, runtime performance problems, bundle size increases, framework-specific issues like expensive re-renders in <code>React</code>, etc., and there are some underlying root causes I’ve seen over and over again. These problems are not necessarily insurmountable, but they do add up to reveal some important gaps and outright falsehoolds in the narrative about the “modern web development approach” that we’ve been sold over the years.</p>
<h3 id="caveats">Caveats</h3>
<p>I don’t think I’ll necessarily bring any groundbreaking revelations to the table, nor do I come with a large corpus of data to back anything up as the unquestionable truth. This is all based on my own experience, and may not apply to what any given project is doing, particularly if it’s a small web app maintained by a focused, dedicated team.</p>
<p>Also note that I’ll be jumping between different aspects of web performance throughout the post, without much thought. That’s because while they’re all distinct, they’re all important! You don’t want to have an application that takes forever to load, any more than one that is sluggish at rendering the characters the user is typing, or one that has a disruptive delay on in-app navigations.</p>
<h3 id="the-pitch-and-the-reality-of-frameworks">The pitch and the reality of frameworks</h3>
<p>With the caveats out of the way, let’s look at the main topic: the long-term performance characteristics of “modern” development, which most of the time involves frameworks of some sort, like <code>React</code>.</p>
<details>
<summary>Yes, <code>React</code> is a framework</summary>

<p>I know there’s some discussion on whether <code>React</code> is a framework or not, with some folks — notably, the authors and maintainers — insisting on calling it a library. I don’t know why they do it, but it’s frankly wrong, as far as agreed-upon terms and shared vocabulary go.</p>
<p>In Computer Science, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_framework">commonly accepted distinction between the two</a> is that a library is something that your code calls into, while a framework is something that you relinquish control unto, so that <strong>it</strong> calls <strong>your code</strong> instead, at the appropriate time. That is, a framework works through Inversion of Control, and a library does not.</p>
<p>By this definition, <code>React</code> is a framework, because an idiomatic <code>React</code> application overwhelmingly consists of code that gets called by <code>React</code>, and lives under its control.</p>
</details>

<p>Frameworks like <code>React</code> are often perceived as accelerators, or even as the only sensible way to do web development. There’s this notion that a more “modern” stack (read: JS-heavy, where the JS ends up running on the user’s browser) allows you to be more agile, release more often with fewer bugs, make code more maintainable, and ultimately launch better sites. In short, the claim is that this approach will offer huge improvements to developer experience, and that these DevEx benefits will trickle down to the user.</p>
<p>But over the years, this narrative has proven to be unrealistic, at best. In reality, for any decently sized JS-heavy project, you should expect that what you build will be slower than advertised, it will keep getting slower over time while it sees ongoing work, and it will take more effort to develop and especially to maintain than what you were led to believe, with as many bugs as any other approach.</p>
<p>Where it comes to performance, the important thing to note is that a JS-heavy approach (and particularly one based on <code>React</code> &amp; friends) will most likely not be a good starting point; in fact, it will probably prove to be a performance minefield that you will need to keep revisiting, risking a detonation with every new commit.</p>
<h3 id="roadmap">Roadmap</h3>
<p>In this post, I’ll start by looking at some of the underlying causes for the most common categories of problems I’ve seen, and follow that up with mitigation strategies you can adopt to prevent some of them.</p>
<p>After that, I’ll reflect on whether JS-heavy approaches are worth it, whether performance is optional, and then explore server-centric development as an alternative, and why it tends to do better.</p>
<p>I’ll then finish up with my plea to our industry to change the way we do things.</p>
<h2 id="the-problems">The problems</h2>
<h3 id="dependencies-are-expensive">Dependencies are expensive</h3>
<p>One of the more immediate problems is that JS-heavy development approaches often deeply rely on the <code>npm</code> global package repository for runtime JS (i.e., the JS that the user’s browser will run). While this can be a great shortcut for getting something out the door quickly, it can come with some less-than-obvious costs, often measured in bytes on your bundle.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Note:</strong> while bundle size isn’t a metric that your users experience directly, most of the time it correlates strongly with ones that do (such as the various paint metrics), particularly in scenarios where large portions of your application get loaded as part of the critical path.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It’s unfortunately common to pull large packages into your bundle, such as huge libraries for time and timezone management, extensive collections of JS utility functions, and entire component systems to kickstart your UI building. Some of these packages are well-designed, and built to be small and modular, so that you only pay for what you use. Many of them are not, however, and end up being monolithic, or close to it, due to their design (e.g. fluent APIs like <code>moment</code>), due to heavily reusing themselves internally (e.g. <code>lodash-es</code>), or due to failing to account for what bundlers need in order to perform effective tree-shaking.</p>
<p>Large dependencies are often bad enough on their own, but sadly, it gets worse: many of these packages grow larger over time. Which means that not only do we carry a ball and chain around, it keeps getting heavier!</p>
<ul>
<li>For example, <code>moment</code> has had a 10% increase in size over the last 5 years. Not outrageous, but lots of small increases like this across a number of dependencies do add up.</li>
<li><code>react-dom</code> has steadily grown over the years, and going from v18 to v19 alone results in a 33% increase in bundle size for a basic Hello World app.</li>
</ul>
<p>These increases are often hidden under the hood, and not something you’d easily come across, as most tools don’t give you this information by default:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>npm</code> won’t tell you how large a package is when you install or update it.</li>
<li>Many bundlers don’t show your bundle size at the end of a build (although some of the more recent ones like <code>Vite</code> or <code>Rsbuild</code>, do).</li>
<li>Your IDE or editor won’t tell you how much an import will add to your bundle unless you’ve specifically added a plugin for this.</li>
<li>If you have a tool like <code>dependabot</code> set up on your repo, it will helpfully point out that new versions are available and even prepare the upgrade PRs for you — but it won’t warn you that the new version is 20% larger.</li>
</ul>
<p>And to make matters worse, sticking to the previous version of a package is often not an option, because the new version includes security or bug fixes, or because another package is forcing you to upgrade a shared dependency.</p>
<p>But let’s say you were mindful when picking your dependencies, and you carefully vet each version upgrade not to balloon your bundle size. You’re also cautious about not adding too much code yourself. Does that mean your web app will be fast?</p>
<h3 id="its-easy-to-make-it-slow">It’s easy to make it slow</h3>
<p>A robust, developer-friendly system should make it easier to do the right thing than the wrong thing. It’s usually not feasible to make mistakes outright impossible, but it’s generally enough to ensure that following the wrong approach involves extra friction.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, where it comes to performance, JS-heavy development approaches often behave the opposite way: they make it easier to do the wrong thing than the right thing.</p>
<p>I’ll focus on <code>React</code> and <code>Redux</code> in some of my examples since that is what I have the most experience with, but much of this applies to other frameworks and to JS-heavy approaches in general. All of the following are issues I came across multiple times, in separate codebases:</p>
<ul>
<li>It’s often much easier to add things on a top-level component’s context and reuse them throughout the app, than it is to add them only where needed. But doing this means you’re paying the cost before (and whether) you need it.</li>
<li>It’s much simpler to add something as a synchronous top-level import and force it to be present on every code path, than it is to load it conditionally and deal with the resulting asynchronicity.</li>
<li>Setting up a bundler to produce one monolithic bundle is trivial, whereas splitting things up per route with shared bundles for the common bits often involves understanding and writing some complex configuration.</li>
<li>It’s less work to build a <code>Redux</code> reducer that blindly rewrites an entire subtree and leads to unnecessary rerenders, than it is to have it check to see if changes are needed.</li>
<li>It’s much more straightforward to write a <code>Redux</code> selector that blindly runs a <code>.map()</code> to generate a new array everytime, than it is to memoise the results correctly.</li>
<li>If you forget to use memoisation on a single prop, your component might now rerender every time something innocuous happens. And if it’s a root-adjacent component, that means potentially a large portion of your render tree needs to be recalculated.</li>
<li>It’s a lot less work to load your entire application state (i.e., all reducers) in the critical path, than it is to split things up so that only the relevant portions of state get loaded on each route.</li>
<li>It’s often much easier to wrap each of your SVG icons in JSX than it is to set things up to load them from an external <code>.svg</code> file with SVG <code>&lt;use&gt;</code>.</li>
</ul>
<p>This is compounded by the fact that developers are often taught the wrong approach by tutorials or other documentation resources. In an effort to make things easier to understand and learn, the code is kept simple — and as we’ve seen, the straightforward strategy is often the wrong one, at least where performance is concerned. Sometimes the docs go on to mention that they’re showing a simplified snippet of code and production code might need to be different. Sometimes they don’t.</p>
<p>These approaches are <strong>fragile</strong>, and make it easy for anyone to break performance at any time.</p>
<p>Which leads me to the next point. How likely is it that an initially fast JS-heavy app remains fast throughout development?</p>
<h3 id="its-hard-to-keep-it-fast">It’s hard to keep it fast</h3>
<p>If a system is fragile, it means that it even if it starts out solid, it will be hard to keep it intact as time goes by.</p>
<p>The unfortunate reality is that some of these performance issues are watershed moments, in that a single wrong move can effectively render all your previous efforts to avoid a given class of performance problems moot:</p>
<ul>
<li>If you’ve carefully made every usage of a library conditional and asynchronous, it only takes a single static import somewhere in the critical path for the library to now need to be parsed, compiled, and executed before your site gets a chance to render.</li>
<li>If you’ve painstakingly removed every instance of a large monolithic library like <code>moment</code>, it only takes a single import for it to come back in its entirety.</li>
<li>If you’ve isolated an endpoint from as much of the rest of the application as possible, it might only take a single import in that endpoint or in the shared core for a huge amount of code to pour back in.</li>
<li>It only takes a single, poorly-coded <code>Redux</code> selector or reducer to potentially affect performance on every action.</li>
</ul>
<p>These problems may be obvious to you as an experienced developer, but they might not be to someone who joined the team recently, or a coder whose experience mostly involves other frameworks or libraries. <strong>Any system that relies on developer discipline</strong> to maintain performance (or any other characteristic, really) <strong>is a fragile thing that requires constant vigilance</strong>, particularly for large teams or projects.</p>
<p>So while it may be easy to resolve the situation by rolling back the change or fixing the new code, the reality is that if you’re not carefully monitoring your web app, you might miss the problem entirely and unwittingly leave things in a worse state than before, despite all the work you had done to prevent the problem in the first place.</p>
<p>I’ve seen it happen time and time again over the years; some kinds of performance improvement efforts don’t tend to last for very long, because it’s just so easy to break things again.</p>
<p><em>“Okay”</em>, you might think, <em>“but these frameworks and friends claim to be focused on developer experience, which means they surely must come with some great tools for debugging performance issues too, right?”</em></p>
<p>Unfortunately, that’s often not the case.</p>
<h3 id="its-hard-to-debug-performance-issues">It’s hard to debug performance issues</h3>
<p>Performance is never easy to debug, even at the best of times.</p>
<p>That said, over the years, browser engines have put an incredible amount of effort into building robust web development tooling. Browser Dev Tools pretty much let you peer into every aspect of your site’s performance, and even into what the browser itself is doing while it loads and renders your site. They show you easy to understand waterfalls for resource loading, and helpful flamecharts for JS execution and rendering. They can throttle CPU and network, and run detailed profiles that combine all sorts of information. They can even now analyse those profiles for you, to point out problems and offer suggestions! These tools easily match and often exceed their server-side counterparts, and they’re a wonderful perk that we rely on daily.</p>
<p>Which is why it’s incredibly frustrating when frameworks like <code>React</code>, which again ostensibly pride themselves on being developer-friendly, throw all of that away to build their own Dev Tools. Poorly.</p>
<p>This is not the case with every framework, mind you; for instance, <code>Preact</code> takes the right approach, in <strong>enhancing</strong> the existing browser DevTools with framework-specific information. So if you run a browser profile on your <code>Preact</code> web app with their Dev Tools enabled, you’ll get some helpful markers added to the native browser profile, indicating when a component renders, for example. This lets you make sense of what’s happening in the browser layer as a result of the framework layer, so you can more quickly zero in on the code that’s seemingly causing a lot of garbage collection passes, or the component that’s triggering layout refreshes at an inconvenient time.</p>
<figure>
  <p><img loading="lazy" src="https://sgom.es/posts/2026-02-13-js-heavy-approaches-are-not-compatible-with-long-term-performance-goals/preact-dev-tools.jpg" alt="Preact-level timing information gets added to browser profiles, and is available to built-in functionality like the aggregate table of where time was spent. Great stuff! 👍">
  </p>
  <figcaption><code>Preact</code>-level timing information gets added to browser profiles, and is available to built-in functionality like the aggregate table of where time was spent. Great stuff! 👍</figcaption>
</figure>





<p>But that’s not the case with <code>React</code>: it has its own tools, which are entirely separate. You can run a <code>React</code> profile, but it doesn’t create a browser profile to go with it, and you have no way of combining <code>React</code> information with the JS sampling information from the browser to get a complete picture of where time is being spent. This means that often, even if you manage to figure out that the problem is in, say, a particular component’s commit to the DOM, you’re unable to understand why. You might need to resort to reproducing the problem twice (once for each profiler), carefully comparing the two separate profiles, and performing some leaps of logic.</p>
<figure>
  <p><img loading="lazy" src="https://sgom.es/posts/2026-02-13-js-heavy-approaches-are-not-compatible-with-long-term-performance-goals/react-dev-tools.jpg" alt="With React DevTools, browser profiles don’t include any React-level timing information 😞">
  </p>
  <figcaption>With <code>React</code> DevTools, browser profiles don’t include any <code>React</code>-level timing information 😞</figcaption>
</figure>





<p>In addition, the <code>React</code> DevTools profiler can be hard to use (from a UI point of view), and is missing essential information, like an aggregate view of where time was spent.</p>
<p>And this is not just a problem with <code>React</code> Dev Tools. The debugging information you need is often not available, and even when it is, you’re frequently forced to jump through extra hoops:</p>
<ul>
<li>In a server-side rendered <code>React</code> app, if your hydration fails and your application needs to render from scratch (a performance problem, in that you’re losing the SSR optimisation), the error messages are often a useless <code>Did not expect server HTML to contain a &lt;div&gt; in &lt;main&gt;.</code> or similar, even when running a debug build. Good luck finding that <code>&lt;div&gt;</code>!</li>
<li><code>Redux</code> Dev Tools don’t include any mechanism to help you find and debug slow reducers or selectors.</li>
<li>Debugging performance issues often requires you to find out about and switch to the “profiling“ build of your frameworks, if they exist at all. If you use a debug build instead, your timings won’t be meaningful, leading you to spend time trying to fix phantom issues; and if you use a production build, you’ll be missing the symbols that help you make sense of what’s happening.</li>
<li>To my knowledge, none of the bundlers default to building a map of what’s inside your bundle, for help with bundle size debugging if needed. Most of the time you need to find out about, install, and configure a separate plugin manually.</li>
</ul>
<p>Now, don’t get me wrong: the web platform can be a challenging performance environment on its own, with plenty of quirks to be aware of. But frameworks rarely address those definitively (if at all), and in fact make debugging performance <strong>harder</strong> than the baseline, because they add additional layers of abstraction.</p>
<p>The bigger the mismatch between a framework’s programming model and the underlying platform’s, the bigger the opportunity for complicated performance problems to arise in the interface between the two. So it sure would be nice if they would at least help with that part!</p>
<h2 id="mitigating-the-problems">Mitigating the problems</h2>
<p>So now that we know the problems and how easy it is for them to show up, what can we do about it? If you’re stuck building a JS-heavy client-side app, don’t despair! There are still actions you can take to improve your chances of making it faster, and keeping it from getting too slow over time.</p>
<p>Be warned, though: in my experience, you shouldn’t expect a consistently performant app, even if you follow all of these suggestions. But following them will help with stopping the bleeding and keeping things from getting too bad without you noticing.</p>
<h3 id="before-you-start">Before you start</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Make sure everyone is on the same page about performance.</strong> You might need to convince some non-technical folks by showing them industry studies that link page performance to business metrics like conversions. As for developers, you may need to remind them that their development devices and connections aren’t a good benchmark for “good enough”, since most users <a href="https://infrequently.org/2025/11/performance-inequality-gap-2026/">will unfortunately be relying on something significantly worse</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Define your performance budget.</strong> While there are some standard numbers across the industry, such as the thresholds Google recommends for <a href="https://web.dev/articles/vitals#core-web-vitals">its Core Web Vitals metrics</a>, not every project is the same. Depending on your audience and use-case, you may need to be more (or less) ambitious in your goals, or pick different metrics entirely. The key thing is to define them ahead of time, and stick to them during development, avoiding the temptation to move the goalposts to fit the outcome.</li>
<li><strong>Carefully choose your architecture and tech stack.</strong> Now’s a good time to figure out whether your client-side application should have a server-side aspect to it, to speed up initial renders. This is especially important if you have API calls in your critical path, and doubly so if they’re sequential in any way. Also, take the opportunity to research what’s out there, and pick the frameworks, libraries, and general approach that best fit your needs.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="early-in-development">Early in development</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Set up code splitting.</strong> A lot of development environments give you this essentially for free, but many others unfortunately do not.<ul>
<li>Make sure that your bundler outputs multiple chunks, that are split in a reasonable way (e.g. per route).</li>
<li>Ensure that bundles for other routes don’t get loaded, or if they do, that it happens lazily, very late into the page loading process (e.g. after the <code>load</code> event). This is to ensure that they don’t compete with critical path resources for network and CPU availability.</li>
<li>Make sure you have things set up so that shared chunks are automatically created, with code that’s common to most bundles. There’s a balance to be found between fewer, larger chunks with more unused code for any given route, and having a multitude of tiny little chunks that all need to be fetched. Thankfully, that balance has been made easier to reach since we got widespread HTTP/2 usage, but do be mindful that there are still performance benefits to be had in keeping things down to fewer critical path resources.</li>
<li>Alternatively, you can create the shared bundles by hand, but keep in mind that this is an additional maintenance cost.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Set up bundle size tracking.</strong> While bundle size isn’t a particularly meaningful metric, it’s an easy one to track, and one that can serve as an early warning to look for actual performance issues.<ul>
<li>Have your bundler output bundle size when you build locally (e.g. <code>npm run build</code>), as a first step.</li>
<li>Once you have a CI (Continuous Integration) environment, add a build size action to it. For something like GitHub Actions, you can find pre-made ones that are fairly easy to set up (e.g. <a href="https://github.com/preactjs/compressed-size-action"><code>compressed-size-action</code></a>).</li>
<li>Once that’s in place, make sure that your CI adds a comment to pull requests where a large increase is detected. The earlier a developer learns about the problem, the better the chances they’ll fix it.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Set up linting.</strong> There aren’t many kinds of performance issues (or potential ones) that can be detected like this, but it’s hugely beneficial for those that can, since developers find out about them early in their work.<ul>
<li>Set up a list of “forbidden” imports, like <code>lodash</code> if you’re using <code>lodash-es</code>, as well as any packages you may have had trouble with in the past and want to avoid entirely.</li>
<li>Set up rules for packages that include both modular and monolithic imports, so that the monolithic ones are banned.</li>
<li>If you have a package or a portion of your application that you want to be loaded dynamically (i.e., with a dynamic <code>import()</code>), set up a rule to prevent static imports.</li>
<li>Keep updating the list as time goes by. Whenever you fix a problem or complete a performance-related migration away from something, consider adding new rules to help prevent the problem from resurfacing.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Set up performance tracking.</strong> You can use a tool like <code>puppeteer</code> or <code>playwright</code> to perform full page loads and in-app navigations, and measure how long things take. This is easily an order of magnitude more difficult than the previous suggestions, but it’s the best way I’m aware of to get somewhat meaningful performance numbers during development.<ul>
<li>Start by setting things up for running tests locally, on demand (e.g. <code>npm run test:perf</code>). Make sure you test both initial loading performance and in-app navigations, and that you use both network and CPU throttling when doing so.</li>
<li>Once that’s working, move it to CI, and run it on every pull request.</li>
<li>The tricky part here is making the numbers reliable, which can be incredibly difficult, depending on your CI environment. For some of them, it may actually be a bit of a lost cause, because they don’t give you any way to achieve reasonable stability.<ul>
<li>On the test suite side of things, you can try calibrating performance by running a pre-test CPU benchmark to determine an appropriate CPU throttling multiplier, as well as ensuring that only a single test runs at a time.</li>
<li>On the CI side of things, you can try to reduce the amount of virtualisation (ideally, to zero), and other concurrent work.</li>
<li>On the hardware side of things, if that’s an option, you can go as far as trying to force a fixed amount of RAM (when virtualising), as well as a fixed CPU speed.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Once you manage to make it stable, with reasonably reliable numbers, have your CI add comments to pull requests whenever a large shift is detected.</li>
<li>If you can, make sure to keep historical data, so that you can visualise long-term trends. Small increases often go by unnoticed (particularly if your data is noisy), but they do add up over time.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="once-you-launch">Once you launch</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Add RUM (Real User Monitoring) performance tracking.</strong> This is the gold standard in performance monitoring, since it reflects what your real users are experiencing, regardless of what your expectations were.<ul>
<li>If your web app is large enough to be featured in the <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/docs/crux">CrUX</a> dataset, start by looking at those numbers. They’re fairly limited for client-side apps, and they won’t give you much in the way of debugging information, but they’ll help you calibrate your expectations with reality.</li>
<li>Choose a RUM vendor and integrate their client code into your app, or roll out your own system. The latter obviously involves more work, but it might help you tailor things better to your application, so that you have the metrics that make the most sense to you (e.g. when the first image rendered, if you’re building an image-focused site).</li>
<li>Consider including debug information in your app. While you don’t want your RUM code to grow huge, and you probably don’t want to collect lots of data for every user action, there may be some useful info around the metrics themselves that will help with debugging. For example, you could complement the Largest Contentful Paint value with ancillary information like what type of element the LCP target was, the external resource it related to (if any), or the portion of the UI it came from.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Collect performance feedback.</strong> If you have a support team, make sure they know who to reach for complaints about performance. Depending on your product, you may find that most users are non-technical and unable to communicate the problem clearly, but you’ll get a general idea of what the pain points are, and where to target your improvement work.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="are-js-heavy-approaches-worth-it">Are JS-heavy approaches worth it?</h2>
<p>If that seems like a lot of overhead to you, we’re definitely in agreement. It’s a lot of running to stay in the same place, and it’s probably not even going to be such a great spot to stick around in anyway.</p>
<p>Implementing all of these mitigations will take a significant amount of time, and keeping the ongoing vigilance will force you to either have a dedicated team that actively tries to counter these effects, or to somehow educate all your developers on all of the pitfalls, and convince them to keep this level of vigilance themselves, constantly.</p>
<p>This level of overhead may be feasible if your organisation is really large or well-funded, but it’s less doable for everyone else.</p>
<p>Given all of this cost and the prospect of bad performance, at some point we should probably look at the benefits we’re getting in return for these JS-heavy approaches. We’ve talked about the promises, but what is reality like?</p>
<h3 id="is-react-worth-it">Is React worth it?</h3>
<p>I’m going to make things a bit more concrete for this section, and talk about <code>React</code> and its ecosystem specifically. They’re dominant, they’ve been around for a while, and they’re what I’ve had the most SPA experience with, so they’re the best examples I’ve got.</p>
<p>I do get the appeal of building in <code>React</code>, really, I do. It’s a fun programming model, and there are inherent organisational benefits to the component paradigm it pushes so hard. There’s also a lot you can reuse out there, and maybe that gives you the confidence that you’ll spend less time in the initial implementation, leaving you longer for improvements and polish.</p>
<p>And that’s fair, you probably won’t find a larger ecosystem of components, libraries, and complementary frameworks, ready to use! But beyond generally poor performance, they come with another pretty big caveat: they don’t seem to last very long. In my experience, there isn’t much in the way of stability in the <code>React</code> ecosystem, or even the JS ecosystem as a whole. Perhaps that’s changing lately, but historically, I’ve seen multiple large applications end up rewriting massive portions of their code after a while, not because of product reasons, but because of dependencies:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>React</code> hooks were meant to be an alternative to class-based components, but their adoption by the broader ecosystem forced substantial rewrites, as keeping class-based components (which can’t use hooks directly) in your code became less feasible.</li>
<li>The concurrency changes in <code>React</code> 18 forced many components to be rewritten to avoid practices that were formerly fine.</li>
<li>The deprecation of Enzyme forced projects to rewrite their entire test suites.</li>
<li>Some long-lived projects went through multiple state management architectures, as the favoured approach changed over the years, from prop drilling, to <code>Flux</code> or <code>MobX</code>, to <code>Redux</code>, to contexts, etc.</li>
</ul>
<p>Of course, I’m a developer as well, and I understand that tradeoffs are needed. When we’re building a project, there are a lot of different concerns that need to be carefully weighed so that it actually launches at some point, and in a half-decent state. So it may well be justifiable to accept all of the JS ecosystem instability, as well as some later code churn, and to view them as a reasonable price to pay for getting off the ground quickly. That’s fair.</p>
<p>That still leaves us with the issue of performance, though.</p>
<h2 id="is-performance-optional">Is performance optional?</h2>
<p>So what about performance, then? If we’re dealing with code churn, new features, and bugfixes, then we probably won’t have a lot of time for it, since as we saw, it comes with a lot of overhead in JS-heavy apps.</p>
<p>So maybe we decide that performance isn’t <strong>that</strong> important to us, and we’re better off forgoing some of the vigilance and monitoring above. If we get to it, great! If we don’t, the app will still work, and that’s what matters. And that can be a perfectly reasonable decision; less work is a good thing, as is not having to worry about performance!</p>
<p>But in the end, someone else will be making a decision: our audience. They’ll be choosing whether to use our site or not, and maybe whether to pay for it. That choice will involve how quickly they can get things done, and how “good” our site feels to use, which is non-trivially impacted by how fast it is for them.</p>
<p>In all likelihood, an unmonitored JS-heavy web app will not work well for all of our users. It’ll work great for some, sure, those with fast devices and connections that are similar to the typical developer’s, but chances are our audience is much broader than that, with all kinds of devices and connections. And so:</p>
<ul>
<li>Do we want to exclude entire classes of folks who can’t afford a high-end phone / laptop and a fast connection, and make them look at long loading screens?</li>
<li>Are we okay with having large portions of our audience see our sites through the lens of a sluggish experience, where every action makes them question whether they tapped the wrong thing or <em>“the site is just being slow again“</em>?</li>
<li>Do we want to keep sending megabytes of JavaScript down the wire (that probably doesn’t even get cached for very long because of a rapid release cycle), and inflating a pay-as-you-go customer’s bills with <strong>our code</strong> instead of <strong>their content</strong>?</li>
</ul>
<p>Is it worth it to give up on providing a great experience to a broad range of users? Opinions will vary, I’m sure, but my answer would be an emphatic “no”. We can do better than that.</p>
<h2 id="the-real-alternative-server-side-work">The real alternative: server-side work</h2>
<p>So as we’ve seen, there’s a whole host of problems when we build our web apps primarily out of JS. Most of them stem from just how expensive JS can be to run on users’ devices, and how easy it is to accidentally arrive at a place where the level of required work exceeds a device’s ability to do it in an acceptable timeframe.</p>
<details>
<summary>Just why is JS so expensive?</summary>

<p>Not all bytes are created equal, and JS is byte-for-byte the heaviest resource for a browser to handle. Parsing and compiling it are both expensive, with its complex syntax and type flexibility. When it finally does run, it mostly does so on a single thread, and can therefore only take advantage of a single core in your device’s CPU or SoC — and if it happens to be a little core in a heterogenous core architecture, it might be very slow indeed.</p>
</details>

<p>The obvious alternative is to shift all or much of this work to the server, so that even if it’s still JS (e.g. <code>nodejs</code>), it can take advantage of more powerful CPUs, dramatically higher power budgets (no battery life to worry about!), longer-lived bytecode caches, and better multi-core utilisation.</p>
<p>A server-centric architecture serves browsers with ready-to-use page content, instead of a recipe and some ingredients that allow them to build that content themselves, at their own expense.</p>
<h3 id="server-side-rendering-with-frameworks">Server-side rendering with frameworks</h3>
<p>However, not all server-side work is equally effective. While some of these JS-heavy architectures do involve a server-side rendering aspect to them, it’s often really only a band-aid, and a poorly-fitting one at that, which negates a lot of the benefits I was talking about.</p>
<p>The best example of this is probably monolithic hydration, where you render the whole page on the server, and ship both the initial markup and the application code to the user. The idea there is that the browser can use the markup to show the page quickly, without waiting for the JS, which only “hydrates“ the page with interactivity afterwards.</p>
<p>While this approach can definitely help with initial paint times, you’re still potentially shipping megabytes of JS down the wire to an unwitting user’s browser. That browser is still going to have to fetch, parse, compile, and run all that code on boot, which may end up resulting in a significant delay between the application being visible and actually being usable. So even if you solve the paint issue, there’s still the interactivity one — and you may have unwittingly made that one worse, if you’re now shipping even more JS down the wire to hydrate that initial state!</p>
<p>Partial hydration strategies can help lessen these costs, but you still need to be mindful of just how much JS is going to run at any one time and keep a watchful eye on that, which means one more thing to worry about and track.</p>
<h3 id="server-centric-models">Server-centric models</h3>
<p>The real alternative, as I see it, is to switch to a server-centric programming model, with the majority of the code intended never to leave the server. It can still be JS, too, if that’s what you prefer! Just not JS you will ever need to ship down the wire to someone’s device.</p>
<p>The server is a much more predictable and scalable environment, and more importantly, you have some level of control over it. Performance logging and debugging can be a lot easier since the bulk of the code is running on machines you manage in some way, not a vast array of wildly heterogenous computing devices entirely outside of your control. And most of the time you don’t need to worry about code size at all!</p>
<p>In a HTML-based approach, if your processing power and your content distribution strategy are sufficient for your needs, it becomes somewhat irrelevant if the user is running a high-end desktop computer with a blazingly fast CPU, or a bargain bin phone with an SoC that costs less than that desktop’s CPU cooler. Your web app will demand a lot less of your users’ devices and connections, providing a great experience to everyone.</p>
<h3 id="some-examples-of-server-centric-approaches">Some examples of server-centric approaches</h3>
<p>The obvious one is simple full-page navigation, which is the foundational architecture of the web. It has a proven track record of consistently hitting performance goals when paired with solid, globally-distributed hosting infrastructure that reduces network latency. Following this approach doesn’t mean that you can’t use JS; but you should lean towards keeping it as a sprinkle on top for some interactive bits here and there, not the engine the entire thing runs on. You can use isolated JS scripts, or other approaches like progressively-enhanced web components, and you can use as much or as little of a build process as you like to transform between source code and production code.</p>
<p>Beyond that, we’ve had various kinds of JS-lite architectures over the years that still do a great job, and have only been getting better. For example, the approach of substituting parts of the page with a new server-rendered HTML payload (made popular by e.g. <code>turbolinks</code>) still works really well, and now even has some level of native support with the <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/View_Transition_API">View Transitions API</a>. HTML-enhancing approaches like <code>htmx</code> or WordPress’s Interactivity API are another kind of JS-lite approach, and can also serve as the foundation for many different kinds of projects.</p>
<h3 id="server-centric-isnt-a-good-fit-for-everything">Server-centric isn’t a good fit for everything</h3>
<p>Of course, we need to be realistic: not all web apps can be built like this, and some of them only really make sense as primarily client-side affairs. A highly interactive application like an editor is one such example, with server roundtrips ideally kept to a minimum, so that the user can focus on what they’re writing and not have to worry about a delay every time they click on something. They might even be willing to tolerate a longer page loading time than usual, if they see it as enough of a “destination”, and if their upcoming task (e.g. writing a post) is going to take long enough to justify the wait.</p>
<p>But even in the context of an entirely client-side application, there are many different approaches you could take, and in 2026, <code>React</code> is honestly one of the least compelling ones. It’s big, it’s slow, it’s riddled with performance pitfalls, and it’s not even fresh and exciting. It does have a huge ecosystem you can rely on, which is a really important point — albeit one that suggests that if that’s the deciding factor for you, you might be prioritising development speed above your users’ needs.</p>
<p>If you really need to go client-side, give one of the other frameworks a try! The framework runtimes are often smaller, they use finer-grained reactivity (which helps with modularity and UI responsiveness), and some of them use fundamentally different approaches that get away from the performance minefield of having to diff large trees all the time. A few have been around for a while, too, so you’re not necessarily relying on unproven dependencies.</p>
<h2 id="lets-change-the-way-we-do-things">Let’s change the way we do things</h2>
<p>To sum things up: in my experience, JS-heavy web apps usually start in a poor place, performance-wise, and they tend to get worse over time. Mitigating this requires significant overhead that is expensive to set up and maintain, and will usually still lead to performance degradation anyway — albeit at a slower rate.</p>
<p>The touted benefits are also not as obvious to me as they’re made out to be. Do frameworks actually make us more agile, and lead to a better overall user experience, or do they just trade one set of problems for another? Do they actually save us development time and effort in the long run, or does dependency-driven code churn in lasting projects undo much of that? I can’t answer any of this definitively, but I do feel that there’s a bit of a blind spot around the costs we’re paying, especially long-term.</p>
<p>Despite this, the industry perception seems to be that JS-heavy approaches are “fine”, performance-wise, and that the benefits are worth it. I find this overly optimistic, as none of the JS-heavy applications I’ve looked at in my work has ever managed to consistently hit good performance over time. Selection bias? Maybe, but <a href="https://infrequently.org/2025/11/performance-inequality-gap-2026/#content-trends">the wider landscape doesn’t provide much of a counterpoint to my anecdotes</a>.</p>
<p>I really do believe that the amount of effort needed to maintain a good level of performance in a healthy, long-running JS-heavy project is so high that it won’t be sustainable long term, in most cases. At some point, you’ll likely learn that your optimisation work was undone by unrelated changes, despite the monitoring you set up. Even if the developer that introduced the problem realised it, when deadlines clash with performance goals, the deadlines typically win.</p>
<p>This is why I’m a strong advocate for more robust systems, that make it harder to break performance in the first place.</p>
<p>Now, don’t get me wrong: building things server-side isn’t a panacea, nor is it the best fit for all projects. It’s certainly possible to build something slow on the server, and performance degradation can occur there as well. All systems have their performance challenges, and the server is no exception.</p>
<p>But maintaining a good level of performance does tend to be easier on the server, from what I’ve seen, because you’re keeping the expensive work where it makes sense: the powerful dedicated servers you own, manage, or rent; and not the slow, underpowered devices that your audience have access to. It’s also often much easier to track and log what’s happening on the server, which will greatly help with finding and fixing performance bugs, and even application logic ones. And there’s a lot less to send over the wire too, if your application code never leaves the server.</p>
<p>It’s time to stop lying to ourselves that JS-heavy client-side approaches are <strong>the way</strong> to develop a web app nowadays. We really should stop reflexively reaching for JS frameworks for everything we build, and to stop basing our architecture decisions on the stack we’re most familiar with.</p>
<p>Many use-cases are simply better suited to a server-side, HTML-centric approach, because the performance tradeoffs more closely align with the expected usage — and that really should be a part of the decision process. Instead of habitually <code>npm install</code>ing some framework boilerplate, we should take a moment to consider if we shouldn’t instead be building a multi-page application on the server.</p>
<p>Will client-side rendering really be helping, or will the user be stuck waiting for API calls anyway?</p>
<p>Will the user offset the upfront loading wait by later saving time on a number of in-app navigations or actions, or will they <a href="https://infrequently.org/2025/11/performance-inequality-gap-2026/#are-spas-working%3F">leave once they’ve done the couple of things they meant to</a>?</p>
<p>Will they get any benefit at all, as we borrow their device to do the work we could be handling on our servers?</p>
<p>We really owe it to our users to do better as an industry, because right now we’re often building the way we want to, not the way they need us to.</p>


  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Peter Thiel: 2,436 emails with Epstein from 2014 to 2019 (172 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://jmail.world/wiki/peter-thiel</link>
            <guid>47028369</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 22:29:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://jmail.world/wiki/peter-thiel">https://jmail.world/wiki/peter-thiel</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47028369">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><!--$?--><template id="B:1"></template><!--/$--><title>Peter Thiel — The Jmail Encyclopedia</title><meta name="description" content="Peter Thiel — The Jmail Encyclopedia. Sourced from 2,429 emails across 1,345 threads in the Jmail archive."><meta name="author" content="Luke Igel"><meta name="author" content="Riley Walz"><meta name="creator" content="Luke Igel &amp; Riley Walz"><meta name="publisher" content="Kino AI"><meta name="robots" content="index, follow"><meta name="googlebot" content="index, follow"><meta property="og:title" content="Peter Thiel — The Jmail Encyclopedia"><meta property="og:description" content="Peter Thiel — The Jmail Encyclopedia. Sourced from 2,429 emails across 1,345 threads in the Jmail archive."><meta property="og:url" content="https://jmail.world/wiki/peter-thiel"><meta property="og:site_name" content="Jmail"><meta property="og:image" content="https://jmail.world/api/og/jwiki/peter-thiel"><meta property="og:image:width" content="1200"><meta property="og:image:height" content="630"><meta property="og:image:alt" content="Peter Thiel — The Jmail Encyclopedia"><meta property="og:type" content="article"><meta name="twitter:card" content="summary_large_image"><meta name="twitter:site" content="@jmailarchive"><meta name="twitter:title" content="Peter Thiel — The Jmail Encyclopedia"><meta name="twitter:description" content="Peter Thiel — The Jmail Encyclopedia. Sourced from 2,429 emails across 1,345 threads in the Jmail archive."><meta name="twitter:image" content="https://jmail.world/api/og/jwiki/peter-thiel"></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Magnus Carlsen Wins the Freestyle (Chess960) World Championship (307 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.fide.com/magnus-carlsen-wins-2026-fide-freestyle-world-championship/</link>
            <guid>47028227</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 22:17:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.fide.com/magnus-carlsen-wins-2026-fide-freestyle-world-championship/">https://www.fide.com/magnus-carlsen-wins-2026-fide-freestyle-world-championship/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47028227">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-id="377e8e4" data-element_type="widget" data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="43662" data-elementor-post-type="post" data-widget_type="theme-post-content.default">
				<div data-id="815ffae" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="image.default">
				<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1000" height="605" src="https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03.jpg 1000w, https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-300x182.jpg 300w, https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-768x465.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px">															</p>
				</div>
				<div data-id="13c5e19" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
									<p><strong>Magnus Carlsen</strong> (Norway) is the 2026 FIDE Freestyle Chess World Champion. A draw in the fourth and final game against <strong>Fabiano Caruana</strong> (USA) was enough to seal a 2.5–1.5 match victory in Weissenhaus, Germany.</p><p><span>&nbsp;</span><span>The decisive moment came in game three. Carlsen won from a dead lost position, turning the match in his favor. Entering the final game, he needed only a draw and achieved it in an equal endgame after Caruana missed late chances to mount a comeback. Both finalists qualified for the 2027 FIDE Freestyle Chess World Championship.</span></p>								</div>
				<div data-id="3d4b435" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="image.default">
				<p><img decoding="async" width="1000" height="661" src="https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Carlsen-Caruana.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Carlsen-Caruana.jpg 1000w, https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Carlsen-Caruana-300x198.jpg 300w, https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Carlsen-Caruana-768x508.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px">															</p>
				</div>
				<div data-id="cb9359c" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
									<p>The 2026 tournament marks the first official FIDE-recognized Freestyle Chess World Championship. World number one Carlsen had previously attempted to win the FIDE Fischer Random World Championship without success. In Weissenhaus, he secured the official FIDE Freestyle Chess title – his 21st world title across formats.</p><p><span>&nbsp;</span><span>In the match for third place, <strong>Nodirbek Abdusattorov</strong> (Uzbekistan) defeated <strong>Vincent Keymer</strong> (Germany). Abdusattorov secured the match by drawing a winning position in the final game, also ensuring qualification for the 2027 championship.</span></p>								</div>
				<div data-id="27aa71b" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="image.default">
				<p><img decoding="async" width="1000" height="670" src="https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Abdusattorov-Keymer.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Abdusattorov-Keymer.jpg 1000w, https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Abdusattorov-Keymer-300x201.jpg 300w, https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Abdusattorov-Keymer-768x515.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px">															</p>
				</div>
				<div data-id="55d317e" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
									<p><span><strong>Hans Niemann</strong> (USA) took fifth place with a 2–0 victory over <strong>Arjun Erigaisi</strong> (India), while <strong>Levon Aronian</strong> (USA) won his Armageddon against <strong>Javokhir Sindarov</strong> (Uzbekistan) to take seventh place.</span></p><p>In the women’s exhibition match, <strong>Bibisara Assaubayeva</strong> (Kazakhstan) prevailed over <strong>Alexandra Kosteniuk</strong> (Switzerland) after winning the third game and drawing the fourth.</p>								</div>
				<div data-id="b1752d4" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="image.default">
				<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1000" height="670" src="https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Kosteniuk-Assaubayeva.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Kosteniuk-Assaubayeva.jpg 1000w, https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Kosteniuk-Assaubayeva-300x201.jpg 300w, https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Kosteniuk-Assaubayeva-768x515.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px">															</p>
				</div>
				<div data-id="20a76b5" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
									<p><strong>Key facts</strong>:</p><ul><li><span>⁠</span><span>⁠<span>Location: Weissenhaus, Germany</span></span></li><li><span><span>⁠</span><span>Dates: February 13–15, 2026</span></span></li><li><span><span>⁠</span><span>Prize fund: $300,000</span></span></li><li><span><span>⁠</span><span>Winner’s prize: $100,000</span></span></li><li><span><span>⁠</span><span>Top three qualify for 2027</span></span></li></ul><p><span>&nbsp;</span><span>A full report is available <a href="https://www.freestyle-chess.com/news/magnus-carlsen-wins-fide-freestyle-chess-world-championship/"><strong>[HERE]</strong></a>.</span></p><p><strong>Written by Till Behrend</strong></p><p><strong>Photos: Lennart Ootes and Steve Bonhage / Freestyle Chess</strong></p><p>Official website:&nbsp;<strong><a href="https://www.freestyle-chess.com/">https://www.freestyle-chess.com/</a></strong></p>								</div>
					</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I’m joining OpenAI (1128 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://steipete.me/posts/2026/openclaw</link>
            <guid>47028013</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 21:54:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://steipete.me/posts/2026/openclaw">https://steipete.me/posts/2026/openclaw</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47028013">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="article" data-astro-cid-vj4tpspi="">  <p><strong>tl;dr: I’m joining OpenAI to work on bringing agents to everyone. <a href="https://openclaw.ai/">OpenClaw</a> will move to a foundation and stay open and independent.</strong></p>
<p>The last month was a whirlwind, never would I have expected that my playground project would create such waves. The internet got weird again, and it’s been incredibly fun to see how my work inspired so many people around the world.</p>
<p>There’s an endless array of possibilities that opened up for me, countless people trying to push me into various directions, giving me advice, asking how they can invest or what I will do. Saying it’s overwhelming is an understatement.</p>
<p>When I started exploring AI, my goal was to have fun and inspire people. And here we are, the lobster is taking over the world. My next mission is to build an agent that even my mum can use. That’ll need a much broader change, a lot more thought on how to do it safely, and access to the very latest models and research.</p>
<p>Yes, I could totally see how OpenClaw could become a huge company. And no, it’s not really exciting for me. I’m a builder at heart. I did the whole creating-a-company game already, poured 13 years of my life into it and learned a lot. What I want is to change the world, not build a large company and teaming up with OpenAI is the fastest way to bring this to everyone.</p>
<p>I spent last week in San Francisco talking with the major labs, getting access to people and unreleased research, and it’s been inspiring on all fronts. I want to thank all the folks I talked to this week and am thankful for the opportunities.</p>
<p>It’s always been important to me that OpenClaw stays open source and given the freedom to flourish. Ultimately, I felt OpenAI was the best place to continue pushing on my vision and expand its reach. The more I talked with the people there, the clearer it became that we both share the same vision.</p>
<p>The community around OpenClaw is something magical and OpenAI has made strong commitments to enable me to dedicate my time to it and already sponsors the project. To get this into a proper structure I’m working on making it a foundation. It will stay a place for thinkers, hackers and people that want a way to own their data, with the goal of supporting even more models and companies.</p>
<p>Personally I’m super excited to join OpenAI, be part of the frontier of AI research and development, and continue building with all of you.</p>
<p>The claw is the law.</p>
<p><img src="https://steipete.me/assets/img/2026/openclaw/clawcon.jpg" alt="ClawCon" loading="lazy"></p> </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[State Attorneys General Want to Tie Online Access to ID (135 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://reclaimthenet.org/40-attorneys-general-back-ids-online-safety-act</link>
            <guid>47026848</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 19:49:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://reclaimthenet.org/40-attorneys-general-back-ids-online-safety-act">https://reclaimthenet.org/40-attorneys-general-back-ids-online-safety-act</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47026848">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-id="7eda0c13" data-element_type="widget" data-e-type="widget" data-widget_type="theme-post-content.default">
					<p>A bloc of 40 state and territorial attorneys general is urging Congress to adopt the Senate’s version of the controversial <a href="https://reclaimthenet.org/kids-online-safety-act-kosa-privacy-surveillance-concerns-2025">Kids Online Safety Act</a>, positioning it as the stronger regulatory instrument and rejecting the House companion as insufficient.</p>
<p>The Act would kill online anonymity and tie online activity and speech to a real-world identity.</p>
<p>Acting through the National Association of Attorneys General, the coalition sent a letter to congressional leadership endorsing S. 1748 and opposing H.R. 6484.</p>
<p><strong>We obtained a copy of the letter for you <a href="https://docs.reclaimthenet.org/ag-letter-supporting-senate-kosa-february-10-2026.pdf">here</a>.</strong></p><div data-id="eb333a5" data-element_type="container" data-e-type="container" data-settings="{&quot;background_background&quot;:&quot;classic&quot;}" data-elementor-type="section" data-elementor-id="235992" data-elementor-post-type="elementor_library">
				<div data-id="4678215" data-element_type="widget" data-e-type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<p>Reclaim Your Digital Freedom.</p>
				</div>
				<div data-id="fe169cc" data-element_type="widget" data-e-type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<p>Get unfiltered coverage of surveillance, censorship, and the technology threatening your civil liberties.</p>
				</div>
				
					</div>

<p>Their request centers on structural differences between the bills. The Senate proposal would create a federally enforceable “Duty of Care” requiring covered platforms to mitigate defined harms to minors.</p>
<p>Enforcement authority would rest with the Federal Trade Commission, which could investigate and sue companies that fail to prevent minors from encountering content deemed to cause “harm to minors.”</p>
<p>That framework would require regulators to evaluate internal content moderation systems, recommendation algorithms, and safety controls.</p>
<p>S. 1748 also directs the Secretary of Commerce, the FTC, and the Federal Communications Commission to study “the most technologically feasible methods and options for developing systems to verify age at the device or operating system level.”</p>
<p>This language moves beyond platform-level age gates and toward infrastructure embedded directly into hardware or operating systems.</p>
<p>Age verification at that layer would not function without some form of credentialing. Device-level verification would likely depend on digital identity checks tied to government-issued identification, third-party age verification vendors, or persistent account authentication systems.</p>
<p>That means users could be required to submit identifying information before accessing broad categories of lawful online speech.&nbsp;Anonymous browsing depends on the ability to access content without linking identity credentials to activity.</p>
<p>A device-level age verification architecture would establish identity checkpoints upstream of content access, creating records that age was verified and potentially associating that verification with a persistent device or account.</p>
<p>Even if content is not stored, the existence of a verified identity token tied to access creates a paper trail.</p>
<p>Constitutional questions follow. The Supreme Court has repeatedly recognized anonymous speech as protected under the First Amendment. Mandating identity verification before accessing lawful speech raises prior restraint and overbreadth concerns, particularly where the definition of “harm to minors” extends into categories that are legal for adults.</p>
<p>Courts have struck down earlier <a href="https://reclaimthenet.org/texas-app-store-accountability-act-blocked-federal-judge-first-amendment">efforts to impose age verification requirements</a> for online content on First Amendment grounds, citing the chilling effect on lawful expression and adult access.</p>
<p>Despite this history, state officials continue to advocate for broader age verification regimes. Several states have enacted or proposed laws requiring age checks for social media or adult content sites, often triggering litigation over compelled identification and privacy burdens.</p>
<p>The coalition’s letter suggests that state attorneys general are not retreating from that position and are instead seeking federal backing.</p>
<p>The attorneys general argue that social media companies deliberately design products that draw in underage users and monetize their personal data through targeted advertising. They contend that companies have not adequately disclosed addictive features or mental health risks and point to evidence suggesting firms are aware of adverse consequences for minors.</p>
<p>Multiple state offices have already filed lawsuits or opened investigations against Meta and TikTok, alleging “harm” to young users.</p>
<p>At the same time, the coalition objects to provisions in H.R. 6484 that would limit state authority. The House bill contains broader federal preemption language, which could restrict states from enforcing parallel or more stringent requirements. The attorneys general warn that this would curb their ability to pursue emerging online harms under state law. They also fault the House proposal for relying on company-maintained “reasonable policies, practices, and procedures” rather than imposing a statutory Duty of Care.</p>
<p>The Senate approach couples enforceable federal standards with preserved state enforcement power.</p>
<p>The coalition calls on the United States House of Representatives to align with the Senate framework, expand the list of enumerated harms to include even suicide, eating disorders, compulsive use, mental health harms, and financial harms, and ensure that states retain authority to act alongside federal regulators. The measure has bipartisan sponsorship in the United States Senate.</p>
<p>The policy direction is clear. Federal agencies would study device-level age verification systems, the FTC would police compliance with harm mitigation duties, and states would continue to pursue parallel litigation. Those mechanisms would reshape how platforms design their systems and how users access speech.</p>
<p>Whether framed as child protection or platform accountability, the architecture contemplated by S. 1748 would move identity verification closer to the heart of internet access.</p>
<p>Once age checks are embedded at the operating system level, the boundary between verifying age and verifying identity becomes difficult to maintain.</p>
<p>The internet would be changed forever.</p>
<!-- CONTENT END 1 -->
				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Microgpt is a GPT you can visualize in the browser (207 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://microgpt.boratto.ca</link>
            <guid>47026186</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 18:40:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://microgpt.boratto.ca">https://microgpt.boratto.ca</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47026186">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Editor's Note: Retraction of article containing fabricated quotations (267 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/staff/2026/02/editors-note-retraction-of-article-containing-fabricated-quotations/</link>
            <guid>47026071</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 18:29:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/staff/2026/02/editors-note-retraction-of-article-containing-fabricated-quotations/">https://arstechnica.com/staff/2026/02/editors-note-retraction-of-article-containing-fabricated-quotations/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47026071">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                      
                      
          <p>On Friday afternoon, Ars Technica published <a href="https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/02/after-a-routine-code-rejection-an-ai-agent-published-a-hit-piece-on-someone-by-name/">an article</a> containing fabricated quotations generated by an AI tool and attributed to a source who did not say them. That is a serious failure of our standards. Direct quotations must always reflect what a source actually said.</p>
<p>That this happened at Ars is especially distressing. We have covered the risks of overreliance on AI tools for years, and our written policy reflects those concerns. In this case, fabricated quotations were published in a manner inconsistent with that policy. We have reviewed recent work and have not identified additional issues. At this time, this appears to be an isolated incident.</p>
<p>Ars Technica does not permit the publication of AI-generated material unless it is clearly labeled and presented for demonstration purposes. That rule is not optional, and it was not followed here.</p>
<p>We regret this failure and apologize to our readers. We have also apologized to Mr. Scott Shambaugh, who was falsely quoted.</p>


          
                      
                  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Radio host David Greene says Google's NotebookLM tool stole his voice (153 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2026/02/15/david-greene-google-ai-podcast/</link>
            <guid>47025864</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 18:05:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2026/02/15/david-greene-google-ai-podcast/">https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2026/02/15/david-greene-google-ai-podcast/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47025864">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2026/02/15/david-greene-google-ai-podcast/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Modern CSS Code Snippets: Stop writing CSS like it's 2015 (510 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://modern-css.com</link>
            <guid>47025851</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 18:04:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://modern-css.com">https://modern-css.com</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47025851">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section id="all-comparisons">
    
    <p><span>Browser compatibility:</span>
      
      
      
      
    </p>
    <div id="tipsGrid">
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/range-style-queries-without-multiple-blocks/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Range style queries without multiple blocks</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>/* Multiple style() blocks */</span><br><span>@container</span> <span>style</span>(<span>--p: 51%</span>) {}<br><span>@container</span> <span>style</span>(<span>--p: 52%</span>) {}<br><span>/* ...for each value */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>@container</span> <span>style</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>--progress &gt; 50%</span><br>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>.bar</span> { ... }<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/sticky-snapped-styling-without-javascript/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Sticky &amp; snapped element styling without JavaScript</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>window</span>.<span>addEventListener</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>'scroll'</span>, () =&gt; {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>/* check position */</span><br>});</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>@container</span> <span>scroll-state</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>stuck: top</span><br>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>.header</span> { ... }<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/typed-attribute-values-without-javascript/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Typed attribute values without JavaScript</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// JS reading dataset</span><br><span>el</span>.<span>style</span>.<span>width</span> =<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>el</span>.<span>dataset</span>.<span>pct</span> + <span>'%'</span>;</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.bar</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>width</span>: <span>attr</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>data-pct</span> <span>type</span>(<span>&lt;percentage&gt;</span>)<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;);<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/inline-conditional-styles-without-javascript/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Inline conditional styles without JavaScript</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// JavaScript toggling</span><br><span>el</span>.<span>classList</span>.<span>toggle</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>'primary'</span>, <span>isPrimary</span><br>);</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.btn</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>background</span>: <span>if</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>style(--variant: primary)</span>:<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>blue</span>; <span>else</span>: <span>gray</span><br>&nbsp;&nbsp;);<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/reusable-css-logic-without-sass-mixins/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Reusable CSS logic without Sass mixins</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// Sass function</span><br><span>@function</span> <span>fluid</span>(<span>$min</span>, <span>$max</span>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>@return</span> <span>clamp</span>(...);<br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>@function</span> <span>--fluid</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>--min</span>, <span>--max</span><br>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>@return</span> <span>clamp</span>(...);<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/corner-shapes-beyond-rounded-borders/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Corner shapes beyond rounded borders</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.card</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>clip-path</span>: <span>polygon</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>...</span> <span>/* 20+ points */</span><br>&nbsp;&nbsp;);<br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.card</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>border-radius</span>: <span>2em</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>corner-shape</span>: <span>squircle</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/responsive-clip-paths-without-svg/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Responsive clip paths without SVG</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.shape</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>clip-path</span>: <span>path</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>'M0 200 L100 0...'</span><br>&nbsp;&nbsp;);<br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.shape</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>clip-path</span>: <span>shape</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>from 0% 100%</span>, ...<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;);<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/scroll-spy-without-intersection-observer/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Scroll spy without IntersectionObserver</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>const</span> <span>observer</span> = <span>new</span><br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>IntersectionObserver</span>(cb);<br><span>/* 15+ lines of JS */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>nav a</span>:<span>target-current</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>color</span>: <span>var(--accent)</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/filling-available-space-without-calc-workarounds/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Filling available space without calc workarounds</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.full</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>width</span>: <span>calc</span>(<span>100%</span> - <span>40px</span>);<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>/* or width: 100% and overflow */</span><br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.full</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>width</span>: <span>stretch</span>;<br>}<br><span>/* fills container, keeps margins */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/staggered-animations-without-nth-child-hacks/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Staggered animations without nth-child hacks</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>li:nth-child(1)</span> { <span>--i</span>: <span>0</span>; }<br><span>li:nth-child(2)</span> { <span>--i</span>: <span>1</span>; }<br><span>li:nth-child(3)</span> { <span>--i</span>: <span>2</span>; }<br><span>/* repeat for every item… */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>li</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>transition-delay</span>:<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>calc</span>(<span>0.1s</span> * (<span>sibling-index()</span> - <span>1</span>));<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/carousel-navigation-without-a-javascript-library/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Carousel navigation without a JavaScript library</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// Swiper.js or Slick carousel</span><br><span>new</span> <span>Swiper</span>(<span>'.carousel'</span>, {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>navigation</span>: { <span>/* … */</span> },<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>pagination</span>: { <span>/* … */</span> },<br>});</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.carousel</span><span>::scroll-button(right)</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>content</span>: <span>"➡"</span>;<br>}<br><span>.carousel li</span><span>::scroll-marker</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>content</span>: <span>''</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/vertical-text-centering-without-padding-hacks/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Vertical text centering without padding hacks</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.btn</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>padding</span>: <span>10px 20px</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>/* looks off-center, tweak top/bottom */</span><br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>padding-top</span>: <span>8px</span>; <span>/* hack */</span><br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>h1</span>, <span>button</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>text-box</span>: <span>trim-both cap alphabetic</span>;<br>}<br><span>/* true optical centering */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/hover-tooltips-without-javascript-events/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Hover tooltips without JavaScript events</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// JS: mouseenter + mouseleave</span><br><span>btn</span>.<span>addEventListener</span>(<span>'mouseenter'</span>,<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;() =&gt; <span>showTooltip</span>())<br><span>/* + focus, blur, positioning */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>&lt;button</span> <span>interestfor</span>=<span>"tip"</span><span>&gt;</span>Hover me<span>&lt;/button&gt;</span><br><span>&lt;div</span> <span>id</span>=<span>"tip"</span> <span>popover</span>=<span>hint</span><span>&gt;</span><br>&nbsp;&nbsp;Tooltip content<br><span>&lt;/div&gt;</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/modal-controls-without-onclick-handlers/" data-baseline="">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Modal controls without onclick handlers</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>&lt;button</span> <span>onclick</span>=<span>"</span><br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>document</span>.<span>querySelector</span>(<span>'#dlg'</span>)<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;.<span>showModal</span>()<span>"</span><span>&gt;</span>Open<span>&lt;/button&gt;</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>&lt;button</span> <span>commandfor</span>=<span>"dlg"</span><br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>command</span>=<span>"show-modal"</span><span>&gt;</span>Open<span>&lt;/button&gt;</span><br><span>&lt;dialog</span> <span>id</span>=<span>"dlg"</span><span>&gt;</span>...<span>&lt;/dialog&gt;</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/dialog-light-dismiss-without-click-outside-listeners/" data-baseline="">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Dialog light dismiss without click-outside listeners</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// JS: listen for click on ::backdrop</span><br><span>dialog</span>.<span>addEventListener</span>(<span>'click'</span>,<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;(e) =&gt; { <span>/* check bounds */</span> })</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>&lt;dialog</span> <span>closedby</span>=<span>"any"</span><span>&gt;</span><br>&nbsp;&nbsp;Click outside to close<br><span>&lt;/dialog&gt;</span><br><span>/* no JS listeners */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/customizable-selects-without-a-javascript-library/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Customizable selects without a JavaScript library</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// Select2 or Choices.js</span><br><span>new</span> <span>Choices</span>(<span>'#my-select'</span>);<br><span>/* rebuilds entire DOM */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>select</span>,<br><span>select</span> <span>::picker(select)</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>appearance</span>: <span>base-select</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/vivid-colors-beyond-srgb/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Vivid colors beyond sRGB</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.hero</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>color</span>: <span>rgb</span>(200, 80, 50);<br>}<br><span>/* sRGB only, washed on P3 */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.hero</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>color</span>: <span>oklch</span>(0.7 0.25 29);<br>}<br><span>/* or color(display-p3 1 0.2 0.1) */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/color-variants-without-sass-functions/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Color variants without Sass functions</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>/* Sass: lighten($brand, 20%), darken($brand, 10%) */</span><br><span>.btn</span> { <span>background</span>: <span>#e0e0e0</span>; }</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.btn</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>background</span>: <span>oklch</span>(<span>from</span> <span>var</span>(--brand) <span>calc</span>(l + 0.2) c h);<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/multiline-text-truncation-without-javascript/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Multiline text truncation without JavaScript</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>/* JS: slice text by chars/words, add "..." */</span><br><span>.card-title</span> { <span>overflow</span>: <span>hidden</span>; }</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.card-title</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>display</span>: <span>-webkit-box</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>-webkit-line-clamp</span>: <span>3</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>line-clamp</span>: <span>3</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/drop-caps-without-float-hacks/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Drop caps without float hacks</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.drop-cap::first-letter</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>float</span>: <span>left</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>font-size</span>: <span>3em</span>; <span>line-height</span>: <span>1</span>;<br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.drop-cap::first-letter</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>initial-letter</span>: <span>3</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/positioning-shorthand-without-four-properties/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Positioning shorthand without four properties</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.overlay</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>top</span>: <span>0</span>; <span>right</span>: <span>0</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>bottom</span>: <span>0</span>; <span>left</span>: <span>0</span>;<br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.overlay</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>position</span>: <span>absolute</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>inset</span>: <span>0</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/lazy-rendering-without-intersection-observer/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Lazy rendering without IntersectionObserver</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// JS IntersectionObserver</span><br><span>new</span> <span>IntersectionObserver</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;(entries) =&gt; { <span>/* render */</span> }<br>).<span>observe</span>(el);</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.section</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>content-visibility</span>: <span>auto</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>contain-intrinsic-size</span>: <span>auto 500px</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/dropdown-menus-without-javascript-toggles/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Dropdown menus without JavaScript toggles</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.menu</span> { <span>display</span>: <span>none</span>; }<br><span>.menu.open</span> { <span>display</span>: <span>block</span>; }<br><span>/* + JS: click, clickOutside, ESC, aria */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>button</span>[<span>popovertarget</span>=<span>menu</span>] { }<br><span>#menu</span>[<span>popover</span>] {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>position</span>: <span>absolute</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/tooltip-positioning-without-javascript/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Tooltip positioning without JavaScript</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>/* Popper.js / Floating UI: compute rect,</span><br><span>   position: fixed, update on scroll */</span><br><span>.tooltip</span> { <span>position</span>: <span>fixed</span>; }</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.trigger</span> { <span>anchor-name</span>: <span>--tip</span>; }<br><span>.tooltip</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>position-anchor</span>: <span>--tip</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>top</span>: <span>anchor(bottom)</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/scoped-styles-without-bem-naming/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Scoped styles without BEM naming</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// BEM: .card__title, .card__body</span><br><span>.card__title</span> { â€¦ }<br><span>.card__body</span> { â€¦ }<br><span>// or CSS Modules / styled-components */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>@scope</span> (<span>.card</span>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>.title</span> { <span>font-size</span>: <span>1.25rem</span>; }<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>.body</span> { <span>color</span>: <span>#444</span>; }<br>}<br><span>/* .title only inside .card */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/typed-custom-properties-without-javascript/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Typed custom properties without JavaScript</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// --hue was a string, no animation</span><br><span>:root</span> { <span>--hue</span>: <span>0</span>; }<br><span>hsl</span>(<span>var</span>(<span>--hue</span>), â€¦) <span>/* no interpolation */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>@property</span> <span>--hue</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>syntax</span>: <span>"&lt;angle&gt;"</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>inherits</span>: <span>false</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>initial-value</span>: <span>0deg</span>;<br>}<br><span>/* animatable, validated */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/independent-transforms-without-the-shorthand/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Independent transforms without the shorthand</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.icon</span> { <span>transform</span>: <span>translateX</span>(<span>10px</span>) <span>rotate</span>(<span>45deg</span>) <span>scale</span>(<span>1.2</span>); }<br><span>/* change one = rewrite all */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.icon</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>translate</span>: <span>10px 0</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>rotate</span>: <span>45deg</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>scale</span>: <span>1.2</span>;<br>}<br><span>/* animate any one without touching the rest */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/animating-display-none-without-workarounds/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Animating display none without workarounds</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// wait for transitionend then display:none</span><br><span>el</span>.<span>addEventListener</span>(<span>'transitionend'</span>, â€¦)<br><span>visibility</span> + <span>opacity</span> + <span>pointer-events</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.panel</span> { <span>transition</span>: <span>opacity .2s, overlay .2s</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>transition-behavior</span>: <span>allow-discrete</span>; }<br><span>.panel.hidden</span> { <span>opacity</span>: <span>0</span>; <span>display</span>: <span>none</span>; }<br><span>/* no JS wait or visibility hack */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/entry-animations-without-javascript-timing/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Entry animations without JavaScript timing</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// add class after paint</span><br><span>requestAnimationFrame</span>(() =&gt; {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>el</span>.<span>classList</span>.<span>add</span>(<span>'visible'</span>);<br>});</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.card</span> { <span>transition</span>: <span>opacity .3s, transform .3s</span>; }<br><span>.card</span> { <span>@starting-style</span> { <span>opacity</span>: <span>0</span>; <span>transform</span>: <span>translateY</span>(<span>10px</span>); } }<br><span>/* no rAF/setTimeout */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/page-transitions-without-a-framework/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Page transitions without a framework</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// Barba.js or React Transition Group</span><br><span>Barba</span>.<span>init</span>({ â€¦ })<br><span>transition</span> hooks + <span>duration</span> state</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>document</span>.<span>startViewTransition</span>(() =&gt; <span>updateDOM</span>());<br><span>.hero</span> { <span>view-transition-name</span>: <span>hero</span>; }<br><span>/* no Barba, no React TG */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/scroll-snapping-without-a-carousel-library/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Scroll snapping without a carousel library</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// Slick, Swiper, or scroll/touch JS</span><br><span>$</span>(<span>'.carousel'</span>).<span>slick</span>({ â€¦ })<br><span>touchstart</span> / <span>scroll</span> handlers</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.carousel</span> { <span>scroll-snap-type</span>: <span>x mandatory</span>; }<br><span>.carousel &gt; *</span> { <span>scroll-snap-align</span>: <span>start</span>; }<br><span>/* no lib, no touch handlers */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/balanced-headlines-without-manual-line-breaks/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Balanced headlines without manual line breaks</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// manual &lt;br&gt; or Balance-Text.js</span><br><span>h1</span> { <span>text-align</span>: <span>center</span>; }<br><span>.balance-text</span> <span>/* JS lib */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>h1</span>, <span>h2</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>text-wrap</span>: <span>balance</span>;<br>}<br><span>/* no br or JS */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/font-loading-without-invisible-text/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Font loading without invisible text</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>@font-face</span> { ... }<br><span>/* Default: invisible text until load */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>@font-face</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>font-family</span>: <span>"MyFont"</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>font-display</span>: <span>swap</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/multiple-font-weights-without-multiple-files/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Multiple font weights without multiple files</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>@font-face</span> { <span>font-weight</span>: <span>400</span>; }<br><span>@font-face</span> { <span>font-weight</span>: <span>700</span>; }<br><span>/* 4+ files */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>@font-face</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>font-family</span>: <span>"MyVar"</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>src</span>: <span>url("MyVar.woff2")</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>font-weight</span>: <span>100 900</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/dark-mode-defaults-without-extra-css/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Dark mode defaults without extra CSS</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>@media</span> (<span>prefers-color-scheme</span>: <span>dark</span>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>input, select, textarea</span> { ... }<br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>:root</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>color-scheme</span>: <span>light dark</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/dark-mode-colors-without-duplicating-values/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Dark mode colors without duplicating values</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>@media</span> (<span>prefers-color-scheme</span>: <span>dark</span>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>color</span>: <span>#eee</span>;<br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>color</span>: <span>light-dark</span>(<span>#111</span>, <span>#eee</span>);<br><span>color-scheme</span>: <span>light dark</span>;          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/low-specificity-resets-without-complicated-selectors/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Low-specificity resets without complicated selectors</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.reset ul, .reset ol</span> { ... }<br><span>/* or (0,0,1) specificity, still wins */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>:where</span>(<span>ul, ol</span>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>margin</span>: <span>0</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>padding-inline-start</span>: <span>1.5rem</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/direction-aware-layouts-without-left-and-right/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Direction-aware layouts without left and right</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>margin-left</span>: <span>1rem</span>;<br><span>padding-right</span>: <span>1rem</span>;<br><span>[dir="rtl"</span>] <span>.box</span> { <span>margin-right</span>: ... }</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>margin-inline-start</span>: <span>1rem</span>;<br><span>padding-inline-end</span>: <span>1rem</span>;<br><span>border-block-start</span>: <span>1px solid</span>;          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/naming-grid-areas-without-line-numbers/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Naming grid areas without line numbers</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>float</span>: <span>left</span>; <span>/* clearfix, margins */</span><br><span>grid-column</span>: <span>1 / 3</span>;<br><span>grid-row</span>: <span>2</span>;</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.layout</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>display</span>: <span>grid</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>grid-template-areas</span>: <span>"header header" "sidebar main" "footer footer"</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/aligning-nested-grids-without-duplicating-tracks/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Aligning nested grids without duplicating tracks</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.child-grid</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>grid-template-columns</span>: <span>1fr 1fr 1fr</span>;<br><span>/* duplicate parent tracks */</span><br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.child-grid</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>display</span>: <span>grid</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>grid-template-columns</span>: <span>subgrid</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/modal-dialogs-without-a-javascript-library/" data-baseline="">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Modal dialogs without a JavaScript library</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.overlay</span> { <span>position</span>: <span>fixed</span>; <span>z-index</span>: <span>999</span>; }<br><span>/* + JS: open/close, ESC, focus trap */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>dialog</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>padding</span>: <span>1rem</span>;<br>}<br><span>dialog::backdrop</span> { <span>background</span>: <span>rgb</span>(0 0 0 / .5); }          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/styling-form-controls-without-rebuilding-them/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Styling form controls without rebuilding them</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>appearance</span>: <span>none</span>;<br><span>// + 20+ lines of custom box/border/background</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>input</span>[<span>type</span>=<span>"checkbox"</span>],<br><span>input</span>[<span>type</span>=<span>"radio"</span>] {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>accent-color</span>: <span>#7c3aed</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/grouping-selectors-without-repetition/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Grouping selectors without repetition</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.card h1</span>, <span>.card h2</span>, <span>.card h3</span>, <span>.card h4</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>margin-bottom</span>: <span>0.5em</span>;<br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.card</span> <span>:is</span>(<span>h1</span>, <span>h2</span>, <span>h3</span>, <span>h4</span>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>margin-bottom</span>: <span>0.5em</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/focus-styles-without-annoying-mouse-users/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Focus styles without annoying mouse users</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>:focus</span> { <span>outline</span>: <span>2px solid blue</span>; }<br><span>// Shows on mouse click too, or people remove it (a11y fail)</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>:focus-visible</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>outline</span>: <span>2px solid</span> <span>var</span>(<span>--focus-color</span>);<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/controlling-specificity-without-important/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Controlling specificity without !important</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.card .title</span> { ... }<br><span>.page .card .title</span> { ... }<br><span>.page .card .title.special</span> { <span>color</span>: <span>red</span> <span>!important</span>; }</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>@layer</span> <span>base</span>, <span>components</span>, <span>utilities</span>;<br><span>@layer</span> <span>utilities</span> { <span>.mt-4</span> { <span>margin-top</span>: <span>1rem</span>; } }          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/theme-variables-without-a-preprocessor/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Theme variables without a preprocessor</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// Sass: $primary: #7c3aed;</span><br><span>// Compiles to static #7c3aed</span><br><span>.btn</span> { <span>background</span>: <span>$primary</span>; }</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>:root</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>--primary</span>: <span>#7c3aed</span>;<br>}<br><span>.btn</span> { <span>background</span>: <span>var</span>(<span>--primary</span>); }          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/fluid-typography-without-media-queries/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Fluid typography without media queries</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>h1</span> { <span>font-size</span>: <span>1rem</span>; }<br><span>@media</span> (<span>min-width</span>: <span>600px</span>) { <span>h1</span> { <span>font-size</span>: <span>1.5rem</span>; } }<br><span>@media</span> (<span>min-width</span>: <span>900px</span>) { <span>h1</span> { <span>font-size</span>: <span>2rem</span>; } }</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>h1</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>font-size</span>: <span>clamp</span>(<span>1rem</span>, <span>2.5vw</span>, <span>2rem</span>);<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/spacing-elements-without-margin-hacks/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Spacing elements without margin hacks</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.grid</span> <span>&gt; *</span> { <span>margin-right</span>: <span>16px</span>; }<br><span>.grid</span> <span>&gt; *:last-child</span> { <span>margin-right</span>: <span>0</span>; }</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.grid</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>display</span>: <span>flex</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>gap</span>: <span>16px</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/aspect-ratios-without-the-padding-hack/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Aspect ratios without the padding hack</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.wrapper</span> { <span>padding-top</span>: <span>56.25%</span>; <span>position</span>: <span>relative</span>; }<br><span>.inner</span> { <span>position</span>: <span>absolute</span>; <span>inset</span>: <span>0</span>; }</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.video-wrapper</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>aspect-ratio</span>: <span>16 / 9</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/sticky-headers-without-javascript-scroll-listeners/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Sticky headers without JavaScript scroll listeners</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// JS: scroll listener + getBoundingClientRect</span><br><span>// then add/remove .fixed class</span><br><span>.header.fixed</span> { <span>position</span>: <span>fixed</span>; }</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.header</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>position</span>: <span>sticky</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>top</span>: <span>0</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/scroll-linked-animations-without-a-library/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Scroll-linked animations without a library</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// JS + IntersectionObserver</span><br><span>observer</span>.<span>observe</span>(el)<br><span>el</span>.<span>style</span>.<span>opacity</span> = …</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>animation-timeline</span>: <span>view()</span>;<br><span>animation-range</span>: <span>entry</span>;<br><span>/* pure CSS, GPU-accelerated */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/nesting-selectors-without-sass-or-less/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Nesting selectors without Sass or Less</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// requires Sass compiler</span><br><span>.nav</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>&amp; a</span> { <span>color</span>: <span>#888</span>; }<br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.nav</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>&amp; a</span> { <span>color</span>: <span>#888</span>; }<br>}<br><span>/* plain .css, no build */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/responsive-components-without-media-queries/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Responsive components without media queries</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>@media</span> (<span>max-width</span>: <span>768px</span>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>.card</span> { … }<br>}<br><span>/* viewport, not container */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>@container</span> (<span>width</span> &lt; <span>400px</span>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>.card</span> { <span>flex-direction</span>: <span>column</span>; }<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/mixing-colors-without-a-preprocessor/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Mixing colors without a preprocessor</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// Sass required</span><br><span>$blend</span>: <span>mix</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>$blue</span>, <span>$pink</span>, <span>60%</span>);</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>background</span>: <span>color-mix</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>in oklch</span>, <span>#3b82f6</span>,<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>#ec4899</span>);          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/selecting-parent-elements-without-javascript/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Selecting parent elements without JavaScript</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// JavaScript required</span><br><span>el</span>.<span>closest</span>(<span>'.parent'</span>)<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;.<span>classList</span>.<span>add</span>(…)</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.card:has(img)</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>grid-template</span>: <span>auto 1fr</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/centering-elements-without-the-transform-hack/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Centering elements without the transform hack</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>position</span>: <span>absolute</span>;<br><span>top</span>: <span>50%</span>; <span>left</span>: <span>50%</span>;<br><span>transform</span>: <span>translate(-50%,-50%)</span>;</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.parent</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>display</span>: <span>grid</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>place-items</span>: <span>center</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
          </div>
  </section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Palantir Gets Millions of Dollars from New York City's Public Hospitals (291 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://theintercept.com/2026/02/15/palantir-contract-new-york-city-health-hospitals/</link>
            <guid>47025624</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 17:37:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://theintercept.com/2026/02/15/palantir-contract-new-york-city-health-hospitals/">https://theintercept.com/2026/02/15/palantir-contract-new-york-city-health-hospitals/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47025624">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    
    <p><span>New York City’s</span> public hospital system is paying millions to Palantir, the controversial ICE and military contractor, according to documents obtained by The Intercept.</p>
<p>Since 2023, the New York City Health and Hospitals Corporation has paid Palantir nearly $4 million to improve its ability to track down payment for the services provided at its hospitals and medical clinics. Palantir, a data analysis firm that’s now a Wall Street giant thanks to its lucrative work with the Pentagon and U.S. intelligence community, deploys its software to make more efficient the billing of Medicaid and other public benefits. That includes automated scanning of patient health notes to “Increase charges captured from missed opportunities,” contract materials reviewed by The Intercept show.</p>
<p>Palantir’s administrative involvement in the business of healing people stands in contrast to its longtime role helping facilitate warfare, <a href="https://theintercept.com/2017/03/02/palantir-provides-the-engine-for-donald-trumps-deportation-machine/">mass deportations</a>, and dragnet surveillance.</p>
<p>In 2016, <a href="https://theintercept.com/2017/02/22/how-peter-thiels-palantir-helped-the-nsa-spy-on-the-whole-world/">The Intercept revealed</a> Palantir’s role behind XKEYSCORE, a secret NSA bulk surveillance program revealed by the whistleblower Edward Snowden that allowed the U.S. and its allies to search the unfathomably large volumes of data they collect. The company has also attracted global scrutiny and criticism for its “<a href="https://www.palantir.com/assets/xrfr7uokpv1b/3MuEeA8MLbLDAyxixTsiIe/9e4a11a7fb058554a8a1e3cd83e31c09/C134184_finaleprint.pdf">strategic partnership</a>” with the Israeli military while it was leveling Gaza.</p>

<p>But it’s Palantir’s work with U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement that is drawing the most protest today. The company provides a variety of services to help the federal government find and deport immigrants. ICE’s Palantir-furnished case management software, for example, “plays a critical role in supporting the daily operations of ICE, ensuring critical mission success,” according to federal contracting documents.</p>
<p>“It’s unacceptable that the same company that is targeting our neighbors for deportation and providing tools to the Israeli military is also providing software for our hospitals,” said Kenny Morris, an organizer with the American Friend Service Committee, which shared the contract documents with The Intercept.</p>
<!-- BLOCK(cta)[0](%7B%22componentName%22%3A%22CTA%22%2C%22entityType%22%3A%22SHORTCODE%22%2C%22optional%22%3Atrue%7D)(%7B%7D) --><!-- END-BLOCK(cta)[0] -->
<p>Established by the state legislature, New York City Health and Hospitals is the nation’s biggest municipal health care system, administering over 70 facilities throughout New York City, including Bellevue Hospital, and providing care for over 1 million New Yorkers annually.</p>
<p>New York City Health and Hospitals spokesperson Adam Shrier did not respond to multiple requests to discuss the contract’s details. Palantir spokesperson Drew Messing said the company does not use or share hospital data outside the bounds of its contract.</p>
<p>Palantir’s contract with New York’s public health care system allows the company to work with patients’ protected health information, or PHI. With permission from New York City Health and Hospitals, Palantir can “de-identify PHI and utilize de-identified PHI for purposes other than research,” the contract states. De-identification generally involves the stripping of certain revealing information, such as names, Social Security numbers, and birthdays. Such provisions are common in contracts involving health data.</p>
<p>Activists who oppose Palantir’s involvement in New York point to a large body of research that indicates re-identifying personal data, including in medial contexts, is <a href="https://georgetownlawtechreview.org/re-identification-of-anonymized-data/GLTR-04-2017/">often</a> <a href="https://techscience.org/a/2017082801/">trivial</a>.</p>
<p>“Any contract that shares any of New Yorkers’ highly personal data from NYC Health &amp; Hospital’s with Palantir, a key player in the Trump administration’s mass deportation effort, is reckless and puts countless lives at risk,” said Beth Haroules of the New York Civil Liberties Union. “Every New Yorker, without exception, has a right to quality healthcare and city services. New Yorkers must be able to seek healthcare without fear that their intimate medical information, or immigration status, will be delivered to the federal government on a silver platter.”</p>
<!-- BLOCK(newsletter)[0](%7B%22componentName%22%3A%22NEWSLETTER%22%2C%22entityType%22%3A%22SHORTCODE%22%2C%22optional%22%3Atrue%7D)(%7B%7D) --><!-- END-BLOCK(newsletter)[0] -->
<p>Palantir has long provided similar services to the U.K. National Health Service, a business relationship that today has an increasing number of detractors. Palantir “has absolutely no place in the NHS, looking after patients’ personal data,” Green Party leader Zack Polanski recently stated in a <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2026/feb/05/calls-to-halt-uk-palantir-contracts-grow-amid-lack-of-transparency-over-deals">letter to the U.K. health secretary</a>.</p>
<figure>
<blockquote>
<p>“Palantir is targeting the exact patients that NYCHH is looking to serve.” </p>
</blockquote>
</figure>
<p>Some New York-based groups feel similarly out of distrust for what the firm could do with troves of sensitive personal data.</p>
<p>“Palantir is targeting the exact patients that NYCHH is looking to serve,” said Jonathan Westin of the Brooklyn-based organization Climate Organizing Hub. “They should immediately sever their contract with Palantir and stand with the millions of immigrant New Yorkers that are being targeted by ICE in this moment.”</p>
<p>“The chaos Palantir is inflicting through its technology is not just limited to the kidnapping of our immigrant neighbors and the murder of heroes like our fellow nurse, Alex Pretti,” said Hannah Drummond, an Asheville, North Carolina-based nurse and organizer with National Nurses United, a nursing union. “As a nurse and patient advocate, I don’t want anything having to do with Palantir in my hospital — and neither should any elected leader who claims to represent nurses.”</p>
<p>Palantir’s vocally right-wing CEO Alex Karp&nbsp;has been a <a href="https://www.axios.com/2025/11/08/alex-karp-palantir-democrats-mamdani">frequent</a> critic <a href="https://www.foxbusiness.com/video/6384521232112">of New York City’s</a> newly inaugurated democratic socialist Mayor Zohran Mamdani. Health and Hospitals operates as a public benefit corporation, but the mayor can exert considerable influence over the network, for instance through the appointment of its board of directors. Its president, Dr. Mitchell Katz, was <a href="https://www.nyc.gov/site/ocme/news/cm1025/mayor-elect-mamdani-renominates-nyc-health-hospitals-president-ceo-dr-mitchell-katz-and">renominated</a> by Mamdani, then the mayor-elect, late last year.</p>
<p>The mayor’s office did not respond in time for publication when asked about its stance on the contract.<a id="_msocom_1"></a></p>
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[LT6502: A 6502-based homebrew laptop (363 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502</link>
            <guid>47025399</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 17:12:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502">https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47025399">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">LT6502</h2><a id="user-content-lt6502" aria-label="Permalink: LT6502" href="#lt6502"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">A 6502 based laptop design</p>
<p dir="auto">Yes, I know I'm crazy, but I figured why not. I'm enjoying working the <a href="https://github.com/TechPaula/PC6502/">PC6502</a> project but having a little tower of PCBs on the sofa isn't the best.
It's very simple, these are the specs</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>65C02 running at 8MHz</li>
<li>46K RAM</li>
<li>BASIC in ROM</li>
<li>65C22 VIA (for timers and some IO)</li>
<li>9" DIsplay (with built in font/simple graphics)</li>
<li>Built in keyboard</li>
<li>Compact Flash for storage</li>
<li>10000mAh battery built in</li>
<li>USBC powered/charged</li>
<li>Serial Console</li>
<li>1 internal expansion slot</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Pictures</h2><a id="user-content-pictures" aria-label="Permalink: Pictures" href="#pictures"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Assembled front view
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/blob/main/Images/Assembled_Front_Open.jpeg?raw=true"><img src="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/raw/main/Images/Assembled_Front_Open.jpeg?raw=true" alt="Picture of the assembled 6502 laptop in it's 3D printed case from the front"></a>
Assembled rear view
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/blob/main/Images/Assembled_Rear_Open.jpeg?raw=true"><img src="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/raw/main/Images/Assembled_Rear_Open.jpeg?raw=true" alt="Picture of the assembled 6502 laptop in it's 3D printed case from the rear"></a>
Assembled LHS view
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/blob/main/Images/Assembled_LHS_Open.jpeg?raw=true"><img src="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/raw/main/Images/Assembled_LHS_Open.jpeg?raw=true" alt="Picture of the assembled 6502 laptop in it's 3D printed case from the left hand side"></a>
Assembled RHS view
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/blob/main/Images/Assembled_RHS_Open.jpeg?raw=true"><img src="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/raw/main/Images/Assembled_RHS_Open.jpeg?raw=true" alt="Picture of the assembled 6502 laptop in it's 3D printed case from the right hand side"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Assembled closed front view
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/blob/main/Images/Assembled_Front_Closed.jpeg?raw=true"><img src="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/raw/main/Images/Assembled_Front_Closed.jpeg?raw=true" alt="Picture of the assembled 6502 laptop in it's 3D printed case from the front when closed"></a>
Assembled closed rear view
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/blob/main/Images/Assembled_Rear_Closed.jpeg?raw=true"><img src="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/raw/main/Images/Assembled_Rear_Closed.jpeg?raw=true" alt="Picture of the assembled 6502 laptop in it's 3D printed case from the rear when closed"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Lower parts (main board, battery, keyboard) in it's case
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/blob/main/Images/LT6502_BaseCase.jpeg?raw=true"><img src="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/raw/main/Images/LT6502_BaseCase.jpeg?raw=true" alt="Picture of the 6502 laptop base in it's 3D printed case"></a>
Screen with BASIC code
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TechPaula/LT6502/refs/heads/main/Images/LT6502_SCREEN_BASIC.jpeg"><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TechPaula/LT6502/refs/heads/main/Images/LT6502_SCREEN_BASIC.jpeg" alt="Picture of the 6502 laptop with screen and basic Jan 2026"></a>
First bring up
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TechPaula/LT6502/refs/heads/main/Images/Keyboard_hello_basic_Test.jpeg"><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TechPaula/LT6502/refs/heads/main/Images/Keyboard_hello_basic_Test.jpeg" alt="Picture of the 6502 laptop as of 5th Jan 2026"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Status</h2><a id="user-content-status" aria-label="Permalink: Status" href="#status"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>2025-11-12 - Initial commit with work in progress PCB, Schematics complete.</li>
<li>2025-12-30 - PCBs arrived!</li>
<li>2026-01-01 - Initial power up of PCBs gives all the correct voltages</li>
<li>2026-01-03 - Bring up of board with simple ROM/RAM/Console working.</li>
<li>2026-01-04 - VIA working, ACIA working, comms to/from the keyboard in basic working. Begun integrating keyboard into firmware</li>
<li>2026-01-05 - Keyboard now integrated into firmware, so you can type on the keyboard and don't need the console for input</li>
<li>2026-01-09 - Compact flash working, Beeper also now working. Also runs from battery just fine.</li>
<li>2026-01-16 - Connected a 4.3" 800x480 RA8875 based display and got that working. I failed to get the LT7683 based display working.</li>
<li>2026-01-17 - work on a number of case related things that did not quite work in actual life.</li>
<li>2026-01-18 - Tweaked CPLD to slow down FTDI read/writes. Also begun work on bios, added start beep and begun work on load/save functions</li>
<li>2026-02-08 - Added more commands, notably SAVE,LOAD and DIR for compact flash</li>
<li>2026-02-13 - Added more graphics commands :)</li>
<li>2026-02-14 - Assembled the case</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">In Progress</h2><a id="user-content-in-progress" aria-label="Permalink: In Progress" href="#in-progress"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Expansion board</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">To do (probably in order)</h2><a id="user-content-to-do-probably-in-order" aria-label="Permalink: To do (probably in order)" href="#to-do-probably-in-order"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>add in larger display (going to try a 10.1" RA8889 based 1024x600, fall back is a 9" RA8875 based 800x480)</li>
<li>Fix buggy keyscan code on MEGA644P</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Memory Map</h2><a id="user-content-memory-map" aria-label="Permalink: Memory Map" href="#memory-map"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The memory map is fairly stable at the moment, everything seems to be working fine.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">High Level</h4><a id="user-content-high-level" aria-label="Permalink: High Level" href="#high-level"></a></p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Start</th>
<th>End</th>
<th>Size (Dec)</th>
<th>Size (Hex)</th>
<th>What is it</th>
<th>Notes</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>0x0000</td>
<td>0xBEAF</td>
<td>48816</td>
<td>0xBEB0</td>
<td>RAM</td>
<td>This includes Zeropage and other bits BASIC may need (more below)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xBE00</td>
<td>0xBFFF</td>
<td>512</td>
<td>0x200</td>
<td>peripherals</td>
<td>This is where the peripherals are mapped (see below)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xC000</td>
<td>0xFFFF</td>
<td>12288</td>
<td>0x3000</td>
<td>ROM</td>
<td>holding EhBASIC, eWoz monitor, bootstrap and vectors</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h5 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">ROM breakdown</h5><a id="user-content-rom-breakdown" aria-label="Permalink: ROM breakdown" href="#rom-breakdown"></a></p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Start</th>
<th>End</th>
<th>Size (Dec)</th>
<th>Size (Hex)</th>
<th>What is it</th>
<th>Notes</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>0xC000</td>
<td>0xFAFF</td>
<td>15104</td>
<td>0x3B0</td>
<td>EhBASIC</td>
<td>EhBASIC 2.22p5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xF000</td>
<td>0xF2FF</td>
<td>768</td>
<td>0x300</td>
<td>eWozMon</td>
<td><a href="https://gist.github.com/BigEd/2760560">Enhanced Wozmon</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xF300</td>
<td>0xFFF9</td>
<td>3322</td>
<td>0xCFA</td>
<td>Bootstrap</td>
<td>startup messages and also input/output/load/save functions</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xFFFA</td>
<td>0xFFFF</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>0x0A</td>
<td>6502 Vectors</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h5 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">RAM breakdown</h5><a id="user-content-ram-breakdown" aria-label="Permalink: RAM breakdown" href="#ram-breakdown"></a></p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Start</th>
<th>End</th>
<th>Size (Dec)</th>
<th>Size (Hex)</th>
<th>What is it</th>
<th>Notes</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>0x0000</td>
<td>0x02FF</td>
<td>768</td>
<td>0x300</td>
<td>RAM</td>
<td>This includes Zeropage and other bits BASIC may need</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x0300</td>
<td>0x07FF</td>
<td>1280</td>
<td>0x500</td>
<td>RAM</td>
<td>This is going to be for the compact flash reading/writing</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x0800</td>
<td>0xBDFF</td>
<td>46592</td>
<td>0xB6B0</td>
<td>ROM</td>
<td>BASIC RAM available</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h5 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">peripherals</h5><a id="user-content-peripherals" aria-label="Permalink: peripherals" href="#peripherals"></a></p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Address</th>
<th>subAddr range</th>
<th>RW</th>
<th>What is it</th>
<th>Notes</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>0xBE0O</td>
<td>00-FF</td>
<td>RW</td>
<td>Expansion slot</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xBF00</td>
<td>00-9F</td>
<td></td>
<td>Unused Currently</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xBFAO</td>
<td>0-0</td>
<td>W</td>
<td>Beeper</td>
<td>just write 0xFF and 0x00 to turn on/off the speaker</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xBFBO</td>
<td>0-7</td>
<td>RW</td>
<td>Compact Flash</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xBFCO</td>
<td>0-F</td>
<td>RW</td>
<td>65C22</td>
<td>on board VIA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xBFDO</td>
<td>0-F</td>
<td>0-1</td>
<td>Display</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xBFEO</td>
<td>0-F</td>
<td>RW</td>
<td>65C21</td>
<td>internal keyboard</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xBFF0</td>
<td>0-1</td>
<td>RW</td>
<td>Console</td>
<td>FTDI USB console port</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">EhBASIC Extra commands</h2><a id="user-content-ehbasic-extra-commands" aria-label="Permalink: EhBASIC Extra commands" href="#ehbasic-extra-commands"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">I've Added a some extra commands to EhBASIC and they are as follows;</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>BEEP P,L - Pitch (P) is 0-255, length (L) = 0 to 255</li>
<li>CIRCLE X,Y,R,C,F - Draws a Circle, X is 0-799, Y is 0-479, R(radius) is 1 - 65535, C is 8bit RGB Value (RRRGGGBB), F is fill (0 = no fill, 1 = fill)</li>
<li>CLS - Clear screen (both graphic and text mode)</li>
<li>COLOUR &lt;0-255&gt; - Sets the colour (text) to 8bit RGB value, in the form RRRGGGBB</li>
<li>DIR - Scans the Compact Flash card and shows slot number and name for any files present</li>
<li>ELIPSE - X,Y,RX,RY,C,F - Draws an elipse, X is 0-799, Y is 0-479, RX is X radius, RY is Y radius, C is colour and F is fill</li>
<li>LINE X,Y,EX,EY,C - Draws a line, X is 0-799, Y is 0-479, EX is X end point (0-799), EY is Y end point (0-479), C is colour</li>
<li>LOAD &lt;0-2047&gt; - LOAD a file from CF</li>
<li>MODE &lt;0,1&gt; - Sets the display mode, MODE 0 is text, MODE 1 is graphics</li>
<li>OUTK - Outputs Text to the 8 character display on the keybed, can be a string or value, anything more than 8 characters will result in text shifting. a String will clear the display and then output the characters</li>
<li>PLOT X,Y,C - Plots a dot, X is 0-799, Y is 0-479 and C is 8bit RGB Value (RRRGGGBB)</li>
<li>SAVE &lt;0-2047&gt;,"" - SAVE current BASIC program into a SLOT and give it a name, upto 16 characters</li>
<li>SQUARE - X,Y,EX,EY,C,F - Draws a square, X is 0-799, Y is 0-479, EX is X end point (0-799), EY is Y end point (0-479), C is colour and F is fill</li>
<li>WOZMON - Jumps to wozmon, Q will exit WOZMON and return to basic (Handy for check chunks of memory)</li>
</ul>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[EU bans the destruction of unsold apparel, clothing, accessories and footwear (1048 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://environment.ec.europa.eu/news/new-eu-rules-stop-destruction-unsold-clothes-and-shoes-2026-02-09_en</link>
            <guid>47025378</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 17:10:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://environment.ec.europa.eu/news/new-eu-rules-stop-destruction-unsold-clothes-and-shoes-2026-02-09_en">https://environment.ec.europa.eu/news/new-eu-rules-stop-destruction-unsold-clothes-and-shoes-2026-02-09_en</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47025378">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>The European Commission today (Feb 9) adopted new measures under the Ecodesign for Sustainable Products Regulation (ESPR) to prevent the destruction of unsold apparel, clothing, accessories and footwear.</p><p>The rules will help cut waste, reduce environmental damage and create a level playing field for companies embracing sustainable business models, allowing them to reap the benefits of a more circular economy.</p><p>Every year in Europe, an estimated<strong> 4-9% of unsold textiles</strong> are destroyed before ever being worn. This waste generates around <strong>5.6 million tons</strong> of CO2 emissions – almost equal to Sweden’s total net emissions in 2021.</p><p>To help reduce this wasteful practice, the ESPR requires companies to disclose information on the unsold consumer products they discard as waste. It also introduces a ban on the destruction of unsold apparel, clothing accessories and footwear.</p><p>The Delegated and Implementing Acts adopted today will support businesses in complying with these requirements by:</p><ul><li><strong>Clarifying derogations</strong>: The Delegated Act outlines specific and justified circumstances under which the destruction will be permitted, for instance, due to safety reasons or product damage. National authorities will oversee compliance.</li><li><strong>Facilitating disclosure:</strong> The Implementing Act introduces a standardised format for businesses to disclose the volumes of unsold consumer goods they discard. This applies from February 2027, giving businesses sufficient time to adapt.</li></ul><p>Instead of discarding stock, companies are encouraged to manage their stock more effectively, handle returns, and explore alternatives such as resale, remanufacturing, donations, or reuse.</p><p>The ban on destruction of unsold apparel, clothing accessories and footwear and the derogations will apply to large companies from <strong>19 July 2026.</strong> Medium-sized companies are expected to follow in 2030. The rules on disclosure under the ESPR <strong>already apply</strong> <strong>to large companies</strong> and will also apply to medium-sized companies in 2030.</p><blockquote><p>"The textile sector is leading the way in the transition to sustainability, but there are still challenges. The numbers on waste show the need to act. With these new measures, the textile sector will be empowered to move towards sustainable and circular practices, and we can boost our competitiveness and reduce our dependencies."</p><p><strong>Jessika Roswall, Commissioner for Environment, Water Resilience and a Competitive Circular Economy</strong></p></blockquote><h4><strong>Background</strong></h4><p>The destruction of unsold goods is a wasteful practice. In France alone, around €630 million worth of unsold products are destroyed each year. Online shopping also fuels the issue: in Germany, nearly 20 million returned items are discarded annually.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><p>Textiles are a major part of the problem, and a key focus for action. To cut waste and reduce the sector’s environmental footprint, the European Commission is promoting more sustainable production while helping European companies stay competitive.&nbsp;</p><p>The ESPR is central to this effort. It will make products on the EU market more durable, reusable and recyclable, while boosting efficiency and circularity.</p><h5><strong>More information</strong></h5><p><a href="https://environment.ec.europa.eu/publications/commission-delegated-regulation-setting-out-derogations-prohibition-destruction-unsold-consumer_en">Delegated Regulation setting out derogations from the prohibition of destruction of unsold consumer products | European Commission</a></p><p><a href="https://environment.ec.europa.eu/publications/commission-implementing-regulation-details-and-format-disclosure-information-discarded-unsold_en">Implementing Regulation on the details and format for the disclosure of information on discarded unsold consumer products | European Commission</a></p><p><a href="https://commission.europa.eu/energy-climate-change-environment/standards-tools-and-labels/products-labelling-rules-and-requirements/ecodesign-sustainable-products-regulation_en">Ecodesign for Sustainable Products Regulation | European Commission</a></p><p><a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX%3A32024R1781&amp;qid=1719580391746">Ecodesign for Sustainable Products Regulation | EUR-Lex</a></p><p><a href="https://environment.ec.europa.eu/strategy/textiles-strategy_en">Textiles strategy | European Commission</a></p><p><a href="https://www.eea.europa.eu/en/analysis/publications/the-destruction-of-returned-and-unsold-textiles-in-europes-circular-economy">The destruction of returned and unsold textiles in Europe’s circular economy | European Environment Agency (EEA)</a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Knock-Knock.net – Visualizing the bots knocking on my server's door (164 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://knock-knock.net</link>
            <guid>47025338</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 17:06:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://knock-knock.net">https://knock-knock.net</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47025338">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <p>KNOCK-KNOCK.NET</p>
	    <p>Set up an unprotected server on the net, and the bots start swarming!</p><p> This site shows bots attempting (unsuccessfully) to break into an ordinary internet server.</p>
            <p>This constant chatter of bots knocking on the doors of machines on the net has been referred to as <em>"the background radiation of the Internet".</em></p>
	    <p>Knock-knock.net is a visualization of this bot traffic.
	    It shows the bot activity in real-time, and provides historic stats of the bot attacks over time: where they are coming from, the most common usernames and passwords attempted, the worst offending ISPs, and in some cases, why the password or username was chosen.</p>
            <p>Have fun! Send questions or comments to:<br><a href="#"></a></p>
            <p><a href="https://www.abuseipdb.com/user/270949" title="AbuseIPDB is an IP address blacklist for webmasters and sysadmins to report IP addresses engaging in abusive behavior on their networks" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
                <img src="https://www.abuseipdb.com/contributor/270949.svg" alt="AbuseIPDB Contributor Badge">
              </a>
            </p>
        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Palantir vs. the "Republik": US analytics firm takes magazine to court (229 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.heise.de/en/news/Palantir-vs-the-Republik-US-analytics-firm-takes-magazine-to-court-11176508.html</link>
            <guid>47025188</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 16:51:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.heise.de/en/news/Palantir-vs-the-Republik-US-analytics-firm-takes-magazine-to-court-11176508.html">https://www.heise.de/en/news/Palantir-vs-the-Republik-US-analytics-firm-takes-magazine-to-court-11176508.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47025188">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          <!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->
          





<a-collapse has-indicator="">
  
  <div data-collapse-target="">
      
  <nav>
    <ol>
        
        <li>

          
            <span aria-current="page">
              Palantir vs. the "Republik": US analytics firm takes magazine to court
            </span>

            
              <ul>
              
                <li>
                
                  <a href="#nav_streisand_effect_0" title="Streisand Effect" data-google-interstitial="false">
                    Streisand Effect
                  </a>
                
                </li>
              
                <li>
                
                  <a href="#nav_swiss__1" title="Swiss Counterstatements" data-google-interstitial="false">
                    Swiss Counterstatements
                  </a>
                
                </li>
              
                <li>
                
                  <a href="#nav_difficult__2" title="Difficult Terrain Europe" data-google-interstitial="false">
                    Difficult Terrain Europe
                  </a>
                
                </li>
              
                <li>
                
                  <a href="#nav__borderline__3" title="&quot;Borderline Conspiracy Theories&quot;" data-google-interstitial="false">
                    "Borderline Conspiracy Theories"
                  </a>
                
                </li>
              
                <li>
                
                  <a href="#nav_palantir__4" title="Palantir Rejects Accusation of Intimidation" data-google-interstitial="false">
                    Palantir Rejects Accusation of Intimidation
                  </a>
                
                </li>
              
              </ul>
            

          

        </li>
    </ol>

    

    

  </nav>

    </div>
  
</a-collapse>


          <!-- RSPEAK_START -->

        

        <p>Palantir Technologies, the US provider of analytics software, finds itself directly affected by two reports from the Swiss online magazine "Republik". After the company unsuccessfully demanded a counterstatement from the magazine, it now wants to enforce one through legal action. It's about a factual comparison, says the software provider. The "Republik" creators appear surprised.</p>
<!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->




  


<!-- RSPEAK_START -->

<h3 id="nav_streisand_effect_0">Streisand Effect</h3>
<p>With the step to court, Palantir has generated more attention for the "Republik" reporting than the objected articles themselves could have caused – 23 years after Barbra Streisand <a href="https://www.heise.de/news/Barbra-Streisand-klagt-gegen-Homepage-Betreiber-79921.html?from-en=1">triggered the effect named after her</a>. And yet, there are reasons why Palantir is acting this way.</p>
<p>While in Germany the provider of data linking and data analysis software for authorities with surveillance powers is successful with at least some state customers. The company has so far had – as far as is known – little state clientele in Switzerland.</p>
<p>In December, "Republik" <a href="https://www.republik.ch/2025/12/08/wie-hartnaeckig-palantir-die-schweiz-umwarb">extensively quoted from Swiss administration files</a>. According to this, Palantir repeatedly sought contact with Swiss authorities – and found it. In some cases, it originated from Palantir, in others, likely from public bodies. The matters concerned the military, police, and health authorities. However, no business deal was apparently concluded.</p>
<p>Palantir feels unfairly treated by the reporting on this. "We can confirm that an application for a counterstatement has been filed with the Commercial Court in this matter," the communications officer of the Cantonal High Court told heise online on Friday upon request.</p>
<h3 id="nav_swiss__1">Swiss Counterstatements</h3>
<p>Swiss law provides for counterstatements, meaning that as soon as a request for a counterstatement has been rejected by a medium, a civil court can examine the matter and hear both sides. The Commercial Court of Zurich is responsible here. The Commercial Court of Zurich is responsible here.</p>
<!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->


  



  




<!-- RSPEAK_START -->

<p>Palantir says it had to sue to uphold its legal claim. "Palantir fully respects press freedom and the essential role of independent media in public debate," said a company spokeswoman. The right to a counterstatement is a "correction instrument intended to provide the public with balanced information."</p>
<p>For Palantir, the "Republik" reporting came at an inopportune time. This is because important procurement decisions are currently being made in several business areas in many European countries: the modernization and expansion of military, intelligence, and secret services, as well as police authorities, would be a promising business for Palantir and its software, which is also helpful for official surveillance.</p>
<p>In its home market, the USA, the company does business with US federal authorities for about a quarter of a billion US dollars, according to transparency data <a href="https://www.usaspending.gov/recipient/1ea8a9a4-3726-3491-9040-66950bb67606-C/latest">approximately a quarter of a billion US dollars</a>. Customers include the US Department of Defense, the Army, and the FBI. The company reports nearly 4.5 billion US dollars in revenue for 2025, about a tenth of SAP's annual revenue. And yet, Palantir is valued on the stock market at around 300 billion euros, while SAP comes in at around 200 billion.</p>
<h3 id="nav_difficult__2">Difficult Terrain Europe</h3>
<p>The European market remains difficult terrain for Palantir. The connection to the Immigration and Customs Enforcement agency (ICE), <a href="https://www.heise.de/hintergrund/USA-Die-Architektur-der-Abschiebung-und-Palantirs-Rolle-im-neuen-ICE-System-11152960.html?from-en=1">which is supposed to track down illegal migrants with brutal methods and a lot of high-tech</a>, causes consternation in Europe. As a US company, Palantir is subject to US law, which increasingly questions international cooperation in security matters – this is unlikely to be conducive to sales for Palantir.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the uproar had just subsided elsewhere: Palantir was criticized for its involvement in Israel. Founders Peter Thiel and Alex Karp had agreed to a strategic partnership with the Israeli Ministry of Defense in January 2024, Bloomberg reported at the time. The report on this is <a href="https://www.palantir.com/assets/xrfr7uokpv1b/3MuEeA8MLbLDAyxixTsiIe/9e4a11a7fb058554a8a1e3cd83e31c09/C134184_finaleprint.pdf">publicly available on the Palantir website</a>.</p>
<p>The small medium from Switzerland is hardly comparable to industry giants like Bloomberg. It has been published ad-free and exclusively online since 2018. It is primarily supported by a good 30,000 subscribers, a majority of whom are also cooperative members with voting rights. Not a media behemoth with a large publisher behind it.</p>
<h3 id="nav__borderline__3">"Borderline Conspiracy Theories"</h3>
<p>Shortly after the publication of the two articles now being heard in court, Courtney Bowman, head of Palantir's "Privacy and Civil Liberties" department, had already set the course on LinkedIn: The reports from "Republik" were "full of distortions, insinuations, and borderline conspiracy theories."</p>
<p>Bowman accuses the authors of having reproduced a report from the Swiss Army Staff too uncritically – whose authors, unfortunately, had "relied on a limited set of search engine hit sources." The Palantir representative, in turn, provided no evidence for his claims.</p>
<p>"I believe we have done excellent research and documented it very comprehensively," says Daniel Binswanger, co-editor-in-chief of "Republik," in an interview with heise online. Research based on Swiss government documents is one of the "best foundations for reporting." He is very confident about the outcome of the proceedings.</p>
<!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->

  




<!-- RSPEAK_START -->

<h3 id="nav_palantir__4">Palantir Rejects Accusation of Intimidation</h3>
<p>Palantir strongly rejects the impression that a multi-billion dollar company is flexing its muscles against a small magazine: Any accusation that this is a strategic attempt to intimidate unfavorable reporting through legal action is unfounded, the company spokeswoman emphasizes: "Palantir merely seeks the publication of a concise and appropriate counterstatement to correct significant inaccuracies."</p>
<p>However, the company does not disclose what specific "significant inaccuracies" Palantir wants to see corrected. Palantir did not respond to a request to send the "corrections" specifically demanded by "Republik" by Friday afternoon.</p>
<p>Whether the company will achieve at least partial success with its approach in court is hardly predictable. The Swiss right to a counterstatement involves no examination by the court whether a statement was actually correct. This is why it is a frequently used form in the Swiss media world when companies feel they have been misrepresented.</p>
<p>"The right to a counterstatement is not about whether something is true or false," explains "Republik" co-editor-in-chief Daniel Binswanger. "It's about whether another version of the facts could also be possible." However, this only concerns factual representation. Opinions, on the other hand, are not challengeable in Switzerland either.</p>
<p>For the Swiss online magazine, however, the effect is noticeable and measurable. "We are overwhelmed," says Daniel Binswanger in an interview with heise online. "The offers of donations, expressions of solidarity – it's gigantic," he says. "We've never experienced a story triggering this." Ms. Streisand sends her regards.</p>


<!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->

<!-- RSPEAK_START -->
<p>

<!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->
<span>(<a href="mailto:vbr@heise.de" title="Volker Briegleb">vbr</a>)</span>
<!-- RSPEAK_START -->
</p>
<div>
    <p>
      Don't miss any news – follow us on
      <a href="https://www.facebook.com/heiseonlineEnglish">Facebook</a>,
      <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/104691972">LinkedIn</a> or
      <a href="https://social.heise.de/@heiseonlineenglish">Mastodon</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      <em>This article was originally published in
      
        <a href="https://www.heise.de/news/Palantir-gegen-die-Republik-US-Analysefirma-geht-gegen-Magazin-vor-Gericht-11176503.html">German</a>.
      
      It was translated with technical assistance and editorially reviewed before publication.</em>
    </p>
  </div>



        

        
        <!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->
        

<a-gift has-access="">
    
</a-gift>


        
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Pocketblue – Fedora Atomic for mobile devices (114 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/pocketblue/pocketblue</link>
            <guid>47025085</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 16:40:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/pocketblue/pocketblue">https://github.com/pocketblue/pocketblue</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47025085">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            


<react-partial partial-name="marketing-navigation" data-ssr="true" data-attempted-ssr="true" data-react-profiling="true">
  
  
  <div data-target="react-partial.reactRoot"><nav aria-label="Global"><ul><li><div><ul><li><div><p><span>AI CODE CREATION</span></p><ul><li><a href="https://github.com/features/copilot" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_copilot&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_copilot_link_platform_navbar&quot;}"><div><p><span>GitHub Copilot</span><span>Write better code with AI</span></p></div></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/features/spark" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_spark&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_spark_link_platform_navbar&quot;}"><div><p><span>GitHub Spark</span><span>Build and deploy intelligent apps</span></p></div></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/features/models" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_models&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_models_link_platform_navbar&quot;}"><div><p><span>GitHub Models</span><span>Manage and compare prompts</span></p></div></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/mcp" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;mcp_registry&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;mcp_registry_link_platform_navbar&quot;}"><div><p><span>MCP Registry<sup>New</sup></span><span>Integrate external tools</span></p></div></a></li></ul></div></li><li><div><p><span>DEVELOPER WORKFLOWS</span></p><ul><li><a href="https://github.com/features/actions" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;actions&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;actions_link_platform_navbar&quot;}"><div><p><span>Actions</span><span>Automate any workflow</span></p></div></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/features/codespaces" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;codespaces&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;codespaces_link_platform_navbar&quot;}"><div><p><span>Codespaces</span><span>Instant dev environments</span></p></div></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/features/issues" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;issues&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;issues_link_platform_navbar&quot;}"><div><p><span>Issues</span><span>Plan and track work</span></p></div></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/features/code-review" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;code_review&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;code_review_link_platform_navbar&quot;}"><div><p><span>Code Review</span><span>Manage code changes</span></p></div></a></li></ul></div></li><li><div><p><span>APPLICATION SECURITY</span></p><ul><li><a href="https://github.com/security/advanced-security" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_advanced_security&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_advanced_security_link_platform_navbar&quot;}"><div><p><span>GitHub Advanced Security</span><span>Find and fix vulnerabilities</span></p></div></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/security/advanced-security/code-security" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;code_security&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;code_security_link_platform_navbar&quot;}"><div><p><span>Code security</span><span>Secure your code as you build</span></p></div></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/security/advanced-security/secret-protection" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;secret_protection&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;secret_protection_link_platform_navbar&quot;}"><div><p><span>Secret protection</span><span>Stop leaks before they start</span></p></div></a></li></ul></div></li><li><div><p><span>EXPLORE</span></p><ul><li><a href="https://github.com/why-github" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;why_github&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;why_github_link_platform_navbar&quot;}"><span>Why GitHub</span></a></li><li><a href="https://docs.github.com/" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;documentation&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;documentation_link_platform_navbar&quot;}" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer"><span>Documentation</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.blog/" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;blog&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;blog_link_platform_navbar&quot;}" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer"><span>Blog</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.blog/changelog" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;changelog&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;changelog_link_platform_navbar&quot;}" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer"><span>Changelog</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/marketplace" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;marketplace&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;marketplace_link_platform_navbar&quot;}"><span>Marketplace</span></a></li></ul></div></li></ul><p><a href="https://github.com/features" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;view_all_features&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;view_all_features_link_platform_navbar&quot;}"><span>View all features</span></a></p></div></li><li><div><ul><li><div><p><span>BY COMPANY SIZE</span></p><ul><li><a href="https://github.com/enterprise" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;enterprises&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;solutions&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;enterprises_link_solutions_navbar&quot;}"><span>Enterprises</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/team" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;small_and_medium_teams&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;solutions&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;small_and_medium_teams_link_solutions_navbar&quot;}"><span>Small and medium teams</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/enterprise/startups" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;startups&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;solutions&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;startups_link_solutions_navbar&quot;}"><span>Startups</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/solutions/industry/nonprofits" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;nonprofits&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;solutions&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;nonprofits_link_solutions_navbar&quot;}"><span>Nonprofits</span></a></li></ul></div></li><li><div><p><span>BY USE CASE</span></p><ul><li><a href="https://github.com/solutions/use-case/app-modernization" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;app_modernization&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;solutions&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;app_modernization_link_solutions_navbar&quot;}"><span>App Modernization</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/solutions/use-case/devsecops" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;devsecops&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;solutions&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;devsecops_link_solutions_navbar&quot;}"><span>DevSecOps</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/solutions/use-case/devops" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;devops&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;solutions&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;devops_link_solutions_navbar&quot;}"><span>DevOps</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/solutions/use-case/ci-cd" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;ci/cd&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;solutions&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ci/cd_link_solutions_navbar&quot;}"><span>CI/CD</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/solutions/use-case" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;view_all_use_cases&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;solutions&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;view_all_use_cases_link_solutions_navbar&quot;}"><span>View all use cases</span></a></li></ul></div></li><li><div><p><span>BY INDUSTRY</span></p><ul><li><a href="https://github.com/solutions/industry/healthcare" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;healthcare&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;solutions&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;healthcare_link_solutions_navbar&quot;}"><span>Healthcare</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/solutions/industry/financial-services" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;financial_services&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;solutions&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;financial_services_link_solutions_navbar&quot;}"><span>Financial services</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/solutions/industry/manufacturing" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;manufacturing&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;solutions&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;manufacturing_link_solutions_navbar&quot;}"><span>Manufacturing</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/solutions/industry/government" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;government&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;solutions&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;government_link_solutions_navbar&quot;}"><span>Government</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/solutions/industry" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;view_all_industries&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;solutions&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;view_all_industries_link_solutions_navbar&quot;}"><span>View all industries</span></a></li></ul></div></li></ul><p><a href="https://github.com/solutions" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;view_all_solutions&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;solutions&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;view_all_solutions_link_solutions_navbar&quot;}"><span>View all solutions</span></a></p></div></li><li><div><ul><li><div><p><span>EXPLORE BY TOPIC</span></p><ul><li><a href="https://github.com/resources/articles?topic=ai" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;ai&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ai_link_resources_navbar&quot;}"><span>AI</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/resources/articles?topic=software-development" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;software_development&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;software_development_link_resources_navbar&quot;}"><span>Software Development</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/resources/articles?topic=devops" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;devops&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;devops_link_resources_navbar&quot;}"><span>DevOps</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/resources/articles?topic=security" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;security&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;security_link_resources_navbar&quot;}"><span>Security</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/resources/articles" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;view_all_topics&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;view_all_topics_link_resources_navbar&quot;}"><span>View all topics</span></a></li></ul></div></li><li><div><p><span>EXPLORE BY TYPE</span></p><ul><li><a href="https://github.com/customer-stories" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;customer_stories&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;customer_stories_link_resources_navbar&quot;}"><span>Customer stories</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/resources/events" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;events__webinars&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;events__webinars_link_resources_navbar&quot;}"><span>Events &amp; webinars</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/resources/whitepapers" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;ebooks__reports&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ebooks__reports_link_resources_navbar&quot;}"><span>Ebooks &amp; reports</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/solutions/executive-insights" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;business_insights&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;business_insights_link_resources_navbar&quot;}"><span>Business insights</span></a></li><li><a href="https://skills.github.com/" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_skills&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_skills_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer"><span>GitHub Skills</span></a></li></ul></div></li><li><div><p><span>SUPPORT &amp; SERVICES</span></p><ul><li><a href="https://docs.github.com/" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;documentation&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;documentation_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer"><span>Documentation</span></a></li><li><a href="https://support.github.com/" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;customer_support&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;customer_support_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer"><span>Customer support</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/orgs/community/discussions" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;community_forum&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;community_forum_link_resources_navbar&quot;}"><span>Community forum</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/trust-center" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;trust_center&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;trust_center_link_resources_navbar&quot;}"><span>Trust center</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/partners" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;partners&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;partners_link_resources_navbar&quot;}"><span>Partners</span></a></li></ul></div></li></ul></div></li><li><div><ul><li><div><p><span>COMMUNITY</span></p><ul><li><a href="https://github.com/sponsors" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_sponsors&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;open_source&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_sponsors_link_open_source_navbar&quot;}"><div><p><span>GitHub Sponsors</span><span>Fund open source developers</span></p></div></a></li></ul></div></li><li><div><p><span>PROGRAMS</span></p><ul><li><a href="https://securitylab.github.com/" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;security_lab&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;open_source&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;security_lab_link_open_source_navbar&quot;}" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer"><span>Security Lab</span></a></li><li><a href="https://maintainers.github.com/" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;maintainer_community&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;open_source&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;maintainer_community_link_open_source_navbar&quot;}" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer"><span>Maintainer Community</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/accelerator" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;accelerator&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;open_source&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;accelerator_link_open_source_navbar&quot;}"><span>Accelerator</span></a></li><li><a href="https://archiveprogram.github.com/" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;archive_program&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;open_source&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;archive_program_link_open_source_navbar&quot;}" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer"><span>Archive Program</span></a></li></ul></div></li><li><div><p><span>REPOSITORIES</span></p><ul><li><a href="https://github.com/topics" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;topics&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;open_source&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;topics_link_open_source_navbar&quot;}"><span>Topics</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/trending" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;trending&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;open_source&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;trending_link_open_source_navbar&quot;}"><span>Trending</span></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/collections" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;collections&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;open_source&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;collections_link_open_source_navbar&quot;}"><span>Collections</span></a></li></ul></div></li></ul></div></li><li><div><ul><li><div><p><span>ENTERPRISE SOLUTIONS</span></p><ul><li><a href="https://github.com/enterprise" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;enterprise_platform&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;enterprise&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;enterprise_platform_link_enterprise_navbar&quot;}"><div><p><span>Enterprise platform</span><span>AI-powered developer platform</span></p></div></a></li></ul></div></li><li><div><p><span>AVAILABLE ADD-ONS</span></p><ul><li><a href="https://github.com/security/advanced-security" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_advanced_security&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;enterprise&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_advanced_security_link_enterprise_navbar&quot;}"><div><p><span>GitHub Advanced Security</span><span>Enterprise-grade security features</span></p></div></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/features/copilot/copilot-business" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;copilot_for_business&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;enterprise&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;copilot_for_business_link_enterprise_navbar&quot;}"><div><p><span>Copilot for Business</span><span>Enterprise-grade AI features</span></p></div></a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/premium-support" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;premium_support&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;enterprise&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;premium_support_link_enterprise_navbar&quot;}"><div><p><span>Premium Support</span><span>Enterprise-grade 24/7 support</span></p></div></a></li></ul></div></li></ul></div></li><li><a href="https://github.com/pricing" data-analytics-event="{&quot;action&quot;:&quot;pricing&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;pricing&quot;,&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;pricing_link_pricing_navbar&quot;}"><span>Pricing</span></a></li></ul></nav></div>
</react-partial>



        <div>
                


<qbsearch-input data-scope="repo:pocketblue/pocketblue" data-custom-scopes-path="/search/custom_scopes" data-delete-custom-scopes-csrf="hLICkXKrSQsCkKyTvc8OyJhpn-mrcH9n8iVSEn_RzDMwlIPg7troIv0Pqp4KEBe23RXcPr78bm3CGMwSYy2LIQ" data-max-custom-scopes="10" data-header-redesign-enabled="false" data-initial-value="" data-blackbird-suggestions-path="/search/suggestions" data-jump-to-suggestions-path="/_graphql/GetSuggestedNavigationDestinations" data-current-repository="pocketblue/pocketblue" data-current-org="pocketblue" data-current-owner="" data-logged-in="false" data-copilot-chat-enabled="false" data-nl-search-enabled="false" data-retain-scroll-position="true">
  <div data-modal-dialog-overlay="" data-action="click:qbsearch-input#searchInputContainerClicked">
  <modal-dialog data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleClose" data-target="qbsearch-input.searchSuggestionsDialog" role="dialog" id="search-suggestions-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="search-suggestions-dialog-header" data-view-component="true">
      <h2 id="search-suggestions-dialog-header">Search code, repositories, users, issues, pull requests...</h2>
    
</modal-dialog></div>
  
  <div>
    
<dialog-helper>
  <dialog data-target="qbsearch-input.feedbackDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" id="feedback-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="feedback-dialog-title" aria-describedby="feedback-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="feedback-dialog-title">
        Provide feedback
      </h2>
        
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="feedback-dialog-title">
        <div data-view-component="true">        <!-- '"` --><!-- </textarea></xmp> --><form id="code-search-feedback-form" data-turbo="false" action="/search/feedback" accept-charset="UTF-8" method="post">
          <p>We read every piece of feedback, and take your input very seriously.</p>
          
          
          <label for="include_email">Include my email address so I can be contacted</label>
</form></div>
      </scrollable-region>
      
</dialog></dialog-helper>

    <custom-scopes data-target="qbsearch-input.customScopesManager">
    
<dialog-helper>
  <dialog data-target="custom-scopes.customScopesModalDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" id="custom-scopes-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="custom-scopes-dialog-title" aria-describedby="custom-scopes-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        Saved searches
      </h2>
        <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-description">Use saved searches to filter your results more quickly</h2>
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</dialog></dialog-helper>
    </custom-scopes>
  </div>
</qbsearch-input>


            <div>
              <p><a href="https://github.com/login?return_to=https%3A%2F%2Fgithub.com%2Fpocketblue%2Fpocketblue" data-hydro-click="{&quot;event_type&quot;:&quot;authentication.click&quot;,&quot;payload&quot;:{&quot;location_in_page&quot;:&quot;site header menu&quot;,&quot;repository_id&quot;:null,&quot;auth_type&quot;:&quot;SIGN_UP&quot;,&quot;originating_url&quot;:&quot;https://github.com/pocketblue/pocketblue&quot;,&quot;user_id&quot;:null}}" data-hydro-click-hmac="23ed231941b8067870d526b65a93d68e8cc1b8b19d7f59c6f3313266ced61770" data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Marketing nav&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to homepage&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_page:Marketing;ref_cta:Sign in;ref_loc:Header&quot;}">
                Sign in
              </a>
            </p></div>

              <p><a href="https://github.com/signup?ref_cta=Sign+up&amp;ref_loc=header+logged+out&amp;ref_page=%2F%3Cuser-name%3E%2F%3Crepo-name%3E&amp;source=header-repo&amp;source_repo=pocketblue%2Fpocketblue" data-hydro-click="{&quot;event_type&quot;:&quot;authentication.click&quot;,&quot;payload&quot;:{&quot;location_in_page&quot;:&quot;site header menu&quot;,&quot;repository_id&quot;:null,&quot;auth_type&quot;:&quot;SIGN_UP&quot;,&quot;originating_url&quot;:&quot;https://github.com/pocketblue/pocketblue&quot;,&quot;user_id&quot;:null}}" data-hydro-click-hmac="23ed231941b8067870d526b65a93d68e8cc1b8b19d7f59c6f3313266ced61770" data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Sign up&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to sign up for account&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_page:/<user-name>/<repo-name>;ref_cta:Sign up;ref_loc:header logged out&quot;}">
                Sign up
              </a></p><p>
    <react-partial-anchor>
      <tool-tip id="tooltip-992a2bf8-d825-433d-8c6b-e6958ed08f19" for="icon-button-edbed850-be30-44d1-b9e8-5badf7c3d113" popover="manual" data-direction="s" data-type="label" data-view-component="true">Appearance settings</tool-tip>

      <template data-target="react-partial-anchor.template">
        <link crossorigin="anonymous" media="all" rel="stylesheet" href="https://github.githubassets.com/assets/primer-react.298ffe31d478a02c.module.css">
<link crossorigin="anonymous" media="all" rel="stylesheet" href="https://github.githubassets.com/assets/appearance-settings.d1797b65cfd73e57.module.css">

<react-partial partial-name="appearance-settings" data-ssr="false" data-attempted-ssr="false" data-react-profiling="true">
  
  <script type="application/json" data-target="react-partial.embeddedData">{"props":{}}</script>
  <div data-target="react-partial.reactRoot"></div>
</react-partial>


      </template>
    </react-partial-anchor>
  </p>

          </div>
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hideki Sato, designer of all Sega's consoles, has died (403 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.videogameschronicle.com/news/hideki-sato-designer-of-segas-consoles-dies-age-75/</link>
            <guid>47024907</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 16:19:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.videogameschronicle.com/news/hideki-sato-designer-of-segas-consoles-dies-age-75/">https://www.videogameschronicle.com/news/hideki-sato-designer-of-segas-consoles-dies-age-75/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47024907">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content_body"><p><span>Hideki Sato, the designer behind virtually every Sega console, and the company’s former president, has died age 77.</span></p><p><span>Japanese games outlet <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://x.com/beep2021/status/2022662105904877996?s=46">Beep21 </a>reports that Sato passed away this weekend.</span></p><p><span>Sato and his R&amp;D team were responsible for the creation of <a title="Companies > Sega [1,106 articles]" href="https://www.videogameschronicle.com/companies/sega/">Sega</a>’s arcade and home console hardware, including the Master System, Genesis / Mega Drive, Saturn, and Dreamcast.</span></p><p><span>The engineer joined Sega in 1971 and was the company’s acting president between 2001 and 2003. He left the company in 2008.</span></p><p><span>“From the beginning, Sega’s home console development has always been influenced by our arcade development,” Sato previously told <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://shmuplations.com/segahistory/">Famitsu</a> in an interview covering Sega’s history.</span></p><p><span>“Our first 8-bit machine was the </span><span>SC-3000</span><span>. This was a <a title="Platforms > PC [11,949 articles]" href="https://www.videogameschronicle.com/platforms/pc/">PC</a> for beginner-level users. At that time, Sega only did arcade games, so this was our first challenge. We had no idea how many units we’d sell.”</span></p><p><span>Sato said of Mega Drive, Sega’s most successful console: “At that point, we decided to start developing a new home console. By then, arcade games were using 16-bit CPUs. </span></p><p><span>“Arcade development was something we were very invested in, so we were always using the most cutting-edge technology there. Naturally, it started us thinking: what if we used that technology in a home console? </span></p><p><span>“Two years after we started development, it was done: a 16-bit CPU home console, the Megadrive. The 68000 chip had also recently come down in price, so the timing was right.”</span></p><p><span>On Dreamcast, the release that ultimately ended Sega’s run in hardware, Sato said the keyword for the development was “play and communication.”</span></p><p><span>“The ultimate form of communication is a direct connection with another, and we included the modem and the linkable VMUs for that purpose,” he said. </span></p><p><span>“We had also planned to have some sort of linking function with cell phones, but we weren’t able to realize it. Consumers were now used to the raging ‘bit wars’, so even though we knew it was a lot of nonsense, we needed to appeal to them in those terms with the Dreamcast. </span></p><p><span>“And so we marketed it as having a ‘128 bit graphics engine RISC CPU’, even the SH-4 was only 64-bit. (laughs) On the other hand, we extensively customized the original SH-4 for the Dreamcast, to the point where I think you could almost call it something new.”</span></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Gwtar: A static efficient single-file HTML format (245 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://gwern.net/gwtar</link>
            <guid>47024506</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 15:37:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://gwern.net/gwtar">https://gwern.net/gwtar</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47024506">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AI is going to kill app subscriptions (124 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nichehunt.app/blog/ai-going-to-kill-app-subscriptions</link>
            <guid>47024387</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 15:21:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nichehunt.app/blog/ai-going-to-kill-app-subscriptions">https://nichehunt.app/blog/ai-going-to-kill-app-subscriptions</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47024387">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><p>The math is simple: if it costs almost nothing to build an app, it costs almost nothing to clone an app. And if cloning is free, subscription pricing dies.</p>
<p>We're already seeing this play out in the numbers. Apple's App Store got 557K new submissions in 2025, up 24% from 2024 (source: Appfigures). That's not because people suddenly got more creative. It's because building an app went from a $50K project to a weekend with Claude.</p>
<h2>What happens to pricing</h2>
<p>For apps that run locally—no servers, no cloud costs—subscriptions make no sense anymore. The only real cost is development, and that's becoming negligible. If someone charges $10/month for a local PDF editor, someone else will build a clone for $5 one-time. Then someone will make it free.</p>
<p>Apps that need servers (sync, AI features, storage) will still have subscriptions, but the price will drop to barely above cost. Same logic applies: easy to copy means no pricing power.</p>
<h2>Apple isn't fighting this</h2>
<p>I thought Apple to tighten App Store review to slow down the flood of apps. Instead they put Claude in Xcode. They're not just okay with AI-generated apps—they're actively supporting it.</p>
<p>The revenue numbers back this up. App Store grew 11% in 2025, Google Play 5%. There's still tons of unmet demand, especially for niche use cases that were never worth building before. Lower development costs mean these niches finally get served.</p>
<h2>Developer perspective</h2>
<p>This sucks for developers trying to make a living from apps. The competitive pressure is going to be brutal. But for users? It's great. People have been complaining about app subscription costs for years. There's that old complaint: "Why do I have to keep paying for software after I already paid $1000 for my iPhone?"</p>
<p>That might actually become reality now.</p></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Amazon, Google Unwittingly Reveal the Severity of the U.S. Surveillance State (864 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://greenwald.substack.com/p/amazons-ring-and-googles-nest-unwittingly</link>
            <guid>47023238</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 12:42:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://greenwald.substack.com/p/amazons-ring-and-googles-nest-unwittingly">https://greenwald.substack.com/p/amazons-ring-and-googles-nest-unwittingly</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47023238">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!MwWG!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!MwWG!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!MwWG!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!MwWG!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!MwWG!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!MwWG!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic" width="1456" height="971" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:971,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:1996048,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/heic&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://greenwald.substack.com/i/187789911?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!MwWG!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!MwWG!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!MwWG!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!MwWG!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a><figcaption><em>One of Google’s Nest surveillance cameras, whose recordings can be accessed          by Google even if users don’t subscribe to the security firm’s services.                   </em><span>CC Photo Lab / Shutterstock</span></figcaption></figure></div><p><strong>That the U.S. Surveillance State is</strong><span> rapidly growing to the point of ubiquity has been demonstrated over the past week by seemingly benign events. While the picture that emerges is grim, to put it mildly, at least Americans are again confronted with crystal clarity over how severe this has become.</span></p><p><span>The latest round of valid panic over privacy began during the Super Bowl held on Sunday. During the game, Amazon ran </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OheUzrXsKrY" rel="">a commercial</a><span> for its Ring camera security system. The ad manipulatively exploited people’s love of dogs to induce them to ignore the consequences of what Amazon was touting. It seems that trick did not work.</span></p><p>The ad highlighted what the company calls its “Search Party” feature, whereby one can upload a picture, for example, of a lost dog. Doing so will activate multiple other Amazon Ring cameras in the neighborhood, which will, in turn, use AI programs to scan all dogs, it seems, and identify the one that is lost. The 30-second commercial was full of heart-tugging scenes of young children and elderly people being reunited with their lost dogs.</p><p>But the graphic Amazon used seems to have unwittingly depicted how invasive this technology can be. That this capability now exists in a product that has long been pitched as nothing more than a simple tool for homeowners to monitor their own homes created, it seems, an unavoidable contrast between public understanding of Ring and what Amazon was now boasting it could do.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0JUB!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0JUB!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0JUB!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0JUB!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0JUB!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0JUB!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png" width="2424" height="1243" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1243,&quot;width&quot;:2424,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:5364048,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://greenwald.substack.com/i/187789911?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd64d01cc-601f-4649-bf9d-c537edb2bff8_2968x1522.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0JUB!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0JUB!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0JUB!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0JUB!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"></picture></div></a><figcaption><em>Amazon’s Super Bowl ad for Ring and its “Search Party” feature.</em></figcaption></figure></div><p>Many people were not just surprised but quite shocked and alarmed to learn that what they thought was merely their own personal security system now has the ability to link with countless other Ring cameras to form a neighborhood-wide (or city-wide, or state-wide) surveillance dragnet. That Amazon emphasized that this feature is available (for now) only to those who “opt-in” did not assuage concerns.</p><p><span>Numerous media outlets sounded the alarm. The online privacy group Electronic Frontier Foundation (EFF) </span><a href="https://abc7chicago.com/post/ring-flock-partnership-amazon-scraps-surveillance-company-safety-super-bowl-commercial-backlash/18596207/" rel="">condemned</a><span> Ring’s program as previewing “a world where biometric identification could be unleashed from consumer devices to identify, track, and locate anything — human, pet, and otherwise.”</span></p><p><span>Many private citizens who previously used Ring also reacted negatively. “Viral videos online show people removing or destroying their cameras over privacy concerns,” </span><a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2026/02/10/ring-super-bowl-ad-dog-camera-privacy/88606738007/" rel="">reported</a><span> USA Today. The backlash became so severe that, just days later, Amazon — seeking to assuage public anger — </span><a href="https://abc7chicago.com/post/ring-flock-partnership-amazon-scraps-surveillance-company-safety-super-bowl-commercial-backlash/18596207/" rel="">announced</a><span> the termination of a partnership between Ring and Flock Safety, a police surveillance tech company (while Flock is unrelated to Search Party, public backlash made it impossible, at least for now, for Amazon to send Ring’s user data to a police surveillance firm).</span></p><p>The Amazon ad seems to have triggered a long-overdue spotlight on how the combination of ubiquitous cameras, AI, and rapidly advancing facial recognition software will render the term “privacy” little more than a quaint concept from the past. As EFF put it, Ring’s program “could already run afoul of biometric privacy laws in some states, which require explicit, informed consent from individuals before a company can just run face recognition on someone.”</p><p>Those concerns escalated just a few days later in the context of the Tucson disappearance of Nancy Guthrie, mother of long-time TODAY Show host Savannah Guthrie. At the home where she lives, Nancy Guthrie used Google’s Nest camera for security, a product similar to Amazon’s Ring.</p><p><span>Guthrie, however, did not pay Google for a subscription for those cameras, instead solely using the cameras for real-time monitoring. As CBS News </span><a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/cybersecurity-experts-nancy-guthrie-surveillance-footage-recovery/" rel="">explained</a><span>, “with a free Google Nest plan, the video should have been deleted within 3 to 6 hours — long after Guthrie was reported missing.” Even professional privacy advocates have understood that customers who use Nest without a subscription will not have their cameras connected to Google’s data servers, meaning that no recordings will be stored or available for any period beyond a few hours.</span></p><p><span>For that reason, Pima County Sheriff Chris Nanos </span><a href="https://fortune.com/2026/02/11/privacy-concerns-nancy-guthrie-google-nest-camera-footage-kidnapping/" rel="">announced</a><span> early on “that there was no video available in part because Guthrie didn’t have an active subscription to the company.” Many people, for obvious reasons, prefer to avoid permanently storing comprehensive daily video reports with Google of when they leave and return to their own home, or who visits them at their home, when, and for how long.</span></p><p>Despite all this, FBI investigators on the case were somehow magically able to “recover” this video from Guthrie’s camera many days later. FBI Director Kash Patel was essentially forced to admit this when he released still images of what appears to be the masked perpetrator who broke into Guthrie’s home. (The Google user agreement, which few users read, does protect the company by stating that images may be stored even in the absence of a subscription.)</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OWb9!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OWb9!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OWb9!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OWb9!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OWb9!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OWb9!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png" width="920" height="642" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:642,&quot;width&quot;:920,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:689574,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://greenwald.substack.com/i/187789911?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OWb9!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OWb9!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OWb9!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OWb9!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption><em>Image obtained through Nancy Guthrie’s unsubscribed Google Nest camera and released by the FBI.</em></figcaption></figure></div><p>While the “discovery” of footage from this home camera by Google engineers is obviously of great value to the Guthrie family and law enforcement agents searching for Guthrie, it raises obvious yet serious questions about why Google, contrary to common understanding, was storing the video footage of unsubscribed users. A former NSA data researcher and CEO of a cybersecurity firm, Patrick Johnson, told CBS: “There's kind of this old saying that data is never deleted, it's just renamed.”</p><p><strong>It is rather remarkable that</strong><span> Americans are being led, more or less willingly, into a state-corporate, Panopticon-like domestic surveillance state with relatively little resistance, though the widespread reaction to Amazon’s Ring ad is encouraging. Much of that muted reaction may be due to a lack of realization about the severity of the evolving privacy threat. Beyond that, privacy and other core rights can seem abstract and less of a priority than more material concerns, at least until they are gone.</span></p><p>It is always the case that there are benefits available from relinquishing core civil liberties: allowing infringements on free speech may reduce false claims and hateful ideas; allowing searches and seizures without warrants will likely help the police catch more criminals, and do so more quickly; giving up privacy may, in fact, enhance security.</p><p>But the core premise of the West generally, and the U.S. in particular, is that those trade-offs are never worthwhile. Americans still all learn and are taught to admire the iconic (if not apocryphal) 1775 words of Patrick Henry, which came to define the core ethos of the Revolutionary War and American Founding: “Give me liberty or give me death.” It is hard to express in more definitive terms on which side of that liberty-versus-security trade-off the U.S. was intended to fall.</p><p><span>These recent events emerge in a broader context of this new Silicon Valley-driven destruction of individual privacy. Palantir’s federal contracts for domestic surveillance and domestic data management continue to expand rapidly, with more and more intrusive data about Americans consolidated under the control of this </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JypG_o7HWT0" rel="">one sinister corporation</a><span>.</span></p><p><span>Facial recognition technology — now fully in use for an array of purposes from Customs and Border Protection at airports to ICE’s patrolling of American streets — means that fully tracking one’s movements in public spaces is easier than ever, and is becoming easier by the day. It was only three years ago that we </span><a href="https://x.com/systemupdate_/status/1712828792320778590" rel="">interviewed</a><span> </span><em>New York Times</em><span> reporter Kashmir Hill about her new book, “Your Face Belongs to Us.” The warnings she issued about the dangers of this proliferating technology have not only come true with startling speed but also appear already beyond what even she envisioned.</span></p><p>On top of all this are advances in AI. Its effects on privacy cannot yet be quantified, but they will not be good. I have tried most AI programs simply to remain abreast of how they function.</p><p>After just a few weeks, I had to stop my use of Google’s Gemini because it was compiling not just segregated data about me, but also a wide array of information to form what could reasonably be described as a dossier on my life, including information I had not wittingly provided it. It would answer questions I asked it with creepy, unrelated references to the far-too-complete picture it had managed to create of many aspects of my life (at one point, it commented, somewhat judgmentally or out of feigned “concern,” about the late hours I was keeping while working, a topic I never raised).</p><p>Many of these unnerving developments have happened without much public notice because we are often distracted by what appear to be more immediate and proximate events in the news cycle. The lack of sufficient attention to these privacy dangers over the last couple of years, including at times from me, should not obscure how consequential they are.</p><p><span>All of this is particularly remarkable, and particularly disconcerting, since we are barely more than a decade removed from the disclosures about mass domestic surveillance enabled by the courageous whistleblower Edward Snowden. Although most of our reporting focused on state surveillance, one of </span><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/jun/06/us-tech-giants-nsa-data" rel="">the first stories</a><span> featured the joint state-corporate spying framework built in conjunction with the U.S. security state and Silicon Valley giants.</span></p><p><span>The Snowden stories sparked years of anger, attempts at reform, changes in diplomatic relations, and even genuine (albeit forced) </span><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/11/19/technology/end-to-end-encryption.html" rel="">improvements</a><span> in Big Tech’s user privacy. But the calculation of the U.S. security state and Big Tech was that at some point, attention to privacy concerns would disperse and then virtually evaporate, enabling the state-corporate surveillance state to march on without much notice or resistance. At least as of now, the calculation seems to have been vindicated.</span></p></div></article></div><div><div id="discussion"><h4>Discussion about this post</h4></div><div><h3>Ready for more?</h3></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>