<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 22:30:05 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PayPal (USA) will automatically share data about you to participating stores (116 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.paypal.com/us/legalhub/upcoming-policies-full</link>
            <guid>41822178</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 20:19:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.paypal.com/us/legalhub/upcoming-policies-full">https://www.paypal.com/us/legalhub/upcoming-policies-full</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41822178">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section id="upcoming-policies-full-introduction"><p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-544"><strong data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-545">Notice of Amendment(s) to the United States PayPal Agreement(s)</strong></p>

<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-547"><strong data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-548">This Page</strong></p>
<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-549">This page details and/or previews updates to PayPal users of changes to the United States PayPal User Agreement or other online agreements, policies, or statements that require notice.<span data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-550">&nbsp;</span><a href="https://www.paypal.com/legalhub/archive-policies-full" title="Past Policy Updates" pa-marked="1" data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-551"><strong data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-552">You can also review Past Policy Updates notices</strong></a>. Note that additional changes could be made to previewed agreements on or before the effective dates listed, provided the applicable notice requirements are met.</p>
<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-553"><strong data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-554">Upcoming Changes</strong></p>
<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-555">We’re making changes to certain agreements (listed below) that govern your relationship with PayPal. These changes will take place automatically on the corresponding effective date(s) shown below.</p>
<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-556"><strong data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-557">Actions Needed</strong></p>
<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-558">Please carefully review the notices below and familiarize yourself with the upcoming changes. By continuing to use our services after the changes take effect, you agree to be bound by those changes. Otherwise, no further action is needed from you to accept such changes. However, if you would prefer to decline them, then you will need to close your PayPal account prior to the applicable effective date, as described in the user agreement.</p>

<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-560"><strong data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-561">Notices</strong></p>
<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-562">Issued: September 23, 2024</p>
<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-563"><strong data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-564">Amendments to the PayPal Privacy Statement</strong><br data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-565"><strong data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-566">Effective November 27, 2024:</strong></p>
<ul data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-567">
    <li data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-568">We are updating our Privacy Statement to explain how, starting early Summer 2025, we will share information to help improve your shopping experience and make it more personalized for you. The key update to the Privacy Statement explains how we will share information with merchants to personalize your shopping experience and recommend our services to you. Personal information we disclose includes, for example, products, preferences, sizes, and styles we think you’ll like. Information gathered about you after the effective date of our updated Privacy Statement, November 27, 2024, will be shared with participating stores where you shop, unless you live in California, North Dakota, or Vermont. For PayPal customers in California, North Dakota, or Vermont, we’ll only share your information with those merchants if you tell us to do so. No matter where you live, you’ll always be able to exercise your right to opt out of this data sharing by updating your preference settings in your account under “Data and Privacy.”</li>
    <li data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-569">We are also making other updates to our Privacy Statement including some additional disclosures related to your right, depending on the jurisdiction in which you reside, to ask us for a list of the third parties to which we have disclosed personal information, and to provide other clarifying information. </li>

</ul>
<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-570">
    <a href="https://www.paypal.com/us/legalhub/preview-privacy-full-effective-november272024" target="_blank" pa-marked="1" data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-571">Review the updated PayPal Privacy Statement </a>
</p>


<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-572">
    <a href="https://www.paypal.com/us/legalhub/preview-privacy-states-effective-november272024" target="_blank" pa-marked="1" data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-573">Review the new California, North Dakota, and Vermont Supplemental Financial Privacy Notice </a>
</p>

<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-576"><strong data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-577">Amendments to PayPal's Seller Protection Program<br data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-578">Effective November 18, 2024:</strong></p>
<ul data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-579">
    <li data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-580">We are revising the ‘Basic Requirements’ for PayPal’s Seller Protection program to include integration requirements for sellers who have integrated a PayPal Checkout product with their website.</li>
    <li data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-581">We are revising PayPal’s Seller Protection Program to extend eligibility to Guest Checkout transactions received by accounts registered in certain countries.</li>
</ul>
<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-582"><a href="https://www.paypalobjects.com/marketing/ua/pdf/US/en/spp-111824.pdf" target="_blank" pa-marked="1" data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-583">Review the updated Seller Protection Program</a></p>


<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-585"><strong data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-586">Amendments to the PayPal Online Payment Services Agreement <br data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-587">Effective November 18, 2024:</strong></p>
<ul data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-588">
    <li data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-589">We are changing this agreement to introduce a new service which will enable merchants to accept Automated Clearing House (“ACH”) payments, allowing their customers to use their bank accounts as a payment method.</li>
    <li data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-590">Consequently, we are also renaming the PayPal Online Card Payment Services Agreement, and all references thereto, to the PayPal Online Payment Services Agreement.</li>
    <li data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-591">We are also changing our Merchant fee page to introduce new fees relating to this service.</li>
</ul>
<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-592"><a href="https://www.paypalobjects.com/marketing/ua/pdf/US/en/popsa-full-111824.pdf" target="_blank" pa-marked="1" data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-593">Review the updated PayPal Online Payment Services Agreement</a></p>

<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-594"><a href="https://www.paypalobjects.com/marketing/ua/pdf/US/en/merchant-fee-111824.pdf" target="_blank" pa-marked="1" data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-595">Review the updated Merchant Fees page</a></p>

<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-596"><a href="https://www.paypalobjects.com/marketing/ua/pdf/US/en/ach-services-addendum-111824.pdf" target="_blank" pa-marked="1" data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-597">Review the new ACH Services Addendum</a></p>

<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-599"><strong data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-600">Discontinuation of the PayPal Fundraisers Program<br data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-601">Effective: October 7, 2024:</strong></p>
<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-602">On October 7, 2024, PayPal will disable the ability to create Fundraisers.</p>
<ul data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-603">
    <li data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-604">All current Fundraisers will remain open until they expire.</li>
    <li data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-605">You will need to move any funds from your existing Fundraisers into your PayPal balance no later than January 12, 2025. If you do not do so, we will move any remaining funds into your PayPal balance on January 13, 2025.</li>
    <li data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-606">If you have created a Fundraiser for Charity, please keep a copy of the list of contributors to your Fundraiser for Charity for your records, as this information will no longer be available after January 12, 2025. You will be able to continue to track contributor information for other Fundraisers in your account activity.</li>
</ul>
<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-607"><span data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-608">The PayPal Fundraisers Terms and Conditions will be removed from our Legal Agreements for PayPal Services page on January 13, 2025. If you wish to retain a copy of the relevant terms, please visit our website and download a copy prior to that date. A pdf copy of the PayPal Fundraisers Terms and Conditions and corresponding fees are also available using the links below.</span></p>
<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-609"><a href="https://www.paypalobjects.com/marketing/ua/pdf/US/en/pp-fundraisers-tnc-092324.pdf" target="_blank" pa-marked="1" data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-610">PayPal Fundraisers Terms and Conditions </a></p>

<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-611"><a href="https://www.paypalobjects.com/marketing/ua/pdf/US/en/Merchant%20-%20fee-%20081424.pdf" target="_blank" pa-marked="1" data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-612">Merchant Fees page </a></p>

<p data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-613"><a href="https://www.paypalobjects.com/marketing/ua/pdf/US/en/Consumer-fee-011624.pdf" target="_blank" pa-marked="1" data-ppui-id="ppui-suggestion-614">Consumer Fees page</a></p></section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The ACF plugin on the WordPress directory has been taken over by WordPress.org (232 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/wp_acf/status/1845169499064107049</link>
            <guid>41821400</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 18:46:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/wp_acf/status/1845169499064107049">https://twitter.com/wp_acf/status/1845169499064107049</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41821400">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Secure Custom Fields by WordPress.org (110 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://wordpress.org/plugins/advanced-custom-fields/</link>
            <guid>41821336</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 18:38:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://wordpress.org/plugins/advanced-custom-fields/">https://wordpress.org/plugins/advanced-custom-fields/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41821336">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
		
<div id="tab-description">
	
	<p>Secure Custom Fields (SCF) turns WordPress sites into a fully-fledged content management system by giving you all the tools to do more with your data.</p>
<p>Use the SCF plugin to take full control of your WordPress edit screens, custom field data, and more.</p>
<p><strong>Add fields on demand.</strong><br>
The SCF field builder allows you to quickly and easily add fields to WP edit screens with only the click of a few buttons! Whether it’s something simple like adding an “author” field to a book review post, or something more complex like the structured data needs of an ecommerce site or marketplace, SCF makes adding fields to your content model easy.</p>
<p><strong>Add them anywhere.</strong><br>
Fields can be added all over WordPress including posts, pages, users, taxonomy terms, media, comments and even custom options pages! It couldn’t be simpler to bring structure to the WordPress content creation experience.</p>
<p><strong>Show them everywhere.</strong><br>
Load and display your custom field values in any theme template file with our hassle-free, developer friendly functions! Whether you need to display a single value or generate content based on a more complex query, the out-of-the-box functions of SCF make templating a dream for developers of all levels of experience.</p>
<p><strong>Any Content, Fast.</strong><br>
Turning WordPress into a true content management system is not just about custom fields. Creating new custom post types and taxonomies is an essential part of building custom WordPress sites. Registering post types and taxonomies is now possible right in the SCF UI, speeding up the content modeling workflow without the need to touch code or use another plugin.</p>
<p><strong>Simply beautiful and intentionally accessible.</strong><br>
For content creators and those tasked with data entry, the field user experience is as intuitive as they could desire while fitting neatly into the native WordPress experience. Accessibility standards are regularly reviewed and applied, ensuring SCF is able to empower as close to anyone as possible.</p>
<p><strong>Documentation and developer guides.</strong><br>
Over 10 plus years of vibrant community contribution alongside an ongoing commitment to clear documentation means that you’ll be able to find the guidance you need to build what you want.</p>
<h4>Features</h4>
<ul>
<li>Simple &amp; Intuitive</li>
<li>Powerful Functions</li>
<li>Over 30 Field Types</li>
<li>Extensive Documentation</li>
<li>Millions of Users</li>
</ul></div>

<div id="screenshots">
	
	<ul><li><figure><a href="https://ps.w.org/advanced-custom-fields/assets/screenshot-1.jpg?rev=3167679" rel="nofollow"><img decoding="async" src="https://ps.w.org/advanced-custom-fields/assets/screenshot-1.jpg?rev=3167679" alt=""></a><figcaption><p>Simple &amp; Intuitive</p></figcaption></figure></li><li><figure><a href="https://ps.w.org/advanced-custom-fields/assets/screenshot-2.jpg?rev=3167679" rel="nofollow"><img decoding="async" src="https://ps.w.org/advanced-custom-fields/assets/screenshot-2.jpg?rev=3167679" alt=""></a><figcaption><p>Made for Developers</p></figcaption></figure></li><li><figure><a href="https://ps.w.org/advanced-custom-fields/assets/screenshot-3.jpg?rev=3167679" rel="nofollow"><img decoding="async" src="https://ps.w.org/advanced-custom-fields/assets/screenshot-3.jpg?rev=3167679" alt=""></a><figcaption><p>All About Fields</p></figcaption></figure></li><li><figure><a href="https://ps.w.org/advanced-custom-fields/assets/screenshot-4.jpg?rev=3167679" rel="nofollow"><img decoding="async" src="https://ps.w.org/advanced-custom-fields/assets/screenshot-4.jpg?rev=3167679" alt=""></a><figcaption><p>Registering Custom Post Types</p></figcaption></figure></li><li><figure><a href="https://ps.w.org/advanced-custom-fields/assets/screenshot-5.jpg?rev=3167679" rel="nofollow"><img decoding="async" src="https://ps.w.org/advanced-custom-fields/assets/screenshot-5.jpg?rev=3167679" alt=""></a><figcaption><p>Registering Taxonomies</p></figcaption></figure></li></ul></div>

<div id="tab-reviews">
	
	<div>
							<article>
					<p><img alt="" src="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/bf074d0d7a71c0804bf72d675dcc9bee?s=60&amp;d=retro&amp;r=g" srcset="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/bf074d0d7a71c0804bf72d675dcc9bee?s=120&amp;d=retro&amp;r=g 2x" height="60" width="60">					</p><div>
						<header>
							
							
						</header>
						<p>So many powerful things possible because of ACF.</p>
					</div>
				</article>
							<article>
					<p><img alt="" src="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/c680a8dc5e64c81ef2cc0834ba949f9d?s=60&amp;d=retro&amp;r=g" srcset="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/c680a8dc5e64c81ef2cc0834ba949f9d?s=120&amp;d=retro&amp;r=g 2x" height="60" width="60">					</p><div>
						<header>
							
							
						</header>
						<p>I probably would use a different framework if it wasn’t for ACF.  Also make sure you download ACF from the creator’s site because they can’t update here at the moment.</p>
					</div>
				</article>
							<article>
					<p><img alt="" src="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/9edd84d4340307ac77da98e902a9f4c2?s=60&amp;d=retro&amp;r=g" srcset="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/9edd84d4340307ac77da98e902a9f4c2?s=120&amp;d=retro&amp;r=g 2x" height="60" width="60">					</p><div>
						<header>
							
							
						</header>
						<p>ACF has always been the best choice (IMHO) for custom fields in WordPress. After WP Engine acquired ACF, it’s gotten even better! Thanks to their developers, the GUI has been vastly improved and you can now create custom post types in ACF. I look forward to a future with the WP Engine team in it!</p>
					</div>
				</article>
							<article>
					<p><img alt="" src="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/87c9bb3486d7280acfda3815409a474a?s=60&amp;d=retro&amp;r=g" srcset="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/87c9bb3486d7280acfda3815409a474a?s=120&amp;d=retro&amp;r=g 2x" height="60" width="60">					</p><div>
						<header>
							
							
						</header>
						<p>Great plugin for demanding custom fields. Everything that good developer needs!</p>
					</div>
				</article>
							<article>
					<p><img alt="" src="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/337d759f095e1f31f874b553bffe3942?s=60&amp;d=retro&amp;r=g" srcset="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/337d759f095e1f31f874b553bffe3942?s=120&amp;d=retro&amp;r=g 2x" height="60" width="60">					</p><div>
						<header>
							
							
						</header>
						<p>I used to write little custom plugins to create custom post types, custom taxonomies, and custom meta data for them. This simplifies the process with a rock solid easy to use interface that drastically reduces the time need to build anything out.



It does everything, is easily transportable between projects, &amp; repeatable. Like butter!</p>
					</div>
				</article>
							<article>
					<p><img alt="" src="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/8e826a449b099c9960502c9c1bde7fee?s=60&amp;d=retro&amp;r=g" srcset="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/8e826a449b099c9960502c9c1bde7fee?s=120&amp;d=retro&amp;r=g 2x" height="60" width="60">					</p><div>
						<header>
							
							
						</header>
						<p>Advanced Custom Fields speeds up the development time of complex projects. Rather than spending countless hours coding custom functionality, we leverage ACF to get the job done in half the time. As long as it can be imagined, it can be accomplished using ACF.</p>
					</div>
				</article>
					</div>

		<p><a href="https://wordpress.org/support/plugin/advanced-custom-fields/reviews/">
			Read all 1,224 reviews		</a></p></div>

<div id="tab-developers"><p>“Secure Custom Fields” is open source software. The following people have contributed to this plugin.</p><p><span>Contributors</span></p>

		</div>

<div id="tab-changelog">
	
	<h4>6.3.6.2</h4>
<p><em>Release Date 12th October 2024</em></p>
<ul>
<li>Security – Harden fix in 6.3.6.1 to cover $_REQUEST as well.</li>
<li>Fork – Change name of plugin to Secure Custom Fields.</li>
</ul>
<h4>6.3.6.1</h4>
<p><em>Release Date 7th October 2024</em></p>
<ul>
<li>Security – ACF defined Post Type and Taxonomy metabox callbacks no longer have access to $_POST data. (Thanks to the Automattic Security Team for the disclosure)</li>
</ul></div>
	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Starship Flight 5 license issued by FAA (175 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://drs.faa.gov/browse/excelExternalWindow/DRSDOCID173891218620231102140506.0001?modalOpened=true</link>
            <guid>41820785</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 17:23:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://drs.faa.gov/browse/excelExternalWindow/DRSDOCID173891218620231102140506.0001?modalOpened=true">https://drs.faa.gov/browse/excelExternalWindow/DRSDOCID173891218620231102140506.0001?modalOpened=true</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41820785">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Germany's 49-euro ticket resulted in significant modal shift from road to rail (248 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.mcc-berlin.net/en/news/information/information-detail/article/49-euro-ticket-resulted-in-significant-modal-shift-from-road-to-rail.html</link>
            <guid>41819481</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 14:47:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.mcc-berlin.net/en/news/information/information-detail/article/49-euro-ticket-resulted-in-significant-modal-shift-from-road-to-rail.html">https://www.mcc-berlin.net/en/news/information/information-detail/article/49-euro-ticket-resulted-in-significant-modal-shift-from-road-to-rail.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41819481">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemscope="itemscope" itemtype="http://schema.org/Article"><p>
                            MCC analysis for the Ariadne energy transition project shows 30 percent more rail journeys. The announced increase in price to 58 euros per month undoes half of this.
                        </p><div><p><a href="https://www.mcc-berlin.net/fileadmin/_processed_/0/8/csm_241008_Hauptbahnhof_K%C3%B6ln_2474346251_Shutterstock-Dimitrios_1000_36b46f6c07.jpg" data-fancybox="" data-caption="Cologne Central Station"><img title="Cologne Central Station" src="https://www.mcc-berlin.net/fileadmin/_processed_/0/8/csm_241008_Hauptbahnhof_K%C3%B6ln_2474346251_Shutterstock-Dimitrios_1000_4b66de10e5.jpg" width="880" height="600" alt=""></a></p><p>Cologne Central Station: tThanks to the 49-euro ticket, there are significantly more train journeys and much lower CO<sub>2</sub> emissions.
                                                    
                                                        | Photo: Shutterstock/Dimitrios
                                                    
                                                    </p></div><p>
                            08.10.2024
                        </p><div><p>The state-subsidised 49-euro ”Deutschland-Ticket”, which allows you to travel by local and regional bus and rail throughout Germany for a month, has led to a significant shift in traffic from road to rail. This has now been determined by a research team from the Berlin-based climate research institute MCC (Mercator Research Institute on Global Commons and Climate Change) for the <a href="https://www.mcc-berlin.net/en/news/information/information-detail/article/shaping-the-energy-transition-together-kopernikus-project-ariadne-launched.html" target="_blank">Ariadne</a> energy transition project funded by the Federal Ministry of Education and Research. With regard to the future modal split, the announced price increase to 58 euros per month is highly counterproductive. Detailed results can be viewed interactively on a web-based German-language ”Ariadne D-Ticket Impact Tracker”.</p><p>The research team looked at the first 12 months since the introduction of the Deutschland-Ticket on 1 May 2023. It statistically evaluated mobile phone and car movement data for Germany, as well as data from a control group of eight other European countries. This allowed the team to determine the causal effect of the Deutschland-Ticket on peoples’s mobility behaviour for the first time.</p><p>According to the study, the Deutschland-Ticket increased the number of train journeys of more than 30 kilometres by 30.4 percent compared to what would have been the case without the measure. By contrast, personal transport was noticeably more moderate across all distances, with 7.6 percent fewer kilometres travelled by car. Because the Deutschland-Ticket did not change the total number of trips across all transport modes – including bike, plane, car and train – this means that the share of train journeys (“modal split”) rose from around 10 percent to 12 percent. This saved around 6.7 million tonnes of CO<sub>2</sub> emissions, corresponding to 4.7 percent of total transport emissions in Germany.</p><p>Based on their empirical analyses, the researchers also predict how the announced price increase will change people’s mobility behaviour, and thus emissions. At a special meeting on 23 September 2024, the transport ministers of the German federal states decided to increase the price of the Deutschland-Ticket from 49 to 58 euros per month. The research team concludes that train journeys may decrease by 14 percent as a result of the price increase, and that kilometres travelled by car may increase by 3.5 percent. This means that the price hike could almost halve the reduction in emissions achieved with the 49-euro ticket in its first year.</p><p>The statistical impact analysis, including changes in mobility patterns, differences between districts, and the extent of emission reductions, can be viewed in the interactive German-language Ariadne D-Ticket Impact Tracker.</p><p><strong>Go to the D-Ticket Impact Tracker:</strong><br><a href="https://mcc-berlin-ariadne.shinyapps.io/dticket-tracker/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">https://mcc-berlin-ariadne.shinyapps.io/dticket-tracker/</a></p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The phone ban has had a big impact on school work (145 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://icelandmonitor.mbl.is/news/news/2024/10/09/the_phone_ban_has_had_a_big_impact_on_school_work/</link>
            <guid>41819442</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 14:43:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://icelandmonitor.mbl.is/news/news/2024/10/09/the_phone_ban_has_had_a_big_impact_on_school_work/">https://icelandmonitor.mbl.is/news/news/2024/10/09/the_phone_ban_has_had_a_big_impact_on_school_work/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41819442">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    <p><a href="https://c.arvakur.is/frimg/1/52/4/1520426.jpg" id="a1520426" target="_blank" title="Valdimar Víðisson, the headmaster of Öldutúnsskóli says that the phoneban has been well received, both by students and their parents." rel="newsimgs"><img src="https://c.arvakur.is/frimg/1/52/4/1520426.jpg" alt="Valdimar Víðisson, the headmaster of Öldutúnsskóli says that the phoneban …" width="730" height="486"></a>
    </p>
      <p>
        Valdimar Víðisson, the headmaster of Öldutúnsskóli says that the phoneban has been well received, both by students and their parents.
          <span>Composite image</span>
      </p>
  </div><div>
        
  
    

        
          <p>
 A phone ban has been in place at Öldutún School since the beginning of 2019, and according to the principal, it has worked well. The school's atmosphere and culture have changed for the better, and there is more peace in the classroom.
</p>

        
          <p>
 However, the headmaster Valdimar Víðisson says that it has not been separately studied whether the phone ban has had a positive effect on literacy and interest in reading. Still, Öldutúnsskóli has scored considerably above average regarding interest in reading.
</p>

        
          

        
          <p>
 "We haven't connected it to the phones directly, but it would be interesting to look at it separately." However, we see this in an improved school culture, and cyberbullying has decreased significantly during school hours with this measure and is now hardly existent."
</p>

        
          <h3>
 More screen time reduces interest
</h3>

        
          <p>
 It has been reported in Morgunblaðið that students who spend more time on smartphones are less interested in reading than those who use their phones little or not at all.
</p>

        
          <p>
 The interest in reading is waning faster and faster as students spend more time on their smart devices.
</p>

        
          <p>
 These are the results of research by Kristján Ketill Stefánsson, assistant professor of pedagogy at the University of Iceland's Faculty of Education. The research is based on data from more than fifteen thousand students in grades 6 to 10 in 120 elementary schools across the country.
</p>

        
          <p>
 Everything seems to indicate that more screen time reduces children's interest in reading.
</p>

        
          <h3>
 The ban was prepared for a whole year
</h3>

        
          <p>
 Stefánsson does not necessarily think it is wise to encourage a general ban on mobile phones in schools, but rather implement some kind of phone “holiday”.
</p>

        
          <p>
 Öldutúnsskóli has, however, taken the route of completely banning the use of phones during school hours. The phone ban is in place in all year groups of the school, from 1st to 10th grade, and the headmaster says he is not about to drop it.
</p>

        
          <p>
 Víðisson says he realizes that phones can be a safety device and that children use them, for example, after the school day ends to reach their parents. "The phone is therefore not prohibited in the building, but its use is not allowed during school hours," he explains.
</p>

        
          <p>
 Both students and parents have welcomed the phone ban, as it was prepared for a whole year in collaboration with the board of the student association, school council and parents, according to Víðisson.
</p>

        
          
  
  

  



        
          <p>
 "We did a lot of things in return, for example, we opened a new space for the teenagers that they designed, so there was no dissatisfaction with this at the time and it has not arisen. People just know that using phones is not allowed, and if the kids are sneaking to use the phone and an employee is nearby, they are very quick to react and know that this is not allowed."
</p>

        
          <h3>
 Phones may not be taken from students
</h3>

        
          <p>
 When asked if phones are taken from students if they don't follow the rules, he says they haven't done so as the school doesn't have the authority to do so.
</p>

        
          <p>
 "However, we have the authority to request that the phone be left at home and that the parents make sure that it does not come to school. But in general, the same applies to violations of telephone rules and violations of other rules. It depends on a certain process, after a certain time there is a meeting with the parents and so on," he says.
</p>

        
          <p>
 "If this is a problem for a child, it has been worked with parents, and in some cases phones have had to be left at home for a while and something like that."
</p>

        
          <h3>
 Spend much less time on the phone
</h3>

        
          <p>
 Stefánsson’s study results also revealed that the majority of children in the top three grades of primary school spend an hour a day or more on smartphones during school hours. There are even examples of children spending up to three hours a day on the phone during school hours.
</p>

        
          <p>
 The headmaster says that in Skólapúlsinn (research portal for schools) it is clearly stated that the children in Öldutúnsskóli, and other schools where the phone ban is in place, spend much less time on the phone than their peers, or less than 30 minutes a day. In Skólapúlsinn, the children themselves answer questions about school work, well-being, activity in studies, and more, and the information is collected without revealing personal information.
</p>

        
          <p>
 "This has fixed and improved the atmosphere at our school and there is much better work peace during lessons. The kids know what the rules are, if they are using the phone, there are certain penalties for that, so it has become part of their culture that the phone is not a teaching tool."
</p>

        
          <p>
 The kids talk more and the teenagers use the new space to play table tennis, pool, and more, listen to music, and play chess.
</p>

    

  

  

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Windows 11 24H2 hoards 8.63 GB of junk you can't delete (139 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theregister.com/2024/10/11/windows_update_cleanup/</link>
            <guid>41818815</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 13:13:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/10/11/windows_update_cleanup/">https://www.theregister.com/2024/10/11/windows_update_cleanup/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41818815">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="body">
<p>Windows 11 24H2 users are finding there is undeletable data that remains on their devices after installing the recently released feature update.</p>
<div><p><img src="https://regmedia.co.uk/2024/05/23/shuttertock_copilot.jpg?x=174&amp;amp;y=115&amp;amp;crop=1" width="174" height="115" alt="Microsoft Copilot logo"></p><h2 title="Complete with Copilot Vision – but sessions won't be stored, insists Redmond">Microsoft hits go on Windows 11 24H2: Fresh features, bugs, and a whole lotta AI</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/10/02/windows_11_24h2/"><span>READ MORE</span></a></p></div>
<p>The known issues list has not grown in the days since the rollout on October 15, however, for many users – this writer included – attempts to clean up the detritus after the update has left 8.63 GB of disk space occupied by "Windows Update Cleanup."</p>
<p>Having file remnants after a Windows update is not unusual, and, according to Microsoft, "Windows keeps copies of all installed updates from Windows Update, even after installing newer versions of updates." Space taken up by the old versions can be reclaimed – at least that's the idea.</p>
<p>The Windows Settings application or the delightfully retro Disk Cleanup tool can be used to clear the temporary files from storage.</p>
<p>However, that 8.63 GB of data appears to persist regardless of how often a user attempts to delete it or restarts Windows 11. A scan of Microsoft's Feedback Hub confirms numerous users are affected.</p>
<ul>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/10/10/pc_market_gartner_canalys/">PC shipments stuck in neutral despite AI buzz</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/10/09/windows_patch_tuesday_fixes/">Microsoft cleans up hot mess of Patch Tuesday preview</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/10/09/copilot_vs_notebooklm/">Copilot's crudeness has left Microsoft chasing Google, again</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/10/08/patch_tuesday_october_2024/">Microsoft issues 117 patches – some for flaws already under attack</a></li>
</ul>
<p><i>El Reg</i> asked Microsoft if it was aware of the problem and when it would be addressed. The Windows vendor has yet to respond - which is pretty much par for the course these days. However, it likely has something to do with how updates are handled in the brave new world of Windows 11 24H2.</p>
<p>In July, Microsoft <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/07/16/microsoft_introduces_checkpoint_cumulative_updates/">said</a> it would implement checkpoint cumulative updates in Windows 11 24H2 and Windows Server 2025. The stated goal of this change is to reduce the size of updates, but a consequence is that a checkpoint is needed from which to start. This is likely the reason why that 8.63 GB appears for some users.</p>

    

<p>The problem is that Windows 11 lists those files as old updates that the user can delete, even when the clean-up tools cannot remove the files. It is possible to remove them manually, but doing so could cause issues when the next set of updates arrive.</p>

        

<p>The need for storage is unlikely to change in the near future. However, the way Windows reports its use will itself need to be updated for the sake of all of those users confused about why they cannot reclaim the space that Windows insists they can. ®</p>                                


                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How I Animate 3Blue1Brown (539 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rbu7Zu5X1zI</link>
            <guid>41818779</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 13:06:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rbu7Zu5X1zI">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rbu7Zu5X1zI</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41818779">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Six transplant patients in Brazil contract HIV from infected organs (137 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.reuters.com/world/americas/six-transplant-patients-brazil-contract-hiv-infected-organs-2024-10-11/</link>
            <guid>41818775</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 13:05:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/americas/six-transplant-patients-brazil-contract-hiv-infected-organs-2024-10-11/">https://www.reuters.com/world/americas/six-transplant-patients-brazil-contract-hiv-infected-organs-2024-10-11/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41818775">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.reuters.com/world/americas/six-transplant-patients-brazil-contract-hiv-infected-organs-2024-10-11/: Error: Request failed with status code 401]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[FreeBSD: How Can We Make It More Attractive to New Users? (103 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://gyptazy.com/freebsd-how-can-we-make-it-more-attractive-to-new-users/</link>
            <guid>41818595</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 12:30:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://gyptazy.com/freebsd-how-can-we-make-it-more-attractive-to-new-users/">https://gyptazy.com/freebsd-how-can-we-make-it-more-attractive-to-new-users/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41818595">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>For nearly 15 years, FreeBSD has been at the core of my personal infrastructure, and my passion for it has only grown over time. As a die-hard fan, I’ve stuck with BSD-based systems because they continue to deliver exactly what I need—storage, networking, and security—without missing a beat. The features I initially fell in love with, like ZFS, jails, and pf, are still rock-solid and irreplaceable. There’s no need to overhaul them, and in many ways, that reliability is what keeps me hooked. My scripts from 20 years ago still work, and that’s a rare kind of stability that few platforms can boast.</p><p>It’s not just me, either—big names like Netflix, Microsoft, and NetApp, alongside companies like Tailscale and AMD, continue to support FreeBSD, further reinforcing my belief in its strength and longevity (you can find the donators and sponsors right <a href="https://freebsdfoundation.org/our-donors/donors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="">here</a>). Yet, while this familiarity is comforting, it’s becoming clear that FreeBSD must evolve to keep pace with the modern landscape of computing.</p><p>In the early days, FreeBSD’s offerings felt revolutionary. Its core features and tools were a breath of fresh air compared to alternatives. But the tech world has changed, and in many ways, FreeBSD needs to catch up. We can’t just cling to what works and ignore the demand for modern features. The challenge isn’t just maintaining a functional and minimalistic system—it’s about embracing newer technologies without losing the simplicity and stability that make FreeBSD special.</p><p>Take virtualization, for example. Years ago, Xen, Proxmox, and VMware were the leading solutions, and FreeBSD had its answer in bhyve. But here we are in 2024, and while bhyve works, there’s still no stable support for live migrations of VMs – a feature that enterprises consider crucial. In the world of IT, nobody wants to schedule maintenance windows to patch systems and reboot hosts. It’s inefficient and outdated. Some are working hard to improve this, but for now, it’s more of a proof of concept than a production-ready solution but it is needed and fully appreciated! At this points also thanks to the developers (<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/oleg-ginzburg-7bb51317/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="">Oleg Ginzburg</a>, Oleg Minin and also <a href="https://papers.freebsd.org/2019/bsdcan/mihailescu-migrating_a_bhyve_guest/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="">Elena Mihailescu</a> and Mihai Carabaș) behind <a href="https://www.bsdstore.ru/en/about.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="">cbsd</a> and <a href="https://clonos.convectix.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="">CloneOS</a> (you can find a blog post about ClonOS from me <a href="https://gyptazy.com/clonos-an-alternative-to-proxmox-based-on-freebsd/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="">here</a>). You can find the interesting papers about it <a href="https://papers.freebsd.org/2019/BSDCan/mihailescu-Migrating_a_bhyve_guest.files/mihailescu-Migrating_a_bhyve_guest.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="">here</a>. But would I use it in production right now? I guess not and many others wouldn’t either.</p><p>Virtualization itself is starting to feel like yesterday’s news. The trend is clearly shifting toward containerization, whether in on-prem solutions or via hyperscalers. FreeBSD, however, is still playing catch-up here too. Podman now supports running Linux containers on FreeBSD 14, but it’s still experimental. Sure, people argue that FreeBSD’s jails are better than other container solutions, and that may well be true. But it doesn’t help users who need to deal with prebuilt images from their colleagues or other companies. Compatibility and ease of use matter, and jails aren’t always the answer when everyone else is using something else.</p><p>This brings me to the heart of the issue. FreeBSD needs to adapt faster and more comprehensively to modern demands if we want to make it attractive to a wider audience. Sure, it’s simple, and that’s a big part of why I love it. But the attitude of “it works for me” isn’t enough anymore. I don’t represent the whole user base, and neither do the people who say everything’s fine as it is. We need to appeal to newcomers, and that means making FreeBSD more accessible and user-friendly, not a system that requires workarounds for basic, modern use cases.</p><p>One of the ongoing challenges for FreeBSD has been its support for devices like Bluetooth, WiFi, and other hardware components on notebooks and desktop systems. While FreeBSD excels in server environments and embedded systems, the user experience on laptops can be frustrating due to the lack of out-of-the-box support for some critical hardware features. Most users want their machines to simply work without needing to tinker with drivers or configurations. Whether it’s connecting to WiFi, using Bluetooth peripherals, or suspending and resuming from sleep mode, these basic features are essential for a smooth, modern computing experience.</p><p>Thankfully, change is on the horizon. The <a href="https://freebsdfoundation.org/blog/why-laptop-support-why-now-freebsds-strategic-move-toward-broader-adoption/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="">FreeBSD Foundation has made a strategic</a> move to address these shortcomings. This shift is crucial for keeping FreeBSD competitive in today’s landscape, where laptops and mobile workstations dominate how people interact with technology. Users expect seamless functionality without having to configure every aspect of their machine, and FreeBSD must step up to meet this expectation.</p><p>Currently, FreeBSD lags behind in key areas such as WiFi and Bluetooth support, as well as laptop-specific functionalities like suspend/resume, digital microphone integration, and hardware buttons for volume and audio controls. These missing features make it hard for many to adopt FreeBSD as their daily driver, particularly for professionals or casual users who rely heavily on their laptops. Closing these gaps is vital if FreeBSD is to broaden its appeal and remain relevant in both personal and enterprise computing. As the FreeBSD Foundation continues to push forward, improving laptop support will not only make FreeBSD more accessible but will also help it thrive in a world that increasingly depends on portable devices.</p><p>The system should work out of the box, with support for current technologies. It shouldn’t feel like driving an old, rusty car when what users want is the efficiency of a modern electric vehicle. We can preserve the core simplicity and minimalism of FreeBSD while still updating it to compete with today’s tech landscape. This philosophy is something I’ve tried to bring to life with my <a href="https://boxybsd.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="">BoxyBSD</a> project. The goal is to help newcomers feel comfortable with BSD-based systems, but even that hasn’t been easy. Offering free VPS instances has its challenges, and it’s not just about the technical backend—it’s about making the interface and overall experience inviting too.</p><p>I’ve always believed in minimalism, in the KISS (Keep It Simple, Stupid) principle. But as I’ve promoted my <a href="https://boxybsd.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="">BoxyBSD</a> project at conferences, I’ve encountered a recurring issue: people often ask if the website is broken or if images and CSS files are missing. They’re not! It’s just a super minimal design. Yet this response highlights a shift in expectations. Many IT professionals today don’t engage with the foundational knowledge we once relied on – like reading man pages, mailing lists, and newsgroups. They’re looking to forums, Reddit, and Discord channels instead.</p><p>This shift in how people learn and interact with technology presents a challenge, but also an opportunity. We have a responsibility to teach, to guide, and to show that BSD, especially FreeBSD, isn’t outdated. It’s more than capable of modern workloads, and we should demonstrate that by adopting new tools and methods. Just because we’ve relied on certain systems for years doesn’t mean we should resist all change. With the <a href="https://bsd.cafe/" title="">BSD Cafe</a> which is operated by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/stefano-marinelli-657a746/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="">Stefano Marinelli</a>, we already have a great place for all kind of BSD enthusiasts in place, also providing an own <a href="https://mastodon.bsd.cafe/home" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="">Fediverse</a> instance and also Matrix Chat as a replacement for Discord but it about us to make people on proprietary platforms aware of this. With the started <a href="https://wiki.bsd.cafe/docs:weekly-bsdpub">BSD Pub weekly</a> meetings by Stefano and <a href="https://gyptazy.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="">gyptazy</a> (me), we also encourage new users to get in touch with the community and to learn in live workshops.</p><p>That’s why I’m evolving too – changing the design of my blog engine (away from <a href="https://github.com/gyptazy/manpageblog" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="">manpageblog</a>, even it’s really cool), moving to more modern solutions, and proving that FreeBSD can stay relevant in a modern way. FreeBSD is not some relic of the past. It’s a robust, adaptable system that, with the right direction, can thrive in the future. Let’s do it together!</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Bug, $50k how Zendesk left a backdoor in Fortune 500 companies (818 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://gist.github.com/hackermondev/68ec8ed145fcee49d2f5e2b9d2cf2e52</link>
            <guid>41818459</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 11:55:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://gist.github.com/hackermondev/68ec8ed145fcee49d2f5e2b9d2cf2e52">https://gist.github.com/hackermondev/68ec8ed145fcee49d2f5e2b9d2cf2e52</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41818459">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>
    1 bug, $50,000+ in bounties, how Zendesk intentionally left a backdoor in hundreds of Fortune 500 companies
  </p><div id="file-zendesk-md">
    <article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto">hi, i'm daniel. i'm a 15-year-old with some programming experience and i do a little bug hunting in my free time. here's the insane story of how I found a single bug that affected over half of all Fortune 500 companies:</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 dir="auto">say hello to zendesk</h2><a id="user-content-say-hello-to-zendesk" aria-label="Permalink: say hello to zendesk" href="#say-hello-to-zendesk"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If you've spent some time online, you’ve probably come across Zendesk.</p>
<p dir="auto">Zendesk is a customer service tool used by some of the world’s top companies. It’s easy to set up: you link it to your company’s support email (like <a href="mailto:support@company.com">support@company.com</a>), and Zendesk starts managing incoming emails and creating tickets. You can handle these tickets yourself or have a support team do it for you. Zendesk is a billion-dollar company, trusted by big names like Cloudflare.</p>
<p dir="auto">Personally, I’ve always found it surprising that these massive companies, worth billions, rely on third-party tools like Zendesk instead of building their own in-house ticketing systems.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 dir="auto">your weakest link</h2><a id="user-content-your-weakest-link" aria-label="Permalink: your weakest link" href="#your-weakest-link"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">As the saying goes, “You’re only as strong as your weakest link.” Since Zendesk is just seen as a basic ticketing tool, companies often set it up without much thought. The most common setup I've seen is is forwarding all emails from <code>support@company.com</code> to Zendesk.</p>
<p dir="auto">Why is that dangerous? Many companies use their @company.com domain for Single Sign-On (SSO), which lets employees quickly log in to internal tools. By connecting Zendesk to the same domain, companies unknowingly create a potential security gap. Zendesk handles all emails for the domain it’s configured for, which means if your SSO system doesn’t properly validate email addresses, anyone who gains access to your Zendesk could potentially exploit this and access your internal systems. (I’ll explain more on this later.)</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 dir="auto">email spoofing</h2><a id="user-content-email-spoofing" aria-label="Permalink: email spoofing" href="#email-spoofing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">At the beginning of the year, I discovered a serious vulnerability in Zendesk that allowed attackers to read customer support tickets from any company using Zendesk. All they had to do was sent a crafted email to a Support email handled by Zendesk. The shocking part? Zendesk didn’t seem to care.</p>
<p dir="auto">The bug itself was surprisingly simple. Zendesk had no effective protection against email spoofing, and this oversight made it possible to exploit their email collaboration feature to gain access to others’ tickets.</p>
<p dir="auto">Here’s how it worked: When you send an email to a company’s Zendesk support portal (e.g., <code>support@company.com</code>), Zendesk creates a new support ticket. To keep track of the email thread, Zendesk automatically generates a reply-to address, which looks like this: <code>support+id{id}@company.com</code>, where <code>{id}</code> is the unique ticket number. This address ensures that any future replies you send go directly to the same ticket.</p>
<p dir="auto">Zendesk also has a feature for ticket collaboration. If you CC someone on one of your email replies, Zendesk automatically adds them to the ticket, allowing them to see the full ticket history in the support portal.</p>
<p dir="auto">The exploit was simple: if an attacker knew the support email address and the ticket ID (which are usually easy to guess since ticket IDs are incremental), they could use email spoofing to impersonate the original sender. By sending a fake email to <code>support+id{id}@company.com</code> from the requestor’s email address and CCing their own email, Zendesk would think the email was legitimate. It would then add the attacker’s email to the ticket, giving them full access to the entire ticket history.</p>
<p dir="auto">This meant an attacker could effectively join any ongoing support conversation, and read sensitive information—all because Zendesk didn’t have proper safeguards against email spoofing.</p>
<p dir="auto">Bug Prerequisites:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Requestor's email</li>
<li>The ticket ID (since Zendesk ticket IDs are incremental, an attacker could brute-force or estimate it)</li>
<li>Access to a public support portal</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 dir="auto">"out of scope," said no attacker ever</h2><a id="user-content-out-of-scope-said-no-attacker-ever" aria-label="Permalink: &quot;out of scope,&quot; said no attacker ever" href="#out-of-scope-said-no-attacker-ever"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">As soon as I discovered this vulnerability, I reported it through Zendesk’s bug bounty program, fully expecting it to be taken seriously and fixed quickly. A week later, I was hit with a disappointing response:
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/60828015/375600604-ac8f16ef-97a5-4519-a6fd-d49c0ac0c7fe.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3Mjg3NDM3MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcyODc0MzQwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii82MDgyODAxNS8zNzU2MDA2MDQtYWM4ZjE2ZWYtOTdhNS00NTE5LWE2ZmQtZDQ5YzBhYzBjN2ZlLnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDEwMTIlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQxMDEyVDE0MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTg0Mjc3ZWNiNDM3OWM0NTNhZjhmYmRhOWI5NjIwN2I1MTRlYTAwMTQzZjQ5NjgwNzFiZTRhNjRmYjk1NjNjMTImWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0In0.oTxsd_74qUSKGtFMPUPOpRyYaUttViJ2k9DdmPMLdxQ"><img width="782" alt="image" src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/60828015/375600604-ac8f16ef-97a5-4519-a6fd-d49c0ac0c7fe.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3Mjg3NDM3MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcyODc0MzQwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii82MDgyODAxNS8zNzU2MDA2MDQtYWM4ZjE2ZWYtOTdhNS00NTE5LWE2ZmQtZDQ5YzBhYzBjN2ZlLnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDEwMTIlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQxMDEyVDE0MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTg0Mjc3ZWNiNDM3OWM0NTNhZjhmYmRhOWI5NjIwN2I1MTRlYTAwMTQzZjQ5NjgwNzFiZTRhNjRmYjk1NjNjMTImWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0In0.oTxsd_74qUSKGtFMPUPOpRyYaUttViJ2k9DdmPMLdxQ"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Because my bug relied on email spoofing, which was considered "out of scope" for their HackerOne program, they rejected my report. It was unbelievable.</p>
<p dir="auto">This response wasn’t even from an actual Zendesk team member. Many companies, like Zendesk, use a HackerOne service to triage reports so their own team can focus on fixing bugs instead of verifying submissions. Realizing this, I asked for the report to be forwarded to an actual Zendesk staff member for review. A few days later, I got another frustrating reply:</p>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/60828015/375601586-ffd6f4e7-d772-4f53-b4f3-4e32a43d3905.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3Mjg3NDM3MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcyODc0MzQwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii82MDgyODAxNS8zNzU2MDE1ODYtZmZkNmY0ZTctZDc3Mi00ZjUzLWI0ZjMtNGUzMmE0M2QzOTA1LnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDEwMTIlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQxMDEyVDE0MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTJmZTM4MmUxNWU3Y2YwYzFjODUwZjBhNjE1MTExNzU0MjU1YTliNWE3YTE4YWNlYTE0OTZlNGJjNWZhZDQyODQmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0In0.0BdRRac2M802ceXf6WHDOyeJw62HCftjI3LnvXVOzPY"><img width="949" alt="image" src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/60828015/375601586-ffd6f4e7-d772-4f53-b4f3-4e32a43d3905.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3Mjg3NDM3MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcyODc0MzQwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii82MDgyODAxNS8zNzU2MDE1ODYtZmZkNmY0ZTctZDc3Mi00ZjUzLWI0ZjMtNGUzMmE0M2QzOTA1LnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDEwMTIlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQxMDEyVDE0MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTJmZTM4MmUxNWU3Y2YwYzFjODUwZjBhNjE1MTExNzU0MjU1YTliNWE3YTE4YWNlYTE0OTZlNGJjNWZhZDQyODQmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0In0.0BdRRac2M802ceXf6WHDOyeJw62HCftjI3LnvXVOzPY"></a>
<p dir="auto">Zendesk refused to reconsider. Despite the security risk, they wouldn’t act on the report because it fell outside their program’s scope. Of course, they’d change their minds in a few weeks—but more on that later.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 dir="auto">escalating this to a full Slack takeover</h2><a id="user-content-escalating-this-to-a-full-slack-takeover" aria-label="Permalink: escalating this to a full Slack takeover" href="#escalating-this-to-a-full-slack-takeover"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">I could have reported the email spoofing bug to individual companies that were affected by it, as it was possible to patch individual instances by disabling email collaboration, prevent attackers from adding themselves to tickets. But I wanted to make a bigger impact.</p>
<p dir="auto">That's when I came across <a href="https://medium.com/intigriti/how-i-hacked-hundreds-of-companies-through-their-helpdesk-b7680ddc2d4c" rel="nofollow">TICKETTRICK</a>, a blog post from 2017. In it, security researcher Inti De Ceukelaire detailed how he exploited Zendesk to infiltrate the private Slack workspaces of hundreds of companies. Since many companies use Slack SSO on the same domain as Zendesk, the researcher figured out he could complete email verifications through a <code>support@company.com</code> email, and gain access to private Slack channels. Back then, Zendesk wasn't as big and there were some bugs that allowed anyone to view your tickets if they had your email.</p>
<p dir="auto">I realized that I could replicate his exploit using my bug, but with a few challenges to overcome.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 dir="auto">Enter OAuth</h3><a id="user-content-enter-oauth" aria-label="Permalink: Enter OAuth" href="#enter-oauth"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">After his disclosure (this was years ago!), Slack changed their email verification system to include a random token in email addresses.</p>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/60828015/375606032-eb140eaa-541e-4546-bd8e-fd675b6ab43e.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3Mjg3NDM3MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcyODc0MzQwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii82MDgyODAxNS8zNzU2MDYwMzItZWIxNDBlYWEtNTQxZS00NTQ2LWJkOGUtZmQ2NzViNmFiNDNlLnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDEwMTIlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQxMDEyVDE0MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPWRkMjkxMTc0NzFlYjU3ZDEwNWExY2RlN2E3YmY3NDIyYjgxOTBmOWU4MGViMzNmOGNkMzg1NDUyZTVkNmZkYzMmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0In0.JABKUgYyC4K6hWpJC8_gAoVScp-xGDB2pykSUGXo97M"><img width="327" alt="image" src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/60828015/375606032-eb140eaa-541e-4546-bd8e-fd675b6ab43e.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3Mjg3NDM3MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcyODc0MzQwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii82MDgyODAxNS8zNzU2MDYwMzItZWIxNDBlYWEtNTQxZS00NTQ2LWJkOGUtZmQ2NzViNmFiNDNlLnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDEwMTIlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQxMDEyVDE0MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPWRkMjkxMTc0NzFlYjU3ZDEwNWExY2RlN2E3YmY3NDIyYjgxOTBmOWU4MGViMzNmOGNkMzg1NDUyZTVkNmZkYzMmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0In0.JABKUgYyC4K6hWpJC8_gAoVScp-xGDB2pykSUGXo97M"></a>
<p dir="auto">Inti's exploit (like mine) required the attacker to know the sending email address of the verification code. Slack added random tokens to their email addresses to combat similar attacks in the future. It was impossible to know what email they would send the verification email from (which is one of the prerequisites required for my exploit) as they generated a random token everytime. Unless...</p>
<p dir="auto">While Slack used a random email token when sending email verification, neither Google or Apple did. Slack supported both methods for OAuth login.</p>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/60828015/375606552-fa1760ab-8ae0-4b1b-a172-6d4ba2463b95.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3Mjg3NDM3MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcyODc0MzQwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii82MDgyODAxNS8zNzU2MDY1NTItZmExNzYwYWItOGFlMC00YjFiLWExNzItNmQ0YmEyNDYzYjk1LnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDEwMTIlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQxMDEyVDE0MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPWViNTYyY2RiMDRhYTE1OGEzNjM4ZTcyZDdlYWUwZDZhMzQxMjNkMzMwNjI0MjA4NTg3NWYyNTA4ZDYwM2NmMjcmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0In0.PP5EuOkpMX4g4hYA6P4QsNzHpbmpnDKNp-BXiCqilrw"><img width="477" alt="image" src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/60828015/375606552-fa1760ab-8ae0-4b1b-a172-6d4ba2463b95.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3Mjg3NDM3MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcyODc0MzQwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii82MDgyODAxNS8zNzU2MDY1NTItZmExNzYwYWItOGFlMC00YjFiLWExNzItNmQ0YmEyNDYzYjk1LnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDEwMTIlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQxMDEyVDE0MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPWViNTYyY2RiMDRhYTE1OGEzNjM4ZTcyZDdlYWUwZDZhMzQxMjNkMzMwNjI0MjA4NTg3NWYyNTA4ZDYwM2NmMjcmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0In0.PP5EuOkpMX4g4hYA6P4QsNzHpbmpnDKNp-BXiCqilrw"></a>
<p dir="auto">It was the most simple bypass. Slack intoduced OAuth login just a few years ago and must have completely forgotten about their protections against this type of attacks.</p>
<p dir="auto">So now the exploit was simple, create a Google account with a <code>support@company.com</code> email, request verification code, use my bug to access the ticket Zendesk automatically creates when it arrives, verify Google account, login with Google to Slack.</p>
<p dir="auto">This was perfect...except it wouldn't work with Google. Google sent verification email from <code>noreply@google.com</code> and Zendesk had started blocking emails from <code>noreply@</code> addresses from being automatically created as tickets (probably after the TICKETTRICK disclosure too) which meant we wouldn't be able to recieve it.</p>
<p dir="auto">Apple didn't do this though, Apple sent verification emails from <code>appleid@</code> address, jackpot.
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/60828015/375607789-92f473e1-4aef-4e50-a92c-d486480b842d.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3Mjg3NDM3MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcyODc0MzQwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii82MDgyODAxNS8zNzU2MDc3ODktOTJmNDczZTEtNGFlZi00ZTUwLWE5MmMtZDQ4NjQ4MGI4NDJkLnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDEwMTIlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQxMDEyVDE0MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTE2ZjQyYmZiNzcxNmQxMzI5ZWY1ZTQ0Zjk3ZDVhNTNjMmRmMGNlYmNjYzExOGRmMGFjY2ZkOThkYjBhYWUxMjImWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0In0.pompxjaGOHbkNw0Qn1_K_IBW0yNGwi-87Fds6-MJ5jA"><img width="336" alt="image" src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/60828015/375607789-92f473e1-4aef-4e50-a92c-d486480b842d.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3Mjg3NDM3MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcyODc0MzQwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii82MDgyODAxNS8zNzU2MDc3ODktOTJmNDczZTEtNGFlZi00ZTUwLWE5MmMtZDQ4NjQ4MGI4NDJkLnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDEwMTIlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQxMDEyVDE0MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTE2ZjQyYmZiNzcxNmQxMzI5ZWY1ZTQ0Zjk3ZDVhNTNjMmRmMGNlYmNjYzExOGRmMGFjY2ZkOThkYjBhYWUxMjImWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0In0.pompxjaGOHbkNw0Qn1_K_IBW0yNGwi-87Fds6-MJ5jA"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 dir="auto">reproduction steps, apple -&gt; zendesk -&gt; slack</h2><a id="user-content-reproduction-steps-apple---zendesk---slack" aria-label="Permalink: reproduction steps, apple -> zendesk -> slack" href="#reproduction-steps-apple---zendesk---slack"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The steps to execute the attack now were simple:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Create an Apple account with <code>support@company.com</code> email and request a verification code, Apple sends verification code from <code>appleid@id.apple.com</code> to <code>support@company.com</code> and Zendesk automatically creates a ticket</li>
<li>At the same time, create a ticket on <code>company.com</code> support portal from my own email address, this allows me to keep track of a ID range</li>
<li>Use the email spoofing bug I mentioned earlier to attempt to add yourself to every ticket within the range from earlier</li>
</ol>
<div dir="auto"><pre><span>const</span> <span>sendmail</span> <span>=</span> <span>require</span><span>(</span><span>'sendmail'</span><span>)</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>

<span>// Assuming the ticket you created in step #2 was assigned a ticket ID of #453 </span>
<span>// verification email landed somewhere near there</span>
<span>const</span> <span>range</span> <span>=</span> <span>[</span><span>448</span><span>,</span> <span>457</span><span>]</span><span>;</span>
<span>for</span> <span>(</span><span>let</span> <span>i</span> <span>=</span> <span>range</span><span>[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span>;</span> <span>i</span> <span>&lt;</span> <span>range</span><span>[</span><span>1</span><span>]</span><span>;</span> <span>i</span><span>++</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>// Send spoofed emails from Apple to Zendesk</span>
    <span>sendmail</span><span>(</span><span>{</span>
        <span>from</span>: <span>'appleid@id.apple.com'</span><span>,</span>
        <span>to</span>: <span>`support+id<span><span>${</span><span>i</span><span>}</span></span>@company.com`</span><span>,</span>
        <span>cc</span>: <span>'daniel@wearehackerone.com'</span><span>,</span>
        <span>subject</span>: <span>''</span><span>,</span>
        <span>html</span>: <span>'comment body'</span><span>,</span>
    <span>}</span><span>,</span> <span>function</span> <span>(</span><span>err</span><span>,</span> <span>reply</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
        <span>console</span><span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span><span>err</span> <span>&amp;&amp;</span> <span>err</span><span>.</span><span>stack</span><span>)</span>
        <span>console</span><span>.</span><span>dir</span><span>(</span><span>reply</span><span>)</span>
    <span>}</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>}</span><span>;</span></pre></div>
<ol start="4" dir="auto">
<li>Login to a company.com support portal (usually at support.company.com) from your account (<code>daniel@wearehackerone.com</code>) and view your CCed tickets.</li>
<li></li>
</ol>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/60828015/375897466-267284d0-af09-456a-90f1-fa89d93588ab.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3Mjg3NDM3MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcyODc0MzQwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii82MDgyODAxNS8zNzU4OTc0NjYtMjY3Mjg0ZDAtYWYwOS00NTZhLTkwZjEtZmE4OWQ5MzU4OGFiLnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDEwMTIlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQxMDEyVDE0MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPWRjOTc4OWRjOGI5YWQzOTJmNGFlMjhhNTU1ODZlYWJmYTI0ZWViNDk3NzRjYmQ5OTBmZjJkY2FkMGNhZTQ0M2EmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0In0.HfyHyE5f7guem9Rj6tk-HclDnTOWPLK0LMRzGZuBz2E"><img width="307" alt="image" src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/60828015/375897466-267284d0-af09-456a-90f1-fa89d93588ab.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3Mjg3NDM3MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcyODc0MzQwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii82MDgyODAxNS8zNzU4OTc0NjYtMjY3Mjg0ZDAtYWYwOS00NTZhLTkwZjEtZmE4OWQ5MzU4OGFiLnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDEwMTIlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQxMDEyVDE0MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPWRjOTc4OWRjOGI5YWQzOTJmNGFlMjhhNTU1ODZlYWJmYTI0ZWViNDk3NzRjYmQ5OTBmZjJkY2FkMGNhZTQ0M2EmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0In0.HfyHyE5f7guem9Rj6tk-HclDnTOWPLK0LMRzGZuBz2E"></a>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/60828015/375620769-aee5ce24-d805-4f43-bbc3-c57a0454a2c5.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3Mjg3NDM3MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcyODc0MzQwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii82MDgyODAxNS8zNzU2MjA3NjktYWVlNWNlMjQtZDgwNS00ZjQzLWJiYzMtYzU3YTA0NTRhMmM1LnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDEwMTIlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQxMDEyVDE0MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPWY1OTRhODdmZDNmOTY1MjExZGQ2YzA2ODg0ZjMyMjFlODY5YmFlOWQ0N2I4N2MzNWFjYjk2Zjc1NDUzMWFlYWQmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0In0.eXmbf7J2eeVytNMbheiLIKCniQu6xO6HaMywBG3iJuo"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/60828015/375620769-aee5ce24-d805-4f43-bbc3-c57a0454a2c5.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3Mjg3NDM3MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcyODc0MzQwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii82MDgyODAxNS8zNzU2MjA3NjktYWVlNWNlMjQtZDgwNS00ZjQzLWJiYzMtYzU3YTA0NTRhMmM1LnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDEwMTIlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQxMDEyVDE0MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPWY1OTRhODdmZDNmOTY1MjExZGQ2YzA2ODg0ZjMyMjFlODY5YmFlOWQ0N2I4N2MzNWFjYjk2Zjc1NDUzMWFlYWQmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0In0.eXmbf7J2eeVytNMbheiLIKCniQu6xO6HaMywBG3iJuo" alt="image"></a></p>
<ol start="5" dir="auto">
<li>Enter the verification code in Apple</li>
<li>Use Slack's "Login with Apple" feature and log in with the Apple account connected to company.com's email</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto">I replicated this 6-step reproduction steps across hundreds of vulnerable Zendesk and Slack instances. After getting everything ready, I started individually reporting the bug to companies using Zendesk.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 dir="auto">aftermath</h2><a id="user-content-aftermath" aria-label="Permalink: aftermath" href="#aftermath"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">I spent about a week reporting the vulnerability to individual companies, some of them took immediate action and patched their instances, while others argued that it was a Zendesk issue. Then, something interesting happened—a comment appeared on my original HackerOne report:</p>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/60828015/375613130-2a887c2c-4d8d-4dc7-b0fe-fb44922a629e.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3Mjg3NDM3MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcyODc0MzQwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii82MDgyODAxNS8zNzU2MTMxMzAtMmE4ODdjMmMtNGQ4ZC00ZGM3LWIwZmUtZmI0NDkyMmE2MjllLnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDEwMTIlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQxMDEyVDE0MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPWEyZDYxZDM0MWM5NmQwZmIwMDc3MjBiNWNkMWFhYTY5YjU0ZmVhMzNhNWNlNzU4ZmJjNmFjMDM0ZDcyMWJkOGMmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0In0.-6X5mVopYnxNm0iRHm8NXriA05h3FphRN_LzrHkoVqo"><img width="786" alt="image" src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/60828015/375613130-2a887c2c-4d8d-4dc7-b0fe-fb44922a629e.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3Mjg3NDM3MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcyODc0MzQwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii82MDgyODAxNS8zNzU2MTMxMzAtMmE4ODdjMmMtNGQ4ZC00ZGM3LWIwZmUtZmI0NDkyMmE2MjllLnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDEwMTIlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQxMDEyVDE0MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPWEyZDYxZDM0MWM5NmQwZmIwMDc3MjBiNWNkMWFhYTY5YjU0ZmVhMzNhNWNlNzU4ZmJjNmFjMDM0ZDcyMWJkOGMmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0In0.-6X5mVopYnxNm0iRHm8NXriA05h3FphRN_LzrHkoVqo"></a>
<p dir="auto">I couldn’t help but find it amusing—they were now asking me to keep the report confidential, despite having initially dismissed it as out of scope.</p>
<p dir="auto">Some companies must have contacted Zendesk after recieving my report and the pressure from this issue had essentially forced Zendesk’s hand. I hadn’t mentioned the Slack exploit in my original report to them because I hadn’t discovered it at that point, now they wanted full detailed reproduction steps for the Slack takeover.</p>
<p dir="auto">I provided the proof of concept for the Slack vulnerability, and they confirmed the issue. Though they claimed they had "started working" on a fix, it would actually take them over two months to resolve it.</p>

<p dir="auto">Once companies vulnerable to this were alerted to the issue, many of them quickly disabled Zendesk’s email collaboration feature to protect their instances. Over the course of my reporting, I earned more than $50,000 in bounties from individual companies on HackerOne and other platforms.</p>
<p dir="auto">Unsurprisingly, Zendesk didn’t come out of this looking good. At least one or two companies reportedly cut ties with Zendesk after my disclosure, canceling their agreements altogether.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 dir="auto">zendesk's fix (and my $0 bounty)</h2><a id="user-content-zendesks-fix-and-my-0-bounty" aria-label="Permalink: zendesk's fix (and my $0 bounty)" href="#zendesks-fix-and-my-0-bounty"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">On July 2, 2024—two months after I submitted the report—Zendesk finally confirmed that they had fixed the issue. Here’s a statement from their Offensive Security Leader:</p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">In most cases, when an end user submits a support request by email, the email becomes a new ticket or adds a comment to an existing ticket. However, in certain cases, the email may be suspended. Suspending an email means putting it aside for further review. It's not necessarily spam. It's just not a ticket in Zendesk Support yet. It remains in limbo until somebody reviews it and decides whether to accept or reject it.
We use two spam filters, Cloudmark and Rspamd EAP to help determine suspicious characteristics in messages. Depending on the score received by these tools, messages may be suspended. If you are curious, we publish a full list of causes for ticket suspension.
In the attack scenario explained here, Cloudmark had very low spam scores of while RSpamD had very high spam scores; unfortunately we weren’t using the RSpamD score in this case, otherwise many of the emails would have been suspended and limited the ability to add CCs at all. The first fix we implemented was to Automatically switch to RSPAMD spam analysis when:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Our automatic ticket threading is triggered to thread an new email into a existing ticket and;</li>
<li>We haven’t previously suspended the message due to the Cloudmark score.
In addition to this, we also implemented filters to automatically suspend the following classes of emails:
User verification emails sent by Apple based on the Reply-To and Message-Id header values
Non-transactional emails from from <a href="mailto:googleworkspace-noreply@google.com">googleworkspace-noreply@google.com</a>
Over the coming months, we will continue to look into opportunities to strengthen our Sender Authentication functionality and provide customers with more gradual and advanced security controls over the types of emails that get suspended or rejected.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto">Despite fixing the issue, Zendesk ultimately chose not to award a bounty for my report. Their reasoning? I had broken HackerOne's disclosure guidelines by sharing the vulnerability with affected companies. I didn’t bother to argue :)</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 dir="auto">conclusion</h2><a id="user-content-conclusion" aria-label="Permalink: conclusion" href="#conclusion"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">What started as a small email bug turned into an exploit that allowed me to infiltrate the internal systems of some of the world’s largest companies. While Zendesk eventually fixed the vulnerability, the journey to get there was a frustrating mix of rejections, slow responses, and ultimately no recognition for the report. But that’s the reality of bug hunting—sometimes you win, sometimes you don’t.</p>
<p dir="auto">If you enjoyed this write-up and want to stay updated on more of my bug hunting adventures, follow me on Twitter/X <a href="https://x.com/hackermondev" rel="nofollow">@hackermondev</a> for future blog posts and insights.</p>
<p dir="auto">read next? <a href="https://x.com/hackermondev/status/1816625357052588539" rel="nofollow">how I stumbled upon a Discord server and left with a $4000 bounty</a></p>
</article>
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PostgreSQL Streaming Replication (WAL); What It Is and How to Configure One (147 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://mindhub365.com/sql/postgresql-streaming-replication-wal-what-it-is-and-how-to-configure-one/</link>
            <guid>41818446</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 11:52:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://mindhub365.com/sql/postgresql-streaming-replication-wal-what-it-is-and-how-to-configure-one/">https://mindhub365.com/sql/postgresql-streaming-replication-wal-what-it-is-and-how-to-configure-one/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41818446">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

                    
                    <p><img src="https://db32393711be2a93bcb07d997ff0daed.r2.cloudflarestorage.com/mindhub365/media/images/pg_replication.2e16d0ba.fill-800x400.jpg?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Credential=e42d293f04f4efad131e9fdee77b8f02%2F20241012%2Fus-east-1%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20241012T183004Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;X-Amz-Signature=129a6d0747c7b6a19a65519fdf29bbf2e0aeee23733f49e3a0ca926206722ad8" alt="">
                    </p>

                    
                        
                            <h2 data-block-key="hwpsk">What is Streaming replication in PostgreSQL?</h2><p data-block-key="fgj4a">Streaming replication in PostgreSQL is an efficient method for maintaining a near real-time replica of a primary database on one or more standby servers. The primary server continuously sends Write-Ahead Log (WAL) records to standby servers as they are generated, ensuring minimal latency in the replication process. This approach is designed to enhance high availability and scalability, allowing read queries to be offloaded to standby servers, thereby reducing the load on the primary server. Streaming replication supports both synchronous and asynchronous modes, enabling flexibility in balancing data consistency with performance. The process involves the standby server connecting to the primary, requesting WAL streaming, and applying the received records to its own copy of the database. This method provides faster failover and reduces the risk of data loss compared to file-based log shipping, making it ideal for geographically distributed environments.</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            <h2 data-block-key="hwpsk">How Is Streaming Replication Done?</h2><p data-block-key="aj56m">Streaming replication works by continuously transferring Write-Ahead Log (WAL) data from the primary server to the standby server in real-time, keeping the standby's database nearly identical to the primary. This can be used for master failover or for using replicas to handle read operations, allowing your system to scale by orders of magnitude.</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            <h2 data-block-key="hwpsk">Lets Start With PostgreSQL Configuration Files And Where To Find Them?</h2><p data-block-key="7so5c">PostgreSQL configuration files play a crucial role in managing the settings and behavior of the database server. The primary configuration file, `postgresql.conf`, contains most server settings and can be found in different locations depending on the operating system, such as `/etc/postgresql/&lt;version&gt;/main/postgresql.conf` on Debian/Ubuntu and `/var/lib/pgsql/&lt;version&gt;/data/postgresql.conf` on Red Hat/CentOS. Another key file is `pg_hba.conf`, which controls client authentication by defining how clients can connect to the server.</p><p data-block-key="efnfs">This file is typically located in the same directory as `postgresql.conf`. Additionally, `pg_ident.conf` is used for username mapping but is less commonly utilized. For versions prior to PostgreSQL 12, `recovery.conf` was used for configuring standby servers, but its contents have since been moved into `postgresql.conf` and `postgresql.auto.conf`, which stores configuration parameters set by `ALTER SYSTEM` commands.</p><p data-block-key="8qha4">The exact locations of these files can vary based on the operating system, installation method, and PostgreSQL version. To locate these files, the SQL command `SHOW config_file;` can be used within a PostgreSQL instance.</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            
<pre><code id="target-element-current">postgres=# SHOW config_file;
               config_file                
------------------------------------------
 /var/lib/postgresql/data/postgresql.conf</code></pre>

                        
                    
                        
                            <h2 data-block-key="hwpsk">List Of Configuration Files And For What They Are Used</h2><p data-block-key="b6umi"><b><code>postgresql.conf</code></b></p><ul><li data-block-key="c4os6">Primary configuration file</li><li data-block-key="bjfoq">Contains most server settings</li><li data-block-key="3ntgd">Typical locations:<ul><li data-block-key="c2dki"><code>/etc/postgresql/&lt;version&gt;/main/<br>postgresql.conf</code> (Debian/Ubuntu)</li><li data-block-key="fl9h7"><code>/var/lib/pgsql/&lt;version&gt;/data/<br>postgresql.conf</code> (Red Hat/CentOS)</li><li data-block-key="jd86"><code>C:\Program Files\PostgreSQL&lt;version&gt;\data<br>\postgresql.conf</code> (Windows)</li></ul></li></ul><p data-block-key="2gkcs"><b><code>pg_hba.conf</code></b><br></p><ul><li data-block-key="1rdoh">Controls client authentication</li><li data-block-key="69q6v">Defines how clients are allowed to connect to the server</li><li data-block-key="1tjue">Usually in the same directory as <code>postgresql.conf<br></code></li></ul><p data-block-key="7su52"><b><code>pg_ident.conf</code></b><br></p><ul><li data-block-key="3evfm">Used for user name mapping</li><li data-block-key="3618f">Often in the same directory as <code>postgresql.conf</code></li><li data-block-key="d1an1">Less commonly used<br></li></ul><p data-block-key="dkmuq"><b><code>recovery.conf</code></b><b> (for versions prior to 12)</b><br></p><ul><li data-block-key="9ga5o">Used to configure standby servers and recovery settings</li><li data-block-key="7oqqd">In PostgreSQL 12 and later, its contents are moved into <code>postgresql.conf</code> and <code>postgresql.auto.conf</code></li><li data-block-key="9s5k6"><b><code>postgresql.auto.conf</code></b><br></li><li data-block-key="4en3k">Stores configuration parameters set by <code>ALTER SYSTEM</code> commands</li><li data-block-key="3c43s">Automatically managed by PostgreSQL</li><li data-block-key="9g5ad">In the same directory as <code>postgresql.conf<br></code></li></ul><p data-block-key="bb60n"><b>The exact locations can vary depending on:</b><br></p><ul><li data-block-key="e3au9">Operating system</li><li data-block-key="390u7">Installation method</li><li data-block-key="er3nh">PostgreSQL version</li></ul>
                        
                    
                        
                            <h2 data-block-key="oqs8q">Examples of WAL (Write ahead logs) And How They Look Like</h2><p data-block-key="bik2g">you can see them using <code>pg_waldump</code> command:</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            
<pre><code id="target-element-current">pg_waldump /var/lib/postgresql/data/pg_wal/000000010000000000000001</code></pre>

                        
                    
                        
                            
<pre><code id="target-element-current">...
rmgr: Standby     len (rec/tot):     42/    42, tx:       1738, lsn: 0/01938698, prev 0/01938668, desc: LOCK xid 1738 db 5 rel 18065 
rmgr: Heap        len (rec/tot):    203/   203, tx:       1738, lsn: 0/019386C8, prev 0/01938698, desc: INSERT off: 12, flags: 0x00, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/1259 blk 25
rmgr: Btree       len (rec/tot):     64/    64, tx:       1738, lsn: 0/01938798, prev 0/019386C8, desc: INSERT_LEAF off: 394, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/2662 blk 4
rmgr: Btree       len (rec/tot):    112/   112, tx:       1738, lsn: 0/019387D8, prev 0/01938798, desc: INSERT_LEAF off: 110, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/2663 blk 1
rmgr: Btree       len (rec/tot):     64/    64, tx:       1738, lsn: 0/01938848, prev 0/019387D8, desc: INSERT_LEAF off: 229, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/3455 blk 4
rmgr: Heap2       len (rec/tot):    176/   176, tx:       1738, lsn: 0/01938888, prev 0/01938848, desc: MULTI_INSERT ntuples: 1, flags: 0x02, offsets: [36], blkref #0: rel 1663/5/1249 blk 113
rmgr: Btree       len (rec/tot):     80/    80, tx:       1738, lsn: 0/01938938, prev 0/01938888, desc: INSERT_LEAF off: 61, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/2658 blk 28
rmgr: Btree       len (rec/tot):     64/    64, tx:       1738, lsn: 0/01938988, prev 0/01938938, desc: INSERT_LEAF off: 319, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/2659 blk 18
rmgr: Heap        len (rec/tot):    197/   197, tx:       1738, lsn: 0/019389C8, prev 0/01938988, desc: INSERT off: 23, flags: 0x00, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/2610 blk 11
rmgr: Btree       len (rec/tot):     64/    64, tx:       1738, lsn: 0/01938A90, prev 0/019389C8, desc: INSERT_LEAF off: 200, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/2678 blk 1
rmgr: Btree       len (rec/tot):     64/    64, tx:       1738, lsn: 0/01938AD0, prev 0/01938A90, desc: INSERT_LEAF off: 180, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/2679 blk 2
rmgr: Heap2       len (rec/tot):     85/    85, tx:       1738, lsn: 0/01938B10, prev 0/01938AD0, desc: MULTI_INSERT ntuples: 1, flags: 0x02, offsets: [132], blkref #0: rel 1663/5/2608 blk 26
rmgr: Btree       len (rec/tot):     72/    72, tx:       1738, lsn: 0/01938B68, prev 0/01938B10, desc: INSERT_LEAF off: 233, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/2673 blk 20
rmgr: Btree       len (rec/tot):     72/    72, tx:       1738, lsn: 0/01938BB0, prev 0/01938B68, desc: INSERT_LEAF off: 43, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/2674 blk 12
rmgr: XLOG        len (rec/tot):     49/   209, tx:       1738, lsn: 0/01938BF8, prev 0/01938BB0, desc: FPI , blkref #0: rel 1663/5/18065 blk 1 FPW
rmgr: XLOG        len (rec/tot):     49/   137, tx:       1738, lsn: 0/01938CD0, prev 0/01938BF8, desc: FPI , blkref #0: rel 1663/5/18065 blk 0 FPW
rmgr: Heap        len (rec/tot):    188/   188, tx:       1738, lsn: 0/01938D60, prev 0/01938CD0, desc: INPLACE off: 12, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/1259 blk 25
rmgr: Transaction len (rec/tot):    242/   242, tx:       1738, lsn: 0/01938E20, prev 0/01938D60, desc: COMMIT 2024-10-02 21:47:28.453226 UTC; inval msgs: catcache 55 catcache 54 catcache 7 catcache 6 catcache 32 catcache 55 catcache 54 relcache 18065 relcache 17640 snapshot 2608 relcache 17640 relcache 18065
rmgr: Storage     len (rec/tot):     42/    42, tx:          0, lsn: 0/01938F18, prev 0/01938E20, desc: CREATE base/5/18066
rmgr: Standby     len (rec/tot):     42/    42, tx:       1739, lsn: 0/01938F48, prev 0/01938F18, desc: LOCK xid 1739 db 5 rel 18066 
rmgr: Heap        len (rec/tot):    203/   203, tx:       1739, lsn: 0/01938F78, prev 0/01938F48, desc: INSERT off: 13, flags: 0x00, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/1259 blk 25
rmgr: Btree       len (rec/tot):     64/    64, tx:       1739, lsn: 0/01939048, prev 0/01938F78, desc: INSERT_LEAF off: 395, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/2662 blk 4
rmgr: Btree       len (rec/tot):    104/   104, tx:       1739, lsn: 0/01939088, prev 0/01939048, desc: INSERT_LEAF off: 116, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/2663 blk 1
rmgr: Btree       len (rec/tot):     64/    64, tx:       1739, lsn: 0/019390F0, prev 0/01939088, desc: INSERT_LEAF off: 230, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/3455 blk 4
rmgr: Heap2       len (rec/tot):    176/   176, tx:       1739, lsn: 0/01939130, prev 0/019390F0, desc: MULTI_INSERT ntuples: 1, flags: 0x02, offsets: [37], blkref #0: rel 1663/5/1249 blk 113
rmgr: Btree       len (rec/tot):     72/    72, tx:       1739, lsn: 0/019391E0, prev 0/01939130, desc: INSERT_LEAF off: 62, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/2658 blk 28
rmgr: Btree       len (rec/tot):     64/    64, tx:       1739, lsn: 0/01939228, prev 0/019391E0, desc: INSERT_LEAF off: 320, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/2659 blk 18
rmgr: Heap        len (rec/tot):    197/   197, tx:       1739, lsn: 0/01939268, prev 0/01939228, desc: INSERT off: 24, flags: 0x00, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/2610 blk 11
rmgr: Btree       len (rec/tot):     64/    64, tx:       1739, lsn: 0/01939330, prev 0/01939268, desc: INSERT_LEAF off: 201, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/2678 blk 1
rmgr: Btree       len (rec/tot):     64/    64, tx:       1739, lsn: 0/01939370, prev 0/01939330, desc: INSERT_LEAF off: 181, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/2679 blk 2
rmgr: Heap2       len (rec/tot):     85/    85, tx:       1739, lsn: 0/019393B0, prev 0/01939370, desc: MULTI_INSERT ntuples: 1, flags: 0x02, offsets: [133], blkref #0: rel 1663/5/2608 blk 26
rmgr: Btree       len (rec/tot):     72/    72, tx:       1739, lsn: 0/01939408, prev 0/019393B0, desc: INSERT_LEAF off: 234, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/2673 blk 20
rmgr: Btree       len (rec/tot):     72/    72, tx:       1739, lsn: 0/01939450, prev 0/01939408, desc: INSERT_LEAF off: 44, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/2674 blk 12
rmgr: XLOG        len (rec/tot):     49/   205, tx:       1739, lsn: 0/01939498, prev 0/01939450, desc: FPI , blkref #0: rel 1663/5/18066 blk 1 FPW
rmgr: XLOG        len (rec/tot):     49/   137, tx:       1739, lsn: 0/01939568, prev 0/01939498, desc: FPI , blkref #0: rel 1663/5/18066 blk 0 FPW
rmgr: Heap        len (rec/tot):    188/   188, tx:       1739, lsn: 0/019395F8, prev 0/01939568, desc: INPLACE off: 13, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/1259 blk 25
rmgr: Transaction len (rec/tot):    242/   242, tx:       1739, lsn: 0/019396B8, prev 0/019395F8, desc: COMMIT 2024-10-02 21:47:28.457807 UTC; inval msgs: catcache 55 catcache 54 catcache 7 catcache 6 catcache 32 catcache 55 catcache 54 relcache 18066 relcache 17640 snapshot 2608 relcache 17640 relcache 18066
...</code></pre>

                        
                    
                        
                            <p data-block-key="oqs8q">Let me break down some key aspects of this WAL output</p><p data-block-key="7vq74">- Structure: Each line represents a WAL record, containing information about database operations.</p><p data-block-key="pjg8">- Components of each record:</p><ul><li data-block-key="apuc9">- rmgr: Resource manager (e.g., Heap, Btree, Transaction)</li><li data-block-key="auf3d">- len: Length of the record</li><li data-block-key="61vch">- tx: Transaction ID</li><li data-block-key="fbgsu">- lsn: Log Sequence Number</li><li data-block-key="6k0cr">- prev: Previous LSN</li><li data-block-key="3bgic">- desc: Description of the operation</li><li data-block-key="a4ats"></li></ul><p data-block-key="fpq3c">- Types of operations visible:</p><ul><li data-block-key="d6foc">- INSERT operations (Heap and Btree)</li><li data-block-key="fukup">- MULTI_INSERT operations (Heap2)</li><li data-block-key="fqjr5">- COMMIT transactions</li><li data-block-key="4uoqu">- File operations (CREATE)</li><li data-block-key="59h3u">- Full Page Writes (FPW)</li></ul><p data-block-key="b1bko">- Specific examples:</p><ul><li data-block-key="hfnp">- Table inserts: `rmgr: Heap len (rec/tot): 203/203, tx: 1738, lsn: 0/019386C8, prev 0/01938698, desc: INSERT off: 12, flags: 0x00, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/1259 blk 25`</li><li data-block-key="2nr4r">- Index updates: `rmgr: Btree len (rec/tot): 64/ 64, tx: 1738, lsn: 0/01938798, prev 0/019386C8, desc: INSERT_LEAF off: 394, blkref #0: rel 1663/5/2662 blk 4`</li><li data-block-key="cosq2">- Transaction commit: `rmgr: Transaction len (rec/tot): 242/ 242, tx: 1738, lsn: 0/01938E20, prev 0/01938D60, desc: COMMIT 2024-10-02 21:47:28.453226 UTC;`</li></ul><p data-block-key="dosoi">This WAL output provides a detailed view of the database operations, allowing for analysis of transaction flow, data modifications, and system activities. It's particularly useful for understanding database behavior, troubleshooting, and in some cases, for point-in-time recovery.</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            <h2 data-block-key="oqs8q">How to work with them using docker</h2>
                        
                    
                        
                            <p data-block-key="oqs8q">In <b><code>postgresql.conf</code></b>, specific settings are crucial for enabling streaming replication. These settings control how the master and replica instances communicate and synchronize. You will need to modify this configuration for both the master and the replica. Here is the snippet from postgresql.conf related to streaming replication:</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            
<pre><code id="target-element-current">...
# REPLICATION
#------------------------------------------------------------------------------

# - Sending Servers -

# Set these on the primary and on any standby that will send replication data.

#max_wal_senders = 10           # max number of walsender processes
                                # (change requires restart)
#max_replication_slots = 10     # max number of replication slots
                                # (change requires restart)
#wal_keep_size = 0              # in megabytes; 0 disables
#max_slot_wal_keep_size = -1    # in megabytes; -1 disables
#wal_sender_timeout = 60s       # in milliseconds; 0 disables
#track_commit_timestamp = off   # collect timestamp of transaction commit
                                # (change requires restart)

# - Primary Server -

# These settings are ignored on a standby server.

#synchronous_standby_names = '' # standby servers that provide sync rep
                                # method to choose sync standbys, number of sync standbys,
                                # and comma-separated list of application_name
                                # from standby(s); '*' = all

# - Standby Servers -

# These settings are ignored on a primary server.

#primary_conninfo = ''                  # connection string to sending server
#primary_slot_name = ''                 # replication slot on sending server
#hot_standby = on                       # "off" disallows queries during recovery
                                        # (change requires restart)
#max_standby_archive_delay = 30s        # max delay before canceling queries
                                        # when reading WAL from archive;
                                        # -1 allows indefinite delay
#max_standby_streaming_delay = 30s      # max delay before canceling queries
                                        # when reading streaming WAL;
                                        # -1 allows indefinite delay
#wal_receiver_create_temp_slot = off    # create temp slot if primary_slot_name
                                        # is not set
#wal_receiver_status_interval = 10s     # send replies at least this often
                                        # 0 disables
#hot_standby_feedback = off             # send info from standby to prevent
                                        # query conflicts
#wal_receiver_timeout = 60s             # time that receiver waits for
                                        # communication from primary
                                        # in milliseconds; 0 disables
#wal_retrieve_retry_interval = 5s       # time to wait before retrying to
                                        # retrieve WAL after a failed attempt
#recovery_min_apply_delay = 0           # minimum delay for applying changes during recovery

# - Subscribers -
# These settings are ignored on a publisher.

#max_logical_replication_workers = 4    # taken from max_worker_processes
                                        # (change requires restart)
#max_sync_workers_per_subscription = 2  # taken from max_logical_replication_workers
#max_parallel_apply_workers_per_subscription = 2        # taken from max_logical_replication_workers
...</code></pre>

                        
                    
                        
                            <h2 data-block-key="oqs8q">Let's Dive Into Docker Compose Example</h2><p data-block-key="ft3k9">What you will need is:</p><ul><li data-block-key="4oav0"><code>init-master.sh:</code></li><li data-block-key="3dfgd"><code>init-replica.sh</code></li><li data-block-key="f1vlf"><code>start-replica.sh</code></li><li data-block-key="birf0"><code>docker-compose.yml</code></li></ul>
                        
                    
                        
                            <p data-block-key="oqs8q">init-master.sh:</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            
<pre><code id="target-element-current">#!/bin/bash
set -e

psql -v ON_ERROR_STOP=1 --username "$POSTGRES_USER" --dbname "$POSTGRES_DB" &lt;&lt;-EOSQL
  CREATE USER replicator WITH REPLICATION ENCRYPTED PASSWORD 'replicatorpass';
  SELECT pg_create_physical_replication_slot('replica_slot');
EOSQL

cat &gt;&gt; ${PGDATA}/postgresql.conf &lt;&lt;EOF
wal_level = replica
max_wal_senders = 10
max_replication_slots = 10
hot_standby = on
EOF

cat &gt;&gt; ${PGDATA}/pg_hba.conf &lt;&lt;EOF
host replicat</code></pre>

                        
                    
                        
                            <p data-block-key="oqs8q">sets up a PostgreSQL master for replication. It connects to the PostgreSQL server using the provided environment variables for username and database, then creates a replication user (`replicator`) with the necessary permissions. It also creates a replication slot (`replica_slot`) to track the replication process. Next, the script configures PostgreSQL by appending settings to `postgresql.conf`, enabling WAL (Write-Ahead Logging) for replication, setting up replication slots, and enabling hot standby for read-only queries. It also updates `pg_hba.conf` to allow the replication user to connect.</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            <p data-block-key="oqs8q">init-replica.sh</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            
<pre><code id="target-element-current">#!/bin/bash
set -e

echo "Waiting for master to be ready..."
until PGPASSWORD=mypassword psql -h postgres_master -U myuser -d mydb -c '\l' &gt;/dev/null 2&gt;&amp;1; do
  echo "Still waiting..."
  sleep 1
done
echo "Master is ready. Attempting to take base backup..."

# Stop PostgreSQL if it's running
pg_ctl -D "$PGDATA" -m fast -w stop || true

# Remove existing data directory contents
rm -rf $PGDATA/*

PGPASSWORD=replicatorpass pg_basebackup -h postgres_master -D ${PGDATA} -U replicator -v -P --wal-method=stream

echo "Base backup completed. Configuring replica..."

cat &gt;&gt; ${PGDATA}/postgresql.conf &lt;&lt;EOF
hot_standby = on
EOF

cat &gt; ${PGDATA}/postgresql.auto.conf &lt;&lt;EOF
primary_conninfo = 'host=postgres_master port=5432 user=replicator password=replicatorpass application_name=replica1'
EOF

touch ${PGDATA}/standby.signal

echo "Replica configuration complete."</code></pre>

                        
                    
                        
                            <p data-block-key="oqs8q">prepares a PostgreSQL replica to connect to the master and start replication. It waits until the master is fully up and running by continuously checking the connection to the master database. Once the master is ready, it stops the local PostgreSQL instance (if running), removes existing data, and performs a base backup from the master using `pg_basebackup`. After the backup is complete, it configures the replica by enabling `hot_standby` for read-only queries and setting the connection info for the master (including host, user, and password). Finally, it signals PostgreSQL that this instance should act as a standby by creating the `standby.signal` file.</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            <p data-block-key="oqs8q">start-replica.sh</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            
<pre><code id="target-element-current">#!/bin/bash
set -e

# Run the init-replica.sh script
/docker-entrypoint-initdb.d/init-replica.sh

# Start PostgreSQL
exec docker-entrypoint.sh postgres</code></pre>

                        
                    
                        
                            <p data-block-key="oqs8q">is used to start a PostgreSQL replica in a Docker container. It first runs the `init-replica.sh` script to handle the initialization and setup of the replication process. After initializing the replica, the script starts PostgreSQL using the default Docker entrypoint (`docker-entrypoint.sh`) with `postgres` as the argument to run the PostgreSQL service inside the container. The `set -e` ensures that the script exits immediately if any command returns a non-zero status (i.e., on error).</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            <p data-block-key="oqs8q">docker-compose.yml</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            
<pre><code id="target-element-current">services:
  postgres_master:
    image: postgres:14
    container_name: postgres_master
    environment:
      POSTGRES_DB: mydb
      POSTGRES_USER: myuser
      POSTGRES_PASSWORD: mypassword
    volumes:
      - ./pgdata_master:/var/lib/postgresql/data
      - ./init-master.sh:/docker-entrypoint-initdb.d/init-master.sh
    ports:
      - "5432:5432"

  postgres_replica:
    image: postgres:14
    container_name: postgres_replica
    environment:
      POSTGRES_DB: mydb
      POSTGRES_USER: myuser
      POSTGRES_PASSWORD: mypassword
    volumes:
      - ./pgdata_replica:/var/lib/postgresql/data
      - ./init-replica.sh:/docker-entrypoint-initdb.d/init-replica.sh
      - ./start-replica.sh:/start-replica.sh
    ports:
      - "5433:5432"
    depends_on:
      - postgres_master
    command: ["/start-replica.sh"]</code></pre>

                        
                    
                        
                            <p data-block-key="oqs8q">Make the scripts executable (init-master.sh, init-replica.sh, start-replica.sh) with:</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            
<pre><code id="target-element-current">chmod +x ....scripts</code></pre>

                        
                    
                        
                            <p data-block-key="oqs8q">And when you run</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            
<pre><code id="target-element-current">docker-compose up -d</code></pre>

                        
                    
                        
                            <p data-block-key="oqs8q">You should see this output:</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            
<pre><code id="target-element-current">Attaching to postgres_master, postgres_replica
postgres_master   | The files belonging to this database system will be owned by user "postgres".
postgres_master   | This user must also own the server process.
postgres_master   | 
postgres_master   | The database cluster will be initialized with locale "en_US.utf8".
postgres_master   | The default database encoding has accordingly been set to "UTF8".
postgres_master   | The default text search configuration will be set to "english".
postgres_master   | 
postgres_master   | Data page checksums are disabled.
postgres_master   | 
postgres_master   | fixing permissions on existing directory /var/lib/postgresql/data ... ok
postgres_master   | creating subdirectories ... ok
postgres_master   | selecting dynamic shared memory implementation ... posix
postgres_master   | selecting default max_connections ... 100
postgres_master   | selecting default shared_buffers ... 128MB
postgres_master   | selecting default time zone ... Etc/UTC
postgres_master   | creating configuration files ... ok
postgres_master   | running bootstrap script ... ok
postgres_replica  | Waiting for master to be ready...
postgres_replica  | Still waiting...
postgres_master   | performing post-bootstrap initialization ... ok
postgres_master   | initdb: warning: enabling "trust" authentication for local connections
postgres_master   | You can change this by editing pg_hba.conf or using the option -A, or
postgres_master   | --auth-local and --auth-host, the next time you run initdb.
postgres_master   | syncing data to disk ... ok
postgres_master   | 
postgres_master   | 
postgres_master   | Success. You can now start the database server using:
postgres_master   | 
postgres_master   |     pg_ctl -D /var/lib/postgresql/data -l logfile start
postgres_master   | 
postgres_master   | waiting for server to start....2024-10-10 19:12:07.091 UTC [49] LOG:  starting PostgreSQL 14.9 (Debian 14.9-1.pgdg120+1) on x86_64-pc-linux-gnu, compiled by gcc (Debian 12.2.0-14) 12.2.0, 64-bit
postgres_master   | 2024-10-10 19:12:07.095 UTC [49] LOG:  listening on Unix socket "/var/run/postgresql/.s.PGSQL.5432"
postgres_master   | 2024-10-10 19:12:07.106 UTC [50] LOG:  database system was shut down at 2024-10-10 19:12:06 UTC
postgres_master   | 2024-10-10 19:12:07.114 UTC [49] LOG:  database system is ready to accept connections
postgres_master   |  done
postgres_master   | server started
postgres_master   | CREATE DATABASE
postgres_master   | 
postgres_master   | 
postgres_master   | /usr/local/bin/docker-entrypoint.sh: running /docker-entrypoint-initdb.d/init-master.sh
postgres_master   | CREATE ROLE
postgres_master   |  pg_create_physical_replication_slot 
postgres_master   | -------------------------------------
postgres_master   |  (replica_slot,)
postgres_master   | (1 row)
postgres_master   | 
postgres_master   | 
postgres_master   | waiting for server to shut down....2024-10-10 19:12:07.384 UTC [49] LOG:  received fast shutdown request
postgres_master   | 2024-10-10 19:12:07.389 UTC [49] LOG:  aborting any active transactions
postgres_master   | 2024-10-10 19:12:07.392 UTC [49] LOG:  background worker "logical replication launcher" (PID 56) exited with exit code 1
postgres_master   | 2024-10-10 19:12:07.392 UTC [51] LOG:  shutting down
postgres_master   | 2024-10-10 19:12:07.419 UTC [49] LOG:  database system is shut down
postgres_master   |  done
postgres_master   | server stopped
postgres_master   | 
postgres_master   | PostgreSQL init process complete; ready for start up.
postgres_master   | 
postgres_master   | 2024-10-10 19:12:07.527 UTC [1] LOG:  starting PostgreSQL 14.9 (Debian 14.9-1.pgdg120+1) on x86_64-pc-linux-gnu, compiled by gcc (Debian 12.2.0-14) 12.2.0, 64-bit
postgres_master   | 2024-10-10 19:12:07.527 UTC [1] LOG:  listening on IPv4 address "0.0.0.0", port 5432
postgres_master   | 2024-10-10 19:12:07.527 UTC [1] LOG:  listening on IPv6 address "::", port 5432
postgres_master   | 2024-10-10 19:12:07.533 UTC [1] LOG:  listening on Unix socket "/var/run/postgresql/.s.PGSQL.5432"
postgres_master   | 2024-10-10 19:12:07.540 UTC [69] LOG:  database system was shut down at 2024-10-10 19:12:07 UTC
postgres_master   | 2024-10-10 19:12:07.552 UTC [1] LOG:  database system is ready to accept connections
postgres_replica  | Master is ready. Attempting to take base backup...
postgres_replica  | pg_ctl: cannot be run as root
postgres_replica  | Please log in (using, e.g., "su") as the (unprivileged) user that will
postgres_replica  | own the server process.
postgres_replica  | pg_basebackup: initiating base backup, waiting for checkpoint to complete
postgres_replica  | pg_basebackup: checkpoint completed
postgres_replica  | pg_basebackup: write-ahead log start point: 0/2000028 on timeline 1
postgres_replica  | pg_basebackup: starting background WAL receiver
postgres_replica  | pg_basebackup: created temporary replication slot "pg_basebackup_78"
postgres_replica  |     0/34859 kB (0%), 0/1 tablespace (...lib/postgresql/data/backup_label)
postgres_replica  | 27884/34859 kB (79%), 0/1 tablespace (.../postgresql/data/base/16384/1247)
postgres_replica  | 34868/34868 kB (100%), 0/1 tablespace (...ostgresql/data/global/pg_control)
postgres_replica  | 34868/34868 kB (100%), 1/1 tablespace                                         
postgres_replica  | pg_basebackup: write-ahead log end point: 0/2000100
postgres_replica  | pg_basebackup: waiting for background process to finish streaming ...
postgres_replica  | pg_basebackup: syncing data to disk ...
postgres_replica  | pg_basebackup: renaming backup_manifest.tmp to backup_manifest
postgres_replica  | pg_basebackup: base backup completed
postgres_replica  | Base backup completed. Configuring replica...
postgres_replica  | Replica configuration complete.
postgres_replica  | 
postgres_replica  | PostgreSQL Database directory appears to contain a database; Skipping initialization
postgres_replica  | 
postgres_replica  | 2024-10-10 19:12:08.283 UTC [1] LOG:  starting PostgreSQL 14.9 (Debian 14.9-1.pgdg120+1) on x86_64-pc-linux-gnu, compiled by gcc (Debian 12.2.0-14) 12.2.0, 64-bit
postgres_replica  | 2024-10-10 19:12:08.284 UTC [1] LOG:  listening on IPv4 address "0.0.0.0", port 5432
postgres_replica  | 2024-10-10 19:12:08.284 UTC [1] LOG:  listening on IPv6 address "::", port 5432
postgres_replica  | 2024-10-10 19:12:08.290 UTC [1] LOG:  listening on Unix socket "/var/run/postgresql/.s.PGSQL.5432"
postgres_replica  | 2024-10-10 19:12:08.299 UTC [39] LOG:  database system was interrupted; last known up at 2024-10-10 19:12:07 UTC
postgres_replica  | 2024-10-10 19:12:08.394 UTC [39] LOG:  entering standby mode
postgres_replica  | 2024-10-10 19:12:08.400 UTC [39] LOG:  redo starts at 0/2000028
postgres_replica  | 2024-10-10 19:12:08.403 UTC [39] LOG:  consistent recovery state reached at 0/2000100
postgres_replica  | 2024-10-10 19:12:08.404 UTC [1] LOG:  database system is ready to accept read-only connections
postgres_replica  | 2024-10-10 19:12:08.426 UTC [43] LOG:  started streaming WAL from primary at 0/3000000 on timeline 1</code></pre>

                        
                    
                        
                            <p data-block-key="oqs8q">Now let's verify the setup...</p><p data-block-key="3cims">Connect to the master:</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            
<pre><code id="target-element-current">docker exec -it postgres_master psql -U myuser -d mydb</code></pre>

                        
                    
                        
                            <p data-block-key="oqs8q">and check replication status</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            
<pre><code id="target-element-current">SELECT pid, usename, application_name, client_addr FROM pg_stat_replication;</code></pre>

                        
                    
                        
                            <p data-block-key="oqs8q">The output will be:</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            
<pre><code id="target-element-current">pid |  usename   | application_name | client_addr 
-----+------------+------------------+-------------
  79 | replicator | replica1         | 172.20.0.3
(1 row)</code></pre>

                        
                    
                        
                            <p data-block-key="oqs8q">Now lets check the replica</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            
<pre><code id="target-element-current">docker exec -it postgres_replica psql -U myuser -d mydb</code></pre>

                        
                    
                        
                            <p data-block-key="oqs8q">The query and the output:</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            
<pre><code id="target-element-current">mydb=# SELECT pg_is_in_recovery();
 pg_is_in_recovery 
-------------------
 t
(1 row)</code></pre>

                        
                    
                        
                            <p data-block-key="j19th">And with these changes, every modification made on the primary server will be reflected on the replica server in real-time. While this article is a bit lengthy, it’s important to showcase the entire configuration process and outputs. This helps to provide a comprehensive view of the many moving parts involved and gives you a better understanding of what’s happening "under the hood."</p>
                        
                    
                        
                            <p data-block-key="j19th">Understanding how PostgreSQL streaming replication works and configuring it correctly can greatly enhance your system’s performance and resilience. Whether you’re preparing for failover scenarios or distributing read loads across replicas, these configurations ensure your database infrastructure is ready to scale and perform reliably. Hopefully, this article has demystified the process and given you clearer insight into how replication operates behind the scenes.</p>
                        
                    
                </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Psilocybin Bests SSRI for Major Depression in First Long-Term Comparison (369 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/psilocybin-bests-ssri-major-depression-first-long-term-2024a1000h77</link>
            <guid>41818420</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 11:46:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/psilocybin-bests-ssri-major-depression-first-long-term-2024a1000h77">https://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/psilocybin-bests-ssri-major-depression-first-long-term-2024a1000h77</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41818420">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>MILAN — Psilocybin leads to a better overall outcome in the treatment of moderate to severe major depressive disorder (MDD) than the selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor (SSRI) <a href="https://reference.medscape.com/drug/lexapro-escitalopram-342961">escitalopram</a>, results of the first long-term comparison of the two treatments suggest.</p><p>"This is the first work to compare the long-term effects of these two drugs in the context of overall well-being, not just freedom from <a href="https://emedicine.medscape.com/article/286759-overview">depression</a>," study investigator Tommaso Barba, PhD, candidate Imperial College London, London, England, said in a press release. "Psilocybin outperformed escitalopram in several measures of well-being, meaning in life, work, and social functioning."</p><p>Findings from the 6-month follow-up study of a phase 2 double-blind, randomized, controlled trial were presented on September 22 at the 37th European College of Neuropsychopharmacology (ECNP) Congress and <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/eclinm/article/PIIS2589-5370(24)00378-X/fulltext">published simultaneously in <em>The Lancet eClinicalMedicine</em>.</a></p><h2><strong>Addressing a Treatment 'Mismatch'</strong></h2><p>The findings are important because they address "a mismatch" between what psychiatrists and what patients think is important, Barba told <em>Medscape Medical News</em>.</p><p>"Psychiatrists really focus on negative symptoms of depression. So, if you are not sad anymore, if your sleep or appetite is not impaired, they think you're better. But if you look at what patients define as important, they say it's the degree in which their life is meaningful, in which they can connect with people around them, in which they can function in everyday life," Barba said.</p><p>"The study suggests that psilocybin therapy might be a more holistic treatment option for depression," added co-first author David Erritzoe, MD, PhD, clinical director and deputy head of the Centre for Psychedelic Research, Imperial College London. "This could make a substantial difference in the overall happiness and daily activities of those suffering from depression, providing a more joined-up approach to mental health treatment."</p><p>The <a href="https://www.nejm.org/doi/10.1056/NEJMoa2032994">initial single-center study</a> included 59 adults with MDD (mean age, 41 years) who were randomized to receive either psilocybin or escitalopram over a 6-week period. The psilocybin arm (n = 30) received two 25-mg oral doses of psilocybin therapy (PT), and the escitalopram arm (n = 29) received 10-20 mg of daily escitalopram plus two (placebo-like) 1-mg doses of psilocybin (ET). Both groups received psychological support.</p><p>Based on change in depression scores on the 16-item Quick Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology-Self-Report (QIDS-SR-16) at week 6, the initial study results suggested non-inferiority between the two treatments in terms of depressive symptoms (primary outcome), but superiority of PT for secondary outcomes including "well-being, anhedonia, social functioning, sexual functioning, and related variables, with fewer side effects compared to ET," the researchers noted.</p><p>The new 6-month follow-up findings, with monthly questionnaires and no additional study treatment or psychiatric treatment restrictions, measured the QIDS-SR-16, plus Work and Social Adjustment Scale (WSAS), Meaning in Life Questionnaire, Flourishing Scale (FS), and Watts Connectedness Scale (WCS).</p><p>Again, both groups maintained similar results on the QIDS-SR-16, with slightly greater reductions in depressive symptoms for PT in the first month (positive false discovery rate [FDR] = 0.021), but not thereafter.</p><p>At both 3 and 6 months, there were greater improvements in WSAS scores for the PT group (pFDR &lt; 0.001 and pFDR = 0.01, respectively), and also greater improvements in meaning in life across all follow-up timepoints (pFDR &lt; 0.001).</p><p>There was also greater improvement in the PT group regarding WCS at both 3 and 6 months (pFDR = 0.02, and pFDR = 0.04) and comparable FS improvements for both groups across all timepoints.</p><p>Confounding follow-up interventions may have muddied the results, with 30.7% of PT participants and 43.5% of ET participants receiving an additional intervention during this period.</p><p>The researchers conclude that while a short course of SSRIs combined with intensive therapeutic support (around 20 hours) "might be enough to induce sustained antidepressant effects," patients treated with psilocybin showed greater improvements in general functioning, connectedness, and meaning in life.</p><p>Although not reassessed in the follow-up, the initial study showed that adverse events, particularly sexual functioning, favored psilocybin, said Barba. "The two treatments seemed to go in opposite directions with psilocybin seeming to improve it and the antidepressant to suppress it. Other side effects associated with psilocybin were less diverse — mainly headaches at the end of the day — but with escitalopram they were way more diverse and more impairing," he added.</p><p>Although many therapists may be unfamiliar with psilocybin-assisted psychotherapy, "it's not a difficult skill to master. It might require some specialization, but I think if you're a good psychotherapist, you can learn how to implement psilocybin into your practice," he said.</p><p>"Normally the journey is quite inward, so patients do not require active support during the psychedelic experience [around 6 hours]. Sometimes they do require some hand-holding, or helping them to 'let go', or breathing exercises. The important part is the integration work that comes afterwards," Barba added.</p><p>He said he envisions a therapy program that involves "psychiatrists working together with psychotherapists. The psychotherapists would be more in charge of the active guiding, and the psychiatrist would do the prescribing, with the follow-up psychological support on Zoom."</p><p>He added a word of caution for therapists that "psilocybin requires active confrontation of painful, negative emotions and people who take this drug need to be open and prepared for the idea that they are going into a state where they may probably end up crying and confronting whatever they are maybe running away from in their lives. Not everyone may want to do this."</p><h2><strong>A New Treatment Paradigm?</strong></h2><p>Commenting on the research for <em>Medscape Medical News</em>, Johan Lundberg, MD, PhD, adjunct professor of psychiatry at the Department of Clinical Neuroscience, Karolinska Institute, Stockholm, Sweden, said the study addresses a key outstanding question about the long-term effects of one or two doses of psilocybin.</p><p>"It's a 6-month follow-up of a short treatment intervention, so in that sense, it's of high interest. It has been talked about that psilocybin might have a long-term effect, but this is the first study that has followed this for a longer term."</p><p>But Lundberg also pointed out that one shortcoming of the study is the diversity of treatments following the intervention.</p><p>"They didn't have control over whether patients received other treatments or when they started. So, that is a key concern. But they transparently reported that, and we do know there was a difference in reported ability to perform activities of daily life, and that is important."</p><p>He added that if psilocybin is eventually approved, it would likely come with an education package for providers — "which is already the case with other treatments like ECT [<a href="https://emedicine.medscape.com/article/1525957-overview">electroconvulsive therapy</a>] or TMS [transcranial magnetic stimulation] — you have to learn how to do it."</p><p>James Rucker, MD, PhD, psychiatrist and senior clinical lecturer at King's College London, London, England, who was not involved in the research, also noted that they have tended to attribute differences observed in this study to comparative differences between the drugs themselves.</p><p>However, he noted, it is also possible that the results reflect biased reporting between groups. This is more likely here because studies involving psilocybin tend to attract those with positive preconceptions about psilocybin and negative preconceptions about conventional antidepressants, and study participants were unblinded during the long-term follow-up phase, so knew which condition they were allocated to.</p><p>"This said, the nature of depression varies hugely between individuals, and this calls for the development of a similarly varied suite of treatment paradigms. Psilocybin therapy is certainly a different paradigm of treatment to escitalopram. The observation of similar levels of effectiveness to antidepressants here is encouraging to see alongside the much larger trials of psilocybin currently underway here in the UK, Europe, and the US," Rucker added.</p><p><em>This work was supported by The Alexander Mosley Charitable Trust and by the founding partners of Imperial College London's Centre for Psychedelic Research.</em></p><p><em>Barba reported having received consulting fees from Adamo Bioscience.</em></p><p><em>Both Lundberg and Rucker are involved in psilocybin research, but neither reported financial links.</em></p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google is preparing to let you run Linux apps on Android, just like Chrome OS (165 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.androidauthority.com/android-linux-terminal-app-3489887/</link>
            <guid>41816756</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 05:49:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.androidauthority.com/android-linux-terminal-app-3489887/">https://www.androidauthority.com/android-linux-terminal-app-3489887/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41816756">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><picture><source sizes="(min-width: 64rem) 51.25rem, 80vw" srcset="https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Terminal_app_on_Android_phone.jpg.webp 1919w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Terminal_app_on_Android_phone-1536w-864h.jpg.webp 1536w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Terminal_app_on_Android_phone-675w-380h.jpg.webp 675w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Terminal_app_on_Android_phone-64w-36h.jpg.webp 64w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Terminal_app_on_Android_phone-1000w-562h.jpg.webp 1000w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Terminal_app_on_Android_phone-300w-170h.jpg.webp 300w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Terminal_app_on_Android_phone-1280w-720h.jpg.webp 1280w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Terminal_app_on_Android_phone-840w-472h.jpg.webp 840w" type="image/webp"><img decoding="async" loading="eager" sizes="(min-width: 64rem) 51.25rem, 80vw" title="Linux Terminal app on a Google Pixel 9" srcset="https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Terminal_app_on_Android_phone.jpg 1919w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Terminal_app_on_Android_phone-1536w-864h.jpg 1536w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Terminal_app_on_Android_phone-675w-380h.jpg 675w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Terminal_app_on_Android_phone-64w-36h.jpg 64w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Terminal_app_on_Android_phone-1000w-562h.jpg 1000w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Terminal_app_on_Android_phone-300w-170h.jpg 300w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Terminal_app_on_Android_phone-1280w-720h.jpg 1280w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Terminal_app_on_Android_phone-840w-472h.jpg 840w" alt="Linux Terminal app on a Google Pixel 9" src="https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Terminal_app_on_Android_phone.jpg"></picture><div><p>Mishaal Rahman / Android Authority</p></div></div><div data-container-type="content"><p>TL;DR</p>
<ul>
<li>Google is developing a Linux terminal app for Android.</li>
<li>The Terminal app can be enabled via developer options and will install Debian in a virtual machine.</li>
<li>This app is likely intended for Chromebooks but might also be available for mobile devices, too.</li>
</ul>
</div><p>Although a lot of work can be done in a web browser these days, some tasks still require installing apps that aren’t available on <a href="https://www.androidauthority.com/what-is-chrome-os-1137371/">Chrome OS</a>, which is why Google lets you install <a href="https://www.androidauthority.com/linux-on-chromebook-1139944/">Linux apps on your Chromebook</a>. While there are ways to run some Linux apps on Android devices, all of those methods have some limitations and aren’t officially supported by Google. Fortunately, though, Google is finally working on an official way to run Linux apps on Android.</p><p>You're reading an&nbsp;<b data-stringify-type="bold">Authority Insights</b>&nbsp;story. Discover&nbsp;<a href="https://www.androidauthority.com/tag/authority-insights/" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-stringify-link="https://www.androidauthority.com/tag/authority-insights/" data-sk="tooltip_parent">Authority Insights</a><b data-stringify-type="bold">&nbsp;</b>for more exclusive reports, app teardowns, leaks, and in-depth tech coverage you won’t find anywhere else.</p><p>Engineers at Google started work on a new Terminal app for Android a couple of weeks ago. This Terminal app is part of the Android Virtualization Framework (AVF) and contains a WebView that connects to a Linux virtual machine via a local IP address, allowing you to run Linux commands from the Android host. Initially, you had to manually enable this Terminal app using a shell command and then configure the Linux VM yourself. However, in recent days, Google began work on integrating the Terminal app into Android as well as turning it into an all-in-one app for running a Linux distro in a VM.</p><p>A set of patches under the tag “<code>ferrochrome-dev-option</code>” was recently submitted to <a href="https://www.androidauthority.com/aosp-explained-1093505/">AOSP</a> that adds a new developer option called <strong>Linux terminal</strong> under <strong>Settings &gt; System &gt; Developer options</strong>. This new option will enable a “Linux terminal app that runs inside the VM,” according to its proposed description. Toggling this option enables the Terminal app that’s bundled with AVF.</p><div><picture><source sizes="(min-width: 64rem) 51.25rem, 80vw" srcset="https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Android_Linux_Terminal_app.jpeg.webp 1116w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Android_Linux_Terminal_app-879w-1440h.jpeg.webp 879w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Android_Linux_Terminal_app-659w-1080h.jpeg.webp 659w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Android_Linux_Terminal_app-527w-864h.jpeg.webp 527w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Android_Linux_Terminal_app-232w-380h.jpeg.webp 232w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Android_Linux_Terminal_app-39w-64h.jpeg.webp 39w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Android_Linux_Terminal_app-1000w-1639h.jpeg.webp 1000w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Android_Linux_Terminal_app-675w-1106h.jpeg.webp 675w" type="image/webp"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 64rem) 51.25rem, 80vw" title="Android Linux Terminal app" srcset="https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Android_Linux_Terminal_app.jpeg 1116w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Android_Linux_Terminal_app-879w-1440h.jpeg 879w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Android_Linux_Terminal_app-659w-1080h.jpeg 659w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Android_Linux_Terminal_app-527w-864h.jpeg 527w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Android_Linux_Terminal_app-232w-380h.jpeg 232w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Android_Linux_Terminal_app-39w-64h.jpeg 39w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Android_Linux_Terminal_app-1000w-1639h.jpeg 1000w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Android_Linux_Terminal_app-675w-1106h.jpeg 675w" alt="Android Linux Terminal app" src="https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Android_Linux_Terminal_app.jpeg"></picture></div><p>Currently, Android’s Terminal app still requires you to manually configure the Linux VM by providing a Debian image and creating a <code>vm_config.json</code> file, but Google plans to upgrade the Terminal app to take care of that for you. In one of the patches under the “<code>ferrochrome-dev-option</code>” tag, Google says that the existing “LinuxInstaller” app, which downloads and configures Debian to run in a VM through AVF, will be “merged to [the] terminal app soon.” This suggests that the Terminal app will become an all-in-one app that downloads, configures, runs, and interfaces with an instance of Debian running in a VM.</p><div><picture><source sizes="(min-width: 64rem) 51.25rem, 80vw" srcset="https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/AOSP_patch_to_add_Terminal_app_to_developer_options.jpg.webp 1497w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/AOSP_patch_to_add_Terminal_app_to_developer_options-675w-203h.jpg.webp 675w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/AOSP_patch_to_add_Terminal_app_to_developer_options-64w-19h.jpg.webp 64w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/AOSP_patch_to_add_Terminal_app_to_developer_options-1000w-301h.jpg.webp 1000w" type="image/webp"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 64rem) 51.25rem, 80vw" title="AOSP patch to add Terminal app to developer options" srcset="https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/AOSP_patch_to_add_Terminal_app_to_developer_options.jpg 1497w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/AOSP_patch_to_add_Terminal_app_to_developer_options-675w-203h.jpg 675w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/AOSP_patch_to_add_Terminal_app_to_developer_options-64w-19h.jpg 64w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/AOSP_patch_to_add_Terminal_app_to_developer_options-1000w-301h.jpg 1000w" alt="AOSP patch to add Terminal app to developer options" src="https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/AOSP_patch_to_add_Terminal_app_to_developer_options.jpg"></picture><div><p>Mishaal Rahman / Android Authority</p></div></div><p>Google is still working on improving the Terminal app as well as AVF before shipping this feature. AVF already supports graphics and some input options, but it’s preparing to add support for backing up and restoring snapshots, nested virtualization, and devices with an x86_64 architecture. It’s also preparing to add some settings pages to the Terminal app, which is pretty barebones right now apart from a menu to copy the IP address and stop the existing VM instance. The settings pages will let you resize the disk, configure port forwarding, and potentially recover partitions.</p><div><picture><source sizes="(min-width: 64rem) 51.25rem, 80vw" srcset="https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/AOSP_patch_to_add_settings_to_Terminal_app.jpg.webp 1531w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/AOSP_patch_to_add_settings_to_Terminal_app-675w-224h.jpg.webp 675w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/AOSP_patch_to_add_settings_to_Terminal_app-64w-21h.jpg.webp 64w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/AOSP_patch_to_add_settings_to_Terminal_app-1000w-331h.jpg.webp 1000w" type="image/webp"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 64rem) 51.25rem, 80vw" title="AOSP patch to add settings to Terminal app" srcset="https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/AOSP_patch_to_add_settings_to_Terminal_app.jpg 1531w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/AOSP_patch_to_add_settings_to_Terminal_app-675w-224h.jpg 675w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/AOSP_patch_to_add_settings_to_Terminal_app-64w-21h.jpg 64w, https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/AOSP_patch_to_add_settings_to_Terminal_app-1000w-331h.jpg 1000w" alt="AOSP patch to add settings to Terminal app" src="https://www.androidauthority.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/AOSP_patch_to_add_settings_to_Terminal_app.jpg"></picture><div><p>Mishaal Rahman / Android Authority</p></div></div><p>What’s particularly interesting about the patch that adds these settings is that it was tested on “tangorpro” and “komodo,” the codenames for the Pixel Tablet and Pixel 9 Pro XL respectively. This suggests that the Terminal app won’t be limited to Chromebooks like the new <a href="https://www.androidauthority.com/desktop-chrome-android-extensions-3488455/">desktop versions of Chrome for Android</a>. I don’t know when the Terminal app will land, but it’s possible we could see it arrive in next year’s <a href="https://www.androidauthority.com/android-16-features-3484159/">Android 16</a> update.</p><p>Here’s an early look at how this could work, courtesy of an anonymous developer. What you see below features the current version of the Terminal app, which lacks some of the automations we’re expecting. That’s why you’ll see LinuxInstaller involved at the beginning here, to help set things up:</p><p>If you’re wondering why you’d want to run Linux apps on Android, then this feature is probably not for you. Google added Linux support to Chrome OS so developers with Chromebooks can run Linux apps that are useful for development. For example, Linux support on Chrome OS allows developers to run the Linux version of Android Studio, the recommended IDE for Android app development, on Chromebooks. It also lets them run Linux command line tools safely and securely in a container.</p><p>Most Chromebooks have x86-based processors, as opposed to most Android devices which have ARM-based ones, so a lot of Linux apps that work on most Chromebooks (like Android Studio) might not work on most Android devices. Still, adding support for Linux apps will greatly improve the utility of Android to developers and make it more viable as a desktop-class platform in the future, especially as more and more apps add support for ARM. Plus, it’s necessary for Google to do as <a href="https://www.androidauthority.com/chrome-os-adopts-android-stack-3451177/">Chrome OS is becoming more like Android</a>, which means it’s adopting more and more of Android’s architecture and frameworks.</p><p><strong>Got a tip? Talk to us!</strong>&nbsp;Email our staff at <a href="mailto:news@androidauthority.com" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-stringify-link="mailto:tips@androidauthority.com" data-sk="tooltip_parent" aria-haspopup="menu">news@androidauthority.com</a>. You can stay anonymous or get credit for the info, it's your choice.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[My WordPress Slack Ban (129 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://linuxjedi.co.uk/my-wordpress-slack-ban/</link>
            <guid>41815614</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 01:37:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://linuxjedi.co.uk/my-wordpress-slack-ban/">https://linuxjedi.co.uk/my-wordpress-slack-ban/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41815614">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>A couple of days ago, I got banned from the WordPress community Slack. As this is about WordPress, I figure I should use my WordPress blog to talk about it.</p><h2>The Checkbox</h2><p>Everything that day revolved around a small, mandatory checkbox which had been added to the wordpress.org sign-in page, declaring that you are not affiliated in any way. This login is pretty much the portal to contribute to the WordPress ecosystem.</p><figure><img data-lazyloaded="1" src="data:image/svg+xml;base64,PHN2ZyB4bWxucz0iaHR0cDovL3d3dy53My5vcmcvMjAwMC9zdmciIHdpZHRoPSIzOTciIGhlaWdodD0iNTM3IiB2aWV3Qm94PSIwIDAgMzk3IDUzNyI+PHJlY3Qgd2lkdGg9IjEwMCUiIGhlaWdodD0iMTAwJSIgc3R5bGU9ImZpbGw6I2NmZDRkYjtmaWxsLW9wYWNpdHk6IDAuMTsiLz48L3N2Zz4=" decoding="async" width="397" height="537" data-src="https://linuxjedi.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot_20241011_072042.png" alt="" data-srcset="https://linuxjedi.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot_20241011_072042.png 397w, https://linuxjedi.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot_20241011_072042-222x300.png 222w" data-sizes="(max-width: 397px) 100vw, 397px"></figure><p>I, and several others, immediately had questions as to how broad this was and the legal ramifications. This is important to me because my work on WordPress represents the MariaDB Foundation, my login uses my Foundation email address. Not only do I not want to be tied-up in legal issues, but I do not want to be responsible for dragging the MariaDB Foundation into them.</p><p>It is also very difficult for me to know if the MariaDB Foundation has a loose affiliation with WP Engine. Sure, I know they aren’t a direct sponsor, but they may be financially tied to one of our sponsors. As I am paid by the MariaDB Foundation, this could financially tie me.</p><p>I needed clarification on this before I could proceed. Others asking questions have clients who host on WP Engine, or use paid-for plugins created by WP Engine. They also needed similar clarification.</p><h2>The Discussion</h2><p>The discussion happened on Slack, and a majority of it that I’m aware about can be seen in the Twitter thread below.</p><figure></figure><p>It continued on a little bit afterwards. Matt emphasised that the value of the checkbox is not stored, and that many people had logged in since the checkbox was added. I pointed out that although the value may not be directly stored, by his own admission, it has been logged who has signed in since the mandatory checkbox was added, so it is effectively stored.</p><p>Shortly after this, my Slack session reset to another instance, and I was confused for a minute as to what happened. I then realised I had been kicked and banned from the server. I attempted to log in to Slack today just to confirm it was still in place. The system sent me this email when I tried.</p><figure><img data-lazyloaded="1" src="data:image/svg+xml;base64,PHN2ZyB4bWxucz0iaHR0cDovL3d3dy53My5vcmcvMjAwMC9zdmciIHdpZHRoPSIxMDI0IiBoZWlnaHQ9IjUyOSIgdmlld0JveD0iMCAwIDEwMjQgNTI5Ij48cmVjdCB3aWR0aD0iMTAwJSIgaGVpZ2h0PSIxMDAlIiBzdHlsZT0iZmlsbDojY2ZkNGRiO2ZpbGwtb3BhY2l0eTogMC4xOyIvPjwvc3ZnPg==" decoding="async" width="1024" height="529" data-src="https://linuxjedi.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot_20241011_062231-1024x529.png" alt="" data-srcset="https://linuxjedi.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot_20241011_062231-1024x529.png 1024w, https://linuxjedi.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot_20241011_062231-300x155.png 300w, https://linuxjedi.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot_20241011_062231-768x397.png 768w, https://linuxjedi.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot_20241011_062231-1536x794.png 1536w, https://linuxjedi.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot_20241011_062231.png 1879w" data-sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure><h2>My Thoughts</h2><p>I don’t think we had a resolution to our questions, and the checkbox remains in place. Several people have stated that they will not sign in until there has been some proper legal clarification. WP Engine said this:</p><figure><img data-lazyloaded="1" src="data:image/svg+xml;base64,PHN2ZyB4bWxucz0iaHR0cDovL3d3dy53My5vcmcvMjAwMC9zdmciIHdpZHRoPSI1ODciIGhlaWdodD0iMjA2IiB2aWV3Qm94PSIwIDAgNTg3IDIwNiI+PHJlY3Qgd2lkdGg9IjEwMCUiIGhlaWdodD0iMTAwJSIgc3R5bGU9ImZpbGw6I2NmZDRkYjtmaWxsLW9wYWNpdHk6IDAuMTsiLz48L3N2Zz4=" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="587" height="206" data-src="https://linuxjedi.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot_20241011_073923.png" alt="" data-srcset="https://linuxjedi.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot_20241011_073923.png 587w, https://linuxjedi.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot_20241011_073923-300x105.png 300w" data-sizes="(max-width: 587px) 100vw, 587px"></figure><p>I’m not fully convinced that this protects everyone. The WordPress Twitter account responded with:</p><figure><img data-lazyloaded="1" src="data:image/svg+xml;base64,PHN2ZyB4bWxucz0iaHR0cDovL3d3dy53My5vcmcvMjAwMC9zdmciIHdpZHRoPSI1OTIiIGhlaWdodD0iNjkzIiB2aWV3Qm94PSIwIDAgNTkyIDY5MyI+PHJlY3Qgd2lkdGg9IjEwMCUiIGhlaWdodD0iMTAwJSIgc3R5bGU9ImZpbGw6I2NmZDRkYjtmaWxsLW9wYWNpdHk6IDAuMTsiLz48L3N2Zz4=" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="592" height="693" data-src="https://linuxjedi.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot_20241011_073937.png" alt="" data-srcset="https://linuxjedi.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot_20241011_073937.png 592w, https://linuxjedi.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot_20241011_073937-256x300.png 256w" data-sizes="(max-width: 592px) 100vw, 592px"></figure><p>I have to say, I love that reader context is still a thing, I’m very surprised the current owner of Twitter did not kill it.</p><p>The MariaDB Foundation is a non-profit, any legal representation would be prohibitively expensive for us. So, I’d rather err on the side of not logging in until it is clear I am safe.</p><h2>Does This Matter?</h2><p>I am a small fry in this, not very important. My contributions mostly go as far as helping out with WordPress database questions, and often via other communication methods. I meet a lot of people face to face in the community and advise on how things could be better, things like that. My personal ban is not that important.</p><p>Several people who were banned at the same time are more important to the community. Having their voices taken away in this way is more damaging. I guess this is the start of the fallout from going nuclear that was talked about at the beginning of the fight.</p><p>I think clarification matters, this Tweet from Anita, quoting Uncle Chuck, says perfectly what I was thinking at the time:</p><figure><div><blockquote data-width="500" data-dnt="true"><div lang="en" dir="ltr"><p>Having coffee with Uncle Chuck (CGPT) 😂☕️ and he said:</p><p>You raise some valid points about the ambiguity of the checkbox. If people are asking Matt Mullenweg for clarification, it indicates a broader concern within the WordPress community about the implications of this statement,…</p></div>— Anita (@TheCre8tiveDiva) <a href="https://twitter.com/TheCre8tiveDiva/status/1843997862943666607?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">October 9, 2024</a></blockquote> </div></figure><h2>Wider Thoughts</h2><p>I think I speak for many in the WordPress community / ecosystem when I say that we don’t want to take sides in this battle. We don’t want to be forced to take sides via a checkbox. We just want to get work done, to improve WordPress for everyone.</p><p>The WordPress community is one of the most welcoming communities I’ve ever been a part of. It has brought friendship, meaning and value to many people. I want to see it succeed.</p><p>One of the things I have said since the beginning of me becoming Chief Contributions Officer is that contributions aren’t just code. Documentation, events, translations, community building, testing, bug reports, just so many things make up important contributions in an open source project. You don’t have to be a coder to contribute. I have seen these values expressed more in the WordPress community than anywhere else.</p><p>I cannot take a side in this battle, for several reasons. Not least because I have friends employed by both sides of it. But I would love for the collateral damage to stop. So that the community can heal.</p><p>I’ve said publicly, I would much rather my ban be permanent for asking the difficult questions and restore the voice to others who are more important. I’m not sure how I can help the community, but in some small way, I will be there for it.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AMD's Turin: 5th Gen EPYC Launched (294 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://chipsandcheese.com/p/amds-turin-5th-gen-epyc-launched</link>
            <guid>41815268</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 00:22:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://chipsandcheese.com/p/amds-turin-5th-gen-epyc-launched">https://chipsandcheese.com/p/amds-turin-5th-gen-epyc-launched</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41815268">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><p>Hello you fine Internet folks, for today we have a video and an article for y’all.</p><p><span>Unlike our prior Granite Rapids coverage where we just had a video, we have had hands-on with Turin, specifically the AMD EPYC 9575F, thanks to </span><a href="https://x.com/SoundTechTen" rel="">Jordan</a><span> from </span><a href="https://www.storagereview.com/" rel="">StorageReview</a><span>. </span></p><div id="youtube2-O_NRYy59eEA" data-attrs="{&quot;videoId&quot;:&quot;O_NRYy59eEA&quot;,&quot;startTime&quot;:null,&quot;endTime&quot;:null}" data-component-name="Youtube2ToDOM"><p><iframe src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/O_NRYy59eEA?rel=0&amp;autoplay=0&amp;showinfo=0&amp;enablejsapi=0" frameborder="0" loading="lazy" gesture="media" allow="autoplay; fullscreen" allowautoplay="true" allowfullscreen="true" width="728" height="409"></iframe></p></div><p><span>This article is going to be a little different from our usual. It’s going to be shorter than usual because we have already covered the Zen 5 core both</span><a href="https://chipsandcheese.com/p/amds-strix-point-zen-5-hits-mobile" rel=""> in mobile</a><span> and </span><a href="https://chipsandcheese.com/p/amds-ryzen-9950x-zen-5-on-desktop" rel="">in desktop</a><span> and the </span><a href="https://chipsandcheese.com/p/zen-5-variants-and-more-clock-for-clock" rel="">differences between them</a><span>, so this article will be focused on the memory subsystem changes that Turin has.</span></p><p><a href="https://www.servethehome.com/amd-epyc-9005-turin-turns-transcendent-performance-solidigm-broadcom/" rel="">Serve the Home</a><span> has an excellent article that has the slides that AMD has put out for the launch of Turin. But because we have our own data, I thought that our data would be more interesting to dive into.</span></p><p>First, looking at the 1T results, we see that the 9575F can pull around 52 GB/s of memory read bandwidth, 48 GB/s of memory write bandwidth, and 95 GB/s of memory add (Read-Modify-Write) bandwidth. </p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0ff6b56-81ca-4188-8c3c-b0cc24070f37_1055x475.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0ff6b56-81ca-4188-8c3c-b0cc24070f37_1055x475.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0ff6b56-81ca-4188-8c3c-b0cc24070f37_1055x475.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0ff6b56-81ca-4188-8c3c-b0cc24070f37_1055x475.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0ff6b56-81ca-4188-8c3c-b0cc24070f37_1055x475.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0ff6b56-81ca-4188-8c3c-b0cc24070f37_1055x475.png" width="1055" height="475" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/f0ff6b56-81ca-4188-8c3c-b0cc24070f37_1055x475.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:475,&quot;width&quot;:1055,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:33342,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0ff6b56-81ca-4188-8c3c-b0cc24070f37_1055x475.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0ff6b56-81ca-4188-8c3c-b0cc24070f37_1055x475.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0ff6b56-81ca-4188-8c3c-b0cc24070f37_1055x475.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0ff6b56-81ca-4188-8c3c-b0cc24070f37_1055x475.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>And looking at the results for how much memory bandwidth a single CCD can get, we can see that a single core can use just under half the total CCD memory read bandwidth, about 55% the total CCD memory write bandwidth, and over two-thirds the total CCD memory add bandwidth.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F57b5957b-1996-474a-8a54-006dac3b1969_1055x475.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F57b5957b-1996-474a-8a54-006dac3b1969_1055x475.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F57b5957b-1996-474a-8a54-006dac3b1969_1055x475.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F57b5957b-1996-474a-8a54-006dac3b1969_1055x475.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F57b5957b-1996-474a-8a54-006dac3b1969_1055x475.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F57b5957b-1996-474a-8a54-006dac3b1969_1055x475.png" width="1055" height="475" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/57b5957b-1996-474a-8a54-006dac3b1969_1055x475.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:475,&quot;width&quot;:1055,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:36216,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F57b5957b-1996-474a-8a54-006dac3b1969_1055x475.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F57b5957b-1996-474a-8a54-006dac3b1969_1055x475.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F57b5957b-1996-474a-8a54-006dac3b1969_1055x475.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F57b5957b-1996-474a-8a54-006dac3b1969_1055x475.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Looking a bit closer at these results, you’ll notice that the 9575F has significantly higher bandwidth to a CCD compared to the desktop Zen 5 parts. And the reason for this is the 9575F has GMI3-W which means that it has 2 GMI links to the IO die instead of the single GMI link that the 9950X gets.</p><p>And this is not only the only change to the GMI links on server. The GMI write link is now 32B per GMI link instead of the 16B per GMI link that you’d see on desktop Zen 5.</p><p>Before moving to the full socket memory performance for the 9575F, let’s clear up the memory speeds that Turin supports. Turin has 12 channels of memory that can run up to DDR5-6400MT/s, however 6400MT/s is only supported on specific validated systems and only for 1 DIMM per channel. </p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa3d1550a-b7b7-4888-bb36-bf54901e2823_675x724.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa3d1550a-b7b7-4888-bb36-bf54901e2823_675x724.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa3d1550a-b7b7-4888-bb36-bf54901e2823_675x724.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa3d1550a-b7b7-4888-bb36-bf54901e2823_675x724.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa3d1550a-b7b7-4888-bb36-bf54901e2823_675x724.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa3d1550a-b7b7-4888-bb36-bf54901e2823_675x724.png" width="675" height="724" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/a3d1550a-b7b7-4888-bb36-bf54901e2823_675x724.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:724,&quot;width&quot;:675,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:275928,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa3d1550a-b7b7-4888-bb36-bf54901e2823_675x724.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa3d1550a-b7b7-4888-bb36-bf54901e2823_675x724.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa3d1550a-b7b7-4888-bb36-bf54901e2823_675x724.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa3d1550a-b7b7-4888-bb36-bf54901e2823_675x724.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>The system we had access to was running 6000MT/s for its memory, and DDR5-6000 MT/s is what most systems will support in a 1 DIMM per channel configuration. Should you want to run 2 DIMMs per channel, then your memory speeds drop to 4400 MT/s; and if you run 1 DIMM per channel in a motherboard with 2 DIMMs per channel then expect 5200 MT/s for your memory speed.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb8964ab8-f489-4ac3-83d4-543a4155fd91_1055x475.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb8964ab8-f489-4ac3-83d4-543a4155fd91_1055x475.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb8964ab8-f489-4ac3-83d4-543a4155fd91_1055x475.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb8964ab8-f489-4ac3-83d4-543a4155fd91_1055x475.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb8964ab8-f489-4ac3-83d4-543a4155fd91_1055x475.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb8964ab8-f489-4ac3-83d4-543a4155fd91_1055x475.png" width="1055" height="475" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/b8964ab8-f489-4ac3-83d4-543a4155fd91_1055x475.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:475,&quot;width&quot;:1055,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:35864,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb8964ab8-f489-4ac3-83d4-543a4155fd91_1055x475.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb8964ab8-f489-4ac3-83d4-543a4155fd91_1055x475.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb8964ab8-f489-4ac3-83d4-543a4155fd91_1055x475.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb8964ab8-f489-4ac3-83d4-543a4155fd91_1055x475.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Now, actually diving into the memory of the full 9575F and we see that we can get nearly 99% of the theoretical 576 GB/s of memory bandwidth using reads. Writes and adds are still an impressive 435 GB/s and 453 GB/s respectively.</p><p>We also tested the socket to socket bandwidth on AMD’s Volcano Platform which only has 3 GMI links between the two 9575Fs. </p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F144c313e-973d-4bc1-b22f-a3e30072c9f0_983x495.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F144c313e-973d-4bc1-b22f-a3e30072c9f0_983x495.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F144c313e-973d-4bc1-b22f-a3e30072c9f0_983x495.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F144c313e-973d-4bc1-b22f-a3e30072c9f0_983x495.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F144c313e-973d-4bc1-b22f-a3e30072c9f0_983x495.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F144c313e-973d-4bc1-b22f-a3e30072c9f0_983x495.png" width="983" height="495" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/144c313e-973d-4bc1-b22f-a3e30072c9f0_983x495.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:495,&quot;width&quot;:983,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:35062,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F144c313e-973d-4bc1-b22f-a3e30072c9f0_983x495.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F144c313e-973d-4bc1-b22f-a3e30072c9f0_983x495.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F144c313e-973d-4bc1-b22f-a3e30072c9f0_983x495.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F144c313e-973d-4bc1-b22f-a3e30072c9f0_983x495.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><span>These results are very similar to our </span><a href="https://chipsandcheese.com/p/testing-amds-bergamo-zen-4c-spam" rel="">Bergamo</a><span> results, which isn’t surprising because that system also had the same 3 GMI link setup.</span></p><p>Moving to memory latency, we see that Turin’s unloaded memory latency is very similar to Genoa’s unloaded memory latency.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F66403d22-bb80-4098-8ed7-131b51be6520_983x493.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F66403d22-bb80-4098-8ed7-131b51be6520_983x493.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F66403d22-bb80-4098-8ed7-131b51be6520_983x493.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F66403d22-bb80-4098-8ed7-131b51be6520_983x493.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F66403d22-bb80-4098-8ed7-131b51be6520_983x493.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F66403d22-bb80-4098-8ed7-131b51be6520_983x493.png" width="983" height="493" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/66403d22-bb80-4098-8ed7-131b51be6520_983x493.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:493,&quot;width&quot;:983,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:30653,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F66403d22-bb80-4098-8ed7-131b51be6520_983x493.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F66403d22-bb80-4098-8ed7-131b51be6520_983x493.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F66403d22-bb80-4098-8ed7-131b51be6520_983x493.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F66403d22-bb80-4098-8ed7-131b51be6520_983x493.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><span>At Hot Chips 2024, </span><a href="https://chipsandcheese.com/p/ampereone-at-hot-chips-2024-maximizing-density" rel="">Ampere Computing showed a graph</a><span> demonstrating the loaded memory latency of an AmpereOne chip and AMD’s Genoa CPU. Now Chester wanted to make a test similar to this, so he made a loaded latency test.</span></p><p>The way that this test works is that it runs our memory bandwidth benchmark on either 7 cores on a CCD or 7 CCDs on the 9575F. This ensures that the IOD to CCD link or the whole memory system is fully loaded. Then, with the 8th core or 8th CCD, we run the memory latency test to see what the latency of the fully loaded system is.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffdecee13-5587-41d0-a173-f6ebe5ee3989_501x295.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffdecee13-5587-41d0-a173-f6ebe5ee3989_501x295.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffdecee13-5587-41d0-a173-f6ebe5ee3989_501x295.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffdecee13-5587-41d0-a173-f6ebe5ee3989_501x295.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffdecee13-5587-41d0-a173-f6ebe5ee3989_501x295.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffdecee13-5587-41d0-a173-f6ebe5ee3989_501x295.png" width="501" height="295" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/fdecee13-5587-41d0-a173-f6ebe5ee3989_501x295.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:295,&quot;width&quot;:501,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:16435,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffdecee13-5587-41d0-a173-f6ebe5ee3989_501x295.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffdecee13-5587-41d0-a173-f6ebe5ee3989_501x295.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffdecee13-5587-41d0-a173-f6ebe5ee3989_501x295.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffdecee13-5587-41d0-a173-f6ebe5ee3989_501x295.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>When a single CCD is loaded up on the 9575F, we see about a 39 nanosecond increase between the unloaded and loaded latency.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5340197-b348-4754-8796-68593252063a_500x296.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5340197-b348-4754-8796-68593252063a_500x296.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5340197-b348-4754-8796-68593252063a_500x296.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5340197-b348-4754-8796-68593252063a_500x296.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5340197-b348-4754-8796-68593252063a_500x296.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5340197-b348-4754-8796-68593252063a_500x296.png" width="500" height="296" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/d5340197-b348-4754-8796-68593252063a_500x296.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:296,&quot;width&quot;:500,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:17479,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5340197-b348-4754-8796-68593252063a_500x296.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5340197-b348-4754-8796-68593252063a_500x296.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5340197-b348-4754-8796-68593252063a_500x296.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5340197-b348-4754-8796-68593252063a_500x296.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>When the whole system is loaded, we see about a 31 nanosecond increase between unloaded and loaded system latency.</p><p>Looking at the single CCD results compared to the fully loaded system results, the 9575F has very similar memory latency behavior regardless if a single CCD is loaded or if the whole system is loaded.</p><p>And lastly, everyone’s favorite graph, the core to core latency graph.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa4cf5acc-e03e-463a-a95e-84d48a7b9e1a_10281x5161.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa4cf5acc-e03e-463a-a95e-84d48a7b9e1a_10281x5161.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa4cf5acc-e03e-463a-a95e-84d48a7b9e1a_10281x5161.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa4cf5acc-e03e-463a-a95e-84d48a7b9e1a_10281x5161.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa4cf5acc-e03e-463a-a95e-84d48a7b9e1a_10281x5161.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_2400,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa4cf5acc-e03e-463a-a95e-84d48a7b9e1a_10281x5161.png" width="1200" height="602.4725274725274" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/a4cf5acc-e03e-463a-a95e-84d48a7b9e1a_10281x5161.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:false,&quot;imageSize&quot;:&quot;large&quot;,&quot;height&quot;:731,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:1200,&quot;bytes&quot;:14446108,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa4cf5acc-e03e-463a-a95e-84d48a7b9e1a_10281x5161.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa4cf5acc-e03e-463a-a95e-84d48a7b9e1a_10281x5161.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa4cf5acc-e03e-463a-a95e-84d48a7b9e1a_10281x5161.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa4cf5acc-e03e-463a-a95e-84d48a7b9e1a_10281x5161.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>For convenience, the list below are the numbers from the chart because a chart this big can be hard to read. </p><ul><li><p>Intra-CCD latency: ~45ns</p></li><li><p>Inter-CCD latency: ~150ns</p></li><li><p>Socket to Socket latency: ~260ns</p></li></ul><p>This is a latency increase compared to Genoa, especially within a CCD.</p><p>Now, a note about the clock speeds we saw with the 9575F. All 64 cores could hit up to 5GHz in single threaded test. This is quite impressive, but we were able to get all 8 cores in a CCD to run at 5GHz in our memory bandwidth testing.</p><p><span>And with all 128 threads chugging away on Cinebench 2024, we saw the 9575F sticking around the 4.3GHz range. Wendell from </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/@Level1Techs" rel="">Level1Techs</a><span> saw about 4.9GHz all core on a web server/TLS transaction workload, which is a less vectorized workload.</span></p><p>Realistically, AMD’s Turin is the generational update you’d normally expect. Not only does AMD have high core count SKUs (9755, 9965), which the hyperscalers will be picking up, they now also have lower core count, very high frequency SKUs (9575F) which the traditional enterprise market will appreciate. Apparently we now think 64 cores is ‘lower core count’. What a world we live in.</p><p>Turin isn’t the step-function revolution that Naples to Rome was; it’s more akin to the evolution we saw with Milan to Genoa, which was a memory bandwidth increase, a core increase, and a core update. Nonetheless, this generation is set to excite a lot of people, as there’s lots of value here in a very competitive ecosystem.</p><p><span>If you like our articles and journalism, and you want to support us in our endeavors, then consider heading over to our&nbsp;</span><a href="https://www.patreon.com/ChipsandCheese" rel="">Patreon</a><span>&nbsp;or our&nbsp;</span><a href="https://www.paypal.com/donate/?hosted_button_id=4EMPH66SBGVSQ" rel="">PayPal</a><span>&nbsp;if you want to toss a few bucks our way. If you would like to talk with the Chips and Cheese staff and the people behind the scenes, then consider joining our&nbsp;</span><a href="https://discord.gg/TwVnRhxgY2" rel="">Discord</a><span>.</span></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Swarm, a new agent framework by OpenAI (191 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/openai/swarm</link>
            <guid>41815173</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 00:05:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/openai/swarm">https://github.com/openai/swarm</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41815173">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/openai/swarm/blob/main/assets/logo.png"><img src="https://github.com/openai/swarm/raw/main/assets/logo.png" alt="Swarm Logo"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Swarm (experimental, educational)</h2><a id="user-content-swarm-experimental-educational" aria-label="Permalink: Swarm (experimental, educational)" href="#swarm-experimental-educational"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">An educational framework exploring ergonomic, lightweight multi-agent orchestration.</p>
<div dir="auto"><p dir="auto">Warning</p><p dir="auto">Swarm is currently an experimental sample framework intended to explore ergonomic interfaces for multi-agent systems. It is not intended to be used in production, and therefore has no official support. (This also means we will not be reviewing PRs or issues!)</p>
<p dir="auto">The primary goal of Swarm is to showcase the handoff &amp; routines patterns explored in the <a href="https://cookbook.openai.com/examples/orchestrating_agents" rel="nofollow">Orchestrating Agents: Handoffs &amp; Routines</a> cookbook. It is not meant as a standalone library, and is primarily for educational purposes.</p>
</div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Install</h2><a id="user-content-install" aria-label="Permalink: Install" href="#install"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Requires Python 3.10+</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="pip install git+ssh://git@github.com/openai/swarm.git"><pre>pip install git+ssh://git@github.com/openai/swarm.git</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">or</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="pip install git+https://github.com/openai/swarm.git"><pre>pip install git+https://github.com/openai/swarm.git</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h2><a id="user-content-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Usage" href="#usage"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="from swarm import Swarm, Agent

client = Swarm()

def transfer_to_agent_b():
    return agent_b


agent_a = Agent(
    name=&quot;Agent A&quot;,
    instructions=&quot;You are a helpful agent.&quot;,
    functions=[transfer_to_agent_b],
)

agent_b = Agent(
    name=&quot;Agent B&quot;,
    instructions=&quot;Only speak in Haikus.&quot;,
)

response = client.run(
    agent=agent_a,
    messages=[{&quot;role&quot;: &quot;user&quot;, &quot;content&quot;: &quot;I want to talk to agent B.&quot;}],
)

print(response.messages[-1][&quot;content&quot;])"><pre><span>from</span> <span>swarm</span> <span>import</span> <span>Swarm</span>, <span>Agent</span>

<span>client</span> <span>=</span> <span>Swarm</span>()

<span>def</span> <span>transfer_to_agent_b</span>():
    <span>return</span> <span>agent_b</span>


<span>agent_a</span> <span>=</span> <span>Agent</span>(
    <span>name</span><span>=</span><span>"Agent A"</span>,
    <span>instructions</span><span>=</span><span>"You are a helpful agent."</span>,
    <span>functions</span><span>=</span>[<span>transfer_to_agent_b</span>],
)

<span>agent_b</span> <span>=</span> <span>Agent</span>(
    <span>name</span><span>=</span><span>"Agent B"</span>,
    <span>instructions</span><span>=</span><span>"Only speak in Haikus."</span>,
)

<span>response</span> <span>=</span> <span>client</span>.<span>run</span>(
    <span>agent</span><span>=</span><span>agent_a</span>,
    <span>messages</span><span>=</span>[{<span>"role"</span>: <span>"user"</span>, <span>"content"</span>: <span>"I want to talk to agent B."</span>}],
)

<span>print</span>(<span>response</span>.<span>messages</span>[<span>-</span><span>1</span>][<span>"content"</span>])</pre></div>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="Hope glimmers brightly,
New paths converge gracefully,
What can I assist?"><pre><code>Hope glimmers brightly,
New paths converge gracefully,
What can I assist?
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Table of Contents</h2><a id="user-content-table-of-contents" aria-label="Permalink: Table of Contents" href="#table-of-contents"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="#overview">Overview</a></li>
<li><a href="#examples">Examples</a></li>
<li><a href="#documentation">Documentation</a>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="#running-swarm">Running Swarm</a></li>
<li><a href="#agents">Agents</a></li>
<li><a href="#functions">Functions</a></li>
<li><a href="#streaming">Streaming</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#evaluations">Evaluations</a></li>
<li><a href="#utils">Utils</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Overview</h2><a id="user-content-overview" aria-label="Permalink: Overview" href="#overview"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Swarm focuses on making agent <strong>coordination</strong> and <strong>execution</strong> lightweight, highly controllable, and easily testable.</p>
<p dir="auto">It accomplishes this through two primitive abstractions: <code>Agent</code>s and <strong>handoffs</strong>. An <code>Agent</code> encompasses <code>instructions</code> and <code>tools</code>, and can at any point choose to hand off a conversation to another <code>Agent</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto">These primitives are powerful enough to express rich dynamics between tools and networks of agents, allowing you to build scalable, real-world solutions while avoiding a steep learning curve.</p>
<div dir="auto"><p dir="auto">Note</p><p dir="auto">Swarm Agents are not related to Assistants in the Assistants API. They are named similarly for convenience, but are otherwise completely unrelated. Swarm is entirely powered by the Chat Completions API and is hence stateless between calls.</p>
</div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Why Swarm</h2><a id="user-content-why-swarm" aria-label="Permalink: Why Swarm" href="#why-swarm"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Swarm explores patterns that are lightweight, scalable, and highly customizable by design. Approaches similar to Swarm are best suited for situations dealing with a large number of independent capabilities and instructions that are difficult to encode into a single prompt.</p>
<p dir="auto">The Assistants API is a great option for developers looking for fully-hosted threads and built in memory management and retrieval. However, Swarm is an educational resource for developers curious to learn about multi-agent orchestration. Swarm runs (almost) entirely on the client and, much like the Chat Completions API, does not store state between calls.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Examples</h2><a id="user-content-examples" aria-label="Permalink: Examples" href="#examples"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Check out <code>/examples</code> for inspiration! Learn more about each one in its README.</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/openai/swarm/blob/main/examples/basic"><code>basic</code></a>: Simple examples of fundamentals like setup, function calling, handoffs, and context variables</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/openai/swarm/blob/main/examples/triage_agent"><code>triage_agent</code></a>: Simple example of setting up a basic triage step to hand off to the right agent</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/openai/swarm/blob/main/examples/weather_agent"><code>weather_agent</code></a>: Simple example of function calling</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/openai/swarm/blob/main/examples/airline"><code>airline</code></a>: A multi-agent setup for handling different customer service requests in an airline context.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/openai/swarm/blob/main/examples/support_bot"><code>support_bot</code></a>: A customer service bot which includes a user interface agent and a help center agent with several tools</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/openai/swarm/blob/main/examples/personal_shopper"><code>personal_shopper</code></a>: A personal shopping agent that can help with making sales and refunding orders</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Documentation</h2><a id="user-content-documentation" aria-label="Permalink: Documentation" href="#documentation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/openai/swarm/blob/main/assets/swarm_diagram.png"><img src="https://github.com/openai/swarm/raw/main/assets/swarm_diagram.png" alt="Swarm Diagram"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Running Swarm</h2><a id="user-content-running-swarm" aria-label="Permalink: Running Swarm" href="#running-swarm"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Start by instantiating a Swarm client (which internally just instantiates an <code>OpenAI</code> client).</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="from swarm import Swarm

client = Swarm()"><pre><span>from</span> <span>swarm</span> <span>import</span> <span>Swarm</span>

<span>client</span> <span>=</span> <span>Swarm</span>()</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><code>client.run()</code></h3><a id="user-content-clientrun" aria-label="Permalink: client.run()" href="#clientrun"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Swarm's <code>run()</code> function is analogous to the <code>chat.completions.create()</code> function in the Chat Completions API – it takes <code>messages</code> and returns <code>messages</code> and saves no state between calls. Importantly, however, it also handles Agent function execution, hand-offs, context variable references, and can take multiple turns before returning to the user.</p>
<p dir="auto">At its core, Swarm's <code>client.run()</code> implements the following loop:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Get a completion from the current Agent</li>
<li>Execute tool calls and append results</li>
<li>Switch Agent if necessary</li>
<li>Update context variables, if necessary</li>
<li>If no new function calls, return</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Arguments</h4><a id="user-content-arguments" aria-label="Permalink: Arguments" href="#arguments"></a></p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Argument</th>
<th>Type</th>
<th>Description</th>
<th>Default</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>agent</strong></td>
<td><code>Agent</code></td>
<td>The (initial) agent to be called.</td>
<td>(required)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>messages</strong></td>
<td><code>List</code></td>
<td>A list of message objects, identical to <a href="https://platform.openai.com/docs/api-reference/chat/create#chat-create-messages" rel="nofollow">Chat Completions <code>messages</code></a></td>
<td>(required)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>context_variables</strong></td>
<td><code>dict</code></td>
<td>A dictionary of additional context variables, available to functions and Agent instructions</td>
<td><code>{}</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>max_turns</strong></td>
<td><code>int</code></td>
<td>The maximum number of conversational turns allowed</td>
<td><code>float("inf")</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>model_override</strong></td>
<td><code>str</code></td>
<td>An optional string to override the model being used by an Agent</td>
<td><code>None</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>execute_tools</strong></td>
<td><code>bool</code></td>
<td>If <code>False</code>, interrupt execution and immediately returns <code>tool_calls</code> message when an Agent tries to call a function</td>
<td><code>True</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>stream</strong></td>
<td><code>bool</code></td>
<td>If <code>True</code>, enables streaming responses</td>
<td><code>False</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>debug</strong></td>
<td><code>bool</code></td>
<td>If <code>True</code>, enables debug logging</td>
<td><code>False</code></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto">Once <code>client.run()</code> is finished (after potentially multiple calls to agents and tools) it will return a <code>Response</code> containing all the relevant updated state. Specifically, the new <code>messages</code>, the last <code>Agent</code> to be called, and the most up-to-date <code>context_variables</code>. You can pass these values (plus new user messages) in to your next execution of <code>client.run()</code> to continue the interaction where it left off – much like <code>chat.completions.create()</code>. (The <code>run_demo_loop</code> function implements an example of a full execution loop in <code>/swarm/repl/repl.py</code>.)</p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><code>Response</code> Fields</h4><a id="user-content-response-fields" aria-label="Permalink: Response Fields" href="#response-fields"></a></p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Field</th>
<th>Type</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>messages</strong></td>
<td><code>List</code></td>
<td>A list of message objects generated during the conversation. Very similar to <a href="https://platform.openai.com/docs/api-reference/chat/create#chat-create-messages" rel="nofollow">Chat Completions <code>messages</code></a>, but with a <code>sender</code> field indicating which <code>Agent</code> the message originated from.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>agent</strong></td>
<td><code>Agent</code></td>
<td>The last agent to handle a message.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>context_variables</strong></td>
<td><code>dict</code></td>
<td>The same as the input variables, plus any changes.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Agents</h2><a id="user-content-agents" aria-label="Permalink: Agents" href="#agents"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">An <code>Agent</code> simply encapsulates a set of <code>instructions</code> with a set of <code>functions</code> (plus some additional settings below), and has the capability to hand off execution to another <code>Agent</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto">While it's tempting to personify an <code>Agent</code> as "someone who does X", it can also be used to represent a very specific workflow or step defined by a set of <code>instructions</code> and <code>functions</code> (e.g. a set of steps, a complex retrieval, single step of data transformation, etc). This allows <code>Agent</code>s to be composed into a network of "agents", "workflows", and "tasks", all represented by the same primitive.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><code>Agent</code> Fields</h2><a id="user-content-agent-fields" aria-label="Permalink: Agent Fields" href="#agent-fields"></a></p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Field</th>
<th>Type</th>
<th>Description</th>
<th>Default</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>name</strong></td>
<td><code>str</code></td>
<td>The name of the agent.</td>
<td><code>"Agent"</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>model</strong></td>
<td><code>str</code></td>
<td>The model to be used by the agent.</td>
<td><code>"gpt-4o"</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>instructions</strong></td>
<td><code>str</code> or <code>func() -&gt; str</code></td>
<td>Instructions for the agent, can be a string or a callable returning a string.</td>
<td><code>"You are a helpful agent."</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>functions</strong></td>
<td><code>List</code></td>
<td>A list of functions that the agent can call.</td>
<td><code>[]</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>tool_choice</strong></td>
<td><code>str</code></td>
<td>The tool choice for the agent, if any.</td>
<td><code>None</code></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Instructions</h3><a id="user-content-instructions" aria-label="Permalink: Instructions" href="#instructions"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><code>Agent</code> <code>instructions</code> are directly converted into the <code>system</code> prompt of a conversation (as the first message). Only the <code>instructions</code> of the active <code>Agent</code> will be present at any given time (e.g. if there is an <code>Agent</code> handoff, the <code>system</code> prompt will change, but the chat history will not.)</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="agent = Agent(
   instructions=&quot;You are a helpful agent.&quot;
)"><pre><span>agent</span> <span>=</span> <span>Agent</span>(
   <span>instructions</span><span>=</span><span>"You are a helpful agent."</span>
)</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">The <code>instructions</code> can either be a regular <code>str</code>, or a function that returns a <code>str</code>. The function can optionally receive a <code>context_variables</code> parameter, which will be populated by the <code>context_variables</code> passed into <code>client.run()</code>.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="def instructions(context_variables):
   user_name = context_variables[&quot;user_name&quot;]
   return f&quot;Help the user, {user_name}, do whatever they want.&quot;

agent = Agent(
   instructions=instructions
)
response = client.run(
   agent=agent,
   messages=[{&quot;role&quot;:&quot;user&quot;, &quot;content&quot;: &quot;Hi!&quot;}],
   context_variables={&quot;user_name&quot;:&quot;John&quot;}
)
print(response.messages[-1][&quot;content&quot;])"><pre><span>def</span> <span>instructions</span>(<span>context_variables</span>):
   <span>user_name</span> <span>=</span> <span>context_variables</span>[<span>"user_name"</span>]
   <span>return</span> <span>f"Help the user, <span><span>{</span><span>user_name</span><span>}</span></span>, do whatever they want."</span>

<span>agent</span> <span>=</span> <span>Agent</span>(
   <span>instructions</span><span>=</span><span>instructions</span>
)
<span>response</span> <span>=</span> <span>client</span>.<span>run</span>(
   <span>agent</span><span>=</span><span>agent</span>,
   <span>messages</span><span>=</span>[{<span>"role"</span>:<span>"user"</span>, <span>"content"</span>: <span>"Hi!"</span>}],
   <span>context_variables</span><span>=</span>{<span>"user_name"</span>:<span>"John"</span>}
)
<span>print</span>(<span>response</span>.<span>messages</span>[<span>-</span><span>1</span>][<span>"content"</span>])</pre></div>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="Hi John, how can I assist you today?"><pre><code>Hi John, how can I assist you today?
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Functions</h2><a id="user-content-functions" aria-label="Permalink: Functions" href="#functions"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Swarm <code>Agent</code>s can call python functions directly.</li>
<li>Function should usually return a <code>str</code> (values will be attempted to be cast as a <code>str</code>).</li>
<li>If a function returns an <code>Agent</code>, execution will be transfered to that <code>Agent</code>.</li>
<li>If a function defines a <code>context_variables</code> parameter, it will be populated by the <code>context_variables</code> passed into <code>client.run()</code>.</li>
</ul>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="def greet(context_variables, language):
   user_name = context_variables[&quot;user_name&quot;]
   greeting = &quot;Hola&quot; if language.lower() == &quot;spanish&quot; else &quot;Hello&quot;
   print(f&quot;{greeting}, {user_name}!&quot;)
   return &quot;Done&quot;

agent = Agent(
   functions=[print_hello]
)

client.run(
   agent=agent,
   messages=[{&quot;role&quot;: &quot;user&quot;, &quot;content&quot;: &quot;Usa greet() por favor.&quot;}],
   context_variables={&quot;user_name&quot;: &quot;John&quot;}
)"><pre><span>def</span> <span>greet</span>(<span>context_variables</span>, <span>language</span>):
   <span>user_name</span> <span>=</span> <span>context_variables</span>[<span>"user_name"</span>]
   <span>greeting</span> <span>=</span> <span>"Hola"</span> <span>if</span> <span>language</span>.<span>lower</span>() <span>==</span> <span>"spanish"</span> <span>else</span> <span>"Hello"</span>
   <span>print</span>(<span>f"<span><span>{</span><span>greeting</span><span>}</span></span>, <span><span>{</span><span>user_name</span><span>}</span></span>!"</span>)
   <span>return</span> <span>"Done"</span>

<span>agent</span> <span>=</span> <span>Agent</span>(
   <span>functions</span><span>=</span>[<span>print_hello</span>]
)

<span>client</span>.<span>run</span>(
   <span>agent</span><span>=</span><span>agent</span>,
   <span>messages</span><span>=</span>[{<span>"role"</span>: <span>"user"</span>, <span>"content"</span>: <span>"Usa greet() por favor."</span>}],
   <span>context_variables</span><span>=</span>{<span>"user_name"</span>: <span>"John"</span>}
)</pre></div>

<ul dir="auto">
<li>If an <code>Agent</code> function call has an error (missing function, wrong argument, error) an error response will be appended to the chat so the <code>Agent</code> can recover gracefully.</li>
<li>If multiple functions are called by the <code>Agent</code>, they will be executed in that order.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Handoffs and Updating Context Variables</h3><a id="user-content-handoffs-and-updating-context-variables" aria-label="Permalink: Handoffs and Updating Context Variables" href="#handoffs-and-updating-context-variables"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">An <code>Agent</code> can hand off to another <code>Agent</code> by returning it in a <code>function</code>.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="sales_agent = Agent(name=&quot;Sales Agent&quot;)

def transfer_to_sales():
   return sales_agent

agent = Agent(functions=[transfer_to_sales])

response = client.run(agent, [{&quot;role&quot;:&quot;user&quot;, &quot;content&quot;:&quot;Transfer me to sales.&quot;}])
print(response.agent.name)"><pre><span>sales_agent</span> <span>=</span> <span>Agent</span>(<span>name</span><span>=</span><span>"Sales Agent"</span>)

<span>def</span> <span>transfer_to_sales</span>():
   <span>return</span> <span>sales_agent</span>

<span>agent</span> <span>=</span> <span>Agent</span>(<span>functions</span><span>=</span>[<span>transfer_to_sales</span>])

<span>response</span> <span>=</span> <span>client</span>.<span>run</span>(<span>agent</span>, [{<span>"role"</span>:<span>"user"</span>, <span>"content"</span>:<span>"Transfer me to sales."</span>}])
<span>print</span>(<span>response</span>.<span>agent</span>.<span>name</span>)</pre></div>

<p dir="auto">It can also update the <code>context_variables</code> by returning a more complete <code>Result</code> object. This can also contain a <code>value</code> and an <code>agent</code>, in case you want a single function to return a value, update the agent, and update the context variables (or any subset of the three).</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="sales_agent = Agent(name=&quot;Sales Agent&quot;)

def talk_to_sales():
   print(&quot;Hello, World!&quot;)
   return Result(
       value=&quot;Done&quot;,
       agent=sales_agent,
       context_variables={&quot;department&quot;: &quot;sales&quot;}
   )

agent = Agent(functions=[talk_to_sales])

response = client.run(
   agent=agent,
   messages=[{&quot;role&quot;: &quot;user&quot;, &quot;content&quot;: &quot;Transfer me to sales&quot;}],
   context_variables={&quot;user_name&quot;: &quot;John&quot;}
)
print(response.agent.name)
print(response.context_variables)"><pre><span>sales_agent</span> <span>=</span> <span>Agent</span>(<span>name</span><span>=</span><span>"Sales Agent"</span>)

<span>def</span> <span>talk_to_sales</span>():
   <span>print</span>(<span>"Hello, World!"</span>)
   <span>return</span> <span>Result</span>(
       <span>value</span><span>=</span><span>"Done"</span>,
       <span>agent</span><span>=</span><span>sales_agent</span>,
       <span>context_variables</span><span>=</span>{<span>"department"</span>: <span>"sales"</span>}
   )

<span>agent</span> <span>=</span> <span>Agent</span>(<span>functions</span><span>=</span>[<span>talk_to_sales</span>])

<span>response</span> <span>=</span> <span>client</span>.<span>run</span>(
   <span>agent</span><span>=</span><span>agent</span>,
   <span>messages</span><span>=</span>[{<span>"role"</span>: <span>"user"</span>, <span>"content"</span>: <span>"Transfer me to sales"</span>}],
   <span>context_variables</span><span>=</span>{<span>"user_name"</span>: <span>"John"</span>}
)
<span>print</span>(<span>response</span>.<span>agent</span>.<span>name</span>)
<span>print</span>(<span>response</span>.<span>context_variables</span>)</pre></div>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="Sales Agent
{'department': 'sales', 'user_name': 'John'}"><pre><code>Sales Agent
{'department': 'sales', 'user_name': 'John'}
</code></pre></div>
<div dir="auto"><p dir="auto">Note</p><p dir="auto">If an <code>Agent</code> calls multiple functions to hand-off to an <code>Agent</code>, only the last handoff function will be used.</p>
</div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Function Schemas</h3><a id="user-content-function-schemas" aria-label="Permalink: Function Schemas" href="#function-schemas"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Swarm automatically converts functions into a JSON Schema that is passed into Chat Completions <code>tools</code>.</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Docstrings are turned into the function <code>description</code>.</li>
<li>Parameters without default values are set to <code>required</code>.</li>
<li>Type hints are mapped to the parameter's <code>type</code> (and default to <code>string</code>).</li>
<li>Per-parameter descriptions are not explicitly supported, but should work similarly if just added in the docstring. (In the future docstring argument parsing may be added.)</li>
</ul>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="def greet(name, age: int, location: str = &quot;New York&quot;):
   &quot;&quot;&quot;Greets the user. Make sure to get their name and age before calling.

   Args:
      name: Name of the user.
      age: Age of the user.
      location: Best place on earth.
   &quot;&quot;&quot;
   print(f&quot;Hello {name}, glad you are {age} in {location}!&quot;)"><pre><span>def</span> <span>greet</span>(<span>name</span>, <span>age</span>: <span>int</span>, <span>location</span>: <span>str</span> <span>=</span> <span>"New York"</span>):
   <span>"""Greets the user. Make sure to get their name and age before calling.</span>
<span></span>
<span>   Args:</span>
<span>      name: Name of the user.</span>
<span>      age: Age of the user.</span>
<span>      location: Best place on earth.</span>
<span>   """</span>
   <span>print</span>(<span>f"Hello <span><span>{</span><span>name</span><span>}</span></span>, glad you are <span><span>{</span><span>age</span><span>}</span></span> in <span><span>{</span><span>location</span><span>}</span></span>!"</span>)</pre></div>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="{
   &quot;type&quot;: &quot;function&quot;,
   &quot;function&quot;: {
      &quot;name&quot;: &quot;greet&quot;,
      &quot;description&quot;: &quot;Greets the user. Make sure to get their name and age before calling.\n\nArgs:\n   name: Name of the user.\n   age: Age of the user.\n   location: Best place on earth.&quot;,
      &quot;parameters&quot;: {
         &quot;type&quot;: &quot;object&quot;,
         &quot;properties&quot;: {
            &quot;name&quot;: {&quot;type&quot;: &quot;string&quot;},
            &quot;age&quot;: {&quot;type&quot;: &quot;integer&quot;},
            &quot;location&quot;: {&quot;type&quot;: &quot;string&quot;}
         },
         &quot;required&quot;: [&quot;name&quot;, &quot;age&quot;]
      }
   }
}"><pre><span>{</span>
   <span>"type"</span>: <span>"function"</span><span>,</span>
   <span>"function"</span>: <span>{</span>
      <span>"name"</span>: <span>"greet"</span><span>,</span>
      <span>"description"</span>: <span>"Greets the user. Make sure to get their name and age before calling.\n\nArgs:\n   name: Name of the user.\n   age: Age of the user.\n   location: Best place on earth."</span><span>,</span>
      <span>"parameters"</span>: <span>{</span>
         <span>"type"</span>: <span>"object"</span><span>,</span>
         <span>"properties"</span>: <span>{</span>
            <span>"name"</span>: <span>{</span><span>"type"</span>: <span>"string"</span><span>}</span><span>,</span>
            <span>"age"</span>: <span>{</span><span>"type"</span>: <span>"integer"</span><span>}</span><span>,</span>
            <span>"location"</span>: <span>{</span><span>"type"</span>: <span>"string"</span><span>}</span>
         <span>}</span><span>,</span>
         <span>"required"</span>: <span>[</span><span>"name"</span><span>,</span> <span>"age"</span><span>]</span>
      <span>}</span>
   <span>}</span>
<span>}</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Streaming</h2><a id="user-content-streaming" aria-label="Permalink: Streaming" href="#streaming"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="stream = client.run(agent, messages, stream=True)
for chunk in stream:
   print(chunk)"><pre><span>stream</span> <span>=</span> <span>client</span>.<span>run</span>(<span>agent</span>, <span>messages</span>, <span>stream</span><span>=</span><span>True</span>)
<span>for</span> <span>chunk</span> <span>in</span> <span>stream</span>:
   <span>print</span>(<span>chunk</span>)</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Uses the same events as <a href="https://platform.openai.com/docs/api-reference/streaming" rel="nofollow">Chat Completions API streaming</a>. See <code>process_and_print_streaming_response</code> in <code>/swarm/repl/repl.py</code> as an example.</p>
<p dir="auto">Two new event types have been added:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>{"delim":"start"}</code> and <code>{"delim":"start"}</code>, to signal each time an <code>Agent</code> handles a single message (response or function call). This helps identify switches between <code>Agent</code>s.</li>
<li><code>{"response": Response}</code> will return a <code>Response</code> object at the end of a stream with the aggregated (complete) response, for convenience.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Evaluations</h2><a id="user-content-evaluations" aria-label="Permalink: Evaluations" href="#evaluations"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Evaluations are crucial to any project, and we encourage developers to bring their own eval suites to test the performance of their swarms. For reference, we have some examples for how to eval swarm in the <code>airline</code>, <code>weather_agent</code> and <code>triage_agent</code> quickstart examples. See the READMEs for more details.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Utils</h2><a id="user-content-utils" aria-label="Permalink: Utils" href="#utils"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Use the <code>run_demo_loop</code> to test out your swarm! This will run a REPL on your command line. Supports streaming.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="from swarm.repl import run_demo_loop
...
run_demo_loop(agent, stream=True)"><pre><span>from</span> <span>swarm</span>.<span>repl</span> <span>import</span> <span>run_demo_loop</span>
...
<span>run_demo_loop</span>(<span>agent</span>, <span>stream</span><span>=</span><span>True</span>)</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Core Contributors</h2><a id="user-content-core-contributors" aria-label="Permalink: Core Contributors" href="#core-contributors"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Ilan Bigio - <a href="https://github.com/ibigio">ibigio</a></li>
<li>James Hills - <a href="https://github.com/jhills20">jhills20</a></li>
<li>Shyamal Anadkat - <a href="https://github.com/shyamal-anadkat">shyamal-anadkat</a></li>
<li>Charu Jaiswal - <a href="https://github.com/charuj">charuj</a></li>
<li>Colin Jarvis - <a href="https://github.com/colin-openai">colin-openai</a></li>
</ul>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>