<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 21:30:08 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cloudflare outage on February 20, 2026 (103 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.cloudflare.com/cloudflare-outage-february-20-2026/</link>
            <guid>47103649</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 19:05:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/cloudflare-outage-february-20-2026/">https://blog.cloudflare.com/cloudflare-outage-february-20-2026/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47103649">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post"><article><p>2026-02-21</p><section><p>9 min read</p><img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/9f2k63fiixI2YXDgsnbGq/4d156aa83c47ff6cecf3bd5c747126ef/unnamed__1_.png" alt=""><div><p>On February 20, 2026, at 17:48 UTC, Cloudflare experienced a service outage when a subset of customers who use Cloudflare’s Bring Your Own IP (BYOIP) service saw their routes to the Internet withdrawn via Border Gateway Protocol (BGP).</p><p>The issue was not caused, directly or indirectly, by a cyberattack or malicious activity of any kind. This issue was caused by a change that Cloudflare made to how our network manages IP addresses onboarded through the BYOIP pipeline. This change caused Cloudflare to unintentionally withdraw customer prefixes.</p><p>For some BYOIP customers, this resulted in their services and applications being unreachable from the Internet, causing timeouts and failures to connect across their Cloudflare deployments that used BYOIP. A subset of 1.1.1.1, specifically our destination one.one.one.one, was also impacted. The total duration of the incident was 6 hours and 7 minutes with most of that time spent restoring prefix configurations to their state prior to the change.</p><p>Cloudflare engineers reverted the change and prefixes stopped being withdrawn when we began to observe failures. However, before engineers were able to revert the change, ~1,100 BYOIP prefixes were withdrawn from the Cloudflare network. Some customers were able to restore their own service by using the Cloudflare dashboard to re-advertise their IP addresses. We resolved the incident when we restored all prefix configurations.</p><p>We are sorry for the impact to our customers. We let you down today. This post is an in-depth recounting of exactly what happened and which systems and processes failed. We will also outline the steps we are taking to prevent outages like this from happening again.</p>
    <p>
      <h2 id="how-did-the-outage-impact-customers">How did the outage impact customers?</h2>
      
    </p>
    <p>This graph shows the amount of prefixes advertised by Cloudflare during the incident to a BGP neighbor, which correlates to impact as prefixes that weren’t advertised were unreachable on the Internet:</p>
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/5QnazHN20Gcf3vLH5r95Cd/c8f42e90f266dd3daeaa308945507024/BLOG-3193_2.png" alt="" width="1970" height="1570" loading="lazy">
          </figure><p>Out of the total 6,500 prefixes advertised to this peer, 4,306 of those were BYOIP prefixes. These BYOIP prefixes are advertised to every peer and represent all the BYOIP prefixes we advertise globally.&nbsp;  </p><p>During the incident, 1,100 prefixes out of the total 6,500 were withdrawn from 17:56 to 18:46 UTC. Out of the 4,306 total BYOIP prefixes, 25% of BYOIP prefixes were unintentionally withdrawn. We were able to detect impact on one.one.one.one and revert the impacting change before more prefixes were impacted. At 19:19 UTC, we published guidance to customers that they would be able to self-remediate this incident by going to the Cloudflare dashboard and re-advertising their prefixes.</p><p>Cloudflare was able to revert many of the advertisement changes around 20:20 UTC, which caused 800 prefixes to be restored. There were still ~300 prefixes that were unable to be remediated through the dashboard because the service configurations for those prefixes were removed from the edge due to a software bug. These prefixes were manually restored by Cloudflare engineers at 23:03 UTC.&nbsp;</p><p>This incident did not impact all BYOIP customers because the configuration change was applied iteratively and not instantaneously across all BYOIP customers. Once the configuration change was revealed to be causing impact, the change was reverted before all customers were affected.&nbsp;</p><p>The impacted BYOIP customers first experienced a behavior called <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/going-bgp-zombie-hunting/"><u>BGP Path Hunting</u></a>. In this state, end user connections traverse networks trying to find a route to the destination IP. This behavior will persist until the connection that was opened times out and fails. Until the prefix is advertised somewhere, customers will continue to see this failure mode. This loop-until-failure scenario affected any product that uses BYOIP for advertisement to the Internet. One.one.one.one, which is a subset of 1.1.1.1, is a prefix onboarded as a BYOIP prefix, and was impacted in this manner. This prefix, which was Cloudflare-maintained but using our own products, allowed us to detect this issue quickly. A full breakdown of the services impacted is below.</p>
<div><table><colgroup>
<col>
<col>
</colgroup>
<thead>
  <tr>
    <th><span>Service/Product</span></th>
    <th><span>Impact Description</span></th>
  </tr></thead>
<tbody>
  <tr>
    <td><span>Core CDN and Security Services</span></td>
    <td><span>Traffic was not attracted to Cloudflare, and users connecting to websites advertised on those ranges would have seen failures to connect</span></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><span>Spectrum</span></td>
    <td><span>Spectrum apps on BYOIP failed to proxy traffic due to traffic not being attracted to Cloudflare</span></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><span>Dedicated Egress</span></td>
    <td><span>Customers who used Gateway Dedicated Egress leveraging BYOIP or Dedicated IPs for CDN Egress leveraging BYOIP would not have been able to send traffic out to their destinations</span></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><span>Magic Transit</span></td>
    <td><span>End users connecting to applications protected by Magic Transit would not have been advertised on the Internet, and would have seen connection timeouts and failures</span></td>
  </tr>
</tbody></table></div><p>There was also a set of customers who were unable to restore service by toggling the prefixes on the Cloudflare dashboard. As engineers began reannouncing prefixes to restore service for these customers, these customers may have seen increased latency and failures despite their IP addresses being advertised. This was because the addressing settings for some users were removed from edge servers due an issue in our own software, and the state had to be propagated back to the edge.&nbsp;</p><p>We’re going to get into what exactly broke in our addressing system, but to do that we need to cover a quick primer on the Addressing API, which is the underlying source of truth for customer IP addresses at Cloudflare.</p>
    <p>
      <h2 id="cloudflares-addressing-api">Cloudflare’s Addressing API</h2>
      
    </p>
    <p>The Addressing API is an authoritative dataset of the addresses present on the Cloudflare network. Any change to that dataset is immediately reflected in Cloudflare's global network. While we are in the process of improving how these systems roll out changes as a part of <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/fail-small-resilience-plan/"><u>Code Orange: Fail Small</u></a>, today customers can configure their IP addresses by interacting with public-facing APIs which configure a set of databases that trigger operational workflows propagating the changes to Cloudflare’s edge. This means that changes to the Addressing API are immediately propagated to the Cloudflare edge.</p><p>Advertising and configuring IP addresses on Cloudflare involves several steps:</p><ul><li><p>Customers signal to Cloudflare about advertisement/withdrawal of IP addresses via the Addressing API or BGP Control</p></li><li><p>The Addressing API instructs the machines to change the prefix advertisements</p></li><li><p>BGP will be updated on the routers once enough machines have received the notification to update the prefix</p></li><li><p>Finally, customers can configure Cloudflare products to use BYOIP addresses via <a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/byoip/service-bindings/"><u>service bindings</u></a> which will assign products to these ranges</p></li></ul><p>The Addressing API allows us to automate most of the processes surrounding how we advertise or withdraw addresses, but some processes still require manual actions. These manual processes are risky because of their close proximity to Production. As a part of <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/fail-small-resilience-plan/"><u>Code Orange: Fail Small</u></a>, one of the goals of remediation was to remove manual actions taken in the Addressing API and replace them with safe workflows.</p>
    <p>
      <h2 id="how-did-the-incident-occur">How did the incident occur?</h2>
      
    </p>
    <p>The specific piece of configuration that broke was a modification attempting to automate the customer action of removing prefixes from Cloudflare’s BYOIP service, a regular customer request that is done manually today. Removing this manual process was part of our Code Orange: Fail Small work to push all change towards safe, automated, health-mediated deployment. Since the list of related objects of BYOIP prefixes can be large, this was implemented as part of a regularly running sub-task that checks for BYOIP prefixes that should be removed, and then removes them. Unfortunately, this regular cleanup sub-task queried the API with a bug.</p><p>Here is the API query from the cleanup sub-task:</p>
            <pre><code> resp, err := d.doRequest(ctx, http.MethodGet, `/v1/prefixes?pending_delete`, nil)
</code></pre>
            <p>And here is the relevant part of the API implementation:</p>
            <pre><code>	if v := req.URL.Query().Get("pending_delete"); v != "" {
		// ignore other behavior and fetch pending objects from the ip_prefixes_deleted table
		prefixes, err := c.RO().IPPrefixes().FetchPrefixesPendingDeletion(ctx)
		if err != nil {
			api.RenderError(ctx, w, ErrInternalError)
			return
		}

		api.Render(ctx, w, http.StatusOK, renderIPPrefixAPIResponse(prefixes, nil))
		return
	}
</code></pre>
            <p>Because the client is passing pending_delete with no value, the result of Query().Get(“pending_delete”) here will be an empty string (“”), so the API server interprets this as a request for all BYOIP prefixes instead of just those prefixes that were supposed to be removed. The system interpreted this as all returned prefixes being queued for deletion. The new sub-task then began systematically deleting all BYOIP prefixes and all of their related dependent objects including <a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/byoip/service-bindings/"><u>service bindings</u></a>, until the impact was noticed, and an engineer identified the sub-task and shut it down.</p>
    <p>
      <h3 id="why-did-cloudflare-not-catch-the-bug-in-our-staging-environment-or-testing">Why did Cloudflare not catch the bug in our staging environment or testing?</h3>
      
    </p>
    <p>Our staging environment contains data that matches Production as closely as possible, but was not sufficient in this case and the mock data we relied on to simulate what would occur was insufficient. </p><p>In addition, while we have tests for this functionality, coverage for this scenario in our testing process and environment was incomplete. Initial testing and code review focused on the BYOIP self-service API journey and were completed successfully. While our engineers successfully tested the exact process a customer would have followed, testing did not cover a scenario where the task-runner service would independently execute changes to user data without explicit input.</p>
    <p>
      <h3 id="why-was-recovery-not-immediate">Why was recovery not immediate?</h3>
      
    </p>
    <p>Affected BYOIP prefixes were not all impacted in the same way, necessitating more intensive data recovery steps. As a part of Code Orange: Fail Small, we are building a system where operational state snapshots can be safely rolled out through health-mediated deployments. In the event something does roll out that causes unexpected behavior, it can be very quickly rolled back to a known-good state. However, that system is not in Production today.</p><p>BYOIP prefixes were in different states of impact during this incident, and each of these different states required different actions:</p><ul><li><p>Most impacted customers only had their prefixes withdrawn. Customers in this configuration could go into the dashboard and toggle their advertisements, which would restore service.&nbsp;</p></li><li><p>Some customers had their prefixes withdrawn and some bindings removed. These customers were in a partial state of recovery where they could toggle some prefixes but not others.</p></li><li><p>Some customers had their prefixes withdrawn and all service bindings removed. They could not toggle their prefixes in the dashboard because there was no <a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/byoip/service-bindings/"><u>service</u></a> (Magic Transit, Spectrum, CDN) bound to them. These customers took the longest to mitigate, as a global configuration update had to be initiated to reapply the service bindings for all these customers to every single machine on Cloudflare’s edge.</p></li></ul>
    <p>
      <h3 id="how-does-this-incident-relate-to-code-orange-fail-small">How does this incident relate to Code Orange: Fail Small?</h3>
      
    </p>
    <p>The change we were making when this incident occurred is part of the Code Orange: Fail Small initiative, which is aimed at improving the resiliency of code and configuration at Cloudflare. As a brief primer of the <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/fail-small-resilience-plan/"><u>Code Orange: Fail Small</u></a> initiatives, the work can be divided into three buckets:</p><ul><li><p>Require controlled rollouts for any configuration change that is propagated to the network, just like we do today for software binary releases.</p></li><li><p>Change our internal “break glass” procedures and remove any circular dependencies so that we, and our customers, can act fast and access all systems without issue during an incident.</p></li><li><p>Review, improve, and test failure modes of all systems handling network traffic to ensure they exhibit well-defined behavior under all conditions, including unexpected error states.</p></li></ul><p>The change that we attempted to deploy falls under the first bucket. By moving risky, manual changes to safe, automated configuration updates that are deployed in a health-mediated manner, we aim to improve the reliability of the service.</p><p>Critical work was already ongoing to enhance the Addressing API's configuration change support through staged test mediation and better correctness checks. This work was ongoing in parallel with the deployed change. Although preventative measures weren't fully deployed before the outage, teams were actively working on these systems when the incident occurred. Following our Code Orange: Fail Small promise to require controlled rollouts of any change into Production, our engineering teams have been reaching deep into all layers of our stack to identify and fix all problematic findings. While this outage wasn't itself global, the blast radius and impact were unacceptably large, further reinforcing Code Orange: Fail Small as a priority until we have re-established confidence in all changes to our network being as gradual as possible. Now let’s talk more specifically about improvements to these systems.</p>
    
    
    <p>
      <h3 id="api-schema-standardization">API schema standardization</h3>
      
    </p>
    <p>One of the issues in this incident is that the pending_delete flag was interpreted as a string, making it difficult for both client and server to rationalize the value of the flag. We will improve the API schema to ensure better standardization, which will make it much easier for testing and systems to validate whether an API call is properly formed or not. This work is part of the third Code Orange workstream, which aims to create well-defined behavior under all conditions.</p>
    <p>
      <h3 id="better-separation-between-operational-and-configured-state">Better separation between operational and configured state</h3>
      
    </p>
    <p>Today, customers make changes to the addressing schema that are persisted in an authoritative database, and that database is the same one used for operational actions. This makes manual rollback processes more challenging because engineers need to utilize database snapshots instead of rationalizing between desired and actual states. We will redesign the rollback mechanism and database configuration to ensure that we have an easy way to roll back changes quickly and also to introduce layers between customer configuration and Production.  </p><p>We will snap shot the data that we read from the database and are applying to Production, and apply those snapshots in the same way that we deploy all our other Production changes, mediated by health metrics that can automatically stop the deployment if things are going wrong. This means that the next time we have a problem where the database gets changed into a bad state, we can near-instantly revert individual customers (or all customers) to a version that was working.</p><p>While this will temporarily block our customers from being able to make direct updates via our API in the event of an outage, it will mean that we can continue serving their traffic while we work to fix the database, instead of being down for that time. This work aligns with the first and second Code Orange workstreams, which involves fast rollback and also safe, health-mediated deployment of configuration.</p>
    <p>
      <h3 id="better-arbitrate-large-withdrawal-actions">Better arbitrate large withdrawal actions</h3>
      
    </p>
    <p>We will improve our monitoring to detect when changes are happening too fast or too broadly, such as withdrawing or deleting BGP prefixes quickly, and disable the deployment of snapshots when this happens. This will form a type of circuit breaker to stop any out-of-control process that is manipulating the database from having a large blast radius, like we saw in this incident.</p><p>We also have some ongoing work to directly monitor that the services run by our customers are behaving correctly, and those signals can also be used to trip the circuit breaker and stop potentially dangerous changes from being applied until we have had time to investigate. This work aligns with the first Code Orange workstream, which involves safe deployment of changes.</p><p>Below is the timeline of events inclusive of deployment of the change and remediation steps: </p>
<div><table><colgroup>
<col>
<col>
<col>
</colgroup>
<thead>
  <tr>
    <th><span>Time (UT</span><span>C</span><span>)</span></th>
    <th><span>Status</span></th>
    <th><span>Description</span></th>
  </tr></thead>
<tbody>
  <tr>
    <td><span>2026-02-05 21:53</span></td>
    <td><span>Code merged into system</span></td>
    <td><span>Broken sub-process merged into code base</span></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><span>2026-02-20 17:46</span></td>
    <td><span>Code deployed into system</span></td>
    <td><span>Address API release with broken sub-process completes</span></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><span>2026-02-20 17:56</span></td>
    <td><span>Impact Start</span></td>
    <td><span>Broken sub-process begins executing. Prefix advertisement updates begin propagating and prefixes begin to be withdrawn </span><span>– IMPACT STARTS – </span></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><span>2026-02-20 18:13</span></td>
    <td><span>Cloudflare engaged</span></td>
    <td><span>Cloudflare engaged for failures on one.one.one.one</span></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><span>2026-02-20 18:18</span></td>
    <td><span>Internal incident declared</span></td>
    <td><span>Cloudflare engineers continue investigating impact</span></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><span>2026-02-20 18:21</span></td>
    <td><span>Addressing API team paged</span></td>
    <td><span>Engineering team responsible for Addressing API engaged and debugging begins</span></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><span>2026-02-20 18:46</span></td>
    <td><span>Issue identified</span></td>
    <td><span>Broken sub-process terminated by an engineer and regular execution disabled; remediation begins</span></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><span>2026-02-20 19:11</span></td>
    <td><span>Mitigation begins</span></td>
    <td><span>Cloudflare Engineers begin to restore serviceability for prefixes that were withdrawn while others focused on prefixes that were removed</span></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><span>2026-02-20 19:19</span></td>
    <td><span>Some prefixes mitigated</span></td>
    <td><span>Customers begin to re-advertise their prefixes via the dashboard to restore service. </span><span>– IMPACT DOWNGRADE –</span></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><span>2026-02-20 19:44</span></td>
    <td><span>Additional mitigation continues</span></td>
    <td><span>Engineers begin database recovery methods for removed prefixes</span></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><span>2026-02-20 20:30</span></td>
    <td><span>Final mitigation process begins</span></td>
    <td><span>Engineers complete release to restore withdrawn prefixes that still have existing service bindings. Others are still working on removed prefixes </span><span>– IMPACT DOWNGRADE –</span></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><span>2026-02-20 21:08</span></td>
    <td><span>Configuration update deploys</span></td>
    <td><span>Engineering begins global machine configuration rollout to restore prefixes that were not self-mitigated or mitigated via previous efforts </span><span>– IMPACT DOWNGRADE –</span></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><span>2026-02-20 23:03</span></td>
    <td><span>Configuration update completed</span></td>
    <td><span>Global machine configuration deployment to restore remaining prefixes is completed. </span><span>– IMPACT ENDS –</span></td>
  </tr>
</tbody></table></div><p>We deeply apologize for this incident today and how it affected the service we provide our customers, and also the Internet at large. We aim to provide a network that is resilient to change, and we did not deliver on our promise to you. We are actively making these improvements to ensure improved stability moving forward and to prevent this problem from happening again.</p></div></section><div><p>Cloudflare's connectivity cloud protects <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/network-services/" rel="noreferrer">entire corporate networks</a>, helps customers build <a target="_blank" href="https://workers.cloudflare.com/" rel="noreferrer">Internet-scale applications efficiently</a>, accelerates any <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/performance/accelerate-internet-applications/" rel="noreferrer">website or Internet application</a>, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/ddos/" rel="noreferrer">wards off DDoS attacks</a>, keeps <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/application-security/" rel="noreferrer">hackers at bay</a>, and can help you on <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/products/zero-trust/" rel="noreferrer">your journey to Zero Trust</a>.</p><p>Visit <a target="_blank" href="https://one.one.one.one/" rel="noreferrer">1.1.1.1</a> from any device to get started with our free app that makes your Internet faster and safer.</p><p>To learn more about our mission to help build a better Internet, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/what-is-cloudflare/" rel="noreferrer">start here</a>. If you're looking for a new career direction, check out <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/careers" rel="noreferrer">our open positions</a>.</p></div><astro-slot> <!--[if astro]>server-island-start<![endif]--> </astro-slot><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/post-mortem/">Post Mortem</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/incident-response/">Incident Response</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/outage/">Outage</a></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What Not to Write on Your Security Clearance Form (318 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://milk.com/wall-o-shame/security_clearance.html</link>
            <guid>47102576</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 17:08:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://milk.com/wall-o-shame/security_clearance.html">https://milk.com/wall-o-shame/security_clearance.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47102576">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">

<i>as reported in the <tt><i>[REDACTED]</i></tt> list and RISKS</i>
<hr><p>

<strong>Date:</strong> 01 Apr 88  1620 PST<br>
<strong>From:</strong> Les Earnest <tt>&lt;<!--LES-->LES...@S...<!--SAIL.Stanford.EDU-->&gt;</tt><br>
<strong>Subject:</strong> The "previous account" referred to in RISKS-6.51<br>

</p><h2>e-t-a-o-n-r-i Spy and the FBI</h2>

Reading a book got me into early trouble--I had an FBI record
by age twelve. This bizarre incident caused a problem much later
when I needed a security clearance. I learned that I could obtain
one only by concealing my sordid past.

<p>
A friend named Bob and I read the book ``Secret and Urgent,'' by
Fletcher Pratt [Blue Ribbon Books; Garden City, NY; 1942] which was
an early popular account of codes and ciphers. Pratt showed how to
use letter frequencies to break ciphers and reported that the most
frequently occurring letters in typical English text are
e-t-a-o-n-r-i, in that order. (The letter frequency order of the
story you are now reading is e-t-a-i-o-n-r. The higher frequency
of ``i'' probably reflects the fact that _I_ use the first person
singular a lot.) Pratt's book also treated more advanced
cryptographic schemes.

</p><p>
Bob and I decided that we needed to have a secure way to
communicate with each other, so we put together a rather elaborate
jargon code based on the principles described in the book. I don't
remember exactly why we thought we needed it--we spent much of
our time outside of school together, so there was ample time to
talk privately. Still, you never could tell when you might need to
send a secret message!

</p><p>
We made two copies of the code key (a description of how to encrypt
and decrypt our messages) in the form of a single typewritten
sheet. We each took a copy and carried it on our persons at all
times when we were wearing clothes.

</p><p>
I actually didn't wear clothes much. I spent nearly all my time
outside school wearing just a baggy pair of maroon swimming trunks.
That wasn't considered too weird in San Diego.

</p><p>
I had recently been given glasses to wear but generally kept them
in a hard case in the pocket of the trousers that I wore to school.
I figured that this was a good place to hide my copy of the code
key, so I carefully folded it to one-eighth of its original size
and stuck it at the bottom of the case, under my glasses.

</p><p>
Every chance I got, I went body surfing at Old Mission Beach. I
usually went by streetcar and, since I had to transfer Downtown, I
wore clothes. Unfortunately, while I was riding the trolley home
from the beach one Saturday, the case carrying my glasses slipped
out of my pocket unnoticed. I reported the loss to my mother that
night. She chastised me and later called the streetcar company.
They said that the glasses hadn't been turned in.

</p><p>
After a few weeks of waiting in vain for the glasses to turn up, we
began to lose hope. My mother didn't rush getting replacement
glasses in view of the fact that I hadn't worn them much and they
cost about $8, a large sum at that time. (To me, $8 represented 40
round trips to the beach by streetcar, or 80 admission fees to the
movies.)

</p><p>
Unknown to us, the case had been found by a patriotic citizen who
opened it, discovered the code key, recognized that it must belong
to a Japanese spy and turned it over to the FBI This was in
1943, just after citizens of Japanese descent had been forced off
their property and taken away to concentration camps. I remember
hearing that a local grocer was secretly a Colonel in the Japanese
Army and had hidden his uniform in the back of his store. A lot of
people actually believed these things.

</p><p>
About six weeks later, when I happened to be off on another
escapade, my mother was visited by a man who identified himself as
an investigator from the FBI (She was a school administrator,
but happened to be at home working on her Ph.D. dissertation.) She
noticed that there were two more men waiting in a car outside. The
agent asked a number of questions about me, including my
occupation. He reportedly was quite disappointed when he learned
that I was only 12 years old.

</p><p>
He eventually revealed why I was being investigated, showed my
mother the glasses and the code key and asked her if she knew where
it came from. She didn't, of course. She asked if we could get
the glasses back and he agreed.

</p><p>
My mother told the investigator how glad she was to get them back,
considering that they cost $8. He did a slow burn, then said
``Lady, this case has cost the government thousands of dollars. It
has been the top priority in our office for the last six weeks. We
traced the glasses to your son from the prescription by examining
the files of nearly every optometrist in San Diego.'' It apparently
didn't occur to them that if I were a <i>real</i> Japanese spy, I might
have brought the glasses with me from headquarters.

</p><p>
The FBI agent gave back the glasses but kept the code key ``for
our records.'' They apparently were not fully convinced that they
were dealing just with kids.

</p><p>
Since our communication scheme had been compromised, Bob and I
devised a new key. I started carrying it in my wallet, which I
thought was more secure. I don't remember ever exchanging any
cryptographic messages. I was always ready, though.

</p><p>
A few years later when I was in college, I got a summer job at the
Naval Electronics Lab, which required a security clearance. One of
the questions on the application form was ``Have you ever been
investigated by the FBI?'' Naturally, I checked ``Yes.'' The next
question was, ``If so, describe the circumstances.'' There was very
little space on the form, so I answered simply and honestly, ``I was
suspected of being a Japanese spy.''

</p><p>
When I handed the form in to the security officer, he scanned it
quickly, looked me over slowly, then said, ``Explain this''--pointing
at the FBI question. I described what had happened.
He got very agitated, picked up my form, tore it in pieces, and
threw it in the waste basket.

</p><p>
He then got out a blank form and handed it to me, saying ``Here,
fill it out again and don't mention that. If you do, I'll make
sure that you <i>never</i> get a security clearance.''

</p><p>
I did as he directed and was shortly granted the clearance. I
never again disclosed that incident on security clearance forms.

</p><p>
On another occasion much later, I learned by chance that putting
certain provocative information on a security clearance form can
greatly speed up the clearance process. But that is another story.

</p><p>
Les Earnest
</p><hr>
<a href="https://milk.com/wall-o-shame/"><img src="https://milk.com/wall-o-shame/wos-mark.gif" alt="WoS"></a>
Edited and converted to HTML by Dan Bornstein.

</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[macOS's Little-Known Command-Line Sandboxing Tool (2025) (177 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://igorstechnoclub.com/sandbox-exec/</link>
            <guid>47101200</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 14:34:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://igorstechnoclub.com/sandbox-exec/">https://igorstechnoclub.com/sandbox-exec/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47101200">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://igorstechnoclub.com/sandbox-exec/: Error: getaddrinfo ENOTFOUND igorstechnoclub.com]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[CXMT has been offering DDR4 chips at about half the prevailing market rate (101 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.koreaherald.com/article/10679206</link>
            <guid>47101171</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 14:32:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.koreaherald.com/article/10679206">https://www.koreaherald.com/article/10679206</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47101171">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="articleText">
<p>CXMT halves DDR4 prices as YMTC gains ground in NAND, raising concerns over Korea’s legacy exposure</p><div>  <figure>     <img src="https://wimg.heraldcorp.com/news/cms/2026/02/20/news-p.v1.20260220.1686b9f4331c4661b835adf082563d1a_P1.png" alt="China’s top DRAM manufacturer CXMT's LPDDR5 DRAM (CXMT's website)">     <figcaption>China’s top DRAM manufacturer CXMT's LPDDR5 DRAM (CXMT's website)</figcaption>  </figure></div><p>Samsung Electronics and SK hynix are locked in a race to mass-produce sixth-generation high-bandwidth memory, but Chinese rivals are making gains elsewhere — flooding the legacy DRAM market with chips priced at roughly half the going rate.</p><p>According to industry sources on Friday, China’s top DRAM manufacturer CXMT has been offering older-generation DDR4 chips at about half the prevailing market rate. The move comes as global supply shortages have driven prices sharply higher, allowing the company to aggressively push legacy products for mobile devices and PCs in a bid to boost market share.</p><p>DDR4 remains a mainstay component in devices such as PCs and TVs, and have risen in price recently.</p><p>Data from DRAMeXchange showed that as of end-January, the average fixed contract price of PC DRAM DDR4 8Gb stood at $11.50, up 23.7 percent from $9.30 a month ago. Compared with $1.35 a year earlier, the price has jumped more than eightfold. DRAM prices have climbed for 10 consecutive months, marking the highest level since the market tracker began compiling data in June 2016.</p><p>Against this backdrop, cut-price Chinese chips are proving tempting. US hardware firms HP and Dell are reportedly conducting quality tests on CXMT’s DRAM, while Taiwan’s Asus and Acer have sought cooperation with Chinese partners. Signs are emerging that aggressive pricing is translating into demand.</p><p>“Chinese firms are waging a volume-based strategy starting with general-purpose memory, backed by state subsidies and domestic demand from AI servers and locally developed GPUs,” said an industry source who requested anonymity. “As Korean companies concentrate on HBM4, there are visible cracks emerging in (their hold on) the legacy market.”</p><p>The challenge for Korean chipmakers is that the legacy segment still accounts for a significant portion of their earnings. More than half of the total DRAM production capacity at both Samsung and SK hynix is understood to be allocated to general-purpose products. Even if they maintain leadership in HBM4, a deepening erosion of the mainstream market could eventually weigh on profitability.</p><p>Chinese players, meanwhile, are not limiting their push to low-cost volume sales. The cash and know-how gained from legacy chips is funding a push into higher-end products.</p><p>CXMT is in the process of converting wafer capacity equivalent to about 20 percent of its total DRAM output — some 60,000 wafers per month — at its Shanghai plant to the fourth-generation HBM3 chip production. The possibility of expanding into post-HBM3E products is also being discussed.</p><p>The Shanghai facility is believed to have production capacity two to three times larger than the company’s headquarters plant in Hefei. Equipment installation is expected to be completed in the second half of this year, with mass production slated for next year. Although HBM3 and the fifth-generation HBM3E chips trail HBM4 in performance, they remain widely used in AI data centers.</p><p>China’s advance is not confined to DRAM. YMTC has been gaining traction in the NAND flash sector as well, capitalizing on competitively priced mobile products. The company recorded a 10 percent share of the global NAND market for the first time last year, and momentum is widely expected to continue.</p><p>YMTC is currently building a third fabrication plant in Wuhan, targeting operations next year. Half of the facility’s production capacity is to be allocated to DRAM. It will initially focus on legacy DRAM products, with the possibility of expanding into HBM production in partnership with local assembly firms. Industry sources say the pattern is familiar — build scale in legacy DRAM, then move up the value chain.</p><p>“At this stage, Chinese manufacturers are relying on aggressive pricing to build scale in legacy DRAM,” the anonymous source said. “But over time, the technology gap may narrow more quickly than expected. Even if Korean firms maintain leadership in HBM, neglecting the mainstream segment could weigh on profitability in the longer run.”</p>
<br>yeeun@heraldcorp.com</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Over 80% of 16 to 24-year-olds would vote to rejoin the EU (101 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.itv.com/news/2026-02-19/over-80-of-16-to-24-year-olds-would-vote-to-rejoin-the-eu-itv-poll-finds</link>
            <guid>47099844</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 11:39:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.itv.com/news/2026-02-19/over-80-of-16-to-24-year-olds-would-vote-to-rejoin-the-eu-itv-poll-finds">https://www.itv.com/news/2026-02-19/over-80-of-16-to-24-year-olds-would-vote-to-rejoin-the-eu-itv-poll-finds</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47099844">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.itv.com/news/2026-02-19/over-80-of-16-to-24-year-olds-would-vote-to-rejoin-the-eu-itv-poll-finds: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Andrej Karpathy talks about "Claws" (268 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://simonwillison.net/2026/Feb/21/claws/</link>
            <guid>47099160</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 09:53:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2026/Feb/21/claws/">https://simonwillison.net/2026/Feb/21/claws/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47099160">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>


<p>21st February 2026</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://twitter.com/karpathy/status/2024987174077432126">Andrej Karpathy talks about "Claws"</a></strong>. Andrej Karpathy tweeted a mini-essay about buying a Mac Mini ("The apple store person told me they are selling like hotcakes and everyone is confused") to tinker with Claws:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I'm definitely a bit sus'd to run OpenClaw specifically [...] But I do love the concept and I think that just like LLM agents were a new layer on top of LLMs, Claws are now a new layer on top of LLM agents, taking the orchestration, scheduling, context, tool calls and a kind of persistence to a next level.</p>
<p>Looking around, and given that the high level idea is clear, there are a lot of smaller Claws starting to pop out. For example, on a quick skim NanoClaw looks really interesting in that the core engine is ~4000 lines of code (fits into both my head and that of AI agents, so it feels manageable, auditable, flexible, etc.) and runs everything in containers by default. [...]</p>
<p>Anyway there are many others - e.g. nanobot, zeroclaw, ironclaw, picoclaw (lol @ prefixes). [...]</p>
<p>Not 100% sure what my setup ends up looking like just yet but Claws are an awesome, exciting new layer of the AI stack.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Andrej has an ear for fresh terminology (see <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Mar/19/vibe-coding/">vibe coding</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2026/Feb/11/glm-5/">agentic engineering</a>) and I think he's right about this one, too: "<strong>Claw</strong>" is becoming a term of art for the entire category of OpenClaw-like agent systems - AI agents that generally run on personal hardware, communicate via messaging protocols and can both act on direct instructions and schedule tasks.</p>
<p>It even comes with an established emoji 🦞</p>




</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[LibreOffice blasts OnlyOffice for working with Microsoft to lock users in (126 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.neowin.net/news/libreoffice-blasts-fake-open-source-onlyoffice-for-working-with-microsoft-to-lock-users-in/</link>
            <guid>47098828</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 08:54:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.neowin.net/news/libreoffice-blasts-fake-open-source-onlyoffice-for-working-with-microsoft-to-lock-users-in/">https://www.neowin.net/news/libreoffice-blasts-fake-open-source-onlyoffice-for-working-with-microsoft-to-lock-users-in/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47098828">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.neowin.net/news/libreoffice-blasts-fake-open-source-onlyoffice-for-working-with-microsoft-to-lock-users-in/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[24 Hour Fitness won't let you unsubscribe from marketing spam, so I fixed it (109 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ahmedkaddoura.com/projects/24hf-unsubscribe</link>
            <guid>47098744</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 08:39:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ahmedkaddoura.com/projects/24hf-unsubscribe">https://ahmedkaddoura.com/projects/24hf-unsubscribe</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47098744">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      
<p>24 Hour Fitness has a broken unsubscribe page. You get one of their marketing emails. You click the unsubscribe link at the bottom. It takes you here:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.24hourfitness.com/members/unsubscribe">https://www.24hourfitness.com/members/unsubscribe</a></p>
<p>You enter your email. You click unsubscribe. You get a mysterious error message in Spanish.</p>
<p>I found the bug. It's one line of JavaScript. I reported it back in November 2025. No response. So I built my own unsubscribe page.</p>

<div>
  <p><img src="https://ahmedkaddoura.com/images/24hf/spanish-error.jpeg" alt="24 Hour Fitness unsubscribe page showing an error message in Spanish"></p><p>"The audacity of a Spanish error message on a US gym website." — Claude</p>
</div>
<h2>What the heck is this? 🤔</h2>
<p><strong>Error de conexión al obtener el token de OneTrust.</strong>
</p>
<p><a href="https://www.onetrust.com/">OneTrust</a> is an American software company that develops privacy, security, and data governance software. Their platform includes tools for consent management and regulatory compliance automation.</p>
<p>The irony: OneTrust is literally a consent management platform focused on regulatory compliance, and 24 Hour Fitness is using it to violate consent regulations. The error is in Spanish for some reason.</p>
<h2>This is actually illegal</h2>
<p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CAN-SPAM_Act_of_2003">CAN-SPAM Act</a> requires commercial emails to have a working opt-out mechanism. Companies that violate this face serious fines:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Verkada:</strong> <a href="https://advertisinglaw.fkks.com/post/102jlit/ftc-gets-record-penalty-in-can-spam-enforcement-action">$2.95 million</a> (2024) - the largest CAN-SPAM penalty ever. They ignored opt-out requests.</li>
<li><strong>Jumpstart Technologies:</strong> <a href="https://www.dmnews.com/internet-marketer-will-pay-900000-canspam-penalty/">$900,000</a> (2006) - didn't process opt-out requests in time.</li>
<li><strong>Experian:</strong> <a href="https://lashback.com/regulatory-alert-ftc-enforces-can-spam-act-650000-penalty/">$650,000</a> (2023) - spammed users with emails they couldn't opt out of.</li>
</ul>
<p>Each individual email can carry a penalty of up to $53,088.</p>
<h2>Marketing email = psychic attack</h2>
<p>I don't subscribe to anything. Not newsletters. Not Substacks. Not even blogs from writers I deeply care about. My inbox is for communication, not marketing.</p>
<p>I'm definitely not subscribing to 24 Hour Fitness marketing spam.</p>
<p>Since October 2025, I've received 40 marketing emails. Every single one links to the same broken unsubscribe page.</p>
<p>Each of these emails is a psychic attack. An attack on my attention. Here are the subject lines:</p>

<p>I'm paying for this membership. I can't opt out of their spam. This is evil.</p>
<h2>This isn't new for 24 Hour Fitness</h2>
<p>I found <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/assholedesign/comments/ams2k8/trying_to_unsubscribe_from_24hr_fitness_spam/">this Reddit post</a> from February 2019:</p>
<div>
  <p><img src="https://ahmedkaddoura.com/images/24hf/reddit-2019.webp" alt="Reddit post from 2019 complaining about 24 Hour Fitness unsubscribe"></p><p>Almost 7 years ago, same problem.</p>
</div>
<p>24 Hour Fitness has had unsubscribe problems for at least 7 years. Not only do they make it hard to cancel your gym membership, they also make it hard to escape their marketing emails.</p>
<p>I hope they fix this. If I'm dealing with it, I'm sure thousands of others are too.</p>
<h2>I reported it. No response.</h2>
<p>I submitted a bug report via <a href="https://www.24hourfitness.com/contact_us/">their contact form</a> back in November 2025.</p>
<p>They replied: "Thank you Ahmed, for reaching out! We will make sure your comments are forwarded to the appropriate person. Please be assured we are doing our best to follow up as soon as possible, typically within 10 business days."</p>
<p>Weeks later. No response. Bug still broken. Emails still coming.</p>
<h2>The one-line JavaScript fix</h2>
<p>I looked at their code. The bug is embarrassingly simple:</p>
<div>
  <pre><code>$.ajax({
    type: "POST",
    url: m.urlPost,
    data: JSON.stringify({...}),
    <span>contentType: !1,</span>  <span>// BUG: !1 === false</span>
    ...
})</code></pre>
</div>
<p><code>contentType: false</code> tells jQuery to skip the Content-Type header. The server expects JSON. It rejects the request.</p>
<p>The fix:</p>
<div>
  <pre><code><span>contentType: "application/json"</span></code></pre>
</div>
<p>One line. Broken for months.</p>
<h2>So I built my own unsubscribe page</h2>
<p>My page calls the same API with the correct header. It just works.</p>

<p>If you know someone on the 24 Hour Fitness engineering team, please share this with them. It's a one-line fix.</p>

    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[EU mandates replaceable batteries by 2027 (2023) (207 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://environment.ec.europa.eu/news/new-law-more-sustainable-circular-and-safe-batteries-enters-force-2023-08-17_en</link>
            <guid>47098687</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 08:28:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://environment.ec.europa.eu/news/new-law-more-sustainable-circular-and-safe-batteries-enters-force-2023-08-17_en">https://environment.ec.europa.eu/news/new-law-more-sustainable-circular-and-safe-batteries-enters-force-2023-08-17_en</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47098687">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>A new law to ensure that batteries are collected, reused and recycled in Europe is entering into force today. The new <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2023/1542/oj">Batteries Regulation</a> will ensure that, in the future, batteries have a low carbon footprint, use minimal harmful substances, need less raw materials from non-EU countries, and are collected, reused and recycled to a high degree in Europe. This will support the shift to a circular economy, increase security of supply for raw materials and energy, and enhance the EU’s strategic autonomy.</p>

<p>In line with the circularity ambitions of the <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/info/strategy/priorities-2019-2024/european-green-deal_en">European Green Deal</a>, the Batteries Regulation is the first piece of European legislation taking a full life-cycle approach in which sourcing, manufacturing, use and recycling are addressed and enshrined in a single law.</p>

<p>Batteries are a key technology to drive the green transition, support sustainable mobility and contribute to climate neutrality by 2050. To that end, starting from 2025, the Regulation will gradually introduce declaration requirements, performance classes and maximum limits on the carbon footprint of electric vehicles, light means of transport (such as e-bikes and scooters) and rechargeable industrial batteries.</p>

<p>The Batteries Regulation will ensure that batteries placed on the EU single market will only be allowed to contain a restricted amount of harmful substances that are necessary. Substances of concerns used in batteries will be regularly reviewed.&nbsp;</p>

<p>Targets for recycling efficiency, material recovery and recycled content will be introduced gradually from 2025 onwards. All collected waste batteries will have to be recycled and high levels of recovery will have to be achieved, in particular of critical raw materials such as cobalt, lithium and nickel. This will guarantee that valuable materials are recovered at the end of their useful life and brought back in the economy by adopting stricter targets for recycling efficiency and material recovery over time.</p>

<p>Starting in 2027, consumers will be able to remove and replace the portable batteries in their electronic products at any time of the life cycle. This will extend the life of these products before their final disposal, will encourage re-use and will contribute to the reduction of post-consumer waste.</p>

<p>To help consumers make informed decisions on which batteries to purchase, key data will be provided on a label. A QR code will provide access to a digital passport with detailed information on each battery that will help consumers and especially professionals along the value chain in their efforts to make the circular economy a reality for batteries.</p>

<p>Under the new law’s due diligence obligations, companies must identify, prevent and address social and environmental risks linked to the sourcing, processing and trading of raw materials such as&nbsp;lithium, cobalt, nickel and natural graphite contained in their batteries. &nbsp;The expected massive increase in demand for batteries in the EU should not contribute to an increase of such environmental and social risks.</p>

<h3>Next steps</h3>

<p>Work will now focus on the application of the law in the Member States, and the redaction of secondary legislation (implementing and delegated acts) providing more detailed rules.</p>

<h3>Background</h3>

<p>Since 2006, batteries and waste batteries have been regulated at EU level under the&nbsp;<a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX%3A32006L0066">Batteries Directive</a>. The Commission&nbsp;<a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX%3A52020PC0798">proposed to revise this Directive</a>&nbsp;in December 2020 due to new socioeconomic conditions, technological developments, markets, and battery uses.</p>

<p>Demand for batteries is increasing rapidly. It is set to increase 14-fold globally by 2030 and the EU could account for 17% of that demand. This is mostly driven by the electrification of transport. Such exponential growth in demand for batteries will lead to an equivalent increase in demand for raw materials, hence the need to minimise their environmental impact.</p>

<p>In 2017, the Commission launched the&nbsp;European Battery Alliance&nbsp;to build an innovative, sustainable and globally competitive battery value chain in Europe, and ensure supply of batteries needed for decarbonising the transport and energy sectors.</p>

<h4>More information</h4>

<p><a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2023/1542/oj">Batteries Regulation</a></p>

<p><a href="https://environment.ec.europa.eu/topics/waste-and-recycling/batteries-and-accumulators_en">Webpage on batteries</a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AI uBlock Blacklist (185 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/alvi-se/ai-ublock-blacklist</link>
            <guid>47098582</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 08:10:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/alvi-se/ai-ublock-blacklist">https://github.com/alvi-se/ai-ublock-blacklist</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47098582">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">AI uBlock Origin Blacklist</h2><a id="user-content-ai-ublock-origin-blacklist" aria-label="Permalink: AI uBlock Origin Blacklist" href="#ai-ublock-origin-blacklist"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">A personal list for <a href="https://github.com/gorhill/uBlock">uBlock Origin</a> blocking AI content farms. Pull requests welcome.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Install</h2><a id="user-content-install" aria-label="Permalink: Install" href="#install"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">You can <a href="https://subscribe.adblockplus.org/?location=https%3A%2F%2Fraw%2Egithubusercontent%2Ecom%2Falvi%2Dse%2Fai%2Dublock%2Dblacklist%2Fmaster%2Flist%2Etxt&amp;title=AI%20Content%20Farms" rel="nofollow">click here</a> to subscribe to this list automatically. This link works only if you have uBlock Origin installed.</p>
<p dir="auto">Alternatively, import the following URL as a 3rd party list in uBlock Origin.</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/alvi-se/ai-ublock-blacklist/master/list.txt</code></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Why?</h2><a id="user-content-why" aria-label="Permalink: Why?" href="#why"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">While browsing it happens <del>sometimes</del> <a href="https://www.axios.com/2025/10/14/ai-generated-writing-humans" rel="nofollow"><strong>most of the times</strong></a> that I come across websites which text is written by generative AI. These websites provide no useful information, have mediocre content and are filled up with ads and referral links to earn money.
So when I find this kind of website, I put it here.</p>
<p dir="auto">The key idea is simple: if I wanted my question to be answered by AI, <em>I</em> would ask AI. If I'm searching online, it means that I want an answer written by a person. A person has experience, opinions, ideas, creativity and a lot more information that might want to share with the web. AI doesn't.</p>
<p dir="auto">What's more, AI content can also be <strong>dangerous</strong>: articles in content farms are not checked by anyone before being published, since they are massively generated. An AI might hallucinate when writing about dangerous topics: it might suggest you to short-circuit on your circuit board. Or to execute dangerous commands on your PC such as <code>rm -rf /</code>. Or to mix bleach and ammonia (DON'T DO THESE THINGS). AI generated content is not reliable, and if no one is checking what is being published, it needs to be blocked.</p>
<p dir="auto">As I said, I'm adding pages as I browse, so each entry is added manually. I'm not considering using automated tools simply because it's hard for an algorithm to understand if a page is AI generated or not, especially with the guidelines I wrote next. An argument could be that this list is useless because it's too short. However, since these websites are doing SEO to appear first on search engines, you will meet the same website more than once, especially for searches related to each other. I've found this list to be blocking websites since the very first day I began writing it, even with very few entries.</p>
<p dir="auto">However, there is indeed some bias for my entries. For example, as I am an Italian citizen, you will find a lot of Italian websites. This is another reason why pull requests are welcome.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How to add websites</h2><a id="user-content-how-to-add-websites" aria-label="Permalink: How to add websites" href="#how-to-add-websites"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If you're not a technical user and don't know how GitHub works, simply report your suspects creating an issue, by clicking <a href="https://github.com/alvi-se/ai-ublock-blacklist/issues/new">here</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">If you want to create a pull request, here's how to add a website to the list.
First, try to find the scope of the AI spammer. Usually, it will be a domain, but I've found also a lot of Medium blogs or dev.to blogs. These platforms should not be blocked as a whole, but just the blog who's spamming.</p>
<p dir="auto">Say that you want to add entry <code>example.com/@slopUser</code>, simply put a line to file <code>list.txt</code> as following:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="||example.com/@slopUser^$doc"><pre><span>||</span>example.com/@slopUser<span>^</span><span>$</span><span>doc</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">The whole <code>example.com</code> domain hosts AI garbage, you say? Add only the domain:</p>

<p dir="auto">If you really hate AI and have a lot of time to spend, you are welcome to do some research about the website you have found. Most of these content farms are built by people or organizations <a href="https://www.fiverr.com/categories/online-marketing/seo-services/seo-packages" rel="nofollow">who sell SEO and digital marketing</a>.
If you find the source, you might also find other content farms they have created. If you do, add them at the bottom of the file.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How websites are added</h2><a id="user-content-how-websites-are-added" aria-label="Permalink: How websites are added" href="#how-websites-are-added"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Content farm have have some patterns that make them recognizable. Here are the ones I understood. Of course, these are not strict rules.</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Unnecessary introduction and conclusion</strong>: this is probably the easiest way to spot content farms. Often, the intro is also annoyingly baroque. For example, you click on some guide on how to use a specific feature in Flutter.
The article would begin giving an introduction about Flutter itself like the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">In today’s fast-moving digital landscape, users expect apps to be fast, beautiful, and consistent across every device they touch.</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto">Probably, no human would write such an introduction to explain a <em>specific</em> feature.
It could fit to generally speak about Flutter (still too baroque though), but not for a super specific code that can be understood only by experienced developers. If I'm writing such an article, I'm supposing that the reader will already know what Flutter is!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>[topic]: A Comprehensive Guide/A Step-To-Step Guide/Ultimate Guide</strong>: LLMs love these catchphrases for titles of tutorials and guides.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>No/few links to external content</strong></p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>No sources and references</strong>: same as above, but for sources about facts. This is very important to check, especially for articles about (pseudo)science, politics and content that could spread misinformation.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Referral links everywhere</strong>: content farms are there just to make money. I've personally seen sites shamelessly putting purchase advice in navbars or footers.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Reference to product of company</strong>: the website is owned by a company that sells some product or service. The page will probably be like "How to solve [problem]" -&gt; buy our product.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Blog with hundreds of thousands of articles</strong>: especially when published in a very short time span. A lot of AI slop blogs post tens or hundreds of articles a day, mostly by the same author.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Hallucinations</strong>: the content is plain wrong.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Date after November 2022</strong>: the AI hype began with the release of ChatGPT in November 2022. A weak guideline for sure, but it adds up to all others. Dates can be easily faked though.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>No/few images, videos, non-text media</strong>: these pages are automatically generated and published, and it's hard to generate other kind of content to be put into the page.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>AI generated images, logos</strong>: usually it's the banner of the article or the blog logo.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Poor text formatting</strong></p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Not-rendered Markdown characters</strong>: text has no formatting and has Markdown syntax.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Long post, with unnecessary or out-of-context content</strong>: at some point the article can start talking about another topic, which can be related to the original one but irrelevant.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Always on top of search engines result</strong>: they are of course abusing SEO.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Know-it-all blog</strong>: the same blog appears in the search engine for completely different topics.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Vague content</strong>: lots of headings, each with a short content that provides no useful information.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Unprofessional or missing contact information</strong>: they have bought a domain, why are they using Gmail for contact?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Vague or missing about page</strong></p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>AI enthusiastic content</strong>: if someone loves ChatGPT they will use it for <strong>everything</strong>. So if you stumble across an AI-devoted blog, it's for sure 100% AI generated.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Google Dorks</h2><a id="user-content-google-dorks" aria-label="Permalink: Google Dorks" href="#google-dorks"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Because AI users are dumb enough to copy-paste LLM responses without reading them, the LLM will sometimes reveal itself, for example in the intro of the content.
The following are some Google Dorks to find 100% AI generated pages. Such pages will have their whole domain put into the uBlock list.
Dorks can be easily generated by asking an LLM to generate naive content, for example by prompting <code>Generate an article for my blog about dogs</code>.
The LLM will answer with an intro like <code>Sure! Here's an article about</code>. Take this phrase and search it surrounded by quotes.</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# English
&quot;Sure! Here's an article about&quot;

# Italian
&quot;Certo! Ecco un articolo&quot;"><pre><code># English
"Sure! Here's an article about"

# Italian
"Certo! Ecco un articolo"
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">NAQ (Never Asked Questions)</h2><a id="user-content-naq-never-asked-questions" aria-label="Permalink: NAQ (Never Asked Questions)" href="#naq-never-asked-questions"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>My website is on your list!</strong></p>
<p dir="auto">Cry about it.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>But I'm just using AI to correct grammar and spell</strong></p>
<p dir="auto">All I hear is skill issue. Imagine needing an AI to write stuff.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>I bought a domain that previously was a content farm, can you remove it?</strong></p>
<p dir="auto">No.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Similar projects</h2><a id="user-content-similar-projects" aria-label="Permalink: Similar projects" href="#similar-projects"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/laylavish/uBlockOrigin-HUGE-AI-Blocklist">uBlockOrigin &amp; uBlacklist Huge AI Blocklist</a>: this projects hides every AI related result from search engines, including
websites that I believe are legit tools (e.g. ChatGPT). What I want instead is blocking access only to garbage AI content farms.</li>
</ul>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Acme Weather (149 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://acmeweather.com/blog/introducing-acme-weather</link>
            <guid>47098296</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 07:13:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://acmeweather.com/blog/introducing-acme-weather">https://acmeweather.com/blog/introducing-acme-weather</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47098296">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <h2>Introducing Acme&nbsp;Weather</h2>
        

        <section>
            <p>Fifteen years ago, we started work on the Dark Sky weather app.</p>
            <p>Over the years it went through numerous iterations — including more than one major redesign — as we worked our way through the process of learning what makes a great weather app. Eventually, in time, it was acquired by Apple, where the forecast and some core features were incorporated into Apple Weather.</p>
            <p>We enjoyed our time at Apple. So why did we leave to start another weather company?</p>
            <p>It’s simple: when looking at the landscape of the countless weather apps out there, many of them lovely, we found ourselves feeling unsatisfied. The more we spoke to friends and family, the more we heard that many of them did too. And, of course, we missed those days as a small scrappy shop.</p>
            <p>So let’s try this again…</p>
            <p>
                <span>
                    <img src="https://acmeweather.com/img/intro/main.png" alt="Acme Weather App">
                </span>
            </p>
        </section>

        <section>
            <h2>Embracing Uncertainty</h2>

            <p>Our biggest pet peeve with most weather apps is how they deal (or rather, don’t deal) with forecast uncertainty. It is a simple fact that no weather forecast will ever be 100% reliable: the weather is moody, fickle, and chaotic. Forecasts are often wrong.</p>
            <p>Understanding this uncertainty is crucial for planning your day. Most weather apps will give you their single best guess, leaving you to wonder how sure they actually are, and what else might happen instead. Will it actually start raining at 9am, or might it end up pushed off until noon? Will there be rain or snow? How sure are you? You can’t plan your day if you don’t know how much you can trust the forecast, or know what other possibilities might arise. Rather than pretending we will always be right, Acme Weather embraces the idea that our forecast will sometimes be wrong. We address this uncertainty in several ways:</p>

            <h3>Alternate Possible Futures</h3>
            <p>Our homegrown forecasts are produced using many different data sources, including numerical weather prediction models, satellite data, ground station observations, and radar data. Most of the time, our forecast will be a reliable source of information (it’s better than the one we had at Dark Sky). But, crucially, we supplement the main forecast with a spread of alternate predictions. These are additional forecast lines that capture a range of alternate possible outcomes:</p>

            <p>
                <span>
                    <img src="https://acmeweather.com/img/intro/timeline-high-spread.png" alt="A forecast showing multiple possible outcomes">
                    <span>A forecast showing multiple possible outcomes</span>
                </span>
            </p>

            <p>This accomplishes a couple things:</p>
            <p>First, the spread of the lines offers a sort of intuition as to how reliable the forecast is. Take the two forecasts below. In the first, the alternate predictions are tightly focused and the forecast can be considered robust and reliable. In the second, there is a significant spread, which is an indication that something is up and the forecast may be subject to change. It’s a call to action to check other conditions or maps, or come back to the app more frequently:</p>

            <p>
                <span>
                    <img src="https://acmeweather.com/img/intro/timeline-low-spread.png" alt="A more reliable forecast">
                    <span>A more reliable forecast</span>
                </span>
                <span>
                    <img src="https://acmeweather.com/img/intro/timeline-high-spread.png" alt="A less reliable forecast">
                    <span>A less reliable forecast</span>
                </span>
            </p>

            <p>Over time, you build up an intuitive sense of just how much you can actually trust the forecast. After using this for the past six months, I never want to go back to a single forecast again!</p>
            <p>Second, it simply shows what else might plausibly happen. In what time range might the storm arrive? Will the snow hit early, or might it be delayed and turn mostly to rain? When the weather is changing rapidly, predictions can become less reliable. We’ll show you different possible futures, so you can be better informed.</p>

            <h3>Community Reporting</h3>
            <p>Alternative Forecasts are designed to help make better hour-to-hour or day-by-day decisions. Community reports are intended to help with real-time weather events. Current conditions often evolve quickly during storms, radar is imperfect and can fail to detect precipitation during light rain, snow versus freezing rain can be volatile, etc.</p>
            <p>To address this, we’ve built a feature that allows any user to submit a report of the current conditions near them, which can be seen on the map:</p>

            <p>
                <span>
                    <img src="https://acmeweather.com/img/intro/community.png" alt="Community reports">
                    <span>Community reports</span>
                </span>
            </p>

            <p>You can choose from a pre-selected list of weather condition icons (or even a list of emojis for when it’s feeling particularly 💩 out). There’s nothing more reliable than when a person nearby tells you what’s happening, so if there are recent reports near you we’ll flag it in the app.</p>
        </section>

        <section>
            <h2>Useful Maps</h2>

            <p>We absolutely love maps. They provide the context around the weather. Sure, the forecast may say you’ll get rain, but a map will complete the picture by showing you the full breadth of the storm, where it will hit, and where you are relative to it.</p>

            <p>
                <span>
                    <img src="https://acmeweather.com/img/intro/map-radar.png" alt="A more reliable forecast">
                </span>
                <span>
                    <img src="https://acmeweather.com/img/intro/map-temperature.png" alt="A less reliable forecast">
                </span>
                <span>
                    <img src="https://acmeweather.com/img/intro/map-precip-totals.png" alt="A less reliable forecast">
                </span>
            </p>

            <p>We’ve built a large number of maps, including radar and lightning, rain and snow totals (why do most other weather apps not offer this?), wind, temperature and humidity, cloud cover, hurricane tracks, etc. While you can explore them all in the map tab, we also make sure to embed the most relevant maps directly inside the forecasts to provide a contextual backdrop.</p>
        </section>

        <section>
            <h2>Notifications</h2>

            <p>A weather app is only useful if you remember to check it. I’ve lost count of the number of times I’ve gotten stuck in the rain — not because the forecast was wrong, but because I simply didn’t check the app.</p>
            <p>The solution? A comprehensive set of weather notifications. Turn them on, and no longer worry about missing important weather events.</p>
            <p>Our notifications include everything from down-to-the-minute rain warnings, to government severe weather alerts, nearby lightning, community reports, and even whether or not a rainbow might be visible outside your house.</p>
            <p>We also let you create custom notifications, tailored to whatever you care about. Want to know if it’ll be windy, or if the UV index will be high, or if you’ll get heavy rain in the next 24 hours? We’ve got you covered.</p>
        </section>

        <section>
            <h2>Acme Labs</h2>

            <p>A weather app shouldn’t just be about helping you avoid bad weather; it should also be fun! There’s a wide world of meteorological phenomena that we would like to highlight. As such, we’re launching “Acme Labs”, which is a set of experimental tools inside the app to highlight fun and interesting things happening where you are.</p>
            <p>We’re starting with a couple initial features, including: <strong>Rainbow alerts</strong>, where we bring our hyperlocal rain forecasts to bear to pinpoint where rainbows are occuring right now, and <strong>beautiful sunsets</strong>, where we'll let you know if the sunset will be particularly lovely this evening.</p>
        </section>

        <section>
            <h2>Privacy &amp; Trust</h2>

            <p>We take your privacy very seriously. Please review our <a href="https://acmeweather.com/privacy">privacy policy</a>, but here is our philosophy in a nutshell:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>We won’t collect any information other than what is necessary to provide the service you’re paying for. This information will only be used to provide that service, and for nothing else.</li>
                <li>We won’t save or store any information that isn’t necessary. We don’t want or need your location history, for example, and simply not storing it in the first place means it can’t fall into the wrong hands.</li>
                <li>We will never sell or give your information to third parties, such as advertisers. We make our money directly from our customers.</li>
                <li>We don’t use third-party trackers or analytics services, because we can’t guarantee what they will or won’t do with the information we send them.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>

        <section>
            <h2>Conclusion</h2>

            <p>Well, that’s Acme Weather. We’ve been making weather apps for 15 years, from Dark Sky to Apple, and this is the culmination (the acme?) of everything we’ve learned along the way. It’s the weather app we’ve always wanted, and always wanted to build.</p>
            <p>Acme Weather is <available right="" now=""> in the iOS App Store, and we plan on offering an Android version soon (if you’re an Android developer and would like help, <a href="https://acmeweather.com/jobs">drop us a line</a>!) The app is a $25/year subscription, with a two-week free trial.</available></p>
            <p>We think you’ll love it. So try it out, and let us know what you think!</p>
        </section>

    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I Verified My LinkedIn Identity. Here's What I Handed Over (985 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://thelocalstack.eu/posts/linkedin-identity-verification-privacy/</link>
            <guid>47098245</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 07:06:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://thelocalstack.eu/posts/linkedin-identity-verification-privacy/">https://thelocalstack.eu/posts/linkedin-identity-verification-privacy/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47098245">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://thelocalstack.eu/posts/linkedin-identity-verification-privacy/: Error: Parse Error: Invalid header value char]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Meta Deployed AI and It Is Killing Our Agency (143 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://mojodojo.io/blog/meta-is-systematically-killing-our-agency/</link>
            <guid>47097502</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 04:29:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://mojodojo.io/blog/meta-is-systematically-killing-our-agency/">https://mojodojo.io/blog/meta-is-systematically-killing-our-agency/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47097502">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p>We manage millions of dollars in annual Meta ad spend. Not thousands. Millions. Our retail clients grow their businesses through Meta Ads, and for a lot of them, it’s their single most important growth channel. We are, by any reasonable definition, a high-value customer.</p>



<p>And yet, for the past several months, Meta has been treating us like we don’t exist.</p>



<p>Here’s what’s been happening, because it’s genuinely one of the more absurd things we’ve experienced running an agency in two decades.</p>



<p><strong>The loop goes like this.</strong> We hire a senior Paid Ads Specialist. They set up a dedicated work account, which, by the way, is standard professional practice. Keeping work and personal accounts separate is basic data hygiene, not a red flag. We upload their government ID for mandatory identity verification. Then, somewhere between five minutes and ten hours later, the account gets instantly banned.</p>



<p>We have done this with multiple specialists and social media managers now. Every single one banned. Before they’ve even opened an ad account or posted a single piece of content.</p>



<p>We have done this with multiple specialists and social media managers now. Every single one banned. Before they’ve even opened an ad account or posted a single piece of content.</p>



<p>Now, we get it. Reading this, you might be thinking there’s something suspicious going on. Maybe a pattern in the logins. Maybe something in the account setup that looks off. Maybe we’re leaving something out. It’s a fair reaction, Meta’s security systems exist for a reason, and when someone says “we keep getting banned,” the natural assumption is that they’re doing something to deserve it.</p>



<p>But here’s the thing. We have been advertising on Facebook since the platform first opened its doors to advertisers, back in 2008. We were there at the beginning. We have spent millions of dollars on it over that time. Our agency history, our billing history, our business identity – it’s all there. There is no shady pattern. There is no hidden behaviour. There is just a broken automated system that cannot distinguish between a bot farm and a professional who created a work account on their first day.</p>



<p>And when we try to fix it? That’s where it gets truly circular. Meta’s standard response is to file an appeal through the Account Quality dashboard. Sounds reasonable, until you realise that the appeal tool is inside the platform – the same platform the specialist is completely locked out of. You cannot appeal a login ban from behind a login screen. </p>



<p>We’ve tried everything. Every forum thread, every concierge support contact, every support line we could find. The answers we get back are remarkably consistent: “just create a new account” or “file an appeal.” So we create a new account. That one gets banned too – often faster than the first. There is no clean slate. There is just the same broken automated system flagging the same professional as a threat, over and over again.</p>



<p>The business impact of this is real and it compounds fast. Clients lose the specialists and managers they hired. Staff, who have done nothing wrong, end up with a black mark attached to their identity documents across multiple banned accounts. And we’re left trying to run campaigns and manage brand pages on a platform that could, at any moment, eliminate a key team member for no legitimate reason.</p>



<p>We never have had this problem with Google or even TikTok.</p>



<p>What we as the enabler of this platform want a simple fix. A manual onboarding pathway for verified agencies that doesn’t collapse the moment an automated system makes a bad call. A human-accessible support channel for login failures, someone who can actually look at an account and click override. And an honest acknowledgement from Meta that their automated identity verification is producing false positives at scale for professional users.</p>



<p>If you’re an agency owner who has hit the same wall, please share this. We’re not the only ones, and the only way this gets fixed is if someone at Meta with actual authority decides it’s worth looking at.</p>



<p>If you work at Meta and are reading this, please email us at hello (at) our domain name.</p>




</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What Is OAuth? (196 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://leaflet.pub/p/did:plc:3vdrgzr2zybocs45yfhcr6ur/3mfd2oxx5v22b</link>
            <guid>47096520</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 01:33:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://leaflet.pub/p/did:plc:3vdrgzr2zybocs45yfhcr6ur/3mfd2oxx5v22b">https://leaflet.pub/p/did:plc:3vdrgzr2zybocs45yfhcr6ur/3mfd2oxx5v22b</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47096520">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p id="0" data-index="0"><span> </span><a href="https://x.com/geoffreylitt/status/2022036670946979875" target="_blank">recently asked a question about OAuth</a><span> on dead-Twitter:</span></p><blockquote id="1" data-index="1"><span>I desperately need a Matt Levine style explanation of how OAuth works. What is the historical cascade of requirements that got us to this place?</span></blockquote><p id="2" data-index="2"><span>There are plenty of explanations of the inner mechanical workings of OAuth, and lots of explanations about how various flows etc work, but Geoffrey is asking a </span><a href="https://x.com/geoffreylitt/status/2022288861284446225?s=20" target="_blank">different question</a><span>:</span></p><blockquote id="3" data-index="3"><span>What I need is to understand </span><span>why it is designed this way</span><span>, and to see </span><span>concrete examples of use cases that motivate the design</span></blockquote><p id="4" data-index="4"><span>In the 19 years (!) since I wrote the first sketch of an OAuth specification, there has been a lot of minutiae and cruft added, but the core idea remains the same. Thankfully, it's a very simple core. Geoffrey's a </span><span>very</span><span> smart guy, and the fact that he's asking this question made me think it's time to write down an answer to this.</span></p><p id="5" data-index="5"><span>It's maybe easiest to start with the Sign-In use-case, which is a much more complicated specification (</span><a href="https://openid.net/developers/how-connect-works/" target="_blank">OpenID Connect</a><span>) than core </span><a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc6749" target="_blank">OAuth</a><span>. OIDC uses OAuth under the hood, but helps us get to the heart of what's actually happening.</span></p><hr><p id="7" data-index="7"><span>OIDC is functionally equivalent to "magic link" authentication.</span></p><p id="8" data-index="8"><span>We send a secret to a place that only the person trying to identify themselves can access, and they prove that they can access that place by showing us the secret.</span></p><p id="9" data-index="9"><span>That's it.</span></p><p id="10" data-index="10"><span>The rest is just accumulated consensus, in part bikeshedding (agreeing on vocabulary, etc), part UX, and part making sure that all the specific mechanisms are secure.</span></p><hr><p id="12" data-index="12"><span>There's also an historical reason to start with OIDC to explain how all this works: in late 2006, I was working on Twitter, and we wanted to support OpenID (then 1.0) so that </span><span>ahem</span><span> Twitter wouldn't become a centralized holder of online identities. After chatting with the OpenID folks, we quickly realized that as it was constructed, we wouldn't be able to support </span><span>both</span><span> desktop clients </span><span>and</span><span> web sign-in, since our users wouldn't have passwords anymore! (mobile apps didn't exist yet, but weren't far out). So, in order to allow OpenID sign-in, we needed a way for folks using Twitter via alternative clients to sign in without a password.</span></p><p id="13" data-index="13"><span>There were plenty of solutions for this; Flickr had an approach, AWS had one, delicious had one, lots of sites just let random other apps sign-in to your account with your password, etc, but virtually every site in the "Web 2.0" cohort needed a way to do this. They were all insecure and all fully custom.</span></p><p id="14" data-index="14"><span>Rather than building TwitterAuth, I figured it was time to have a standard. Insert XKCD 927:</span></p><a id="15" data-index="15" href="https://xkcd.com/927/" target="_blank"><div><p>Standards</p><p>Fortunately, the charging one has been solved now that we&amp;#39;ve all standardized on mini-USB. Or is it micro-USB? Shit.</p><p>https://xkcd.com/927/</p></div></a><p id="16" data-index="16"><span>Thankfully, against all odds, we now have one standard for delegated auth. What it </span><span>does</span><span> is very simple:</span></p><hr><p id="18" data-index="18"><span>At its core, OAuth for delegation is a standard way to do the following:</span></p><ul><li><p id="19.0" data-index="19.0"><span>The first half exists to send, with consent, a multi-use secret to a known delegate.</span></p></li><li><p id="19.1" data-index="19.1"><span>The other half of OAuth details how the delegate can use that secret to make subsequent requests on behalf of the person that gave the consent in the first place.</span></p></li></ul><p id="20" data-index="20"><span>That's it. </span><span>The rest is (sadly, mostly necessary) noise.</span></p><hr><p id="22" data-index="22"><span>Obviously, the above elides </span><span>absolute volumes</span><span> of detail about how this is done securely and in a consistent interoperable way. This is the unenviable work of standards bodies. I have plenty of opinions on the pros and cons of our current standards bodies, but that's for another time.</span></p><p id="23" data-index="23"><span>There are very credible arguments that the-set-of-IETF-standards-that-describe-OAuth are less a standard than a framework. I'm not sure that's a bad thing, though. HTML is a framework, too –&nbsp;not all browsers need to implement all features, by design.</span></p><p id="24" data-index="24"><span>OIDC itself is an interesting thing – immediately after creating OAuth, we realized that we could compose OpenID's behaviour out of OAuth, even though it was impossible to use OpenID to do what OAuth did. For various social, political, technical, and operational reasons it took the better part of a decade to write down the bits to make that insight a thing that was true in the world. I consider it one of my biggest successes with OAuth that I was in no way involved in that work. I don't have children, but know all the remarkable and complicated feelings of having created something that takes on a life of its own.</span></p><p id="25" data-index="25"><span>More generally, though, authentication and authorization are complicated, situated beasts, impossible to separate from the UX and architectural concerns of the systems that incorporate them.</span></p><p id="26" data-index="26"><span>The important thing when implementing a standard like OAuth is to understand first </span><span>what </span><span>you're trying to do and </span><span>why</span><span>. Once that's in place, the </span><span>how</span><span> is usually a "simple" question of mechanics with fairly constrained requirements. I think that's what makes Geoffrey's question so powerful –&nbsp;it digs into the core of the reason why OAuth is often so inscrutable to so many: the complicated machinery of the standard means that the actual goals it encodes are lost.</span></p><p id="27" data-index="27"><span>Hopefully, this post helps clear that up!</span></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cord: Coordinating Trees of AI Agents (140 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.june.kim/cord</link>
            <guid>47096466</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 01:27:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.june.kim/cord">https://www.june.kim/cord</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47096466">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><p>AI agents are good at doing one thing at a time. Give Claude a focused task and it performs. But real work isn’t one task. It’s a tree of tasks with dependencies, parallelism, and context that needs to flow between them.</p><p>The multi-agent frameworks are multiplying. They’re all solving the wrong problem.</p><h2 id="whats-out-there">What’s out there</h2><p><strong>LangGraph</strong> models coordination as a state machine. You define nodes and edges in Python. The developer decides upfront how agents hand off work. It’s powerful for fixed workflows, but the graph is static. If an agent realizes mid-task that the work should be split differently, tough luck. The developer has to anticipate every decomposition pattern in advance.</p><p><strong>CrewAI</strong> is role-based. You define agents with personas — “researcher,” “analyst,” “writer” — and assign them tasks. Intuitive, but the roles are decided by the developer, not discovered by the agents. A crew of three can’t decide it actually needs five people, or that “researcher” should be split into two parallel tracks.</p><p><strong>AutoGen</strong> puts agents in a group chat. They coordinate by talking to each other. Flexible, but there’s no structure. No dependency tracking, no authority scoping, no typed results. Coordination emerges from conversation, which means it’s unpredictable and hard to inspect.</p><p><strong>OpenAI Swarm</strong> is the most minimal — lightweight handoffs between agents. Agent A decides it’s time for Agent B and transfers control. Simple, but linear. No parallelism, no tree structure, no way for an agent to spawn three subtasks and wait for all of them.</p><p><strong>Claude’s tool-use loops</strong> — Anthropic’s own pattern — put a single agent in a loop with tools. Handles sequential complexity well but runs into context window limits on large tasks and can’t parallelize. One agent, one thread, one context.</p><p>The common thread: every framework requires the developer to predefine the coordination structure. <em>You</em> decide the workflow graph, the agent roles, the handoff pattern. The agents execute within your boundaries.</p><p>This made sense when agents were unreliable. You’d never let GPT-3 decide how to decompose a project. But current models are good at planning. They break problems into subproblems naturally. They understand dependencies. They know when a task is too big for one pass.</p><p>So why are we still hardcoding the decomposition?</p><h2 id="let-the-agent-build-the-tree">Let the agent build the tree</h2><p>I built <a href="https://github.com/kimjune01/cord">Cord</a>. You give it a goal:</p><div><pre><code>cord run "Should we migrate our API from REST to GraphQL? Evaluate and recommend."
</code></pre></div><p>One agent launches. It reads the goal, decides it needs research before it can answer, and creates subtasks:</p><div><pre><code>● #1 [active] GOAL Should we migrate our API from REST to GraphQL?
  ● #2 [active] SPAWN Audit current REST API surface
  ● #3 [active] SPAWN Research GraphQL trade-offs for our stack
  ○ #4 [pending] ASK How many concurrent users do you serve?
    blocked-by: #2
  ○ #5 [pending] FORK Comparative analysis
    blocked-by: #3, #4
  ○ #6 [pending] SPAWN Write migration recommendation
    blocked-by: #5
</code></pre></div><p>No workflow was hardcoded. The agent decided this structure at runtime.</p><p>It parallelized the API audit (#2) and the GraphQL research (#3). It created an <code>ask</code> node (#4) — a question for the human — because it realized the recommendation depends on scale, something it can’t research on its own. It blocked #4 on #2 because the question makes more sense with the audit results as context. It made #5 a <code>fork</code> so the analysis inherits everything learned so far. And it sequenced the final recommendation after the analysis.</p><p>Then you watch it run:</p><div><pre><code>✓ #2 [complete] SPAWN Audit current REST API surface
  result: 47 endpoints. 12 heavily nested resources...
✓ #3 [complete] SPAWN Research GraphQL trade-offs
  result: Key advantages: reduced over-fetching...

? How many concurrent users do you serve?
  Options: &lt;1K, 1K-10K, 10K-100K, &gt;100K
&gt; 10K-100K

● #5 [active] FORK Comparative analysis
  blocked-by: #3, #4
</code></pre></div><p>The research runs in parallel. When both finish and you answer the question, the analysis launches with all three results in its context. It produces a recommendation tailored to your actual scale and API surface — not a generic blog post about GraphQL.</p><h2 id="spawn-vs-fork">Spawn vs fork</h2><p>This is the one idea I think is genuinely new: the distinction between <code>spawn</code> and <code>fork</code> as a context-flow primitive.</p><p>A <strong>spawned</strong> agent gets a clean slate. Just its prompt and the results of nodes it explicitly depends on. Like hiring a contractor — here’s the spec, go. Cheap to restart, easy to reason about.</p><p>A <strong>forked</strong> agent gets all completed sibling results injected into its context. Like briefing a team member — they know everything the team has learned so far. More expensive, but necessary for analysis that builds on prior work.</p><p>This isn’t about concurrency. Both can run in parallel or sequentially. It’s about <em>what the child knows</em>. In the example above, the agent chose <code>spawn</code> for the independent research tasks and <code>fork</code> for the analysis that needs everything. It made this choice on its own — the model understands the distinction intuitively.</p><h2 id="under-the-hood">Under the hood</h2><p>Each agent is a Claude Code CLI process with MCP tools backed by a shared SQLite database:</p><ul><li><code>spawn(goal, prompt, blocked_by)</code> — create a child task</li><li><code>fork(goal, prompt, blocked_by)</code> — create a context-inheriting child</li><li><code>ask(question, options)</code> — ask the human a question</li><li><code>complete(result)</code> — mark yourself done</li><li><code>read_tree()</code> — see the full coordination tree</li></ul><p>Agents don’t know they’re in a coordination tree. They see tools and use them as needed. The protocol — dependency resolution, authority scoping, result injection — is enforced by the MCP server.</p><p>When an <code>ask</code> node becomes ready, the engine pauses to prompt the human in the terminal. The answer is stored as a result, and downstream nodes unblock. The human is a participant in the tree, not an observer.</p><p>~500 lines of Python. SQLite + MCP.</p><h2 id="the-moment-it-clicked">The moment it clicked</h2><p>Before writing the runtime, I had to answer one question: would Claude actually <em>get</em> this? The whole design hinges on agents understanding coordination tools they’ve never seen before. If they couldn’t figure out <code>spawn</code> vs <code>fork</code>, or if they ignored <code>blocked_by</code>, the protocol was dead on arrival.</p><p>So I built a throwaway MCP server with the five tools, pointed Claude Code at it, and ran 15 tests. No runtime. No engine. Just Claude, the tools, and a task.</p><p>The first test: “decompose this project into subtasks.” Claude called <code>read_tree()</code> to see the current state — unprompted — then created five children with correct dependency ordering. It wrote detailed prompts for each one. It called <code>read_tree()</code> again after to verify they were created.</p><p>I hadn’t told it to do any of that.</p><p>Then the fork test. I gave it a scenario with both independent research tasks and a synthesis step. It chose <code>spawn</code> for the research and <code>fork</code> for the analysis. When I asked why, it said fork is like “briefing a team member” while spawn is like “hiring a contractor.” That was the exact metaphor from my spec. It had never seen my spec.</p><p>15 out of 15 tests passed. Claude decomposed tasks into 3-6 subtasks with correct dependencies. It asked humans well-scoped questions instead of guessing. When it tried to stop a sibling node and got rejected for lack of authority, it didn’t retry or hack around it — it escalated through <code>ask parent</code>, which is exactly the right pattern.</p><p>That was the moment I knew the runtime was worth building. The model already understood the protocol. I just had to build the infrastructure around it.</p><h2 id="what-this-is-not">What this is not</h2><p>This implementation uses Claude Code CLI and SQLite. But the protocol — five primitives, dependency resolution, authority scoping, two-phase lifecycle — is independent of all that.</p><p>You could implement Cord over Postgres for multi-machine coordination. Over the Claude API directly, without the CLI overhead. With multiple LLM providers — GPT for cheap tasks, Claude for complex ones. With human workers for some nodes.</p><p>The protocol is the contribution. This repo is a proof of concept.</p><h2 id="try-it">Try it</h2><div><pre><code>git clone https://github.com/kimjune01/cord.git
<span>cd </span>cord
uv <span>sync
</span>cord run <span>"your goal here"</span> <span>--budget</span> 2.0
</code></pre></div><p>You can also point it at a planning doc:</p><div><pre><code>cord run plan.md <span>--budget</span> 5.0
</code></pre></div><p>The root agent reads the markdown and decomposes it into a coordination tree. Write your plan however you want — bullet points, sections, prose — and the agent figures out the task structure, dependencies, and parallelism.</p><p>Requires <a href="https://docs.anthropic.com/en/docs/claude-code">Claude Code CLI</a> and a subscription that includes it.</p><p><a href="https://github.com/kimjune01/cord">GitHub</a> | <a href="https://github.com/kimjune01/cord/blob/master/RFC.md">RFC</a> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47096466">HN Discussion</a></p></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Claws are now a new layer on top of LLM agents (120 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/karpathy/status/2024987174077432126</link>
            <guid>47096253</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 00:56:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/karpathy/status/2024987174077432126">https://twitter.com/karpathy/status/2024987174077432126</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47096253">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="ScriptLoadFailure"><form action="" method="GET"><div><p><span>Something went wrong, but don’t fret — let’s give it another shot.</span></p><p><img alt="⚠️" draggable="false" src="https://abs-0.twimg.com/emoji/v2/svg/26a0.svg"><span> Some privacy related extensions may cause issues on x.com. Please disable them and try again.</span></p></div></form></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Be wary of Bluesky (167 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://kevinak.se/blog/be-wary-of-bluesky</link>
            <guid>47095597</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 23:35:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://kevinak.se/blog/be-wary-of-bluesky">https://kevinak.se/blog/be-wary-of-bluesky</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47095597">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://kevinak.se/blog/be-wary-of-bluesky: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[CERN rebuilt the original browser from 1989 (2019) (241 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://worldwideweb.cern.ch</link>
            <guid>47095429</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 23:19:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://worldwideweb.cern.ch">https://worldwideweb.cern.ch</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47095429">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div role="main">

    <section>
<h3>Hello, World</h3>
<p>In December 1990, an application called WorldWideWeb was developed on a NeXT machine at The European Organization for Nuclear Research (known as CERN) just outside of Geneva. This program&nbsp;– WorldWideWeb — is the antecedent of most of what we consider or know of as "the web" today.</p>
<p>In February 2019, in celebration of the thirtieth anniversary of the development of WorldWideWeb, a group of developers and designers convened at CERN to rebuild the original browser <em>within</em> a contemporary browser, allowing users around the world to experience the rather humble origins of this transformative technology.</p>
<p>This project was supported by the US Mission in Geneva through the CERN &amp; Society Foundation.</p>
<h3>Party like it’s 1989</h3>
<p>Ready to browse the World Wide Web using WorldWideWeb?</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="https://worldwideweb.cern.ch/browser">Launch the WorldWideWeb browser</a>.</li>
<li>Select "Document" from the menu on the side.</li>
<li>Select "Open from full document reference".</li>
<li>Type a URL into the "reference" field.</li>
<li>Click "Open".</li>
</ol>
<p>Click here to jump in (and remember you need to double-click on links):</p>
<p><a href="https://worldwideweb.cern.ch/browser" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Launch WorldWideWeb</a></p>
<h3>How To Open a URL</h3>
<video controls="" src="https://worldwideweb.cern.ch/images/howto/openurl_small.mp4">
How to open a URL using the original NeXT browser
</video>
<br>
<h3>How to edit a document and make a link</h3>
<video controls="" src="https://worldwideweb.cern.ch/images/howto/links.mp4">
How to edit a document and make a link using the original NeXT browser
</video>
<hr>
<h3>Contents</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://worldwideweb.cern.ch/history/">History</a> — a brief history of the application which was built in 1989 as a progenitor to what we know as "the web" today.</li>
<li><a href="https://worldwideweb.cern.ch/timeline/">Timeline</a> — a timeline of the thirty years of influences leading up to (and the thirty years of influence leading out from) the publication of the memo that lead to the development of the first web browser.</li>
<li><a href="https://worldwideweb.cern.ch/worldwideweb/">The Browser</a> — instructions for using the recreated WorldWideWeb browser, and a collection of its interface patterns.</li>
<li><a href="https://worldwideweb.cern.ch/typography/">Typography</a> — details of the NeXT computer's fonts used by the WorldWideWeb browser.</li>
<li><a href="https://worldwideweb.cern.ch/code/">Inside the Code</a> — a look at some of the original code of WorldWideWeb.</li>
<li><a href="https://worldwideweb.cern.ch/production/">Production Process</a> — a behind the scenes look at how the WorldWideWeb browser was rebuilt for today.</li>
<li><a href="https://worldwideweb.cern.ch/related/">Related Links</a> — links to additional historical and technical resources around the production of WorldWideWeb.</li>
<li><a href="https://worldwideweb.cern.ch/colophon/">Colophon</a> — a bit of info about the folks behind the project.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section>
<p><img src="https://worldwideweb.cern.ch/images/www_project.png" alt="WorldWideWeb"></p>
</section>


  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Across the US, people are dismantling and destroying Flock surveillance cameras (415 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bloodinthemachine.com/p/across-the-us-people-are-dismantling</link>
            <guid>47095134</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 22:50:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bloodinthemachine.com/p/across-the-us-people-are-dismantling">https://www.bloodinthemachine.com/p/across-the-us-people-are-dismantling</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47095134">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><p><span>Silicon Valley is </span><a href="https://www.bloodinthemachine.com/p/what-trump-really-wants-with-ai" rel="">tightening its ties with Trumpworld</a><span>, the </span><a href="https://www.bloodinthemachine.com/p/google-is-censoring-anti-ice-speech" rel="">surveillance state is rapidly expanding</a><span>, and big tech’s AI data center buildout is booming. Civilians are pushing back. </span></p><p>In today’s edition of Blood in the Machine:</p><ul><li><p>Across the nation, people are dismantling and destroying Flock cameras that conduct warrantless vehicle surveillance, and whose data is shared with ICE.</p></li><li><p>An Oklahoma man airing his concerns about a local data center project at a public hearing is arrested after he exceeded his allotted time by a couple seconds.</p></li><li><p>Uber and Lyft drivers deliver a petition signed by 10,000 gig workers demanding that stolen wages be returned to them.</p></li><li><p>PLUS: A climate researcher has a new report that unravels the ‘AI will solve climate change’ mythos, Tesla’s Robotaxis are crashing 4 times as often as humans, and AI-generated public comments helped kill a vote on air quality.</p></li></ul><p>A brief note that this reporting, research, and writing takes a lot of time, resources, and energy. I can only do it thanks to the paid subscribers who chip in a few bucks each month; if you’re able, and you find value in this work, please consider upgrading to a paid subscription so I can continue on. Many thanks, hammers up, and onwards.</p><p>Last week, in La Mesa, a small city just east of San Diego, California, observers happened upon a pair of destroyed Flock cameras. One had been smashed and left on the median, the other had key parts removed. The destruction was obviously intentional, and appears perhaps even staged to leave a message: It came just weeks after the city decided, in the face of public protest, to continue its contracts with the surveillance company.</p><p>Flock cameras are typically mounted on 8 to 12 foot poles and powered by a solar panel. The smashed remains of all of the above in La Mesa are the latest examples of a widening anti-Flock backlash. In recent months, people have been smashing and dismantling the surveillance devices, in incidents reported in at least five states, from coast to coast. </p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!szBv!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe4c8e48-8b26-457b-8969-f95db3c9c113_2048x1366.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!szBv!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe4c8e48-8b26-457b-8969-f95db3c9c113_2048x1366.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!szBv!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe4c8e48-8b26-457b-8969-f95db3c9c113_2048x1366.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!szBv!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe4c8e48-8b26-457b-8969-f95db3c9c113_2048x1366.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!szBv!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe4c8e48-8b26-457b-8969-f95db3c9c113_2048x1366.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!szBv!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe4c8e48-8b26-457b-8969-f95db3c9c113_2048x1366.jpeg" width="1456" height="971" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/fe4c8e48-8b26-457b-8969-f95db3c9c113_2048x1366.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:971,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:609392,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.bloodinthemachine.com/i/188520032?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe4c8e48-8b26-457b-8969-f95db3c9c113_2048x1366.jpeg&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!szBv!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe4c8e48-8b26-457b-8969-f95db3c9c113_2048x1366.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!szBv!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe4c8e48-8b26-457b-8969-f95db3c9c113_2048x1366.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!szBv!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe4c8e48-8b26-457b-8969-f95db3c9c113_2048x1366.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!szBv!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe4c8e48-8b26-457b-8969-f95db3c9c113_2048x1366.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a><figcaption><span>Photos by Bill Paul of </span><a href="https://sdslackers.com/2026/02/16/flock-cameras-destroyed-in-la-mesa-amid-surveillance-backlash/" rel="">SD Slackers</a><span>, used with permission.</span></figcaption></figure></div><p><span>Bill Paul, who runs the local news outlet San Diego Slackers, and who first reported on </span><a href="https://sdslackers.com/2026/02/16/flock-cameras-destroyed-in-la-mesa-amid-surveillance-backlash/" rel="">the smashed Flock equipment</a><span>, tells me that the sabotage comes just a month or two after San Diego held a raucous city council meeting over whether to keep operating the Flock cameras. A clear majority of public attendees present were in favor of shutting them down. </span></p><p>There was “a huge turnout against them,” he tells me, “but the council approved continuation of the contract.”</p><figure data-drag-handle="true" data-component-name="ImageGallery"><div><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!h9q9!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc4a900a-ac82-46de-9293-093e5b5cd85b_2048x1366.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!h9q9!,w_720,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc4a900a-ac82-46de-9293-093e5b5cd85b_2048x1366.jpeg 720w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!h9q9!,w_720,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc4a900a-ac82-46de-9293-093e5b5cd85b_2048x1366.jpeg" sizes="100vw" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!h9q9!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc4a900a-ac82-46de-9293-093e5b5cd85b_2048x1366.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!h9q9!,w_720,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc4a900a-ac82-46de-9293-093e5b5cd85b_2048x1366.jpeg 720w" width="720"></picture><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OsAI!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffef9b4d2-b545-4042-93da-c521914148cb_2048x1366.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OsAI!,w_720,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffef9b4d2-b545-4042-93da-c521914148cb_2048x1366.jpeg 720w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OsAI!,w_720,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffef9b4d2-b545-4042-93da-c521914148cb_2048x1366.jpeg" sizes="100vw" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OsAI!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffef9b4d2-b545-4042-93da-c521914148cb_2048x1366.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OsAI!,w_720,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffef9b4d2-b545-4042-93da-c521914148cb_2048x1366.jpeg 720w" width="720"></picture></div><figcaption>Photos by Bill Paul, SD Slackers.</figcaption></div></figure><p><span>The tenor of the meeting reflects a growing anger and concern over the surveillance technology that’s gone nationwide: Flock, which is based in Atlanta and is </span><a href="https://www.flocksafety.com/blog/flock-safety-secures-major-funding" rel="">currently valued at $7.5 billion</a><span>, operates automatic license plate readers (ALPR) that have now been installed in some 6,000 US communities. They gather not just license plate images, but other identifying data used to ‘fingerprint’ vehicles, their owners, and their movements. This data can be collected, stored, and accessed without a warrant, making it a popular workaround for law enforcement. Perhaps most controversially, </span><a href="https://www.404media.co/ice-taps-into-nationwide-ai-enabled-camera-network-data-shows/" rel="">Flock’s vehicle data is routinely accessed by ICE</a><span>. </span></p><p><span>If you’ve heard Flock’s name come up recently, it’s likely as a result of their </span><a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/878447/ring-flock-partnership-canceled" rel="">now-canceled partnership with Ring</a><span>, made instantly famous by a particularly dystopian Super Bowl ad that promised to turn regular neighborhoods into a surveillance dragnet.</span></p><p><span>Meanwhile, abuses have been prevalent. A Georgia police chief </span><a href="https://lookout.co/georgia-police-chief-arrested-for-using-flock-cameras-for-stalking-and-harassment-searched-capitola-data-earlier-this-year/story" rel="">was arrested</a><span> and charged with using Flock data to stalk and harass private citizens. Flock data has been used to track citizens who cross state lines for abortions when the procedure is illegal in their state. And municipalities have found that federal agencies have accessed local flock data without their knowledge or consent. </span><a href="https://sfstandard.com/2025/12/29/san-francisco-police-flock-license-plate-cameras-lawsuit/" rel="">Critics claim</a><span> that this warrantless data collection is Orwellian and unconstitutional; a violation of the 4th amendment. As a result, civilians from Oregon to Virginia to California and beyond are pushing their governments to abandon Flock contracts. In some cases, </span><a href="https://www.npr.org/2026/02/17/nx-s1-5612825/flock-contracts-canceled-immigration-survillance-concerns" rel="">they’re succeeding</a><span>. Cities like Santa Cruz, CA, and Eugene, OR, have cancelled their contracts with Flock. </span></p><p><span>In Oregon’s case, the public outcry was accompanied by a campaign of destruction against the surveillance devices: Last year, at least six Flock license plate readers mounted on poles located in Eugene and Springfield </span><a href="https://lookouteugene-springfield.com/story/justice/2025/10/15/police-investigate-vandalism-to-flock-cameras-in-eugene-springfield/" rel="">were cut down and destroyed</a><span>, according to the </span><em>Lookout Eugene-Springfield.</em><span> </span></p><p>A note reading “Hahaha get wrecked ya surveilling fucks” was attached to one of the destroyed poles, and somewhat incredibly, broadcast on the local news. </p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!8xvl!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9ae97c44-2f57-41fa-b0de-172e4c5185ae_1658x1030.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!8xvl!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9ae97c44-2f57-41fa-b0de-172e4c5185ae_1658x1030.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!8xvl!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9ae97c44-2f57-41fa-b0de-172e4c5185ae_1658x1030.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!8xvl!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9ae97c44-2f57-41fa-b0de-172e4c5185ae_1658x1030.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!8xvl!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9ae97c44-2f57-41fa-b0de-172e4c5185ae_1658x1030.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!8xvl!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9ae97c44-2f57-41fa-b0de-172e4c5185ae_1658x1030.png" width="1658" height="1030" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/9ae97c44-2f57-41fa-b0de-172e4c5185ae_1658x1030.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1030,&quot;width&quot;:1658,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:2390406,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.bloodinthemachine.com/i/188520032?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb3981a0-6566-4554-9e85-079cebfe5d55_1658x1030.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!8xvl!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9ae97c44-2f57-41fa-b0de-172e4c5185ae_1658x1030.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!8xvl!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9ae97c44-2f57-41fa-b0de-172e4c5185ae_1658x1030.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!8xvl!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9ae97c44-2f57-41fa-b0de-172e4c5185ae_1658x1030.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!8xvl!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9ae97c44-2f57-41fa-b0de-172e4c5185ae_1658x1030.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><span>In Greenview, Illinois, a Flock camera pole was </span><a href="https://www.wcia.com/news/menard-county/menard-co-sheriffs-office-investigating-damaged-flock-camera-burglary/" rel="">severed at the base</a><span> and the device destroyed. In Lisbon, Connecticut, police </span><a href="https://theday.com/news/830843/police-investigate-damaged-flock-camera-in-lisbon/#:~:text=Lisbon%20%E2%80%94%20State%20police%20said,also%20known%20as%20Route%20169." rel="">are investigating </a><span>another smashed Flock camera.</span></p><p><span>In Virginia, last December, a man was arrested for dismantling and destroying 13 Flock cameras throughout the state over the course of the year. He’s apparently already admitted to doing so, </span><a href="https://www.wavy.com/news/local-news/suffolk/suffolk-man-charged-with-destroying-13-flock-cameras/" rel="">according to local news</a><span>: </span></p><blockquote><p>Jefferey S. Sovern, 41, was arrested in October after detectives say he “intentionally destroyed” 13 Flock Safety cameras between April and October of this year. He was charged with 13 counts of destruction of property, six counts of petit larceny and six counts of possession of burglary tools.</p><p>Sovern admitted to the crimes, according to a criminal complaint filed in Suffolk General District Court, going as far as to say he used vice grips to help him disassemble the tow-piece polls. He also admitted to keeping some of the wiring, batteries and solar panels taken from the cameras. Some of the items were recovered by police after they searched the property.</p></blockquote><div id="youtube2-zGEhd90Epjk" data-attrs="{&quot;videoId&quot;:&quot;zGEhd90Epjk&quot;,&quot;startTime&quot;:null,&quot;endTime&quot;:null}" data-component-name="Youtube2ToDOM"><p><iframe src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/zGEhd90Epjk?rel=0&amp;autoplay=0&amp;showinfo=0&amp;enablejsapi=0" frameborder="0" loading="lazy" gesture="media" allow="autoplay; fullscreen" allowautoplay="true" allowfullscreen="true" width="728" height="409"></iframe></p></div><p><span>After his arrest, Sovern </span><a href="https://www.gofundme.com/f/jeff-sovern-legal-fund" rel="">created a GoFundMe</a><span> to help cover his legal costs, in which he sheds a little light on his intentions:</span></p><blockquote><p>My name is Jeff and I appreciate my privacy. I appreciate everyone's right to privacy, enshrined in the fourth amendment. With the local news outlets finding my legal issues and creating a story that is starting to grow, there has been community support for me that I humbly welcome.</p></blockquote><p>(I reached out to Sovern, who is out on bail, for comment, and will update or follow up if I hear back.) </p><p><span>Sovern points his GoFundMe contributors to </span><a href="https://deflock.org/" rel="">DeFlock</a><span>, a website aimed at tracking and countering the rise of Flock cameras in US communities. It counts 46 cities that have officially rejected Flock and other ALPRs since its campaign began.</span></p><p>In fact, it’s hard to think of a tech product or project this side of generative AI that is more roundly opposed and reviled, on a bipartisan level, than Flock, and resistance takes many forms and stripes. Here’s the YouTuber Benn Jordan, showing his viewers how to Flock-proof their license plates and render their vehicles illegible to the company’s data ingestion systems:</p><div id="youtube2-Pp9MwZkHiMQ" data-attrs="{&quot;videoId&quot;:&quot;Pp9MwZkHiMQ&quot;,&quot;startTime&quot;:null,&quot;endTime&quot;:null}" data-component-name="Youtube2ToDOM"><p><iframe src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Pp9MwZkHiMQ?rel=0&amp;autoplay=0&amp;showinfo=0&amp;enablejsapi=0" frameborder="0" loading="lazy" gesture="media" allow="autoplay; fullscreen" allowautoplay="true" allowfullscreen="true" width="728" height="409"></iframe></p></div><p><span>In response to such Flock counter-tactics, Florida </span><a href="https://www.tallahassee.com/story/news/2025/12/09/florida-license-plate-frames-law/87686065007/" rel="">passed a law last year</a><span> making it i</span><a href="http://youtube.com/watch?time_continue=1&amp;v=qEllWdK4l_A&amp;embeds_referring_euri=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.reddit.com%2F" rel="">llegal to cover or alter your license plate</a><span>.</span></p><p>In his GoFundMe, Sovern also mentioned the support for him he’d seen on forums online, so I went over to Reddit to get a sense for how his actions were being received online. Here was the page that shared news of his arrest for destroying the Flock cameras:</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!LxpP!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc1e5bb23-eec8-47c9-a882-d034c4f23cdf_604x792.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!LxpP!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc1e5bb23-eec8-47c9-a882-d034c4f23cdf_604x792.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!LxpP!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc1e5bb23-eec8-47c9-a882-d034c4f23cdf_604x792.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!LxpP!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc1e5bb23-eec8-47c9-a882-d034c4f23cdf_604x792.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!LxpP!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc1e5bb23-eec8-47c9-a882-d034c4f23cdf_604x792.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!LxpP!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc1e5bb23-eec8-47c9-a882-d034c4f23cdf_604x792.png" width="604" height="792" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/c1e5bb23-eec8-47c9-a882-d034c4f23cdf_604x792.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:792,&quot;width&quot;:604,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:112230,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.bloodinthemachine.com/i/188520032?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc1e5bb23-eec8-47c9-a882-d034c4f23cdf_604x792.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!LxpP!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc1e5bb23-eec8-47c9-a882-d034c4f23cdf_604x792.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!LxpP!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc1e5bb23-eec8-47c9-a882-d034c4f23cdf_604x792.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!LxpP!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc1e5bb23-eec8-47c9-a882-d034c4f23cdf_604x792.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!LxpP!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc1e5bb23-eec8-47c9-a882-d034c4f23cdf_604x792.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>There was, in other words, nearly universal support for Sovern’s Flock dismantling campaign. Bear in mind that this is r/Norfolk, and while it’s still reddit users we’re talking about, it’s not like this is r/anarchism here: </p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!HlEH!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fabfe132e-8190-4dc5-a8fc-cdf1c145c861_707x578.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!HlEH!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fabfe132e-8190-4dc5-a8fc-cdf1c145c861_707x578.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!HlEH!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fabfe132e-8190-4dc5-a8fc-cdf1c145c861_707x578.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!HlEH!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fabfe132e-8190-4dc5-a8fc-cdf1c145c861_707x578.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!HlEH!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fabfe132e-8190-4dc5-a8fc-cdf1c145c861_707x578.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!HlEH!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fabfe132e-8190-4dc5-a8fc-cdf1c145c861_707x578.png" width="707" height="578" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/abfe132e-8190-4dc5-a8fc-cdf1c145c861_707x578.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:578,&quot;width&quot;:707,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:81405,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.bloodinthemachine.com/i/188520032?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fabfe132e-8190-4dc5-a8fc-cdf1c145c861_707x578.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!HlEH!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fabfe132e-8190-4dc5-a8fc-cdf1c145c861_707x578.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!HlEH!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fabfe132e-8190-4dc5-a8fc-cdf1c145c861_707x578.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!HlEH!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fabfe132e-8190-4dc5-a8fc-cdf1c145c861_707x578.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!HlEH!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fabfe132e-8190-4dc5-a8fc-cdf1c145c861_707x578.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>The San Diego reddit threads carrying news of the destroyed Flock equipment told a similar story:</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Q0oa!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F937c18c7-463a-4cb4-9e1b-c3b3769487bc_686x482.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Q0oa!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F937c18c7-463a-4cb4-9e1b-c3b3769487bc_686x482.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Q0oa!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F937c18c7-463a-4cb4-9e1b-c3b3769487bc_686x482.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Q0oa!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F937c18c7-463a-4cb4-9e1b-c3b3769487bc_686x482.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Q0oa!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F937c18c7-463a-4cb4-9e1b-c3b3769487bc_686x482.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Q0oa!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F937c18c7-463a-4cb4-9e1b-c3b3769487bc_686x482.png" width="686" height="482" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/937c18c7-463a-4cb4-9e1b-c3b3769487bc_686x482.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:482,&quot;width&quot;:686,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:98502,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.bloodinthemachine.com/i/188520032?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F937c18c7-463a-4cb4-9e1b-c3b3769487bc_686x482.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Q0oa!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F937c18c7-463a-4cb4-9e1b-c3b3769487bc_686x482.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Q0oa!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F937c18c7-463a-4cb4-9e1b-c3b3769487bc_686x482.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Q0oa!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F937c18c7-463a-4cb4-9e1b-c3b3769487bc_686x482.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Q0oa!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F937c18c7-463a-4cb4-9e1b-c3b3769487bc_686x482.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>There were plenty of outright endorsements of the sabotage:</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!qTpN!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34c4632d-073f-45cc-a3e9-c7cdb6bf991d_1416x1064.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!qTpN!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34c4632d-073f-45cc-a3e9-c7cdb6bf991d_1416x1064.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!qTpN!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34c4632d-073f-45cc-a3e9-c7cdb6bf991d_1416x1064.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!qTpN!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34c4632d-073f-45cc-a3e9-c7cdb6bf991d_1416x1064.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!qTpN!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34c4632d-073f-45cc-a3e9-c7cdb6bf991d_1416x1064.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!qTpN!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34c4632d-073f-45cc-a3e9-c7cdb6bf991d_1416x1064.png" width="1416" height="1064" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/34c4632d-073f-45cc-a3e9-c7cdb6bf991d_1416x1064.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1064,&quot;width&quot;:1416,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:241505,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.bloodinthemachine.com/i/188520032?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34c4632d-073f-45cc-a3e9-c7cdb6bf991d_1416x1064.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!qTpN!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34c4632d-073f-45cc-a3e9-c7cdb6bf991d_1416x1064.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!qTpN!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34c4632d-073f-45cc-a3e9-c7cdb6bf991d_1416x1064.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!qTpN!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34c4632d-073f-45cc-a3e9-c7cdb6bf991d_1416x1064.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!qTpN!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F34c4632d-073f-45cc-a3e9-c7cdb6bf991d_1416x1064.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Off the message boards and in real civic life, Bill Paul, the reporter with the San Diego Slacker, says anger is boiling over, too. He points again to that heated December 2025 city council meeting, in which public outrage was left unaddressed. The city, perhaps aware of the stigma Flock now carries, apparently tried to highlight that their focus was on the “smart streetlights” made by another company, while downplaying the fact that those streetlights run on Flock software. </p><p>“San Diego gets to hide behind a slight facade in that their contract is with Ubicquia,” the smart streetlight manufacturer, Paul says, “but the software layer is Flock. You can easily see Flock hardware on retail properties, looking at the same citizens, with zero oversight, and SDPD can claim they have clean hands.” </p><p>Weeks later, pieces of smashed Flock cameras littered the ground.</p><p>Across the country, in other words, municipal governments are overriding public will to make deals with a profiteering tech company to surveil their citizens and to collaborate with federal agencies like ICE. It might be taken as a sign of the times that in states and cities across the US, thousands of miles apart, those opposed to the technology are refusing to countenance what they view as violations of privacy and civil liberty, and are instead taking up vice grips and metal cutters. And in many cases, they’re getting hailed by their peers as heroes. </p><p><em><span>If you’ve heard stories of smashed Flock cameras or dismantled surveillance equipment in your neighborhood, please share—drop a link in the comments, or contact me on </span><a href="https://signal.me/#eu/E2j_txDDi5ubEMjBPwi1kTT0GsEbfgUTsHtQp_1zAJm0PsnmYf9PLbFYZb9vyXYx" rel="">Signal</a><span> or at briancmerchant@proton.me. </span></em></p><p><em><span>Thanks to </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/gleemie.bsky.social" rel="">Lilly Irani</a><span> for the tip on the smashed Flock cams in San Diego.</span></em></p><p>In case you missed it, I shared my five takeaways on the most recent round of ultraheated AI discourse here:</p><div data-component-name="DigestPostEmbed"><a href="https://www.bloodinthemachine.com/p/five-takeaways-from-an-unhinged-ai" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><h2>Five takeaways from an unhinged AI discourse </h2></a><div><div><a href="https://www.bloodinthemachine.com/p/five-takeaways-from-an-unhinged-ai" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ybcS!,w_280,h_280,c_fill,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_auto/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa68354c7-3ca6-4944-9267-f42dd25ed42e_1550x1150.png"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ybcS!,w_280,h_280,c_fill,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_auto/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa68354c7-3ca6-4944-9267-f42dd25ed42e_1550x1150.png" sizes="100vw" alt="Five takeaways from an unhinged AI discourse " width="280" height="280"></picture></a></div><div><p>The AI discourse has been particularly, let’s say, “heated” lately. It’s hitting a lot of the beats we’ve heard before—people are not ready for what’s coming, critics are too dismissive, and at everyone’s peril, “the left” is getting AI all wrong, etc—but delivered at a fever pitch.</p></div></div></div><p>The exchange was filmed and recorded on YouTube:</p><div id="youtube2-xLPF3rTT0mY" data-attrs="{&quot;videoId&quot;:&quot;xLPF3rTT0mY&quot;,&quot;startTime&quot;:&quot;7122s&quot;,&quot;endTime&quot;:null}" data-component-name="Youtube2ToDOM"><p><iframe src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/xLPF3rTT0mY?start=7122s&amp;rel=0&amp;autoplay=0&amp;showinfo=0&amp;enablejsapi=0" frameborder="0" loading="lazy" gesture="media" allow="autoplay; fullscreen" allowautoplay="true" allowfullscreen="true" width="728" height="409"></iframe></p></div><p><span data-state="closed"><a href="https://open.substack.com/users/3392854-matthew-gault?utm_source=mentions" target="_blank" rel="noopener" data-attrs="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;Matthew Gault&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:3392854,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;user&quot;,&quot;url&quot;:null,&quot;photo_url&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/44f3e19e-0034-462b-aa59-30228b4a1901_506x587.jpeg&quot;,&quot;uuid&quot;:&quot;b145a699-bf98-405b-aadf-0afe31a65a13&quot;}" data-component-name="MentionUser">Matthew Gault</a></span><span> at </span><a href="https://www.404media.co/man-opposing-data-center-arrested-for-speaking-slightly-too-long/" rel="">404 Media reports the details</a><span>: </span></p><blockquote><p>Police in Claremore, Oklahoma arrested a local man after he went slightly over his time giving public remarks during a city council meeting opposing a proposed data center. Darren Blanchard showed up at a Claremore City Council meeting on Tuesday to talk about public records and the data center. When he went over his allotted 3 minutes by a few seconds, the city had him arrested and charged with trespassing.</p><p><span>The subject of the city council meeting was </span><a href="https://claremore.com/project-mustang-faq/?ref=404media.co" rel="">Project Mustang</a><span>, a proposed data center that would be located within a local industrial park. In a mirror of fights playing out across the United States, developer Beale Infrastructure is attempting to build a large data center in a small town and the residents are concerned about water rights, spiking electricity bills, and noise.</span></p><p>The public hearing was a chance for the city council to address some of these concerns and all residents were given a strict three minute time limit. The entire event was livestreamed and archive of it is on YouTube. Blanchard was warned, barely, to “respect the process” by one of the council members but was clearly finishing reading from papers he had brought to read from, was not belligerent, and went over time by just a few seconds. Anyone who has ever attended or watched a city council meeting anywhere will know that people go over their time at essentially any meeting that includes public comment.</p><p>Blanchard arrived with documents in hand and questions about public records requests he’d made. During his remarks, people clapped and cheered and he asked that this not be counted against his three minutes. “There are major concerns about the public process in Claremore,” Blanchard said, referencing compliance documents and irregularities he’d uncovered in public records.</p></blockquote><p><span>Blanchard was then arrested as the crowd jeered in disbelief. Also disconcerting was the way the local news framed the event, with </span><a href="https://www.newson6.com/tulsa-oklahoma-news/arrest-made-during-heated-claremore-meeting-over-proposed-data-center" rel="">a local anchor defending </a><span>authorities by claiming he was “warned multiple times.” Seems like a pretty surefire way to make people hate data centers and the governments protecting them even more!</span></p><p>On Wednesday, I headed to Pershing Square in downtown Los Angeles, where dozens of gig workers and organizers with Rideshare Drivers United had assembled to deliver a petition to the California Labor Commission signed by thousands of workers, calling on the body to deliver a settlement on their behalf. Organizers made short speeches on the steps of the square while local radio and TV stations captured the moment. “</p><p>“They’re robbing us!” A speaker yelled. “Wage theft!” the crowd replied.</p><p>The Labor Commission is suing the gig companies on drivers’ behalf, alleging that Uber and Lyft stole billions of dollars worth of wages from drivers before Prop 22 was enacted in 2020. The commission is believed to be in negotiations with the gig companies right now that will determine a settlement.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!eDLz!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5bfce5c-3f28-4809-8945-2d21eb858275_1500x2000.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!eDLz!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5bfce5c-3f28-4809-8945-2d21eb858275_1500x2000.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!eDLz!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5bfce5c-3f28-4809-8945-2d21eb858275_1500x2000.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!eDLz!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5bfce5c-3f28-4809-8945-2d21eb858275_1500x2000.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!eDLz!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5bfce5c-3f28-4809-8945-2d21eb858275_1500x2000.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!eDLz!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5bfce5c-3f28-4809-8945-2d21eb858275_1500x2000.jpeg" width="1456" height="1941" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/c5bfce5c-3f28-4809-8945-2d21eb858275_1500x2000.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1941,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:1186950,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.bloodinthemachine.com/i/188520032?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5bfce5c-3f28-4809-8945-2d21eb858275_1500x2000.jpeg&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!eDLz!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5bfce5c-3f28-4809-8945-2d21eb858275_1500x2000.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!eDLz!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5bfce5c-3f28-4809-8945-2d21eb858275_1500x2000.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!eDLz!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5bfce5c-3f28-4809-8945-2d21eb858275_1500x2000.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!eDLz!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc5bfce5c-3f28-4809-8945-2d21eb858275_1500x2000.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>I spoke with one driver, Karen, who had traveled from San Diego to join the demonstration, and asked her why she came. “It’s important we build driver power” she said. “Without driver power, we won’t get what we need, and we just want fairness.” She said she was hoping to claim at least $20,000 in stolen wages. </p><p>“We’re fighting for wages that were stolen for us from us and continue to be stolen from us every single day by these app companies from hell,” RDU organizer Nicole Moore told me. “So we’re marching in downtown L.A. to deliver 10,000 signatures of drivers demanding that the state fight hard for us, and don’t let these companies rip us off.”</p><p><span>According to Tesla’s own numbers, its new RoboTaxis in Austin are crashing at a rate 4 times higher than human drivers. The EV trade publication </span><a href="https://electrek.co/2026/02/17/tesla-robotaxi-adds-5-more-crashes-austin-month-4x-worse-than-humans/" rel="">Electrek reports</a><span>:</span></p><blockquote><p>With 14 crashes now on the books, Tesla’s “Robotaxi” crash rate in Austin continues to deteriorate. Extrapolating from Tesla’s Q4 2025 earnings mileage data, which showed roughly 700,000 cumulative paid miles through November, the fleet likely reached around 800,000 miles by mid-January 2026. That works out to one crash every 57,000 miles.</p><p><span>The irony is that Tesla’s own numbers condemn it. </span><strong><a href="https://www.tesla.com/fsd/safety" rel="">Tesla’s Vehicle Safety Report</a></strong><span> claims the average American driver experiences a minor collision every 229,000 miles and a major collision every 699,000 miles. By Tesla’s own benchmark, its “Robotaxi” fleet is crashing nearly 4 times more often than what the company says is normal for a regular human driver in a minor collision, and virtually every single one of these miles was driven with a trained safety monitor in the vehicle who could intervene at any moment, which means they likely prevented more crashes that Tesla’s system wouldn’t have avoided.</span></p><p>Using NHTSA’s broader police-reported crash average of roughly one per 500,000 miles, the picture is even worse, Tesla’s fleet is crashing at approximately 8 times the human rate.</p></blockquote><p><span>-“</span><a href="https://aftermath.site/anthropic-claude-ai-leftist-technology/" rel="">The Left Doesn’t Hate Technology, We Hate Being Exploited,”</a><span> by Gita Jackson at Aftermath. </span></p><p><a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/02/meta-drops-65-million-into-super-pacs-to-boost-tech-friendly-state-candidates-00759567" rel="">“Meta drops $65 million into super PACs to boost tech-friendly state candidates,”</a><span> by Christine Mui in Politico.</span></p><p><span>-A great new report from climate researcher Ketan Joshi, </span><a href="https://ketanjoshi.co/2026/02/17/big-tech-greenwashing-report/" rel="">“The AI Climate Hoax: Behind the Curtain of How Big Tech Greenwashes Impacts,”</a><span> has been making headlines and is well worth a read. Perhaps we’ll dig deeper into it in a future issue. </span></p><p><span>-The </span><a href="https://www.latimes.com/environment/story/2026-02-17/ai-powered-campaign-may-have-killed-key-vote-on-air-quality" rel="">LA Times reports</a><span> that the Southern California air board rejected new pollution rules after an AI-generated flood of made-up comments. Here’s UCLA’s Evan George on how AI poses </span><a href="https://legal-planet.org/2026/02/18/a-i-pollution-in-the-air-and-the-public-comments/" rel="">a unique threat to the civic process</a><span>.</span></p><p><span>-A good profile of Nick Land, </span><a href="https://www.newyorker.com/culture/the-lede/silicon-valleys-favorite-doomsaying-philosopher" rel="">“Silicon Valley’s Favorite Doomsaying Philosopher,”</a><span> by James Duesterberg.</span></p><p>Okay okay, that’s it for this week. Thanks as always for reading. Hammers up.</p></div></article></div><div><div id="discussion"><h4>Discussion about this post</h4></div><div><h3>Ready for more?</h3></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Don't create .gitkeep files, use .gitignore instead (2023) (110 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://adamj.eu/tech/2023/09/18/git-dont-create-gitkeep/</link>
            <guid>47094877</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 22:27:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://adamj.eu/tech/2023/09/18/git-dont-create-gitkeep/">https://adamj.eu/tech/2023/09/18/git-dont-create-gitkeep/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47094877">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><time datetime="2023-09-18">2023-09-18</time><img alt="Crystal a or simpler crystal b?" title="Crystal a or simpler crystal b?" src="https://adamj.eu/tech/assets/2023-09-18-crystals.jpeg"><p>Git only tracks files, not directories. It will only create a directory if it contains a tracked file. But sometimes you need to “track” a directory, to ensure it exists for fresh clones of a repository. For example, you might need an output directory called <code>build</code>.</p><p>In this post, we’ll look at two ways to achieve this. First, the common but slightly flawed <code>.gitkeep</code> technique, then a simpler one using only a <code>.gitignore</code> file.</p><div id="the-gitkeep-technique"><h2>The <code>.gitkeep</code> technique<a title="Permalink to this headline" href="#the-gitkeep-technique"></a></h2><p>This technique uses an empty file called <code>.gitkeep</code>:</p><p>The empty file ensures that Git creates the directory with minimal cost. Any other filename may be used, as Git doesn’t treat <code>.gitkeep</code> files any differently.</p><p>To set this up, you might create an empty file with <code>touch</code>:</p><p>Then ignore all files in the directory, except <code>.gitkeep</code>, by adding patterns in the repository’s <code>.gitignore</code> file:</p><div><pre><span></span>/build/<span>*</span>
<span>!</span>/build/.gitkeep
</pre></div><p>The first pattern ignores everything in the <code>build</code> directory. The second one then un-ignores the <code>.gitkeep</code> file, allowing it to be committed.</p><p>This technique works, but it has some downsides:</p><ol><li>It requires editing two files.</li><li>If the directory is renamed, <code>.gitignore</code> needs updating, which is easy to miss.</li><li><code>.gitkeep</code> is not a name recognized by Git, so there’s no documentation on it, potentially confusing other developers.</li></ol><p>There’s a better way that doesn’t have these flaws.</p></div><div id="the-better-gitignore-technique"><h2>The better <code>.gitignore</code> technique<a title="Permalink to this headline" href="#the-better-gitignore-technique"></a></h2><p>This technique uses only a short <code>.gitignore</code> file inside the directory:</p><p>The <code>.gitignore</code> file has these contents:</p><p>The first pattern ignores all files in the directory. The second one then un-ignores the <code>.gitignore</code> file, so it can be committed.</p><p>You can create this file with <code>echo</code> and file redirection:</p><div><pre><span></span><span>$ </span><span>echo</span><span> </span><span>'*\n!.gitignore'</span><span> </span>&gt;<span> </span>build/.gitignore
</pre></div><p>When you add and commit the directory, Git will pick up on the <code>.gitignore</code> file first, skipping other files within the directory:</p><div><pre><span></span><span>$ </span>git<span> </span>add<span> </span>build

<span>$ </span>git<span> </span>status
<span>On branch main</span>
<span>Changes to be committed:</span>
<span>        new file:   build/.gitignore</span>

<span>$ </span>git<span> </span>commit<span> </span>-m<span> </span><span>"Track build directory"</span>
<span>[main </span><span>1cc9120</span><span>]</span><span> Track build directory</span>
<span> 1 file changed, 2 insertions(+)</span>
<span> create mode 100644 build/.gitignore</span>
</pre></div><p>The directory is now “tracked” with a single, standard file that will work even after renames.</p></div><div id="fin"><h2>Fin<a title="Permalink to this headline" href="#fin"></a></h2><p>Don’t ignore this technique,</p><p>—Adam</p></div><hr><p>😸😸😸 Check out my new book on using GitHub effectively, <strong><a href="https://adamj.eu/tech/2025/11/11/boost-your-github-dx-out-now/">Boost Your GitHub DX</a></strong>! 😸😸😸</p><hr><p><small>One summary email a week, no spam, I pinky promise.</small></p><p><strong>Related posts:</strong></p><ul><li><a href="https://adamj.eu/tech/2023/08/21/git-output-root-directory/">Git: Output the top-level directory of the current repository</a></li><li><a href="https://adamj.eu/tech/2023/08/20/git-output-just-current-branch-name/">Git: Output just the current branch name</a></li><li><a href="https://adamj.eu/tech/2023/01/31/git-add-remove-execute-permissions/">Git: How to add and remove execute permissions</a></li></ul><p><strong>Tags:</strong> <a href="https://adamj.eu/tech/tag/git/" rel="tag">git</a></p></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[FCC asks stations for "pro-America" programming, like daily Pledge of Allegiance (116 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/02/fcc-asks-stations-for-pro-america-programming-like-daily-pledge-of-allegiance/</link>
            <guid>47094635</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 22:02:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/02/fcc-asks-stations-for-pro-america-programming-like-daily-pledge-of-allegiance/">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/02/fcc-asks-stations-for-pro-america-programming-like-daily-pledge-of-allegiance/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47094635">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                      
                      
          <p>Federal Communications Commission Chairman Brendan Carr today urged broadcasters to join a “Pledge America Campaign” that Carr established to support President Trump’s “Salute to America 250” project.</p>
<p>Carr said in a <a href="https://docs.fcc.gov/public/attachments/DOC-418890A1.pdf">press release</a> that “I am inviting broadcasters to pledge to air programming in their local markets in support of this historic national, non-partisan celebration.” The press release said Carr is asking broadcasters to “air patriotic, pro-America programming in support of America’s 250th birthday.”</p>
<p>Carr gave what he called examples of content that broadcasters can run if they take the pledge. His examples include “starting each broadcast day with the ‘Star Spangled Banner’ or Pledge of Allegiance”; airing “PSAs, short segments, or full specials specifically promoting civic education, inspiring local stories, and American history”; running “segments during regular news programming that highlight local sites that are significant to American and regional history, such as National Park Service sites”; airing “music by America’s greatest composers, such as John Philip Sousa, Aaron Copland, Duke Ellington, and George Gershwin”; and providing daily “Today in American History” announcements highlighting significant events from US history.</p>
<p>Carr apparently wants this to start now and last until at least July 4. Carr’s press release starts by touting Trump’s <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/america250/">Salute to America 250</a> project and quotes a White House statement that said, “Under the President’s leadership, Task Force 250 has commenced the planning of a full year of festivities to officially launch on Memorial Day, 2025 and continue through July 4, 2026.”</p>
<p>That White House quote cited by the FCC today is <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20250418202816/https://www.whitehouse.gov/america250/">nearly a year old</a>, as you might have guessed by the reference to Memorial Day in 2025. More recently, Trump has said he wants the celebration to last throughout 2026. A Trump proclamation <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/presidential-actions/2026/01/year-of-celebration-and-rededication-2026/">last month</a> declared a “yearlong commemoration” of American independence that began on January 1, 2026.</p>
<h2>“Voluntary” pledge</h2>
<p>Today’s FCC press release said, “Broadcasters can voluntarily choose to indicate their commitment to the Pledge America Campaign and highlight their ongoing and relevant programming to their viewing and listening audiences.” Although it’s described as voluntary, Carr said broadcasters can meet their public interest obligations by taking the pledge. This is notable because Carr has repeatedly threatened to punish broadcast stations for violating the public interest standard.</p>

          
                      
                  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>