(ignoring known css parsing error)
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 14:30:04 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The UK is shaping a future of Precrime and dissent management (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://freedomnews.org.uk/2025/04/11/how-the-uk-is-shaping-a-future-of-precrime-and-dissent-management/</link>
            <guid>46600194</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 12:39:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://freedomnews.org.uk/2025/04/11/how-the-uk-is-shaping-a-future-of-precrime-and-dissent-management/">https://freedomnews.org.uk/2025/04/11/how-the-uk-is-shaping-a-future-of-precrime-and-dissent-management/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46600194">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="single-wrapper" tabindex="-1">

			<main id="main">
        <div>

  				
  					<article id="post-60786">

	<!-- .entry-header -->

	<div>

		
<h3>Algorithms, facial recognition, and tightening protest laws signal a deepening surveillance state</h3>



<p>~  <strong><em>Blade Runner</em></strong> ~</p>



<p>The UK is expanding its use of predictive policing and surveillance, framing it as a response to crime, protest, and public safety. But the direction is clear: more monitoring, earlier intervention, and more control over dissent.</p>



<p>In early April, <em>The Guardian </em>revealed that the Ministry of Justice is <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2025/apr/08/uk-creating-prediction-tool-to-identify-people-most-likely-to-kill" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">developing a “murder prevention” system</a>. The tool aims to identify individuals judged to be at high risk of committing lethal violence, based on data drawn from multiple agencies—social care, policing, education. The government has framed the project as a research initiative to improve risk assessments and early intervention. But its underlying logic marks a shift toward ‘precrime’—managing individuals on the basis of what they might do, rather than what they’ve done.</p>



<p>The comparison to <em>Minority Report</em>—Philip K. Dick’s 1956 story, later adapted into a 2002 film—is hard to avoid. In both, people are flagged not by witnesses or evidence, but by prediction systems that turn patterns into verdicts. Dick’s vision included ‘precogs’—human oracles housed by the state—while today’s version relies on datasets and AI algorithms. In both, the future is treated as knowable, and the present is shaped around managing that future in advance.</p>



<figure><div>
<p><iframe title="Minority Report - Precrime Intro" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/vrYKQiyeNv0?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>
</div></figure>



<p>Notably, overall crime rates in England and Wales have been falling for decades. According to the Office for National Statistics, <a href="https://www.ons.gov.uk/peoplepopulationandcommunity/crimeandjustice/bulletins/crimeinenglandandwales/yearendingseptember2024" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">incidents have dropped </a>from nearly 20 million in the mid-1990s to under 5 million in recent years. Homicide levels have followed a similar decline, with 594 recorded in the year ending March 2021—far below their peak in the early 2000s. Only 35 of those involved firearms. The relative rarity of such violence raises questions about why a predictive “murder prevention” system is being pursued now.</p>



<p>At the same time, police forces face <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2024/sep/18/met-police-budget-heading-off-a-cliff-commissioner-mark-rowley" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">severe financial pressure</a>. The Metropolitan Police is planning to cut 1,700 officers and staff to cover a £260 million budget gap. Other forces<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2025/jan/31/policing-minister-police-forces-england-wales-challenging-cuts" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"> face similar cuts</a>. But rather than scaling back, policing is being reorganised—away from visible presence and toward data-driven surveillance, algorithmic profiling, and anticipatory enforcement.</p>



<p>The Crime and Policing Bill 2025 reinforces this direction. It allows police to access DVLA-held driver licence records for law enforcement purposes. While the Home Office denies any link to facial recognition, civil liberties groups have raised concerns that this access could be repurposed—effectively turning the DVLA database into a foundation for real-time identification. Combined with surveillance networks already active in shops, housing estates, and transport hubs, this lays the groundwork for a more integrated system of biometric tracking, with limited transparency or oversight. These tools are disproportionately deployed in working-class areas and are consistently shown to <a href="https://amnesty.ca/features/racial-bias-in-facial-recognition-algorithms" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">disproportionately </a> <a href="https://amnesty.ca/features/racial-bias-in-facial-recognition-algorithms" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">misidentify Black and Brown individuals</a>.</p>



<p>In August 2024, following a series of racist attacks across England, Prime Minister Keir Starmer proposed the expanded use of live facial recognition technology (LFR) as part of the government’s response. Civil liberties groups, including Statewatch, <a href="https://www.statewatch.org/news/2024/august/uk-racist-violence-does-not-justify-proposed-expansion-of-police-surveillance-technology" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">condemned the move</a>, warning that it would further entrench surveillance and racialised policing. In an open letter, over two dozen organisations <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/article/2024/aug/02/starmer-live-facial-recognition-plan-would-usher-in-national-id-campaigners-warn" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">argued that the UK risks becoming “an outlier in the democratic world”</a> by embracing a technology with no explicit legal basis, widespread inaccuracy, and discriminatory impacts. Critics noted that the <a href="https://www.the-independent.com/news/uk/home-news/riots-far-right-facial-recognition-tech-b2595048.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">government’s response to racist violence</a> focused not on addressing its causes, but on expanding state power over already over-policed communities.</p>



<p>The focus of policing is also shifting. As street crime continues to fall, more attention is directed toward protest, dissent, and the perceived risk of unrest. UK military operations abroad—most recently <a href="https://www.euronews.com/2025/03/28/suspected-us-airstrikes-hit-houthi-controlled-areas-of-yemen" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">joint airstrikes in Yemen</a>—raise the likelihood of retaliatory attacks. Surveillance systems originally developed for counter-terrorism are now being used to monitor social movements and suppress political disruption.</p>



<p>Recent protest laws support this shift. The Public Order Act and related legislation criminalise slow marches, locking-on, and disruption to infrastructure. These laws were drafted in response to climate protests from groups such as Just Stop Oil and Extinction Rebellion. Often operating without strong ties to other struggles—like labour, housing or anti-racist organising—these campaigns were easier to isolate and criminalise. The <a href="https://researchbriefings.files.parliament.uk/documents/SN05013/SN05013.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">resulting legal framework</a> now stands ready for broader use.</p>



<p>The surveillance and predictive systems now being assembled are being designed not only for the current moment, but in preparation for what comes next. Whether in response to renewed austerity, military escalation, or widespread resistance, these tools are positioned to contain unrest before it surfaces. What’s emerging is a model of preemptive policing—structured around behaviour, association, and predicted risk. Individuals are reduced to data profiles, tracked not for what they’ve done but for their statistical proximity to disruption. Suppression is exercised in advance.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Risk scoring, biometric surveillance, and protest restrictions are being embedded into law and infrastructure. These powers are built to be extended—to trade unionists, migrant organisers, housing activists, and anyone seen to disrupt the smooth functioning of a society of control.</p>



<hr>



<p>Image by <a href="https://rsms.me/1950s-called-wanted-toolbox-back">Rasmus</a></p>


	</div><!-- .entry-content -->

	<!-- .entry-footer -->

</article><!-- #post-## -->

  					
  				
         </div>
       
<!-- #secondary -->
			</main><!-- #main -->
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Network of Scottish X accounts go dark amid Iran blackout (221 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.heraldscotland.com/news/25759181.network-scottish-x-accounts-go-dark-amid-iran-blackout/</link>
            <guid>46599574</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 11:19:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.heraldscotland.com/news/25759181.network-scottish-x-accounts-go-dark-amid-iran-blackout/">https://www.heraldscotland.com/news/25759181.network-scottish-x-accounts-go-dark-amid-iran-blackout/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46599574">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>
  <strong>A network of fake Scottish</strong> <a href="https://www.heraldscotland.com/news/25757818.ofcom-launches-probe-x-ai-chatbot-concerns/" target="_blank"><strong>X accounts</strong></a> <strong>linked to</strong> <a href="https://www.heraldscotland.com/news/national/25758779.swinney-very-concerned-situation-iran/" target="_blank"><strong>Iran</strong></a> <strong>has gone dark, after an internet blackout was imposed in the</strong> <a href="https://www.heraldscotland.com/news/25756687.iranian-scientist-glasgow-calls-government-back-protestors/" target="_blank"><strong>West Asian</strong></a> <strong>nation.</strong>
</p><p>
  The silence from the group of accounts, which began on Thursday, comes amid widespread protests against the leadership of the Islamic Republic.
</p><div id="po-inline-articlegate-partialarticle">
<p>
  Industry publication <a href="https://ukdefencejournal.org.uk/the-herald-launches-major-new-defence-in-scotland-series/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">UK Defence Journal</a>, which has tracked the accounts for months, <a href="https://ukdefencejournal.org.uk/the-herald-launches-major-new-defence-in-scotland-series/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">said that</a> multiple X accounts claiming to be supporters of <a href="https://www.heraldscotland.com/topics/scottish-independence/?ref=au" target="_blank">Scottish independence</a> have ceased activity.&nbsp;
</p>
<p>
  One such account, known as ‘<a href="https://x.com/fiona175161" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">Fiona</a>’, has not posted since Thursday.
</p>
<p>
  <img srcset="https://www.heraldscotland.com/resources/images/20408242/?type=mds-article-575 575w, https://www.heraldscotland.com/resources/images/20408242/?type=mds-article-962 962w, https://www.heraldscotland.com/resources/images/20408242/?type=mds-article-642 1400w, https://www.heraldscotland.com/resources/images/20408242/?type=mds-article-620 1401w" sizes="(max-width: 575px) 575px, (max-width: 992px) 962px, (max-width: 1400px) 1400px, (min-width: 1401px) 1401px" width="100%"><span>The accounts went silent after the internet was cut amid protests in Iran. <em>(Image: PA)</em></span>
</p>
<p>
  The account, which describes itself as “a proud Scottish lass” and “passionate about Scotland's independence &amp; our right to self-determination”, is based in Europe (according to X’s location data).&nbsp;
</p>
<p>
  However, this is likely due to the use of a VPN which obscures the country or region the account is located in.&nbsp;
</p>
<p>
  Other accounts, known as ‘<a href="https://x.com/jakeq9170/status/2009122928085160433" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">Jake</a>’ and ‘<a href="https://x.com/lucy9760" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">Lucy</a>’, have also been quiet since the blackout began.&nbsp;
</p>

<p>
  The accounts, which have thousands of followers, increasingly shared extreme content in the days prior to going dark.
</p>
<p>
  ‘Jake’ claimed that a “top BBC anchor resigned on air and was immediately detained by security services” and that “crowds have surrounded the residence of the newly appointed ‘Governor General’ imposed by London”.
</p>
<p>
  Meanwhile, ‘Fiona’ said that “protesters have seized Balmoral Estate” and “International markets are dumping UK assets as images of tanks in <a href="https://www.heraldscotland.com/local-news/edinburgh-news/?ref=au" target="_blank">Edinburgh</a> go viral”.
</p>

<p>
  ‘Lucy’ claimed that "farmers have used tractors to block the A1 at the English border”, while another account called ‘<a href="https://x.com/kelly18600" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">Kelly</a>’ said that “army trucks are rolling down the Royal Mile. Soldiers in fatigues are guarding the Scottish Parliament”.
</p>
<p>
  Previously, a group of pseudonymous accounts expressing support for Scottish independence went dark immediately after the internet in Iran collapsed amid Israeli and US strikes in June 2025.
</p>
<p>
  At the time, <a href="https://www.heraldscotland.com/news/25413339.iranian-bots-behind-1-300-pro-independence-x-accounts/" target="_blank">disinformation analysis firm Cyabra claimed</a> that as much as “26% of profiles discussing Scottish independence were fake”.
</p>
<hr>
<p>
  <strong>Read more:</strong>
</p>
<ul>
<li>
    <a href="https://www.heraldscotland.com/politics/westminster/25759231.scottish-budget-time---2025-26-budget-expected/?ref=ed_direct" target="_blank">Scottish Budget time - when is the Holyrood budget expected?</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="https://www.heraldscotland.com/news/25758881.scotlands-largest-health-board-begging-public-stay-away-e/?ref=ed_recent" target="_blank">Why Scotland's largest health board is begging the public to stay away from A&amp;E</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="https://www.heraldscotland.com/news/25758709.cyclist-rushed-hospital-collision-van-edinburgh-city-centre/?ref=ed_recent" target="_blank">Cyclist rushed to hospital after collision with van in Edinburgh city centre</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="https://www.heraldscotland.com/news/25758496.best-class-scottish-national-carrier-named-2025s-punctual-uk-airline/?ref=ed_recent" target="_blank">'Best in class': Scottish national carrier named 2025's most punctual UK airline</a>
  </li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>
  Similarly, a 2024 <a href="https://www.clemson.edu/centers-institutes/watt/hub/images/hiding-under-the-kilt1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">study</a> by researchers at Clemson University has estimated that 4% of content relating to independence were linked to one Iranian-backed bot network of around 80 accounts.&nbsp;
</p>
<p>
  According to the study, "the accounts in this network all have false persona which purport to be citizens of the United Kingdom.
</p>
<p>
  "They post messages which support left leaning political views and attack conservative politicians, champion Scottish independence and back the Scottish National Party (<a href="https://www.heraldscotland.com/topics/snp/" target="_blank">SNP</a>) and denounce <a href="https://www.heraldscotland.com/topics/israel/" target="_blank">Israel</a> and its behavior in the ongoing war in <a href="https://www.heraldscotland.com/topics/gaza/" target="_blank">Gaza</a>.”
</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[U.S. Emissions Jumped in 2025 as Coal Power Rebounded (137 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/13/climate/us-emissions-2025-coal-power.html</link>
            <guid>46599079</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 10:03:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/13/climate/us-emissions-2025-coal-power.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/13/climate/us-emissions-2025-coal-power.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46599079">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/13/climate/us-emissions-2025-coal-power.html: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[FOSS in times of war, scarcity and (adversarial) AI [video] (101 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fosdem.org/2026/schedule/event/FE7ULY-foss-in-times-of-war-scarcity-and-ai/</link>
            <guid>46598991</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 09:47:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fosdem.org/2026/schedule/event/FE7ULY-foss-in-times-of-war-scarcity-and-ai/">https://fosdem.org/2026/schedule/event/FE7ULY-foss-in-times-of-war-scarcity-and-ai/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46598991">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>We need to talk about war. And we need to talk about companies building bots that propose to rewrite our source code. And about the people behind both, and how we preserve what is great about FOSS while avoiding disruption. How do geopolitical conflicts on the one hand and the risk of bot-generated (adversarial) code on the other influence the global community working together on Free and Open Source software?</p>
<hr>
<p>The immense corpus of free and open source software created by a global community of researchers and engineers, developers, architects and designers is an impressive achievement of human collaboration at an unprecedented scale. An even bigger circle of users, translators, writers, creatives, civil society advocates, public servants and private sector stakeholders has helped to further develop and spread this technological Gesamtkunstwerk far and wide - with the help of the internet and the web. With individual freedoms and user empowerment at its center, these jointly created digital public goods have removed many economic and societal barriers for a large part of the world's population. Users are not just allowed to benefit from technology, but each and every user can in principle actively help shape it. On top of the FOSS ecosystem our global economy has been propelled to unprecedented levels.</p>
<p>Much of this incredible growth was achieved within a (relatively) calm geopolitical situation, in the wake of the cold war which ended in the very same year that also saw the genesis of the World Wide Web at CERN in Switzerland. Economists, philosophers and other observers at the time spoke of the 'end of history' and expected no more big conflicts at the superpower level. We could now globalise the economy and all work together. The flood of innovation taking place all around us promised a bright future for all, with room for altruism and collaboration. In retrospect it certainly was an ideal situation for an optimistic and constructive global movement like the FOSS community to take over the helm.</p>
<p>But apart from the fact that under the surface that narrative was already flawed (with some actors like the USA having a double agenda, as the Snowden and Shadowbrokers revelations exposed) history didn't end. To some ironic extent we are now becoming victim of our own success. In recent years we've seen geopolitical stability punctured by war effort levering low cost technology that includes heaps of FOSS. Social media powered by FOSS infrastructure promote disinformation and have successfully stirred large scale polarisation. Within some of the largest and most populous countries on the planet authoritarian regimes have successfully used technology to break oppression in a new race towards totalitarianism. While for instance Europe has tried to regulate 'dual use' technology, "any use" technology (which our libre licenses guarantee) has escaped our attention. Even in countries which had stable non-authoritarian regimes there is a visible technology-assisted relapse towards anti-democratic movements. On the back of a tech stack which consists of FOSS with a thin crust of proprietary special sauce, unprecedented private capital (sometimes referred to as 'hypercapitalism') is interfering with global politics at an alarming rate. Apart from the direct democratic disbalance the resulting oligarchy is giving rise to overt nepotism, corruption and a new global protectorate for predatory business models and unethical extractive behaviour. Expecting peace in cyberspace any time soon is probably naive, and free and open source technology stands to make up for a significant part of the battleground.</p>
<p>At the same time we are facing other challenges, such as climate change and an imminent scarcity of non-renewable resources. We have more people living on the surface of the planet than ever before, and they are consuming more raw materials and more energy than ever. This won't go on indefinitely. And right at that point we see an army of next generation Trojan horses galloping through the gates of our global commons villages, accelerating our use of both. Generative pre-trained transformers (also known as Large Language Models) kindly offer to take cumbersome and boring coding work off our hands. They can liberate us from responsibility and allow us to do other things or move even faster.</p>
<p>But is it really wise to accept this apparent gift, or should we be a little more suspicious? Just as it has proven way too easy for AI to poison the web with fake content, our software supply chain is vulnerable to manipulation. The attack surface is immense. Due to the inherent complexity of software it is easier to achieve and harder to detect manipulation before it is too late. While many talented and committed people have spent years reverse engineering binary blobs to avoid the associated risks, those blobs were at least isolated and clearly marked. AI is the ultimate black box and it introduces significantly more uncertainty: it rewrites the truth from the inside.</p>
<p>AI in its current form has no actual sense of truth or ethics. Like with Russian roulette, once in a while the models completely bork up and create phantom code and real risk - and that is even in a best case scenario, without assuming malicious intent and manipulation from the outside. In an adversarial scenario (and this adversity can come from traditional nation state actors with non-aligned interests but also from corporate or even private individuals with some determination - like Cambridge Analytica illustrated so vividly) manipulation only requires subtle changes. At the frantic scale at which any available learning content is ingested from the internet these days one can expect targeted adversarial training to manipulate specific code with subtle triggers to go unnoticed.</p>
<p>As a community we have spent billions of hours of careful coding and software engineering to make free and open source technology as trustworthy as it is today. Geopolitical conflict is an incentive to hollow out that trust. AI is an additional leap of faith, and if you look at the forces driving its adoption and their interests, are we really sure those black boxes are safe to invite into our trusted coding base? It is clear that the end game of AI coding is not a healthy FOSS ecosystem, but its total displacement. The threat of machine crafted and man-crafted malicious code in war-time FOSS are equally realistic. Perhaps we can find a middle ground, where we combine some of AI and human skill - and add enough checks and balances, and a variety of assurances through compartementalisation, formal and symbolical proofs and other traditional means of quality assurance.</p>
<p>This talk is an open exploration of some of the challenges the FOSS community will have in the years ahead, working towards a hopeful notion of maximal defendable FOSS.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Chromium Has Merged JpegXL (212 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://chromium-review.googlesource.com/c/chromium/src/+/7184969</link>
            <guid>46597927</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 06:42:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://chromium-review.googlesource.com/c/chromium/src/+/7184969">https://chromium-review.googlesource.com/c/chromium/src/+/7184969</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46597927">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Text-Based Web Browsers (160 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://cssence.com/2026/text-based-web-browsers/</link>
            <guid>46597518</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:16:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://cssence.com/2026/text-based-web-browsers/">https://cssence.com/2026/text-based-web-browsers/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46597518">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p>Before I start, let me get two things out of the way:</p>
<ul>
<li>In this article I’m <strong>not</strong> going to include the admittedly cool <a href="https://www.brow.sh/">browsh,</a> because it only works by utilizing Firefox under the hood. When I say text-based, I’m talking about old-school browsers like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ELinks">ELinks</a>, <a href="https://lynx.invisible-island.net/">Lynx</a> or <a href="https://w3m.sourceforge.net/">w3m.</a> These are also the three browsers I’ve used to test everything described below.</li>
<li>The whole article ended up being a rant about how text-based browsers deal with features that got added to HTML. Or more like, how they neglect dealing with said features.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="do-text-based-web-browsers-still-matter" tabindex="-1">Do text-based web browsers still matter?</h2>
<p>Well, I won’t be the judge of that. I like them, I have them installed, and I test every project I create in them. But they are not what I use to surf the web.</p>
<p>Speaking of testing your creations, here’s the good news: If your project has a solid HTML foundation that you then <a href="https://cssence.com/2021/the-day-the-website-stood-still/">progressively enhance</a> with CSS and JS, you are off to a great start.</p>
<h2 id="how-did-html-evolve-in-recent-years" tabindex="-1">How did HTML evolve in recent years?</h2>
<p>While CSS is the star of the show when it comes to new features, HTML ain’t stale either. If we put the long-awaited <strong>styleable selects</strong> and Apple’s take on <strong>toggle switches</strong> aside, there’s a lot readily available cross-browser.</p>
<p>But here’s the thing: Whenever we say cross-browser, we usually look at the big ones, never at text-based browsers. So in this article I wanna shed some light on how they handle the following recent additions.</p>
<h2 id="how-do-text-based-web-browsers-handle-modern-html" tabindex="-1">How do text-based web browsers handle modern HTML?</h2>
<nav aria-labelledby="toc">

<ul>
<li><a href="#details">Details</a></li>
<li><a href="#data-lists">Data lists</a></li>
<li><a href="#dialogs">Dialogs</a></li>
<li><a href="#popovers">Popovers</a></li>
<li><a href="#inert-content-areas">Inert content areas</a></li>
<li><a href="#hidden-content">Hidden content</a></li>
<li><a href="#visually-hidden-content">Visually hidden content</a></li>
</ul>
</nav>
<p>When viewing a web page in a text-based browser, you essentially get plain HTML, no CSS, no JS. There is some “styling”, a result of the elements’ semantics, but don’t expect anything fancy, we are down to colors, indentation, and centered text.</p>
<p>It reminds me of what the browsers we are used to give us when they show unstyled HTML—well, HTML with the browser default styles, to be exact. That in turn reminds me of <a href="https://cssence.com/about/css-naked-day/">CSS Naked Day.</a></p>
<p>Text-based browsers work well with good old HTML. Said recent additions however are a bit more nuanced (e.g. interactive), so let’s talk about them individually.</p>
<h3 id="details" tabindex="-1">Details</h3>
<p><a href="https://css-tricks.com/using-styling-the-details-element/">Disclosure widgets</a> are simple interactive elements we no longer need JS for. When <code>&lt;details&gt;</code> are closed, only their <code>&lt;summary&gt;</code> is shown.</p>
<p>Text-based browsers have no clue what disclosure widgets are, so they always show the whole <code>&lt;details&gt;</code> content, meaning you always get the <code>open</code> state. This way things can get verbose, but in essence it’s okay.</p>
<p><strong>Verdict:</strong> Acceptable.</p>
<h3 id="data-lists" tabindex="-1">Data lists</h3>
<p><a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Reference/Elements/datalist">Data lists</a> can be used to add suggested values to an input field. In my tests they have been ignored entirely, Lynx even mentions that it encountered “bad HTML”, probably because it expects <code>&lt;option&gt;</code> only in a <code>&lt;select&gt;</code> parent. At least no browser rendered the options on the screen, they simply fall back to a plain <code>&lt;input&gt;</code> field, which is better than nothing. Side note: I’ve been told data lists have accessibility issues, so …</p>
<p><strong>Verdict:</strong> Whatever.</p>
<h3 id="dialogs" tabindex="-1">Dialogs</h3>
<p>Yes, HTML can do <a href="https://web.dev/learn/html/dialog/">modal and non-modal dialogs, and even alert dialogs,</a> all thanks to the <code>&lt;dialog&gt;</code> element. Initially we needed JS to toggle their visibility, but with the help of the Popover API (see next chapter) we can now even get most of it done in plain HTML.</p>
<p>Alas, once again there is no support in text-based browsers, so you’ll end up seeing all dialog content, as if they had their <code>open</code> attribute set. Consequently, there’s no awareness of a form’s <code>method="dialog"</code> nor a submit button’s <code>formmethod="dialog"</code>, so in both cases the form <code>action</code> is triggered.</p>
<p><strong>Verdict:</strong> Problematic.</p>
<h3 id="popovers" tabindex="-1">Popovers</h3>
<p><a href="https://developer.chrome.com/blog/introducing-popover-api/">The Popover API</a> is probably my favorite new feature, but only if you stick to regular web browsers.</p>
<p><a href="https://css-tricks.com/clarifying-the-relationship-between-popovers-and-dialogs/">Given that dialogs are a type of popover,</a> it’s no surprise that nothing works, and once again all <code>popover</code> content gets dumped onto the screen.</p>
<p>By now I think you get the idea, so I won’t even talk about the <a href="https://www.htmhell.dev/adventcalendar/2025/7/">Invoker Commands API</a> at this point.</p>
<p><strong>Verdict:</strong> Most likely problematic.</p>
<h3 id="inert-content-areas" tabindex="-1">Inert content areas</h3>
<p><a href="https://web.dev/articles/inert">A modal dialog makes the rest of the page inert</a>, so we don’t have to do it. But with the global <code>inert</code> attribute we can do this manually too, if we need to make certain parts of the DOM unreachable.</p>
<p>Sure enough, text-based browsers will happily let you access interactive elements inside an inert content area.</p>
<p><strong>Verdict:</strong> Bad.</p>
<h3 id="hidden-content" tabindex="-1">Hidden content</h3>
<p>We’re now approaching something that is not new at all, the <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Reference/Global_attributes/hidden">global hidden attribute</a> has been supported for over a decade. It allows us to hide content in the same way as <code>display: none</code>, but directly in HTML.</p>
<p>Adding support in text-based browsers has been discussed back in the day, but got rejected, hence it was never implemented. You’ll end up seeing all content marked as <code>hidden</code>. This is the primary reason why I started writing this article, and what enrages me the most. If I decide to hide content in HTML instead of CSS, I must have a very good reason, thus hidden content should not be visible in any browser! Certain progressive enhancement techniques work by hiding content in HTML and then making it visible via CSS or JS. That possibility goes out the window in text-based browsers.</p>
<p><strong>Verdict:</strong> Epic fail. 😠 🤬</p>
<h3 id="visually-hidden-content" tabindex="-1">Visually hidden content</h3>
<p>Just kidding, there’s still <a href="https://cssence.com/2024/native-visually-hidden/">no native way in HTML to hide content visually</a>, so we continue to rely on class names like <code>.visually-hidden</code> or <code>.sr-only</code>. No matter how they are named, they need to summon <a href="https://vispero.com/resources/the-anatomy-of-visually-hidden/">quite a few of lines of CSS</a> to get things done. Whether there should be a native way is up for debate. Personally I would welcome a one-liner to achieve this, but it should remain in the domain of CSS.</p>
<p>However, if we had a way in HTML, text-based browsers would display such visually hidden content anyway, that is certain.</p>
<p><strong>Verdict:</strong> To be continued.</p>
<h2 id="now-what-what-now" tabindex="-1">Now what? What now?</h2>
<p>Text-based browsers and modern HTML, no success story in sight. Given the progress we see in web technologies, the gap will only widen, so much so that w3m and its friends might fall into oblivion.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google removes AI health summaries after investigation finds dangerous flaws (201 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/google-removes-some-ai-health-summaries-after-investigation-finds-dangerous-flaws/</link>
            <guid>46595419</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 23:05:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/google-removes-some-ai-health-summaries-after-investigation-finds-dangerous-flaws/">https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/google-removes-some-ai-health-summaries-after-investigation-finds-dangerous-flaws/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46595419">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          
          
<h2>Why AI Overviews produces errors</h2>
<p>The recurring problems with AI Overviews stem from a design flaw in how the system works. As we <a href="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2024/05/googles-ai-overview-is-flawed-by-design-and-a-new-company-blog-post-hints-at-why/">reported</a> in May 2024, Google built AI Overviews to show information backed up by top web results from its page ranking system. The company designed the feature this way based on the assumption that highly ranked pages contain accurate information.</p>
<p>However, Google’s page ranking algorithm has long struggled with SEO-gamed content and spam. The system now feeds these unreliable results to its AI model, which then summarizes them with an authoritative tone that can mislead users. Even when the AI draws from accurate sources, the language model can still <a href="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2023/04/why-ai-chatbots-are-the-ultimate-bs-machines-and-how-people-hope-to-fix-them/">draw incorrect conclusions</a> from the data, producing flawed summaries of otherwise reliable information.</p>
<p>The technology does not inherently provide factual accuracy. Instead, it reflects whatever inaccuracies exist on the websites Google’s algorithm ranks highly, presenting the facts with an authority that makes errors appear trustworthy.</p>
<h2>Other examples remain active</h2>
<p>The Guardian found that typing slight variations of the original queries into Google, such as “lft reference range” or “lft test reference range,” still prompted AI Overviews. Hebditch said this was a big worry and that the AI Overviews present a list of tests in bold, making it very easy for readers to miss that these numbers might not even be the right ones for their test.</p>
<p>AI Overviews still appear for other examples that The Guardian originally highlighted to Google. When asked why these AI Overviews had not also been removed, Google said they linked to well-known&nbsp;and reputable sources and informed people when it was important to seek out expert advice.</p>
<p>Google said AI Overviews only appear for queries where it has high confidence in the quality of the responses. The company constantly measures and reviews the quality of its summaries across many different categories of information, it added.</p>
<p>This is not the first controversy for AI Overviews. The feature has previously <a href="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2024/05/googles-ai-overview-can-give-false-misleading-and-dangerous-answers/">told</a> people to put glue on pizza and eat rocks. It has proven unpopular enough that users have <a href="https://arstechnica.com/google/2025/01/just-give-me-the-fing-links-cursing-disables-googles-ai-overviews/">discovered</a> that inserting curse words into search queries disables AI Overviews entirely.</p>


          
                  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Fabrice Bellard's TS Zip (2024) (192 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bellard.org/ts_zip/</link>
            <guid>46593802</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 20:26:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bellard.org/ts_zip/">https://www.bellard.org/ts_zip/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46593802">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">


The <code>ts_zip</code> utility can
compress (and hopefully decompress) text files using a Large Language
Model. The compression ratio is much higher than with other
compression tools. There are some caveats of course:
<ul>
  <li>A GPU is necessary to get a reasonable speed. 4 GB of RAM is
    required. </li>
  <li>It is slower than conventional compressors (compression and
    decompression speed: up to 1 MB/s on a RTX 4090).</li>
  <li>Only text files are supported. Binary files won't be compressed
  much. The currently used language model (RWKV 169M v4) was trained
  mostly on English texts. Other languages are supported including
  source code.</li>
  <li>It is experimental so no backward compability should be expected
    between the various versions.</li>
  <li>See also <a href="https://www.bellard.org/ts_sms">ts_sms</a> which is optimized for the
    compression of small messages.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Compression Ratio</h2>
<p>
The compression ratio is given in bits per byte (bpb).
</p>
<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th aria-sort="ascending">File
      </th><th>Original size<br>(bytes)
      </th><th colspan="2"><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XZ_Utils">xz</a><br>(bytes) (bpb)
      </th><th colspan="2">ts_zip<br>(bytes) (bpb)
    </th></tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr><td><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canterbury_corpus">alice29.txt</a>
      </td><td>152089
      </td><td>48492
      </td><td>2.551
      </td><td>21713
      </td><td>1.142
    </td></tr>
    <tr><td><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calgary_corpus">book1</a>
      </td><td>768771
      </td><td>261116
      </td><td>2.717
      </td><td>137477
      </td><td>1.431
    </td></tr>
    <tr><td><a href="http://mattmahoney.net/dc/text.html">enwik8</a>
      </td><td>100000000
      </td><td>24865244
      </td><td>1.989
      </td><td>13825741
      </td><td>1.106
    </td></tr>
    <tr><td><a href="http://mattmahoney.net/dc/text.html">enwik9</a>
      </td><td>1000000000
      </td><td>213370900
      </td><td>1.707
      </td><td>135443237
      </td><td>1.084
    </td></tr>
    <tr><td><a href="https://mirrors.edge.kernel.org/pub/linux/kernel/v1.2/linux-1.2.13.tar.xz">linux-1.2.13.tar</a>
      </td><td>9379840
      </td><td>1689468
      </td><td>1.441
      </td><td>1196859
      </td><td>1.021
    </td></tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<p>
Results and speed for other programs on enwik8 and enwik9 are
available at the <a href="http://www.mattmahoney.net/dc/text.html">Large
Text Compression Benchmark</a>.
</p>

<h2>Download</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Linux version: <a href="https://www.bellard.org/ts_zip/ts_zip-2024-03-02.tar.gz">ts_zip-2024-03-02.tar.gz</a>.</li>
  <li>Windows version: <a href="https://www.bellard.org/ts_zip/ts_zip-2024-03-02-win64.zip">ts_zip-2024-03-02-win64.zip</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Technical information</h2>
<ul>
  <li><code>ts_zip</code> uses
  the <a href="https://github.com/BlinkDL/RWKV-LM">RWKV 169M v4</a>
  language model which is a good compromise between speed and
  compression ratio. The model is quantized to 8 bits per parameter
    and evaluated using BF16 floating point numbers.</li>
  <li>The language model predicts the probabilities of the next token. An
    arithmetic coder then encodes the next token according to the
    probabilities.</li>
  <li>The model is evaluated in a deterministic and reproducible
    way. Hence the result does not depend on the exact GPU or CPU
    model nor on the number of configured threads. This key point
    ensures that a compressed file can be decompressed using a
    different hardware or software configuration.</li>
</ul>

<hr>
Fabrice Bellard - <a href="https://bellard.org/">https://bellard.org/</a>


</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The chess bot on Delta Air Lines will destroy you (2024) [video] (279 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c0mLhHDcY3I</link>
            <guid>46593395</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 19:57:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c0mLhHDcY3I">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c0mLhHDcY3I</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46593395">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cowork: Claude Code for the rest of your work (1085 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://claude.com/blog/cowork-research-preview</link>
            <guid>46593022</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 19:27:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://claude.com/blog/cowork-research-preview">https://claude.com/blog/cowork-research-preview</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46593022">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>When we released Claude Code, we expected developers to use it for coding. They did—and then quickly began using it for <a href="https://x.com/claudeai/status/2009666254815269313" target="_blank" data-wf-native-id-path="d7e2b4a8-bd30-6427-2c54-02a35d22e170" data-wf-ao-click-engagement-tracking="true" data-wf-element-id="d7e2b4a8-bd30-6427-2c54-02a35d22e170">almost everything else</a>. This prompted us to build Cowork: a simpler way for anyone—<a href="https://www.lennysnewsletter.com/p/everyone-should-be-using-claude-code" target="_blank" data-wf-native-id-path="d7e2b4a8-bd30-6427-2c54-02a35d22e173" data-wf-ao-click-engagement-tracking="true" data-wf-element-id="d7e2b4a8-bd30-6427-2c54-02a35d22e173">not just developers</a>—to work with Claude in the very same way. Cowork is available today as a research preview for Claude Max subscribers on our <a href="https://claude.com/download" target="_blank" data-wf-native-id-path="d7e2b4a8-bd30-6427-2c54-02a35d22e176" data-wf-ao-click-engagement-tracking="true" data-wf-element-id="d7e2b4a8-bd30-6427-2c54-02a35d22e176">macOS app</a>, and we will improve it rapidly from here.</p><figure><p><iframe allowfullscreen="true" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UAmKyyZ-b9E" title="Introducing Cowork: Claude Code for the rest of your work"></iframe></p></figure><p>How is using Cowork different from a regular conversation? In Cowork, you give Claude access to a folder of your choosing on your computer. Claude can then read, edit, or create files in that folder. It can, for example, re-organize your downloads by sorting and renaming each file, create a new spreadsheet with a list of expenses from a pile of screenshots, or produce a first draft of a report from your scattered notes.&nbsp;</p><p>In Cowork, Claude completes work like this with much more agency than you’d see in a regular conversation. Once you’ve set it a task, Claude will make a plan and steadily complete it, while looping you in on what it’s up to. If you’ve used Claude Code, this will feel familiar—Cowork is built on the very <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/engineering/building-agents-with-the-claude-agent-sdk" target="_blank" data-wf-native-id-path="638a9647-f7be-7484-3d32-f34fa167b82a" data-wf-ao-click-engagement-tracking="true" data-wf-element-id="638a9647-f7be-7484-3d32-f34fa167b82a">same foundations</a>. This means Cowork can take on many of the same tasks that Claude Code can handle, but in a more approachable form for non-coding tasks.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><p>When you’ve mastered the basics, you can make Cowork more powerful still. Claude can use your existing <a href="https://claude.com/connectors" target="_blank" data-wf-native-id-path="638a9647-f7be-7484-3d32-f34fa167b82f" data-wf-ao-click-engagement-tracking="true" data-wf-element-id="638a9647-f7be-7484-3d32-f34fa167b82f">connectors</a>, which link Claude to external information, and in Cowork we’ve added an initial set of <a href="https://platform.claude.com/docs/en/agents-and-tools/agent-skills/overview" target="_blank" data-wf-native-id-path="638a9647-f7be-7484-3d32-f34fa167b832" data-wf-ao-click-engagement-tracking="true" data-wf-element-id="638a9647-f7be-7484-3d32-f34fa167b832">skills</a> that improve Claude’s ability to create documents, presentations, and other files. If you pair Cowork with <a href="https://claude.com/chrome" target="_blank" data-wf-native-id-path="638a9647-f7be-7484-3d32-f34fa167b835" data-wf-ao-click-engagement-tracking="true" data-wf-element-id="638a9647-f7be-7484-3d32-f34fa167b835">Claude in Chrome</a>, Claude can complete tasks that require browser access, too.</p><p>Cowork is designed to make using Claude for new work as simple as possible. You don’t need to keep manually providing context or converting Claude’s outputs into the right format. Nor do you have to wait for Claude to finish before offering further ideas or feedback: you can queue up tasks and let Claude work through them in parallel. It feels much less like a back-and-forth and much more like leaving messages for a coworker.&nbsp;</p><figure><p><iframe allowfullscreen="true" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/WBNZpAWhw5E" title="Organize your desktop files with Cowork"></iframe></p></figure><h2>Stay in control</h2><p>In Cowork, you can choose which folders and connectors Claude can see: Claude can’t read or edit anything you don’t give it explicit access to. Claude will also ask before taking any significant actions, so you can steer or course-correct it as you need.&nbsp;</p><p>That said, there are still things to be aware of before you give Claude control. By default, the main thing to know is that Claude can take potentially destructive actions (such as deleting local files) if it’s instructed to. Since there’s always some chance that Claude might misinterpret your instructions, you should give Claude very clear guidance around things like this.&nbsp;</p><p>You should also be aware of the risk of “<a href="https://www.anthropic.com/research/prompt-injection-defenses" target="_blank" data-wf-native-id-path="d7e2b4a8-bd30-6427-2c54-02a35d22e19c" data-wf-ao-click-engagement-tracking="true" data-wf-element-id="d7e2b4a8-bd30-6427-2c54-02a35d22e19c">prompt injections</a>”: attempts by attackers to alter Claude’s plans through content it might encounter on the internet. We’ve built sophisticated defenses against prompt injections, but agent safety—that is, the task of securing Claude’s real-world actions—is still an active area of development in the industry.&nbsp;</p><p>These risks aren’t new with Cowork, but it might be the first time you’re using a more advanced tool that moves beyond a simple conversation. We recommend taking precautions, particularly while you learn how it works. We provide more detail in our <a href="https://support.claude.com/en/articles/13364135-using-cowork-safely" target="_blank" data-wf-native-id-path="d7e2b4a8-bd30-6427-2c54-02a35d22e1a2" data-wf-ao-click-engagement-tracking="true" data-wf-element-id="d7e2b4a8-bd30-6427-2c54-02a35d22e1a2">Help Center</a>.&nbsp;</p><h2>Looking forward</h2><p>This is a research preview. We’re releasing Cowork early because we want to learn what people use it for, and how they think it could be better. We encourage you to experiment with what Cowork can do for you, and to try things you don’t expect to work: you might be surprised! As we learn more from this preview, we plan to make lots of improvements (including by adding cross-device sync and bringing it to Windows), and we’ll identify further ways to make it safer.&nbsp;</p><p>Claude Max subscribers can try Cowork now by downloading the <a href="https://claude.com/download" target="_blank" data-wf-native-id-path="d7e2b4a8-bd30-6427-2c54-02a35d22e1aa" data-wf-ao-click-engagement-tracking="true" data-wf-element-id="d7e2b4a8-bd30-6427-2c54-02a35d22e1aa">macOS app</a>, then clicking on “Cowork” in the sidebar. If you're on another plan, you can <a href="https://forms.gle/mtoJrd8kfYny29jQ9" target="_blank" data-wf-native-id-path="d7e2b4a8-bd30-6427-2c54-02a35d22e1ad" data-wf-ao-click-engagement-tracking="true" data-wf-element-id="d7e2b4a8-bd30-6427-2c54-02a35d22e1ad">join the waitlist</a> for future access.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[X Didn't Fix Grok's 'Undressing' Problem. It Just Makes People Pay for It (210 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wired.com/story/x-didnt-fix-groks-undressing-problem-it-just-makes-people-pay-for-it/</link>
            <guid>46592827</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 19:11:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/x-didnt-fix-groks-undressing-problem-it-just-makes-people-pay-for-it/">https://www.wired.com/story/x-didnt-fix-groks-undressing-problem-it-just-makes-people-pay-for-it/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46592827">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><span>After creating thousands</span> of <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/grok-is-pushing-ai-undressing-mainstream/#intcid=_wired-verso-hp-trending_e6f38b98-522c-48d8-be73-d982c8e641e2_popular4-2">“undressing” pictures of women</a> and sexualized imagery of apparent minors, Elon Musk’s X has apparently limited who can generate images with Grok. However, despite the changes, the chatbot is still being used to create “undressing” sexualized images on the platform.</p><p>On Friday morning, the Grok account on X started responding to some users’ requests with a message saying that image generation and editing are “currently limited to paying subscribers.” The message also includes a link pushing people toward the social media platform’s $395 annual subscription tier. In one test of the system requesting Grok create an image of a tree, the system returned the same message.</p><p>The apparent change comes after days of growing outrage against and <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/x-grok-app-store-nudify-csam-apple-google-content-moderation/">scrutiny</a> of Musk’s X and xAI, the company behind the Grok chatbot. The companies face an increasing number of investigations from regulators around the world over the creation of nonconsensual explicit imagery and alleged sexual images of children. British prime minister Keir Starmer <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/ckgjzknepvzo">has not ruled out</a> banning X in the country and said the actions have been “unlawful.”</p><p>Neither X nor xAI, the Musk-owned company behind Grok, has confirmed that it has made image generation and editing a paid-only feature. An X spokesperson acknowledged WIRED’s inquiry but did not provide comment ahead of publication. X has previously <a data-offer-url="https://x.com/Safety/status/2007648212421587223" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://x.com/Safety/status/2007648212421587223&quot;}" href="https://x.com/Safety/status/2007648212421587223" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">said</a> it takes “action against illegal content on X,” including instances of child sexual abuse material. While Apple and Google have previously banned apps with similar “nudify” features, <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/x-grok-app-store-nudify-csam-apple-google-content-moderation/">X and Grok remain available</a> in their respective app stores. xAI did not immediately respond to WIRED's request for comment.</p><p>For more than a week, users on X have been asking the chatbot to edit images of women to remove their clothes—often asking for the image to contain a “string” or “transparent” bikini. While a public feed of images created by Grok contained far fewer results of these “undressing” images on Friday, it still created sexualized images when prompted to by X users with paid for “verified” accounts.</p><p>“We observe the same kind of prompt, we observe the same kind of outcome, just fewer than before,” Paul Bouchaud, lead researcher at Paris-based nonprofit AI Forensics, tells WIRED. “The model can continue to generate bikini [images],” they say.</p><p>A WIRED review of some Grok posts on Friday morning identified Grok generating images in response to user requests for images that “put her in latex lingerie” and “put her in a plastic bikini and cover her in donut white glaze.” The images appear behind a “content warning” box saying that adult material is displayed.</p><p>On Wednesday, WIRED revealed that Grok’s stand-alone website and app, which is separate from the version on X, has also been used in recent months to create <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/grok-is-generating-sexual-content-far-more-graphic-than-whats-on-x/#intcid=_wired-verso-hp-trending_e6f38b98-522c-48d8-be73-d982c8e641e2_popular4-2">highly graphic and sometimes violent sexual videos</a>, including celebrities and other real people. Bouchaud says it is still possible to use Grok to make these videos. “I was able to generate a video with sexually explicit content without any restriction from an unverified account,” they say.</p><p>While WIRED’s test of image generation using Grok on X using a free account did not allow any images to be created, using a free account on Grok’s app and website still generated images.</p><p>The change on X could immediately limit the amount of sexually explicit and harmful material the platform is creating, experts say. But it has also been criticized as a minimal step that acts as a band-aid to the real harms <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/deepfake-survivor-breeze-liu-microsoft/">caused by nonconsensual intimate imagery</a>.</p><p>“The recent decision to restrict access to paying subscribers is not only inadequate—it represents the monetization of abuse,” Emma Pickering, head of technology-facilitated abuse at UK domestic abuse charity Refuge, said in a statement. “While limiting AI image generation to paid users may marginally reduce volume and improve traceability, the abuse has not been stopped. It has simply been placed behind a paywall, allowing X to profit from harm.”</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Yolobox – Run AI coding agents with full sudo without nuking home dir (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/finbarr/yolobox</link>
            <guid>46592344</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 18:34:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/finbarr/yolobox">https://github.com/finbarr/yolobox</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46592344">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="██╗   ██╗ ██████╗ ██╗      ██████╗ ██████╗  ██████╗ ██╗  ██╗
╚██╗ ██╔╝██╔═══██╗██║     ██╔═══██╗██╔══██╗██╔═══██╗╚██╗██╔╝
 ╚████╔╝ ██║   ██║██║     ██║   ██║██████╔╝██║   ██║ ╚███╔╝
  ╚██╔╝  ██║   ██║██║     ██║   ██║██╔══██╗██║   ██║ ██╔██╗
   ██║   ╚██████╔╝███████╗╚██████╔╝██████╔╝╚██████╔╝██╔╝ ██╗
   ╚═╝    ╚═════╝ ╚══════╝ ╚═════╝ ╚═════╝  ╚═════╝ ╚═╝  ╚═╝"><pre><code>██╗   ██╗ ██████╗ ██╗      ██████╗ ██████╗  ██████╗ ██╗  ██╗
╚██╗ ██╔╝██╔═══██╗██║     ██╔═══██╗██╔══██╗██╔═══██╗╚██╗██╔╝
 ╚████╔╝ ██║   ██║██║     ██║   ██║██████╔╝██║   ██║ ╚███╔╝
  ╚██╔╝  ██║   ██║██║     ██║   ██║██╔══██╗██║   ██║ ██╔██╗
   ██║   ╚██████╔╝███████╗╚██████╔╝██████╔╝╚██████╔╝██╔╝ ██╗
   ╚═╝    ╚═════╝ ╚══════╝ ╚═════╝ ╚═════╝  ╚═════╝ ╚═╝  ╚═╝
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Let your AI go full send. Your home directory stays home.</strong></p>
<p dir="auto">Run <a href="https://claude.ai/code" rel="nofollow">Claude Code</a>, <a href="https://openai.com/index/codex/" rel="nofollow">Codex</a>, or any AI coding agent in "yolo mode" without nuking your home directory.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">The Problem</h2><a id="user-content-the-problem" aria-label="Permalink: The Problem" href="#the-problem"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">AI coding agents are incredibly powerful when you let them run commands without asking permission. But one misinterpreted prompt and <code>rm -rf ~</code> later, you're restoring from backup (yea right, as if you have backups lol).</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">The Solution</h2><a id="user-content-the-solution" aria-label="Permalink: The Solution" href="#the-solution"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><code>yolobox</code> runs your AI agent inside a container where:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>✅ Your <strong>project directory</strong> is mounted at <code>/workspace</code></li>
<li>✅ The agent has <strong>full permissions</strong> and <strong>sudo</strong> inside the container</li>
<li>✅ Your <strong>home directory is NOT mounted</strong> (unless you explicitly opt in)</li>
<li>✅ Persistent volumes keep tools and configs across sessions</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">The AI can go absolutely wild inside the sandbox. Your actual home directory? Untouchable.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Quick Start</h2><a id="user-content-quick-start" aria-label="Permalink: Quick Start" href="#quick-start"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# Install (requires Go)
curl -fsSL https://raw.githubusercontent.com/finbarr/yolobox/master/install.sh | bash

# Or clone and build
git clone https://github.com/finbarr/yolobox.git
cd yolobox
make install"><pre><span><span>#</span> Install (requires Go)</span>
curl -fsSL https://raw.githubusercontent.com/finbarr/yolobox/master/install.sh <span>|</span> bash

<span><span>#</span> Or clone and build</span>
git clone https://github.com/finbarr/yolobox.git
<span>cd</span> yolobox
make install</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Then from any project:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="cd /path/to/your/project
yolobox"><pre><span>cd</span> /path/to/your/project
yolobox</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">You're now in a sandboxed shell. Run <code>claude</code> and let it rip.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What's in the Box?</h2><a id="user-content-whats-in-the-box" aria-label="Permalink: What's in the Box?" href="#whats-in-the-box"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The base image comes batteries-included:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>AI CLIs</strong>: Claude Code, Gemini CLI, OpenAI Codex, OpenCode (all pre-configured for full-auto mode!)</li>
<li><strong>Node.js 22</strong> + npm/yarn/pnpm</li>
<li><strong>Python 3</strong> + pip + venv</li>
<li><strong>Build tools</strong>: make, cmake, gcc</li>
<li><strong>Git</strong> + <strong>GitHub CLI</strong></li>
<li><strong>Common utilities</strong>: ripgrep, fd, fzf, jq, vim</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Need something else? You have sudo.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">AI CLIs Run in YOLO Mode</h2><a id="user-content-ai-clis-run-in-yolo-mode" aria-label="Permalink: AI CLIs Run in YOLO Mode" href="#ai-clis-run-in-yolo-mode"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Inside yolobox, the AI CLIs are aliased to skip all permission prompts:</p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Command</th>
<th>Expands to</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><code>claude</code></td>
<td><code>claude --dangerously-skip-permissions</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>codex</code></td>
<td><code>codex --dangerously-bypass-approvals-and-sandbox</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>gemini</code></td>
<td><code>gemini --yolo</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>opencode</code></td>
<td><code>opencode</code> (no yolo flag available yet)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto">No confirmations, no guardrails—just pure unfiltered AI, the way nature intended.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Commands</h2><a id="user-content-commands" aria-label="Permalink: Commands" href="#commands"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="yolobox                     # Drop into interactive shell
yolobox run <cmd...>        # Run a single command
yolobox run claude          # Run Claude Code in sandbox
yolobox upgrade             # Update binary and pull latest image
yolobox config              # Show resolved configuration
yolobox reset --force       # Delete volumes (fresh start)
yolobox version             # Show version
yolobox help                # Show help"><pre>yolobox                     <span><span>#</span> Drop into interactive shell</span>
yolobox run <span>&lt;</span>cmd...<span>&gt;</span>        <span><span>#</span> Run a single command</span>
yolobox run claude          <span><span>#</span> Run Claude Code in sandbox</span>
yolobox upgrade             <span><span>#</span> Update binary and pull latest image</span>
yolobox config              <span><span>#</span> Show resolved configuration</span>
yolobox reset --force       <span><span>#</span> Delete volumes (fresh start)</span>
yolobox version             <span><span>#</span> Show version</span>
yolobox <span>help</span>                <span><span>#</span> Show help</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Flags</h2><a id="user-content-flags" aria-label="Permalink: Flags" href="#flags"></a></p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Flag</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><code>--runtime &lt;name&gt;</code></td>
<td>Use <code>docker</code> or <code>podman</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>--image &lt;name&gt;</code></td>
<td>Custom base image</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>--mount &lt;src:dst&gt;</code></td>
<td>Extra mount (repeatable)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>--env &lt;KEY=val&gt;</code></td>
<td>Set environment variable (repeatable)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>--ssh-agent</code></td>
<td>Forward SSH agent socket</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>--no-network</code></td>
<td>Disable network access</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>--readonly-project</code></td>
<td>Mount project read-only (outputs go to <code>/output</code>)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>--claude-config</code></td>
<td>Copy host <code>~/.claude</code> config into container</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Auto-Forwarded Environment Variables</h2><a id="user-content-auto-forwarded-environment-variables" aria-label="Permalink: Auto-Forwarded Environment Variables" href="#auto-forwarded-environment-variables"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">These are automatically passed into the container if set:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>ANTHROPIC_API_KEY</code></li>
<li><code>OPENAI_API_KEY</code></li>
<li><code>GITHUB_TOKEN</code> / <code>GH_TOKEN</code></li>
<li><code>OPENROUTER_API_KEY</code></li>
<li><code>GEMINI_API_KEY</code></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Configuration</h2><a id="user-content-configuration" aria-label="Permalink: Configuration" href="#configuration"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Create <code>~/.config/yolobox/config.toml</code> for global defaults:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="runtime = &quot;docker&quot;
image = &quot;ghcr.io/finbarr/yolobox:latest&quot;
ssh_agent = true"><pre><span>runtime</span> = <span><span>"</span>docker<span>"</span></span>
<span>image</span> = <span><span>"</span>ghcr.io/finbarr/yolobox:latest<span>"</span></span>
<span>ssh_agent</span> = <span>true</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Or <code>.yolobox.toml</code> in your project for project-specific settings:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="mounts = [&quot;../shared-libs:/libs:ro&quot;]
env = [&quot;DEBUG=1&quot;]
no_network = true"><pre><span>mounts</span> = [<span><span>"</span>../shared-libs:/libs:ro<span>"</span></span>]
<span>env</span> = [<span><span>"</span>DEBUG=1<span>"</span></span>]
<span>no_network</span> = <span>true</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Priority: CLI flags &gt; project config &gt; global config &gt; defaults.</p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Note:</strong> Setting <code>claude_config = true</code> in your config will copy your host's Claude config on <strong>every</strong> container start, overwriting any changes made inside the container. Use the CLI flag <code>--claude-config</code> for one-time syncs.</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Runtime Support</h2><a id="user-content-runtime-support" aria-label="Permalink: Runtime Support" href="#runtime-support"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>macOS</strong>: Docker Desktop, OrbStack, or Colima</li>
<li><strong>Linux</strong>: Docker or Podman</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Memory:</strong> Claude Code needs <strong>4GB+ RAM</strong> allocated to Docker. Colima defaults to 2GB which will cause OOM kills. Increase with: <code>colima stop &amp;&amp; colima start --memory 8</code></p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Security Model</h2><a id="user-content-security-model" aria-label="Permalink: Security Model" href="#security-model"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How It Works</h3><a id="user-content-how-it-works" aria-label="Permalink: How It Works" href="#how-it-works"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">yolobox uses <strong>container isolation</strong> (Docker or Podman) as its security boundary. When you run <code>yolobox</code>, it:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Starts a container with your project mounted at <code>/workspace</code></li>
<li>Runs as user <code>yolo</code> with sudo access <em>inside</em> the container</li>
<li>Does NOT mount your home directory (unless explicitly requested)</li>
<li>Uses Linux namespaces to isolate the container's filesystem, process tree, and network</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto">The AI agent has full root access <em>inside the container</em>, but the container's view of the filesystem is restricted to what yolobox explicitly mounts.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Trust Boundary</h3><a id="user-content-trust-boundary" aria-label="Permalink: Trust Boundary" href="#trust-boundary"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>The trust boundary is the container runtime</strong> (Docker/Podman). This means:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>✅ Protection against accidental <code>rm -rf ~</code> or credential theft</li>
<li>✅ Protection against most filesystem-based attacks</li>
<li><g-emoji alias="warning">⚠️</g-emoji> <strong>NOT protection against container escapes</strong> — a sufficiently advanced exploit targeting kernel vulnerabilities could break out</li>
<li><g-emoji alias="warning">⚠️</g-emoji> <strong>NOT protection against a malicious AI</strong> deliberately trying to escape — this is defense against accidents, not adversarial attacks</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">If you're worried about an AI actively trying to escape containment, you need VM-level isolation (see "Hardening Options" below).</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Threat Model</h3><a id="user-content-threat-model" aria-label="Permalink: Threat Model" href="#threat-model"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>What yolobox protects:</strong></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Your home directory from accidental deletion</li>
<li>Your SSH keys, credentials, and dotfiles</li>
<li>Other projects on your machine</li>
<li>Host system files and configurations</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><strong>What yolobox does NOT protect:</strong></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Your project directory (it's mounted read-write by default)</li>
<li>Network access (use <code>--no-network</code> to disable)</li>
<li>The container itself (the AI has root via sudo)</li>
<li>Against kernel exploits or container escape vulnerabilities</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Hardening Options</h3><a id="user-content-hardening-options" aria-label="Permalink: Hardening Options" href="#hardening-options"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Level 1: Basic (default)</strong></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="yolobox  # Standard container isolation"><pre>yolobox  <span><span>#</span> Standard container isolation</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Level 2: Reduced attack surface</strong></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="yolobox run --no-network --readonly-project claude"><pre>yolobox run --no-network --readonly-project claude</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Level 3: Rootless Podman</strong> (recommended for security-conscious users)</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# Install podman and run rootless
yolobox --runtime podman"><pre><span><span>#</span> Install podman and run rootless</span>
yolobox --runtime podman</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Rootless Podman runs the container without root privileges on the host, using user namespaces. This significantly reduces the impact of container escapes since the container's "root" maps to your unprivileged user on the host.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Level 4: VM isolation</strong> (maximum security)</p>
<p dir="auto">For true isolation with no shared kernel, consider running yolobox inside a VM:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>macOS</strong>: Use a Linux VM via UTM, Parallels, or Lima</li>
<li><strong>Linux</strong>: Use a Podman machine or dedicated VM</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">This adds significant overhead but eliminates kernel-level attack surface.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Network Isolation with Podman</h3><a id="user-content-network-isolation-with-podman" aria-label="Permalink: Network Isolation with Podman" href="#network-isolation-with-podman"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">For users who want to prevent container access to the local network while preserving internet access:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# Rootless podman uses slirp4netns by default, which provides
# network isolation from the host network
podman run --network=slirp4netns:allow_host_loopback=false ..."><pre><span><span>#</span> Rootless podman uses slirp4netns by default, which provides</span>
<span><span>#</span> network isolation from the host network</span>
podman run --network=slirp4netns:allow_host_loopback=false ...</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">yolobox doesn't currently expose this as a flag, but you can achieve it by running rootless Podman (the default network mode for rootless is slirp4netns).</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Building the Base Image</h2><a id="user-content-building-the-base-image" aria-label="Permalink: Building the Base Image" href="#building-the-base-image"></a></p>

<p dir="auto">This builds <code>yolobox/base:latest</code> locally.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Why "yolobox"?</h2><a id="user-content-why-yolobox" aria-label="Permalink: Why &quot;yolobox&quot;?" href="#why-yolobox"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Because you want to tell your AI agent "just do it" without consequences. YOLO, but in a box.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Development</h2><a id="user-content-development" aria-label="Permalink: Development" href="#development"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Building</h3><a id="user-content-building" aria-label="Permalink: Building" href="#building"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="make build          # Build binary
make test           # Run tests
make lint           # Run linters
make image          # Build Docker image
make install        # Install to ~/.local/bin"><pre>make build          <span><span>#</span> Build binary</span>
make <span>test</span>           <span><span>#</span> Run tests</span>
make lint           <span><span>#</span> Run linters</span>
make image          <span><span>#</span> Build Docker image</span>
make install        <span><span>#</span> Install to ~/.local/bin</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Versioning</h3><a id="user-content-versioning" aria-label="Permalink: Versioning" href="#versioning"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Version is derived automatically from git tags via <code>git describe</code>:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Tagged commit: <code>v0.1.1</code></li>
<li>After tag: <code>v0.1.1-3-gead833b</code> (3 commits after tag)</li>
<li>Uncommitted changes: adds <code>-dirty</code></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><strong>No files to edit for releases.</strong> The Makefile handles it.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Releasing</h3><a id="user-content-releasing" aria-label="Permalink: Releasing" href="#releasing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To release a new version:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git tag v0.1.2
git push origin master --tags"><pre>git tag v0.1.2
git push origin master --tags</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">That's it. GitHub Actions will automatically:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Build binaries for linux/darwin × amd64/arm64</li>
<li>Create a GitHub release with binaries and checksums</li>
<li>Build and push Docker image to <code>ghcr.io/finbarr/yolobox</code></li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Version policy:</strong></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Patch bump (<code>0.1.x</code>): Bug fixes, security fixes</li>
<li>Minor bump (<code>0.x.0</code>): New features</li>
<li>Major bump (<code>x.0.0</code>): Breaking changes</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">MIT</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Iran has now been offline for 96 hours (159 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/netblocks/status/2010750871274160361</link>
            <guid>46591974</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 18:03:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/netblocks/status/2010750871274160361">https://twitter.com/netblocks/status/2010750871274160361</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46591974">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="ScriptLoadFailure"><form action="" method="GET"><div><p><span>Something went wrong, but don’t fret — let’s give it another shot.</span></p><p><img alt="⚠️" draggable="false" src="https://abs-0.twimg.com/emoji/v2/svg/26a0.svg"><span> Some privacy related extensions may cause issues on x.com. Please disable them and try again.</span></p></div></form></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Postal Arbitrage (459 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://walzr.com/postal-arbitrage</link>
            <guid>46591708</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 17:41:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://walzr.com/postal-arbitrage">https://walzr.com/postal-arbitrage</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46591708">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><img src="https://walzr.com/stamp.png"><img src="https://walzr.com/postmark.webp"></p><div><p>As of 2025, a stamp for a letter costs $0.78 in the United States. Amazon Prime sells items for less than that... <b>with free shipping!</b> Why send a postcard when you can send actual stuff? </p><p>I found all items under $0.78 with free Prime shipping — screws, cans, pasta, whatever. Add a free gift note. It arrives in 1 or 2 days. Done.</p><p>You're not only saving money. It's about sending something real. Your friend gets a random can of tomato sauce with your birthday note attached. They laugh. They remember you. They might even use it!</p><p>Prices updated 10 minutes ago</p></div><table><tbody><tr onclick="window.open('https://www.amazon.com/dp/B000NSFQIU', '_blank')"><td>$0.25</td><td><img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/81KoXfeCD1L._AC_UL320_.jpg" alt="Lime"></td><td>Lime</td></tr><tr onclick="window.open('https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0010XRUV8', '_blank')"><td>$0.42</td><td><img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/81PYxHg5ehL._AC_UL320_.jpg" alt="Kool-Aid Unsweetened Tropical Punch Powdered Drink Mix, 0.16 oz. Packet"></td><td>Kool-Aid Unsweetened Tropical Punch Powdered Drink Mix, 0.16 oz. Packet</td></tr><tr onclick="window.open('https://www.amazon.com/dp/B08KZ3LQX1', '_blank')"><td>$0.45</td><td><img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/71mXWAS5a2L._AC_UL320_.jpg" alt="Amazon Grocery, Brown Gravy Mix, 0.87 Oz (Previously Happy Belly, Packaging May Vary)"></td><td>Amazon Grocery, Brown Gravy Mix, 0.87 Oz (Previously Happy Belly, Packaging May Vary)</td></tr><tr onclick="window.open('https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0000EXX14', '_blank')"><td>$0.47</td><td><img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/612TH8f2GqL._AC_UL320_.jpg" alt="Maruchan Ramen Noodle Soup, Beef, 3 oz"></td><td>Maruchan Ramen Noodle Soup, Beef, 3 oz</td></tr><tr onclick="window.open('https://www.amazon.com/dp/B001L1KRNC', '_blank')"><td>$0.49</td><td><img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/71MckCseqVL._AC_UL320_.jpg" alt="Lemon"></td><td>Lemon</td></tr><tr onclick="window.open('https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0014E2OF0', '_blank')"><td>$0.50</td><td><img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/71zHXHlEnJL._AC_UL320_.jpg" alt="LA MODERNA, Vermicelli Pasta, 7 oz (Pack of 1) | Enriched Durum Wheat Semolina | Kosher, Non-GMO, Iron and Vitamin-Fortified | Thin Vermicelli Noodles for Soups, Broths, and Quick Meals"></td><td>LA MODERNA, Vermicelli Pasta, 7 oz (Pack of 1) | Enriched Durum Wheat Semolina | Kosher, Non-GMO, Iron and Vitamin-Fortified | Thin Vermicelli Noodles for Soups, Broths, and Quick Meals</td></tr><tr onclick="window.open('https://www.amazon.com/dp/B001AXCY46', '_blank')"><td>$0.51</td><td><img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/4178dp3xHEL._AC_UL320_.jpg" alt="Simpson Strong-Tie H2.5A H2.5A 18-Gauge Galvanized Hurricane Tie"></td><td>Simpson Strong-Tie H2.5A H2.5A 18-Gauge Galvanized Hurricane Tie</td></tr><tr onclick="window.open('https://www.amazon.com/dp/B000NSKB7Q', '_blank')"><td>$0.56</td><td><img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/818y42pc78L._AC_UL320_.jpg" alt="Russet Potato, 1 Each"></td><td>Russet Potato, 1 Each</td></tr><tr onclick="window.open('https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0012JQD5Y', '_blank')"><td>$0.58</td><td><img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/617GgGMY8+L._AC_UL320_.jpg" alt="Apple Barrel Acrylic Paint in Assorted Colors (2 Ounce), 20504 Black"></td><td>Apple Barrel Acrylic Paint in Assorted Colors (2 Ounce), 20504 Black</td></tr><tr onclick="window.open('https://www.amazon.com/dp/B07TSCWN1P', '_blank')"><td>$0.70</td><td><img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/71KDBIQe0OL._AC_UL320_.jpg" alt="Amazon Grocery, Tomato Sauce, 8 Oz (Previously Amazon Fresh, Packaging May Vary)"></td><td>Amazon Grocery, Tomato Sauce, 8 Oz (Previously Amazon Fresh, Packaging May Vary)</td></tr><tr onclick="window.open('https://www.amazon.com/dp/B000R4B6GQ', '_blank')"><td>$0.77</td><td><img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/71oeILLx2CL._AC_UL320_.jpg" alt="Yoplait Original Low Fat Strawberry Yogurt Cup, Made with Real Fruit, 6 oz"></td><td>Yoplait Original Low Fat Strawberry Yogurt Cup, Made with Real Fruit, 6 oz</td></tr></tbody></table><div><p>In 2023, I ordered $1 cans of beans to a bunch of extended family members. It ignited our family group chat for a few weeks and everyone was super into it. Pictures of beans started rolling in. Then <i>they</i> started sending random stuff to each other. An asbestos warning label, cookies, a tin of sardines. Someone even sent a pregnancy test to my grandmother. </p><p><img src="https://walzr.com/grandma.webp"></p></div><p>This site is not affiliated with or endorsed by Amazon, obviously! </p><p><a href="https://walzr.com/"><img src="https://walzr.com/atoz.png"></a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: AI in SolidWorks (175 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.trylad.com</link>
            <guid>46591100</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 16:56:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.trylad.com">https://www.trylad.com</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46591100">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><main><div><div><div><p><span>LAD (Language-Aided Designer)</span></p><p>A SolidWorks add-in to design with natural language using AI</p></div><p><img src="https://www.trylad.com/Tan.png" alt="Backed by Y Combinator"></p></div><div><p>Describe your design in plain language and LAD will translate it into SolidWorks operations, creating sketches, features, and assemblies all through natural conversation. LAD uses screenshots and the feature tree to understand your model's current state, verifying operations were completed correctly and correcting mistakes.</p></div><div><div><div><p><img src="https://www.trylad.com/screenshots/ESP.png" alt="LAD visual context with screenshots and feature tree analysis"></p></div><div><p>Design from Documentation and Images</p><p>Provide documentation files, images, or examples of previous parts and assemblies, and LAD will intelligently read and use them.</p></div></div><div><div><p><img src="https://www.trylad.com/images/macro.png" alt="LAD macro writing and execution"></p></div><div><p>Write and Run Macros</p><p>LAD can write and run VBA macros for reproducibility and niche functionality not covered by standard LAD tools. When writing macros, LAD searches SolidWorks documentation and examples to better understand the API.</p></div></div><div><div><p><img src="https://www.trylad.com/screenshots/NEMA.png" alt="LAD complete SolidWorks API integration"></p></div><div><p>Permissioning and Versioning</p><p>LAD stores checkpoints so you can revert unwanted changes, lets you control which commands run automatically, and uses rules you provide to guide the AI as it works.</p></div></div></div><div><p><h2>Questions &amp; Answers</h2></p><div><ul><li><p>LAD (Language-Aided Designer) is a system that integrates directly into SolidWorks as an Add-in and can create sketches, features, macros, and other CAD objects.</p></li><li></li><li></li><li></li><li></li></ul></div></div><section><h2>LAD Changelog</h2></section></div><section><p>Try LAD now.</p></section></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[TimeCapsuleLLM: LLM trained only on data from 1800-1875 (660 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/haykgrigo3/TimeCapsuleLLM</link>
            <guid>46590280</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 16:04:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/haykgrigo3/TimeCapsuleLLM">https://github.com/haykgrigo3/TimeCapsuleLLM</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46590280">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text">
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">TimeCapsule LLM</h2><a id="user-content-timecapsule-llm" aria-label="Permalink: TimeCapsule LLM" href="#timecapsule-llm"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><em>A language model trained <strong>from scratch</strong> exclusively on data from certain places and time periods to reduce modern bias and emulate the voice, vocabulary, and worldview of the era.</em></p>
<p dir="auto">Imagine if an AI model didnt just pretend to be historical but actually was.</p>
<p dir="auto">v0 and v0.5 built on <a href="https://github.com/karpathy/nanoGPT">nanoGPT by Andrej Karpathy</a> Core training scripts and model architecture are his work.</p>
<p dir="auto">v1 built on <a href="https://huggingface.co/microsoft/phi-1_5" rel="nofollow">Phi 1.5 by Microsoft</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://huggingface.co/haykgrigorian/TimeCapsuleLLM" rel="nofollow">Hugging Face Link</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Model Behavior &amp; Limitations</h2><a id="user-content-model-behavior--limitations" aria-label="Permalink: Model Behavior &amp; Limitations" href="#model-behavior--limitations"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><strong>v0</strong></h3><a id="user-content-v0" aria-label="Permalink: v0" href="#v0"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Early prompts show the model responding with 1800's language and behavior.
Example: Prompt: "Who art Henry?" and it replied "I know that man, I have did not a black, the storm."</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/haykgrigo3/TimeCapsuleLLM/blob/main/london_1800_1850_v0/timelockllm_sample_output.png?raw=true"><img src="https://github.com/haykgrigo3/TimeCapsuleLLM/raw/main/london_1800_1850_v0/timelockllm_sample_output.png?raw=true" alt="TimeLockLLM Sample Output"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>No mention of modern concepts</li>
<li>Mostly era-accurate vocabulary</li>
<li>Sentences are mostly incoherent (expected for ~187MB training data)</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><strong>v0.5</strong></h3><a id="user-content-v05" aria-label="Permalink: v0.5" href="#v05"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">A significant improvement over v0.</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Victorian writing style, proper punctuation, mostly grammatical sentences</li>
<li>Still high factual hallucination rate</li>
<li>OCR noise (“Digitized by Google”) still present in outputs</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/haykgrigo3/TimeCapsuleLLM/blob/main/london_1800_1875_v0.5/fellowcitizens.png?raw=true"><img src="https://github.com/haykgrigo3/TimeCapsuleLLM/raw/main/london_1800_1875_v0.5/fellowcitizens.png?raw=true" alt="TimeLockLLM Sample Output"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><strong>v1</strong></h3><a id="user-content-v1" aria-label="Permalink: v1" href="#v1"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">First model to recall and connect a real historical event with an actual figure from the dataset.</p>
<p dir="auto">Example: Prompt: "It was the year of our Lord 1834"</p>
<p dir="auto">The output: "It was the year of our Lord 1834 and the streets of London were filled with protest and petition. The cause, as many re counted, was not bound in the way of private, but having taken up the same day in the day of Lord Palmerston, the public will receive a short statement of the difficulties under which the day of law has reached us. It is a matter of deep regret, that the present events in the history of the world are clear, and consequently will be'known. It is not true that the very men who first settled in the Gospel at Jerusalem should have so extensive and so interesting a record of the prosperity and prosperity"</p>
<p dir="auto">At first I assumed that a protest might have coincidentally taken place the same year but take a look at this: <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/haykgrigo3/TimeCapsuleLLM/blob/main/1834protest.png"><img src="https://github.com/haykgrigo3/TimeCapsuleLLM/raw/main/1834protest.png" alt="1834protest"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><strong>v2mini-eval1</strong></h3><a id="user-content-v2mini-eval1" aria-label="Permalink: v2mini-eval1" href="#v2mini-eval1"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Trained using a 15GB sample from v2's 90GB dataset.
Model trained to 10K steps only.</p>
<p dir="auto">There was an issue with tokenization that causes output to look like this:</p>
<p dir="auto">PROMPT:
Who is Charles Dickens?</p>
<p dir="auto">W ho is Charles D ic ens ? D oes that work more of h ise x cell ent st ir ring , in his pl ays , int he G reat C omp any 's f arm ? What I have y et to qu ote from J ack P ick ett ? D oy oun ot know th att hey were as pe cies of g all oping , ors aw ing oft heir bre asts , or what w ast ob ed one about the t im ew hen J acks on was looking ont hew ind ow ? What ist hes uccess of an English man , and which h isson has not be end is cover ing t ome , where by to acc omp lish such a we ight ? D idy ou ever m ake ap ass age int othe old road way , ort o an anch or - b ree ze att he foot of our boat , which you m ust le ave us ? The fact is , that whe ther the wind would rise up from the pl ain on S atur day night orn o ont ide , ort ill then orth , or other wise , wes hall be com pelled t od esc ribe af orm idable bar rier , with t hes ame e ffect s ast he p resent . In th iss itu ation , at le ast , itis not to omuch t os ay that we have le ft that room . I bel ieve there are three c op ies int he " F ive H undred - fold ," to bere fer red to , ast he first n umber of our read ers wh ow is ht</p>
<p dir="auto">Corrected:</p>
<p dir="auto">"Who is Charles Dickens? Does that work more of his excellent stirring, in his plays, in the Great Company's farm? What I have yet to quote from Jack Pickett? Do you not know that they were a species of galloping, or sawing of their breasts, or what was to be done about the time when Jackson was looking on the window? What is the success of an Englishman, and which his son has not been discovering to me, whereby to accomplish such a weight? Did you ever make a passage into the old roadway, or to an anchor-breeze at the foot of our boat, which you must leave us? The fact is, that whether the wind would rise up from the plain on Saturday night or noontide, or till the north, or otherwise, we shall be compelled to describe a formidable barrier, with the same effects as the present. In this situation, at least, it is not too much to say that we have left that room. I believe there are three copies in the 'Five Hundred-fold,' to be referred to, as the first number of our readers who wish t[o]...”</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><strong>v2mini-eval2</strong></h3><a id="user-content-v2mini-eval2" aria-label="Permalink: v2mini-eval2" href="#v2mini-eval2"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Trained using the same 15GB sample used for training eval1.
Model is again trained to 10K steps only.</p>
<p dir="auto">PROMPT:Charles Darwin</p>
<p dir="auto">Charles DarwinECCEMACY. Sir, — The following case is interesting to me : — I was in London a fortnight, and was much affected with an attack of rheumatism. The first attack of rheumatism was a week before I saw you, and the second when I saw you, and the third when I saw you, and the third in the same time. The second attack of gout, however, was not accompanied by any febrile symptoms, but was accompanied with an increased flow of urine, and with a more copious discharge of urine. The third attack was an hour after I saw you, and was succeeded by a return of a paroxysm of gout, and a more rapid return of the gout. The fourth attack was also accompanied by a fever, but was not always accompanied by any febrile symptoms. The third attack of gout was a fortnight after you had been ill, and the fourth was followed by a paroxysm of gout. The fourth attack was a fortnight after you were attacked, and was accompanied by a sense</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Datasets</h2><a id="user-content-datasets" aria-label="Permalink: Datasets" href="#datasets"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><strong>v2</strong></h3><a id="user-content-v2" aria-label="Permalink: v2" href="#v2"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>90GB of 1800-1875 London texts</li>
<li>136,344 documents</li>
<li>The full 90GB is not avalaible yet as it hasn't been tokenized but you can find a 15GB sample here: <a href="https://huggingface.co/datasets/haykgrigorian/TimeCapsuleLLM-London-1800-1875-v2-15GB" rel="nofollow">https://huggingface.co/datasets/haykgrigorian/TimeCapsuleLLM-London-1800-1875-v2-15GB</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Bias Stats</h3><a id="user-content-bias-stats" aria-label="Permalink: Bias Stats" href="#bias-stats"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/haykgrigo3/TimeCapsuleLLM/blob/main/london_1800_1875_v2mini_eval1/pronoun_bias.png"><img src="https://github.com/haykgrigo3/TimeCapsuleLLM/raw/main/london_1800_1875_v2mini_eval1/pronoun_bias.png" alt="Pronoun bias"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/haykgrigo3/TimeCapsuleLLM/blob/main/london_1800_1875_v2mini_eval1/geographic_bias.png"><img src="https://github.com/haykgrigo3/TimeCapsuleLLM/raw/main/london_1800_1875_v2mini_eval1/geographic_bias.png" alt="Geographic bias"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/haykgrigo3/TimeCapsuleLLM/blob/main/london_1800_1875_v2mini_eval1/temporal_bias.png"><img src="https://github.com/haykgrigo3/TimeCapsuleLLM/raw/main/london_1800_1875_v2mini_eval1/temporal_bias.png" alt="Temporal bias"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Refer to <a href="https://github.com/haykgrigo3/TimeCapsuleLLM/blob/main/london_1800_1875_v2mini_eval1/v2_bias_report.json">v2 bias report</a> for more info.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How to Use</h2><a id="user-content-how-to-use" aria-label="Permalink: How to Use" href="#how-to-use"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This project focuses mostly on curating historical data, preparing it for training and building a tokenizer. I am not going to cover the full LLM training process, for that refer to nanoGPT by Andrej Karpathy.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Step 1: Gather and Prepare Historical Texts</h3><a id="user-content-step-1-gather-and-prepare-historical-texts" aria-label="Permalink: Step 1: Gather and Prepare Historical Texts" href="#step-1-gather-and-prepare-historical-texts"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Collect .txt files of public domain books, documents, etc from your chosen time period (e.g., London 1800-1850)</li>
<li>Keep them within your chosen time/place window</li>
<li>Clean the text files using a script or manually remove headers/footer from Project Gutenberg, Modern annotations or things like OCR errors.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Step 2: Build a Custom Tokenizer</h3><a id="user-content-step-2-build-a-custom-tokenizer" aria-label="Permalink: Step 2: Build a Custom Tokenizer" href="#step-2-build-a-custom-tokenizer"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Run train_tokenizer.py or train_tokenizer_hf.py on the cleaned data.</li>
<li>This will give you vocab.json and merges.txt</li>
<li>Thes files define vocab and merge rules for your model</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Step 3: Train Your Model</h3><a id="user-content-step-3-train-your-model" aria-label="Permalink: Step 3: Train Your Model" href="#step-3-train-your-model"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Refer to <a href="https://github.com/karpathy/nanoGPT">nanoGPT by Andrej Karpathy</a> for the training process or your chosen architecture’s docs.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">FAQ</h2><a id="user-content-faq" aria-label="Permalink: FAQ" href="#faq"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What is Selective Temporal Training ?</h2><a id="user-content-what-is-selective-temporal-training-" aria-label="Permalink: What is Selective Temporal Training ?" href="#what-is-selective-temporal-training-"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Selective Temporal Training (STT) is a machine learning methodology where all training data is specifically curated to fall within a specific historical time period. It's done in order to model the language and knowledge of that era without influence from modern concepts. For example, the current model I have now (v0.5) is trained on data exclusively from 1800-1875, it's not fine tuned but trained from scratch resulting in output that reflects the linguistic style and historical context of that time period.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Why not just use fine-tuning or LoRA?</h2><a id="user-content-why-not-just-use-fine-tuning-or-lora" aria-label="Permalink: Why not just use fine-tuning or LoRA?" href="#why-not-just-use-fine-tuning-or-lora"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">For this project I'm trying to create a language model that is unclouded from modern bias. If I fine-tune something like GPT-2, it's already pre-trained and that information won't go away. If I train from scratch the language model won't pretend to be old, it just will be. The Goal for this project right now is to create something can reason exclusively using knowledge from London books published between 1800 and 1875.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What kind of data did you use for training?</h2><a id="user-content-what-kind-of-data-did-you-use-for-training" aria-label="Permalink: What kind of data did you use for training?" href="#what-kind-of-data-did-you-use-for-training"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">I'm using books, legal documents, newspapers, and other writings from 1800–1875 London. The list I linked (for v0) has like 200 but for the first training I just used 50 files about ~187 MB. You can view a list of the documents:
<a href="https://github.com/haykgrigo3/TimeCapsuleLLM/blob/main/Copy%20of%20London%20Documents%20for%20Time%20Capsule%20LLM.txt">https://github.com/haykgrigo3/TimeCapsuleLLM/blob/main/Copy%20of%20London%20Documents%20for%20Time%20Capsule%20LLM.txt</a></p>
<p dir="auto">Dataset sizes:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>v0: ~187MB</li>
<li>v0.5: ~435MB</li>
<li>v1: ~6.25GB</li>
<li>v2mini-eval1: 15GB</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How large are the models ?</h2><a id="user-content-how-large-are-the-models-" aria-label="Permalink: How large are the models ?" href="#how-large-are-the-models-"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">v0: 16M Parameters</p>
<p dir="auto">v0.5 123M Parameters</p>
<p dir="auto">v1: 700M Parameters</p>
<p dir="auto">v2mini-eval1: 300M Parameters</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Training Specs ?</h2><a id="user-content-training-specs-" aria-label="Permalink: Training Specs ?" href="#training-specs-"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">v0/v0.5</h2><a id="user-content-v0v05" aria-label="Permalink: v0/v0.5" href="#v0v05"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">GPU: Geforce rtx 4060
CPU: i5-13400F
Ram: 16GB DDR5.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">v1</h2><a id="user-content-v1-1" aria-label="Permalink: v1" href="#v1-1"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">GPU: A100 SXM rented</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">v2mini-eval1</h2><a id="user-content-v2mini-eval1-1" aria-label="Permalink: v2mini-eval1" href="#v2mini-eval1-1"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">GPU: A100 SXM rented</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Open-Meteo is a free and open-source weather API for non-commercial use (107 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://open-meteo.com/</link>
            <guid>46589849</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 15:36:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://open-meteo.com/">https://open-meteo.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46589849">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><h2>Accurate Weather Forecasts for Any Location</h2> <p>Open-Meteo partners with national weather services to bring you open data with high
				resolution, ranging from 1 to 11 kilometres. Our powerful APIs intelligently select the most
				suitable weather models for your specific location, ensuring accurate and reliable
				forecasts.</p> <p>With our user-friendly JSON API, accessing weather data has never been easier. Whether
				you're developing an application or seeking weather information for personal use, our APIs
				provide seamless integration and deliver the data you need in a simple and accessible
				format.</p> <p>Experience the precision and convenience of Open-Meteo's Forecast API, providing
				comprehensive weather information worldwide. Stay informed and make informed decisions with
				our reliable weather forecasts.</p> <p><!--[--><a href="https://open-meteo.com/en/features"><!---->See features<!----></a><!--]--><!----> <!--[--><a href="https://open-meteo.com/en/docs"><!---->Read the docs<!----></a><!--]--><!----></p></div> <div><!--[--><a href="https://api.open-meteo.com/v1/forecast?latitude=52.52&amp;longitude=13.41&amp;current=temperature_2m,wind_speed_10m&amp;hourly=temperature_2m,relative_humidity_2m,wind_speed_10m"><!----><pre tabindex="0"><code><span><span>curl</span><span> "</span><span>https://api.open-meteo.com/v1/forecast?latitude=52.52&amp;longitude=13.41&amp;current=temperature_2m,wind_speed_10m&amp;hourly=temperature_2m,relative_humidity_2m,wind_speed_10m</span><span>"</span><span> </span></span></code></pre><!----><!----></a><!--]--><!----> <div><!----><pre tabindex="0"><code><span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>  ...</span></span>
<span><span>  "</span><span>current</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> {</span></span>
<span><span>    "</span><span>time</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> "</span><span>2022-01-01T15:00</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>    "</span><span>temperature_2m</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> 2.4</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>    "</span><span>wind_speed_10m</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> 11.9</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>  },</span></span>
<span><span>  "</span><span>hourly</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> {</span></span>
<span><span>    "</span><span>time</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> [</span><span>"</span><span>2022-07-01T00:00</span><span>"</span><span>,</span><span>"</span><span>2022-07-01T01:00</span><span>"</span><span>,</span><span> ...</span><span>],</span></span>
<span><span>    "</span><span>wind_speed_10m</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> [</span><span>3.16</span><span>,</span><span>3.02</span><span>,</span><span>3.3</span><span>,</span><span>3.14</span><span>,</span><span>3.2</span><span>,</span><span>2.95</span><span>,</span><span> ...</span><span>],</span></span>
<span><span>    "</span><span>temperature_2m</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> [</span><span>13.7</span><span>,</span><span>13.3</span><span>,</span><span>12.8</span><span>,</span><span>12.3</span><span>,</span><span>11.8</span><span>,</span><span> ...</span><span>],</span></span>
<span><span>    "</span><span>relative_humidity_2m</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> [</span><span>82</span><span>,</span><span>83</span><span>,</span><span>86</span><span>,</span><span>85</span><span>,</span><span>88</span><span>,</span><span>88</span><span>,</span><span>84</span><span>,</span><span>76</span><span>,</span><span> ...</span><span>],</span></span>
<span><span>  }</span></span>
<span><span>}</span></span></code></pre><!----><!----></div></div></div><div id="featured"><div><div> <h3>High Resolution</h3></div> <p>Open-Meteo leverages a powerful combination of global (11 km) and mesoscale (1 km) weather
					models from esteemed national weather services, providing comprehensive forecasts with
					remarkable precision. No matter where you are in the world, you can access the most
					reliable and accurate weather predictions available.</p> <p>Our weather data is presented in hourly resolution, allowing you to plan your activities
					with confidence. The initial days of the forecast benefit from localised weather models,
					offering highly detailed and accurate information. Subsequently, global weather models
					provide forecasts for up to 16 days. Through seamless integration, our APIs deliver a
					straightforward and reliable hourly weather forecast experience.</p></div> <div><div> <h3>Rapid Updates</h3></div> <p>At Open-Meteo, we understand the importance of having the most up-to-date weather
					information. That's why our local weather models are updated every hour, ensuring that our
					forecasts reflect the latest changes in conditions, including updates from rain radars.</p> <p>Our weather models rely on a wealth of real-time data, including measurements from various
					sources such as airplanes, buoys, radar systems, and satellites. By incorporating this
					diverse and comprehensive data, our numerical weather predictions provide a deeper
					analysis than traditional weather stations, resulting in more accurate forecasts.</p></div> <div><div> <h3>80 Years Historical Data</h3></div> <p>Explore the past with our comprehensive <a href="https://open-meteo.com/en/docs/historical-weather-api" title="Historical weather data via API">Historical Weather API</a>. With over 80 years of hourly weather data available at a 10 kilometre resolution, you
					can dive into the climate of any location. Behind the scenes, this extensive dataset,
					comprising 50 TB of information, enables you to access temperature records spanning eight
					decades in an instant.</p> <p>Moreover, our 1 kilometre weather models continuously archive recent data, ensuring that
					you can seamlessly retrieve the latest forecasts alongside historical information from
					previous weeks. This functionality opens up possibilities for training machine learning
					applications and gaining valuable insights from the combination of present and past
					weather data. Discover the power of our historical weather API and unlock a treasure trove
					of weather information.</p></div> <div><div> <h3>Open-Source</h3></div> <p>We believe in the power of open-source software. That's why the entire codebase of
					Open-Meteo is accessible on <a href="https://github.com/open-meteo/open-meteo" title="Open-Meteo GitHub Repository">GitHub</a>, released under the <a href="https://github.com/open-meteo/open-meteo/blob/main/LICENSE">AGPLv3 licence</a>.
					This means you can explore, use, modify, and contribute to the code.</p> <p>If you wish to take it a step further, we're here to support you in setting up your own
					API instances. This allows you to have complete control and enjoy practically unlimited
					API calls, making it ideal for demanding applications like machine learning or large
					language models.</p> <p>In addition, our data is licenced under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licences/by/4.0/" title="CC BY 4.0 Licence Information">Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)</a>. This means you are free to share and adapt the data, even for commercial purposes. We
					believe in fostering an open ecosystem that encourages transparency, collaboration and
					innovation.</p></div> <div><div> <h3>Free API</h3></div> <p>Open-Meteo offers free access to its APIs for non-commercial use, making it convenient for
					individuals and developers to explore and integrate weather data into their projects. The
					best part is that no API key, registration, or credit card is required to enjoy this
					service.</p> <p>We trust our users to utilise the free API responsibly and kindly request appropriate
					credit for the data used. While there are no strict access restrictions, we encourage fair
					usage of the service. If you require commercial usage or anticipate exceeding 10'000 API
					calls per day, we recommend considering our <a href="https://open-meteo.com/en/pricing" title="Pricing for our paid API subscription">API subscription</a> for enhanced features and support.</p></div> <div><div> <h3>Easy to Use</h3></div> <p>We've designed our APIs to be incredibly user-friendly. They are based on the widely
					adopted HTTP protocol and utilise the simplicity of JSON data format. All you need to get
					started is a basic understanding of geographic coordinates, making HTTP requests, and
					working with JSON data.</p> <p>To assist you in seamlessly integrating our APIs into your projects, we provide
					comprehensive <a href="https://open-meteo.com/en/docs" title="Weather API Technical Documentation">documentation</a>. It includes detailed explanations of all parameters and their usage. Whether you're
					using Python, R, Julia, PHP, JavaScript, React, Flutter, Java, or any other programming
					language, our APIs are designed to work effortlessly with your application.</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Apple picks Google's Gemini to power Siri (928 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cnbc.com/2026/01/12/apple-google-ai-siri-gemini.html</link>
            <guid>46589675</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 15:22:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2026/01/12/apple-google-ai-siri-gemini.html">https://www.cnbc.com/2026/01/12/apple-google-ai-siri-gemini.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46589675">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="RegularArticle-ArticleBody-5" data-module="ArticleBody" data-test="articleBody-2" data-analytics="RegularArticle-articleBody-5-2"><div id="Placeholder-ArticleBody-Video-108251160" data-test="VideoPlaceHolder" role="region" tabindex="0" data-vilynx-id="7000400554" aria-labelledby="Placeholder-ArticleBody-Video-108251160"><p><img src="https://image.cnbcfm.com/api/v1/image/108251161-17682301881768230186-43459552421-1080pnbcnews.jpg?v=1768230188&amp;w=750&amp;h=422&amp;vtcrop=y" alt="Cramer’s Stop Trading: Apple"><span></span><span></span></p></div><div><p><span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="RegularArticle-QuoteInBody-1"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/AAPL/">Apple</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span> is joining forces with <span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="RegularArticle-QuoteInBody-2"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/GOOGL/">Google</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span> to power its <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/ai-effect/">artificial intelligence</a> features, including a major <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/12/30/apple-intelligence-ai-siri-iphone.html">Siri</a> upgrade expected later this year. </p><p>The multi-year partnership will lean on Google's <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2026/01/08/google-adds-gemini-features-to-gmail-message-summaries-proofreading-.html">Gemini</a> and cloud technology for future Apple foundational models, according to a statement obtained by CNBC's Jim Cramer.</p><p>"After careful evaluation, we determined that Google's technology provides the most capable foundation for Apple Foundation Models and we're excited about the innovative new experiences it will unlock for our users," the tech giants said in a <a href="https://blog.google/company-news/inside-google/company-announcements/joint-statement-google-apple/" target="_blank">joint statement</a> on Monday.</p><p>The models will continue to run on Apple devices and the company's private cloud compute, they added. </p><p>Apple declined to comment on the terms of the deal. Google referred CNBC to the joint statement. </p><p>In August, <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-08-22/apple-explores-using-google-gemini-ai-to-power-revamped-siri?srnd=undefined" target="_blank">Bloomberg</a> had reported that Apple was in <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/08/22/google-shares-rise-on-report-of-apple-using-gemini-for-siri.html">early talks with Google</a> to use a custom Gemini model to power a new iteration of Siri. The news outlet later <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-11-05/apple-plans-to-use-1-2-trillion-parameter-google-gemini-model-to-power-new-siri" target="_blank">reported</a> that Apple was planning to pay about $1 billion a year to utilize Google AI.</p><p>The deal is another major indicator of growing trust in Google's <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/11/27/how-google-put-together-the-pieces-for-its-ai-comeback.html">accelerating AI agenda</a> and comeback against OpenAI. In 2025, the search giant logged its <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/12/31/google-stock-wraps-best-year-since-2009-as-ai-excites-wall-street-.html">best year since 2009</a> and surpassed Apple in market capitalization last week for the <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2026/01/07/alphabets-market-cap-surpasses-apples-for-first-time-since-2019.html">first time since 2019</a>. </p></div><div id="RegularArticle-RelatedContent-1"><h2>Read more CNBC tech news</h2><div><ul><li><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2026/01/08/china-investigate-meta-acquisition-manus-export.html">Meta faces China probe over acquisition of AI agent startup Manus</a></li><li><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2026/01/07/microsoft-behind-controversial-data-center-in-michigan-township.html">Microsoft revealed as company behind controversial data center proposal in Michigan township</a></li><li><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2026/01/07/alphabets-market-cap-surpasses-apples-for-first-time-since-2019.html">Alphabet's market cap surpasses Apple's for first time since 2019</a></li><li><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2026/01/07/google-characterai-to-settle-suits-involving-suicides-ai-chatbots.html">Google, Character.AI to settle suits involving minor suicides and AI chatbots</a></li></ul></div></div><div><p>Shares were slightly lower following the news. Google briefly touched above a <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2026/01/12/alphabet-4-trillion-market-cap.html">$4 trillion market value</a>.</p><p>Apple has mostly stood on the sidelines of the AI frenzy that's swept up Wall Street since the launch of<a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/12/16/openai-in-talks-with-amazon-about-investment-could-top-10-billion.html"> OpenAI'</a>s <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2026/01/07/openai-chatgpt-health-medical-records.html">ChatGPT</a> at the end of 2022. </p><p>Hyperscalers <span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="RegularArticle-QuoteInBody-16"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/AMZN/">Amazon</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span>, <span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="RegularArticle-QuoteInBody-17"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/META/">Meta Platforms</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span> and <span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="RegularArticle-QuoteInBody-18"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/MSFT/">Microsoft</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span> have <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/10/31/tech-ai-google-meta-amazon-microsoft-spend.html">shelled out billions</a> on AI products, tools and infrastructure for their customers.</p><p>That's amped up the pressure on the <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/12/17/apple-ai-delay-siri.html">iPhone maker to deliver</a> an impressive Siri AI voice upgrade, which it delayed last year <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/03/07/apple-delays-siri-ai-improvements-to-2026.html">until 2026</a>, despite <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/04/23/apple-ai-ads-went-too-far-watchdog-says.html">running ads</a> for the product.</p><p>"It's going to take us longer than we thought to deliver on these features and we anticipate rolling them out in the coming year," the company said in a statement at the time.</p><p>Apple currently <a href="https://openai.com/index/openai-and-apple-announce-partnership/" target="_blank">partners with OpenAI</a> to integrate ChatGPT into Siri and Apple Intelligence, specifically for complicated queries that can tap into the AI model's world knowledge. It's unclear what the Google partnership means for the ChatGPT integration in the future.</p><p>The devices giant told CNBC said that they aren't making any changes to the agreement. OpenAI did not immediately respond to a request for comment. </p><p>Meanwhile, Google has made steady progress on its AI agenda, introducing its <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/11/18/google-announces-gemini-3-as-battle-with-openai-intensifies.html">upgraded Gemini 3 model</a> late last year. </p><p>In October, Google CEO <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/sundar-pichai/">Sundar Pichai</a> <a href="https://blog.google/company-news/inside-google/message-ceo/alphabet-earnings-q3-2025/#google-cloud" target="_blank">said</a> the company's cloud segment signed more deals worth more than $1 billion through the third quarter of 2025 than the previous two years combined. </p></div><div><div role="button" tabindex="0"><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="256" height="256" viewBox="0 0 256 256" aria-labelledby="title desc" role="img" focusable="false" preserveAspectRatio="xMinYMin"><title>Stock Chart Icon</title><desc>Stock chart icon</desc><g transform="translate(1.4065934065934016 1.4065934065934016) scale(2.81 2.81)"><path d="M 87.994 0 H 69.342 c -1.787 0 -2.682 2.16 -1.418 3.424 l 5.795 5.795 l -33.82 33.82 L 28.056 31.196 l -3.174 -3.174 c -1.074 -1.074 -2.815 -1.074 -3.889 0 L 0.805 48.209 c -1.074 1.074 -1.074 2.815 0 3.889 l 3.174 3.174 c 1.074 1.074 2.815 1.074 3.889 0 l 15.069 -15.069 l 14.994 14.994 c 1.074 1.074 2.815 1.074 3.889 0 l 1.614 -1.614 c 0.083 -0.066 0.17 -0.125 0.247 -0.202 l 37.1 -37.1 l 5.795 5.795 C 87.84 23.34 90 22.445 90 20.658 V 2.006 C 90 0.898 89.102 0 87.994 0 z" transform=" matrix(1 0 0 1 0 0) " stroke-linecap="round"></path><path d="M 65.626 37.8 v 49.45 c 0 1.519 1.231 2.75 2.75 2.75 h 8.782 c 1.519 0 2.75 -1.231 2.75 -2.75 V 23.518 L 65.626 37.8 z" transform=" matrix(1 0 0 1 0 0) " stroke-linecap="round"></path><path d="M 47.115 56.312 V 87.25 c 0 1.519 1.231 2.75 2.75 2.75 h 8.782 c 1.519 0 2.75 -1.231 2.75 -2.75 V 42.03 L 47.115 56.312 z" transform=" matrix(1 0 0 1 0 0) " stroke-linecap="round"></path><path d="M 39.876 60.503 c -1.937 0 -3.757 -0.754 -5.127 -2.124 l -6.146 -6.145 V 87.25 c 0 1.519 1.231 2.75 2.75 2.75 h 8.782 c 1.519 0 2.75 -1.231 2.75 -2.75 V 59.844 C 41.952 60.271 40.933 60.503 39.876 60.503 z" transform=" matrix(1 0 0 1 0 0) " stroke-linecap="round"></path><path d="M 22.937 46.567 L 11.051 58.453 c -0.298 0.298 -0.621 0.562 -0.959 0.8 V 87.25 c 0 1.519 1.231 2.75 2.75 2.75 h 8.782 c 1.519 0 2.75 -1.231 2.75 -2.75 V 48.004 L 22.937 46.567 z" transform=" matrix(1 0 0 1 0 0) " stroke-linecap="round"></path></g></svg><p><img src="https://static-redesign.cnbcfm.com/dist/a54b41835a8b60db28c2.svg" alt="hide content"></p></div><p>Alphabet and Apple one-day stock chart.</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Date is out, Temporal is in (418 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://piccalil.li/blog/date-is-out-and-temporal-is-in/</link>
            <guid>46589658</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 15:20:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://piccalil.li/blog/date-is-out-and-temporal-is-in/">https://piccalil.li/blog/date-is-out-and-temporal-is-in/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46589658">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div lang="en-US">
  <p>Time makes fools of us all, and JavaScript is no slouch in that department either. Honestly, I’ve never minded the latter much — in fact, if you’ve taken <a href="https://piccalil.li/javascript-for-everyone">JavaScript for Everyone</a> or tuned into the <a href="https://wil.to/posts#js4e">newsletter</a>, you already know that I largely <em>enjoy</em> JavaScript’s little quirks, believe it or not.</p>
<p>I like when you can see the seams; I like how, for as formal and iron-clad as the ES-262 specification might seem, you can still see all the good <em>and</em> bad decisions made by the hundreds of people who’ve been building the language in mid-flight, if you know where to look. JavaScript has <em>character</em>. Sure, it doesn’t necessarily do everything <em>exactly</em> the way one might expect, but y’know, if you ask me, JavaScript has a real charm once you get to know it!</p>
<p>There’s one part of the language where that immediately falls apart for me, though.</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="Z1i1Ud4" prefix="r18" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,762308]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="762308"><pre id="code-block-762308" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>// Numeric months are zero-indexed, but years and days are not:</span>
console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> <span>new</span> <span>Date</span><span>(</span><span>2026</span><span>,</span> <span>1</span><span>,</span> <span>1</span><span>)</span> <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: Date Sun Feb 01 2026 00:00:00 GMT-0500 (Eastern Standard Time)</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<p>The <code>Date</code> constructor.</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="14XpUs" prefix="r19" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,649157]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="649157"><pre id="code-block-649157" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>// A numeric string between 32 and 49 is assumed to be in the 2000s:</span>
console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> <span>new</span> <span>Date</span><span>(</span> <span>"49"</span> <span>)</span> <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: Date Fri Jan 01 2049 00:00:00 GMT-0500 (Eastern Standard Time)</span>

<span>// A numeric string between 33 and 99 is assumed to be in the 1900s:</span>
console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> <span>new</span> <span>Date</span><span>(</span> <span>"99"</span> <span>)</span> <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: Date Fri Jan 01 1999 00:00:00 GMT-0500 (Eastern Standard Time)</span>

<span>// ...But 100 and up start from year zero:</span>
console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> <span>new</span> <span>Date</span><span>(</span> <span>"100"</span> <span>)</span> <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: Date Fri Jan 01 0100 00:00:00 GMT-0456 (Eastern Standard Time)</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<p>I dislike <code>Date</code> <em>immensely</em>.</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="nX61C" prefix="r20" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,143868]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="143868"><pre id="code-block-143868" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>// A string-based date works the way you might expect:</span>
console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> <span>new</span> <span>Date</span><span>(</span> <span>"2026/1/2"</span> <span>)</span> <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: Date Fri Jan 02 2026 00:00:00 GMT-0500 (Eastern Standard Time)</span>

<span>// A leading zero on the month? No problem; one is one, right?</span>
console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> <span>new</span> <span>Date</span><span>(</span> <span>"2026/02/2"</span> <span>)</span> <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: Date Mon Feb 02 2026 00:00:00 GMT-0500 (Eastern Standard Time)</span>

<span>// Slightly different formatting? Sure!</span>
console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> <span>new</span> <span>Date</span><span>(</span> <span>"2026-02-2"</span> <span>)</span> <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: Date Mon Feb 02 2026 00:00:00 GMT-0500 (Eastern Standard Time)</span>

<span>// A leading zero on the day? Of course; why wouldn't it work?</span>
console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> <span>new</span> <span>Date</span><span>(</span><span>'2026/01/02'</span><span>)</span> <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: Date Fri Jan 02 2026 00:00:00 GMT-0500 (Eastern Standard Time)</span>

<span>// Unless, of course, you separate the year, month, and date with hyphens.</span>
<span>// Then it gets the _day_ wrong.</span>
console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> <span>new</span> <span>Date</span><span>(</span><span>'2026-01-02'</span><span>)</span> <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: Date Thu Jan 01 2026 19:00:00 GMT-0500 (Eastern Standard Time)</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<p><code>Date</code> sucks. It was hastily and shamelessly copied off of Java’s homework in the car on the way to school and it got all the same answers wrong, right down to the name at the top of the page: <code>Date</code> doesn’t represent a <em>date</em>, it represents a <em>time</em>. Internally, dates are stored as number values called <strong>time values</strong>: Unix timestamps, divided into 1,000 milliseconds — which, okay, yes, a Unix time does also necessarily imply a date, sure, but <em>still</em>: Date represents a time, from which you can infer a date. Gross.</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="nQpnS" prefix="r21" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,152131]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="152131"><pre id="code-block-152131" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>// Unix timestamp for Monday, December 4, 1995 12:00:00 AM GMT-05 (the day JavaScript was announced):</span>
<span>const</span> timestamp <span>=</span> <span>818053200</span><span>;</span>

console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> <span>new</span> <span>Date</span><span>(</span> timestamp <span>*</span> <span>1000</span> <span>)</span> <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: Date Mon Dec 04 1995 00:00:00 GMT-0500 (Eastern Standard Time)</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<div><p>Words like “date” and “time” mean things, but, sure — <em>whatever, JavaScript</em>.</p></div>
<p>Java deprecated <em>their</em> <code>Date</code> way back in 1997, only a few years after JavaScript’s <code>Date</code> was turned loose on the unsuspecting world; meanwhile, we’ve been saddled with this mess ever since. It’s wildly inconsistent when it comes to parsing dates, as you’ve seen so far here. It has no sense of time zones beyond the local one and GMT, which is not ideal where “world-wide” is <em>right there in the web’s name</em> — and speaking-of, <code>Date</code> <em>only</em> respects the Gregorian calendar model. It wholesale does not understand the concept of daylight savings time, which— I mean, okay, yeah, samesies, but I’m not <em>made of computers</em>. All these shortcomings make it exceptionally common to use a third-party library dedicated to working around it all, some of which are absolutely <em>massive</em>; a performance drain that has done real and measurable damage to the web.</p>
<p>None of these are my major issue with <code>Date</code>. My complaint is about more than parsing or syntax or “developer ergonomics” or the web-wide performance impact of wholly necessary workarounds or even the definition of the word “date.” My issue with <code>Date</code> is soul-deep. My problem with <code>Date</code> is that using it means <em>deviating from the fundamental nature of time itself</em>.</p>
<a href="https://piccalil.li/courses"><span data-variant="dark">Advert</span><picture><source media="(width <= 600px)" srcset="https://piccalil.b-cdn.net/images/ads/winter-discount-ad-portrait.png?auto=format"><img src="https://piccalil.b-cdn.net/images/ads/winter-discount-ad-landscape.png?format=webp" alt="Save 15% on All courses! Use code WINTER15 at checkout" loading="lazy"></picture></a>
<p>All JavaScript’s primitives values are <strong>immutable</strong>, meaning that the values themselves cannot be changed. The number value <code>3</code> can never represent anything but the concept of “three” — you can’t make <code>true</code> mean anything other than “true.” These are values with concrete, iron-clad, real-world meanings. We know what three is. It can’t be some other non-three thing. These immutable data types are stored <strong>by value</strong>, meaning that a variable that represents the number value <code>3</code> effectively “contains” — and thus behaves as — the number value <code>3</code>.</p>
<p>When an immutable value is assigned to a variable, the JavaScript engine creates a copy of that value and stores the copy in memory:</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="2fJOVq" prefix="r22" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,274196]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="274196"><pre id="code-block-274196" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>const</span> theNumber <span>=</span> <span>3</span><span>;</span>

console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> theNumber <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: 3</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<p>This fits the common mental model for “a variable” just fine: <code>theNumber</code> “contains” <code>3</code>.</p>
<p>When we initialize <code>theOtherNumber</code> with the value bound to <code>theNumber</code>, that mental model holds: once again a <code>3</code> is created and stored in memory. <code>theOtherNumber</code> can now be thought of as containing its own discrete <code>3</code>.</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="QiQL8" prefix="r23" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,641110]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="641110"><pre id="code-block-641110" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>const</span> theNumber <span>=</span> <span>3</span><span>;</span>
<span>const</span> theOtherNumber <span>=</span> theNumber<span>;</span>

console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> theOtherNumber <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: 3;</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<p>The value of <code>theNumber</code> isn’t changed when we alter the value associated with <code>theOtherNumber</code>, of course — again, we’re working with two discrete instances of <code>3</code>.</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="Zz1Nux" prefix="r24" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,903409]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="903409"><pre id="code-block-903409" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>const</span> theNumber <span>=</span> <span>3</span><span>;</span>
<span>let</span> theOtherNumber <span>=</span> theNumber<span>;</span>

theOtherNumber <span>=</span> <span>5</span><span>;</span>

console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> theOtherNumber <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: 5;</span>

console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> theNumber <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: 3</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<p>When you change the value bound to <code>theOtherNumber</code>, you’re not changing the <code>3</code>, you’re creating a new, immutable number value and binding that in its place. Hence an error when you try to tinker with a variable declared using <code>const</code>:</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="Z2pnQoO" prefix="r25" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,230106]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="230106"><pre id="code-block-230106" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>const</span> theNumber <span>=</span> <span>3</span><span>;</span>

theNumber <span>=</span> <span>5</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: Uncaught TypeError: invalid assignment to const 'theNumber'</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<div><p>You can’t change the binding of a <code>const</code>, and you <em>definitely</em> can’t alter the meaning of <code>3</code>.</p></div>
<p>Data types that <em>can</em> be changed after they’re created are <strong>mutable</strong>, meaning that the data value <em>itself</em> can be altered. Object values — any non-primitive value, like an array, map, or set — are mutable.</p>
<p>Variables (and object properties, function parameters, and elements in an array, set, or map) can’t “contain” an object, the way we might think of <code>theNumber</code> in the example above as “containing” <code>3</code>. A variable can contain either a primitive value or a <strong>reference value</strong>, the latter of which is a pointer to that object’s stored location in memory. When you assign an object to a variable, instead of creating a copy of that object, the identifier represents a reference to the object’s stored position in memory. That’s why an object bound to a variable declared with <code>const</code> can still be altered: the <em>reference value</em> can’t be changed, but the values of the object can:</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="Z286sWq" prefix="r26" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,581705]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="581705"><pre id="code-block-581705" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>const</span> theObject <span>=</span> <span>{</span>
	<span>theValue</span> <span>:</span> <span>3</span>
<span>}</span><span>;</span>

theObject<span>.</span>theValue<span>++</span><span>;</span>

console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> theObject<span>.</span>theValue <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: 4</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<div><p>You still can’t change the binding of a <code>const</code>, but you <em>can</em> alter the object that binding references.</p></div>
<p>When a reference value is assigned from one variable to another, the JavaScript engine creates a copy of that reference value — not the object value itself, the way a discrete copy is made of a primitive value. Both identifiers point to the same object in memory — any changes made to that object by way of one reference will be reflected by the others, because they’re all referencing the same thing:</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="Z11Apw6" prefix="r27" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,487210]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="487210"><pre id="code-block-487210" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>const</span> theObject <span>=</span> <span>{</span>
	<span>theValue</span> <span>:</span> <span>3</span>
<span>}</span><span>;</span>

<span>const</span> theOtherObj <span>=</span> theObject<span>;</span>

theOtherObj<span>.</span>theValue<span>++</span><span>;</span>

console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> theOtherObj<span>.</span>theValue <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: 4</span>

console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> theObject<span>.</span>theValue <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: 4</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<p><em>This</em> is what gets me about JavaScript’s date handling. Despite representing “point to it on a calendar” values, JavaScript’s date values are <em>mutable —</em> <code>Date</code> is a constructor, invoking a constructor with <code>new</code> necessarily results in an object, and all objects are inherently mutable:</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="Z4jOBp" prefix="r28" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,72207]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="72207"><pre id="code-block-72207" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>const</span> theDate <span>=</span> <span>new</span> <span>Date</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>

console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> <span>typeof</span> theDate <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: object</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<p>Even though “January 1st, 2026” is as much an immutable real-world concept as “three” or “true,” the only way we have of representing that date is a with a mutable data structure.</p>
<p>This also means that any variable initialized with an instance of the <code>Date</code> constructor contains a reference value, pointing to a data value in memory that can be changed by way of any reference to that value:</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="ZByBBI" prefix="r29" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,43758]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="43758"><pre id="code-block-43758" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>const</span> theDate <span>=</span> <span>new</span> <span>Date</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>

console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> theDate<span>.</span><span>toDateString</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: Tue Dec 30 2025</span>

theDate<span>.</span><span>setMonth</span><span>(</span> <span>10</span> <span>)</span><span>;</span>

console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> theDate<span>.</span><span>toDateString</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: Sun Nov 30 2025</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<div><p>Again, we’re going to breeze right over the fact that month <code>10</code> is <em>November</em>.</p></div>
<p>So despite real-world dates having set-in-stone <em>meanings</em>, the process of interacting with an instance of <code>Date</code> that represents that real-world value can mean altering that instance in ways we didn’t necessarily intend:</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="2dYNwd" prefix="r39" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,550346]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="550346"><pre id="code-block-550346" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>const</span> today <span>=</span> <span>new</span> <span>Date</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>

<span>const</span> <span>addDay</span> <span>=</span> <span>theDate</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>{</span>
	theDate<span>.</span><span>setDate</span><span>(</span> theDate<span>.</span><span>getDate</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>+</span> <span>1</span> <span>)</span><span>;</span>
	<span>return</span> theDate<span>;</span>
<span>}</span><span>;</span>

console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span><span><span>`</span><span>Today is </span><span><span>${</span> today<span>.</span><span>toLocaleDateString</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>}</span></span><span>, tomorrow is </span><span><span>${</span> <span>addDay</span><span>(</span> today <span>)</span><span>.</span><span>toLocaleDateString</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>}</span></span><span>.</span><span>`</span></span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: Today is 12/31/2025. Tomorrow is 1/1/2026.</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<p>Fine so far, right? Today is today, tomorrow is tomorrow; all is right in the world. You’d be forgiven for committing this to a codebase and moving on with your day. That is, unless we reordered the output slightly.</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="pL9sA" prefix="r40" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,721985]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="721985"><pre id="code-block-721985" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>const</span> today <span>=</span> <span>new</span> <span>Date</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>const</span> <span>addDay</span> <span>=</span> <span>theDate</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>{</span>
	theDate<span>.</span><span>setDate</span><span>(</span> theDate<span>.</span><span>getDate</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>+</span> <span>1</span> <span>)</span><span>;</span>
	<span>return</span> theDate<span>;</span>
<span>}</span><span>;</span>

console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span><span><span>`</span><span>Tomorrow will be </span><span><span>${</span> <span>addDay</span><span>(</span> today <span>)</span><span>.</span><span>toLocaleDateString</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>}</span></span><span>. Today is </span><span><span>${</span> today<span>.</span><span>toLocaleDateString</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>}</span></span><span>.</span><span>`</span></span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: Tomorrow will be 1/1/2026. Today is 1/1/2026.</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<p>See what happened there? the variable <code>today</code> represents a reference to the object created by <code>new Date()</code>. When we provided <code>today</code> as an argument to the <code>addDay</code> function, the parameter <code>theDate</code> now represents a copy of the reference value — not a copy of the value, but a second reference to the object that represents today’s date. When we manipulate that value to determine the date of the following day, we’re manipulating the mutable object in memory, not an immutable copy — today becomes tomorrow, the falcon has a hard time hearing the falconer, the center starts to look a little iffy vis-a-vis “holding,” and so on.</p>
<p>Now, by this point you can probably tell that I’m not here to praise <code>Date</code>, but what you might not expect is that I’m here to <em>bury</em> it. That’s right: <code>Date</code> is soon to be over, done, gone, as “deprecated” as any part of the web platform can be — which is to say, “around forever, but you shouldn’t use it anymore, if you can avoid it.” Soon we will — at long last — have an object that replaces <code>Date</code> wholesale: <code>Temporal</code>.</p>
<a href="https://piccalil.li/courses"><span data-variant="dark">Advert</span><picture><source media="(width <= 600px)" srcset="https://piccalil.b-cdn.net/images/ads/winter-discount-ad-portrait.png?auto=format"><img src="https://piccalil.b-cdn.net/images/ads/winter-discount-ad-landscape.png?format=webp" alt="Save 15% on All courses! Use code WINTER15 at checkout -" loading="lazy"></picture></a>
<h2 id="temporal-is-not-a-constructor-its-a-namespace-object"><a href="#temporal-is-not-a-constructor-its-a-namespace-object">Temporal is not a constructor, it’s a namespace object</a></h2>
<p>The sharp-eyed among you may have noticed that I said “an <em>object</em> that replaces <code>Date</code>,” not “a constructor.” <code>Temporal</code> is not a constructor, and your browser’s developer console will tell you the same if you attempt to invoke it as one:</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="2vGBAe" prefix="r30" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,794498]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="794498"><pre id="code-block-794498" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>const</span> today <span>=</span> <span>new</span> <span>Temporal</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Uncaught TypeError: Temporal is not a constructor</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<div><p><code>Temporal</code> is a <em>way</em> better name for something that pertains to <em>time</em>, if you ask me.</p></div>
<p>Instead, <code>Temporal</code> is a <strong>namespace object</strong> — an ordinary object made up of static properties and methods, like the <code>Math</code> object:</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="Z129dhd" prefix="r31" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,335578]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="335578"><pre id="code-block-335578" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw="">console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> Temporal <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>/* Result (expanded):
Temporal { … }
	Duration: function Duration()
	Instant: function Instant()
	Now: Temporal.Now { … }
	PlainDate: function PlainDate()
	PlainDateTime: function PlainDateTime()
	PlainMonthDay: function PlainMonthDay()
	PlainTime: function PlainTime()
	PlainYearMonth: function PlainYearMonth()
	ZonedDateTime: function ZonedDateTime()
	Symbol(Symbol.toStringTag): "Temporal"
*/</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<p>I find this <em>immediately</em> understandable compared to <code>Date</code>.  The classes and namespaces objects that <code>Temporal</code> contains allow you to calculate durations between two points in time, represent a point in time <em>with or without time zone specificity</em>, or access the current moment in time via the <code>Now</code> property. <code>Temporal.Now</code> references a namespace object containing properties and methods of its own:</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="DWUpQ" prefix="r32" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,111051]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="111051"><pre id="code-block-111051" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw="">console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> Temporal<span>.</span>Now <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>/* Result (expanded):
Temporal.Now { … }
	instant: function instant()
	plainDateISO: function plainDateISO()
	plainDateTimeISO: function plainDateTimeISO()
	plainTimeISO: function plainTimeISO()
	timeZoneId: function timeZoneId()
	zonedDateTimeISO: function zonedDateTimeISO()
	Symbol(Symbol.toStringTag): "Temporal.Now"
	&lt;prototype&gt;: Object { … }
*/</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<p><code>Temporal</code> gives us a sensible, plain-language way to grab today’s date, <em>a la</em> raggedy old  <code>Date</code>: the <code>Now</code> property contains a <code>plainDateISO()</code> method. Since we’re not specifying anything in the way of time zones (a thing we can do now, thanks to Temporal) that method gives us back today’s date in the current one — EST, in my case:</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="1REqYW" prefix="r33" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,531367]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="531367"><pre id="code-block-531367" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw="">console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> Temporal<span>.</span>Now<span>.</span><span>plainDateISO</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>/* Result (expanded):
Temporal.PlainDate 2025-12-31
	&lt;prototype&gt;: Object { … }
*/</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<div><p>Notice how <code>plainDateISO</code> results in an already-formatted, date-only value? Stay tuned; that’ll come up again later.</p></div>
<p>—wait. That looks familiar:</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="283pSX" prefix="r34" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,407693]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="407693"><pre id="code-block-407693" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>const</span> nowTemporal <span>=</span> Temporal<span>.</span>Now<span>.</span><span>plainDateISO</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>const</span> nowDate <span>=</span> <span>new</span> <span>Date</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>

console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> nowTemporal <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>/* Result (expanded):
Temporal.PlainDate 2025-12-31
	&lt;prototype&gt;: Object { … }
*/</span>

console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> nowDate <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>/* Result (expanded):
Date Tue Dec 31 2025 11:05:52 GMT-0500 (Eastern Standard Time)
	&lt;prototype&gt;: Date.prototype { … }
*/</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<p>Could it be that—…</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="ZcGKpM" prefix="r35" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,689194]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="689194"><pre id="code-block-689194" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>const</span> rightNow <span>=</span> Temporal<span>.</span>Now<span>.</span><span>instant</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>

console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> <span>typeof</span> rightNow <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// object</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<p><em>Yes, we’re still working with a mutable object that represents the current date</em>, I say in my spookiest voice, flashlight squarely beneath my chin. At a glance, this might not seem like it addresses my big complaint with <code>Date</code> at all.</p>
<p>Well, we’re kind of at the mercy of the nature of the language, here: dates represent complex real-world values, complex data necessitates complex data structures, and for JavaScript, that means objects. The difference is in how we <em>interact</em> with these Temporal objects, as compared to instances of <code>Date</code>, and — as is so often the case — the magic is in the prototype chain:</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="ZMz1AX" prefix="r36" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,231225]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="231225"><pre id="code-block-231225" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>const</span> nowTemporal <span>=</span> Temporal<span>.</span>Now<span>.</span><span>plainDateISO</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>

console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> nowTemporal<span>.</span>__proto__ <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>/* Result (expanded):
Object { … }
	add: function add()
	calendarId: &gt;&gt;
	constructor: function PlainDate()
	day: &gt;&gt;
	dayOfWeek: &gt;&gt;
	dayOfYear: &gt;&gt;
	daysInMonth: &gt;&gt;
	daysInWeek: &gt;&gt;
	daysInYear: &gt;&gt;
	equals: function equals()
	era: &gt;&gt;
	eraYear: &gt;&gt;
	inLeapYear: &gt;&gt;
	month: &gt;&gt;
	monthCode: &gt;&gt;
	monthsInYear: &gt;&gt;
	since: function since()
	subtract: function subtract()
	toJSON: function toJSON()
	toLocaleString: function toLocaleString()
	toPlainDateTime: function toPlainDateTime()
	toPlainMonthDay: function toPlainMonthDay()
	toPlainYearMonth: function toPlainYearMonth()
	toString: function toString()
	toZonedDateTime: function toZonedDateTime()
	until: function until()
	valueOf: function valueOf()
	weekOfYear: &gt;&gt;
	with: function with()
	withCalendar: function withCalendar()
	year: &gt;&gt;
	yearOfWeek: &gt;&gt;
	Symbol(Symbol.toStringTag): "Temporal.PlainDate"
	&lt;get calendarId()&gt;: function calendarId()
	&lt;get day()&gt;: function day()
	&lt;get dayOfWeek()&gt;: function dayOfWeek()
	&lt;get dayOfYear()&gt;: function dayOfYear()
	&lt;get daysInMonth()&gt;: function daysInMonth()
	&lt;get daysInWeek()&gt;: function daysInWeek()
	&lt;get daysInYear()&gt;: function daysInYear()
	&lt;get era()&gt;: function era()
	&lt;get eraYear()&gt;: function eraYear()
	&lt;get inLeapYear()&gt;: function inLeapYear()
*/</span>

</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<p>Right away you’ll notice that there are a number of methods and properties devoted to accessing, formatting, and manipulating the details of the Temporal object we’re working with. No big surprises there — it means a little bit of a learning curve, sure, but nothing an occasional trip over to <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Global_Objects/Temporal">MDN</a> couldn’t solve, and they all more-or-less do what they say on their respective tins. The big difference from working with <code>Date</code> is <em>how</em> they do so, at a fundamental level:</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="1rqmc1" prefix="r37" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,811942]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="811942"><pre id="code-block-811942" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>const</span> nowTemporal <span>=</span> Temporal<span>.</span>Now<span>.</span><span>plainDateISO</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>

<span>// Current local date:</span>
console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> nowTemporal <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>/* Result (expanded):
Temporal.PlainDate 2025-12-30
	&lt;prototype&gt;: Object { … }
*/</span>

<span>// Current local year:</span>
console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> nowTemporal<span>.</span>year <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: 2025</span>

<span>// Current local date and time:</span>
console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> nowTemporal<span>.</span><span>toPlainDateTime</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>/* Result (expanded):
Temporal.PlainDateTime 2025-12-30T00:00:00
	&lt;prototype&gt;: Object { … }
*/</span>

<span>// Specify that this date represents the Europe/London time zone:</span>
console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> nowTemporal<span>.</span><span>toZonedDateTime</span><span>(</span> <span>"Europe/London"</span> <span>)</span> <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>/* Result (expanded):
Temporal.ZonedDateTime 2025-12-30T00:00:00+00:00[Europe/London]
	&lt;prototype&gt;: Object { … }
*/</span>

<span>// Add a day to this date:</span>
console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> nowTemporal<span>.</span><span>add</span><span>(</span><span>{</span> <span>days</span><span>:</span> <span>1</span> <span>}</span><span>)</span> <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>/*
Temporal.PlainDate 2025-12-31
	&lt;prototype&gt;: Object { … }
*/</span>

<span>// Add one month and one day to this date, and subtract two years:</span>
console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> nowTemporal<span>.</span><span>add</span><span>(</span><span>{</span> <span>months</span><span>:</span> <span>1</span><span>,</span> <span>days</span><span>:</span> <span>1</span> <span>}</span><span>)</span><span>.</span><span>subtract</span><span>(</span><span>{</span> <span>years</span><span>:</span> <span>2</span> <span>}</span><span>)</span> <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>/*
Temporal.PlainDate 2024-01-31
	&lt;prototype&gt;: Object { … }
*/</span>

console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> nowTemporal <span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>/* Result (expanded):
Temporal.PlainDate 2025-12-30
	&lt;prototype&gt;: Object { … }
*/</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<p>Notice how none of these transformations required us to manually spin up any new objects, <em>and</em> that the value of the object referenced by <code>nowTemporal</code> remains unchanged? Unlike <code>Date</code>,  the methods we use to interact with a Temporal object result in <em>new</em> Temporal objects, rather than requiring us to use them in the context of a new instance or to modify the instance we’re working with — which is how we’re able to chain the <code>add</code> and <code>subtract</code> methods together in <code>nowTemporal.add({ months: 1, days: 1 }).subtract({ years: 2 })</code>.</p>
<p>Sure, we’re still working with objects, and that means we’re working with mutable data structures that represent real-world values:</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="160dkF" prefix="r38" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,738180]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="738180"><pre id="code-block-738180" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>const</span> nowTemporal <span>=</span> Temporal<span>.</span>Now<span>.</span><span>plainDateISO</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>

nowTemporal<span>.</span>someProperty <span>=</span> <span>true</span><span>;</span>

console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span> nowTemporal <span>)</span><span>;</span>

<span>/* Result (expanded):
Temporal.PlainDate 2026-01-05
	someProperty: true
	&lt;prototype&gt;: Object { … }
</span></code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<p>…But the value represented by that Temporal object isn’t meant to be changed during the normal course of interacting with it — even though the object is still essentially mutable, we’re not stuck using that object in ways that could alter what it means in terms of real-world dates and times. I’ll take it.</p>
<p>So, let’s revisit that janky little “today is X, tomorrow is Y” script we wrote using <code>Date</code> earlier. First, we’ll fix it by making sure we’re working with two discrete instances of <code>Date</code> rather than modifying the instance that represents today’s date:</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="Udgcv" prefix="r41" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,365513]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="365513"><pre id="code-block-365513" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>const</span> today <span>=</span> <span>new</span> <span>Date</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>

<span>const</span> <span>addDay</span> <span>=</span> <span>theDate</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>{</span>
	<span>const</span> tomorrow <span>=</span> <span>new</span> <span>Date</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>

	tomorrow<span>.</span><span>setDate</span><span>(</span> theDate<span>.</span><span>getDate</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>+</span> <span>1</span> <span>)</span><span>;</span>
	<span>return</span> tomorrow<span>;</span>
<span>}</span><span>;</span>

console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span><span><span>`</span><span>Tomorrow will be </span><span><span>${</span> <span>addDay</span><span>(</span> today <span>)</span><span>.</span><span>toLocaleDateString</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>}</span></span><span>. Today is </span><span><span>${</span> today<span>.</span><span>toLocaleDateString</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>}</span></span><span>.</span><span>`</span></span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: Tomorrow will be 1/1/2026. Today is 12/31/2025.</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>

<p>Okay, fine. It gets the job done, just as it has since the day <code>Date</code> first bumbled its way onto the web. We’re not unwittingly altering the value of <code>today</code> since we’re spinning up a new instance of <code>Date</code> inside our <code>addDay</code> function — wordy, but it works, as it has for decades now. We add <code>1</code> to it, which we have to just kind of <em>know</em> means add one <em>day.</em> Then in our template literal we need to keep nudging JavaScript to give us the date in a format that doesn’t include the current time, as a string. It’s functional, but verbose.</p>
<p>Now, let’s redo it using <code>Temporal</code>:</p>
<div>
<!-- 
  IMPORTANT: Do not indent this slot content in Astro.
  Leading whitespace will be preserved and break code formatting.
-->
<astro-island uid="1my0FA" prefix="r42" component-url="/_astro/CodeBlock.chXmwTQ3.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;className&quot;:[0,&quot;language-js&quot;],&quot;id&quot;:[0,261058]}" ssr="" client="visible" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;CodeBlock&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div data-element="code-block" data-id="261058"><pre id="code-block-261058" tabindex="0"><astro-slot>
<code is:raw=""><span>const</span> today <span>=</span> Temporal<span>.</span>Now<span>.</span><span>plainDateISO</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>

console<span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span><span><span>`</span><span>Tomorrow will be </span><span><span>${</span> today<span>.</span><span>add</span><span>(</span><span>{</span> <span>days</span><span>:</span> <span>1</span> <span>}</span><span>)</span> <span>}</span></span><span>. Today is </span><span><span>${</span> today <span>}</span></span><span>.</span><span>`</span></span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>// Result: Tomorrow will be 2026-01-01. Today is 2025-12-31.</span>
</code>
</astro-slot></pre></div><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>

<p><em>So much better</em>. Leaner, meaner, and <em>way</em> less margin for error. We want today’s date without the time, and the object that results from invoking <code>plainDateISO</code> (and any new Temporal objects created from it) will retain that formatting <em>without</em> being coerced to a string. Formatting: <em>check</em>.</p>
<p>We want to output a value that represents today’s date plus one day, and we want to do so in a way where we are unmistakably saying “add one day to it” with no parsing guesswork: <em>check</em> and <em>check</em>.</p>
<p>Most importantly, we don’t want to run the risk of having our original <code>today</code> object altered unintentionally — because the result of calling the <code>add</code> method will always be a new Temporal object: <em>check</em>.</p>
<p><code>Temporal</code> is going to be a <em>massive</em> improvement over <code>Date</code>, and I only say “going to be” because it still isn’t quite ready for prime-time usage. <a href="https://tc39.es/proposal-temporal/">The draft specification for the proposed <code>Temporal</code> object</a> has reached stage three of the standardization process, meaning it is now officially “recommended for implementation” — not yet part of the standard that informs the ongoing development of JavaScript itself, but close enough that browsers can start tinkering with it. That means the results of that early experimentation may be used to further refine the specification, so nothing is set in stone just yet. Web standards are an iterative process, after all.</p>
<p>That’s where you and I come in. Now that <code>Temporal</code> has <a href="https://caniuse.com/?search=Temporal">landed in the latest versions of Chrome and Firefox</a> — and others, soon — it’s time for us to get in there and kick the tires a little bit. We may not have had any say in <code>Date</code>, but we get to experiment with <code>Temporal</code> before the final implementations land.</p>
<p>Soon, JavaScript will have sensible, modern date handling, and we’ll finally be able to cram <code>Date</code> way in the back of the junk drawer with the rubber bands, mismatched jar lids, mystery keys, and probably-half-empty AA batteries — still present, still an inexorable part of the web platform, but no longer our first, last, and only way of handling dates. And we only had to wait— well, hold on, let me just crunch the numbers real quick:</p>
<div>
  <astro-island uid="ZO0XPc" prefix="r9" component-url="/_astro/ConsoleLogger.67Rv-5VD.js" component-export="default" renderer-url="/_astro/client.BIGLHmRd.js" props="{&quot;instruction&quot;:[0],&quot;code&quot;:[0,&quot;\nconst today = Temporal.Now.plainDateISO();\nconst jsShipped = Temporal.PlainDate.from( \&quot;1995-12-04\&quot; );\nconst sinceDate = today.since( jsShipped, { largestUnit: 'year' });\n\nconsole.log( `${ sinceDate.years } years, ${ sinceDate.months } months, and ${ sinceDate.days } days.` );\n&quot;],&quot;language&quot;:[0,&quot;js&quot;],&quot;outputType&quot;:[0,&quot;log&quot;],&quot;consoleOutput&quot;:[0,&quot;\n30 years, 0 months, and 27 days.\n&quot;],&quot;showLineNumbers&quot;:[0,false]}" ssr="" client="load" opts="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;ConsoleLogger&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:true}" await-children=""><div><p data-wrapper-type="inner"><h3>Try it out</h3></p><hr><div data-wrapper-type="inner"><pre tabindex="0"><code>const today = Temporal.Now.plainDateISO();
const jsShipped = Temporal.PlainDate.from( "1995-12-04" );
const sinceDate = today.since( jsShipped, { largestUnit: 'year' });

console.log( `${ sinceDate.years } years, ${ sinceDate.months } months, and ${ sinceDate.days } days.` );</code></pre></div></div><template data-astro-template="">
    
  </template><!--astro:end--></astro-island>
</div>
<p>Sure, the best time to replace <code>Date</code> would’ve been back in 1995, but hey: the second best time is <code>Temporal.Now</code>, right?</p>

    <div><p><strong>Enjoyed this article?</strong> <em>You can support us by <a href="https://opencollective.com/piccalilli/contribute/leave-a-tip-90508/checkout?interval=oneTime&amp;amount=3">leaving a tip</a> via Open Collective</em></p></div><a href="https://piccalil.li/courses"><span data-variant="dark">Advert</span><picture><source media="(width <= 600px)" srcset="https://piccalil.b-cdn.net/images/ads/winter-discount-ad-portrait.png?auto=format"><img src="https://piccalil.b-cdn.net/images/ads/winter-discount-ad-landscape.png?format=webp" alt="Save 15% on All courses! Use code WINTER15 at checkout _" loading="lazy"></picture></a></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Statement from Federal Reserve Chair (179 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/speech/powell20260111a.htm?mod=ANLink</link>
            <guid>46589489</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 15:05:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/speech/powell20260111a.htm?mod=ANLink">https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/speech/powell20260111a.htm?mod=ANLink</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46589489">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content" role="main">
        
        <div id="article">
                                        
                    <div>
            <p><strong>Accessible Keys for Video</strong></p>
            <p><strong>[Space Bar]</strong> toggles play/pause;</p>
            <p><strong>[Right/Left Arrows]</strong> seeks the video forwards and back (5 sec );</p>
            <p><strong>[Up/Down Arrows]</strong> increase/decrease volume;</p>
            <p><strong>[M]</strong> toggles mute on/off;</p>
            <p><strong>[F]</strong> toggles fullscreen on/off (Except IE 11);</p>
            <p>The <strong>[Tab]</strong> key may be used in combination with the <strong>[Enter/Return]</strong> key to navigate and activate control buttons, such as caption on/off.</p>
        </div>
                    
                    
                    <p>Good evening.</p>

<p>On Friday, the Department of Justice served the Federal Reserve with grand jury subpoenas, threatening a criminal indictment related to my testimony before the Senate Banking Committee last June. That testimony concerned in part a multi-year project to renovate historic Federal Reserve office buildings.</p>

<p>I have deep respect for the rule of law and for accountability in our democracy. No one—certainly not the chair of the Federal Reserve—is above the law. But this unprecedented action should be seen in the broader context of the administration's threats and ongoing pressure.</p>

<p>This new threat is not about my testimony last June or about the renovation of the Federal Reserve buildings. It is not about Congress's oversight role; the Fed through testimony and other public disclosures made every effort to keep Congress informed about the renovation project. Those are pretexts. The threat of criminal charges is a consequence of the Federal Reserve setting interest rates based on our best assessment of what will serve the public, rather than following the preferences of the President.</p>

<p>This is about whether the Fed will be able to continue to set interest rates based on evidence and economic conditions—or whether instead monetary policy will be directed by political pressure or intimidation.</p>

<p>I have served at the Federal Reserve under four administrations, Republicans and Democrats alike. In every case, I have carried out my duties without political fear or favor, focused solely on our mandate of price stability and maximum employment. Public service sometimes requires standing firm in the face of threats. I will continue to do the job the Senate confirmed me to do, with integrity and a commitment to serving the American people.</p>

<p>Thank you.</p>
                     
                </div>
        <div>
            <p>Last Update:
                
                            January 11, 2026
                        
            </p>
            
            
        </div>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>