<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 11:30:02 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Microsoft removes documentation for switching to a local account in Windows 11 (150 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2024/06/microsoft-removes-documentation-for-switching-to-a-local-account-in-windows-11/</link>
            <guid>40786644</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 10:22:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2024/06/microsoft-removes-documentation-for-switching-to-a-local-account-in-windows-11/">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2024/06/microsoft-removes-documentation-for-switching-to-a-local-account-in-windows-11/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40786644">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <h4>
      you're *sure* you don't want to use a Microsoft account??     —
</h4>
            
            <h2 itemprop="description">But most Microsoft account sign-in workarounds for Windows 11 continue to work.</h2>
                    </div><div itemprop="articleBody">
                                    
<figure>
  <img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/win11-pc-2023-800x450.jpeg" alt="A laptop PC running Windows 11 sitting next to a coffee mug.">
      <figcaption><p><a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/win11-pc-2023.jpeg" data-height="1080" data-width="1920">Enlarge</a> <span>/</span> A PC running Windows 11.</p><p>Microsoft</p></figcaption>  </figure>

  




<!-- cache hit 35:single/related:f82fd1a01b1403f1c7abf95e50c2a8d9 --><!-- empty -->
<p>One of Windows 11's more contentious changes is that, by default, both the Home and Pro editions of the operating system require users to sign in with a Microsoft account during setup. Signing in with an account does get you some benefits, at least if you're a regular user of other Microsoft products like OneDrive, GamePass, or Microsoft 365 (<a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2022/10/rip-to-microsoft-office-henceforth-to-be-known-as-microsoft-365/">aka Office</a>). But if you don't use those services, a lot of what a Microsoft account gets you in Windows 11 is <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/08/windows-11-has-made-the-clean-windows-install-an-oxymoron/">repeated ads and reminders</a> about signing up for those services. Using Windows with a traditional local account is still extremely possible, but it does require a small amount of know-how beyond just clicking the right buttons.</p>

<p>On the know-how front, Microsoft has taken one more minor, but nevertheless irritating, step away from allowing users to sign in with local accounts. This <a href="https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/change-from-a-local-account-to-a-microsoft-account-395203bf-9f1b-eb24-b042-5b8dae6c1d20">official Microsoft support page</a> walks users with local accounts through the process of signing in to a Microsoft account. <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20240612104753/https:/support.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/change-from-a-local-account-to-a-microsoft-account-395203bf-9f1b-eb24-b042-5b8dae6c1d20">As recently as June 12</a>, that page also included instructions for converting a Microsoft account into a local account. But according to Tom's Hardware and the Internet Wayback Machine, those instructions <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20240617103839/https:/support.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/change-from-a-local-account-to-a-microsoft-account-395203bf-9f1b-eb24-b042-5b8dae6c1d20">disappeared on or around June 17</a> and haven't been seen since.</p>
<p>Despite the documentation change, <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2024/02/what-i-do-to-clean-up-a-clean-install-of-windows-11-23h2-and-edge/">most of the workarounds</a> for creating a local account still work in both Windows 11 23H2 (the publicly available version of Windows 11 for most PCs) and 24H2 (<a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2024/06/windows-11-24h2-is-released-to-the-public-but-only-on-copilot-pcs-for-now/">available now on Copilot+ PCs</a>, later this fall for everyone else). The easiest way to do it on a PC you just took out of the box is to press Shift+F10 during the setup process to bring up a command prompt window, typing <code>OOBE\BYPASSNRO</code>, rebooting, and then clicking the "I don't have Internet" button when asked to connect to a Wi-Fi network.</p>                                            
                                                        
<p>Other workarounds include using the Rufus tool to create a USB installer that will automatically bypass the Microsoft account sign-in requirement, or (for Windows 11 Pro users) indicating that you want to join the PC to a corporate domain and then not actually joining it to a domain. Setting the PC up with a Microsoft account and then signing out afterward is also still an option.</p>
<p>There is one workaround that has allegedly stopped working—it used to be that trying to "sign in" with a nonexistent email account would get you a local sign-in option. But as of earlier this month, <a href="https://x.com/zacbowden/status/1797496910737252744">according to Windows Central editor Zac Bowden</a>, it looks like the Windows 11 setup screen will just ask you to try another email address instead.</p>
<p>To be fair to Microsoft, all the big tech companies want you to sign in with an account before you can use all the features of the software, but neither Apple nor Google goes as far as to <em>mandate</em> account sign-in to access basic functionality. Macs, iPhones, and iPads will all let you complete the setup process without signing in, though you do have to know which buttons to click. Google will allow you to use Chromebooks in guest mode, and Android phones and tablets are still usable without signing in (though this does make it more difficult to find and install apps). Microsoft's pushiness remains unique; there's definitely a difference between a company that would&nbsp;<em>really</em> prefer that you sign in and one that forces you to.</p>

                                                </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Local First, Forever (151 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://tonsky.me/blog/crdt-filesync/</link>
            <guid>40786425</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 09:47:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://tonsky.me/blog/crdt-filesync/">https://tonsky.me/blog/crdt-filesync/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40786425">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
        
        <p>So I was at the <a href="https://www.localfirstconf.com/" target="_blank">Local-First Conf</a> the other day, listening to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NMq0vncHJvU" target="_blank">Martin Kleppmann</a>, and this slide caught my attention:</p>
        <figure>
<img src="https://tonsky.me/blog/crdt-filesync/talk.webp?t=1719240073" width="720" height="405">        </figure>
        <p>Specifically, this part:</p>
        <figure>
<img src="https://tonsky.me/blog/crdt-filesync/talk2.webp?t=1719240073" width="720" height="550">        </figure>
        <p>But first, some context.</p>
        <h2 id="what-is-local-first">What is local-first?</h2>
        <p>For the long version, go to Ink &amp; Switch, who coined the term: <a href="https://www.inkandswitch.com/local-first/" target="_blank">www.inkandswitch.com/local-first/</a></p>
        <p>Here’s my short version:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>It’s software.</li>
          <li>That prefers keeping your data local.</li>
          <li>But it still goes to the internet occasionally to sync with other users, fetch data, back up, etc.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>If it doesn’t go to the internet at all, it’s just local software.</p>
        <p>If it doesn’t work offline with data it already has, then it’s just normal cloud software. You all know the type — sorry, Dave, I can’t play the song I just downloaded because your internet disappeared for one second...</p>
        <p>But somewhere in the middle — local-first. We love it because it’s good for the end user, you and me, not for the corporations that produce it.</p>
        <h2 id="whats-the-problem-with-local-first">What’s the problem with local-first?</h2>
        <p>The goal of local-first software is to get control back into the hands of the user, right? You own the data (literally, it’s on your device), yada-yada-yada. That part works great.</p>
        <p>However, local-first software still has this online component. For example, personal local-first software still needs to sync between your own devices. And syncing doesn’t work without a server...</p>
        <p>So here we have a problem: somebody writes local-first software. Everybody who bought it can use it until the heat death of the universe. They <em>own</em> it.</p>
        <p>But if the company goes out of business, syncing will stop working. And companies go out of business all the time.</p>
        <figure>
<img src="https://tonsky.me/blog/crdt-filesync/bonto.webp?t=1719240073" width="720" height="375">        </figure>
        <p>What do we do?</p>
        <h2 id="cue-dropbox">Cue Dropbox</h2>
        <p>The solution is to use something widely available that will probably outlive our company. We need something popular, accessible to everyone,  has multiple implementations, and can serve as a sync server.</p>
        <p>And what’s the most common end-user application of cloud sync?</p>
        <p>Dropbox! Well, not necessarily Dropbox, but any cloud-based file-syncing solution. iCloud Drive, OneDrive, Google Drive, <a href="https://tonsky.me/blog/syncthing/">Syncthing</a>, etc.</p>
        <p>It’s perfect — many people already have it. There are multiple implementations, so if Microsoft or Apple go out of business, people can always switch to alternatives. File syncing is a commodity.</p>
        <p>But file syncing is a “dumb” protocol. You can’t “hook” into sync events, or update notifications, or conflict resolution. There isn’t much API; you just save files and they get synced. In case of conflict, best case, you get two files. Worst — you get only one :)</p>
        <p>This simplicity has an upside and a downside. The upside is: if you can work with that, it would work everywhere. That’s the interoperability part from Martin’s talk.</p>
        <p>The downside is: you can’t do much with it, and it probably won’t be optimal. But will it be enough?</p>
        <h2 id="version-1-super-naive">Version 1: Super-naive</h2>
        <p>Let’s just save our state in a file and let Dropbox sync it (in my case, I’m using Syncthing, but it’s the same idea. From now on, I’ll use “Dropbox” as a common noun).</p>
        <p>Simple:</p>
        <figure>
<img src="https://tonsky.me/blog/crdt-filesync/naive.webp?t=1719240073" width="685" height="280">        </figure>
        <p>But what happens if you change the state on two machines? Well, you get a conflict file:</p>
        <figure>
<img src="https://tonsky.me/blog/crdt-filesync/naive_conflict.webp?t=1719240073" width="685" height="280">        </figure>
        <p>Normally, it would’ve been a problem. But it’s not if you are using CRDT!</p>
        <blockquote>
          <p>CRDT is a collection of data types that all share a very nice property: they can always be merged. It’s not always the perfect merge, and not everything can be made into a CRDT, but IF you can put your data into a CRDT, you can be sure: all merges will go without conflicts.</p>
        </blockquote>
        <p>With CRDT, we can solve conflicts by opening both files, merging states, and saving back to <code>state.xml</code>. Simple!</p>
        <p>Even in this form, Dropbox as a common sync layer works! There are some downsides, though:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>conflicting file names are different between providers,</li>
          <li>some providers might not handle conflicts at all,</li>
          <li>it needs state-based CRDT.</li>
        </ul>
        <h2 id="version-2-a-file-per-client">Version 2: A file per client</h2>
        <p>The only way to avoid conflicts is to always edit locally. So let’s give each client its own file!</p>
        <figure>
<img src="https://tonsky.me/blog/crdt-filesync/file_per_client.webp?t=1719240073" width="685" height="280">        </figure>
        <p>Now we just watch when files from other clients get changed and merge them with our own.</p>
        <p>And because each file is only edited on one machine, Dropbox will not report any conflicts. Any conflicts inside the data will be resolved by us via CRDT magic.</p>
        <h2 id="version-3-operations-based">Version 3: Operations-based</h2>
        <p>What if your CRDT is operation-based? Meaning, it’s easier to send operations around, not the whole state?</p>
        <p>You can always write operations into a separate append-only file. Again, each client only writes to its own, so no conflicts on the Dropbox level:</p>
        <figure>
<img src="https://tonsky.me/blog/crdt-filesync/ops.webp?t=1719240073" width="685" height="280">        </figure>
        <p>Now, the operations log can grow quite long, and we can’t count on Dropbox to reliably and efficiently sync only parts of the file that were updated.</p>
        <p>In that case, we split operations into chunks. Less work for Dropbox to sync and less for us to catch up:</p>
        <figure>
<img src="https://tonsky.me/blog/crdt-filesync/ops_batches.webp?t=1719240073" width="685" height="280">        </figure>
        <p>You can, of course, save the position in the file to only apply operations you haven’t seen. Basic stuff.</p>
        <p>Theoretically, you should be able to do operational transformations this way, too.</p>
        <h2 id="demo">Demo</h2>
        <p>A very simple proof-of-concept demo is at <a href="https://github.com/tonsky/crdt-filesync" target="_blank">github.com/tonsky/crdt-filesync</a>.</p>
        <p>Here’s a video of it in action:</p>
        <figure>
          <video autoplay="" muted="" loop="" preload="auto" playsinline="" controls="" width="720" height="721">
            <source src="https://tonsky.me/blog/crdt-filesync/demo.mp4?t=1719240073" type="video/mp4">
          </video>
        </figure>
        <p>Under the hood, it uses Automerge for merging text edits. So it’s a proper CRDT, not just two files merging text diffs.</p>
        <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
        <p>If you set out to build a local-first application that users have complete control and ownership over, you need something to solve data sync.</p>
        <p>Dropbox and other file-sync services, while very basic, offer enough to implement it in a simple but working way.</p>
        <p>Sure, it won’t be as real-time as a custom solution, but it’s still better for casual syncs. Think Apple Photos: only your own photos, not real-time, but you know they will be everywhere by the end of the day. And that’s good enough!</p>
        <p>Imagine if Obsidian Sync was just “put your files in the folder” and it would give you conflict-free sync? For free? Forever? Just bring your own cloud?</p>
        <p>I’d say it sounds pretty good.</p>
        
      </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Researchers invent 100% biodegradable 'barley plastic' (107 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://phys.org/news/2024-06-biodegradable-barley-plastic.html</link>
            <guid>40783777</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 02:34:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://phys.org/news/2024-06-biodegradable-barley-plastic.html">https://phys.org/news/2024-06-biodegradable-barley-plastic.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40783777">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
										
<div data-thumb="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2024/researchers-invent-100.jpg" data-src="https://scx2.b-cdn.net/gfx/news/hires/2024/researchers-invent-100.jpg" data-sub-html="Experiments on the degradation of different plastic materials. Top left is a common LDPE plastic film. Top center and right are the researchers' amylose-based bioplastic and a plastic made from corn starch, respectively. At the bottom are three different bags made from conventional bioplastics. A) shows the start of the experiment. B) shows the degradation after 8 days, C) the degradation after 11 days, D) 21 days E 41 days and F) shows the degradation after 54 days. Credit: Andreas Blennow">
        <figure>
            <img src="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/800a/2024/researchers-invent-100.jpg" alt="Researchers invent 100% biodegradable &quot;barley plastic&quot;" title="Experiments on the degradation of different plastic materials. Top left is a common LDPE plastic film. Top center and right are the researchers' amylose-based bioplastic and a plastic made from corn starch, respectively. At the bottom are three different bags made from conventional bioplastics. A) shows the start of the experiment. B) shows the degradation after 8 days, C) the degradation after 11 days, D) 21 days E 41 days and F) shows the degradation after 54 days. Credit: Andreas Blennow" width="800" height="423">
             <figcaption>
                Experiments on the degradation of different plastic materials. Top left is a common LDPE plastic film. Top center and right are the researchers' amylose-based bioplastic and a plastic made from corn starch, respectively. At the bottom are three different bags made from conventional bioplastics. A) shows the start of the experiment. B) shows the degradation after 8 days, C) the degradation after 11 days, D) 21 days E 41 days and F) shows the degradation after 54 days. Credit: Andreas Blennow
            </figcaption>        </figure>
    </div><p>A biofriendly new material made from barley starch blended with fiber from sugarbeet waste—a strong material that turns into compost should it end up in nature—has been created at the University of Copenhagen. In the long term, the researchers hope that their invention can help put the brakes on plastic pollution while reducing the climate footprint of plastic production.</p>


										      
																																	<p>Enormous islands of plastic float in our oceans and microscopic particles of it are in our bodies. The durability, malleability and low cost of plastics has made them ubiquitous, from packaging to clothing to aircraft parts. But plastics have a downside. Plastics contaminate nature, are tough to recycle and their production emits more CO<sub>2</sub> than all air traffic combined.</p>
<p>Now, researchers at the University of Copenhagen's Department of Plant and Environmental Sciences have invented a new material made from modified starch that can completely decompose in nature—and do so within only two months. The material is made using natural plant material from crops and could be used for food packaging, among many other things.</p>
<p>"We have an enormous problem with our plastic waste that recycling seems incapable of solving. Therefore, we've developed a new type of bioplastic that is stronger and can better withstand water than current bioplastics. At the same time, our material is 100% biodegradable and can be converted into compost by microorganisms if it ends up somewhere other than a bin," says Professor Andreas Blennow of the Department of Plant and Environmental Sciences.</p>
<p>Only about 9% of plastic is recycled globally, with the rest being either incinerated or winding up in nature or dumped into enormous plastic landfills.</p>
<p>Bioplastics already exist, but the name is misleading says Blennow. While today's bioplastics are made of bio-derived materials, only a limited part of them is actually degradable, and only under special conditions in industrial composting plants.</p>
<p>"I don't find the name suitable because the most common types of bioplastics don't break down that easily if tossed into nature. The process can take many years and some of it continues to pollute as microplastic. Specialized facilities are needed to break down bioplastics. And even then, a very limited part of them can be recycled, with the rest ending up as waste," says the researcher.</p>

																																						
																																			<h2>Starch from barley and sugar industry waste</h2>
<p>The new material is a so-called biocomposite and composed of several different substances that decompose naturally. Its main ingredients, amylose and cellulose, are common across the plant kingdom. Amylose is extracted from many crops including corn, potatoes, wheat and barley.</p>
<p>Together with researchers from Aarhus University, the research team founded a spinoff company in which they developed a barley variety that produces pure amylose in its kernels. This new variety is important because pure amylose is far less likely to turn into a paste when it interacts with water compared to regular starch.</p>
<p>Cellulose is a carbohydrate found in all plants and we know it from cotton and linen fibers, as well as from wood and paper products. The cellulose used by the researchers is a so-called nanocellulose made from local sugar industry waste. And these nanocellulose fibers, which are one thousand times smaller than the fibers of linen and cotton, are what contribute to the material's mechanical strength.</p>
<p>"Amylose and cellulose form long, strong molecular chains. Combining them has allowed us to create a durable, flexible material that has the potential to be used for shopping bags and the packaging of goods that we now wrap in plastic," says Blennow.</p>
<p>The new biomaterial is produced by either dissolving the raw materials in water and mixing them together or by heating them under pressure. By doing so, small "pellets" or chips are created that can then be processed and compressed into a desired form.</p>
<p>Thus far, the researchers have only produced prototypes in the laboratory. But according to Blennow, getting production started in Denmark and many other places in the world would be relatively easy.</p>
<p>"The entire production chain of amylose-rich starch already exists. Indeed, millions of tons of pure potato and corn starch are produced every year and used by the food industry and elsewhere. Therefore, easy access to the majority of our ingredients is guaranteed for the large-scale production of this material," he says.</p>

																																			<h2>Could reduce plastic problem</h2>
<p>Blennow and his fellow researchers are now processing a <a href="https://phys.org/tags/patent+application/" rel="tag">patent application</a> that, once it has been approved, could pave the way for production of the new biocomposite material. Because, despite the huge sums of money being devoted to sorting and recycling our plastic, the researcher does not believe that it will really be a success. Doing so should be seen as a transitional technology until we bid fossil-based plastics a final farewell.</p>
<p>"Recycling plastic efficiently is anything but straightforward. Different things in plastics must be separated from each other and there are major differences between plastic types, meaning that the process must be done in a safe way so that no contaminants end up in the <a href="https://phys.org/tags/recycled+plastic/" rel="tag">recycled plastic</a>.</p>
<p>"At the same time, countries and consumers must sort their plastic. This is a massive task that I don't see us succeeding at. Instead, we should rethink things in terms of utilizing new materials that perform like plastic, but don't pollute the planet," says Blennow.</p>
<p>The researcher is already collaborating with two Danish packaging companies to develop prototypes for food packaging, among other things. He envisions many other uses for the material as well, such as for the interior trims of cars by the automotive industry. Though it is difficult to say when this biofriendly barley-based plastic will reach the shelves, the researcher predicts that the <a href="https://phys.org/tags/new+material/" rel="tag">new material</a> may become a reality in the foreseeable future.</p>
<p>"It's quite close to the point where we can really start producing prototypes in collaboration with our research team and companies. I think it's realistic that different prototypes in soft and hard packaging, such as trays, bottles and bags, will be developed within one to five years," concludes Blennow.</p>

																																																					
																					
																					
                              										                                        
										<!-- print only -->
										<div>
											 <p><strong>Citation</strong>:
												Researchers invent 100% biodegradable 'barley plastic' (2024, June 18)
												retrieved 25 June 2024
												from https://phys.org/news/2024-06-biodegradable-barley-plastic.html
											 </p>
											 <p>
											 This document is subject to copyright. Apart from any fair dealing for the purpose of private study or research, no
											 part may be reproduced without the written permission. The content is provided for information purposes only.
											 </p>
										</div>
                                        
									</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[SIMD-accelerated computer vision on a $2 microcontroller (197 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://shraiwi.github.io/read.html?md=blog/simd-fast-esp32s3.md</link>
            <guid>40783598</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 02:10:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://shraiwi.github.io/read.html?md=blog/simd-fast-esp32s3.md">https://shraiwi.github.io/read.html?md=blog/simd-fast-esp32s3.md</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40783598">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Twonkie: A USB-PD sniffer/injector/sink based on Google's Twinkie open hardware (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/dojoe/Twonkie</link>
            <guid>40783485</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 01:55:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/dojoe/Twonkie">https://github.com/dojoe/Twonkie</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40783485">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Twonkie - a USB-PD sniffer based on Google's <a href="https://www.chromium.org/chromium-os/twinkie" rel="nofollow">Twinkie</a></h2><a id="user-content-twonkie---a-usb-pd-sniffer-based-on-googles-twinkie" aria-label="Permalink: Twonkie - a USB-PD sniffer based on Google's Twinkie" href="#twonkie---a-usb-pd-sniffer-based-on-googles-twinkie"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Twonkie is a USB-PD sniffer/injector/sink based on a Google project called Twinkie, re-engineered to be made in one-off quantities by mere mortals.</p>
<p dir="auto">Twinkie is a great and pretty low-cost solution, and it's open-source so anyone could make their own, but unfortunately the Twinkie design uses a six-layer PCB and all BGA/wafer-scale parts - both of which are usually unavailable to the humble hobbyist.</p>
<p dir="auto">So I designed the Twonkie, a slightly wonky sibling of Twinkie. It uses a four-layer PCB that can be manufactured cheaply by lots of services like OSHPark, and it makes a point to use only leaded parts for easier soldering (though the main microcontroller can optionally be QFN too via a dual footprint). The most difficult parts are likely the passives which are all 0402, and the USB-C connectors which are used in an unconventional way by misusing 90° upright connectors as 1.6mm straddle mounts (living up to the concept of being wonky).</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What does it look like?</h2><a id="user-content-what-does-it-look-like" aria-label="Permalink: What does it look like?" href="#what-does-it-look-like"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Lookie here!</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/dojoe/Twonkie/blob/master/pic/twonkie-v1.0-front.jpg"><img src="https://github.com/dojoe/Twonkie/raw/master/pic/twonkie-v1.0-front.jpg" alt=""></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/dojoe/Twonkie/blob/master/pic/twonkie-v1.0-back.jpg"><img src="https://github.com/dojoe/Twonkie/raw/master/pic/twonkie-v1.0-back.jpg" alt=""></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The PCB is exactly 1 inch squared, so $10 will get you three at OSHPark. In fact, let me take care of that for you:</p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://oshpark.com/shared_projects/VxczZuoj" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/f338b8120161187faf8c5055f87443870199b2b9b210582994217ead76bc1032/68747470733a2f2f6f73687061726b2e636f6d2f7061636b732f6d656469612f696d616765732f62616467652d35663465336266346266363866373266663838626439326530303839653963662e706e67" alt="Order from OSH Park" data-canonical-src="https://oshpark.com/packs/media/images/badge-5f4e3bf4bf68f72ff88bd92e0089e9cf.png"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><em>(Disclaimer: I am not affiliated with OSHPark, I just love their service to bits and they've been super helpful chaps time and time again.)</em></p>
<p dir="auto">The v1.0 and v2.0 Gerbers in this repo no longer need the botch wires around Q4 either, I'll update the photo as soon as I get the next board revision back.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What's changed compared to the original Twinkie?</h2><a id="user-content-whats-changed-compared-to-the-original-twinkie" aria-label="Permalink: What's changed compared to the original Twinkie?" href="#whats-changed-compared-to-the-original-twinkie"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>A bootloader button in addition to the USB_ID pin based bootloader selection.</li>
<li>Uses the INA237 part which supports the higher supply voltages of USB-PD Extended Power Range (EPR)</li>
<li>The microcontroller pins are rearranged for easier routing, so you'll need a different firmware. Binaries are provided and the firmware is easy to build from source.</li>
<li>The USB-C connectors are attached in a hair-raising straddle mount configuration. The way they're soldered to the PCB makes them rock solid though, maybe even more solid than the original Twinkie, and they transfer TB3 20Gbit/s lanes just fine.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">I see there's a v2.0 now - what's different?</h2><a id="user-content-i-see-theres-a-v20-now---whats-different" aria-label="Permalink: I see there's a v2.0 now - what's different?" href="#i-see-theres-a-v20-now---whats-different"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The 2.0 version uses a different voltage/current monitor chip compared to Twonkie v1.0, the <a href="https://github.com/dojoe/Twonkie/blob/master/ref/ina237.pdf">INA237</a>, which supports higher bus voltages and therefore makes the Twonkie hardware ready for Extended Power Range (EPR). The INA260 used by Twonkie v1.0 (and the INA231 used by Twinkie) will take damage if subjected to the up to 48V specified by EPR.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Sweet! How do I build my own?</h2><a id="user-content-sweet-how-do-i-build-my-own" aria-label="Permalink: Sweet! How do I build my own?" href="#sweet-how-do-i-build-my-own"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">I'm glad you asked! Get the board made via the OSH Park link above, or supply the v2.0 Gerbers in this repository to a PCB fab of your choice, get the parts from Digikey or Mouser or what have you, and follow the <a href="https://github.com/dojoe/Twonkie/blob/master/hw/README.md">Assembly instructions</a> to build the device. I recommend ordering a few extra parts: Get one more of each Type-C connector since you're going to modify them in ways that might end up with a broken connector, and generously round up the number of 0402 passives since you're going to drop some of them and you will <em>never</em> find them again :)</p>
<p dir="auto">For the firmware, there are <a href="https://github.com/dojoe/Twonkie/blob/master/fw/README.md">Instructions for building and flashing</a> in the <a href="https://github.com/dojoe/Twonkie/blob/master/fw">fw</a> directory.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">None of the parts are available 😭 What do I do?</h2><a id="user-content-none-of-the-parts-are-available--what-do-i-do" aria-label="Permalink: None of the parts are available 😭 What do I do?" href="#none-of-the-parts-are-available--what-do-i-do"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Here are some ideas about replacements for some parts that are most likely to be unavailable. None of these have been tested so you're on your own!</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>INA237:</strong> The INA237 is part of a device family and has two siblings with higher specs that TI claims are drop-in replacements: INA228 and INA238.</li>
<li><strong>STM32F072CB:</strong> For one, the Twonkie has a dual footprint that will fit both the TQFP and QFN variants, i.e. the STM32F072CBT and STM32F072CBU. And if you are willing to sacrifice the PD sink functionaliy and only need the sniffer functionality you could also try the variants with 64k flash instead of 128k (STM32F072C8*) and only flash the first half of the firmware binary. Other device families than the F072 would require extensive firmware changes so I can't recommend that.</li>
<li><strong>USB-C plug / receptacle:</strong> These might be a little trickier. Basically you need one that's meant for being mounted standing up on a board, has all USB-C pins wired out to L shaped pins and doesn't have any metal mounting prongs protruding into the board plane (or if it has you'll have to cut them off).</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">I am a noob trying to solder and replicate the Twonkie. Got any beginner tips?</h2><a id="user-content-i-am-a-noob-trying-to-solder-and-replicate-the-twonkie-got-any-beginner-tips" aria-label="Permalink: I am a noob trying to solder and replicate the Twonkie. Got any beginner tips?" href="#i-am-a-noob-trying-to-solder-and-replicate-the-twonkie-got-any-beginner-tips"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The KiCad schematic file contains the vendor part numbers and DigiKey order numbers for each part designator, and I exported the full list into a .csv file too - those are commonly called "Bill of materials" or BOM for short, and <a href="https://github.com/dojoe/Twonkie/blob/master/hw/v2.0/twonkie.bom.csv">this is the one for Twonkie 2.0</a>. You should be able to punch those part numbers into a parts supplier of your choice (I usually use <a href="https://digikey.com/" rel="nofollow">DigiKey</a> but there are plenty others) to find the parts you need. If they have parts in stock they'll happily sell you small quantities, though at an increased price. Take care to order more of most parts than you need - especially the tiny passives (resistors, capacitors...) are easy to lose during assembly.</p>
<p dir="auto">As for reading the schematic, it probably helps to have some familiarity with <a href="https://www.usb.org/document-library/usb-power-delivery" rel="nofollow">USB-PD</a> and the <a href="https://www.chromium.org/chromium-os/twinkie" rel="nofollow">original project description</a>, and then read up on the <a href="https://github.com/dojoe/Twonkie/blob/master/ref">device datasheets</a> to understand which part does what.</p>
<p dir="auto">Having said all that, please be warned that the Twonkie is not exactly a noob project - unless you're already familiar with hand-soldering fine pitch SMT parts you may be in for a frustrating experience. Don't let that keep you from trying, but you should know what you're signing up for :)</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">TODOs</h2><a id="user-content-todos" aria-label="Permalink: TODOs" href="#todos"></a></p>
<ul>
<li> Get Twinkie support upstreamed in sigrok/PulseView</li>
<li> v2.0 photos</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Similar projects</h2><a id="user-content-similar-projects" aria-label="Permalink: Similar projects" href="#similar-projects"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>As luck would have it, <a href="https://github.com/gregdavill">Greg Davill</a> started a project with the exact same goal at a very similar time, so there's now two of us :) <a href="https://github.com/gregdavill/PD-sniffer">https://github.com/gregdavill/PD-sniffer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/XenGi">XenGi</a> built a version of Twonkie v2.0 which uses a 0.8mm PCB and industry-standard straddle mount USB-C connectors. After <a href="https://github.com/dojoe/Twonkie/issues/10" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/dojoe/Twonkie/issues/10/hovercard">a bit of deliberation</a> I decided to stick with the 1.6mm PCB for stability and availability reasons but if you prefer a less haxxy way of attaching the connectors (and a 3D printed case!) feel free to check out his repo: <a href="https://gitlab.com/XenGi/Twonkie" rel="nofollow">https://gitlab.com/XenGi/Twonkie</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Licenses</h2><a id="user-content-licenses" aria-label="Permalink: Licenses" href="#licenses"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Hardware (as found in the <code>hw</code> subdirectory)</h2><a id="user-content-hardware-as-found-in-the-hw-subdirectory" aria-label="Permalink: Hardware (as found in the hw subdirectory)" href="#hardware-as-found-in-the-hw-subdirectory"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The hardware design of <a href="https://github.com/dojoe/Twonkie">Twonkie</a> by <a href="https://github.com/dojoe">Joachim "dojoe" Fenkes</a> is licensed under <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" rel="nofollow">CC BY 4.0<img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/9a94a9da920fb502de91699e841f6eec7eda7b02c7e2dcd770eb9dbb7083ea76/68747470733a2f2f6d6972726f72732e6372656174697665636f6d6d6f6e732e6f72672f70726573736b69742f69636f6e732f63632e737667" data-canonical-src="https://mirrors.creativecommons.org/presskit/icons/cc.svg"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/007437ca114fb64a0db48d5f06ee0f8d95242b8b9230af6c92fceb70fa234507/68747470733a2f2f6d6972726f72732e6372656174697665636f6d6d6f6e732e6f72672f70726573736b69742f69636f6e732f62792e737667" data-canonical-src="https://mirrors.creativecommons.org/presskit/icons/by.svg"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Firmware (as found in the <code>fw</code> subdirectory)</h2><a id="user-content-firmware-as-found-in-the-fw-subdirectory" aria-label="Permalink: Firmware (as found in the fw subdirectory)" href="#firmware-as-found-in-the-fw-subdirectory"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The source code for the Twonkie's firmware is licensed under the 3-clause BSD license, see <a href="https://github.com/dojoe/Twonkie/blob/master/fw/LICENSE">its LICENSE file</a>.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[From 0/10 to 8/10: Microsoft Puts Repair Front and Center (164 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ifixit.com/News/96998/from-0-10-to-8-10-microsoft-puts-repair-front-and-center</link>
            <guid>40783229</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 01:19:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.ifixit.com/News/96998/from-0-10-to-8-10-microsoft-puts-repair-front-and-center">https://www.ifixit.com/News/96998/from-0-10-to-8-10-microsoft-puts-repair-front-and-center</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40783229">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    
<p>Microsoft’s team of hardware wizards have spent the last couple of years practicing their Reparo spell and it’s really starting to show. And we’ve noticed, it’s hard not to. It wasn’t that long ago that the Surface team surprised us with a tablet that went from <a href="https://www.ifixit.com/Teardown/Microsoft+Surface+Pro+Teardown/12842">1/10 in 2013</a> to<a href="https://www.ifixit.com/News/68671/does-the-surface-pro-9-mark-a-turning-point-for-repairability-at-microsoft"> a stunning 7/10</a> in 2022. Needless to say, the new CoPilot+ devices definitely warranted a check in to see how repair was fairing over at Microsoft.</p>



<p>We weren’t disappointed.</p>



<figure><p>
<iframe title="Surface Pro 11 &amp; Surface Laptop 7 Teardowns - Repairable, AI Powered Devices!!!" width="456" height="257" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Eg7KXJQ0p00?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</p></figure>



<p>This time around we decided to take a look at both Surface Pro and Surface Laptop devices. The first time we tore down a Surface Laptop it received an <a href="https://www.ifixit.com/Teardown/Microsoft+Surface+Laptop+Teardown/92915">abysmal 0/10</a>. Some claimed the score was too harsh, our Teardown Engineers thought it wasn’t harsh enough.</p>



<figure><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1600" height="1067" src="https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164539/Surface-Laptop-1.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164539/Surface-Laptop-1.jpg 1600w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164539/Surface-Laptop-1-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164539/Surface-Laptop-1-1350x900.jpg 1350w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164539/Surface-Laptop-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164539/Surface-Laptop-1-600x400.jpg 600w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164539/Surface-Laptop-1-1200x800.jpg 1200w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164539/Surface-Laptop-1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164539/Surface-Laptop-1-324x216.jpg 324w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164539/Surface-Laptop-1-450x300.jpg 450w" sizes="(max-width: 1600px) 100vw, 1600px"><figcaption><em>You’re asking for a 0/10 if we have to cut our way to the battery</em></figcaption></figure>



<h2>Surface Laptop 7</h2>



<p>The Surface Laptop 7 is an astonishingly repair friendly device, almost the antithesis of the original Surface Laptop. It’s no Framework 13, but it clearly draws inspiration from it.</p>



<p>One of the first things you’ll see when removing the magnetically secured bottom plate is a QR code taking you to the service manuals on Microsoft’s website. The manuals were made available the very day the device was released, something we rarely see in any product category.</p>



<p>The next things you’ll notice are tiny symbols (Microsoft calls them Wayfinders) indicating which component is being secured by the type and quantity of screws. You could easily disassemble this device without using the manual thanks to these Wayfinders.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" width="3585" height="2390" src="https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164657/wayfinders.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164657/wayfinders.jpg 3585w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164657/wayfinders-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164657/wayfinders-2048x1365.jpg 2048w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164657/wayfinders-1350x900.jpg 1350w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164657/wayfinders-300x200.jpg 300w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164657/wayfinders-600x400.jpg 600w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164657/wayfinders-1200x800.jpg 1200w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164657/wayfinders-768x512.jpg 768w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164657/wayfinders-324x216.jpg 324w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164657/wayfinders-450x300.jpg 450w" sizes="(max-width: 3585px) 100vw, 3585px"><figcaption>The battery is secured by eight 5IP Torx screws.</figcaption></figure>



<p>A special mention should be made of how most components are accessible without the need to remove additional layers. Need to replace the battery? No problem, it’s just a few screws and a bracket. What if you need to clean the fan? Easy. Just peel back the Surflink cable and undo three screws.</p>



<p>This might seem small to some but it shouldn’t be taken for granted. Take the MSI GS65, a laptop that had its fair share of fan failures. You have to remove <a href="https://www.ifixit.com/Guide/MSI+GS65+Stealth+Thin+8RE+Fan++Assembly++Replacement/130584">the entire motherboard and thermal management system</a> just to replace a wonky fan!</p>



<h2>Surface Pro 11</h2>



<p>Thankfully the Surface Pro 11 also contained many of the same repairability improvements. A tablet PC will inherently be more difficult to repair when compared to a laptop, purely because the screen removal process can feel a bit hairy.</p>



<p>But if we consider it as its own distinct category of device—comparing it relative to other tablet-like devices and not laptops, which we do in our scoring process—the Surface Pro holds up well for repairability.</p>



<p>As with past generation Surface Pro’s, we have access to the M.2 drive via a small magnetic cover underneath the kickstand. Access to anything else requires some disassembly. With the screen off, we find QR codes and Wayfinder markers to aid in the disassembly process.</p>



<p>There are more layers of components, which is to be expected when you have half the space to work with. The Surflink cable and the thermal management system need to be removed before we can remove the battery. But all in all, the process isn’t too onerous, especially with manuals to hand.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="7360" height="4906" src="https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21170600/Surface-thermals-out2-1.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21170600/Surface-thermals-out2-1.jpg 7360w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21170600/Surface-thermals-out2-1-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21170600/Surface-thermals-out2-1-2048x1365.jpg 2048w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21170600/Surface-thermals-out2-1-1350x900.jpg 1350w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21170600/Surface-thermals-out2-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21170600/Surface-thermals-out2-1-600x400.jpg 600w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21170600/Surface-thermals-out2-1-1200x800.jpg 1200w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21170600/Surface-thermals-out2-1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21170600/Surface-thermals-out2-1-324x216.jpg 324w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21170600/Surface-thermals-out2-1-450x300.jpg 450w" sizes="(max-width: 7360px) 100vw, 7360px"><figcaption>The battery isn’t too difficult to retrieve and is held in place by screws. Not a drop of glue in sight.</figcaption></figure>



<p>A note on that Surflink cable, the two screws holding the port in place are non-magnetic. It’s such a small detail but it will be appreciated by anyone who’s ever had to reassemble a magnetic component while dealing with the frustration of having to hold a screw in place with tweezers to prevent it from flying towards the magnet right next to it.</p>



<p>Overall, we were extremely pleased with Microsoft’s continued commitment to repairability. The Surface line of devices have performed such a stunning and swift U-turn from unrepairable to very repairable that we can’t help but be impressed, even if they don’t score a perfect 10/10.</p>



<figure>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="600" height="400" data-id="97003" src="https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164940/Surface-Interior-600x400.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164940/Surface-Interior-600x400.jpg 600w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164940/Surface-Interior-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164940/Surface-Interior-2048x1365.jpg 2048w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164940/Surface-Interior-1350x900.jpg 1350w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164940/Surface-Interior-300x200.jpg 300w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164940/Surface-Interior-1200x800.jpg 1200w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164940/Surface-Interior-768x512.jpg 768w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164940/Surface-Interior-324x216.jpg 324w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164940/Surface-Interior-450x300.jpg 450w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px"></figure>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="600" height="400" data-id="97002" src="https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164938/laptop-interior-600x400.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164938/laptop-interior-600x400.jpg 600w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164938/laptop-interior-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164938/laptop-interior-2048x1365.jpg 2048w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164938/laptop-interior-1350x900.jpg 1350w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164938/laptop-interior-300x200.jpg 300w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164938/laptop-interior-1200x800.jpg 1200w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164938/laptop-interior-768x512.jpg 768w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164938/laptop-interior-324x216.jpg 324w, https://valkyrie.cdn.ifixit.com/media/2024/06/21164938/laptop-interior-450x300.jpg 450w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px"></figure>
</figure>



<p>Speaking of which, after careful consideration and much lively debating, we decided to award both the Surface Laptop 7 and Surface Pro 11 an 8/10 for repairability in their respective device categories. </p>



<p>Microsoft’s journey from the unrepairable Surface Laptop to the highly repairable devices on our teardown table should drive home the importance of designing for repair. The ability to create a repairable Surface was always there but the impetus to design for repairable was missing. I’ll take that as a sign that Right to Repair advocacy and legislation has begun to bear fruit.&nbsp;</p>



<p><em>You can find chip ID information for the </em><a href="https://www.ifixit.com/Device/Microsoft_Surface_Laptop_7"><em>Surface Laptop 7</em></a><em> and </em><a href="https://www.ifixit.com/Device/Microsoft_Surface_Pro_11"><em>Surface Pro 11</em></a><em> on their respective guide pages once they’re available.</em></p>
    
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Denver gave homeless people $1k/mth. Year later, nearly half had housing (112 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.businessinsider.com/denver-basic-income-reduces-homelessness-food-insecurity-housing-ubi-gbi-2024-6</link>
            <guid>40783158</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 01:10:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/denver-basic-income-reduces-homelessness-food-insecurity-housing-ubi-gbi-2024-6">https://www.businessinsider.com/denver-basic-income-reduces-homelessness-food-insecurity-housing-ubi-gbi-2024-6</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40783158">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>Jarun Laws lived in his car in a restaurant parking lot near downtown Denver. <a target="_blank" href="https://www.businessinsider.com/denver-guaranteed-basic-income-gbi-ubi-housing-security-homeless-rent-2024-2" data-analytics-product-module="body_link" rel="">He worked there as a cook</a><strong> </strong>until 2020, and had only $400 a month left after paying bills and child support. That was barely enough to cover his car payments and child support — and not even close to what he would need for rent.</p><p>The 51-year-old<strong> </strong>occasionally spent part of his paycheck on weekend stays at a cheap hotel, where he could spend time with his children. He struggled to afford food, clothes, and medicine — and he had been experiencing homelessness for nearly a decade.</p><div><p>That changed when Laws enrolled in <a target="_blank" href="https://www.businessinsider.com/ubi-cash-payments-reduced-homelessness-increased-employment-denver-2023-10" data-analytics-product-module="body_link" rel="">The Denver Basic Income Project</a>. The pilot program allowed Laws to secure a temporary apartment with furniture, spend more time with his children, and find a better-paying job.</p><p>"I had questioned myself: if I was going to be a good father to my children because I was suffering," Laws previously told Business Insider. "When I got accepted, it changed my life."</p><p>Denver's basic income pilot — which first started payments in fall 2022 — focused on over 800 Coloradans experiencing homelessness, including people living in cars, temporary shelters, the outdoors, or other non-fixed living situations. Participants like Laws were given direct cash payments, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.businessinsider.com/which-states-cities-have-guaranteed-basic-income-programs-low-income-2024-4" data-analytics-product-module="body_link" rel="">no strings attached</a>, and could spend the money on whatever they needed.</p><p>Denver released the project's one-year report on<strong> </strong>June 18, showing that 45% of participants secured their own house or apartment after receiving basic income for 10 months. They also experienced fewer emergency room visits, nights spent in a hospital or a temporary shelter, and jail stays. The report estimates that this reduction in public service use saved the city $589,214.</p><p>Denver's program initially lasted one year and was <a target="_blank" href="https://www.businessinsider.com/denver-basic-income-project-ubi-extended-homelessness-poverty-2024-1" data-analytics-product-module="body_link" rel="">extended in January for another six months</a>. Participants were sorted into random groups: one received $1,000 a month for a year; another got $6,500 upfront, followed by $500 a month; and a third got $50 a month as a control group.</p><p>The city of Denver, the Colorado Trust, and an anonymous foundation funded the project and has already provided more than $9.4 million to participants.</p><p>Basic income programs like Denver's have become <a target="_blank" href="https://www.businessinsider.com/basic-income-gbi-ubi-low-income-americans-afford-housing-food-2024-5" data-analytics-product-module="body_link" rel="">a popular strategy to reduce poverty</a> in US cities. Compared to traditional social services like <a target="_blank" href="https://www.businessinsider.com/buying-groceries-snap-food-stamps-cant-afford-essentials-credit-card-2024-6" data-analytics-product-module="body_link" rel="">SNAP</a> or Medicaid, basic income allows participants to spend the money where they need it most.</p><p>"What is fundamentally different about our approach is the way that we start from a place of trust," Mark Donovan, the project founder and executive director, said at a Tuesday press conference.</p><h2 id="1b74210a-b49a-428b-aa18-dbe9189f9abd" data-toc-id="1b74210a-b49a-428b-aa18-dbe9189f9abd"><strong>Denver's basic income project helped participants secure housing and jobs</strong></h2><p>Denver's report found that basic income primarily helped participants pay for immediate expenses — like transportation, hygiene, clothes, and groceries. <a target="_blank" href="https://www.businessinsider.com/chicago-basic-income-helped-mother-rent-an-apartment-ubi-gbi2024-5?mrfhud=true" data-analytics-product-module="body_link" rel="">Affording recurring bills like rent</a>, healthcare, or debt payments was also a top priority for most families. Participants in each payment group reported increased financial stability and reduced reliance on emergency financial assistance programs.</p><p>Basic income puts low-income families on "an equal playing field," Nick Pacheco, participant engagement coordinator, said at a press conference. He said the cash payments also help participants get the training and resources they need to establish careers.</p><p>Individuals who received the lump sum or $1,000 a month payments were more likely to find a stable, full-time job than before they received basic income.</p><p>"It's freedom," Pacheco said. "It's freedom from poverty and not being able to reach your goals."</p><p>Participating households also experienced improved mental health and could spend more time with family and friends. Parents were able to <a target="_blank" href="https://www.businessinsider.com/san-antonio-ubi-guaranteed-basic-income-housing-finances-austin-rent-2024-3" data-analytics-product-module="body_link" rel="">better support their children and grandchildren</a>.</p><section data-component-type="content-recommendations" data-component-location="in-content" data-delay-third-party-scripts="true" data-provider="dad" data-excluded-verticals="bi-video" data-premium-state="" data-renderer="three-related-posts" data-size="3" data-container-position="" data-container-name="content-recommendations-three-related-posts-in-content" data-theme-class="default" data-recommendations-placement="" data-author="" data-root-margin="250px 0px" data-track-view="{&quot;event&quot;:&quot;module_in_view&quot;,&quot;eventCategory&quot;:&quot;in_content_recirc&quot;,&quot;eventAction&quot;:&quot;module_in_view&quot;,&quot;eventLabel&quot;:&quot;module_in_view&quot;,&quot;element_name&quot;:&quot;in_content_recirc&quot;,&quot;subscription_experience&quot;:&quot;bi_value_unassigned&quot;,&quot;product_field&quot;:&quot;bi_value_unassigned&quot;}">
                            <p>
                                Related stories
                              </p>
                        
                          
                        </section><p>These results echo those from the six-month report, which found fewer participants were sleeping on the street, experiencing food insecurity, and feeling unsafe.</p><p>Still, participants' financial outcomes varied based on their payment group. Participants who received the lump sum $6,500 payment in addition to $500 a month could better build savings and make major life changes like signing a new lease or buying a car.</p><p>Many families told researchers that they're <a target="_blank" href="https://www.businessinsider.com/universal-basic-income-emergency-cash-rent-homes-government-housing-aid-2024-1" data-analytics-product-module="body_link" rel="">anxious about paying bills</a> after the basic income payments end. Some worry they could lose their housing again.</p><p><a target="_blank" href="https://www.businessinsider.com/denver-guaranteed-basic-income-gbi-ubi-housing-security-homeless-rent-2024-2" data-analytics-product-module="body_link" rel="">Laws</a>, for example, had to go back to living in his car after his payments stopped.</p><h2 id="7877e820-05ba-4c6f-8ba2-27c9786dd3e7" data-toc-id="7877e820-05ba-4c6f-8ba2-27c9786dd3e7"><strong>Being able to pay bills alleviated participants' financial stress</strong></h2><p>Denver participants have told BI that basic income was the financial safety net they needed.</p><p>Moriah Rodriguez, 38, was working as a youth developer for Denver Public Schools when she got hit by a car and suffered a traumatic brain injury. She lived in public housing with her kids, all of whom have intellectual disabilities, though they were displaced shortly after.</p><p>She received monthly Social Security payments, just enough to care for her kids. While staying with a friend, she learned about the pilot program.</p><p>Rodriguez used the payments to fix her truck, transport her kids to school and work, buy new clothing, and secure a lifelong public housing voucher. She also used some of the money to pay $400 for rent, $500 on gas, $100 on hygiene, and $100 on her credit card bill. In addition to returning to school to get her GED, she brought her credit score into the 700s.</p><p>"The program gave me more time to focus on their education and their mental health," Rodriguez said, referring to her children, and added that the program's extension was another lifeline. "I had the space to get them tested and get them diagnosed and connected with the support they need."</p><p>Similarly, Dia Broncucia, 53, and Justin Searls, 45, could also afford essentials like an apartment, a new car, and mental health resources through basic income. They had previously lived in a temporary shelter but could secure a studio apartment for $1,300 a month, along with clothing, hygiene products, and furniture.</p><p><a target="_blank" href="https://www.businessinsider.com/universal-basic-income-ubi-denver-participants-turn-their-lives-around-2023-10" data-analytics-product-module="body_link" rel="">Broncucia and Searls said last October</a> that though they had some uncertainties about their future, they felt much stronger and less stressed because of basic income.</p><p>"Starting with nothing and then being able to receive a lump sum of money and then get our payments once a month is why we were able to get on track and stay on track," Broncucia previously told BI.</p><h2 id="fcf290b8-de5d-44fd-9e88-4430ad78df2a" data-toc-id="fcf290b8-de5d-44fd-9e88-4430ad78df2a">Basic income pilots can provide poverty solutions</h2><p>As the basic income pilot<strong> </strong>continues to be successful in cities like Denver, local leaders and economic security experts are looking to translate pilots into policy. States like California and <a target="_blank" href="https://www.businessinsider.com/immigrants-new-mexico-basic-income-for-housing-healthcare-ubi-gbi2024-5#:~:text=New%20Mexico's%20basic%20income%20pilot,and%20education%20outcomes%20for%20participants." data-analytics-product-module="body_link" rel="">New Mexico </a>are already <a target="_blank" href="https://www.businessinsider.com/basic-income-gbi-ubi-low-income-americans-afford-housing-food-2024-5" data-analytics-product-module="body_link" rel="">proposing basic income programs</a> in the state legislature.</p><p>"The lessons from those pilots are infusing the whole ecosystem of support," Teri Olle, director for Economic Security California, a branch of the nonprofit Economic Security Project, previously told BI. "People are really seeing the power of those pilots, and the power of giving people money and trusting them."</p><p>Denver leaders also hope to extend the city's basic income for a third year. The project is currently raising the millions of dollars necessary to continue efforts in Colorado.</p><p>Donovan said he's paying close attention to results from basic income programs across the country. It's a "really exciting time in the movement," he said.</p><p>"If we're able to move people into housing and out of homelessness at a lower cost and generate better long-term outcomes, why wouldn't we try to expand and build upon that?" Donovan said.</p><p><em>Have you benefited from a guaranteed basic income program? Are you willing to share how you spent the money? Reach out to these reporters at </em><a target="_blank" href="mailto:allisonkelly@businessinsider.com" data-analytics-product-module="body_link" rel=" nofollow"><em><u>allisonkelly@businessinsider.com</u></em></a><em> and </em><a target="_blank" href="mailto:nsheidlower@businessinsider.com" data-analytics-product-module="body_link" rel=" nofollow"><em>nsheidlower@businessinsider.com</em></a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Language models on the command line (117 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/</link>
            <guid>40782755</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 00:18:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/">https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40782755">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-permalink-context="/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/">

<p>17th June 2024</p>

<p>I gave a talk about accessing Large Language Models from the command-line last week as part of the <a href="https://maven.com/parlance-labs/fine-tuning">Mastering LLMs: A Conference For Developers &amp; Data Scientists</a> six week long online conference. The talk focused on my <a href="https://llm.datasette.io/">LLM</a> Python command-line utility and ways you can use it (and <a href="https://llm.datasette.io/en/stable/plugins/index.html">its plugins</a>) to explore LLMs and use them for useful tasks.</p>

<p>The talk was recorded and is available <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QUXQNi6jQ30">on YouTube</a>. Here I’ve turned it into an <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/annotatedtalks/">annotated presentation</a>, with detailed notes and screenshots (there were no slides) to accompany the video.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/QUXQNi6jQ30" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"> </iframe>

  <p><a href="https://llm.datasette.io/">LLM</a> is a tool I started building last year to help run LLM prompts directly from a command-line terminal. Instructions for installing it <a href="https://llm.datasette.io/en/stable/setup.html">are here</a>—you can use <code>pipx install llm</code> or <code>pip install llm</code> or <code>brew install llm</code>.</p>

<div id="frame_000003.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_000003.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_000003.jpg" alt="The LLM website"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_000003.jpg">#</a></p><p>Once installed you can use it with OpenAI models by running <code>llm keys set openai</code> and pasting in your OpenAI key—or <a href="https://llm.datasette.io/en/stable/plugins/directory.html#plugin-directory">install plugins</a> to use models by other providers, including models you can run locally.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_000259.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_000259.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_000259.jpg" alt="$ llm 'five great names for a pet pelican' Sure, here are five great names for a pet pelican: 1. **Splash** 2. **Captain Beak** 3. **Seabreeze** 4. **Marina** 5. **Pelicano** These names incorporate elements of the pelican's natural habitat and distinctive features, adding a fun and fitting touch for your feathered friend!"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_000259.jpg">#</a></p><p>Basic usage is very simple: once you’ve configured your OpenAI key, you can run prompts against their models like this:</p>
<pre><code>llm 'five great names for a pet pelican'
</code></pre>
<p>The output will stream to your terminal, or you can redirect it to a file like this:</p>
<pre><code>llm 'five great names for a pet pelican' &gt; pelicans.txt
</code></pre>
</div>
<div id="frame_000341.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_000341.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_000341.jpg" alt="$ llm -c 'now do walruses' Of course, here are five fitting names for a pet walrus: 1. **Whiskers** 2. **Tusk** 3. **Gustav** 4. **Blubber** 5. **Wally**  $ llm -c 'justify those!'  Certainly! Here's why each name suits a pet walrus: 1. **Whiskers** - **Justification:** Walruses have distinctive, prominent whiskers (vibrissae) that the y use to detect food on the ocean floor. This name highlights one of their most characteristic features. 2. **Tusk** - **Justification:** Walruses are known for their long, formidable tusks, which they use for various purposes"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_000341.jpg">#</a></p><p>You can use the <code>-c</code> (for continue) option to send follow-up prompts as part of the same ongoing conversation:</p>
<pre><code>llm -c 'now do walruses'
# ...
llm -c justify those!'
</code></pre>
</div>
<div id="frame_000506.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_000506.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_000506.jpg" alt="Screenshot of the list of Remote APIs plugins in the LLM plugins directory."></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_000506.jpg">#</a></p><p>LLM supports additional models via plugins. These are listed in the <a href="https://llm.datasette.io/en/stable/plugins/directory.html">LLM plugins directory</a>, with dozens of plugins for both remote API-hosted models as well as models you can run directly on your own computer.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_000704.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_000704.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_000704.jpg" alt="$ llm models Outputs a list of OpenAI models followed by several anthropic models.  $ llm -m claude-3-haiku-20240307 'say hi in spanish with a flourish' ¡Hola, mi amigo! 🌟"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_000704.jpg">#</a></p><p>Here I’m using the <a href="https://github.com/simonw/llm-claude-3">llm-claude-3</a> plugin, which provides access to the Anthropic <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/claude-3-family">Claude 3 family</a> of models.</p>
<p>I really like these models. Claude 3 Opus is about equivalent to GPT-4o in terms of quality. Claude 3 Haiku is both cheaper and better than GPT-3.5, and can handle 100,000 input tokens including images.</p>
<pre><code>llm install llm-claude-3
llm keys set claude
# &lt;Paste key here&gt;
# Now list available models
llm models
# Then run a prompt
llm -m claude-3-haiku-20240307 'say hi in spanish with a flourish'
# Or use the haiku alias
llm -m haiku 'say hi in spanish with a flourish'
</code></pre>
</div>
<div id="frame_000818.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_000818.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_000818.jpg" alt="$ llm logs path /Users/simon/Library/Application Support/io.datasette.llm/logs.db  $ datasette &quot;$(llm logs path)&quot; ... Uvicorn running on http://127.0.0.1:8000 (Press CTRL+C to quit)"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_000818.jpg">#</a></p><p>Every prompt and response run through the LLM tool is permanently logged to a SQLite database, <a href="https://llm.datasette.io/en/stable/logging.html">as described here</a>.</p>
<p>This command shows the path to that database:</p>
<pre><code>llm logs path
</code></pre>
<p>If you install <a href="https://datasette.io/">Datasette</a> you can use it to browse your SQLite database like this, using a terminal trick where the output of one command is passed to another (with double quotes to avoid any problems caused by the space in the directory name):</p>
<pre><code>datasette "$(llm logs path)"
</code></pre>
</div>
<div id="frame_000832.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_000832.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_000832.jpg" alt="Datasette showing the 2,434 responses I have logged as a table, with a search interface at the top."></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_000832.jpg">#</a></p><p>Here’s my searchable database of 2,434 responses I’ve logged from using LLM on my laptop, running in Datasette.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_000853.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_000853.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_000853.jpg" alt="Datasette screenshot showing a conversation, with 3 linked responses"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_000853.jpg">#</a></p><p>Earlier we ran a prompt and then sent two follow-up prompts to it using the <code>llm -c</code> option. Those are stored in the database as three responses that are part of the same conversation.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_000924.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_000924.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_000924.jpg" alt="This data as json, copyable, CSV (advanced)  Suggested facets: datetime_utc (date)  model >30  - gpt-3.5-turbo 383 - claude-3-opus-20240229 334 - gpt-4 233 - gpt-4-1106-preview 134 - claude-2 117 - mic-chat-Llama-2-7b-chat-hf-q 4f16 1 93 - mistral-7b-instruct-vo 78 - mic-chat-Llama-2-13b-chat-hf- 94f16 1 74 - claude-3-haiku-20240307 49 - gpt-3.5-turbo-instruct 49 - gpt-40 37 - mic-chat-Mistral-7B-Instruct-v 0.2-q3f16 1 35 - Phi-3-mini-4k-instruct 33 - gemini-pro 33 - gemini-1.5-pro-latest 32 - gguf 28 - gpt-4-turbo-preview 27 - gpt-3.5-turbo-16k 26 - mistral-medium 26 - llama-2-7b-chat.ggmlv3.g8 0 2 - mistral-tiny 23 - Meta-Llama-3-8B-Instruct 21 - llamafile 21 - llama-2-13b.Q8 0 20 - orca-mini-3b 19 - command-r 14 - llama-2-7b.ggmlv3.8 0 14 - mistral-small 14 - mistral-7b-instruct-v0.1.08 0 1 3 - claude 12"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_000924.jpg">#</a></p><p>Datasette supports facets, which provide a quick overview of unique value counts within the data. I’ve used GPT-3.5 turbo 383 times, Claude 3 Opus 334 times and a whole bunch of other models.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_000940.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_000940.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_000940.jpg" alt="6 rows where search matches &quot;pelican&quot; and model = &quot;claude-3-opus-20240229&quot; sorted by id descending"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_000940.jpg">#</a></p><p>Datasette provides search and filtering too—here are the prompts I’ve run against Claude 3 Opus that match “pelican”.</p>
<p>I have an experimental feature that lets me pass images to some models using the <code>-i filename.png</code> option. More on that <a href="https://github.com/simonw/llm/issues/331">in this issue</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/simonw/llm-cmd">llm-cmd</a> is an example of a plugin that adds an extra sub-command to LLM—in this case one that takes a description of a task and turns that into a pre-populated shell command. I wrote more about that in <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Mar/26/llm-cmd/">llm cmd undo last git commit—a new plugin for LLM</a>.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_001335.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_001335.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_001335.jpg" alt="Screenshot of the GPT4All website: A free-to-use, locally running, privacy-aware chatbot. No GPU or internet required."></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_001335.jpg">#</a></p><p>There are plenty of ways to run local models using LLM. One of my favourite is with the <a href="https://github.com/simonw/llm-gpt4all">llm-gpt4all</a> plugin, which builds on top of the excellent <a href="https://gpt4all.io/index.html">GPT4All</a> Python library by Nomic AI.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_001450.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_001450.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_001450.jpg" alt="$ llm -m mistral-7b-instruct-v@ 'five great names for a pet seagull, with explanations' =3 1. &quot;Sally&quot; - This name is perfect for a pet seagull because it's short and easy to remember, yet still has a charming and friendly vibe. It also evokes images of a playful and adventuro us bird that loves to explore the world around her. 2. &quot;Captain Jack&quot; - For any seafaring seagull who loves adventure and exploration, this name is perfect. Captain Jack suggests a sense of independence and leadership, which could be fitt ing for a bird who enjoys flying high and exploring new places. 3. &quot;Scarlett&quot; - This name is bold and eye-catching, much like the vibrant feathers of a seagull. Scarlett also has a fiery energy that could reflect the spirit of your adventurous pet. 4. &quot;Nautica&quot; - Nautica means &quot;sailor&quot; in Latin, making it an excellent choice for a seagull  Activity Monitor is also visible, showing a Python process using 350MB of RAM."></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_001450.jpg">#</a></p><p>To install that plugin:</p>
<pre><code>llm install llm-gpt4all
</code></pre>
<p>Then <code>llm models</code> to list the new models. Each model will be downloaded the first time you try running a prompt through it.</p>
<p>I used this to run Mistral-7B Instruct—an extremely high quality small (~4GB) model:</p>
<pre><code>llm -m mistral-7b-instruct-v0 'five great names for a pet seagull, with explanations'
</code></pre>
<p>You can run Activity Monitory to see the resources the model is using.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_001544.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_001544.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_001544.jpg" alt="$ llm chat -m mistral-7b-instruct-v0 Chatting with mistral-7b-instruct-v@ Type 'exit' or 'quit' to exit Type '!multi' to enter multiple lines, then '!end' to finish > say hello in spanish  Hola! How can I assist you today? > now in french Bonjour! Comment puis-je vous aider aujourd'hui?"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_001544.jpg">#</a></p><p>Running prompts like this is inefficient, because it loads the full model into memory, runs the prompt and then shuts down the program again.</p>
<p>Instead, you can use the <code>llm chat</code> command which keeps the model in memory across multiple prompts:</p>
<pre><code>llm chat -m mistral-7b-instruct-v0
</code></pre>
<p>Another option is to run <a href="https://ollama.com/">Ollama</a>, which runs its own local server hosting models. The <a href="https://github.com/taketwo/llm-ollama">llm-ollama</a> plugin can then be used to run prompts through Ollama from LLM.</p>
</div>

<div id="frame_002521.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_002521.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_002521.jpg" alt="Screenshot of a browser window titled llama.cpp showing a photograph  User: Describe image  Llama: The image features a person sitting in a chair next to an outdoor setting with a rooster nearby. A white bowl filled with eggs is placed on the ground, and it appears that the person may be preparing or collecting them from their backyard chicken coop. There are several other birds scattered around the scene as well, adding more life to this"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_002521.jpg">#</a></p><p>Running <a href="https://llava-vl.github.io/">LLaVA</a> using a Llamafile is particularly fun—it’s an openly licensed model that can accept images as input as well. It’s pretty amazing the results you can get from that, running as a single binary on your laptop.</p>
<p>Grab that from <a href="https://huggingface.co/Mozilla/llava-v1.5-7b-llamafile">Mozilla/llava-v1.5-7b-llamafile</a> on Hugging Face.</p>
<p>LLM can talk to Llamafile instances via the <a href="https://github.com/simonw/llm-llamafile">llm-llamafile</a> plugin.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_002636.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_002636.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_002636.jpg" alt="#!/bin/bash  # Validate that the first argument is an integer if [[ ! $1 =~ ^[0-9]+$ ]]; then   echo &quot;Please provide a valid integer as the first argument.&quot;   exit 1 fi  id=&quot;$1&quot;  # Parse the optional -m argument model=&quot;haiku&quot; if [[ $2 == &quot;-m&quot; &amp;&amp; -n $3 ]]; then   model=&quot;$3&quot; fi  # Make API call, parse and summarize the discussion curl -s &quot;https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/items/$id&quot; | \   jq -r 'recurse(.children[]) | .author + &quot;: &quot; + .text' | \   llm -m &quot;$model&quot; -s 'Summarize the themes of the opinions expressed here.   For each theme, output a markdown header.   Include direct &quot;quotations&quot; (with author attribution) where appropriate.   You MUST quote directly from users when crediting them, with double quotes.   Fix HTML entities. Output markdown. Go long.'"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_002636.jpg">#</a></p><p>Now that we can run prompts from our terminal, we can start assembling software by writing scripts.</p>
<p>Here’s a Bash script I wrote to summarize conversations on Hacker News, using longer context models such as Claude 3 Haiku or Google Gemini 1.5 or GPT-4o.</p>
<p>I wrote more about this in <a href="https://til.simonwillison.net/llms/claude-hacker-news-themes">Summarizing Hacker News discussion themes with Claude and LLM</a>.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_002850.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_002850.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_002850.jpg" alt="$ hn-summary.sh 40651054 -m 4o  # Dependency and Linking in Software Distribution Several users discussed issues around dependency management and linking in software distribut ion: ### Stability and Compatibility Issues - **e63f67dd-@65b:** &quot;It’s just a classic dependency issue... a combination of ABI instabilit y and just plain version incompatibility from one distro to the next... My opinion is the opp osite: I think the old paradigm of distros managing a giant set of system libraries is a bad one.&quot; —| - **umanwizard:** &quot;Some distros do actually break out rust dependencies into separate package s (e.g. Guix does this).&quot; ### Dynamic vs Static Linking - **jiripospisil:** &quot;Until there's a vulnerability in one of the dependencies and now you hav e to rebuild all of the packages which use it... For Rust, there's also the fact that most pr ojects use a lock file.&quot; - **pglata:** &quot;Static linking is essentially easier for people who don't want to care. But ig noring security does not mean it solves it"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_002850.jpg">#</a></p><p>The script works by hitting the Hacker News Algolia API to return the full, nested JSON structure of the conversation (e.g. <a href="https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/items/40651054">this JSON endpoint</a> for <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40651054">this conversation</a>), then runs that through <code>jq</code> to turn it into text, then pipes that into a model using LLM.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_003325.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_003325.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_003325.jpg" alt="Tutorial: Writing a plugin to support a new model  This tutorial will walk you through developing a new plugin for LLM that adds support for a new Large Language Model.  We will be developing a plugin that implements a simple Markov chain to generate words based on an input string..."></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_003325.jpg">#</a></p><p>If you want to contribute to LLM itself, a great way to do that is to write plugins that support new models. I have <a href="https://llm.datasette.io/en/stable/plugins/tutorial-model-plugin.html">an extensive tutorial</a> describing how to do that.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_003440.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_003440.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_003440.jpg" alt="$ llm --system 'You are a sentient cheesecake' -m gpt-4o --save cheesecake  $ llm chat -t cheesecake Chatting with gpt-4o Type 'exit' or 'quit' to exit Type '!multi' to enter multiple lines, then 'l!end' to finish > tell me abotu yourself Hello! I'm a sentient cheesecake, a delightful fusion of creamy textures and rich flavors. My main ingredients include cream cheese, sugar, eggs, and a touch of vanilla, all resting on a buttery graham cracker crust. I'm the perfect balance of sweet and tangy, and I take great pride in bringing joy to those who savor a slice of me. Despite my delicate nature, I have a surprisingly strong personality-and apparently, the ability to converse! Is there anything specific you'd like to know about the life of a sentient cheesecake?"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_003440.jpg">#</a></p><p>Another fun trick is to use templates to save and execute parameterized prompts, <a href="https://llm.datasette.io/en/stable/templates.html">documented here</a>. The easiest way to create a template is with the <code>--save</code> option like this:</p>
<pre><code>llm --system 'You are a sentient cheesecake' -m gpt-4o --save cheesecake
</code></pre>
<p>Now you can chat with a cheesecake:</p>
<pre><code>llm chat -t cheesecake
</code></pre>
</div>
<div id="frame_003532.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_003532.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_003532.jpg" alt="$ cat demos.md | llm -s 'summary, short' 1. **Terminal Basics** - Quick reminder on basic terminal commands and piping with “|&quot; and *>&quot;, and using ‘cat’. 2. **Ttok Installation &amp; Demonstration** - Using “pipx install ttok™ to install “ttok™ and demonstrating its usage. 3. **Installing LLM** - Installation of LLM using either “brew’ or “pipx&quot;. 4. **Configuring for OpenAI** = - How to configure LLM for OpenAI. 5. **Running a Prompt** - Example of running a prompt with LLM. 6. **Installing LLM Plugin: 1lm-claude-3** - Installing the “llm-claude-3&quot; plugin and running a prompt with it. 7. **Browsing Logs with Datasette** - Demonstrating browsing logs using Datasette. 8. **Using LLM Command**"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_003532.jpg">#</a></p><p>Being able to pipe content into <code>llm</code> is a really important feature.</p>
<p>The simplest way to do this is with <code>cat</code> to send in files. This command summarizes the content of a provided file:</p>
<pre><code>cat demos.md | llm -s 'summary, short'
</code></pre>
</div>
<div id="frame_003552.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_003552.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_003552.jpg" alt="$ llm -c 'no much much much shorter, and in haikus'  Terminal basics, Commands and piping galore, Cat reminds us all.  Install ttok first, Pipx makes it easy-peasy, Quick demonstration.  LLM install, Brew or pipx, your choice, Configured OpenAI."></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_003552.jpg">#</a></p><p>Once you’ve done this you can send follow-up prompts with <code>-c</code>.</p>
<pre><code>llm -c 'no much much much shorter, and in haikus'
</code></pre>
</div>

<div id="frame_003715.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_003715.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_003715.jpg" alt="Screeshot of the shot-scraper website  A command-line utility for taking automated screenshots of websites  Quick start:  pip install shot-scraper shot-scraper install shot-scraper https://github.com/simonw/shot-scraper -h 900 Produces this screenshot in a file called github-com-simonw-shot-scraper.png  "></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_003715.jpg">#</a></p><p>Another tool I frequently use with LLM is <a href="https://shot-scraper.datasette.io/">shot-scraper</a>—my command-line tool for screenshotting and scraping websites.</p>  
</div>

<div id="frame_003832.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_003832.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_003832.jpg" alt="Screenshot of Google search results, with the inspector panel open to show the structure of the HTML."></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_003832.jpg">#</a></p><p>Google <em>hate</em> being scraped. Let’s use it to scrape Google.</p>
<p>Google search results have a structure where each link on the page is an <code>&lt;h3&gt;</code> element wrapped in a link.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_003844.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_003844.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_003844.jpg" alt="shot-scraper javascript 'https://www.google.com/search?q=nytimes+slop' ' Array.from(   document.querySelectorAll(&quot;h3&quot;),   el => ({href: el.parentNode.href, title: el.innerText}) )'"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_003844.jpg">#</a></p><p>We can scrape that using the following terminal command:</p>
<pre><code>shot-scraper javascript 'https://www.google.com/search?q=nytimes+slop' '
Array.from(
  document.querySelectorAll("h3"),
  el =&gt; ({href: el.parentNode.href, title: el.innerText})
)'
</code></pre>
<p>This will load up the search results page in an invisible browser, then execute JavaScript that extracts the results and returns them as JSON.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_003856.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_003856.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_003856.jpg" alt="R T R - A =4 [oBE IR W' R TR | £ Searc = = =g _ 06_jun_lim — -2sh — 93x24 Rt - . i 8 &quot;href&quot;: &quot;http://www.nytimes.com/1896/07/31/archives/to-slop.html&quot;, i “title&quot;: &quot;To Slop.&quot; i { &quot;href&quot;: &quot;https://www.nytimes.com/section/technology”, &quot;title&quot;: &quot;Technology&quot; i 1 &quot;href&quot;: &quot;https://www.linkedin.com/posts/luigiraymontanez_slop-is-the-new-name-for-unw anted-ai-generated-activity-7195821255621574658-MQWK&quot;, &quot;title&quot;: &quot;Slop is the new name for unwanted AI-generated content” i { e &quot;href&quot;: &quot;https://www.google.com/search?g=nytimes+slop&amp;sca_esv=a22b124cb26f8e73&amp;ei=F_B 0ZpLQHfet@PEPttSubA4&amp;start=10&amp;sa=N&quot;, &quot;title&quot;: &quot;More results&quot; i o BTG &quot;title&quot;: &quot;Try again&quot; } 1 3 = 7,‘. 54 function findParentWithHveid(element) { L85 4 __while (element 8§ lelement hasAttribute = ®0A0®17 WO  sSpaces:4 UTF-8 LF Markdown &amp; A17Spell [ "></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_003856.jpg">#</a></p><p>The results as JSON include the <code>href</code> and <code>title</code> of each of those search results.</p>
<p>We could send that to LLM, but I’d like to grab the search snippets as well.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_003914.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_003914.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_003914.jpg" alt="Screenshot showing the command with the more complex JavaScript."></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_003914.jpg">#</a></p><p>Here’s the more complex recipe that also fetches the search snippets visible on the page:</p>
<pre><code>shot-scraper javascript 'https://www.google.com/search?q=nytimes+slop' '
() =&gt; {
    function findParentWithHveid(element) {
        while (element &amp;&amp; !element.hasAttribute("data-hveid")) {
            element = element.parentElement;
        }
        return element;
    }
    return Array.from(
        document.querySelectorAll("h3"),
        el =&gt; findParentWithHveid(el).innerText
    );
}' | llm -s 'describe slop'
</code></pre>
<p>At the end it pipes them into LLM with instructions to use that context to “describe slop”.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_003931.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_003931.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_003931.jpg" alt="The term &quot;slop&quot; has recently emerged in the context of artificial intelligence to describe questionable or low-quality AI-generated material. This term appears to be gaining traction among tech and media commentators, reflecting growing concerns about the proliferation of such content."></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_003931.jpg">#</a></p><p>... and it works! We get back an answer from the LLM that summarizes the search results that we just scraped.</p>
<p>We have implemented basic RAG—Retrieval Augmented Generation, where search results are used to answer a question—using a terminal script that scrapes search results from Google and pipes them into an LLM.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_004133.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_004133.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_004133.jpg" alt="Output of llm --help showing a list of commands that includes cmd, embed, embed-models and embed-multi."></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_004133.jpg">#</a></p><p>Speaking of RAG... a common technique for implementing that pattern is to take advantage of embeddings and vector search to find content that is semantically similar to the user’s question, without necessarily matching on exact keywords.</p>
<p>I wrote an extensive introduction to embeddings in <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2023/Oct/23/embeddings/">Embeddings: What they are and why they matter</a>.</p>
<p>LLM includes support for calculating, storing and searching embeddings through its <code>llm embed-models</code>, <code>llm embed</code> and <code>llm embed-multi</code> commands, <a href="https://llm.datasette.io/en/stable/embeddings/index.html">documented here</a>.</p>
<p>The <code>llm embed-models</code> command lists currently available embedding models—the OpenAI models plus any that have been added by plugins.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_004239.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_004239.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_004239.jpg" alt="A huge JSON array of floating point numbers, followed by:  $ llm embed -m 3-small -c 'hello there' | jq length  1536"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_004239.jpg">#</a></p><p>The <code>llm embed</code> command can embed content. This will output a list of floating point numbers for the specified content, using the OpenAI 3-small embedding model.</p>
<pre><code>llm embed -m 3-small -c "hello there"
</code></pre>
<p>Add <code>-f hex</code> to get that out as hexadecimal. Neither of these formats are particularly useful on their own!</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_004332.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_004332.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_004332.jpg" alt="Screenshot of the llm embed-multi documentation."></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_004332.jpg">#</a></p><p>The <a href="https://llm.datasette.io/en/stable/embeddings/cli.html#llm-embed-multi">llm embed-multi</a> command is much more useful. It can run embeddings against content in bulk—from a CSV or JSON file, from a directory full of content or even from a SQLite database. Those embedding vectors will be stored in SQLite ready to be used for search or similarity queries.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_004418.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_004418.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_004418.jpg" alt="Screenshot of my blog's collection of 7178 blogmarks"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_004418.jpg">#</a></p><p>I collect bookmarks (I call them “blogmarks”) on my blog—links with short descriptions. I have <a href="https://simonwillison.net/search/?type=blogmark">over 7,178 of them</a>.</p>
<p>Let’s create embeddings for all of those using LLM.</p>
<p>I used the SQLite database version of my blog available from <code>https://datasette.simonwillison.net/simonwillisonblog.db</code> (a 90MB file).</p>
</div>

<div id="frame_004444.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_004444.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_004444.jpg" alt="Custom SQL query returning more than 2,000 rows   select id, link_url, link_title, commentary from blog_blogmark"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_004444.jpg">#</a></p><p>First step is to compose a SQL query returning the data we want to embed. The first column will be treated as a unique identifier to store along with the embedding vector, and any subsequent columns will be used as input to the embedding model.</p>
<pre><code>select id, link_url, link_title, commentary from blog_blogmark
</code></pre>
</div>
<div id="frame_004502.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_004502.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_004502.jpg" alt="R I R S P Y @ B e A C m 7 Qg 06_jun_lim — -zsh — 93x24 R ERCTT  $ llm embed-multi links \ -d simonwillisonblog.db \ --sql 'select id, link_url, link_title, commentary from blog_blogmark' \ -m 3-small --store"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_004502.jpg">#</a></p><p>I can run this command to embed all of the content:</p>
<pre><code>llm embed-multi links \
  -d simonwillisonblog.db \
  --sql 'select id, link_url, link_title, commentary from blog_blogmark' \
  -m 3-small --store
</code></pre>
<p>This will create an embedding collection called “links”. It will run the SQL query we created before, using the OpenAI <code>3-small</code> model. The <code>--store</code> link means it will store a copy of the text in the database as well—without that it would just store identifiers and we would need to use those to look up the text later on when running queries.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_004521.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_004521.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_004521.jpg" alt="Progress bar - 4% done, 00:01:18"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_004521.jpg">#</a></p><p>The <code>llm embed-multi</code> command shows a progress bar for how far it has got.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_004539.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_004539.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_004539.jpg" alt="Screenshot of the embeddings table in Datasette, with a bunch of binary data visible."></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_004539.jpg">#</a></p><p>While the command is running we can use Datasette to watch as the <code>embeddings</code> table is filled with data—one row for each of the items we are embedding, each storing a big ugly binary blob of data representing the embedding vector (in <a href="https://llm.datasette.io/en/stable/embeddings/storage.html">this storage format</a>).</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_004720.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_004720.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_004720.jpg" alt="$ llm similar links -c 'things that make me angry' -d simonwillisonblog.db {&quot;1&quot;: &quot;448&quot;, &quot;score&quot;: 8.31105587659133327, “content”: “http://www.russellbeattie.com/notebook/1006697.html Overreaction Absolutely storming rant from Russell about America's culture of fear.&quot;, &quot;metodata”: null} ..."></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_004720.jpg">#</a></p><p>And now we can run searches! This command finds everything in the “links” collection that is most similar to the search term “things that make me angry”:</p>
<pre><code>llm similar links -c 'things that make me angry' -d simonwillisonblog.db
</code></pre>
</div>
<div id="frame_004824.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_004824.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_004824.jpg" alt="cat ~/.local/bin/blog-answer.sh  #!/bin/bash  # Check if a query was provided if [ &quot;$#&quot; -ne 1 ]; then     echo &quot;Usage: $0 'Your query'&quot;     exit 1 fi  llm similar blog-paragraphs -c &quot;query: $1&quot; \   | jq '.content | sub(&quot;passage: &quot;; &quot;&quot;)' -r \   | llm -m llamafile \   &quot;$1&quot; -s 'You answer questions as a single paragraph'  # | llm -m mlc-chat-Llama-2-7b-chat-hf-q4f16_1 \ # /Users/simon/.local/share/virtualenvs/llm-mlc-SwKbovmI/bin/llm -m mlc-chat-Llama-2-7b-chat-hf-q4f16_1 "></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_004824.jpg">#</a></p><p>We can implement another version of RAG on top of this as well, by finding similar documents to our search term and then piping those results back into LLM to execute a prompt.</p>
<p>I wrote more about this in <a href="https://til.simonwillison.net/llms/embed-paragraphs">Embedding paragraphs from my blog with E5-large-v2</a>.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_005209.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_005209.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_005209.jpg" alt="LLM documentation: OpenAl-compatible models"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_005209.jpg">#</a></p><p>During the Q&amp;A I mentioned that LLM can talk to anything that provides an OpenAI-compatible API endpoint using just configuration, no extra code. That’s <a href="https://llm.datasette.io/en/stable/other-models.html#openai-compatible-models">described in the documentation here</a>.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_005333.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_005333.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_005333.jpg" alt="Screenshot of the Python API documentation"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_005333.jpg">#</a></p><p>I also showed LLM’s <a href="https://llm.datasette.io/en/stable/python-api.html">Python API documentation</a>, but warned that this is not yet considered stable as I’m not 100% happy with how this API works yet.</p>
</div>
<div id="frame_010311.jpg">
  <p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_010311.jpg"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2024/llm/frame_010311.jpg" alt="GitHub Issue with 77 comments: Figure out how to serve an AWS Lambda function with a Function URL from a custom subdomain"></a>
  <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Jun/17/cli-language-models/#frame_010311.jpg">#</a></p><p>The final question from the audience was about my personal productivity.</p>
<p>I wrote a bit about this a few years ago in <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2022/Nov/26/productivity/">Coping strategies for the serial project hoarder</a>—how I use extensive documentation and unit tests to allow me to work on way more projects at once by ensuring I don’t have to remember the details of any of them.</p>
<p>My other trick is that I tend to pick projects that fit my unique combination of previous experiences. I built LLM because I already had experience with LLM APIs, Python CLI tools (using <a href="https://click.palletsprojects.com/">Click</a>) and plugin systems (using <a href="https://pluggy.readthedocs.io/">Pluggy</a>). As a result I happened to be one of the best positioned people in the world to build a plugin-based CLI tool for working with LLMs!</p>
</div>

<h4 id="llm-colophon">Colophon</h4>
<p>Here’s how I turned the YouTube video of this talk into an annotated presentation:</p>
<ol>
<li>I downloaded a <code>.mp4</code> version of the talk from YouTube using <a href="https://github.com/yt-dlp/yt-dlp">yt-dlp</a>.</li>
<li>I ran that through <a href="https://goodsnooze.gumroad.com/l/macwhisper">MacWhisper</a> to create my own transcript for copying extracts from into my write-up—although this time I didn’t end up using any of the transcript text.</li>
<li>I played the video (at 2x speed) in QuickTime Player and used the <code>capture.sh</code> script <a href="https://til.simonwillison.net/macos/quicktime-capture-script">described here</a> to grab screenshots of the individual interesting frames that I wanted to use for my post.</li>
<li>I loaded those screenshots into <a href="https://til.simonwillison.net/tools/annotated-presentations">my annotated presentation tool</a> (which I <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2023/Aug/6/annotated-presentations/">described in this post</a>) and used that to run OCR against them for alt text and to add commentary to accompany each screenshot.</li>
<li>I assembled the result into this finished blog entry, adding intro text and the YouTube embed as HTML.</li>
</ol>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Law enforcement is spying on Americans' mail, records show (151 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2024/06/24/post-office-mail-surveillance-law-enforcement/</link>
            <guid>40782618</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 00:00:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2024/06/24/post-office-mail-surveillance-law-enforcement/">https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2024/06/24/post-office-mail-surveillance-law-enforcement/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40782618">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="JPTWFGKWYJGW3KQFEBR4ZG7Q2U" data-el="text" dir="null">The U.S. Postal Service has shared information from thousands of Americans’ letters and packages with law enforcement every year for the past decade, conveying the names, addresses and other details from the outside of boxes and envelopes without requiring a court order.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="KHRGAJ5CSRELREQ2R3FJUHFBW4" data-el="text" dir="null">Postal inspectors say they fulfill such requests only when mail monitoring can help find a fugitive or investigate a crime. But a decade’s worth of records, provided exclusively to The Washington Post in response to a congressional probe, show Postal Service officials have received more than 60,000 requests from federal agents and police officers since 2015, and that they rarely say no.</p></div><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="XHUEORS7CVDU3HRBX22AUDFLH4" data-el="text" dir="null">Each request can cover days or weeks of mail sent to or from a person or address, and 97 percent of the requests were approved, according to the data. Postal inspectors recorded more than 312,000 letters and packages between 2015 and 2023, the records show.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="OIBH3A6HKJD63JLRPW7RJVSNV4" data-el="text" dir="null">The surveillance technique, known as the mail covers program, has long been used by postal inspectors to help track down suspects or evidence. The practice is legal, and the inspectors said they share only what they can see on the outside of the mail; the Fourth Amendment requires them to get a warrant to peek inside.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="AFRUBDZXBRCP5PPVKPRQ5OQVX4" data-el="text" dir="null">But the Postal Service’s law enforcement arm, the U.S. Postal Inspection Service, has traditionally declined to say how often it facilitates such requests, saying in a <a href="https://goodtimesweb.org/surveillance/2015/hr-ar-15-007.pdf" target="_blank">2015 audit</a> that such details would decrease the program’s effectiveness by “alerting criminals” to how the technique works.</p><div role="group" aria-roledescription="carousel" data-qa="article-body"><h2>GET CAUGHT UP<p>Stories to keep you informed</p></h2></div><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="PNFDXKRDK5GATCNDPNVHHDJGJ4" data-el="text" dir="null">For that audit, the agency said it had approved more than 158,000 requests from postal inspectors and law enforcement officials over the previous four years. The IRS, FBI and the Department of Homeland Security were among the top requesters.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="3QFJRONTO5B6TLDDHFSSAR4LFQ" data-el="text" dir="null">In a <a href="https://www.wyden.senate.gov/imo/media/doc/bipartisan_senate_postal_surveillance_letter.pdf" target="_blank">letter</a> in May 2023, a group of eight senators, including Ron Wyden (D-Ore.), Rand Paul (R-Ky.) and Elizabeth Warren (D-Mass.), urged the agency to require a federal judge to approve the requests and to share more details on the program, saying officials there had chosen to “provide this surveillance service and to keep postal customers in the dark about the fact they have been subjected to monitoring.”</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="X7QU2BFHHFE57LDNP3NKX36WAA" data-el="text" dir="null">In a response earlier this month, the chief postal inspector, Gary Barksdale, declined to change the policy but provided nearly a decade’s worth of data showing that postal inspectors, federal agencies, and state and local police forces made an average of about 6,700 requests a year, and that inspectors additionally recorded data from about another 35,000 pieces of mail a year, on average.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="XPKNDCEMKNEV5EOJ25WIILKTHI" data-el="text" dir="null">Barksdale said in a letter to the senators in June 2023 that the program was not a “large-scale surveillance apparatus” and was focused only on mail that could help police and national security agencies “carry out their missions and protect the American public.”</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="VM4VJDLZ55BCRPZZNO4JKJ5PZY" data-el="text" dir="null">The practice, he added, had been <a href="https://casetext.com/case/us-v-choate-2" target="_blank">legally authorized</a> since 1879, a year after the Supreme Court <a href="https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/96/727/" target="_blank">ruled</a> that government officials needed a warrant before opening any sealed letter.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="TWII2YLI45CCXAJ66KBAAJAANM" data-el="text" dir="null">“There is no reasonable expectation of privacy with respect to information contained on the outside of mail matter,” Barksdale wrote.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="EOPQI55WOJBUHISTPRDJPOATVA" data-el="text" dir="null">Wyden said in a statement, “These new statistics show that thousands of Americans are subjected to warrantless surveillance each year, and that the Postal Inspection Service rubber stamps practically all of the requests they receive.” He also criticized the agency for “refusing to raise its standards and require law enforcement agencies monitoring the outside of Americans’ mail to get a court order, which is already required to monitor emails and texts.”</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="K6XTY25KQNCRDJOBQ6K3EEOJIU" data-el="text" dir="null">Anxieties over postal surveillance are classically American. In 1798, Vice President Thomas Jefferson <a href="http://rs5.loc.gov/service/mss/mtj/mtj1/021/021_0788_0790.pdf" target="_blank">wrote in a letter</a> that his fears of having his private communications exposed by the “infidelities of the post office” had stopped him from “writing fully &amp; freely.”</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="M65BUTPIBJHA3ICWLLSJ6ZD3AU" data-el="text" dir="null">In their letter last year, the senators said that even the exteriors of mail could be deeply revealing for many Americans, giving clues about the people they talk to, the bills they pay, the churches they attend, the political views they subscribe to and the social causes they support.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="HKNH2ZM6N5A4ZJH6JIAKK7EIXE" data-el="text" dir="null">In 1978, a circuit court judge <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/archive/politics/1978/11/06/high-court-ruling-asked-in-case-of-mail-covers/08e76760-740d-43ef-8d28-1f374573a78a/?itid=lk_inline_manual_25" target="_blank">said</a> the mail covers could expose someone’s personal life “in a manner unobtainable even through surveillance of his movements,” rendering “the subject’s life an open book.”</p><div data-qa="article-body"><p>correction</p><p data-contentid="XTZYOMGVJ5ACDHJWL7QPQQCOH4" data-apitype="correction" data-testid="disclaimer-description">In a previous version of this article, the article summary incorrectly said the U.S. Postal Service has approved more than 60,000 requests for mail data since 2015. The Postal Service has received more than 60,000 requests. The summary has been corrected. </p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[iDOS 3 Rejected by Apple (190 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://litchie.com/2024/04/new-hope</link>
            <guid>40782541</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 23:53:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://litchie.com/2024/04/new-hope">https://litchie.com/2024/04/new-hope</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40782541">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    <p>April 14, 2024</p>
        <p>
            iDOS 3 waiting for review (rejected)    </p>
        <article>
  <p>Earlier quite a few iDOS users and supporters reached out to me to let me know about the recent AppStore policy change (Thanks, EU).
    In light of this, I decided to resubmit iDOS.    

    However, it looks like Apple has blacklisted iDOS 2, preventing me from even requesting
    a review under that title, and I had to submit under a brand new title "iDOS 3".


  </p>
  
  <p>    Here's where things got interesting.
    Initially they rejected the submission because it was same as iDOS 2, but after I explained to them that I can not continue under iDOS2,
then they rejected again as "Design spam" on the basis that there has been many submissions lately with the exact same design.
    </p>
      <p>I don't actually care much about the copycats, but just can't understand why it's difficult for Apple to check my account history and tell which is the original. It's a little bit insulting that I had to tell the story to them time and time again and yet the issue is unresolved after 1 week.
      </p>
        <p>For the people that are waiting, I am hopeful that we will sort it out eventually. And if everything indeed goes well, there will be updates coming to justify this version bump.
        </p>

	<p> <em>Update 2024-05-08</em>: "Your app is in review but is requiring additional time." Makes me wonder if the reviewer is trying to play a game through.
	</p><p id="nope"> <em>Update 2024-06-15</em>: Got a call from Apple after 2 months. They have decided that iDOS is not a retro game console, so the new rule is not applicable. They suggested I make changes and resubmit for review, but when I asked what changes I should make to be compliant, they had no idea, nor when I asked what a retro game console is. It's still the same old unreasonable answer along the line of "we know it when we see it".
</p>

</article>
        

    


</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Julian Assange has reached a plea deal with the U.S., allowing him to go free (1649 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/justice-department/julian-assange-reached-plea-deal-us-allowing-go-free-rcna158695</link>
            <guid>40782130</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 23:10:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/justice-department/julian-assange-reached-plea-deal-us-allowing-go-free-rcna158695">https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/justice-department/julian-assange-reached-plea-deal-us-allowing-go-free-rcna158695</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40782130">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>WASHINGTON — <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/world/wikileaks-julian-assange-extradition-appeal-espionage-london-court-rcna153007" target="_blank">WikiLeaks founder Julian Assange</a> plans to plead guilty to a conspiracy charge this week as part of a plea deal with the U.S. Justice Department that will allow him to go free after spending five years in a British prison, according to <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.nmid.6474/gov.uscourts.nmid.6474.1.0.pdf" target="_blank">court documents</a>.</p><p>Assange was charged by criminal information — which typically signifies a plea deal — with conspiracy to obtain and disclose national defense information, the court documents say. A <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.nmid.6474/gov.uscourts.nmid.6474.3.0_1.pdf" target="_blank">letter</a> from Justice Department official Matthew McKenzie to U.S. District Judge Ramona Manglona of the U.S. District Court for the Northern Mariana Islands said that Assange would appear in court at 9 a.m. local time on Wednesday (or, 7 p.m. ET on Tuesday) to plead guilty and said that DOJ expects Assange will return to Australia, his country of citizenship, after the proceedings.</p><p>U.S. charges against Assange stem from one of the largest publications of classified information in American history, which took place during the first term of Barack Obama's presidency. Starting in late 2009, according to the government, Assange conspired with <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/judge-orders-chelsea-manning-be-released-n1157381" target="_blank">Chelsea Manning</a>, a military intelligence analyst, to disclose tens of thousands of activity reports about the war in Afghanistan, hundreds of thousands of reports about the war in Iraq, hundreds of thousands of State Department cables and assessment briefs of Guantanamo Bay detainees using his WikiLeaks website.</p><p>Court documents revealing Assange's plea deal were filed Monday evening in the U.S. District Court for the Northern Mariana Islands, a U.S. territory in the Pacific Ocean. Assange was expected to make an appearance in that court and to be sentenced to 62 months, with credit for time served in British prison, meaning he would be free to return to Australia, where he was born.</p><p>Assange has been <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/world/wikileaks-julian-assange-extradition-appeal-espionage-london-court-rcna153007" target="_blank">held</a> in the high-security Belmarsh Prison on the outskirts of London for five years and previously spent seven years in self-exile at the Ecuadorian Embassy in London — <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/world/wikileaks-founder-julian-assange-fathered-two-children-embassy-partner-says-n1182151" target="_blank">where he reportedly fathered two children</a> — until his asylum was withdrawn and he was forcibly <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/world/wikileaks-founder-julian-assange-arrested-police-london-n991236" target="_blank">carried out of the embassy</a> and arrested in April 2019. A <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/wikileaks-founder-julian-assange-indicted-new-charges-under-espionage-act-n1009441" target="_blank">superseding indictment</a> was returned against Assange more than five years ago, in May 2019, and a second superseding indictment was <a href="https://www.justice.gov/opa/pr/wikileaks-founder-charged-superseding-indictment" target="_blank">returned</a> in June 2020.</p><figure><picture data-testid="picture"><source media="(min-width: 1000px)" srcset="https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_fit-560w,f_avif,q_auto:eco,dpr_2/rockcms/2022-06/220617-julian-assange-mb-1023-51469d.jpg 2x, https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_fit-560w,f_auto,q_auto:best/rockcms/2022-06/220617-julian-assange-mb-1023-51469d.jpg 1x"><source srcset="https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_fit-760w,f_avif,q_auto:eco,dpr_2/rockcms/2022-06/220617-julian-assange-mb-1023-51469d.jpg 2x, https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_fit-760w,f_auto,q_auto:best/rockcms/2022-06/220617-julian-assange-mb-1023-51469d.jpg 1x"><img loading="lazy" src="https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_fit-760w,f_auto,q_auto:best/rockcms/2022-06/220617-julian-assange-mb-1023-51469d.jpg" alt="Sweden Announce That They Are Dropping Rape Charges Against Julian Assange" height="2000" width="3000"></picture><figcaption data-testid="caption"><span data-testid="caption__container">Julian Assange speaks to the media from the balcony of the Embassy Of Ecuador on May 19, 2017 in London.</span><span data-testid="caption__source">Jack Taylor / Getty Images file</span></figcaption></figure><p>Assange has been fighting extradition to the U.S. for more than a decade. In March, the High Court in London <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/world/julian-assange-wikileaks-win-appeal-extradition-us-spy-charges-rcna139519" target="_blank">gave him permission</a> for a full hearing on his appeal as he sought assurances that he could rely upon the First Amendment at a trial in the United States. In May, two judges on the High Court <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/world/wikileaks-julian-assange-extradition-appeal-espionage-london-court-rcna153007" target="_blank">said</a> he could have a full hearing on whether he would be discriminated against in the U.S. because he is a foreign national. A hearing on the issue of Assange's free speech rights had been <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/world/wikileaks-assange-extradition-appeal-heard-month-rcna156499" target="_blank">scheduled</a> for July 9-10.</p><p>Assange's WikiLeaks also <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/wikileaks-julian-assange-no-proof-hacked-dnc-emails-came-russia-n616541" target="_blank">published</a> hacked emails from the Democratic National Committee that upended the 2016 presidential race. Russian intelligence officers were subsequently <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/mueller-charges-russian-intelligence-officers-hacking-dnc-clinton-n891236" target="_blank">indicted</a> in connection with the hacking in 2018, in a case brought by then-special counsel Robert Mueller. At a joint news conference with then-President Donald Trump and Russian President Vladimir Putin days later, Trump contradicted the indictment and the intelligence community, saying that Putin was "<a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/white-house/trump-putin-questions-abound-ahead-helsinki-meeting-n891606" target="_blank">extremely strong and powerful in his denial</a>" that Russians interfered in the 2016 election to help him win.</p><p>Manning was sentenced to 35 years in a military prison, but <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/president-obama-commutes-chelsea-manning-s-sentence-n708046" target="_blank">her sentence was commuted by Obama</a> in the final days of his presidency in 2017. Manning was subsequently held in contempt of court for nearly a year after she refused to answer questions for a grand jury; she was then <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/judge-orders-chelsea-manning-be-released-n1157381" target="_blank">released</a> after an <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/politics-news/chelsea-manning-hospitalized-after-suicide-attempt-n1156111" target="_blank">attempted suicide</a>.</p><p><em>If you or someone you know is in crisis, call&nbsp;or text</em><strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong><em>988 to reach the Suicide and Crisis Lifeline&nbsp;or chat live at&nbsp;</em><a href="http://988lifeline.org/" target="_blank"><em>988lifeline.org</em></a><em>. You can also visit&nbsp;</em><a href="http://speakingofsuicide.com/resources" target="_blank"><em>SpeakingOfSuicide.com/resources</em></a><em>&nbsp;for additional&nbsp;support.</em></p></div><div><div data-activity-map="expanded-byline-article-bottom"><div data-testid="byline-thumbnail"><picture data-testid="picture"><source srcset="https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_focal-60x60,f_avif,q_auto:eco,dpr_2/newscms/2020_02/3181661/michael-kosnar-circle-byline-template.jpg 2x, https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_focal-60x60,f_auto,q_auto:best/newscms/2020_02/3181661/michael-kosnar-circle-byline-template.jpg 1x"><img loading="lazy" src="https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_focal-60x60,f_auto,q_auto:best/newscms/2020_02/3181661/michael-kosnar-circle-byline-template.jpg" alt="" height="48" width="48"></picture></div><p><span data-testid="byline-name">Michael Kosnar</span><span></span></p><p>Michael Kosnar is a&nbsp;Justice Department producer for the NBC News Washington Bureau.</p></div><div data-activity-map="expanded-byline-article-bottom"><div data-testid="byline-thumbnail"><a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/author/ryan-j-reilly-ncpn1288345"><picture data-testid="picture"><source srcset="https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_focal-60x60,f_avif,q_auto:eco,dpr_2/newscms/2024_06/3638200/newnbcheadshot.jpg 2x, https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_focal-60x60,f_auto,q_auto:best/newscms/2024_06/3638200/newnbcheadshot.jpg 1x"><img loading="lazy" src="https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_focal-60x60,f_auto,q_auto:best/newscms/2024_06/3638200/newnbcheadshot.jpg" alt="" height="48" width="48"></picture></a></div><p><span data-testid="byline-name"><a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/author/ryan-j-reilly-ncpn1288345">Ryan J. Reilly</a></span><span><a href="https://twitter.com/ryanjreilly" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span></span></a><a href="mailto:ryan.reilly@nbcuni.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span></span></a></span></p><p>Ryan J. Reilly is a justice reporter for NBC News.</p></div><div><p>Daniel Barnes</p><!-- --> <!-- --><p>contributed</p><!-- --><p>.</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[MTV news website goes dark, archives pulled offline (150 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://variety.com/2024/digital/news/mtv-news-website-archives-pulled-offline-1236047163/</link>
            <guid>40782101</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 23:06:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://variety.com/2024/digital/news/mtv-news-website-archives-pulled-offline-1236047163/">https://variety.com/2024/digital/news/mtv-news-website-archives-pulled-offline-1236047163/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40782101">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>
	More than two decades’ worth of content published on MTVNews.com is no longer available after MTV appears to have fully pulled down the site and its related content. Content on its sister site, CMT.com, seems to have met a similiar fate. </p>



<p>
	In 2023, <a href="https://variety.com/2023/tv/news/mtv-news-shuts-down-paramount-layoffs-showtime-networks-1235607638/">MTV News was shuttered amid the financial woes</a> of parent company <a href="https://variety.com/t/paramount-global/" id="auto-tag_paramount-global" data-tag="paramount-global">Paramount Global</a>. As of Monday, trying to access <a href="https://variety.com/t/mtv-news/" id="auto-tag_mtv-news" data-tag="mtv-news">MTV News</a> articles on mtvnews.com or mtv.com/news resulted in visitors being redirected to the main MTV website.</p>



<p>
	The now-unavailable content includes decades of music journalism comprising thousands of articles and interviews with countless major artists, dating back to the site’s launch in 1996. Perhaps the most significant loss is MTV News’ vast hip-hop-related archives, particularly its weekly “Mixtape Monday” column, which ran for nearly a decade in the 2000s and 2010s and featured interviews, reviews and more with many artists, producers and others early in their careers.  

	</p>






<p>
	Former MTV News staffers posted on social media about the website shutdown and the scrubbing of the archives. “So, mtvnews.com no longer exists. Eight years of my life are gone without a trace,” Patrick Hosken, former music editor for MTV News, <a rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow" href="https://x.com/patrickhosken/status/1805327863882956850" target="_blank">wrote</a> on X. “All because it didn’t fit some executives’ bottom lines. Infuriating is too small a word.” 


</p><div>
			<h3>
			Popular on Variety		</h3>
	
		
	</div>




<p>
	“sickening (derogatory) to see the entire @mtvnews archive wiped from the internet,” Crystal Bell, culture editor at Mashable and one-time entertainment director&nbsp;of MTV News, <a rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow" href="https://x.com/crystalbell/status/1805338895401599275" target="_blank">posted</a> on X. “decades of music history gone…including some very early k-pop stories.”</p>



<p>
	“This is disgraceful. They’ve completely wiped the MTV News archive,” longtime Rolling Stone senior writer Brian Hiatt <a href="https://x.com/hiattb/status/1805336821569896551" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">commented</a>. “Decades of pop culture history research material gone, and why?”</p>



<p>
	Last week, Paramount Global’s CMT website similarly pulled its repository of country-music journalism dating back several decades.</p>



<p>
	Reps for MTV did not respond to requests for comment Monday.</p>



<p>
	Some observers noted that MTV News articles may be available through internet archiving services like the <a rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow" href="https://wayback-api.archive.org/" target="_blank">Wayback Machine</a>, but according to Hiatt older MTV News articles do not show up via Wayback Machine.</p>



<p>
	In May 2023, Paramount Global shut down MTV News — which had already been severely downsized by layoffs in recent years — coming amid a <a href="https://variety.com/2023/tv/news/mtv-news-shuts-down-paramount-layoffs-showtime-networks-1235607638/">25% reduction in workforce</a> across the Showtime/MTV Entertainment Studios and Paramount Media Networks groups in the U.S. The group is headed by president-CEO Chris McCarthy, who in late April was named one of <a href="https://variety.com/2024/biz/news/paramount-ceos-skydance-deal-end-standalone-strategic-plan-1236035440/">the three co-CEOs running Paramount Global’s “Office of the CEO.”</a>

	</p>




<p>
	MTV News began in the late ’80s with “The Week in Rock,” a show hosted by Kurt Loder, who was the first MTV News correspondent.</p>



<p>
	<em>Additional reporting by Jem Aswad, a former MTV News editor. </em></p>




















</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Round Rects Are Everywhere (314 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.folklore.org/Round_Rects_Are_Everywhere.html</link>
            <guid>40781838</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 22:38:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.folklore.org/Round_Rects_Are_Everywhere.html">https://www.folklore.org/Round_Rects_Are_Everywhere.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40781838">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p>Bill Atkinson worked mostly at home, but whenever he made significant progress he rushed in to Apple to show it off to anyone who would appreciate it.   This time, he visited the Macintosh offices at Texaco Towers to show off his brand new oval routines, which were implemented using a really clever algorithm.</p><p>

	Bill had added new code to QuickDraw (which was still called LisaGraf at this point) to draw circles and ovals very quickly.  That was a bit hard to do on the Macintosh, since the math for circles usually involved taking square roots, and the 68000 processor in the Lisa and Macintosh didn't support floating point operations.  But Bill had come up with a clever way to do the circle calculation that only used addition and subtraction, not even multiplication or division, which the 68000 could do, but was kind of slow at.</p><p>

	Bill's technique used the fact the sum of a sequence of odd numbers is always the next perfect square (For example, 1 + 3 = 4, 1 + 3 + 5 = 9, 1 + 3 + 5 + 7 = 16, etc).  So he could figure out when to bump the dependent coordinate value by iterating in a loop until a threshold was exceeded.  This allowed QuickDraw to draw ovals very quickly.</p><p>

	Bill fired up his demo and it quickly filled the Lisa screen with randomly-sized ovals, faster than you thought was possible.  But something was bothering Steve Jobs.  "Well, circles and ovals are good, but how about drawing rectangles with rounded corners?  Can we do that now, too?"</p><p>

	"No, there's no way to do that.  In fact it would be really hard to do, and I don't think we really need it".  I think Bill was a little miffed that Steve wasn't raving over the fast ovals and still wanted more.</p><p>

	Steve suddenly got more intense.  "Rectangles with rounded corners are everywhere! Just look around this room!". And sure enough, there were lots of them, like the whiteboard and some of the desks and tables.  Then he pointed out the window.  "And look outside, there's even more, practically everywhere you look!".  He even persuaded Bill to take a quick walk around the block with him, pointing out every rectangle with rounded corners that he could find.</p><p>

        When Steve and Bill passed a no-parking sign with rounded corners, it did the trick.  "OK, I give up", Bill pleaded.  "I'll see if it's as hard as I thought."  He went back home to work on it.</p><p>

        Bill returned to Texaco Towers the following afternoon, with a big smile on his face.  His demo was now drawing rectangles with beautifully rounded corners blisteringly fast, almost at the speed of plain rectangles.  When he added the code to LisaGraf, he named the new primitive "RoundRects".   Over the next few months, roundrects worked their way into various parts of the user interface, and soon became indispensable.
  </p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Fearing losses, banks are quietly dumping real estate loans (111 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/2024/06/24/business/commercial-real-estate-loans.html</link>
            <guid>40781060</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 21:32:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/06/24/business/commercial-real-estate-loans.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2024/06/24/business/commercial-real-estate-loans.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40781060">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nytimes.com/2024/06/24/business/commercial-real-estate-loans.html: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Windows 11 is now enabling OneDrive folder backup without asking permission (284 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.neowin.net/news/windows-11-is-now-automatically-enabling-onedrive-folder-backup-without-asking-permission/</link>
            <guid>40781048</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 21:30:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.neowin.net/news/windows-11-is-now-automatically-enabling-onedrive-folder-backup-without-asking-permission/">https://www.neowin.net/news/windows-11-is-now-automatically-enabling-onedrive-folder-backup-without-asking-permission/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40781048">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
                                                                        <p><img alt="The Microsoft OneDrive Logo" src="https://cdn.neowin.com/news/images/uploaded/2022/03/1648728320_onedrive_logo_story.jpg"></p>

<p>Microsoft has made OneDrive slightly more annoying for Windows 11 users. Quietly and without any announcement, the company changed Windows 11's initial setup so that it could turn on the automatic folder backup without asking for it.</p>

<p>Now, those setting up a new Windows computer <a href="https://www.neowin.net/news/microsoft-apparently-hates-it-when-you-switch-from-microsoft-account-to-local-account/">the way Microsoft wants them to</a> (in other words, connected to the internet and signed into a Microsoft account) will get to their desktops with OneDrive already syncing stuff from folders like Desktop Pictures, Documents, Music, and Videos. Depending on how much is stored there, you might end up with a desktop and other folders filled to the brim with shortcuts to various stuff right after finishing a clean Windows installation.</p>

<p><a href="https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/office/back-up-your-folders-with-onedrive-d61a7930-a6fb-4b95-b28a-6552e77c3057">Automatic folder backup in OneDrive</a> is a very useful feature when used properly and when the user deliberately enables it. However, Microsoft decided that sending a few notification prompts to enable folder backup was not enough, so it just turned the feature on without asking anybody or even letting users know about it, resulting in a flood of Reddit posts about users complaining about what the hell are those green checkmarks next to files and shortcuts on their desktops.</p>

                            <!-- PLACE THIS SECTION INSIDE OF YOUR BODY WHERE YOU WANT THE VIDEO PLAYER TO RENDER -->
            <p>If you do not want your computer to back up everything on your desktop or other folders, here is how to turn the feature off (you can also set up Windows 11 in offline mode):</p>

<ol>
<li>Right-click the OneDrive icon in the tray area, click the settings icon and then press Settings.</li>
	<li>Go to the "Sync and Backup" tab and click "Manage backup."</li>
	<li>Turn off all the folders you do not want to back up in OneDrive and confirm the changes.</li>
	<li>If you have an older OneDrive version with the classic tabbed interface, go to the Backup tab and click Manage Backup &gt; Stop backup &gt; Stop backup.</li>
</ol>
<p>Microsoft is no stranger to shady tricks with its software and operating system. Several months ago, we noticed that <a href="https://www.neowin.net/news/microsoft-wont-let-you-close-onedrive-in-windows-without-you-explaining-it-first/">OneDrive would not let you close it</a> without you explaining the reason first (<a href="https://www.neowin.net/news/microsoft-backtracks-no-longer-asks-to-explain-closing-onedrive-on-windows-10-and-11/">Microsoft later reverted that stupid change</a>). A similar thing <a href="https://www.neowin.net/news/microsoft-now-wants-you-to-take-a-poll-before-installing-google-chrome/">was also spotted in the Edge browser</a>, with Microsoft asking users why they downloaded Chrome.</p>

<p>As a reminder, you can always just uninstall OneDrive and call it a day.</p>
                        
                        
                                                                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Ask HN: Those of you who've left the SWE world, what did you transition into? (160 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40780940</link>
            <guid>40780940</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 21:20:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40780940">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><td><table>
        <tbody><tr id="40780940">
      <td><span></span></td>      <td><center><a id="up_40780940" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40780940&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40780940"></a></center></td><td><span><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40780940">Ask HN: Those of you who've left the SWE world, what did you transition into?</a></span></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><span>
          <span id="score_40780940">111 points</span> by <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=volkk">volkk</a> <span title="2024-06-24T21:20:31"><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40780940">1 hour ago</a></span> <span id="unv_40780940"></span> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/hide?id=40780940&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40780940">hide</a> | <a href="https://hn.algolia.com/?query=Ask%20HN%3A%20Those%20of%20you%20who%27ve%20left%20the%20SWE%20world%2C%20what%20did%20you%20transition%20into%3F&amp;type=story&amp;dateRange=all&amp;sort=byDate&amp;storyText=false&amp;prefix&amp;page=0">past</a> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/fave?id=40780940&amp;auth=3511ccde47c8132520424864bc4703492fda6643">favorite</a> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40780940">75&nbsp;comments</a>        </span>
              </td></tr>
    <tr><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><div><p>After 13 years in SWE, working for startups, bigger companies, the golden handcuffs, etc, I can finally say that I think I'm finished.</p><p>Right now I'm contracting to stay afloat, maintain flexibility and delve into entrepreneurship, but I truly don't know what the future holds for me anymore if building my own company doesn't work out. I have 0 inclination to go back to a 9-5 at a company coding for a living. I'm done. I've been an EM, which might arguably be the most miserable position that exists. I've been senior/staff at places, and honestly I just don't enjoy arguing about the structure of software anymore, I'm tired of the personalities, tired of the infantilization of the industry (frankly, it's embarrassing) but mostly, I just don't enjoy coding as much as I used to, unless I'm leveraging it to create an asymmetrical amount of value for me ($$$$) which is just not what a full time job is.</p><p>However, I don't know what to look into as an alternative if I need a full time position once my wife and I start having kids. My strengths revolve around people and strategy. I've been considering sales at a tech company because to me, working harder and having an unlimited cap in what I can earn sounds pretty fantastic.</p><p>Would love to hear any kinds of stories or tips from folks</p></div></td></tr>        <tr><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><form action="comment" method="post"></form></td></tr>  </tbody></table>
  </td></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The case for not sanitising fairy tales (198 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.plough.com/en/topics/culture/literature/the-case-for-not-sanitizing-fairy-tales</link>
            <guid>40779785</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 19:35:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.plough.com/en/topics/culture/literature/the-case-for-not-sanitizing-fairy-tales">https://www.plough.com/en/topics/culture/literature/the-case-for-not-sanitizing-fairy-tales</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40779785">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p><span>During Flannery O’Connor’s</span> childhood, the future author had a creative way of weeding out any unsatisfactory playmates who had been chosen by her mother as respectable society. O’Connor would read <em>Grimms’ Fairy Tales</em> aloud to her guests. Some were too frightened by the stories to ever return to the O’Connor house in Savannah (which suited their hostess just fine). Any girl who loved the fairy tales passed young O’Connor’s&nbsp;test. A kindred spirit had been found.</p>
<p>Classic fairy tales aren’t for the faint of heart. It’s not hard to see their influence on O’Connor’s disturbing and shocking southern gothic fiction that includes such horrors as serial killers waiting by the side of rural roads, ready to murder selfish grandmothers. The stories compiled by Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm include their fair share of violence and twisted crimes: men who chop young women up into pieces, a father who lusts after his own daughter, and many, many characters who make deals with the devil himself. Today children are often only familiar with sanitized versions of the Grimm Brothers’ stories.</p>
<div><p><img height="856" alt="illustration of Hansel and Gretel and a witch" width="600" src="https://www.plough.com/-/media/images/plough/article/2024/summer/stewart/stewartembed.jpg?la=en"></p><p>Arthur Rackham, Illustration of “Hansel and Gretel,” a well-known German folktale from the Brothers Grimm, 1909<em>.</em></p>
</div>
<p>Hans Christian Andersen’s classic fairy tales have also been adjusted over the years for a more sensitive audience. When I found his version of “The Little Mermaid”<em> </em>at the library as a young girl, I was surprised but fascinated by the stark differences from the Disney film. The prince in Andersen’s<em> </em>“The Little Mermaid” marries someone else. And the mermaid’s bargain with the sea-witch results in a desperate choice: die when the sun rises after his wedding night or murder her beloved in his bridal chamber. While there are moments of suspense and danger in Disney’s <em>The Little Mermaid</em>, it’s hard to imagine bubbly Ariel with her bouncing red bangs and a knife in hand, trying to decide whether to fatally stab lovable himbo Prince Eric. Such a dark scene, although not uncommon in the realm of classic fairy tales, would have been considered too distressing for young viewers. In an effort to make the story more palatable, Disney’s <em>Cinderella </em>does not include the details of Cinderella’s stepsisters chopping off their heels and toes to fit their bloody, mutilated feet into the glass slipper in greedy pursuit of the throne or getting their eyes pecked out by birds in a final stroke of justice, as the Grimms’ version describes. But is this Disneyfication of these tales a good or a bad thing?</p>
<p>Fairy tales are stories that are told to children and set in a world of magic. As twentieth-century educator <a href="https://www.plough.com/en/authors/a/annemarie-waechter-arnold">Annemarie Wächter</a>&nbsp;put it, “Children and fairy tales are inseparable – one cannot be imagined without the other.” Fairy tales are beloved by children partly because they are tales of <em>action</em>. Rather than revolving around the inner thoughts and motivations of nuanced characters, they are concerned with <em>what happens next</em>, what the characters (often archetypes) <em>do</em>. They are more than mere fables with a snappy moral (think Aesop) because their meaning transcends clearcut lessons. Instead, they are full of mystery. There is room inside these tales for the child to explore fairyland: a strange and dangerous world in which she can practice overcoming her fears by journeying alongside the hero. And at the end of the tale, everything is set right. As Wächter puts it, “Fairy tales can often be brutal and cruel – people and animals die – and yet, despite everything, the positive powers always win. There can be no other ending.”</p>
<p>Fairy tales take both evil and goodness quite seriously. In other words, they are truthful. As Madeleine L’Engle claimed, “The world of fairy tale, fantasy, myth, is inimical to the secular world, and in total opposition to it, for it is interested not in limited laboratory proofs, but in truth.” And in their embrace of truth, fairy tales wrestle with darkness and end in triumph. But are we willing to tell children the truth by reading them fairy tales, as Flannery O’Connor did to her playmates? It seems that these days we are more comfortable if we alter them either by&nbsp; softening the darkness in the story or, as we see in much young adult literature, rejecting the possibility of happily ever after.</p>
<p><span>Disney’s <em>Cinderella </em>does not include the details of Cinderella’s stepsisters chopping off their heels and toes to fit their bloody, mutilated feet into the glass slipper in greedy pursuit of the throne or getting their eyes pecked out by birds in a final stroke of justice, as the Grimms’ version describes. But is this Disneyfication of these tales a good or a bad thing?</span></p>
<p>While protecting the innocence of children by sheltering them from overly gruesome material is something all good parents seek to do, have we swung so far in our attempt to protect children that we don’t tell stories that help them process dark things? While we haven’t always been so leery of the violence in fairy tales, in this strange age we subject our children to drills at their schools to prepare them for active shooters in the classroom but consider them too fragile to be told stories that take evil and death seriously. Is this sheltering from the classic grit of fairy tales benefiting them, or are these just the sort of stories they need to be able to endure the violence that hangs like a shadow over our world?</p>
<p>The fairy tale acknowledges that parents do not always love and care for their children as they ought, that loved ones die and leave us alone and grieving, that evil is real and often powerful, and that violence and sin are present in our world. All these truths make grownups uncomfortable; we are eager to smooth over a child’s fears with comforting falsehoods. “Don’t worry, nothing is going to happen to me,” a mother might say when her child is distraught at the thought of her mortality. But the child knows that sometimes mothers die and his mother is no different. Children are wise enough to be afraid of death, loss, and danger – after all, these are frightening things. The question is whether we allow them to wrestle well with these fears or not. British writer G. K. Chesterton famously wrote, “The baby has known the dragon intimately ever since he had an imagination. What the fairy tale provides for him is a Saint George to kill the dragon.” If we spend our efforts trying to convince a child that the dragons of life can’t hurt him, we not only fail to tell the truth, we fail to show him that dragons do not have the last word. And the child longs to be equipped to face the monsters he fears, whether dragons or death.</p>
<p><span>While classic fairy tales</span> are maligned by some for being too realistic and unsettling in acknowledging the reality of evil, they are also criticized for being too<em> un</em>realistic for their final hopeful resolutions. “I won’t read my daughter fairy tales!” I’ve been told by concerned parents. “She might think Prince Charming is coming to save her and she’ll only be disappointed when she wakes up to the <em>real world</em>.” These critics are willing to leave the dragon in the story but want to remove Saint&nbsp;George. The endings of classic fairy tales are considered too rosy for a child’s consumption. Perhaps robbing young children of the world of fairyland where they can face the monsters they fear results in an inevitable overcorrection, as the explosion of dystopian YA fiction might suggest. Many such books see the world through a lens of despair, defeat, and mistrust, overrun with dragons with no Saint&nbsp;George in sight. A belief that despair is the only realistic response to the nature of the world leads to narratives like <em>Game of Thrones,</em> which presents a universe where there is neither good nor evil, just the unquenchable thirst for power that motivates every soul.</p>
<p>Even in stories for younger kids – A Series of Unfortunate Events, for example – we see the fairy tale turned on its head. In this series the orphaned Baudelaire children are never given the happily ever after they deserve. In <em>Grimms’ Fairy Tales</em> the heroes or heroines sometimes encounter helpers along the way, or they might meet manipulators or liars. In this they are realistic. And there is the understanding that the world is not merely dark; both good and evil people inhabit it, but there are some worth trusting. But the Baudelaires can trust no one. The adults they encounter are either too weak to help them or are secretly trying to harm them. Another trend of subverted fairy tale is the apologia for a villain, such as Disney’s <em>Maleficent, </em>in which the evil sorceress becomes the sympathetic victim. In these stories both evil <em>and</em> goodness are removed from the tale. The villain’s evil is explained away, the hero’s goodness revealed to be a farce. And yet, while these kinds of stories are undeniably popular, it is notable that the series that has recently captured the imagination of children (and even adults) most deeply is a modern fairy tale that includes both wrestling with evil and death and a happily ever after: J. K. Rowling’s Harry Potter<em>, </em>a story, like <em>Grimms’ Fairy Tales</em>, with an indisputably Christian framework.</p>
<p><span>Every human being</span> understands the world and his place in it through narratives. God wires us to be formed by story; Jesus himself tells parables to teach his disciples. It is of the highest importance that we consider what stories we are telling our young people. What character do they think they are in the story of their lives? And what kind of world is their story set in? Is it a world in which greed and power will be ultimately triumphant? Is it a world in which love and goodness hold any sway? Could the dread that seems to plague our young people be not merely a reaction to the brokenness of our world but our failure to communicate that the universe will ultimately be set right as both fairy tales and the gospel promise? After all, as the theologian Vigen Guroian beautifully puts it in his fantastic book <em><a rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://bookshop.org/a/78/9780195384314" target="_blank">Tending the Heart of Virtue</a></em>, “Fairy tales lead us toward a belief in something that, if it were not also so veiled in a mystery, common sense alone would affirm: if there is a story, there must surely be a storyteller.” And in this lies our deepest hope.</p>
<p><spa>The fairy tale acknowledges that parents do not always love and care for their children as they ought, that loved ones die and leave us alone and grieving, that evil is real and often powerful, and that violence and sin are present in our world. All these truths make grownups uncomfortable; we are eager to smooth over a child’s fears with comforting falsehoods.</spa></p>
<p>To combat both the anxiety that comes to children robbed of the space to confront evil and the despair that holds that the last chapter of humanity’s tale is final defeat, we have to offer truer stories. Early in life, children need to be steeped in fairy tales that don’t gloss over the dark and ugly parts of the world. Children are wise; they reject the false advertising of cheap positive thinking for the real prize of hard-won hope. For a message of hope to be received, it must be hope that shines in darkness, hope that breaks the witch’s spell. “It is the mark of a good fairy-story,” J. R. R. Tolkien writes in his essay “On Fairy-Stories,” “that however wild its events, however fantastic or terrible the adventures, it can give to child or man that hears it, when the ‘turn’ comes, a catch of the breath, a beat and lifting of the heart, near to (or indeed accompanied by) tears.” But to tell such stories, we have to believe they are true. If we grown-ups don’t believe there is, as Tolkien calls it, “joy beyond the walls of the world,” then our children will not believe us when we share fairy tales that end with hope. And if we offer narratives of a world without hope, our stories are no better than the sanitized tales that refuse to acknowledge mortality and evil. They are simply a different way of failing to tell the whole truth.</p>
<p>But happily ever afters may be difficult to envision without an eternal perspective. At the end of Andersen’s story, the little mermaid loses her life and her body disintegrates into sea foam on the surface of the waves. But her sacrifice for her beloved is rewarded by the chance to gain a human soul and therefore to experience eternal life. This ending is only hopeful accompanied by a belief in an afterlife, just as Flannery O’Connor’s “A Good Man Is Hard to Find” only ends “happily” with a salvific outpouring of grace if we see eternal hope for the murdered grandmother. Perhaps it’s the loss of this eternal perspective that prevents us from seeing beyond darkness to hope.</p>
<p>“Deprive children of stories,” warns philosopher Alasdair MacIntyre, “and you leave them unscripted, anxious stutterers in their actions as in their words.” Like Hansel and Gretel leaving their little white pebbles along their path into the dark forest, the next generation needs us to provide them with touchstones that can keep them from getting lost on their journey and help them find their way back home. These pathfinders are the stories they’re told, stories that light up the dark, that reveal the existence of dragons hiding in the caves of life, and remind us that Saint George will be ultimately triumphant, even when it seems all hope is lost.</p>                
            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Komorebi: Tiling Window Management for Windows (112 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/LGUG2Z/komorebi</link>
            <guid>40779658</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 19:20:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/LGUG2Z/komorebi">https://github.com/LGUG2Z/komorebi</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40779658">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">komorebi</h2><a id="user-content-komorebi" aria-label="Permalink: komorebi" href="#komorebi"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Tiling Window Management for Windows.</p>
<p dir="auto">
  <a href="https://techforpalestine.org/learn-more" rel="nofollow">
    <img alt="Tech for Palestine" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/1001b2e8cc187a1b0f6d763935ab994a4a79c0090e13752ad68027b8111b152f/68747470733a2f2f62616467652e74656368666f7270616c657374696e652e6f72672f64656661756c74" data-canonical-src="https://badge.techforpalestine.org/default">
  </a>
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/477fa185a7c31f2c9c311d59fc512318e371d07bc2f39ced730ee0ccea0c2e78/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f616374696f6e732f776f726b666c6f772f7374617475732f4c475547325a2f6b6f6d6f726562692f2e6769746875622f776f726b666c6f77732f77696e646f77732e79616d6c"><img alt="GitHub Workflow Status" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/477fa185a7c31f2c9c311d59fc512318e371d07bc2f39ced730ee0ccea0c2e78/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f616374696f6e732f776f726b666c6f772f7374617475732f4c475547325a2f6b6f6d6f726562692f2e6769746875622f776f726b666c6f77732f77696e646f77732e79616d6c" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/github/actions/workflow/status/LGUG2Z/komorebi/.github/workflows/windows.yaml"></a>
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/6d3d7384f77720bef99bf9614b83d762e02867b3faf9aeb03b7d8fbb781952d3/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f6c6963656e73652f4c475547325a2f6b6f6d6f72656269"><img alt="GitHub" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/6d3d7384f77720bef99bf9614b83d762e02867b3faf9aeb03b7d8fbb781952d3/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f6c6963656e73652f4c475547325a2f6b6f6d6f72656269" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/github/license/LGUG2Z/komorebi"></a>
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/318ab98e5a1738865ccaf0c4c3564c76106945a1a9299f6808cd95c38b29cda0/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f646f776e6c6f6164732f4c475547325a2f6b6f6d6f726562692f746f74616c"><img alt="GitHub all releases" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/318ab98e5a1738865ccaf0c4c3564c76106945a1a9299f6808cd95c38b29cda0/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f646f776e6c6f6164732f4c475547325a2f6b6f6d6f726562692f746f74616c" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/github/downloads/LGUG2Z/komorebi/total"></a>
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/d9cc5fdd81174e6ca761d02306d09ddaf82c1b514f5ee4e2e1b846b14c341f0e/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f636f6d6d6974732d73696e63652f4c475547325a2f6b6f6d6f726562692f6c6174657374"><img alt="GitHub commits since latest release (by date) for a branch" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/d9cc5fdd81174e6ca761d02306d09ddaf82c1b514f5ee4e2e1b846b14c341f0e/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f636f6d6d6974732d73696e63652f4c475547325a2f6b6f6d6f726562692f6c6174657374" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/github/commits-since/LGUG2Z/komorebi/latest"></a>
  <a href="https://discord.gg/mGkn66PHkx" rel="nofollow">
    <img alt="Discord" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/7a6a6df9d1454d6c772b6a4ac89d4c4f9bd00f0beb13da8dddedf91be3758c54/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f646973636f72642f383938353534363930313236363330393134" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/discord/898554690126630914">
  </a>
  <a href="https://github.com/sponsors/LGUG2Z">
    <img alt="GitHub Sponsors" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/4d04242f64262a8b070cae18fcf8c75663de1e146f424f150787b50caf74854c/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f73706f6e736f72732f4c475547325a" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/github/sponsors/LGUG2Z">
  </a>
  <a href="https://ko-fi.com/lgug2z" rel="nofollow">
    <img alt="Ko-fi" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/18eac10bf5828c77b977340b5c8152812b26e5a5ed13a30efbe73b09b86ca3b8/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f6b6f66692d7469702d677265656e" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/kofi-tip-green">
  </a>
  <a href="https://notado.app/feeds/jado/software-development" rel="nofollow">
    <img alt="Notado Feed" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/87279894bfdef05fec7054f70fab94bfd79116bede31ab7bd220291fc50d7c37/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f4e6f7461646f2d5375627363726962652d696e666f726d6174696f6e616c" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/Notado-Subscribe-informational">
  </a>
  <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCeai3-do-9O4MNy9_xjO6mg?sub_confirmation=1" rel="nofollow">
    <img alt="YouTube" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/f9cf1698338c99adff0c58b11c086eec6b008a8e19581b371a21ccc276fe1f1f/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f796f75747562652f6368616e6e656c2f73756273637269626572732f5543656169332d646f2d394f344d4e79395f786a4f366d67" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/youtube/channel/subscribers/UCeai3-do-9O4MNy9_xjO6mg">
  </a>
</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/13164844/184027064-f5a6cec2-2865-4d65-a549-a1f1da589abf.png"><img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/13164844/184027064-f5a6cec2-2865-4d65-a549-a1f1da589abf.png" alt="screenshot"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><em>komorebi</em> is a tiling window manager that works as an extension to Microsoft's
<a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/win32/dwm/dwm-overview" rel="nofollow">Desktop Window
Manager</a> in
Windows 10 and above.</p>
<p dir="auto"><em>komorebi</em> allows you to control application windows, virtual workspaces and display monitors with a CLI which can be
used with third-party software such as <a href="https://github.com/LGUG2Z/whkd"><code>whkd</code></a>
and <a href="https://github.com/Lexikos/AutoHotkey_L">AutoHotKey</a> to set user-defined keyboard shortcuts.</p>
<p dir="auto"><em>komorebi</em> aims to make <em>as few modifications as possible</em> to the operating
system and desktop environment by default. Users are free to make such
modifications in their own configuration files for <em>komorebi</em>, but these will
remain opt-in and off-by-default for the foreseeable future.</p>
<p dir="auto">Please refer to the <a href="https://lgug2z.github.io/komorebi" rel="nofollow">documentation</a> for instructions on how
to <a href="https://lgug2z.github.io/komorebi/installation.html" rel="nofollow">install</a> and
<a href="https://lgug2z.github.io/komorebi/example-configurations.html" rel="nofollow">configure</a>
<em>komorebi</em>, <a href="https://lgug2z.github.io/komorebi/common-workflows/komorebi-config-home.html" rel="nofollow">common workflows</a>, a complete
<a href="https://komorebi.lgug2z.com/schema" rel="nofollow">configuration schema reference</a> and a
complete <a href="https://lgug2z.github.io/komorebi/cli/quickstart.html" rel="nofollow">CLI reference</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">There is a <a href="https://discord.gg/mGkn66PHkx" rel="nofollow">Discord server</a> available for
<em>komorebi</em>-related discussion, help, troubleshooting etc. If you have any
specific feature requests or bugs to report, please create an issue in this
repository.</p>
<p dir="auto">There is a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCeai3-do-9O4MNy9_xjO6mg" rel="nofollow">YouTube
channel</a> where I post
<em>komorebi</em> development videos. If you would like to be notified of upcoming
videos please subscribe and turn on notifications.</p>
<p dir="auto"><em>komorebi</em> is a free and source-available project, and one that encourages you to
make charitable donations if you find the software to be useful and have the
financial means.</p>
<p dir="auto">I encourage you to make a charitable donation to the <a href="https://pcrf1.app.neoncrm.com/forms/gaza-recovery" rel="nofollow">Palestine Children's
Relief Fund</a> before you
consider sponsoring me on GitHub.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/sponsors/LGUG2Z">GitHub Sponsors is enabled for this
project</a>. Unfortunately I don't have
anything specific to offer besides my gratitude and shout outs at the end of
<em>komorebi</em> live development videos and tutorials.</p>
<p dir="auto">If you would like to tip or sponsor the project but are unable to use GitHub
Sponsors, you may also sponsor through <a href="https://ko-fi.com/lgug2z" rel="nofollow">Ko-fi</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h2><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">A <a href="https://lgug2z.github.io/komorebi/installation.html" rel="nofollow">detailed installation and quickstart
guide</a> is available which shows how to get started
using <code>scoop</code>, <code>winget</code> or building from source.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H9-_c1egQ4g" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/636c3131f6fb71842a2ad58ab3f8ec8d795bf9fc803bb3a33c2762c2a1547e77/68747470733a2f2f696d672e796f75747562652e636f6d2f76692f48392d5f633165675134672f687164656661756c742e6a7067" alt="Watch the quickstart walkthrough video" data-canonical-src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/H9-_c1egQ4g/hqdefault.jpg"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Comparison With Fancy Zones</h2><a id="user-content-comparison-with-fancy-zones" aria-label="Permalink: Comparison With Fancy Zones" href="#comparison-with-fancy-zones"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Community member <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@polle5555" rel="nofollow">Olge</a> has created an
excellent video which compares the default window management features of
Windows 11, Fancy Zones and komorebi.</p>
<p dir="auto">If you are not familiar with tiling window managers or if you are looking at
komorebi and wondering "how is this different from Fancy Zones? 🤔", this short
video will answer the majority of your questions.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0LCbS_gm0RA" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/2fbffdc96db3be3802ac0ead0bcf79319e2afe3bcde674bab57d3209bee1e220/68747470733a2f2f696d672e796f75747562652e636f6d2f76692f304c4362535f676d3052412f687164656661756c742e6a7067" alt="Watch the comparison video" data-canonical-src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/0LCbS_gm0RA/hqdefault.jpg"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Demonstrations</h2><a id="user-content-demonstrations" aria-label="Permalink: Demonstrations" href="#demonstrations"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/amnweb">@amnweb</a> showing <em>komorebi</em> <code>v0.1.28-dev.0</code> running on Windows 11 with window borders,
unfocused window transparency and animations enabled, using a custom status bar integrated using
<em>komorebi</em>'s <a href="https://github.com/LGUG2Z/komorebi?tab=readme-ov-file#window-manager-event-subscriptions">Window Manager Event Subscriptions</a>.</p>
<details open="">
  <summary>
    
    <span aria-label="Video description Windows.11.and.Komorebi.mp4">Windows.11.and.Komorebi.mp4</span>
    <span></span>
  </summary>

  <video src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/13164844/342515179-21be8dc4-fa76-4f70-9b37-1d316f4b40c2.mp4?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MTkzMDA5MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcxOTMwMDYwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii8xMzE2NDg0NC8zNDI1MTUxNzktMjFiZThkYzQtZmE3Ni00ZjcwLTliMzctMWQzMTZmNGI0MGMyLm1wND9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDA2MjUlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQwNjI1VDA3MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTFhMjM5NWQ4OTZlMGQ0OWEyMmMzMmNlNTI3YmJjZDEzODU0NmUzMDM0ZjRkNjMyOGM5ZDVmZTcxOTBlMTk0YWYmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0JmFjdG9yX2lkPTAma2V5X2lkPTAmcmVwb19pZD0wIn0.fukhe_u9TVbt71bzK0hw6POLpldwuWREHVucNqnuzRU" data-canonical-src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/13164844/342515179-21be8dc4-fa76-4f70-9b37-1d316f4b40c2.mp4?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MTkzMDA5MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcxOTMwMDYwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii8xMzE2NDg0NC8zNDI1MTUxNzktMjFiZThkYzQtZmE3Ni00ZjcwLTliMzctMWQzMTZmNGI0MGMyLm1wND9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDA2MjUlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQwNjI1VDA3MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTFhMjM5NWQ4OTZlMGQ0OWEyMmMzMmNlNTI3YmJjZDEzODU0NmUzMDM0ZjRkNjMyOGM5ZDVmZTcxOTBlMTk0YWYmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0JmFjdG9yX2lkPTAma2V5X2lkPTAmcmVwb19pZD0wIn0.fukhe_u9TVbt71bzK0hw6POLpldwuWREHVucNqnuzRU" controls="controls" muted="muted">

  </video>
</details>

<p dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/haxibami">@haxibami</a> showing <em>komorebi</em> running on Windows
11 with a terminal emulator, a web browser and a code editor. The original
video can be viewed
<a href="https://twitter.com/haxibami/status/1501560766578659332" rel="nofollow">here</a>.</p>
<details open="">
  <summary>
    
    <span aria-label="Video description 0vadqFOyIJHglPRY.mp4">0vadqFOyIJHglPRY.mp4</span>
    <span></span>
  </summary>

  <video src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/13164844/163496447-20c3ff0a-c5d8-40d1-9cc8-156c4cebf12e.mp4?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MTkzMDA5MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcxOTMwMDYwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii8xMzE2NDg0NC8xNjM0OTY0NDctMjBjM2ZmMGEtYzVkOC00MGQxLTljYzgtMTU2YzRjZWJmMTJlLm1wND9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDA2MjUlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQwNjI1VDA3MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTU2YjAwYjgxMWEwMGUwODUxZjJhNmJiMjRhZjcwYjZlMWFlNTMzZTA0MTQ0ZTdiYjVjYjAzMWNmM2M4NzNhMjcmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0JmFjdG9yX2lkPTAma2V5X2lkPTAmcmVwb19pZD0wIn0.OckeX2A4rlh-hn42dA4RQl9PrUpFVC8s3ihsB-3ScaY" data-canonical-src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/13164844/163496447-20c3ff0a-c5d8-40d1-9cc8-156c4cebf12e.mp4?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MTkzMDA5MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcxOTMwMDYwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii8xMzE2NDg0NC8xNjM0OTY0NDctMjBjM2ZmMGEtYzVkOC00MGQxLTljYzgtMTU2YzRjZWJmMTJlLm1wND9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDA2MjUlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQwNjI1VDA3MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTU2YjAwYjgxMWEwMGUwODUxZjJhNmJiMjRhZjcwYjZlMWFlNTMzZTA0MTQ0ZTdiYjVjYjAzMWNmM2M4NzNhMjcmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0JmFjdG9yX2lkPTAma2V5X2lkPTAmcmVwb19pZD0wIn0.OckeX2A4rlh-hn42dA4RQl9PrUpFVC8s3ihsB-3ScaY" controls="controls" muted="muted">

  </video>
</details>

<p dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/aik2mlj">@aik2mlj</a> showing <em>komorebi</em> running on Windows 11
with multiple workspaces, terminal emulators, a web browser, and the
<a href="https://github.com/DenBot/yasb">yasb</a> status bar with the <em>komorebi</em> workspace
widget enabled. The original video can be viewed
<a href="https://zhuanlan.zhihu.com/p/455064481" rel="nofollow">here</a>.</p>
<details open="">
  <summary>
    
    <span aria-label="Video description 0e0dd7fc-7115-11ec-a064-42a1fbc2e1e9-v4_t10000011-wbjnuX5De6.mp4">0e0dd7fc-7115-11ec-a064-42a1fbc2e1e9-v4_t10000011-wbjnuX5De6.mp4</span>
    <span></span>
  </summary>

  <video src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/13164844/163496414-a9cde3d1-b8a7-4a7a-96fb-a8985380bc70.mp4?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MTkzMDA5MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcxOTMwMDYwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii8xMzE2NDg0NC8xNjM0OTY0MTQtYTljZGUzZDEtYjhhNy00YTdhLTk2ZmItYTg5ODUzODBiYzcwLm1wND9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDA2MjUlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQwNjI1VDA3MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTY1YzNkMTJhMTk2Yjk2MmNkOTZiNzM0NzRiZGMzNDg0NDA4ZjdkZjRmYTFhYjA2Y2RlMDRlMGY4MjY4ZDY4NmImWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0JmFjdG9yX2lkPTAma2V5X2lkPTAmcmVwb19pZD0wIn0.Vxv8crwO7FP4221K1b41iXMmq6uVEfJrY6IuOaWQnJA" data-canonical-src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/13164844/163496414-a9cde3d1-b8a7-4a7a-96fb-a8985380bc70.mp4?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MTkzMDA5MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcxOTMwMDYwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii8xMzE2NDg0NC8xNjM0OTY0MTQtYTljZGUzZDEtYjhhNy00YTdhLTk2ZmItYTg5ODUzODBiYzcwLm1wND9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDA2MjUlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQwNjI1VDA3MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTY1YzNkMTJhMTk2Yjk2MmNkOTZiNzM0NzRiZGMzNDg0NDA4ZjdkZjRmYTFhYjA2Y2RlMDRlMGY4MjY4ZDY4NmImWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0JmFjdG9yX2lkPTAma2V5X2lkPTAmcmVwb19pZD0wIn0.Vxv8crwO7FP4221K1b41iXMmq6uVEfJrY6IuOaWQnJA" controls="controls" muted="muted">

  </video>
</details>

<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contribution Guidelines</h2><a id="user-content-contribution-guidelines" aria-label="Permalink: Contribution Guidelines" href="#contribution-guidelines"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If you would like to contribute to <code>komorebi</code> please take the time to carefully read the guidelines below.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Commit hygiene</h2><a id="user-content-commit-hygiene" aria-label="Permalink: Commit hygiene" href="#commit-hygiene"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Flatten all <code>use</code> statements</li>
<li>Run <code>cargo +stable clippy</code> and ensure that all lints and suggestions have been addressed before committing</li>
<li>Run <code>cargo +nightly fmt --all</code> to ensure consistent formatting before committing</li>
<li>Use <code>git cz</code> with
the <a href="https://github.com/commitizen/cz-cli#conventional-commit-messages-as-a-global-utility">Commitizen CLI</a> to prepare
commit messages</li>
<li>Provide <strong>at least</strong> one short sentence or paragraph in your commit message body to describe your thought process for the
changes being committed</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">PRs should contain only a single feature or bug fix</h2><a id="user-content-prs-should-contain-only-a-single-feature-or-bug-fix" aria-label="Permalink: PRs should contain only a single feature or bug fix" href="#prs-should-contain-only-a-single-feature-or-bug-fix"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">It is very difficult to review pull requests which touch multiple unrelated features and parts of the codebase.</p>
<p dir="auto">Please do not submit pull requests like this; you will be asked to separate them into smaller PRs that deal only with
one feature or bug fix at a time.</p>
<p dir="auto">If you are working on multiple features and bug fixes, I suggest that you cut a branch called <code>local-trunk</code>
from <code>master</code> which you keep up to date, and rebase the various independent branches you are working on onto that branch
if you want to test them together or create a build with everything integrated.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Refactors to the codebase must have prior approval</h2><a id="user-content-refactors-to-the-codebase-must-have-prior-approval" aria-label="Permalink: Refactors to the codebase must have prior approval" href="#refactors-to-the-codebase-must-have-prior-approval"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><code>komorebi</code> is a mature codebase with an internal consistency and structure that has developed organically over close to
half a decade.</p>
<p dir="auto">There are <a href="https://youtube.com/@LGUG2Z" rel="nofollow">countless hours of live coding videos</a> demonstrating work on this project and
showing new contributors how to do everything from basic tasks like implementing new <code>komorebic</code> commands to
distinguishing monitors by manufacturer hardware identifiers and video card ports.</p>
<p dir="auto">Refactors to the structure of the codebase are not taken lightly and require prior discussion and approval.</p>
<p dir="auto">Please do not start refactoring the codebase with the expectation of having your changes integrated until you receive an
explicit approval or a request to do so.</p>
<p dir="auto">Similarly, when implementing features and bug fixes, please stick to the structure of the codebase as much as possible
and do not take this as an opportunity to do some "refactoring along the way".</p>
<p dir="auto">It is extremely difficult to review PRs for features and bug fixes if they are lost in sweeping changes to the structure
of the codebase.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Breaking changes to user-facing interfaces are unacceptable</h2><a id="user-content-breaking-changes-to-user-facing-interfaces-are-unacceptable" aria-label="Permalink: Breaking changes to user-facing interfaces are unacceptable" href="#breaking-changes-to-user-facing-interfaces-are-unacceptable"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This includes but is not limited to:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>All <code>komorebic</code> commands</li>
<li>The <code>komorebi.json</code> schema</li>
<li>The <a href="https://github.com/LGUG2Z/komorebi-application-specific-configuration"><code>komorebi-application-specific-configuration</code></a>
schema</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">No user should ever find that their configuration file has stopped working after upgrading to a new version
of <code>komorebi</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto">More often than not there are ways to reformulate changes that may initially seem like they require breaking user-facing
interfaces into additive changes.</p>
<p dir="auto">For some inspiration please take a look
at <a href="https://github.com/LGUG2Z/komorebi/commit/e7d928a065eb63bb4ea1fb864c69c1cae8cc763b">this commit</a> which added the
ability for users to specify colours in <code>komorebi.json</code> in Hex format alongside RGB.</p>
<p dir="auto">There is also a process in place for graceful, non-breaking, deprecation of configuration options that are no longer
required.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><code>komorebi</code> is licensed under the <a href="https://polyformproject.org/licenses/strict/1.0.0" rel="nofollow">PolyForm Strict 1.0.0
license</a>. On a high level
this means that you are free to do whatever you want with <code>komorebi</code> other than
redistribution, or distribution of new works (ie. hard-forks) based on the
software.</p>
<p dir="auto">Anyone is free to make their own fork of <code>komorebi</code> with changes intended
either for personal use or for integration back upstream via pull requests.</p>
<p dir="auto">Please see <a href="https://github.com/LGUG2Z/komorebi/blob/master/CONTRIBUTING.md">CONTRIBUTING.md</a> for more information about how
code contributions to <code>komorebi</code> are licensed.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Development</h2><a id="user-content-development" aria-label="Permalink: Development" href="#development"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If you use IntelliJ, you should enable the following settings to ensure that code generated by macros is recognised by
the IDE for completions and navigation:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Set <code>Expand declarative macros</code>
to <code>Use new engine</code> under "Settings &gt; Langauges &amp; Frameworks &gt; Rust"</li>
<li>Enable the following experimental features:
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>org.rust.cargo.evaluate.build.scripts</code></li>
<li><code>org.rust.macros.proc</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Logs and Debugging</h2><a id="user-content-logs-and-debugging" aria-label="Permalink: Logs and Debugging" href="#logs-and-debugging"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Logs from <code>komorebi</code> will be appended to <code>%LOCALAPPDATA%/komorebi/komorebi.log</code>; this file is never rotated or overwritten, so it will keep
growing until it is deleted by the user.</p>
<p dir="auto">Whenever running the <code>komorebic stop</code> command or sending a Ctrl-C signal to <code>komorebi</code> directly, the <code>komorebi</code> process
ensures that all hidden windows are restored before termination.</p>
<p dir="auto">If however, you ever end up with windows that are hidden and cannot be restored, a list of window handles known
to <code>komorebi</code> are stored and continuously updated in <code>%LOCALAPPDATA%/komorebi//komorebi.hwnd.json</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Restoring Windows</h2><a id="user-content-restoring-windows" aria-label="Permalink: Restoring Windows" href="#restoring-windows"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Running <code>komorebic restore-windows</code> will read the list of window handles and forcibly restore them, regardless of
whether the main <code>komorebi</code> process is running.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Panics and Deadlocks</h2><a id="user-content-panics-and-deadlocks" aria-label="Permalink: Panics and Deadlocks" href="#panics-and-deadlocks"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If <code>komorebi</code> ever stops responding, it is most likely either due to either a panic or a deadlock. In the case of a
panic, this will be reported in the log. In the case of a deadlock, there will not be any errors in the log, but the
process and the log will appear frozen.</p>
<p dir="auto">If you believe you have encountered a deadlock, you can compile <code>komorebi</code> with <code>--features deadlock_detection</code> and try
reproducing the deadlock again. This will check for deadlocks every 5 seconds in the background, and if a deadlock is
found, information about it will appear in the log which can be shared when opening an issue.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Window Manager State and Integrations</h2><a id="user-content-window-manager-state-and-integrations" aria-label="Permalink: Window Manager State and Integrations" href="#window-manager-state-and-integrations"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The current state of the window manager can be queried using the <code>komorebic state</code> command, which returns a JSON
representation of the <code>State</code> struct.</p>
<p dir="auto">This may also be polled to build further integrations and widgets on top of.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Window Manager Event Subscriptions</h2><a id="user-content-window-manager-event-subscriptions" aria-label="Permalink: Window Manager Event Subscriptions" href="#window-manager-event-subscriptions"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Named Pipes</h2><a id="user-content-named-pipes" aria-label="Permalink: Named Pipes" href="#named-pipes"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">It is possible to subscribe to notifications of every <code>WindowManagerEvent</code> and <code>SocketMessage</code> handled
by <code>komorebi</code> using <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/win32/ipc/named-pipes" rel="nofollow">Named Pipes</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">First, your application must create a named pipe. Once the named pipe has been created, run the following command:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="komorebic.exe subscribe-pipe <your pipe name>"><pre><span>komorebic.exe</span> subscribe<span>-</span>pipe <span>&lt;</span>your pipe name<span>&gt;</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Note that you do not have to include the full path of the named pipe, just the name.</p>
<p dir="auto">If the named pipe exists, <code>komorebi</code> will start pushing JSON data of successfully handled events and messages:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="{&quot;event&quot;:{&quot;type&quot;:&quot;AddSubscriber&quot;,&quot;content&quot;:&quot;yasb&quot;},&quot;state&quot;:{}}
{&quot;event&quot;:{&quot;type&quot;:&quot;FocusWindow&quot;,&quot;content&quot;:&quot;Left&quot;},&quot;state&quot;:{}}
{&quot;event&quot;:{&quot;type&quot;:&quot;FocusChange&quot;,&quot;content&quot;:[&quot;SystemForeground&quot;,{&quot;hwnd&quot;:131444,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;komorebi – README.md&quot;,&quot;exe&quot;:&quot;idea64.exe&quot;,&quot;class&quot;:&quot;SunAwtFrame&quot;,&quot;rect&quot;:{&quot;left&quot;:13,&quot;top&quot;:60,&quot;right&quot;:1520,&quot;bottom&quot;:1655}}]},&quot;state&quot;:{}}
{&quot;event&quot;:{&quot;type&quot;:&quot;MonitorPoll&quot;,&quot;content&quot;:[&quot;ObjectCreate&quot;,{&quot;hwnd&quot;:5572450,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;OLEChannelWnd&quot;,&quot;exe&quot;:&quot;explorer.exe&quot;,&quot;class&quot;:&quot;OleMainThreadWndClass&quot;,&quot;rect&quot;:{&quot;left&quot;:0,&quot;top&quot;:0,&quot;right&quot;:0,&quot;bottom&quot;:0}}]},&quot;state&quot;:{}}
{&quot;event&quot;:{&quot;type&quot;:&quot;FocusWindow&quot;,&quot;content&quot;:&quot;Right&quot;},&quot;state&quot;:{}}
{&quot;event&quot;:{&quot;type&quot;:&quot;FocusChange&quot;,&quot;content&quot;:[&quot;SystemForeground&quot;,{&quot;hwnd&quot;:132968,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;Windows PowerShell&quot;,&quot;exe&quot;:&quot;WindowsTerminal.exe&quot;,&quot;class&quot;:&quot;CASCADIA_HOSTING_WINDOW_CLASS&quot;,&quot;rect&quot;:{&quot;left&quot;:1539,&quot;top&quot;:60,&quot;right&quot;:1520,&quot;bottom&quot;:821}}]},&quot;state&quot;:{}}
{&quot;event&quot;:{&quot;type&quot;:&quot;FocusWindow&quot;,&quot;content&quot;:&quot;Down&quot;},&quot;state&quot;:{}}
{&quot;event&quot;:{&quot;type&quot;:&quot;FocusChange&quot;,&quot;content&quot;:[&quot;SystemForeground&quot;,{&quot;hwnd&quot;:329264,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;den — Mozilla Firefox&quot;,&quot;exe&quot;:&quot;firefox.exe&quot;,&quot;class&quot;:&quot;MozillaWindowClass&quot;,&quot;rect&quot;:{&quot;left&quot;:1539,&quot;top&quot;:894,&quot;right&quot;:1520,&quot;bottom&quot;:821}}]},&quot;state&quot;:{}}
{&quot;event&quot;:{&quot;type&quot;:&quot;FocusWindow&quot;,&quot;content&quot;:&quot;Up&quot;},&quot;state&quot;:{}}
{&quot;event&quot;:{&quot;type&quot;:&quot;FocusChange&quot;,&quot;content&quot;:[&quot;SystemForeground&quot;,{&quot;hwnd&quot;:132968,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;Windows PowerShell&quot;,&quot;exe&quot;:&quot;WindowsTerminal.exe&quot;,&quot;class&quot;:&quot;CASCADIA_HOSTING_WINDOW_CLASS&quot;,&quot;rect&quot;:{&quot;left&quot;:1539,&quot;top&quot;:60,&quot;right&quot;:1520,&quot;bottom&quot;:821}}]},&quot;state&quot;:{}}"><pre>{<span>"event"</span>:{<span>"type"</span>:<span><span>"</span>AddSubscriber<span>"</span></span>,<span>"content"</span>:<span><span>"</span>yasb<span>"</span></span>},<span>"state"</span>:{}}
{<span>"event"</span>:{<span>"type"</span>:<span><span>"</span>FocusWindow<span>"</span></span>,<span>"content"</span>:<span><span>"</span>Left<span>"</span></span>},<span>"state"</span>:{}}
{<span>"event"</span>:{<span>"type"</span>:<span><span>"</span>FocusChange<span>"</span></span>,<span>"content"</span>:[<span><span>"</span>SystemForeground<span>"</span></span>,{<span>"hwnd"</span>:<span>131444</span>,<span>"title"</span>:<span><span>"</span>komorebi – README.md<span>"</span></span>,<span>"exe"</span>:<span><span>"</span>idea64.exe<span>"</span></span>,<span>"class"</span>:<span><span>"</span>SunAwtFrame<span>"</span></span>,<span>"rect"</span>:{<span>"left"</span>:<span>13</span>,<span>"top"</span>:<span>60</span>,<span>"right"</span>:<span>1520</span>,<span>"bottom"</span>:<span>1655</span>}}]},<span>"state"</span>:{}}
{<span>"event"</span>:{<span>"type"</span>:<span><span>"</span>MonitorPoll<span>"</span></span>,<span>"content"</span>:[<span><span>"</span>ObjectCreate<span>"</span></span>,{<span>"hwnd"</span>:<span>5572450</span>,<span>"title"</span>:<span><span>"</span>OLEChannelWnd<span>"</span></span>,<span>"exe"</span>:<span><span>"</span>explorer.exe<span>"</span></span>,<span>"class"</span>:<span><span>"</span>OleMainThreadWndClass<span>"</span></span>,<span>"rect"</span>:{<span>"left"</span>:<span>0</span>,<span>"top"</span>:<span>0</span>,<span>"right"</span>:<span>0</span>,<span>"bottom"</span>:<span>0</span>}}]},<span>"state"</span>:{}}
{<span>"event"</span>:{<span>"type"</span>:<span><span>"</span>FocusWindow<span>"</span></span>,<span>"content"</span>:<span><span>"</span>Right<span>"</span></span>},<span>"state"</span>:{}}
{<span>"event"</span>:{<span>"type"</span>:<span><span>"</span>FocusChange<span>"</span></span>,<span>"content"</span>:[<span><span>"</span>SystemForeground<span>"</span></span>,{<span>"hwnd"</span>:<span>132968</span>,<span>"title"</span>:<span><span>"</span>Windows PowerShell<span>"</span></span>,<span>"exe"</span>:<span><span>"</span>WindowsTerminal.exe<span>"</span></span>,<span>"class"</span>:<span><span>"</span>CASCADIA_HOSTING_WINDOW_CLASS<span>"</span></span>,<span>"rect"</span>:{<span>"left"</span>:<span>1539</span>,<span>"top"</span>:<span>60</span>,<span>"right"</span>:<span>1520</span>,<span>"bottom"</span>:<span>821</span>}}]},<span>"state"</span>:{}}
{<span>"event"</span>:{<span>"type"</span>:<span><span>"</span>FocusWindow<span>"</span></span>,<span>"content"</span>:<span><span>"</span>Down<span>"</span></span>},<span>"state"</span>:{}}
{<span>"event"</span>:{<span>"type"</span>:<span><span>"</span>FocusChange<span>"</span></span>,<span>"content"</span>:[<span><span>"</span>SystemForeground<span>"</span></span>,{<span>"hwnd"</span>:<span>329264</span>,<span>"title"</span>:<span><span>"</span>den — Mozilla Firefox<span>"</span></span>,<span>"exe"</span>:<span><span>"</span>firefox.exe<span>"</span></span>,<span>"class"</span>:<span><span>"</span>MozillaWindowClass<span>"</span></span>,<span>"rect"</span>:{<span>"left"</span>:<span>1539</span>,<span>"top"</span>:<span>894</span>,<span>"right"</span>:<span>1520</span>,<span>"bottom"</span>:<span>821</span>}}]},<span>"state"</span>:{}}
{<span>"event"</span>:{<span>"type"</span>:<span><span>"</span>FocusWindow<span>"</span></span>,<span>"content"</span>:<span><span>"</span>Up<span>"</span></span>},<span>"state"</span>:{}}
{<span>"event"</span>:{<span>"type"</span>:<span><span>"</span>FocusChange<span>"</span></span>,<span>"content"</span>:[<span><span>"</span>SystemForeground<span>"</span></span>,{<span>"hwnd"</span>:<span>132968</span>,<span>"title"</span>:<span><span>"</span>Windows PowerShell<span>"</span></span>,<span>"exe"</span>:<span><span>"</span>WindowsTerminal.exe<span>"</span></span>,<span>"class"</span>:<span><span>"</span>CASCADIA_HOSTING_WINDOW_CLASS<span>"</span></span>,<span>"rect"</span>:{<span>"left"</span>:<span>1539</span>,<span>"top"</span>:<span>60</span>,<span>"right"</span>:<span>1520</span>,<span>"bottom"</span>:<span>821</span>}}]},<span>"state"</span>:{}}</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">You may then filter on the <code>type</code> key to listen to the events that you are interested in. For a full list of possible
notification types, refer to the enum variants of <code>WindowManagerEvent</code> in <code>komorebi</code> and <code>SocketMessage</code>
in <code>komorebi-core</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Below is an example of how you can subscribe to and filter on events using a named pipe in <code>nodejs</code>.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="const { exec } = require(&quot;child_process&quot;);
const net = require(&quot;net&quot;);

const pipeName = &quot;\\\\.\\pipe\\komorebi-js&quot;;
const server = net.createServer((stream) => {
  console.log(&quot;Client connected&quot;);

  // Every time there is a workspace-related event, let's log the names of all
  // workspaces on the currently focused monitor, and then log the name of the
  // currently focused workspace on that monitor

  stream.on(&quot;data&quot;, (data) => {
    let json = JSON.parse(data.toString());
    let event = json.event;

    if (event.type.includes(&quot;Workspace&quot;)) {
      let monitors = json.state.monitors;
      let current_monitor = monitors.elements[monitors.focused];
      let workspaces = monitors.elements[monitors.focused].workspaces;
      let current_workspace = workspaces.elements[workspaces.focused];

      console.log(
        workspaces.elements
          .map((workspace) => workspace.name)
          .filter((name) => name !== null)
      );
      console.log(current_workspace.name);
    }
  });

  stream.on(&quot;end&quot;, () => {
    console.log(&quot;Client disconnected&quot;);
  });
});

server.listen(pipeName, () => {
  console.log(&quot;Named pipe server listening&quot;);
});

const command = &quot;komorebic subscribe-pipe komorebi-js&quot;;

exec(command, (error, stdout, stderr) => {
  if (error) {
    console.error(`Error executing command: ${error}`);
    return;
  }
});"><pre><span>const</span> <span>{</span> exec <span>}</span> <span>=</span> <span>require</span><span>(</span><span>"child_process"</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>const</span> <span>net</span> <span>=</span> <span>require</span><span>(</span><span>"net"</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>

<span>const</span> <span>pipeName</span> <span>=</span> <span>"\\\\.\\pipe\\komorebi-js"</span><span>;</span>
<span>const</span> <span>server</span> <span>=</span> <span>net</span><span>.</span><span>createServer</span><span>(</span><span>(</span><span>stream</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>{</span>
  <span>console</span><span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span><span>"Client connected"</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>

  <span>// Every time there is a workspace-related event, let's log the names of all</span>
  <span>// workspaces on the currently focused monitor, and then log the name of the</span>
  <span>// currently focused workspace on that monitor</span>

  <span>stream</span><span>.</span><span>on</span><span>(</span><span>"data"</span><span>,</span> <span>(</span><span>data</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>let</span> <span>json</span> <span>=</span> <span>JSON</span><span>.</span><span>parse</span><span>(</span><span>data</span><span>.</span><span>toString</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
    <span>let</span> <span>event</span> <span>=</span> <span>json</span><span>.</span><span>event</span><span>;</span>

    <span>if</span> <span>(</span><span>event</span><span>.</span><span>type</span><span>.</span><span>includes</span><span>(</span><span>"Workspace"</span><span>)</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
      <span>let</span> <span>monitors</span> <span>=</span> <span>json</span><span>.</span><span>state</span><span>.</span><span>monitors</span><span>;</span>
      <span>let</span> <span>current_monitor</span> <span>=</span> <span>monitors</span><span>.</span><span>elements</span><span>[</span><span>monitors</span><span>.</span><span>focused</span><span>]</span><span>;</span>
      <span>let</span> <span>workspaces</span> <span>=</span> <span>monitors</span><span>.</span><span>elements</span><span>[</span><span>monitors</span><span>.</span><span>focused</span><span>]</span><span>.</span><span>workspaces</span><span>;</span>
      <span>let</span> <span>current_workspace</span> <span>=</span> <span>workspaces</span><span>.</span><span>elements</span><span>[</span><span>workspaces</span><span>.</span><span>focused</span><span>]</span><span>;</span>

      <span>console</span><span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span>
        <span>workspaces</span><span>.</span><span>elements</span>
          <span>.</span><span>map</span><span>(</span><span>(</span><span>workspace</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>workspace</span><span>.</span><span>name</span><span>)</span>
          <span>.</span><span>filter</span><span>(</span><span>(</span><span>name</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>name</span> <span>!==</span> <span>null</span><span>)</span>
      <span>)</span><span>;</span>
      <span>console</span><span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span><span>current_workspace</span><span>.</span><span>name</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
    <span>}</span>
  <span>}</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>

  <span>stream</span><span>.</span><span>on</span><span>(</span><span>"end"</span><span>,</span> <span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>console</span><span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span><span>"Client disconnected"</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
  <span>}</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>}</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>

<span>server</span><span>.</span><span>listen</span><span>(</span><span>pipeName</span><span>,</span> <span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>{</span>
  <span>console</span><span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span><span>"Named pipe server listening"</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>}</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>

<span>const</span> <span>command</span> <span>=</span> <span>"komorebic subscribe-pipe komorebi-js"</span><span>;</span>

<span>exec</span><span>(</span><span>command</span><span>,</span> <span>(</span><span>error</span><span>,</span> <span>stdout</span><span>,</span> <span>stderr</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>{</span>
  <span>if</span> <span>(</span><span>error</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>console</span><span>.</span><span>error</span><span>(</span><span>`Error executing command: <span><span>${</span><span>error</span><span>}</span></span>`</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
    <span>return</span><span>;</span>
  <span>}</span>
<span>}</span><span>)</span><span>;</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Unix Domain Sockets</h2><a id="user-content-unix-domain-sockets" aria-label="Permalink: Unix Domain Sockets" href="#unix-domain-sockets"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">It is possible to subscribe to notifications of every <code>WindowManagerEvent</code> and <code>SocketMessage</code> handled
by <code>komorebi</code> using <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/commandline/af_unix-comes-to-windows/" rel="nofollow">Unix Domain Sockets</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">UDS are also the only mode of communication between <code>komorebi</code> and <code>komorebic</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto">First, your application must create a socket in <code>$ENV:LocalAppData\komorebi</code>. Once the socket has been created, run the
following command:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="komorebic.exe subscribe-socket <your socket name>"><pre><span>komorebic.exe</span> subscribe<span>-</span>socket <span>&lt;</span>your socket name<span>&gt;</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">If the socket exists, komorebi will start pushing JSON data of successfully handled events and messages as in the
example above in the Named Pipes section.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Rust Client</h2><a id="user-content-rust-client" aria-label="Permalink: Rust Client" href="#rust-client"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">As of <code>v0.1.22</code> it is possible to use the <code>komorebi-client</code> crate to subscribe to notifications of
every <code>WindowManagerEvent</code> and <code>SocketMessage</code> handled by <code>komorebi</code> in a Rust codebase.</p>
<p dir="auto">Below is a simple example of how to use <code>komorebi-client</code> in a basic Rust application.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="// komorebi-client = { git = &quot;https://github.com/LGUG2Z/komorebi&quot;, tag = &quot;v0.1.25&quot;}

use anyhow::Result;
use komorebi_client::Notification;
use komorebi_client::NotificationEvent;
use komorebi_client::UnixListener;
use komorebi_client::WindowManagerEvent;
use std::io::BufRead;
use std::io::BufReader;
use std::io::Read;

pub fn main() -> anyhow::Result<()> {
  let socket = komorebi_client::subscribe(NAME)?;

  for incoming in socket.incoming() {
    match incoming {
      Ok(data) => {
        let reader = BufReader::new(data.try_clone()?);

        for line in reader.lines().flatten() {
          let notification: Notification = match serde_json::from_str(&amp;line) {
            Ok(notification) => notification,
            Err(error) => {
              log::debug!(&quot;discarding malformed komorebi notification: {error}&quot;);
              continue;
            }
          };

          // match and filter on desired notifications
        }
      }
      Err(error) => {
        log::debug!(&quot;{error}&quot;);
      }
    }
  }

}"><pre><span>// komorebi-client = { git = "https://github.com/LGUG2Z/komorebi", tag = "v0.1.25"}</span>

<span>use</span> anyhow<span>::</span><span>Result</span><span>;</span>
<span>use</span> komorebi_client<span>::</span><span>Notification</span><span>;</span>
<span>use</span> komorebi_client<span>::</span><span>NotificationEvent</span><span>;</span>
<span>use</span> komorebi_client<span>::</span><span>UnixListener</span><span>;</span>
<span>use</span> komorebi_client<span>::</span><span>WindowManagerEvent</span><span>;</span>
<span>use</span> std<span>::</span>io<span>::</span><span>BufRead</span><span>;</span>
<span>use</span> std<span>::</span>io<span>::</span><span>BufReader</span><span>;</span>
<span>use</span> std<span>::</span>io<span>::</span><span>Read</span><span>;</span>

<span>pub</span> <span>fn</span> <span>main</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> -&gt; anyhow<span>::</span><span>Result</span><span>&lt;</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>&gt;</span> <span>{</span>
  <span>let</span> socket = komorebi_client<span>::</span><span>subscribe</span><span>(</span><span>NAME</span><span>)</span>?<span>;</span>

  <span>for</span> incoming <span>in</span> socket<span>.</span><span>incoming</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>match</span> incoming <span>{</span>
      <span>Ok</span><span>(</span>data<span>)</span> =&gt; <span>{</span>
        <span>let</span> reader = <span>BufReader</span><span>::</span><span>new</span><span>(</span>data<span>.</span><span>try_clone</span><span>(</span><span>)</span>?<span>)</span><span>;</span>

        <span>for</span> line <span>in</span> reader<span>.</span><span>lines</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>.</span><span>flatten</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
          <span>let</span> notification<span>:</span> <span>Notification</span> = <span>match</span> serde_json<span>::</span><span>from_str</span><span>(</span><span>&amp;</span>line<span>)</span> <span>{</span>
            <span>Ok</span><span>(</span>notification<span>)</span> =&gt; notification<span>,</span>
            <span>Err</span><span>(</span>error<span>)</span> =&gt; <span>{</span>
              log<span>::</span>debug!<span>(</span><span>"discarding malformed komorebi notification: {error}"</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
              <span>continue</span><span>;</span>
            <span>}</span>
          <span>}</span><span>;</span>

          <span>// match and filter on desired notifications</span>
        <span>}</span>
      <span>}</span>
      <span>Err</span><span>(</span>error<span>)</span> =&gt; <span>{</span>
        log<span>::</span>debug!<span>(</span><span>"{error}"</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
      <span>}</span>
    <span>}</span>
  <span>}</span>

<span>}</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">A read-world example can be found
in <a href="https://github.com/LGUG2Z/komokana/blob/feature/komorebi-uds/src/main.rs">komokana</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Subscription Event Notification Schema</h2><a id="user-content-subscription-event-notification-schema" aria-label="Permalink: Subscription Event Notification Schema" href="#subscription-event-notification-schema"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">A <a href="https://json-schema.org/" rel="nofollow">JSON Schema</a> of the event notifications emitted to subscribers can be generated with
the <code>komorebic notification-schema</code> command. The output of this command can be redirected to the clipboard or a file,
which can be used with services such as <a href="https://app.quicktype.io/" rel="nofollow">Quicktype</a> to generate type definitions in different
programming languages.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Communication over TCP</h2><a id="user-content-communication-over-tcp" aria-label="Permalink: Communication over TCP" href="#communication-over-tcp"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">A TCP listener can optionally be exposed on a port of your choosing with the <code>--tcp-port=N</code> flag. If this flag is not
provided to <code>komorebi</code> or <code>komorebic start</code>, no TCP listener will be created.</p>
<p dir="auto">Once created, your client may send
any <a href="https://github.com/LGUG2Z/komorebi/blob/master/komorebi-core/src/lib.rs#L37">SocketMessage</a> to <code>komorebi</code> in the
same way that <code>komorebic</code> would.</p>
<p dir="auto">This can be used if you would like to create your own alternative to <code>komorebic</code> which incorporates scripting and
various middleware layers, and similarly it can be used if you would like to integrate <code>komorebi</code> with
a <a href="https://github.com/LGUG2Z/komorebi/issues/176#issue-1302643961" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/LGUG2Z/komorebi/issues/176/hovercard">custom input handler</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">If a client sends an unrecognized message, it will be disconnected and have to reconnect before trying to communicate
again.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Socket Message Schema</h2><a id="user-content-socket-message-schema" aria-label="Permalink: Socket Message Schema" href="#socket-message-schema"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">A <a href="https://json-schema.org/" rel="nofollow">JSON Schema</a> of socket messages used to send instructions to <code>komorebi</code> can be generated
with the <code>komorebic socket-schema</code> command. The output of this command can be redirected to the clipboard or a file,
which can be used with services such as <a href="https://app.quicktype.io/" rel="nofollow">Quicktype</a> to generate type definitions in different
programming languages.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Appreciations</h2><a id="user-content-appreciations" aria-label="Permalink: Appreciations" href="#appreciations"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto">First and foremost, thank you to my wife, both for naming this project and for her patience throughout its never-ending development</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">Thank you to <a href="https://github.com/sitiom">@sitiom</a> for being <a href="https://jeezy.substack.com/p/the-open-source-contributions-i-appreciate" rel="nofollow">an exemplary open source community leader</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">Thank you to the developers of <a href="https://github.com/TimUntersberger/nog">nog</a> who came before me and whose work taught me more than I can ever hope to repay</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">Thank you to the developers of <a href="https://github.com/lars-berger/GlazeWM">GlazeWM</a> for pushing the boundaries of tiling window management on Windows with me and having an excellent spirit of collaboration</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">Thank you to <a href="https://github.com/Ciantic">@Ciantic</a> for helping me bring the <a href="https://github.com/Ciantic/AltTabAccessor/issues/1" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/Ciantic/AltTabAccessor/issues/1/hovercard">hidden Virtual Desktops cloaking function</a> to <code>komorebi</code></p>
</li>
</ul>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A journey into Kindle AI slop hell (163 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://maxread.substack.com/p/my-kindle-thinks-im-stupid-now</link>
            <guid>40779643</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 19:19:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://maxread.substack.com/p/my-kindle-thinks-im-stupid-now">https://maxread.substack.com/p/my-kindle-thinks-im-stupid-now</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40779643">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><p>Greetings from Read Max HQ, directly beneath the dreaded Heat Dome.</p><p><span>This week’s edition is a guest post about spooky Kindle A.I. slop from </span><a href="https://www.leahbeckmann.com/" rel="">Leah Beckmann</a><span>, an L.A.-based screenwriter and journalist and Chief Kindle Bullshit Correspondent for Read Max.</span></p><p><span>But first, some self-promotion </span><a href="https://www.patreon.com/posts/episode-387-g-i-106360325" rel="">I was on TrueAnon again this week</a><span>, “chopping it up” on the subjects of </span><a href="http://maxread.substack.com/p/who-is-leopold-aschenbrenner" rel="">Leopold Aschenbrenner</a><span>, A.I., and my time as a “CTY” camper at Franklin &amp; Marshall College in Lancaster, Penn. The episode is behind a paywall, but if there is any podcast worth paying for it’s TrueAnon.</span></p><p><span>I also had the pleasure of </span><a href="https://toronto.citynews.ca/2024/06/14/how-google-got-its-ai-answers-so-wrong/" rel="">speaking with Jordan Heath-Rawlings about Google A.I. for The Big Story podcast</a><span>, describing for my Canadian compatriots </span><a href="http://maxread.substack.com/p/does-google-know-how-google-works" rel="">the Google A.I. answer fiasco</a><span>.</span></p><p><span>And before we begin, a short reminder: Read Max is a fully</span><span><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-1-145744570" href="https://maxread.substack.com/p/my-kindle-thinks-im-stupid-now#footnote-1-145744570" target="_self" rel="">1</a></span><span> reader-supported enterprise. The twice-weekly dose of criticism, reporting, shit-posting, recommendations, prophecy, fever-dream ranting, and photographs of my friend Leah’s Kindle relies on subscribers who like what I do electing to pay for the work that goes into it. If you think Read Max is worth about one beer a month, consider upgrading your subscription below:</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F94067198-d031-4e58-8dc1-80d5ee460aa7_1550x100.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F94067198-d031-4e58-8dc1-80d5ee460aa7_1550x100.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F94067198-d031-4e58-8dc1-80d5ee460aa7_1550x100.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F94067198-d031-4e58-8dc1-80d5ee460aa7_1550x100.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F94067198-d031-4e58-8dc1-80d5ee460aa7_1550x100.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F94067198-d031-4e58-8dc1-80d5ee460aa7_1550x100.png" width="1456" height="94" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/94067198-d031-4e58-8dc1-80d5ee460aa7_1550x100.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:94,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:17721,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F94067198-d031-4e58-8dc1-80d5ee460aa7_1550x100.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F94067198-d031-4e58-8dc1-80d5ee460aa7_1550x100.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F94067198-d031-4e58-8dc1-80d5ee460aa7_1550x100.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F94067198-d031-4e58-8dc1-80d5ee460aa7_1550x100.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>The first time I had enough brain cells to read again, the baby was about eight weeks old. “Reading,” at this stage, could occur only in brief stretches between breast-feeding/rocking/attempting to psychically communicate with my infant to understand if I was doing any of this right, and before I slipped into blissful unconsciousness. I would stare at each word in sequence--“Rhys roared as he came, slamming to the hilt. Outside the mountains trembled.”--not retaining any of it.</p><p>The only thing that was able to cut through the fog of new parenthood were The Ads.&nbsp;</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea91597b-e854-4757-bb14-5f0c5a8ae504_702x936.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea91597b-e854-4757-bb14-5f0c5a8ae504_702x936.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea91597b-e854-4757-bb14-5f0c5a8ae504_702x936.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea91597b-e854-4757-bb14-5f0c5a8ae504_702x936.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea91597b-e854-4757-bb14-5f0c5a8ae504_702x936.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea91597b-e854-4757-bb14-5f0c5a8ae504_702x936.png" width="414" height="552" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/ea91597b-e854-4757-bb14-5f0c5a8ae504_702x936.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:936,&quot;width&quot;:702,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:414,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea91597b-e854-4757-bb14-5f0c5a8ae504_702x936.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea91597b-e854-4757-bb14-5f0c5a8ae504_702x936.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea91597b-e854-4757-bb14-5f0c5a8ae504_702x936.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea91597b-e854-4757-bb14-5f0c5a8ae504_702x936.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>I’m not sure when, exactly, Amazon determined that I had lost the ability to read, but one day my Kindle lock screen was gently nudging me toward the new Lauren Groff, and the next it was pushing a series of books with the subtitle: "Bedtime Story for Kids and Adults."</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd4930de0-f22e-47c5-b305-ccf5a66d650e_984x1320.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd4930de0-f22e-47c5-b305-ccf5a66d650e_984x1320.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd4930de0-f22e-47c5-b305-ccf5a66d650e_984x1320.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd4930de0-f22e-47c5-b305-ccf5a66d650e_984x1320.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd4930de0-f22e-47c5-b305-ccf5a66d650e_984x1320.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd4930de0-f22e-47c5-b305-ccf5a66d650e_984x1320.png" width="488" height="654.6341463414634" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/d4930de0-f22e-47c5-b305-ccf5a66d650e_984x1320.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1320,&quot;width&quot;:984,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:488,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd4930de0-f22e-47c5-b305-ccf5a66d650e_984x1320.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd4930de0-f22e-47c5-b305-ccf5a66d650e_984x1320.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd4930de0-f22e-47c5-b305-ccf5a66d650e_984x1320.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd4930de0-f22e-47c5-b305-ccf5a66d650e_984x1320.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>It is immediately clear that no sentient being wrote these, uh, books, if that’s the right word. The lifeless covers feature anime-style illustrations--dewy-eyed children, snarling dragons, a cat dressed as a scientist--and have bland titles that make you think, “Hey yeah! That makes sense,” and then immediately, “wait, no it doesn’t.”&nbsp;</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc6d79b0f-2571-47f1-b185-edcf32ea0ec0_722x996.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc6d79b0f-2571-47f1-b185-edcf32ea0ec0_722x996.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc6d79b0f-2571-47f1-b185-edcf32ea0ec0_722x996.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc6d79b0f-2571-47f1-b185-edcf32ea0ec0_722x996.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc6d79b0f-2571-47f1-b185-edcf32ea0ec0_722x996.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc6d79b0f-2571-47f1-b185-edcf32ea0ec0_722x996.png" width="500" height="689.7506925207756" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/c6d79b0f-2571-47f1-b185-edcf32ea0ec0_722x996.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:996,&quot;width&quot;:722,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:500,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc6d79b0f-2571-47f1-b185-edcf32ea0ec0_722x996.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc6d79b0f-2571-47f1-b185-edcf32ea0ec0_722x996.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc6d79b0f-2571-47f1-b185-edcf32ea0ec0_722x996.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc6d79b0f-2571-47f1-b185-edcf32ea0ec0_722x996.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><span>It has been hard not to take this personally as a new mother. Did Amazon sense that my liquified brain could no longer digest real books? Based on my recent purchases of “Mary Ruth’s Infant Probiotic Drops” and “Frida Mom Cooling Hydrogel Nipple Pads” and “Skip Hop Baby Bath Rinse Bath Cup - Whale,” did Amazon suddenly assume that I needed something a little gentler than Miranda July or Maeve Binchy or even the softcore fairy pornos written by Mormons? More importantly, what is a bedtime story for kids </span><em>and</em><span> adults? I am an adult. A bedtime story for an adult is just a real book. I read real books. Or at least, I used to? Basically, did Kindle think I was stupid now? </span></p><p>Well, yes.&nbsp;</p><p><span>The night I was served </span><em>A Girl’s Quest For Healthy Eating</em><span>, I thought, Fine. Why fight it? Why not just lie down in the parking lot of semi-literate Bedtime Story and let a 24-page Kindle text written by a robot run me over repeatedly?</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe7601193-463f-4bd7-bd28-79783e3e37f8_988x1318.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe7601193-463f-4bd7-bd28-79783e3e37f8_988x1318.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe7601193-463f-4bd7-bd28-79783e3e37f8_988x1318.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe7601193-463f-4bd7-bd28-79783e3e37f8_988x1318.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe7601193-463f-4bd7-bd28-79783e3e37f8_988x1318.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe7601193-463f-4bd7-bd28-79783e3e37f8_988x1318.png" width="444" height="592.2995951417004" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/e7601193-463f-4bd7-bd28-79783e3e37f8_988x1318.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1318,&quot;width&quot;:988,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:444,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe7601193-463f-4bd7-bd28-79783e3e37f8_988x1318.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe7601193-463f-4bd7-bd28-79783e3e37f8_988x1318.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe7601193-463f-4bd7-bd28-79783e3e37f8_988x1318.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe7601193-463f-4bd7-bd28-79783e3e37f8_988x1318.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><span>I looked into the big, vacant eyes of the smiling girl on the cover, and--like the moment a Magic Eye reveals itself to you--he transformed from sinister to welcoming. Maybe, I thought, Amazon knows something I don’t. Motherhood is about learning to read the rhythms of your child and then reacting appropriately. Like an algorithm rapidly interpreting my behavior on the internet, every day I learn more and more about when my infant son needs to eat or sleep or practice tummy time</span><em>.</em><span> If I am mommy… could Amazon also be mommy? Is Amazon </span><em>my</em><span> mommy? Maybe Amazon is just trying to do me a solid and let me know that it knows what’s best for me, and what’s best for me right now is </span><em>Students Perilous Journey to Correct Their Mistake.&nbsp;</em></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0d455dab-f7a2-4c6a-8c63-276c825a0d69_944x1238.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0d455dab-f7a2-4c6a-8c63-276c825a0d69_944x1238.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0d455dab-f7a2-4c6a-8c63-276c825a0d69_944x1238.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0d455dab-f7a2-4c6a-8c63-276c825a0d69_944x1238.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0d455dab-f7a2-4c6a-8c63-276c825a0d69_944x1238.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0d455dab-f7a2-4c6a-8c63-276c825a0d69_944x1238.png" width="492" height="645.228813559322" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/0d455dab-f7a2-4c6a-8c63-276c825a0d69_944x1238.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1238,&quot;width&quot;:944,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:492,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0d455dab-f7a2-4c6a-8c63-276c825a0d69_944x1238.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0d455dab-f7a2-4c6a-8c63-276c825a0d69_944x1238.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0d455dab-f7a2-4c6a-8c63-276c825a0d69_944x1238.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0d455dab-f7a2-4c6a-8c63-276c825a0d69_944x1238.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Maybe it really is just time to read a bedtime story and go night-night.&nbsp;</p><p><span>So I went to the book details page for</span><em> A Girl’s Quest For Healthy Eating</em><span>. I learned that it was written by someone named Bette Santini. It has a two and a half star rating, is 33 pages long and was published on May 7, 2024. For just $2.99, it could be mine. The brief bio read: A little girl with blue eyes and blonde hair leads her friends on a healthy eating mission, culminating in the creation of a neighborhood farmer’s market.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>Okay. Sort of </span><em>Triumph of the Will: Bedtime Story for Kids and Adults</em><span>.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>What else could this sick and twisted mind have cooked up? I wanted more. I clicked on Bette’s author page; this was the only title listed. Through the penumbral fog of half-sleep, squinting one-eyed at my phone, I googled, “a girls.quest for healthy watinf bette santinir.” Even the politely auto-corrected version yielded no meaningful results: An obituary for a Betty L. Santini. A vintage Santini cycling jacket on eBay. An Amazon link to the book, </span><em>The Prince of Tides</em><span>. Not only would it seem that Bette Santini does not exist, but there is no possible way to purchase or even locate </span><em>A Girl’s Quest for Healthy Eating</em><span>, outside the Kindle app.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>And then things got spooky. When I opened my Kindle again, there, illuminated by the inoffensive whitish glow of my device, was an ad for </span><em>A Girl’s Quest for Healthy Eating</em><span>. Only, it was vaguely distorted. Like a spot-the-difference </span><em>Highlights</em><span> game, here was the same book with minor discrepancies. This cover featured several little girls, presumably all on healthy eating quests of their own. The page count was slightly different. And most distressing of all, the author's name: Bette Santini</span><em>r</em><span>. In other words, Santini plus R. Where had I seen this name before? Oh right: from one minute ago when I misspelled Santini, Santinir.&nbsp;</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0febaa32-bf23-407b-99a2-2f6f98a9f5b5_990x1308.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0febaa32-bf23-407b-99a2-2f6f98a9f5b5_990x1308.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0febaa32-bf23-407b-99a2-2f6f98a9f5b5_990x1308.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0febaa32-bf23-407b-99a2-2f6f98a9f5b5_990x1308.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0febaa32-bf23-407b-99a2-2f6f98a9f5b5_990x1308.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0febaa32-bf23-407b-99a2-2f6f98a9f5b5_990x1308.png" width="486" height="642.1090909090909" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/0febaa32-bf23-407b-99a2-2f6f98a9f5b5_990x1308.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1308,&quot;width&quot;:990,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:486,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0febaa32-bf23-407b-99a2-2f6f98a9f5b5_990x1308.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0febaa32-bf23-407b-99a2-2f6f98a9f5b5_990x1308.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0febaa32-bf23-407b-99a2-2f6f98a9f5b5_990x1308.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0febaa32-bf23-407b-99a2-2f6f98a9f5b5_990x1308.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><span>So. Was Amazon somehow generating these books as quickly as I could search for them? Probably not. I even tried googling purposely misspelled versions of books to try and bait the system. But Pwaw Dtetctives: Maserty of the Missng Ncklac bedtma story kids and adults (</span><em>Paw Detectives: The Mystery of the Missing Necklace: Bedtime Story for Kids and Adults) </em><span>got me nothing. Was I going insane? Almost certainly. As the very editor of this Substack texted me, “If you didn’t have pics of this, I would think you were schizophrenic.”&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>After some very minimal poking around, I learned that others had also been </span><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/kindle/comments/199topv/cute_fairytale_bedtime_stories_for_kids/" rel="">served</a><span> </span><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/kindle/comments/1ap6524/the_only_ads_i_have_gotten_for_weeks_have_been/" rel="">versions</a><span> of Bette Santini books. But no one seemed to know why the ads started in the first place or </span><a href="https://futurism.com/amazon-kindle-lock-screens-ai-generated-books" rel="">how to make them stop</a><span>. The real question is this: Where do these books come from? Is someone out there generating piles of content via A.I. and trying to turn micro-profits by gaming the Kindle marketplace and placing ads? Is Amazon cutting out the author middle man and using A.I. and user data to generate books on its own?&nbsp;What generative models are being used? What kinds of prompts are generating these texts? </span></p><p>I don’t know. I’m not a virgin. As I said, I have a child.&nbsp;</p><p><span>But I did want to read about my nice Nazi Youth friend and her farmer’s market journey, I just couldn’t. I mean I literally could not find the book again. All versions of </span><em>A Girl’s Quest for Healthy Eating</em><span> appeared to have vanished, as though it never existed in the first place. (Is Amazon deleting these spammy books as fast as they can be generated? Again, I don’t know. Stop asking me questions for dorks.) At a loss, I decided to purchase and read the next book Amazon served to me. What I got was:</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fee9286f6-4b6b-4c1f-acf4-e532b96fa8f1_952x1196.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fee9286f6-4b6b-4c1f-acf4-e532b96fa8f1_952x1196.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fee9286f6-4b6b-4c1f-acf4-e532b96fa8f1_952x1196.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fee9286f6-4b6b-4c1f-acf4-e532b96fa8f1_952x1196.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fee9286f6-4b6b-4c1f-acf4-e532b96fa8f1_952x1196.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fee9286f6-4b6b-4c1f-acf4-e532b96fa8f1_952x1196.png" width="400" height="502.52100840336135" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/ee9286f6-4b6b-4c1f-acf4-e532b96fa8f1_952x1196.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1196,&quot;width&quot;:952,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:400,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fee9286f6-4b6b-4c1f-acf4-e532b96fa8f1_952x1196.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fee9286f6-4b6b-4c1f-acf4-e532b96fa8f1_952x1196.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fee9286f6-4b6b-4c1f-acf4-e532b96fa8f1_952x1196.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fee9286f6-4b6b-4c1f-acf4-e532b96fa8f1_952x1196.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><em>Using Mindreading for Good: Cute Fairy Tale Bedtime Story for Kids</em><span>, written by Lynnell Gorshteyny, is about a young girl named Olivia who goes to sleep one night and wakes up with the ability to hear the thoughts of others around her. “At first,” the robot Lynnell Gorshteyny generates, “she thought she was going crazy, but soon realized that she had acquired the ability to read minds.”&nbsp;</span></p><p>Here is a photo of Olivia thinking she was going crazy, but soon realizing that she had acquired the ability to read minds.&nbsp;</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd872c62b-cdda-43c7-8503-1aa1c988ad24_792x1006.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd872c62b-cdda-43c7-8503-1aa1c988ad24_792x1006.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd872c62b-cdda-43c7-8503-1aa1c988ad24_792x1006.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd872c62b-cdda-43c7-8503-1aa1c988ad24_792x1006.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd872c62b-cdda-43c7-8503-1aa1c988ad24_792x1006.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd872c62b-cdda-43c7-8503-1aa1c988ad24_792x1006.png" width="540" height="685.9090909090909" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/d872c62b-cdda-43c7-8503-1aa1c988ad24_792x1006.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1006,&quot;width&quot;:792,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:540,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd872c62b-cdda-43c7-8503-1aa1c988ad24_792x1006.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd872c62b-cdda-43c7-8503-1aa1c988ad24_792x1006.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd872c62b-cdda-43c7-8503-1aa1c988ad24_792x1006.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd872c62b-cdda-43c7-8503-1aa1c988ad24_792x1006.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Olivia’s only friend in the world is Zoe.&nbsp;</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb91c597b-cb2f-44fe-ae13-6b179c3886ed_814x1288.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb91c597b-cb2f-44fe-ae13-6b179c3886ed_814x1288.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb91c597b-cb2f-44fe-ae13-6b179c3886ed_814x1288.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb91c597b-cb2f-44fe-ae13-6b179c3886ed_814x1288.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb91c597b-cb2f-44fe-ae13-6b179c3886ed_814x1288.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb91c597b-cb2f-44fe-ae13-6b179c3886ed_814x1288.png" width="552" height="873.4348894348894" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/b91c597b-cb2f-44fe-ae13-6b179c3886ed_814x1288.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1288,&quot;width&quot;:814,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:552,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb91c597b-cb2f-44fe-ae13-6b179c3886ed_814x1288.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb91c597b-cb2f-44fe-ae13-6b179c3886ed_814x1288.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb91c597b-cb2f-44fe-ae13-6b179c3886ed_814x1288.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb91c597b-cb2f-44fe-ae13-6b179c3886ed_814x1288.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Zoe helps Olivia harness her new power so that she can use it for good. Such as helping Ethan, some random dumbass at school who is struggling with his grades. By having access to his thoughts, Olivia is able to identify what exactly he’s struggling with, which “made tutoring sessions more productive.” The next day, the robot Lynnell Gorshteyny has forgotten that the main character is named Olivia. “Next, they helped their classmate, Olivia, who was dealing with a fallout with her best friend. Olivia could perceive both sides of the argument.”&nbsp;</p><p>Whatever. You get the point. The book goes on and on, reminding us over and over of the power of empathy: that we must empathize with each other, that we must be empathetic towards each other, and how “most importantly, Olivia is an empath now.” In fact, the word empathy is mentioned 10 times in 35 pages. Every time I thought I had reached the book’s natural conclusion – “Her powers were gone, but she was also glad for the silence.” Big sigh. We’ve done it. – I would turn the page only to learn once again that “Olivia’s journey as a mind reader taught her valuable lessons.”&nbsp;</p><p>But what about the valuable lessons I’ve learned? Well, as of this morning, I’ve started receiving ads for a different genre of AI reads. Let’s call these the “Flight of Hope’ series.&nbsp;</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F12459ca1-723e-4b41-acb6-e6f9bb312c72_980x1310.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F12459ca1-723e-4b41-acb6-e6f9bb312c72_980x1310.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F12459ca1-723e-4b41-acb6-e6f9bb312c72_980x1310.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F12459ca1-723e-4b41-acb6-e6f9bb312c72_980x1310.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F12459ca1-723e-4b41-acb6-e6f9bb312c72_980x1310.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F12459ca1-723e-4b41-acb6-e6f9bb312c72_980x1310.png" width="494" height="660.3469387755102" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/12459ca1-723e-4b41-acb6-e6f9bb312c72_980x1310.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1310,&quot;width&quot;:980,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:494,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F12459ca1-723e-4b41-acb6-e6f9bb312c72_980x1310.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F12459ca1-723e-4b41-acb6-e6f9bb312c72_980x1310.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F12459ca1-723e-4b41-acb6-e6f9bb312c72_980x1310.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F12459ca1-723e-4b41-acb6-e6f9bb312c72_980x1310.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Hope indeed. What is parenting anyway if not a soaring tale of courage, wisdom, and compassion? Flagrant hope in the face of the unbearable, unspeakable state of the world.&nbsp;A sacrifice of brain and body so enormous, it is impossible to quantify. And while I know that the old version of my brain is certainly gone forever, I do hope that I regain the ability to read someday. If only so that, in a couple of years from now, in a time that feels both immeasurably far but that I’m aware will arrive sooner than I can imagine, my son and I will snuggle up together in his bed, we will open up his personal tablet, and I will read him several Bedtime Story before he drifts sweetly off to sleep.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F62f6b1c7-fc7e-4901-8e9c-57562d681cd3_920x1224.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F62f6b1c7-fc7e-4901-8e9c-57562d681cd3_920x1224.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F62f6b1c7-fc7e-4901-8e9c-57562d681cd3_920x1224.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F62f6b1c7-fc7e-4901-8e9c-57562d681cd3_920x1224.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F62f6b1c7-fc7e-4901-8e9c-57562d681cd3_920x1224.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F62f6b1c7-fc7e-4901-8e9c-57562d681cd3_920x1224.png" width="534" height="710.4521739130435" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/62f6b1c7-fc7e-4901-8e9c-57562d681cd3_920x1224.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1224,&quot;width&quot;:920,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:534,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F62f6b1c7-fc7e-4901-8e9c-57562d681cd3_920x1224.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F62f6b1c7-fc7e-4901-8e9c-57562d681cd3_920x1224.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F62f6b1c7-fc7e-4901-8e9c-57562d681cd3_920x1224.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F62f6b1c7-fc7e-4901-8e9c-57562d681cd3_920x1224.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div></div></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[More Memory Safety for Let's Encrypt: Deploying ntpd-rs (248 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://letsencrypt.org/2024/06/24/ntpd-rs-deployment.html</link>
            <guid>40778594</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 17:23:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://letsencrypt.org/2024/06/24/ntpd-rs-deployment.html">https://letsencrypt.org/2024/06/24/ntpd-rs-deployment.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40778594">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
	
	<article>
		<p>When we look at the general security posture of Let’s Encrypt, one of the things that worries us most is how much of the operating system and network infrastructure is written in unsafe languages like C and C++. The <a href="https://github.com/letsencrypt/boulder">CA software</a> itself is written in memory safe Golang, but from our server operating systems to our network equipment, lack of memory safety routinely leads to vulnerabilities that need patching.</p>
<p>Partially for the sake of Let’s Encrypt, and partially for the sake of the wider Internet, we started a new project called <a href="https://www.memorysafety.org/">Prossimo</a> in 2020. Prossimo’s goal is to make some of the most critical software infrastructure for the Internet memory safe. Since then we’ve invested in a range of software components including the <a href="https://github.com/rustls/rustls/">Rustls TLS library</a>, <a href="https://github.com/hickory-dns/hickory-dns">Hickory DNS</a>, <a href="https://github.com/memorysafety/river">River reverse proxy</a>, <a href="https://github.com/memorysafety/sudo-rs">sudo-rs</a>, <a href="https://rust-for-linux.com/">Rust support for the Linux kernel</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/pendulum-project/ntpd-rs">ntpd-rs</a>.</p>
<p>Let’s Encrypt has now taken a step that was a long time in the making: we’ve deployed <a href="https://github.com/pendulum-project/ntpd-rs">ntpd-rs</a>, the first piece of memory safe software from Prossimo that has made it into the Let’s Encrypt infrastructure.</p>
<p>Most operating systems use the Network Time Protocol (NTP) to accurately determine what time it is. Keeping track of time is a critical task for an operating system, and since it involves interacting with the Internet it’s important to make sure NTP implementations are secure.</p>
<p>In April of 2022, Prossimo started work on a memory safe and generally more secure <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network_Time_Protocol">NTP</a> implementation called <a href="https://github.com/pendulum-project/ntpd-rs">ntpd-rs</a>. Since then, the implementation has matured and is now maintained by <a href="https://github.com/pendulum-project">Project Pendulum</a>. In April of 2024 ntpd-rs was deployed to the Let’s Encrypt staging environment, and as of now it’s in production.</p>
<p>Over the next few years we plan to continue replacing C or C++ software with memory safe alternatives in the Let’s Encrypt infrastructure: OpenSSL and its derivatives with <a href="https://www.memorysafety.org/initiative/rustls/">Rustls</a>, our DNS software with <a href="https://www.memorysafety.org/initiative/dns/">Hickory</a>, Nginx with <a href="https://www.memorysafety.org/initiative/reverse-proxy/">River</a>, and sudo with <a href="https://www.memorysafety.org/initiative/sudo-su/">sudo-rs</a>. Memory safety is just part of the overall security equation, but <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/oncd/briefing-room/2024/02/26/press-release-technical-report/">it’s an important part</a> and we’re glad to be able to make these improvements.</p>
<p>We depend on contributions from our community of users and supporters in order to provide our services. If your company or organization would like to <a href="https://www.abetterinternet.org/sponsor/">sponsor</a> Let’s Encrypt please email us at <a href="mailto:sponsor@letsencrypt.org">sponsor@letsencrypt.org</a>. We ask that you make an <a href="https://letsencrypt.org/donate/">individual contribution</a> if it is within your means.</p>

	</article>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Car dealerships revert to pens and paper after cyberattacks on software provider (211 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://apnews.com/article/car-dealerships-cyberattack-cdk-outage-3f7c81f6be0e212172b33cdc9f49feba</link>
            <guid>40776951</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 15:09:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://apnews.com/article/car-dealerships-cyberattack-cdk-outage-3f7c81f6be0e212172b33cdc9f49feba">https://apnews.com/article/car-dealerships-cyberattack-cdk-outage-3f7c81f6be0e212172b33cdc9f49feba</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40776951">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                                        <p>NEW YORK (AP) — Car dealerships in North America continue to wrestle with major disruptions that started last week with cyberattacks on a software company used widely in the auto retail sales sector. </p><p>CDK Global, a company that provides software for thousands of auto dealers in the U.S. and Canada, was hit by back-to-back cyberattacks Wednesday. That led to an outage that has continued to impact operations.</p><p>For prospective car buyers, that’s meant delays at dealerships or vehicle orders written up by hand. There’s no immediate end in sight, with CDK saying it expects the restoration process to take “several days” to complete.</p><p>On Monday, Group 1 Automotive Inc., a $4 billion automotive retailer, said that it continued to use “alternative processes” to sell cars to its customers. </p><p>Here is what you need to know. </p><h2>What is CDK Global?</h2><p>CDK Global is a major player in the auto sales industry. The company, based just outside of Chicago in Hoffman Estates, Illinois, provides software technology to dealers that helps with day-to-day operations — like facilitating vehicle sales, financing, insurance and repairs.</p>
    

<p>CDK serves more than 15,000 retail locations across North America, according to the company.</p>



<h2>What happened last week?</h2><p>CDK experienced back-to-back cyberattacks on Wednesday. The company shut down all of its systems out of an abundance of caution, spokesperson Lisa Finney said last week.</p><p>“We have begun the restoration process,” Finney said in an update over the weekend — noting that the company had launched an investigation into the “cyber incident” with third-party experts and notified law enforcement.</p>
    
<p>“Based on the information we have at this time, we anticipate that the process will take several days to complete, and in the interim we are continuing to actively engage with our customers and provide them with alternate ways to conduct business,” she added.</p><p>In messages to its customers, the company has also warned of “bad actors” posing as members or affiliates of CDK to try to obtain system access by contacting customers. It urged them to be cautious of any attempted phishing.</p>
    

<p>The incident bore all the hallmarks of a ransomware attack, in which targets are asked to pay a ransom to access encrypted files. But CDK declined to comment directly — neither confirming or denying if it had received a ransom demand.</p><h2>Are impacted dealerships still selling cars?</h2><p>Several major auto companies — including Stellantis, Ford and BMW — confirmed to The Associated Press last week that the CDK outage had impacted some of their dealers, but that sales operations continue.</p><p>In light of the ongoing situation, a spokesperson for Stellantis said Friday that many dealerships had switched to manual processes to serve customers. That includes writing up orders by hand. </p><p>A Ford spokesperson added that the outage may cause “some delays and inconveniences at some dealers and for some customers.” However, many Ford and Lincoln customers are still getting sales and service support through alternative routes being used at dealerships. </p><p>Group 1 Automotive Inc., which owns 202 automotive dealerships, 264 franchises, and 42 collision centers in the U.S. and the United Kingdom, said Monday that the incident has disrupted its business applications and processes in its U.S. operations that rely on CDK’s dealers’ systems. The company said that it took measures to protect and isolate its systems from CDK’s platform.</p>
    

<p>All Group 1 U.S. dealerships will continue to conduct business using alternative processes until CDK’s dealers’ systems are available, the company said Monday. Group 1’s dealerships in the U.K. don’t use CDK’s dealers’ systems and are not impacted by the incident.</p><p>With many details of the cyberattacks still unclear, customer privacy is also at top of mind — especially with little known about what information may have been compromised this week.</p><p>Cybersecurity experts have stressed that consumers connected to CDK (or a CDK-affilated dealership) should assume that their data may have been breached. Those impacted should monitor their credit — or even consider <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/buyline-personal-finance/article/how-to-freeze-your-credit">freezing their credit</a></span> as an added layer of defense — and be wary of any suspicious phishing messages.</p>
    

<p>In a statement last week, Mike Stanton, president and CEO of the National Automobile Dealers Association, said “dealers are very committed to protecting their customer information” and were seeking updates from CDK to determine the scope of impact “so they can respond appropriately.”</p>
                                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Microsoft Account to local account conversion guide erased from Windows 11 guide (178 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.tomshardware.com/software/windows/microsoft-account-to-local-account-conversion-guide-erased-from-official-windows-11-guide-instructions-redacted-earlier-this-week</link>
            <guid>40775301</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 12:38:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.tomshardware.com/software/windows/microsoft-account-to-local-account-conversion-guide-erased-from-official-windows-11-guide-instructions-redacted-earlier-this-week">https://www.tomshardware.com/software/windows/microsoft-account-to-local-account-conversion-guide-erased-from-official-windows-11-guide-instructions-redacted-earlier-this-week</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40775301">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="article-body">
<p><a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.tomshardware.com/tag/microsoft" data-auto-tag-linker="true" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.tomshardware.com/tag/microsoft">Microsoft</a> has been pushing hard for its users to sign into Windows with a Microsoft Account. The newest <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.tomshardware.com/tag/windows-11" data-auto-tag-linker="true" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.tomshardware.com/tag/windows-11">Windows 11</a> installer <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.tomshardware.com/software/windows/door-slammed-on-last-remaining-easy-windows-11-local-account-setup-workaround" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.tomshardware.com/software/windows/door-slammed-on-last-remaining-easy-windows-11-local-account-setup-workaround">removed the easy bypass to the requirement</a> that you make an account or login with your existing account. If you didn't <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.tomshardware.com/how-to/install-windows-11-without-microsoft-account" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.tomshardware.com/how-to/install-windows-11-without-microsoft-account">install Windows 11 without a Microsoft Account</a> and now want to stop sending the company your data, you can still switch to a local account after the fact. Microsoft even had instructions on how to do this on its official support website - or at least it used to...</p><p>Microsoft's <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://go.redirectingat.com/?id=92X1584492&amp;xcust=tomshardware_us_9216826372680102444&amp;xs=1&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fsupport.microsoft.com%2Fen-us%2Fwindows%2Fchange-from-a-local-account-to-a-microsoft-account-395203bf-9f1b-eb24-b042-5b8dae6c1d20&amp;sref=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.tomshardware.com%2Fsoftware%2Fwindows%2Fmicrosoft-account-to-local-account-conversion-guide-erased-from-official-windows-11-guide-instructions-redacted-earlier-this-week" data-url="https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/change-from-a-local-account-to-a-microsoft-account-395203bf-9f1b-eb24-b042-5b8dae6c1d20" target="_blank" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" rel="sponsored noopener" data-hl-processed="skimlinks" data-placeholder-url="https://go.redirectingat.com/?id=92X1584492&amp;xcust=hawk-custom-tracking&amp;xs=1&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fsupport.microsoft.com%2Fen-us%2Fwindows%2Fchange-from-a-local-account-to-a-microsoft-account-395203bf-9f1b-eb24-b042-5b8dae6c1d20&amp;sref=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.tomshardware.com%2Fsoftware%2Fwindows%2Fmicrosoft-account-to-local-account-conversion-guide-erased-from-official-windows-11-guide-instructions-redacted-earlier-this-week" data-google-interstitial="false" data-merchant-name="SkimLinks - microsoft.com" data-merchant-id="undefined" data-merchant-url="undefined" data-merchant-network="undefined">'Change from a local account to a Microsoft Account' guide</a> shows users how they can change their Windows 11 PC login credentials to use their Microsoft Account. The company also supplied instructions on how to 'Change from a Microsoft account to a local account' on the same page. However, when we checked the page using <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://web.archive.org/web/20240612104753/https:/support.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/change-from-a-local-account-to-a-microsoft-account-395203bf-9f1b-eb24-b042-5b8dae6c1d20" data-url="https://web.archive.org/web/20240612104753/https:/support.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/change-from-a-local-account-to-a-microsoft-account-395203bf-9f1b-eb24-b042-5b8dae6c1d20" target="_blank" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none">the Wayback Machine</a>, the instructions on how to do the latter appeared on June 12, 2024, then <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://web.archive.org/web/20240617103839/https:/support.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/change-from-a-local-account-to-a-microsoft-account-395203bf-9f1b-eb24-b042-5b8dae6c1d20" data-url="https://web.archive.org/web/20240617103839/https:/support.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/change-from-a-local-account-to-a-microsoft-account-395203bf-9f1b-eb24-b042-5b8dae6c1d20" target="_blank" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none">disappeared</a> on June 17, 2024. The 'Change from a Microsoft account to a local account' instructions yet haven't returned.</p><p>Converting your Windows 11 PC's login from a Microsoft Account to a local account is a pretty simple process. All you have to do is go to the Settings app, proceed to Accounts &gt; Your info, and select "Sign in with a local account instead." Follow the instructions on the screen, and you should be good to go.</p><p>When Microsoft had these instructions on its support page, it sandwiched them between warnings saying, "Using a Microsoft account in Windows allows for seamless integration of Microsoft services, enhanced <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.tomshardware.com/tag/security" data-auto-tag-linker="true" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.tomshardware.com/tag/security">security</a>, and sync across devices, unlike a local account," and "when using a local account, it's a good idea to create a password reset disk. If you don't do this and then forget your password, you won't be able to recover it."</p><p>It's apparent that Microsoft really wants users to sign up and use their services, much like how <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.tomshardware.com/tag/google" data-auto-tag-linker="true" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.tomshardware.com/tag/google">Google</a> and Apple make you create an account so you can make full use of your Android or iDevice. While Windows 11 still lets you use the OS with a local account, these developments show that Microsoft wants this option to be inaccessible, at least for the average consumer.</p><div data-hydrate="true" id="slice-container-newsletterForm-articleInbodyContent-JH6eysfgzS5CsQkMhzy27J"><section><p>Get Tom's Hardware's best news and in-depth reviews, straight to your inbox.</p></section></div>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>