<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 16:30:02 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Claude 3.5 Sonnet (257 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.anthropic.com/news/claude-3-5-sonnet</link>
            <guid>40738916</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 14:03:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/claude-3-5-sonnet">https://www.anthropic.com/news/claude-3-5-sonnet</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40738916">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><figure><img alt="Claude head illustration" loading="eager" width="2880" height="1620" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.anthropic.com/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww-cdn.anthropic.com%2Fimages%2F4zrzovbb%2Fwebsite%2F4e78f69ef8d4186fb5691714abe36224483d91b0-2880x1620.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 1x" src="https://www.anthropic.com/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww-cdn.anthropic.com%2Fimages%2F4zrzovbb%2Fwebsite%2F4e78f69ef8d4186fb5691714abe36224483d91b0-2880x1620.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></figure><p>Today, we’re launching Claude 3.5 Sonnet—our first release in the forthcoming Claude 3.5 model family. Claude 3.5 Sonnet raises the industry bar for intelligence, outperforming competitor models and Claude 3 Opus on a wide range of evaluations, with the speed and cost of our mid-tier model, Claude 3 Sonnet.</p><p>Claude 3.5 Sonnet is now available for free on Claude.ai and the Claude iOS app, while Claude Pro and Team plan subscribers can access it with significantly higher rate limits. It is also available via the Anthropic API, Amazon Bedrock, and Google Cloud’s Vertex AI. The model costs $3 per million input tokens and $15 per million output tokens, with a 200K token context window.</p><figure><img alt="Claude model family" loading="eager" width="2200" height="1174" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.anthropic.com/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww-cdn.anthropic.com%2Fimages%2F4zrzovbb%2Fwebsite%2F1f044104447e9db6b22db3a06e45d114f50f274e-2200x1174.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 1x" src="https://www.anthropic.com/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww-cdn.anthropic.com%2Fimages%2F4zrzovbb%2Fwebsite%2F1f044104447e9db6b22db3a06e45d114f50f274e-2200x1174.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></figure><h3>Frontier intelligence at 2x the speed</h3><p>Claude 3.5 Sonnet sets new industry benchmarks for graduate-level reasoning (GPQA), undergraduate-level knowledge (MMLU), and coding proficiency (HumanEval). It shows marked improvement in grasping nuance, humor, and complex instructions, and is exceptional at writing high-quality content with a natural, relatable tone.</p><p>Claude 3.5 Sonnet operates at twice the speed of Claude 3 Opus. This performance boost, combined with cost-effective pricing, makes Claude 3.5 Sonnet ideal for complex tasks such as context-sensitive customer support and orchestrating multi-step workflows.</p><p>In an <a href="https://cdn.sanity.io/files/4zrzovbb/website/fed9cc193a14b84131812372d8d5857f8f304c52.pdf">internal agentic coding evaluation</a>, Claude 3.5 Sonnet solved 64% of problems, outperforming Claude 3 Opus which solved 38%. Our evaluation tests the model’s ability to fix a bug or add functionality to an open source codebase, given a natural language description of the desired improvement. When instructed and <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/tool-use-ga">provided with the relevant tools</a>, Claude 3.5 Sonnet can independently write, edit, and execute code with sophisticated reasoning and troubleshooting capabilities. It handles code translations with ease, making it particularly effective for updating legacy applications and migrating codebases.</p><figure><img alt="Claude 3.5 Sonnet benchmarks" loading="lazy" width="2200" height="1894" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.anthropic.com/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww-cdn.anthropic.com%2Fimages%2F4zrzovbb%2Fwebsite%2Fcf2c754458e9102b7334731fb18a965bfeb7ad08-2200x1894.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 1x" src="https://www.anthropic.com/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww-cdn.anthropic.com%2Fimages%2F4zrzovbb%2Fwebsite%2Fcf2c754458e9102b7334731fb18a965bfeb7ad08-2200x1894.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></figure><h3>State-of-the-art vision</h3><p>Claude 3.5 Sonnet is our strongest vision model yet, surpassing Claude 3 Opus on standard vision benchmarks. These step-change improvements are most noticeable for tasks that require visual reasoning, like interpreting charts and graphs. Claude 3.5 Sonnet can also accurately transcribe text from imperfect images—a core capability for retail, logistics, and financial services, where AI may glean more insights from an image, graphic or illustration than from text alone.</p><!--$!--><template data-dgst="NEXT_DYNAMIC_NO_SSR_CODE"></template><!--/$--><figure><img alt="Claude 3.5 Sonnet vision evals" loading="lazy" width="2200" height="1110" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.anthropic.com/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww-cdn.anthropic.com%2Fimages%2F4zrzovbb%2Fwebsite%2Fcaff3d60763b27b59fe33e4ae984530f0dba4ddb-2200x1110.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 1x" src="https://www.anthropic.com/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww-cdn.anthropic.com%2Fimages%2F4zrzovbb%2Fwebsite%2Fcaff3d60763b27b59fe33e4ae984530f0dba4ddb-2200x1110.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></figure><h3>Artifacts—a new way to use Claude</h3><p>Today, we’re also introducing Artifacts on Claude.ai, a new feature that expands how users can interact with Claude. When a user asks Claude to generate content like code snippets, text documents, or website designs, these Artifacts appear in a dedicated window alongside their conversation. This creates a dynamic workspace where they can see, edit, and build upon Claude’s creations in real-time, seamlessly integrating AI-generated content into their projects and workflows.</p><p>This preview feature marks Claude’s evolution from a conversational AI to a collaborative work environment. It’s just the beginning of a broader vision for Claude.ai, which will soon expand to support team collaboration. In the near future, teams—and eventually entire organizations—will be able to securely centralize their knowledge, documents, and ongoing work in one shared space, with Claude serving as an on-demand teammate.</p><!--$!--><template data-dgst="NEXT_DYNAMIC_NO_SSR_CODE"></template><!--/$--><h3>Commitment to safety and privacy</h3><p>Our models are subjected to rigorous testing and have been trained to reduce misuse. Despite Claude 3.5 Sonnet’s leap in intelligence, our red teaming assessments have concluded that Claude 3.5 Sonnet remains at <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/anthropics-responsible-scaling-policy">ASL-2</a>. More details can be found in the <a href="https://cdn.sanity.io/files/4zrzovbb/website/fed9cc193a14b84131812372d8d5857f8f304c52.pdf">model card addendum</a>.</p><p>As part of our commitment to safety and transparency, we’ve engaged with external experts to test and refine the safety mechanisms within this latest model. We recently provided Claude 3.5 Sonnet to the UK’s Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute (UK AISI) for pre-deployment safety evaluation. The UK AISI completed tests of 3.5 Sonnet and shared their results with the US AI Safety Institute (US AISI) as part of a Memorandum of Understanding, made possible by the partnership between the US and UK AISIs <a href="https://www.commerce.gov/news/press-releases/2024/04/us-and-uk-announce-partnership-science-ai-safety">announced earlier this year</a>.</p><p>We have integrated policy feedback from outside subject matter experts to ensure that our evaluations are robust and take into account new trends in abuse. This engagement has helped our teams scale up our ability to evaluate 3.5 Sonnet against various types of misuse. For example, we used feedback from child safety experts at <a href="https://www.thorn.org/">Thorn</a> to update our classifiers and fine-tune our models.</p><p>One of the core constitutional principles that guides our AI model development is privacy. We do not train our generative models on user-submitted data unless a user gives us explicit permission to do so. To date we have not used any customer or user-submitted data to train our generative models.</p><h3>Coming soon</h3><p>Our aim is to substantially improve the tradeoff curve between intelligence, speed, and cost every few months. To complete the Claude 3.5 model family, we’ll be releasing Claude 3.5 Haiku and Claude 3.5 Opus later this year.</p><p>In addition to working on our next-generation model family, we are developing new modalities and features to support more use cases for businesses, including integrations with enterprise applications. Our team is also exploring features like Memory, which will enable Claude to remember a user’s preferences and interaction history as specified, making their experience even more personalized and efficient.</p><p>We’re constantly working to improve Claude and love hearing from our users. You can submit feedback on Claude 3.5 Sonnet directly in-product to inform our development roadmap and help our teams to improve your experience. As always, we look forward to seeing what you build, create, and discover with Claude.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[NPM and NodeJS should do more to make ES Modules easy to use (123 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://borischerny.com/javascript,/typescript/2024/06/19/ES-Modules-Are-A-Mess.html</link>
            <guid>40737508</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 11:40:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://borischerny.com/javascript,/typescript/2024/06/19/ES-Modules-Are-A-Mess.html">https://borischerny.com/javascript,/typescript/2024/06/19/ES-Modules-Are-A-Mess.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40737508">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
    <section role="heading">
      <header role="heading">
        <h2>
          <a href="https://borischerny.com/">Boris Cherny's Blog</a>
        </h2>
      </header>
      
    </section>
    <section role="article">
<h3>June 19, 2024</h3>

<p>Coming back to JavaScript and TypeScript after a few years neck deep in Python and Hack, I kept hitting a number of new, cryptic errors when running NodeJS code in my dev environment:</p>

<div><pre><code><span># when I ran ESM TypeScript code the wrong way:</span>
Error <span>[</span>ERR_REQUIRE_ESM]: Must use import to load ES Module

<span># when I imported an ESModule from a CommonJS .js file:</span>
Error <span>[</span>ERR_REQUIRE_ESM]: require<span>()</span> of ES Module .../lodash.js from .../index.cjs not supported

<span># when I imported an ESModule from a .ts file:</span>
error TS1479: The current file is a CommonJS module whose imports will produce <span>'require'</span> calls

<span># when I used ES6 import syntax in a .js file:</span>
SyntaxError: Cannot use import statement outside a module
</code></pre></div>

<p>These errors are all related to importing, typechecking, and loading modules. The JavaScript ecosystem moves fast, and things changing over the last few years was not a surprise. However, it was surprising to see so many errors related to such a core piece of the language!</p>

<h2 id="how-we-got-here">How we got here</h2>

<p>Modules in JavaScript and TypeScript have changed significantly over time:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Years ago, there was no module system for JavaScript and TypeScript. A number of solutions sprang up around ways to declare and load modules: IIFEs, <a href="https://github.com/getify/LABjs">LabJS</a>, <a href="https://github.com/amdjs/amdjs-api/blob/master/AMD.md">AMD</a>, <a href="https://requirejs.org/">require.js</a>, <a href="https://www.typescriptlang.org/docs/handbook/namespaces.html">TypeScript namespaces</a>, and more. Tooling support and interop were hit or miss.</li>
  <li>CommonJS emerged as a standard-by-convention for modules, across browser, server, JavaScript, and TypeScript.</li>
  <li>When ES6 came out, folks started switching over to <code>import</code> and <code>export</code> syntax (from CommonJS’s <code>require</code> and <code>module.exports</code>), using tools like Babel and TypeScript to compile code down to CommonJS.</li>
  <li>CommonJS can be challenging to statically analyze, and uses an <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=W5CXzo4TZVU">inefficient</a>, synchronous module loading algorithm at runtime. ES Modules were <a href="https://tc39.es/ecma262/#sec-modules">introduced</a> as the way to use <code>import</code> and <code>export</code>, while at the same time improving code load times at runtime.</li>
  <li>ES Modules introduced significant complexity for NodeJS in particular: instead of reusing the <em>.js</em> and <em>.ts</em> file extensions, ES Modules in NodeJS require either using <em>.mjs</em>, or setting <code>type=module</code> in your <em>package.json</em>. Interoperating these modules with an ecosystem-ful of CommonJS remains painful.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="current-state-by-the-numbers">Current state, by the numbers</h2>

<p>I was curious – since ES Modules (<code>import</code>/<code>export</code>) were introduced in <a href="https://262.ecma-international.org/6.0/#sec-modules">2015</a>, and NodeJS has supported <code>type=module/commonjs</code>, <em>.mjs</em>, and <em>.cjs</em>, with the goal of replacing <em>.js</em>, since <a href="https://nodejs.org/api/packages.html#type">2019</a>, to what degree have these new conventions been adopted?</p>

<p>I answered this with data, using two approaches:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Looking at the most starred JavaScript and TypeScript repos on Github</li>
  <li>Looking at the most downloaded packages on NPM</li>
</ol>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/bcherny/es-module-stats">results</a> are not rosy. After 5+ years, adoption of ES Modules remains weak:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Between 9-27% of JavaScript/TypeScript projects declare themselves to be ES Modules via the <code>type</code> (and lesser-used <code>exports</code>) fields in their <em>package.json</em>s.</li>
  <li>Less than 6% of JavaScript/TypeScript files declare that they are ES Modules via the <em>.mjs</em>, <em>.cjs</em>, <em>.mts</em>, etc. file extensions.</li>
</ol>

<p>Note that these ranges come from the two approaches I used to estimate the numbers. Head <a href="https://github.com/bcherny/es-module-stats">here</a> for more detailed data and code.</p>

<h2 id="how-do-we-fix-it">How do we fix it?</h2>

<p>This helps explain why it’s so painful to interoperate ES Modules and CommonJS across both NodeJS and TypeScript: enough libraries use ES Modules that for many projects you need to either use ES Modules, or figure out how to interoperate ES Modules with your CommonJS code. At the same time, enough code still uses CommonJS that you often need to figure out how to include that legacy code in your otherwise-ES Module project.</p>

<p>The benefits of ES Modules are significant. Rolling everything back to CommonJS is not the way forward. Is there more we can do to simplify the ecosystem, and push harder on adoption? Some ideas:</p>

<ol>
  <li>We should kill <em>.mjs</em>, <em>.cjs</em>, <em>.mts</em>, etc. The vast majority of projects use <code>type=module</code> in their <em>package.json</em>, rather than file extensions. It would simplify things considerably if we drop support for these new file extensions and stick to <em>.js</em>, <em>.jsx</em>, <em>.ts</em>, and <em>.tsx</em>.</li>
  <li>We should make <code>type=module</code> the <a href="https://github.com/npm/cli/issues/7594">default</a> for new <em>package.json</em> files for the <code>npm init</code>, <code>yarn init</code>, and <code>pnpm init</code> commands. Package managers’ <code>publish</code> commands should warn when <code>type</code> is not set to <code>module</code>.</li>
  <li>We should upgrade the most common libraries used by the community to ES Modules, either manually or through automated pull requests (this feels like something that can be semi-automated).</li>
  <li>The NPM registry can require an explicit <code>module</code> field on new packages, making it clear when a package intentionally uses CommonJS (eg. because it targets legacy NodeJS versions).</li>
  <li>NodeJS can officially drop support for <code>require</code> and <code>module.exports</code> in a future version, creating a bit more pressure to migrate.</li>
</ol>

<p>I’d love to hear others’ thoughts. Have you also felt the pain of interoperating ES Modules and CommonJS?</p>

<hr>

<p>Discuss this post on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40737508">HackerNews</a> or on <a href="https://www.threads.net/@boris_cherny/post/C8aDJuGI5HM">Threads</a>.</p>

</section>
  

</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Curl is inside 22,734 Steam games (130 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://daniel.haxx.se/blog/2024/06/20/inside-22734-steam-games/</link>
            <guid>40737349</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 11:18:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://daniel.haxx.se/blog/2024/06/20/inside-22734-steam-games/">https://daniel.haxx.se/blog/2024/06/20/inside-22734-steam-games/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40737349">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="page">

	<div id="primary" role="main">
			
<article id="post-25020">
	
		<p><img width="672" height="372" src="https://daniel.haxx.se/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/GTA-end-credits-libcurl-672x372.jpg" alt="" decoding="async" srcset="https://daniel.haxx.se/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/GTA-end-credits-libcurl-672x372.jpg 672w, https://daniel.haxx.se/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/GTA-end-credits-libcurl-200x110.jpg 200w, https://daniel.haxx.se/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/GTA-end-credits-libcurl-1038x576.jpg 1038w" sizes="(max-width: 672px) 100vw, 672px">		</p>

		
	<!-- .entry-header -->

		<div>
		
<p>About a year ago I blogged about <a href="https://daniel.haxx.se/blog/2023/06/09/games-curl-too/" data-type="post" data-id="22459">games that use curl</a>. In that post I listed a bunch of well-known titles I knew use curl and there was a list of 136 additional games giving credit to curl.</p>



<p>Kind of amazing that over <em>one hundred games</em> decided to use curl!</p>



<p>At the time, lots of people told me that number was probably way low and while I kind of had that feeling as well it was just a feeling and nothing else. We cannot be <em>absolutely certain</em> unless there is data or evidence to actually back it up.</p>



<p>The speculation could stop this week when someone provided me with a link to a database of Steam titles (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steam_(service)">Steam</a>, as in the video game service). <a href="https://steamdb.info/">SteamDB</a> is a third-party site that among other things extracts data and figures out which “SDKs” are used by Steam games: <a href="https://steamdb.info/tech/SDK/cURL/">Their list of game titles on Steam using curl</a>.</p>



<p>Since that list is capped at 10,000 titles, I had to filter it and add up the number of titles based on release year. Out of the 91,559 titles they currently list in their database, <strong>22,734</strong> are identified to be using curl: <strong>24.8%</strong>.</p>



<p>Not too shabby for a hobby.</p>


<div>
<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;uploadedSrc&quot;:&quot;https:\/\/daniel.haxx.se\/blog\/wp-content\/uploads\/2024\/04\/curl-is-just-2000.jpg&quot;,&quot;figureClassNames&quot;:&quot;aligncenter size-full&quot;,&quot;figureStyles&quot;:null,&quot;imgClassNames&quot;:&quot;wp-image-24622&quot;,&quot;imgStyles&quot;:null,&quot;targetWidth&quot;:2000,&quot;targetHeight&quot;:1500,&quot;scaleAttr&quot;:false,&quot;ariaLabel&quot;:&quot;Enlarge image&quot;,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image"><img decoding="async" width="2000" height="1500" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://daniel.haxx.se/blog/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/curl-is-just-2000.jpg" alt=""></figure></div>	</div><!-- .entry-content -->
	
	</article><!-- #post-25020 -->
		<nav>
		<h2>
			Post navigation		</h2>
		<!-- .nav-links -->
		</nav><!-- .navigation -->
		
<!-- #comments -->
		</div><!-- #primary -->

<!-- #content-sidebar -->
<div id="secondary">
		<h2>tech, open source and networking</h2>
	
	
		<!-- #primary-sidebar -->
	</div><!-- #secondary -->

		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Delusion of Advanced Plastic Recycling (108 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.propublica.org/article/delusion-advanced-chemical-plastic-recycling-pyrolysis</link>
            <guid>40737308</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 11:12:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/delusion-advanced-chemical-plastic-recycling-pyrolysis">https://www.propublica.org/article/delusion-advanced-chemical-plastic-recycling-pyrolysis</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40737308">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-pp-location="article body">

        
        
        




                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="2.0"><span>Last year,</span> I became obsessed with a plastic cup. </p>

<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="2.1">It was a small container that held diced fruit, the type thrown into lunch boxes. And it was the first product I’d seen born of what’s being touted as a cure for a crisis.</p>
        
    
                        


   
            
            
            
            

   
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="4.0">Plastic doesn’t break down in nature. If you turned all of what’s been made into cling wrap, it would <a href="https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/01/160127083854.htm">cover every inch of the globe</a>. It’s piling up, <a href="https://www.epa.gov/plastics/impacts-plastic-pollution">leaching into our water</a> and <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/microplastics-nanoplastics-heart-attacks-strokes-health">poisoning our bodies</a>.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="5.0">Scientists say the key to fixing this is to make less of it; the world churns out 430 million metric tons each year.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="6.0">But businesses that rely on plastic production, like fossil fuel and chemical companies, have worked since the <a href="https://grist.org/accountability/petrochemical-companies-have-known-for-40-years-that-plastics-recycling-wouldnt-work/">1980s to spin the pollution as a failure of waste management</a> — one that can be solved with recycling.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="7.0"><a href="https://www.npr.org/2020/03/31/822597631/plastic-wars-three-takeaways-from-the-fight-over-the-future-of-plastics">Industry leaders knew then</a> what we know now: Traditional recycling <a href="https://theintercept.com/2019/07/20/plastics-industry-plastic-recycling/">would </a><a href="https://theintercept.com/2019/07/20/plastics-industry-plastic-recycling/">barely put a dent in the trash heap</a>. It’s hard to transform flimsy candy wrappers into sandwich bags, or to make containers that once held motor oil clean enough for milk.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="8.0">Now, the industry is heralding nothing short of a miracle: an “advanced”type of recycling known as pyrolysis — “pyro” means fire and “lysis” means separation. It uses heat to break plastic all the way down to its molecular building blocks.</p>
        
    
                    
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="10.0">While old-school, “mechanical” recycling yields plastic that’s degraded or contaminated, this type of “chemical” recycling promises plastic that behaves like it’s new, and could usher in what the industry casts as a green revolution: Not only would it save hard-to-recycle plastics like frozen food wrappers from the dumpster, but it would turn them into new products that can replace the old ones and be chemically recycled again and again.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="11.0">So when three companies used ExxonMobil’s pyrolysis-based technology to successfully conjure up that fruit cup, <a href="https://www.packworld.com/supplier-news/news/22871469/printpack-printpack-exxonmobil-pacific-coast-producers-bring-circularity-to-fruit-cups">they announced it to the world</a>.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="12.0">“This is a significant milestone,” said Printpack, which turned the plastic into cups. The fruit supplier Pacific Coast Producers called it “the most important initiative a consumer-packaged goods company can pursue.”</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="13.0">“ExxonMobil is supporting the circularity of plastics,” the August 2023 news release said, citing <a href="https://grist.org/accountability/circular-economy-plastics-recycling-reuse-waste-conference-seattle/">a </a><a href="https://grist.org/accountability/circular-economy-plastics-recycling-reuse-waste-conference-seattle/">buzzword</a> that implies an infinite loop of using, recycling and reusing.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="14.0">They were so proud, I hoped they would tell me all about how they made the cup, how many of them existed and where I could buy one.</p>

<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="14.1">So began my long — and, well, circular — pursuit of the truth at a time when it really matters.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="15.0">This year, nearly all of the world’s countries are hammering out a <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/plastics-waste-united-nations-international-conference-treaty-ottawa">United Nations treaty to deal with the plastic crisis</a>. As they consider limiting production, <a href="https://www.ehn.org/chemical-recycling-of-plastics-2667297273.html">the industry is making a hard push to shift the conversation</a> to the wonders of chemical recycling. It’s also buying ads during cable news shows as U.S. states consider laws to limit plastic packaging and lobbying federal agencies to loosen the very definition of what it means to recycle.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="16.0">It’s been selling governments on chemical recycling, with quite a bit of success. American and <a href="https://www.euwid-recycling.com/news/business/lyondellbasell-to-receive-eur40m-in-eu-funding-for-chemical-recycling-plant-080124/">European regulators</a> <a href="https://theintercept.com/2023/10/31/plastics-pollution-advanced-recycling/">have spent tens of </a><a href="https://theintercept.com/2023/10/31/plastics-pollution-advanced-recycling/">millions</a><a href="https://theintercept.com/2023/10/31/plastics-pollution-advanced-recycling/"> subsidizing pyrolysis facilities</a>. <a href="https://www.americanchemistry.com/chemistry-in-america/news-trends/press-release/2024/with-wyoming-half-the-country-open-to-advanced-recycling">Half of all U.S. states</a> have <a href="https://e360.yale.edu/features/advanced-plastics-recycling-pyrolysis">eased air pollution rules</a> for the process, which has been found to <a href="https://www.nrdc.org/sites/default/files/chemical-recycling-greenwashing-incineration-ib.pdf">release carcinogens like benzene and dioxins</a> and <a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acssuschemeng.2c05497#">give off more greenhouse gases than making plastic from crude oil</a>.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="17.0">Given the high stakes of this moment, I set out to understand exactly what the world is getting out of this recycling technology. For months, I tracked press releases, interviewed experts, tried to buy plastic made via pyrolysis and learned more than I ever wanted to know about the science of recycled molecules.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="18.0">Under all the math and engineering, I found an inconvenient truth: Not much is being recycled at all, nor is pyrolysis capable of curbing the plastic crisis.  </p>

<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="18.1">Not now. Maybe not ever.</p>
        
    
                    

<figure data-pp-id="20" data-pp-blocktype="image">

    


                    
    


    <img alt="" width="300" height="200" loading="lazy" js-autosizes="" src="https://img.assets-d.propublica.org/v5/images/item-10.png?crop=focalpoint&amp;fit=crop&amp;fm=webp&amp;fp-x=0.5&amp;fp-y=0.5&amp;h=533&amp;q=80&amp;w=800&amp;s=7c0cf6520a1b45b5c6b466ab9f20c825" srcset="https://img.assets-d.propublica.org/v5/images/item-10.png?crop=focalpoint&amp;fit=crop&amp;fm=webp&amp;fp-x=0.5&amp;fp-y=0.5&amp;h=267&amp;q=80&amp;w=400&amp;s=c2a95b75734aaec3d82ebab09ca6e07a 400w, https://img.assets-d.propublica.org/v5/images/item-10.png?crop=focalpoint&amp;fit=crop&amp;fm=webp&amp;fp-x=0.5&amp;fp-y=0.5&amp;h=533&amp;q=80&amp;w=800&amp;s=7c0cf6520a1b45b5c6b466ab9f20c825 800w, https://img.assets-d.propublica.org/v5/images/item-10.png?crop=focalpoint&amp;fit=crop&amp;fm=webp&amp;fp-x=0.5&amp;fp-y=0.5&amp;h=800&amp;q=80&amp;w=1200&amp;s=35a4dfd7efe9417e228127c272472461 1200w, https://img.assets-d.propublica.org/v5/images/item-10.png?crop=focalpoint&amp;fit=crop&amp;fm=webp&amp;fp-x=0.5&amp;fp-y=0.5&amp;h=867&amp;q=80&amp;w=1300&amp;s=292b2d8c2964a3aea440141efbaf99da 1300w, https://img.assets-d.propublica.org/v5/images/item-10.png?crop=focalpoint&amp;fit=crop&amp;fm=webp&amp;fp-x=0.5&amp;fp-y=0.5&amp;h=967&amp;q=80&amp;w=1450&amp;s=fbb209578b9489431171ea59aa2b5947 1450w, https://img.assets-d.propublica.org/v5/images/item-10.png?crop=focalpoint&amp;fit=crop&amp;fm=webp&amp;fp-x=0.5&amp;fp-y=0.5&amp;h=1067&amp;q=80&amp;w=1600&amp;s=0651de84e0db97e13899d7e6ac61577d 1600w, https://img.assets-d.propublica.org/v5/images/item-10.png?crop=focalpoint&amp;fit=crop&amp;fm=webp&amp;fp-x=0.5&amp;fp-y=0.5&amp;h=1333&amp;q=80&amp;w=2000&amp;s=4d3b38b00a27b9a622eeebf3dd17ed4e 2000w">

            
    
<figcaption>
    
    
    
    </figcaption>

</figure>

        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="21.0"><span>Let’s take</span> a closer look at that Printpack press release, which uses convoluted terms to describe the recycled plastic in that fruit cup: </p>

<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="21.1">“30% ISCC PLUS certified-circular”</p>

<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="21.2">“mass balance free attribution”</p>

<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="21.3">It’s easy to conclude the cup was made with 30% recycled plastic — until you break down the numerical sleight of hand that props up that number. </p>

<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="21.4">It took interviews with a dozen academics, consultants, environmentalists and engineers to help me do just that. </p>

<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="21.5">Stick with me as I unravel it all.</p>
        
            
    
    
    
                            

<figure data-pp-id="1" data-pp-blocktype="embed">

    


                        <div id="lesson-one">
    <div>
         <p>
         <h3><span>Lesson 1</span></h3>
         </p>
          <h2>Most of the old plastic that goes <span>into</span> pyrolysis doesn’t actually become new&nbsp;plastic.
</h2>
      </div>
         <p><img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/graphics/2024-plastics/images/item-1.png">
       <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/graphics/2024-plastics/images/item-2.png">
        <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/graphics/2024-plastics/images/item-3.png">
         <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/graphics/2024-plastics/images/item-5.png">
     
      
    </p>
</div>
            
    
<figcaption>
    
    
    
    </figcaption>


</figure>

            
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="24.0"><span>In traditional recycling,</span> plastic is turned into tiny pellets or flakes,  which you can melt again and mold back into recycled plastic products.</p>

<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="24.1">Even in a real-life scenario, where bottles have labels and a little bit of juice left in them, most of the plastic products that go into the process find new life.</p>
        
            
    
    
    
                            

<figure data-pp-id="1" data-pp-blocktype="embed">

    


                        <!-- Generated by ai2html v0.115.1 - 2024-06-13 12:31 -->
<!-- ai file: plastic-recyclingrate-mechanical-ai2html.ai -->




<!-- End ai2html - 2024-06-13 12:31 -->
            
    
<figcaption>
    
    
    
    </figcaption>


</figure>

            
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="26.0">The numbers are much lower for pyrolysis.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="27.0">It’s “very, very, very, very difficult” to break down plastic that way, said Steve Jenkins, vice president of chemicals consulting at Wood Mackenzie, an energy and resources analytics firm. “The laws of nature and the laws of physics are trying to stop you.”</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="28.0">Waste is heated until it turns into oil. Part of that oil is composed of a liquid called naphtha, which is essential for making plastic. </p>

<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="28.1">There are two ingredients in the naphtha that recyclers want to isolate: propylene and ethylene — gases that can be turned into solid plastics.</p>

<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="28.2">To split the naphtha into different chemicals, it’s fed into a machine called a steam cracker. Less than half of what it spits out becomes propylene and ethylene.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="29.0">This means that if a pyrolysis operator started with 100 pounds of plastic waste, it can expect to end up with 15-20 pounds of reusable plastic. Experts told me the process can yield less if the plastic used is dirty or more if the technology is particularly advanced.</p>
        
            
    
    
    
                            

<figure data-pp-id="1" data-pp-blocktype="embed">

    


                        <!-- Generated by ai2html v0.115.1 - 2024-06-13 12:31 -->
<!-- ai file: plastic-recyclingrate-chemical-ai2html.ai -->




<!-- End ai2html - 2024-06-13 12:31 -->
            
    
<figcaption>
    
    
    
    </figcaption>


</figure>

            
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="31.0">I reached out to several companies to ask how much new plastic their processes actually yield, and none provided numbers. The American Chemistry Council, the nation’s largest plastic lobby, told me that because so many factors impact a company’s yield, it’s impossible to estimate that number for the entire industry.</p>
        
            
    
    
    
                            

<figure data-pp-id="1" data-pp-blocktype="embed">

    


                        <div id="lesson-two">

    <div>
         <p>
         <h3><span>Lesson 2</span></h3>
         </p>
          <h2> The plastic that comes <span>out of</span> pyrolysis contains very little recycled material. 

</h2>
      </div>
       <p><img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/graphics/2024-plastics/images/item-7.png">

         <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/graphics/2024-plastics/images/item-5.png">
         <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/graphics/2024-plastics/images/item-2.png">
         <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/graphics/2024-plastics/images/item-6.png">




   </p>


</div>


            
    
<figcaption>
    
    
    
    </figcaption>


</figure>

            
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="34.0"><span>With mechanical recycling,</span> it’s hard to make plastic that’s 100% recycled; it’s expensive to do, and the process degrades plastic. Recycled pellets are often combined with new pellets to make stuff that’s 25% or 50% recycled, for example.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="35.0">But far less recycled plastic winds up in products made through pyrolysis. </p>

<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="35.1">That’s because the naphtha created using recycled plastic is contaminated. Manufacturers add all kinds of chemicals to make products bend or keep them from degrading in the sun.</p>
        
            
    
    
    
                            

<figure data-pp-id="1" data-pp-blocktype="embed">

    


                        

    <img alt="" width="1460" height="2285" loading="lazy" js-autosizes="" src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/graphics/2024-plastics/graphics/plastic-steamcracker-mobile-FINAL.png">
            
    
<figcaption>
    
    
    
    </figcaption>


</figure>

            
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="37.0">Recyclers can overpower them by heavily diluting the recycled naphtha. With what, you ask? Nonrecycled naphtha made from ordinary crude oil!</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="38.0">This is the quiet — and convenient — part of the industry’s revolutionary pyrolysis method: It relies heavily on extracting fossil fuels. At least 90% of the naphtha used in pyrolysis is fossil fuel naphtha. Only then can it be poured into the steam cracker to separate the chemicals that make plastic.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="39.0">So at the end of the day, nothing that comes out of pyrolysis physically contains more than 10% recycled material (though experts and studies have shown that, in practice, it’s more like 5% or 2%).</p>
        
            
    
    
    
                            

<figure data-pp-id="1" data-pp-blocktype="embed">

    


                        

    <img alt="" width="1460" height="2285" loading="lazy" js-autosizes="" src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/graphics/2024-plastics/graphics/plastic-steamcracker-mobile-FINAL.png">
            
    
<figcaption>
    
    
    
    </figcaption>


</figure>

            
        
            
    
    
    
                            

<figure data-pp-id="1" data-pp-blocktype="embed">

    


                        <div id="lesson-three">

    <div>
         <p>
         <h3><span>Lesson 3</span></h3>
         </p>
          <h2>The industry uses mathematical acrobatics to make pyrolysis look like a&nbsp;success. 
</h2>
      </div>

        <p><img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/graphics/2024-plastics/images/item-3.png">


              <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/graphics/2024-plastics/images/item-7.png">

     </p>


</div>


            
    
<figcaption>
    
    
    
    </figcaption>


</figure>

            
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="43.0"><span>Ten percent</span> doesn’t look very impressive. Some consumers are willing to pay <a href="https://theconversation.com/climate-explained-are-consumers-willing-to-pay-more-for-climate-friendly-products-146757">a premium for sustainability</a>, so companies use a form of accounting called mass balance to inflate the recycled-ness of their products. It’s not unlike offset schemes I’ve uncovered that <a href="https://features.propublica.org/brazil-carbon-offsets/inconvenient-truth-carbon-credits-dont-work-deforestation-redd-acre-cambodia/">absolve refineries of their carbon emissions</a> and <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/biodiversity-offsets-guinea-world-bank-group-chimpanzees-outbreak">enable mining companies to kill chimpanzees</a>. Industry-affiliated groups like the International Sustainability and Carbon Certification write the rules. (ISCC didn’t respond to requests for comment.)</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="44.0">To see how this works, let’s take a look at what might happen to a batch of recycled naphtha. Let’s say the steam cracker splits the batch into 100 pounds of assorted ingredients.</p>
        
            
    
    
    
                            

<figure data-pp-id="1" data-pp-blocktype="embed">

    


                        

  

      <section id="scrolly-1">
        <div>

                <!-- persistent labels -->
                  <p>
                    = 1 pound
                  </p>
                  <p id="recycled-dot-label">
                    = 1 "recycled" pound
                  </p>
                  <p>
                    Propylene
                  </p>
                  <p>
                    Ethylene
                  </p>
                  <p>
                    Other chemicals, including fuel
                  </p>


                  
                  
                <!-- close all-content below -->
                </div>
          

        <div>
          <p>You'll get some colorless gasses that are used to make plastic: 13 pounds of propylene and 30 pounds of ethylene. You'll also wind up with 57 pounds of other chemicals.</p>
          <p>Propylene makes sturdy material such as butter tubs <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/graphics/2024-plastics/explainer/inline-butter.png">; ethylene makes flexible plastics like yogurt pouches <span><img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/graphics/2024-plastics/explainer/inline-yogurt.png">.</span> Many of the other chemicals <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/graphics/2024-plastics/explainer/inline-chemicals.png"> aren't used to make plastic — some get used to make rubber and paint or are used as fuel. </p>
          <p>All of these outputs are technically 10% recycled, since they were made from 10% recycled naphtha. (I’m using this optimistic hypothetical to make the math easy.) </p>
          <p>But companies can do a number shuffle to assign all of the recycled value from the butter tubs <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/graphics/2024-plastics/explainer/inline-butter.png"> to the yogurt pouches <span><img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/graphics/2024-plastics/explainer/inline-yogurt.png">.</span>  </p>
          <p>That way they can market the yogurt pouches <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/graphics/2024-plastics/explainer/inline-yogurt.png"> as 14% recycled (or “circular”), even though nothing has physically changed about the makeup of the pouches.  </p>
          <p>What's more, through a method called free attribution, companies can assign the recycled value from other chemicals <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/graphics/2024-plastics/explainer/inline-chemicals.png"> (even if they would never be turned into plastic) to the yogurt pouches <span><img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/graphics/2024-plastics/explainer/inline-yogurt.png">.</span></p>
          <p>Now, the yogurt pouches <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/graphics/2024-plastics/explainer/inline-yogurt.png"> can be sold as 33% recycled. </p>
 
        </div>
      </section>

  
    
            
    
<figcaption>
    
    
    
    </figcaption>


</figure>

            
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="46.0">There are many flavors of this kind of accounting. Another version of free attribution would allow the company to take that entire 30-pound batch of “33% recycled” pouches and split them even further:</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="47.0">A third of them, 10 pounds, could be labeled 100% recycled — shifting the value of the full batch onto them — so long as the remaining 20 pounds aren’t labeled as recycled at all.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="48.0">As long as you avoid double counting, Jenkins told me, you can attribute the full value of recycled naphtha to the products that will make the most money. Companies need that financial incentive to recoup the costs of pyrolysis, he said.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="49.0">But it’s hard to argue that this type of marketing is transparent. Consumers aren’t going to parse through the caveats of a 33% recycled claim or understand how the green technology they’re being sold perpetuates the fossil fuel industry. I posed the critiques to the industry, including environmentalists’ accusations that mass balance is just a fancy way of greenwashing.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="50.0">The American Chemistry Council told me it’s impossible to know whether a particular ethylene molecule comes from pyrolysis naphtha or fossil fuel naphtha; the compounds produced are “fungible” and can be used for multiple products, like making rubber, solvents and paints that would reduce the amount of new fossil fuels needed. Its statement called mass balance a “well-known methodology” that’s been used by other industries including fair trade coffee, chocolate and renewable energy.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="51.0">Legislation in the European Union already forbids free attribution, and leaders are debating whether to allow other forms of mass balance. U.S. regulation is far behind that, but as the Federal Trade Commission revises its general guidelines for green marketing, the industry is arguing that mass balance is crucial to the future of advanced recycling. “The science of advanced recycling simply does not support any other approach because the ability to track individual molecules does not readily exist,” said a <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/24688789-2023-04-24-exxonmobil-ftc-comments#document/p5/a2562175">comment from ExxonMobil</a>.</p>
        
    
                    

<figure data-pp-id="53" data-pp-blocktype="image">

    


                    
    


    <img alt="" width="300" height="200" loading="lazy" js-autosizes="" src="https://img.assets-d.propublica.org/v5/images/item-4.png?crop=focalpoint&amp;fit=crop&amp;fm=webp&amp;fp-x=0.5&amp;fp-y=0.5&amp;h=533&amp;q=80&amp;w=800&amp;s=4295b6950dd8b4d6cbca0138e6620862" srcset="https://img.assets-d.propublica.org/v5/images/item-4.png?crop=focalpoint&amp;fit=crop&amp;fm=webp&amp;fp-x=0.5&amp;fp-y=0.5&amp;h=267&amp;q=80&amp;w=400&amp;s=0967e518b1a2cf3cc2f1ad07c56bf7ff 400w, https://img.assets-d.propublica.org/v5/images/item-4.png?crop=focalpoint&amp;fit=crop&amp;fm=webp&amp;fp-x=0.5&amp;fp-y=0.5&amp;h=533&amp;q=80&amp;w=800&amp;s=4295b6950dd8b4d6cbca0138e6620862 800w, https://img.assets-d.propublica.org/v5/images/item-4.png?crop=focalpoint&amp;fit=crop&amp;fm=webp&amp;fp-x=0.5&amp;fp-y=0.5&amp;h=800&amp;q=80&amp;w=1200&amp;s=d06685d5ac9a42c7b8f8e122aaf2dc61 1200w, https://img.assets-d.propublica.org/v5/images/item-4.png?crop=focalpoint&amp;fit=crop&amp;fm=webp&amp;fp-x=0.5&amp;fp-y=0.5&amp;h=867&amp;q=80&amp;w=1300&amp;s=d6a7708b4b0eabe988f74f0041f3f0f2 1300w, https://img.assets-d.propublica.org/v5/images/item-4.png?crop=focalpoint&amp;fit=crop&amp;fm=webp&amp;fp-x=0.5&amp;fp-y=0.5&amp;h=967&amp;q=80&amp;w=1450&amp;s=40944522eff6cdd5c523b4d3ccb5d794 1450w, https://img.assets-d.propublica.org/v5/images/item-4.png?crop=focalpoint&amp;fit=crop&amp;fm=webp&amp;fp-x=0.5&amp;fp-y=0.5&amp;h=1067&amp;q=80&amp;w=1600&amp;s=ca693587302aff1f58ee145d106798c1 1600w, https://img.assets-d.propublica.org/v5/images/item-4.png?crop=focalpoint&amp;fit=crop&amp;fm=webp&amp;fp-x=0.5&amp;fp-y=0.5&amp;h=1333&amp;q=80&amp;w=2000&amp;s=f381d567cd668920d90865bf81773611 2000w">

            
    
<figcaption>
    
    
    
    </figcaption>

</figure>

        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="54.0"><span>If you think</span> navigating the ins and outs of pyrolysis is hard, try getting your hands on actual plastic made through it.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="55.0">It’s not as easy as going to the grocery store. Those water bottles you might see with 100% recycled claims are almost certainly made through traditional recycling. The biggest giveaway is that the labels don’t contain the asterisks or fine print typical of products made through pyrolysis, like “mass balance,” “circular” or “certified.”</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="56.0">When I asked about the fruit cup, ExxonMobil directed me to its partners. Printpack didn’t respond to my inquiries. Pacific Coast Producers told me it was “engaged in a small pilot pack of plastic bowls that contain post-consumer content with materials certified” by third parties, and that it “has made no label claims regarding these cups and is evaluating their use.”</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="57.0">I pressed the American Chemistry Council for other examples.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="58.0">“Chemical recycling is a proven technology that is already manufacturing products, conserving natural resources, and offering the potential to dramatically improve recycling rates,” said Matthew Kastner, a media relations director. His colleague added that much of the plastic made via pyrolysis is “being used for food- and medical-grade packaging, oftentimes not branded.”</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="59.0">They provided links to products including a Chevron Phillips Chemical announcement about bringing recycled plastic food wrapping <a href="https://www.waste360.com/waste-producers/chevron-phillips-chemical-and-charter-next-generation-to-bring-circular-polyethylene-to-retail-stores">to retail stores</a>.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="60.0">“For competitive reasons,” a Chevron spokesperson declined to discuss brand names, the product’s availability or the amount produced.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="61.0">In another case, a grocery store chain sold <a href="https://www.exxonmobilchemical.com/en/resources/library/library-detail/107131/circularity_demo_press_release_en">chicken wrapped in plastic</a> made by ExxonMobil’s pyrolysis process. The producers told me they were part of a small project that’s now discontinued.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="62.0">In the end, I ran down half a dozen claims about products that came out of pyrolysis; each either existed in limited quantities or had its recycled-ness obscured with mass balance caveats. </p>

<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="62.1">Then this April, nearly eight months after I’d begun my pursuit, I could barely contain myself when I got my hands on an actual product.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="63.0">I was at a United Nations treaty negotiation in Ottawa, Ontario, and an industry group had set up a nearby showcase. On display was a case of Heinz baked beans, packaged in “39% recycled plastic*.” (The asterisk took me down an online rabbit hole about certification and circularity. Heinz didn’t respond to my questions.)</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="64.0">This, too, was part of an old trial. The beans were expired.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="65.0">Pyrolysis is a “fairy tale,” I heard from Neil Tangri, the science and policy director at the environmental justice network Global Alliance for Incinerator Alternatives. He said he’s been hearing pyrolysis claims since the ’90s but has yet to see proof it works as promised.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="66.0">“If anyone has cracked the code for a large-scale, efficient and profitable way to turn plastic into plastic,” he said, “every reporter in the world” would get a tour.</p>

<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="66.1">If I did get a tour, I wondered, would I even see all of that stubborn, dirty plastic they were supposedly recycling?</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="67.0">The industry’s marketing implied we could soon toss sandwich bags and string cheese wrappers into curbside recycling bins, where they would be diverted to pyrolysis plants. But I grew skeptical as I watched a webinar for ExxonMobil’s pyrolysis-based technology, the kind used to make the fruit cup. The company showed photos of plastic packaging and oil field equipment as examples of its starting material but then mentioned something that made me sit up straight: It was using pre-consumer plastic to “give consistency” to the waste stream.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="68.0">Chemical plants need consistency, so it’s easier to use plastic that hasn’t been gunked up by consumer use, Jenkins explained.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="69.0">But plastic waste that had never been touched by consumers, such as industrial scrap found at the edges of factory molds, could easily be recycled the old-fashioned way. Didn’t that negate the need for this more polluting, less efficient process?</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="70.0">I asked ExxonMobil how much post-consumer plastic it was actually using. Catie Tuley, a media relations adviser, said it depends on what’s available. “At the end of the day, advanced recycling allows us to divert plastic waste from landfills and give new life to plastic waste.”</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="71.0">I posed the same question to several other operators. A company in Europe told me it uses “mixed post-consumer, flexible plastic waste” and does not recycle pre-consumer waste.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="72.0">But this spring at an environmental journalism conference, an American Chemistry Council executive confirmed the industry’s preference for clean plastic as he talked about an Atlanta-based company and its pyrolysis process. My colleague Sharon Lerner asked whether it was sourcing curbside-recycled plastic for pyrolysis.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="73.0">If Nexus Circular had a “magic wand,” it would, he acknowledged, but right now that kind of waste “isn’t good enough.” He added, “It’s got tomatoes in it.”</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="74.0">(Nexus later confirmed that most of the plastic it used was pre-consumer and about a third was post-consumer, including motor oil containers sourced from car repair shops and bags dropped off at special recycling centers.)</p>
        
    
                                  
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="76.0">Clean, well-sorted plastic is a valuable commodity. If the chemical recycling industry grows, experts told me, those companies could end up competing with the far more efficient traditional recycling.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="77.0">To spur that growth, the American Chemistry Council is lobbying for mandates that would require more recycled plastic in packaging; it wants to make sure that chemically recycled plastic counts. “This would create market-driven demand signals,” Kastner told me, and ease the way for large-scale investment in new chemical recycling plants.</p>
        
    
                    
<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="78.0">I asked Jenkins, the energy industry analyst, to play out this scenario on a larger scale. </p>

<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="78.1">Were all of these projects adding up? Could the industry conceivably make enough propylene and ethylene through pyrolysis to replace much of our demand for new plastic? </p>

<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="78.2">He looked three years into the future, using his company’s latest figures on global pyrolysis investment, and gave an optimistic assessment. </p>

<p data-pp-blocktype="copy" data-pp-id="78.3">At best, the world could replace 0.2% of new plastic churned out in a year with products made through pyrolysis.</p>
        
    
                    <div data-pp-location="bottom-note">
                                    

                                    
        <div data-pp-location="bottom-note">
                        <h2><strong>About the Math</strong></h2>
<p>Our article is focused on pyrolysis because it’s the most popular form of chemical recycling. Other types of chemical recycling technologies have their own strengths and weaknesses.</p>
<p>There are different variations of pyrolysis, and steam crackers produce a range of ethylene and propylene yields. Companies are secretive about their operations. To estimate the efficiencies of pyrolysis and mass balance, I read dozens of peer-reviewed studies, reports, industry presentations, advertisements and news stories. I also fact checked with a dozen experts who have different opinions on pyrolysis, mass balance and recycling. Some of them, including Jenkins and Anthony Schiavo, senior director at Lux Research, provided estimates of overall yields for companies trying to make plastic. All of that information coalesced around a 15% to 20% yield for conventional pyrolysis processes and 25% to 30% for more advanced technologies. We are showcasing the conventional process because it’s the most common scenario.</p>
<p>We took steps to simplify the math and jargon. For instance, we skipped over the fact that a small amount of the naphtha fed into the steam cracker is consumed as fuel. And we called the fraction of pyrolysis oil that’s suitable for a steam cracker “pyrolysis naphtha”; it is technically a naphtha-like product.</p>
<p>These processes may improve over time as new technologies are developed. But there are hard limits and tradeoffs associated with the nature of steam cracking, the contamination in the feedstock, the type of feedstock used and financial and energy costs.</p>

        </div>

    


                                    
        <div data-pp-location="bottom-note">
                        <p>Graphics and development by <a href="https://www.propublica.org/people/lucas-waldron">Lucas Waldron</a>. Design and development by <a href="https://www.propublica.org/people/Anna-Donlan">Anna Donlan</a>. <a href="https://www.propublica.org/people/Mollie-Simon">Mollie Simon</a> and <a href="https://www.propublica.org/people/Gabriel-Sandoval">Gabriel Sandoval</a> contributed research.</p>

        </div>

    
            </div><!-- end .article-body__bottom-notes -->
        
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tetris as Font (358 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://erikdemaine.org/fonts/tetris/</link>
            <guid>40737294</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 11:11:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://erikdemaine.org/fonts/tetris/">https://erikdemaine.org/fonts/tetris/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40737294">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><table id="data"><tbody><tr><td><label for="text">Enter text to render: &nbsp;</label><p><label for="rot">Obscure in URL</label></p></td><td><label for="anim">Animate</label><p><label for="rotate">Include rotations</label><br><label for="speed">Speed:</label>&nbsp;</p><label for="puzzle">Puzzle font</label><br><label for="black">Black pieces (dissection puzzle)</label></td><td><label for="grid">Grid</label><br><label for="center">Rotation center</label><br><label for="floor">Bottom floor</label><br></td></tr></tbody></table><p>GIF width:<a id="download"></a></p><hr><p><b><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tetris">Tetris</a></b> is
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_best-selling_video_games">among the best-selling</a> (and perhaps best-known) video games ever.
We grew up playing the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Game_Boy">Game Boy</a> and
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spectrum_HoloByte">Spectrum HoloByte</a> PC editions.
Erik is even a <a href="http://erikdemaine.org/images/tetris_award_large.jpg">Tetris Master</a>.
Nowadays you can play
<a href="https://tetris.com/play-tetris/">in your browser</a>
or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tetris_99">on a Switch</a>
or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tetris_Effect">on PS4/PC/VR</a>.
</p><p><b>Font design.</b>  Each letter and digit in this typeface is made up of
exactly one of each of the Tetris pieces:
<span id="pieceI"></span> (I),
<span id="pieceJ"></span> (J),
<span id="pieceL"></span> (L),
<span id="pieceO"></span> (O),
<span id="pieceS"></span> (S),
<span id="pieceT"></span> (T), and
<span id="pieceZ"></span> (Z).
Furthermore, the letter is designed so that it can actually be constructed
by stacking these pieces one at a time and be supported by previous pieces,
as in Tetris.
These designs were found by hand, aided by the
<a href="http://burrtools.sourceforge.net/">BurrTools</a> software
which enabled searching for whether the Tetris pieces could fit inside
a candidate outline for a letter.
The piece colors roughly follow
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tetris#Game_pieces">The Tetris Company's standard colors</a>,
or you can switch to black pieces.
The initial rotations follow the standard
<a href="https://tetris.fandom.com/wiki/SRS">Super Rotation System</a>.
</p><p><b>Puzzles.</b>
In the <b>puzzle font</b>, the letters are at the correct rotations and
horizontal positions, and their vertical position represents their drop
sequence.  Drop the pieces in your head (or via <b>animate</b>) to figure
out what letter is encoded.
•
Even without puzzle font turned on, in the <b>animated</b> font, you can
try to guess what the letter is before all the pieces have arrived.
•
One final set of puzzles: In the unanimated unpuzzle <b>black-pieces</b> font,
try to figure out how one of each Tetris piece perfectly packs that shape.
(This is the task that BurrTools is very good at.)
</p><p><b>Related mathematics.</b>
(Perfect-information)
<a href="http://erikdemaine.org/papers/Tetris_IJCGA/">Tetris is NP-complete</a>,
meaning that it's computationally intractable to figure out whether you can
survive, or clear the board, given an initial board configuration and a
sequence of <i>n</i> pieces to come.
<a href="http://erikdemaine.org/papers/TotalTetris_JIP/">Similar results
hold</a> for <i>k</i>-tris played with
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyomino"><i>k</i>-ominoes</a>
instead of tetrominoes.  Most recently, we
<a href="http://erikdemaine.org/papers/ThinTetris_JIP/">analyzed the
complexity of Tetris with few rows or columns</a>; this font appears
in that paper.
</p><p><b>Acknowledgments.</b>  This font was inspired by a collaboration with
Alex Streif and Kate Jones of
<a href="http://www.gamepuzzles.com/">Kadon Enterprises</a>
during <a href="https://bridgesmathart.org/bridges-2017/">BRIDGES 2017</a>,
where we started designing a font using just 5 pieces:
the “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tetromino">free
tetrominoes</a>” where S is the same piece as Z and J is the same
piece as L.
Relatedly, Kate Jones designed <a href="https://erikdemaine.org/fonts/tetris/kadon_fonts.jpg">other polyomino
fonts included in some Kadon manuals</a>.
By contrast, this typeface aims closer to the rules of Tetris,
where reflection matters and the pieces must stack and be supported.
</p><p>Check out <a href="http://erikdemaine.org/fonts/">other mathematical and
puzzle fonts</a>. • Feedback or not working?
<a href="mailto:edemaine+fonts@mit.edu">Email Erik</a>. •
<a href="https://github.com/edemaine/font-tetris">Source code on GitHub</a>.</p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[EU Council has withdrawn the vote on Chat Control (638 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://stackdiary.com/eu-council-has-withdrawn-the-vote-on-chat-control/</link>
            <guid>40736771</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 09:45:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://stackdiary.com/eu-council-has-withdrawn-the-vote-on-chat-control/">https://stackdiary.com/eu-council-has-withdrawn-the-vote-on-chat-control/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40736771">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
				
<p>The EU Council and its participants have decided to withdraw the vote on the contentious Chat Control plan proposed by Belgium, the current EU President.</p>



<p>According to <a href="https://netzpolitik.org/2024/etappensieg-belgien-scheitert-mit-abstimmung-zur-chatkontrolle/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Netzpolitik</a> (<em>German</em>), “The EU Council did not make a decision on chat control today, as the agenda item was removed due to the lack of a majority, confirmed by Council and member state spokespersons”.</p>



<p>Belgium’s draft law, which was supposed to be adopted as the Council’s negotiating position, was instead postponed indefinitely. Although the Committee of Permanent Representatives meets weekly, Belgium cannot currently present a proposal that would gain a majority. In July, the Council Presidency will transfer from Belgium to Hungary, which has stated its intention to advance negotiations on chat control as part of its work program.</p>



<p>At the start of 2022, the European Commission proposed <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=COM%3A2022%3A209%3AFIN&amp;qid=1652451192472" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">monitoring all chat messages</a> and other forms of digital communication among citizens. This initiative includes client-side scanning for end-to-end encrypted services, meaning all messages would be checked irrespective of suspicion.</p>



<p>The plan targets the detection of both known and unknown abusive material and grooming activities. Experts have cautioned that such measures are prone to generating numerous false positives, particularly when identifying unknown content, leading to innocent citizens being misidentified as senders of abusive material.</p>



<p>European legislation is formed through a trialogue process involving negotiations between the European Commission, the European Parliament, and the Council of Ministers. Initially, the European Parliament rejected the European Commission’s proposal and <a href="https://oeil.secure.europarl.europa.eu/oeil/popups/ficheprocedure.do?reference=2022/0155(COD)&amp;l=en" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">introduced its own</a>, which, while still critical, excluded end-to-end encrypted services. However, Belgium’s new proposal <a href="https://www.euronews.com/next/2024/05/21/diplomats-mull-online-child-abuse-with-no-deal-in-sight" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">reintroduced client-side scanning</a> for these services, stipulating that users must consent to chat controls; otherwise, they would lose the ability to send photos, videos, and URLs. </p>



<p>This method, termed “upload moderation” by Belgium, has been criticized by opponents as merely a rebranding of the original concept.</p>



<h2>Signal and other apps threaten to leave the EU if the proposal is enacted as law</h2>



<p>Meredith Whittaker, president of the chat app Signal, <a href="https://x.com/mer__edith/status/1796508893822238881" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">has been vocal</a> against these plans. She argues that implementing such measures within end-to-end encrypted communications fundamentally undermines encryption and introduces significant vulnerabilities in the digital infrastructure. </p>



<p>Whittaker emphasizes that these vulnerabilities have far-reaching global implications, not just within Europe. She has repeatedly highlighted the issue, stating, “There is no way to implement such proposals without fundamentally undermining encryption and introducing dangerous vulnerabilities.”</p>



<p>On June 17, Whittaker published <a href="https://signal.org/blog/pdfs/upload-moderation.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">an official position</a> condemning the EU’s proposed “upload moderation” as a rebranding of client-side scanning that fundamentally undermines end-to-end encryption. </p>



<p>She emphasized that despite attempts to mask the dangers through marketing, these measures expose encrypted communications to mass surveillance, creating vulnerabilities exploitable by hackers and hostile nations. Whittaker urged a cessation of such rhetorical games, reiterating that any form of mandated mass scanning compromises encryption, thereby threatening global security and privacy at a critically unstable geopolitical moment.</p>



<p>The privacy messenger Threema published <a href="https://threema.ch/en/blog/posts/stop-chat-control" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">a blog post</a> saying the EU’s proposed Chat Control bill represents a dangerous mass surveillance initiative that would undermine data security, violate privacy rights, and negatively impact professionals and minors.</p>



<p>Patrick Breyer, <a href="https://stackdiary.com/patrick-breyer-and-pirate-party-lose-eu-parliament-seats/">the outgoing MEP</a> from the Pirate Party, raised concerns, noting that proponents of chat control have leveraged the period following the European elections, when attention is lower and the European Parliament is in transition, to advance their agenda. Breyer has called on European citizens <a href="https://www.patrick-breyer.de/en/council-to-greenlight-chat-control-take-action-now/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">to take action</a> and urge their politicians to oppose the measures.</p>



<p>Edward Snowden, the NSA whistleblower, <a href="https://x.com/Snowden/status/1803127597158760735" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">criticized the proposal</a>, stating, “EU apparatchiks are trying to legislate a terrible mass surveillance measure, despite universal public opposition (no sane person wants this), by inventing a new word for it – upload moderation – and hoping no one finds out what it is until it’s too late.”</p>



<h2>What happens next?</h2>



<p>With the EU Council withdrawing the vote on the Chat Control proposal today, the legislative process faces new uncertainty. The proposal will return to the drawing board, as the European Commission[<a href="#footnote">1</a>] and the European Parliament continue to deliberate on the best way forward.</p>



<p>The discussions will resume after the summer, once the new Parliament is seated and Hungary assumes the Council presidency from Belgium in July. Hungary has already committed to developing a comprehensive legislative framework to prevent and combat online child sexual abuse and revising the directive against the sexual exploitation of children.</p>



<p>The forthcoming negotiations are anticipated to be highly contentious, especially since the European Parliament has firmly opposed any measures that would circumvent end-to-end encryption. The Member States and the Parliament have until April 2026 to agree. This deadline is crucial, as <a href="https://www.europarl.europa.eu/news/en/press-room/20240408IPR20311/child-sexual-abuse-online-current-rules-extended-until-april-2026" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">an existing exemption</a> allowing social networks to self-moderate content will expire, potentially eliminating current safeguards against sharing sensitive images.</p>



<p>In the meantime, privacy advocates and digital rights organizations will likely continue to voice their concerns, urging EU citizens to remain vigilant and engaged in the debate over digital privacy and surveillance. The next steps will involve intense negotiations and potential revisions to address the complex issues at stake.</p>



<p id="footnote"><em>[footnote #1]: On June 20, at the European Data Protection Supervisor (EDPS) 20th anniversary summit, EU Commissioner for Justice Vera Jourová&nbsp;<a href="https://x.com/ellajakubowska1/status/1803709746429538685" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stated</a>&nbsp;that the European Commission’s proposal for the Child Sexual Abuse Regulation (CSAR) would break encryption. This marks the first time the European Commission has publicly acknowledged that the CSAR proposal would compromise encryption, a significant departure from the stance maintained over the past three years by Home Affairs Commissioner Ylva Johansson, who consistently claimed that the proposal would not affect encryption.</em></p>

			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Bun is much faster than Node.js 22 at decoding Base64 but both rely on same lib (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/lemire/status/1803598132334436415</link>
            <guid>40736685</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 09:31:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/lemire/status/1803598132334436415">https://twitter.com/lemire/status/1803598132334436415</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40736685">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Free software hijacked Philip Hazel's life (169 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lwn.net/SubscriberLink/978463/608c876c1153fd31/</link>
            <guid>40736577</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 09:14:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lwn.net/SubscriberLink/978463/608c876c1153fd31/">https://lwn.net/SubscriberLink/978463/608c876c1153fd31/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40736577">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<p>Philip Hazel was 51 when he began the <a href="https://www.exim.org/">Exim</a> message transfer agent (MTA)
project in 1995, which
led to the <a href="https://github.com/PCRE2Project/pcre2">Perl-Compatible Regular
Expressions</a> (PCRE) project in 1998. At 80,
he's maintained PCRE, and its successor PCRE2, for more than 27
years. For those doing the math, that's a year longer than LWN has
been in publication. Exim maintenance was handed off around the time
of his retirement in 2007. Now, he is ready to hand off PCRE2 as well,
if a successor can be found.</p>

<h4>Punch cards to flat screens</h4>

<p>Hazel's tenure as a free-software developer is exceptional, if not
record-breaking in its length. Linus Torvalds began
working on Linux in 1991 as a college student and is still leading its development 33 years
later with no signs of slowing. However, as Hazel <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/10TAOEgIL--CmzqOl0fkdP-cagjSLBM4J/view?usp=sharing">wrote</a>
in his technical memoir <em>From Punched Cards To Flat Screens</em>,
he began contributing to free software "<q>nearer the end than the
start</q>" of his career.</p>

<blockquote>
	<b>Like what you are reading?</b>
    		<a href="https://lwn.net/Promo/slink-trial-terse/claim">Try LWN for free</a> for 1 month,
    		no credit card required.
</blockquote>


<p>At the start of his career, Hazel was introduced to computers as an
undergraduate when the University of Cape Town (UCT) received its
first computer: an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ICT_1301">International Computers
and Tabulators (ICT) 1301</a>, with a dazzling capacity to read as
many as 600 punched cards per minute. He attended introductory
programming lectures, read the Manchester <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Autocode">Autocode</a> programming
manual from cover to cover, and began writing test programs encoded onto paper punch cards:</p>

<blockquote>
If you were lucky and your program worked, the output appeared on the
printer; more often that not (at least at the start) all you got was
an error message, which meant that you had to fix your program, return
to the back of the queue, and hope to get another run before the end
of the session. The more attempts it took to get a program to work,
the more useful scrap paper one accumulated.
</blockquote>

<p>He later moved on to the University of Cambridge as a PhD
student. Cambridge was blessed with four computers when Hazel arrived
in 1967: a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Titan_(1963_computer)">Titan</a>,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IBM_1130">IBM 1130</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IBM_System/360">IBM 360</a>, and
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PDP-7">PDP-7</a>. Because Hazel
knew the Manchester Autocode language, which is similar to Titan Autocode, he
was given an account on the Titan "<q>and that was the start of the
slippery slope down which I have been sliding ever since</q>".</p>

<p>That slope, as well-detailed in Hazel's memoir (and mercilessly
abbreviated here), ultimately led to his joining the Cambridge
Computing Service as a software developer in 1971. During his tenure
at Cambridge, and at home, Hazel had the opportunity to work with a
number of interesting systems including the PDP-11, Ultrix,
Sinclair&nbsp;ZX-81, and BBC&nbsp;Micro. In 1990 the Computing Service
decided to set up a cluster of Unix systems for the use of staff and
graduate students, and he began working with Sun boxes
running SunOS. This coincided with the transition from the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X.25">X.25</a> wide-area network
standard to the Internet Protocol (IP).</p>

<p>Hazel was responsible for the email service, and found it difficult
to configure <a href="https://www.proofpoint.com/us/products/email-protection/open-source-email-solution">Sendmail</a>
to choose between IP and X.25 to
deliver email. A colleague suggested that he try the free-software <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smail">Smail</a> MTA instead. Hazel
took him up on the suggestion and added two features to Smail to
manage the DNS lookups and decide whether to send mail via SMTP or
X.25. While managing Smail for Cambridge, he submitted additional
features to cope with messages that had bad senders:</p>

<blockquote>
If such a message could not be delivered, the bad sender meant that an error report could
also not be delivered, and the postmaster (me) had to intervene to sort things
out. By rejecting messages whose sender address could not be verified, I pushed
the onus of dealing with this problem out to the sending MTA. This kind of
checking is now standard MTA practice (along with many other checks for
spam and viruses).
</blockquote>

<p>This was a small start that led Hazel to thinking about more
checking and verification that would be needed for MTAs. He
considered, but decided against, trying to modify Smail. It was
written in pre-standard C and carried "<q>a lot of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UUCP">UUCP</a> baggage</q>". Hazel
wanted to write an MTA for modern (at the time) operating systems with
standard C compilers and runtimes, and permanent connections to a
TCP/IP network. He began working on the Experimental Internet Mailer
(Exim) in March 1995. By November it was "<q>just about able to send
and receive emails</q>".</p>

<h4>Exim</h4>

<p>Hazel had informed a colleague, Piete Brooks, that he was working
on Exim. Brooks wanted to try it out, but Hazel demurred because he
had not written any documentation. (This may be the first known case
of a programmer refusing to distribute undocumented code...) Brooks
response was "<q>I don't want the documentation, I want the
code.</q>" Even so, Hazel insisted on writing a first cut of the Exim
manual before packaging up the code and sending it off to meet its fate.</p>

<p>Brooks put the code into service right away, and started
telling others about it. Hazel put Exim releases on a public FTP site,
and gave a talk on Exim at a "Campus Mail Day" in Aberdeen, which led
to more usage. A request from Richard Stallman persuaded him to switch
from a homegrown license for Exim to the GPL. It began being ported to
other operating systems, and eventually found its way to Linux in 1997
or 1998, "<q>which by then had become an operating system that could be
used in production environments</q>". Over time, Exim would become
(and still is) a popular MTA used all over the planet. Its adoption
far exceeded Hazel's expectations:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>I never expected commercial sites to get involved, nor for it to
become the default MTA in any operating systems. In short, I did not
foresee that it would grow into the fully-fledged open source
development project that it has.</p>
</blockquote>

<h4>PCRE</h4>

<p>Regular expressions play a rather large part in managing mail, and
Hazel wanted to have more flexible regular expressions for Exim than were
present in Smail. He chose a regular-expression library
written by Henry Spencer for early versions of Exim, but found it
limiting compared to Perl's extended pattern-matching features. He
thought about lifting Perl's implementation, but it was too integrated
to be easily adapted to Exim. "<q>In the end, I solved the problem the
way programmers generally solve their problems: by writing something
myself.</q>" That, of course, became PCRE.</p>

<p>Hazel bundled PCRE with Exim and also released it as a standalone
library. Like Exim, it filled a need that he did not even realize
existed. PCRE was adopted by Apache HTTPD, and Hazel was
"<q>particularly gratified</q>" to find that it had been included with
the <a href="https://www.postfix.org/">Postfix</a> MTA. After a while, PCRE looked beyond Perl
to include features such as recursion inside a regular expression, and
named subpatterns (borrowed from Python), as well as other ideas taken
from other regular-expression implementations.</p>

<p>In 2014, Hazel decided that PCRE's API was "<q>not capable of much
further extension</q>" and began working on a new, incompatible,
version of the code. The first PCRE2 release (starting at version
10.00 to avoid confusion with then-current PCRE 8.x releases) was <a href="https://lists.exim.org/lurker/message/20150105.162835.0666407a.en.html">announced</a>
in January 2015. Hazel continued supporting PCRE until its <a href="https://lists.exim.org/lurker/message/20210615.162400.c16ff8a3.en.html">final release</a> in 2021. PCRE2 <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/pcre2-dev/c/OUI1FYTcm_E">moved to GitHub</a> in 2022. The most recent release of PCRE2, <a href="https://github.com/PCRE2Project/pcre2/releases/tag/pcre2-10.44">10.44</a>,
came out on June 7, 2024.</p>

<p>Hazel wrote that PCRE may now be even
more important than Exim was "<q>because of its widespread use in many
different applications and operating systems</q>". Indeed, just
looking to see the installed software that depends on the PCRE2
library on Fedora&nbsp;40 turns up use by Git, Grep, MariaDB, nmap,
SELinux's command-line tools, Sway, Wget&nbsp;2, and quite a few others.</p>

<p>In his memoir, Hazel had written that it felt right to pass
maintenance of Exim on to others after so long. "<q>More than a decade on one
project is long enough.</q>" In his 2017 update to the memoir, he
noted that the sentence had come back to bite him: He was still
working on PCRE 19 years after he started to write it. Little did he
suspect he would still be maintaining it in 2024. He would like to <a href="https://github.com/PCRE2Project/pcre2/issues/426">hand it
off</a> while he can help with the transition.</p>

<h4>Passing the torch</h4>

<p>I emailed Hazel with a few questions about his thoughts on
long-term free-software maintenance, changes to the industry, and what
he might do once PCRE was handed off. Hazel wrote that he does not
have any post-PCRE plans. All of <a href="http://quercite.dx.am/">his projects</a>, with the exception of the <a href="https://github.com/PhilipHazel/b2pf">base to presentation
form</a> (B2PF) library for converting Unicode characters for
printing, were started while he was still working. "Since I retired I
haven't felt a lack of anything enough to spur me into writing something
new". He added that he would continue to maintain his non-PCRE2
projects "if necessary" and would help with PCRE2 if needed.</p>

<p>When asked how new generations of tools, and developers, had
changed his work habits, Hazel replied that he has changed
little. "I am sufficiently old that I am well stuck in my ways, and
haven't changed how I do things since the 90s" with the exception
of moving development to GitHub. He admitted that he was not good at
anticipating or keeping up with trends in development. For example, he
said he was not aware of Unicode when he began PCRE development, so it
was written to support ASCII and with a limit of 64K for compiled
patterns. Others had to persuade him to extend PCRE with Unicode
support, and the option for larger patterns. Contributors,
he said, have not changed. The world has, though:</p>

<blockquote>
When I was born, there were no digital computers, though their
predecessors, for example the Colossus at Bletchley Park, were around. The
world has gone from nothing to where we are now in just one lifetime.
Incredible! What particularly amazes me more than the CPU power is the
amount of storage that I carry in my pocket.
</blockquote>

<p>Hazel did offer some advice for those starting new software
projects, though he noted he was not the first to make this point:</p>

<blockquote>
It's worth remembering that the effort needed to maintain a piece of
successful software over its lifetime far outweighs the effort of
writing it in the first place. In the case of PCRE there have been
several major re-designs and re-writes of the internals as
well as continual extensions to the user-visible features.
</blockquote>

<p>He also suggested that developers think about how software would be
tested as it is designed: "Effort put into building test harnesses is
never wasted."</p>

<p>I asked Hazel, given the recent <a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/967866/">XZ backdoor</a> attempt, how
he intended to vet any prospective PCRE2 maintainers. He replied that it
was a good question "to which I have no answer. I will have to see
who (if anyone) makes an offer". To date, he said he had received
"no communications whatsoever" about taking over the
project. Perhaps, once the word gets out more widely, a qualified
maintainer will step forward to take PCRE2 into the future.</p><br clear="all">
               <br clear="all">
               <hr><p>
           (<a href="https://lwn.net/Login/?target=/Articles/978463/">Log in</a> to post comments)
           </p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Oldest white wine in the world found in a first-century tomb in Spain (148 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jasrep.2024.104636</link>
            <guid>40735743</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 06:58:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jasrep.2024.104636">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jasrep.2024.104636</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40735743">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Protecting Children's Safety Requires End-to-End Encryption (107 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://simplex.chat/blog/20240601-protecting-children-safety-requires-e2e-encryption.html</link>
            <guid>40735627</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 06:37:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://simplex.chat/blog/20240601-protecting-children-safety-requires-e2e-encryption.html">https://simplex.chat/blog/20240601-protecting-children-safety-requires-e2e-encryption.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40735627">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="article">
<p>As lawmakers grapple with the serious issue of child exploitation online, some proposed solutions would fuel the very problem they aim to solve. Despite expert warnings, the Belgian Presidency persists in pushing for the implementation of client-side scanning on encrypted messaging services, rebranding the effort as "upload moderation". Their <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=COM%3A2022%3A209%3AFIN&amp;qid=1652451192472">latest proposal</a> mandates that providers of private communication services obtain user consent for AI-based scanning of their private chats. If users do not consent, they will be prohibited from sharing images, videos, and URLs.</p>
<p>Privacy critics have long pushed for measures like centralized scanning of private photos and messaging data, arguing it could detect illicit content. However, invasive monitoring of private communications would create detrimental risks that far outweigh any perceived benefits.</p>
<h2 id="why-were-taking-action" tabindex="-1">Why we’re taking action</h2>
<p>SimpleX Chat signed a <a href="https://www.globalencryption.org/2024/05/joint-statement-on-the-dangers-of-the-may-2024-council-of-the-eu-compromise-proposal-on-eu-csam/">joint statement</a> about the dangers of the EU compromise proposal on EU CSAM because maintaining end-to-end encryption is crucial for protecting privacy and security for everyone, including and especially children.</p>
<p>We urge the Ministers in the Council of the EU to stand firm against any scanning proposals that undermine end-to-end encryption, which would enable mass surveillance and misuse by bad actors, whether framed as client-side scanning, upload moderation, or any other terminology. Compromising this basic principle opens the door to devastating privacy violations. We also urge any organizations or individuals reading this to write to their representatives and voice their concerns. European Digital Rights has <a href="https://edri.org/our-work/be-scanned-or-get-banned/">outlined these issues</a> in greater detail for anyone seeking more information.</p>
<h2 id="why-compromising-privacy-endangers-children" tabindex="-1">Why compromising privacy endangers children</h2>
<p>The core issue is that compromising encryption and privacy makes innocent people vulnerable to malicious hackers and criminals seeking to exploit users data. Centralized scanning systems become a tempting target, potentially exposing millions of private family photos when breached. This would easily open up avenues for blackmail, abuse, and victimization of children. A case in point is the recent <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/01/17/unredacted-meta-documents-reveal-historical-reluctance-to-protect-children-new-mexico-lawsuit/">criminal charges</a> against Meta in New Mexico, which highlights how the tech giant's algorithms enabled child exploitation by encouraging connections between minors and sexual predators. Privacy-eroding initiatives like client-side scanning would play into the hands of malicious actors by making more sensitive information accessible and weaponized in the same way that it has been on Meta platforms.</p>
<h2 id="what-should-be-done" tabindex="-1">What should be done</h2>
<p>Rather than undermining privacy, to achieve child safety online users should be empowered with high standards for encryption and data control. For example, adopting a model where children (and users in general) cannot be discovered or approached on networks unless they or their parents permit it, similar to the SimpleX network privacy model. Intelligent multi-device synchronization could enable this oversight without compromising end-to-end encryption overall. It’s always possible to protect children without opening everyone, especially children themselves, to greater vulnerabilities due to such proposals.</p>
<p>However, some recent legislative efforts have bizarrely moved in the opposite direction by seeking to limit parental access. The chilling truth is that the least private platforms have been major enablers of child exploitation. Eroding privacy protections on other services will only aid criminals further, not protect children. Preserving strong encryption and user privacy must be the foundation for any credible effort to combat online child exploitation. Initiatives trading privacy for supposed safety are not just technically flawed, but would achieve the exact opposite of their stated intent. We must avoid being gaslighted by narratives that defy logic, and instead provide users with the highest possible standards for privacy protections as a core principle.</p>
<p>Protecting end-to-end encryption without carving out backdoors or vulnerabilities should be non-negotiable for children's and everyone’s safety. It is critical to redirect the discourse to focus on taking genuine privacy further by protecting against <a href="https://simplex.chat/blog/20240416-dangers-of-metadata-in-messengers.html">metadata hoarding</a> and other means by which people’s data can be abused or subjected to surveillance.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OSRD: Open-Source Railway Designer (147 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://osrd.fr/en/</link>
            <guid>40733705</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 00:21:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://osrd.fr/en/">https://osrd.fr/en/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40733705">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><main role="main"><div id="td-cover-block-0"><p><img src="https://osrd.fr/logos/logo_white.svg"></p><h2>Open Source Railway Designer</h2></div><div><p>An open source web application for railway infrastructure design, capacity analysis, timetabling and more!</p></div><div><div><h4>Railway design</h4><p>Design railway infrastructure and timetables</p></div><div><h4>Capacity Analysis</h4><p>Detect conflicts and visualize capacity</p></div><div><h4>Short-term planning</h4><p>Automatically add new trains to an existing timetable</p></div></div><div><div><h4>Open source development</h4><p>Anyone can use, develop and distribute OSRD</p><p><a href="https://osrd.fr/en/about/opensource/">Read more …</a></p></div><div><h4>Open governance</h4><p>OSRD is publicly designed, decisions are taken collectively</p><p><a href="https://osrd.fr/en/about/governance/">Read more …</a></p></div><div><h4>Designed for interoperability</h4><p>Make custom infrastructure formats and signaling systems work together</p></div></div><section><video controls="">
<source src="https://osrd.fr/en/video.en.webm" type="video/webm"></video></section><section><h2>Sponsors</h2><p><img src="https://osrd.fr/sponsors/france-dot.svg" width="180px" height="180px" alt="Ministère chargé des Transports">
<img src="https://osrd.fr/sponsors/european-union.svg" width="180px" height="180px" alt="European Union">
<img src="https://osrd.fr/sponsors/sncf-reseau.svg" width="180px" height="180px" alt="SNCF Réseau"></p></section></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Nobody knows what's going on (203 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.raptitude.com/2024/06/nobody-knows-whats-going-on/</link>
            <guid>40733615</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 00:06:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.raptitude.com/2024/06/nobody-knows-whats-going-on/">https://www.raptitude.com/2024/06/nobody-knows-whats-going-on/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40733615">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p><img src="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/artem-beliaikin-v6kii3H5CcU-unsplash.jpg" width="600" height="400" alt="Post image for Nobody Knows What’s Going On"></p><p>A major online publication once reported in a profile on me that I had retired at 33. A few old friends and acquaintances reached out to congratulate me on my financial independence.</p>



<p>I think it was an honest mistake on the part of the reporter. I told her I had quit my job to write full time, and I guess she thought that meant I must have millions of dollars.</p>



<p>To be clear, I was not then, and am not now financially independent. The 100 or so people that actually know me could discern that just by seeing my kitchen. Yet perhaps 20,000 people read somewhere that I am. That means potentially 200 times more people are wrong than right on this question, because of an inference made by a reporter.</p>



<p>This scenario, in which there’s much more wrongness going around than rightness, is probably the norm. People make bad inferences like that all day long. These wrong ideas replicate themselves whenever the person tells someone else what they know, which the internet makes easier than ever.</p>



<p>Consider the possibility that <em>most</em> of the information being passed around, on whatever topic, is bad information, even where there’s no intentional deception. As George Orwell said, “The most fundamental mistake of man is that he thinks he knows what’s going on. Nobody knows what’s going on.”</p>



<p>Technology may have made this state of affairs inevitable. Today, the vast majority of a person’s worldview is assembled from second-hand sources, not from their own experience. Second-hand knowledge, from “reliable” sources or not, usually functions as hearsay – if it <em>seems</em> true, it is immediately incorporated into one’s worldview, usually without any attempt to substantiate it. Most of what you “know” is just something you heard somewhere.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/titanic-onion.jpg"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="300" height="297" src="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/titanic-onion-300x297.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/titanic-onion-300x297.jpg 300w, https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/titanic-onion-150x150.jpg 150w, https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/titanic-onion-194x192.jpg 194w, https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/titanic-onion.jpg 400w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"></a><figcaption><em>Standard editorial approach</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>When people go on to share what they “know”, there’s usually no penalty for being wrong, but there are rewards for convincing people you’re right: attention, money, adoration, public rhetorical victories over others, and many other things humans enjoy.</p>



<h3>The Two Kinds of Knowing</h3>



<p>First-hand knowledge is a whole different thing from the second-hand kind. When you experience an event with your senses, you’re not just accepting a verbal claim, such as “There’s fighting in the streets of Kabul” — the truth is actually happening to you. The experienced sailor <em>knows</em> that looming cloud formation means trouble. The soldier knows the attack on his unit’s position was repelled. The dog owner knows exactly how long she can leave Rocco alone at home before he relieves himself on the floor. The friend sitting on my fifteen-year-old couch knows I’m not independently wealthy. Experience imprints reality right into your neurons; it doesn’t just add another thought to the abstract space in your brain where you keep your axioms and factoids.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/jamie-street-s9Tf1eBDFqw-unsplash600.jpg"><img decoding="async" width="300" height="225" src="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/jamie-street-s9Tf1eBDFqw-unsplash600-300x225.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/jamie-street-s9Tf1eBDFqw-unsplash600-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/jamie-street-s9Tf1eBDFqw-unsplash600-256x192.jpg 256w, https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/jamie-street-s9Tf1eBDFqw-unsplash600.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"></a><figcaption><em>Good for about six hours</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Only a tiny percentage of what a given person “knows” is in this first-hand, embodied form. The rest is made of impressions gathered from anecdotes, newspapers, books, schoolteachers, blogs, and things our older siblings told us when we were little.</p>



<p>If you ever read an article on a subject with which you have a lot of first-hand experience, you’ll notice that they <em>always</em> get major things wrong – basic facts, dates, names of people and organizations, the stated intentions of involved parties, the reasons a thing is happening – things even a novice in the space would know better about.</p>



<p>It makes perfect sense, if you think about it, that reporting is so reliably unreliable. Why do we expect reporters to learn about a suddenly newsworthy situation, gather information about it under deadline, then confidently explain the subject to the rest of the nation after having known about it for all of a week? People form their entire worldviews out of this stuff.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/owlsnot-as-they-seem500.jpg"><img decoding="async" width="300" height="278" src="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/owlsnot-as-they-seem500-300x278.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/owlsnot-as-they-seem500-300x278.jpg 300w, https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/owlsnot-as-they-seem500-207x192.jpg 207w, https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/owlsnot-as-they-seem500.jpg 500w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"></a><figcaption><em>Me forming my worldview</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>What doesn’t make sense is that we immediately become credulous again as soon as the subject matter changes back to a topic on which we <em>don’t </em>have first-hand experience. You know they don’t know what they hell they’re talking about on Subject A, but hey what’s this about Subject B? In 2002, author Michael Crichton named this the “Gell-Mann Amnesia effect”:</p>



<blockquote>
<p>Briefly stated, the Gell-Mann Amnesia effect is as follows. You open the newspaper to an article on some subject you know well. In [Murray Gell-Mann’s] case, physics. In mine, show business. You read the article and see the journalist has absolutely no understanding of either the facts or the issues. Often, the article is so wrong it actually presents the story backward—reversing cause and effect. I call these the “wet streets cause rain” stories. Paper’s full of them.</p>



<p>In any case, you read with exasperation or amusement the multiple errors in a story, and then turn the page to national or international affairs, and read as if the rest of the newspaper was somehow more accurate about Palestine than the baloney you just read. You turn the page, and forget what you know.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Crichton clarifies in the <a href="https://www.docdroid.net/4wgVecr/why-speculate-michael-crichton-pdf#page=2">full speech</a> that by “media” he’s not only talking about newspapers, but books, television, and internet too, and of course anybody’s recounting of what these sources say. Well, that accounts for just about 100% of our second-hand knowledge.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/gaurav-bagdi-K-fbBy5HNSg-unsplash600cropped.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="282" height="300" src="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/gaurav-bagdi-K-fbBy5HNSg-unsplash600cropped-282x300.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/gaurav-bagdi-K-fbBy5HNSg-unsplash600cropped-282x300.jpg 282w, https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/gaurav-bagdi-K-fbBy5HNSg-unsplash600cropped-181x192.jpg 181w, https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/gaurav-bagdi-K-fbBy5HNSg-unsplash600cropped.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 282px) 100vw, 282px"></a><figcaption>“<em>The situation is developing”</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>People do know things though. We have airplanes and phones and spaceships. Clearly somebody knows something. Human beings <em>can</em> be reliable sources of knowledge, but only about small slivers of the whole of what’s going on. They know things because they deal with their sliver every day, and they’re personally invested in how well they know their sliver, which gives them constant feedback on the quality of their beliefs.</p>



<p>Plumbing knowledge, for example, is constantly tested by whether the place floods after you’ve advanced your theory about what pipe connects to what. You need to get it right because it costs you something when you get it wrong.</p>



<p>The mechanic has seen a thousand check-engine lights and knows how each of them was resolved. The English professor has seen a thousand essays and can tell you what’s wrong with yours. The night club bouncer has dealt with a thousand drunk patrons and knows which guests will be trouble even before they do.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/rivage-4CNNH2KEjhc-unsplash600.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="225" src="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/rivage-4CNNH2KEjhc-unsplash600-300x225.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/rivage-4CNNH2KEjhc-unsplash600-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/rivage-4CNNH2KEjhc-unsplash600-256x192.jpg 256w, https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/rivage-4CNNH2KEjhc-unsplash600.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"></a><figcaption><em>Somebody’s sliver, thankfully</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>There are ways to carefully gather, scrutinize, and compare high-quality second-hand sources, and maybe learn something reliable, but this is extremely difficult for the groupish, emotional creature we are. It is <a href="https://www.raptitude.com/2023/05/how-to-think-about-politics-without-going-insane/">viscerally unpleasant</a> (not to mention time-consuming) to honestly question beliefs you feel positively towards, or honestly entertain ones you don’t, and ultimately you’re just determining what “feels right” anyway.</p>



<p>Aside from our own respective slivers of reliable knowledge, we mostly carry a lot of untested beliefs — teetering piles of them, accumulated over years, from random people assuring us “this is how it is.” Most of these beliefs are bunk, but we don’t know which ones. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<h3>Beliefs are Mostly Mind-Candy</h3>



<p>Humans love beliefs, not because they’re reliable pointers to what’s true, but because they often feel good in some way, or have social rewards. Expressing and sharing beliefs can get us attention and social status, make us feel competent, sell our goods and services, and motivate people to do things for us, and they can just feel satisfying to say aloud. A convincing belief is simply one that feels good to the ears, or the mind.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/ryan-brooklyn-e5Ja8Z_WEvA-unsplash600.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/ryan-brooklyn-e5Ja8Z_WEvA-unsplash600-300x200.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/ryan-brooklyn-e5Ja8Z_WEvA-unsplash600-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/ryan-brooklyn-e5Ja8Z_WEvA-unsplash600-288x192.jpg 288w, https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/ryan-brooklyn-e5Ja8Z_WEvA-unsplash600.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"></a><figcaption><em>Beliefs of mine, awaiting testing</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Theory feels good. Pithiness and analogy feel good. A tight sentence feels good. Neat and snappy stories about what’s “true” are like candy to the sense-craving part of the human brain.</p>



<p>Notice how many smart people believe things like, “You can’t reason yourself out of a belief you didn’t reason yourself into.” This is a belief nobody would arrive at through reason. It doesn’t stand up to even a minute’s logical scrutiny. You certainly didn’t reason yourself into a belief that North-Pole-dwelling elves made your childhood toys, but you probably reasoned yourself out of it. Both beliefs are just mind-candy, only for different audiences.</p>



<p>In short, human beings are bad at gathering information, inferring the right things from it, and responsibly passing it on to others. It is incredible what we’ve achieved in spite of this — almost entirely by carefully combining and testing our respective reliable slivers — but as a species we remain supremely untalented at knowing what’s true outside the range of our senses.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/Kids_in_the_Hall_Brain_Candy_poster.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="257" height="388" src="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/Kids_in_the_Hall_Brain_Candy_poster.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/Kids_in_the_Hall_Brain_Candy_poster.jpg 257w, https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/Kids_in_the_Hall_Brain_Candy_poster-199x300.jpg 199w, https://www.raptitude.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/Kids_in_the_Hall_Brain_Candy_poster-127x192.jpg 127w" sizes="(max-width: 257px) 100vw, 257px"></a><figcaption><em>A relevant documentary (1996)</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Much of the problem is that we want so badly to be believed, to be seen as someone who knows stuff. In the rest of Crichton’s speech, he explains why he named the Gell-Mann Amnesia effect after Murray Gell-Mann: because he’s famous, and he’s a physicist. People believe things named after physicists because we know they’re smart. And Crichton is a medical doctor, so you should listen to the guy.</p>



<p>Also, none of you will be able to confirm this, but George Orwell did not say the line in the intro of this article. I just said that he did so you would take my own assertions more seriously. And it’s too late — you’ve already tasted the candy. I mean, Orwell could have said something like that. He might as well have said it. He probably did, basically! I will sleep soundly anyway. There are few penalties for bullshit, and many rewards. Because nobody knows what’s going on.</p>



<p>***</p>



<p><em>Images by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@belart84">Artem Beliaikin</a>, <a href="https://www.theonion.com/">The Onion</a>, <a href="https://unsplash.com/@jamie452">Jamie Street</a>, <a href="https://unsplash.com/@sigmund">Rivage</a>, <a href="https://unsplash.com/@rbrooklyn">Ryan Brooklyn</a>, <a href="https://unsplash.com/@dfyngrvty">Gaurav Bagdi</a></em></p>

            

        				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hypermedia Systems (206 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://hypermedia.systems/</link>
            <guid>40733160</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 22:39:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://hypermedia.systems/">https://hypermedia.systems/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40733160">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <ul id="blurb" role="list" data-cols="1 3" data-cols@s="1" data-rows="1 3">
        <li>The revolutionary ideas that empowered the Web</li>
        <li>A simpler approach to building applications on the Web and beyond with <a href="https://htmx.org/">htmx</a> and <a href="https://hyperview.org/">Hyperview</a></li>
        <li>Enhancing web applications without using SPA frameworks</li>
        <li></li>
        </ul>

        <ul data-cols="4 5" data-cols@s="1" role="list">
        <li><strong><a href="https://hypermedia.systems/book/contents">
            <span>
                Read online
                <small>(Free, forever)</small>
            </span>
        </a></strong>
        </li>
        <li><strong><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0C9S88QV6/ref=sr_1_1">
            <span>
                Hard copy
                <small>(Buy on Amazon)</small>
            </span>
        </a></strong>
        </li>
        <li><strong><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Hypermedia-Systems-Carson-Gross-ebook/dp/B0CC315VJK/ref=tmm_kin_swatch_0">
            <span>
                Ebook
                <small>(Buy on Amazon)</small>
            </span>
        </a></strong>
        </li>
        </ul>

        <p data-cols="4 5" data-cols@s="1">
            For web developers frustrated with the complexity of modern practice,<span></span>
            those looking to brush up on web fundamentals,<span></span>
            web development shops looking to bring their apps to mobile,<span></span>
            and any workaday programmer looking for an introduction to hypermedia and REST.
        </p>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Unique3D: Image-to-3D Generation from a Single Image (125 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/AiuniAI/Unique3D</link>
            <guid>40732490</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 21:20:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/AiuniAI/Unique3D">https://github.com/AiuniAI/Unique3D</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40732490">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><strong><a href="https://github.com/AiuniAI/Unique3D/blob/main/README_zh.md">中文版本</a></strong></p>
<p dir="auto"><strong><a href="https://github.com/AiuniAI/Unique3D/blob/main/README_jp.md">日本語版</a></strong></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Unique3D</h2><a id="user-content-unique3d" aria-label="Permalink: Unique3D" href="#unique3d"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Official implementation of Unique3D: High-Quality and Efficient 3D Mesh Generation from a Single Image.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=VTU0gysAAAAJ&amp;hl=zh-CN&amp;oi=ao" rel="nofollow">Kailu Wu</a>, <a href="https://liuff19.github.io/" rel="nofollow">Fangfu Liu</a>, Zhihan Cai, Runjie Yan, Hanyang Wang, Yating Hu, <a href="https://duanyueqi.github.io/" rel="nofollow">Yueqi Duan</a>, <a href="https://group.iiis.tsinghua.edu.cn/~maks/" rel="nofollow">Kaisheng Ma</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20343" rel="nofollow">Paper</a> | <a href="https://wukailu.github.io/Unique3D/" rel="nofollow">Project page</a> | <a href="https://huggingface.co/spaces/Wuvin/Unique3D" rel="nofollow">Huggingface Demo</a> | <a href="https://u45213-bcf9-ef67553e.westx.seetacloud.com:8443/" rel="nofollow">Gradio Demo</a> | <a href="https://www.aiuni.ai/" rel="nofollow">Online Demo</a></h2><a id="user-content-paper--project-page--huggingface-demo--gradio-demo--online-demo" aria-label="Permalink: Paper | Project page | Huggingface Demo | Gradio Demo | Online Demo" href="#paper--project-page--huggingface-demo--gradio-demo--online-demo"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Demo inference speed: Gradio Demo &gt; Huggingface Demo &gt; Huggingface Demo2 &gt; Online Demo</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><strong>If the Gradio Demo unfortunately hangs or is very crowded, you can use the Online Demo <a href="https://www.aiuni.ai/" rel="nofollow">aiuni.ai</a>, which is free to try (get the registration invitation code Join Discord: <a href="https://discord.gg/aiuni" rel="nofollow">https://discord.gg/aiuni</a>). However, the Online Demo is slightly different from the Gradio Demo, in that the inference speed is slower, and the generation results is less stable, but the quality of the material is better.</strong></p>
<p dir="auto">
    <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/AiuniAI/Unique3D/blob/main/assets/teaser_safe.jpg"><img src="https://github.com/AiuniAI/Unique3D/raw/main/assets/teaser_safe.jpg"></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto">High-fidelity and diverse textured meshes generated by Unique3D from single-view wild images in 30 seconds.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">More features</h2><a id="user-content-more-features" aria-label="Permalink: More features" href="#more-features"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The repo is still being under construction, thanks for your patience.</p>
<ul>
<li> Upload weights.</li>
<li> Local gradio demo.</li>
<li> Detailed tutorial.</li>
<li> Huggingface demo.</li>
<li> Detailed local demo.</li>
<li> Comfyui support.</li>
<li> Windows support.</li>
<li> Docker support.</li>
<li> More stable reconstruction with normal.</li>
<li> Training code release.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Preparation for inference</h2><a id="user-content-preparation-for-inference" aria-label="Permalink: Preparation for inference" href="#preparation-for-inference"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Linux System Setup.</h3><a id="user-content-linux-system-setup" aria-label="Permalink: Linux System Setup." href="#linux-system-setup"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Adapted for Ubuntu 22.04.4 LTS and CUDA 12.1.</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="conda create -n unique3d python=3.11
conda activate unique3d

pip install ninja
pip install diffusers==0.27.2

pip install mmcv-full -f https://download.openmmlab.com/mmcv/dist/cu121/torch2.3.1/index.html

pip install -r requirements.txt"><pre lang="angular2html"><code>conda create -n unique3d python=3.11
conda activate unique3d

pip install ninja
pip install diffusers==0.27.2

pip install mmcv-full -f https://download.openmmlab.com/mmcv/dist/cu121/torch2.3.1/index.html

pip install -r requirements.txt
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/oak-barry">oak-barry</a> provide another setup script for torch210+cu121 at <a href="https://github.com/oak-barry/Unique3D">here</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Windows Setup.</h3><a id="user-content-windows-setup" aria-label="Permalink: Windows Setup." href="#windows-setup"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Thank you very much <code>jtydhr88</code> for the windows installation method! See <a href="https://github.com/AiuniAI/Unique3D/issues/15" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/AiuniAI/Unique3D/issues/15/hovercard">issues/15</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">According to <a href="https://github.com/AiuniAI/Unique3D/issues/15" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/AiuniAI/Unique3D/issues/15/hovercard">issues/15</a>, implemented a bat script to run the commands, so you can:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Might still require Visual Studio Build Tools, you can find it from <a href="https://visualstudio.microsoft.com/downloads/?q=build+tools" rel="nofollow">Visual Studio Build Tools</a>.</li>
<li>Create conda env and activate it
<ol dir="auto">
<li><code>conda create -n unique3d-py311 python=3.11</code></li>
<li><code>conda activate unique3d-py311</code></li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>download <a href="https://huggingface.co/madbuda/triton-windows-builds/resolve/main/triton-2.1.0-cp311-cp311-win_amd64.whl" rel="nofollow">triton whl</a> for py311, and put it into this project.</li>
<li>run <strong>install_windows_win_py311_cu121.bat</strong></li>
<li>answer y while asking you uninstall onnxruntime and onnxruntime-gpu</li>
<li>create the output folder <strong>tmp\gradio</strong> under the driver root, such as F:\tmp\gradio for me.</li>
<li>python app/gradio_local.py --port 7860</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto">More details prefer to <a href="https://github.com/AiuniAI/Unique3D/issues/15" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/AiuniAI/Unique3D/issues/15/hovercard">issues/15</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Interactive inference: run your local gradio demo.</h3><a id="user-content-interactive-inference-run-your-local-gradio-demo" aria-label="Permalink: Interactive inference: run your local gradio demo." href="#interactive-inference-run-your-local-gradio-demo"></a></p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Download the weights from <a href="https://huggingface.co/spaces/Wuvin/Unique3D/tree/main/ckpt" rel="nofollow">huggingface spaces</a> or <a href="https://cloud.tsinghua.edu.cn/d/319762ec478d46c8bdf7/" rel="nofollow">Tsinghua Cloud Drive</a>, and extract it to <code>ckpt/*</code>.</li>
</ol>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="Unique3D
    ├──ckpt
        ├── controlnet-tile/
        ├── image2normal/
        ├── img2mvimg/
        ├── realesrgan-x4.onnx
        └── v1-inference.yaml"><pre><code>Unique3D
    ├──ckpt
        ├── controlnet-tile/
        ├── image2normal/
        ├── img2mvimg/
        ├── realesrgan-x4.onnx
        └── v1-inference.yaml
</code></pre></div>
<ol start="2" dir="auto">
<li>Run the interactive inference locally.</li>
</ol>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="python app/gradio_local.py --port 7860"><pre>python app/gradio_local.py --port 7860</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">ComfyUI Support</h2><a id="user-content-comfyui-support" aria-label="Permalink: ComfyUI Support" href="#comfyui-support"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Thanks for the <a href="https://github.com/jtydhr88/ComfyUI-Unique3D">ComfyUI-Unique3D</a> implementation from <a href="https://github.com/jtydhr88">jtydhr88</a>!</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Tips to get better results</h2><a id="user-content-tips-to-get-better-results" aria-label="Permalink: Tips to get better results" href="#tips-to-get-better-results"></a></p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Unique3D is sensitive to the facing direction of input images. Due to the distribution of the training data, orthographic front-facing images with a rest pose always lead to good reconstructions.</li>
<li>Images with occlusions will cause worse reconstructions, since four views cannot cover the complete object. Images with fewer occlusions lead to better results.</li>
<li>Pass an image with as high a resolution as possible to the input when resolution is a factor.</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Acknowledgement</h2><a id="user-content-acknowledgement" aria-label="Permalink: Acknowledgement" href="#acknowledgement"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">We have intensively borrowed code from the following repositories. Many thanks to the authors for sharing their code.</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/CompVis/stable-diffusion">Stable Diffusion</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/xxlong0/Wonder3D">Wonder3d</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/SUDO-AI-3D/zero123plus">Zero123Plus</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Profactor/continuous-remeshing">Continues Remeshing</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/YertleTurtleGit/depth-from-normals">Depth from Normals</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Collaborations</h2><a id="user-content-collaborations" aria-label="Permalink: Collaborations" href="#collaborations"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Our mission is to create a 4D generative model with 3D concepts. This is just our first step, and the road ahead is still long, but we are confident. We warmly invite you to join the discussion and explore potential collaborations in any capacity. <span><strong>If you're interested in connecting or partnering with us, please don't hesitate to reach out via email (<a href="mailto:wkl22@mails.tsinghua.edu.cn">wkl22@mails.tsinghua.edu.cn</a>)</strong></span>.</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Follow us on twitter for the latest updates: <a href="https://x.com/aiuni_ai" rel="nofollow">https://x.com/aiuni_ai</a></li>
<li>Join AIGC 3D/4D generation community on discord: <a href="https://discord.gg/aiuni" rel="nofollow">https://discord.gg/aiuni</a></li>
<li>Research collaboration, please contact: <a href="mailto:ai@aiuni.ai">ai@aiuni.ai</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Citation</h2><a id="user-content-citation" aria-label="Permalink: Citation" href="#citation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If you found Unique3D helpful, please cite our report:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="@misc{wu2024unique3d,
      title={Unique3D: High-Quality and Efficient 3D Mesh Generation from a Single Image}, 
      author={Kailu Wu and Fangfu Liu and Zhihan Cai and Runjie Yan and Hanyang Wang and Yating Hu and Yueqi Duan and Kaisheng Ma},
      year={2024},
      eprint={2405.20343},
      archivePrefix={arXiv},
      primaryClass={cs.CV}
}"><pre><span>@misc</span>{<span>wu2024unique3d</span>,
      <span>title</span>=<span><span>{</span>Unique3D: High-Quality and Efficient 3D Mesh Generation from a Single Image<span>}</span></span>, 
      <span>author</span>=<span><span>{</span>Kailu Wu and Fangfu Liu and Zhihan Cai and Runjie Yan and Hanyang Wang and Yating Hu and Yueqi Duan and Kaisheng Ma<span>}</span></span>,
      <span>year</span>=<span><span>{</span>2024<span>}</span></span>,
      <span>eprint</span>=<span><span>{</span>2405.20343<span>}</span></span>,
      <span>archivePrefix</span>=<span><span>{</span>arXiv<span>}</span></span>,
      <span>primaryClass</span>=<span><span>{</span>cs.CV<span>}</span></span>
}</pre></div>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[X debut 40 years ago (1984) (303 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.talisman.org/x-debut.shtml</link>
            <guid>40731922</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 20:09:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.talisman.org/x-debut.shtml">https://www.talisman.org/x-debut.shtml</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40731922">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.talisman.org/x-debut.shtml: Error: connect ENETUNREACH 2001:470:b8ba:1::99:443]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[EasyOS: An Experimental Linux Distribution (262 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://easyos.org/</link>
            <guid>40731360</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 18:59:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://easyos.org/">https://easyos.org/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40731360">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div width="620">
 <tbody>
  <tr>
   <td>
<div id="divbodyholder"><div>
<h3>Web pages index</h3>
<ul>
<h3><a href="https://easyos.org/about/index.html">Overview of EasyOS</a></h3>
<a href="https://easyos.org/about/how-and-why-easyos-is-different.html">How and why EasyOS is different</a><br>
<a href="https://easyos.org/about/why-the-iso-format-has-to-die.html">Why the ISO format has to die</a><br>
<a href="https://easyos.org/about/legal-disclaimers-miscellania.html">Legal, disclaimers, miscellania</a><br>
<a href="https://easyos.org/about/easyos-forum-amp-other-links.html">EasyOS Forum &amp; other links</a><br>
<h3><a href="https://easyos.org/apps/index.html"><img src="https://easyos.org/apps/images/logo48.png" width="48" height="48"><span>Applications in EasyOS</span></a></h3>
<a href="https://easyos.org/apps/easyshare-super-easy-network-file-and-printer-sharing.html">EasyShare, super easy network file and printer sharing</a><br>
<a href="https://easyos.org/apps/bluepup-easy-bluetooth-management.html">BluePup easy Bluetooth management</a><br>
<h3><a href="https://easyos.org/dev/index.html">Development, programming</a></h3>
<a href="https://easyos.org/dev/guidelines-for-debugging-easyos.html">Guidelines for debugging EasyOS</a><br>
<a href="https://easyos.org/dev/translate-easyos-to-your-language.html">Translate EasyOS to your language</a><br>
<a href="https://easyos.org/dev/coding-for-easyos.html">Coding for EasyOS</a><br>
<a href="https://easyos.org/dev/how-to-compile-a-linux-distribution-from-source.html">How to compile a Linux distribution from source</a><br>
<a href="https://easyos.org/dev/how-to-run-a-linux-distribution-in-a-container.html">How to run a Linux distribution in a container</a><br>
<h3><a href="https://easyos.org/install/index.html">Installation tutorials</a></h3>
<a href="https://easyos.org/install/easy-frugal-installation.html">Easy frugal installation</a><br>
<a href="https://easyos.org/install/how-to-install-easyos-on-a-new-ssd.html">How to install EasyOS on a new SSD</a><br>
<a href="https://easyos.org/install/limine-bootloader.html">Limine bootloader</a><br>
<a href="https://easyos.org/install/install-to-pc-with-existing-refind-boot-manager.html">Install to PC with existing rEFind boot manager</a><br>
<a href="https://easyos.org/install/how-to-write-easyos-to-a-flash-drive.html">How to write EasyOS to a flash drive</a><br>
<a href="https://easyos.org/install/how-to-install-easyos-on-your-hard-drive.html">How to install EasyOS on your hard drive</a><br>
<a href="https://easyos.org/install/prepare-your-computer-for-booting-linux.html">Prepare your computer for booting Linux</a><br>
<h3><a href="https://easyos.org/tech/index.html">Technical details of EasyOS</a></h3>
<a href="https://easyos.org/tech/how-easy-works-part-2.html">How Easy works, part 2</a><br>
<a href="https://easyos.org/tech/how-easy-works.html">How Easy works</a><br>
<h3><a href="https://easyos.org/user/index.html">Usage guidelines</a></h3>
<a href="https://easyos.org/user/package-manager-concepts.html">Package manager concepts</a><br>
<a href="https://easyos.org/user/how-to-update-easyos.html">How to update EasyOS</a><br>
<a href="https://easyos.org/user/easy-version-upgrade-and-downgrade.html">Easy version upgrade and downgrade</a><br>
<a href="https://easyos.org/user/using-easy-containers.html">Using Easy Containers</a><br>
<a href="https://easyos.org/user/ultra-secure-web-browsing.html">Ultra-secure web browsing</a><br>
<a href="https://easyos.org/user/how-to-fix-broken-video.html">How to fix broken video</a><br>
</ul>

</div>

<p><small>
 <br>
 © Copyright 
 <a href="https://bkhome.org/">Barry Kauler</a> 2018, 2019, 2020, 2021, 2022, 2023
 <br>
 Generated with <a href="https://bkhome.org/shellcms">shellCMS</a> 
 </small>
</p>
</div>
   </td>
  </tr>
 </tbody>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[F (2006) (139 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://www.nsl.com/k/f/f.htm</link>
            <guid>40730228</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 17:14:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://www.nsl.com/k/f/f.htm">http://www.nsl.com/k/f/f.htm</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40730228">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">

<h2>F</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.nsl.com/k/f/f.k">F</a> is a pure functional concatenative 
language originally designed as an extension of <a href="http://www.nsl.com/papers/false.htm">False</a>. F contains the list-operations of <a href="http://www.kx.com/">K3</a> and the <em>dip</em> combinator 
of <a href="http://www.latrobe.edu.au/philosophy/phimvt/joy.html">Joy</a>. Floating-point and symbolic datatypes are supported. One-time assignment
is enforced in syntax. A theory of function-valence and -charge is outlined. F also contains a general continuation
primitive $, and the pattern sublanguage of <a href="http://www.nsl.com/k/xy/xy.htm">XY</a>.  <a href="http://www.nsl.com/k/f/g.k">G</a> is a variant of F in which the K3 adverbs are implemented as primitives.</p>

<h2>0. Introduction</h2>

<p>F has the following properties:</p>

<blockquote>
    <ul>
        <li>The language is concatenative</li>
        <li>The language is purely functional</li>
        <li>All K verbs are implemented</li>
        <li>All primitives are denoted by single symbols</li>
        <li>Primitive symbols are as mnemonic as possible</li>
    </ul>
</blockquote>

<p><em>The language is concatenative.</em> F tokens are words,
words denote functions, and the concatenation of words denotes
the composition of functions. In classical concatenative
languages, everything is a function from stacks to stacks. In F,
everything is a function from triples of
(environment;stack;queue) to triples of
(environment;stack;queue).</p>

<p><em>The language is purely functional.</em> There are no
side-effects. F has assignment, but not reassignment. This means
that you can't use a variable to store dynamic state. F
assignment associates names with values in an environment which
is passed as an argument and returned as a value. F also has
commands for interacting with the run-time environment and the
file-system, but these operations are notationally differentiated
from the operators of F: "h", "r", &amp;c.
They are intended as debugging aids only.</p>

<p><em>All K verbs are implemented.</em> Some K verbs are
implemented as primitives, and some are derived in the F prelude.
For example, the <em>atom</em> primitive @ of K is defined as
[#ints~]; i.e. shape matches the empty integer vector. Where K
provides a pair of functions, one of which is easily defined in
terms of the other, F implements one as a primitive and derives the
other. For example, <em>and</em> is primitive (&amp;) and <em>or</em>
is derived.  The criterion for dividing related pairs is simply
this:  the derived definition must not be egregiously inefficient
when compared to the primitive it supplants.</p>

<p><em>All primitives are denoted by single symbols.</em>
Although list-notation ([x y z]) is supported, any list can be
constructed functionally with ' (<em>quote</em>) and , (<em>join</em>).</p>

<p><em>Primitive symbols are as mnemonic as possible.</em> There
are five ways the mapping of a function to a symbol can be
mnemonic:</p>

<blockquote>
    <ol>
        <li>The symbol is in common use for the mapped function
            (e.g. + for addition)</li>
        <li>The symbol is mapped to that function in K (e.g. ?
            for <em>find</em>) or False (e.g. ! for <em>unquote</em>)</li>
        <li>The name of the symbol is a homonym for the mapped
            function (e.g. ' for <em>quote</em>)</li>
        <li>A pair of related functions (inverses, or
            near-inverses) are mapped to a pair of related
            symbols (e.g. / and \ for <em>take</em> and <em>drop</em>)</li>
        <li>Where several K primitives are mapped to one symbol,
            the primitives should form an easily remembered group
            based on some common property; e.g. both <em>upgrade</em>
            and <em>enum</em> return indices based on an
            ascending relation, so both are mapped to &lt;. </li>
    </ol>
</blockquote>

<h2>1. Datatypes</h2>

<p>The initial state of the interpreter consists of an
environment containing the F words of the prelude, an empty
result stack, and a string (character-vector) to be evaluated.
The input string is tokenized and parsed to obtain the initial
queue. </p>

<p>The input queue is a K list, possibly containing integers,
floats, symbols, <em>null</em>, functions, and lists
("quotations"). The result stack is initially empty.
The environment is a K dictionary. F processes the environment,
stack, and queue repeatedly until the queue is empty. </p>

<p>If the first item on the queue is an integer, float, <em>null</em>,
the prototype symbol `, or a list, the item is pushed onto the
stack.</p>

<p>If the first item is an undefined symbol, then if it's a <em>shuffle</em>
it's applied; otherwise, a variable is created (in the environment)
having the top of the stack as the value. </p>

<p>If the first item is a defined symbol, its value is
retrieved (from the environment) and pushed onto the stack.</p>

<p>If the first item is a function, then it is applied to the
environment, stack, and queue to produce a new environment,
stack, and queue.</p>

<p>Observe that the domain of the result stack is a proper subset
of the domain of the input queue. On the queue we may find
character-atoms, such as "r", and strings, such as
"blah". But character-atoms are executed away when they
are evaluated, and no F primitive ever produces one, and strings
are comments, which are not processed.</p>

<p>The <em>trace</em> command displays the stack and queue for
selected objects in the trace list T:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>F&gt;[fac] "t"

F&gt;3 fac!
                                       3 ♦ fac !
                                     3 2 ♦ fac ! *
                                   3 2 1 ♦ fac ! * *
6
F&gt;

F&gt;[fac cond] "t"

F&gt;3 fac!
                                       3 ♦ fac !
       3 [1 =] [] [dup ! pred ! fac ! *] ♦ cond !
                                     3 2 ♦ fac ! *
     3 2 [1 =] [] [dup ! pred ! fac ! *] ♦ cond ! *
                                   3 2 1 ♦ fac ! * *
   3 2 1 [1 =] [] [dup ! pred ! fac ! *] ♦ cond ! * *
6
F&gt;

F&gt;[] "t"

F&gt;3 fac!
6</pre>
</blockquote>

<h2>2. Primitives</h2>

<h3>Operators (O)</h3>

<blockquote>
    <pre>09*-		int		123 -&gt; 123
09*.09*-	float		123.45 -&gt; 123.45

az.AZ*		name		myName -&gt; value or null
az*-AZ*		shuffle		10 20 ab-ba -&gt; 20 10

[..]		list		[10 + [3 a]] -&gt; [10 + [3 a]]

+		add		1 2 + -&gt; 3
-		sub		2 3 - -&gt; 1
*		mul		3 4 * -&gt; 12
%		div		5 3 % -&gt; 1.666667
^		power		2 3 ^ -&gt; 8
_		floor		3.2 _ -&gt; 3

=		equal		2 2 = -&gt; 1
&gt;		more		4 6 &gt; -&gt; 0
&amp;		and/min		4 3 &amp; -&gt; 3

~		match		[1 2][1 2] ~ -&gt; 1

#		shape		[1 2 3] # -&gt; [3]

|		reverse		[1 2 3] | -&gt; [3 2 1]

@		where		[0 1 1 0 1] @ -&gt; [1 2 4]
@		flip		[[1 2 3][4 5 6]] @ -&gt; [[1 4][2 5][3 6]]

/		take		2[1 2 3] / -&gt; [1 2]
/		reshape		[3 2][1 2 3] / -&gt; [[1 2][3 1][2 3]]

\		drop		2[1 2 3] \ -&gt; [3]
\		cut		[0 2][1 2 3] \ -&gt; [[1 2][3]]
\		rotate		[1 2 3 4] 2 \ -&gt; [3 4 1 2]

?		find		[10 20 30] 20 ? -&gt; 1
?		mod		2 [3 4 5] ? -&gt; [1 0 1]

;		unique		[10 20 10 10 30] ; -&gt; [10 20 30]
:		group		[10 20 10 10 30] : -&gt; [[0 2 3][1][4]]

&lt;		enum		3 &lt; -&gt; [0 1 2]
&lt;		upgrade		[10 30 20] &lt; -&gt; [0 2 1]

.		infra		1 2 [[2 3 +]] . 3 4 -&gt; 1 2 [5] 3 4
.		index		[[1 2 3][[1 0]]] . -&gt; [2 1]
.		monad		[[1 2 3][[1 0]][-1*]] . -&gt; [-1 -2 3]
.		dyad		[[1 2 3][[1 0]]+[3 8]] . -&gt; [9 5 3]

!		unquote		2 [3 +] ! -&gt; 5
`		dip		2 3 4 [+] ` -&gt; 5 4
'		quote		'+ -&gt; [+]

,		join  		[1][2 3] , -&gt; [1 2 3]

$		state		1 2 3 '\ $ 4 5 6 -&gt; 4 5 6 1 2 3

)		s -&gt; s		stack-&gt;stack pattern
(		s -&gt; q		stack-&gt;queue pattern

}		q -&gt; s		queue-&gt;stack pattern
{		q -&gt; q		queue-&gt;queue pattern</pre>
</blockquote>

<h3>System Functions (K)</h3>

<p>The K system functions have reserved names:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>type (4::)
log exp abs sqr sqrt floor dot mul inv lsq
sin cos tan asin acos atan sinh cosh tanh
draw
in lin bin binl dv dvl di vs sv</pre>
</blockquote>

<h3>Literals (L)</h3>

<p>F has nine reserved names for literals:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>Nan		minint (0N)
Inf		maxint (0I)

nan		NaN (0n)
inf		infinity (0i)

null		null (_n)
sym		prototype sym (`)

ints		empty integer vector (!0)
floats		empty float vector (0#0.)
syms		empty sym vector (0#`)</pre>
</blockquote>

<h3>Commands (I)</h3>

<p>F has the following interactive commands:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>".."		comment		1 "skip" 2	comment not processed

"b"		break		'x "b"		signal error ('x)
"c"		clear		1 2 "c" 3 4	clear, load f, prelude
"d"		defined		'foo "d"	is foo defined?
"e"		error		0 "e"		set/unset error trap (\e)
"f"		F		"f" 2 unit!	set F semantics, clear
"j"		Joy		"j" 2 unit	set Joy semantics, clear
"k"		K		1 2 "k" 3 4	exit to K
"l"		load		'x "l"		load f/x.f|x.j
"m"		measure		[10&lt;] "m"	measure time in ms
"o"		words		'map "o"	show word form
"p"		precision	3 "p"		print precision (\p)
"r"		read		1 2 "r" 3 4	read, parse, eval
"s"		store		y 'x "s"	store f/x.f|x.j
"t"		trace		null "t" 3 4	set trace-list (T)
"u"		undefine	x "u"		undefine vars in x
"v"		variables	1 2 "v" 3 4	show vars (!environment)
"x"		exit		1 2 "x" 3 4	_exit 0
"w"		write		1 2 "w" 3 4	format, write
"z"		halt		1 2 "z" 3 4	: to continue
</pre></blockquote>

<h3>Names and numbers</h3>

<p>Spaces (<em>blank</em>, <em>tab</em>, <em>return</em>) are
necessary to separate names from names and numbers from numbers,
but not names from numbers.</p>

<p>A name must begin with a letter and may contain letters, .,
or a single -.  A name containing a - is a shuffle-symbol.</p>

<p>A numerical expression must begin with either a digit or - 
followed by a digit, and must end with a digit.  A floating-point 
numerical expression must contain exactly one . which
must be flanked by digits.</p>

<h3>Operators</h3>

<p>The math, logic, and relational operators are <em>atomic
functions</em>. For example,</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>F&gt;[1 2 3][[4 5 6] 7 8]+
[[5 6 7] 9 11]</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>In several instances, distinct K operations have been mapped
to one symbol: </p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>int &lt;			enum			!x
~atom &lt;			upgrade			&lt;x
atom &lt;			nonce

int/ints @		where			&amp;x
list @			flip			+x
			nonce

atom y ?		mod			y!x
~atom y ?		find			x?y

list atom \		rotate			y!x
atom list \		drop			x _ y
atom atom \		drop			x _(),y
list list \		cut			x _ y

1=#x .			infra
x .			index/monad/dyad	. x</pre>
</blockquote>

<h3>Iterators</h3>

<p>The False combinators <em>if</em> and <em>while</em> have been
eliminated, and <em>cond</em>, <em>if</em>, and <em>while</em>
have been defined as words in the prelude. The truth-values of F
are more general than those of K: 0 is <em>false</em>, any other
value is <em>true</em>.</p>

<h3>Assignment</h3>

<p>Assignment has the form <em>value unassigned_name</em>. An
assigned name may not be re-assigned.</p>

<p>Reserved names cannot be assigned:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>F&gt;12 inf
12 inf</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>Use of an assigned name (a variable) places the value assigned
to it on the stack:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>F&gt;10 a

F&gt;a
10
F&gt;12 a
10 12 10
F&gt;a
10 12 10 10</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>A symbol can be produced indirectly:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>F&gt;10 foo

F&gt;foo
10
F&gt;[foo] first!
foo
F&gt;!
10</pre>
</blockquote>

<h3>Quotation</h3>

<p>The <em>quote</em> primitive ' takes the next item on the
queue and quotes it:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>F&gt;'+
[+]
F&gt;
F&gt;'[1 2 3]
[[1 2 3]]
F&gt;
F&gt;''
[']</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>The <em>unquote</em> combinator ! is Joy's <em>i</em>. ! takes
the top item <em>x</em> on the stack and prepends the elements of
<em>x</em> to the queue:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>F&gt;2 3 '+ !
5</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>The <em>dip</em> combinator is defined as it is in Joy. `
takes the top two items <em>x</em> <em>y</em> on the stack and
prepends <em>y,,x</em> to the queue. For example, with trace on,
the input queue is displayed to the right of the diamond and the
result stack to the left:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>F&gt;10 2 3 4 20 [+*]`
                                         ♦ 10 2 3 4 20 [+ *] `
                                      10 ♦ 2 3 4 20 [+ *] `
                                    10 2 ♦ 3 4 20 [+ *] `
                                  10 2 3 ♦ 4 20 [+ *] `
                                10 2 3 4 ♦ 20 [+ *] `
                             10 2 3 4 20 ♦ [+ *] `
                       10 2 3 4 20 [+ *] ♦ `
                                10 2 3 4 ♦ + * 20
                                  10 2 7 ♦ * 20
                                   10 14 ♦ 20
                                10 14 20 ♦
F&gt;</pre>
</blockquote>

<h3>State</h3>

<p>F has two programs for manipulating the stack, and two for
manipulating the queue:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>stack		push the stack onto the stack
unstack		set the stack to the top of the stack  
queue		move the top of the stack to the queue
unqueue		move the end of the queue to the stack</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>These are defined using the <em>state</em> combinator $:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>[[[|uncons!|swap!]`swap!unit!,]$]       queue
[[|uncons!|[unit!,]`]$]                 unqueue

[[[dup!unit!,]`]$]                      stack
[[[last!]`]$]                           unstack</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>$ expects a program on top of the stack. The program expects
two quotations beneath it: the current queue, and beneath that,
the current stack. F expects the program to return two
quotations: the new queue, and beneath that, the new list.</p>

<h3>Stack Operations</h3>

<p>The False stack operators <em>pop</em>, <em>dup</em>, and <em>swap</em>
are defined using shuffles:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>[a-]                            pop
[ab-ba]                         swap
[a-aa]                          dup</pre>
</blockquote>

<h3>List Operations</h3>

<p>The list operations <em>cons</em> and <em>uncons</em> are
total: </p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>F&gt;1 2 cons!
[1 2]
F&gt;

F&gt;[1 2] uncons!
1 [2]
F&gt;

F&gt;[1] uncons!
1 ints
F&gt;

F&gt;[] uncons!
null []
F&gt;

F&gt;2 uncons!
2 ints</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>These are defined using the ( and ) operators:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>[[[[a A]]a A])]                 uncons
[[[a b][a]b,](]                 cons</pre>
</blockquote>

<h3>Errors</h3>
<blockquote><pre><em>F stack</em>			The stack-valence greater than the stack-size.

<em>F queue</em>			The queue-valence is greater than the queue-size.

<em>F pattern</em>		The stack-size is greater than the pattern scheme-size.

<em>F char: &lt;x&gt;</em>		x is an illegal character.

<em>F nonce: &lt;x&gt;</em>		Primitive x is not defined for the arguments supplied.
</pre></blockquote>

<h2>3. Implementation</h2>

<p>The implementation consists of a single <a href="http://www.nsl.com/k/f/f.k">script</a><a> which defines a
node (.f) on the K tree.</a></p><a>

<h3>Globals</h3>

<blockquote>
    <pre>J	0 (F semantics) 1 (Joy semantics).

O	Look-up table of operator character, operator

I	I.x is an interactive (or interpreter) command.

L	L.x is a literal whose representation is x.

K	K.x is a K system function

C	C i is a vector of characters of lexical category i.

V	A string of state-names.

W	A string of final-state-names.

X	In V i read a character in C j, go to X[i;j].

T	0 (no trace) 1 (trace).

E	Global environment.

S	Global stack.

Z	(states x 256) transition matrix.</pre>
</blockquote>

<h3>Functions</h3>

<blockquote>
    <pre>F	F interpreter.

n	Interpret pattern.

q	Interpret shuffle-symbol.
    
i	Transform dictionary -&gt; list.

j	Transform list -&gt; dictionary.

l	Load and interpret a .f script.

s	Format an F value and save it to a .f script.

u	Update the stack (S) and environment (E).

p	Tokenize and parse an input string to create a queue.

v	Evaluate token.

r	Recursively construct a list from ("[";...;"]").

m	<em>infra</em>, <em>index</em>, <em>monadic amend</em>, <em>dyadic amend</em>.

e	Evaluate the queue (z) on the stack (y) in the environment (x).

a	Apply the top of the queue to the stack in the environment.

b	Evaluate symbol.

k	Create a variable in the environment.

c	Process the value of a defined symbol (J-sensitive).

x	Apply n-ad f, append the enlisted result to the stack.

y	Apply n-ad f, append the result to the stack.

z	Apply n-ad f, prepend the result to the queue.

w	Apply n-ad f to stack, queue, return new stack, new queue.

t	If T is a non-empty list, trace the impending step.

d	Display the trace.

f	Format the stack.

g	Format an element on the stack.

h	Pretty printer

o	Translate symbols into names.</pre>
</blockquote>

<h2>4. Operation</h2>

<p>Say</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>k f</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>to start the F interpreter.</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>k f .. &lt;script&gt; ..</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>starts the interpreter, then reads and evaluates the F
scripts. For example</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>k f f/fac</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>Joy or F semantics may be specified with an initial boolean
value of J:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>k f 1 f/fac</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>The prompt is F&gt; for F semantics and J&gt; for Joy
semantics.</p>

<p>If, in a .f or .j script, the interpreter encounters a single
unmated ", evaluation on that script terminates. (Analogous
to \ in .k scripts.)</p>

<p>Exit to K, or from the current trace or stop, by entering a
single space. Clear the stack by pressing &lt;return&gt; with
null input.</p>

<h2>5. Examples</h2>

</a><p><a>The F prelude is </a><a href="http://www.nsl.com/k/f/f/prelude.f">here</a>. </p>

<p>An F implementation of <em>factorial</em> is <a href="http://www.nsl.com/k/f/f/fac.f">here</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>F&gt;[[1=][][dup!pred!fac!*]cond!]fac

F&gt;6fac!
720</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>An F script containing synonyms for the symbolic operations is
<a href="http://www.nsl.com/k/f/f/f.f">here</a>.</p>

<p>Versions of the prelude and factorial function adapted for Joy
semantics are <a href="http://www.nsl.com/k/f/f/prelude.j">here</a> and <a href="http://www.nsl.com/k/f/f/fac.j">here</a>.</p>

<h2>6. Comments</h2>

<h3>Names</h3>

<p>In Joy, use of a name causes the value associated with the
name to be executed against the stack:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>plustwo == 2 +</pre>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
    <pre>3 plustwo .
5</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>In F, use of a name causes the value associated with the name
to placed on the stack:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>F&gt;[2 +] plustwo

F&gt;3 plustwo
3 [2 +]</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>The value may then be executed with !:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>3 [2 +]
F&gt;!
5</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>In Joy, adjacent names must be separated by a blank, or the
equivalent. The corresponding F code has greater visual density,
but is nearly as concise. For example, the <em>reduce</em>
combinator is:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>[swap!dup!proto!swap!unit!bot!over!]</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>as opposed to:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>[swap dup proto swap unit bot over]</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>One might say that F occupies a middle-ground between Joy,
which evaluates names aggressively, and False, which breaks the
semantics of name evaluation into even smaller steps:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>[swap;!dup;!proto;!swap;!unit;!bot;!over;!]</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>In False, a name leaves itself on the stack. ; takes a
name and leaves the value of the name on the stack. ! executes
values.</p>

<p>In addition, F semantics makes it easy for one program to
modify the code of another: invoke the program by name, which
leaves a quotation on the stack, modify the quotation, execute.</p>

<p>In any case, it should be noted that switching F to Joy
semantics is a trivial matter. The <em>c</em> function takes the
value of a defined symbol <em>z</em>, the stack <em>x</em>, and
the queue <em>y</em> and appends it to the stack:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>(x,,z;y)</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>For Joy, we change this to:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>(x;z,y)</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>which prepends the <em>contents</em> of <em>z</em> to the <em>queue</em>.
Subsequent processing will evaluate elements of the value
one-by-one.</p>

<p>It is important to note that in both dialects, some primitives
have names. For example, <em>in</em> is a primitive system function, so:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>F&gt;10 [2 3 4 10 12 2] in
1</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>is valid code in both Joy and F dialects.</p>

<p>Note: this switch has been implemented in the script for F,
viz. J is 0 for F semantics, 1 for Joy semantics.</p>

<p>Note: The "o" command spells out F programs. In Joy
mode:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>F&gt;'map "o"
[[dup count [] top] dip swap
 [quote uncons dip dup top
  [cons unit eval first swons]
  dipd] 
 do pop pop rev]</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>It is possible to write programs in this way, using the words
defined in the <a href="http://www.nsl.com/k/f/f/f.f">f</a> scripts.</p>

<h3>Program = List = Quotation</h3>

<p>In Joy, a quotation is a list and also a program. All programs
are lists, and vice-versa. Intuitively, there does seem to be a
difference between [1 2 3] and [2 +]. It cannot be that the
former contains "data elements" and the latter a data
element and a function, since numbers are just as much functions
as the + operator. Both 2 and + are functions from stacks to
stacks.</p>

<p>The difference between quotations-as-lists and
quotations-as-programs reduces to this: a quotation is list-like
when we want to examine or manipulate its parts or structure; and
a quotation is program-like when want to execute it. So the same
object can appear list-like in certain contexts and program-like
in others. Indeed, it can appear to be neither if we are merely
pushing it onto the stack without regard to its structure or
execution-properties, or both if we first manipulate contents and
structure and then execute it.</p>

<h3>Valence and Charge</h3>

<p>The <em>valence</em> of a program is a pair of integers. The
first element of the pair is the <em>stack-valence</em>. The
stack-valence of a program is the number of elements it takes
from the stack. The second element is the <em>queue-valence</em>.
The queue-valence is the number of elements it takes from the
queue. </p>

<p>The <em>quote</em> operator ' is the only primitive having
non-zero queue-valence: it expects to find one element on the
queue, which it enlists and pushes onto the stack. Hence, <em>quote</em>
has stack-valence 1.</p>

<p>The + operator has stack-valence 2. It takes two elements from
the stack and pushes the sum onto the stack.</p>

<p>The <em>charge</em> of a program is also a pair of integers.
The first element is the <em>stack-charge</em>, and the second is
the <em>queue-charge</em>. </p>

<p>+ has stack-charge 1 (it pushes a single element onto the
stack) and queue-charge 0. <em>dup</em> has stack-valence 1 and
stack-charge 2. <em>swap</em> has stack-valence 2 and
stack-charge 2.</p>

<p>! (<em>unquote</em>) has stack-valence 1 and infinite
queue-charge: it takes a quotation off the stack and pushes as
many elements onto the queue as there are in the quotation.</p>

<p>` (<em>dip</em>) has stack-valence 2 and infinite
queue-charge: it takes two things off the stack: a quotation and
an element X and pushes first X, and then the quotation onto the
queue.</p>

<p>All primitives have non-negative charge and valence. A
negative value means that the program operates on the <em>bottom</em>
of the stack or queue.</p>

<p>If the stack has fewer elements than the (absolute value of
the) stack-valence, an <em>F stack</em> error is signalled. If
the queue has fewer elements than the (absolute value of the)
queue-valence, an <em>F queue</em> error is signalled.</p>

<h3>XY operators: Stack, Unstack, Queue, Unqueue</h3>

<p>F implements four <a href="http://www.nsl.com/k/xy/xy.htm">XY</a> operators:</p>

<p>The <em>stack</em> program takes the stack, enlists it, and
appends it to the stack:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>F&gt;1 2 3 stack!
1 2 3 [1 2 3]</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>The <em>unstack</em> program expects a quotation <em>q</em> at
the top of the stack, and sets the stack to the contents of <em>q</em>:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>F&gt;1 2 3 [4 5 6] unstack!
4 5 6</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>The <em>queue</em> program expects a quotation at the top of
the stack, and appends it to the end of the queue:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>F&gt;1 2 3 [4 5 6] queue! 7 8 9
1 2 3 7 8 9 [4 5 6]</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>The <em>unqueue</em> program expects a quotation at the end of
the queue, and pushes it onto the stack:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>F&gt;1 2 3 unqueue! 4 5 6 [7 8 9]
1 2 3 [7 8 9] 4 5 6</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>The XY programs have valence and charge:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>operator	stack-valence	stack-charge	queue-valence	queue-charge
--------	-------------	------------	-------------	------------
stack		inf		1		0		0
unstack		1		inf		0		0
queue		1		0		0		-1
unqueue		0		1		-1		0</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>The implementation of $ is one of two primitives which
recursively calls the F evaluator <em>e</em>. $ is a K function
which takes <em>x</em>, the environment, <em>y</em>, the stack,
and <em>z</em>, the queue, and is defined:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>{x,e[x;(-1_ y;z);*-1#y]1}</pre>
</blockquote>

<h3>Infra, Index, Monad, Dyad</h3>

<p>The implementation of . is the other primitive which
recursively calls the F evaluator <em>e</em>. </p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>m:{:[1=#y           ;e[x;();*y]1                                  / infra
     2=#y           ;(*y). e[x;();y 1]1                           / index
     (4:*y)_in 4 6  ;'"G nonce: ."                                / no assignment
     3=#y           ;.@[y;2;{{*-1#e[*x;y,();x 1]1}[(x;y)]}[x]]    / monad
                     .@[y;2;{{*-1#e[*x;y,,z;x 1]1}[(x;y)]}[x]]]}  / dyad</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>where <em>y</em> is the quotation on top of the stack and <em>x</em>
is the environment.</p>

<p>Assignment to globals (*y a symbol) or null (*y null) is blocked.</p>

<p>For example, if the expression to be evaluated is</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>[[10 20 30][[0 1]]] .</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>then the count of <em>y</em> is 2. <em>m</em> indexes the
first element of y, which is 10 20 30, by the value of the second
element of y in the environment x, which is ,0 1.</p>

<h3>Patterns and Shuffles</h3>

<p>F incorporates a version of the pattern sublanguage of <a href="http://www.nsl.com/k/xy/xy.htm">XY</a>.</p>

<p>A <em>pattern</em> is a list whose head is a scheme and whose
tail is a template</p>

<p>A <em>scheme</em> is a name or a list of schemes. The case of
the first letter in a name is significant. If lower-case, the
name matches a single element. If upper-case, the name must occur
as the final element in a list of schemes, and will match zero or
more elements, viz. the remainder of the list whose initial
elements are matched by schemes preceding the terminal name.</p>

<p>A <em>template</em> is a list. If <em>s</em> is a symbol in
the template which also occurs in the scheme, the value matched
by <em>s</em> is substituted for <em>s</em> in the template.</p>

<p>F contains four primitive operations on patterns:</p>

<blockquote><pre>)       Applies a pattern to the stack and pushes the result onto the stack.

(       Applies a pattern to the stack and prepends the result to the queue.

}       Applies a pattern to the queue and pushes the result onto the stack.

{       Applies a pattern to the queue and prepends the result to the queue.</pre></blockquote>

<p>Although F supports the <em>dip</em> combinator as a primitive,
it is possible to define it as a pattern:</p>

<blockquote><pre>F&gt;[[[f a]f!a](] pdip
F&gt;10 20 5 pdip!
30 5
</pre></blockquote>

<p>As an example of how patterns can simplify programming in F,
compare the definition of <em>cond</em> as given in the prelude:</p>

<blockquote><pre>[pair![dupd!]dip!quote!!dip!swap!false!pair!index!!]        cond
</pre></blockquote>

<p>with an equivalent definition using the stack-to-queue operator
(:</p>

<blockquote><pre>[[[d i t f]d[[t f]]d i!false!join!index!!](]                pcond
</pre></blockquote>

<p><em>pcond</em> expects a data-item <em>d</em>, a condition <em>i</em> of <em>d</em>, 
a program <em>t</em> to evaluate on <em>d</em> if <em>d i</em> is true (i.e. not false),
and a program <em>f</em> to evaluate on <em>d</em> if <em>d i</em> is false.</p>

<p>The template evaluates the condition and uses the result to index out
the appropriate program, which is then evaluated on the data-item.</p>

<p>The extent to which patterns can be used to avoid list construction and
deconstruction can be seen in this version, in which the template is used
to create a diagram of the penultimate structure.  <em>infra</em> evaluates
the quotation, <em>index</em> selects the right piece of the result, which
is then evaluated on the data-item:</p>

<blockquote><pre>[[[d i t f]d[[[t f]d i!false!]]infra!index!!](]             qcond
</pre></blockquote>

<p>The pattern versions are arguably clearer than the version which
makes use of stack operators.  One objection to the use of patterns is that
the resulting programs violate the Concatenativity property: a concatenative
program can be cut into two sub-programs, both of which are concatenative
programs, as long as the cut does not fall within the boundaries of a 
quotation.  For example, <em>cond</em> can be cut into:</p>

<blockquote><pre>[pair![dupd!]dip!quote!!dip!]                               acond
[swap!false!pair!index!!]                                   bcond
</pre></blockquote>

<p>and then <em>cond</em> can be defined as:

</p><blockquote><pre>[acond!bcond!]                                              abcond
</pre></blockquote>

<p>But <em>pcond</em> cannot be cut into smaller programs, because every
pattern-based program has the structure <em>[[[scheme] template] operator]</em>.
The only point available for the cut is between the pattern and the operator.
This is a consequence of the fact that the meaning of symbols in the pattern-template 
depends on the assignments implied by the pattern-scheme.</p>

<p>F also supports <em>shuffle-symbols</em>, a simplified, weaker
version of ). For example, <em>swap</em> is:</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>F&gt;10 20 ab-ba
20 10</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>Shuffles can reduce stack-noise, but the resulting programs still
have the Concatenativity property.  For example, <em>cond</em> can be defined
as:</p>

<blockquote><pre>[ditf-dditf pair!unit!quote!!dip!swap!false!join!index!!]   scond
</pre></blockquote>

<p>A potentially fruitful approach to program construction would require that 
all programs be defined as alternating pairs of shuffles and stack-manipulation-free
stretches of functional code.  For example,</p><blockquote><pre>[ab-bab     +*
 abc-bcca   -|,.]</pre></blockquote>
 
<p>In such programs, one would never find on the right-hand side
programs such as <em>pop</em> or <em>swap</em>.</p>

<p>Note: This material has benefited greatly from discussions
with William Tanksley, Jr.</p>

<h2>7. Notes</h2>

<p>F began as an exercise in extending Wouter van Oormerssen's concatenative language <a href="http://www.nsl.com/papers/false.htm">False</a>, but it rapidly acquired a life of its own.  At
this point, little trace remains of the original.</p>

<p>See Randall Holmes' functional extensions to False, <a href="http://math.boisestate.edu/~holmes/holmes/sfdocs.pdf">Strictly
False</a>, which stimulated the present project.</p>

<p>An earlier version of F with primitive stack and list operations
and a somewhat different mapping of primitives to symbols is <a href="http://www.nsl.com/k/f_obsolete/f.htm">here</a>.</p>

<h2>8. K and F</h2>

<h3>Verbs: K -&gt; F</h3>

<blockquote>
    <pre>	       <strong>Dyad</strong>				      <strong>Monad</strong>
               ====				      =====
	<strong>K</strong>		<strong>F</strong>			<strong>K</strong>		<strong>F</strong>
	-		-			-		-
+       plus            +			flip		@
-       minus           -			negate		<em>neg</em>
*       times           *			first		<em>first</em>
%       divide          %			reciprocal	<em>rec</em>
&amp;       min/and         &amp;			where		@
|       max/or          <em>max</em>,<em>or</em>			reverse		|
&gt;       more            &gt;			downgrade	<em>down</em>
&lt;	less		<em>less</em>			upgrade		&lt;
=       equal           =			group		:
^       power           ^			shape		#
!       mod/rotate      ? \			enum		&lt;
~       match           ~			not		<em>not</em>
,       join            ,			enlist		'
#       take/reshape    /			count		<em>count</em>
_       drop/cut        \			floor		_ 
$       form/format     NA			format		NA
?       find/invert     ?			unique		;
@       at              NA			atom		<em>atom</em>
.       dot             .			value		.
:	dex		<em>pop</em>			identity	<em>id</em></pre>
</blockquote>

<h3>Adverbs: K -&gt; F</h3>

<blockquote>
    <pre><strong>K</strong>	<strong>F</strong>
-	-
'	<em>each</em>
/	<em>over</em>, <em>do</em>, <em>while</em>, <em>vector</em>, <em>matrix</em>
\	<em>Over</em>, <em>Do</em>, <em>While</em>, <em>Vector</em>, <em>Matrix</em>
':	<em>prior</em>
/:	<em>right</em>
\:	<em>left</em></pre>
</blockquote>

<h3>Redefinitions</h3>

<blockquote>
    <pre>	<strong>K</strong>		<strong>F</strong>
	-		-
$	format		state
\	scan		drop
/	over		take
!	enum		unquote
`	symbol		dip
'	each		quote
;	seperator	unique
:	dex		group
[	open apply	open list
]	close apply	close list
{	open lambda	queue -&gt; queue
}	close lambda	queue -&gt; stack
(	open expr	stack -&gt; queue
)	close expr	stack -&gt; stack
?	find		find/mod
@	at		where/flip
"	quotation	command/comment</pre>
</blockquote>

<h2>9. G</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.nsl.com/k/f/g.k">G</a> variant of F implements the adverbs of K as primitives.</p>

<blockquote>
    <pre>09*-		int		123 -&gt; 123
09*.09*-	float		123.45 -&gt; 123.45

az.AZ*		name		myName -&gt; value or null
az*-AZ*		shuffle		10 20 ab-ba -&gt; 20 10

[..]		list		[10 + [3 a]] -&gt; [10 + [3 a]]

+		add		1 2 + -&gt; 3
-		sub		2 3 - -&gt; 1
*		mul		3 4 * -&gt; 12
%		div		5 3 % -&gt; 1.666667
^		power		2 3 ^ -&gt; 8
_		floor		3.2 _ -&gt; 3

=		equal		2 2 = -&gt; 1
&gt;		more		4 6 &gt; -&gt; 0
&amp;		and/min		4 3 &amp; -&gt; 3

~		match		[1 2][1 2] ~ -&gt; 1

#		shape		[1 2 3] # -&gt; [3]

|		reverse		[1 2 3] | -&gt; [3 2 1]

@		where		[0 1 1 0 1] @ -&gt; [1 2 4]
@		flip		[[1 2 3][4 5 6]] @ -&gt; [[1 4][2 5][3 6]]

(		take		2[1 2 3] ( -&gt; [1 2]
(		reshape		[3 2][1 2 3] ( -&gt; [[1 2][3 1][2 3]]

)		drop		2[1 2 3] ) -&gt; [3]
)		cut		[0 2][1 2 3] ) -&gt; [[1 2][3]]
)		rotate		[1 2 3 4] 2 ) -&gt; [3 4 1 2]

?		find		[10 20 30] 20 ? -&gt; 1
?		mod		2 [3 4 5] ? -&gt; [1 0 1]

}		unique		[10 20 10 10 30] } -&gt; [10 20 30]
{		group		[10 20 10 10 30] { -&gt; [[0 2 3][1][4]]

&lt;		enum		3 &lt; -&gt; [0 1 2]
&lt;		upgrade		[10 30 20] &lt; -&gt; [0 2 1]

.		infra		1 2 [[2 3 +]] . 3 4 -&gt; 1 2 [5] 3 4
.		index		[[1 2 3][[1 0]]] . -&gt; [2 1]
.		monad		[[1 2 3][[1 0]][-1*]] . -&gt; [-1 -2 3]
.		dyad		[[1 2 3][[1 0]]+[3 8]] . -&gt; [9 5 3]

!		unquote		2 [3 +] ! -&gt; 5
'		quote		'+ -&gt; [+]

,		join  		[1][2 3] , -&gt; [1 2 3]

$		state		1 2 3 '\ $ 4 5 6 -&gt; 4 5 6 1 2 3

/		over		3 [1 2 3]'+/ -&gt; 9
\		under		3 [1 2 3]'+\ -&gt; [3 4 6 9]

:		each		[[[1 2][3 4 5]]][!#]: -&gt; ['2 '3]
;		prior		[1 3 2 4]'-; -&gt; [2 -1 2]

`		s -&gt; s		stack-&gt;stack pattern</pre>
</blockquote>

<p><em>dip</em> is defined:</p>

<blockquote><pre>[[[a b][b!a]]`!]                dip
</pre></blockquote>

<p>The <em>each-right</em> and <em>each-left</em> adverbs are defined:</p>

<blockquote><pre>[[unit!]dip!:popd!]             right
[swapd![swap!]swap!,right!]     left
</pre></blockquote>

<p id="copyright">Copyright (c) 2006-7, Stevan Apter. All Rights
Reserved.</p>


</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ilya Sutskever starts Safe Superintelligence Inc (1118 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ssi.inc</link>
            <guid>40730156</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 17:06:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ssi.inc">https://ssi.inc</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40730156">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent">
  
    <p><b>Superintelligence is within reach.</b></p>
  <p>Building safe superintelligence (SSI) is the most important technical problem of our​​ time.</p>
  <p>We have started the world’s first straight-shot SSI lab, with one goal and one product: a safe superintelligence.</p>
  <p>It’s called Safe Superintelligence Inc.</p>
  <p>SSI is our mission, our name, and our entire product roadmap, because it is our sole focus. Our team, investors, and business model are all aligned to achieve SSI.</p>
  <p>We approach safety and capabilities in tandem, as technical problems to be solved through revolutionary engineering and scientific breakthroughs. We plan to advance capabilities as fast as possible while making sure our safety always remains ahead.</p>
  <p>This way, we can scale in peace.</p>
  <p>Our singular focus means no distraction by management overhead or product cycles, and our business model means safety, security, and progress are all insulated from short-term commercial pressures. </p>
  <p>We are an American company with offices in Palo Alto and Tel Aviv, where we have deep roots and the ability to recruit top technical talent.</p>
  <p>We are assembling a lean, cracked team of the world’s best engineers and researchers dedicated to focusing on SSI and nothing else. </p>
  <p>If that’s you, we offer an opportunity to do your life’s work and help solve the most important technical challenge of our age.</p>
  <div><p>Now is the time. Join us.
  </p></div><p>Ilya Sutskever, Daniel Gross, Daniel Levy</p>
  <p>June 19, 2024</p>
  
  
  <p><a href="https://ssi.inc/contact">Contact</a>

  
  </p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[1/25-scale Cray C90 wristwatch (361 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://www.chrisfenton.com/1-25-scale-cray-c90-wristwatch/</link>
            <guid>40729906</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 16:40:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://www.chrisfenton.com/1-25-scale-cray-c90-wristwatch/">http://www.chrisfenton.com/1-25-scale-cray-c90-wristwatch/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40729906">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section id="content">
		<main id="main" role="main">
					
			
<article id="post-842" class="page">

	
	<!-- .entry-header -->

	<div>

		
<figure><a href="http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/j90_watch.jpg"><img width="800" height="775" src="http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/j90_watch.jpg" alt="" srcset="http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/j90_watch.jpg 800w, http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/j90_watch-300x291.jpg 300w, http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/j90_watch-768x744.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px"></a><figcaption>“Ah, it’s time to order a more practical watch!”</figcaption></figure>



<p>Welcome to the latest edition of my on-going series in Cray-related computational necromancy. This was another just-for-fun project. Over the many years Andras and I have been working on our Cray revival efforts, there has always been a big lag between our available software (and <a href="https://www.modularcircuits.com/blog/articles/the-cray-files/">Andras’ amazing simulator</a>) and my FPGA-compatible Verilog implementation. My free time and interests have oscillated wildly over the years, and implementing and debugging hardware is generally everything-intensive. My original cycle-accurate (but buggy) Cray-1 RTL gradually morphed first into a binary-compatible, but less-accurate Cray X-MP (which is mostly just a Cray-1 with 24-bit addresses instead of 22-bit), and finally into a binary-compatible and not-at-all cycle-accurate Cray Y-MP/C90/J90 core (which is mostly just a Cray-1 with 32-bit addresses). During the final transition, it got a full re-write in System Verilog and a vast simplification in the hopes I’ll someday actually be able to boot up UNICOS on it. That hasn’t quite happened yet, but it’s far enough along that I felt it was ready to play around with and make it into a ‘real’ project. What to do with this? A Cray Wristwatch, of course!</p>



<p>A benefit of the extremely slow pace and long duration of my Cray-related work is the ongoing march of Moore’s law in the background. Very capable FPGA boards are now cheaper and smaller, and it seemed time to give another scale model Cray Supercomputer a shot. As I mentioned, this one isn’t quite as cycle-accurate (or CPU-count accurate), but I’m still quite happy with how it turned out. </p>



<h3>But . . . Why??</h3>



<p>I had a tiny Cray supercomputer and a round OLED display just looking for a project, and a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cray_C90">Cray C916</a> just happens to be the right shape for the supercomputer wristwatch you’ve always dreamed about. If you wanted something practical, go read someone else’s blog.</p>



<h3>How is this different from the Cray-1?</h3>



<p>The Cray “Parallel Vector Processor” (PVP) line that extended from the Cray-1A in 1976 all the way to the final <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cray_X1">Cray X1E</a> in 2005 really did maintain quite a bit of compatibility. The main differences between them were the extension from 22 address bits with the original Cray-1 to 24 bits with the X-MP and 32 bits with the X-MP/EA and Y-MP machines. As Cray PVP machines are only 64-bit word addressable (bytes? what are those?), 32-bit addresses give you access to a respectable 32 gigabytes of memory. </p>



<p>Later machines also switched from 64-bit “Cray” floating point to IEEE double-precision 64-bit floating point and added a ‘bit matrix multiply’ functional unit, but aside from that there were architecturally few differences across ~30 years of development. So programming my Cray J90 core is pretty much identical to the Cray-1, ignoring the address widths (this means the actual Address Registers were extended from 24 bits on the Cray-1 to 32-bits in my J90 core). </p>



<p>This was a from-scratch re-write with the intent of it being both debuggable and maintainable by me though, so I changed quite a few of the micro-architectural details with those goals in mind. Vector chaining is gone, the vector registers are now implemented in a big 2R1W SRAM, and the instruction cache maps much more nicely to the available block RAMs in my FPGA. Generally cleaner, simpler, and a little slower (but I did manage to get the clock all the way up to the 105 MHz that the real J90 ran at!). </p>



<h3>System Architecture</h3>



<p>The heart of the system is a <a href="https://store.digilentinc.com/cmod-a7-breadboardable-artix-7-fpga-module/">Diligent CMOD-A7 FPGA board</a>. The FPGA contains the Cray CPU core running at a respectable 105 MHz (actually matching the clock speed of the J90, although still fairly far from the 244 MHz of the real C90), a few KW of SRAM and a pair of DMA channels connected to a SPI interface via FIFOs. A Teensy 3.6 microcontroller serves as the ‘Front-End’ processor, and controls the reset signals and the SPI interface going to the J90. It also drives a neato circular OLED display I picked up (the previous generation of <a href="https://4dsystems.com.au/products/featured-products/pixxilcd-13p2">this one</a>, I think). In practice, the Teensy dead-starts the J90 by initializing its memory via SPI and taking it out of reset, and then it just dumps frames of data from the J90 DMA engine, converts them to an appropriately formatted image and dumps them to the display.</p>



<h3>Software</h3>



<p>My work with supercomputers both modern and historical has made me quite fond of N-body gravity simulations – to show off the vector prowess of my J90 core, my wristwatch runs a full n-body simulation of Jupiter and 63 of its moons. That’s right! Each body gravitationally interacts with all 63 other bodies. Remarkably, through effective use of vector registers, the whole simulation requires only 127 carefully-chosen instructions, and is able to sustain 40 MFLOPS!</p>



<p>As I still don’t really have a proper development environment, I first wrote my program in Python using some simple primitives mimicking the Cray vector instructions. I then modified that to spit out some simple machine code, and ran it on my RTL simulator verify that nothing blew up numerically. At that point I was able to boot it on the real FPGA board and run it for a few hours to verify the stability.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="756" height="655" src="http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/IMG_1428.png" alt="" srcset="http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/IMG_1428.png 756w, http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/IMG_1428-300x260.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 756px) 100vw, 756px"></figure>



<h3>But how do you tell the time?</h3>



<p>With great difficulty. The display shows a free-running simulation of Jupiter and 63 of its moons. For convenience, I just plot the X/Y coordinates of each moon in the ecliptic plane. The ephemerides come from the <a href="https://ssd.jpl.nasa.gov/horizons.cgi">HORIZONS</a> server that NASA operates, at a specified date and time. The J90 just dumps a new frame whenever the Teensy has pulled the previous one, so with a <em>teensy</em> (ha!) bit of calibration on the micro controller side, it would be pretty easy to have the frames dumped in ‘real time’, which, knowing the starting time and date, would allow you to not-at-all-easily infer the current time by looking at the positions of Jupiter’s moons. Which is exactly what I was going for with my Supercomputer Wristwatch – using it should be as incomprehensible as my motivation for creating it in the first place!</p>



<h3>Why a C90?</h3>



<figure><a href="http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/cray_c90.jpg"><img loading="lazy" width="250" height="283" src="http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/cray_c90.jpg" alt=""></a><figcaption>A 25:1 Replica of my wristwatch</figcaption></figure>



<p>Although it does maintain binary compatibility, the real Cray Y-MP C916 was a 244 MHz, 16-CPU monster – my 1/25-scale version is a mere single-CPU running at 105 MHz (and lacks other performance enhancements like dual-issue vector pipelines) . . . this model was mostly chosen because of the convenient circular dome in the middle that could hold my nifty OLED watch face. </p>



<p>I designed the model and built it with a 3D printer, carefully trimmed my circuit boards to fit, mounted the display, and still had enough room for a battery left over. </p>



<h2>The Final Product</h2>



<p>I love how this project turned out – it’s adorable, it’s programmable, and it pushes the boundaries of uselessness and complexity. The final case can accommodate a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Watch_strap">NATO-style wrist strap </a> and has a built-in battery charger, but in practice it makes a better desk novelty than a watch. </p>



<figure><a href="http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/trimmed_boards.jpg"><img loading="lazy" width="640" height="853" src="http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/trimmed_boards.jpg" alt="" srcset="http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/trimmed_boards.jpg 640w, http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/trimmed_boards-225x300.jpg 225w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px"></a><figcaption>The final (very trimmed down) board</figcaption></figure>



<figure><a href="http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/j90_underside.jpg"><img loading="lazy" width="640" height="853" src="http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/j90_underside.jpg" alt="" srcset="http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/j90_underside.jpg 640w, http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/j90_underside-225x300.jpg 225w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px"></a><figcaption>A densely packed C90.</figcaption></figure>



<figure><a href="http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/j90_complete.jpg"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="1016" src="http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/j90_complete-1024x1016.jpg" alt="" srcset="http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/j90_complete-1024x1016.jpg 1024w, http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/j90_complete-300x298.jpg 300w, http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/j90_complete-150x150.jpg 150w, http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/j90_complete-768x762.jpg 768w, http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/j90_complete-1536x1524.jpg 1536w, http://www.chrisfenton.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/j90_complete.jpg 1991w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a><figcaption>The final product</figcaption></figure>

		
	</div><!-- .entry-content -->

</article>

<!-- #comments -->
		
		</main><!-- #main -->
	</section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The return of pneumatic tubes (129 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.technologyreview.com/2024/06/19/1093446/pneumatic-tubes-hospitals/</link>
            <guid>40729809</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 16:30:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2024/06/19/1093446/pneumatic-tubes-hospitals/">https://www.technologyreview.com/2024/06/19/1093446/pneumatic-tubes-hospitals/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40729809">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div> <p>Pneumatic tubes were touted as something that would revolutionize the world. In science fiction, they were envisioned as a fundamental part of the future—even in dystopias like <a href="https://archive.org/details/nineteeneightyfo0000unse_d3d1/page/38/mode/2up?view=theater&amp;q=pneumatic">George Orwell’s <em>1984</em></a>, where the main character, Winston Smith, sits in a room peppered with pneumatic tubes that spit out orders for him to alter previously published news stories and historical records to fit the ruling party’s changing narrative. &nbsp;</p> <div> <figure><img src="https://wp.technologyreview.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/2CTK80D.jpg?w=1999" alt="Doctor holding pneumatic tube carrier while standing in pharmacy"><figcaption>Abandoned by most industries at midcentury, pneumatic tube systems have become ubiquitous in hospitals.</figcaption><p>ALAMY</p> </figure> </div> <p>In real life, the tubes were expected to transform several industries in the late 19th century through the mid-20th. “The possibilities of compressed air are not fully realized in this country,” declared an 1890 article in the <em>New York Tribune</em>. “The pneumatic tube system of communication is, of course, in use in many of the downtown stores, in newspaper offices […] but there exists a great deal of ignorance about the use of compressed air, even among engineering <a href="https://www.newspapers.com/article/the-kansas-city-star-possibilities-of-th/144128367/">experts</a>.”</p> </div><div> <p>Pneumatic tube technology involves moving a cylindrical carrier or capsule through a series of tubes with the aid of a blower that pushes or pulls it into motion. For a while, the United States took up the systems with gusto. Retail stores and banks were especially interested in their potential to move money more efficiently: “Besides this saving of time to the customer the store is relieved of all the annoying bustle and confusion of boys running for cash on the various retail floors,” one 1882 article in the<em> Boston Globe</em> reported. The benefit to the owner, of course, was reduced labor costs, <a href="https://www.newspapers.com/article/the-boston-globe-american-pneumatic-comp/144127475/">with tube manufacturers claiming</a> that stores would see a return on their investment within a year. &nbsp;</p>  <p>“The motto of the company is to substitute machines for men and for children as carriers, in every possible way,” a <a href="https://www.newspapers.com/image/430870427/?fcfToken=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJmcmVlLXZpZXctaWQiOjQzMDg3MDQyNywiaWF0IjoxNzEyMjY5OTM5LCJleHAiOjE3MTIzNTYzMzl9.buThdlwwE6wKNKm8fzeNXbMddLadhWM5xEXWYpR7M3g&amp;terms=motto&amp;match=2&amp;clipping_id=144127475">1914 <em>Boston Globe</em></a> article said about Lamson Service, one of the largest proprietors of tubes at the time, adding, “[President] Emeritus Charles W. Eliot of Harvard says: ‘No man should be employed at a task which a machine can perform,’ and the Lamson Company supplements that statement by this: ‘Because it doesn’t pay.’”</p> 
 <p>By 1912, Lamson had over 60,000 customers globally in sectors including retail, banks, insurance offices, courtrooms, libraries, hotels, and industrial plants. The postal service in cities such as Boston, Philadelphia, Chicago, and New York also used tubes to deliver the mail, with at least 45 miles of Lamson tubing in place by 1912.</p> </div><div> <p>On the transportation front, <a href="https://daily.jstor.org/pneumatic-subway/">New York City’s first attempt at a subway system, in 1870</a>, also ran on a pneumatic system, and the idea of using tubes to move people continues to beguile innovators to this day. (See Elon Musk’s largely abandoned Hyperloop concept of the 2010s.)</p> 
 <p>But by the mid to late 20th century, use of the technology had largely fallen by the wayside. It had become cheaper to transport mail by truck than by tube, and as transactions moved to credit cards, there was less demand to make change for cash payments. Electrical rail won out over compressed air, paper records and files disappeared in the wake of digitization, and tubes at bank drive-throughs started being replaced by ATMs, while only a fraction of pharmacies used them for their own such services. Pneumatic tube technology became virtually obsolete.</p>  <p>Except in hospitals.&nbsp;</p>  <p>“A pneumatic tube system today for a new hospital that’s being built is ubiquitous. It’s like putting a washing machine or a central AC system in a new home. It just makes too much sense to not do it,” says Cory Kwarta, CEO of Swisslog Healthcare, a corporation that—under its TransLogic company—has provided pneumatic tube systems in health-care facilities for over 50 years. And while the sophistication of these systems has changed over time, the fundamental technology of using pneumatic force to move a capsule from one destination to another has remained the same.&nbsp;</p>  <p>By the turn of the 20th century, health care had become a more scientific endeavor, and different spaces within a hospital were designated for new technologies (like x-rays) or specific procedures (like surgeries). “Instead of having patients in one place, with the doctors and the nurses and everything coming to them, and it’s all happening in the ward, [hospitals] became a bunch of different parts that each had a role,” explains Jeanne Kisacky, an architectural historian who wrote <a href="https://jeannekisacky.com/rise-of-the-modern-hospital/book-rise-of-the-modern-hospital-an-architectural-history-of-health-and-healing/"><em>Rise of the Modern Hospital: An Architectural History of Health and Healing, 1870–1940</em></a><em>.&nbsp;</em></p> </div><div> <p>Designating different parts of a building for different medical specialties and services, like specimen analysis, also increased the physical footprint of health-care facilities. The result was that nurses and doctors had to spend much of their days moving from one department to another, which was an inefficient use of their time. Pneumatic tube technology provided a solution.</p>  <p>By the 1920s, more and more hospitals started installing tube systems. At first, the capsules primarily <a href="https://archive.org/details/sim_modern-hospital_1929-12_33_6/page/68/mode/2up?q=%22pneumatic+tube%22">moved medical records</a>, prescription orders, and items like <a href="https://archive.org/details/sim_modern-hospital_1930-11_35_5/page/88/mode/2up?q=%22pneumatic+tube%22">money and receipts</a>—similar cargo to what was moved around in banks and retail stores at the time. <a href="https://archive.org/details/sim_modern-hospital_1927-11_29_5/page/104/mode/2up?q=%22pneumatic+tube%22&amp;view=theater">As early as 1927</a>, however, the systems were also marketed to hospitals as a way to transfer specimens to a central laboratory for analysis.&nbsp;</p> </div><div><div> <figure><img src="https://wp.technologyreview.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/GettyImages-1457963603.jpg?w=2001" alt="&quot;&quot;"><figcaption>Two men stand among the 2,000 pneumatic tube canisters in the basement of the Lexington Avenue Post Office in New York City, circa 1915.</figcaption><p>GETTY IMAGES</p> </figure> </div><div> <figure><img src="https://wp.technologyreview.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/GettyImages-3373364.jpg?w=2000" alt="two people reading a note at a table"><figcaption>In 1955, clubbers at the Reni Ballroom in Berlin exchanged requests for dances via pneumatic tube in a sort of precursor to texting.</figcaption><p>GETTY IMAGES</p> </figure> </div></div><div><div> <figure><img src="https://wp.technologyreview.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/Smithsonian1.jpg?w=2764" alt="&quot;&quot;"><figcaption>In the late 1940s and ’50s, canisters like this one, traveling at around 35 miles an hour, carried as many as 600 letters daily throughout New York City.</figcaption><p>SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTE</p> </figure> </div><div> <figure><img src="https://wp.technologyreview.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/Pevco-smart-path1-pneumatic-tube1.jpg?w=918" alt="system of tubes"><figcaption>The Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania traffics nearly 4,000 specimens daily through its pneumatic tubes.</figcaption><p>COURTESY OF PERELMAN SCHOOL OF MEDICINE/UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA HEALTH SYSTEM</p> </figure> </div></div><div> <p>By the 1960s, pneumatic tubes were becoming standard in health care. As a hospital administrator explained in the January 1960 issue of <a href="https://archive.org/details/sim_modern-hospital_1960-01_94_1/page/86/mode/2up?q=%22pneumatic+tube%22"><em>Modern Hospital</em></a>, “We are now getting eight hours’ worth of service per day from each nurse, where previously we had been getting about six hours of nursing plus two hours of errand running.”</p>  <p>As computers and credit cards started to become more prevalent in the 1980s, reducing paperwork significantly, the systems shifted to mostly carrying lab specimens, pharmaceuticals, and blood products. Today, lab specimens are roughly 60% of what hospital tube systems carry; pharmaceuticals account for 30%, and blood products for phlebotomy make up 5%.</p> 

 <p>The carriers or capsules, which can hold up to five pounds, move through piping six inches in diameter—just big enough to hold a 2,000-milliliter IV bag—at speeds of 18 to 24 feet per second, or roughly 12 to 16 miles per hour. The carriers are limited to those speeds to maintain specimen <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6051325/">integrity</a>. If blood samples move faster, for example, blood cells can be destroyed.</p>  <p>The pneumatic systems have also gone through major changes in structure in recent years, evolving from fixed routes to networked systems. “It’s like a train system, and you’re on one track and now you have to go to another track,” says Steve Dahl, an executive vice president at Pevco, a manufacturer of these systems.</p> <div> <figure><img src="https://wp.technologyreview.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/GettyImages-3376933.jpg?w=2667" alt="illustration of people waiting to ride the tube"><figcaption>Exhibition-goers wait to ride the first pneumatic passenger railway in the US at the Exhibition of the American Institute at the New York City Armory in 1867. </figcaption><p>GETTY IMAGES</p> </figure> </div> <p>Manufacturers try to get involved early in the hospital design process, says Swisslog’s Kwarta, so “we can talk to the clinical users and say, ‘Hey, what kind of contents do you anticipate sending through this pneumatic tube system, based on your bed count, based on your patient census, and from where and to where do these specimens or materials need to go?’”</p>  <p>Penn Medicine’s University City Medical District in Philadelphia opened up the state-of-the-art Pavilion in 2021. It has three pneumatic systems: the main one is for items directly related to health care, like specimens, and two separate ones handle linen and trash. The main system runs over 12 miles of pipe and completes more than 6,000 transactions on an average day. Sending a capsule between the two farthest points of the system—a distance of multiple city blocks—takes just under five minutes. Walking that distance would take around 20 minutes, not including getting to the floor where the item needs to go.&nbsp;</p> </div><div><p>Michigan Medicine has a system dedicated solely for use in nuclear medicine, which relies on radioactive materials for treatment. Getting the materials where they need to go is a five- to eight-minute walk—too long given their short shelf life. With the tubes, it gets there—in a lead-lined capsule—in less than a minute.&nbsp;</p>  <p>Steven Fox, who leads the electrical engineering team for the pneumatic tubes at Michigan Medicine, describes the scale of the materials his system moves in terms of African elephants, which weigh about six tons. “We try to keep [a carrier’s] load to five pounds apiece,” he says. “So we could probably transport about 30,000 pounds per day. That’s two and a half African elephants that we transport from one side of the hospital to the other every day.”</p>  <p>The equipment to maintain these labyrinthian highways is vast. Michigan and Penn have between 150 and 200 stations where doctors, nurses, and technicians can pick up a capsule or send one off. Keeping those systems moving also requires around 30 blowers and over 150 transfer units to shift carriers to different tube lines as needed. At Michigan Medicine, moving an item from one end of the system to another requires 20 to 25 pieces of equipment.</p>  <p>Before the turn of the century, triggering the blower to move a capsule from point A to point B would be accomplished by someone turning or pressing an electronic or magnetic switch. In the 2000s, technicians managed the systems on DOS; these days, the latest systems run on programs that monitor every capsule in real time and allow adjustments based on the level of traffic, the priority level of a capsule, and the demand for additional carriers. The systems run 24 hours a day, every day.&nbsp;</p> 
 <p>“We treat [the tube system] no different than electricity, steam, water, gas. It’s a utility,” says Frank Connelly, an assistant hospital director at Penn. “Without that, you can’t provide services to people that need it in a hospital.”</p>  <p>“You’re nervous—you just got blood taken,” he continues. “‘How long is it going to be before I get my results back?’ Imagine if they had to wait all that extra time because you’re not sending one person for every vial—they’re going to wait awhile until they get a basket full and then walk to the lab. Nowadays they fill up the tube and send it to the lab. And I think that helps patient care.”&nbsp;</p>  <p><em>Vanessa Armstrong is a freelance writer whose work has appeared in the&nbsp;</em>New York Times<em>,&nbsp;</em>Atlas Obscura<em>,&nbsp;</em>Travel + Leisure<em>, and elsewhere.</em>&nbsp; </p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>