<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:30:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AI Demos by Meta (157 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://aidemos.meta.com/</link>
            <guid>42992643</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 18:49:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://aidemos.meta.com/">https://aidemos.meta.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42992643">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Blog If Nobody Reads It? (231 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://andysblog.uk/why-blog-if-nobody-reads-it/</link>
            <guid>42992159</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 17:50:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://andysblog.uk/why-blog-if-nobody-reads-it/">https://andysblog.uk/why-blog-if-nobody-reads-it/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42992159">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    

    
        
    

    
        

        <p>
            <i>
                <time datetime="2025-02-05T08:13Z">
                    05 Feb, 2025
                </time>
            </i>
        </p>
    

    <p>Back in the day, advertising legend Bill Bernbach said, “The most powerful element in advertising is the truth.”</p>
<p>Let’s tell the truth, then: Nobody reads your blog.</p>
<p>At least, not as many as you’d like. Maybe a handful, maybe none. You pour your thoughts into it, craft each sentence, pick the right image — then silence. No likes, no shares, no engagement.</p>
<p>So what’s the point?</p>
<p>There’s two lies we tell ourselves:</p>
<ol>
<li><em>If I write it, they will come.</em> They won’t. There are billions of blog posts out there. The internet is an infinite void, and your blog is a whisper in a hurricane.</li>
<li>If nobody reads it, it’s a waste of time.</li>
</ol>
<p>Is it, though?</p>
<p>There is a hidden value in blogging.
There’s an old Zen saying: “Chop wood, carry water.” You do it not for the applause but because it needs doing.</p>
<p>Blogging forces clarity. It makes you structure your thoughts, sharpen your perspective. You stop writing fluff because — let’s be honest — you’re writing for yourself. And if you can’t keep yourself interested, nobody else stands a chance.</p>
<p>When you write, you think better. When you think better, you create better.</p>
<p>So, who’s there real audience?</p>
<p>You’re not just writing for today’s invisible audience. You’re writing for:</p>
<ul>
<li>Future you. Your posts become a time capsule of your evolving mind.</li>
<li>One right person. Maybe one day, someone stumbles across your words at exactly the right moment. And that changes something for them.</li>
<li>The work itself. Consistency beats virality. A hundred posts with depth will outlast a single viral hit.</li>
</ul>
<p>And there’s another thing. My other passion is street photography. Which is a bit like blogging.</p>
<p>You walk through the city, camera in hand. You see a scene — a moment of light, shadow, humanity. You capture it.</p>
<p>Nobody cares.</p>
<p>But that’s not why you did it. You did it because you saw something.</p>
<p>Like blogging. You write because you think, because you observe, because you need to put it somewhere.</p>
<p>If someone reads it? Bonus. If not? The work still got done.</p>
<p>And that’s the real point.</p>


    

    
        
            <p>
                
                    <a href="https://andysblog.uk/blog/?q=blogging">#blogging</a>
                
                    <a href="https://andysblog.uk/blog/?q=writing">#writing</a>
                
            </p>
        

        
            


        
    


  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[UnitedHealth Is Sick of Everyone Complaining About Its Claim Denials (132 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.rollingstone.com/culture/culture-news/unitedhealth-defends-image-claim-denials-mangione-thompson-1235259054/</link>
            <guid>42992121</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 17:43:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/culture/culture-news/unitedhealth-defends-image-claim-denials-mangione-thompson-1235259054/">https://www.rollingstone.com/culture/culture-news/unitedhealth-defends-image-claim-denials-mangione-thompson-1235259054/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42992121">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

		

		


<p>Two months after UnitedHealthcare's CEO was murdered, the insurer is moving to protect its image    </p>
	</div><div><p>
	Two months after the <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/culture/culture-news/unitedhealthcare-ceo-shooting-details-emerge-everything-to-know-1235193146/">killing</a> of <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/t/unitedhealthcare/">UnitedHealthcare</a> CEO Brian Thompson sent shockwaves through the <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/politics/political-commentary/luigi-mangione-unitedhealthcare-health-care-scam-1235214858/">much-reviled U.S. health insurance industry</a>, the company’s parent, UnitedHealth Group, is making aggressive moves to protect its image.</p>



<p>
	Responding to a slew of attacks online, often coupled with the glorification of <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/t/luigi-mangione/">Luigi Mangione</a> (who was charged with Thompson’s murder outside a Midtown Manhattan hotel in December, and allegedly wrote a short manifesto calling health insurers “parasites”), the company has hired a law firm that specializes in defamation cases. Clare Locke, the Virginia-based practice, previously represented Dominion Voting Systems in a bombshell defamation suit that saw Fox News pay a settlement of <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/politics/politics-news/foxs-primetime-hosts-dominion-settlement-1234717513/">$787.5 million</a> for airing false allegations about the company’s supposed role in voter fraud during the 2020 election.</p>



<p>
	UnitedHealth appears eager to make a similar example of Elisabeth Potter, an Austin, Texas, plastic surgeon, and is accusing the doctor of “using her social media following to perpetuate inaccuracies, which is irresponsible, unethical and dangerous.” On Jan. 7, Potter posted a <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DEid-1npNbA/?hl=en" rel="nofollow" target="_blank">video</a> on <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/t/instagram/">Instagram</a> sharing her frustration with the U.S. insurance system, explaining in a text caption that during a procedure, “I was interrupted by a call from United Healthcare — while the patient was already asleep on the operating table. They demanded information about her diagnosis and inpatient stay justification. I had to scrub out mid-surgery to call United, only to find that the person on the line didn’t even have access to the patient’s full medical information, despite the procedure already being pre-approved.” 

	</p>




<p>
	“It’s beyond frustrating and, frankly, unacceptable,” Potter continued. “We should be focused on care, not bureaucracy.” The comments were rife with fury at UniteHealthcare and for-profit health insurance more broadly. “Luigi for President,” wrote one person, while another put in, “One day these health insurance companies will be dead.” 


</p><section>
			

	<h2 id="section-heading">

	
		Editor’s picks
	
	</h2>

	
	
</section>




<p>
	Days later, according to reporting from <em><a href="https://news.bloomberglaw.com/business-and-practice/unitedhealth-hires-defamation-firm-to-counter-social-media-posts" rel="nofollow" target="_blank">Bloomberg</a></em>, Potter’s attorney received a letter from Clare Locke instructing her to amend the post, apologize, and disavow threats of violence that UnitedHealth claimed had stemmed from the video. But Potter’s legal counsel, Jessica Underwood, has said that there is nothing inaccurate in the video that needs correcting. “Dr. Potter will not be silenced by UnitedHealthcare’s attempts to threaten and harass her,” Underwood has said. The company, meanwhile, has argued that “Dr. Potter’s claims that she was called out of surgery are false.” Potter’s Instagram video remains up on the platform, where it has received more than 350,000 likes.

	</p>




<p>
	Elsewhere, UnitedHealth took measures to prevent the dissemination of internal data about its denials of customer claims. (UnitedHealth Group’s individual market plans are known to have one of the <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.startribune.com/unitedhealth-group-two-blues-plans-had-highest-denial-rates-for-aca-health-plans-in-2023/601212605" target="_blank">highest denial rates</a> among all U.S. insurers, a fact that received much media attention in the wake of Thompson’s death.) As <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.levernews.com/amazon-and-unitedhealths-inaugural-demands-post/" target="_blank">The Lever reported</a>, a day after <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/t/donald-trump/">President Donald Trump</a>‘s inauguration in January, UnitedHealth submitted a <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.sec.gov/files/corpfin/no-action/14a-8/muellerunitedhealth12125-14a8inc.pdf" target="_blank">letter</a> to the Securities and Exchange Commission asking for approval to block a shareholder proposal that it use a third-party auditor to assess “previous customer denial claims, particularly where a death was involved, to determine if denial letters included factually incorrect and insensitive information.” In cases where this outside analyst determined that a coverage claim should not have been denied, the proposal says, those individuals and family members affected are to be sent an apology letter hand-signed by both a UnitedHealth executive and a member of the company’s board of directors.</p>



<p>
	UnitedHealth’s rationale for refusing a vote on such a policy, as its legal team wrote in the letter, is that the proposal was not submitted before “the applicable deadline.”</p>



<p>
	Then, on Jan. 31, the insurer sent a <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.sec.gov/files/corpfin/no-action/14a-8/durocherunitedhealth13125-14a8inc.pdf" target="_blank">second letter</a> to the SEC, seeking to prevent a shareholder vote on another proposal related to its claim denials. This proposal, if passed by investors, would recommend that UnitedHealth “evaluate how company practices impact access to <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/t/health-care/" id="auto-tag_health-care" data-tag="health-care">health care</a> and patient outcomes, including analyses of how often prior authorization requirements or denials of coverage lead to delay or abandonment of medical treatment and serious adverse events for patients.” The report produced through this review is also intended to encompass “the public health-related costs and macroeconomic risks created by the company’s practices that limit or delay access to health care.”


</p><section>
			

	<h2 id="section-heading">

	
		Related Content
	
	</h2>

	
	
</section>




<p>
	In their letter, UniteHealth rejected the notion of putting this proposal to a shareholder vote because it is “vague and indefinite,” and, it argued, an attempt to “impermissibly micromanage” the company.</p>



<p>
	The insurance giant’s attempts to police social media chatter about its business practices and its overtures to Trump’s SEC dovetailed earlier this week when hedge fund billionaire <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/culture/culture-news/bill-ackman-wife-guy-harvard-claudine-gay-1234943020/">Bill Ackman</a> shared his opinion of the company’s future. “If I still shorted stocks, I would short United Healthcare,” he posted to X on Tuesday, adding that the SEC “should do a thorough investigation of the company.” He further mused, “I would not be surprised to find that the company’s profitability is massively overstated due to its denial of medically necessary procedures and patient care.” 

</p>



<p>
	Ackman later deleted the speculation, but UnitedHealth <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/ae98e904-748b-4012-b36f-b5c323de4317" rel="nofollow" target="_blank">flagged his comments to the SEC</a> for potential investigation. The company’s stock price dipped the following day, and ended the week about 2.7 percent lower than it was on Tuesday. “Health insurance has long been subject to significant regulatory oversight and earnings caps,” UnitedHealth said in a statement responding to the outspoken investor, one of many ultra-wealthy figures to back Trump in 2024 and post prolifically on social media about how only the MAGA movement could save the country. “Any claims that health insurers, which typically have low- to mid-single digit margins, can somehow over-earn are grossly uninformed about the structure and strong regulatory oversight of the sector,” the company noted.

	</p>




<p>
	All told, UnitedHealth is mounting a far stronger defense of its reputation than it two months ago, when Thompson’s slaying unleashed a flood of hostility that caught it somewhat off-guard. Now, the company looks like it’s prepared to grind it out as Mangione’s parallel state and federal trials get underway, with heated rhetoric likely to flare up once again.</p>
















</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[LIMO: Less Is More for Reasoning (215 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03387</link>
            <guid>42991676</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 16:33:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03387">https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03387</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42991676">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content-inner">
    
    
                
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2502.03387">View PDF</a>
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/html/2502.03387v1">HTML (experimental)</a></p><blockquote>
            <span>Abstract:</span>We present a fundamental discovery that challenges our understanding of how complex reasoning emerges in large language models. While conventional wisdom suggests that sophisticated reasoning tasks demand extensive training data (&gt;100,000 examples), we demonstrate that complex mathematical reasoning abilities can be effectively elicited with surprisingly few examples. Through comprehensive experiments, our proposed model LIMO demonstrates unprecedented performance in mathematical reasoning. With merely 817 curated training samples, LIMO achieves 57.1% accuracy on AIME and 94.8% on MATH, improving from previous SFT-based models' 6.5% and 59.2% respectively, while only using 1% of the training data required by previous approaches. LIMO demonstrates exceptional out-of-distribution generalization, achieving 40.5% absolute improvement across 10 diverse benchmarks, outperforming models trained on 100x more data, challenging the notion that SFT leads to memorization rather than generalization. Based on these results, we propose the Less-Is-More Reasoning Hypothesis (LIMO Hypothesis): In foundation models where domain knowledge has been comprehensively encoded during pre-training, sophisticated reasoning capabilities can emerge through minimal but precisely orchestrated demonstrations of cognitive processes. This hypothesis posits that the elicitation threshold for complex reasoning is determined by two key factors: (1) the completeness of the model's encoded knowledge foundation during pre-training, and (2) the effectiveness of post-training examples as "cognitive templates" that show the model how to utilize its knowledge base to solve complex reasoning tasks. To facilitate reproducibility and future research in data-efficient reasoning, we release LIMO as a comprehensive open-source suite at <a href="https://github.com/GAIR-NLP/LIMO" rel="external noopener nofollow">this https URL</a>.
    </blockquote>

    <!--CONTEXT-->
    
  </div><div>
      <h2>Submission history</h2><p> From: Zhen Huang [<a href="https://arxiv.org/show-email/43e4049b/2502.03387" rel="nofollow">view email</a>]      <br>    <strong>[v1]</strong>
        Wed, 5 Feb 2025 17:23:45 UTC (8,774 KB)<br>
</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Kanata: Cross-platform multi-layer keyboard remapper with advanced customization (107 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/jtroo/kanata</link>
            <guid>42991019</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 14:52:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata">https://github.com/jtroo/kanata</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42991019">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Kanata</h2><a id="user-content-kanata" aria-label="Permalink: Kanata" href="#kanata"></a></p>
<div dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/blob/main/assets/kanata-icon.svg"><img alt="Image of a keycap with the letter K on it in pink tones" title="Kanata" height="160" src="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/raw/main/assets/kanata-icon.svg"></a>
</h3><a id="user-content---" aria-label="Permalink: " href="#--"></a></div>
<p>
  Improve your keyboard comfort
</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What does this do?</h2><a id="user-content-what-does-this-do" aria-label="Permalink: What does this do?" href="#what-does-this-do"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This is a cross-platform software keyboard remapper for Linux, macOS and Windows.
A short summary of the features:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>multiple layers of key functionality</li>
<li>advanced key behaviour customization (e.g. tap-hold, macros, unicode)</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">To see all of the features, see the <a href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/blob/main/docs/config.adoc">configuration guide</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">You can find pre-built binaries in the <a href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/releases">releases page</a>
or read on for build instructions.</p>
<p dir="auto">You can see a <a href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/blob/main/docs/platform-known-issues.adoc">list of known issues here</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Demo</h3><a id="user-content-demo" aria-label="Permalink: Demo" href="#demo"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Demo video</h4><a id="user-content-demo-video" aria-label="Permalink: Demo video" href="#demo-video"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/6634136/183001314-f64a7e26-4129-4f20-bf26-7165a6e02c38.mp4" rel="nofollow">Showcase of multi-layer functionality (30s, 1.7 MB)</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Online simulator</h4><a id="user-content-online-simulator" aria-label="Permalink: Online simulator" href="#online-simulator"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">You can check out the <a href="https://jtroo.github.io/" rel="nofollow">online simulator</a>
to test configuration validity and test input simulation.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Why is this useful?</h2><a id="user-content-why-is-this-useful" aria-label="Permalink: Why is this useful?" href="#why-is-this-useful"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Imagine if, instead of pressing Shift to type uppercase letters, we had giant
keyboards with separate keys for lowercase and uppercase letters. I hope we can
all agree: that would be a terrible user experience!</p>
<p dir="auto">A way to think of how Shift keys work is that they switch your input to another
layer of functionality where you now type uppercase letters and symbols
instead of lowercase letters and numbers.</p>
<p dir="auto">What kanata allows you to do is take this alternate layer concept that Shift
keys have and apply it to any key. You can then customize what those layers do
to suit your exact needs and workflows.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h2><a id="user-content-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Usage" href="#usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Running kanata currently does not start it in a background process.
You will need to keep the window that starts kanata running to keep kanata active.
Some tips for running kanata in the background:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Windows: <a data-error-text="Failed to load title" data-id="4579845" data-permission-text="Title is private" data-url="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/discussions/193" data-hovercard-type="discussion" data-hovercard-url="/jtroo/kanata/discussions/193/hovercard" href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/discussions/193">#193</a></li>
<li>Linux: <a data-error-text="Failed to load title" data-id="4373258" data-permission-text="Title is private" data-url="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/discussions/130" data-hovercard-type="discussion" data-hovercard-url="/jtroo/kanata/discussions/130/hovercard?comment_id=10227272" href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/discussions/130#discussioncomment-10227272">#130 (reply in thread)</a></li>
<li>Run from tray icon: <a href="https://github.com/rszyma/kanata-tray">kanata-tray</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Pre-built executables</h3><a id="user-content-pre-built-executables" aria-label="Permalink: Pre-built executables" href="#pre-built-executables"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">See the
<a href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/releases">releases page</a>
for executables and instructions.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Build it yourself</h3><a id="user-content-build-it-yourself" aria-label="Permalink: Build it yourself" href="#build-it-yourself"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This project uses the latest Rust stable toolchain. If you installed the
Rust toolchain using <code>rustup</code>, e.g. by using the instructions from the
<a href="https://www.rust-lang.org/learn/get-started" rel="nofollow">official website</a>,
you can get the latest stable toolchain with <code>rustup update stable</code>.</p>
<details>
<summary>Instructions</summary>
<p dir="auto">Using <code>cargo install</code>:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="cargo install kanata

# On Linux and macOS, this may not work without `sudo`, see below
kanata --cfg <your_configuration_file>"><pre><code>cargo install kanata

# On Linux and macOS, this may not work without `sudo`, see below
kanata --cfg &lt;your_configuration_file&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Build and run yourself in Linux:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/jtroo/kanata &amp;&amp; cd kanata
cargo build   # --release optional, not really perf sensitive

# sudo is used because kanata opens /dev/ files
#
# See below if you want to avoid needing sudo:
# https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/wiki/Avoid-using-sudo-on-Linux
sudo target/debug/kanata --cfg <your_configuration_file>"><pre><code>git clone https://github.com/jtroo/kanata &amp;&amp; cd kanata
cargo build   # --release optional, not really perf sensitive

# sudo is used because kanata opens /dev/ files
#
# See below if you want to avoid needing sudo:
# https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/wiki/Avoid-using-sudo-on-Linux
sudo target/debug/kanata --cfg &lt;your_configuration_file&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Build and run yourself in Windows.</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/jtroo/kanata; cd kanata
cargo build   # --release optional, not really perf sensitive
target\debug\kanata --cfg <your_configuration_file>"><pre><code>git clone https://github.com/jtroo/kanata; cd kanata
cargo build   # --release optional, not really perf sensitive
target\debug\kanata --cfg &lt;your_configuration_file&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Build and run yourself in macOS:</p>
<p dir="auto">For macOS version 11 and newer: Install the <a href="https://github.com/pqrs-org/Karabiner-DriverKit-VirtualHIDDevice/blob/main/dist/Karabiner-DriverKit-VirtualHIDDevice-5.0.0.pkg">Karabiner VirtualHiDDevice Driver</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">To activate it:</p>
<p dir="auto"><code>/Applications/.Karabiner-VirtualHIDDevice-Manager.app/Contents/MacOS/Karabiner-VirtualHIDDevice-Manager activate</code></p>
<p dir="auto">For macOS version 10 and older:
Install the <a href="https://github.com/pqrs-org/Karabiner-VirtualHIDDevice">Karabiner kernel extension</a>.</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/jtroo/kanata &amp;&amp; cd kanata
cargo build   # --release optional, not really perf sensitive

# sudo is needed to gain permission to intercept the keyboard

sudo target/debug/kanata --cfg <your_configuration_file>"><pre><code>git clone https://github.com/jtroo/kanata &amp;&amp; cd kanata
cargo build   # --release optional, not really perf sensitive

# sudo is needed to gain permission to intercept the keyboard

sudo target/debug/kanata --cfg &lt;your_configuration_file&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">The full configuration guide is <a href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/blob/main/docs/config.adoc">found here</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Sample configuration files are found in <a href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/blob/main/cfg_samples">cfg_samples</a>. The
<a href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/blob/main/cfg_samples/simple.kbd">simple.kbd</a> file contains a basic configuration file
that is hopefully easy to understand but does not contain all features. The
<code>kanata.kbd</code> contains an example of all features with documentation. The
release assets also have a <code>kanata.kbd</code> file that is tested to work with that
release. All key names can be found in the <a href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/blob/main/src/keys/mod.rs">keys module</a>,
and you can also define your own key names.</p>
</details>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Feature flags</h3><a id="user-content-feature-flags" aria-label="Permalink: Feature flags" href="#feature-flags"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">When either building yourself or using <code>cargo install</code>,
you can add feature flags that
enable functionality that is turned off by default.</p>
<details>
<summary>Instructions</summary>
<p dir="auto">If you want to enable the <code>cmd</code> actions,
add the flag <code>--features cmd</code>.
For example:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="cargo build --release --features cmd
cargo install --features cmd"><pre><code>cargo build --release --features cmd
cargo install --features cmd
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">On Windows,
if you want to compile a binary that uses the Interception driver,
you should add the flag <code>--features interception_driver</code>.
For example:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="cargo build --release --features interception_driver
cargo install --features interception_driver"><pre><code>cargo build --release --features interception_driver
cargo install --features interception_driver
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">To combine multiple flags,
use a single <code>--features</code> flag
and use a comma to separate the features.
For example:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="cargo build --release --features cmd,interception_driver
cargo install --features cmd,interception_driver"><pre><code>cargo build --release --features cmd,interception_driver
cargo install --features cmd,interception_driver
</code></pre></div>
</details>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Other installation methods</h2><a id="user-content-other-installation-methods" aria-label="Permalink: Other installation methods" href="#other-installation-methods"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://repology.org/project/kanata/versions" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/aef8ac9aeb0281c0151e86b957de11ecc4d7e8836c58999b8020744f6f22a3bc/68747470733a2f2f7265706f6c6f67792e6f72672f62616467652f766572746963616c2d616c6c7265706f732f6b616e6174612e737667" alt="Packaging status" data-canonical-src="https://repology.org/badge/vertical-allrepos/kanata.svg"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Notable features</h2><a id="user-content-notable-features" aria-label="Permalink: Notable features" href="#notable-features"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Human-readable configuration file.
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/blob/main/cfg_samples/minimal.kbd">Minimal example</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/blob/main/docs/config.adoc">Full guide</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/blob/main/cfg_samples/simple.kbd">Simple example with explanations</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/blob/main/cfg_samples/kanata.kbd">All features showcase</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Live reloading of the configuration for easy testing of your changes.</li>
<li>Multiple layers of key functionality</li>
<li>Advanced actions such as tap-hold, unicode output, dynamic and static macros</li>
<li>Vim-like leader sequences to execute other actions</li>
<li>Optionally run a TCP server to interact with other programs
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Other programs can respond to <a href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/issues/47" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/jtroo/kanata/issues/47/hovercard">layer changes or trigger layer changes</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20240209172129/http://www.oblita.com/interception" rel="nofollow">Interception driver</a> support (use <code>kanata_wintercept.exe</code>)
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Note that this issue exists, which is outside the control of this project:
<a data-error-text="Failed to load title" data-id="138779117" data-permission-text="Title is private" data-url="https://github.com/oblitum/Interception/issues/25" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/oblitum/Interception/issues/25/hovercard" href="https://github.com/oblitum/Interception/issues/25">oblitum/Interception#25</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing</h2><a id="user-content-contributing" aria-label="Permalink: Contributing" href="#contributing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Contributions are welcome!</p>
<p dir="auto">Unless explicitly stated otherwise, your contributions to kanata will be made
under the LGPL-3.0-only<a href="https://www.gnu.org/licenses/identify-licenses-clearly.html" rel="nofollow">*</a> license.</p>
<p dir="auto">Some directories are exceptions:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/blob/main/keyberon">keyberon</a>: MIT License</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/blob/main/interception">interception</a>: MIT or Apache-2.0 Licenses</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/blob/main/docs/design.md">Here's a basic low-effort design doc of kanata</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How you can help</h2><a id="user-content-how-you-can-help" aria-label="Permalink: How you can help" href="#how-you-can-help"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Try it out and let me know what you think. Feel free to file an issue or
start a discussion.</li>
<li>Usability issues and unhelpful error messages are considered bugs that should
be fixed. If you encounter any, I would be thankful if you file an issue.</li>
<li>Browse the open issues and help out if you are able and/or would like to. If
you want to try contributing, feel free to ping jtroo for some pointers.</li>
<li>If you know anything about writing a keyboard driver for Windows, starting an
open-source alternative to the Interception driver would be lovely.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Community projects related to kanata</h2><a id="user-content-community-projects-related-to-kanata" aria-label="Permalink: Community projects related to kanata" href="#community-projects-related-to-kanata"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/rszyma/vscode-kanata">vscode-kanata</a>: Language support for kanata configuration files in VS Code</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/LGUG2Z/komokana">komokana</a>: Automatic application-aware layer switching for <a href="https://github.com/LGUG2Z/komorebi"><code>komorebi</code></a> (Windows)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/rszyma/kanata-tray">kanata-tray</a>: Control kanata from a tray icon</li>
<li>Application-aware layer switching:
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/veyxov/qanata">qanata (Linux)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Aqaao/kanawin">kanawin (Windows)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/reidprichard/window_tools">window_tools (Windows)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/mdSlash/nata">nata (Linux)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/devsunb/kanata-vk-agent">kanata-vk-agent (macOS)</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What does the name mean?</h2><a id="user-content-what-does-the-name-mean" aria-label="Permalink: What does the name mean?" href="#what-does-the-name-mean"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">I wanted a "k" word since this relates to keyboards. According to Wikipedia,
kanata is an indigenous Iroquoian word meaning "village" or "settlement" and is
the origin of Canada's name.</p>
<p dir="auto">There's also PPT✧.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Motivation</h2><a id="user-content-motivation" aria-label="Permalink: Motivation" href="#motivation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">TLDR: QMK features but for any keyboard, not just fancy mechanical ones.</p>
<details>
  <summary>Long version</summary>
<p dir="auto">I have a few keyboards that run <a href="https://docs.qmk.fm/#/" rel="nofollow">QMK</a>. QMK allows the
user to customize the functionality of their keyboard to their heart's content.</p>
<p dir="auto">One great use case of QMK is its ability map keys so that they overlap with the
home row keys but are accessible on another layer. I won't comment on
productivity, but I find this greatly helps with my keyboard comfort.</p>
<p dir="auto">For example, these keys are on the right side of the keyboard:</p>

<p dir="auto">On one layer I have arrow keys in the same position, and on another layer I
have a numpad.</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="arrows:       numpad:
- - -         7 8 9
- ↑ -         4 5 6
← ↓ →         1 2 3
- - -         0 * ."><pre><code>arrows:       numpad:
- - -         7 8 9
- ↑ -         4 5 6
← ↓ →         1 2 3
- - -         0 * .
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">One could add as many customizations as one likes to improve comfort, speed,
etc. Personally my main motivator is comfort due to a repetitive strain injury
in the past.</p>
<p dir="auto">However, QMK doesn't run everywhere. In fact, it doesn't run on <strong>most</strong>
hardware you can get. You can't get it to run on a laptop keyboard or any
mainstream office keyboard. I believe that the comfort and empowerment QMK
provides should be available to anyone with a computer on their existing
hardware, instead of having to purchase an enthusiast mechanical keyboard
(which are admittedly very nice — I own a few — but can be costly).</p>
<p dir="auto">The best alternative solution that I found for keyboards that don't run QMK was
<a href="https://github.com/kmonad/kmonad">kmonad</a>. This is an excellent project
and I recommend it if you want to try something similar.</p>
<p dir="auto">The reason for this project's existence is that kmonad is written in Haskell
and I have no idea how to begin contributing to a Haskell project. From an
outsider's perspective I think Haskell is a great language but I really can't
wrap my head around it. And there are a few <a href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/blob/main/docs/kmonad_comparison.md">outstanding issues</a>
at the time of writing that make kmonad suboptimal for my personal workflows.</p>
<p dir="auto">This project is written in Rust because Rust is my favourite programming
language and the prior work of the awesome <a href="https://github.com/TeXitoi/keyberon">keyberon crate</a>
exists.</p>
</details>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Similar Projects</h2><a id="user-content-similar-projects" aria-label="Permalink: Similar Projects" href="#similar-projects"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The most similar project is <a href="https://github.com/kmonad/kmonad">kmonad</a>,
which served as the inspiration for kanata. <a href="https://github.com/jtroo/kanata/blob/main/docs/kmonad_comparison.md">Here's a comparison document</a>.
Other similar projects:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://docs.qmk.fm/#/" rel="nofollow">QMK</a>: Open source keyboard firmware</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/TeXitoi/keyberon">keyberon</a>: Rust <code>#[no_std]</code> library intended for keyboard firmware</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ItayGarin/ktrl">ktrl</a>: Linux-only keyboard customizer with layers, a TCP server, and audio support</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/timokroeger/kbremap">kbremap</a>: Windows-only keyboard customizer with layers and unicode</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/alols/xcape">xcape</a>: Linux-only tap-hold modifiers</li>
<li><a href="https://karabiner-elements.pqrs.org/" rel="nofollow">karabiner-elements</a>: Mac-only keyboard customizer</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/cajhin/capsicain">capsicain</a>: Windows-only key remapper with driver-level key interception</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/rvaiya/keyd">keyd</a>: Linux-only key remapper very similar to QMK, kmonad, and kanata</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/k0kubun/xremap">xremap</a>: Linux-only application-aware key remapper inspired more by Emacs key sequences vs. QMK layers/Vim modes</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/houmain/keymapper">keymapper</a>: Context-aware cross-platform key remapper with a different transformation model (Linux, Windows, Mac)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/jbensmann/mouseless">mouseless</a>: Linux-only mouse-focused key remapper that also has layers, key combo and tap-hold capabilities</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Why the list?</h3><a id="user-content-why-the-list" aria-label="Permalink: Why the list?" href="#why-the-list"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">While kanata is the best tool for some, it may not be the best tool for
you. I'm happy to introduce you to tools that may better suit your needs. This
list is also useful as reference/inspiration for functionality that could be
added to kanata.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Donations/Support?</h2><a id="user-content-donationssupport" aria-label="Permalink: Donations/Support?" href="#donationssupport"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The author (jtroo) will not accept monetary donations for work on kanata.
Please instead donate your time and/or money to charity.</p>
<p dir="auto">Some links are below. These links are provided for learning and as interesting
reads. They are <strong>not</strong> an endorsement.</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://www.effectivealtruism.org/" rel="nofollow">https://www.effectivealtruism.org/</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.givewell.org/" rel="nofollow">https://www.givewell.org/</a></li>
</ul>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hard disk fraud: long runtimes on new Seagate hard disks (115 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.heise.de/en/news/Hard-disk-fraud-Increasing-evidence-of-origin-in-China-10269059.html</link>
            <guid>42991006</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 14:50:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.heise.de/en/news/Hard-disk-fraud-Increasing-evidence-of-origin-in-China-10269059.html">https://www.heise.de/en/news/Hard-disk-fraud-Increasing-evidence-of-origin-in-China-10269059.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42991006">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          <!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->
          





<a-collapse has-indicator="">
  
  <div data-collapse-target="">
      
  <nav>
    <ol>
        
        <li>

          
            <span aria-current="page">
              Hard disk fraud: Increasing evidence of origin in China
            </span>

            
              <ul>
              
                <li>
                
                  <a href="#nav_cases_from_all__0" title="Cases from all over the world" data-google-interstitial="false">
                    Cases from all over the world
                  </a>
                
                </li>
              
                <li>
                
                  <a href="#nav_slabs_from_chia__1" title="Slabs from chia farms?" data-google-interstitial="false">
                    Slabs from chia farms?
                  </a>
                
                </li>
              
                <li>
                
                  <a href="#nav_warranty_far__2" title="Warranty far too short" data-google-interstitial="false">
                    Warranty far too short
                  </a>
                
                </li>
              
              </ul>
            

          

        </li>
    </ol>

    

    

  </nav>

    </div>
  
</a-collapse>


          <!-- RSPEAK_START -->

        <p>Recently, many online retailers have sent out Seagate hard disks as new that have already been running somewhere <a href="https://www.heise.de/news/Gebrauchte-Seagate-Festplatten-als-Neuware-im-Umlauf-10254276.html?from-en=1">for many</a>, <a href="https://www.heise.de/news/Betrug-mit-Seagate-Festplatten-Dutzende-Leser-melden-Verdachtsfaelle-10258657.html?from-en=1">many</a> <a href="https://www.heise.de/news/Festplatten-Betrug-Weitere-Haendler-betroffen-erste-Ruecknahmen-10264019.html?from-en=1">hours.</a> As yet unknown fraudsters had reset the SMART values of used drives and smuggled them back into distribution via equally unknown channels. Official Seagate dealers are also affected.</p>

    
  

  <!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->
  
  <a-paternoster height="360" media="(min-width: 320px) and (max-width: 767px)">
    

  

  </a-paternoster>
  <!-- RSPEAK_START -->



<p>However, Seagate server hard disks also log their runtimes and other parameters elsewhere: The so-called FARM values cannot (yet?) be reset by the fraudsters (FARM stands for Field Accessible Reliability Metrics). These can also be read out with the <a href="https://www.heise.de/download/product/smartmontools-56954">smartmontools</a> or the <a href="https://www.seagate.com/de/de/support/downloads/seatools/" rel="external noopener" target="_blank">Seagate Seatools</a>. According to the readers, the affected drives have been in operation for an average of around 25,000 hours.</p>
<h3 id="nav_cases_from_all__0">Cases from all over the world</h3>
<p>However, not only German customers are affected. We have received reports from Switzerland, Austria, Luxembourg, the UK, the Czech Republic and the USA. The online retailer East Digital from Hong Kong is also said to be sending out such drives. They have now sold out of the drives, but apparently they often have such “special offers” in their program. We have also seen forum entries from Australian East Digital customers who are now also experiencing long FARM runtimes.</p>
<p>We have also received reports from Japan that the case is being reported there. We are happy to receive further information <a href="mailto:ll@ct.de?subject=Festplatten-Betrug">by e-mail</a> –. If you prefer to remain anonymous, you can do so via our <a href="https://www.heise.de/investigativ/">anonymous mailbox</a>.</p>
<h3 id="nav_slabs_from_chia__1">Slabs from chia farms?</h3>
<p>Where the slabs came from and how they got to Germany is still unclear. However, many such used drives are said to be on sale in China at the moment. These could come from former <a href="https://www.heise.de/news/Kryptowaehrung-Chia-2-Exabyte-ueberschritten-und-erstmalig-handelbar-6037645.html?from-en=1">computing farms for the cryptocurrency Chia</a>, which are now being shut down as farming such coins is no longer profitable: The energy costs are now higher than the expected profit.</p>

  





<p>The available storage space in this network was initially <a href="https://www.heise.de/news/Kryptowaehrung-Chia-verursacht-Lieferprobleme-in-Asien-6045592.html?from-en=1">only a few exabytes</a>, but later rose sharply. Since the summer of 2024, the storage space in the Chia network has been decreasing, from around 34 exabytes at the time to around 19 exabytes now. The loss of around 15 exabytes corresponds to around one million hard disks with a gross capacity of 16 TByte. Not all of these will come from Seagate; however, the manufacturer currently has a share of more than 40 percent of the hard disk market. Roughly speaking, more than 400,000 used Seagate drives with 16 TByte could have been discarded from the Chia farms.</p>


  



  





<p>The message from an affected person in a forum fits in with this. When asked, Seagate stated that his hard disk was originally sold to a Chinese company from Mongolia. Seagate's German representative is not so forthcoming about the origin of the drives, citing data protection and assuring that the company is not involved in the scam.</p>
<h3 id="nav_warranty_far__2">Warranty far too short</h3>
<p>Some of the disks still have a few months of warranty left, but most of them have long since expired. Many were sold as part of a larger system – and therefore as so-called OEM disks, for which the manufacturer provides no warranty. If they were sold in a Dell system, for example, then Dell is responsible for the warranty processing in this system, it is effectively no longer a Seagate disk.</p>


<!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->

<!-- RSPEAK_START -->

<p>Many of our readers have complained, even long before these cases of fraud, about the practice of dealers selling OEM disks without a manufacturer's warranty. We therefore recommend that you visit the warranty inquiries of the dealers immediately after receiving a drive and check the status <a href="https://www.seagate.com/de/de/support/warranty-and-replacements/" rel="external noopener" target="_blank">(Seagate</a>, <a href="https://www.storrepair.com/toshiba_products/" rel="external noopener" target="_blank">Toshiba</a>, <a href="https://support-de.wd.com/app/Warranty_Status" rel="external noopener" target="_blank">Western Digital</a>). The serial number is sometimes already noted on the invoice and can otherwise be read through the anti-static packaging before it is opened; this also allows the production date to be identified. If this is several years in the past, caution is advised and a return is at least worth considering.</p>
<a-opt-in checkbox-text="Preisvergleiche immer laden" type="Preisvergleichinternetservices">
    <div>
      <h2>Empfohlener redaktioneller Inhalt</h2>
      <p>
    Mit Ihrer Zustimmung wird hier ein externer Preisvergleich (heise Preisvergleich) geladen.
  </p>
      <p><label>
            
            Preisvergleiche immer laden
          </label>
        
        
      </p>
      <p>
    Ich bin damit einverstanden, dass mir externe Inhalte angezeigt werden.
    Damit können personenbezogene Daten an Drittplattformen (heise Preisvergleich) übermittelt werden.
    Mehr dazu in unserer
    <a href="https://www.heise.de/Datenschutzerklaerung-der-Heise-Medien-GmbH-Co-KG-4860.html">Datenschutzerklärung</a>.
  </p>
      
    </div>
  </a-opt-in>


<p>

<!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->
<span>(<a href="mailto:ll@ct.de" title="Lutz Labs">ll</a>)</span>
<!-- RSPEAK_START -->
</p>
<div>
    <p>
      Don't miss any news – follow us on
      <a href="https://www.facebook.com/heiseonlineEnglish">Facebook</a>,
      <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/104691972">LinkedIn</a> or
      <a href="https://social.heise.de/@heiseonlineenglish">Mastodon</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      <em>This article was originally published in
      
        <a href="https://www.heise.de/news/Festplatten-Betrug-Hinweise-auf-Ursprung-in-China-verdichten-sich-10268897.html">German</a>.
      
      It was translated with technical assistance and editorially reviewed before publication.</em>
    </p>
  </div>



        
        

        
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Baffled by generational garbage collection – wingolog (104 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://wingolog.org/archives/2025/02/09/baffled-by-generational-garbage-collection</link>
            <guid>42990819</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 14:16:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://wingolog.org/archives/2025/02/09/baffled-by-generational-garbage-collection">https://wingolog.org/archives/2025/02/09/baffled-by-generational-garbage-collection</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42990819">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Usually in this space I like to share interesting things that I find
out; you might call it a research-epistle-publish loop.  Today, though,
I come not with answers, but with questions, or rather one question, but
with fractal surface area: <i>what is the value proposition of
generational garbage collection?</i></p><h3>hypothesis</h3><p>The conventional wisdom is encapsulated in a 2004 Blackburn, Cheng, and
McKinley paper, <a href="https://www.steveblackburn.org/pubs/papers/mmtk-sigmetrics-2004.pdf">“Myths and Realities:  The Performance Impact of
Garbage
Collection”</a>,
which compares whole-heap mark-sweep and copying collectors to their
generational counterparts, using the Jikes RVM as a test harness.  (It
also examines a generational reference-counting collector, which is an
interesting predecessor to the 2022
<a href="https://www.steveblackburn.org/pubs/papers/lxr-pldi-2022.pdf">LXR</a> work
by Zhao, Blackburn, and McKinley.)</p><p>The paper finds that generational collectors spend less time than their
whole-heap counterparts for a given task.  This is mainly due to less
time spent collecting, because generational collectors avoid
tracing/copying work for older objects that mostly stay in the same
place in the live object graph.</p><p>The paper also notes an improvement for mutator time under generational
GC, but only for the generational mark-sweep collector, which it
attributes to the locality and allocation speed benefit of bump-pointer
allocation in the nursery.  However for copying collectors, generational
GC tends to slow down the mutator, probably because of the write
barrier, but in the end lower collector times still led to lower total
times.</p><p>So, I expected generational collectors to always exhibit lower
wall-clock times than whole-heap collectors.</p><h3>test workbench</h3><p>In <a href="https://github.com/wingo/whippet">whippet</a>, I have a garbage
collector with an abstract API that specializes at compile-time to the
mutator’s object and root-set representation and to the collector’s
allocator, write barrier, and other interfaces.  I embed it in
<a href="https://github.com/wingo/whiffle">whiffle</a>, a simple Scheme-to-C
compiler that can run some small multi-threaded benchmarks, for example
the classic Gabriel benchmarks.  We can then test those benchmarks
against different collectors, mutator (thread) counts, and heap sizes.
I expect that the generational parallel copying collector takes less
time than the whole-heap parallel copying collector.</p><h3>results?</h3><p>So, I ran some benchmarks.  Take the splay-tree benchmark, derived from
Octane’s
<a href="https://github.com/chromium/octane/blob/master/splay.js">splay.js</a>.  I
have a port to Scheme, and the results are... not good!</p><p><img src="https://wingolog.org/pub/splay.scm-generational-scalability-8.png"></p><p>In this graph the “pcc” series is the whole-heap copying collector, and
“generational-pcc” is the generational counterpart, with a nursery sized
such that after each collection, its size is 2 MB times the number of
active mutator threads in the last collector.  So, for this test with
eight threads, on my 8-core Ryzen 7 7840U laptop, the nursery is 16MB
including the copy reserve, which happens to be the same size as the L3
on this CPU.  New objects are kept in the nursery one cycle before being
promoted to the old generation.</p><p>There are also results for <a href="https://github.com/wingo/whippet/blob/main/doc/collector-mmc.md">“mmc” and “generational-mmc”
collectors</a>,
which use an Immix-derived algorithm that allows for bump-pointer
allocation but which doesn’t require a copy reserve.  There, the
generational collectors use a <a href="https://wingolog.org/archives/2022/10/22/the-sticky-mark-bit-algorithm">sticky mark-bit
algorithm</a>,
which has very different performance characteristics as promotion is
in-place, and the nursery is as large as the available heap size.</p><p>The salient point is that at all heap sizes, and for these two very
different configurations (mmc and pcc), generational collection takes
more time than whole-heap collection.  It’s not just the splay benchmark
either; I see the same thing for the very different <a href="https://wingolog.org/pub/nboyer.scm-5-generational-scalability-8.png">nboyer
benchmark</a>.
What is the deal?</p><p>I am honestly quite perplexed by this state of affairs.  I wish I had a
narrative to tie this together, but in lieu of that, voici some
propositions and observations.</p><h3>“generational collection is good because bump-pointer allocation”</h3><p>Sometimes people say that the reason generational collection is good is
because you get bump-pointer allocation, which has better locality and
allocation speed.  This is misattribution: it’s bump-pointer allocators
that have these benefits.  You can have them in whole-heap copying
collectors, or you can have them in whole-heap mark-compact or immix
collectors that bump-pointer allocate into the holes.  Or, true, you can
have them in generational collectors with a copying nursery but a
freelist-based mark-sweep allocator.  But also you can have generational
collectors without bump-pointer allocation, for free-list
sticky-mark-bit collectors.  To simplify this panorama to “generational
collectors have good allocators” is incorrect.</p><h3>“generational collection lowers pause times”</h3><p>It’s true, generational GC does lower median pause times:</p><p><img src="https://wingolog.org/pub/nboyer.scm-5-generational-p50-8.png"></p><p>But because a major collection is usually slightly more work under
generational GC than in a whole-heap system, because of e.g. the need to
reset remembered sets, the maximum pauses are just as big and even a
little bigger:</p><p><img src="https://wingolog.org/pub/nboyer.scm-5-generational-p100-8.png"></p><p>I am not even sure that it is meaningful to compare median pause times
between generational and non-generational collectors, given that the
former perform possibly orders of magnitude more collections than the
latter.</p><p>Doing fewer whole-heap traces is good, though, and in the ideal case,
the less frequent major traces under generational collectors allows time
for concurrent tracing, which is the true mitigation for long pause
times.</p><h3>is it whiffle?</h3><p>Could it be that the test harness I am using is in some way
unrepresentative?  I don’t have more than one test harness for Whippet
yet.  I will start work on a second Whippet embedder within the next few
weeks, so perhaps we will have an answer there.  Still, there is ample
time spent in GC pauses in these benchmarks, so surely as a GC workload
Whiffle has some utility.</p><p>One reasons that Whiffle might be unrepresentative is that it is an
ahead-of-time compiler, whereas nursery addresses are assigned at
run-time.  Whippet exposes the necessary information to allow a
just-in-time compiler to specialize write barriers, for example the
inline check that the field being mutated is not in the nursery, and an
AOT compiler can’t encode this as an immediate.  But it seems a small
detail.</p><p>Also, Whiffle doesn’t do much compiler-side work to elide write
barriers.  Could the cost of write barriers be over-represented in
Whiffle, relative to a production language run-time?</p><p>Relatedly, Whiffle is just a baseline compiler.  It does some partial
evaluation but no CFG-level optimization, no contification, no nice
closure conversion, no specialization, and so on: is it not
representative because it is not an optimizing compiler?</p><h3>is it something about the nursery size?</h3><p>How big should the nursery be?  I have no idea.</p><p>As a thought experiment, consider the case of a 1 kilobyte nursery.  It
is probably too small to allow the time for objects to die young, so the
survival rate at each minor collection would be high.  Above a certain
survival rate, generational GC is probably a lose, because your program
violates the weak generational hypothesis: it introduces a needless copy
for all survivors, and a synchronization for each minor GC.</p><p>On the other hand, a 1 GB nursery is probably not great either.  It is
plenty large enough to allow objects to die young, but the number of
survivor objects in a space that large is such that pause times would
not be very low, which is one of the things you would like in
generational GC.  Also, you lose out on locality: a significant fraction
of the objects you traverse are probably out of cache and might even
incur TLB misses.</p><p>So there is probably a happy medium somewhere.  My instinct is that for
a copying nursery, you want to make it about as big as L3 cache, which
on my 8-core laptop is 16 megabytes.  Systems are different sizes
though; in Whippet my current heuristic is to reserve 2 MB of nursery
per core that was active in the previous cycle, so if only 4 threads are
allocating, you would have a 8 MB nursery.  Is this good?  I don’t know.</p><h3>is it something about the benchmarks?</h3><p>I don’t have a very large set of benchmarks that run on Whiffle, and
they might not be representative.  I mean, they are microbenchmarks.</p><p>One question I had was about heap sizes.  If a benchmark’s maximum heap
size fits in L3, which is the case for some of them, then probably
generational GC is a wash, because whole-heap collection stays in cache.
When I am looking at benchmarks that evaluate generational GC, I make
sure to choose those that exceed L3 size by a good factor, for example
the 8-mutator splay benchmark in which minimum heap size peaks at 300
MB, or the 8-mutator nboyer-5 which peaks at 1.6 GB.</p><p>But then, should nursery size scale with total heap size?  I don’t know!</p><p>Incidentally, the way that I scale these benchmarks to multiple mutators
is a bit odd: they are serial benchmarks, and I just run some number of
threads at a time, and scale the heap size accordingly, assuming that
the minimum size when there are 4 threads is four times the minimum size
when there is just one thread.  However, <a href="https://wingolog.org/archives/2024/07/10/copying-collectors-with-block-structured-heaps-are-unreliable">multithreaded programs are
unreliable</a>,
in the sense that there is no heap size under which they fail and above
which they succeed; I quote:</p><blockquote>
"Consider 10 threads each of which has a local object graph that is
usually 10 MB but briefly 100MB when calculating: usually when GC
happens, total live object size is 10×10MB=100MB, but sometimes as
much as 1 GB; there is a minimum heap size for which the program
sometimes works, but also a minimum heap size at which it always
works."
</blockquote><h3>is it the write barrier?</h3><p>A generational collector partitions objects into old and new sets, and a
minor collection starts by visiting all old-to-new edges, called the
“remembered set”.  As the program runs, mutations to old objects might
introduce new old-to-new edges.  To maintain the remembered set in a
generational collector, the mutator invokes <i>write barriers</i>: little
bits of code that run when you mutate a field in an object.  This is
overhead relative to non-generational configurations, where the mutator
doesn’t have to invoke collector code when it sets fields.</p><p>So, could it be that Whippet’s write barriers or remembered set are
somehow so inefficient that my tests are unrepresentative of the state
of the art?</p><p>I used to use card-marking barriers, but I started to suspect they cause
too much overhead during minor GC and introduced too much cache
contention.  I switched to <a href="https://wingolog.org/archives/2024/10/03/preliminary-notes-on-a-nofl-field-logging-barrier">precise field-logging
barriers</a>
some months back for Whippet’s Immix-derived space, and we use the same
kind of barrier in the generational copying (pcc) collector.  I think
this is state of the art.  I need to see if I can find a configuration
that allows me to measure the overhead of these barriers, independently
of other components of a generational collector.</p><h3>is it something about the generational mechanism?</h3><p>A few months ago, my only generational collector used the <a href="https://wingolog.org/archives/2022/10/22/the-sticky-mark-bit-algorithm">sticky
mark-bit</a>
algorithm, which is an unconventional configuration: its nursery is not
contiguous, non-moving, and can be as large as the heap.  This is part
of the reason that I implemented generational support for the parallel
copying collector, to have a different and more conventional collector
to compare against.  But generational collection loses on some of these
benchmarks in both places!</p><h3>is it something about collecting more often?</h3><p>On one benchmark which repeatedly constructs some trees and then
verifies them, I was seeing terrible results for generational GC, which
I realized were because of cooperative safepoints: generational GC
collects more often, so it requires that all threads reach safepoints
more often, and the non-allocating verification phase wasn’t emitting
any safepoints.  I had to change the compiler to emit safepoints at
regular intervals (in my case, on function entry), and it sped up the
generational collector by a significant amount.</p><p>This is one instance of a general observation, which is that any work
that doesn’t depend on survivor size in a GC pause is more expensive
with a generational collector, which runs more collections.
Synchronization can be a cost.  I had one bug in which tracing
ephemerons did work proportional to the size of the whole heap, instead
of the nursery; I had to specifically add generational support for the
way Whippet deals with ephemerons during a collection to reduce this
cost.</p><h3>is it something about collection frequency?</h3><p>Looking deeper at the data, I have partial answers for the splay benchmark,
and they are annoying :)</p><p>Splay doesn’t actually allocate all that much garbage.  At a 2.5x heap,
the stock parallel MMC collector (in-place, sticky mark bit)
collects... one time.  That’s all.  Same for the generational MMC
collector, because the first collection is always major.  So at 2.5x we
would expect the generational collector to be slightly slower.  The
benchmark is simply not very good – or perhaps the most generous
interpretation is that it represents tasks that allocate 40 MB or so of
long-lived data and not much garbage on top.</p><p>Also at 2.5x heap, the whole-heap copying collector runs 9 times, and
the generational copying collector does 293 minor collections and... 9
major collections.  We are not reducing the number of major GCs.  It
means either the nursery is too small, so objects aren’t dying young
when they could, or the benchmark itself doesn’t conform to the weak
generational hypothesis.</p><p>At a 1.5x heap, the copying collector doesn’t have enough space to run.
For MMC, the non-generational variant collects 7 times, and generational
MMC times out.  Timing out indicates a bug, I think.  Annoying!</p><p>I tend to think that if I get results and there were fewer than, like, 5
major collections for a whole-heap collector, that indicates that the
benchmark is probably inapplicable at that heap size, and I should
somehow surface these anomalies in my analysis scripts.</p><h3>collecting more often redux</h3><p>Doing a similar exercise for nboyer at 2.5x heap with 8 threads (4GB for
1.6GB live data), I see that pcc did 20 major collections, whereas
generational pcc lowered that to 8 major collections and 3471 minor
collections.  Could it be that there are still too many fixed costs
associated with synchronizing for global stop-the-world minor
collections?  I am going to have to add some fine-grained tracing to
find out.</p><h3>conclusion?</h3><p>I just don’t know!  I want to believe that generational collection was an out-and-out win,
but I haven’t yet been able to prove it is true.</p><p>I do have some homework to do.  I need to find a way to test the
overhead of my write barrier – probably using the MMC collector and
making it only do major collections.  I need to fix generational-mmc for
splay and a 1.5x heap.  And I need to do some fine-grained performance
analysis for minor collections in large heaps.</p><p>Enough for today.  Feedback / reactions very welcome.  Thanks for
reading and happy hacking!</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Don't "optimize" conditional moves in shaders with mix()+step() (286 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://iquilezles.org/articles/gpuconditionals/</link>
            <guid>42990324</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 12:42:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://iquilezles.org/articles/gpuconditionals/">https://iquilezles.org/articles/gpuconditionals/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42990324">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main">



<h3>Intro</h3><hr><p>
In this article I want to correct a popular misconception that's been making the rounds in computer graphics aficionado circles for a long time now. It has to do with branching in the GPUs. Unfortunately there are a couple of educational websites out there that are spreading some misinformation and it would be nice correcting that. I tried contacting the authors without success, so without further ado, here goes my attempt to fix things up:</p><h3>The issue</h3><hr><p>
So, say I have this code, which I actually published the other day:</p><p><span>vec2</span> snap45( <span>in vec2</span> v )
{
    <span>vec2</span> s = <span>sign</span>(v);
    <span>float</span> x = <span>abs</span>(v.x);
    <span>return</span> x&gt;<span>0.923880</span>?<span>vec2</span>(s.x,<span>0.0</span>):
           x&gt;<span>0.382683</span>?s*<span>sqrt</span>(<span>0.5</span>):
                      <span>vec2</span>(<span>0.0</span>,s.y);
}</p>
<p>
The exact details of what it does don't matter for this discussion. All we care about is the two ternary operations, which as you know, implement conditional execution. Indeed, depending on the value of the variable <b>x</b>, the function will return different results. This could be implemented also with regular <b>if</b> statements, and all that I'm going to say stays the same.</p><p>

But here's the problem - when seeing code like this, somebody somewhere will invariably propose the following "optimization", which replaces what they believe (erroneously) are "conditional branches" by arithmetical operations. They will suggest something like this:</p><p><span>vec2</span> snap45( <span>in vec2</span> v )
{
    <span>vec2</span> s = <span>sign</span>(v);
    <span>float</span> x = <span>abs</span>(v.x);

    <span>float</span> w0 = <span>step</span>(<span>0.92387953</span>,x);
    <span>float</span> w1 = <span>step</span>(<span>0.38268343</span>,x)*(<span>1.0</span>-w0);
    <span>float</span> w2 = <span>1.0</span>-w0-w1;

    <span>vec2</span> res0 = <span>vec2</span>(s.x,<span>0.0</span>);
    <span>vec2</span> res1 = <span>vec2</span>(s.x,s.y)*<span>sqrt</span>(<span>0.5</span>);
    <span>vec2</span> res2 = <span>vec2</span>(<span>0.0</span>,s.y);

    <span>return</span> w0*res0 + w1*res1 + w2*res2;
}</p>
<p>
There are two things wrong with this practice. The first one shows an incorrect understanding of how the GPU works. In particular, the original shader code had no conditional branching in it. Selecting between a few registers with a ternary operator or with a plain <b>if</b> statement does not lead to conditional branching; all it involves is a conditional move (a.k.a. "select"), which is a simple instruction to route the correct bits to the destination register. You can think of it as a bitwise AND+NAND+OR on the source registers, which is a simple combinational circuit. Again, there is no branching - the instruction pointer isn't manipulated, there's no branch prediction involved, no instruction cache to invalidation, no nothing.</p><p>

For the record, of course real branches do happen in GPU code, but those are not what's used by the GPU for small moves between registers like we have here. This is true for any GPU made in the last 20+ years. While I'm not an expert in CPUs, I am pretty sure this is true for them as well.</p><p>

The second wrong thing with the supposedly optimizer version is that it actually runs much slower than the original version. The reason is that the <b>step()</b> function is actually implemented like this:</p><p><span>float</span> step( <span>float</span> x, <span>float</span> y )
{
    <span>return</span> x &lt; y ? <span>1.0</span> : <span>0.0</span>;
}</p>
<p>
So people using the step() "optimization" are using the ternary operation anyways, which produces the <b>0.0</b> or <b>1.0</b> which they will use to select the output, only wasting two multiplications and one or two additions. The values could have been conditionally moved directly, which is what the original shader code did.</p><p>

But don't take my word for it, let's look at the generated machine code for the relevant part of the shader I published:</p><div>

<div><p>
GLSL</p><hr>
<p><span>return</span> x&gt;<span>0.923880</span>?<span>vec2</span>(s.x,<span>0.0</span>):
       x&gt;<span>0.382683</span>?s*<span>sqrt</span>(<span>0.5</span>):
                  <span>vec2</span>(<span>0.0</span>,s.y);</p>
</div>
<div><p>
AMD Compiler</p><hr>
<p><span>s_mov_b32</span>     s0, <span>0x3ec3ef15</span>
<span>v_mul_f32</span>     v3, <span>0x3f3504f3</span>, v1
<span>v_mul_f32</span>     v4, <span>0x3f3504f3</span>, v0
<span>s_mov_b32</span>     s1, <span>0x3f6c835e</span>
<span>v_cmp_gt_f32</span>  vcc, <span>abs</span>(v2), s0
<span>v_cndmask_b32</span> v3, 0, v3, vcc
<span>v_cndmask_b32</span> v0, v0, v4, vcc
<span>v_cmp_ngt_f32</span> vcc, <span>abs</span>(v2), s1
<span>v_cndmask_b32</span> v1, v1, v3, vcc
<span>v_cndmask_b32</span> v0, 0, v0, vcc</p>
</div>
<div><p>
Microsoft Compiler</p><hr>
<p><span>lt</span>   r0.xy, l(<span>0</span>, <span>0</span>), v0.xy
<span>lt</span>   r0.zw, v0.xy, l(<span>0</span>, <span>0</span>)
<span>iadd</span> r0.xy, -r0.xyxx, r0.zwzz
<span>itof</span> r0.xy, r0.xyxx
<span>mul</span>  r1.xyzw, r0.xyxy, l4(<span>0.707107</span>)
<span>lt</span>   r2.xy, l(<span>0.923880</span>,<span>0.382683</span>), <span>|</span>v0.xx<span>|</span>
<span>mov</span>  r0.z, l(<span>0</span>)
<span>movc</span> r1.xyzw, r2.yyyy, r1.xyzw, r0.zyzy
<span>movc</span> o0.xyzw, r2.xxxx, r0.xzxz, r1.xyzw</p>
</div>
</div><p>
Here we can see that the GPU is not branching. Instead, according to the AMD compiler, it's performing the required comparisons (<span>v_cmp_gt_f32</span> and <span>v_cmp_ngt_f32</span> - cmp=compare, gt=greater than, ngt=not greated than), and then using the result to mask the results with the bitwise operations mentioned earlier (<span>v_cndmask_b32</span> - cnd=conditional).</p><p>

The Microsoft compiler has expressed the same idea/implementation in a different format, but you can still see the comparison (<span>lt</span> - "lt"=less than) and the masking or conditional move (<span>movc</span> - mov=move, c=conditionally).</p><p>

Not related to the discussion, but also note that the <b>abs()</b> call does not become a GPU instruction and instead becomes an instruction modifier, which is free.</p><h3>Conclusion</h3><hr>
<p>
So, if you ever see somebody proposing this</p><p><span>float</span> a = <span>mix</span>( b, c, <span>step</span>( y, x ) );</p><p>
as an optimization to</p><p><span>float</span> a = x &lt; y ? b : c</p><p>
then please correct them for me. The misinformation has been around for 20 years / 10 GPU generation, and that's more than too long.</p><p>

Thanks!
</p><!-- -------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- -->

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Classic Data science pipelines built with LLMs (151 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/Pravko-Solutions/FlashLearn/tree/main/examples</link>
            <guid>42990036</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 11:39:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/Pravko-Solutions/FlashLearn/tree/main/examples">https://github.com/Pravko-Solutions/FlashLearn/tree/main/examples</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42990036">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">FlashLearn – Examples Directory</h2><a id="user-content-flashlearn--examples-directory" aria-label="Permalink: FlashLearn – Examples Directory" href="#flashlearn--examples-directory"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Below you’ll find an overview of each file, what it showcases, and links to the actual code. You can run these examples (assuming you’ve installed FlashLearn and set your “OPENAI_API_KEY”) simply by using:</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How to Run</h2><a id="user-content-how-to-run" aria-label="Permalink: How to Run" href="#how-to-run"></a></p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Clone or download the FlashLearn repository (or just copy the examples folder).</li>
<li>Install FlashLearn:

</li>
<li>Set your “OPENAI_API_KEY” (or other provider keys) in your environment:
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="export OPENAI_API_KEY=&quot;YOUR_API_KEY&quot;"><pre><span>export</span> OPENAI_API_KEY=<span><span>"</span>YOUR_API_KEY<span>"</span></span></pre></div>
</li>
<li>Navigate to the “examples” folder and pick any script. Then run, for example:
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="python sentiment_classification.py"><pre>python sentiment_classification.py</pre></div>
</li>
<li>Check the console output and JSON results files (e.g., “results.jsonl”).</li>
</ol>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Dear Mr. Vice President, Please Take Off Your Apple Watch (107 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.watchesofespionage.com/blogs/woe-dispatch/vice-president-jd-vance-apple-watch-smartwatch-intelligence-risks</link>
            <guid>42990000</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 11:29:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.watchesofespionage.com/blogs/woe-dispatch/vice-president-jd-vance-apple-watch-smartwatch-intelligence-risks">https://www.watchesofespionage.com/blogs/woe-dispatch/vice-president-jd-vance-apple-watch-smartwatch-intelligence-risks</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42990000">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
              <h2><strong>An Open Letter To JD Vance From A Former CIA Officer On The Counterintelligence Risks Of Smartwatches</strong></h2>
<p>Mr. Vice President,</p>
<p>Congratulations on your ascendancy to the Vice President of the United States of America. While we are an apolitical platform, we wish you nothing but success, the country depends on you. &nbsp;</p>
<p>In a recent picture of you onboard Air Force Two, we couldn't help but notice the Apple Watch on your left wrist. As a former CIA case officer who spent most of his adult life recruiting spies and stealing secrets, I feel implored to highlight some of the potential vulnerabilities of your smartwatch before suggesting a simple solution.</p>
<p><strong>As Vice President, you are now a priority intelligence collection target for the world's most capable bad actors, and the Apple Watch is an effective vector for potential exploitation</strong>. We do not doubt that hostile intelligence services are working around the clock to exploit (“hack”) your devices and would be genuinely surprised if they haven't already.</p>
<p><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0582/0291/4931/files/Untitled_design_971_600x600.png?v=1738589239" alt="jd vance apple watch security counterintelligence risks"></p>
<h6>The photograph in question, reportedly from 28 Jan 2025.</h6>
<p>To be clear, we are not anti-technology or troglodytes. We are big fans of Apple and believe the iPhone and iPad are two of the most consequential products of the last century. For most people, the Apple Watch is a great tool and offers significant lifestyle benefits: fitness tracking, optimizing communication, and sleep and health monitoring. But you are not like most people. You are one of the most powerful world leaders and thus a priority target for extremely capable hostile intelligence services, including Russia, China, Iran, and North Korea—all of which are considered Advanced Persistent Threats (APTs). &nbsp;</p>
<p>From an intelligence perspective, the Apple Watch offers unique data collection and access for exploitation and even manipulation. Of particular concern, the watch contains a microphone that when worn is capable of detecting and recording the user's conversations.</p>
<p><img alt="us army smartwatch apple watch counterintelligence warning" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0582/0291/4931/files/IMG_4733_600x600_81f2f8bd-6fe4-4817-bc37-d8378abdc991_600x600.webp?v=1738420836"></p>
<p>As Vice President, nearly everything you say and do is of interest to foreign intelligence services (FIS). This includes not only strategic-level discussions with the President and National Security officials but also conversations with your wife, political donors, and college friends. While the Apple Watch has security features in place, you must operate under the assumption that it can be compromised and exploited.</p>
<p>Through a process called hot micing, the microphone can be remotely activated or set to passively collect audio without the wearer's knowledge. Additionally, the Apple Watch collects GPS location, movement, and biometric data including heart rate and sleep patterns, representing potential vulnerabilities for exploitation by bad actors. If the device is compromised, all of this data is available to a hostile intelligence service. &nbsp; <br></p>
<p><img alt="French newspaper Le Monde has exposed a number of intelligence links using data from Strava, a popular fitness tracker. (Photo Credit: Le Monde)" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0582/0291/4931/files/Untitled_design_963_600x600.png?v=1738420893"></p>
<h6>French newspaper <em>Le Monde</em> has exposed a number of intelligence links using data from Strava, a popular fitness tracker. (Photo Credit: Le Monde)</h6>
<p>Further, the average iOS Apple operating system has an estimated 40-80 third-party applications installed. Many of these apps collect data and resell it to advertisers. If a product is free, you are the product. While in theory this data is anonymized, we have our doubts. Just ask your new Secret Service Director Sean Curran. According to an investigative report by the French newspaper <em>Le Monde</em>, data collected through the fitness app Strava was leveraged to identify 26 Secret Service agents as well as the locations of sensitive meetings.</p>
<p><img alt="“It's this new app—you put in your Social Security number, and it makes you look like a cat.” (Credit: New York Times)" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0582/0291/4931/files/DC072619_480x480.webp?v=1738420969"></p>
<p>“It's this new app—you put in your Social Security number, and it makes you look like a cat.” (Credit: New York Times)</p>
<p>As you are likely aware, connected devices are prohibited in Sensitive Compartmented Information Facilities (SCIF) and regardless of location, many of your conversations occur at this level or higher. In September 2024, the US Army issued a warning to Department of Defense (DOD) personnel on the counterintelligence (CI) risks of smartwatches with a social media campaign:</p>
<p>“<em>Smartwatches can transmit sensitive information. Don’t be an insider threat - Think before you use a smartwatch in the field or on deployment</em>.”</p>
<p>While state-sponsored hackers (APTs) are likely the greatest threat, it is important to understand that private companies allegedly also maintain this capability. In 2021, Apple reportedly sued Israeli cybersecurity firm NSO Group:</p>
<p>“<em>NSO Group creates sophisticated, state-sponsored surveillance technology that allows its highly targeted spyware to surveil its victims. These attacks are only aimed at a very small number of users, and they impact people across multiple platforms, including iOS and Android. Researchers and journalists have publicly documented a history of this spyware being abused to target journalists, activists, dissidents, academics, and government officials</em>.”</p>
<p><img alt="le monde graphic cell phone data hacked intelligence apple watch risks espionage" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0582/0291/4931/files/00dc-spyware-superJumbo_600x600.jpg?v=1738421077"></p>
<h6>(Credit: New York Times)</h6>
<p>To be very clear, there is nothing inherently wrong with Apple products or the Apple Watch. In fact, we would say that they are probably one of the most secure, or least vulnerable, tech products on the market. That said, any device can be hacked. &nbsp;</p>
<p>If you don’t believe us, we encourage you to reach out to your newly appointed Director of CIA John Ratcliffe and Director of National Security Agency (NSA) General Timothy D. Haugh for a demonstration of our capabilities. You will be amazed.</p>
<p>I am a firm believer that you should not highlight a problem without providing a solution. So here are three watches we would recommend, not only are they great tools backed by intriguing heritage, but they are also all completely safe from the prying eyes of foreign intelligence services.</p>
<h2><strong>Sangin Instruments Neptune</strong></h2>
<p><img alt="Sangin Instruments Neptune jd vance apple watch risks" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0582/0291/4931/files/Untitled_design_967_1024x1024.png?v=1738421163"></p>
<p>We are told there is no such thing as a “former” Marine. Given your time serving in the Corps, we can’t help but think a watch <a rel="noopener" title="Sangin Instruments - The Marine Owned “Raider Rolex”" href="https://www.watchesofespionage.com/blogs/woe-dispatch/sangin-instruments-the-marine-owned-raider-rolex" target="_blank">described as “A Marine Raider Rolex”</a> would fit the bill. Founded by Jacob Servantes, a Marine Special Operations veteran, Sangin produces a range of capable tool watches informed by the founder’s military experience and appreciation of watches. The Neptune is on the more refined end of the brand’s spectrum, capable of 300 meters of water resistance while still looking elegant enough for White House wear.</p>
<h2><strong>Marathon 41mm Diver’s Automatic (GSAR)</strong></h2>
<p><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0582/0291/4931/files/Untitled_design_969_1024x1024.png?v=1738421280" alt="marine special operations raider marathon 41mm gsar automatic"></p>
<p><strong></strong>Another brand with legitimate links to the Marine Corps is <a rel="noopener" title="Marathon, Watch Maker for the Modern Military" href="https://www.watchesofespionage.com/blogs/woe-dispatch/marathon-watch-maker-for-the-modern-military" target="_blank">Marathon, a Canadian brand that has seen its watches issued to numerous US Military units including Marine Force Reconnaissance</a>. For your purposes, we would recommend <a rel="noopener" title="Diving With The Marathon Search and Rescue" href="https://www.watchesofespionage.com/blogs/woe-dispatch/diving-with-the-marathon-sar" target="_blank">the automatic GSAR</a>, which is powered by a Swiss Sellita movement while still offering significant water resistance and tritium tubes for constant nighttime legibility. Besides, if President Trump really does make Canada the 51st state, this watch will be almost made in the USA (just kidding… kind of).</p>
<h2><strong>Breitling “White House” Aerospace</strong></h2>
<p><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0582/0291/4931/files/933584F9-4929-47F9-81B3-66827F6F27AE_1_600x600.jpg?v=1738421478" alt="Breitling “White House” Aerospace"></p>
<p>Thus far, we’ve suggested commercially available watches, but why not take advantage of your new position just a little bit with a customized Breitling “unit watch” that is only available to White House staff? The so-called <a rel="noopener" title="The Watches Of The Trump Administration" href="https://www.watchesofespionage.com/blogs/woe-dispatch/president-trump-administration-watches-rolex-omega-2025" target="_blank">“White House” Breitling Aerospace</a> is a customized version of one of the brand’s most popular models from a military and intelligence perspective, offering a broad swath of digital timekeeping functions that will help to offset the Apple Watch loss without having potentially dangerous counterintelligence implications.</p>
<p><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0582/0291/4931/files/0D7585C5-DFF7-4CB8-8E7D-0260D279996D_600x600.jpg?v=1737465049" alt="white house breitling aerospace jd vance"></p>
<p>During the previous Trump administration, someone set up a program where White House employees could order a version of several models with the White House Seal on the dial as well as a special caseback engraving. As a note, we’re not calling you sketchy, but it’s important to know that <a rel="noopener" title="Sketchy Dudes Wear Breitling - We Don’t Make The Rules" href="https://www.watchesofespionage.com/blogs/woe-dispatch/sketchy-dudes-wear-breitling" target="_blank">Sketchy Dudes Wear Breitling</a>. We don’t make the rules.</p>
<h2><strong>It's Never Just a Watch</strong></h2>
<p>Whether you know it or not, as a US Marine, you are a member of the W.O.E. community. Given the gravity of your new role, a watch may seem like an insignificant nuisance. But decades from now when you move on in life, the watch you wear over the next four years will be a talisman of your service to this country and treasured by your grandchildren. Unless it's an Apple Watch, in that case, it will be in a landfill.</p>
<p>Sincerely,&nbsp;</p>
<p>-Watches of Espionage (W.O.E.)</p>
<p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UZEZTJTYE5Y?si=MswKk4pWK5XV-3K_" title="YouTube video player"></iframe></p>
<p>For more information on this topic check out our article on the <a rel="noopener" title="Counterintelligence Risks of Smartwatches" href="https://www.watchesofespionage.com/blogs/woe-dispatch/cia-officers-and-apple-watches" target="_blank">Counterintelligence Risks of Smartwatches</a> as well as our Youtube video <a rel="noopener" title="CIA Officer Explains Apple Watch Risks" href="https://youtu.be/UZEZTJTYE5Y" target="_blank">HERE</a>.</p>
<p><span><strong>If you enjoyed this article, please consider signing up for our weekly free newsletter for further updates</strong> <a rel="noopener" href="http://eepurl.com/h8jvsv" title="Watches of Espionage Email Signup Link" target="_blank">HERE</a>.</span></p>
<p><strong>Read Next: </strong><a rel="noopener" title="The Watches Of The Trump Administration" href="https://www.watchesofespionage.com/blogs/woe-dispatch/president-trump-administration-watches-rolex-omega-2025" target="_blank">The Watches Of The Trump Administration</a></p>
<p><a rel="noopener" title="The Watches Of The Trump Administration" href="https://www.watchesofespionage.com/blogs/woe-dispatch/president-trump-administration-watches-rolex-omega-2025" target="_blank"><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0582/0291/4931/files/Untitled_design_902_240x240.png?v=1737465223" alt="donald trump president vacheron patek rolex"></a></p>
<p><em>This article has been reviewed by the CIA's Prepublication Classification Review Board to prevent the disclosure of classified information.</em><br></p>
          </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[RetroFab: Playable 3D simulations of vintage electronic games (142 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://itizso.itch.io/retrofab</link>
            <guid>42989628</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 09:50:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://itizso.itch.io/retrofab">https://itizso.itch.io/retrofab</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42989628">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Playable 3D simulations of classic handheld electronic games including packaging and browseable instruction guides.</p>
<p>Playable 3D simulations of vintage electronic games</p>
<p>Game &amp; Watch, Nintendo, Konami, Coleco, Tiger Electronics, Handheld, LCD, Simulation, Emulator, Simulator, 3D, Vintage Electronic Game, Itizso</p>
<div>
	<p>
	RetroFab is a new online collection of vintage electronic game simulations that can be played in the browser.
	<br>
	I am now releasing in to <strong>early access</strong> the first  simulations in this collection.
	</p>
	<p>
	<span>Latest News:</span> <a href="https://itizso.itch.io/retrofab/devlog/573139/retrofab-098-out-now" target="_blank">RetroFab now supports gamepads and touchscreens!</a>
	</p>
	
	
</div>
<div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1nLzg0OTk2NDQucG5n/original/ptwOzj.png" loading="lazy"></p><p>Gameplay</p>
			<p>Playable 3D simulation<br>of original electronic device</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1nLzg0OTk2NTIucG5n/original/Yzzhcs.png" loading="lazy"></p><p>Box Art</p>
			<p>Rotatable 3D views<br>of original packaging</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1nLzg0OTk2NTUucG5n/original/UeMNE%2F.png" loading="lazy"></p><p>Instructions</p>
			<p>Browseable scans of <br>original instruction guides</p>
		</div>
	</div>









<div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjA4Mjk0Ni8xMjI1NDE1Ni5wbmc=/347x500/tNjPiz.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;Bart Simpson's™<br>Cupcake Crisis</p>
				<p>Acclaim Entertainment</p>
				<p>1990</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>

		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjAzMDQwNy8xMTk0MDUxNi5wbmc=/347x500/63W2ke.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;Bartman™<br>Avenger of Evil</p>
				<p>Acclaim Entertainment</p>
				<p>1991</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
	</div>









<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTkxNTA2MS8xMTMzMzgzMC5wbmc=/250x600/TjL7AB.png" loading="lazy"></p>
			
		</div>









<div>
		<br>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjEyNjg1Ni8xMjUyOTg4Mi5wbmc=/250x600/dCx8Gy.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Las Vegas</p>
				<p>Bandai Electronics</p>
				<p>1981</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
		<br>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTgwOTg5MS8xMDYyNzA4MS5wbmc=/347x500/oZVRvM.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Airport Panic</p>
				<p>Bandai Electronics</p>
				<p>1982</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
		<br>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTk5NTc3MS8xMTczMjY3Ni5wbmc=/250x600/H0m7y2.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Catch a Coke</p>
				<p>Bandai Electronics</p>
				<p>1983</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
		<br>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjY0MDc0MC8xNTczNjE5OC5wbmc=/347x500/xGzJuS.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Beauty Salon</p>
				<p>Bandai Electronics</p>
				<p>1981</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
		
	</div>









<div>

		
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMzExMzY3Ny8xODYxMDI5My5wbmc=/347x500/nCpOJA.png" loading="lazy"></p>
			
		</div>
		<br>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjU0NzU4Mi8xNTE1ODY4OC5wbmc=/347x500/N5FvSK.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Western Sheriff</p>
				<p>Casio</p>
				<p>1987</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
		
	</div>




















<div>


	

		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjQ0NDE1MC8xNDQ3OTkzMi5wbmc=/347x500/rUTOM8.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Nu, Pogodi!</p>
				<p>Elektronika</p>
				<p>1984</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
		
		
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjQ0NDE0Ny8xNDQ3OTkyNi5wbmc=/347x500/icG8xs.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Mickey Mouse</p>
				<p>Elektronika</p>
				<p>1984</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>



		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjA1MTAzNi8xMjA2MTk3My5wbmc=/original/WiiX%2BF.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Explorers of Space</p>
				<p>Elektronika</p>
				<p>1989</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>

		
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjQ0NDEzOS8xNDQ3OTg4MC5wbmc=/347x500/4qTcAp.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Monkey Goalkeeper</p>
				<p>Elektronika</p>
				<p>1989</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>

		
		
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjQ0NDE0NS8xNDQ3OTkwMi5wbmc=/347x500/Nv6CDb.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Frogling</p>
				<p>Elektronika</p>
				<p>1991</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>

		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjQ0NDEzNS8xNDQ3OTg1My5wbmc=/347x500/0TU%2B4b.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Cat Fisherman</p>
				<p>Elektronika</p>
				<p>1991</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>

		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjQ0NDE1Mi8xNDQ3OTk0MC5wbmc=/347x500/5XG0LR.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Ocean Secrets</p>
				<p>Elektronika</p>
				<p>1989</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>


		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjQ0Njk3NC8xNDQ5ODM0NS5wbmc=/347x500/ApDu63.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Space Bridge</p>
				<p>Elektronika</p>
				<p>1989</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
	
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjYyNTM3MC8xNTY0MjgzMi5wbmc=/347x500/RcC20E.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Merry Cook</p>
				<p>Elektronika</p>
				<p>1989</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>


	</div>






<div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMzAyMDM0MC8xODA2MjA5OS5wbmc=/347x500/qpqFts.png" loading="lazy"></p>
			
		</div>
		<br>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjU2NTc0Ny8xNTI2ODM0OS5wbmc=/347x500/DmPjUY.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Mickey &amp; Minnie</p>
				<p>Epoch</p>
				<p>1990</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
	</div>






<div>
		<br>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjc3Mjc5OS8xNjU4MzQyMy5wbmc=/347x500/Li7k%2Fp.png" loading="lazy"></p>
			
		</div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjc3MjgxMC8xNjc3Nzg5NS5wbmc=/347x500/7dOJpC.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Donkey Angler</p>
				<p>Gakken</p>
				<p>1982</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
		
	</div>



<div>
		<br>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMzA1OTA1Ni8xODI5NDI4My5wbmc=/347x500/XYjJu%2F.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>BMX Flyer</p>
				<p>Grandstand</p>
				<p>1983</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
		
	</div>










<div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjQ3MzkxNS8xNDY4NjE1NS5wbmc=/347x500/s6qsQX.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Milton Bradley<br>Connect Four</p>
				<p>Milton Bradley</p>
				<p>1995</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjcwMTE2Mi8xNjEwMjU2My5wbmc=/347x500/FeZb7a.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Milton Bradley<br>Yahtzee</p>
				<p>Milton Bradley</p>
				<p>1995</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
	</div>











<div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvOTIwMjQzLzExMDkwNzUyLnBuZw==/250x600/amNZQl.png" loading="lazy"></p>
			
		</div>	
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvOTIwMjQzLzg3MjIxNTMucG5n/347x500/zmaMpA.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles</p>
				<p>Konami</p>
				<p>1989</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>	

		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjk5NjU2My8xNzkyMzcwNy5wbmc=/347x500/KVwIJt.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>The Lone Ranger</p>
				<p>Konami</p>
				<p>1989</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>

		
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMzAzNDAyNy8xODE0NDU5My5wbmc=/347x500/5xALX8.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Blades of Steel</p>
				<p>Konami</p>
				<p>1989</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
		
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjcyODk4Ni8xNjI3Njg3NC5wbmc=/347x500/Pjs%2Bxl.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Star Trek 25th Anniversary</p>
				<p>Konami</p>
				<p>1991</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>			



		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1nLzg5MDA0NjIucG5n/original/eEVMk0.png" loading="lazy"></p>
			
		</div>



	</div>











<div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjY4NTE3NS8xNjAwNTc2My5wbmc=/347x500/pbw9Ik.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Les Téléphones Fous<br>( Hot Line )</p>
				<p>Ludotronic</p>
				<p>1982</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>

		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjM0OTA4My8xMzkxNTIzMC5wbmc=/347x500/SoY6%2FG.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Asterix™<br>Hunt for the Boars</p>
				<p>Ludotronic</p>
				<p>1984</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>

	</div>













<div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTg1NjAwNC8xMDg5ODQwNC5wbmc=/347x500/nAUg26.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Auto Race</p>
				<p>Mattel Electronics</p>
				<p>1976</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjEyNjI1NS8xMzQ0MjU0Ni5wbmc=/347x500/lOPrOr.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Missile Attack \ Space Alert</p>
				<p>Mattel Electronics</p>
				<p>1977</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjIyNTc2My8xMzE3MzY3OC5wbmc=/250x600/c7BE8I.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Mind Boggler</p>
				<p>Mattel Electronics</p>
				<p>1978</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
	</div>







<div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMzE1MTI3Ni8xODgyNDkzMS5wbmc=/347x500/7LH4%2Bl.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Sonic's Speedway</p>
				<p>McDonalds</p>
				<p>2003</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>

		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMzE1MTEzOS8xODgyMjUwMi5wbmc=/347x500/SNf8Tj.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Tony Stewart Racing</p>
				<p>McDonalds</p>
				<p>2004</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>

	</div>
















<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjc0NzA2NC8xNjM5MjY5MC5wbmc=/347x500/Qfy19H.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Star Trek™ First Contact</p>
				<p>MGA</p>
				<p>1996</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>









<div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTk1NTEyNy8xMTQ5NjkwOC5wbmc=/347x500/wg%2Fzb7.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Block Buster</p>
				<p>Microvision</p>
				<p>1979</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTk1NTEzOC8xMTQ5NjkwNy5wbmc=/original/3Zk%2Bd6.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Phaser Strike</p>
				<p>Microvision</p>
				<p>1979</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
	</div>






<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMzIwMDY0Mi8xOTEwOTY4Ni5wbmc=/347x500/re10nC.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Splatter House</p>
				<p>Namco</p>
				<p>1988</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
























<div>
	
	
		<div>
			<p>Silver Series</p>
			<p>( April 1980 - October 1980 )</p>
			<p>In 1980 Nintendo released it's first series of handheld electronic games each featuring a dedicated LCD game with a bonus watch function. The silver metallic front plate gave the series it's name. </p>
		</div>	
	
	
		
		
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTc4NzI3Ny8xMDUwMjc4NC5wbmc=/347x500/fmcDu%2F.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>	
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTc4NzI4Mi8xMDUwMjgwMy5wbmc=/347x500/Oh6EeS.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>	
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTc4NzMxOS8xMDUwMjk3OS5wbmc=/347x500/2ZZ%2Bgd.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjE1ODI5Ni8xMjcxODg1MS5wbmc=/347x500/0Hvr7%2F.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjE3MzU4Ni8xMjgyNzk3MC5wbmc=/347x500/i6R6cG.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>

	
	
	
	
		<div>
			<p>Gold Series</p>
			<p>( January 1981 - April 1981 )</p>
			<p>After the huge success of the Silver Series Nintendo released the next generation of it's Game &amp; Watch™ handhelds the following year, featuring a new alarm function, color background-foils and a distinctive gold metallic front plate.  </p>
		</div>
	
	
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTc5ODMwMi8xMDU2MzY4OC5wbmc=/347x500/q8DN4W.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>	
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTc5ODMyMy8xMDU2Mzg3Ni5wbmc=/347x500/oiArp5.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>	
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTc5ODM0Ni8xMDU2Mzk0My5wbmc=/347x500/pDqAHw.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>

	
		<div>
			<p>Wide Screen Series</p>
			<p>( June 1981 - April 1982 )</p>
			<p>A bigger LCD screen and a brand new box design were the most prominent innovations in Nintendo's follow up to the Gold Series with an impressive line-up of timeless classics. </p>
			<p>Featuring a wide LCD screen and impressive line-up of timeless classics (including some of the first licenced titles) Nintendo's Wide Screen Series ranks among some of the most popular Game &amp; Watch™ titles.  </p>
		</div>
		

			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTQ1NTUxMi85MjE5NzU1LnBuZw==/250x600/4v6NP2.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>	
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTU5MzIyMS85MzE1NzIwLnBuZw==/250x600/eT%2B3yC.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>	
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvOTIwMjQzLzkyMjAxMzUucG5n/250x600/WaQYfH.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjM2MTIyMy8xMzk4NjIzNS5wbmc=/347x500/Eq3CWa.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjM2NjczMS8xNDAxNzA2MC5wbmc=/347x500/3iEDbX.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Mickey Mouse</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1981</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjEyNjI1NS8xNDAxNzYwNC5wbmc=/250x600/B96ksX.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjYyNTQ2Mi8xNTY0MzIyNy5wbmc=/347x500/WmOq5z.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjMxNTEwMy8xMzcxNzI0NC5wbmc=/347x500/P4njPB.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Fire Attack</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1982</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>		
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjMyNTIzMC8xMzc3MzQyNC5wbmc=/347x500/QdCErX.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Turtle Bridge</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1982</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjQzNTI5OS8xNDQyMDE3My5wbmc=/347x500/RKZHet.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Snoopy Tennis</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1982</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>		
			
		
		<div>
			<p>Multi Screen Series</p>
			<p>( May 1982 - August 1989 )</p>
			<p>In 1982 Nintendo introduced the innovative Multi Screen series whose most prominent feature was the use of two LCD screens in one foldable handheld with beautiful background-foil artwork and fine LCD elements.</p>
		</div>	
		
		
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1nLzg0OTg0MzQucG5n/original/S4tIOw.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Mario Bros.</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1983</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTY2ODc2NS85ODI1NDUxLnBuZw==/250x600/H8jF3B.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Rain Shower</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1983</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1nLzg0OTg0MjQucG5n/original/3P3%2Fpl.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>		
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTY2ODc2My85ODI1NDQ0LnBuZw==/250x600/VK1JzK.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1nLzg0OTg0MTcucG5n/original/6gVlA7.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Donkey Kong</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1982</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1nLzg0OTg0MjEucG5n/original/r3MIhA.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Donkey Kong II</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1983</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>	
		
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTc4MjgxMi8xMDQ4MDA4MS5wbmc=/250x600/hrEv7G.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Mickey &amp; Donald</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1982</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>	

			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTgyMDU5My8xMDY4ODAzMS5wbmc=/347x500/Cesp4g.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Green House</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1982</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>	

			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTkzNDE2NS8xMTM3MTU3Mi5wbmc=/347x500/SVjvHZ.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Safe Buster</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1988</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>	
			
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjQyNDM3My8xNDM0OTIyMS5wbmc=/347x500/anRpQw.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>	
		
	
		<div>
			<p>New Wide Screen Series</p>
			<p>( October 1982 - October 1991 )</p>
			<p>Nintendo made further subtle improvements to the earlier Wide Screen series with a new box design featuring vivid artwork and a more colorful metallic front plate making the single screen LCD handhelds even classier.</p>
		</div>	
		
		
		
		
		
		
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTc0Mjk3Ni8xMDI1NzMzNy5wbmc=/250x600/6Zg8Sy.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Donkey Kong Jr.</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1982</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>	
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjAxNjczMC8xMTg2MjQ3MC5wbmc=/347x500/D19zAE.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Mario's Cement Factory</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1983</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>	
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjQwNjQ3Mi8xNDI0NTQ5Mi5wbmc=/347x500/AVVrQe.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>		
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTk3MzExMS8xMTYwMjMzNi5wbmc=/347x500/fSxKPu.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Tropical Fish</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1985</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>		
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTkyNzgyMC8xMTMzMzU0Ny5wbmc=/347x500/m6VrWu.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Balloon Fight</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1988</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>	
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTczNTE0NC8xMDI1NzQxOS5wbmc=/250x600/BZ9prr.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>	

			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTcyNjA3NC8xMDI1NzQyMy5wbmc=/250x600/jm7QIo.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Super Mario Bros.</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1988</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>	

			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjUzMjg5MS8xNTA2NDIzMS5wbmc=/347x500/trM2kl.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Mario The Juggler</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1991</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>		


				
	
		<div>
			<p>Table Top Series</p>
			<p>( April 1983 - August 1983 )</p>		
			<p>Nintendo fulfilled the dream of many gamers to have their own mini arcade machine with the introduction of the Table Top Series which featured full color LCD graphics for the first time.</p>
		</div>		
		
		
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTY1ODI1MS85NzU4ODY3LnBuZw==/250x600/oQMoe6.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>	
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTU4MDgwOS85NzU4OTE1LnBuZw==/250x600/zIq36W.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Donkey Kong Jr.</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1983</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>
			
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTY1ODE0NS85NzU4NDIzLnBuZw==/250x600/uW9L35.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>	
				
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTY1ODA5NC85NzU4MDg5LnBuZw==/250x600/%2BUBcRw.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Mario's Cement Factory</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1983</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>

			
		<div>
			<p>Panorama Screen Series</p>
			<p>( August 1983 - September 1984 )</p>		
			<p>A few months after the introduction of the Table Top Series, Nintendo released a refinement of that technology in the form of the more portable Panorama Screen Series\.</p>
		</div>	
		
	
	
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTY1ODIxOC85NzU4ODYyLnBuZw==/250x600/1JjwLw.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTU4MDgwOS85NzU5MDY2LnBuZw==/250x600/TYM0uR.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Donkey Kong Jr.</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1983</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>	
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTQ1NTUxMi84OTc5NDE4LnBuZw==/250x600/Y%2FL7xz.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>		
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvOTIwMjQzLzg4MjQyMzIucG5n/original/3gR0se.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Donkey Kong Circus</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1984</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvOTIwMjQzLzg4MjQyMzgucG5n/original/mIWdkU.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Mario's Bombs Away</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1983</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTQ1NTUxMi84OTc5NDEwLnBuZw==/250x600/b0S%2FjX.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Mickey Mouse</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1984</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>
	
	
		<div>
			<p>Micro Vs. System</p>
			<p>( July 1984 - November 1984 )</p>		
			<p>The Micro Vs. System introduced two-player gaming to the Game &amp; Watch™ series by attaching two wired controllers to a foldable unit that featured a wide LCD screen.</p>
		</div>	
		
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTY4NTg2Ni85OTMwMTg2LnBuZw==/250x600/2O5SkG.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTY4NTg3Ni85OTMwMjkwLnBuZw==/250x600/NiORxd.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Donkey Kong 3</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1984</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTY4NTg5MS85OTI5OTc1LnBuZw==/250x600/iTN3zr.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Donkey Kong Hockey</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1984</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>

			
		<div>
			<p>Crystal Screen Series</p>
			<p>( June 1986 - November 1986 )</p>		
			<p>The Crystal Screen series introduced a new wide format translucent LCD handheld featuring a transparent see-thru screen and innovative side-scrolling gameplay.</p>
		</div>			
		
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTc4MjgxMi8xMDQ4MDA4MC5wbmc=/250x600/63eYKA.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Super Mario Bros</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1986</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTc4MjgxMi8xMDQ4MDA3OC5wbmc=/250x600/Rd%2BrhW.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>
			<br>
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjAxMDgzMC8xMjQ3Mzg2My5wbmc=/347x500/xm36eZ.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Balloon Fight</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1986</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>
	
		<div>
			<p>SuperColor Series</p>
			<p>( February 1984 )</p>		
			<p>Featuring a colored LCD screen that no longer required an external light source (required by the Table Top and Panorama Screen series) and a new large portrait format LCD screen, the Super Color Series was perfectly suited for the two games released in this format.</p>
		</div>			

			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTk0MjIyMy8xMTgyMzU0OS5wbmc=/347x500/xU9EPX.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Spitball Sparky</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1984</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjAxMDc5Ni8xMTgyMzQ1OC5wbmc=/347x500/mDJHjJ.png" loading="lazy"></p>
				
			</div>

	
		<div>
			<p>Special Editions</p>
			<p>( August 1987 )</p>		
			<p>Nintendo released a limited edition of it's Super Mario Bros handheld LCD game as a prize for winners of a competition it held in 1987. Only 10,000 copies were given away, making it the most rare of the 3 Game &amp; Watch versions of the game.</p>
		</div>			
	
			<div>
				<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTc4MjgxMi8xMDQ4MDA4Mi5wbmc=/250x600/jJiCMI.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
					<p>Super Mario Bros.</p>
					<p>Nintendo</p>
					<p>1987</p>
				</div>
				
			</div>
	</div>


<div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTg1ODgzNi8xMTA0MjYwNi5wbmc=/250x600/aMIpjQ.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Game Boy Gallery</p>
				<p>Nintendo</p>
				<p>1995</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvOTIwMjQzLzkxMDkzNjcucG5n/250x600/mXfyq0.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Game &amp; Watch Gallery</p>
				<p>Nintendo</p>
				<p>1997</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
		<br>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTQ1NTUxMi85MTU1MzI5LnBuZw==/250x600/KT22kH.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Game &amp; Watch Gallery 2</p>
				<p>Nintendo</p>
				<p>1998</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvOTIwMjQzLzkxOTIxOTMucG5n/250x600/UT0IIi.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Game &amp; Watch Gallery 3</p>
				<p>Nintendo</p>
				<p>1999</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>	
		<br>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTY5MjU4Ny85OTcxMDE0LnBuZw==/original/suYvNw.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Game &amp; Watch Gallery 4</p>
				<p>Nintendo</p>
				<p>2002</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>	
	</div>


<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMzE4MDE0NC8xODk5MDEwMy5wbmc=/347x500/ASk1kN.png" loading="lazy"></p>
			
		</div>




<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTg0MjAxMC8xMDgwOTMzNi5wbmc=/347x500/ERBOOW.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Game &amp; Watch Collection</p>
				<p>Nintendo</p>
				<p>2006</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>













<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjAwNjExMS8xMTc5Mzg2Ny5wbmc=/347x500/km4xiN.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Wildfire</p>
				<p>Parkey Brothers</p>
				<p>1979</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>


<div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMzA5MzEwNS8xODQ5NDk1MC5wbmc=/347x500/w47Wz7.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Plane &amp; Tank</p>
				<p>Radio Shack</p>
				<p>1986</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjg4ODg0MS8xNzI3Njk5NC5wbmc=/347x500/3dS0mf.png" loading="lazy"></p>
			
		</div>
		<br>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMzI1MzI3Ny8xOTQyNDE4Mi5wbmc=/347x500/aI7F3S.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Space Alien</p>
				<p>Radio Shack</p>
				<p>1989</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>

	</div>



<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjg2NjA2My8xNzEzNDE1NS5wbmc=/347x500/fU0Hnm.png" loading="lazy"></p>
			
		</div>




<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjk3NDY5OS8xNzc5Mzg3OC5wbmc=/347x500/m6rCuq.png" loading="lazy"></p>
			
		</div>







<div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjE1Mjg5OC8xMjY5NTA4NS5wbmc=/347x500/mBFjd6.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Peter Pan &amp; The Pirates</p>
				<p>Tiger Electronics</p>
				<p>1991</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMTYxNjAyNy85NDYxNDY0LnBuZw==/250x600/SqL%2BC7.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Dennis the Menace</p>
				<p>Tiger Electronics</p>
				<p>1993</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
		<br>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjUyMDE1Ni8xNDk4NTYyMS5wbmc=/347x500/6ULx9w.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>The Simpsons™<br>Bart vs Homersaurus</p>
				<p>Tiger Electronics</p>
				<p>1994</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMzI5MjcxMC8xOTY1NjE4MS5wbmc=/347x500/9TeWyz.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>All Out Action<br>Snowboarding</p>
				<p>Tiger Electronics</p>
				<p>1999</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
	
	</div>













<div>
		
		
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjI3Nzk2Mi8xMzQ5Njc3Ny5wbmc=/347x500/nvxAUl.png" loading="lazy"></p>
			
		</div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjI2MTU4Mi8xMzQwNzMyOC5wbmc=/347x500/YPXkVX.png" loading="lazy"></p><div>
				<p>Thundering Turbo</p>
				<p>TOMY</p>
				<p>1983</p>
			</div>
			
		</div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjc2NTI4MC8xNjQ5NzQyNS5wbmc=/347x500/uv0LWb.png" loading="lazy"></p>
			
		</div>

		<br>
		
		
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjEyNjI1NS8xNDExMjg2NC5wbmc=/250x600/PVPyEb.png" loading="lazy"></p>
			
		</div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjM1ODI3My8xNDExMjM1MC5wbmc=/347x500/9vKq2%2B.png" loading="lazy"></p>
			
		</div>		

		<br>
		
		
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://img.itch.zone/aW1hZ2UvMjk0MDExNi8xNzYwNzUxNS5wbmc=/347x500/vMYcm1.png" loading="lazy"></p>
			
		</div>

		
	</div>












</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mathematics in the 20th century, by Michael Atiyah [pdf] (2002) (104 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://marktomforde.com/academic/miscellaneous/images/atiyah20thcentury.pdf</link>
            <guid>42989419</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 08:54:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://marktomforde.com/academic/miscellaneous/images/atiyah20thcentury.pdf">https://marktomforde.com/academic/miscellaneous/images/atiyah20thcentury.pdf</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42989419">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Modern-Day Oracles or Bullshit Machines (533 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://thebullshitmachines.com</link>
            <guid>42989320</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 08:24:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://thebullshitmachines.com">https://thebullshitmachines.com</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42989320">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="article" role="main">
      <header id="section-Title-2kXZCkIeDI" data-effects="eyJ0ZXh0UGVyTGluZSI6ZmFsc2UsInRleHRGYWRlIjoibm9uZSIsImhhc0VmZmVjdHMiOmZhbHNlLCJuZWVkc0JhY2tncm91bmRDbG9uZSI6ZmFsc2UsImVuY29kZWQiOiIifQ==">
        
        
      </header>
      <div data-scrollymoly-basis="true" data-testid="ENG-5457" id="section-EqRDrghv5N" data-effects="eyJ0ZXh0UGVyTGluZSI6ZmFsc2UsInRleHRGYWRlIjoiYm90aCIsInRleHRCbHVyIjoiYm90aCIsImJhY2tncm91bmRCbHVyIjoiYm90aCIsImJhY2tncm91bmRHcmF5c2NhbGUiOiJvdXQiLCJoYXNFZmZlY3RzIjp0cnVlLCJuZWVkc0JhY2tncm91bmRDbG9uZSI6dHJ1ZSwiZW5jb2RlZCI6IiJ9">
                  <h2><span>MODERN-DAY </span><span>ORACLES  </span><br><span>or </span><span>BULLSHIT</span><span><strong> </strong>MACHINES?</span></h2>
                  <p><span>How to thrive in a ChatGPT world  </span></p>
                  
                  <h4><span>Developed by Carl T. Bergstrom and Jevin D. West</span></h4>
                </div>
      
      
      <div id="section-Effects-on-life-gXGw9X23fi" data-effects="eyJ0ZXh0UGVyTGluZSI6ZmFsc2UsImhhc0VmZmVjdHMiOmZhbHNlLCJuZWVkc0JhY2tncm91bmRDbG9uZSI6ZmFsc2UsImVuY29kZWQiOiIifQ==">
              <div>
                    <p>Technologists and publicists gush about how Large Language Models (LLMs) will revolutionize the way we work, learn, play, communicate, create, and connect to another. </p>
                    <p>They are right that artificial intelligence (AI) will affect nearly every aspect of our daily lives. </p>
                    <p>And they are right that by providing a way for people to talk with machines in ordinary language, LLMs constitute a dramatic step forward in making computing accessible to everyone. </p>
                    <p>Yet for all the good that AI systems will do, they will also saturate our information environment with bullshit at a scale we’ve never before encountered.</p>
                    
                  </div>
              <div>
                      <blockquote><span>I think it's going to be the most transformative technology humanity has ever created, potentially on par with or exceeding the invention of the printing press, electricity, and the internet.</span>
                        
                      </blockquote>
                    </div>
            </div>
      <div data-scrollymoly-basis="true" data-testid="ENG-5457" id="section-Course-goals-We6QHjJFqp" data-effects="eyJ0ZXh0UGVyTGluZSI6ZmFsc2UsImhhc0VmZmVjdHMiOmZhbHNlLCJuZWVkc0JhY2tncm91bmRDbG9uZSI6ZmFsc2UsImVuY29kZWQiOiIifQ==">
                  <p><span>For better or for worse, LLMs are here to stay. We all read content that they produce online, most of us interact with LLM chatbots, and many of us use them to produce content of our own.</span></p>
                  
                  <p>In a series of five- to ten-minute lessons, we will explain what these machines are, how they work, and how to thrive in a world where they are everywhere.</p>
                  
                  <p>You will learn when these systems can save you a lot of time and effort. You will learn when they are likely to steer you wrong. And you will discover how to see through the hype to tell the difference. <span><em>?</em></span></p>
                </div>
      <div id="section-O0UgCe5GaC" data-effects="eyJ0ZXh0UGVyTGluZSI6ZmFsc2UsImhhc0VmZmVjdHMiOmZhbHNlLCJuZWVkc0JhY2tncm91bmRDbG9uZSI6ZmFsc2UsImVuY29kZWQiOiIifQ==">
                    <p><strong>Notice of Rights. </strong>The materials provided on this website are freely accessible for personal self-study and for non-commercial educational use in K-12 schools, colleges, and universities. For any commercial or corporate use, please <a href="mailto:cbergst@uw.edu,jevinw@uw.edu">contact the authors</a> to discuss terms and obtain the necessary permissions. Redistribution of website content is prohibited without prior written consent from the authors. However, individual copies may be created to accommodate accessibility needs directly related to educational instruction. </p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise stated, all content is copyrighted © 2025 by the authors. All rights reserved.</p>
                  </div>
      
      
    </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Brain Hyperconnectivity in Children with Autism and Its Links to Social Deficits (2013) (119 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cell.com/cell-reports/fulltext/S2211-1247(13)00570-6</link>
            <guid>42988303</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 03:54:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cell.com/cell-reports/fulltext/S2211-1247(13)00570-6">https://www.cell.com/cell-reports/fulltext/S2211-1247(13)00570-6</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42988303">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.cell.com/cell-reports/fulltext/S2211-1247(13)00570-6: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>