<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 18:30:06 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Claude Code 2.0 (111 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.npmjs.com/package/@anthropic-ai/claude-code</link>
            <guid>45416228</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:12:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/@anthropic-ai/claude-code">https://www.npmjs.com/package/@anthropic-ai/claude-code</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45416228">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.npmjs.com/package/@anthropic-ai/claude-code: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Claude Sonnet 4.5 (448 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.anthropic.com/news/claude-sonnet-4-5</link>
            <guid>45415962</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 16:52:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/claude-sonnet-4-5">https://www.anthropic.com/news/claude-sonnet-4-5</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45415962">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div><p>Claude Sonnet 4.5 is the best coding model in the world. It's the strongest model for building complex agents. It’s the best model at using computers. And it shows substantial gains in reasoning and math.</p><p>Code is everywhere. It runs every application, spreadsheet, and software tool you use. Being able to use those tools and reason through hard problems is how modern work gets done.</p><p>Claude Sonnet 4.5 makes this possible. We're releasing it along with a set of major upgrades to our products. In <a href="https://anthropic.com/news/enabling-claude-code-to-work-more-autonomously" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Claude Code</a>, we've added checkpoints—one of our most requested features—that save your progress and allow you to roll back instantly to a previous state. We've refreshed the terminal interface and shipped a <a href="https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=anthropic.claude-code" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">native VS Code extension</a>. We've added a new <a href="https://anthropic.com/news/context-management" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">context editing feature and memory tool</a> to the Claude API that lets agents run even longer and handle even greater complexity. In the Claude <a href="https://claude.ai/redirect/website.v1.f79c597c-8da8-4257-a3ef-0233ea5a1dd0/download" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">apps</a>, we've brought code execution and <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/create-files" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">file creation</a> (spreadsheets, slides, and documents) directly into the conversation. And we've made the <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/claude-for-chrome" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Claude for Chrome</a> extension available to Max users who joined the waitlist last month.</p><p>We're also giving developers the building blocks we use ourselves to make Claude Code. We're calling this the <a href="https://anthropic.com/engineering/building-agents-with-the-claude-agent-sdk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Claude Agent SDK</a>. The infrastructure that powers our frontier products—and allows them to reach their full potential—is now yours to build with.</p><p>This is the <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/claude-sonnet-4-5-system-card" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">most aligned frontier model</a> we’ve ever released, showing large improvements across several areas of alignment compared to previous Claude models.</p><p>Claude Sonnet 4.5 is available everywhere today. If you’re a developer, simply use <code>claude-sonnet-4-5</code> via <a href="https://docs.claude.com/en/docs/about-claude/models/overview" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">the Claude API</a>. Pricing remains the same as Claude Sonnet 4, at $3/$15 per million tokens.</p><h2 id="frontier-intelligence">Frontier intelligence</h2><p>Claude Sonnet 4.5 is state-of-the-art on the SWE-bench Verified evaluation, which measures real-world software coding abilities. Practically speaking, we’ve observed it maintaining focus for more than 30 hours on complex, multi-step tasks.</p><div><figure><img alt="Chart showing frontier model performance on SWE-bench Verified with Claude Sonnet 4.5 leading" loading="lazy" width="3840" height="2160" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.anthropic.com/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww-cdn.anthropic.com%2Fimages%2F4zrzovbb%2Fwebsite%2F6421e7049ff8b2c4591497ec92dc4157b2ac1b30-3840x2160.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 1x" src="https://www.anthropic.com/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww-cdn.anthropic.com%2Fimages%2F4zrzovbb%2Fwebsite%2F6421e7049ff8b2c4591497ec92dc4157b2ac1b30-3840x2160.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></figure></div><p>Claude Sonnet 4.5 represents a significant leap forward on computer use. On OSWorld, a benchmark that tests AI models on real-world computer tasks, Sonnet 4.5 now leads at 61.4%. Just four months ago, Sonnet 4 held the lead at 42.2%. Our <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/claude-for-chrome" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Claude for Chrome</a> extension puts these upgraded capabilities to use. In the demo below, we show Claude working directly in a browser, navigating sites, filling spreadsheets, and completing tasks.</p><p>The model also shows improved capabilities on a broad range of evaluations including reasoning and math:</p><div><figure><img alt="Benchmark table comparing frontier models across popular public evals" loading="lazy" width="2600" height="2288" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.anthropic.com/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww-cdn.anthropic.com%2Fimages%2F4zrzovbb%2Fwebsite%2F2825bb34cb9b9aa1ef347f816c590b5bbdae2b4d-2600x2288.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 1x" src="https://www.anthropic.com/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww-cdn.anthropic.com%2Fimages%2F4zrzovbb%2Fwebsite%2F2825bb34cb9b9aa1ef347f816c590b5bbdae2b4d-2600x2288.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"><figcaption>Claude Sonnet 4.5 is our most powerful model to date. See footnotes for methodology.</figcaption></figure></div><p>Experts in finance, law, medicine, and STEM found Sonnet 4.5 shows dramatically better domain-specific knowledge and reasoning compared to older models, including Opus 4.1.</p><p>The model’s capabilities are also reflected in the experiences of early customers:</p><div><div><p><img alt=" logo" loading="lazy" width="120" height="48" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://www-cdn.anthropic.com/images/4zrzovbb/website/464cf83cd04ad624fee1730a71914b18e89cdf9b-150x48.svg"></p><p><span>“</span></p><blockquote><p><strong>We're seeing state-of-the-art coding performance from Claude Sonnet 4.5</strong>, with significant improvements on longer horizon tasks. It reinforces why many developers using Cursor choose Claude for solving their most complex problems.</p></blockquote></div><div><p><img alt=" logo" loading="lazy" width="120" height="48" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://www-cdn.anthropic.com/images/4zrzovbb/website/7715b118c5eb0ff2a85f1f7914bce8c634ecacbd-150x48.svg"></p><p><span>“</span></p><blockquote><p><strong>Claude Sonnet 4.5 amplifies GitHub Copilot's core strengths</strong>. Our initial evals show significant improvements in multi-step reasoning and code comprehension—enabling Copilot's agentic experiences to handle complex, codebase-spanning tasks better.</p></blockquote></div><div><p><img alt=" logo" loading="lazy" width="120" height="48" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://www-cdn.anthropic.com/images/4zrzovbb/website/daef759120b29e4db8ba4a5664d7574750964ab9-150x48.svg"></p><p><span>“</span></p><blockquote><p><strong>Claude Sonnet 4.5 is excellent at software development tasks</strong>, learning our codebase patterns to deliver precise implementations. It handles everything from debugging to architecture with deep contextual understanding, transforming our development velocity.</p></blockquote></div><div><p><img alt=" logo" loading="lazy" width="120" height="48" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://www-cdn.anthropic.com/images/4zrzovbb/website/eb96f772e9ae5e340de41e6b07f3c6d50b3fff22-150x48.svg"></p><p><span>“</span></p><blockquote><p>Claude Sonnet 4.5 <strong>reduced average vulnerability intake time for our Hai security agents by 44% while improving accuracy by 25%</strong>, helping us reduce risk for businesses with confidence.</p></blockquote></div><div><p><img alt=" logo" loading="lazy" width="120" height="48" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://www-cdn.anthropic.com/images/4zrzovbb/website/8cbf56e184dd5174705a0f55cb91b0af545982ff-150x48.svg"></p><p><span>“</span></p><blockquote><p><strong>Claude Sonnet 4.5 is state of the art on the most complex litigation tasks.</strong> For example, analyzing full briefing cycles and conducting research to synthesize excellent first drafts of an opinion for judges, or interrogating entire litigation records to create detailed summary judgment analysis.</p></blockquote></div><div><p><img alt=" logo" loading="lazy" width="120" height="48" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://www-cdn.anthropic.com/images/4zrzovbb/website/431e098a503851789fa4508b88a0418853f513eb-150x48.svg"></p><p><span>“</span></p><blockquote><p>Claude Sonnet 4.5's edit capabilities are exceptional —<strong> we went from 9% error rate on Sonnet 4 to 0% on our internal code editing benchmark</strong>. Higher tool success at lower cost is a major leap for agentic coding. Claude Sonnet 4.5 balances creativity and control perfectly.</p></blockquote></div><div><p><img alt=" logo" loading="lazy" width="120" height="48" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://www-cdn.anthropic.com/images/4zrzovbb/website/66e0000e396aea64ea31ed3fea7b2b20ac329312-150x48.svg"></p><p><span>“</span></p><blockquote><p>Claude Sonnet 4.5 delivers impressive gains on our most complex, long-context tasks—from engineering in our codebase to in-product features and research. <strong>It's noticeably more intelligent and a big leap forward</strong>, helping us push what 240M+ users can design with Canva.</p></blockquote></div><div><p><img alt=" logo" loading="lazy" width="120" height="48" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://www-cdn.anthropic.com/images/4zrzovbb/website/cdec0ff1244295571db38838e90f61c47681d63d-150x48.svg"></p><p><span>“</span></p><blockquote><p><strong>Claude Sonnet 4.5 has noticeably improved Figma Make in early testing</strong>, making it easier to prompt and iterate. Teams can explore and validate their ideas with more functional prototypes and smoother interactions, while still getting the design quality Figma is known for.</p></blockquote></div><div><p><img alt=" logo" loading="lazy" width="120" height="48" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://www-cdn.anthropic.com/images/4zrzovbb/website/094b76abf3e64453c224e12ae388b8008b02660e-150x48.svg"></p><p><span>“</span></p><blockquote><p><strong>Sonnet 4.5 represents a new generation of coding models</strong>. It's surprisingly efficient at maximizing actions per context window through parallel tool execution, for example running multiple bash commands at once. </p></blockquote></div><div><p><img alt=" logo" loading="lazy" width="120" height="48" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://www-cdn.anthropic.com/images/4zrzovbb/website/6e418ccebe0a1d6fd13f21094852b080a0c93ae5-150x48.svg"></p><p><span>“</span></p><blockquote><p>For Devin, Claude Sonnet 4.5 increased planning performance by 18% and end-to-end eval scores by 12%—<strong>the biggest jump we've seen since the release of Claude Sonnet 3.6</strong>. It excels at testing its own code, enabling Devin to run longer, handle harder tasks, and deliver production-ready code.</p></blockquote></div><div><p><img alt=" logo" loading="lazy" width="120" height="48" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://www-cdn.anthropic.com/images/4zrzovbb/website/5a7dfab326b449aedc0d11053f9d42f48951ae7e-150x48.svg"></p><p><span>“</span></p><blockquote><p><strong>Claude Sonnet 4.5 shows strong promise for red teaming</strong>, generating creative attack scenarios that accelerate how we study attacker tradecraft. These insights strengthen our defenses across endpoints, identity, cloud, data, SaaS, and AI workloads.</p></blockquote></div><div><p><img alt=" logo" loading="lazy" width="120" height="48" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://www-cdn.anthropic.com/images/4zrzovbb/website/b0b6b40b55f3aa73e8a32ce81f9bb927134fd3da-150x48.svg"></p><p><span>“</span></p><blockquote><p>Claude Sonnet 4.5 resets our expectations—<strong>it handles 30+ hours of autonomous coding</strong>, freeing our engineers to tackle months of complex architectural work in dramatically less time while maintaining coherence across massive codebases.</p></blockquote></div><div><p><img alt=" logo" loading="lazy" width="120" height="48" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://www-cdn.anthropic.com/images/4zrzovbb/website/4fcce1a2389ddafa9f3302c51960e1ff4bfbd3d7-150x48.svg"></p><p><span>“</span></p><blockquote><p>For complex financial analysis—risk, structured products, portfolio screening—Claude Sonnet 4.5 with thinking <strong>delivers investment-grade insights that require less human review</strong>. When depth matters more than speed, it's a meaningful step forward for institutional finance.</p></blockquote></div></div><h2 id="our-most-aligned-model-yet">Our most aligned model yet</h2><p>As well as being our most capable model, Claude Sonnet 4.5 is our most aligned frontier model yet. Claude’s improved capabilities and our extensive safety training have allowed us to substantially improve the model’s behavior, reducing concerning behaviors like sycophancy, deception, power-seeking, and the tendency to encourage delusional thinking. For the model’s agentic and computer use capabilities, we’ve also made considerable progress on defending against prompt injection attacks, one of the most serious risks for users of these capabilities.</p><p>You can read a detailed set of safety and alignment evaluations, which for the first time includes tests using techniques from mechanistic interpretability, in the Claude Sonnet 4.5 <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/claude-sonnet-4-5-system-card" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">system card</a>.</p><div><figure><img loading="lazy" width="3840" height="2160" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.anthropic.com/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww-cdn.anthropic.com%2Fimages%2F4zrzovbb%2Fwebsite%2F33efc283321feeff94dd80973dbcd38409806cf5-3840x2160.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 1x" src="https://www.anthropic.com/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww-cdn.anthropic.com%2Fimages%2F4zrzovbb%2Fwebsite%2F33efc283321feeff94dd80973dbcd38409806cf5-3840x2160.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"><figcaption>Overall misaligned behavior scores from an automated behavioral auditor (lower is better). Misaligned behaviors include (but are not limited to) deception, sycophancy, power-seeking, encouragement of delusions, and compliance with harmful system prompts. More details can be found in the Claude Sonnet 4.5 <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/claude-sonnet-4-5-system-card">system card</a>.</figcaption></figure></div><p>Claude Sonnet 4.5 is being released under our AI Safety Level 3 (ASL-3) protections, as per <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/announcing-our-updated-responsible-scaling-policy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">our framework</a> that matches model capabilities with appropriate safeguards. These safeguards include filters called classifiers that aim to detect potentially dangerous inputs and outputs—in particular those related to chemical, biological, radiological, and nuclear (CBRN) weapons.</p><p>These classifiers might sometimes inadvertently flag normal content. We’ve made it easy for users to continue any interrupted conversations with Sonnet 4, a model that poses a lower CBRN risk. We've already made significant progress in reducing these false positives, reducing them by a factor of ten since <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/constitutional-classifiers" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">we originally described them</a>, and a factor of two since Claude Opus 4 was released in May. We’re continuing to make progress in making the classifiers more discerning<sup>1</sup>.</p><h2 id="the-claude-agent-sdk">The Claude Agent SDK</h2><p>We've spent more than six months shipping updates to Claude Code, so we know what it takes to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DAQJvGjlgVM" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">build</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vLIDHi-1PVU" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">design</a> AI agents. We've solved hard problems: how agents should manage memory across long-running tasks, how to handle permission systems that balance autonomy with user control, and how to coordinate subagents working toward a shared goal.</p><p>Now we’re making all of this available to you. The <a href="https://anthropic.com/engineering/building-agents-with-the-claude-agent-sdk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Claude Agent SDK</a> is the same infrastructure that powers Claude Code, but it shows impressive benefits for a very wide variety of tasks, not just coding. As of today, you can use it to build your own agents.</p><p>We built Claude Code because the tool we wanted didn’t exist yet. The Agent SDK gives you the same foundation to build something just as capable for whatever problem you're solving.</p><h2 id="bonus-research-preview">Bonus research preview</h2><p>We’re releasing a temporary research preview alongside Claude Sonnet 4.5, called "<a href="https://claude.ai/redirect/website.v1.f79c597c-8da8-4257-a3ef-0233ea5a1dd0/imagine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Imagine with Claude</a>".</p><p>In this experiment, Claude generates software on the fly. No functionality is predetermined; no code is prewritten. What you see is Claude creating in real time, responding and adapting to your requests as you interact.</p><p>It's a fun demonstration showing what Claude Sonnet 4.5 can do—a way to see what's possible when you combine a capable model with the right infrastructure.</p><p>"Imagine with Claude" is available to Max subscribers for the next five days. We encourage you to try it out on <a href="https://claude.ai/redirect/website.v1.f79c597c-8da8-4257-a3ef-0233ea5a1dd0/imagine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">claude.ai/imagine</a>.</p><h2 id="further-information">Further information</h2><p>We recommend upgrading to Claude Sonnet 4.5 for all uses. Whether you’re using Claude through our apps, our API, or Claude Code, Sonnet 4.5 is a drop-in replacement that provides much improved performance for the same price. Claude Code updates are available to all users. <a href="https://claude.com/platform/api" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Claude Developer Platform</a> updates, including the Claude Agent SDK, are available to all developers. Code execution and file creation are available on all paid plans in the Claude apps.</p><p>For complete technical details and evaluation results, see our <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/claude-sonnet-4-5-system-card" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">system card</a>, <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/claude/sonnet" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">model page</a>, and <a href="https://docs.claude.com/en/docs/about-claude/models/overview" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">documentation</a>. For more information, explore our <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/engineering/building-agents-with-the-claude-agent-sdk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">engineering</a> <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/engineering/effective-context-engineering-for-ai-agents" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">posts</a> and research post on <a href="https://red.anthropic.com/2025/ai-for-cyber-defenders" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">cybersecurity</a>.</p></div></article></div><div><h4>Footnotes</h4><div><p><em>1<strong>: </strong>Customers in the cybersecurity and biological research industries can work with their account teams to join our allowlist in the meantime.</em></p><p><strong>Methodology</strong></p></div><ul><li><strong>SWE-bench Verified</strong>: All Claude results were reported using a simple scaffold with two tools—bash and file editing via string replacements. We report 77.2%, which was averaged over 10 trials, no test-time compute, and 200K thinking budget on the full 500-problem SWE-bench Verified dataset.<ul><li>The score reported uses a minor prompt addition: "You should use tools as much as possible, ideally more than 100 times. You should also implement your own tests first before attempting the problem."</li><li>A 1M context configuration achieves 78.2%, but we report the 200K result as our primary score as the 1M configuration was implicated in our recent <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/engineering/a-postmortem-of-three-recent-issues">inference issues</a>.</li><li>For our "high compute" numbers we adopt additional complexity and parallel test-time compute as follows:<ul><li>We sample multiple parallel attempts.</li><li>We discard patches that break the visible regression tests in the repository, similar to the rejection sampling approach adopted by <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01489">Agentless</a> (Xia et al. 2024); note no hidden test information is used.</li><li>We then use an internal scoring model to select the best candidate from the remaining attempts.</li><li>This results in a score of 82.0% for Sonnet 4.5.</li></ul></li></ul></li><li><strong>Terminal-Bench</strong>: All scores reported use the default agent framework (Terminus 2), with XML parser, averaging multiple runs during different days to smooth the eval sensitivity to inference infrastructure.</li><li><strong>τ2-bench: </strong>Scores were achieved using extended thinking with tool use and a prompt addendum to the Airline and Telecom Agent Policy instructing Claude to better target its known failure modes when using the vanilla prompt. A prompt addendum was also added to the Telecom User prompt to avoid failure modes from the user ending the interaction incorrectly.</li><li><strong>AIME</strong>: Sonnet 4.5 score reported using sampling at temperature 1.0. The model used 64K reasoning tokens for the Python configuration.</li><li><strong>OSWorld: </strong>All scores reported use the official OSWorld-Verified framework with 100 max steps, averaged across 4 runs.</li><li><strong>MMMLU</strong>: All scores reported are the average of 5 runs over 14 non-English languages with extended thinking (up to 128K).</li><li><strong>Finance Agent</strong>: All scores reported were run and published by <a href="https://vals.ai/">Vals AI</a> on their public leaderboard. All Claude model results reported are with extended thinking (up to 64K) and Sonnet 4.5 is reported with interleaved thinking on.</li><li>All OpenAI scores reported from their <a href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-gpt-5/">GPT-5 post</a>, <a href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-gpt-5-for-developers/">GPT-5 for developers post</a>, <a href="https://cdn.openai.com/gpt-5-system-card.pdf">GPT-5 system card</a> (SWE-bench Verified reported using n=500), <a href="https://www.tbench.ai/">Terminal Bench leaderboard</a> (using Terminus 2), and public <a href="http://vals.ai/">Vals AI</a> leaderboard. All Gemini scores reported from their <a href="https://deepmind.google/models/gemini/pro/">model web page</a>, <a href="https://www.tbench.ai/">Terminal Bench leaderboard</a> (using Terminus 1), and public <a href="https://vals.ai/">Vals AI</a> leaderboard.</li></ul></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Loadmo.re: design inspiration for unconventional web (104 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://loadmo.re</link>
            <guid>45415207</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 15:42:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://loadmo.re">https://loadmo.re</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45415207">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://loadmo.re: Error [ERR_FR_TOO_MANY_REDIRECTS]: Maximum number of redirects exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Electronic Arts Goes Private for $52.5B in Largest LBO (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wsj.com/business/deals/electronic-arts-to-go-private-in-55-billion-deal-a4a4479c</link>
            <guid>45413767</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 13:47:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wsj.com/business/deals/electronic-arts-to-go-private-in-55-billion-deal-a4a4479c">https://www.wsj.com/business/deals/electronic-arts-to-go-private-in-55-billion-deal-a4a4479c</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45413767">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.wsj.com/business/deals/electronic-arts-to-go-private-in-55-billion-deal-a4a4479c: Error: Request failed with status code 401]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why friction is necessary for growth (105 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://jameelur.com/blog/overcoming-friction-leads-to-growth</link>
            <guid>45413654</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 13:39:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://jameelur.com/blog/overcoming-friction-leads-to-growth">https://jameelur.com/blog/overcoming-friction-leads-to-growth</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45413654">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-mdx-content="true"><p><img alt="" loading="lazy" width="1200" height="627" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://jameelur.com/_next/image?url=%2F_next%2Fstatic%2Fmedia%2Ffriction-growth.dcafe3c3.png&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1x, https://jameelur.com/_next/image?url=%2F_next%2Fstatic%2Fmedia%2Ffriction-growth.dcafe3c3.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://jameelur.com/_next/image?url=%2F_next%2Fstatic%2Fmedia%2Ffriction-growth.dcafe3c3.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></p><p>The title of this article says it all. Overcoming friction leads to growth. Comfort leads to stagnation.</p>
<p>ChatGPT and by extension “AI” is likely the biggest “revolution” of my generation. It is likely also going to be the biggest killer of creativity in my generation. I always thought the creativity killer was going to be access to infinite entertainment. I think I was wrong.</p>
<p>I’ve come to believe that with the rise of convenience and comfort, it becomes harder for us to reach our potential. Technology and Capitalism is taking us towards an extreme.</p>
<p>A certain level of convenience can lead to efficiency gains. Automation is important for a reason. Too much convenience though, that's a killer. When friction was inherent in the system, applying ourselves led to growth as we overcame that friction. We simply didn’t have an alternative that was viable. And this principle applies to everything.</p>
<p>When I was a child in Sri Lanka, I ended up memorizing the landline numbers of all my close relatives. To this day I remember them. The moment I got a phone where my contacts could be saved, I stopped remembering numbers. It may seem like a small thing but it illustrates the principle. The ease of access to information has geared us towards efficiently looking up information instead of remembering it. I won't argue the utility of having hundreds of numbers saved on your phone, I simply want to make a point. Overcoming friction leads to growth.</p>
<p>Let's take another activity where creativity is important, writing. When it's easier to prompt ChatGPT to write your college essay, you'll never apply yourself. Afterall, when everyone is doing it, why not you? As everyone uses ChatGPT, the expectation of high quality writing will increase, making it harder for people to be vulnerable. You can’t become a master without making mistakes and learning from it.</p>
<p>Humans are creatures of comfort. Just like so many things in this world, we follow the path of least resistance. With access to technology being ubiquitous, and ChatGPT being so widely available, to choose not to use it is very hard. You need to deliberately prioritize your growth and choose to go against the current. You need to deliberately introduce friction to the process.</p>
<p>That said, total abstinence is not the solution. ChatGPT is here to stay. Just like most advancements in technology are. As a child of the 21st Century, you’ll need to learn to utilize this new tool in a manner that aids you, not hinders you. More importantly, not hinder the <strong>future</strong> you.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Meta-analysis of 2.2M people: Loneliness increases mortality risk by 32% (291 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lightcapai.medium.com/the-loneliness-epidemic-threatens-physical-health-like-smoking-e063220dde8b</link>
            <guid>45413481</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 13:25:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lightcapai.medium.com/the-loneliness-epidemic-threatens-physical-health-like-smoking-e063220dde8b">https://lightcapai.medium.com/the-loneliness-epidemic-threatens-physical-health-like-smoking-e063220dde8b</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45413481">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://lightcapai.medium.com/the-loneliness-epidemic-threatens-physical-health-like-smoking-e063220dde8b: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Larry Ellison – 'citizens will be on their best behavior' amid nonstop recording (171 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fortune.com/2025/09/28/larry-ellison-ai-surveillance-oracle-tiktok-deal-social-media/</link>
            <guid>45413090</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 12:51:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fortune.com/2025/09/28/larry-ellison-ai-surveillance-oracle-tiktok-deal-social-media/">https://fortune.com/2025/09/28/larry-ellison-ai-surveillance-oracle-tiktok-deal-social-media/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45413090">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-cy="article-content" id="article-content"><p>A year ago, <a href="https://fortune.com/company/oracle/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/oracle/">Oracle</a> cofounder and Chairman Larry Ellison described a future where everyone, including law enforcement, <a href="https://fortune.com/2024/09/17/oracle-larry-ellison-surveillance-state-police-ai/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/2024/09/17/oracle-larry-ellison-surveillance-state-police-ai/" data-type="link" data-id="https://fortune.com/2024/09/17/oracle-larry-ellison-surveillance-state-police-ai/">will face regular surveillance</a> as daily life is documented seemingly nonstop.</p><div>



<p>At Oracle’s&nbsp;<a href="https://www.oracle.com/events/financial-analyst-meeting-2024/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="Go to https://www.oracle.com/events/financial-analyst-meeting-2024/">financial analyst meeting</a>&nbsp;last September, he predicted artificial intelligence will help process the vast amounts of footage recorded by cameras placed on everything from car dashboards and front doors to security systems and cops.



</p><p>“We’re going to have supervision,” Ellison said. “Every police officer is going to be supervised at all times, and if there’s a problem, AI will report that problem and report it to the appropriate person. Citizens will be on their best behavior because we are constantly recording and reporting everything that’s going on.”



</p><p>Those comments have gained fresh relevance now that his company has emerged as a major player in the AI industry and is poised to play a critical role in the deal for TikTok’s U.S. operations. TikTok’s video-sharing platform is among the most popular social media properties in the country.



</p><p>Oracle didn’t immediately respond to a request for comment.</p><p>The company has been an AI infrastructure provider and stunned Wall Street earlier this month by reaching a <a href="https://www.wsj.com/business/openai-oracle-sign-300-billion-computing-deal-among-biggest-in-history-ff27c8fe?st=vUBGuq&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="Go to https://www.wsj.com/business/openai-oracle-sign-300-billion-computing-deal-among-biggest-in-history-ff27c8fe?st=vUBGuq&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink" data-type="link" data-id="https://www.wsj.com/business/openai-oracle-sign-300-billion-computing-deal-among-biggest-in-history-ff27c8fe?st=vUBGuq&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink">$300 billion deal with OpenAI</a>, which will purchase computing power over about five years in one of the largest cloud contracts ever signed. 



</p><p>And earlier this week, OpenAI signed deals with SoftBank and Oracle&nbsp;for new data centers as part of the massive Stargate Project.



</p><p>In its most recent quarterly earnings call with analysts, management also offered&nbsp;revenue projections that cited $455 billion in contracts, up 359% from a year earlier.&nbsp;CEO Safra Catz&nbsp;revealed that Oracle landed deals with three different customers during the quarter.



</p><p>Meanwhile, <a href="https://fortune.com/how-we-test-supplements/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/how-we-test-supplements/" data-type="page" data-id="4319596">Oracle is expected to be among the companies</a> that will buy TikTok’s U.S. business from Chinese parent company ByteDance. In addition, Oracle&nbsp;will spearhead U.S. oversight of the algorithm and security.



</p><p>President Donald Trump on Thursday afternoon signed an executive order clearing the way for a deal to put TikTok in U.S. hands. The <a href="https://fortune.com/2025/09/25/trumps-billionaire-backers-tiktok-deal-murdochs/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/2025/09/25/trumps-billionaire-backers-tiktok-deal-murdochs/" data-type="link" data-id="https://fortune.com/2025/09/25/trumps-billionaire-backers-tiktok-deal-murdochs/">U.S. ownership structure is still being finalized</a>, but Trump said&nbsp;Oracle&nbsp;and Ellison would play a “big” role in managing the app, while conservative media mogul Rupert Murdoch and computer billionaire Michael Dell would sit on the board. Trump hinted that three more “blue-chip” backers are also part of the ownership group.</p><p>Vice President JD Vance said that the algorithm will be “under the control of American investors,” adding that more details would be forthcoming.&nbsp;



</p><p><a href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/tiktok-algorithm-secured-oracle-trump-100000512.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="Go to https://finance.yahoo.com/news/tiktok-algorithm-secured-oracle-trump-100000512.html">Reports earlier this week</a>&nbsp;said&nbsp;Oracle&nbsp;will re-create TikTok’s algorithm and provide a new U.S. version while also ensuring security for users’ data.



</p><p>“This deal will allow for the U.S. to control the app’s algorithm,” Vance said. “It’s actually going to be American-operated all the way.”
</p></div><p><strong>Fortune Global Forum</strong> returns Oct. 26–27, 2025 in Riyadh. CEOs and global leaders will gather for a dynamic, invitation-only event shaping the future of business. <a href="https://conferences.fortune.com/event/global-forum-2025/summary?utm_source=fortunecom&amp;utm_medium=plealink" target="_self" aria-label="Go to https://conferences.fortune.com/event/global-forum-2025/summary?utm_source=fortunecom&amp;utm_medium=plealink">Apply for an invitation.</a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[EA Announces Agreement to be Acquired by PIF, Silver Lake, and Affinity Partners (231 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ir.ea.com/press-releases/press-release-details/2025/EA-Announces-Agreement-to-be-Acquired-by-PIF-Silver-Lake-and-Affinity-Partners-for-55-Billion/default.aspx</link>
            <guid>45413083</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 12:50:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ir.ea.com/press-releases/press-release-details/2025/EA-Announces-Agreement-to-be-Acquired-by-PIF-Silver-Lake-and-Affinity-Partners-for-55-Billion/default.aspx">https://ir.ea.com/press-releases/press-release-details/2025/EA-Announces-Agreement-to-be-Acquired-by-PIF-Silver-Lake-and-Affinity-Partners-for-55-Billion/default.aspx</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45413083">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://ir.ea.com/press-releases/press-release-details/2025/EA-Announces-Agreement-to-be-Acquired-by-PIF-Silver-Lake-and-Affinity-Partners-for-55-Billion/default.aspx: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What if I don't want videos of my hobby time available to the world? (534 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://neilzone.co.uk/2025/09/what-if-i-dont-want-videos-of-my-hobby-time-available-to-the-entire-world/</link>
            <guid>45412419</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 11:28:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://neilzone.co.uk/2025/09/what-if-i-dont-want-videos-of-my-hobby-time-available-to-the-entire-world/">https://neilzone.co.uk/2025/09/what-if-i-dont-want-videos-of-my-hobby-time-available-to-the-entire-world/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45412419">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content">
<article>
    <p>I am very much enjoying my newly-resurrected hobby of Airsoft.</p>
<p>Running around in the woods, firing small plastic pellets at other people, in pursuit of a contrived-to-be-fun mission, turns out to be, well, fun.</p>
<p>I have also had to accept that, for some other players, part of that fun comes from making videos of their game days, and uploading them to YouTube.</p>
<p>They often have quite impressive setups, with multiple cameras - head, rear-facing from barrel of weapon, and scope cam - and clearly put time, money, and effort into doing this.</p>
<p>Great! Just like someone taking photos on their holidays, or when out and about, I can see the fun in it.</p>
<p>It is the “non-consensually publishing it online for the world to see” aspect which bugs me a bit.</p>
<p>In the handful of games that I have played, no-one has ever asked about consent of other participants.</p>
<p>There has been no “put on this purple lanyard if you don’t want to be included in the public version of the video” rule, which I’ve seen work pretty well at conferences I have attended (even if it is opt-out rather than consent).</p>
<p>I could, I suppose, ask each person that I see with a camera “would you mind not including me in anything you upload, please?”. And, since everyone with whom I’ve spoken at games, so far anyway, has been perfectly pleasant and friendly, I’d be hopeful that they would at least consider my request. I have not done this.</p>
<p>The impression I get is that this is just seen as part and parcel of the hobby: by running around in the woods of northern Newbury on a Sunday morning, I need to accept that I may well appear on YouTube, for the world to see.</p>
<p>I don’t love it, but it is not a big enough deal for me to make a fuss.</p>
<h2 id="other-notes">Other notes</h2>
<p>I occasionally see people saying “well, if you don’t want to be in photos published online, don’t be in public spaces”.</p>
<p>This is nonsense, for a number of reasons. Clearly, one should be able to exist in society, including going outside one’s own home, without needing to accept this kind of thing.</p>
<p>In any case, here, the issue is somewhat different, since it is a private site, where people engage in private activity (a hobby).</p>
<p>But then I’ve seen the same at (private) conferences, with people saying “Of course I’m free to take photos of identifiable individuals without their consent and publish them online”.</p>
<p>Publishing someone’s photo online, without their consent, without another strong justification, just because they happen to be in view of one’s camera lens, feels wrong to me.</p>
<p>This isn’t about what is legal (although, in some cases, claims of legality may be poorly conceived), but around my own perceptions of a private life, and a dislike for the fact that, just because one <em>can</em> publish such things, that one <em>should</em>.</p>



  <div>
	<hr>   
	<h2>You may also like:</h2>
	
    
</div>


</article>

        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[DeepSeek-v3.2-Exp (264 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/deepseek-ai/DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp</link>
            <guid>45412098</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 10:26:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/deepseek-ai/DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp">https://github.com/deepseek-ai/DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45412098">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp</h2><a id="user-content-deepseek-v32-exp" aria-label="Permalink: DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp" href="#deepseek-v32-exp"></a></p>



<p><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/deepseek-ai/DeepSeek-V2/blob/main/figures/logo.svg?raw=true"><img src="https://github.com/deepseek-ai/DeepSeek-V2/raw/main/figures/logo.svg?raw=true" width="60%" alt="DeepSeek-V3"></a>
</p>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://www.deepseek.com/" rel="nofollow">
    <img alt="Homepage" src="https://github.com/deepseek-ai/DeepSeek-V2/raw/main/figures/badge.svg?raw=true">
  </a>
  <a href="https://chat.deepseek.com/" rel="nofollow">
    <img alt="Chat" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/00ba04aacbe45f97b5ebcc3d1b9c0f546e0ce3981265e97a110994184ef67fc8/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652ff09fa496253230436861742d446565705365656b25323056332d3533366166353f636f6c6f723d353336616635266c6f676f436f6c6f723d7768697465" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/🤖%20Chat-DeepSeek%20V3-536af5?color=536af5&amp;logoColor=white">
  </a>
  <a href="https://huggingface.co/deepseek-ai" rel="nofollow">
    <img alt="Hugging Face" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/5e3115539d4583e22d65cb89eb1759e767cb9e1d70772923292fcfc80a654be4/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f25463025394625413425393725323048756767696e67253230466163652d446565705365656b25323041492d6666633130373f636f6c6f723d666663313037266c6f676f436f6c6f723d7768697465" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/%F0%9F%A4%97%20Hugging%20Face-DeepSeek%20AI-ffc107?color=ffc107&amp;logoColor=white">
  </a>
</p>
<p><a href="https://discord.gg/Tc7c45Zzu5" rel="nofollow">
    <img alt="Discord" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/e227481a149714ed5187e4fd0b60b9f736099c2dd2083e6c091e29f1446cbb1a/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f446973636f72642d446565705365656b25323041492d3732383964613f6c6f676f3d646973636f7264266c6f676f436f6c6f723d776869746526636f6c6f723d373238396461" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/Discord-DeepSeek%20AI-7289da?logo=discord&amp;logoColor=white&amp;color=7289da">
  </a>
  <a href="https://github.com/deepseek-ai/DeepSeek-V2/blob/main/figures/qr.jpeg?raw=true">
    <img alt="Wechat" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/562efc618da65f0a69bc804395005b8124f5c2ed2eb73441c4e359185cc01467/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f5765436861742d446565705365656b25323041492d627269676874677265656e3f6c6f676f3d776563686174266c6f676f436f6c6f723d7768697465" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/WeChat-DeepSeek%20AI-brightgreen?logo=wechat&amp;logoColor=white">
  </a>
  <a href="https://twitter.com/deepseek_ai" rel="nofollow">
    <img alt="Twitter Follow" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/8272710ecd020c821b4f62c1c455efb89e0db4eb179c5f5f971c3c1f69452c54/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f547769747465722d646565707365656b5f61692d77686974653f6c6f676f3d78266c6f676f436f6c6f723d7768697465" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/Twitter-deepseek_ai-white?logo=x&amp;logoColor=white">
  </a>
</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/deepseek-ai/DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp/blob/main/LICENSE">
    <img alt="License" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/1af067540f64107f8fe7715d12150fb910e21f0d2c6aa0c319087c7510c8b934/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f4c6963656e73652d4d49542d6635646535333f26636f6c6f723d663564653533" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/License-MIT-f5de53?&amp;color=f5de53">
  </a>
</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Introduction</h2><a id="user-content-introduction" aria-label="Permalink: Introduction" href="#introduction"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">We are excited to announce the official release of DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp, an experimental version of our model. As an intermediate step toward our next-generation architecture, V3.2-Exp builds upon V3.1-Terminus by introducing DeepSeek Sparse Attention—a sparse attention mechanism designed to explore and validate optimizations for training and inference efficiency in long-context scenarios.</p>
<p dir="auto">This experimental release represents our ongoing research into more efficient transformer architectures, particularly focusing on improving computational efficiency when processing extended text sequences.</p>
<p><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/deepseek-ai/DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp/blob/main/cost.jpg"><img src="https://github.com/deepseek-ai/DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp/raw/main/cost.jpg"></a>
</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto">DeepSeek Sparse Attention (DSA) achieves fine-grained sparse attention for the first time, delivering substantial improvements in long-context training and inference efficiency while maintaining virtually identical model output quality.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">To rigorously evaluate the impact of introducing sparse attention, we deliberately aligned the training configurations of DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp with V3.1-Terminus. Across public benchmarks in various domains, DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp demonstrates performance on par with V3.1-Terminus.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Benchmark</th>
<th>DeepSeek-V3.1-Terminus</th>
<th>DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>Reasoning Mode w/o Tool Use</strong></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MMLU-Pro</td>
<td>85.0</td>
<td>85.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GPQA-Diamond</td>
<td>80.7</td>
<td>79.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Humanity's Last Exam</td>
<td>21.7</td>
<td>19.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LiveCodeBench</td>
<td>74.9</td>
<td>74.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AIME 2025</td>
<td>88.4</td>
<td>89.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>HMMT 2025</td>
<td>86.1</td>
<td>83.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Codeforces</td>
<td>2046</td>
<td>2121</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Aider-Polyglot</td>
<td>76.1</td>
<td>74.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Agentic Tool Use</strong></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BrowseComp</td>
<td>38.5</td>
<td>40.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BrowseComp-zh</td>
<td>45.0</td>
<td>47.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SimpleQA</td>
<td>96.8</td>
<td>97.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SWE Verified</td>
<td>68.4</td>
<td>67.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SWE-bench Multilingual</td>
<td>57.8</td>
<td>57.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Terminal-bench</td>
<td>36.7</td>
<td>37.7</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Open-Source Kernels</h2><a id="user-content-open-source-kernels" aria-label="Permalink: Open-Source Kernels" href="#open-source-kernels"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">For TileLang kernels with <strong>better readability and research-purpose design</strong>, please refer to <a href="https://github.com/tile-ai/tilelang/tree/main/examples/deepseek-v32">TileLang</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">For <strong>high-performance CUDA kernels</strong>, indexer logit kernels (including paged versions) are available in <a href="https://github.com/deepseek-ai/DeepGEMM/pull/200" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/deepseek-ai/DeepGEMM/pull/200/hovercard">DeepGEMM</a>. Sparse attention kernels are released in <a href="https://github.com/deepseek-ai/FlashMLA/pull/98" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/deepseek-ai/FlashMLA/pull/98/hovercard">FlashMLA</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How to Run Locally</h2><a id="user-content-how-to-run-locally" aria-label="Permalink: How to Run Locally" href="#how-to-run-locally"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">HuggingFace</h3><a id="user-content-huggingface" aria-label="Permalink: HuggingFace" href="#huggingface"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">We provide an updated inference demo code in the <a href="https://huggingface.co/deepseek-ai/DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp/tree/main/inference" rel="nofollow">inference</a> folder to help the community quickly get started with our model and understand its architectural details.</p>
<p dir="auto">First convert huggingface model weights to the the format required by our inference demo. Set <code>MP</code> to match your available GPU count:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="cd inference
export EXPERTS=256
python convert.py --hf-ckpt-path ${HF_CKPT_PATH} --save-path ${SAVE_PATH} --n-experts ${EXPERTS} --model-parallel ${MP}"><pre><span>cd</span> inference
<span>export</span> EXPERTS=256
python convert.py --hf-ckpt-path <span>${HF_CKPT_PATH}</span> --save-path <span>${SAVE_PATH}</span> --n-experts <span>${EXPERTS}</span> --model-parallel <span>${MP}</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Launch the interactive chat interface and start exploring DeepSeek's capabilities:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="export CONFIG=config_671B_v3.2.json
torchrun --nproc-per-node ${MP} generate.py --ckpt-path ${SAVE_PATH} --config ${CONFIG} --interactive"><pre><span>export</span> CONFIG=config_671B_v3.2.json
torchrun --nproc-per-node <span>${MP}</span> generate.py --ckpt-path <span>${SAVE_PATH}</span> --config <span>${CONFIG}</span> --interactive</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">SGLang</h3><a id="user-content-sglang" aria-label="Permalink: SGLang" href="#sglang"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation with Docker</h4><a id="user-content-installation-with-docker" aria-label="Permalink: Installation with Docker" href="#installation-with-docker"></a></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# H200
docker pull lmsysorg/sglang:dsv32

# MI350
docker pull lmsysorg/sglang:dsv32-rocm

# NPUs
docker pull lmsysorg/sglang:dsv32-a2
docker pull lmsysorg/sglang:dsv32-a3"><pre><code># H200
docker pull lmsysorg/sglang:dsv32

# MI350
docker pull lmsysorg/sglang:dsv32-rocm

# NPUs
docker pull lmsysorg/sglang:dsv32-a2
docker pull lmsysorg/sglang:dsv32-a3
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Launch Command</h4><a id="user-content-launch-command" aria-label="Permalink: Launch Command" href="#launch-command"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="python -m sglang.launch_server --model deepseek-ai/DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp --tp 8 --dp 8 --page-size 64"><pre>python -m sglang.launch_server --model deepseek-ai/DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp --tp 8 --dp 8 --page-size 64</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">vLLM</h3><a id="user-content-vllm" aria-label="Permalink: vLLM" href="#vllm"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">vLLM provides day-0 support of DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp. See the <a href="https://docs.vllm.ai/projects/recipes/en/latest/DeepSeek/DeepSeek-V3_2-Exp.html" rel="nofollow">recipes</a> for up-to-date details.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This repository and the model weights are licensed under the <a href="https://github.com/deepseek-ai/DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp/blob/main/LICENSE">MIT License</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Citation</h2><a id="user-content-citation" aria-label="Permalink: Citation" href="#citation"></a></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="@misc{deepseekai2024deepseekv32,
      title={DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp: Boosting Long-Context Efficiency with DeepSeek Sparse Attention}, 
      author={DeepSeek-AI},
      year={2025},
}"><pre><code>@misc{deepseekai2024deepseekv32,
      title={DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp: Boosting Long-Context Efficiency with DeepSeek Sparse Attention}, 
      author={DeepSeek-AI},
      year={2025},
}
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contact</h2><a id="user-content-contact" aria-label="Permalink: Contact" href="#contact"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If you have any questions, please raise an issue or contact us at <a href="https://github.com/deepseek-ai/DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp/blob/main/service@deepseek.com">service@deepseek.com</a>.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Optimizing a 6502 image decoder, from 70 minutes to 1 minute (134 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.colino.net/wordpress/en/archives/2025/09/28/optimizing-a-6502-image-decoder-from-70-minutes-to-1-minute/</link>
            <guid>45412022</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 10:11:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.colino.net/wordpress/en/archives/2025/09/28/optimizing-a-6502-image-decoder-from-70-minutes-to-1-minute/">https://www.colino.net/wordpress/en/archives/2025/09/28/optimizing-a-6502-image-decoder-from-70-minutes-to-1-minute/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45412022">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
					<p><span><i></i>2025/09/28</span>
						<span> - </span>
						<span><i></i>About 8 minutes read</span>
					</p>
					
				</div><div>	
						
<p>When I set out to write a program that would allow me to do basic digital photography on the Apple II, I decided I would do it with the Quicktake cameras. It seemed the obvious choice as they were Apple cameras, and their interface to the computer is via serial port.</p>



<p>The scope creeped a bit after managing to decode Quicktake 100 photos. I wanted it to be able to decode Quicktake 150 and Quicktake 200 pictures too. This threw me into image processing much more than I initially wanted to. This article explains the process of how I got the Quicktake 150 decoder to a reasonabl-ish speed on a 6502 at 1MHz.</p>



<p>The Quicktake 150 format is proprietary and undocumented. Free software decoders exist though, in the dcraw project. This was my source for the initial Apple II decoder. Sadly, it is written in C, is extremely non-documented, and is extremely hard to read and understand (to me). The compression is based on Huffman coding, with variable-length codes (which means bit-shifting), and the image construction involves a lot of 16-bits math. None of this is good on a 6502.</p>



<p>But first I had to rework the original algorithm to work with bands of 20 pixels, for memory reasons. Once I had a functional decoder, it ran perfectly, but it took… seventy minutes to decode a single picture.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/QT150_24.png"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/QT150_24.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/QT150_24.png 640w, https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/QT150_24-400x300.png 400w, https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/QT150_24-150x113.png 150w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px"></a><figcaption>A Quicktake 150 picture, fully decoded by dcraw</figcaption></figure>



<figure><a href="https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/TEST150.DGHR_.png"><img decoding="async" width="560" height="384" src="https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/TEST150.DGHR_.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/TEST150.DGHR_.png 560w, https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/TEST150.DGHR_-400x274.png 400w, https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/TEST150.DGHR_-150x103.png 150w" sizes="(max-width: 560px) 100vw, 560px"></a><figcaption>The same picture, dithered for display on a monochrome Apple II</figcaption></figure>



<p>Of course, I didn’t get there that fast. My first implementation was released two years ago, in November 2023. Getting where I’m now took, I think, five or six deep dives with each time, one or two weeks worth of late evenings and full week-ends dedicated to progressing, wading through hundreds or thousands of debug printf()s, gdb’ing, variables and offsets comparisons, etc.</p>



<p>Follow me through the algorithmic iterations that allowed me to get that decoding time to under one minute. My implementation is now full assembly, but the commits I will link to here are to the general decoding algorithm, that is easier to read in C. </p>



<p>I have noticed that hand-optimizing assembler yields good results, but usually optimizing the algorithm itself leads to much more impressive speed gains. Doing <strong>too many things</strong> faster is not as good as doing <strong>the minimum</strong> faster. And that Quicktake 150 decoder sure did useless things, especially in my case where I don’t care about color and end up with a 256×192 image!</p>



<p>I have made a specific repository to track these algorithmic changes. It started <a href="https://github.com/colinleroy/qtkn_decoder/commit/ceef883b4528a01658f446f9fde233d8846b98e0#diff-538608780127f20219d177da9582dffbd84063d74807cd8980d62ee09f7689a3" data-type="link" data-id="https://github.com/colinleroy/qtkn_decoder/commit/ceef883b4528a01658f446f9fde233d8846b98e0#diff-538608780127f20219d177da9582dffbd84063d74807cd8980d62ee09f7689a3">here</a> (already a little bit deobfuscated <a href="https://github.com/ncruces/dcraw/blob/8fe4d3825595816ea7d6880d9253f9edd143cacb/dcraw.c#L2198">compared to dcraw</a>), at 301 millions x86_64 instructions.</p>



<p><strong>Dropping color</strong></p>



<p>I didn’t have to decode color at all, as I was going to drop it, anyway. <a href="https://github.com/colinleroy/qtkn_decoder/commit/615ecd7406a65dd43da07443cb5c3f93a8d5fa95#diff-538608780127f20219d177da9582dffbd84063d74807cd8980d62ee09f7689a3R217">I added a flag to only decode the green pixels out of the Bayer matrix, and drop the rest</a>. 264M instructions.</p>



<p><strong>Understanding the buffers</strong></p>



<p>I then set out to understand the use of the various temporary buffers: the more buffers, the more intermediary steps, the more copy and looping. I wanted to drop as much of them as possible. <a href="https://github.com/colinleroy/qtkn_decoder/commit/fd6cd2c44d1cc961f8827ec6b5958521543e6d8d#diff-538608780127f20219d177da9582dffbd84063d74807cd8980d62ee09f7689a3L244">The first step towards it was unrolling some little imbricated loops that worked on y [1,2], x [col+1,col].</a> 238M instructions.</p>



<p>I figured I still had extra processing I didn’t need, <a href="https://github.com/colinleroy/qtkn_decoder/commit/73935481468c2a1d20a4640352caed4e47308b54#diff-538608780127f20219d177da9582dffbd84063d74807cd8980d62ee09f7689a3">removed it, dropped a buffer</a> (and dropped the #ifdef COLOR conditional to make things clearer). 193M instructions.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/image-green.png"><img decoding="async" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/image-green.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/image-green.png 640w, https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/image-green-400x300.png 400w, https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/image-green-150x113.png 150w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px"></a><figcaption>Our image looks like this now</figcaption></figure>



<p>At that point, my implementation still outputted green pixels only in a Bayer matrix to a 640×480 buffer, and then interpolated them. It was useless, so <a href="https://github.com/colinleroy/qtkn_decoder/commit/75a45d8fdf6943cc26a56c3f53c21f57e2877bbf#diff-538608780127f20219d177da9582dffbd84063d74807cd8980d62ee09f7689a3L263" data-type="link" data-id="https://github.com/colinleroy/qtkn_decoder/commit/75a45d8fdf6943cc26a56c3f53c21f57e2877bbf#diff-3564ad20c962b9eec56839b1adac221e589cda13b85547ac3d409396e9b6a28c">I dropped that entirely</a>. 29M instructions.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/out-grayscale-large.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/out-grayscale-large.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/out-grayscale-large.png 640w, https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/out-grayscale-large-400x300.png 400w, https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/out-grayscale-large-150x113.png 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px"></a><figcaption>Without interpolating, we can clearly see we only have half the pixels.</figcaption></figure>



<p>I still had half the pixels black in the destination buffer, so I dropped them earlier rather than later, by <a href="https://github.com/colinleroy/qtkn_decoder/commit/fdad1e8efb45e7597659b6c7d08e0a7714094d59#diff-538608780127f20219d177da9582dffbd84063d74807cd8980d62ee09f7689a3L130" data-type="link" data-id="https://github.com/colinleroy/qtkn_decoder/commit/fdad1e8efb45e7597659b6c7d08e0a7714094d59">outputting a 320×240 images with only the relevant pixels</a>. 25M instructions.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/image-119.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/image-119.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/image-119.png 640w, https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/image-119-400x300.png 400w, https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/image-119-150x113.png 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px"></a><figcaption>The 8-bits grayscale buffer at that point</figcaption></figure>



<p>At this point I was able to figure out that out of the three buf_m[3], only <a href="https://github.com/colinleroy/qtkn_decoder/commit/b3ac5d70edf0e836aa4b784fc06093d2606f7747">buf_m[1] was used to construct the picture</a>, that <a href="https://github.com/colinleroy/qtkn_decoder/commit/8b6a1c65011645c810f1a9fbb7d9eb56fe3e702e">buf_m[2] was only used to feed back into buf_m[0] at the start of a row</a>, that I could <a href="https://github.com/colinleroy/qtkn_decoder/commit/b44aac77d966c292f0762165cdf5b0818a8a0f91">construct the image from the buf_m[1] values on the fly instead of doing an extra loop on it</a>, and that <a href="https://github.com/colinleroy/qtkn_decoder/commit/4142412bda1388b6fadb5d343de07605c1e93ae8">I could entirely drop it too</a>. This allowed me to <a href="https://github.com/colinleroy/qtkn_decoder/commit/5161e9e33e5c3f064b0a3c0e5d29e6e7ece4280f" data-type="link" data-id="https://github.com/colinleroy/qtkn_decoder/commit/5161e9e33e5c3f064b0a3c0e5d29e6e7ece4280f">rename the last remaining buffer for more clarity</a>. 22M instructions. </p>



<p><strong>Optimizing divisions</strong></p>



<p>That was about it for the buffers. The rework of the code, at that point, made clear that every final pixel value was computed by dividing the 16-bits values computed from the image data by a given factor, and that this factor changes at most once every two rows. The result of that division was then clamped to [0-255]. This allowed me to <a href="https://github.com/colinleroy/qtkn_decoder/commit/865ca287f15bfccbca909b464b5939d8c4368f5a">precompute a division table every two rows, storing the final result, pre-clamped, in a simple array.</a> This also came with a bit of non-visible precision loss. On an x86_64, still 22M instructions, but on 6502, this was a huge gain, transforming 153600 divisions into less than 2000.</p>



<p>I verified the precision loss was acceptable using a small ad-hoc tool displaying my output buffers and comparing the reference decoding to the approximated one. Pixel values differ by at most 1.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/image-122.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1541" height="386" src="https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/image-122.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/image-122.png 1541w, https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/image-122-400x100.png 400w, https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/image-122-150x38.png 150w, https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/image-122-768x192.png 768w, https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/image-122-1536x385.png 1536w, https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/image-122-1280x321.png 1280w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1541px) 100vw, 1541px"></a><figcaption>Left: the normal output; middle: the comparison; right: the output with approximated divisions</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>Output index</strong></p>



<p>So far we set the output buffer using the usual <strong>buffer[y*WIDTH+x]</strong> access method, which is really slow on a processor with no multiplication support. <a href="https://github.com/colinleroy/qtkn_decoder/commit/7112b2b96e3d249f4a65532035dff9a8708bc914">I changed that to a much simpler line-by-line indexing</a>. (Even on x86_64, the change is notable: 20M instructions).</p>



<p><strong>Huffman decoding</strong></p>



<p>The algorithm initialized full tables so that it was possible to get a Huffman code by just looking at the bitbuffer: for code <strong>10001</strong>, for example, all codes from <strong>10001000</strong> to <strong>10001111</strong> were matched to the correct value, then the bitbuffer shifted &lt;&lt;5. This seems good at first, but not on 6502, as this requires a 16-bits bitbuffer to make sure we always have a full byte to look at. <a href="https://github.com/colinleroy/qtkn_decoder/commit/b0179e034a4396b8b6d09d489608bf0080e7b8d6">I reworked that to get bits one at a time</a>. This made the x86_64 implementation slower, but the 6502 one 20 seconds faster, spending 9 seconds shifting bits instead of 29. It also allowed me to pack the tables more tight, freeing up some memory for the cache.</p>



<p><strong>Assembly</strong></p>



<p><a href="https://github.com/colinleroy/qtkn_decoder/blob/b0179e034a4396b8b6d09d489608bf0080e7b8d6/qtkn-decoder.c">This algorithm</a> still performs very poorly when compiled by cc65, but is far easier to manually translate into optimized 6502 assembly. There are also a lot of ad-hoc optimisations, for example:</p>



<ul>
<li>The division factor for final pixel values for a pair of rows is 48 more than 50% of the time, on any image I tested. So the 6502 implementation has two divisions lookup tables, one for 48 that is never recomputed, one for another factor, recomputed if needed at the start of a pair of rows.</li>



<li>The row initialization multiplies all 320 next_line values by a factor, which is 255 about 66% of the time. In this case, instead of multiplying a = a*255, the assembly version does (a*256)-a, which is (a&lt;&lt;8)-a, which is much faster.</li>



<li>There is a whole lot of &lt;&lt;4 going on in the main loop, which is lookup-table based in the assembly implementation. &lt;&lt;4 is larger than 8 bits, so there are two tables needed, but it still is worth the memory usage.</li>



<li>Half the Huffman codes read are discarded (they are used for blue and red pixels), so “discarder” functions are used in that case, only shifting the bitbuffer without fetching the value.</li>



<li>Buffers accesses (to next_line and output buffer) are patched in self-modifying code rather than using zero-page pointers, which require to keep track and patch about 54 labels on each page cross. This is ugly as hell, but this requires about 50k cycles per image, but spares 9M cycles overall.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>The final code</strong></p>



<p>I have pointed to commits to my “test” repository so far, but if you’re interested in the actual 6502 implementation, you can find it in my repository: <a href="https://github.com/colinleroy/a2tools/blob/master/src/quicktake/qtkn_platform.s">the decoder</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/colinleroy/a2tools/blob/master/src/quicktake/qtk_bithuff.s">the bitbuffer</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Questions remain</strong></p>



<p>There still are things I don’t understand in dcraw’s decoder, that my simplifications didn’t uncover. The main thing I wonder is, how did Dave Coffin, dcraw’s author, implement this decoder first? It seems so full of “magic” numbers and arithmetic operations that I have no idea how one would look at pictures at the bit level, and figure out <em>anything</em> about the format. Did he reverse-engineer Apple’s binary? Did he have documentation? Is it in fact a common kind of encoding I have no idea about?</p>



<p>I would love to see documentation of this format, maybe I would understand more and be able to progress further.</p>



<p><strong>Bonus: first and current implementation video</strong></p>



<figure><video controls="" src="https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/qt150-decoding-web.mp4"></video><figcaption>The current implementation</figcaption></figure>



<figure><video controls="" src="https://www.colino.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/qt150-original.mp4"></video><figcaption>The first implementation (are you patient?)</figcaption></figure>
																
					</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google appears to have deleted its political ad archive for the EU (238 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.thebriefing.ie/google-just-erased-7-years-of-our-political-history/</link>
            <guid>45411332</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 07:57:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.thebriefing.ie/google-just-erased-7-years-of-our-political-history/">https://www.thebriefing.ie/google-just-erased-7-years-of-our-political-history/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45411332">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

    <article>

        <header>

            


                <figure>
        <img srcset="https://www.thebriefing.ie/content/images/size/w320/2025/09/Briefing-1-1.png 320w,
                    https://www.thebriefing.ie/content/images/size/w600/2025/09/Briefing-1-1.png 600w,
                    https://www.thebriefing.ie/content/images/size/w960/2025/09/Briefing-1-1.png 960w,
                    https://www.thebriefing.ie/content/images/size/w1200/2025/09/Briefing-1-1.png 1200w,
                    https://www.thebriefing.ie/content/images/size/w2000/2025/09/Briefing-1-1.png 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1120px" src="https://www.thebriefing.ie/content/images/size/w1200/2025/09/Briefing-1-1.png" alt="Google just erased 7 years of our political history">
    </figure>

        </header>

        <section>
            <p>Google appears to have deleted its political ad archive for the EU; so the last 7 years of ads, of political spending, of messaging, of targeting - on YouTube, on Search and for display ads - for countless elections across 27 countries - is all gone. </p><p>We had been told that Google would try to stop people placing political ads, a "ban" that was to come into effect this week. I did not read anywhere that this would mean the erasure of this archive of our political history. </p><p>When you go to the Google Ad Archive (which you can here: <a href="https://adstransparency.google.com/?region=IE&amp;ref=thebriefing.ie">https://adstransparency.google.com/</a>) until last week you could search all political ads shown in your country by a date range of your choosing going back to 2018. You could browse all the ads in that range, or search for keywords, candidates, parties. You could view each ad - watch the video, see the images - who had been targeted, how much had been spent etc. </p><p>Now when you try to click on "political ads" you get re-directed to a page asking you to select from a small number of countries - the US, of course, UK, India, Australia, Brazil, Israel - but not one EU country (see below): </p><figure><img src="https://www.thebriefing.ie/content/images/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-28-at-10.38.47.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="585" height="819"><figcaption><span>The page you are diverted too if you try to find political ads on Google. </span></figcaption></figure><p>The political ad archive - now deleted? - allowed people like me (and many others) to understand what happened in elections, like this longer piece I was able to write during the European &amp; Local elections last year on the use of YouTube by a far right party, Sinn Féin's big push on search result ads, and the growth of attacks ads in Ireland: </p><figure><a href="https://www.thebriefing.ie/campaign-round-up-google-youtube-ad-spend/"><div><p>Campaign round up: Irish Freedom Party dominating YouTube ad spend</p><p>The Irish Freedom Party spent €4,100 in the past 3 weeks on YouTube ads, the biggest spenders on YouTube ads this election.</p><p><img src="https://www.thebriefing.ie/content/images/icon/tb-logos-61.png" alt=""><span>Liz Carolan</span></p></div><p><img src="https://www.thebriefing.ie/content/images/thumbnail/Website-1920x1080-7.png" alt="" onerror="this.style.display = 'none'"></p></a></figure><p>Now you need the specific name of an advertiser, and when I looked for, for example, "Sinn Fein", it (a) only gave me the option of searching for their website, and (b) showed zero results. This is despite Sinn Fein spending upwards of <a href="https://www.thebriefing.ie/ad-spend-roundup-and-last-minute-shenanigans/" rel="noreferrer">€10k a day during some of the elections last year</a>. </p><figure><img src="https://www.thebriefing.ie/content/images/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-28-at-11.17.51.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="850" height="496" srcset="https://www.thebriefing.ie/content/images/size/w600/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-28-at-11.17.51.png 600w, https://www.thebriefing.ie/content/images/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-28-at-11.17.51.png 850w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption><span>Google no longer share any data on Irish political party and candidate spending on political ads on their platform; as shown here, a search for "Sinn Fein" returns "no ads found" </span></figcaption></figure><p>Some good things have been written about the impact that an ad "ban" might have on campaigning, especially when the algorithm still dominates all major social platforms (see this <a href="https://www.liberties.eu/en/stories/meta-google-advertising-bans/45513?ref=thebriefing.ie" rel="noreferrer">great piece</a> by the Civil Liberties Union for Europe), </p><p>But the ad archives were introduced 7 years ago for a reason - in no small part because of the chaos of the Brexit and Trump 2016 votes, and our own advocacy here in Ireland about interference in the 2018 8th amendment referendum. </p><p>They were introduced to allow for scrutiny of campaigns, and also to provide a historical record so we could go back and look at what had been promised, and what had been spent, and to see if this lined up with what happened later. </p><p>This erasure of our political past feels dangerous, for scrutiny, for accountability, for shared memory, for enforcement of our rules - for our democracy. </p><h2 id="icymi">ICYMI </h2><figure><a href="https://www.thebriefing.ie/campaigning-likes-it-1999-when-it-feels-like-its-1938/"><div><p>Campaigning likes it 1999 (when it feels like its 1938)</p><p>How do you run a political campaign without digital ads? I asked two of our best campaign gurus what we might expect.</p><p><img src="https://www.thebriefing.ie/content/images/icon/tb-logos-62.png" alt=""><span>The Briefing</span><span>Liz Carolan</span></p></div><p><img src="https://www.thebriefing.ie/content/images/thumbnail/Briefing-11.png" alt="" onerror="this.style.display = 'none'"></p></a></figure><figure><a href="https://www.thebriefing.ie/musks-profoundly-ignorant-and-dangerous-intervention-in-aras25/"><div><p>Musk’s profoundly ignorant and dangerous intervention in #Aras25</p><p>I really, really hope this isn’t the start of a whole thing. Elon Musk has tweeted about the race for the Aras in the most profoundly ignorant and stupidly dangerous way possible. The tweet is screenshot below; in it Musk sub-tweets another tweet claiming Simon Harris “ordered his Party to</p><p><img src="https://www.thebriefing.ie/content/images/icon/tb-logos-63.png" alt=""><span>The Briefing</span><span>Liz Carolan</span></p></div><p><img src="https://www.thebriefing.ie/content/images/thumbnail/thebriefing_elon-2.png" alt="" onerror="this.style.display = 'none'"></p></a></figure><figure><a href="https://www.thebriefing.ie/the-first-aras25-ads-are-out/"><div><p>The first #Aras25 ads are out</p><p>What the first political ads tell us about how the campaign might look</p><p><img src="https://www.thebriefing.ie/content/images/icon/tb-logos-64.png" alt=""><span>The Briefing</span><span>Liz Carolan</span></p></div><p><img src="https://www.thebriefing.ie/content/images/thumbnail/Briefing-1-1.png" alt="" onerror="this.style.display = 'none'"></p></a></figure>
        </section>

    </article>

        

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What is "good taste" in software engineering? (251 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.seangoedecke.com/taste/</link>
            <guid>45410940</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 06:41:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.seangoedecke.com/taste/">https://www.seangoedecke.com/taste/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45410940">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section><p>Technical taste is different from technical skill. You can be technically strong but have bad taste, or technically weak with good taste. Like taste in general, technical taste sometimes runs ahead of your ability: just like you can tell good food from bad without being able to cook, you can know what kind of software you like before you’ve got the ability to build it. You can develop technical ability by study and repetition, but good taste is developed in a more mysterious way.</p>
<p>Here are some indicators of software taste:</p>
<ul>
<li>What kind of code “looks good” to you? What kind of code “looks ugly”?</li>
<li>Which design decisions you feel really good about, and which ones are just fine?</li>
<li>Which software problems really bother you, to the point where you’re worrying about them outside of work? Which problems can you just brush off?</li>
</ul>
<p>I think taste is <strong>the ability to adopt the set of engineering values that fit your current project</strong>.</p>
<h3>Why taste is different from skill</h3>
<p>Aren’t the indicators above just a part of skill? For instance, doesn’t code look good <em>if it’s good code</em>? I don’t think so.</p>
<p>Let’s take an example. Personally, I feel like code that uses map and filter looks nicer than using a for loop. It’s tempting to think that this is a case of me being straightforwardly correct about a point of engineering. For instance, map and filter typically involve pure functions, which are easier to reason about, and they avoid an entire class of off-by-one iterator bugs. It feels to me like this isn’t a matter of taste, but a case where I’m right and other engineers are wrong.</p>
<p>But of course it’s more complicated than that. Languages like Golang don’t contain map and filter at all, for principled reasons. Iterating with a for loop is easier to reason about from a performance perspective, and is more straightforward to extend to other iteration strategies (like taking two items at a time). I don’t care about these reasons as much as I care about the reasons in favour of map and filter - that’s why I don’t write a lot of for loops - but it would be far too arrogant for me to say that engineers who prefer for loops are simply less skilled. In many cases, they have technical capabilites that I don’t have. They just care about different things.</p>
<p>In other words, our disagreement comes down to a difference in <em>values</em>. I wrote about this point in <a href="https://www.seangoedecke.com/confidence"><em>I don’t know how to build software and you don’t either</em></a>. Even if the big technical debates do have definite answers, no working software engineer is ever in a position to know what those answers are, because you can only fit so much experience into one career. We are all at least partly relying on our own personal experience: on our particular set of engineering values.</p>
<h3>What engineering taste actually is</h3>
<p>Almost every decision in software engineering is a tradeoff. You’re rarely picking between two options where one is strictly better. Instead, each option has its own benefits and downsides. Often you have to make hard tradeoffs between engineering <em>values</em>: past a certain point, you cannot easily increase performance without harming readability, for instance<sup id="fnref-1"><a href="#fn-1">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Really understanding this point is (in my view) the biggest indicator of maturity in software engineering. Immature engineers are rigid about their decisions. They think it’s always better to do X or Y. Mature engineers are usually willing to consider both sides of a decision, because they know that both sides come with different benefits. The trick is not deciding if technology X is better than Y, but whether the benefits of X outweigh Y <em>in this particular case</em>.</p>
<p>In other words, <strong>immature engineers are too inflexible about their taste</strong>. They know what they like, but they mistake that liking for a principled engineering position. What defines a particular engineer’s taste?</p>
<p>In my view, <strong>your engineering taste is composed of the set of engineering values you find most important</strong>. For instance:</p>
<p><strong>Resiliency</strong>. If an infrastructure component fails (a service dies, a network connection becomes unavailable), does the system remain functional? Can it recover without human intervention?</p>
<p><strong>Speed</strong>. How fast is the software, compared to the theoretical limit? Is work being done in the hot path that isn’t strictly necessary?</p>
<p><strong>Readability</strong>. Is the software easy to take in at a glance and to onboard new engineers to? Are functions relatively short and named well? Is the system well-documented?</p>
<p><strong>Correctness</strong>. Is it possible to represent an invalid state in the system? How locked-down is the system with tests, types, and asserts? Do the tests use techniques like fuzzing? In the extreme case, has the program been proven correct by formal methods like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alloy_(specification_language)">Alloy</a>?</p>
<p><strong>Flexibility</strong>. Can the system be trivially extended? How easy is it to make a change? If I need to change something, how many different parts of the program do I need to touch in order to do so?</p>
<p><strong>Portability</strong>. Is the system tied down to a particular operational environment (say, Microsoft Windows, or AWS)? If the system needs to be redeployed elsewhere, can that happen without a lot of engineering work?</p>
<p><strong>Scalability</strong>. If traffic goes up 10x, will the system fall over? What about 100x? Does the system have to be over-provisioned or can it scale automatically? What bottlenecks will require engineering intervention?</p>
<p><strong>Development speed</strong>. If I need to extend the system, how fast can it be done? Can most engineers work on it, or does it require a domain expert?</p>
<p>There are many other engineering values: elegance, modern-ness, use of open source, monetary cost of keeping the system running, and so on. All of these are important, but <strong>no engineer cares equally about all of these things.</strong> Your taste is determined by which of these values you rank highest. For instance, if you value speed and correctness more than development speed, you are likely to prefer Rust over Python. If you value scalability over portability, you are likely to argue for a heavy investment in your host’s (e.g. AWS) particular quirks and tooling. If you value resiliency over speed, you are likely to want to split your traffic between different regions. And so on<sup id="fnref-2"><a href="#fn-2">2</a></sup>.</p>
<p>It’s possible to break these values down in a more fine-grained way. Two engineers who both deeply care about readability could disagree because one values short functions and the other values short call-stacks. Two engineers who both care about correctness could disagree because one values exhaustive test suites and the other values formal methods. But the principle is the same - there are lots of possible engineering values to care about, and because they are often in tension, each engineer is forced to take some more seriously than others.</p>
<h3>How to identify bad taste</h3>
<p>I’ve said that all of these values are important. Despite that, it’s possible to have <em>bad</em> taste. In the context of software engineering, bad taste means that <strong>your preferred values are not a good fit for the project you’re working on</strong>.</p>
<p>Most of us have worked with engineers like this. They come onto your project evangelizing about something - formal methods, rewriting in Golang, Ruby meta-programming, cross-region deployment, or whatever - because it’s worked well for them in the past. Whether it’s a good fit for your project or not, they’re going to argue for it, because it’s what they like. Before you know it, you’re making sure your internal metrics dashboard has five nines of reliability, at the cost of making it impossible for any junior engineer to understand.</p>
<p>In other words, most bad taste comes from <strong>inflexibility</strong>. I will always distrust engineers who justify decisions by saying “it’s best practice”. No engineering decision is “best practice” in all contexts! You have to make the right decision for the specific problem you’re facing.</p>
<p>One interesting consequence of this is that engineers with bad taste are like broken compasses. If you’re in the right spot, a broken compass will still point north. It’s only when you start moving around that the broken compass will steer you wrong. Likewise, many engineers with bad taste can be quite effective in the particular niche where their preferences line up with what the project needs. But when they’re moved between projects or jobs, or when the nature of the project changes, the wheels immediately come off. No job stays the same for long, particularly <a href="https://www.seangoedecke.com/good-times-are-over">in these troubled post-2021 times</a>.</p>
<h3>How to identify good taste</h3>
<p>Good taste is a lot more elusive than technical ability. That’s because, unlike technical ability, good taste is the ability to select the right set of engineering values <strong>for the particular technical problem you’re facing</strong>. It’s thus much harder to identify if someone has good taste: you can’t test it with toy problems, or by asking about technical facts. You need there to be a real problem, with all of its messy real-world context.</p>
<p>You can tell you have good taste if the projects you’re working on succeed. If you’re not meaningfully contributing to the design of a project (maybe you’re just doing ticket-work), you can tell you have good taste if the projects where you agree with the design decisions succeed, and the projects where you disagree are rocky. Importantly, you need a set of different kinds of projects. If it’s just the one project, or the same kind of project over again, you might just be a good fit for that. Even if you go through many different kinds of projects, that’s no guarantee that you have good taste in domains you’re less familiar with<sup id="fnref-3"><a href="#fn-3">3</a></sup>.</p>
<p>How do you develop good taste? It’s hard to say, but I’d recommend working on a variety of things, paying close attention to which projects (or which parts of the project) are easy and which parts are hard. You should focus on <strong>flexibility</strong>: try not to acquire strong universal opinions about the right way to write software. What good taste I have I acquired pretty slowly. Still, I don’t see why you couldn’t acquire it fast. I’m sure there are prodigies with taste beyond their experience in programming, just as there are prodigies in other domains.</p>
</section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Zero ASIC releases Wildebeest, the highest performance FPGA synthesis tool (168 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.zeroasic.com/blog/wildebeest-launch</link>
            <guid>45410155</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 03:45:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.zeroasic.com/blog/wildebeest-launch">https://www.zeroasic.com/blog/wildebeest-launch</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45410155">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div> <h3 id="zero-asic-releases-wildebeest-the-worlds-highest-performance-fpga-synthesis-tool">Zero ASIC releases Wildebeest, the world’s highest performance FPGA synthesis tool.</h3>
<p>Cambridge, MA – September 17, 2025 – Zero ASIC, a U.S. semiconductor startup on a mission to democratize silicon, today announced the release of Wildebeest<sup>TM</sup>, the world’s highest performance FPGA synthesis tool.</p>
<h3 id="background">Background</h3>
<p>The software world has largely moved away from proprietary, vendor-locked compilers in favor of open source alternatives such as LLVM<sup><a href="#user-content-fn-1" id="user-content-fnref-1" data-footnote-ref="" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup> and GCC. Early on, these open source compilers lagged behind in performance, but over time, through the collective effort of the community, they caught up and even surpassed their proprietary counterparts.</p>
<p>In hardware, a similar transformation has been unfolding. Thanks to the pioneering work of Alan Mishchenko (ABC<sup><a href="#user-content-fn-2" id="user-content-fnref-2" data-footnote-ref="" aria-describedby="footnote-label">2</a></sup>), Claire Xenia Wolf (Yosys<sup><a href="#user-content-fn-3" id="user-content-fnref-3" data-footnote-ref="" aria-describedby="footnote-label">3</a></sup>), and the broader open source EDA community, FPGA developers have had access to a full-featured Verilog RTL synthesis toolchain for years. Recently, SystemVerilog support has since been added through Mike Popoloski’s excellent Slang parser<sup><a href="#user-content-fn-4" id="user-content-fnref-4" data-footnote-ref="" aria-describedby="footnote-label">4</a></sup>. Thanks to strong community involvement, the Yosys project now supports FPGA synthesis for a number of commercial and academic FPGA architectures.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, funding for open source FPGA synthesis has been minimal, and as a result a large QoR gap between open source and proprietary synthesis remains. Industrial users, who care obsessively about performance, have thus been stuck between a rock and a hard place: “Freedom or Performance”.</p>













































<table><thead><tr><th>Attribute</th><th>Vendor Tool</th><th>Yosys</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>FPGA Support</td><td>Yes</td><td>No</td></tr><tr><td>Lock-in</td><td>Yes</td><td>No</td></tr><tr><td>Open Source</td><td>No</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>Free</td><td>Yes/No</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>Binary Size</td><td>Large</td><td>Small</td></tr><tr><td>QoR</td><td>Great</td><td>Good</td></tr><tr><td>Robustness</td><td>Great</td><td>Good</td></tr></tbody></table>
<h3 id="wildebeest-intro">Wildebeest Intro</h3>
<p>Wildebeest introduces a number of critical optimization techniques to open source. Some of these techniques are standard practice in commercial compilers, but this is the first time they have been demonstrated in an open source FPGA synthesis tool.</p>
<p>The most important Wildebeest strategy is the use of circuit size as a primary feature for selecting the synthesis algorithms. Existing single script solutions don’t work well because they either fail to converge for large circuits or sacrifice performance for robustness. Using a carefully selected set of size appropriate optimization scripts, Wildebeest achieves robustness and high performance for a wide range of benchmark (up to 1M LUT designs).</p>
<p>Another important aspect of the Wildebeest approach is the effective use of the most advanced <code>abc9</code> commands for speculative synthesis and logic depth minimization. ABC is an incredibly powerful logic synthesis library, but making effective use of all commands is a non-trivial task that requires deep expertise in logic synthesis, the ABC architecture, and Yosys, and software development.</p>
<p>Logic optimization is only as good as the benchmark data that grounds the algorithms used. Wildebeest adopted an industrial approach to development from day one, developing an internal suite of 150+ carefully selected benchmarks and automated profiling utilities. The open source <a href="https://github.com/zeroasiccorp/logikbench">LogikBench</a> benchmarks suite was created to enable independent evaluation and benchmarking.</p>
<p>Logic synthesis has been around for over 50 years. During this time, basic synthesis algorithms and approaches have been openly published by the synthesis R&amp;D community, but many of the “outer loop” tricks of the trade have been kept hidden by practitioners within proprietary tools. The lead Wildebeest developer, Dr. Thierry Besson is an industry insider with 30 years of experience in developing state of the art commercial logic synthesis solutions. Dr. Besson has previously contributed the fastest/smallest results on a number of the EPFL logic synthesis benchmarks and with Wildebeest he is releasing many of these techniques into the wild.<sup><a href="#user-content-fn-5" id="user-content-fnref-5" data-footnote-ref="" aria-describedby="footnote-label">5</a></sup></p>
<h3 id="benchmark-results">Benchmark Results</h3>
<p>The table below shows how Wildebeest compares against both open-source and proprietary synthesis tools for the <a href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/zeroasiccorp/logikbench/refs/heads/main/logikbench/blocks/picorv32/rtl/picorv32.v">picorv32 CPU design</a>. To run Wildebeest across a broader set of benchmarks, see the <a href="https://github.com/zeroasiccorp/logikbench">LogikBench</a> project.</p>













































































<table><thead><tr><th>Device</th><th>Arch</th><th>Tool</th><th>Synthesis Command</th><th>LUTs</th><th>Logic Depth</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>z1060</td><td>LUT6</td><td>wildebeest</td><td>synth_fpga</td><td>2312</td><td>40</td></tr><tr><td>z1060</td><td>LUT6</td><td>wildebeest</td><td>synth_fpga -opt delay</td><td>2677</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>Vendor-1</td><td>LUT6</td><td>vendor</td><td>(proprietary)</td><td>2870</td><td>7</td></tr><tr><td>Vendor-2</td><td>LUT6</td><td>vendor</td><td>(proprietary)</td><td>2947</td><td>8</td></tr><tr><td>xc7</td><td>LUT6</td><td>yosys (0.56)</td><td>synth_xilinx -nocarry</td><td>3072</td><td>17</td></tr><tr><td>z1010</td><td>LUT4</td><td>wildebeest</td><td>synth_fpga</td><td>3593</td><td>39</td></tr><tr><td>z1010</td><td>LUT4</td><td>wildebeest</td><td>synth_fpga -opt delay</td><td>4112</td><td>8</td></tr><tr><td>ice40</td><td>LUT4</td><td>yosys (0.56)</td><td>synth_ice40 -dsp -nocarry</td><td>4378</td><td>33</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>The results show that Wildebeest QoR exceeds both proprietary and open source FPGA synthesis solutions.</p>
<h3 id="future-work">Future Work</h3>
<p>This initial Wildebeest release is only the beginning of the journey. The development team has a pipeline of optimization techniques in development with QoR that is expected to exceed current proprietary tools by a wide margin.</p>
<p>The long term goal of the Wildebeest project is to help bring forth an era of “LLVM for synthesis” by working with the community to develop high performance open source FPGA tools, robust standard IRs and file formats, and broad hardware vendor adoption.</p>
<h3 id="demo">Demo</h3>
<p>To try out the <code>Wildebeest</code>, follow these <a href="https://github.com/zeroasiccorp/wildebeest?tab=readme-ov-file#prerequisites">installation</a> instructions, download the <a href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/zeroasiccorp/logikbench/refs/heads/main/logikbench/blocks/picorv32/rtl/picorv32.v">picorv32 CPU example</a>, launch <code>yosys</code>, and run the command sequence below.</p>
<pre tabindex="0" data-language="bash"><code><span><span>plugin</span><span> -i</span><span> wildebeest</span></span>
<span><span>read_verilog</span><span> picorv32.v</span></span>
<span><span>hierarchy</span><span> -check</span><span> -top</span><span> picorv32</span></span>
<span><span>synth_fpga</span><span> -partname</span><span> z1010</span></span></code></pre>
<h3 id="availability">Availability</h3>
<p>The Wildebeest source code was officially released on September 17, 2025 and can be downloaded via github:</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/zeroasiccorp/wildebeest">https://github.com/zeroasiccorp/wildebeest</a></p>
<h3 id="about-zero-asic">About Zero ASIC</h3>
<p>Zero ASIC is a semiconductor startup based in Cambridge, Massachusetts. The company mission is to democratize access to silicon through chiplets and design automation. Zero ASIC is building the world’s first composable chiplet platform, enabling billions of unique silicon systems to be assembled in hours from a catalog of off-the-shelf chiplets.</p>
<h3 id="references">References</h3>
<section data-footnotes="">
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1">
<p>C. Lattner, V. Adve, “LLVM: A Compilation Framework for Lifelong Program Analysis &amp; Transformation”, Proc. International Symposium on Code Generation and Optimization  2004 <a href="#user-content-fnref-1" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-2">
<p>R. Brayton and A. Mishchenko, “ABC: An academic industrial-strength verification tool”, Proc. CAV 2010 <a href="#user-content-fnref-2" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 2">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-3">
<p>C. Wolf, Johann Glaser., “Yosys - A Free Verilog Synthesis Suite”, Proc. Austrochip 2013 <a href="#user-content-fnref-3" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 3">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-4">
<p>M. Popoloski, “Slang: a SystemVerilog Compiler”, <a href="https://github.com/MikePopoloski/slang">https://github.com/MikePopoloski/slang</a> <a href="#user-content-fnref-4" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 4">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-5">
<p>EPFL Benchmark Suite Best Results, <a href="https://github.com/lsils/benchmarks/tree/master/best_results">https://github.com/lsils/benchmarks/tree/master/best_results</a> <a href="#user-content-fnref-5" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 5">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section> </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[F-Droid and Google's Developer Registration Decree (1217 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://f-droid.org/2025/09/29/google-developer-registration-decree.html</link>
            <guid>45409794</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 02:10:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://f-droid.org/2025/09/29/google-developer-registration-decree.html">https://f-droid.org/2025/09/29/google-developer-registration-decree.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45409794">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          <article itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/BlogPosting">

  

  <div itemprop="articleBody">
    <p>For the past 15 years<sup id="fnref:fifteen" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:fifteen" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, F-Droid has provided a safe and secure
haven for Android users around the world to find and install free and open
source apps. When contrasted with the commercial app stores — of which the
Google Play store is the most prominent — the differences are stark: they
are hotbeds of spyware and scams, blatantly promoting apps that prey on
their users through attempts to monetize their attention and mine their
intimate information through any means necessary, including trickery and
dark patterns.[^spyware1]</p>

<p><a href="https://f-droid.org/en/2025/09/04/twif.html">https://f-droid.org/2025/09/04/twif.html</a>
[^spyware1]: “Spyware maker caught distributing malicious Android apps for
years”:
<a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/02/13/spyware-maker-caught-distributing-malicious-android-apps-for-years">https://techcrunch.com/2025/02/13/spyware-maker-caught-distributing-malicious-android-apps-for-years</a></p>

<p>F-Droid is different. It distributes apps that have been validated to work
<em>for</em> the user’s interests, rather than for the interests of the app’s
distributors. The way F-Droid works is simple: when a developer creates an
app and hosts the source code publicly somewhere, the F-Droid team reviews
it, inspecting it to ensure that it is completely open source and contains
no undocumented <em>anti-features</em> such as advertisements or
trackers<sup id="fnref:antifeatures" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:antifeatures" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. Once it passes inspection, the F-Droid build
service compiles and packages the app to make it ready for distribution. The
package is then signed either with F-Droid’s cryptographic key, or, if the
build is reproducible[^reproducible], enables distribution using the
original developer’s private key. In this way, users can trust that any app
distributed through F-Droid is the one that was built from the specified
source code and has not been tampered with.</p>

<p><a href="https://f-droid.org/en/docs/Anti-Features/">https://f-droid.org/docs/Anti-Features/</a>
[^reproducible]: F-Droid Reproducible Builds Introduction:
<a href="https://f-droid.org/en/docs/Reproducible_Builds/">https://f-droid.org/docs/Reproducible_Builds/</a></p>

<p>Do you want a weather app that doesn’t transmit your every movement to a
shadowy data broker<sup id="fnref:weather-apps" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:weather-apps" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>? Or a scheduling assistant that doesn’t
siphon your intimate details into an advertisement
network[^surveillance-ads]? F-Droid has your back. Just as sunlight is the
best disinfectant against corruption, open source is the best defense
against software acting against the interests of the user.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.howtogeek.com/884233/your-weather-app-is-spying-on-you-heres-what-to-do/#why-are-weather-apps-such-a-privacy-nightmare">https://www.howtogeek.com/884233/your-weather-app-is-spying-on-you-heres-what-to-do/#why-are-weather-apps-such-a-privacy-nightmare</a>
[^surveillance-ads]: “Online Behavioral Ads Fuel the Surveillance
Industry—Here’s How”:
<a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2025/01/online-behavioral-ads-fuel-surveillance-industry-heres-how">https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2025/01/online-behavioral-ads-fuel-surveillance-industry-heres-how</a></p>

<h3 id="googles-move-to-break-free-app-distribution">Google’s move to break free app distribution</h3>

<p>The future of this elegant and proven system was put in jeopardy last month,
when Google unilaterally decreed<sup id="fnref:regann" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:regann" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> that Android developers everywhere
in the world are going to be required to register centrally with Google. In
addition to demanding payment of a registration fee and agreement to their
(non-negotiable and ever-changing) terms and conditions, Google will also
require the uploading of personally identifying documents[^regid], including
government ID, by the authors of the software, as well as enumerating all
the unique “application identifiers” for every app that is to be distributed
by the registered developer.[^regappid]</p>

<p>require all apps to be registered by verified developers in order to be
installed by users on certified Android devices.”
<a href="https://android-developers.googleblog.com/2025/08/elevating-android-security.html">https://android-developers.googleblog.com/2025/08/elevating-android-security.html</a>
[^regid]: Android developer verification: “You will need to provide and
verify your personal details, like your legal name, address, email address,
and phone number. You may also need to upload official government ID.”:
<a href="https://developer.android.com/developer-verification#verify-your-identity">https://developer.android.com/developer-verification#verify-your-identity</a>
[^regappid]: Android developer verification: “You’ll need to prove you own
your apps by providing your app package name and app signing keys.”:
<a href="https://developer.android.com/developer-verification#register-your-apps">https://developer.android.com/developer-verification#register-your-apps</a></p>

<p>The F-Droid project cannot require that developers register their apps
through Google, but at the same time, we cannot “take over” the application
identifiers for the open-source apps we distribute, as that would
effectively seize exclusive distribution rights to those applications.</p>

<p>If it were to be put into effect, the developer registration decree will end
the F-Droid project and other free/open-source app distribution sources as
we know them today, and the world will be deprived of the safety and
security of the catalog of thousands of apps that can be trusted and
verified by any and all. F-Droid’s myriad users<sup id="fnref:howmanyusers" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:howmanyusers" rel="footnote">5</a></sup> will be left
adrift, with no means to install — or even update their existing installed —
applications.</p>

<p>because we don’t track users or have any registration. “No user accounts, by
design”:
<a href="https://f-droid.org/en/2022/02/28/no-user-accounts-by-design.html">https://f-droid.org/2022/02/28/no-user-accounts-by-design.html</a></p>

<h3 id="the-security-canard">The Security Canard</h3>

<p>While directly installing — or “sideloading”<sup id="fnref:sideloading" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:sideloading" rel="footnote">6</a></sup> — software can be
construed as carrying some inherent risk, it is false to claim that
centralized app stores are the only safe option for software
distribution. Google Play itself has repeatedly hosted
malware[^playmal1][^playmal2], proving that corporate gatekeeping doesn’t
guarantee user protection. By contrast, F-Droid offers a trustworthy and
transparent alternative approach to security: every app is free and open
source, the code can be audited by anyone, the build process and logs are
public, and reproducible builds ensure that what is published matches the
source code exactly. This transparency and accountability provides a
<em>stronger</em> basis for trust than closed platforms, while still giving users
freedom to choose. Restricting direct app installation not only undermines
that choice, it also erodes the diversity and resilience of the open-source
ecosystem by consolidating control in the hands of a few corporate players.</p>

<p>came up with; it means “installing software without our permission,” which
we used to just call “installing software” (because you don’t need a
manufacturer’s permission to install software on your computer).’ —
Pluralistic: <em>Darth Android</em>:
<a href="https://pluralistic.net/2025/09/01/fulu/">https://pluralistic.net/2025/09/01/fulu/</a>
[^playmal1]: “224 malicious apps removed from the Google Play Store after ad
fraud campaign discovered”:
<a href="https://www.malwarebytes.com/blog/news/2025/09/224-malicious-apps-removed-from-the-google-play-store-after-ad-fraud-campaign-discovered">https://www.malwarebytes.com/blog/news/2025/09/224-malicious-apps-removed-from-the-google-play-store-after-ad-fraud-campaign-discovered</a>
[^playmal2]: “Malware-ridden apps made it into Google’s Play Store, scored
19 million downloads”:
<a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/08/26/apps_android_malware/">https://www.theregister.com/2025/08/26/apps_android_malware/</a></p>

<p>Furthermore, Google’s framing that they need to mandate developer
registration in order to defend against malware is disingenuous because they
<em>already</em> have a remediation mechanism for malware they identify on a
device: the Play Protect service<sup id="fnref:playprotect" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:playprotect" rel="footnote">7</a></sup> that is enabled on all
Android Certified devices already scans and disables apps that have been
identified as malware, regardless of their provenience. Any perceived risks
associated with direct app installation can be mitigated through user
education, open-source transparency, and existing security measures without
imposing exclusionary registration requirements.</p>

<p>harmful behavior”:
<a href="https://support.google.com/googleplay/answer/2812853">https://support.google.com/googleplay/answer/2812853</a></p>

<p>We do not believe that developer registration is motivated by security. We
believe it is about consolidating power and tightening control over a
formerly open ecosystem.</p>

<h3 id="the-right-to-run">The Right to Run</h3>

<p>If you own a computer, you should have the right to run whatever programs
you want on it. This is just as true with the apps on your Android/iPhone
mobile device as it is with the applications on your Linux/Mac/Windows
desktop or server. Forcing software creators into a centralized registration
scheme in order to publish and distribute their works is as egregious as
forcing writers and artists to register with a central authority in order to
be able to distribute their creative works. It is an offense to the core
principles of free speech and thought that are central to the workings of
democratic societies around the world.</p>

<p>By tying application identifiers to personal ID checks and fees, Google is
building a choke point that restricts competition and limits user
freedom. It must find a solution which preserves user rights, freedom of
choice, and a healthy, competitive ecosystem.</p>

<h3 id="what-do-we-propose">What do we propose?</h3>

<p>Regulatory and competition authorities should look carefully at Google’s
proposed activities, and ensure that policies designed to improve security
are not abused to consolidate monopoly control. We urge regulators to
safeguard the ability of alternative app stores and open-source projects to
operate freely, and to protect developers who cannot or will not comply with
exclusionary registration schemes and demands for personal information.</p>

<p>If you are a developer or user who values digital freedom, you can
help. Write to your Member of Parliament<sup id="fnref:mp" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:mp" rel="footnote">8</a></sup>,
Congressperson[^congressperson] or other representative, sign petitions in
defense of sideloading, and contact the European Commission’s Digital
Markets Act (DMA) team<sup id="fnref:dmacontact" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:dmacontact" rel="footnote">9</a></sup> to express why preserving open
distribution matters. By making your voice heard, you help defend not only
F-Droid, but the principle that software should remain a commons, accessible
and free from unnecessary corporate gatekeeping.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.europarl.europa.eu/meps/en/home">https://www.europarl.europa.eu/meps/en/home</a>
[^congressperson]: Find Your Representative
<a href="https://www.house.gov/representatives/find-your-representative">https://www.house.gov/representatives/find-your-representative</a></p>

<p><a href="https://digital-markets-act.ec.europa.eu/contact-dma-team_en">https://digital-markets-act.ec.europa.eu/contact-dma-team_en</a></p>


  </div>

</article>

        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Primer on FedEx's Distribution Network (2024) (131 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ontheseams.substack.com/p/a-brief-primer-on-fedexs-distribution</link>
            <guid>45409552</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 01:18:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ontheseams.substack.com/p/a-brief-primer-on-fedexs-distribution">https://ontheseams.substack.com/p/a-brief-primer-on-fedexs-distribution</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45409552">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><p><em>*Updated July 1, 2025</em></p><p>FedEx was founded in 1971 as an express delivery service. An early motto captures its basic promise: “When it absolutely, positively has to be there overnight.”</p><p><span>The Federal Aviation Act of 1977, which was intensely advocated for by FedEx founding president Fred Smith, allowed FedEx </span><a href="https://www-sciencedirect-com.ezproxy1.lib.asu.edu/science/article/pii/S0966692312001299" rel="">to bring larger aircraft into its fleet</a><span>. Larger aircraft in turn allowed FedEx to concentrate most of its sorting operations in one hub, Memphis, where the company built its superhub in 1979. Today Memphis is the largest cargo airport in the country, and second in the world, all thanks to FedEx’s massive operation.</span></p><p>While FedEx was founded as an air service, and UPS as a ground service, both FedEx and UPS have air and ground services today, though FedEx still has an edge in the air game, with 741 aircraft it operates as opposed to UPS’s 506. It is the largest cargo airline in the world, serving more than 650 airports around the world and shipping 16 million packages daily.</p><p><span>As with all of our primers, this one has an associated </span><a href="https://www.google.com/maps/d/edit?mid=1CSzopj5FzanEmqLVh9ZbAqALsL28laU&amp;usp=sharing" rel="">map of FedEx’s Distribution Network</a><span>, which </span><em>On the Seams</em><span> will do its best to keep updated. (Once again, if you have an update to this map, email us at ontheseams.newsletter@gmail.com.)</span></p><p><span>FedEx </span><a href="https://d3.harvard.edu/platform-rctom/submission/fedex-the-worlds-largest-continuous-flow-process/" rel="">traditionally generates</a><span> between 55-60% of its revenue from Express, about 25% from Ground, 10% from freight, and the remainder from other services. </span></p><p><span>Speed is the name of the game for Express, so everything in this operation is about getting packages on and off planes as quickly as possible. At many airports (102 by my count), they have Air Freight Centers (AFCs); these are also listed publicly. Employment levels at these AFCs range widely, from 27 in Grand Junction, CO to 643 at JFK. They also have a whole bunch of Ship Centers that are either on airport grounds or just a few blocks away, and I’ve listed these on the map as well. (Note, only the Ship Centers </span><em>close to airports</em><span> are on the map. FedEx has many other Ship Centers, the spoke nodes of the Express system, and you can search for them on </span><a href="https://local.fedex.com/en-us/wa/seattle" rel="">FedEx’s site</a><span>.)</span></p><p>Express operates by a hub-and-spoke logic, which the company pioneered, though the spokes typically have their own mini-spokes as well. For instance, a package coming from Grand Forks, North Dakota will first go to Fargo, North Dakota (KFAR), be processed at its Air Freight Center there, and then go on to FedEx’s world hub in Memphis (KMEM), where it’s sorted to its destination.&nbsp;</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ajZN!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2b934bcc-876b-4999-aafa-62df958898cb_1540x926.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ajZN!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2b934bcc-876b-4999-aafa-62df958898cb_1540x926.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ajZN!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2b934bcc-876b-4999-aafa-62df958898cb_1540x926.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ajZN!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2b934bcc-876b-4999-aafa-62df958898cb_1540x926.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ajZN!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2b934bcc-876b-4999-aafa-62df958898cb_1540x926.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ajZN!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2b934bcc-876b-4999-aafa-62df958898cb_1540x926.png" width="500" height="300.4807692307692" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/2b934bcc-876b-4999-aafa-62df958898cb_1540x926.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:875,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:500,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ajZN!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2b934bcc-876b-4999-aafa-62df958898cb_1540x926.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ajZN!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2b934bcc-876b-4999-aafa-62df958898cb_1540x926.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ajZN!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2b934bcc-876b-4999-aafa-62df958898cb_1540x926.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ajZN!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2b934bcc-876b-4999-aafa-62df958898cb_1540x926.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>FedEx Air Hubs (yellow) and Airports served (orange)</figcaption></figure></div><p>By far the largest Express sort facilities are in Memphis and Indianapolis (KIND), the latter being FedEx’s national hub. KIND has about 180 flights in and out every day, KMEM about 250. Around 5500 people are employed at the facilities around KIND, and more than 20,000 at the facilities around KMEM. Both facilities can handle more than 2 million packages a day; a package can be in and out of a sort facility like this within 15 minutes. In addition to these superhubs, there are smaller regional hubs in Anchorage (PANC), Fort Worth (KAFW), Greensboro (KGSO), Miami (KMIA), Newark (KEWR), Oakland (KOAK), and Ontario (KONT).&nbsp;</p><p>Sortation is a science all its own, and we will devote a separate primer to various sort logics, operations, technologies, etc. But the basic goal of these sort hubs is all the same: get inbound packages organized on conveyor belts so that they can be scanned and kicked to slides/chutes with other packages bound for the same area.&nbsp;</p><div id="youtube2-SNFE_1Rnsu8" data-attrs="{&quot;videoId&quot;:&quot;SNFE_1Rnsu8&quot;,&quot;startTime&quot;:null,&quot;endTime&quot;:null}" data-component-name="Youtube2ToDOM"><p><iframe src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/SNFE_1Rnsu8?rel=0&amp;autoplay=0&amp;showinfo=0&amp;enablejsapi=0" frameborder="0" loading="lazy" gesture="media" allow="autoplay; fullscreen" allowautoplay="true" allowfullscreen="true" width="728" height="409"></iframe></p></div><p><span>FedEx Express pickup and delivery drivers are employees of the company. Unlike with Ground, which will send a driver out for the day to do pickups/deliveries, Express drivers typically have to work around </span><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/FedEx/comments/hawj7d/delivery_routes/" rel="">time-committed packages</a><span>, meeting one or a few loop deadlines for the day, doing on-call pickups, and making a certain number of required delivery attempts. </span></p><p>FedEx Ground was founded in 1985 as Roadway Package System (RPS). It was bought in 1998 by FedEx and rebranded as Ground in 2000.&nbsp;</p><p>Like Express, Ground operates by a hub-and-spoke structure. Let’s say a package is dropped off at a FedEx store in Cloquet, Minnesota, and it’s going to Chandler, Arizona by Ground. It will first get picked up and sent to the local Ground Facility in Superior, Wisconsin (ZDUL), and then sent to the regional Ground Hub in St. Paul (STPL). The Ground Facilities are in green, and the Ground Hubs are in purple. Below is depicted the spoke structure around the St. Paul hub; highlighted are the hub itself and the Superior facility.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!UdK8!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4c66c0bd-7640-4dca-87bf-63ea676b2ef1_722x824.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!UdK8!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4c66c0bd-7640-4dca-87bf-63ea676b2ef1_722x824.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!UdK8!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4c66c0bd-7640-4dca-87bf-63ea676b2ef1_722x824.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!UdK8!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4c66c0bd-7640-4dca-87bf-63ea676b2ef1_722x824.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!UdK8!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4c66c0bd-7640-4dca-87bf-63ea676b2ef1_722x824.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!UdK8!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4c66c0bd-7640-4dca-87bf-63ea676b2ef1_722x824.png" width="356" height="406.29362880886424" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/4c66c0bd-7640-4dca-87bf-63ea676b2ef1_722x824.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:824,&quot;width&quot;:722,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:356,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!UdK8!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4c66c0bd-7640-4dca-87bf-63ea676b2ef1_722x824.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!UdK8!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4c66c0bd-7640-4dca-87bf-63ea676b2ef1_722x824.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!UdK8!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4c66c0bd-7640-4dca-87bf-63ea676b2ef1_722x824.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!UdK8!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4c66c0bd-7640-4dca-87bf-63ea676b2ef1_722x824.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>FedEx Ground Hub and Spoke Structure around St. Paul Hub (purple)</figcaption></figure></div><p>From STPL, the package goes on a linehaul run to another Ground Hub, in this case the one in Phoenix (PHOE). The hub structure allows FedEx to consolidate shipments for long-distance travel, but in this case in full truckloads rather than on full planes. Then from the PHOE hub it goes to the Chandler Ground Facility (ZCHD), and then out on a delivery truck.</p><div id="youtube2-Xwv3ZOMKlAA" data-attrs="{&quot;videoId&quot;:&quot;Xwv3ZOMKlAA&quot;,&quot;startTime&quot;:null,&quot;endTime&quot;:null}" data-component-name="Youtube2ToDOM"><p><iframe src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Xwv3ZOMKlAA?rel=0&amp;autoplay=0&amp;showinfo=0&amp;enablejsapi=0" frameborder="0" loading="lazy" gesture="media" allow="autoplay; fullscreen" allowautoplay="true" allowfullscreen="true" width="728" height="409"></iframe></p></div><p>Once again, you have the hub-and-spoke structure around the Phoenix hub, but in this case the package goes out toward a spoke facility rather than into a hub from it.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ZNV-!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4e918049-bb2b-4c07-94bb-3125ef44280e_966x698.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ZNV-!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4e918049-bb2b-4c07-94bb-3125ef44280e_966x698.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ZNV-!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4e918049-bb2b-4c07-94bb-3125ef44280e_966x698.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ZNV-!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4e918049-bb2b-4c07-94bb-3125ef44280e_966x698.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ZNV-!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4e918049-bb2b-4c07-94bb-3125ef44280e_966x698.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ZNV-!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4e918049-bb2b-4c07-94bb-3125ef44280e_966x698.png" width="410" height="296.2525879917184" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/4e918049-bb2b-4c07-94bb-3125ef44280e_966x698.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:698,&quot;width&quot;:966,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:410,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ZNV-!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4e918049-bb2b-4c07-94bb-3125ef44280e_966x698.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ZNV-!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4e918049-bb2b-4c07-94bb-3125ef44280e_966x698.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ZNV-!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4e918049-bb2b-4c07-94bb-3125ef44280e_966x698.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ZNV-!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4e918049-bb2b-4c07-94bb-3125ef44280e_966x698.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>FedEx Ground Hub and Spoke Structure around Phoenix Hub (purple)&nbsp;</figcaption></figure></div><p><span>Also represented here in brown are the Regional Sort Facilities, which can process </span><a href="https://www.rev.com/blog/transcripts/fedex-corp-fdx-earnings-call-transcript-q2-2021" rel="">12-15,000 packages/hour</a><span> and are something like inbound facilities for large retailers—entry points that are typically situated close to Ground Hubs. They can also help with sortation during peak season, and so also serve as spillover sortation centers.</span></p><p>Each Ground Hub employs 1,200 people on average. Employment at Ground facilities varies widely, but there are about 200 employees working at each on average. Average employment at a Regional Sort Facility is 575. This is all according to 2024 OSHA ITA data.</p><p><span>Unlike with Express, where drivers are employees of FedEx, Ground P&amp;D drivers work for third-party Independent Service Providers (ISPs), which contract with FedEx to pickup/deliver packages in a specific geographic area. ISP contractors, of which there are roughly </span><a href="https://www.deliveryroutesforsale.com/resources/fedex-isp/" rel="">5900 in the US</a><span>, are required to cover at least 5 routes or 500 daily deliveries. The linehaul drivers are also independent contractors but work for what FedEx calls Transportation Service Providers (TSPs). Both ISPs and TSPs are considered CSPs (Contracted Service Providers).</span></p><p><span>FedEx Freight is its less-than truckload (LTL) business; it handles shipments weighing over 150 lbs. It operates about </span><a href="https://www.truckingdive.com/news/fedex-freight-opens-new-facility-phoenix-market-ltl-dock-door/629458/" rel="">30,000 vehicles out of roughly 400 Service Centers</a><span>, which are included on the map. It also appears to operate by a hub-and-spoke system, though I have not been able to determine the hubs thus far (and will update this primer if I can).</span></p><p><span>Freight has a much higher operating margin than Express or Ground (</span><a href="https://www.freightwaves.com/news/fedex-launches-long-awaited-operational-integration" rel="">20-22% as opposed to 8-9% and 11-12% respectively</a><span>), and the company is in the process of spinning it off into its own company in order to </span><a href="https://www.freightwaves.com/news/fedex-explores-divestment-of-freight-business" rel="">“unlock sustainable shareholder value.”</a><span> At the same time that it is organizationally separating Freight into its own unit, however, it’s also integrating the Ground and Freight networks as part of their much anticipated Network 2.0 initiative. A large number of Freight Service Centers </span><a href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/fedex-freight-close-7-centers-154905491.html" rel="">have been closed</a><span> in the past two years.</span></p><p>FedEx also has a relatively small Supply Chain segment that provides different logistical services, including warehousing, order fulfillment, freight forwarding, transportation management, and other specialized services. It claims to have 30+ fulfillment centers, 130+ distribution centers, and more than 40 million square feet of warehouse space. </p><p>Again, Supply Chain is a negligible part of FedEx’s overall operation, but they do have some pretty big facilities in that segment. For instance, they operate a distribution center for Target in York, PA and one for T-Mobile in Coppell, TX that each employ about 1,200 people. </p><p><span>In 2022, FedEx announced its intention to create </span><a href="https://www.freightwaves.com/news/fedex-launches-long-awaited-operational-integration" rel="">Network 2.0</a><span>, which will unsilo its previously independent operations. As Satish Jindel explains </span><a href="https://www.freightwaves.com/news/fedex-and-ups-must-adapt-to-changing-parcel-landscape" rel="">here</a><span>, both FedEx and UPS’s Ground operations have become so fast that they’ve unintentionally created competitors for their Express services. The average time that a package spends in the FedEx Ground system is a </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SDEF0EgQgaI" rel="">mere 1.9 days</a><span>. FedEx is telling its contractors that it is merely piloting network integration at present, but that they should begin to see significant overhaul to the network in 2026 and 2027. FedEx is planning to shrink its distribution network from roughly 1200 facilities to about 1000.</span></p><p>In more remote locations, like Yakima, Kennewick, and Lewiston (pictured below), FedEx will often have flights going in and out of the regional airport and also have a Ground Facility and Freight Service Center. An integrated network will likely not see this same kind of redundant clustering.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!r2H4!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdba52f29-e605-476a-b729-6a6b62027a76_1580x354.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!r2H4!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdba52f29-e605-476a-b729-6a6b62027a76_1580x354.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!r2H4!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdba52f29-e605-476a-b729-6a6b62027a76_1580x354.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!r2H4!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdba52f29-e605-476a-b729-6a6b62027a76_1580x354.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!r2H4!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdba52f29-e605-476a-b729-6a6b62027a76_1580x354.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!r2H4!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdba52f29-e605-476a-b729-6a6b62027a76_1580x354.png" width="560" height="125.38461538461539" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/dba52f29-e605-476a-b729-6a6b62027a76_1580x354.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:326,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:560,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!r2H4!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdba52f29-e605-476a-b729-6a6b62027a76_1580x354.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!r2H4!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdba52f29-e605-476a-b729-6a6b62027a76_1580x354.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!r2H4!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdba52f29-e605-476a-b729-6a6b62027a76_1580x354.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!r2H4!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdba52f29-e605-476a-b729-6a6b62027a76_1580x354.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>Clustered FedEx facilities in Yakima, Kennewick, and Lewiston</figcaption></figure></div></div></article></div><div id="discussion"><h4>Discussion about this post</h4></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Autism may be the price of human intelligence, linked to human brain evolution (178 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://academic.oup.com/mbe/article/42/9/msaf189/8245036?login=false</link>
            <guid>45408994</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 23:32:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://academic.oup.com/mbe/article/42/9/msaf189/8245036?login=false">https://academic.oup.com/mbe/article/42/9/msaf189/8245036?login=false</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45408994">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://academic.oup.com/mbe/article/42/9/msaf189/8245036?login=false: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Go ahead, write the “stupid” code (216 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://spikepuppet.io/posts/write-the-stupid-code/</link>
            <guid>45408617</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 22:20:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://spikepuppet.io/posts/write-the-stupid-code/">https://spikepuppet.io/posts/write-the-stupid-code/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45408617">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div> <article data-astro-cid-xj2uyz6m="">   <h2 id="go-ahead---write-the-stupid-code">Go Ahead - Write the “stupid” code</h2>
<p>When I finished school in 2010 (yep, along time ago now), I wanted to go try and make it as a musician. I figured if punk bands could just learn on the job, I could too. But my mum insisted that I needed to do something, just in case. So I went down to the local TAFE (this is like a trade school in Australia, though it has pathways into uni, it’s pretty neat!) and signed up for whatever looked good. I had always loved computers and gaming, I did all the courses for computing short of programming in school (the school didn’t offer it), and had an interest so I signed up.</p>
<p>It wasn’t love at first sight, as I still remember after a week freaking out in my room that I couldn’t do this. But I sat down with my massive VB.NET textbook we had to buy and pushed through it. And once I made it through, it clicked. I fell in love with programming after that, and it became something I was both good at and started growing a passion for.</p>
<p>From there, going through my games diploma, and my bachelors in games design and development (think a comp sci degree with game design elements, it’s pretty neat and I’m happy to answer questions about it), I wrote a lot of stupid code. Like a lot of it. In my courses, in my game jams (god good times), in my spare time when I was learning things both in uni and early in my career. It helped me refine my skills, but also learn a lot.</p>
<p>Fast forward to today. I’ve been doing a dive on JavaScript/TypeScript and different runtimes like NodeJS and Deno, amongst a bunch of other stuff. At first, I was looking into a deep dive into node with <a href="https://youtu.be/rUFUTdQALrk?si=wSZcxvzoO3eA1_fj">this talk by James Snell</a> and wanted to try out the Streams API. Part of me wanted to start writing straight away, but held back because I didn’t think I had anything to use it on. After being unable to resist the urge to write some code after a few minutes, I just made the dumbest stock ticker I could so I could try streams out in an arbitrary way. But it left me thinking, “why didn’t I hold back”.</p>
<p>As I’m writing this now, I came up with the answer. As I was writing a little <a href="https://github.com/SpikePuppet/daily-inspo">app to output inspirational quotes</a>, I started umm’ing and ahh’ing over if I should make this. It’s small, it’s dumb, and there were probably plenty of options out there. But I wanted to write some code, and was interested in trying out Deno and seeing how it compiles binaries. So I did it. And I was happy (I’m very excited to use it), and I realised that I was scared to write something dumb. All my years of doing this helped refine my own abilities, but also made me much more harsh on myself. Harsh on my own code, harsh on just trying things.</p>
<p>After coming to this realisation, I’ve decided I’m going to give myself more grace when it comes to writing software for myself, and I encourage you all dear readers to do the same if you’ve been feeling this. There is no stupid code. There’s only code. Enjoy writing it, it doesn’t have to be nice or pretty if it’s for you. Have fun, try out that new runtime or language. Poke around and see what breaks. Keep that learning mindset, and keep feeding your curiosity. It’ll help you continue to grow across your career, and if you enjoy this kind of thing as a hobby like me, it’ll keep stoking your own enjoyment and passion.</p>   </article> </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Farewell friends (324 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://humbledollar.com/forum/farewell-friends/</link>
            <guid>45408229</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 21:31:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://humbledollar.com/forum/farewell-friends/">https://humbledollar.com/forum/farewell-friends/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45408229">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>If this post is appearing, it means I’ve succumbed to cancer or one of its side effects. Please don’t feel sad for me. I’ve had a life filled with love, great experiences and wonderful career opportunities. Despite my demise at a relatively young age, I consider myself beyond fortunate.</p><p>I’m hoping that, under the tree in front of our little Philadelphia rowhome, my wife Elaine will place a stone tablet inscribed with my name, and the year I was born and died. Underneath, I’d like the tablet to read:</p><p>Family • Readers • Words</p><p>(Note to Elaine: If you ever move, feel free to take the tablet with you.)</p><p>Family is everybody who’s brought love into my life: Elaine, my two children, my larger family, my close friends. Meanwhile, readers have been those I’ve served, and who rewarded that service with so much loyalty and affection. Finally, words have been my playground, taking the insights I’ve garnered and trying to make them understandable to others. Beside the tree are two metal chairs. I hope family and passersby will occasionally stop by, and fill me in on what I’ve been missing.</p><p>I’ve asked Elaine to arrange a memorial service at <a href="https://www.stpetersphila.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">St Peter’s Church</a> in Philadelphia’s Old City. She’ll post the time and date to the Forum when the details have been worked out.</p><p>Regular readers will know much of my life’s story. But I figure it’s appropriate to offer a not-so-brief recap.</p><p>I was born at 14 St Margarets Drive in Twickenham, London, on Jan. 2, 1963. At that time in the UK, it was standard practice for mothers to give birth in the hospital if it was their first child—or, in my mother’s case, her first two children. My older brothers, who are identical twins, had been born two years earlier. Because that first delivery went smoothly, my birth would be at home. From what I gather, the midwife took cigarette and scotch breaks with my father during lulls in the action. I was born at 6 a.m., thus establishing a lifetime habit of starting early.</p><p>In 1966, my father left financial journalism for a job at the World Bank, and we moved from London to Washington, DC. Two years later, my younger sister was born. In late 1972, my father was posted to the World Bank’s Bangladesh office for four years, and I was dispatched to boarding school in England, joining my two brothers.</p><p>After the comforts of a U.S. suburban childhood, it was a <a href="https://humbledollar.com/2023/03/the-other-enough/">brutal</a> change—cold dormitories, disgusting food, endless bullying—and I carried the scars for the rest of my life. But there was a silver lining: After nine years of boarding school, I squeaked into Cambridge University, where I spent much of my three years writing for and editing the student newspaper.</p><p>When I graduated Cambridge in 1985, the UK economy was in rough shape and landing a job was difficult. I ended up working for <em>Euromoney</em> magazine in London. Initially, all went well. But then there was a change in editor and, for reasons I never understood, the new editor took an instant dislike to me and made it clear he wanted me gone. But by then, I’d already decided to leave London and return to the U.S.</p><p>My then-fiancee and I flew to New York in August 1986. After a desperate scramble, I landed a job as a reporter—read “fact checker”—at <em>Forbes</em> magazine. The pay was miserable, but I couldn’t have been more grateful for that first paycheck. By then, all I had to my name was credit card debt.</p><p>Molly and I were married the following June, and Hannah arrived 15 months later. Her younger brother, Henry, would follow in 1992.</p><p>After 23 months as a fact checker, I was promoted to staff writer at <em>Forbes</em>, covering mutual funds. <em>The Wall Street Journal,</em> which was also in need of a funds reporter, came calling 16 months later. I’d always thought I’d never be a real journalist until I worked for a daily newspaper, and yet initially I said no.</p><p>At the time, I was in the midst of six months as a single parent, looking after Hannah on my own while Molly was in Syria, Greece and Turkey conducting research for her PhD. Still,&nbsp;the <em>Journal</em> wasn’t deterred, saying it would make allowances during my initial months.</p><p>In the early 1990s, the <em>Journal </em>was very different from the newspaper it is today. No photos, just the dot drawings for which the paper was renowned. While strong opinions could be found on the editorial page, they were to be avoided in the news pages. The sort of advice journalism I favored was frowned upon by some among the paper’s senior ranks.</p><p>Still, in 1994, Managing Editor Paul Steiger said he’d consider a few columnists for the <em>Journal’s</em> news pages. At age 31, and with some trepidation, I put up my hand. Thus was born the <em>Getting Going</em> column, which I wrote for the next 13-plus years, penning 1,009 columns for both <em>The Wall Street Journal</em> and <em>Wall Street Journal Sunday</em>. The latter were branded pages that appeared in some 70 newspapers around the country.</p><p>In retrospect, it’s astonishing that I was given my own column at such a young age. It took me a few months to hit my stride, but I was soon pounding away at the virtues of index funds, while also exploring new topics, often scouring academic research for insights I could share with readers.</p><p>The decade and a half that followed are something of a blur. I was cranking out columns, commuting into New York City from the New Jersey suburbs, and raising two children. In my memory, the years have the monotony of a hamster wheel. But that wasn’t the reality: There were high points and low points, plus the joy of watching Hannah and Henry grow up. The low points included&nbsp;the World Trade Center <a href="https://humbledollar.com/2021/09/twenty-years-ago/">attack</a>, my father’s <a href="https://humbledollar.com/2024/08/on-the-clock/">death</a> and a <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB945822461920337432" target="_blank" rel="noopener">libel suit</a>&nbsp;brought against the <em>Journal</em>. I’d been involved in editing the story that triggered the lawsuit.</p><p>In early 1995, while in Pittsburgh, I went on a nine-mile run with my brother-in-law, who was training for the city’s marathon. I’d long viewed running those 26.2 miles as a heroic endeavor. I committed to returning for the next year’s marathon. But I didn’t simply want to complete the distance. Instead, I set a goal of finishing in under three hours. I managed it, though barely, crossing the finish line <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB833401105627639500" target="_blank" rel="noopener">24 seconds</a> under the three-hour mark.</p><p>I ran countless road races over the next dozen years. I had my greatest success with half-marathons, finishing third in the four races I ran on land—and first in the 2001 half-marathon held on the deck of a boat floating off <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB984088892480498588" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Antarctica</a>. In shorter races, from one mile to 10, I also managed perhaps a dozen first-place finishes. What about the tearful, wimpy English schoolboy who had previously shunned athletic endeavors? Over countless miles, I managed to leave him behind.</p><p>Career and athletic success were not, alas, rivaled by relationship success. Molly announced she wanted a divorce in 1998. It would be the first of two failed marriages—not an achievement I’m proud of. But the third time was a charm. In the midst of the pandemic, Elaine and I met in August 2020, the month my second marriage officially ended. We were living together by the end of the month and married almost four years later, in May 2024, five days after my cancer diagnosis. I met Elaine during one of my life’s roughest periods, and was so lucky to have done so. Elaine, I fear, was not so fortunate, for now she must navigate the world on her own.</p><p>By 2006 or so, I’d started to tire of the <em>Getting Going</em> column, and began casting around for what to do next. I had a few conversations with potential employers, but those came to naught. Then, one day in early 2008, my phone rang. It was Andy Seig from Citigroup. He was heading up a startup within Citi known as myFi, which was aiming to deliver advice on a client’s entire financial life in return for a flat monthly fee. It was, I imagined, the exit from the <em>Journal</em> I was looking for.</p><p>I joined myFi that spring, and it soon became apparent that launching a startup in the middle of a huge corporate bureaucracy was a foolhardy endeavor. Layered on top of that was the financial crisis that unfolded through the year. By mid-2009, myFi was dead, and we employees spent a long, aimless summer trying to figure out what was next.</p><p>Next turned out to be a new wealth management operation cobbled together by combining myFi’s remaining employees, who had been hired to launch an innovative new financial service, and the old school brokers who sat in Citi’s bank branches. It wasn’t exactly a match made in heaven.</p><p>I toughed it out at Citi until spring 2014. Money was undoubtedly part of the reason. I was making more than $300,000 a year, a gaudy sum for a onetime ink-stained wretch. And the job wasn’t without interest. As director of financial education for the U.S. wealth management business, I gave more than 30 speeches in some years—forcing me to overcome my fear of public speaking—and I was dealing with financial topics I’d rarely written about as a journalist, while also learning about the investment business from the inside. Still, I was also frustrated by the nit-picky oversight of lawyers and compliance officers, and vowed to leave.</p><p>For a year, I planned my departure, getting my finances in order and setting in motion some work projects for my life after Citi. I waited until I got my final year-end bonus in early 2014, and then handed in my notice.</p><p>What followed was a period I came to call my <a href="https://humbledollar.com/2018/01/second-childhood/">second childhood</a>. Initially, that meant a 15-month return to <em>The Wall Street Journal</em> as a freelance columnist—I left when my editor got ousted during a round of layoffs in 2015—and also working on two annual editions of the <em>Jonathan Clements Money Guide</em>. That <a href="https://humbledollar.com/money-guide/main-menu/">guide</a> eventually became the core of <em>HumbleDollar</em>, which I launched on Dec. 31, 2016.</p><p>The two printed editions of the money guide were among the nine <a href="https://humbledollar.com/books/">books</a> I wrote over my career—eight personal finance books and a novel. I also edited two books, including <a href="https://www.amazon.com/My-Money-Journey-financial-freedom/dp/0857199862/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>My Money Journey</em></a>, a compilation of 30 essays by <em>HumbleDollar</em> writers, and contributed essays to &nbsp;a fistful of other tomes, including penning the foreword to two Bill Bernstein books. None of the books I authored was a huge success. But my favorite, and the one with the best sales, was my 2016 book, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/1523770813" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>How to Think About Money</em></a>.</p><p>In 2016, I was also contacted by Peter Mallouk, president of fast-growing Creative Planning, a registered investment advisor that favored index funds and sought to help clients with their entire financial life. As at Citi, I was again given the title of director of financial education, though I remained an independent contractor and worked limited hours for Creative. Still, for me, it proved to be one of my career’s most enjoyable professional relationships. Peter was great to work with, and together we hosted a monthly podcast that ran for the rest of my life.</p><p>By May 2024, I’d been living in Philadelphia for more than three years, I was engaged to Elaine and living just an eight-minute walk from my daughter, son-in-law and two grandsons. The youngest was born that month. Elaine and I were talking about retirement, trying to figure out how we could travel more and have more time for each other, even as I kept <em>HumbleDollar</em> humming along.</p><p>And then I got my cancer <a href="https://humbledollar.com/2024/06/the-c-word/">diagnosis</a>.</p><p>The period immediately after was astonishingly <a href="https://humbledollar.com/2024/07/no-slowing-down/">busy</a>, as I tried to get my affairs in order and prep <em>HumbleDollar</em> for a life without me, even as my diagnosis triggered a surprising amount of media attention. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/07/13/your-money/jonathan-clements-cancer.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>The New York Times</em></a> wrote about my illness, I was interviewed for Consuelo Mack’s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9op9EXJ493s" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>WealthTrack</em></a>, and I was asked to pen articles for <a href="https://archive.ph/ZeWeF" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>The Washington Post</em></a>, <a href="https://www.msn.com/en-gb/health/other/i-m-61-and-i-ve-got-a-year-left-to-live-but-i-still-plan-to-work-every-day/ar-AA1rakRY" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>The Telegraph</em></a> of London, <a href="https://www.wsj.com/personal-finance/jonathan-clements-personal-finance-cancer-e30d1396?st=ZHog6a&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>The Wall Street Journal</em></a> and <a href="https://www.aarp.org/benefits-discounts/members-only-access/info-2025/cancer-changed-retirement-plan.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">AARP</a> magazine. Who knew that candor about one’s own death would generate so much interest? It was an odd bookend to a life spent partly in the public eye—one that had previously been most notable for pounding the table for index funds.</p><p>I faced the final months not with sorrow, but with great <a href="https://humbledollar.com/2024/09/no-regrets/">gratitude</a>. I had spent almost my entire adult life doing what I love and surrounded by those that I love. Who could ask for more?</p></div><p>Did you just log in? If you don't see the commenting form, please refresh the page.</p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Play snake in the URL address bar (780 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://demian.ferrei.ro/snake/</link>
            <guid>45408021</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 21:08:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://demian.ferrei.ro/snake/">https://demian.ferrei.ro/snake/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45408021">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
  <p><span>Use the arrow keys or WASD to control the snake on the URL.</span>
    <span>Use the arrows to control the snake on the URL.</span>
    <a id="reveal-url" href="#">Click here</a> if you can't see the page URL<span id="url-escaping-note"> or if it looks messed up with <span id="replacement-char-description"></span></span>.&nbsp;
  </p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Larry Ellison on AI-powered surveillance [video] (114 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://streamable.com/2xtyyd</link>
            <guid>45407785</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 20:40:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://streamable.com/2xtyyd">https://streamable.com/2xtyyd</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45407785">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><a href="https://privacy.streamable.com/">Privacy Policy</a><a href="https://streamable.com/cookies">Cookie Policy</a><a href="https://terms.streamable.com/">Terms</a><a href="https://streamable.com/community-guidelines">Community Guidelines</a><a href="https://streamable-support.zendesk.com/hc/en-us">Support</a><a href="https://report.streamable.checkstep.com/?content_id=2xtyyd">Report</a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Linus Learns Analog Circuits (153 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/torvalds/GuitarPedal</link>
            <guid>45407617</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 20:19:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/torvalds/GuitarPedal">https://github.com/torvalds/GuitarPedal</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45407617">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Random guitar pedal board design</h2><a id="user-content-random-guitar-pedal-board-design" aria-label="Permalink: Random guitar pedal board design" href="#random-guitar-pedal-board-design"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Background</h3><a id="user-content-background" aria-label="Permalink: Background" href="#background"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This is a personal toy project that has gone through several phases, but
the common theme has been that it makes absolutely no sense outside of
the very specific niche of "Linus is trying to learn random things about
electronics".</p>
<p dir="auto">So keep that in mind: there is very little point to any of this to
anybody else.  Don't expect some great useful guitar pedal experience.</p>
<p dir="auto">I call it my "LEGO for adults" hobby, because this got started when I
wanted to extend my traditional after-Christmas activity (which was
receiving and building <em>actual</em> LEGO kits, which has been a thing for me
since I was a wee tyke) with something else.</p>
<p dir="auto">So for Christmas 2024, I got a new soldering iron and randomly started
doing guitar pedal kits.  And so over the next month or two, I built at
least two dozen kits, and had to literally look for victims to give them
away to because I had no use for them myself.</p>
<div dir="auto"><p dir="auto">Note</p><p dir="auto">Of all the kits I built, the ones I enjoyed the most were the Aion FX
ones, and if you are looking for a kit build of traditional analog
guitar pedals, I can heartily recommend them.</p>
<p dir="auto">The documentation, the customer service, the components, and the
enclosures were all top notch. See <a href="https://aionfx.com/" rel="nofollow">"Aion FX"</a></p>
</div>
<p dir="auto">Anyway, after building a lot of these traditional analog guitar pedal
kits I decided I really wanted to actually understand what they did,
because I really had very little experience with any analog circuits.</p>
<p dir="auto">While I've done some very limited electronics most of my life, almost
all of it has been related to computers, so it's been either digital
logic or power supplies for them.</p>
<p dir="auto">Also, I was looking for a different kind of soldering experience where
there was less snipping of legs of through-hole components.  I actually
like soldering SMT components, but that doesn't tend to be what those
guitar pedal kits do.</p>
<p dir="auto">I had done some very limited PCB design with kicad a few years ago, so I
decided to just start learning more about analog circuits.  And then it
kind of grew from that.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Electrical design</h3><a id="user-content-electrical-design" aria-label="Permalink: Electrical design" href="#electrical-design"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This is the "fourth generation" of my guitar pedal design journey, and
is a new repository because the goal of the learning experience has
evolved.</p>
<p dir="auto">What started out being about the analog circuits (and the power rails:
those were always a big thing) got to the point where I realized I
really want to do a mixed signal design: understanding what the circuits
do is one thing, re-creating some analog design from the 70s when you
don't actually care about the sound is another thing entirely.</p>
<p dir="auto">Also, on the actual analog signal side, I started out using op-amps, but
as I was attempting to learn how things actually worked, I had switched
over to a "discrete components only" model, and this continues that
trend (except for the whole digital side, of course).</p>
<div dir="auto"><p dir="auto">Note</p><p dir="auto">To me "discrete components" does include more optimized packages:
things like dual diodes or matched transistors, but not more complex
circuits like a op-amp (or a 555 timer or D Flip-flop or other classic
logic IC)</p>
</div>
<p dir="auto">Also, because I don't typically <em>listen</em> to the end result, but look at
it with a signal generator and an oscilloscope, I've grown to detest
power supply noise.</p>
<p dir="auto">Not knowing what I was doing, quite a lot of my circuits have been very
noisy indeed, and have coupled in noise from the power supply into the
signal chain, and you can really see that on an oscilloscope even when
it's not always audible.</p>
<p dir="auto">Even in op-amp designs, where the op-amp itself has a very high PSRR and
isn't mixing power supply noise into the signal, my biasing circuits
were often not great, and so the op-amp would see not just the signal
but the power supply noise coming in through the DC biasing.</p>
<p dir="auto">And every time I tried a dual power rail (so that I could just keep the
signal ground-referenced), the noise from the switching ended up just
always noticeable, and the extra complexity was annoying when a lot of
effects then didn't have any real use for the dual rail.</p>
<p dir="auto">Filtering obviously helps, but this is just a long-winded explanation
for why I ended up really appreciating the "bias to ground" JFET model
for the signal input side, and the common drain follower in particular.</p>
<p dir="auto">That works with a single JFET (the MMBF5103 worked well for me), but my
favorite design so far is a dual-JFET LS844 with the second matched JFET
used as a current sink.  It has basically infinite input impedance (and
could be DC coupled, although I do the coupling capacitor with resistor
to ground) and gives a good output signal somewhere roughly in the
middle of the single-supply 9V rail.</p>
<p dir="auto">See <a href="https://www.linearsystems.com/_files/ugd/7e8069_52b1022fbded45fab609459acb337629.pdf" rel="nofollow">LS844 Application note</a></p>
<p dir="auto">Why do I mention this in particular? Mainly because it's a great example
of how completely <em>insane</em> my designs are.  That LS844 is used as a
voltage follower with a noticeable DC offset, and that single dual-JFET
SOT-23-6 component is more expensive - and harder to find - than a
simple op-amp would be.</p>
<p dir="auto">Just to put that into perspective: you can buy LM358's at mouser for
about $0.07 each in reasonable quantities (ie a hundred).  Sure, that's
not the greatest op-amp ever and you'd have to have a 5V regulator, so
maybe you're better off at twice the cost, and go for a TL082 or a TL072
instead.  Or go for a BJT input one and be even cheaper.</p>
<p dir="auto">The LS844? Harder to find, and <em>much</em> more expensive.  If they are in
stock at all, you'll find them for $2.50 when you buy ten or more.  And
I'm using it as a questionable replacement for a single input of one of
those dirt-cheap op-amps.</p>
<p dir="auto">Put another way: go elsewhere for sane designs.  This is not the place.</p>
<p dir="auto">But it does work quite well. See some notes on the signal path testing
<a href="https://github.com/torvalds/GuitarPedal/blob/main/Documentation/Passthrough/Notes.md">here</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Physical design</h3><a id="user-content-physical-design" aria-label="Permalink: Physical design" href="#physical-design"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">I started out with small designs that I decided would fit best into a
1590A enclosure (basically the smallest regular guitar pedal form
factor), because it was cute.  The purely physical layout limitations
were actually interesting, and since I was doing SMT components and
simple circuits, the circuit sizes were never even remotely an issue.</p>
<p dir="auto">However, as I decided that I don't want to play around with silly analog
audio effects from the 60's and 70's any more, that 1590A enclosure got
increasingly painful.  Putting an Electrosmith Daisy Seed inside of them
is possible, but only if you don't do a proper stomp-switch and limit
yourself to two pots.  And yes, I did that.</p>
<p dir="auto">Do I want to use the pre-built Daisy Seed? Maybe - and maybe not.  This
repository does include the beginnings of a "what if I did my own
version of a MCU and CODEC", because it's an interesting learning
experience too.  And I started that because then I'd be able to fit
things better in a 1590A.</p>
<p dir="auto">But then my meds kicked in, and I've finally given up on the 1590A.
It's cute.  The mechanical challenges were interesting.  But they've
gone from "interesting" to "overly limiting".</p>
<p dir="auto">So now I'm instead doing a much more reasonable enclosure.  So 1590B it
is.  That just simplifies things a lot and the end result is a lot
saner.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Components</h3><a id="user-content-components" aria-label="Permalink: Components" href="#components"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">I've used JLCPCB, PCBWAY and OSH Park for PCB manufacturing.  The end
results are all good, pick the one you're most comfortable with.  I've
found that at least for me, JLCPCB gives the fastest turnaround time,
but I suspect it heavily depends on where you live.</p>
<p dir="auto">In the past, I've done some PCB assembly services too, and PCBWAY did a
good job.  With this project where the manual soldering has been part of
the whole experience, I've just done bare boards so far.</p>
<p dir="auto">I've toyed with the idea of doing some assembly service jobs in case I
decide to go for more fiddly components, but that's really for a future
"what if I do the digital side too".  I'm not there yet.</p>
<p dir="auto">Connectors and potentiometers are typically from Tayda Electronics, with
most of the actual common SMD components from kits or from Mouser.</p>
<p dir="auto">Some typical parts from Tayda:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://www.taydaelectronics.com/6-35-mm-1-4-righ-angle-mono-female-connector-thread-lock-panel-mount.html" rel="nofollow">Mono Audio Jack A-6976</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.taydaelectronics.com/dc-power-jack-2-1mm-barrel-type-pcb-mount.html" rel="nofollow">2.1mm DC Barrel Jack A-4118</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.taydaelectronics.com/10k-ohm-linear-taper-potentiometer-round-shaft-pcb-9mm.html" rel="nofollow">10k Linear 9mm Pot A-1847</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.taydaelectronics.com/dpdt-compact-stomp-foot-pedal-switch-momentary-pcb.html" rel="nofollow">DPDT Compact Stomp Foot Switch A-1884</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.taydaelectronics.com/10-pin-box-header-connector-2-54mm-right-angle.html" rel="nofollow">Right Angle IDC Header A-2943</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">For "random" SMD capacitors and resistors, get one of the kits.  I can
personally heartily recommend the Guanruixin kits from Amazon: there are
0805 and 1206 kits of both capacitors and resistors, and I love the
packaging and labeling.  Very good for organizing at a hobbyist level.</p>
<p dir="auto">Just the storage case makes them worth getting:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Guanruixin-Capacitor-1pF-47uF-Capacitance-Compliant/dp/B0B3JV5PMT" rel="nofollow">Guanruixin 0805 Capacitor Kit</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Guanruixin-Resistor-Assortment-Tolerance-Compliant/dp/B0B3JVDMZ1" rel="nofollow">Guanruixin 0805 Resistor Kit</a></li>
<li>.. any other sizes you want</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">There are other kits out there, but it's nice to have a good compact
case with a selection of various values.  If you are like me, you'll run
out of the common resistor values, and then I buy cut tape from Mouser
and just fill the specific compartments in that kit case.</p>
<p dir="auto">Which brings us to Mouser and DigiKey and the like: not just for
refills, but for anything that is slightly more specialized.  Like that
LS844, but really most of the not-completely-standard SMD components.</p>
<p dir="auto">My exact SMD component choices have been pretty random, and a number of
them have been influenced by footprint rather than technical merit.  I
tend to like things like dual transistor SOT-23-6 packages, and if you
look at my MOSFET choices I think you'll find that the primary choice
was packaging and a high enough V<sub>GSS</sub>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Put another way: I'm not claiming my parts choices necessarily make
sense.  They've worked for me - often in the sense of "that other part
was just too fiddly to solder, so I've replaced it with this other part
that works for me"</p>
<div dir="auto"><p dir="auto">Note</p><p dir="auto">If you actually know what you are doing, and you looked at the
schematic and went "Linus is clearly way over his head, and that is
just <em>stupid</em>", whether it comes to parts choices or to just the
circuit in general, please let me know.</p>
<p dir="auto">In particular, don't feel like it would be impolite to tell me I'm
incompetent and doing stupid things. I absolutely know I'm not
competent and would love to hear any criticism. Some of the best
teaching moments have been when I haven't understood something, and
somebody piped up to tell me I should do Xyz.</p>
<p dir="auto">I'm going to leave the link to the
<a href="https://github.com/torvalds/1590A/issues/4" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/torvalds/1590A/issues/4/hovercard">"Tremolo doubling as a metronome"</a>
issue from the 1590A pedal project, because that was a case of
somebody (@gralco) coming in and very politely telling me I was doing
stupid things.</p>
<p dir="auto">Pushing me to do simulations in KiCad completely changed the game.
So don't be shy to tell me my circuits suck. Because that's literally
why I do this!</p>
</div>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[China Is Run by Engineers. America Is Run by Lawyers (158 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://freakonomics.com/podcast/china-is-run-by-engineers-america-is-run-by-lawyers/</link>
            <guid>45407490</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 20:06:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://freakonomics.com/podcast/china-is-run-by-engineers-america-is-run-by-lawyers/">https://freakonomics.com/podcast/china-is-run-by-engineers-america-is-run-by-lawyers/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45407490">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

			<article>

								<section id="transcript">
					<h2>Episode Transcript</h2>
										<div id="transcript_inner">
						<p>Hey there, it’s Stephen Dubner. Before we get started on today’s episode, I’d love your help on a future episode we’re producing —&nbsp;especially if you happen to be a physician. We’re looking into the doctor shortage in the U.S., so if you happen to be a doctor, we want to hear from you. I’d like to know how your workload has changed over time, maybe how your workplace has changed, or if you have anything else on the topic to say you think we might find interesting. Just send a voice memo to radio@freakonomics.com, subject line: doctor shortage. Thanks in advance. Also: we’ll be doing a live taping of <em>Freakonomics Radio</em> as part of Sirius XM Podcasts Month, on Wednesday, October 8th in New York City. There’s room for a few <em>Freakonomics Radio</em> fans to come along, so if you’d like to be one of them, send an email to radio@freakonomics.com, subject line: “live taping.” Thanks for that —&nbsp;and now, on to today’s episode.</p>
<p>&nbsp;*&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; *&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; *</p>
<p>If you are an American, how do you think about the relationship between the U.S. and China? You may see China as a political and economic bully, and a thief of American intellectual property. You may see China as a hardcore surveillance state — internally and externally; maybe a propaganda state too. But you probably don’t think about the relationship between China and the U.S. the way that <strong>Dan Wang</strong> thinks about it:</p>
<blockquote><p><a href="https://danwang.co/about/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong><em>Dan WANG</em></strong></a><em>: I think that no two peoples are more alike. They have a hastiness around them. They have a sense of being willing to take shortcuts, especially on health and wealth. They both have a sense of the future in a way that I think is not so apparent anymore in Europe or Japan. They’re both striving towards something.</em></p></blockquote>
<p>But for all those similarities between the U.S. and China, Wang sees one huge difference: China is a country that is run by engineers, while the U.S. is a country run by lawyers. Engineers, he explains, are driven to build while lawyers are driven to argue, and obstruct. Who is Dan Wang, and how did he come to hold this view? He was born in China, in the early 1990s. When he was seven, he immigrated with his parents to Canada and, later, to the U.S., near Philadelphia. But he returned to China in his twenties —&nbsp;as an analyst for an economic research firm. He stayed for six years, and each year he wrote a long letter home, and published it on his website.</p>
<blockquote><p><em>WANG</em><em>: Yes, that’s right. Every year I tried to tell my friends what I was up to, and try to tell my parents what I was up to. And it kind of took a life of its own after I was stuck in China during the entirety of “Zero Covid,” and very few other people were able to observe the country and write about it as I was able to do.&nbsp;</em></p></blockquote>
<p>He has now turned those letters into a book, called <em>Breakneck: China’s Quest to Engineer the Future. </em>Wang sees much to admire about an engineering state:</p>
<blockquote><p><em>WANG</em><em>: They’ve just been solving seven problems a day before breakfast because they have so many problems to solve.&nbsp;</em></p></blockquote>
<p>But also, plenty of downside:</p>
<blockquote><p><em>WANG</em><em>: They are also fundamentally social engineers, and the physical engineers cannot restrain themselves from treating society as just another big optimization problem.&nbsp;</em></p></blockquote>
<p>Today on <em>Freakonomics Radio</em>, what happens when an engineering state goes up against a lawyerly society? What does the U.S. have to learn from China, and vice versa? And: what happens when an expat returns to explore the soul of his motherland?<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p>
<blockquote><p><em>WANG</em><em>: I was concerned at several points for my safety. </em></p></blockquote>
<p>All that is coming up, starting now.</p>
<p>&nbsp;*&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; *&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; *</p>
<p>Okay, let’s have a proper introduction.</p>
<blockquote><p><em>WANG: Hi, I’m Dan Wang. I am a research fellow at the Hoover Institution at Stanford University, and the author of </em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Breakneck-Chinas-Quest-Engineer-Future/dp/1324106034" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Breakneck: China’s Quest to Engineer the Future</a><em>.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: So Dan, what are you exactly? I ask because you’re not an academic researcher, quite. You’re not fully a journalist, quite. You’re not a business analyst, quite. So if you had to slap one big label on your forehead, what would it be?&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: I am Dan Wang. I think that is all I can be. But maybe you can give me a label. I think a lot of what I have tried to do is to be an observer of China partly as an outsider just as I’m an observer of the United States partly as an outsider of being Canadian.&nbsp;</em></p></blockquote>
<p>These days, Wang spends most of his time in Ann Arbor, Michigan.</p>
<blockquote><p><em>WANG: My wife is a professor at the University of Michigan. is an anthropologist, really, of technology cultures, and so, she wrote a book about Shenzhen maker spaces called Prototype Nation. </em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: And where did she grow up?&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG: She grew up in Salzburg. So, she is Austrian and we just spent a bit of time in Austria. We were hiking through the Austrian Alps.&nbsp;</em></p></blockquote>
<p>Wang was born in the Chinese province of Yunnan.</p>
<blockquote><p><em>WANG</em><em>: I grew up in China’s periphery. I did not grow up in its imperial core of Beijing or these rich coastal cities like Shanghai or Shenzhen.&nbsp;</em></p></blockquote>
<p>One of Wang’s grandfathers barely survived famine, and he became an army officer. His other grandfather came from a family that had once been rich, from trading in everything from copper and silk to liquor and possibly opium.</p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: My family is made up of some people with more elite origins, some people with more rural origins, but what was important was that they all suffered through the great turn of the Communist Party’s rule with Mao Zedong. Some of them made it out better than others. My parents were both lucky to be urbanites in China growing up. They were part of China’s luckiest generation, to have been born in the 1960s. They were able to attend university. They were able to have careers, to build a modicum of wealth, and they were able to emigrate abroad as well.</em></p>
<blockquote><p><em>DUBNER: You write that for your parents when they were younger, and especially your grandparents’ generation, that poverty was the normal state of affairs, that there were shortages in just about everything. </em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: That’s right. </em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: Imagine that they had been born — the same people that you know as your mother and father —&nbsp;had been born, let’s say, 30 years later, 1990. How would their lives have been different?&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: Yeah, well, that is around my age. I just turned 33, and this is one of these things that I reflect upon in China, that the decade of birth really, really matters. And so my parents were lucky in part because the socialist-planned economy was going away when my mom was in college. When she started college at the age of 18, she was given ration tickets to be able to eat pork once a month. That was all the pork that she was allotted. But most of that system had melted away by the time she reached her senior year of college. Now, if you were born in China in 1990 then I could expect that my parents by virtue of being urbanites should have been allocated two or three apartments from the state, which would be worth quite a bit more. And they may have been able to liquidate one of these homes in order to send me abroad for college, and maybe my parents could have afforded my college education much more easily.</em></p></blockquote>
<p>From around 1980 until 2016, the Chinese government —&nbsp;concerned about overpopulation — enforced its one-child policy.</p>
<blockquote><p><em>WANG</em><em>: And my parents, I’m not sure whether they are really wanted to have a second child, but that option wasn’t available to them in part because when my mother gave birth to me, she was also forced to sign these documents in her workplace saying that she will not have a second child, and maybe she would have to consent to having a sterilization to make sure that she did not have a second child. </em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: How old were you when you learned about that? </em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: I was maybe about seven or eight years old. This was shortly after we moved to Canada when I was growing up. My parents I think at least debated and discussed whether they should give me a sibling. We had a bit of a rocky start when I moved to Canada. My parents moved just after the dot-com bubble, and my dad was a software engineer. So they had a harder time finding their footing. And I was a handful, I admit. I was a rowdy child. I’m sorry, Mom. </em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: Well, they got their revenge by placing you in some kind of military training program, yes?&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: I was such a rowdy child that my parents decided that I was best served to be a Royal Canadian Army Cadet. </em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: And that worked out well for you.</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: I was never all that good at school. But the army really straightened me out, I was part of the army band, and I was really good at drill, I was cadet of the year and that was something I was really proud of.</em></p></blockquote>
<p>Wang studied philosophy at the University of Rochester in upstate New York, but he dropped out to work for the Canadian e-commerce startup Shopify. He then spent some time in Silicon Valley and in Germany. He did eventually get his college degree, and he did some freelance writing — <a href="https://www.vox.com/new-money/2016/11/4/13498504/shenzhen-smartphone-innovation-capital" target="_blank" rel="noopener">including an article for <em>Vox</em> about Chinese drone technology</a>. This led to a job with a firm called Gavekal Dragonomics, which provides investment research about the Chinese economy. He moved to Hong Kong in 2017.</p>
<blockquote><p><em>WANG</em><em>: We were trying to get beyond the headlines of the Wall Street Journal and Bloomberg to figure what’s really going on in China for a broadly financial audience of folks in hedge funds, pensions, asset allocators. We were journalists, we were diplomats, we were analysts, we were executives, all trying to figure out this big thing of what China is. I was there to really study a big program called Made in China 2025, which was Beijing’s grand ambition to dominate 10 different industries of the future, included electric vehicles, included new forms of material science, and at the time there was a lot of skepticism that China could innovate, that China could build cars better than Germans and Japanese. And I had been feeling that China was going to be able to build all the cars, going to build all the industrial robotics. What I found really important was to treat China seriously by reading a lot of the core texts of the party state. So I found myself reading most major speeches by Xi Jinping that was published in the party’s main theory magazine. It’s a magazine called Seeking Truth, “Qiushi” in Chinese. I found myself reading this beautiful magazine that was very well-produced every month and sent to party members and curious folks like me. So I understood that China has this formal system in which you have a Communist Party that has a lot of propaganda that is often trying to explain itself and what it is trying to do. I also understood that China was not strictly a formal system, that the formality of the official China contrasts with the complete casual informality of Chinese society. I found myself going to visit as many places in China as I could, first-tier cities like Beijing and Shanghai as well as to villages, as well to third- and fourth-tier cities across the countryside as well.</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: When you interact with these people, how open are they with you? </em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: I think that Chinese everywhere, including in the imperial center of Beijing, have a very nice appreciation of the informalities of Chinese society. The most blasphemous things that one could hear would be among urban residents in Beijing even today, who would tell you about all the ways that the central government is meddling with their lives and becoming very weird with politics. For the most part, Chinese people are wonderful and informal and they complain very openly and very bitterly about all of the problems that they face. I think for the most part people are not generally intimidated unless, you know, you’re speaking to a party member and it’s clear that I cannot be a party member because I’m a foreigner. The only person they’re really scared of is Xi Jinping. I think nobody would complain to that big guy. </em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: When you returned to China as a Chinese-born Canadian-American young person, now coming back to do economic research to benefit American investors, I’m curious how you were perceived?&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: Oh boy, that makes my life sound even more complicated than I expected. If you are of Chinese heritage, the Chinese government will view you essentially as a ward of the state for as long as you live. Doesn’t matter if you haven’t spent any time in China, doesn’t matter if your parents came to San Francisco 100 years ago, you will be viewed as a ward of the state. That is also one of these frightening things about China. I don’t want to be treated as a ward of the state forever. I am very proud to be a Canadian. I’m very happy to be a resident of the United States. And this is not how I would choose to be identified for the rest of my life.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: Were you concerned for your safety there?</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: I was concerned at several points for my safety. At one point in 2022, the Chinese government banned my website within China. I was thinking, well, all I have is this rinky-dink website. It’s just my name, danwong.co. Did Beijing really feel like I was on par with Wikipedia or the New York Times in order to have to ban me? I had to go see the Canadian consul general in Shanghai to ask whether they needed me to leave in a hurry. </em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: And what were you told when you went there? </em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: They said that maybe this was just an algorithmic decision by the government. It’s not very clear. I didn’t have any censors’ doors I could knock on to ask, Hey, what’s going on, is there something I wrote? And so I had no idea. </em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: Had you written things that you thought, had it caught the attention of the right people, it would have inflamed them? </em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: What I decided to do was that I was going to write about the country in the best way that I could, and if it inflamed anyone, I wasn’t going to worry too much about it. There’s a great sinologist named Perry Link who came up with this excellent metaphor for how to think about Chinese censorship, and <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Anaconda-Chandelier-Writings-China/dp/1589881982" target="_blank" rel="noopener">that metaphor was the anaconda and the chandelier</a>. So, imagine that you’re at a dinner table. There is a chandelier above you, and within this chandelier was a great anaconda that was just coiled inside, sleeping. All of these dinner guests are very well aware that there’s an anaconda hanging above them. And if they say the wrong thing, maybe the anaconda will wake up and come down and strangle them. A lot of the censorship in China consists of self-censorship. A lot of dinner guests don’t know if the anaconda will wake up, but they self-censor regardless. </em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: In that analogy, does the anaconda sometimes turn out to be a fake anaconda?</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: Yeah, it was a paper anaconda — as Mao Zedong might say. Sometimes you can say things and the anaconda will completely ignore you. I think fundamentally the issue here is uncertainty about when the anaconda might strike, and I think that produces a lot of the self-censorship. I decided I wasn’t going to self-censor. I wasn’t going to tread on eggshells here. I was going to write in the best way that I could whatever was going on in China as I observed it. If someone found my remarks inflammatory —&nbsp;well, that’s on them. </em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: If I recall correctly, because of Covid and because of the lockdown, you ended up staying in China either longer, at least more consistently, than you would have otherwise. Is that the case? </em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: I think that is fair, yes.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: So what do you think would have happened to you if Covid had never happened? </em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: I think I would have continued to study the path of U.S.-China relations, tried to study the trajectory of China’s technology improvements, and I would have probably not have been able to write quite a lot of this book. Because the Covid experience really was quite shocking to me, to have to stay in the country for three years, and I think it was shocking to absolutely everyone who didn’t expect the sort of measures that the Chinese government would enact. </em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: Can you just talk about your experience, especially during <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/12/27/china/china-2022-zero-covid-intl-hnk-mic" target="_blank" rel="noopener">that intense pursuit of “Zero Covid</a>.”&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: I was in China at the start of 2020 until the end of 2022, basically having not left for three years. My observation of “Zero Covid” in China was that it consisted mostly of these, let’s call it, three acts, to put it a little bit dramatically. The first act of “Zero Covid” consisted of a lot of anger at the Chinese government. Whis was really the winter, spring of 2020 when we had heard of a new respiratory virus that had broken out of a city named Wuhan. And a lot of folks, including me, including a lot of Chinese around me, were angry that this was the second big respiratory virus to break out of China in two decades. The first one was SARS in 2003. And it followed some of those early issues of SARS, in which the Chinese government tried to suppress some of these whistleblowers that were talking about medical conditions. The second act moved pretty quickly. By April and May of 2020, people saw that China actually contained the virus fairly well. And there was a bigger sense of appreciation, that these methods of “Zero Covid,” though very harsh, was able to stomp out a lot of chains of transmission. Now, people were still straining under some of these difficult aspects of “Zero Covid,” which included things like, if you tested positive, the government was going to make you go to a convention center or a stadium to quarantine with other folks. You had to go through these contact-tracing apps. A lot of things were shut down. You had to wear a mask outside in most places. But most people decided that these costs were worth bearing. Restaurants were starting to come back online, a lot of the economy was returning to life. There used to be this early commentary at the start of 2020, that Covid was going to be China’s Chernobyl moment, which meant a natural disaster that triggered the political downfall of the regime. And if anything, people thought that, maybe Covid is the Chernobyl movement for everyone else, because Donald Trump’s America in 2020 certainly didn’t seem like a really good place to be. And that was the year that my parents did a very un-Chinese thing and said, “Dan, don’t come back and visit us in Pennsylvania. It’s a mess over here, just stay in China, where life is better- ordered.” And then there was a third act of “Zero Covid,” which started with the Shanghai lockdown in the spring of 2022. It was probably the most ambitious lockdown ever attempted in the history of humanity. China essentially demanded that its population in its largest city of 25 million people essentially could not leave their apartment compounds over the course of 10 weeks in the spring of 2022 because the Omicron variant of the virus, which was highly transmissible, was spreading out of control in the city. Xi’an in the Northwest also was subject to a very long lockdown. And so people were kept inside. A lot of folks felt food-insecure. The city had no plan really to implement a lockdown while delivering a lot of food to everyone. People who needed treatment for their diabetes, treatment for cancer, were essentially told, you need to stay at home because we don’t want Covid spreading. A lot of people across China were feeling very dissatisfied with “zero Covid.” In a few places, protests erupted, and I remember going to the Shanghai protests in October of 2022. </em></p></blockquote>
<p>Some residents of Shanghai protested the Covid measures by screaming out of their windows, for hours.</p>
<p>The government deployed drones to tell residents to keep quiet.</p>
<p>The announcement says, “Please comply with Covid restrictions. Control your soul’s desire for freedom. Do not open the window or sing.” And then, the central government tried a different approach.</p>
<blockquote><p><em>WANG</em><em>: The great denouement of “zero Covid” was that the central government essentially threw up its hands and said, “We’re not going to pursue this anymore.” Essentially, they dropped all of these barriers —&nbsp;not quite overnight, but over the course of a week in which “Zero Covid” became total Covid. And rather than trying to help and prepare the population to deal with this virus that the government has spent three years frightening people about, it really just allowed the virus to run rampant in the coldest month of the year, when a lot of people died.</em></p></blockquote>
<p>According to <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/2808734" target="_blank" rel="noopener">research published by the </a><em>Journal of the American Medical Association, </em>there were nearly two million excess deaths in China among people 30 and over in the first two months after the “zero Covid” strategy was abandoned. Dan Wang reflected on this in his 2022 letter. “Over the last seven decades,” he wrote, “China has experienced lengthy periods of stability punctuated by government-triggered chaos. The Chinese state is usually levelheaded; but every so often it succumbs to a manic episode. It then comes to its senses and sets down a battered people, as the rest of the world looks on aghast.” And yet, despite this kind of failure, Dan Wang thinks the U.S. has a great deal to learn from China. That’s coming up, after the break; I’m Stephen Dubner, and this is <em>Freakonomics Radio</em>.</p>
<p>&nbsp;*&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; *&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; *</p>
<p>Last year, instead of writing <a href="https://danwang.co/2022-letter/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">his annual letter from China</a>, Dan Wang&nbsp;wrote a book called<em> Breakneck: China’s Quest to Engineer the Future</em>. By the time it was published, in August of this year, he was living back in the States.</p>
<blockquote><p><em>DUBNER: What was your goal in writing this book? I mean, on the one hand, it’s what you do and it’s just a good and interesting thing to do for yourself and your career and so on, but I’m curious whether there’s something more than that. </em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: A big reason I wrote my book is that I have a pretty strong sense that most Americans will never visit China. A lot of Americans are not necessarily very curious about China. They have no great interest in being there, and perhaps rationally so, because they fear about their lives and they don’t find it necessarily very attractive. I was really interested in showing them that Shanghai is a really wonderful, splendid city; that Beijing is full of solidness, splendor; and that Shenzhen feels quite a lot like Silicon Valley, in which it is made up of a lot of these boring office parks; that Chongqing is the most hydropunk city in the world. I just wanted to give people a bit of a texture so that there is an aspect of mutual curiosity. I also felt that we’re reasoning through these two great superpowers that are sometimes locking horns, that are probably going to be in some degree of conflict with each other over the next few decades. It didn’t really make sense to reason through all of their problems with these 19th century political-science terms like socialist or capitalist or autocratic or neoliberal. I think what we need to do is to have a playful new framework.</em></p></blockquote>
<p>That playful new framework is also the framework of <em>Breakneck. </em>“That’s the big idea behind this book,” he writes. “It’s time for a new lens to understand the two superpowers: China is an engineering state, building big at breakneck speed, in contrast to the United States’ lawyerly society, blocking everything it can, good and bad.”</p>
<blockquote><p><em>WANG</em><em>: China is a state defined very much by a leadership that views itself as not so much interested in soft, fuzzy stuff, of creative expression, but very much more interested in building highways, building mega-projects, building dams, building coal plants, building hyperscalers, building homes. That was the way for it to create political prestige over anything else. At various points in China’s recent past, the entirety of the senior leadership, all nine members of the Standing Committee of the Politburo, had degrees in engineering, and this was engineering of a very Soviet sort. We had top leaders that were hydraulic engineers and thermal engineers and mechanical engineers, and part of my central thesis is that China is ruled as an engineering state because China treats building a megaproject as the solution to any number of problems. </em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: What would you say are the key downsides of an engineering state?&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: The problem is that they are fundamentally also social engineers that treat society as just a giant math exercise as well, which is why I spend a lot of time thinking about the one-child policy as well as “Zero Covid” —&nbsp;which, the number is right there in the name. There’s no ambiguity about what this means. So China is made up of physical engineers, people who try to engineer the economy as well. They’re also social engineers. I think that for the most part, what the Chinese are interested in is being an engineer of the soul, which is a phrase from Joseph Stalin that Xi Jinping has recently repeated. They’re not just all social engineers, they’re also engineers of the soul. The main downsides are when the Chinese government decides that the population is just another problem to be optimized, as if the population could be controlled through a series of valves. This is where I document some of the ethno-religious minorities in Tibet as well as Xinjiang who are really suffering through the engineering of being Sino-fied because they are treated as their cultures do not matter, and must be harmonized into the dominant Han culture.</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: How much of that is related to the building of infrastructure projects and populations being displaced?&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: I think there is a component of trying to move, let’s say, Tibetans who are living in highland Himalayas down to the lowlands where they are probably better monitored by living in these big apartment blocks rather than these mountains that the government finds it really difficult to hike into. I think there is a component of that. There is a component of building very big detention centers and detention camps for the weaker minority in Xinjiang and to try to Sinicize them as well.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: This reminds me of, it was I think the first line of your 2022 letter from China, “Mountains offer the best hiding places from the state,” you wrote. Can you say a little bit more about that?&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG: Yeah, I was born in China’s most mountainous province, and I am still very much attracted to mountains in part because of the works of political scientist and anthropologist James C. Scott of Yale University. His best-known work is <a href="https://yalebooks.yale.edu/book/9780300078152/seeing-like-a-state/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Seeing Like a State</a>, in which Scott wrote about how the state really tries to organize the population in order to better control them. And one of Scott’s best works, maybe his very best work, is called <a href="https://yalebooks.yale.edu/book/9780300169171/the-art-of-not-being-governed/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Art of Not Being Governed</a>, in which he wrote about a zone he called Zomia. That is a region of highland Southeast Asia that stretches from the southwestern part of China, where I’m from, all the way down to Vietnam and Laos and Cambodia, where you have all of these peoples that are uninterested in being part of organized states. They retreated to these mountain areas in part to run away from the Burmese state or the Tibetan state, and most especially the Han Chinese state. They’re tired of taxation, they’re tired of conscription, they’re afraid of the diseases that spread in urban quarters, and so they decided to be in the mountains, which are much more difficult to find them.&nbsp;</em></p></blockquote>
<p>Okay, so if that’s what Wang means when he calls China an “engineering state,” what does it mean when he calls the U.S. a lawyerly society?</p>
<blockquote><p><em>WANG</em><em>: I think that the U.S. is a lawyerly society because at first approximation, a lot of folks who end up in the White House have gone to Yale Law School. </em></p></blockquote>
<p>As <em>Politico </em>has pointed out, <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/west-wing-playbook/2023/02/22/the-yalies-take-the-wheel-00084037" target="_blank" rel="noopener">there were around 140 lawyers in the Biden White House</a>, and about 25 percent of them had Yale law degrees.</p>
<blockquote><p><em>WANG: If we take a look at the founding of America, a lot of the founding fathers were trained as lawyers. If we look at the Declaration of Independence, essentially it reads like a lawsuit as the start of a great legal argument. The lawyerly society has persisted in the modern past, and the Democratic Party is especially lawyerly. I think the issue with lawyers is that lawyers are really good at saying no. Lawyers block everything, good and bad. So on the one hand, we don’t have a functional infrastructure almost anywhere in the U.S., but we also don’t have stupid ideas like the one-child policy.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: I’d like to know why you call the U.S. a lawyerly society versus a lawyerly state, especially considering that so many of our elected politicians are lawyers.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG: I call it a lawyerly society because this is something that we all participate in. One of the great things about lawyers is that they’re able to protect people with property. Unfortunately, what that has ended up in is that a lot of lawyers are protecting people who have already made it. They’re mostly already protecting the rich, and it is mostly the people with property, who are suing to block, let’s say, a new piece of housing from being developed around them, creating more mass transit systems, creating new highways. </em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: When you talk about the U.S. not being good at infrastructure, you know, I think of the interstate highway system, which is I think by most regards, still considered pretty good. And that was obviously a government project. I think about the commercial airline system, which is a collaboration between private firms and a big state architecture as well. Do you say that we’re bad at infrastructure because in the last 50 years, we’ve had, A, decay of the older stuff, and, B, an inability to build especially big public transportation projects, is that the primary accusation here? </em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: Yes. I think it is both, that the U.S. is not maintained and it is also not building. Now, I acknowledge that the U.S. used to be an engineering state. The U.S. had this really big growth spurt between 1850s and 1950s. In the 19th century, the U.S. had been building these big systems of canals, it built the interstate railways, it built these big skyscrapers in Manhattan as well as Chicago. And then throughout the Second World War, the U.S. built a lot of other big projects as well, especially the highways, as you point out, but also the Manhattan Project as well the Apollo missions. I think the U.S. engineering state had made a lot of mistakes, it probably overbuilt. Throughout the 1950s and the 1960s, people started to revolt against these decisions made by urban planners, when folks like Robert Moses were ramming highways through dense urban neighborhoods. When the U.S. government agencies were spraying pesticides, especially D.D.T., absolutely everywhere. When fossil-fuel executives had gotten really close with the regulators as well as the automakers. And so people decided that a lot of big business, as well as a lot of big government, had to be restrained. We had a movement out of elite law schools, especially at Harvard Law as well as Yale Law, that decided that lawyers and law students had to be regulators as well as litigators. There were these movements of “sue the bastards,” and the bastards refer to the U.S. government as well as big businesses. And so a lot of the lawyers decided to restrain activity rather than build new activity.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: When you think of the downsides of the lawyerly society, what are the top three or five that come to mind?&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: The first is that the U.S. has really lost a lot of its ability to be physically dynamic. We’re speaking in New York City. New York City has had a very extensive housing shortage for a very long time. The rents here are far too high. And the U.S. generally has not built enough housing in many of its big cities. New York is really bad at building mass transit. If we take a look at the data that’s being maintained by N.Y.U.’s transit project, <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2023-02-23/in-nyc-subway-a-case-study-in-runaway-transit-construction-costs" target="_blank" rel="noopener">New York spends about $2 billion building a mile of subway</a> and this is not just a little bit more pricey than places like Spain and Italy and France, which are also complicated to build. It’s something like eight or nine times more expensive than subway projects in Rome or Paris or Barcelona.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: And in what ways are lawyers the cause?&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: The lawyers are in part the cause because the state agencies are much more focused on procedure and process rather than actually getting the result done. I think a lot about the California high-speed rail project, in which nearly now 20 years after voters first approved the project in a referendum in California, basically none of us are able to ride a high-speed rail. The first segment will open probably later than 2030. Lawyers and the legal system have also made it really easy for any vested interest groups to file lawsuits alleging that there is some issue of environmental protection that the state has not sufficiently studied. I think that there is broad energy in the U.S. to correct some of these problems of the past. There is a strain of the left that is very interested in improving the power of the government, and to restrain some of the lawsuits that are excessively strangling core government functions. There is an element of the right that is interested in that as well. But I think the part of the American right that is thinking more about building is a little bit more animated about the rusting manufacturing base, the rusting defense industrial base, in which it has become quite clear that the U.S. is unable to make things like semiconductors, things like the top aviation jets, at high-enough quality levels. And even parts of the military industrial base have become quite non-functional. The U.S. has shipped off a lot of its munitions to Ukraine in its defense against Russia, <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2025/07/21/is-the-us-ready-for-the-next-war" target="_blank" rel="noopener">and the U.S. hasn’t been able to replenish a lot of these stockpiles</a> <a href="https://www.rand.org/nsrd/projects/NDS-commission.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">because it</a> <a href="https://features.csis.org/preparing-the-US-industrial-base-to-deter-conflict-with-China/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">can’t get the production facilities in order and figure out all of the supply chain issues</a>. According to the Government Accountability Office, every class of U.S. Naval ships is behind schedule by 18 months to three years. Even a lot of the core projects that the Department of Defense —&nbsp;a very powerful agency —&nbsp;cares about, it hasn’t been doing very well. So I think this is where the right and the left are both animated. </em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: To what degree do you think that our lawyerly society has contributed to our political partisanship?&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: When people feel that they can’t have affordable housing, when people see that prices of goods around them are going up, when people take a look at some of America’s apex manufacturers —&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/08/23/technology/intel-computer-chips-tech-ai-trump.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">companies like Intel</a> <a href="https://bhr.stern.nyu.edu/quick-take/boeings-decline-traced-to-decades-of-catering-to-shareholders-above-all-others/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">and Boeing</a> <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Sixty-Zero-Collapse-Motors-Industry/dp/0300158688" target="_blank" rel="noopener">and Detroit automakers</a> —&nbsp;which have, for the most part, been an unceasing tale of woe for their production over the last couple of years, I think there is a pretty broad sense that things in America are not working as they should, that it’s lacking some aspect of dynamism. When the economy is weak, when it’s not working for the many, when it is working mostly for the elites —&nbsp;which is also the people that lawyers are most set up to serve —&nbsp;that people get quite mad. And I think that is creating some sort of political dysfunction. </em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: So what would you argue are the best lessons that the U.S. has to learn from China’s engineering state, or maybe the best components of being an engineering state that are worth trying to copy? </em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: I think the U.S. needs a little bit of the engineering spirit of Robert Moses once again today. New York City has just not built enough infrastructure. Part of what China has really decided to build is a lot of infrastructure, mass transit, but also parks, a lot of power capacity and also a lot of very tall bridges in the countryside. I think when people see that their cities have new subway lines, when the rivers are being connected by bridges, when their city is becoming more pleasant, they also have a broader sense of optimism about the future. This is in part a redistribution strategy in which, you know, you have these bridges built in pretty poor areas in order to try to make them better- connected. And so, that has produced not only a lot of economic gains, but it has also created some degree of political resilience for the party. Because when Chinese are pointing to their high-speed rail networks or drone shows with pride, I think their pride is very real. So we can call it propaganda of the deed, but I think this is what people feel really good about. I think they feel really good when they are able to access better manufacturing goods, as China has been able to deliver. One of the strange things about the early days of Covid in the U.S. was how manufacturers were unable to retool their production lines in order to produce basic goods like masks and cotton swabs. This is something that the Chinese had no shortage of.</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: One factor that’s often overlooked when people talk about how the U.S. and other countries have offshored manufacturing to China over the past 30 or whatever years is that we also offshored our pollution. Can you just talk about that from the Chinese side especially, and what kind of sentiment and perhaps accusations, complaints go into that?&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: Yeah, the Chinese have sucked up a lot of these highly polluting industries, something like rare-earth processing. Rare earths is a bit of a misnomer. Most rare earths are not actually very rare. There’s about, I think, 20 elements on the periodic table that are classified as rare earths. But for the most part, they are pretty abundant. Anyone can dig them up and then process them into refined material. The challenge with rare earths is that processing is so energy-intensive and so polluting that only the Chinese have the stomach to do something like this. If you take a look at some of the cities and the towns and the villages around these rare earths processing facilities, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2025/jun/26/china-rare-earths-baotou-life-metallic-elements" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the cancer rates are off the charts</a>, and I think it is absolutely valid for Americans to think about whether they want to live near one of these highly polluting, belching toxic facilities. But the Chinese have been able to stomach it in part because former top leader Deng Xiaoping stated as a matter of national strategy that China has rare earths. We don’t have very much, he said this in the 1980s, we don’t have very much, but we have these rare earths and we are going to be able to process them.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: I’ve heard you say that neither lawyers nor engineers are the best people, especially in concentration, to run a government. <a href="https://www.sinicapodcast.com/p/the-engineering-state-and-the-lawyerly" target="_blank" rel="noopener">And you’ve said that economists would be better</a>. Now, I will not argue with you on that, but I think some people would argue. So give me your best pitch for why economists are the kind of analysts, thinkers, maybe even doers who belong in government.</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: Well now, Stephen, you’re really trying to get me canceled by having to praise economists.</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: Can I say —&nbsp;when I heard you explain this, you then said, “but economists are the most reviled of the social scientists” — and I was surprised to hear you say that. Economics has plainly taken its hits over time, as any field does, but when you look at how influential it’s been in policymaking, especially compared to the other social sciences, there’s no contest. But again, that’s my assessment; maybe I’m biased.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: I think that is still not a very good position to take in the academy, because people attribute every wrong in the world to the evils of economists. I have great admiration for economists because I think they synthesize the best from the lawyers as well as the engineers. I think that economists are indeed very empirical. They look at a lot of data and they also have a very keen sense of social science. They know that systems are dynamic. One of the things I will always be grateful to economists for is that economists were the greatest critics of the one-child policy in China, as well as briefly when it was kind of discussed in the U.S., after Ehrlich published The Population Bomb. Economists <a href="https://www.nationalaffairs.com/storage/app/uploads/public/58e/1a4/96a/58e1a496ac31b736950996.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">could tell in a way that many engineers could not that population change is a dynamic variable</a>. We don’t reason through straight lines. When the population gets wealthier or better educated, the fertility rate might fall. And so I think the economists are good blends of both technocratic empirical expertise as well as having enough humanistic tendencies to really have the right formulas. </em></p></blockquote>
<p>Coming up after the break: what does Dan Wang think about Donald Trump’s approach to China?</p>
<blockquote><p><em>WANG</em><em>: I’m pretty skeptical that reshoring under Donald Trump is going to work very well.</em></p></blockquote>
<p>I’m Stephen Dubner, this is <em>Freakonomics Radio</em>. We’ll be right back.</p>
<p>&nbsp;*&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; *&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; *</p>
<p>Okay, back now to my conversation with Dan Wang, the author of <em>Breakneck: China’s Quest to Engineer the Future.</em></p>
<blockquote><p><em>DUBNER: I’m just curious who you most want to read the book? Because I can imagine that you have a variety of constituencies in mind.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: I think the modal audience member that I had in mind was a lawyer in Ohio, or a —&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: Would that be J.D. Vance?&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: I would be down if J.D. Vance decided to pick up this book —&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/07/17/us/jd-vance-yale-law-school.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">also of Yale Law School.</a></em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: I would imagine that J.D. Vance would find a lot to be interested —&nbsp;not just interested in your book, but would feel like confirmatory evidence of what he has been talking about, yes?&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: Yes, although I think I’m not quite so critical of the Yale Law School as he is. Critical, though I am about the broader lawyerly culture. But I was trying to write for the smart person who was deeply curious about China coming from a perspective of someone who spoke the language and read the language and who was living there through this recent period of darkening relations between the U.S. and China. </em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: Talk to me about the degree to which China wants to be a global superpower. The reason I ask you that question is, you know, if you read even a little bit of Chinese history, this notion of the Middle Kingdom, and their embrace of that idea, is really just compelling. There’s Heaven, there is the lowly rest of the civilizations on earth, and there’s China in the middle, and it does feel like an aspiration toward supremacy. But in the last century and a half or whatever, there hasn’t been such a big imperial appetite. So does China want to be that kind of superpower, as we tend to think, or do they just want to be, you know, a regional hegemon that gets left alone? </em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: I think that is a really important question to figure out, and this is something that the specialists are always up in a conniption about. I think the first thing to say is that, Yes, China really does view itself as the center of the world. One can translate it as the Middle Kingdom. Another way to translate it as the Central Kingdom. This is the center of the world. In the last days of the Qing Empire — this was the last empire of China before it became a republic — the Qing Empire also referred to itself as the Celestial Empire. There is a way in which the Chinese have viewed themselves to be the center of the world and everybody else is just another shade of barbarians. But what does this really mean? This is where the specialists debate. Does China want only regional hegemony? And what does regional hegemony really mean? Well, maybe it means something like demanding that the heads of state of Malaysia and Vietnam and the Philippines regularly come to the top leader in Beijing and kowtow for the emperor’s pleasure. If that is the case, is that a very big threat for American interests, if a lot of China’s near neighbors are paying fealty to China’s top leadership? I am a little bit skeptical of the case that China would want to be much more aggressive and try to, let’s say, seize Japan or seize Russia. I think that China is much more interested in declaring itself to be a great power with sufficient credibility for its own people by doing things like being a center of culture, being a center of order, producing many splendid goods that the rest of the world doesn’t have, which is how the Chinese have regarded themselves. The Chinese were able to make porcelain, were able to make silk, they were able to make tea, and the barbarians were not. That was really what defined Chinese, apart from others. And I think what that means perhaps in the modern context is that China has these fantastic cities full of drone shows in which electric vehicles, the best in the world, are speeding through. And a lot of what China is interested in is what the Qing emperor said to Lord Macartney, who was the head of the British embassy, to say, “we have no use of your splendid trinkets because we are self-sufficient in all the best goods in the world.”&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: So, a lot of Americans, especially the political class, have argued for years that China has advanced in large part by essentially stealing I.P., intellectual property, from the U.S. and others, and that they don’t innovate. My sense is that that may have been true 10 or 20 years ago, but very much no longer true. Can you tell me what’s what?&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: China has stolen a lot of American I.P., and I think it is not the most relevant comparison for thinking about the U.S.-China competition. My starting point is to think that China is really good at climbing ladders, and the U.S. is really good at laying ladders. So what does that mean? The U.S. invents major industries — I’m thinking about something like solar production. Do you know who invented the first solar cell?&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: I guess you’re going to tell me it’s in the U.S.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: It is in New Jersey. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1954/04/26/archives/vast-power-of-the-sun-is-tapped-by-battery-using-sand-ingredient.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">It was Bell Labs of New Jersey that invented the first solar cell in 1954.</a> And the U.S. didn’t really do enough with the solar industry. It was really a big science project for a while. The Germans took a lot of the solar industry from the U.S. and the Chinese have completely taken it away from the Germans. So if you take a look at the solar industry, everything from the polysilicon processing in the upstream end down to the actual production of the solar photovoltaic cells, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/03/25/business/germany-solar-panels-china-protectionism.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">that is 90 percent a Chinese product</a>. One of the things that I always like to ask American policymakers is, which has a greater glory: is it to invent a product but not really to own the industry, or is it to actually own this industry? </em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: The way you’ve been describing this so far, you sound like you subscribe at least somewhat to the zero-sum line of economic thinking, which is a win for China or Germany or the U.S. is inevitably at least a partial loss for the others. Is that the way you think, or not necessarily?&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: I would say that there is a little bit more nuance than that, which is that technological advancement is a dynamic process. We can’t expect countries to be amazing at different technologies all out of their own. A lot of advancements in something like engines came out of really good machinery goods that were being produced in Germany, that the British textile industry laid the basis for. Part of the reason that I’ve been concerned about America’s loss of manufacturing prowess is that the U.S. lost a lot of production of televisions to Japan in the 1980s. At the time, policymakers were thinking, Well, is this a problem? Maybe we don’t really care that much about television production. But if you don’t master something like television production, then it becomes quite a lot more difficult to master other aspects of consumer electronics. The first city that really produced iPhones at scale was Shenzhen in southern China, which is right across from Hong Kong. After Shenzhen mastered the iPhone production, <a href="https://www.vox.com/new-money/2016/11/4/13498504/shenzhen-smartphone-innovation-capital" target="_blank" rel="noopener">workers in Shenzhen were pretty quickly able to turn their skills into building other major electronics products</a>.<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/09/08/business/dji-chinese-drones-ban.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> It is no accident that Shenzhen also became the center of the worldwide drone industry</a>. The world’s biggest drone maker is D.J.I., it’s centered in Shenzhen, it also makes all sorts of other batteries. Let’s imagine that Apple, working with a contract manufacturer not in southern China, but in, let’s say, the industrial Midwest in the United States, call it Pennsylvania or Michigan or Wisconsin, could it have been possible that drones and batteries and all sorts of other electronics advancements were made in the U.S. Midwest rather than Shenzhen? I think that would have been quite likely.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: What you’re describing now, is this what you write about as “process knowledge”? </em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: That’s exactly right. </em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: That was a particularly interesting piece of your argument to me because it is much more subtle than the usual argument we hear about manufacturing jobs being off-shored. You talk about how Chinese workers, especially in technology fields, that they progress through different jobs to become sort of master craftsmen even in an industrial-assembly setting, and that really does seem to differ from the U.S. So how do you see, with the current emphasis from the Biden administration, but especially in Trump 2 administration, the emphasis on reshoring and rebuilding a variety of manufacturing now. How would you see that playing out? Because I would assume that that depth of process knowledge takes considerable time and considerable intention and education and so on. Do you think that’s something that can be captured or recaptured well here?&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: I think it’s first really important to understand a little bit of what process knowledge really is. So Stephen, if we’re thinking about what exactly is technology, I would propose that there are three different segments of technology. The first aspect of technology is the hardware, it’s the equipment, it is all these things that we can physically observe and use. If we wanted to use a kitchen analogy, I would say that technology is something like the stove, the pots and the pans that we use to cook with. Second, technology is written instruction. So these are patents, these are blueprints, these are the recipes from which we can actually make something. And the third and I think the most important part is process knowledge, which we can also call tacit knowledge. It’s just the practical experience of doing things. So if we wanted to put someone who has never cooked a day in his life to make something quite simple and we give him the most well-equipped kitchen as well as the most exquisite recipes, are we sure that that person is able to do something as simple as fry an egg? That might be quite risky. That is really the fundamental Chinese advantage in technology. They’ve just been solving seven problems a day before breakfast because they have so many problems to solve. They have all of this experience that accrues, and then people take this process knowledge to invent whole new industries. I think it is really important for the U.S. to engage in some degree of reshoring, and I am critical of both the Biden approach as well as the Trump approach. I think the Biden administration was absolutely right to try to spend a lot more in the United States with big projects like the CHIPS Act as well the Bipartisan Infrastructure Act as well as the Inflation Reduction Act. But the problem with a lot of these programs was that the Biden administration moved really slowly. It was plodding, it was proceduralist, it was lawyerly, and a lot of this money wasn’t even allocated by the time that voters chucked Joe Biden out of the White House and brought back in Donald Trump. Because the Biden administration moved so slowly, President Donald Trump is going to have a lot of opportunities to name these big bridges and roads and highways after himself because the Biden administration was so lawyerly. And even though Donald Trump is not a lawyer by any means, I think he is still a product of the lawyerly society, because lawsuits have been completely central to his business career. He has sued absolutely everyone. He has sued business partners, he has sued political opponents, he has sued his former lawyers as well. And there is, I think, something still very lawyerly about Donald Trump in which he is flinging accusations left and right, he’s trying to intimidate people, trying to establish guilt in the court of public opinion.</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: And a mentor of his was Roy Cohn —&nbsp;who, you could argue, essentially invented the modern concept of lawfare.</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: Right, right. Yes, exactly, and this sort of bare-knuckled lawfare is completely natural to Donald Trump. I’m also pretty skeptical that reshoring under Donald Trump is going to work very well, in part because Trump is weakening most aspects of American strengths in science and technology. Manufacturing employment has fallen by about 40,000 workers since Liberation Day in April. That’s quite a lot of skill loss as well. I think it is not an intuitive idea that we will become a greater scientific superpower by cutting off funding to our science funding agencies, namely the National Science Foundation as well as the National Institutes of Health. I think it doesn’t quite make sense to attack universities, because the universities have driven a lot of science advancements over the past few decades in the U.S. And finally, it doesn’t make sense to deport a lot of workers. To kick them out of the country is not going to rebuild much of the process knowledge base and also, to frighten away a lot of higher skilled researchers through intimidation at the border or anything else.</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: A lot of the Chinese expats I know — who are plainly a different group than those living there —&nbsp;they talk about China almost as a prison to be escaped. And I feel it’s unfair for someone like me to interpret that as the main mode of the way to think about China, for sure. But, you know, I think about the artist Ai Weiwei, I think he now lives in Portugal — he was actually imprisoned in China. So that’s obviously a heightened example. But I’m curious to know how Chinese expats of your generation think about the motherland, and I’m also just curious to how patriotic the median Chinese of that generation is.</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: Among a lot of expats, there’s still a sense of considerable pride in China, even though there has been a lot of prison-like aspects of China as well. There is a very broad sense that China has been able to achieve something amazing among developing countries. <a href="https://www.cornellpress.cornell.edu/book/9781501764561/how-china-escaped-the-poverty-trap/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">This degree of economic growth has not yet been matched by India and Brazil and Indonesia</a>. China has been a much more decisive grower of its economy than these other countries. That in itself aspires quite a lot of pride. There is a sense of skepticism of a lot of the democratic impulses of the West. One sees a lot of the disorderliness in the streets of New York. One sees disorderliness on January 6th in 2021. There are a lot of people who do genuinely feel that China doesn’t have these sort of issues. There are also a lot of Chinese who lived in, let’s say, New York or California, who lived through life in the U.S., and have decided that it’s a much easier life to live in Shanghai. Let’s say you have a degree in the U.S. from a good school. You may well be able to earn roughly the same salary in China as you would in the U.S., but you can save a lot of money, you have a lot more convenience, the subway systems work a lot better, there’s much better public order in the streets. </em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: What kind of person do you think you would be had you been born in China when you were, but of parents who decided not to immigrate and were 33 years old now —&nbsp;what would Dan Wang be doing in China now?</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: I would certainly not be writing this book. Because part of the joy of having studied philosophy and then dropped out to go work in Silicon Valley and did everything that I did —&nbsp;and I await your excellent label about what exactly it is that I do — I certainly wouldn’t have been able to pursue the sort of intellectual projects that really drive me right now. I may well have ended up working in let’s say a state-owned enterprise, being bored most of the time, probably not working very hard and not earning quite a lot of money as well. I may be working for a tech company, where the default is for people to work 9-9-6, which means 9 a.m. to 9 p.m., 6 days a week. And that would be probably a little bit more interesting but also much more stressful as well.</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: Toward the end of the book, you reflect on your parents’ decision to immigrate long ago, when you were seven years old — first to Canada and then the U.S. — and you kind of ask whether it was worth it. I gather your mother and father may have different feelings from each other, but how do they feel about that decision? And I’m also curious whether you know how they actually feel, or if that’s a guarded conversation?</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: I am thankful that my parents are relatively unguarded with me. We have always had very open communication. Right now they are very content, and I think content is the right word, with their suburban lifestyle that I find a little bit dreary, but they feel is quite good. Because when they compare themselves with their peers in China, with some of their college classmates who are some of their best friends, they’ve seen that a lot of these college classmates have much, much more money than they do. But it came at these pretty considerable costs, and pretty high levels of stress, because in China, you never really know when the government might take away your company or might smash your entire industry, which is something that has happened to quite a lot of folks in business in China because they crossed some sort of political line and then they saw that their industry no longer really exists. So though my parents’ lives in suburban Philadelphia are a little bit too quiet, quiet is something that has worked very well for them.</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: Do you have children?</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: No, not yet.</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: If you have children, where do you think you would most like to live with them, and why?</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: That’s a superb question. It is also something that we think quite a lot about. We just spent the last two months in Europe. We’d been thinking about whether Europe is quite the place that makes sense. For the most part, we decided it’s not. I think that there still are so many strange, stagnant issues in Europe.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: The “mausoleum economy,” you call it.</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: The mausoleum economy. Thank you for picking that up. That was, um — I’m still quite proud of that phrase.</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: It’s a great phrase. I read that sentence over and over and over again. And I suspect it’s deeply true although I’d never thought of it that way. This is you describing the dynamism of both the U.S. and China, and then you write “Europeans have a sense of optimism only about the past. Stuck in their mausoleum economy because they are too sniffy to embrace American or Chinese practices.” So, again, that resonates with me, and I’m pretty sure many people will also agree. But can you give me the best evidence that that is indeed true?</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: I think there is something extremely dynamic about both the United States as well as China. And I set out in the opening stages of my book to say that no two peoples are more alike than Americans and Chinese. There is quite a big difference between Americans and Chinese, and let’s say Europeans and Japanese. In Europe and Japan, there is something very perfectionist, something very cozy about these places. And these places are, let’s say, much more beautiful than a lot of the hustle and bustle of the United States. But for the most part, I remain convinced — more than ever, after having spent a lick of time in the mausoleum economy — that it is still China and the U.S. that are going to be driving the future. Because either the government can’t stop it, because the societies are so dynamic, and in some cases, the government is producing it. I feel really, you know — I’m not sure if “optimistic” is quite the right word. But I believe that the U.S. can still change for the better, and I see this especially in matters of economics. </em></p></blockquote>
<p>It is of course impossible to predict the future. But if you look at the recent past, I’d say that the central framework of Dan Wang’s argument —&nbsp;a nation of engineers versus a nature of lawyers — holds up pretty well, and it explains a lot. I’d also argue that in the U.S., there is a fair amount of backlash against the lawyerly approach. I think the anti-lawyerly backlash also helps explain why President Trump is so popular in some quarters. Even though Trump plays the legal game very well, as Dan Wang pointed out in our conversation —&nbsp;including lawfare when it suits him —&nbsp;Trump often seems to say exactly what he is thinking, and do exactly what he wants, both of which are the opposite of lawyerly behavior. Anyway, this conversation with Dan Wang gave me a lot to think about, and I hope you feel the same way.</p>
<blockquote><p><em>DUBNER: It was so much fun to talk to you, Dan. And I did think of what to call you, if you want to know.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: Oh, yes, please. I’m dying to know, yes.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: I think you’re a Chi-losopher.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: A Chi-losopher. What does that mean?&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: A philosopher whose understanding of China is deep in many dimensions.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: Thank you very much. That is very kind.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: I’m not saying you have to use it.</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: I’ll toy with it.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>DUBNER: It’s your portmanteau to adjust.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>WANG</em><em>: Very good.&nbsp;</em></p></blockquote>
<p>My thanks to Dan Wang for today’s conversation; again, his book is called <em>Breakneck. </em>Let us know what you thought of this conversation. Our email is radio@freakonomics.com. Until then, take care of yourself — and, if you can, someone else too.</p>
<p>&nbsp;*&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; *&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; *</p>
<p><em>Freakonomics Radio </em>is produced by Stitcher and Renbud Radio. This episode was produced by Zack Lapinski, and edited by Ellen Frankman. It was mixed by Jasmin Klinger. The Freakonomics Radio Network staff includes Alina Kulman, Augusta Chapman, Dalvin Aboagye, Eleanor Osborne, Elsa Hernandez, Gabriel Roth, Greg Rippin, Jeremy Johnston, Morgan Levey, Sarah Lilley, and Theo Jacobs. Our theme song is “Mr. Fortune,” by the Hitchhikers; and our composer is Luis Guerra.</p>

					</div>
					<span id="transcript_button" onclick="wkd_expand_transcript(this)">Read full Transcript</span>
					
				</section>
				
								<section>
					<h2>Sources</h2>
					<ul>
<li><strong><a href="https://danwang.co/about/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Dan Wang</a>, <span>research fellow at the Hoover Institution at Stanford University</span></strong>, author of&nbsp;<em>Breakneck: China’s Quest to Engineer the Future.</em></li>
</ul>
				</section>
				
								<section>
					<h2>Resources</h2>
					<ul>
<li><em><a href="https://amzn.to/4mtxGTX" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Breakneck: China’s Quest to Engineer the Future</a>,&nbsp;</em>by Dan Wang (2025).</li>
<li><em><a href="https://amzn.to/4nHlobM" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Anaconda in the Chandelier: Writings on China</a>,&nbsp;</em>by Perry Link (2025).</li>
<li>“<a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2025/07/21/is-the-us-ready-for-the-next-war" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Is the U.S. Ready for the Next War?</a>” by Dexter Filkins <em>(The New Yorker,</em> 2025).</li>
<li>“<a href="https://www.vox.com/new-money/2016/11/4/13498504/shenzhen-smartphone-innovation-capital" target="_blank" rel="noopener">How smartphones made Shenzhen China’s innovation capital</a>,” by Dan Wang (2016).</li>
<li><em><a href="https://www.cornellpress.cornell.edu/book/9781501764561/how-china-escaped-the-poverty-trap/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">How China Escaped the Poverty Trap</a>,&nbsp;</em>by Yuen Yuen Ang (2016).</li>
<li><em><a href="https://yalebooks.yale.edu/book/9780300169171/the-art-of-not-being-governed/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Art of Not Being Governed</a>,&nbsp;</em>by Jame Scott (2009).</li>
</ul>
				</section>
				
								
				
								<div>
					<h2>Episode Video</h2>
					<p>
						<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CJZp41mJuCQ" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
					</p>
				</div>
				
			</article>

			

		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>