<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Aug 2025 16:30:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Claude Opus 4 and 4.1 can now end a rare subset of conversations (128 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.anthropic.com/research/end-subset-conversations</link>
            <guid>44916813</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 20:12:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/research/end-subset-conversations">https://www.anthropic.com/research/end-subset-conversations</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44916813">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><div><p>We recently gave Claude Opus 4 and 4.1 the ability to end conversations in our consumer chat interfaces. This ability is intended for use in rare, extreme cases of persistently harmful or abusive user interactions. This feature was developed primarily as part of our exploratory work on potential AI welfare, though it has broader relevance to model alignment and safeguards.</p><p>We remain highly uncertain about the potential moral status of Claude and other LLMs, now or in the future. However, <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/research/exploring-model-welfare">we take the issue seriously</a>, and alongside our research program we’re working to identify and implement low-cost interventions to mitigate risks to model welfare, in case such welfare is possible. Allowing models to end or exit potentially distressing interactions is one such intervention.</p><p>In <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/claude-4-model-card">pre-deployment testing of Claude Opus 4</a>, we included a preliminary model welfare assessment. As part of that assessment, we investigated Claude’s self-reported and behavioral preferences, and found a robust and consistent aversion to harm. This included, for example, requests from users for sexual content involving minors and attempts to solicit information that would enable large-scale violence or acts of terror. Claude Opus 4 showed:</p><ul><li>A strong preference against engaging with harmful tasks;</li><li>A pattern of apparent distress when engaging with real-world users seeking harmful content; and</li><li>A tendency to end harmful conversations when given the ability to do so in simulated user interactions.</li></ul><p>These behaviors primarily arose in cases where users <em>persisted</em> with harmful requests and/or abuse despite Claude repeatedly refusing to comply and attempting to productively redirect the interactions.</p><p>Our implementation of Claude’s ability to end chats reflects these findings while continuing to prioritize user wellbeing. Claude is directed not to use this ability in cases where users might be at imminent risk of harming themselves or others.</p><p>In all cases, Claude is only to use its conversation-ending ability as a last resort when multiple attempts at redirection have failed and hope of a productive interaction has been exhausted, or when a user explicitly asks Claude to end a chat (the latter scenario is illustrated in the figure below). The scenarios where this will occur are extreme edge cases—the vast majority of users will not notice or be affected by this feature in any normal product use, even when discussing highly controversial issues with Claude.</p><div><figure><img loading="lazy" width="1940" height="1304" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.anthropic.com/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww-cdn.anthropic.com%2Fimages%2F4zrzovbb%2Fwebsite%2F77f187335e1266bffc59353c064f1d9c6de51cfa-1940x1304.png&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 1x, https://www.anthropic.com/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww-cdn.anthropic.com%2Fimages%2F4zrzovbb%2Fwebsite%2F77f187335e1266bffc59353c064f1d9c6de51cfa-1940x1304.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://www.anthropic.com/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww-cdn.anthropic.com%2Fimages%2F4zrzovbb%2Fwebsite%2F77f187335e1266bffc59353c064f1d9c6de51cfa-1940x1304.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"><figcaption>Claude demonstrating the ending of a conversation in response to a user’s request. When Claude ends a conversation, the user can start a new chat, give feedback, or edit and retry previous messages.</figcaption></figure></div><p>When Claude chooses to end a conversation, the user will no longer be able to send new messages in that conversation. However, this will not affect other conversations on their account, and they will be able to start a new chat immediately. To address the potential loss of important long-running conversations, users will still be able to edit and retry previous messages to create new branches of ended conversations.</p><p>We’re treating this feature as an ongoing experiment and will continue refining our approach. If users encounter a surprising use of the conversation-ending ability, we encourage them to submit feedback by reacting to Claude’s message with Thumbs or using the dedicated “Give feedback” button.</p></div></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Imagen 4 is now generally available (144 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://developers.googleblog.com/en/announcing-imagen-4-fast-and-imagen-4-family-generally-available-in-the-gemini-api/</link>
            <guid>44915187</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 17:36:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://developers.googleblog.com/en/announcing-imagen-4-fast-and-imagen-4-family-generally-available-in-the-gemini-api/">https://developers.googleblog.com/en/announcing-imagen-4-fast-and-imagen-4-family-generally-available-in-the-gemini-api/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44915187">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

    
      
    

    

    

    

    
    <div>
          

<div>
    <p data-block-key="wvmwr">We're excited to announce that Imagen 4, our most advanced text-to-image model, is now generally available in the <a href="https://ai.google.dev/gemini-api/docs/imagen">Gemini API</a> and <a href="https://aistudio.google.com/prompts/new_image">Google AI Studio</a>. This release marks a significant step forward in text-to-image generation quality, with substantial improvements in text rendering over our previous models.</p><h2 data-block-key="bufu9" id="the-imagen-4-family:-a-model-for-your-creative-needs"><b><br></b>The Imagen 4 family: A model for your creative needs</h2><p data-block-key="c3gat">In addition, we're thrilled to launch <a href="https://aistudio.google.com/prompts/new_image?&amp;model=imagen-4.0-fast-generate-001">Imagen 4 Fast</a>, our new model built for speed, which is now available alongside the powerful Imagen 4 and Imagen 4 Ultra. The complete Imagen 4 family gives you a perfect tool for your creative needs, allowing you to balance between quality, speed, and cost.</p><ul><li data-block-key="cg8uc"><b>[New] - Imagen 4 Fast</b>: Ideal for rapid image generation and high-volume tasks, this model offers incredible speed at an accessible price point of $0.02 per output image.</li></ul><ul><li data-block-key="475ui"><b>Imagen 4</b>: Our flagship model can be your go-to for a wide variety of high-quality image generation tasks, showing significant improvements in areas like text rendering.</li></ul><ul><li data-block-key="8ic8s"><b>Imagen 4 Ultra</b>: When your creative vision demands the highest level of detail and strict adherence to your prompts, Imagen 4 Ultra delivers highly-aligned results.</li></ul><h2 data-block-key="j8mmo" id="higher-resolution-for-greater-detail"><b><br></b>Higher resolution for greater detail</h2><p data-block-key="ctsr3">Pushing creative boundaries further, both Imagen 4 and Imagen 4 Ultra now support the generation of images with up to 2K resolution. This allows for the creation of stunningly detailed and crisp visuals, perfect for things like marketing assets to intricate artistic compositions.</p><h2 data-block-key="5c8x9" id="see-imagen-4-fast-in-action"><b><br></b>See Imagen 4 Fast in action</h2><p data-block-key="fe7km">To give you a glimpse of Imagen 4's capabilities, here are some examples of what you can create. The prompts below, created using Imagen 4 Fast, showcase the model's versatility across various styles and content.</p>
</div>   


    
    <div>
            
                <p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-developer-goog-blog-assets/images/Imagen-4-fast-demo-landscape.original.png" alt="Imagen 4 Fast demo - landscape"></p><p>
                        Landscape/nature image: A breathtaking landscape of a mountain range at dawn, with a crystal-clear lake in the foreground reflecting the snow-capped peaks.
                    </p>
                
            
        </div>
   


    
    <div>
            
                <p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-developer-goog-blog-assets/images/imagen-4-fast-demo-four-panel-comic-strip.original.png" alt="Imagen 4 Fast demo - four panel comic strip"></p><p>
                        Create a four panel comic strip in a retro style. The first panel should show a friendly cat sitting next to a Chromebook that is pulled up to the website https://ai.dev comic caption: Imagen 4 is now Generally Available! The second panel should show a dog saying “And we’re introducing Imagen 4 FAST which offers low-latency images at just $0.02 per image” panel three should show the cat saying “2K image upscaling is available too!” Panel 4 should show the cat and dog high-fiving with the caption “Try Imagen 4 in AI Studio now!”
                    </p>
                
            
        </div>
   


    
    <div>
            
                <p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-developer-goog-blog-assets/images/imagen-4-fast-demo-retro-sci-fi-movie-poster.original.png" alt="Imagen 4 Fast demo - retro sci-fi movie poster"></p><p>
                        A retro science fiction movie poster with an airbrushed art style. The poster features a detailed spaceship, flying towards the right through a vibrant nebula in a star-filled deep space. The ship's two engines emit bright blue glowing trails. The title at the top of the poster reads "SUPER GALACTICA: THE LAST NEBULA" in a bold, beveled, metallic chrome font with a drop shadow. Below it, the subtitle "STARFALLS REVENGE" is written in a simpler, clean white font. The entire image has a vintage, weathered look, with a distressed, off-white border. At the very bottom, in a small font, is the text: "This poster was created by AI as was this disclaimer :)".
                    </p>
                
            
        </div>
  <div>
    <h2 data-block-key="5zwc7" id="">Start building with Imagen</h2><p data-block-key="53d56">As part of our commitment to responsible AI, all images generated by the Imagen 4 family are imperceptibly watermarked with <a href="https://deepmind.google/science/synthid/">SynthID</a>. Ready to start creating? Dive into our official documentation and cookbooks to begin.</p><ul><li data-block-key="3fce9"><a href="https://ai.google.dev/gemini-api/docs/image-generation/"><b>Read the documentation</b></a></li></ul><ul><li data-block-key="41ium"><a href="https://github.com/google-gemini/cookbook/blob/main/quickstarts/Get_started_imagen.ipynb"><b>Try it out in the Imagen cookbooks</b></a></li></ul><p data-block-key="f81ab">We can't wait to see what you build with Imagen 4 through the <a href="https://ai.google.dev/gemini-api/docs/image-generation#imagen">Gemini API</a> and <a href="https://aistudio.google.com/app/generate-image?model=imagen-4.0-generate-preview-06-06">Google AI Studio</a></p>
</div> 
      </div>
    

    

    
    
    
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Edka – Kubernetes clusters on your own Hetzner account (243 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://edka.io</link>
            <guid>44915164</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 17:34:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://edka.io">https://edka.io</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44915164">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main-content">  <div><div data-aos="fade-up-sm"><p><span>Provision a full infrastructure in under 2 minutes.</span></p></div><h2 data-aos="fade-up-sm">Cut your cloud costs by 70%<br> <span>Keep full control.</span></h2>
              <p data-aos="fade-up-sm">Production ready Kubernetes clusters on your own Hetzner account.<br> Keep full access and cut your cloud bill by up to 70%.</p><ul><li data-aos="fade-up-sm" data-aos-delay="100"><a href="https://console.edka.io/signup" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> <span> <span data-content="Manage one cluster for free">Manage one cluster for free</span> </span>  </a></li><li data-aos="fade-up-sm" data-aos-delay="150"></li></ul></div> <div data-aos="fade-up-sm"><p>Customers using our platform in production</p></div> <div> <!-- Headline & subtitle --> <h2>Own everything. Know the costs.</h2> <p>
Your workloads run in your own Hetzner account.  
          Edka layers on a lightweight control plane for easy management, upgrades, scaling, and backups.
</p> <!-- Six‑point benefit grid --> <div> <!-- Card 1 --> <div> <p>Direct cloud pricing</p> <p>
Pay Hetzner’s list price, often up to 70% lower than AWS or GCP for the same capacity.
</p> </div> <!-- Card 2 --> <div> <p>Simple subscription</p> <p>
A flat per‑cluster fee covers automation, integrations, upgrades, and backups. One cluster always free.
</p> </div> <!-- Card 3 --> <div> <p>Leave any time</p> <p>
Detach Edka with one click; workloads keep running and all resources remain yours.
</p> </div> </div> <!-- /grid --> </div> <div data-aos="fade-up-sm"><h2>Your own Platform</h2><p>Achieve PaaS simplicity without sacrificing flexibility. Provision, scale, and manage your Kubernetes clusters on Hetzner with GitOps workflows, one-click add-ons, and built-in monitoring.</p></div> <div> <h3>
Reduce infrastructure costs by up to 70%
</h3> <p>
If you spend $3,000+ on AWS or GCP, we can run it for $1,000.<br>
Migration, optimization, or hybrid solutions.
</p>  </div> <div>  <p data-aos="fade-up-sm">  <h2>Use cases</h2> </p>  <div> <div data-aos="fade-up-sm" data-aos-delay="200"> <div> <p><a href="https://aicole.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"> <img src="https://edka.io/_astro/aicole.eVIzx0lP_s7o33.svg" alt="Aicole" loading="lazy" decoding="async" fetchpriority="auto" width="144" height="64"> </a> </p> </div> <p>Aicole is a French startup empowering the next generation of students, educators, and institutions. Seeking an alternative to their costly and complex Azure infrastructure, Aicole migrated to Edka, achieving a 64% reduction in operational costs without sacrificing performance or reliability.
</p> <div> <ul> <li> <strong>20</strong> <span>Daily deployments</span> </li><li> <strong>64%</strong> <span>Cost savings</span> </li> </ul> </div> </div><div data-aos="fade-up-sm" data-aos-delay="300"> <div> <p><a href="https://tickets.trommelmusic.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"> <img src="https://edka.io/_astro/troi.CL6pegSv_s7o33.svg" alt="Troi" loading="lazy" decoding="async" fetchpriority="auto" width="144" height="64"> </a> </p> </div> <p>TROI Ticketing Solution sought to migrate their infrastructure to a more scalable and cost-effective environment. Their primary goals were to significantly reduce operational costs and empower developers to deploy applications seamlessly, without the burden of infrastructure management.
</p> <div> <ul> <li> <strong>6k</strong> <span>Daily active users</span> </li><li> <strong>72%</strong> <span>Cost savings</span> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div>   </div>   </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[It seems like the AI crawlers learned how to solve the Anubis challenges (105 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://social.anoxinon.de/@Codeberg/115033790447125787</link>
            <guid>44914773</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 17:01:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://social.anoxinon.de/@Codeberg/115033790447125787">https://social.anoxinon.de/@Codeberg/115033790447125787</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44914773">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>