<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2024 08:30:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[X.com refuses to open with Firefox strict tracking protection enabled (160 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://x.com/</link>
            <guid>41022408</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2024 04:37:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://x.com/">https://x.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41022408">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Initial details about why CrowdStrike's CSAgent.sys crashed (271 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/patrickwardle/status/1814343502886477857</link>
            <guid>41021366</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2024 00:17:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/patrickwardle/status/1814343502886477857">https://twitter.com/patrickwardle/status/1814343502886477857</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41021366">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Empathy for the user having sex with your software (234 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://docs.buttplug.io/docs/dev-guide/intro/buttplug-ethics/</link>
            <guid>41021029</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 23:27:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://docs.buttplug.io/docs/dev-guide/intro/buttplug-ethics/">https://docs.buttplug.io/docs/dev-guide/intro/buttplug-ethics/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41021029">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><blockquote><p>"<!-- -->…<!-- --> Society has put a lot of evils in our brains that we need to transcend before we make out." </p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/ONi7QwYNQz4" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Cex - Not Trying</a></p></blockquote><p>No, really. For as much fun as butts and their surrounding body parts can be, applying technology to them is just a nightmare of conflicting issues and requirements and considerations that's absolutely exhausting to think about for too long.</p><p>So I'll try to keep this short.</p><p>Before we delve into what Buttplug is from the technical side, I'd like to take a minute to think about it from the social and ethical side. It's impossible to solve everything that may come up when using this library in a single page of a developer guide (it'd still be a tall order at a million pages. Thank Turing and his infernal machines for that), but I can at least go over a few things to think about while developing sex tech apps, other than whether your threads are deadlocking or memory is leaking.</p><h2 id="empathy-for-the-user-having-sex-with-your-software">Empathy for the User Having Sex With Your Software<a href="#empathy-for-the-user-having-sex-with-your-software" aria-label="Direct link to Empathy for the User Having Sex With Your Software" title="Direct link to Empathy for the User Having Sex With Your Software">​</a></h2><p>Let's start with the user of the software you're about to create.</p><p>When working on Buttplug applications, something that should be at the forefront of your design thinking is:</p><blockquote><p>Someone is going to fuck this.</p></blockquote><p>The context of this usage should influence all levels of design, from UI/UX to low level code decisions. Assuming the user will approach a piece of software that involves Buttplug in the same way they would, say, a word processor, will end up in a fuckable word processor. If that's what you were aiming for, great, but otherwise this will just end up in a frustrated user and something that looked like a cat walked across the keyboard.</p><p>As you build projects using Buttplug, ask yourself questions that the user will encounter:</p><ul><li>Could I use this while turned on?</li><li>If I'm REALLY turned on, how long does it take for me to go from "I wanna use this" to "I am using this"?</li><li>What happens if my hardware disconnects?</li><li>Do I have a quick way to stop whatever the hardware may be doing?</li><li>Can I control this while possibly covered in <!-- -->[lube or other things]<!-- -->?</li></ul><p>Since Buttplug programs are meant to be sexual, there's a good chance the user <em>won't</em> be considering these questions before embarking on whatever technical adventure you've implemented for them. Therefore it's your job to think about these issues first.</p><h2 id="github-after-dark">Github After Dark<a href="#github-after-dark" aria-label="Direct link to Github After Dark" title="Direct link to Github After Dark">​</a></h2><p>Developing sex software isn't a practice with much best practices or documented history or even a community of developers willing to admit they'd do such a thing. While we hope to change all of those with this library, that's going to take time. In order to gain acceptance in larger software communities, we hope to share our code in public forums, such as GitHub. </p><p>These hopes have to be tempered by the issues of the general sterility of software, though. GitHub, StackOverflow, Glitch, and other community sites were not really made with NSFW content in mind. While there are certainly "adult" projects on GitHub in the form of porn site scrapers, adult games, and other applications, it's still not the norm by any means. How you present your sex software project as the community grows could end up setting standards for how services deal with NSFW code projects in the future.</p><p>Most of the code in Buttplug library isn't extremely explicit, but applications implementing Buttplug may be. Be careful with anything involving media assets that may be deemed inappropriate for certain age groups, especially on sites that don't allow search removal or age checking. Self hosting is always an option for projects involving sensitive materials.</p><p>If you would like to use a project site for Buttplug work, and they don't have an obvious policy stating how they might feel about their site being used with sensitive materials, it may be in your best interest to contact them. If you don't feeling comfortable handling this yourself, feel free to <a href="https://github.com/buttplugio/buttplug/issues" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">file an issue on the main Buttplug repo</a> and we'll be happy to reach out and discuss. The Core Buttplug Developer Team has communicated with services in the past to figure out best practices for hosting sensitive code content, and the outcomes are usually positive.</p><p>Additionally, we highly recommend that any open source or community project using Buttplug should also have a Code of Conduct. While there have been many lively discussions on projects like databases and kernels adopting CoCs, there are some very concrete contextual reasons to have them for sex software projects. This rings especially true if it is a project that may involve some sort of generic, multiple-community/interest use.</p><p>For instance, let's say someone is writing an audio player/movie player that controls sex toys with Buttplug. A massive variety of media could be fed into this application, and there is a good chance that media used by some users may be found offensive by others. These user groups will still need support, and may possibly be sharing the same issue/bug tracker for their needs. Having a CoC in place guides moderation of situations where interests may conflict.</p><p>As for which CoC to use (if looking for a prewritten one), you can <a href="https://github.com/metafetish/metafetish-project-docs/blob/master/CODE_OF_CONDUCT.md" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">check out ours</a> as an example. It's really just a slightly modified version of the <a href="https://www.contributor-covenant.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Contributor's Covenant</a>. Using stock CoC's on sex software projects can prove difficult due to rules about "appropriate wording", due to the sexually explicit context of the project itself. Addendums or rewording may be required, though we do recommend being cautious in how these are presented. We welcome discussion of these issues on <a href="https://metafetish.club/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">our message boards</a> or <a href="https://discord.buttplug.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">discord server</a>.</p><p>Finally, you should consider if and how you'll handle contributions to your project. Regardless of whether you're running the project under your own identity, through a pseudonym, or anonymously, you shouldn't expect your contributors to all make the same choice as you did. Be ready to consider situations where someone wants to contribute but may need to use an anonymous account to do so, or may want to use their real and/or well-known identity, and how that may affect the optics and upkeep of your project.</p><h2 id="mistakes-will-be-made">Mistakes Will Be Made<a href="#mistakes-will-be-made" aria-label="Direct link to Mistakes Will Be Made" title="Direct link to Mistakes Will Be Made">​</a></h2><p>Now that we've covered users and services, let's focus on you, the developer.</p><p>The theme here will be as it was in the other sections: Plan ahead. Making a mistake that ends in something like data loss or crashing programs is one thing, but with sex software, there's just as likely to be social/ethical problems around technically competent implementations. How you respond to these problems affects not only your project, but the field of sex tech in general. Isn't responsibility fun?</p><p>This might seem like putting way too much burden on someone making a tiny vibrator app with a new interface, but context outweights technology here. Technology as applied to sex means people will concentrate on the sex more than the technology when discussing the topic. This is why security breaches in commercial sex tech seem extra bad, even if they may impact far fewer users than a large, non-sex related technical service being hacked. As it goes with larger companies, so it will go with smaller projects. A small project that makes some sort of mistake around sex tech may still see more fire than, say, someone's reimplementation of an algorithm or database or something. Social context matters.</p><p>Does this means you shouldn't develop for sex tech? Absolutely not. It just means you should treat it with more caution and planning than you might normally for less "interesting" software projects (and for everyone thinking "but most software is devoid of usage context and could be perverted for whatever reason!", yes I get it but I want to keep this section short, remember? So just go with it here.). </p><p>As you'd think your design through for your users based on the criteria from the first section of this section, think your design through for yourself too. What is it you want to be responsible for with the software you're releasing? What do and don't you want your users to be able to do with it?</p><p>Note that this list is maleable. You don't have to get it right the first time, and it doesn't need to be formally stated for most smaller projects. It can grow and change as your software grows and changes, but having the stated requirements will help both you and your users in case things ever "blow up".</p><h2 id="the-buttplug-mission-statement">The Buttplug Mission Statement<a href="#the-buttplug-mission-statement" aria-label="Direct link to The Buttplug Mission Statement" title="Direct link to The Buttplug Mission Statement">​</a></h2><p>Buttplug isn't a "smaller" project though, so we do get to take on the formal statement.</p><p>For Buttplug as a project, it felt best to sum up all of the information in this section as The Buttplug Mission Statement (written by someone far smarter than me after I said it far more verbosely and with a bunch of handwaving and probably some cursing).</p><blockquote><p>Buttplug is committed to the safety, autonomy, and human rights of people using it as a sex technology standard, and stands in solidarity with the many intersectional rights of all individuals to be sex positive. As such, Buttplug encourages individual empowerment through self-directed education, and responsible behaviors which are also respectful of the needs and the choices available to everyone.</p></blockquote><p>Getting the paragraphs in this section (plus a bunch of stuff not covered) squeezed into an almost-tweetable chunk means using dense wording that may sound odd for a project named "Buttplug", but this is a Load Bearing Mission Statement. It has a lot to explain and contextualize in a small space, and it does what the project needs. As your project may be more specific than "abstract hardware controller", odds are you may not need something of this manner, but it's good to at least think about what you'd say to sum up what it is you're doing and why you're doing it, before you actually have to do so.</p><h2 id="mo-butts-mo-problems">Mo' Butts Mo' Problems<a href="#mo-butts-mo-problems" aria-label="Direct link to Mo' Butts Mo' Problems" title="Direct link to Mo' Butts Mo' Problems">​</a></h2><p>This section, at best, should provide a framework about how to think about things as you develop your application. Your experience will be unique, and may require you to come up with your own strategies to continue development and distribution in a way that works for you and/or your community.</p><p>If you have any suggestions, please feel free to reach out via the contact info on the home page of this document! I'd love to hear about how developers create and adapt tech as they need for their users.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google Distributed Cloud air-gapped appliance (118 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://cloud.google.com/blog/topics/hybrid-cloud/google-distributed-cloud-air-gapped-appliance-is-ga</link>
            <guid>41019777</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 20:52:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://cloud.google.com/blog/topics/hybrid-cloud/google-distributed-cloud-air-gapped-appliance-is-ga">https://cloud.google.com/blog/topics/hybrid-cloud/google-distributed-cloud-air-gapped-appliance-is-ga</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41019777">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div jsname="tx2NYc"><section><span jsaction="rcuQ6b:npT2md" jscontroller="YSybTb" data-track-type="" soy-skip="" ssk="5:kbe95"><p><span>In harsh, disconnected, or mobile environments like disaster zones, remote research stations, or long-haul trucking operations, organizations face significant challenges in providing computing capabilities. Previously, organizations with mission-critical workloads lacked access to important cloud and AI capabilities when in demanding edge environments, including those that present unique challenges and requirements.</span></p>
<p><span>Today, we are excited to announce the general availability of Google Distributed Cloud air-gapped appliance, a new configuration of </span><a href="https://cloud.google.com/distributed-cloud-hosted?hl=en"><span>Google Distributed Cloud</span></a><span> that brings Google’s cloud and AI capabilities to tactical edge environments. The integrated hardware and software solution unlocks real-time local data processing for AI use cases such as object detection, medical imaging analysis, and predictive maintenance for critical infrastructure. The appliance can be conveniently transported in a rugged case or mounted in a rack within customer-specific local operating environments.</span></p>
<p><span>Google Distributed Cloud air-gapped appliance offers:</span></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Department of Defense (DoD) Impact Level 5 (IL5) accreditation:</strong><span> The appliance has achieved&nbsp; Impact Level 5 accreditation, the highest level of security controls and protection required for unclassified, but sensitive information.&nbsp; The appliance is also designed to meet Impact Level 6 and higher accreditations, and is actively working towards achieving these certifications.</span></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Advanced AI capabilities</strong><span>: Customers can enhance the performance of their mission-critical applications by utilizing built-in AI solutions from the Google Distributed Cloud air-gapped appliance like translation, speech, and optical character recognition (OCR). For instance, they can use OCR and translation features to scan and translate documents written in different languages, making them accessible and understandable for their end users.&nbsp;</span></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Rugged and portable design</strong><span>: Built to withstand harsh environmental conditions, including extreme temperatures, shock, and vibration, Google Distributed Cloud air-gapped appliance has a rugged and portable design that meets stringent accreditation requirements like MIL-STD-810H, ensuring reliable operation even in challenging scenarios. Weighing approximately 100lbs, it's human-portable, making it easy to transport and deploy in various locations.</span></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Full isolation</strong><span>: Google Distributed Cloud air-gapped appliance is designed to operate without any connectivity to Google Cloud or the public internet. The appliance remains fully functional in disconnected environments, preserving the security and isolation of the infrastructure, services, and the APIs that it manages. This makes it ideal for processing sensitive data, while meeting strict regulatory, compliance, and sovereignty requirements. </span></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Integrated cloud services: &nbsp; </strong><span>Google Distributed Cloud air-gapped appliance offers both infrastructure-as-a-services (IaaS) features like compute, networking, and storage, and Google Cloud services like data transfer and data analytics technologies.&nbsp;</span></p>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Data security</strong><span>: </span><span>Google Distributed Cloud air-gapped appliance </span><span>includes robust security features like encryption, data isolation, firewalls, and secure boot to protect sensitive information.</span></p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><span>The Google Distributed Cloud air-gapped appliance enables a wide array of use cases for organizations with stringent security requirements, including:</span></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Disaster response</strong><span>: In the aftermath of a disaster, timely and accurate information is crucial for coordinating relief efforts and saving lives. However, disaster-stricken areas often lack the necessary infrastructure to support traditional communication and data processing systems. As a self-contained, ruggedized device, the Google Distributed Cloud air-gapped appliance can be rapidly deployed to disaster-affected areas, even in the absence of internet connectivity. It comes pre-loaded with essential software and tools for data collection and analysis, enabling immediate response to emergencies. By leveraging the Google Distributed Cloud air-gapped appliance, aid organizations can enhance their disaster response capabilities, improve coordination, and save lives in times of crisis.</span></p>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Industrial automation</strong><span>: Google Distributed Cloud air-gapped appliance offers an innovative solution for remote equipment monitoring, predictive maintenance, and process optimization in challenging environments at the edge. For instance, in the manufacturing sector, the appliance can be leveraged to track and optimize equipment performance in remote plants, leading to enhanced productivity and minimized downtime.</span></p>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Transportation and logistics</strong><span>: Google Distributed Cloud air-gapped appliance supports the unique demands of fleet management, autonomous vehicles, and real-time logistics optimization. For example, the appliance can facilitate the deployment and operation of autonomous vehicles by enabling the real-time collection, processing, and decision-making, helping autonomous vehicles safely and efficiently navigate complex environments.</span></p>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Restricted workloads for federal and defense</strong><span>: Google Distributed Cloud's air-gapped appliance is designed to meet the demands of restricted workloads, such as sensitive data analysis, AI inference and simulations, and intelligence translation, while adhering to security and supporting compliance regulations.</span></p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><span>“Google Distributed Cloud air-gapped appliance will enable the Air Force Rapid Sustainment Office (RSO) to bring the maintenance digital ecosystem to Airmen in austere and forward deployed locations, supporting the Air Force's agile objectives while prioritizing security and reliability,” said Michael Roquemore, Director of the RSO’s Rapid, Agile, Integrated Capabilities Team. “By delivering a secure and compliant edge compute platform, the RSO can leverage already developed Google-based technologies in both connected cloud and disconnected edge to bring digital innovation to the Service Members wherever they operate.”</span></p>
<p><span>To learn more, visit the </span><a href="https://cloud.google.com/distributed-cloud/hosted/docs/latest/appliance/overview"><span>Google Distributed Cloud air-gapped appliance website</span></a><span>. If you would like to discuss your air-gapped cloud requirements, please complete this </span><a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSfNaRPXtgmHVWd-m2h34dXMiJEU_qq06ynm8VQ45j7N6IfjFg/viewform" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><span>form</span></a><span>, and a member of our team will be in touch.</span></p></span></section><section><span>Posted in</span><ul><li><a href="https://cloud.google.com/blog/topics/modernize-it" track-metadata-position="body" track-metadata-eventdetail="cloud.google.com/blog/topics/modernize-it" track-metadata-module="tag list" track-metadata-module_headline="posted in">Hybrid &amp; Multicloud</a></li><li><a href="https://cloud.google.com/blog/products/compute" track-metadata-position="body" track-metadata-eventdetail="cloud.google.com/blog/products/compute" track-metadata-module="tag list" track-metadata-module_headline="posted in">Compute</a></li></ul></section></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Minuteman missile communications (233 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://computer.rip/2024-07-20-minuteman-missile-communications.html</link>
            <guid>41019604</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 20:33:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://computer.rip/2024-07-20-minuteman-missile-communications.html">https://computer.rip/2024-07-20-minuteman-missile-communications.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41019604">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>


<p>A programming note: I am looking at making some changes to how I host things
like Computers Are Bad and <a href="https://wikimap.wiki/">wikimap</a> that are going to
involve a lot more recurring expense. For that and other reasons, I want to see
if y'all would be willing to throw some money my way. If everyone reading this
gave $3 a month, we could probably buy Jimbo Wales a nice lunch or something.</p>
<p>I do not intend to paywall anything that I post here. Instead, I'm going to
take some of the things that tend to be very long Mastodon threads (how this
article originally started!) and send them out to supporters, probably about
once a month. They'll be things that I wouldn't post here, usually because
they're too short or don't quite have a hook to make a while article
interesting.</p>
<p>So <a href="https://ko-fi.com/jbcrawford">consider supporting me on ko-fi</a>---or don't,
it's your decision, and I respect that. I'll probably work a plug into each
article but I promise not to be annoying about it. I'm also going to be making
some new YouTube videos and I'll probably make those available to supporters
first, so that's something else to look forward to.</p>
<p>Speaking of annoying, this is kind of a long and dry one. I started looking
into something called HICS after visiting a historic site, posted about it a
bit on Mastodon, realized that there just wasn't a lot of good historic
information about it in general. And I felt like if I was going to talk about
communications in Minuteman missile fields, I also had to cover how they would
get their war orders.</p>
<p>Look on the  bright side: it's got pictures!</p>
<p><img alt="Blast door of LCC" src="https://computer.rip/f/minuteman/door.jpg"></p>
<h2>Minuteman Missiles</h2>
<p>Since the early days of the Cold War, the United States has maintained a
nuclear triad: independent capabilities to deliver nuclear weapons from land,
sea, and air. The sea and air components are straightforward, consisting of
submarines carrying submarine-launched ballistic missiles (SLBMs) and
long-range strategic bombers. The land leg is more often forgotten: the
intercontinental ballistic missiles, or ICBMs.</p>
<p>The US ICBM arsenal currently consists of 400 Minuteman III missiles emplaced
throughout the midwest: the Air Force's 90th Missile Wing, 150 missiles,
Wyoming Nebraska, and Colorado; the 91st Missile Wing, 150 missiles, in North
Dakota; and the 341st Missile Wing, 100 missiles, in Montana. Historically,
there were as many as 1,000 active Minuteman missiles, to say nothing of
retired missile programs like Titan and Atlas. At least three Minuteman missile
facilities are now historic sites open to the public, a somewhat incongruous
experience considering their broad similarity to the facilities still in active
use. Many others are abandoned, typically in various states of permanent
destruction to satisfy treaty obligations. Fifty Minuteman IIIs of the 341st
are currently held in an inactive "reserve" state, out of service but ready for
future emplacement, a notable situation given the strict limits Cold War
treaties place on stockpiled ICBMs.</p>
<p>Minuteman employed a significantly different launch configuration from earlier
ICBM programs. Large facilities were difficult to protect from a first strike;
distance was the only effective protection from increasingly accurate Soviet
weapons. Scattered single facilities were difficult and costly to staff.
Minuteman selected a compromise point: clusters of ten independent Launch
Facilities (LFs), spaced miles apart and called a "flight," are remotely
monitored and operated from a single Missile Alert Facility (MAF). Groups of
four to five missile flights constitute a squadron, and about four squadrons
compose a wing, which is supported by an Air Force Base.</p>
<p>In each Missile Alert Facility, a Missile Combat Crew Commander (MCCC) and
Deputy Missile Combat Crew Commander (DMCCC) lock themselves into an
underground capsule called a Launch Control Center (LCC) for each 24 hour
watch. Originally designed by Boeing, the LCC resembles the interior of an
aircraft more than a building, fitting its crew of Air Force officers. The
LCC is an isolated, self-contained system with all of the equipment needed to
monitor, configure, and launch the missiles. A surface building above contains
a security control center and quarters for the security force, responsible not
only for the MAF but also for the ten LFs under its supervision. Still, the
surface building is both powerless over and largely unneeded by the LCC beneath
it. In the event of nuclear war, it was assumed, surface structures in these
sparsely populated but strategically critical parts of the country would be
wiped cleanly away from the earth. Only the hardened infrastructure would
remain: the LCCs, the LFs, and communications infrastructure.</p>
<p><img alt="Missile Alert Facility" src="https://computer.rip/f/minuteman/quebec.jpg"></p>
<p>Minuteman missile combat crews had more duties than just to wait. They
performed remote tests on the missiles, launch, and control equipment; they
monitored alarm systems that reported malfunctions and remotely supervised the
work of maintenance crews; and they monitored the security systems that
protected the unmanned LFs, authorizing access and dispatching security forces
on the surface to any unknown intrusion. Still, their primary responsibility,
the one for which we all know them, is the disposition of Emergency War Orders
(EWO).</p>
<p>In fine Air Force tradition, actions that may very well presage the end of the
world a we know it are presented in the form of a checklist. EWOs are
authenticated against codes and secrets. Two keys, just like in the movies, are
inserted. The missiles are enabled by remote command. Targeting information is
transmitted to the missiles. The keys are turned, the launch code sent, and the
rest is automated, under the control of the missiles themselves. The missile
crew are miles away, so the Real Thing, the Shit Hitting the Fan, must feel
pretty anticlimactic. The only apocalyptic horsemen they'll see are a series of
indicator lights on the MCCC's console: LCH CMD. LCH IN PROC. MISSILE AWAY.</p>
<p>The realities of ICBM operation are fascinating and incline one towards drama.
Somehow the work of submarine and bomber crews seems more ordinary; they are at
least "out there," in or near enemy territory. Missile crews are sealed in a
very small room buried below a small building in a corner cut out of a farm
field near, but not too near, to a highway for logistical convenience. They are
entirely dependent on electronic communications, not only to receive their
orders, but even to use their weapons. They have the original email job: since
1962, they have served primarily to send and receive messages, mostly by text.</p>
<p>With the rather purple introduction complete, I am going to talk about this
communications technology. But first, just a little more preface.</p>
<p>Most of the reduction of the Minuteman force has been a direct response to
treaties, which imposed progressively lower caps on the nuclear stockpile.
Some reductions were more of a historical accident. In the 1980s, political
considerations lead to a decision to "temporarily" deploy the Peacekeeper
missile, with 10 MIRV (multiple independent reentry vehicle) warheads, to a set
of fifty silos of the 90th Missile Wing's 400th Missile Squadron, in Wyoming.
The Peacekeeper, fielded late in the Cold War, was a profoundly controversial
program. The fifty Peacekeepers retrofitted into Minuteman silos would be the
only ever installed, and their temporary homes became permanent. Most of the
missile's warheads were removed for compliance with Start II treaty, which
Russia never ratified and the United States withdrew from. Still, for
cost-savings reasons, the odd-duck Peacekeeper program was terminated. The last
Peacekeeper missiles were retired in 2005.</p>
<p>I got it into my head to write a detailed description of the missile field
communications system because of my visit to QUEBEC-01, one of the five MAFs
associated with these Peacekeeper missiles, and now a Wyoming State Historical
Site. For that reason, I will most closely describe the communications system
as installed in the 90th Missile Wing, the remainder of which is still active
today. Minuteman missile fields were built over a period of years by different
contractors and have since been through multiple modernization programs. Each
change has introduced inconsistencies. While I will point out some of the more
interesting variations between Minuteman installations, this is best taken as a
description of the "average" Minuteman squadron, one that is typical of the
others but does not exactly exist.</p>
<p>Although I am not exactly aiming for academic rigor, this information is based
mostly on documents available through the Defense Technical Information Center,
which include both original documentation from the Minuteman program and more
recent documents related to modernization programs, proposed changes, and the
retirement of many Minuteman facilities. I have supplemented those documents
with recollections by former Air Force personnel when available, and as always,
I welcome any corrections or additional information. One of the pleasures of
writing about military history is the tendency of veterans to reach out to me
with corrections and stories; I apologize that I am not always good about
getting back to people, particularly phone calls.</p>
<p>The Minuteman III, a fairly direct evolution of the original Minuteman
design, is still in active service. Many detailed materials about the
Minuteman program are probably currently classified, most of the others are
formerly classified and thus have not consistently made their way to archives.
Certain basic questions remain frustratingly unanswered. That's just how it
goes.</p>
<p>I'm also going to try really hard not to be too annoying with the acronyms, but
it's not easy.</p>
<h2>Personnel</h2>
<p>While there were originally three-person crews, Minuteman LCCs have had two
crew members for many decades, the MCCC and DMCCC. The MCCC is superior to the
DMCCC, but the nature of missile operations and such a small crew mean that
their roles are somewhat more complex than commander and deputy. Missile crews
operate according to the "two-person concept," a general prohibition on any
person working alone. This rule is intended to improve safety, reduce mistakes,
and most importantly, mitigate the risk of an unauthorized launch. There are
additional safeguards against unauthorized launch in the Minuteman system which
will be discussed later. Both the MCCC and the DMCCC are required to initiate a
launch.</p>
<p>The MCCC sits at a console that is focused around monitoring and control of the
launch facilities. They have ready access to procedures and documentation. The
DMCCC sits at a separate console that is focused on communications. Their chair
slides on rails, allowing them to access the equipment racks and teleprinters
to the sides of the DMCCC position. The DMCCC is primarily responsible for
communications, so we are most interested in the equipment under their control.</p>
<p>Missile Alert Facilities were designed with a goal of self-containment for
survivability. Most communications equipment is within the LCC itself, readily
available to the DMCCC so that they can at least diagnose problems, if not make
a repair. To this end, DMCCCs receive significant training on technical details
of the communications and computer systems.</p>
<p>Should a problem occur outside of the LCC, the MCC would request assistance
from the Air Force Base. Several Air Force ratings had expertise in
communications equipment, ranging from communications technicians that would
investigate problems within the LF to cable splicers that would repair damage
in the outside plant.</p>
<p>The Minuteman program is somewhat unusual in the extensive construction of
long-distance communications equipment by the Air Force.  AT&amp;T's role in the
missile fields was surprisingly limited; most communications followed routes
fully under the control of the Air Force.</p>
<h2>External Communications</h2>
<p>We can generally divide Minuteman communications systems into two categories:
external and internal. External communications systems are primarily used by
the Missile Combat Crew (MCC) to receive orders, including Emergency War Orders
authorizing the use of nuclear weapons. Internal communications systems are
used within the missile field, primarily to allow the MCC to communicate with
the launch facilities under their control. Some details blur the lines: for
example, there are communications systems which allow the MCC to contact their
Air Force Base, where support facilities and maintenance crews are found. I
will consider these internal systems, but you could argue for the opposite.</p>
<p>The external communications systems available to Minuteman crews have varied
over time. Perhaps the most exotic was the Survivable Low Frequency
Communications System (SLFCS), based on the LF equipment used by the Navy for
communications with submarines. Missile facilities are not underwater, but
nuclear detonations cause significant disruption to the atmosphere that greatly
interferes with radio propagation in the HF range. LF communications are
expected to be less affected in a nuclear combat environment. SLFCS
specifically operated between 14kHz and 60kHz. Some, but not all, Minuteman
MAFs were equipped with a magnetic loop antenna, about 6' in diameter,  buried
shallowly underground.</p>
<p>All MAFs were equipped with HF antennas, although they were decommissioned in
the 1980s. The HF antennas are described as hardened, but it is not feasible to
truly harden an HF antenna. They must be fairly large, and HF does not
penetrate the ground well, making it impractical to bury them. Instead,
hardened HF antennas are perhaps better described as "hidden" HF antennas.  The
typical design is a monopole that stores in a long, narrow silo underground,
awaiting post-attack deployment. MAFs had two separate hardened HF antennas,
one for transmit, and one for receive.</p>
<p>The receive antenna was the most critical, as it would be needed to receive war
orders over the High Frequency Global Communications System (HFGCS). HFGCS is
one of the primary ways that an Emergency War Order would be distributed to Air
Force units including both missiles and bombers. The hardened HF receive
antenna assembly actually included six 160' monopoles: one was extended for
normal use, but in the event of nuclear attack, the five others were stored
telescoped in a silo about 30' deep and could be deployed by a small explosive
charge. There were, in the parlance apparently used by the Air Force, five
"reloads."</p>
<p>The HF transmit antenna, being less important in an attack scenario, had only
one replacement. A "soft" HF transmit antenna of conventional design was in normal
use but backed up by a single 120' hardened antenna stored in a separate silo.
A 50' radius buried ground plane surrounded the hardened antenna.</p>
<p>Near the MAF surface building, a small, white metal cone protrudes from the
ground. The cone consists of a huge cast steel blast deflector with a
depression in the center, which is covered by a fiberglass cone. The cone
houses a compact UHF antenna. This antenna, a 1970s upgrade, can receive war
orders via several satellite systems or directly from an aircraft such as the
E-6. The E-6 airborne command post can serve in various roles, including as a
"Looking Glass" airborne command post (taking control of nuclear forces in the
event of a loss of ground-based command posts) or a "TACAMO" Take Charge and
Move Out relay, transmitting a war order from elsewhere to forces in the field.</p>
<p><img alt="Hardened UHF antenna" src="https://computer.rip/f/minuteman/uhf.jpg"></p>
<p>UHF communications are essentially line of sight, especially with the use of a
partially in-ground hardened antenna.  In a scenario with extensive loss of
communications infrastructure, particularly with ASAT warfare disabling
military communications satellites, an E-6 or another similarly equipped
aircraft would fly over Minuteman missile fields and deliver an emergency war
order directly to each LCC.</p>
<p>Complimenting this capability, in-service Minuteman launch facilities have
themselves been equipped with a similar UHF antenna. Looking Glass and TACAMO
aircraft actually have Air Force missileers on board who serve as an Airborne
Launch Control Center (ALCC). In the event of a loss of most of the LCCs in a
missile field, an ALCC can issue launch instructions directly to each LF
without any need for the regular missile crews or internal communications
infrastructure.</p>
<p>During the early '90s, a super high frequency (SHF) small satellite terminal
was installed at each active MAF. It is housed in a small, white radome at the
top of a pole near the surface building. SHF is widely used by modern military
satellite systems, such as the Air Force's Wideband Global SATCOM.</p>
<p><img alt="Satellite terminal" src="https://computer.rip/f/minuteman/sat.jpg"></p>
<p>Each of these antennas is connected by buried conduits to radio equipment in
the LCC's radio racks. At the DMCCC's position, the telephone console allows
the DMCCC to talk or listen on each radio by selecting it with a pushbutton.
Over time, the radios were also attached to more modern digital systems.
Depending on the year, teleprinters or computer displays would receive text
messages via the UHF and SHF radio systems.</p>
<p>The external radio systems were actually all backup or secondary. The primary
means of nuclear C2 within the Strategic Air Command and, later, Global Strike
Command, has long been a digital computer network. While Minuteman
installations began with just a teleprinter to receive orders via leased
telephone line, the late '60s saw the introduction of the Strategic Automated
Command and Control System (SACCS), which was itself replaced by the Strategic
Air Command Digital Network (SACDIN). A small (for the era) computer in a rack
to the right of the DMCCC's station allowed two-way messaging with SAC
headquarters over leased telephone lines. Reportedly, these and other Bell
System telephone lines to LCCs were carried by buried telephone cable to small
hardened exchange buildings serving each missile field. I have not yet
researched this topic closely.</p>
<p>In Peacekeeper LCCs as well as Minuteman LCCs from the '70s to the '90s, the
specific computer used for this purpose was called the Command Data Buffer
(CDB). The CDB was connected to both SACCS/SACDIN and the internal
communications network, in order to accurately relay targeting information to
the missiles. This will be discussed later in the context of rapid retargeting.
In the 1990s, the REACT system was installed for a similar purpose.</p>
<p>Quebec-01 LCC was equipped with a teleprinter with a selector between SACDIN
and AFSAT (UHF satellite) receivers. I'm not sure why the teleprinter was
retained after the CDB upgrade, very possibly just for redundancy.</p>
<p><img alt="SACDIN Teleprinter" src="https://computer.rip/f/minuteman/teleprinter.jpg"></p>
<p>Somewhere between external and internal, each LCC had access to two dial
telephone lines. These connected directly to the PSTN. Some circumstantial
evidence leads me to think these dial lines were shared with the surface
building, which probably explains the need for two.  The dial lines were mostly
used to contact support crews at the Air Force Base for routine maintenance
issues.</p>
<h2>HICS Digital Communications</h2>
<p><img alt="HICS cable splice" src="https://computer.rip/f/minuteman/splice.jpg"></p>
<p>I was most interested in the internal communications systems, which have
garnered less historical documentation than the external links. In most cases,
there is only really one: the Hardened Intersite Cable System, HICS.</p>
<p>HICS consists of multipair pressurized telephone cables trenched between
Minuteman facilities. HICS carries digital traffic for C2, and many Air Force
documents use the term "HICS" exclusively to mean the digital channel, but the
same cables carried multiple voice pairs. Let's consider the digital capability
first, though.</p>
<p>HICS, as originally installed, operated at 1.3Kbps. Details on the actual
encoding are hard to come by, but given the time period I assume it was
generally similar to the AFSK schemes used by other early telephone data links.
The punch line, of course, is that the 1.3Kbps stuck---based on some Air Force
journal articles on options for upgrades, it seems that contemporary Minuteman
III fields still communicate over HICS at 1.3Kbps. Remember that when we get to
retargeting.</p>
<p>The topology of the digital HICS network is rather interesting. It was designed
for redundancy and reliability, but prior to most of our modern understanding
of computer networking. There's a mix of a few different ideas.</p>
<p>One of the things I'm not completely confident of is the size of the collision
domain within HICS, or how much of the cable network was a common bus. From
reading between the lines of some different reports and considering the overall
design, I'm fairly confident that the entire digital HICS network was a single
shared bus within each flight, and I think it is likely that it was a shared
bus within each squadron. This bus would be tens of miles long with multiple
branches, a challenging electrical situation that perhaps explains why the Air
Force has repeatedly found it to be infeasible to make HICS faster.</p>
<p><img alt="HICS cable map" src="https://computer.rip/f/minuteman/hics.jpg"></p>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://minutemanmissile.com/">minutemanmissile.com</a> for this image
of the Warren AFB/90th Missile Wing HICS map, which is far more legible
than the photo I had taken.</p>
<p>Each of the LCCs, denoted in the map by open rectangles, is connected to four
"loops" of HICS cable. The legs of adjacent loops to the LCC are shared,
though, so it's perhaps easier to describe this way: each LCC is surrounded by
a ring of HICS cable, to which it is connected by four legs spread roughly 90
degrees apart. This design gives a fair amount of redundancy, a break anywhere
in the ring or even breaks of more than one of the LCC's legs would still leave
a working path.</p>
<p>This latter scenario was probably one of the designer's greatest concerns, as
the LCCs would be obvious targets for inbound nuclear attacks. The cable layout
provides four-times redundancy on the cables to the LCC, but no redundancy at
all on the cables to individual LFs. That tells you a lot about their threat
modeling. Facilities were spaced far enough apart that a precision strike on an
LF would probably disable only that single LF; a precision strike on an LCC,
though, could potentially disable ten LFs at once. As the accuracy and power of
nuclear warheads improved, it seemed more likely that a first strike would
succeed in disabling at least some LCCs. A lot of the complexity of HICS is
intended to account for that possibility.</p>
<p>Each of the LFs is connected to the ring via a single leg. In some cases,
multiple LFs are along the same leg. These are often the same long runs that
connect the rings of two different LCCs together. In general, each LCC ring is
connected to two of its neighbors, although sometimes it will instead have two
redundant connections to a single neighbor. Based on the map and situation on
the ground, these inter-flight connections don't seem to have required any
active equipment, only a splice case. That supports the theory that an entire
squadron was a shared bus, although it's possible that a separate pair to the
"foreign" LCC ring would home-run to the LCC to allow separately sending
messages to either. The network doesn't seem to have that kind of selective
routing capability, though, so I find it unlikely.</p>
<p>Digital messages do seem to have been packetized, and were distributed through
the network on a "flood fill" basis. That is, every active node on the digital
network repeated every message it received. You might wonder about flow control
and the avoidance of cycles; only a very primitive method was used. Each node,
after transmitting a message, would "lock out" the cable it was transmitted on
for a long enough period for the node on the other end to finish repeating the
message.</p>
<p>This explanation is a little more difficult to understand, though, when applied
to the actual layout of the HICS system. What exactly constitutes a node? You
will note that the map distinctly shows intersquadron connections, with both
thicker lines and open circles where they connect to an LCC ring. My theory is
that these intersquadron connections where the only places where active
repeating of messages was required. Whether or not repeating messages between
squadrons was selective is unclear. Did a message from an LCC to one of its
nearby LFs get repeated across squadrons to the opposite end of the field?  If
repeating had originally been completely non-selective, I suspect that was
changed as part of the work done to facilitate retargeting.</p>
<p>We can infer certain things about the HICS network from the equipment in
Quebec-01.  For example, HICS must have had a fair number of active repeaters.
along a path.</p>
<p><img alt="HICS diagnostic panel" src="https://computer.rip/f/minuteman/hics_equip.jpg"></p>
<p>Inside of the LCC, we find something like a tiny long-distance telephone test
desk. A rack includes pressurization alarms for five cables (we know of four
legs to the LCC ring, is the fifth perhaps a cable to the local telephone
exchange?), and a fault isolation panel. When a cable seemed to have been lost,
the DMCCC could use this panel to locate the problem along the cable. This
probably relied on a loopback test feature of the repeaters, but I'm not sure
exactly the operating principle. Further down in the rack is what appears to
be a cable power supply.</p>
<p>Repeaters were definitely installed inside the LCCs, but the number of
selections on this test panel makes me suspect that there were also in-line
repeaters on the cable, perhaps taking power from that power supply. This is
entirely speculative, but A repeaters may have been located along the LCC ring
and B repeaters on legs, making the two-knob selector arrangement useful to
test a specific repeater on a specific leg.</p>
<p><img alt="HICS termination point" src="https://computer.rip/f/minuteman/hics_term.jpg"></p>
<p>In the equipment side of the LCC, where the generator and chiller are located,
we also find the terminations of the HICS cables. Note the mostly empty rack
that would have held repeater equipment, and the air dryer and flow gauges
for cable pressurization.</p>
<p>Finally, I should talk a bit about the exception to all of this: the 321st
Missile Wing, in North Dakota, was built later than the 90th and 91st and by a
different contractor. Sylvania, not Boeing, won the bid to build the LCCs and
LFs. Much of the equipment is the same, but Sylvania did inject a few of their
own ideas, and one of them was radio redundancy for HICS. The 321st apparently
had a simplified HICS topology; I'm not sure of the details but I would guess
that they may not have provided the four redundant cables to each LCC.</p>
<p>To make up for it, each LCC and LF in the 321st is equipped with a large,
buried antenna, a grid-like arrangement of crossing dipoles that took up an
area similar to the sewage lagoons outside of the fence. These antennas made up
a medium-frequency, ground-wave communications network that could be used as an
alternative to HICS. The 321sts redundant radio system, apparently called
"Deuce" at the time, could be viewed as a precursor to the later nationwide
GWEN radio C2 network. It seems to have carried the same digital messages as
HICS, and the DMCCC had selectors to choose whether messages would be sent by
cable or radio.</p>
<h2>HICS Voice Communications</h2>
<p>Now, let's take a close look at the DMCCC's communications console, which tells
us a lot about the voice capabilities.</p>
<p><img alt="DMCCC communications console" src="https://computer.rip/f/minuteman/telephone.jpg"></p>
<p>They get a lot of buttons! There appear to be two separate busses, I'm not
completely sure of the significance of that layout. I know from an airman's
anecdote that the DMCCCs could conference together LF phones and the dial
telephone lines, and sometimes did so that maintenance crews stuck at an LF
overnight could make apologies to their families. This makes me think that it
is not a matter of "one selection per bus," but rather probably indicates that
lines can only be joined within a bus. The logic behind that design is not
clear to me.</p>
<p>Anyway, let's see if we know enough to explain all of these buttons. Some are
easy: for the speaker and handset, there are selectors each of the radios.
The "LF Lines" correspond to each of the ten LFs, numbered 2-11 since the LCC
is numbered as site 1. We see the two dial lines, regular telephone lines
provided at each site, and they are even labeled with their phone numbers. The
five-digit notation dates this hand-written addition to the 2L-5N era, which
probably persisted unusually late in rural Wyoming.</p>
<p>The rest of the buttons correspond to specific pairs that would emerge in
different places in the HICS network. The "SCC" button likely allows
communications with the security command center in the surface building, just
up the elevator from the LCC. The "LCC" button I am less sure of; perhaps it
was a party line of other LCCs in the squadron?  The "LCC Ring" selections must
correspond to the four HICS cable rings extending from the LCC, but I'm not
sure which devices would be found on those pairs. They may be "order wires,"
available in the splice boxes and as jacks at sites and normally used only by
maintenance crews working on cables outside of the LFs.</p>
<p>The EWO buttons are interesting. EWO is, of course, Emergency War Order, but in
the context of Minuteman was also the term used for party lines connecting the
Air Force Base to the LCCs. These could be used, of course, as a redundant way
to deliver EWOs, as well as for general communications across the missile
field. There are two for redundancy: one was routed via AT&amp;T infrastructure,
following a cable from the LCC to a telephone exchange. The other was routed
via HICS. I am not sure why only one merits a "RNG" button, that could apply
ringing voltage to get the attention of other stations.</p>
<p>I am assuming, by the magic of speculation, that the "OPR" button on the left
of each bus probably selected which bus the headset was connected to. There is
also a dial, for use with the dial lines.</p>
<p>These voice connections within the field were of critical importance because of
Minuteman's strict security posture. The unattended LFs were equipped with
intrusion alarms for physical security, initially a bistatic radar system more
similar to that used at Titan, and later a DSP-based monostatic radar system
called the IMPSS. Any personnel or, reportedly, large rabbits approaching an LF
would cause an alarm, and security forces were dispatched to investigate unless
the intruder used a HICS voice circuit to authenticate themselves to the LCC.
The process of "penetrating" a secure LF could take a missile crew thirty
minutes or more, and involved multiple calls to the LCC as different alarms
were triggered.</p>
<h2>HICS Outside Plant</h2>
<p>Old aerial images and historical documents from the Air Force give us some
insight into the construction of HICS. HICS cables were installed in open
trenches and then covered, rather than placed directly with a vibratory plow as
would become common later. Splices were done in large holes with scotch-lok
connectors and cast iron splice casings. Over time, many of the splice casings
had to be replaced due to premature corrosion, and different materials were
tried before settling on brass. A cathodic protection system was installed
as a permanent solution to the problem.</p>
<p>I have done my best to trace some of the HICS cables along their routes. The
holes used for splicing are sometimes visible as scars, but it does not appear
that any manholes were installed; instead splices were made near RoW markers
and will have to be excavated for repairs. The lack of manholes suggests that
there may not be active equipment along the cable routes, I'm not really sure.</p>
<p>The RoW markers used by the Air Force are substantially similar to the style
used by AT&amp;T at the time. They are round wooden posts, about 6' tall, with
metal bands around the top. Unlike AT&amp;T, the Air Force used white bands, and it
seems that there are always two. Shorter markers are used in some places, I
suspect where there are splice cases not near road crossings. Where the cables
cross roads, the Air Force usually installed gates with sturdy metal posts in
the roadside fences. Sometimes these gates are the easiest evidence to find in
aerial photos.</p>
<p>One of my biggest questions is about the inter-squadron relays. The map depicts
them as nodes, but they aren't located at LFs or other facilities. I wondered
if there might be active equipment, but I found one of the locations where in
inter-squadron cable takes off from an LCC ring and there is no indication of
even a manhole. In case you might be interested, <a href="https://computer.rip/f/minuteman/90th-mw.kmz">here is a KML</a>
with the cable tracks I have worked out so far.</p>
<h2>Cross-Flight Communications</h2>
<p>HICS served primarily to allow an LCC to communicate within the ten missiles
in its flight. However, the entire squadron and then the entire missile wing
were interconnected, and Minuteman took advantage of this capability for
several purposes.</p>
<p>First, a specific LCC in each squadron was designated as the Squadron Command
Post (SCP). The SCP was capable of sending launch orders to any missile within
the squadron, and of countermanding launch orders issued by any of the
squadron's LCCs. This provided a measure of protection against a destroyed or
compromised LCC.</p>
<p>Over time, the security of Minuteman missiles was further enhanced by the
addition of a "vote to launch" system. Minuteman missiles can only be launched
if launch orders are sent by at least two LCCs, requiring a total of four
individuals.</p>
<p>In some Minuteman fields (and all current fields), a Wing command post serves
in a role similar to the SCP but across the entire wing. It provides one
central point where the entire wing's missile inventory can be monitored and,
if necessary, controlled.</p>
<h2>Alarms</h2>
<p>Besides missile C2 and voice communications, one of the main functions of the
HICS was the reporting of alarms within unattended LFs to the LCC. Some alarms,
particularly related to the missile itself, would be sent by the missile
guidance computer over the HICS digital network. These alarms would be printed
by the teleprinter below the DMCCC's desk, along with confirmations of commands
received and other routine traffic.</p>
<p>There was also a second, dedicated alarm system called the Voice Reporting
Status Assembly or VRSA. VRSA seems to have relied on its own pairs in the HICS
cables, and resembled the simple alarm reporting telephones coming into use by
AT&amp;T. The DMCCC could select an LF and press a button to send a tone, which
triggered a device at the LF to "read back" any status alarms via voice
recordings. At the time this almost certainly involved some interesting
magnetic tape equipment, but I haven't found much information on the LF end of
the VRSA. Toggle switches on the VRSA console allowed the DMCCC to reset the
alarm device in the LF, clearing any recorded alarms that weren't active.</p>
<p>The VRSA was an upgrade over the original Minuteman installations, which used a
very similar panel to send a safe/arm tone to the LFs as part of the launch
process. Since part of standard testing practice was for DMCCCs to flip the
toggle switch for an LF to remove the "safe" tone and arm the site, it was a
fairly obvious evolution to have the site report any faults in response to a
tone. Reportedly, the VRSA panels were the original safe/arm panels with
modifications.</p>
<h2>Retargeting</h2>
<p>When Minuteman was originally installed, each missile's targeting data was
loaded from tape using equipment in the LF. To retarget a missile, a
maintenance crew had to travel to the site, access it, run the new target tape
through equipment in the LF that sent the data to the guidance computer, and
complete a recalibration of the inertial reference platform in the missile.
This was something like a 12-hour process overall, and retargeting a squadron
would take weeks.</p>
<p>Fixed targets were practical when the "enemy" was self-evidently the Soviet
Union and any attack would be all-out. Over the 70-year lifespan of the
Minuteman program, though, the geopolitical and military environment has
changed. There are now other nuclear adversaries, and their military assets are
increasingly mobile. The biggest challenge to Minuteman's targeting was the
Soviet Union's development of road-mobile ICBMs like the RT-21.  To eliminate
the USSR's nuclear capability, we would have to fire on these mobile systems
wherever they were located. Aerial and satellite surveillance could be
surprisingly effective in keeping track of these large, slow-moving TELs, but
the Minuteman missiles could not be retargeted to keep up with that
intelligence.</p>
<p>In response, a series of enhancements were made (often as part of the Minuteman
II program) to introduce "rapid retargeting." Rapid retargeting allowed the
missiles to be retargeted from within the LCC. During the 1970s, a computer
system called the Command Data Buffer (CDB) was installed in each LCC. The CDB
could receive targeting parameters from SAC and then transmit them to the LFs.
It was theoretically possible to retarget missiles shortly before launch. In
practice, the "shortly" wasn't very achievable</p>
<p><img alt="DMCCC station with CDB" src="https://computer.rip/f/minuteman/dmccc.jpg"></p>
<p>The HICS network was capable of 1.3Kbps, and because of the "flood" design of
the network, that was essentially 1.3Kbps of total capacity across a single
collision domain. In other words, only 1.3Kbps of total traffic could be
handled, with far less available from point to point when the network is under
heavy use. Further, enhancements to the Minuteman system added cryptographic
authentication of messages over HICS and, later, encryption of the messages
themselves. The added overhead of the cryptographic system further reduced
network capacity.</p>
<p>Retargeting a squadron of Minuteman missiles via the CDB took over 20 hours.
Retargeting a single missile could take 30 minutes.</p>
<p>CDB represented a major step forward in Minuteman C2, particularly with its
real-time messaging capability. Retargeting was still a severely limited
capability, though. </p>
<p>During the 1990s, active Minuteman sites were upgraded to the Rapid Execution
and Combat Targeting System, or REACT. More than just an upgrade for
retargeting, REACT brought a completely new control system that significantly
changed the layout of LCCs. Instead of sitting at opposite ends of the tube,
REACT put the MCCC and DMCCC directly alongside each other and centralized
almost all control functionality onto computer displays.</p>
<p>It also further refined retargeting: retargeting an entire squadron now takes
only ten hours. More radically, though, a single missile can be retargeted in
only a couple of minutes, making it feasible to retarget a missile just before
firing in a limited attack scenario.</p>
<h2>The future of HICS</h2>
<p>While both over budget and behind schedule, the Sentinel program is expected to
replace the Minuteman missiles. Sentinel will likely be an in-place upgrade,
installing new missiles and control systems in the existing Minuteman silos.
It has been clear for decades now that HICS isn't capable of meeting modern
expectations, so Sentinel will include a complete replacement.</p>
<p>Various options including DSL over HICS cables and radio were considered, but
the current plan is to trench new fiber-optic cables across the launch fields.
They're less interesting, but fiber optic cables have both capacity and
reliability advantages over telephone cables, and could easily remain in
service for the life of the Sentinel program.</p>
	</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Intel vs. Samsung vs. TSMC (115 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://semiengineering.com/intel-vs-samsung-vs-tsmc/</link>
            <guid>41019561</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 20:29:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://semiengineering.com/intel-vs-samsung-vs-tsmc/">https://semiengineering.com/intel-vs-samsung-vs-tsmc/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41019561">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

					<p>The three leading-edge foundries — <a href="https://semiengineering.com/entities/intel-corp/">Intel</a>, <a href="https://semiengineering.com/entities/samsung-foundry/">Samsung</a>, and <a href="https://semiengineering.com/entities/tsmc/">TSMC</a> — have started filling in some key pieces in their roadmaps, adding aggressive delivery dates for future generations of chip technology and setting the stage for significant improvements in performance with faster delivery time for custom designs.</p>
<p>Unlike in the past, when a single industry roadmap dictated how to get to the next process node, the three largest foundries increasingly are forging their own paths. They all are heading in the same general direction with 3D transistors and packages, a slew of enabling and expansive technologies, and much larger and more diverse ecosystems. But some key differences are emerging in their methodologies, architectures, and third-party enablement.</p>
<p>Roadmaps for all three show that transistor scaling will continue at least into the 18/16/14 angstrom range, with a possible move from nanosheets and <a href="https://semiengineering.com/knowledge_centers/integrated-circuit/transistors/3d/forksheet-fet/">forksheet FETs</a>, followed by <a href="https://semiengineering.com/knowledge_centers/integrated-circuit/transistors/3d/cfet/">complementary FETs</a> (CFETs) at some point in the future. The key drivers are AI/ML and the explosion of data that needs to be processed, and in most cases these will involve arrays of processing elements, usually with high levels of redundancy and homogeneity, in order to achieve higher yields.</p>
<p>In other cases, these designs may contain dozens or hundreds of <a href="https://semiengineering.com/knowledge_centers/packaging/advanced-packaging/chiplets/">chiplets</a>, some engineered for specific data types and others for more general processing. Those chiplets can be mounted on a substrate in a <a href="https://semiengineering.com/knowledge_centers/packaging/advanced-packaging/2-5d-ic/">2.5D</a> configuration, an approach that has gained traction in data centers because it simplifies the integration of high-bandwidth memory (<a href="https://semiengineering.com/knowledge_centers/memory/volatile-memory/dynamic-random-access-memory/high-bandwidth-memory/">HBM</a>), as well as in mobile devices, which also include other features such as image sensors, power supplies, and additional digital logic used for non-critical functions. All three foundries are working on full <a href="https://semiengineering.com/knowledge_centers/packaging/advanced-packaging/3d-ics/">3D-ICs</a>, as well. And there will be hybrid options available, where logic is stacked on logic and mounted on a substrate, but separated from other features in order to minimize physical effects such as heat — a heterogeneous configuration that has been called both 3.5D and 5.5D.</p>
<p><strong>Rapid and mass customization</strong><br>
One of the biggest changes involves bringing domain-specific designs to market much more quickly than in the past. Mundane as this may sound, it’s a competitive necessity for many leading-edge chips, and it requires fundamental changes in the way chips are designed, manufactured, and packaged. Making this scheme work demands a combination of standards, innovative connectivity schemes, and a mix of engineering disciplines that in the past had limited interactions, if any.</p>
<p>Sometimes referred to as “mass customization,” it includes the usual power, performance, and area/cost (PPA/C) tradeoffs, as well as rapid assembly options. That is the promise of heterogeneous chiplet assemblies, and from a scaling perspective it marks the next phase of <a href="https://semiengineering.com/knowledge_centers/standards-laws/laws/moores-law/">Moore’s Law</a>. The entire semiconductor ecosystem has been laying the groundwork for this shift incrementally for more than a decade.</p>
<p>But getting heterogeneous chiplets — essentially hardened IP from multiple vendors and foundries — to work together is both a necessary and daunting engineering challenge. The first step is connecting the chiplets together in a consistent way to achieve predictable results, and this is where the foundries have spent much of their effort, particularly with the <a href="https://semiengineering.com/knowledge_centers/communications-io/on-chip-communications/universal-chiplet-interconnect-express-ucie/">Universal Chiplet Interconnect Express</a> (UCIe) and <a href="https://semiengineering.com/knowledge_centers/communications-io/on-chip-communications/bunch-of-wires-bow/">Bunch of Wires</a> (BoW) standards. While that connectivity is a critical requirement for all three, it’s also one of the main areas of divergence.</p>
<p>Intel Foundry’s current solution, prior to fully integrated 3D-ICs, is to develop what industry sources describe as “sockets” for chiplets. Instead of characterizing each chiplet for a commercial marketplace, the company defines the specification and the interface so that chiplet vendors can develop these limited-function mini-chips to meet those specs. That addresses one of the big stumbling blocks for a commercial chiplet marketplace. All the pieces need to work together, from data speed to thermal and noise management.</p>
<p>Intel’s scheme relies heavily on its Embedded Multi-Die Interconnect Bridge (EMIB), first introduced in 2014. “The really cool thing about an EMIB base is you can add any amount of chiplets,” said Lalitha Immaneni, vice president of technology development at Intel. “We don’t have a limitation on the number of IPs that we can use in design, and it won’t increase the interposer size, so it’s cost-effective and it’s agnostic of the process. We have given out a package assembly design kit, which is like your traditional PDK for the assembly. We give them the design rules, the reference flows, and we tell them the allowable constructions. It will also give them any collaterals that we need to take it into our assembly.”</p>
<p>Depending upon the design, there can be multiple EMIBs in a package, complemented by thermal interface materials (TIMs), in order to dissipate heat that can become trapped inside a package. TIMs typically are pads that are engineered to conduct heat away from the source, and they are becoming more common as the amount of compute inside a package increases and as the substrates are thinned to shorten the distance signals need to travel.</p>
<p>But the thinner the substrate, the less effective it is at heat dissipation, which can result in thermal gradients that are workload-dependent and therefore difficult to anticipate. Eliminating that heat may require TIMs, additional heat sinks, and potentially even more exotic cooling approaches such as microfluidics.</p>
<p>Both TSMC and Samsung offer bridges, as well. Samsung has embedded bridges inside the RDL — an approach it calls 2.3D or I-Cube ETM — and it’s using them to connect sub-systems to those bridges in order to speed time to working silicon. Instead of relying on a socket approach, some of the integration work will be pre-done in known-good modules.</p>
<p>“Putting together two, four, or eight CPUs into a system is something that very sophisticated customers know how to go out and do,” said <a href="https://semiengineering.com/entities/arm/">Arm</a> CEO Rene Haas, in a keynote speech at a recent Samsung Foundry event. “But if you want to build an SoC that has 128 CPUs attached to a neural network, memory structures, interrupt controllers that interface to an NPU, an off-chip bus to go to another chiplet, that is a lot of work. In the last year and a half, we’ve seen a rush of people building these complex SoCs wanting more from us.”</p>
<p>Samsung also has been building mini-consortia [1] of chiplet providers, targeted at specific markets. The initial concept is that one company builds an I/O die, another builds the interconnect, and a third builds the logic, and when that is proven to work, then others are added into the mix to provide more choices for customers.</p>
<p>TSMC has experimented with a number of different options, including both RDL and non-RDL bridges, fan-outs, 2.5D chip-on-wafer-on-substrate (CoWoS), and System On Integrated Chips (SoIC), a 3D-IC concept in which chiplets are packed and stacked inside a substrate using very short interconnects. In fact, TSMC has a process design kit for just about every application, and it has been active in creating assembly design kits for advanced packaging, including reference designs to go with them.</p>
<p>The challenge is that foundry customers willing to invest in these complex packages increasingly want very customized solutions. To facilitate that, TSMC rolled out a new language called 3Dblox, a top-down design scheme that fuses physical and connectivity constructs, allowing assertions to be applied across both. This sandbox approach allows customers to leverage any of its packaging approaches — InFO, CoWoS, and SoIC. It’s also essential to TSMC’s business model, because the company is the only pure-play foundry of the three [2] — although both Intel and Samsung have distanced their foundry operations in recent months.</p>
<p>“We started from a concept of modularization,” said Jim Chang, vice president of advanced technology and mask engineering at TSMC, in a presentation when 3Dblox was first introduced in 2023. “We can build a full 3D-IC stacking with this kind of language syntax plus assertions.”</p>
<p>Chang said the genesis of this was a lack of consistency between the physical and connectivity design tools. But he added that once this approach was developed, it also enabled reuse of chiplets in different designs because much of the characterization was already well-defined and the designs are modular.</p>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/1.png?resize=780%2C435&amp;ssl=1" alt="" width="780" height="435" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/1.png?w=780&amp;ssl=1 780w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/1.png?resize=300%2C167&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/1.png?resize=768%2C428&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/1.png?resize=600%2C335&amp;ssl=1 600w" sizes="(max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px" data-recalc-dims="1"><br>
<strong>Fig. 1: TSMC’s 3Dblox approach. Source: TSMC</strong></p>
<p>Samsung followed with its own system description language, 3DCODE, in December 2023. Both Samsung and TSMC claim their languages are standards, but they’re more like new foundry rule decks because it’s unlikely these languages will be used outside of their own ecosystems. Intel’s 2.5D approach doesn’t require a new language because the rules are dictated by the socket specification, trading off some customization with a shortened time to market and a simpler approach for chiplet developers.</p>
<p><strong>The chiplet challenge</strong><br>
Chiplets have obvious benefits. They can be designed independently at whatever process node makes sense, which is particularly important for analog features. But figuring out how to put the pieces together with predictable results has been a major challenge. The initial LEGO-like architecture scheme floated by DARPA has proven much more complicated than first envisioned, and it has required a massive and ongoing efforts by broad ecosystems to make it work.</p>
<p>Chiplets need to be precisely synchronized so that critical data is processed, stored, and retrieved without delay. Otherwise, there can be timing issues, in which one computation is either delayed or out-of-sync with other computations, leading to delays and potential deadlocks. In the context of mission- or safety-critical applications, the loss of a fraction of a second can have serious consequences.</p>
<p>Simplifying the design process, particularly with domain-specific designs where one size does not fit all, is an incredibly complex endeavor. The goal for all three foundries is to provide more options for companies that will be developing high-performance, low-power chips. With an estimated 30% to 35% of all leading-edge design starts now in the hands of large systems companies such as Google, Meta, Microsoft, and Tesla, the economics of leading-edge chip and package design have changed significantly, and so have the PPA/C formulas and tradeoffs.</p>
<p>Chips developed for these systems companies probably will not be sold commercially. So if they can achieve higher performance per watt, then the design and manufacturing costs can be offset by lower cooling power and higher utilization rates — and potentially fewer servers. The reverse is true for chips sold into mobile devices and commodity servers, where high development costs can be amortized across huge volumes. The economics for customized designs in advanced packages work for both, but for very different reasons.</p>
<p><strong>Scaling down, up, and out</strong><br>
It’s assumed that within these complex systems of chiplets there will be multiple types of processors, some highly specialized and others more general-purpose. At least some of these will likely be developed at the most advanced process nodes due to limited power budgets. Advanced nodes still provide higher energy efficiency, which allows more transistors to be packed into the same area in order to improve performance. This is critical for AI/ML applications, where processing more data faster requires more multiply/accumulate operations in highly parallel configurations. Smaller transistors provide greater energy efficiency, allowing more processing per square millimeter of silicon, but the gate structure needs to be changed to prevent leakage, which is why forksheet FETs and CFETs are on the horizon.</p>
<p>Put simply, process leadership still has value. Being first to market with a leading-edge process is good for business, but it’s only one piece of a much larger puzzle. All three foundries have announced plans to push well into the angstrom range. Intel plans to introduce its 18A this year, followed by 14A a couple years later.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/2.png?resize=1430%2C635&amp;ssl=1" alt="" width="1430" height="635" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/2.png?w=1430&amp;ssl=1 1430w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/2.png?resize=300%2C133&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/2.png?resize=1024%2C455&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/2.png?resize=768%2C341&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/2.png?resize=600%2C266&amp;ssl=1 600w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" data-recalc-dims="1"><br>
<strong>Fig. 2: Intel’s process roadmap. Source: Intel Foundry</strong></p>
<p>TSMC, meanwhile, will add A16 in 2027 (see figure 3, below.)</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/3.jpg?resize=1430%2C598&amp;ssl=1" alt="" width="1430" height="598" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/3.jpg?w=1430&amp;ssl=1 1430w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/3.jpg?resize=300%2C125&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/3.jpg?resize=1024%2C428&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/3.jpg?resize=768%2C321&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/3.jpg?resize=600%2C251&amp;ssl=1 600w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" data-recalc-dims="1"><br>
<strong>Fig. 3: TSMC’s scaling roadmap into the angstrom era. Source: TSMC</strong></p>
<p>And Samsung will push to 14 angstroms sometime in 2027 with its SF1.4, apparently skipping 18/16 angstroms. (See figure 4)</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/4.jpg?resize=1430%2C809&amp;ssl=1" alt="" width="1430" height="809" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/4.jpg?w=1430&amp;ssl=1 1430w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/4.jpg?resize=300%2C170&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/4.jpg?resize=1024%2C579&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/4.jpg?resize=768%2C434&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/4.jpg?resize=600%2C339&amp;ssl=1 600w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" data-recalc-dims="1"><br>
<strong>Fig. 4: Samsung’s process scaling roadmap. Source: Samsung Foundry</strong></p>
<p>From a process node standpoint, all three foundries are on the same track. But advances are no longer tied to the process node alone. The focus increasingly is about latency and performance per watt in a specific domain, and this is where stacking logic-on-logic in a true 3D-IC configuration will excel, using hybrid bonds to connect chiplets to a substrate and each other. Moving electrons through a wire on a planar die is still the fastest (assuming a signal doesn’t have to travel from one end of the die to another), but stacking transistors on top of other transistors is the next best thing, and in some cases even better than a planar SoC because some vertical signal paths may be shorter.</p>
<p>In a recent presentation, Taejoong Song, Samsung Foundry’s vice president of foundry business development, showed a roadmap featuring logic-on-logic mounted on a substrate, combining a 2nm (SF2) die on top of a 4nm (SF4X) die, both mounted on top of another substrate. This is basically a 3D-IC on a 2.5D package, which is the 3.5D or 5.5D concept mentioned earlier. Song said the foundry will begin stacking an SF1.4 on top of SF2P, starting in 2027. What’s particularly attractive about this approach are the thermal dissipation possibilities. With the logic separated from other functions, heat can be channeled away from the stacked dies through the substrate or any of the five exposed sides.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/5.png?resize=1430%2C381&amp;ssl=1" alt="" width="1430" height="381" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/5.png?w=1430&amp;ssl=1 1430w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/5.png?resize=300%2C80&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/5.png?resize=1024%2C273&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/5.png?resize=768%2C205&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/5.png?resize=600%2C160&amp;ssl=1 600w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" data-recalc-dims="1"><br>
<strong>Fig. 5: Samsung’s 3D-IC architecture for AI. Source: Samsung</strong></p>
<p>Intel, meanwhile, will leverage its Foveros Direct 3D to stack logic on logic, either face-to-face or face-to-back. The approach allows chips or wafers from different foundries, with the connection bandwidth determined by the copper via pitch, according to a new Intel white paper. The paper noted that the first version would use a copper pitch of 9µm, while the second generation would use a 3µm pitch.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/6.png?resize=936%2C402&amp;ssl=1" alt="" width="936" height="402" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/6.png?w=936&amp;ssl=1 936w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/6.png?resize=300%2C129&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/6.png?resize=768%2C330&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/6.png?resize=600%2C258&amp;ssl=1 600w" sizes="(max-width: 936px) 100vw, 936px" data-recalc-dims="1"><br>
<strong>Fig. 6: Intel’s Foveros Direct 3D. Source: Intel</strong></p>
<p>“The true 3D-IC comes with Foveros, and then also with hybrid bonds,” said Intel’s Immaneni. “You cannot go in the tradition route of design where you put it together and run validation, and then find, ‘Oops, I have an issue.’ You cannot afford to do this anymore because you’re impacting your time to market. So you really want to provide a sandbox to make it predictable. But even before I step into this detailed design environment, I want to run my mechanical/electrical/thermal analysis. I want to look at the connectivity so I don’t have opens and shorts. The burden for 3D-IC resides more in the code design than the execution.”</p>
<p>Foveros allows an active logic die to be stacked on either another active or passive die, with the base die used to connect all the die in a package at a 36 micron pitch. By leveraging advanced sort, Intel claims it can guarantee 99% known good die, and 97% yield at post-assembly test.</p>
<p>TSMC’s CoWoS, meanwhile, already is in use by NVIDIA and AMD for their advanced packaging for AI chips. CoWoS is essentially a 2.5D approach, using an interposer to connect SoCs and HBM memory using through-silicon vias. The company’s plans for SoIC are more ambitious, packaging both memory on logic along with other elements, such as sensors, in a 3D-IC at the front end of the line. This can significantly reduce assembly time of multiple layers, sizes, and functions. TSMC contends that its bonding scheme enables faster and shorter connections than other 3D-IC approaches. One report said Apple will begin using TSMC’s SoIC technology starting next year, while AMD will expand its use of this approach.</p>
<p><strong>Other innovations</strong><br>
Putting the process and packaging technology in place opens the door to a much broader set of competitive options. Unlike in the past, when big chipmakers, equipment vendors, and EDA companies defined the roadmap for chips, the chiplet world provides the tools for end customers to make those decisions. This is due, in no small part, to the number of features that can be put into a package versus those that can fit inside the reticle limits of an SoC. Packages can be expanded horizontally or vertically, as needed, and in some cases they can improve performance just through vertical floor-planning.</p>
<p>But given the vast opportunity in the cloud and the edge — particularly with the rollout of AI everywhere — the three big foundries, as well as their ecosystems, are racing to developing new capabilities and features. In some cases, this involves leveraging what they already have. In other cases, it requires brand new technologies.</p>
<p>For example, Samsung has started detailing plans about custom HBM, which includes 3D DRAM stacks with a configurable logic layer underneath. This is the second time around for this approach. Back in 2011, Samsung and Micron co-developed the Hybrid Memory Cube, packaging a DRAM stack on a layer of logic. HBM won the war after JEDEC turned it into a standard, and HMC largely disappeared. But there was nothing wrong with the HMC approach, other than perhaps bad timing.</p>
<p>In its new form, Samsung plans to offer customized HBM as an option. Memory is one of the key elements that determine performance, and the ability to read/write and move data back and forth more quickly between memory and processors can have a big impact on performance and power. And those numbers can be significantly better if the memory is right-sized to a specific workload or data type, and if some of the processing can be done inside the memory module so there is less data to move.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/7.png?resize=1145%2C583&amp;ssl=1" alt="" width="1145" height="583" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/7.png?w=1145&amp;ssl=1 1145w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/7.png?resize=300%2C153&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/7.png?resize=1024%2C521&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/7.png?resize=768%2C391&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/semiengineering.com/wp-content/uploads/7.png?resize=600%2C306&amp;ssl=1 600w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" data-recalc-dims="1"><br>
<strong>Fig. 7: Samsung roadmap and innovations. Source: Semiconductor Engineering/MemCon 2024</strong></p>
<p>Intel, meanwhile, has been working on a better way to deliver power to densely packed transistors, a persistent problem as the transistor density and number of metal layers increases. In the past, power was delivered from the top of the chip down, but two problems have emerged at the most advanced nodes. One is the challenge of actually delivering enough power to every transistor. The second is noise, which can come from power, substrates, or electromagnetic interference. Without proper shielding — something that is becoming more difficult at each new node due to thinner dielectrics and wires — that noise can impact signal integrity.</p>
<p>Delivering power through the backside of a chip minimizes those kinds of issues and reduces wiring congestion. But it also adds other challenges, such as how to drill holes through a thinner substrate without structural damage. Intel apparently has solved these issues, with plans to offer its PowerVia backside power scheme this year.</p>
<p>TSMC said it plans to deliver backside power delivery at A16 in 2026/2027. Samsung is roughly on the same schedule, delivering it in the SF2Z 2nm process.</p>
<p>Intel also has announced plans for glass substrates, which can provide better planarity and lower defectivity than CMOS. This is especially important at advanced nodes, where even nano-sized pits can cause issues. As with backside power delivery, handling issues abound. The upside is that glass has the same coefficient of thermal expansion as silicon, so it is compatible with the expansion and contraction of silicon components, such as chiplets. After years of sitting on the sidelines, glass is suddenly very attractive. In fact, both TSMC and Samsung are working on glass substrates, as well, and the whole industry is starting to design with glass, handle it without cracking it, and to inspect it.</p>
<p>TSMC, meanwhile, has focused heavily on building an ecosystem and expanding its process offerings. Numerous industry sources say TSMC’s real strength is the ability to deliver process development kits for just about any process or package. The foundry produces about 90% of the most advanced chips globally, according to Nikkei. It also has the most experience with advanced packaging of any foundry, and the largest and broadest ecosystem, which is important.</p>
<p>That ecosystem is critical. The chip industry is so complex and varied that no single company can do everything. The question going forward will be how complete those ecosystems truly are, particularly if the number of processes continues to grow. For example, EDA vendors are essential enablers, and for any process or packaging approach to be successful, design teams need automation. But the more processes and packaging options, the more difficult it will be for EDA vendors to support every incremental change or improvement, and potentially the greater the lag time between announcement and delivery.</p>
<p><strong>Conclusion</strong><br>
The recent supply chain glitches and geopolitics have convinced the United States and Europe that they need to re-shore and “friend-shore” manufacturing. The investments in semiconductor fabs, equipment, tools, and research are unprecedented. How that affects the three largest foundries remains to be seen, but it certainly is providing some of the impetus behind new technologies such as co-packaged optics, a raft of new materials, and cryogenic computing.</p>
<p>The impact of all of these changes on market share is becoming harder to track. It’s no longer about which foundry is producing chips at the smallest process node, or even the number of chips being shipped. A single advanced package may have dozens of chiplets. The real key is the ability to deliver solutions that matter to customers, quickly and efficiently. In some cases the driver will be performance per watt, while in others it may be time to results with power as a secondary consideration. And in still others, it may be a combination of features that only one of the leading-edge foundries can provide in sufficient quantity. But what is clear is that the foundry race is significantly more complex than ever before, and becoming more so. In this highly complex world, simple metrics for comparison no longer apply.</p>
<p><strong>References</strong><br>
1. <a href="https://semiengineering.com/mini-consortia-forming-around-chiplets/">Mini-Consortia Forming Around Chiplets</a>, March 20, 2023; E. Sperling/Semiconductor Engineering<br>
2. TSMC also is the largest shareholder (35%) in Global Unichip Corp., a design services company.</p>

					<br>

				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Global IT outage shows dangers of cashless society, campaigners say (149 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/technology/article/2024/jul/20/cash-global-it-outage-cashless-society-dangers-payment-choice-alliance</link>
            <guid>41018726</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 18:52:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/article/2024/jul/20/cash-global-it-outage-cashless-society-dangers-payment-choice-alliance">https://www.theguardian.com/technology/article/2024/jul/20/cash-global-it-outage-cashless-society-dangers-payment-choice-alliance</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41018726">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p>Campaigners say the chaos caused by the global IT outage last week underlines the risk of moving towards a cashless society.</p><p>Supermarkets, banks, pubs, cafes, train stations and airports were all hit by the failure of <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/microsoft" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">Microsoft</a> systems on Friday, leaving many unable to accept electronic payments. The impact was especially severe for businesses that no longer accept cash.</p><p>The Payment Choice Alliance (PCA), which campaigns against the move towards a cashless society, lists 23 firms and groups, at least some of whose outlets take only credit or debit cards.</p><p>“There will always be outages,” said Ron Delnevo, the PCA’s chair. “But if there is no alternative, then the whole thing can collapse around you.”</p><p>Cash payments increased for the first time in a decade last year, according to UK Finance, which represents banks. The number of people who never use cash, or use it less than once a month, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2023/sep/14/cash-payments-rise-in-uk-as-people-seek-ways-to-manage-budgets" data-link-name="in body link">reached 23.1m</a> in 2021, but declined to 21.6m last year.</p><p>UK Finance said there was “definitely still a place” for cash. “It’s up to individual businesses, but we think it’s good to give people a choice. Most businesses still do offer cash.”</p><p>The <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/gmb-union" data-link-name="in body link">GMB Union</a> said the outage reinforced what it had been saying for years: that “cash is a vital part of how our communities operate”. “When you take cash out of the system, people have nothing to fall back on, impacting on how they do the everyday basics.”</p><figure data-spacefinder-role="inline" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.NewsletterSignupBlockElement"><a data-ignore="global-link-styling" href="#EmailSignup-skip-link-7">skip past newsletter promotion</a><p id="EmailSignup-skip-link-7" tabindex="0" aria-label="after newsletter promotion" role="note">after newsletter promotion</p></figure><figure id="c4728897-74c3-4df7-aaec-41771abd2952" data-spacefinder-role="supporting" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-2"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=380&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 1300px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1300px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=380&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 1300px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=300&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 980px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 980px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=300&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 980px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="debit cards" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" width="445" height="556.0493084786531" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption data-spacefinder-role="inline"><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>In March big retailers suffered problems with their payment systems.</span> Photograph: Andrew Matthews/PA</figcaption></figure><p>Several smaller, unrelated outages had already affected retailers this year. In March, McDonald’s, Tesco, Sainsbury’s and Gregg’s <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2024/mar/16/sainsburys-grocery-deliveries-hit-by-technical-issue" data-link-name="in body link">suffered</a> problems with their payment systems. All of the outlets also accept cash.</p><p>Authorities in China and the US have fined businesses for not accepting cash. Delnevo said the UK should have a law requiring all businesses to take cash.</p><p>Martin Quinn, campaign director for the PCA, said using cash allowed for anonymity. “I don’t want my data sold on, and I don’t want banks, credit card companies and even online retailers to know every facet of my life,” he said. Budgeting by using cash is also easier for some, he added.</p><p>“If I go out for a night and decide to spend £50, then I might wake up with a bit of shrapnel in my pockets. But if I’m in the pub and I’m just going tap, tap, tap, then the next morning I’ll wake up and find I’ve gone into my overdraft.”</p><p>Link said that, overall, its cash machines were at normal levels, but busier around supermarkets.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Linux kernel syscall implementation tracker (278 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://syscalls.mebeim.net/?table=x86/64/x64/latest</link>
            <guid>41018135</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 17:34:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://syscalls.mebeim.net/?table=x86/64/x64/latest">https://syscalls.mebeim.net/?table=x86/64/x64/latest</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41018135">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section id="container">
			<h2>Architecture:  Kernel&nbsp;version: </h2>
			<h3>
				Powered by <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/mebeim/systrack" title="Systrack on GitHub">Systrack</a> v<span id="systrack-version"></span>
				<span>[<a id="json-link" target="_blank" href="" title="See this syscall table in JSON format">JSON&nbsp;table</a>]</span>
				<span>[<a id="config-link" target="_blank" href="" title="Configuration to build a kernel with the same syscalls in this table">kernel&nbsp;config</a>]</span>
				<span>[<a id="stderr-link" target="_blank" href="" title="Systrack analysis log">analysis&nbsp;log</a>]</span>
				<span>[<a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/mebeim/linux-syscalls" title="Source code for this website on GitHub">website&nbsp;source</a>]</span>
			</h3>
			<table>
				<tbody><tr>
					<th colspan="6"></th>
					<th data-column="signature"><span title="Click to expand/collapse"></span><span> Signature <span id="compact-sig-toggle" title="Click to toggle between compact C-style and extended multi-column arguments"></span></span></th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<th colspan="2" title="Click to sort by this column">Number</th>
					<th data-column="name" title="Click to sort by this column"><span title="Click to expand/collapse"></span><span> Name</span></th>
					<th data-column="symbol" title="Click to sort by this column"><span title="Click to expand/collapse"></span><span> Symbol</span></th>
					<th data-column="location" title="Click to sort by this column"><span title="Click to expand/collapse"></span><span> Definition location</span></th>
					<th data-column="kconfig" title="Click to sort by this column"><span title="Click to expand/collapse"></span><span> Kconfig</span></th>
				</tr>
			</tbody></table>
			
		</section><p>Copyright © 2023-2024 Marco Bonelli — Licensed under the GNU General Public License v3.0</p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[CrowdStrike broke Debian and Rocky Linux months ago, but no one noticed (269 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.neowin.net/news/crowdstrike-broke-debian-and-rocky-linux-months-ago-but-no-one-noticed/</link>
            <guid>41018029</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 17:21:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.neowin.net/news/crowdstrike-broke-debian-and-rocky-linux-months-ago-but-no-one-noticed/">https://www.neowin.net/news/crowdstrike-broke-debian-and-rocky-linux-months-ago-but-no-one-noticed/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41018029">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                                                    <span>When you purchase through links on our site, we may earn an affiliate commission. <a href="https://www.neowin.net/terms">Here’s how it works</a>.</span>
                        
                        
                        <p>
    
    <time datetime="Jul 19, 2024 17:14 EDT" pubdate="pubdate">
    Jul 19, 2024 17:14 EDT
    </time>
         · <span>Hot!</span>    
    
    
    </p>

                    </div><div itemprop="articleBody">
                                                                        <figure><a href="https://cdn.neowin.com/news/images/uploaded/2024/07/1721412936_crowdstrike_linux.jpg"><img alt="crowdstrike" src="https://cdn.neowin.com/news/images/uploaded/2024/07/1721412936_crowdstrike_linux_story.jpg"></a></figure><p>A widespread <a href="https://www.neowin.net/news/the-crowdstrike-windows-outage-continues-to-affect-tons-of-critical-businesses-worldwide/">Blue Screen of Death (BSOD) issue on Windows PCs</a> disrupted operations across various sectors, notably impacting airlines, banks, and healthcare providers. The issue was caused by a problematic channel file delivered via an update from the popular cybersecurity service provider, CrowdStrike. CrowdStrike confirmed that this crash did not impact Mac or Linux PCs.</p>

<p>It turns out that similar problems have been occurring for months without much awareness, despite the fact that many may view this as an isolated incident. Users of Debian and Rocky Linux also experienced significant disruptions as a result of CrowdStrike updates, raising serious concerns about the company's software update and testing procedures. These occurrences highlight potential risks for customers who rely on their products daily.</p>

<p>In April, a CrowdStrike update caused all Debian Linux servers in a civic tech lab to crash simultaneously and refuse to boot. The update proved incompatible with the latest stable version of Debian, despite the specific Linux configuration being supposedly supported. The lab's IT team discovered that removing CrowdStrike allowed the machines to boot and reported the incident.</p>

                            <!-- PLACE THIS SECTION INSIDE OF YOUR BODY WHERE YOU WANT THE VIDEO PLAYER TO RENDER -->
            <p>A team member involved in the incident expressed dissatisfaction with CrowdStrike's delayed response. It took them weeks to provide a root cause analysis after acknowledging the issue a day later. The analysis revealed that the Debian Linux configuration was not included in their test matrix.</p>

<p>"Crowdstrike's model seems to be 'we push software to your machines any time we want, whether or not it's urgent, without testing it'," lamented the team member.</p>

<p>This was not an isolated incident. CrowdStrike users also reported similar issues after upgrading to RockyLinux 9.4, with their servers crashing due to a kernel bug. Crowdstrike support acknowledged the issue, highlighting a pattern of inadequate testing and insufficient attention to compatibility issues across different operating systems.</p>

<p>To avoid such issues in the future, CrowdStrike should prioritize rigorous testing across all supported configurations. Additionally, organizations should approach CrowdStrike updates with caution and have contingency plans in place to mitigate potential disruptions.</p>

<p>Source: <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41005936">Ycombinator</a>, <a href="https://forums.rockylinux.org/t/crowdstrike-freezing-rockylinux-after-9-4-upgrade/14041">RockyLinux</a></p>
                        
                        
                                                                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A brief interview with Tcl creator John Ousterhout (2023) (140 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://pldb.io/blog/JohnOusterhout.html</link>
            <guid>41017367</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 15:56:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://pldb.io/blog/JohnOusterhout.html">https://pldb.io/blog/JohnOusterhout.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41017367">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p><span>February 8, 2023 — </span><a href="https://web.stanford.edu/~ouster/cgi-bin/home.php">Dr. John Ousterhout</a> is a computer science luminary who has made significant contributions to the field of computer science, particularly in the areas of operating systems and file systems. He is the creator of the <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/tcl.html">Tcl</a> scripting language, and has also worked on several major software projects, including the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Log-structured_file_system">Log-Structured file system</a> and the <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/sprite-os.html">Sprite operating system</a>. John Ousterhout's creation of Tcl has had a lasting impact on the technology industry, transforming the way developers think about scripting and automation.</p>
<p><span>*</span></p>
<div><h4>What is unique about Tcl?</h4>
<p><strong>Dr. Ousterhout:</strong> I would highlight 2 things:</p>
</div>
<p>The first thing is its embeddable nature: I designed Tcl so that the library could be embedded in applications, with Tcl providing generic scripting features and the application adding its own commands to the built-in command set. The boundary between Tcl and the application is extremely fluid, and applications can extend Tcl in very powerful ways, such as adding new control structures to the  language. I don't think any other scripting language has achieved embeddability to the degree that Tcl did.</p>
<p>The second thing is Tcl's "everything is a string" philosophy. This played a big role in Tcl's embeddability and made it easy to extend Tcl in a variety of ways. But, it also carried a performance penalty; even with a lot of work, Tcl has never become as efficient as other languages with more traditional types, such as <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/python.html">Python</a>. The string focus is also responsible for Tcl's unusual command syntax, which some people love and some people hate.</p>
<p><span>*</span></p>
<p><h4>How different would Tcl be had you stayed on with the development team? :)</h4>
</p>
<p><strong>Dr. Ousterhout:</strong> I don't think it would have been very different. Tcl was quite mature by the time I passed off development responsibility. Tcl had its heyday in the 1990's, due in large part to the power of the <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/tk.html">Tk toolkit</a> and the awfulness of the other X Window GUI toolkits; Tcl/Tk was the easiest and most powerful way to create GUI apps. Unfortunately, Tcl didn't make the jump to the Web, and most of the applications for which people would have used Tcl in the 1990s became Web applications.</p>
<p>Interesting footnote: the founding of Netscape occurred at the same time I was deciding where to go in industry when I left Berkeley in 1994. Jim Clarke and Marc Andreessen approached me about the possibility of my joining Netscape as a founder, but I eventually decided against it (they hadn't yet decided to do Web stuff when I talked with them). This is one of the biggest "what if" moments of my career. If I had gone to Netscape, I think there's a good chance that Tcl would have become the browser language instead of <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/javascript.html">JavaScript</a> and the world would be a different place! However, in retrospect I'm not sure that Tcl would actually be a better language for the Web than JavaScript, so maybe the right thing happened.</p>
<p><span>*</span></p>
<p><h4>As a long time educator, what do you predict the next paradigm shift in programming languages will be?</h4>
</p>
<p><strong>Dr. Ousterhout:</strong> I don't really know. It used to be that every 5-10 years a major new language came along, but it's been almost 20 or years since the last interesting new language I can think of (<a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/go.html">Go</a>). Maybe others would count <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/rust.html">Rust</a>, in which case maybe the 5-10 year interval is still holding.</p>
<p>One interesting note on this. Historically, I think the most widely used programming linkages have come not from the programming language research committee, but rather from people who build systems and wanted a language to help themselves. PL researchers tend to create languages that are useful for PL researchers: they have interesting theoretical and conceptual properties (e.g., <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/ml.html">ML</a>) but aren't usually useful for real systems. Systems people create languages that are useful for systems builders, so they get widely adopted. Examples are <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/c.html">C</a>, <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/cpp.html">C++</a> (I think?), <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/perl.html">Perl</a>, <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/java.html">Java</a>, and <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/go.html">Go</a>. I would put <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/tcl.html">Tcl</a> in this category as well, and perhaps <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/python.html">Python</a> also?</p>
<p><span>⁂</span></p>
<figure><a href="https://pldb.io/blog/images/JohnO.jpg" target="_blank"><img src="https://pldb.io/blog/images/JohnO.jpg" width="1638" height="1068" loading="lazy"></a><figcaption><p><a href="https://www.facesofopensource.com/">Image source</a>. Thank you for your time Dr. Ousterhout!</p></figcaption></figure>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[CrowdStrike debacle provides road map of American vulnerabilities to adversaries (256 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/2024/07/19/us/politics/crowdstrike-outage.html</link>
            <guid>41017077</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 15:18:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/07/19/us/politics/crowdstrike-outage.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2024/07/19/us/politics/crowdstrike-outage.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41017077">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nytimes.com/2024/07/19/us/politics/crowdstrike-outage.html: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Siblings miss crucial life-extending treatment because of CrowdStrike outage (139 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.kiro7.com/news/local/siblings-miss-crucial-life-extending-treatment-seattle-childrens-because-crowdstrike-outage/Y5EMEXGGQJE7PHDEAEKCWG6U4M/</link>
            <guid>41016987</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 15:06:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.kiro7.com/news/local/siblings-miss-crucial-life-extending-treatment-seattle-childrens-because-crowdstrike-outage/Y5EMEXGGQJE7PHDEAEKCWG6U4M/">https://www.kiro7.com/news/local/siblings-miss-crucial-life-extending-treatment-seattle-childrens-because-crowdstrike-outage/Y5EMEXGGQJE7PHDEAEKCWG6U4M/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41016987">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div role="main" id="fusion-app" tabindex="-1"><br>
<center>
<h2>We’re Sorry!</h2>
<p>This website is unavailable in your location.&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Error 451</h2>
<p>It appears you are attempting to access this website from a country outside of the United States, therefore access cannot be granted at this time.</p>
</center></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to pwn a billion dollar VC firm using inspect element (524 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.kibty.town/blog/a16z/</link>
            <guid>41016768</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 14:33:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.kibty.town/blog/a16z/">https://www.kibty.town/blog/a16z/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41016768">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><div><h2>background</h2>
<p>i like to do this thing where i search twitter, looking for companies, and then try giving them a quick pentest. i've done a lot of my hacks this way and its more effective than you think it is.</p>
<p>on this search, i use the "Relevant People" tab more often than you think, this is how i got to a16z</p>
<ul>
<li>crypto bullshit -&gt; venture capital firms for crypto -&gt; a16z crypto -&gt; a16z</li>
</ul>
<h2>the hack</h2>
<p>while looking into a16z, i did a usual subdomain scan and used tooling from <a href="https://lunchcat.dev/">lunchcat</a> which does common checks on domains, scanning for secrets in js files, etc.</p>
<p>in this search, i came across <code>portfolio.a16z.com</code>, a site that seems like a portfolio management tool for companies that are in a16z. while doing cursory checks like i usually do, lunchcat seemed to catch a AWS key referenced somewhere in the website.</p>
<p>i confirmed this and what i saw in the js, was this.</p>
<pre><code>{
    <span>MARKETPLACE_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>DATABASE_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SALESFORCE_CLIENT_ID</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SALESFORCE_SECURITY_TOKEN</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>npm_config_user_agent</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SALESFORCE_CLIENT_SECRET</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SALESFORCE_USERNAME</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>OKTA_CLIENT_ID</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>OKTA_CLIENT_SECRET</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SESSION_SECRET</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>API_USERNAME</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>GOOGLE_CLIENT_ID_DEVELOPMENT</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>CLIENT_TOKEN_SECRET</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>GOOGLE_CLIENT_SECRET_DEVELOPMENT</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>AWS_BUCKET_NAME</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>npm_config_prefix</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>REACT_APP_SENTRY_DSN</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>AWS_BUCKET_TEAM_PAGES</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>MAILGUN_API_KEY</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>GOOGLE_CLIENT_ID</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>AWS_LOGO_BUCKET_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SALESFORCE_KEY</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>GOOGLE_CLIENT_SECRET</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>PAPERTRAIL_API_TOKEN</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>MAILGUN_PASSWORD</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>OKTA_CALLBACK_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SALESFORCE_PASSWORD</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>MAILGUN_USER</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>PNPM_CONFIG_CACHE</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>MAILGUN_DOMAIN</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>GOOGLE_CALLBACK_URL_DEVELOPMENT</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>API_PASSWORD</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SENTRY_DSN</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SALESFORCE_LOGIN_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>COOKIE_SECRET</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>OKTA_DOMAIN</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>NODE_MODULES_CACHE</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>GOOGLE_CALLBACK_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,,
    <span>NODE_ENV</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>HEROKU_POSTGRESQL_CRIMSON_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>TALENTPLACE_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
}
</code></pre>
<p>this was. horrifying, it was the entire <code>process.env</code> of a heroku instance, in the JS. put in dynamically.</p>
<p>i did a quick valid look of the credentials and they didnt seem like fake credentials. they. were. real. and all someone had to do find them was go to the sources tab of inspect element.</p>
<h2>impact</h2>
<p>the compromised list of services:</p>
<ul>
<li>their database (containing PII)</li>
<li>their AWS</li>
<li>their salesforce (never checked, account may be limited)</li>
<li>mailgun (arbitrary emails from a16z domains, and also could read older emails)</li>
<li>... and probably more</li>
</ul>
<h2>reward</h2>
<p>a16z did not give me any bug bounty on this because of the fact i publicly reached out instead of trying to reach out privately. the only reason i did it this way was because:</p>
<ul>
<li>there was no available contact on their main site</li>
<li>the email i could find <code>engineering@a16z.com</code> bounced my emails</li>
</ul>
<p>so, i dunno. imo this is unfair.</p>
<h2>related</h2>
<p>techcrunch article (lorenzo reached out to me seeing my tweet trying to get in contact with them and wrote a piece!): https://techcrunch.com/2024/07/18/researcher-finds-flaw-in-a16z-website-that-exposed-some-company-data/</p>
</div></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to choose a textbook that is optimal for oneself? (201 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://matheducators.stackexchange.com/questions/27964/how-to-choose-a-textbook-that-is-pedagogically-optimal-for-oneself</link>
            <guid>41016650</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 14:13:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://matheducators.stackexchange.com/questions/27964/how-to-choose-a-textbook-that-is-pedagogically-optimal-for-oneself">https://matheducators.stackexchange.com/questions/27964/how-to-choose-a-textbook-that-is-pedagogically-optimal-for-oneself</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41016650">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="text">
<p><strong>Do you agree with my point that problems that are too hard is not the optimal way of learning and teaching?</strong></p>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p>A lot of people fall into the trap of thinking that to train up their math skills, they should be focusing on the hardest problem types where they think really hard, struggle for a while, and eventually solve it or look up the answer. These problems can be fun (for a certain type of person) but they're not an efficient way to learn.</p>
<p>Approaching challenging problems without having the foundational skills down pat is like jumping into a game of basketball without having developed dribbling and shooting skills. It might feel fun but you're just going to be whiffing every shot and getting the ball stolen from you. You might make one layup the entire game &amp; feel good about it, but that's barely any training volume.</p>
<p>It’s like going to the gym to lift weights but only eeking out a single rep over the entire course of your workout. You need to be banging out more reps if you want to get stronger, and the only way you can bang out those reps is by working with a level of weight that's appropriate for you.</p>
<p>Math is the same way. In an hour-long session, you're going to make a lot more progress by solving 30 problems that each take 2 minutes given your current level of knowledge, than by attempting a single competition problem that you struggle with for an hour. (This assumes those 30 problems are grouped into minimal effective doses, well-scaffolded &amp; increasing in difficulty, across a variety of topics at the edge of your knowledge.)</p>
<p>Now, I'm not saying that challenge problems are bad. I'm just saying that they're not a good use of time until you've developed the foundational skills that are necessary to grapple with these problems in a productive and timely fashion.</p>
<p><em>Some References</em></p>
<p>I should point out that while I've made heavy use of analogies here, this is all grounded in decades of research into the cognitive science of learning.</p>
<p>One key empirical result is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expertise_reversal_effect" rel="nofollow noreferrer">expertise reversal effect</a>, a well-replicated phenomenon that instructional techniques that promote the most learning in experts, promote the least learning in beginners, and vice versa. It's true that many highly skilled professionals spend a lot of time solving open-ended problems, and in the process, discovering new knowledge as opposed to obtaining it through direct instruction. But that doesn't mean beginners should do the same. The expertise reversal effect suggests the opposite – that beginners (i.e., students) learn most effectively through direct instruction.</p>
<p>Additionally (and relatedly), there's a mountain of empirical evidence that you can increase the number of examples &amp; problem-solving experiences in a student's knowledge base – but a lack of evidence that you can increase the student’s ability to generalize from those examples (by doing things other than equipping them with progressively more advanced examples &amp; problem-solving experiences).</p>
<p>In other words, research indicates the best way to improve your problem-solving ability in any domain is simply by acquiring more foundational skills in that domain. The way you increase your ability to make mental leaps is not by learning to jump further, but by building bridges.</p>
<p>So, there does not seem to be any tangible, empirically-supported reason to struggle with a challenge problem for a long period of time, when you consider that you could be making more educational progress using that time to learn more content. For instance, in an hour-long session, you're going to make a lot more progress by solving 30 problems that each take 2 minutes given your current level of knowledge, than by attempting a single competition problem that you struggle with for an hour. (This assumes those 30 problems are grouped into minimal effective doses, well-scaffolded &amp; increasing in difficulty, across a variety of topics at the edge of your knowledge.)</p>
<p><em>(Note: When I say "2 minute problems" I don't mean that as a hard cap. I just mean that you come into the problem with enough background knowledge that you can work 100% productively to complete it in a minimal amount of time. For low-level high school math courses, the minimal amount of time might be lower for many problems, like 1 minute or less. For more theoretical courses in late undergrad, the minimal amount of time might rise to, say, 5-10 minutes for some problems. But I can't imagine a scenario in which a student spends a full hour on a non-research problem while working productively the whole time, unless the solution itself is commensurately long -- e.g., the solution requires writing a chunk of code to implement an algorithm, or there's a proof that requires many cases/sub-proofs, or there are otherwise many different parts to the problem that require solving.)</em></p>
<p>As Sweller, Clark, and Kirschner sum it up in their 2010 article <a href="https://ams.org/notices/201010/rtx101001303p.pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Teaching General Problem-Solving Skills Is Not a Substitute for, or a Viable Addition to, Teaching Mathematics</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Although some mathematicians, in the absence of adequate instruction, may have learned to solve mathematics problems by discovering solutions without explicit guidance, this approach was never the most effective or efficient way to learn mathematics. ... In short, the research suggests that we can teach aspiring mathematicians to be effective problem solvers only by providing them with a large store of domain-specific schemas. Mathematical problem-solving skill is acquired through a large number of specific mathematical problem-solving strategies relevant to particular problems. There are no separate, general problem-solving strategies that can be learned."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Another good reference is <a href="https://aft.org/sites/default/files/Clark.pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Putting Students on the Path to Learning: The Case for Fully Guided Instruction</a> by the same authors in 2012. (It's like an expanded version of the 2010 article.)</p>
<p><strong>What is in your opinion the most pedagogically sound way of writing a textbook? And most importantly, how can you choose a textbook that is pedagogically optimal for oneself?</strong></p>
<p>I don't have a long checklist of highly-specific things to do or look for, but I can tell you the underlying principle that it all boils down to: <em>deliberate practice.</em></p>
<p>In the field of talent development, there is absolutely no debate about the most superior form of training. It's <em>deliberate practice</em>: mindful repetition on performance tasks just beyond the edge of one's capabilities.</p>
<p>Deliberate practice is about making performance-improving adjustments on every single repetition. Any individual adjustment is small and yields a small improvement in performance – but when you compound these small changes over a massive number of action-feedback-adjustment cycles, you end up with massive changes and massive gains in performance.</p>
<p>Deliberate practice is superior to all other forms of training. That is a "solved problem" in the academic field of talent development. It might as well be a law of physics. There is a mountain of research supporting the conclusion that the volume of accumulated deliberate practice is the single biggest factor responsible for individual differences in performance among elite performers across a wide variety of talent domains. (The next biggest factor is genetics, and the relative contributions of deliberate practice vs genetics can can vary significantly across talent domains.)</p>
<p><em>So, how can you write or find a textbook that implements deliberate practice?</em></p>
<p>What you need to do is avoid the two failure modes -- that is, cutting corners on either of the two key attributes of deliberate practice ("mindful" and "repetition").</p>
<p>Deliberate practice is not mindless repetition. If you're doing the same thing over and over again, then you're doing deliberate practice wrong. Deliberate practice is about making performance-improving adjustments on every single repetition. Any individual adjustment is small and yields a small improvement in performance, but when you compound these small changes over a massive number of cycles, you end up with massive changes and massive gains in performance. None of this happens if you're mindlessly doing the same thing over and over again without making adjustments.</p>
<p>Likewise, even if you're mindful during practice, you can't skimp on repetition and still call it "deliberate practice." Deliberate practice necessitates a high volume of action-feedback-adjustment cycles in every single training session. Otherwise, the compounding doesn't happen. Any activity that throttles the number of these cycles cannot be described as deliberate practice.</p>
<p>Many heated debates in math education stem from these misinterpretations of deliberate practice. Mindless repetition, doing the same thing over and over again without making performance-improving adjustments, is not deliberate practice. Likewise, any activity that throttles the volume of action-feedback-adjustment cycles (e.g., excessively challenging problems, or think-pair-share type of stuff) is not deliberate practice.</p>
<p><strong>Addendum 1: Worked examples are needed</strong></p>
<p>Math gets hard for different students at different levels – it can be as early as high school algebra or as late as graduate-level algebraic topology – but everyone eventually reaches a level where things no longer feel obvious and they can't figure things out as quickly on the fly. If you're not yet at the edge of human knowledge, that's where worked examples and instructional scaffolding come in to keep you making fast progress.</p>
<p>Without worked examples, learners eventually reach a point where unguided problem-solving overwhelms their working memory and puts them in a state of cognitive overload. They feel frustrated, confused, and are unable to solve problems. And even before that point, even if a student is able to solve problems successfully without worked examples, it typically takes a lot longer, which throttles the volume of practice.</p>
<p>If you don't have worked examples and instructional scaffolding to help carry you through once math becomes hard for you, then every problem basically blows up into a research project for you. That's okay if you're a research mathematician (or maybe late-stage graduate student) at the edge of your field, but if you're a student who still has a ways to go before reaching the edge of human mathematical knowledge, then it's just less efficient, even if you have fun with it.</p>
<p>If you want to maximize how far you get in a talent domain, then you need to grab all the examples &amp; problem-solving experiences in the direction that you're going, as quickly as possible, and then only once you reach the end of the road with known examples and problem-solving experiences, do you switch over to creative production. Creative production is a way less efficient way of moving forward so you want to save it for the end when it's the only way to continue moving forward.</p>
<p><em>(To be clear: this is not just my opinion, this is based on findings from Benjamin Bloom's research on talent development. This is the same Bloom who created Bloom's taxonomy, which many educators use as justification for having students spend a lot of time working on project – but that is actually misinterpreting Bloom's taxonomy in a way that is not aligned with Bloom's seminal work that came later in his career. I've written more about that <a href="https://justinmath.com/how-blooms-taxonomy-gets-misinterpreted" rel="nofollow noreferrer">here</a>.)</em></p>
<p><strong>Addendum 2: But how can you develop deep understanding if you use worked examples?</strong></p>
<p>First of all: I'm not advocating for mindless mimicry here. There should be plenty of practice on theoretical foundations, including derivations, reasoning about the conditions under which a theorem might apply, etc. This is not inherently at odds with the idea of deliberate practice using worked examples &amp; practice problems. It is trickier to construct worked examples &amp; practice problems that meaningfully test learners on theoretical foundations, but it can be done.)</p>
<p>Second of all, when you continually layer advanced skills on top of existing skills, it forces you to deepen your understanding, really internalizing those existing skills and the ideas behind them. This is basically the idea of "structural integrity" in the context of knowledge.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>When advanced features are built on top of a system, they sometimes fail in ways that reveal previously-unknown foundational weaknesses in the underlying structure. This forces engineers to fortify the underlying structure so that the system can accommodate new elements without compromising its integrity.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Fortifying the underlying structure often requires improving its organization and elegance, which, in the context of student knowledge, produces deep understanding and insight.</p>
</li>
<li><p>When the structural integrity of a system is increased, it also becomes easier to add more advanced features in general. In the same way, when the structural integrity of a student’s knowledge is increased, it becomes easier to assimilate new knowledge in general.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>When you layer on advanced skills, it forces understanding. If there’s some level of understanding you're lacking in some component knowledge, you eventually get to a point where the lack of understanding prevents you from successfully learning more advanced skills.</p>
<p>For instance, there's no way that you can get through a legitimate calculus course without having a real understanding of algebra. In fact, many math students will tell you that calculus is what really deepened their understanding of algebra.</p>
<p><strong>Addendum 3: For anyone who suggests that this answer does not apply to advanced mathematics (analysis, topology, abstract algebra, etc.)...</strong></p>
<p>... I recognize that there's barely any empirical research into education at this level of math. But are you aware of any research where deliberate practice was not found to be the most efficient practice technique, in any talent domain? As far as I'm aware, no counterexamples have been found (though I'd be really interested to read about any if there's something I've missed).</p>
<p>Basically, it seems like there's a mountain of circumstantial empirical evidence (in both talent development &amp; cognitive science research) suggesting that the superiority of deliberate practice would carry over to the setting of advanced mathematics. So in the absence of any contradictory research, why would we expect anything otherwise?</p>
<p>If you're a math professor, then I recognize that you have plenty of experience studying/teaching advanced mathematics, and if you claim that doesn't carry over into advanced math in your personal experience, then that's a claim worth considering. But at the same time, I do have some experience myself in studying/teaching advanced mathematics (not as much as you, but some), and in my experience, the superiority of deliberate practice is fully supported.</p>
<p>Just to name one example: last year, I tutored a student who was taking analysis at an elite university, and each problem set consisted of those "think really hard for a long period of time" problems. Things were going the way of a train wreck: despite her best efforts, she was spinning her wheels on these problems and making very little progress. Not only was she unable to solve the problems, but also, she was not noticeably improving any supporting knowledge by trying and failing to solve them.</p>
<p>What I ended up doing was engaging her in deliberate practice on all of the component knowledge that was being pulled together in each problem. Something like this (the following is non-exhaustive):</p>
<ul>
<li><p><em>Deliberate Practice on Definitions:</em> I give you a mathematical object and you tell me whether it meets the definition (and why or why not). Repeat over and over again increasing in difficulty. Okay, now suppose we remove some criterion from the definition. What's an object that didn't meet the original definition but does now after dropping that criterion? Repeat over and over dropping different criteria.</p>
</li>
<li><p><em>Deliberate Practice on Theorems:</em> I give you a scenario and you tell me whether it meets the assumptions of the theorem. If so, you tell me specifically what else you know is true about the scenario, according to the theorem. Repeat over and over again increasing in difficulty. Okay, if this is a one-way implication, tell me some scenarios where the converse does not hold.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>As soon as we took a step back from the homework problems and started doing that, she started making actual progress on her supporting knowledge. After enough cycles of deliberate practice, she'd re-attempt the homework problems, often solving them completely or at least getting a lot further before starting to spin her wheels again.</p>
<p><em>The result:</em> her exam performance skyrocketed and she ended up finishing the course with an A.</p>
<p><em>What could have happened:</em> without this deliberate practice intervention, she would have gotten a low grade in the course and possibly even dropped out of the major entirely.</p>
<p><em>(Note: Even after learning metacognitive techniques for thinking critically about definitions and theorems, she still required me to create deliberate practice problems for her by targeting weaknesses and selecting specific objects / scenarios to highlight key features &amp; scaffold from easy to hard difficulty.</em></p>
<p><em>In general, a learner typically cannot construct their own deliberate practice experience without expert guidance since they are typically unable to construct information-rich &amp; scaffolded practice problems, much less correctly identify their areas of weakness for targeted practice to begin with.</em></p>
<p><em>So, it would <strong>not</strong> be accurate to suggest that the student could carry out future deliberate practice on her own after learning metacognitive skills for parsing definitions/theorems, implying that the kinds of problems given to the student could be construed as effective for independent practice once those metacognitive skills were learned.)</em></p>
<p><strong>Addendum 4: "Could you suggest some talent development / expertise literature in psychology? I'd greatly appreciate it."</strong></p>
<p>I'd start with K. Anders Ericsson, the academic father of deliberate practice. His work is <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=Ym0clGUAAAAJ" rel="nofollow noreferrer">extensive</a>. Here are some of my selections:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Ericsson, K. A. (2008). <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1111/j.1553-2712.2008.00227.x" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Deliberate practice and acquisition of expert performance: a general overview.</a> <em>Academic emergency medicine, 15</em>(11), 988-994.</p>
<p>Ericsson, K. A. (2006). <a href="https://www.ida.liu.se/%7Enilda08/Anders_Ericsson/Ericsson_delib_pract.pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">The influence of experience and deliberate practice on the development of superior expert performance.</a> <em>The Cambridge handbook of expertise and expert performance, 38</em>(685-705), 2-2.</p>
<p>Ericsson, K. A. (2003). <a href="https://nibmehub.com/opac-service/pdf/read/The%20Psychology%20of%20Problem%20Solving.pdf#page=86" rel="nofollow noreferrer">The acquisition of expert performance as problem solving: Construction and modification of mediating mechanisms through deliberate practice.</a> <em>The psychology of problem solving</em>, 31-83.</p>
<p>Ericsson, K. A., Krampe, R. T., &amp; Tesch-Römer, C. (1993). <a href="https://graphics8.nytimes.com/images/blogs/freakonomics/pdf/DeliberatePractice(PsychologicalReview).pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">The role of deliberate practice in the acquisition of expert performance.</a> <em>Psychological review, 100</em>(3), 363.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Some other references worth checking out, related to deliberate practice:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Anderson, J. R., Reder, L. M., Simon, H. A., Ericsson, K. A., &amp; Glaser, R. (1998). <a href="http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/reder/publications/98_jra_lmr_has.pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Radical constructivism and cognitive psychology.</a> <em>Brookings papers on education policy</em>, (1), 227-278. <strong>(See, especially, the comment by Ericsson starting on page 255)</strong></p>
<p>Coughlan, E. K., Williams, A. M., McRobert, A. P., &amp; Ford, P. R. (2014). <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/24001022/" rel="nofollow noreferrer">How experts practice: A novel test of deliberate practice theory.</a> <em>Journal of Experimental Psychology: Learning, Memory, and Cognition, 40</em>(2), 449.</p>
<p>Lehtinen, E., Hannula-Sormunen, M., McMullen, J., &amp; Gruber, H. (2017). <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Jake-Mcmullen/publication/317035771_Cultivating_mathematical_skills_From_drill-and-practice_to_deliberate_practice/links/6192129bd7d1af224bef75bb/Cultivating-mathematical-skills-From-drill-and-practice-to-deliberate-practice.pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Cultivating mathematical skills: From drill-and-practice to deliberate practice.</a> <em>ZDM, 49</em>, 625-636.</p>
<p>Plant, E. A., Ericsson, K. A., Hill, L., &amp; Asberg, K. (2005). <a href="https://www.academia.edu/download/54133889/Why_study_time_does_not_predict_grade_po20170813-2588-hxvq2s.pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Why study time does not predict grade point average across college students: Implications of deliberate practice for academic performance.</a> <em>Contemporary educational psychology, 30</em>(1), 96-116.</p>
<p>Reeves, W. R. (2014). <a href="https://repositories.lib.utexas.edu/server/api/core/bitstreams/c8cc4a4f-e641-462b-9a72-654e60f71485/content" rel="nofollow noreferrer"><em>Creativity as a learned skill: The role of deliberate practice in the development of creativity</em></a> (Doctoral dissertation).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And some lighter reading:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Clear, J. <a href="https://jamesclear.com/beginners-guide-deliberate-practice" rel="nofollow noreferrer">The Beginner’s Guide to Deliberate Practice.</a> <em>JamesClear.com.</em></p>
<p>Ericsson, K. A., Prietula, M. J., &amp; Cokely, E. T. (2007). <a href="https://hbr.org/2007/07/the-making-of-an-expert" rel="nofollow noreferrer">The making of an expert.</a> <em>Harvard business review, 85</em>(7/8), 114.</p>
<p>Parrish, S. <a href="https://fs.blog/deliberate-practice-guide/" rel="nofollow noreferrer">The Ultimate Deliberate Practice Guide: How to Be the Best.</a> <em>FS.blog.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Oh, you probably also want to read about Bloom's 3-stage process of talent development that describes the striking commonalities Bloom discovered when studying the backgrounds of extremely successful individuals across a wide variety of fields.</p>
<p>The 3-stage process is the main thesis of Benjamin Bloom’s 1985 book <a href="https://archive.org/details/developingtalent0000unse" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Developing Talent in Young People</a>. The stages are summarized well in the 2002 paper <a href="https://www.mcgill.ca/sportpsych/files/sportpsych/2002_-_bloom_g.a._2002._role_of_the_elite_coach_in_the_development_of_talent._in_j.m._silva_d.e._stevens_eds._psychological_foundations_of_sport_pp._466-483._boston-_allyn_and_bacon.pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Role of the Elite Coach in the Development of Talent</a> by Gordon Bloom.</p>
<p>Some other interesting reads from Benjamin Bloom on the topic of talent development:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Bloom, B. S., &amp; Sosniak, L. A. (1981). <a href="https://files.ascd.org/staticfiles/ascd/pdf/journals/ed_lead/el_198111_bloom.pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Talent development vs. schooling.</a> <em>Educational Leadership, 39</em>(2), 86-94.</p>
<p>Brandt, R. S. (1985). <a href="https://files.ascd.org/staticfiles/ascd/pdf/journals/ed_lead/el_198509_brandt2.pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">On Talent Development: A Conversation with Benjamin Bloom.</a> <em>Educational Leadership, 43</em>(1), 33-35.</p>
<p>Bloom, B. S. (1986). <a href="https://files.ascd.org/staticfiles/ascd/pdf/journals/ed_lead/el_198602_bloom.pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Automaticity: "The Hands and Feet of Genius."</a> <em>Educational leadership, 43</em>(5), 70-77.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Another reference worth checking out:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Luo, L., &amp; Kiewra, K. A. (2021). <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/0261429420934436" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Parents' roles in talent development.</a> <em>Gifted Education International, 37</em>(1), 30-40.</p>
</blockquote>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[10% of Cubans left Cuba between 2022 and 2023 (344 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.miamiherald.com/news/nation-world/world/americas/cuba/article290249799.html</link>
            <guid>41016441</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 13:43:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.miamiherald.com/news/nation-world/world/americas/cuba/article290249799.html">https://www.miamiherald.com/news/nation-world/world/americas/cuba/article290249799.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41016441">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.miamiherald.com/news/nation-world/world/americas/cuba/article290249799.html: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[No Uptime Hosting – Guaranteed Server Downtime (245 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nouptime.com/</link>
            <guid>41016290</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 13:21:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nouptime.com/">https://nouptime.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41016290">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content">


<p>

	- 200Kb of Storage<br>

	- 10Mb of Bandwidth<br>

	- PHP 4, 5 and 6<br>

	- MySQL, SQL and Oracle<br>

	- Dedicated Dedication<br>

	- Host Up To 6.8 Sites<br>

	- Free Identity Theft

</p>



<p>

	- Lots of Storage<br>

	- 10Kb of Bandwidth<br>

	- PHP 5, 6 and 7<br>

	- MySQL and ReiserFS<br>

	- 2 Glow Sticks<br>

	- Free Broken Toaster<br>

	- 24/8 Email Support

</p>



<p>

	- 200Gb of Storage<br>

	- 10 Bytes of Path Bandwidth<br>

	- Ruby on Railroads<br>

	- Dedicated Support Geek<br>

	- Dedicated Win 3.11<br>

	- Steve Ballmer<br>

	- Ruby on Boats

</p>



<p>

	Currently Hosting Over <b>5,568,120</b> Websites

</p><!--sites-hosted-->



<p>

	Hosting Websites Since <b>1969</b>!

</p>



<br clear="all">



<div>

	<p><img id="graph" src="https://nouptime.com/images/graph.gif" alt="Downtime Graph"></p>

	<p>We are constantly working to improve our server downtime.</p>

	<p>Keeping you awake at night is our #1 priority.</p><br>

	<h2>Clusters and Scalability</h2>

	<p>If your websites go down we'll make sure to confuse</p>

	<p>you with technical terms and instructions. It's our</p>

	<p>job to keep you aggravated, and we never disappoint.<br clear="all"></p>

</div>



<div>

	<p><img id="testimonials" src="https://nouptime.com/images/testimonials.gif" alt="Testimonials"></p><p>We have over <b>359</b> testimonials from happy customers around the world:</p>

	<!--testimonial-box-->

	

</div>



<!--? include("bottom.php");?--></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[1989 Networking: NetWare 386 (122 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://www.os2museum.com/wp/1989-networking-netware-386/</link>
            <guid>41016104</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 12:51:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://www.os2museum.com/wp/1989-networking-netware-386/">http://www.os2museum.com/wp/1989-networking-netware-386/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41016104">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
						
<p>Thanks to the recent warez mega dump, another long lost gem has come to light: NetWare 386, also known as NetWare 3.0.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="http://www.os2museum.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/nw30-boot.png"><img decoding="async" width="640" height="356" src="http://www.os2museum.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/nw30-boot-640x356.png" alt="" srcset="http://www.os2museum.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/nw30-boot-640x356.png 640w, http://www.os2museum.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/nw30-boot-300x167.png 300w, http://www.os2museum.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/nw30-boot.png 720w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px"></a><figcaption>Booting NetWare 3.0</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>In September 1989, Novell released NetWare 386 V3.0, the first in a long line of 32-bit network operating systems. At the time, Novell’s mainstay was NetWare 2.15, a system designed to run on 286-based machines.</p>



<p>NetWare 386, as the name suggests, required at least a 386 processor. It was a major redesign of the NetWare OS intended to take advantage of (then) high end 32-bit hardware. Whereas NetWare 2.x was linked from object modules during installation (much like commercial UNIX implementations), NetWare 386 utilized modules (NLMs, or NetWare Loadable Modules) which could be loaded and unloaded at run-time.</p>



<p>Disk drivers, network drivers, protocols, and all sorts of added functionality were implemented as NLMs in NetWare 386. This made NetWare 3.0 installation and maintenance far simpler compared to NetWare 2.x. The NetWare 2.x kernel had to be linked during installation (a lengthy process), and any change of a disk or network driver required the OS to be re-generated again. In NetWare 3.0, all it took was copying a new driver and changing a configuration file.</p>



<p>NetWare 3.0 was in some ways a limited release, although at the same time it was a fully functioning file server which could support up to 250 users (compared to the 100 user maximum of NetWare 2.x). That was reflected in the pricing—$7,995. NetWare 3.0 was Novell’s flagship product, even though it didn’t fully realize the NetWare 386 vision. Only the IPX protocol was supported, the set of available disk and network drivers was quite limited, and third-party NLMs were more or less nonexistent. </p>



<p>When NetWare 3.0 was released, the NLM development kit was not yet available. That is likely also the reason why NetWare 3.0 did not ship with CLIB.NLM, MATHLIB.NLM, and a few other NLMs. These NLMs became available a few months after the NetWare 3.0 release though, together with the development kit.</p>



<p>Installing NetWare 3.0 is not fundamentally different from installing later 3.x releases. The installation procedure is completely different from installing NetWare 2.x. Rather than configuring and linking the OS kernel first, it is initiated by booting the NetWare 3.0 OS, and all requisite drivers are dynamically loaded as separate modules.</p>



<p>For reasons that are not entirely clear, NetWare 2.x could boot directly from hard disk (using so called “cold boot loader”) but NetWare 3.x cannot. NetWare 3.x requires DOS to be loaded first, and then SERVER.EXE must be run. Unlike NetWare 2.x, it is possible to completely shut down NetWare 3.x and return back to DOS. For that reason, NetWare 3.x requires either a small bootable DOS partition or a bootable DOS floppy.</p>



<p>To install NetWare 3.0, one simply runs SERVER.EXE, loads the appropriate disk driver, and then loads INSTALL.NLM. While NetWare 2.x required a separate external installer, NetWare 3.0 is installed from a running NetWare system.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="http://www.os2museum.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/nw30-copy.png"><img decoding="async" width="640" height="356" src="http://www.os2museum.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/nw30-copy-640x356.png" alt="" srcset="http://www.os2museum.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/nw30-copy-640x356.png 640w, http://www.os2museum.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/nw30-copy-300x167.png 300w, http://www.os2museum.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/nw30-copy.png 720w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px"></a><figcaption>Installing NetWare 3.0 files</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>NetWare 3.0 is old enough that it didn’t ship with ODI-based client drivers and used the old monolithic shell. It’s also of course old enough that it only supports DOS 3.x and 4.0 clients. But it has no trouble talking to newer clients running ODI and PC DOS 2000, for example.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="http://www.os2museum.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/nw30-syscon.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="640" height="356" src="http://www.os2museum.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/nw30-syscon-640x356.png" alt="" srcset="http://www.os2museum.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/nw30-syscon-640x356.png 640w, http://www.os2museum.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/nw30-syscon-300x167.png 300w, http://www.os2museum.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/nw30-syscon.png 720w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px"></a><figcaption>NetWare 3.0 SYSCON</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Original NetWare 3.0 disks are yet to be found. It is possible that only a few thousand copies were ever sold, and since they would have been sold primarily to large corporations (given the eight thousand dollar price tag), the vast majority of the extant copies were no doubt destroyed.</p>



<p>And yet, thanks to software pirates of 1990, NetWare 3.0 can run again after 35 years.</p>
											</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Robot dog cleans up beaches with foot-mounted vacuums (116 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://spectrum.ieee.org/robot-dog-vacuum</link>
            <guid>41015945</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 12:18:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/robot-dog-vacuum">https://spectrum.ieee.org/robot-dog-vacuum</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41015945">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-headline="Robot Dog Cleans Up Beaches With Foot-Mounted Vacuums"><p>Cigarette butts are the second most common undisposed-of litter on Earth—of the six trillion-ish cigarettes inhaled every year, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30782533/" target="_blank">it’s estimated</a> that over 4 trillion of the butts are just tossed onto the ground, each one leeching over 700 different toxic chemicals into the environment. Let’s not focus on the fact that all those toxic chemicals are <em><em>also</em></em> going into people’s lungs, and instead talk about the ecosystem damage that they can do and also just the general grossness of having bits of sucked-on trash everywhere. Ew.</p><p>Preventing those cigarette butts from winding up on the ground in the first place would be the best option, but it would require a pretty big shift in human behavior. Operating under the assumption that humans changing their behavior is a nonstarter, roboticists from the <a href="https://dls.iit.it/" target="_blank">Dynamic Legged Systems</a> unit at the Italian Institute of Technology (IIT), in Genoa, have instead designed a novel platform for cigarette-butt cleanup in the form of a quadrupedal robot with vacuums attached to its feet.</p><p><span data-rm-shortcode-id="1221ce054f5104cd582d1a9d3d1789c9"><iframe frameborder="0" height="auto" type="lazy-iframe" scrolling="no" data-runner-src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/O8BqvAe-moI?rel=0" width="100%"></iframe></span><small placeholder="Add Photo Credit...">IIT</small></p><p>There are, of course, far more efficient ways of at least partially automating the cleanup of litter with machines. The challenge is that most of that automation relies on mobility systems with wheels, which won’t work on the many beautiful beaches (and many beautiful flights of stairs) of Genoa. In places like these, it still falls to humans to do the hard work, which is less than ideal.<strong></strong></p><p>This robot, developed in <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/claudio-semini" target="_blank">Claudio Semini’s lab at IIT</a>, is called VERO (Vacuum-cleaner Equipped RObot). It’s based around an AlienGo from Unitree, with a commercial vacuum mounted on its back. Hoses go from the vacuum down the leg to each foot, with a custom 3D-printed nozzle that puts as much suction near the ground as possible without tripping the robot up. While the vacuum is novel, the real contribution here is how the robot autonomously locates things on the ground and then plans how to interact with those things using its feet.</p><p>First, an operator designates an area for VERO to clean, after which the robot operates by itself. After calculating an exploration path to explore the entire area, the robot uses its onboard cameras and a neural network to detect cigarette butts. This is trickier than it sounds, because there may be a lot of cigarette butts on the ground, and they all probably look pretty much the same, so the system has to filter out all of the potential duplicates. The next step is to plan its next steps: VERO has to put the vacuum side of one of its feet right next to each cigarette butt while calculating a safe, stable pose for the rest of its body. Since this whole process can take place on sand or stairs or other uneven surfaces, VERO has to prioritize not falling over before it decides how to do the collection. The final collecting maneuver is fine-tuned using an extra <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/intel">Intel</a> RealSense depth camera mounted on the robot’s chin. </p><p><img alt="A collage of six photos of a quadruped robot navigating different environments." data-rm-shortcode-id="a558e68c65459dc391adc6aa6e78231d" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" data-runner-src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/a-collage-of-six-photos-of-a-quadruped-robot-navigating-different-environments.png?id=52820248&amp;width=980" height="1104" id="eb956" lazy-loadable="true" src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/a-collage-of-six-photos-of-a-quadruped-robot-navigating-different-environments.png?id=52820248&amp;width=980" width="1449"><small placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">VERO has been tested successfully in six different scenarios that challenge both its locomotion and detection capabilities.</small><small placeholder="Add Photo Credit...">IIT</small></p><p>Initial testing with the robot in a variety of different environments showed that it could successfully collect just under 90 percent of cigarette butts, which I bet is better than I could do, and I’m also much more likely to get fed up with the whole process. The robot is not very quick at the task, but unlike me it will never get fed up as long as it’s got energy in its battery, so speed is somewhat less important.</p><p>As far as the authors of this paper are aware (and I assume they’ve done their research), this is “the first time that the legs of a legged robot are <em>concurrently</em> utilized for locomotion and for a different task.” This is distinct from other robots that can (for example) open doors with their feet, because those robots stop using the feet as feet for a while and instead use them as manipulators.</p><p>So, this is about a lot more than cigarette butts, and the researchers suggest a variety of other potential use cases, including spraying weeds in crop fields, inspecting cracks in infrastructure, and placing nails and rivets during construction.</p><p>Some use cases include potentially doing multiple things at the same time, like planting different kinds of seeds, using different surface sensors, or driving both nails and rivets. And since quadrupeds have four feet, they could potentially host four completely different tools, and the software that the researchers developed for VERO can be slightly modified to put whatever foot you want on whatever spot you need.</p><p><em><em><a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/rob.22350" target="_blank">VERO: A Vacuum‐Cleaner‐Equipped Quadruped Robot for Efficient Litter Removal</a></em></em>, by Lorenzo Amatucci, Giulio Turrisi, Angelo Bratta, Victor Barasuol, and Claudio Semini from IIT, was published in the <em>Journal of Field <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/topic/robotics/">Robotics</a></em>.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Public toilets are vanishing and that's a civic catastrophe (216 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://psyche.co/ideas/public-toilets-are-vanishing-and-thats-a-civic-catastrophe</link>
            <guid>41015731</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 11:37:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://psyche.co/ideas/public-toilets-are-vanishing-and-thats-a-civic-catastrophe">https://psyche.co/ideas/public-toilets-are-vanishing-and-thats-a-civic-catastrophe</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41015731">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="articleContent"><h2>New research shows it is a nightmare for all of us, but especially for people with health issues and marginalised groups</h2><p>The most terrifying moments often unfold in mundane situations. My own taste of horror emerges every time I enter a bar and I’m met with a prolonged silence after asking: ‘Can I use the toilet, please?’ In supposedly affluent Western nations, the dire state or absence of public toilets has become a universal nightmare, impacting the health and quality of life of all of us, but particularly for marginalised groups.</p>
<p>What I find most scary is that we seem to be accepting this cruel reality without confronting it. It is like there is a monster in the city that is affecting the life of everyone, but the people who can make a difference don’t even care.</p>
<p>I have been aware of the monster since 2013 when I was diagnosed with ulcerative colitis. This is a chronic inflammatory bowel disease that causes long-lasting inflammation and ulcers in the digestive tract and affects life in different ways, such as needing the toilet frequently, pain and fatigue. That’s when I realised the impact a simple toilet can have, not only on an individual’s health but also on public health. This is the story of the <em>shitty</em> life that the poor quality of public toilets confers <span>upon us</span>.</p>
<p>Making public bathrooms accessible and appropriate is a matter of human dignity</p>
<p><strong>Toilets were one of the biggest steps</strong> forward for humanity: they allowed us to <a href="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/8/8/779" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">create</a> cleaner spaces, reducing death and improving health. By the <span>19th century</span>, in Western countries, bathrooms with toilets were increasingly included in home design, catering to essential human needs, such as urination, defecation and personal cleaning. With the emergence of new hygiene standards through the <span>20th century</span>, the focus of bathrooms shifted further towards convenience and cleanliness. In contemporary times, the role of domestic bathrooms has <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.2752/174063109X12462745321345" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">expanded</a> beyond their practical utility to symbolise places of wellbeing, with more affluent homes including features such as hot tubs and toilets with hi-tech and luxury functions.</p>
<p>And yet, the vast majority of public restrooms have not yet embraced this aspect of wellbeing. On the contrary, the poor state of them often elicits disgust and repulsion. In severe situations, for some people, these adverse psychological responses can escalate to pathological levels, including incontinence, urinary problems, anxiety, and significant alterations to their normal social life.</p>
<p>For many people, most of the time, the state of restrooms is something they think about only when they fail, if they are unusable or unavailable, or there simply aren’t any. Yet toilets often fail when you need them the most. And it’s in such moments you realise that these invisible parts of our cities are fundamental. So, why are restrooms typically tucked away at the back of establishments, hidden both literally and metaphorically? We all must keep in mind that the use of public bathrooms is inevitable, and that making them accessible and appropriate is a matter of human dignity.</p>
<p><strong>The toilet problem has two differentiable</strong> branches. The first is the global sanitation crisis in developing countries and in extreme situations such as refugee camps, which provokes disease and death. The second branch pertains to the problems in developed countries, causing issues in daily life and negatively impacting quality of life.</p>
<p>Fear of public bathrooms will be greater in those most disadvantaged by society</p>
<p>Worldwide, the World Bank highlights three critical <a href="https://blogs.worldbank.org/en/water/3-hard-truths-about-global-sanitation-crisis" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">facts</a>: a quarter of the world’s population lacks access to decent toilets, only <span>39 per cent</span> of human waste is safely managed worldwide, and the global cost of inadequate sanitation reaches <span>$260 billion</span> annually. These facts emphasise the severe health, economic and environmental impacts of inadequate sanitation. Lack of access to toilets is a silent global burden: people die as disease spreads due to the lack of sanitation.</p>
<p>The problem is different when looking to Western, educated, industrialised, rich and democratic (WEIRD) countries. Here we often take adequate sewage disposal for granted. And yet free access to toilets is gradually <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/langas/article/PIIS2468-1253(21)00438-6/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">disappearing</a>. As the journalist Lezlie Lowe <a href="https://chbooks.com/Books/N/No-Place-To-Go" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">documents</a> in <em>No Place to Go</em> (2018), institutions are retiring from ensuring the availability of public toilets. This withdrawal of support for basic sanitary facilities has left many people, especially in urban areas, struggling to find accessible restrooms when needed. For instance, data collected in the United Kingdom in 2018 showed that the number of public toilets had dropped by <span>39 per cent</span> over the previous two decades. Quite simply, Lowe was right: there is often no place <span>to go</span>.</p>
<p>Yet, having access to toilets is essential for everyone’s dignity and to help support everyone’s mental, physical and social health. When women can’t easily use public toilets, it harms their <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31510038/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">wellbeing</a> and denies their <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0282917" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">basic rights</a>. The list of problems associated with public restrooms doesn’t end there. For instance, transgender and gender-nonconforming individuals <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6747507/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">face</a> <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10964-017-0652-1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">difficulties</a> accessing restrooms due to transphobia. There is also a noticeable rise in urogenital issues due to holding in the urge to use the restroom at <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28671729/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">work</a> or due to <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/15987005/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">schools</a> not adapting to the needs of children. Everyone can easily find a reason to fear public bathrooms, although these fears will be greater in those most disadvantaged by society.</p>
<p>For those of us with gastrointestinal problems, our minds always reserve a considerable space for public restrooms: we often worry about when we’ll have to use them, if we’ll find one, and if it will meet minimum standards. Dependency reshapes your reality: you are no longer concerned about whether you can park at the beach, but whether there will be a nearby restroom; you are not so worried about being late for the bus, but suddenly having an urgency in a <span>45-minute</span>-long journey. Life changes when you are dependent on toilets. Note that everyone can find themselves toilet dependent, even if only temporarily – like that week after you ate a meal that upset your stomach.</p>
<p>Women reported more negative incidents with public restrooms than men</p>
<p><strong>These thoughts drove me to conduct</strong> some scientific studies on what people face with public toilets and how it affects their daily lives. Our studies started with interviews with the true experts in public restrooms: patients with bowel diseases (such as Crohn’s disease, ulcerative colitis or irritable bowel syndrome). In our case, these were people from Spain, and with their help we <a href="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/17/21/7817" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">developed</a> some assessment tools to use in surveys. We confirmed what we suspected: people struggle with public toilets because they are dirty, don’t offer any privacy, and lack the basic things needed to use them. The ideal public toilet – the one with the adequate levels of cleanliness, privacy and usability – is hard to find. Another <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/nau.25118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> from our team showed that, for people who are toilet dependent, these negative situations can increase the shame they feel about their illness. This illness-related shame is associated with poorer health outcomes, such as reduced seeking of help or support from others.</p>
<p>When we asked people about the struggles they face with public toilets, such as ‘being unable to find an open unoccupied public toilet’ or ‘feeling unsafe or exposed in a public toilet’, we <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/sjop.12914" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">found</a> that the more often they experienced these negative events, the lower their quality of life (even after accounting for any differences in their health or socioeconomic status). What’s more, we found that people from poorer and less educated backgrounds had more of these negative toilet experiences – probably because they usually live further from work and in places with fewer available high-quality toilets. Consistent with previous research, we found that gender also influences (negative) experiences with public restrooms: women reported more negative incidents than men, perhaps due to distinct needs that are so often ignored.</p>
<p>Considering the data and experiences, it might seem we’re losing the battle for quality public toilets. There is just cause for anger, which should be channelled into action. Yet, there’s also reason to hope for a future with better toilets that restore our dignity. Some public administrations are taking the availability of quality public restrooms seriously in their facilities. Increasingly, patient and consumer associations are initiating campaigns for universal access to public toilets. For instance, in my country of Spain, there is the ‘I can’t wait!’ <a href="https://www.nopucesperar.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">campaign</a> in Catalonia, and the <a href="https://cecu.es/publicaciones/informe-sobre-la-presencia-de-banos-publicos-y-fuentes-de-agua/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">report</a> about public bathrooms from the Spanish Federation of Consumers and Users, which called for their greater availability.</p>
<p>Recognising this issue and assessing the situation is the initial stride toward a future where everyone can access high-quality restrooms tailored to their individual needs. One thing is clear: we need to talk about public restrooms openly, not in secret. Loudly, not whispering. We need to assert our fundamental right to access a restroom without having to wait until we’re back home.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Aro – Zig's new C compiler (169 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/Vexu/arocc</link>
            <guid>41015588</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 11:03:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/Vexu/arocc">https://github.com/Vexu/arocc</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41015588">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/ca4ee0f647f08be0ce9f8fbddbde415c2449ada0d665b5caa06063f52ffe802a/68747470733a2f2f61726f2e766578752e65752f61726f2d6c6f676f2e737667"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/ca4ee0f647f08be0ce9f8fbddbde415c2449ada0d665b5caa06063f52ffe802a/68747470733a2f2f61726f2e766578752e65752f61726f2d6c6f676f2e737667" alt="Aro" width="120px" data-canonical-src="https://aro.vexu.eu/aro-logo.svg"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Aro</h2><a id="user-content-aro" aria-label="Permalink: Aro" href="#aro"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">A C compiler with the goal of providing fast compilation and low memory usage with good diagnostics.</p>
<p dir="auto">Aro is included as an alternative C frontend in the <a href="https://github.com/ziglang/zig">Zig compiler</a>
for <code>translate-c</code> and eventually compiling C files by translating them to Zig first.
Aro is developed in <a href="https://github.com/Vexu/arocc">https://github.com/Vexu/arocc</a> and the Zig dependency is
updated from there when needed.</p>
<p dir="auto">Currently most of standard C is supported up to C23 and as are many of the common
extensions from GNU, MSVC, and Clang</p>
<p dir="auto">Basic code generation is supported for x86-64 linux and can produce a valid hello world:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="$ cat hello.c
extern int printf(const char *restrict fmt, ...);
int main(void) {
    printf(&quot;Hello, world!\n&quot;);
    return 0;
}
$ zig build &amp;&amp; ./zig-out/bin/arocc hello.c -o hello
$ ./hello
Hello, world!"><pre>$ <span>cat hello.c</span>
<span>extern int printf(const char *restrict fmt, ...);</span>
<span>int main(void) {</span>
<span>    printf("Hello, world!\n");</span>
<span>    return 0;</span>
<span>}</span>
$ <span>zig build <span>&amp;&amp;</span> ./zig-out/bin/arocc hello.c -o hello</span>
$ <span>./hello</span>
<span>Hello, world!</span></pre></div>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>