<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 11:30:02 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Search My Site – open-source search engine for personal and independent websites (125 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://searchmysite.net</link>
            <guid>43467541</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 02:19:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://searchmysite.net">https://searchmysite.net</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43467541">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
					<h2>About searchmysite.net</h2>
					<p>
						What is the search engine and why should I use it?
					</p>
					<blockquote>
						The searchmysite.net search engine is a niche search, focussing on the "indieweb" or "small web" or "digital gardens", i.e. non-commercial content, primarily personal and independent websites.
					</blockquote>
					<p>
						If you want to research people's personal experiences of or deep-dives into certain topics, hobbies or interests, then you may find the searchmysite.net public search useful to avoid having to wade through all the marketing websites and blog spam that fill the big search engines. It differs from the commercial search engines because it:
					</p>

					<ul>
						<li>Indexes only user-submitted and moderated sites, rather than indexing the entire internet with all of its spam, "search engine optimisation" and "click-bait" content.</li>
						<li>Does not show adverts and promotes advert-free results pages, to remove the incentives for spam and surveillance capitalism.</li>
						<li>Aims to have a sustainable and user-aligned operating model, planning to pay running costs via the "search as a service" features, rather than relying on advertising which could put it in conflict with user needs.</li>
						<li>Offers an unusually high level of privacy for a search engine, thanks to the operating model which is not based on advertising or collecting personal information for sale to advertisers (see the Privacy Policy for full details).</li>
						<li>Is fully open source, for even greater transparency of the searching, ranking and indexing processes, and for greater community involvement in improving the service.</li>
					</ul>

				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Jeffrey Goldberg on being added to the group chat by Trump Administration (113 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theatlantic.com/newsletters/archive/2025/03/jeffrey-goldberg-group-chat-military-houthi-yemen/682160/</link>
            <guid>43466983</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:45:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/newsletters/archive/2025/03/jeffrey-goldberg-group-chat-military-houthi-yemen/682160/">https://www.theatlantic.com/newsletters/archive/2025/03/jeffrey-goldberg-group-chat-military-houthi-yemen/682160/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43466983">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section data-event-module="article body" data-flatplan-body="true"><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><small><i>This is an edition of </i>The Atlantic<i> Daily, a newsletter that guides you through the biggest stories of the day, helps you discover new ideas, and recommends the best in culture. </i><a data-event-element="inline link" data-gtm-vis-first-on-screen31117857_899="351" data-gtm-vis-has-fired31117857_899="1" data-gtm-vis-recent-on-screen31117857_899="351" data-gtm-vis-total-visible-time31117857_899="100" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/newsletters/sign-up/atlantic-daily/"><i>Sign up for it here.</i></a></small></p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The Trump administration has provided many jaw-dropping moments, but few have been as shocking as editor in chief <a data-event-element="inline link" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2025/03/trump-administration-accidentally-texted-me-its-war-plans/682151/">Jeffrey Goldberg’s scoop</a> published today. Goldberg reported on how he was inadvertently added to a discussion of a military strike on Houthi militias in Yemen, conducted over the encrypted messaging app Signal. In essence, a reporter was invited to listen while the nation’s top security officials weighed and debated a military action, and was sent detailed information about the strike.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">Even President Donald Trump seemed unaware of the breach. “You’re saying that they had what?” he replied when asked about the news. Trump added that he is “not a big fan of <i>The Atlantic</i>,” something he’s <a data-event-element="inline link" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2024/10/trump-attacks-atlantics-jeffrey-goldberg-over-hitler/680422/">previously made clear</a>, and which makes the unintentional leak all the more remarkable. A spokesperson for the National Security Council said, “This appears to be an authentic message chain, and we are reviewing how an inadvertent number was added to the chain.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">I called Goldberg this afternoon to learn more about how the story came about and what the disclosure reveals about the Trump administration. This interview has been condensed and edited.</p><hr><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>David A. Graham: </b>Has anything like this ever happened to you before?</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>Jeffrey Goldberg:</b> I think that on one level, this is very relatable. Everyone has sent a text or an email to an unintended recipient, and sometimes they’ve embarrassed themselves by doing that. This is, I would say, at a different level—but it kind of proves a point, which is that there’s a reason people who work on sensitive issues in the government aren’t supposed to use Signal, even though it is end-to-end encrypted. Anyone can use Signal, so if you’re not careful, you might pull into your conversation a Houthi sympathizer or a magazine editor.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">Our colleague <a data-event-element="inline link" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/author/shane-harris/">Shane Harris</a> points out that the phones of top senior defense and national-security and intelligence officials are targets of intelligence operations. Imagine what you can do if you saw everything that the CIA director may be texting, even on a secure phone—especially on a secure phone. I’m mindful of the fact that the Trump team has already dealt with a <a data-event-element="inline link" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2025/01/classified-documents-trump-case/681327/">serious issue</a> in the securing of sensitive documents in Mar-a-Lago. If you’re going to make a big deal about <a data-event-element="inline link" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2017/07/but-his-emails/533274/">Hillary Clinton’s emails</a>, you may want to have excellent communication hygiene.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>David:</b> Tell me how you came to conclude that this group was real.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>Jeffrey: </b>It was actually chilling: 11:44 a.m., Saturday the 15th, eastern time, in my car in a parking lot, just checking my phone, and I see a text from Pete Hegseth, or somebody who’s hoaxing me as Pete Hegseth. It provides information about upcoming military operations with timings attached: <em>T</em><i>his is going to happen. Then this happens, then this happens, and this happens.</i> I’m sitting there in my car and thinking I’m about to find out if this was an elaborate scam or not. So I thought to myself,<i> I’m sitting here for the next two hours with my hands around my phone.</i> I check on X around 1:55, and yes, Sanaa is being bombed, so then I have the realization that this is almost certainly a real channel and not just an elaborate fakery of some sort. And that’s when I began to realize that I had to write about this massive security breach.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>David: </b>You have done a lot of sensitive national-security reporting. Have you ever received any information like this?</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>Jeffrey: </b>No, nothing like this. This was like an intravenous drip of information that no one in the government thinks journalists should have. Until almost the very last minute, I could not believe that this was actually happening, that there could be a Mack-truck-size breach, that somehow, the editor in chief of <i>The Atlantic</i> was invited into a conversation with the intelligence agencies, secretaries, the national security adviser. Like most reporters, I’ve been a recipient of leaks. A leak is a totally different thing. That’s a whistleblower trying to make complaints. This is just reckless.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>David: </b>There’s the horror that something like this would happen on an operational level, but in terms of what we learn from the substance of the conversation, what are the most important things that people should take away?</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>Jeffrey: </b>The actual conversation that they have is fascinating, and in a certain way impressive. It’s nice to see that they’re disagreeing with one another. It’s very useful for the public to know that the vice president has a more hands-off approach than other members of the administration. One of the things that I found interesting was that when a person named “S M” in the chat, who I took to be Stephen Miller, comes in and says, “As I heard it, the president was clear,” this kind of shuts down the conversation. It suggests that Stephen Miller can be in a conversation with, among others, the vice president of the United States and still can get his way. (Miller did not reply to a request for comment or confirm that he is “S M.”)</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>David: </b>In addition to the question of how secure Signal is, this is also notable, because without this report, none of these conversations might be preserved for posterity. You note that National Security Adviser Michael Waltz set some messages to disappear after a week or so.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>Jeffrey: </b>This is an interesting question: Are they using Signal because it’s convenient? Are they using Signal because it disappears? According to the experts Shane interviewed, the administration should not have established a Signal thread for such conversations in the first place, but once it did, what one is supposed to do legally is copy an official government account, and that government account will then send these threads to the National Archives for posterity, for research, for accountability. But if you’re using a disappearing-text app, I don’t know. That’s one of the questions that I’ve asked and have not gotten answered yet.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>David:</b> It is remarkable that this would happen with any reporter. It’s even more remarkable that this would happen with someone like you, and with a publication that has been specifically singled out by the president. Do you have any sense of how this happened?</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>Jeffrey: </b>I literally have no idea. The remarkable thing is that no one in the group asked, <i>Who’s JG?</i>, and when I removed myself from the group, seemingly nobody said, <i>Hey, why did JG leave?</i></p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>David:</b> Are you concerned about retaliation from the Trump administration because of this story?</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>Jeffrey: </b>It’s not my role to care about the possibility of threats or retaliation. We just have to come to work and do our jobs to the best of our ability. Unfortunately, in our society today—we see this across corporate journalism and law firms and other industries—there’s too much preemptive obeying for my taste. All we can do is just go do our jobs.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><a data-event-element="inline link" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2025/03/trump-administration-accidentally-texted-me-its-war-plans/682151/"><b>Read the full article he</b></a><b><a data-event-element="inline link" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2025/03/trump-administration-accidentally-texted-me-its-war-plans/682151/">re</a></b><a data-event-element="inline link" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2025/03/trump-administration-accidentally-texted-me-its-war-plans/682151/"><b>.</b></a></p></section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[German parliament votes as a Git contribution graph (405 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://abstimmung.eu/git/2024</link>
            <guid>43466509</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 23:29:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://abstimmung.eu/git/2024">https://abstimmung.eu/git/2024</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43466509">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><h2>17. Januar 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/53"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Jahresbericht 2022 der Wehrbeauftragten (Entschließungsantrag)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Verteidigung</span><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Ukraine</span><span data-slot="badge">Bundeswehr</span><span data-slot="badge">Militär</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Entschließungsantrag der CDU/CSU-Fraktion zum Jahresbericht 2022 der Wehrbeauftragten, der die Bundesregierung auffordert, einsatzbereite TAURUS-Marschflugkörper an die Ukraine zu liefern und diese unverzüglich nachzubeschaffen.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>18. Januar 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/54"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Entlastung der Landwirtschaft</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Landwirtschaft</span><span data-slot="badge">Wirtschaft</span><span data-slot="badge">Steuerpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Agrarpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Innovation</span><span data-slot="badge">Bürokratie</span></p><p>Der Antrag der CDU/CSU-Fraktion betrifft die Unterstützung der Landwirtschaft und zielt darauf ab, die Wettbewerbsfähigkeit der Landwirtschaft zu erhalten und zu verbessern, anstatt sie durch politische Maßnahmen zu schwächen. Der Antrag fordert die Bundesregierung auf, Maßnahmen zu ergreifen, um die Landwirtschaft zu fördern und zu entlasten.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/55"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Friedensinitiative für die Ukraine und Russland (Beschlussempfehlung)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Friedenspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Ukraine</span><span data-slot="badge">Russland</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft einen Antrag der AfD-Fraktion, der eine Friedensinitiative mit Sicherheitsgarantien für die Ukraine und Russland fordert, um Deutschlands Verantwortung für den Frieden in Europa gerecht zu werden.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>19. Januar 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/56"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Modernisierung des Staatsangehörigkeitsrechts (GesEntw BReg)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Staatsangehörigkeit</span><span data-slot="badge">Integration</span><span data-slot="badge">Recht</span><span data-slot="badge">Gesellschaft</span><span data-slot="badge">Migration</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Modernisierung des Staatsangehörigkeitsrechts (StARModG), um den Zugang zur deutschen Staatsangehörigkeit zu erleichtern und die Integration von Ausländern zu fördern.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>01. Februar 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/57"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Änderung des Bundeswahlgesetzes</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Wahlrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Innenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Bevölkerungsentwicklung</span><span data-slot="badge">Kommunalpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Gesetzgebung</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Änderung des Bundeswahlgesetzes, um die Wahlkreiseinteilung an die aktuelle Bevölkerungsentwicklung anzupassen und kommunale Gebietsänderungen zu berücksichtigen. Ziel ist es, sicherzustellen, dass die Wahl zum Deutschen Bundestag auf einer fairen und gleichmäßigen Grundlage stattfindet.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>22. Februar 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/58"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Zehn Jahre russischer Krieg gegen die Ukraine</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Ukraine</span><span data-slot="badge">Russland</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Militär</span><span data-slot="badge">Völkerrecht</span></p><p>Der Antrag betrifft die Unterstützung der Ukraine angesichts des russischen Krieges und zielt darauf ab, die deutsche und europäische Sicherheit zu stärken sowie die Verantwortlichen für Kriegsverbrechen zur Rechenschaft zu ziehen.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/60"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Deutsche Außen- und Sicherheitspolitik (Antrag CDU/CSU)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Verteidigung</span><span data-slot="badge">Internationale Beziehungen</span><span data-slot="badge">Bevölkerungsschutz</span></p><p>Der Antrag der CDU/CSU betrifft eine Neuausrichtung der deutschen Außen- und Sicherheitspolitik, um auf die veränderte Bedrohungslage durch Russland zu reagieren und Deutschlands Rolle in Europa und der Welt zu stärken. Er fordert eine "echte Zeitenwende" mit konkreten Maßnahmen zur Stärkung der Verteidigungsfähigkeit, des Bevölkerungsschutzes und der internationalen Zusammenarbeit.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>23. Februar 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/59"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Wachstumschancengesetz;Kfz-Haftpflichtversicherung (BeschlEmpf Vermittlungsausschuss)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Wirtschaft</span><span data-slot="badge">Steuerrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Investition</span><span data-slot="badge">Innovation</span><span data-slot="badge">Finanzen</span></p><p>Die Beschlussempfehlung des Vermittlungsausschusses betrifft das Gesetz zur Stärkung von Wachstumschancen, Investitionen und Innovation sowie Steuervereinfachung und Steuerfairness (Wachstumschancengesetz). Sie zielt darauf ab, Änderungen an diesem Gesetz vorzunehmen, um Wachstum, Investitionen und Innovation zu fördern sowie das Steuersystem zu vereinfachen und fairer zu gestalten.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/61"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Cannabisgesetz (GesEntwurf BReg)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Gesundheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Drogenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Jugendschutz</span><span data-slot="badge">Justiz</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheit</span></p><p>Das Cannabisgesetz regelt den kontrollierten Umgang mit Cannabis und ändert weitere Vorschriften. Es zielt darauf ab, den Gesundheitsschutz zu verbessern, den illegalen Markt einzudämmen und den Kinder- und Jugendschutz zu stärken.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/62"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Bundeswehreinsatz EUNAVFOR ASPIDES (BeschlEmpf)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Europäische Union</span><span data-slot="badge">Militär</span><span data-slot="badge">Internationaler Handel</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Beteiligung bewaffneter deutscher Streitkräfte an der von der Europäischen Union geführten Operation EUNAVFOR ASPIDES, die zum Schutz der Schifffahrt im Roten Meer und angrenzenden Gebieten beitragen soll. Der Bundestag stimmt über den Antrag der Bundesregierung zur Entsendung von bis zu 700 Soldaten bis maximal zum 28. Februar 2025 ab.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>14. März 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/63"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Ablehnung von Lieferung des Taurus-Marschflugkörpers (Beschlussempfehlung)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Verteidigung</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Ukraine</span><span data-slot="badge">Militär</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Antrag der CDU/CSU, die Bundesregierung aufzufordern, der Ukraine Taurus-Marschflugkörper aus Bundeswehrbeständen zu liefern, die Integration des Waffensystems in ukrainische Flugzeuge zu unterstützen, ukrainische Soldaten auszubilden, Hemmnisse bei der Weitergabe sensibler Informationen zu beseitigen, Ausrüstungslücken bei der Bundeswehr durch Nachbeschaffung zu schließen, die Produktionskapazitäten der Industrie zu erhöhen und weitere Taurus-Marschflugkörper zu beschaffen. Der Antrag wird abgelehnt.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>20. März 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/64"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Steuervergünstigung für Agrardiesel (Antrag AfD)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Landwirtschaft</span><span data-slot="badge">Steuerpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Subventionen</span><span data-slot="badge">Haushaltspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Agrardiesel</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Antrag der AfD-Fraktion, die Steuervergünstigung für Agrardiesel beizubehalten, um die deutsche Landwirtschaft nicht zusätzlich zu belasten und die Lebensmittelpreise nicht künstlich zu verteuern. Der Antrag sieht vor, Kürzungen in anderen Bereichen des Haushalts vorzunehmen, falls Einsparungen notwendig sind, und die Bundesregierung aufzufordern, Beschlüsse der Parlamentsgremien zu respektieren.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>21. März 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/65"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Bundeswehreinsatz SEA GUARDIAN im Mittelmeer (Antrag BReg)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Militär</span><span data-slot="badge">NATO</span><span data-slot="badge">Mittelmeer</span><span data-slot="badge">Terrorismusbekämpfung</span><span data-slot="badge">Internationale Beziehungen</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Fortsetzung der Beteiligung bewaffneter deutscher Streitkräfte an der NATO-geführten maritimen Sicherheitsoperation SEA GUARDIAN (MSO SG) im Mittelmeer, um zur Sicherheit und Stabilität in der Region beizutragen. Der Deutsche Bundestag stimmt über den Antrag der Bundesregierung zur Verlängerung dieses Einsatzes ab.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/66"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Bundeswehreinsatz in der Republik Südsudan (UNMISS)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Verteidigung</span><span data-slot="badge">Humanitäre Hilfe</span><span data-slot="badge">Friedensmission</span><span data-slot="badge">UN</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Fortsetzung der Beteiligung bewaffneter deutscher Streitkräfte an der UN-Friedensmission UNMISS (United Nations Mission in South Sudan) in der Republik Südsudan. Es geht darum, ob der Bundestag der von der Bundesregierung beschlossenen Verlängerung des Einsatzes zustimmt.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>12. April 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/67"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Selbstbestimmung in Bezug auf den Geschlechtseintrag</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Gesellschaftspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Gleichstellung</span><span data-slot="badge">Selbstbestimmung</span><span data-slot="badge">Transgender</span><span data-slot="badge">Recht</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Entwurf eines Gesetzes über die Selbstbestimmung in Bezug auf den Geschlechtseintrag und zur Änderung weiterer Vorschriften. Das Gesetz zielt darauf ab, die Regelungen zur Änderung des Geschlechtseintrags zu vereinfachen und zu vereinheitlichen.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/68"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Änderung des Energiewirtschaftsgesetzes</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Energiewirtschaft</span><span data-slot="badge">Wasserstoff</span><span data-slot="badge">Infrastruktur</span><span data-slot="badge">Netzentwicklung</span><span data-slot="badge">Finanzierung</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft ein Gesetz zur Änderung des Energiewirtschaftsgesetzes (EnWG), um den Aufbau einer nationalen Wasserstoffinfrastruktur zu fördern und die Finanzierung des Wasserstoff-Kernnetzes zu regeln.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>25. April 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/141"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Operation EUNAVFOR MED IRINI (Beschlussempfehlung)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Europäische Union</span><span data-slot="badge">Militär</span><span data-slot="badge">Libyen</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Fortsetzung der Beteiligung bewaffneter deutscher Streitkräfte an der Operation EUNAVFOR MED IRINI der Europäischen Union. Ziel ist es, das Waffenembargo gegen Libyen weiterhin durchzusetzen und zur Stabilisierung des Landes beizutragen.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>26. April 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/69"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Erneuerbare-Energien-Gesetz (Solarpaket)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Erneuerbare Energien</span><span data-slot="badge">Photovoltaik</span><span data-slot="badge">Klimaschutz</span><span data-slot="badge">Energiewende</span><span data-slot="badge">Bürokratieabbau</span><span data-slot="badge">Netzausbau</span></p><p>Das Gesetz zur Änderung des Erneuerbare-Energien-Gesetzes (EEG) zielt darauf ab, den Ausbau der Photovoltaik (PV) in Deutschland zu beschleunigen und zu steigern, um die Klimaziele zu erreichen. Es werden Anreize für Solaranlagen geschaffen und Bürokratie abgebaut.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>16. Mai 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/70"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Ablehnung eines Antrags gegen den WHO-Pandemievertrag</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Gesundheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Internationale Beziehungen</span><span data-slot="badge">Souveränität</span><span data-slot="badge">WHO</span><span data-slot="badge">Pandemie</span><span data-slot="badge">Demokratie</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Antrag der AfD-Fraktion, den WHO-Pandemievertrag und die überarbeiteten Internationalen Gesundheitsvorschriften abzulehnen. Der Antrag zielt darauf ab, die Souveränität Deutschlands in Gesundheitsfragen zu wahren und eine vermeintliche Machtausweitung der WHO zu verhindern.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>05. Juni 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/71"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Ablehnung eines Antrags zur Abschaffung des Solidaritätszuschlags</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Steuerpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Finanzen</span><span data-slot="badge">Wirtschaft</span><span data-slot="badge">Solidaritätszuschlag</span><span data-slot="badge">Abgabenlast</span><span data-slot="badge">Steuerreform</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Antrag der AfD-Fraktion zur Abschaffung des Solidaritätszuschlags als ersten Schritt einer umfassenden Steuerreform zur Entlastung von Mittelstand, Unternehmen und Arbeitnehmern. Der Finanzausschuss empfiehlt die Ablehnung des Antrags.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>06. Juni 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/72"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Ablehnung eines Antrags zur Bekämpfung des politischen Islam</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Inneres und Heimat</span><span data-slot="badge">Politischer Islam</span><span data-slot="badge">Demokratie</span><span data-slot="badge">Recht</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Migration</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Antrag der CDU/CSU-Fraktion, den politischen Islam als Gefahr für die freiheitliche Demokratie wirksam zu bekämpfen. Der Ausschuss für Inneres und Heimat empfiehlt die Ablehnung des Antrags.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/73"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Beschleunigung immissionsschutzrechtlicher Genehmigungsverfahren</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Umwelt</span><span data-slot="badge">Klimaschutz</span><span data-slot="badge">Energie</span><span data-slot="badge">Wirtschaft</span><span data-slot="badge">Genehmigungsverfahren</span><span data-slot="badge">Erneuerbare Energien</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft ein Gesetz zur Verbesserung des Klimaschutzes, zur Beschleunigung von Genehmigungsverfahren im Immissionsschutz und zur Umsetzung von EU-Recht, mit dem Ziel, Verfahren zu vereinfachen und den Ausbau erneuerbarer Energien zu fördern.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>13. Juni 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/74"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Antrag zu Konsequenzen aus dem Terror von Mannheim</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Innere Sicherheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Migration</span><span data-slot="badge">Integration</span><span data-slot="badge">Terrorismusbekämpfung</span><span data-slot="badge">Rechtspolitik</span></p><p>Der Antrag der CDU/CSU-Fraktion betrifft die Forderung nach klaren Konsequenzen aus dem Terroranschlag von Mannheim und zielt darauf ab, die Migrations- und Integrationspolitik zu verschärfen sowie die Sicherheitsmaßnahmen zu erhöhen.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/75"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Ablehnung eines Antrags zum Verbot des Vereins Muslim Interaktiv</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Inneres und Heimat</span><span data-slot="badge">Vereinsrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Extremismus</span><span data-slot="badge">Islamismus</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Antrag der AfD-Fraktion, den Verein Muslim Interaktiv zu verbieten, da dieser als extremistisch und gegen die freiheitliche demokratische Grundordnung gerichtet angesehen wird. Der Bundestag lehnt den Antrag ab.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/76"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Antrag zum Eintritt in die zweite Beratung zur Aufhebung des Lieferkettengesetzes</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Wirtschaft</span><span data-slot="badge">Recht</span><span data-slot="badge">Soziales</span><span data-slot="badge">Europäische Union</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft einen Antrag der CDU/CSU-Fraktion, direkt in die zweite Beratung eines Gesetzentwurfs zur Aufhebung des Lieferkettensorgfaltspflichtengesetzes (LkSG) einzutreten.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>27. Juni 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/77"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Bundeswehreinsatz EUFOR ALTHEA</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Europäische Union</span><span data-slot="badge">Bundeswehr</span><span data-slot="badge">Bosnien und Herzegowina</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Fortsetzung der Beteiligung bewaffneter deutscher Streitkräfte an der EU-geführten Sicherheitsoperation EUFOR ALTHEA in Bosnien und Herzegowina bis zum 30. Juni 2025.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/78"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Bundeswehreinsatz im Kosovo (KFOR)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Verteidigung</span><span data-slot="badge">Kosovo</span><span data-slot="badge">Bundeswehr</span><span data-slot="badge">Internationale Beziehungen</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Fortsetzung der Beteiligung bewaffneter deutscher Streitkräfte an der internationalen Sicherheitspräsenz im Kosovo (KFOR). Es geht darum, das Mandat für den Einsatz der Bundeswehr im Rahmen von KFOR zu verlängern.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/79"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Bundeswehreinsatz im Libanon (UNIFIL)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Bundeswehr</span><span data-slot="badge">Libanon</span><span data-slot="badge">UNIFIL</span><span data-slot="badge">Friedensmission</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Fortsetzung der Beteiligung bewaffneter deutscher Streitkräfte an der "United Nations Interim Force in Lebanon" (UNIFIL), einer Friedensmission der Vereinten Nationen im Libanon. Es geht um die Verlängerung des Mandats und die damit verbundenen Aufgaben und Befugnisse der deutschen Soldaten.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>05. Juli 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/80"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Änderung des Schwangerschaftskonfliktgesetzes</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Soziales</span><span data-slot="badge">Familie</span><span data-slot="badge">Frauenrechte</span><span data-slot="badge">Gesundheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Recht</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Änderung des Schwangerschaftskonfliktgesetzes (SchKG) und zielt darauf ab, einen bundeseinheitlichen und rechtssicheren Umgang mit sogenannten Gehsteigbelästigungen vor Schwangerschaftsberatungsstellen und Einrichtungen zur Vornahme von Schwangerschaftsabbrüchen sicherzustellen.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>17. Oktober 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/81"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Entwurf zur Aufhebung des Lieferkettengesetzes</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Wirtschaft</span><span data-slot="badge">Menschenrechte</span><span data-slot="badge">Umwelt</span><span data-slot="badge">Lieferketten</span><span data-slot="badge">Gesetzgebung</span><span data-slot="badge">Europäische Union</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Gesetzentwurf der CDU/CSU zur Aufhebung des Lieferkettensorgfaltspflichtengesetzes (LkSG), das Unternehmen zur Einhaltung von Menschenrechten in ihren Lieferketten verpflichtet.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/82"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Gesetzentwurf zur Krankenhausreform</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Gesundheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Krankenhaus</span><span data-slot="badge">Versorgung</span><span data-slot="badge">Finanzierung</span><span data-slot="badge">Qualitätssicherung</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Entwurf eines Gesetzes zur Verbesserung der Versorgungsqualität im Krankenhaus und zur Reform der Vergütungsstrukturen (KHVVG), das darauf abzielt, die Krankenhausversorgung zu verbessern und die Finanzierung zu reformieren.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/83"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Bundeswehreinsatz im Irak</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Militär</span><span data-slot="badge">Irak</span><span data-slot="badge">Terrorismusbekämpfung</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Fortsetzung des Einsatzes bewaffneter deutscher Streitkräfte im Irak, um die Stabilisierung des Landes zu sichern, ein Wiedererstarken des IS (Islamischer Staat) zu verhindern und die Versöhnung im Irak zu fördern. Der Bundestag stimmt über den Antrag der Bundesregierung ab, diesen Einsatz bis zum 31. Januar 2026 mit bis zu 500 Soldatinnen und Soldaten zu verlängern.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>18. Oktober 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/84"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Änderungsantrag zur „Verbesserung der inneren Sicherheit“</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Innere Sicherheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Asylrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Migrationspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Grenzschutz</span><span data-slot="badge">Terrorismusbekämpfung</span><span data-slot="badge">Waffenrecht</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft einen Änderungsantrag der CDU/CSU-Fraktion zu einem Gesetzentwurf, der die innere Sicherheit und das Asylsystem verbessern soll, insbesondere durch Änderungen im Asylgesetz und im Ausweisungsrecht.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/85"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Artikel 5 des Entwurfs „Verbesserung der inneren Sicherheit“ (2. Beratung)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Inneres</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Waffenrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Extremismus</span><span data-slot="badge">Terrorismus</span><span data-slot="badge">Öffentliche Sicherheit</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft Artikel 5 eines Gesetzentwurfs, der darauf abzielt, das Waffenrecht zu verschärfen, um Extremisten und Terroristen den Zugang zu Waffen zu erschweren und die öffentliche Sicherheit zu erhöhen.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/86"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Gesetzentwurf „Verbesserung der Terrorismusbekämpfung“</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Innere Sicherheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Terrorismusbekämpfung</span><span data-slot="badge">Extremismusprävention</span><span data-slot="badge">Datenschutz</span><span data-slot="badge">Bürgerrechte</span><span data-slot="badge">Waffenrecht</span></p><p>Der Gesetzentwurf zur Verbesserung der Terrorismusbekämpfung zielt darauf ab, den Sicherheitsbehörden im digitalen Raum zusätzliche Befugnisse zu geben und die Zusammenarbeit zwischen Bund, Ländern und zivilgesellschaftlichen Akteuren zu stärken, um extremistischen und islamistischen Tendenzen entgegenzuwirken.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/87"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Gesetzentwurf „Verbesserung der inneren Sicherheit“</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Innere Sicherheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Asylrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Waffenrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Extremismus</span><span data-slot="badge">Terrorismusbekämpfung</span></p><p>Der Gesetzentwurf zur Verbesserung der inneren Sicherheit und des Asylsystems betrifft die Anpassung von Gesetzen, um die innere Sicherheit Deutschlands zu stärken und das Asylsystem effektiver zu gestalten. Er reagiert auf aktuelle Bedrohungen und soll den Behörden mehr Handlungsspielraum geben.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/88"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Erster Entschließungsantrag zur „Verbesserung der inneren Sicherheit“</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Innere Sicherheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Asylpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Migrationspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Waffenrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Islamismus</span><span data-slot="badge">Extremismusbekämpfung</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Entschließungsantrag der CDU/CSU zum Gesetzentwurf zur Verbesserung der inneren Sicherheit und des Asylsystems, der sich mit der Migrationspolitik, dem Waffenrecht und der Bekämpfung des Islamismus auseinandersetzt.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/89"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Zweiter Entschließungsantrag zur „Verbesserung der inneren Sicherheit“</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Innere Sicherheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Asylpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Waffenrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Migrationspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Extremismusprävention</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft einen Entschließungsantrag der CDU/CSU zum Gesetzentwurf zur Verbesserung der inneren Sicherheit und des Asylsystems, der sich gegen die Schwerpunkte der Regierungsfraktionen im Bereich Waffenrecht richtet und stattdessen eine andere Migrations- und Sicherheitspolitik fordert.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/90"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Dritter Entschließungsantrag zur „Verbesserung der inneren Sicherheit“</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Innere Sicherheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Asylrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Migration</span><span data-slot="badge">Grenzschutz</span><span data-slot="badge">EU-Recht</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft einen Entschließungsantrag der CDU/CSU-Fraktion zu einem Gesetzentwurf, der die innere Sicherheit und das Asylsystem verbessern soll. Der Antrag zielt darauf ab, die Bundesregierung zu umfassenden Zurückweisungen von Personen ohne Einreiserecht an den deutschen Grenzen aufzufordern.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/91"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Ablehnung eines Antrags zu Messerangriffen</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Inneres</span><span data-slot="badge">Recht</span><span data-slot="badge">Kriminalität</span><span data-slot="badge">Waffenrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Migration</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheit</span></p><p>Die Beschlussempfehlung des Ausschusses für Inneres und Heimat betrifft die Ablehnung eines Antrags der AfD-Fraktion, der eine gezielte Sanktionierung von Messerangriffen anstelle von Verschärfungen im Waffenrecht fordert.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/92"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Ablehnung eines Antrags zu Drittstaatenangehörigen</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Asylrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Migrationspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Grenzkontrolle</span><span data-slot="badge">Rücknahmeabkommen</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Antrag der AfD-Fraktion, die Bundesregierung zu verpflichten, Drittstaatsangehörige an den Außengrenzen Deutschlands zurückzuweisen und bilaterale Rücknahmeabkommen mit Nachbarstaaten anzuwenden.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>16. Dezember 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/93"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Antrag gemäß Artikel 68 des Grundgesetzes (Vertrauensfrage)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Politik</span><span data-slot="badge">Regierung</span><span data-slot="badge">Grundgesetz</span><span data-slot="badge">Vertrauensfrage</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Vertrauensfrage gemäß Artikel 68 des Grundgesetzes, bei der der Bundeskanzler das Vertrauen des Bundestages ausspricht. Der Bundeskanzler beabsichtigt, vor der Abstimmung eine Erklärung abzugeben.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>19. Dezember 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/94"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Gesetzentwurf zur Änderung von Artikel 93 und 94 des Grundgesetzes (Bundesverfassungsgericht)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Verfassungsrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Bundesverfassungsgericht</span><span data-slot="badge">Rechtsstaat</span><span data-slot="badge">Politik</span><span data-slot="badge">Justiz</span></p><p>Der Gesetzentwurf betrifft die Änderung des Grundgesetzes in Bezug auf die Stellung und Struktur des Bundesverfassungsgerichts, indem Artikel 93 und 94 punktuell ergänzt und deren Inhalte systematisch neu geordnet werden. Ziel ist es, die Organqualität des Bundesverfassungsgerichts sowie die unmittelbare Bindung der öffentlichen Gewalt an seine Entscheidungen stärker hervorzuheben.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Arc-AGI-2 and ARC Prize 2025 (169 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arcprize.org/blog/announcing-arc-agi-2-and-arc-prize-2025</link>
            <guid>43465147</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 20:35:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arcprize.org/blog/announcing-arc-agi-2-and-arc-prize-2025">https://arcprize.org/blog/announcing-arc-agi-2-and-arc-prize-2025</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43465147">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
		

<div>
    <p><a href="https://arcprize.org/arc-agi#arc-agi-2"><img src="https://arcprize.org/media/images/blog/arc-agi-2-years.jpg" alt="ARC-AGI-2 challenges test-time reasoning"></a>
    </p>
    <p><a href="https://arcprize.org/competition"><img src="https://arcprize.org/media/images/blog/arc-prize-2025-card.png" alt="Launching ARC Prize 2025"></a>
    </p>
</div>

<h3 id="level-up-to-reach-agi">Level Up to Reach AGI</h3>

<p>Good AGI benchmarks act as useful progress indicators. Better AGI benchmarks clearly discern capabilities. The best AGI benchmarks do all this and actively inspire research and guide innovation.</p>

<p>At ARC Prize, our mission is to serve as a North Star towards AGI through enduring benchmarks, directing efforts towards systems capable of general intelligence and significantly compressing the timeline for scientific breakthroughs.</p>

<p>ARC-AGI-1 has measured progress towards AGI since 2019 and was the only benchmark to <a href="https://arcprize.org/oai-o3-pub-breakthrough">pinpoint the exact moment in late 2024</a> when AI moved beyond pure memorization. OpenAI used ARC-AGI-1 to demonstrate this progress with their o3 system which combines deep learning-based LLMs with reasoning synthesis engines.</p>

<p>ARC Prize 2024 inspired thousands of independent <a href="https://arcprize.org/blog/2024-university-tour-recap">students</a> and <a href="https://arcprize.org/2024-results">researchers</a> to work alongside frontier labs on new test-time adaption ideas.</p>

<p>But there is more work to do to reach AGI. AGI still needs new ideas.</p>

<p>We can characterize systems like o3 as going from "zero to one" on the fluid intelligence spectrum. But these systems are highly inefficient and currently require significant human supervision during the training process to adapt to new domains.</p>

<h4 id="announcements">Announcements</h4>

<p>Today we’re excited to launch ARC-AGI-2 to challenge the new frontier. ARC-AGI-2 is even harder for AI (in particular, AI reasoning systems), while maintaining the same relative ease for humans. Pure LLMs score 0% on ARC-AGI-2, and public AI reasoning systems achieve only single-digit percentage scores. In contrast, every task in ARC-AGI-2 has been solved by at least 2 humans in under 2 attempts.</p>

<p>Alongside it, today we're announcing <a href="https://arcprize.org/competition">ARC Prize 2025</a> (going live on Kaggle this week), designed to drive open-source progress on highly efficient, general systems capable of beating ARC-AGI-2.</p>

<hr>

<h3 id="easy-for-humans-hard-for-ai">Easy for Humans, Hard for AI</h3>

<p>All other AI benchmarks focus on superhuman capabilities or specialized knowledge by testing "PhD++" skills. ARC-AGI is the only benchmark that takes the opposite design choice – by focusing on tasks that are relatively easy for humans, yet hard, or impossible, for AI, we shine a spotlight on capability gaps that do not spontaneously emerge from "scaling up".</p>

<p>The ARC Prize Foundation adapts this into our definition for measuring AGI: the gap between the set of tasks that are easy for humans and hard for AI. When this gap is zero, when there are no remaining tasks, we can find that challenge AI, we will have achieved AGI.</p>

<p>Addressing these capability gaps requires novel insight and new ideas. Importantly, ARC-AGI does not exist purely to measure AGI progress. It also exists to inspire researchers to work on new ideas.</p>

<p>Intelligence requires the ability to generalize from limited experience and apply knowledge in new, unexpected situations. AI systems are already superhuman in many specific domains (e.g., playing Go and image recognition.) However, these are narrow, specialized capabilities. The "human-ai gap" reveals what's missing for general intelligence - highly efficiently acquiring new skills.</p>

<hr>

<h3 id="introducing-arc-agi-2">Introducing ARC-AGI-2</h3>

<p>The ARC-AGI-2 benchmark launches today. This second edition in the ARC-AGI series raises the bar for difficulty for AI while maintaining the same relative ease for humans.</p>

<p>Every ARC-AGI-2 task was solved by at least 2 humans in 2 attempts or less in a controlled study with hundreds of human participants. This matches the rules we hold for AI, which gets two attempts per task.</p>

<p>ARC-AGI-1, introduced in 2019, was designed to challenge deep learning. Specifically, it was designed to resist the ability to simply "memorize" the training dataset. ARC-AGI comprises a training dataset and several evaluation sets, including a private eval set used for the ARC Prize 2024 contest. The training set is intended to teach the Core Knowledge Priors required to solve tasks in the evaluation sets. To solve the evaluation tasks, AI systems must demonstrate basic fluid intelligence or the ability to adapt to novel, never-before-seen tasks.</p>

<p>As an analogy, think of the training set as a way to learn grade school math symbols, and the evaluation set requires you to solve algebra equations using your knowledge of those symbols. You cannot simply memorize your way to the answer, you must apply existing knowledge to new problems.</p>

<p>Any AI system capable of beating ARC-AGI-1 demonstrates a binary level of fluid intelligence. In contrast, ARC-AGI-2 significantly raises the bar for AI. To beat it, you must demonstrate <em>both</em> a high level of adaptability and high efficiency.</p>

<p>While designing ARC-AGI-2, we studied these properties of frontier AI reasoning systems. Below are example tasks to illustrate some of what we discovered. All of the following tasks are part of ARC-AGI-2 and were (1) solved by at least 2 humans in under 2 attempts and (2) unsolved by any frontier AI reasoning system.</p>

<p><em>Note: special thank you to the ARC Prize community for contributing to this analysis, including <a href="https://substack.com/home/post/p-153619775">Mace</a>, <a href="https://anokas.substack.com/p/llms-struggle-with-perception-not-reasoning-arcagi">Mikel</a>, and many members in the <a href="https://discord.com/channels/1237180803335720961/1319729162466099290">ARC Prize Discord</a>.</em></p>

<hr>

<h3 id="still-hard-for-ai">Still Hard for AI</h3>

<h4 id="symbolic-interpretation">Symbolic Interpretation</h4>

<p>We found that frontier AI reasoning systems struggle with tasks requiring symbols to be interpreted as having meaning beyond their visual patterns. Systems attempted symmetry checking, mirroring, transformations, and even recognized connecting elements, but failed to assign semantic significance to the symbols themselves.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://arcprize.org/media/images/blog/arc-agi-2-unsolved-1.png" alt="ARC-AGI-2 Pubic Eval Task: #e3721c99">
  <figcaption>Example of symbolic interpretation, ARC-AGI-2 Pubic Eval Task #e3721c99. <a href="https://arcprize.org/play?id=e3721c99" target="_blank">Try this task.</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<h4 id="compositional-reasoning">Compositional Reasoning</h4>

<p>We found AI reasoning systems struggle with tasks requiring simultaneous application of rules, or application of multiple rules that interact with each other. In contrast, if a task only has one, or very few, global rules, we found these systems can consistently discover and apply them.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://arcprize.org/media/images/blog/arc-agi-2-unsolved-2.png" alt="ARC-AGI-2 Pubic Eval Task: #cbebaa4b">
  <figcaption>Example of compositional reasoning, ARC-AGI-2 Pubic Eval Task #cbebaa4b. <a href="https://arcprize.org/play?id=cbebaa4b" target="_blank">Try this task.</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<h4 id="contextual-rule-application">Contextual Rule Application</h4>

<p>We found AI reasoning systems struggle with tasks where rules must be applied differently based on context. Systems tend to fixate on superficial patterns rather than understanding the underlying selection principles.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://arcprize.org/media/images/blog/arc-agi-2-unsolved-3.png" alt="ARC-AGI-2 Pubic Eval Task: #b5ca7ac4">
  <figcaption>Example of contextual rule application, ARC-AGI-2 Pubic Eval Task #b5ca7ac4. <a href="https://arcprize.org/play?id=b5ca7ac4" target="_blank">Try this task.</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<hr>

<h3 id="datasets">Datasets</h3>

<p>ARC-AGI-2 is comprised of the following datasets:</p>

<table>
    <tbody><tr>
        <th>Dataset</th>
        <th>Task Quantity</th>
        <th>Calibration</th>
        <th>Visibilty</th>
        <th>Description</th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td><a href="https://github.com/arcprize/ARC-AGI-2/tree/main/data/training">Training</a></td>
        <td>1000</td>
        <td>Uncalibrated</td>
        <td>Public</td>
        <td>A spectrum of difficulty ranging from very easy to very difficult for both humans and AI, designed to expose and teach Core Knowledge Priors; use to train your system.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td><a href="https://github.com/arcprize/ARC-AGI-2/tree/main/data/evaluation">Public Eval</a></td>
        <td>120</td>
        <td>Calibrated</td>
        <td>Public</td>
        <td>All tasks solved pass@2 by at least two humans; use to test your system.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td><a href="https://arcprize.org/guide#semi-private">Semi-Private Eval</a></td>
        <td>120</td>
        <td>Calibrated</td>
        <td>Private</td>
        <td>All tasks solved pass@2 by at least two humans, used for the Kaggle live contest leaderboard and ARC Prize leaderboard. "Semi" means these tasks may have been exposed to limited third-parties (e.g., via API.)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td><a href="https://arcprize.org/guide#private">Private Eval</a></td>
        <td>120</td>
        <td>Calibrated</td>
        <td>Private</td>
        <td>All tasks solved pass@2 by at least two humans, used for Kaggle final contest leaderboard. "Private" means these tasks have not been exposed to third-parties.</td>
    </tr>
</tbody></table>

<p><code>Calibrated</code> means that these tasks are IDD (independent and identically distributed). In principle, non-overfit scores across the public, semi-private, and private eval sets should be directly comparable. To gather these data, we tested with over 400 humans live in a controlled setting. Human solvability data for public tasks will be open-sourced alongside the ARC-AGI-2 paper in the coming weeks.</p>

<p>Like ARC-AGI-1, ARC-AGI-2 uses a <code>pass@2</code> measurement system to account for the fact that certain tasks have explicit ambiguity and require two guesses to disambiguate. As well as to catch any unintentional ambiguity or mistakes in the dataset. Given controlled human testing with ARC-AGI-2, we are more confident in the task quality compared to ARC-AGI-1.</p>

<p>Here's the official <code>changelog</code> for ARC-AGI-2:</p>

<ol>
    <li>All eval sets (public, semi-private, private) now contain 120 tasks (up from 100).</li>
    <li>Removed tasks from eval sets that were susceptible to brute force search (all solved tasks from the original <a href="https://www.kaggle.com/competitions/abstraction-and-reasoning-challenge">2020 Kaggle contest</a>).</li>
    <li>Performed controlled human testing to calibrate eval set difficulty to ensure IDD and verify pass@2 solvability by at least 2 humans (to match AI rules).</li>
    <li>Designed new tasks to challenge AI reasoning systems based on study (symbolic interpretation, compositional reasoning, contextual rules, and more).</li>
</ol>

<p>We've also re-evaluated ARC-AGI-2 against all public AI systems. Here are the starting scores.</p>

<table>
    <tbody><tr>
        <td><b>System</b></td>
        <td><b>ARC-AGI-1</b></td>
        <td><b>ARC-AGI-2</b></td>
        <td><b>Efficiency (cost/task)</b></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>Human panel (at least 2 humans)</td>
        <td>98%</td>
        <td>100%</td>
        <td>$17</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>Human panel (average)</td>
        <td>64.2%</td>
        <td>60%</td>
        <td>$17</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>o3-low (CoT + Search/Synthesis)</td>
        <td>75.7%</td>
        <td>4%*</td>
        <td>$200</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>o1-pro (CoT + Search/Synthesis)</td>
        <td>~50%</td>
        <td>1%*</td>
        <td>$200*</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>ARChitects (Kaggle 2024 Winner)</td>
        <td>53.5%</td>
        <td>3%</td>
        <td>$0.25</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>o3-mini-high (Single CoT)</td>
        <td>35%</td>
        <td>0.0%</td>
        <td>$0.41</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>r1 and r1-zero (Single CoT)</td>
        <td>15.8%</td>
        <td>0.3%</td>
        <td>$0.08</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>gpt-4.5 (Pure LLM)</td>
        <td>10.3%</td>
        <td>0.0%</td>
        <td>$0.29</td>
    </tr>
</tbody></table>

<p><em>Scores labeled with * are in-progress estimates based on partial results we've been able to aggregate so far and o1-pro pricing. Full results will be published once available.</em></p>

<p>All scores reported pass@2 and on the semi-private eval set (except ARC-AGI-1 human panel and ARChitects, which used public and private eval, respectively).</p>

<p>Human panel efficiency is based upon a $115-150 show-up fee, plus a $5/task solve incentive. We optimized costs to produce show-ups (only 70% of registrations actually showed up). Even though we believe the true limit to human intelligence cost efficiency is likely in the $2-5/task range, we report $17/task to reflect the actual data we collected.</p>

<p>We are looking forward to testing the production version of OpenAI o3 low/high once API access is available. Using ARC-AGI-1 tasks that transferred to ARC-AGI-2, we estimate that o3-low would score ~4% and o3-high would potentially score up to 15-20% with very high compute (thousands of dollars per task).</p>

<hr>

<h3 id="intelligence-is-not-just-capability">Intelligence Is Not Just Capability</h3>

<p>Going forward, all ARC-AGI reporting will come along with an efficiency metric. We are starting with cost because it is the most directly comparable between human and AI performance.</p>

<p>Intelligence is not solely defined by the ability to solve problems or achieve high scores. The efficiency with which those capabilities are acquired and deployed is a crucial, defining component. The core question being asked is not just, "Can AI acquire skill to solve a task?" but also, "At what efficiency or cost?"</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://arcprize.org/media/images/arc-agi-2-efficiency.jpg" alt="ARC-AGI-2: Scale is Not Enough">
  <figcaption>Frontier AI system scores on ARC-AGI-1 vs. ARC-AGI-2</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>We know that brute-force search could eventually solve ARC-AGI (given unlimited resources and time to search). This would not represent true intelligence. Intelligence is about finding the solution efficiently, not exhaustively.</p>

<p>This focus on efficiency is a core principle behind the ARC-AGI. We will now explicitly quantify the cost of intelligence, requiring solutions to demonstrate not just capability, but also the efficient use of resources that defines general intelligence.</p>

<p>Our <a href="https://arcprize.org/leaderboard">new leaderboard page</a> reports progress along both a score and cost axis.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://arcprize.org/media/images/leaderboard-20250323.png" alt="ARC-AGI new leaderboard">
  <figcaption>ARC-AGI's new leaderboard showing both score and efficiency as of March 24, 2025</figcaption>
</figure>

<hr>

<h3 id="competition-goes-live-this-week-1000000-in-prizes">Competition Goes Live this Week! $1,000,000 in Prizes</h3>

<p>
<iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/z6cTTkVqAyg?si=ndNcx1LavLvp2sQ8&amp;controls=0" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</p>

<!--Alongside ARC-AGI-2, we're excited to announce the <a href="https://www.kaggle.com/competitions/arc-prize-2025">ARC Prize 2025 Kaggle Competition</a>.-->
<p>Alongside ARC-AGI-2, we're excited to announce <a href="https://arcprize.org/competition">ARC Prize 2025 is back</a>! The contest will be again hosted on Kaggle between March and November. The competition goes live later this week, sign up <a href="#" data-modal-id="signup">here</a> to get notified.</p>

<p>There is $125K in guaranteed progress prizes, with an additional $700K Grand Prize (up $100k from last year!) waiting to be unlocked by a solution that scores greater than 85%, as well as $175K to-be-announced prizes.</p>

<p>Unlike the <a href="https://arcprize.org/leaderboard">public leaderboard</a> on arcprize.org, Kaggle rules restrict you from using internet APIs, and you only get ~$50 worth of compute per submission. In order to be eligible for prizes, contestants must open source and share their solution and work into the public domain at the end of the competition.</p>

<p>Last year's competition saw incredible success — over 1,500 teams participated, generating 40 influential research papers. ARC Prize-winning researchers introduced innovations now adopted across the AI industry.</p>

<p>What progress can you unlock and share with the world this year?</p>

<h4 id="prize-categories">Prize Categories</h4>

<p><strong>Grand Prize ($700K)</strong><br>
Unlocked once first team reaches 85% within Kaggles efficiency limits.</p>

<p><strong>Top Score Prize ($75K)</strong><br>
Awarded to the highest-scoring submissions.</p>

<p><strong>Paper Prize ($50K)</strong><br>
Awarded to the submission demonstrating the most significant conceptual progress toward solving ARC-AGI. Papers must be tied to a scored submission, but innovative ideas matter more than achieving a high score.</p>

<p><strong>To-be-announced Prizes ($175k)</strong><br>
More details on these coming during the 2025 competition.</p>

<p>You can find more details on our <a href="https://arcprize.org/competition">Competition page</a>.</p>

<h4 id="changelog">Changelog</h4>

<p>Here's a quick look at the competition <code>changelog</code> from 2024 to 2025.</p>

<ol>
    <li><strong>ARC-AGI-2:</strong> we've replaced the ARC-AGI-1 dataset going forward.</li>
    <li><strong>New leaderboard reporting:</strong> The Kaggle live contest leaderboard will report scores on semi-private, with final prize results reported one time on the private eval after content closes.</li>
    <li><strong>Stronger open-source provisions:</strong> teams will be required to open source their solutions before receiving official private eval set scores.</li>
    <li><strong>More compute:</strong> 2x compute vs. 2024 (L4x4s), about $50 worth now.</li>
    <li><strong>More overfit prevention:</strong> we've made additional changes to score reporting on Kaggle to reduce data mining and overfiting and to incentivize conceptual progress.</li>
</ol>

<hr>

<h3 id="progress-depends-on-new-ideas--maybe-yours">Progress Depends On New Ideas — Maybe Yours?</h3>

<p>The current state of AI operates in an idea-constrained environment. The next breakthrough might not come from a major AI lab but from a new, creative approach from someone like you.</p>

<p>If you're driven by curiosity, inspired by complexity, and committed to the rigorous pursuit of genuine general intelligence, ARC Prize 2025 is your opportunity.</p>

<p>Join us in the pursuit of open science.</p>

<h4 id="ready-to-get-started">Ready to get started?</h4>

<p>Good luck! We can't wait to see what you build.</p>



	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cottagecore Programmers (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://tjmorley.com/blogposts/cottagecoreprogrammers.html</link>
            <guid>43464914</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 20:08:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://tjmorley.com/blogposts/cottagecoreprogrammers.html">https://tjmorley.com/blogposts/cottagecoreprogrammers.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43464914">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="Essay">
    <p>
    Every programmer I know has at some point longingly expressed how “[they] want to work with [their] hands”. Some say they wish they were a carpenter, some want to be in the fields on a farm, some want to raise chickens, or milk cows. It is however inevitable that I either hear someone say it or agree with it at some point. Often, the sentiment is accompanied by a general dissatisfaction with the impact of the speaker’s work or profession. Maybe someone just got a particularly mind-numbing feature request, or spent several weeks arguing in meetings about several pixels of padding for text on a button on a support page in a single app.
    </p>
    <p>
    One of the first examples that got me to notice this ongoing trend was back around the end of 2020, when a number of my friends shared and commented on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=24541964">a hackernews thread</a> about someone who had responded to a request to add an RSS feed to a DBMS with the news that he had quit programming and switched to carpentry, in a particularly pithy manner (as an aside, I took a look at his <a href="https://www.longwalkwoodworking.com/">woodworking shop</a> while writing this up, and it is quite beautiful, you should definitely check it out).
    </p>
    <p><img src="https://tjmorley.com/assets/rss_dbms_github.png" alt="Screenshot of a githhub post saying that the author missed a comment of many months ago because they no longer build software, but instead make furniture out of wood."></p><p>
    Now the relevant part here isn’t necessarily this particular post or person (It seems to me that he really prefers and loves woodworking over software which is of course completely valid, and I honestly understand it in many ways), but the reactions to it, many of which were wistful among people I knew as well as among the comments online. Though there was certainly debate between commenters(see the thread linked earlier if curious). If I had to sum up the reactions, they fell into two camps. It was split between a group who mainly expressed admiration and a desire to be doing similar work, interspersed with condemnations leveled towards modern software practices and businesses, and a second group who mainly saw the flaws in modern development as being similar to those in any other job, or who thought that other jobs were even worse off. My real interest in writing this post is exploring why people – especially tech workers – seem to resonate so strongly with stories such as this one, where other tech workers leave behind their positions to return to work based in crafts, agriculture, or homesteading. This is particularly interesting to me given the seeming stability of this fascination regardless of the economic situation for tech workers (in 2020, the market was quite strong, though there’s been noted layoffs in recent years). In fact, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/cscareerquestions/comments/1bjsan7/i_think_i_get_the_whole_drop_out_of_tech_and_do/">here</a> is another thread on reddit from a year ago referencing the same phenomenon. Another one <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/sysadmin/comments/p85p6b/this_guy_actually_did_leave_the_tech_life_to_be_a/?rdt=43971">here</a> I've only looked through the comments of, but many discuss their desire to leave IT for farming. If you aren't a tech worker, trust me in that you will hear people say how much they want this if you are a tech worker.
    </p>
    <p>
    ebd2’s post was just one particularly salient example, but if you’ve been online enough over the last decade or so, you’ve probably seen plenty of these kinds of posts in the same way I have, and not just from software developers or general tech workers. Across tech, it appears that many people are tired of working in offices, with computers, with meetings or emails, and want to abandon this life and start anew in more meaningful labor. In fact, over the last few years, there’s been a noted increase(see <a href="https://fox8.com/news/homesteading-taking-off-in-popularity-particularly-among-younger-generations/">here</a> or <a href="https://www.bbc.com/culture/article/20201208-cottagecore-and-the-rise-of-the-modern-rural-fantasy">here</a>) in a style of content that portrays idyllic lifestyles in times perceived as simpler, especially in short form video content. I can’t help but propose this “cottagecore” type content as deriving from the same zeitgeist.  For popular examples, take a look at <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nara_Smith">Nara Smith</a> making all sorts of odd things from scratch, or at the popular but ominous <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@TheBallerinaFarm/shorts">ballerina farm</a>, which inspired significant discussion over it’s formation (discussed <a href="https://www.thetimes.com/magazines/the-sunday-times-magazine/article/meet-the-queen-of-the-trad-wives-and-her-eight-children-plfr50cgk">here</a> among other places). If this content is so wildly popular, there’s certainly some form of backlash against modernity and a desire to turn back the clock.
    </p>
    <p>
    After hearing this desire to return to a more hands-on type of labor once again recently, I began to ask myself why it was so common. Why does everyone who sits behind a computer long to be out in the fields or workshops? Is this specific to some subgroup in tech that I happen to cross paths with regularly, or is it a broader modern ennui? To understand why I find the topic so interesting though, you’ll probably require a bit of background on me. I currently work as a researcher in the application of machine learning to problems in healthcare and genetics, but I was raised on a farm in a very rural area of Vermont. My mother’s side of the family have been farmers in the area for generations, generally growing and selling hay, as well as sheep and some amount of dairy farming. As a child on a farm, I of course helped work on the farm – throwing hay bales, carrying water buckets, shoveling massive piles of manure. I also worked in the associated side industries, like basic construction. I appreciate what I learned from this work, and the lessons were deeply valuable ones, but at the same time I would be lying if I didn’t admit that the intensity of it was a serious motivator for me to study harder than I otherwise would have and focus on technical skills, precisely so that I wouldn’t have to do physical labor anymore. I dreamed about the idea of getting paid to sit in an air conditioned office, free of clouds of dust, never having to deal with the constant little cuts and pricks from the blades of dried grass in the air of a hayloft slicing my arms over and over. Personally, I still like gardening, and there are parts of farming I enjoy quite a lot. If I lived in an area with more space, I would likely still farm as a hobby, but having your income or food supply come from it is a very different concept in terms of stress.
    </p>
    <p>
    Considering that, I hope it makes sense as to why I find this trend puzzling. Why would people who are so comfortable, whose job was to me a lifelong goal, want to do exactly what I worked so hard to move away from? I suspect the answer is tied up in the nature of our work in the modern world, as well as in the inspection of who has been mythologized in American history. So we’ll be taking a short departure from the modern day to look into this, if you’ll excuse the seeming change in subject. In the following sections, I’ll largely focus on this from the perspective of farming in terms of verbiage and discussion, but I believe many of these psychological yearnings and trends in the American populace in relation to manual craftsperson or homesteading type work have some similarities.
    </p>
    <h3>The Homesteader within the American Mythos</h3>
    <p>
    Farmers and small landowners in general have been largely lionized in American history, where examples abound of political figures extolling the virtues, necessity of, and unique individualism belonging to farmers. I’ll admit it’s a little flattering when people talk about the sort of work I did for so long as uniquely virtuous, but I’m left feeling unsure as to how healthy it is for a society to degrade some types of work in order to raise up others. For an example, think of William Jennings Bryan, an American politician popular among farmers in the late 19th century and after its turn. He had a large effect on the views of many rural Americans and regularly espoused the idea that agrarian work was inherently superior to other forms of labor. The classic example of his views is his famous “Cross of Gold” speech, where he said the following:
    </p>
    <blockquote cite="https://www.historymatters.gmu.edu/d/5354/">
        “You come to us and tell us that the great cities are in favor of the gold standard. I tell you that the great cities rest upon these broad and fertile prairies. Burn down your cities and leave our farms, and your cities will spring up again as if by magic. But destroy our farms and the grass will grow in the streets of every city in the country.” 
    </blockquote>
    <p><cite>William Jennings Bryan: “<a href="https://www.historymatters.gmu.edu/d/5354/">Cross of Gold” July 9, 1896, Chicago</a></cite></p>
    <p>The idea expressed here is clear – farms power the existence of the cities, so they should be shown more respect.</p>
    <p>
    Stepping back another century, think of Thomas Jefferson. He was arguably the primary supporter for the United States to be an agrarian republic during its founding, through his writings such as “Notes on the State of Virginia.” In mentioning this book, I must note that many viewpoints he expresses in it are clearly and deeply reprehensible, primarily his comments on race, and those on the law. Still, the views of Jefferson were advanced by many in the early days of the United States and he influenced much of the national consciousness, regardless of my opinion on him. Richard Hofstadter, an American historian has written thoroughly on the subject of this phenomenon and its impact on American values. His work includes much discussion of the social establishment of virtues in the United States around agrarianism, with one example being his essay “The Myth of the Happy Yeoman.” In it, he gives an excellent and concise description of the manner in which people such as Jefferson or Bryan argued about the superiority of rural life:
    </p>
    <blockquote cite="">
        “Like any complex of ideas, the agrarian myth cannot be defined in a phrase, but its component themes form a clear pattern. Its hero was the yeoman farmer, its central conception the notion that he is the ideal man and the ideal citizen. Unstinted praise of the special virtues of the farmer and the special values of rural life was coupled with the assertion that agriculture, as a calling uniquely productive and uniquely important to society, had a special right to the concern and protection of government. The yeoman, who owned a small farm and worked it with the aid of his family, was the incarnation of the simple, honest, independent, healthy, happy human being. Because he lived in close communion with beneficent nature, his life was believed to have a wholesomeness and integrity impossible for the depraved populations of cities.”
    </blockquote>
    <p><cite>Richard Hofstadter: “<a href="https://www.americanheritage.com/myth-happy-yeoman">The Myth of the Happy Yeoman</a>”, 1956</cite></p>
    <p>
    To me, this feels almost as if it could have been written today, in description aimed towards the varying videos and posts on social media waxing poetically on the forgotten idyllic lifestyles of life on the farm. Yet this was written almost seventy years ago, about topics which were in heavy discussion more than fifty years prior. Hofstadter even seems to imply in the essay that this ideal of the yeoman had declined, and says that “agrarian myth” was subsumed and replaced by an “even stronger ideal, the notion of opportunity, of career, of the self-made man.” If the agrarian myth declined and was subsumed, why does it seem to be re-energized today? The key here is the ideal of the self-made man, which brings our focus back to the present day. Though I think the feelings of ennui expressed by many tech workers that inspired me to write this are most pronounced in the field of programming, I don’t think they are limited solely to them.
    </p>
    <h3>Psychological Shifts in American Ideals</h3>
    <p>
    My general opinion is that the ideal of the “self-made man” has made a transition from a widely accepted goal to one viewed as contentious, and to many, unrealistic. The average American citizen no longer views stability in this way as a plausible concept, disheartened by <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/social-trends/2020/01/09/trends-in-income-and-wealth-inequality/">rising income inequality</a> and disillusioned by the proliferation of easily accessed get-rich-quick schemes (with obviously low rates of success) such as cryptocurrency, app-based stock trading within meme stocks, and exploitation of audiences by sudden social media stars. These feelings of despair often center around the idea of homeownership – central to the ideal of the yeoman and of any independent citizen is the idea of owning a residence, and of setting roots in an area. Whether or not owning housing is as achievable as it was in the past in the US is a complicated question – the rate of increase in housing costs has been significantly higher than the rate of increase in average wage over the last <a href="https://www.thezebra.com/resources/home/housing-trends-visualized/">60 years</a>, so housing is unarguably taking up a larger percentage of our income. Though data prior to 1980 on homeownership by age group is harder to come by, it appears that it has not changed dramatically for most groups (the main difference being a slight downward trend and a significant drop during and after the 2008 subprime mortgage crisis for most groups which are not older than age 65, while the 65+ group has over time increased their homeownership rates by about 5%).
    </p>
    <p><img src="https://tjmorley.com/assets/censushousing.png" alt="U.S. Census Bureau Housing and Vacancy survery showing 5 age categories percent homeownership rate remaining relatively stable from 1980s to today, with the only exceptions being those mentioned above."></p><p>
    One could argue, as many have, that some of this increase in housing cost is offset by decreased costs in other expenditures such as food or technology. However, the important point here is not about whether the material reality has effectively changed, but in how individuals currently perceive both the current reality and the past. As recently as two years ago, Americans polled on whether they believe that life for people like now compared to 50 years ago was better or worse generally said that they <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/short-reads/2023/04/24/americans-take-a-dim-view-of-the-nations-future-look-more-positively-at-the-past/">believed life was now worse.</a> There is a pervasive belief that life was better in the past and I believe that individuals who feel this way tend to move themselves towards social values that they see as indicative of the past, such as agrarian lifestyles. They retreat to an earlier part of the American psyche, to that of the independent farmer, escaping from the confusion and fear they see in a modern economy and impersonality of technology.
    </p>
    <p>
    One counterpoint to this is as follows – if this is prevalent in individuals employed in tech, could it truly be linked to income inequality? Many tech workers enjoy high incomes relative to the average worker in this country. This is true, but it draws us to our next point, that of alienation. This is a topic which is less grounded in surveys or statistics, but one which is more readily understood simply through discussion of how we view the nature of work. Many individuals find satisfaction from being appreciated for what they contribute in their work, a simple enough proposition. However, direct service and interaction with the individuals who benefit from your work is generally not an efficiency within a market. One baker making bread for his neighbors may find more satisfaction in that, but wouldn’t it be more efficient to have a centralized bread distribution factory, staffed by hundreds of bakers, who have their pooled effort in the form of hearty loaves of glutenous manna distributed efficiently across multiple communities? As we create more and more efficient economies across a variety of fields of work, we continually disentangle and alienate individuals from the effects and recipients of their labor. When you become detached from the meaning behind your work in this way though, it becomes difficult to assign meaning to your work.
    </p>
    <p>
    It is difficult to think of any field more forcibly disentangled from any sort of understanding of the impact of your labor than the majority of positions in tech. Through a series of entirely digital processes you are completing tasks which often, upon reflection, feel almost imaginary. Programs pushed through layers of committees work well to distribute responsibility for potential bugs or issues, but they have a secondary effect of  stripping much of the individual ownership of a given product. If you were some engineer working on a large corporate website, it’s less that you made the whole experience, and more that you contributed to it. You likely never see any indication of whether people appreciate or like the things that you made beyond abstract visit rates and click-through statistics, as opposed to a person acknowledging that you created something that they appreciate. Of course people in this position would feel deeply alienated from the work that they do over time, even when they logically understand the economic or personal value of what they create, the emotional connection they seek to find value through work is lacking. This is exactly where it ties back into the rising income inequality though – say you’re a programmer working at a company that you feel is draining your soul. You feel no connection to your work. But what else can you do? You’re fully aware that other careers pay far less, so why would you work in a different position, especially when you’ve already worked your way up the ladder within this one? This choice could feel even worse if you had a family depending on you. So instead many people detach, they start to feel more apathetic and they simply step through the motions. Some others instead start to yearn to turn back the clock to an almost mythical time period that they see depicted in popular media as better. It is exactly this combination of alienation from the meaning of one’s labor, a lack of confidence in the viability of a stable career-driven path to “success” or becoming “self-made” without luck, and a view of craft-based or agricultural labor as existing in a different time period possessing greater intrinsic meaning and inherent nobility which combine together within the American psyche to form a fascination with these types of work across social strata. Idealization of farming seems much more likely now that it almost feels mythical as compared to when most individuals likely either were engaged in it or knew someone who was.
    </p>
    <p><img src="https://tjmorley.com/assets/percent_labor_force_agricultural.png" alt="A chart with percent and year, with percent dropping from ~74% to ~2%-3% from the years 1800 to 2000."></p><p><cite>Image: Percent of the Labor Force Employed in Agriculture, United States, 1800 to 2000. Source: Ruggles, Steven. (2007). The Decline of Intergenerational Coresidence in the United States, 1850 to 2000. American sociological review. 72. 964-989. 10.1177/000312240707200606.</cite></p>
    <p>
    In the above chart, Dr. Ruggles demonstrates as part of his paper on the decline of intergenerational coresidence in the US the astronomical change in the amount of agricultural workers in the country, dropping from it being the occupation of the vast majority of the labor force to only a tiny percent over the last few decades. Importantly, there is now no American alive who remembers the country when more than a 20%-30% of its workers were employed in agriculture. The median American by age, in their late 30s currently, has only ever known a world where a single-digit proportion of the US workforce was working agriculturally.
    </p>
    <p>
    In fact, given these statistics I would take the point of these sort of agrarian type jobs seeming mythical a step further, given that so few Americans are familiar with the actual work behind jobs in the agricultural sector or related ones, I would argue that for many Americans the reality of this type of work is almost indistinguishable from fables or myth in their psychological context, due to lack of exposure. Due to that seeming separation from their mental context of what work is, it enhances the feeling of escapism which this work-fantasy provides, though the conception many hold of it is even more accurately described as a fable due to the significant difference between reality and the projection which many seem to aim for in their cottagecore fantasy. Certainly on Instagram or TikTok you can find depictions of women waltzing through their gardens, baby in their arms, cheery-faced while their husband walks around with flannel and chops wood and their goats bleat in the distance and a chicken pecks in the yard. This idyllic view certainly leaves out the part where she has to take a pick and scrape dirt and feces out of those goats hooves and trim them on a regular basis to prevent foot-rot (They certainly didn’t evolve to walk in dirt all day, but to jump around on rocks). It doesn’t touch on when they hadn’t realized that they had too high a rooster hen ratio, and woke up to find one rooster pulling the eyes of another one out of its skull. It certainly doesn’t display the economic difficulties inherent in these agricultural endeavors: checking your fruit trees and seeing half your apples have one large bite out of them from deer, looking in your coop and seeing that several of your hens got dragged off by foxes or coyotes, having one of your prime dairy cows die due to complications after a stillbirth, going to water your large tomato crop and finding that blister beetles have started stripping all the foliage from your plants. The possibilities are endless and the situations are often dirty and difficult, and while for a hobby farm these are just unfortunate setbacks, if your ability to put food on the table for your family is determined by the outcome of these sort of situations, then they’re less of a setback and more of a devastating blow to whether or not you can remain economically solvent.
    </p>
    <p>
    The idealization of farmers and craftsmen is not unique to the USA either(see Tolstoy’s opinions on agrarianism as well), but I can primarily speak to how people feel about the current climate of work within our country. I will say that I think many people yearning to turn back many changes in society are largely misguided in this – though there is absolutely value in hands on work, in serving one’s community, turning back the clock in all aspects risks erasing so many true gains we’ve made as a society, especially if the core of the issue is in our relationship with work as a society. Personally, I can’t deny that seeing someone doing work with their own two hands feels more authentic and true to me. I find the idea of others in my field who have never experienced physical labor very strange to consider. There is a clear flaw with some of this idealization though. The ideal of finding our value in work and making something of ourselves through the sweat of our brow is a noble one in many ways but contains a corrosive core as well. If you center your value entirely in how appreciative others are of the contributions you make, and in what you can provide, you ignore the actual concept of community, and you potentially build a worldview that denigrates those who you view as not contributing “enough” in your manner. This is purely my opinion, but I think the healthier way to approach this concept is one of sacrifice and service. If you have the capability to contribute work in some way – physical strength, knowledge, or mental acuity, then you have a moral responsibility to do so – yet not having as much capability as some other person is not something that should negate your self-worth. Instead, the act of doing what you can is what should be seen as virtuous, rather than the absolute economic output of your personal capability. Do what you can, build a community through simple acts of socialization and giving to others, and improve the lives of everyone around you. That is how we find fulfillment in a world such as this one.
    </p>
    <p><cite> Theodore Morley</cite></p>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Internet Archive Europe – Bringing Collections to Life (135 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.internetarchive.eu/</link>
            <guid>43464230</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 18:52:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.internetarchive.eu/">https://www.internetarchive.eu/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43464230">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content">

		
					<main id="main">
				<article class="page" id="post-282" itemtype="https://schema.org/CreativeWork" itemscope="itemscope">
	
				 <!-- .entry-header -->
		
<div data-ast-blocks-layout="true" itemprop="text">

	
	
<div><div><p><span>building</span></p><h2>Collective Intelligence</h2></div><p>Using AI Tools and our Shared Cultural Heritage</p><p><a href="https://www.internetarchive.eu/#contact" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer" onclick="return true;"><span>Get Involved</span><svg xmlns="https://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 512 512"><path d="M504.3 273.6l-112.1 104c-6.992 6.484-17.18 8.218-25.94 4.406c-8.758-3.812-14.42-12.45-14.42-21.1L351.9 288H32C14.33 288 .0002 273.7 .0002 255.1S14.33 224 32 224h319.9l0-72c0-9.547 5.66-18.19 14.42-22c8.754-3.809 18.95-2.075 25.94 4.41l112.1 104C514.6 247.9 514.6 264.1 504.3 273.6z"></path></svg></a></p></div>



<div>
<p>Internet Archive Europe is a project by the Dutch non-profit research library Stichting Internet Archive. It is building collections and tools to bring them to life.</p>



<p>Working with libraries, museums, and archives, we share these tools and collections to further everyone’s services.</p>
</div>



<div id="about">
<div><div><p>Our Journey</p><h2>Our role in Archiving and Preservation</h2></div><p>Internet Archive Europe began preserving European digital materials since its founding in 2004 in the Netherlands.  Then, working with dozens of European libraries and government agencies to build web collections, Internet Archive Europe prioritized collaboration with cultural heritage organizations to safeguard our collective history.<br></p></div>



<div><p><h2>Bringing research collections to life</h2></p><p>More recently, the library is leveraging AI and other tools to bring collections to life and demonstrate new interactions. If you would like to join us on these adventures, please contact us.<br></p></div>
</div>







<div id="team">
<p><h2>Our Team</h2></p>



<div>
<div id="beatrice"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Beatrice-Avatar-300x300.jpg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Beatrice Murch</h3><p><span>Program Manager</span></p><p>Beatrice returns to Non-Profit management after a long hiatus and is thrilled to once again be working to help preserve Universal Access to all Knowledge.</p></div>



<div id="ben"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/ben-cerveny-300x300.jpg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Ben Cerveny</h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>For over 25 years Ben Cerveny has worked as an executive, strategist, and designer in the context of operating systems, media applications, web services, products, the built environment, and digital games.</p></div>



<div id="bernt"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Bernt-Hugenholtz-crop-300x300.jpg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Bernt Hugenholtz</h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>Bernt Hugenholtz specializes in copyright, neighboring rights and information law. He is emeritus professor of Intellectual Property Law at the University of Amsterdam and former director of the Institute for Information Law (IViR).</p></div>



<div id="brewster"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Brewster-Kahle-300x300.jpeg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Brewster Kahle</h3><p><span>Board Member</span></p><p>A passionate advocate for public Internet access and a successful entrepreneur, Brewster Kahle has spent his career intent on a singular focus: providing Universal Access to All Knowledge. </p></div>



<div id="brigitte"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Brigitte_Veniza-150x150.jpeg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Brigitte Vezina </h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>Brigitte has a deep passion for issues raised by new and emerging technologies and loves to navigate uncharted waters to explore how the law, public policy, and evolving social frameworks can respond and anticipate challenges to the sharing of information, technological innovation, and new forms of creativity.</p></div>



<div id="daniel"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Daniel_Erasmus-150x150.jpeg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Daniel Erasmus</h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>Daniel has been and is facilitating scenario processes for diverse clients across three continents.&nbsp;Daniel pioneered the use of scenarios to facilitate deep dialogue about the emerging information society.&nbsp;</p></div>



<div id="edwin"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Edwin-van-Huis-LNKIN-150x150.jpeg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Edwin van Huis</h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>Edwin is the director of Naturalis Biodiversity Centre in Leiden. Previously he worked at the Rijksmuseum Amsterdam and at the Sound and Vision, the national archive for documentary film, television, radio and music, and the Ministry of Culture.</p></div>



<div id="jeff"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/JeffUbois-150x150.jpg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Jeff Ubois</h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>Jeff is a generalist with a background in philanthropy, innovation, media, archives, software, policy, research, venture-backed startups, and voluntary associations.</p></div>



<div id="jill"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Jill-Cousins-300x300.jpeg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Jill Cousins</h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>Jill Cousins continues the&nbsp;work with Digital Libraries&nbsp;and Europeana started in 2004&nbsp;advocating for&nbsp;digital transformation of cultural heritage, emphasizing the importance of open access, collaboration, and partnerships in making cultural heritage accessible to all.</p></div>



<div id="kaitlin"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/KaitlinThaney-300x300.jpg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Kaitlin Thaney</h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>Kaitlin Thaney’s career has been centered around open infrastructure organizations; helping them think strategically about program design, participatory engagement, and sustainability.</p></div>



<div id="marleen"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Marleen-Stikker-300x300.jpg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Marleen Stikker</h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>Marleen Stikker is founder and executive director of Waag Futurelab in Amsterdam. Waag has grown into a leading European research institute for technology and society, and encourages active citizenship by developing open, fair and inclusive technology.</p></div>



<div id="martin"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/martin-senftleben-150x150.jpg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Martin Senftleben</h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>Martin Senftleben is Professor of Intellectual Property Law and Director of the Institute for Information Law (IViR) at the Amsterdam Law School focusing on the reconciliation of private intellectual property rights with competing public interests of a social, cultural or economic nature.&nbsp;</p></div>



<div id="paul"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Paul_by_Stewart_Acker_Holt_CC_BY_b_w-300x300.jpg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Paul Keller</h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>Paul is the Director of Policy at Open Future. He has 20+ years of experience as a media activist, open policy advocate and systems architect to improve access to knowledge and culture.&nbsp;</p></div>



<div id="tony"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/TonyGuepin-300x300.jpeg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Tony Guepin</h3><p><span>Board Member</span></p><p>A long-time Software Entrepreneur, Tony brings his knowledge and detailed overview to support Universal Access to All Knowledge as a member of the board of the Stichting Internet Archive.</p></div>
</div>
</div>







<div>
<div>
<p><h3>Impact in Numbers</h3></p>
</div>



<div>
<div><p><span data-duration="1.5" data-to-value="500" data-from-value="0" data-delimiter=","></span><span>+</span></p><p>Over 1 million cultural items digitally archived since our inception, making history accessible to everyone.</p></div>



<div><p><span data-duration="1.5" data-to-value="95" data-from-value="0" data-delimiter=","></span><span>%</span></p><p>More than 500 partnerships with libraries, museums, and educational institutions across Europe and beyond.</p></div>
</div>
</div>



<div><div><p>Take Action Today</p><h2>Support Cultural Heritage Preservation Efforts</h2></div><p>Join our community and help us ensure that Europe’s rich cultural history remains accessible to all.</p></div>

	
	
</div><!-- .entry-content .clear -->

	
	
</article><!-- #post-## -->

			</main><!-- #main -->
			
		
	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Qwen2.5-VL-32B: Smarter and Lighter (475 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://qwenlm.github.io/blog/qwen2.5-vl-32b/</link>
            <guid>43464068</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 18:35:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://qwenlm.github.io/blog/qwen2.5-vl-32b/">https://qwenlm.github.io/blog/qwen2.5-vl-32b/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43464068">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div><p><a href="https://chat.qwenlm.ai/" target="_blank">QWEN CHAT</a>
<a href="https://github.com/QwenLM/Qwen2.5-VL" target="_blank">GITHUB</a>
<a href="https://huggingface.co/collections/Qwen/qwen25-vl-6795ffac22b334a837c0f9a5" target="_blank">HUGGING FACE</a>
<a href="https://modelscope.cn/collections/Qwen25-VL-58fbb5d31f1d47" target="_blank">MODELSCOPE</a>
<a href="https://discord.gg/yPEP2vHTu4" target="_blank">DISCORD</a></p><h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2><p>At the end of January this year, we launched the Qwen2.5-VL series of models, which received widespread attention and positive feedback from the community. Building on the Qwen2.5-VL series, we continued to optimize the model using reinforcement learning and open-sourced the new VL model with the beloved 32B parameter scale under the Apache 2.0 license — <strong>Qwen2.5-VL-32B-Instruct</strong>. Compared to the previously released Qwen2.5-VL series models, the features of this 32B VL model are as follows:</p><ul><li><strong>Responses More Aligned with Human Preferences</strong>: Adjusted the output style to provide more detailed, better-formatted answers that align more closely with human preferences.</li><li><strong>Mathematical Reasoning</strong>: Significant improvement in the accuracy of solving complex mathematical problems.</li><li><strong>Fine-grained Image Understanding and Reasoning</strong>: Enhanced accuracy and detailed analysis in tasks such as image parsing, content recognition, and visual logic deduction.</li></ul><h2 id="performance">Performance</h2><p>Extensive benchmarking against state-of-the-art (SoTA) models of comparable scale, <strong>Qwen2.5-VL-32B-Instruct</strong> has demonstrated superiority over baselines, e.g., Mistral-Small-3.1-24B and Gemma-3-27B-IT, even surpassing the larger <strong>Qwen2-VL-72B-Instruct</strong>. Notably, it achieves significant advantages in multimodal tasks such as <strong>MMMU</strong>, <strong>MMMU-Pro</strong>, and <strong>MathVista</strong>, which focus on complex, multi-step reasoning. On <strong>MM-MT-Bench</strong>, a benchmark emphasizing subjective user experience evaluation, <strong>Qwen2.5-VL-32B-Instruct</strong> outperforms its predecessor <strong>Qwen2-VL-72B-Instruct</strong> by a substantial margin.</p><figure><img src="https://qianwen-res.oss-cn-beijing.aliyuncs.com/Qwen2.5-VL-32B/qwen2.5vl-32b-vision.jpg" width="100%"></figure><p>In addition to excelling in visual capabilities, Qwen2.5-VL-32B-Instruct has also achieved top-tier performance in pure text capabilities at the same scale.</p><figure><img src="https://qianwen-res.oss-cn-beijing.aliyuncs.com/Qwen2.5-VL-32B/qwen2.5vl-32b-text.jpg" width="100%"></figure><h2 id="demo-cases">Demo Cases</h2><div><p><span>Fine-grained Image Understanding and Reasoning</span>
<a>Next</a></p><div><p>User</p><p>I am driving a large truck on this road, and it is now 12 o’clock. Can I reach a place 110 kilometers away before 13 o’clock?
<img loading="lazy" src="https://qianwen-res.oss-cn-beijing.aliyuncs.com/Qwen2.5-VL-32B/reasoning.png" alt="image"></p><p>Qwen2.5-VL-32B</p><div><p>To determine whether you can reach a place 110 kilometers away before 13:00, we need to analyze the information provided:</p><ol><li><strong>Current Time</strong>: It is 12:00.</li><li><strong>Distance to Destination</strong>: 110 kilometers.</li><li><strong>Speed Limit for Trucks</strong>: The speed limit sign indicates that the maximum speed for trucks is <strong>100 km/h</strong>.</li></ol><h3 id="step-by-step-analysis">Step-by-Step Analysis:</h3><h4 id="1-calculate-the-required-travel-time">1. <strong>Calculate the Required Travel Time</strong></h4><p>The formula to calculate travel time is:
\[
\text{Time} = \frac{\text{Distance}}{\text{Speed}}
\]
Given:</p><ul><li>Distance = 110 km</li><li>Maximum Speed = 100 km/h</li></ul><p>Substitute the values:
\[
\text{Time} = \frac{110 \text{ km}}{100 \text{ km/h}} = 1.1 \text{ hours}
\]</p><h4 id="2-convert-time-to-hours-and-minutes">2. <strong>Convert Time to Hours and Minutes</strong></h4><p>1.1 hours is equivalent to:
\[
1 \text{ hour} + 0.1 \times 60 \text{ minutes} = 1 \text{ hour} + 6 \text{ minutes} = 1 \text{ hour and } 6 \text{ minutes}
\]</p><h4 id="3-determine-arrival-time">3. <strong>Determine Arrival Time</strong></h4><p>If you start at 12:00 and it takes 1 hour and 6 minutes to travel 110 kilometers, your arrival time will be:
\[
12:00 + 1 \text{ hour and } 6 \text{ minutes} = 13:06
\]</p><h4 id="4-compare-with-target-time">4. <strong>Compare with Target Time</strong></h4><p>You want to arrive before 13:00. However, based on the calculations, you will arrive at 13:06, which is <strong>after</strong> 13:00.</p><h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion:</h3><p>Given the speed limit of 100 km/h for trucks, it is <strong>not possible</strong> to reach a place 110 kilometers away before 13:00.</p><p>Thus, the final answer is:
\[
\boxed{\text{No}}
\]</p></div></div></div><h2 id="next-step">Next Step</h2><p>While <strong>Qwen2.5-VL-32B</strong> has focused on optimizing subjective experience and mathematical reasoning through reinforcement learning—operating within the paradigm of <strong>“fast thinking”</strong>. Our next research direction will prioritize <strong>long and effective reasoning processes</strong> to push the boundaries of visual models in tackling highly complex, multi-step visual reasoning tasks.</p><h2 id="citation">Citation</h2><p>If you find our model helpful, feel free to cite it:</p><pre tabindex="0"><code>@article{Qwen2.5-VL,
  title={Qwen2.5-VL Technical Report},
  author={Bai, Shuai and Chen, Keqin and Liu, Xuejing and Wang, Jialin and Ge, Wenbin and Song, Sibo and Dang, Kai and Wang, Peng and Wang, Shijie and Tang, Jun and Zhong, Humen and Zhu, Yuanzhi and Yang, Mingkun and Li, Zhaohai and Wan, Jianqiang and Wang, Pengfei and Ding, Wei and Fu, Zheren and Xu, Yiheng and Ye, Jiabo and Zhang, Xi and Xie, Tianbao and Cheng, Zesen and Zhang, Hang and Yang, Zhibo and Xu, Haiyang and Lin, Junyang},
  journal={arXiv preprint arXiv:2502.13923},
  year={2025}
}
</code></pre></div></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I won't connect my dishwasher to your cloud (703 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/i-wont-connect-my-dishwasher-your-stupid-cloud</link>
            <guid>43463200</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 17:09:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/i-wont-connect-my-dishwasher-your-stupid-cloud">https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/i-wont-connect-my-dishwasher-your-stupid-cloud</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43463200">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>This weekend I had to buy a new dishwasher because our old GE died.</p>

<p>I bought a Bosch 500 series because that's what Consumer Reports recommended, and more importantly, I could find one in stock.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/bosch-dishwasher-open.jpg" width="700" height="394" data-insert-type="image" data-entity-type="file" data-entity-uuid="insert-image-882e0a2c-ac38-4027-8ed5-62f41af514f4" data-insert-attach="{&quot;id&quot;:&quot;882e0a2c-ac38-4027-8ed5-62f41af514f4&quot;,&quot;attributes&quot;:{&quot;alt&quot;:[&quot;alt&quot;,&quot;description&quot;],&quot;title&quot;:[&quot;title&quot;]}}" alt="Bosch dishwasher open control panel"></p>

<p>After my dad and I got it installed, I went to run a rinse cycle, only to find that <em>that</em>, along with features like delayed start and eco mode, require an app.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/bosch-dishwasher-home-connect.jpg" width="700" height="394" data-insert-type="image" data-entity-type="file" data-entity-uuid="insert-image-75c66f24-bf26-4873-9ca6-695e60ce93df" data-insert-attach="{&quot;id&quot;:&quot;75c66f24-bf26-4873-9ca6-695e60ce93df&quot;,&quot;attributes&quot;:{&quot;alt&quot;:[&quot;alt&quot;,&quot;description&quot;],&quot;title&quot;:[&quot;title&quot;]}}" alt="Bosch dishwasher Home Connect logo"></p>

<p>Not only that, to <em>use</em> the app, you have to connect your dishwasher to WiFi, set up a cloud account in something called Home Connect, and then, and only then, can you start using all the features on the dishwasher.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This blog post is a lightly-edited transcript of my latest YouTube video on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@Level2Jeff">Level 2 Jeff</a>: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5M_hmwBBPnc">I won't connect my dishwasher to your stupid cloud</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So getting back first to that old GE dishwasher, it was, I don't know, I think that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planned_obsolescence">planned obsolescence</a> is something that applies to many consumer products today.</p>

<p>Companies know if they design something to last only 5 or 10 years, that means in 5 or 10 years someone's going to have to buy a whole new one.</p>

<p>And on my GE Amana dishwasher, it started having weird power issues, like the controls would just not light up unless I reset the circuit breaker for a few minutes. That started happening more often, and this past Saturday it just wouldn't come on no matter what, even after I tested and re-wired it all the way from the panel up to the dishwasher's internal power connector.</p>

<p>So it was dead.</p>

<p>Next up, I looked at what it took to get a control board. Well... <a href="https://www.repairclinic.com/PartDetail/Control-Board/WD21X24901C/4980378">$299 for a control board</a> that was 'special order' and might not even fix the problem? That's a non-starter for my $600, 8-year-old dishwasher.</p>

<p>Even if I got it fixed, the front panel was starting to rust out at the hinge points (leaving some metal jaggies that my soon-to-be-crawling 6 month old could slice his fingers on), and other parts of the machine were showing signs of rust/potential future leaks...</p>

<p>It was Saturday night, and for a family of five, a dishwasher is kinda important. We don't have 1.5 hours every night to spend hand-washing dishes (not to mention the water bill!).</p>

<p>So I needed to get a new one, and it's really hard for me to schedule a few hours for my Dad and I to get it done in the middle of the week (plus that's multiple days without a dishwasher!).</p>

<p>So I did some research, and I found Bosch <em>seemed</em> to have the best bet for under $1,000, available locally on a Sunday.</p>

<p>Consumer Reports, random Redditors, etc. seemed to have some praises for Bosch—on Reddit many also praised Miele, but I couldn't find any of those available locally. And Consumer Reports especially praised <em>all</em> the Bosch units, with them topping all their reliability and customer satisfaction charts!</p>

<p>I remembered five or ten years ago, whenever I had bought my old GE, I remembered Bosch topped the charts too, but back then I settled for GE to save a few bucks...</p>

<h2>Installation was (mostly) great!</h2>

<p>So I spent a little more this time, hoping for a better experience. And installation was actually great—it was a lot easier to install the Bosch than it was that the GE.</p>

<p>It has a plastic base that slides better on the floor, and there's easier routing of the drain hose, inlet hose, and power wire that makes it less risky when you're pushing the thing into the blind cutout under the counter.</p>

<p>The one weird thing was that whoever like tightened the feet on the bottom at the factory must've used an impact driver or something because they were all practically embedded, and wouldn't budge.</p>

<p>I was turning the little screw on the front that pushes the rear foot down through a little gearing, but the worm gear slipped out and kinda shoved the long rod that connects the front to the back out of place. I had to buy a 10mm hex socket to wiggle the foot loose enough the gearing would actually work.</p>

<p>But once that was done, the rest of the install was seamless. (Thanks especially to some help from my Dad).</p>

<h2>First use, encountering the Cloud requirement</h2>

<p>So I turned it on, and immediately hated the new touch sensor stuff on it.</p>

<p>The old GE had buttons: you press them in, they click and you know that you pressed a button.</p>

<p>The touch sensor, you kind of touch it and the firmware—like this new dishwasher actually takes time to boot up! I had to reset it like three times and my wife meanwhile was like laughing at me like look at this guy who does tech stuff and he can't even figure out how to change the cycle on it.</p>

<p>That took about five minutes, sadly.</p>

<p>But eventually I pulled out the manual book because I was like... "this is actually confusing."</p>

<p>It should be like: I touch the button and it changes to that mode! But that was not how it was working.</p>

<p>I wanted to run just a rinse cycle to make sure the water would go in, the water would pump out through the sump, and everything worked post-install.</p>

<p>But I couldn't find a way to do a rinse cycle on the control panel.</p>

<p>So I looked in the manual and found this note:</p>

<p><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/bosch-dishwasher-manual-features-home-connect.jpg" width="700" height="394" data-insert-type="image" data-entity-type="file" data-entity-uuid="insert-image-b39c0aae-ac8e-4760-9392-88c7efa29bd6" data-insert-attach="{&quot;id&quot;:&quot;b39c0aae-ac8e-4760-9392-88c7efa29bd6&quot;,&quot;attributes&quot;:{&quot;alt&quot;:[&quot;alt&quot;,&quot;description&quot;],&quot;title&quot;:[&quot;title&quot;]}}" alt="Bosch dishwasher manual mention of Home Connect"></p>

<p>It says options with an asterisk—including Rinse, Machine Care (self-cleaning), HalfLoad, Eco, and Delay start, are "available through Home Connect app only and depending on your model."</p>

<p>The 500 series model I bought isn't premium enough to feature a 7-segment display like the $400-more-expensive <em>800</em> series, so these fancy modes are hidden behind an app and cloud service.</p>

<p>I was like, "Okay, I'll look up this app and see if I can use it over Bluetooth or locally or whatever."</p>

<p>Nope! To use the app, you have to connect your <em>dishwasher</em> to your <em>Wi-Fi</em>, which lets the dishwasher reach out on the internet to this Home Connect service.</p>

<p>You have to set up an account on Home Connect, set up the Home Connect app on your phone, and <em>then</em> you can control your dishwasher <em>through the Internet</em> to run a rinse cycle.</p>

<p>That doesn't make any sense to me.</p>

<p>An app? I mean, I can understand maybe adding some neat convenience features for those <em>who want them</em>. Like on my new fridge—which I chose not to connect to WiFI—it has an app that would allow me to monitor the inside temperature or look up service codes more easily. If I wanted those add-on features, which my old fridge didn't have, I could get them.</p>

<p>But requiring an app to access features that <em>used</em> to be controllable via buttons on the dishwasher itself—or <em>are still</em> if you pay $400 more for the fancy "800" model? That's <em>no bueno</em>.</p>

<h2>What can I do?</h2>

<p>Well, first of all, I could just not use those features. That's kind of annoying because I bought it with the assumption that I could run the cleaning cycle, that I could run the rinse cycle without having to have an app and Wi-Fi.</p>

<p>Another option is I could just connect it to my Wi-Fi, maybe on an IoT VLAN.</p>

<p>But it's not like a video doorbell, where an Internet connection adds on functionality, like being able to see who rang while you're on vacation, or storing security footage clips on the cloud so you have them available even after someone robs your house...</p>

<p>But a dishwasher... I'm not going to remote control my dishwasher and like, run an extra rinse cycle while I'm on a beach somewhere.</p>

<p>I don't need Internet on my dishwasher.</p>

<p>Another <em>third</em> option is somebody has reverse engineered this protocol and built <a href="https://github.com/osresearch/hcpy">HCPY</a>, a Home Connect Python library.</p>

<p>But here's the problem: I already spent like four hours getting this dishwasher installed in my kitchen. I don't want to spend another four hours configuring my own web UI for it—which still requires at least a one-time connection through Home Connect!—and maintaining that as a service on my local network, relying on an unauthorized third party library using reverse-engineering to get at the private dishwasher API!</p>

<h2>What can <em>we</em> do?</h2>

<p>I don't think we should let vendors get away with this stuff.</p>

<p>First, it lets product designers get lazy.</p>

<p>A feature like a little display, a little seven segment display that can show like two letters and a number of minutes remaining or something like that... How much does that cost?</p>

<p>How hard is it to integrate that into every model, even the cheap ones?</p>

<p>A lot of cheap dishwashers actually <em>have</em> those things, but not Bosch!</p>

<p>With Bosch, you have to pay $400 for the privilege of a little display!</p>

<p>Second, this might be a little bit conspiracy theory or whatever, but it feels like it's part of planned obsolescence. Just like with the GE, where a lot of parts are designed to rust out after 5 or 10 years.</p>

<p>If you have a cloud app, that means there's a cloud service that has to be running. That costs money to maintain.</p>

<p>And if there's no subscription fee right now, that means one of two things:</p>

<ol>
<li>They could be selling our data already.</li>
<li>At some point, they'll either close the service because it's a cost center (so the rinse cycle and eco mode on all these dishwashers just goes "POOF!"), <em>or</em> they're going move to a subscription model.</li>
</ol>

<p>All of a sudden, if you want to run the self-cleaning cycle, you better start paying five bucks to Bosch every month. <em>Forever</em>.</p>

<p>That's insane.</p>

<p>Third, it's a security hole in your local network.</p>

<p>Bosch might be a <em>little</em> better than some no-name light bulb company making IoT light bulbs on Amazon, but only a little.</p>

<p>I don't want to have Bosch having full internet access on my local network.</p>

<p>Their API would be able to talk back to my dishwasher, and the dishwasher—unless I put it on a VLAN, which 99% of consumers have no clue how to do that...</p>

<p>That's just something that shouldn't have to happen.</p>

<p>This is a dishwasher!</p>

<p>I don't know.</p>

<h2>What <em>should</em> be done?</h2>

<p>When I posted on social media about this, a lot of people told me to return it.</p>

<p>But I spent four hours installing this thing built into my kitchen.</p>

<p>I hooked it up to the water, it's running through cycles... it <em>is</em> working. I'll give them that. It does the normal stuff, but you know, there are some features that don't work without the app.</p>

<p>At a minimum, I think what Bosch should do is make it so that the dishwasher can be accessed locally with no requirement for a cloud account. (Really, it'd be even better to have all the functions accessible on the control panel!)</p>

<p>Anyone building an IoT device, here is my consumer-first, e-waste-reduction maxim:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>First local, <em>then</em> cloud.</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Cloud should be an add-on.</p>

<p>It should be a convenience for people who don't know how to do things like connect to their dishwasher with an app locally.</p>

<p>And it's not <em>that</em> hard.</p>

<p>A little ESP32, a little $1 chip that you can put in there could do all this stuff locally with no cloud requirement at all.</p>

<p>I think that there might be some quants or people who want to make a lot of money building all these cloud services.</p>

<p>I don't think that it's people who are consumer-first and eco-conscious because if they were, they would give <em>us</em> control first and <em>then</em> add on 'nice' quality of life features through a cloud service.</p>

<p>With my Bosch 500 series dishwasher, I was excited after the easy install (besides those leveling feet), then was let down <em>so hard</em> once I found out I couldn't use all the features it came with.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Project Operation Whitecoat (2010) (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://scholarworks.lib.csusb.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1201&amp;context=history-in-the-making</link>
            <guid>43462882</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 16:35:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://scholarworks.lib.csusb.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1201&#x26;context=history-in-the-making">https://scholarworks.lib.csusb.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1201&#x26;context=history-in-the-making</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43462882">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Trump Administration Accidentally Texted Me Its War Plans (974 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2025/03/trump-administration-accidentally-texted-me-its-war-plans/682151/</link>
            <guid>43462783</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 16:23:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2025/03/trump-administration-accidentally-texted-me-its-war-plans/682151/">https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2025/03/trump-administration-accidentally-texted-me-its-war-plans/682151/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43462783">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><header data-event-module="hero"><div><div><p>U.S. national-security leaders included me in a group chat about upcoming military strikes in Yemen. I didn’t think it could be real. Then the bombs started falling.</p></div><div><figure><div data-flatplan-lead_figure_media="true"><picture><img alt="A photo of Mike Waltz, JD Vance, and Pete Hegseth in the Oval Office" sizes="(min-width: 976px) 976px, 100vw" srcset="https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/f7Tr-k9n3n15dk24f6hAtRgLiUM=/0x312:6000x3687/750x422/media/img/mt/2025/03/GettyImages_2204323444-1/original.jpg 750w, https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/Y30kBmuhz6fmh-ITHUv5a-iG2Vs=/0x312:6000x3687/828x466/media/img/mt/2025/03/GettyImages_2204323444-1/original.jpg 828w, https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/D_O_vZvowTDT8nqHx0byy0U6ioE=/0x312:6000x3687/960x540/media/img/mt/2025/03/GettyImages_2204323444-1/original.jpg 960w, https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/-bqDGhPvCn4xGz7sgQaNIfKjziw=/0x312:6000x3687/976x549/media/img/mt/2025/03/GettyImages_2204323444-1/original.jpg 976w, https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/aB28uMeLzYWXTc3bBiWVg55IFdY=/0x312:6000x3687/1952x1098/media/img/mt/2025/03/GettyImages_2204323444-1/original.jpg 1952w" src="https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/D_O_vZvowTDT8nqHx0byy0U6ioE=/0x312:6000x3687/960x540/media/img/mt/2025/03/GettyImages_2204323444-1/original.jpg" id="article-lead-image" width="960" height="540"></picture></div><figcaption data-flatplan-lead_figure_caption="true">Andrew Harnik / Getty</figcaption></figure></div></div><div><p><time datetime="2025-03-24T16:06:10Z" data-flatplan-timestamp="true">March 24, 2025, 12:06 PM ET</time> </p></div><gpt-ad format="injector" sizes-at-0="mobile-wide" targeting-pos="injector-article-start" sizes-at-976="desktop-wide"></gpt-ad></header><section data-event-module="article body" data-flatplan-body="true"><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The world found out shortly before 2 p.m. eastern time on March 15 that the United States was bombing Houthi targets across Yemen.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">I, however, knew two hours before the first bombs exploded that the attack might be coming. The reason I knew this is that Pete Hegseth, the secretary of defense, had texted me the war plan at 11:44 a.m. The plan included precise information about weapons packages, targets, and timing.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">This is going to require some explaining.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The story technically begins shortly after the Hamas invasion of southern Israel, in October 2023. The Houthis—an Iran-backed terrorist organization whose motto is “God is great, death to America, death to Israel, curse on the Jews, victory to Islam”—soon launched attacks on Israel and on international shipping, creating havoc for global trade. Throughout 2024, the Biden administration was ineffective in countering these Houthi attacks; the incoming Trump administration promised a tougher response.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">This is where Pete Hegseth and I come in.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">On Tuesday, March 11, I received a connection request on Signal from a user identified as Michael Waltz. Signal is an open-source encrypted messaging service popular with journalists and others who seek more privacy than other text-messaging services are capable of delivering. I assumed that the Michael Waltz in question was President Donald Trump’s national security adviser. I did not assume, however, that the request was from the actual Michael Waltz. I have met him in the past, and though I didn’t find it particularly strange that he might be reaching out to me, I did think it somewhat unusual, given the Trump administration’s contentious relationship with journalists—and Trump’s periodic fixation on me specifically. It immediately crossed my mind that someone could be masquerading as Waltz in order to somehow entrap me. It is not at all uncommon these days for nefarious actors to try to induce journalists to share information that could be used against them.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">I accepted the connection request, hoping that this was the actual national security adviser, and that he wanted to chat about Ukraine, or Iran, or some other important matter.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">Two days later—Thursday—at 4:28 p.m., I received a notice that I was to be included in a Signal chat group. It was called the “Houthi PC small group.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">A message to the group, from “Michael Waltz,” read as follows: “Team – establishing a principles [<em>sic</em>] group for coordination on Houthis, particularly for over the next 72 hours. My deputy Alex Wong is pulling together a tiger team at deputies/agency Chief of Staff level following up from the meeting in the Sit Room this morning for action items and will be sending that out later this evening.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The message continued, “Pls provide the best staff POC from your team for us to coordinate with over the next couple days and over the weekend. Thx.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The term <em>principals committee</em> generally refers to a group of the senior-most national-security officials, including the secretaries of defense, state, and the treasury, as well as the director of the CIA. It should go without saying—but I’ll say it anyway—that I have never been invited to a White House principals-committee meeting, and that, in my many years of reporting on national-security matters, I had never heard of one being convened over a commercial messaging app.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">One minute later, a person identified only as “MAR”—the secretary of state is Marco Antonio Rubio—wrote, “Mike Needham for State,” apparently designating the current counselor of the State Department as his representative. At that same moment, a Signal user identified as “JD Vance” wrote, “Andy baker for VP.” One minute after that, “TG” (presumably Tulsi Gabbard, the director of national intelligence, or someone masquerading as her) wrote, “Joe Kent for DNI.” Nine minutes later, “Scott B”—apparently Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent, or someone spoofing his identity, wrote, “Dan Katz for Treasury.” At 4:53 p.m., a user called “Pete Hegseth” wrote, “Dan Caldwell for DoD.” And at 6:34 p.m., “Brian” wrote “Brian McCormack for NSC.” One more person responded: “John Ratcliffe” wrote at 5:24 p.m. with the name of a CIA official to be included in the group. I am not publishing that name, because that person is an active intelligence officer.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The principals had apparently assembled. In all, 18 individuals were listed as members of this group, including various National Security Council officials; Steve Witkoff, President Trump’s Middle East and Ukraine negotiator; Susie Wiles, the White House chief of staff; and someone identified only as “S M,” which I took to stand for Stephen Miller. I appeared on my own screen only as “JG.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">That was the end of the Thursday text chain.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">After receiving the Waltz text related to the “Houthi PC small group,” I consulted a number of colleagues. We discussed the possibility that these texts were part of a disinformation campaign, initiated by either a foreign intelligence service or, more likely, a media-gadfly organization, the sort of group that attempts to place journalists in embarrassing positions, and sometimes succeeds. I had very strong doubts that this text group was real, because I could not believe that the national-security leadership of the United States would communicate on Signal about imminent war plans. I also could not believe that the national security adviser to the president would be so reckless as to include the editor in chief of <em>The Atlantic</em> in such discussions with senior U.S. officials, up to and including the vice president.</p><hr><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The next day, things got even stranger.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">At 8:05 a.m. on Friday, March 14, “Michael Waltz” texted the group: “Team, you should have a statement of conclusions with taskings per the Presidents guidance this morning in your high side inboxes.” (<em>High side</em>, in government parlance, refers to classified computer and communications systems.) “State and DOD, we developed suggested notification lists for regional Allies and partners. Joint Staff is sending this am a more specific sequence of events in the coming days and we will work w DOD to ensure COS, OVP and POTUS are briefed.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">At this point, a fascinating policy discussion commenced. The account labeled “JD Vance” responded at 8:16: “Team, I am out for the day doing an economic event in Michigan. But I think we are making a mistake.” (Vance was indeed in Michigan that day.) The Vance account goes on to state, “3 percent of US trade runs through the suez. 40 percent of European trade does. There is a real risk that the public doesn’t understand this or why it’s necessary. The strongest reason to do this is, as POTUS said, to send a message.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The Vance account then goes on to make a noteworthy statement, considering that the vice president has not deviated publicly from Trump’s position on virtually any issue. “I am not sure the president is aware how inconsistent this is with his message on Europe right now. There’s a further risk that we see a moderate to severe spike in oil prices. I am willing to support the consensus of the team and keep these concerns to myself. But there is a strong argument for delaying this a month, doing the messaging work on why this matters, seeing where the economy is, etc.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">A person identified in Signal as “Joe Kent” (Trump’s nominee to run the National Counterterrorism Center is named Joe Kent) wrote at 8:22, “There is nothing time sensitive driving the time line. We’ll have the exact same options in a month.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">Then, at 8:26 a.m., a message landed in my Signal app from the user “John Ratcliffe.” The message contained information that might be interpreted as related to actual and current intelligence operations.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">At 8:27, a message arrived from the “Pete Hegseth” account. “VP: I understand your concerns – and fully support you raising w/ POTUS. Important considerations, most of which are tough to know how they play out (economy, Ukraine peace, Gaza, etc). I think messaging is going to be tough no matter what – nobody knows who the Houthis are – which is why we would need to stay focused on: 1) Biden failed &amp; 2) Iran funded.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The Hegseth message goes on to state, “Waiting a few weeks or a month does not fundamentally change the calculus. 2 immediate risks on waiting: 1) this leaks, and we look indecisive; 2) Israel takes an action first – or Gaza cease fire falls apart – and we don’t get to start this on our own terms. We can manage both. We are prepared to execute, and if I had final go or no go vote, I believe we should. This [is] not about the Houthis. I see it as two things: 1) Restoring Freedom of Navigation, a core national interest; and 2) Reestablish deterrence, which Biden cratered. But, we can easily pause. And if we do, I will do all we can to enforce 100% OPSEC”—operations security. “I welcome other thoughts.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">A few minutes later, the “Michael Waltz” account posted a lengthy note about trade figures, and the limited capabilities of European navies. “Whether it’s now or several weeks from now, it will have to be the United States that reopens these shipping lanes. Per the president’s request we are working with DOD and State to determine how to compile the cost associated and levy them on the Europeans.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The account identified as “JD Vance” addressed a message at 8:45 to @Pete Hegseth: “if you think we should do it let’s go. I just hate bailing Europe out again.” (The administration has argued that America’s European allies benefit economically from the U.S. Navy’s protection of international shipping lanes.)</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The user identified as Hegseth responded three minutes later: “VP: I fully share your loathing of European free-loading. It’s PATHETIC. But Mike is correct, we are the only ones on the planet (on our side of the ledger) who can do this. Nobody else even close. Question is timing. I feel like now is as good a time as any, given POTUS directive to reopen shipping lanes. I think we should go; but POTUS still retains 24 hours of decision space.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">At this point, the previously silent “S M” joined the conversation. “As I heard it, the president was clear: green light, but we soon make clear to Egypt and Europe what we expect in return. We also need to figure out how to enforce such a requirement. EG, if Europe doesn’t remunerate, then what? If the US successfully restores freedom of navigation at great cost there needs to be some further economic gain extracted in return.”</p><div data-flatplan-inline_image="true"><figure><picture><img alt="A screenshot of a group chat" loading="lazy" srcset="https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/rySa44yfmkE7OFEgHayLiak2F78=/665x484/media/img/posts/2025/03/IMG_0328/original.jpg" src="https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/rySa44yfmkE7OFEgHayLiak2F78=/665x484/media/img/posts/2025/03/IMG_0328/original.jpg" width="665" height="484"></picture></figure></div><div data-flatplan-inline_image="true"><figure><picture><img alt="Screenshot of a group chat" loading="lazy" srcset="https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/w6AXYEmE7rQSN42_PflDXUN1HG8=/665x979/media/img/posts/2025/03/IMG_0329/original.jpg" src="https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/w6AXYEmE7rQSN42_PflDXUN1HG8=/665x979/media/img/posts/2025/03/IMG_0329/original.jpg" width="665" height="979"></picture><figcaption>A screenshot from the Signal group shows debate over the president’s views ahead of the attack.</figcaption></figure></div><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">That message from “S M”—presumably President Trump’s confidant Stephen Miller, the deputy White House chief of staff, or someone playing Stephen Miller—effectively shut down the conversation. The last text of the day came from “Pete Hegseth,” who wrote at 9:46 a.m., “Agree.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">After reading this chain, I recognized that this conversation possessed a high degree of verisimilitude. The texts, in their word choice and arguments, sounded as if they were written by the people who purportedly sent them, or by a particularly adept AI text generator. I was still concerned that this could be a disinformation operation, or a simulation of some sort. And I remained mystified that no one in the group seemed to have noticed my presence. But if it was a hoax, the quality of mimicry and the level of foreign-policy insight were impressive.</p><hr><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">It was the next morning, Saturday, March 15, when this story became truly bizarre.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">At 11:44 a.m., the account labeled “Pete Hegseth” posted in Signal a “TEAM UPDATE.” I will not quote from this update, or from certain other subsequent texts. The information contained in them, if they had been read by an adversary of the United States, could conceivably have been used to harm American military and intelligence personnel, particularly in the broader Middle East, Central Command’s area of responsibility. What I will say, in order to illustrate the shocking recklessness of this Signal conversation, is that the Hegseth post contained operational details of forthcoming strikes on Yemen, including information about targets, weapons the U.S. would be deploying, and attack sequencing.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The only person to reply to the update from Hegseth was the person identified as the vice president. “I will say a prayer for victory,” Vance wrote. (Two other users subsequently added prayer emoji.)</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">According to the lengthy Hegseth text, the first detonations in Yemen would be felt two hours hence, at 1:45 p.m. eastern time. So I waited in my car in a supermarket parking lot. If this Signal chat was real, I reasoned, Houthi targets would soon be bombed. At about 1:55, I checked X and searched <em>Yemen</em>. Explosions were then being heard across Sanaa, the capital city.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">I went back to the Signal channel. At 1:48, “Michael Waltz” had provided the group an update. Again, I won’t quote from this text, except to note that he described the operation as an “amazing job.” A few minutes later, “John Ratcliffe” wrote, “A good start.” Not long after, Waltz responded with three emoji: a fist, an American flag, and fire. Others soon joined in, including “MAR,” who wrote, “Good Job Pete and your team!!,” and “Susie Wiles,” who texted, “Kudos to all – most particularly those in theater and CENTCOM! Really great. God bless.” “Steve Witkoff” responded with five emoji: two hands-praying, a flexed bicep, and two American flags. “TG” responded, “Great work and effects!” The after-action discussion included assessments of damage done, including the likely death of a specific individual. The Houthi-run Yemeni health ministry reported that at least 53 people were killed in the strikes, a number that has not been independently verified.</p><div data-flatplan-inline_image="true"><figure><picture><img alt="Screenshot of a group chat" loading="lazy" srcset="https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/eNC-qJzV_jbc18944_z6t1QhGDc=/665x758/media/img/posts/2025/03/IMG_0330/original.jpg" src="https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/eNC-qJzV_jbc18944_z6t1QhGDc=/665x758/media/img/posts/2025/03/IMG_0330/original.jpg" width="665" height="758"></picture><figcaption>A screenshot from the Signal group shows reactions to the strikes.</figcaption></figure></div><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">On Sunday, Waltz appeared on ABC’s <em>This Week</em> and contrasted the strikes with the Biden administration’s more hesitant approach. “These were not kind of pinprick, back-and-forth—what ultimately proved to be feckless attacks,” he said. “This was an overwhelming response that actually targeted multiple Houthi leaders and took them out.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The Signal chat group, I concluded, was almost certainly real. Having come to this realization, one that seemed nearly impossible only hours before, I removed myself from the Signal group, understanding that this would trigger an automatic notification to the group’s creator, “Michael Waltz,” that I had left. No one in the chat had seemed to notice that I was there. And I received no subsequent questions about why I left—or, more to the point, who I was.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">Earlier today, I emailed Waltz and sent him a message on his Signal account. I also wrote to Pete Hegseth, John Ratcliffe, Tulsi Gabbard, and other officials. In an email, I outlined some of my questions: Is the “Houthi PC small group” a genuine Signal thread? Did they know that I was included in this group? Was I (on the off chance) included on purpose? If not, who did they think I was? Did anyone realize who I was when I was added, or when I removed myself from the group? Do senior Trump-administration officials use Signal regularly for sensitive discussions? Do the officials believe that the use of such a channel could endanger American personnel?</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">Brian Hughes, the spokesman for the National Security Council, responded two hours later, confirming the veracity of the Signal group. “This appears to be an authentic message chain, and we are reviewing how an inadvertent number was added to the chain,” Hughes wrote. “The thread is a demonstration of the deep and thoughtful policy coordination between senior officials. The ongoing success of the Houthi operation demonstrates that there were no threats to troops or national security.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">William Martin, a spokesperson for Vance, said that despite the impression created by the texts, the vice president is fully aligned with the president. “The Vice President’s first priority is always making sure that the President’s advisers are adequately briefing him on the substance of their internal deliberations,” he said. “Vice President Vance unequivocally supports this administration’s foreign policy. The President and the Vice President have had subsequent conversations about this matter and are in complete agreement.”</p><hr><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">I have never seen a breach quite like this. It is not uncommon for national-security officials to communicate on Signal. But the app is used primarily for meeting planning and other logistical matters—not for detailed and highly confidential discussions of a pending military action. And, of course, I’ve never heard of an instance in which a journalist has been invited to such a discussion.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">Conceivably, Waltz, by coordinating a national-security-related action over Signal, may have violated several provisions of the Espionage Act, which governs the handling of “national defense” information, according to several national-security lawyers interviewed by my colleague Shane Harris for this story. Harris asked them to consider a hypothetical scenario in which a senior U.S. official creates a Signal thread for the express purpose of sharing information with Cabinet officials about an active military operation. He did not show them the actual Signal messages or tell them specifically what had occurred.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">All of these lawyers said that a U.S. official should not establish a Signal thread in the first place. Information about an active operation would presumably fit the law’s definition of “national defense” information. The Signal app is not approved by the government for sharing classified information. The government has its own systems for that purpose. If officials want to discuss military activity, they should go into a specially designed space known as a sensitive compartmented information facility, or SCIF—most Cabinet-level national-security officials have one installed in their home—or communicate only on approved government equipment, the lawyers said. Normally, cellphones are not permitted inside a SCIF, which suggests that as these officials were sharing information about an active military operation, they could have been moving around in public. Had they lost their phones, or had they been stolen, the potential risk to national security would have been severe.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">Hegseth, Ratcliffe, and other Cabinet-level officials presumably would have the authority to declassify information, and several of the national-security lawyers noted that the hypothetical officials on the Signal chain might claim that they had declassified the information they shared. But this argument rings hollow, they cautioned, because Signal is not an authorized venue for sharing information of such a sensitive nature, regardless of whether it has been stamped “top secret” or not.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">There was another potential problem: Waltz set some of the messages in the Signal group to disappear after one week, and some after four. That raises questions about whether the officials may have violated federal records law: Text messages about official acts are considered records that should be preserved.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">“Under the records laws applicable to the White House and federal agencies, all government employees are prohibited from using electronic-messaging applications such as Signal for official business, unless those messages are promptly forwarded or copied to an official government account,” Jason R. Baron, a professor at the University of Maryland and the former director of litigation at the National Archives and Records Administration, told Harris.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">“Intentional violations of these requirements are a basis for disciplinary action. Additionally, agencies such as the Department of Defense restrict electronic messaging containing classified information to classified government networks and/or networks with government-approved encrypted features,” Baron said.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">Several former U.S. officials told Harris and me that they had used Signal to share unclassified information and to discuss routine matters, particularly when traveling overseas without access to U.S. government systems. But they knew never to share classified or sensitive information on the app, because their phones could have been hacked by a foreign intelligence service, which would have been able to read the messages on the devices. It is worth noting that Donald Trump, as a candidate for president (and as president), repeatedly and vociferously demanded that Hillary Clinton be imprisoned for using a private email server for official business when she was secretary of state. (It is also worth noting that Trump was indicted in 2023 for mishandling classified documents, but the charges were dropped after his election.)</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">Waltz and the other Cabinet-level officials were already potentially violating government policy and the law simply by texting one another about the operation. But when Waltz added a journalist—presumably by mistake—to his principals committee, he created new security and legal issues. Now the group was transmitting information to someone not authorized to receive it. That is the classic definition of a leak, even if it was unintentional, and even if the recipient of the leak did not actually believe it was a leak until Yemen came under American attack.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">All along, members of the Signal group were aware of the need for secrecy and operations security. In his text detailing aspects of the forthcoming attack on Houthi targets, Hegseth wrote to the group—which, at the time, included me—“We are currently clean on OPSEC.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><em>Shane Harris contributed reporting. </em></p></section><div data-event-module="footer"><p><h3>About the Author</h3></p><div><address id="article-writer-0" data-event-element="author" data-event-position="1" data-flatplan-bio="true"><div><div><p><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/author/jeffrey-goldberg/" data-event-element="image"><img alt="" loading="lazy" src="https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/umxEbDHzu_6lWzJxYOnCZNM4_sg=/0x0:2977x2977/120x120/media/img/authors/2021/06/Jeffrey_Goldberg_Headshot_bw_1/original.png" width="60" height="60"></a></p></div><div><p><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/author/jeffrey-goldberg/" data-label="https://www.theatlantic.com/author/jeffrey-goldberg/" data-action="click author - name">Jeffrey Goldberg</a> is the editor in chief of <em>The Atlantic<strong> </strong></em>and the moderator of <em>Washington Week With The Atlantic</em>.</p></div></div></address></div></div><gpt-ad format="injector" sizes-at-0="mobile-wide,native,house" targeting-pos="injector-most-popular" sizes-at-976="desktop-wide,native,house"></gpt-ad></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mastering Delphi 5 2025 Annotated Edition Is Now Complete (182 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.marcocantu.com/blog/2025-march-mastering-delphi5-annotated-complete.html</link>
            <guid>43462299</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 15:40:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.marcocantu.com/blog/2025-march-mastering-delphi5-annotated-complete.html">https://blog.marcocantu.com/blog/2025-march-mastering-delphi5-annotated-complete.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43462299">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>I've now completed the review of the 2025 Annotated Edition of Mastering Delphi 5.</p><div>
<p xmlns:gxi="http://geode.it/gxi/2.0/">As I <a href="https://blog.marcocantu.com/blog/2025-february-mastering-delphi5-annotated.html">announced on&nbsp;February 14</a>, I've been creating a free to download edition of my classic "Mastering Delphi 5" with footnotes indicating what is different today. The new edition is now <strong>complete</strong>. You can find it for download at&nbsp;<a href="https://www.marcocantu.com/md52025/">www.marcocantu.com/md52025/</a>.</p>
<p xmlns:gxi="http://geode.it/gxi/2.0/">The final annotated edition is <strong>1,139 pages</strong> and it has<strong>&nbsp;475 footnotes</strong>, plus dozen of new screen snapshots comparing the old the the new UI of the IDE, and in some cases of the running applications. Not everything in the original source code compiles, but most of the programs run untouched, which is almost incredible given the 25 years since that edition.</p>
<p xmlns:gxi="http://geode.it/gxi/2.0/">I hope you like it, it's nice a read and you can probably read something on today's Delphi, but even if you know everything it's an interesting way to go down the memory lane, for those who've been using Delphi since that time.</p>
<p xmlns:gxi="http://geode.it/gxi/2.0/">As mentioned, this is my present to the community for Delphi's 30th anniversary, we celebrated recently.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Triforce – a beamformer for Apple Silicon laptops (533 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://crates.io/crates/triforce-lv2</link>
            <guid>43461701</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 14:45:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://crates.io/crates/triforce-lv2">https://crates.io/crates/triforce-lv2</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43461701">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://crates.io/crates/triforce-lv2: Error: Request failed with status code 404]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Goblin.tools: simple, single-task tools to help neurodivergent people with tasks (315 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://goblin.tools/</link>
            <guid>43461375</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 14:15:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://goblin.tools/">https://goblin.tools/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43461375">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="syncHelp"><p>
                            Please provide credentials to synchronize your ToDo list across devices.<br>
                            There are no accounts, your username must simply be unique. <br>
                            We recommend taking a backup with <i></i> before activating sync on new devices.<br>
                            <a data-bs-toggle="collapse" href="#collapseText" role="button" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="collapseText">
                                How does this work?
                            </a></p><p>
                                All devices with the same username and password will synchronise lists.<br>
                                Your list is encrypted on your devices using your username and password. It can not be seen or decrypted by admins or anyone who doesn't have your credentials. <br>
                                Synchronization is not instant, it can take a few seconds for your changes to come through on other devices.
                            </p>
                        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>