<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 01:00:06 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The darker side of being a doctor (301 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://drericlevi.substack.com/p/the-darker-side-of-being-a-doctor</link>
            <guid>40025261</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 19:10:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://drericlevi.substack.com/p/the-darker-side-of-being-a-doctor">https://drericlevi.substack.com/p/the-darker-side-of-being-a-doctor</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40025261">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><p>I’m a surgeon. I’d like to think that I’m resilient and well adjusted, having gone through medical school and rigorous surgical training. I’ve been a doctor for 13 years and much of that period has been spent training to be as good a surgeon as I could ever be. I have great family support, a physician wife who understands my work and I’ve never been diagnosed with a mental illness.</p><p>The suicide death of Dr Andrew Bryant, a Brisbane gastroenterologist last week hit a raw nerve. His wife wrote this honest and courageous letter.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6a3736c1-1049-4bae-8748-536a27406ec6_374x588.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel="nofollow ugc noopener"><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6a3736c1-1049-4bae-8748-536a27406ec6_374x588.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6a3736c1-1049-4bae-8748-536a27406ec6_374x588.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6a3736c1-1049-4bae-8748-536a27406ec6_374x588.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6a3736c1-1049-4bae-8748-536a27406ec6_374x588.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6a3736c1-1049-4bae-8748-536a27406ec6_374x588.jpeg" width="374" height="588" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/6a3736c1-1049-4bae-8748-536a27406ec6_374x588.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:588,&quot;width&quot;:374,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6a3736c1-1049-4bae-8748-536a27406ec6_374x588.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6a3736c1-1049-4bae-8748-536a27406ec6_374x588.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6a3736c1-1049-4bae-8748-536a27406ec6_374x588.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6a3736c1-1049-4bae-8748-536a27406ec6_374x588.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Although I’ve never had serious suicidal thoughts, I – like many other doctors – have been through many dark seasons. Depression, anxiety, burnout, suicidality, hopelessness, lethargy, anhedonia, feeling flat, worry, and the like are all different flavours of the same phenomena: the negative human response to internal or external stressors. Of course, the causes are always multifactorial. It cannot and should not be oversimplified to family history, genetics, behavioural deficiencies, bad environment or poor social support.</p><p>When I carefully dissect my dark seasons, some common themes often emerge. Work is often the critical exacerbating and perpetuating factor in those dark times. Because as a surgeon I spend the vast majority of my lifetime at work, what happens there influences all other aspects of my life including my marriage, family and social life.</p><p><strong>Here are 3 common things that have thrown me into some dark pit of despair:</strong></p><p>I have lost control of my days. I had worked in a hospital where I was oncall 24/7, 12 days out of 14. I had fortnightly weekends off. When I was preparing for surgical exams, I’d be working and studying from 6.30am to 10pm everyday, seeing my family only on the weekends for lunch. I had worked in a hospital network that covered 4 campuses and drove 500kms a week when covering these sites. I had worked in a hospital where I didn’t get home for days at a time, sleeping overnight in hospital quarters, outpatient clinic benches and in my car. I used to have my sleeping bag, toiletries and change in the boot of my car because I didn’t know if I was going to make it home some nights. Plans change every single day at work because of emergencies. I can’t even be sure what the next hour will bring when I am on call. You might ask, why can’t you work less? It’s not as easy as that. If I decide to work less, who is going to cover the hospital? If the hospital aren’t employing other doctors, we can’t allow patients to go uncovered. I accept the fact that I have a duty of care to be on call. The intensity and personal damage of these on call periods are often forgotten.</p><p>Not only that, we are losing control of health care in general. Everyday, there’s a new form, a new guideline, a new protocol, a new health software, a new policy all dictating, restricting and modifying clinician activities. Some of these policies are written by people who do not see patients. There’s a whole paid industry dedicated to restructuring what doctors and nurses do to reduce costs and increase output.</p><p>Just imagine. I start my days at 6am. I wake up to an email alerting me of the number of discharge summaries that haven’t been completed and the various computer based modules I have to complete (hand washing, privacy, lifting patients, etc). Round starts at 7am. I see 15-20 patients with various travel forms, certificates, scripts that need completing. All to be done via the electronic health system, clunky, not user friendly, takes a long time to log in. Then I start an overbooked operating list at 8am. There are 7 cases booked. I have no say on who gets on the operating list and the order of patients. The first patient haven’t been checked in. The diabetic one is hypoglycaemic. The infant is cranky. The autistic child is running away. The interpreter is not here yet. The computer is still not logging in. The password is expired. I used to be able to arrange the operating list because I know that some operations take longer than others. But now, the bookings office determine that that all my tonsillectomies take 14 minutes because that’s the average time recorded on the computer. The moment I scrub in, the timer starts. The moment I unscrub timer stops. Click. Click. Click. Because the theatre bookings does not take into account the interpreter time, pre-med period or transfer to ICU, the list is running late. The nurse in charge is breathing down my neck to finish on time. I still took about 14 minutes on each case, but the team is delayed by external clinical reasons. The theatre team is anxious to finish, everything is rushed, and mistakes are bound to occur.</p><p>In the mean time, I field 12 phone calls from ED, GP and other units. By now there are 3 patients waiting for me in ED and 1 being flown in from another hospital. The operating list is finished late. I rushed to ED, and gulped down a cup of instant coffee. Then I arrive late to the afternoon clinic, which again is overbooked. Clinic nurses are not happy. I see 8-10 patients while taking more calls. I try to discuss complex surgeries with patients but I keep getting interrupted by calls and paperwork. Then I run back to theatre for an emergency case. By this time I’m set up for failure. I’m tired, cranky and my head is full of jobs to do. I do the afternoon round, see more consults, admit more patients and dictate letters. I have taken up to 70 calls on a 24h on call period. By 6pm I’m totally exhausted. I grab a packet of chips, ginger beer, and start working on the papers I was meant to write up. I review the case notes for the next couple of days. I get home between 7-8pm. Grab dinner and put the kids to bed. I get called back in and I take a patient to theatre for an emergency procedure. I come back just after midnight and sleep. I get called four more times between midnight and 6am.</p><p>6am. Repeat.</p><p>I have lost control of my days and I have lost support. When can I actually find support? I don’t have time to talk to my colleagues about life. I don’t have time with my family. I don’t have time to catch up with friends. Social ties are lost when one stepped into medical school. I’ve lost count of the number of significant life events I have missed (birthdays, anniversaries, reunions, school recitals, first walks, etc.)</p><p>I delivered my third child with my own hands because the obstetrician was stuck in a traffic jam. The following morning I went to work because if I didn’t 12 patients have to miss their surgeries, 2 anaesthetists and about 8 nurses will miss out on their day’s income. More importantly, admin would not be happy because a cancelled operating list is a huge financial loss to the hospital.</p><p>I know where I can get support, but practically, when and how am I going to get that support? </p><p>In addition, doctors who scream for help may be formally reported, therefore having restrictions placed on their practice and then incurring higher medical indemnity fees in some situations. Trainees who ask for help may be labelled as underperforming and have to be commenced on probation or remediation. We may not have practical access to the support that are often advertised. </p><p>Interestingly, the above physical and emotional stressors are reasonably manageable to me. I’m understanding my own physical and emotional limits. These stressors induce  exhaustion, but the excitement of the work and the intellectual challenge of the job bring a lot of personal satisfaction. I do get emotionally shaken at times because I deal with dying cancer patients, emergency airway disasters and sick complex children, but I get by.</p><p>I am realising more and more that what brings me greatest distress is the relentless administrative pressure which take away the meaningful clinical engagement I have with my patients. And I wonder if this is what many young doctors are experiencing as well. Medicine used to be a meaningful pursuit. Now it has become a tiresome industry. The joy, purpose and meaning of medicine has been codified, sterilised, protocolised, industrialised and regimented. Doctors are caught in a web of business, no longer a noble vocation. The altruism of young doctors have been replaced by the shackles of efficiency, productivity and key performance indicators.</p><p>I have little say in organising my very own operating lists or clinics. Even the power to re-order the operating list has been taken from the surgeon. The thing that I love doing (operating &amp; seeing patients) is being measured, recorded and benchmarked. The clinics are overbooked to get numbers through. The paperwork for each patient encounter is increasing with each passing year. There are so many other non-clinical departments dictating what I should do and how best to do it. The mantra is “cost-effectiveness and increased productivity.”</p><p>I went into medicine knowing that I will have to sacrifice much for the sake of my patients. What I am realising is that today in modern medicine, a doctor is just one of the many commodities in this complex industry. It’s no longer about the patient. It’s about the business of hospitals. Patient satisfaction officers, Theatre Utilisation officers, Patient Flow Coordinators. These are all business roles.</p><p>As a surgeon I spent a year in a hospital where I smiled on the way to work and I am so grateful for my job. I looked forward to long days because I knew what I was doing was significant. Another year in another hospital, I dreaded going to work. I hated being on call. I was burned out and I couldn’t control my emotions at work and at home. I’m not inherently an offensive or rude person, I’m just a person pushed to the limits and set to fail because of the circumstances around my work. Same surgeon, different jobs. The forces that pushed me to losing control of my emotions are likely the same forces that might push some of us to suicide. </p><p>To some hospitals and their business, I’m not a Surgeon. I’m just an employee. Overworked, burned out, replaceable. The noble call to Medicine has been suffocated by the bureaucratic force exerting itself as the medical industry. </p><p>Would you agree or disagree with my thoughts? What other “Dark Side of Doctoring” issues can you think of?</p></div></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: My $1k self-install, off-grid solar backup build for renters (167 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://sunboxlabs.com</link>
            <guid>40025195</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 18:59:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://sunboxlabs.com">https://sunboxlabs.com</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40025195">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      <p>Cables / Tender:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://amzn.to/43NkcuJ">https://amzn.to/43NkcuJ</a> - $14.79</li>
  <li><a href="https://amzn.to/4cwxY8Y">https://amzn.to/4cwxY8Y</a> - $30.42</li>
  <li><a href="https://amzn.to/4cuS3fx">https://amzn.to/4cuS3fx</a> - $13.00</li>
  <li><a href="https://amzn.to/43u3ikz">https://amzn.to/43u3ikz</a> x2 - $17.00</li>
  <li><a href="https://amzn.to/43u3r7B">https://amzn.to/43u3r7B</a> - $12.99</li>
  <li><a href="https://amzn.to/43y5Qhx">https://amzn.to/43y5Qhx</a> - $8.89</li>
  <li><strong>Total</strong>: $114.09</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>=&gt; $1,124 total</strong></p>

<p>Remote tracking (optional):</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://amzn.to/3Vs3COI">https://amzn.to/3Vs3COI</a> - $7.99</li>
  <li><a href="https://amzn.to/3TPaXGI">https://amzn.to/3TPaXGI</a> - $23.92</li>
  <li><a href="https://amzn.to/4a6UMdI">https://amzn.to/4a6UMdI</a> - $6.99</li>
  <li><a href="https://solar-assistant.io/">https://solar-assistant.io</a> - $55.83</li>
  <li><strong>Total</strong> (additional): $94.73</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="how-to-guide">How to guide</h3>

<p>Coming soon, for now refer to Will Prowse’s wiring guide on his very-similar <a href="https://www.mobile-solarpower.com/mobile-48v-system.html">48V 3000W off-grid solar system</a> which I followed and works great for me!</p>

<h3 id="financial-payback--embodied-energy">Financial Payback &amp; Embodied Energy</h3>

<div><pre><code>Financial payback period for 3000W
System cost : $1,124 on Amazon in 2024
Yearly energy creation: 365d * 4.26hsun/d * 1.280kW = 2,000kWh/y (but more like 1,000kWh/year after losses)
Yearly value creation: 1,000kWh/y * $0.55/kWh in SF = $550/y energy created
100W system payback period: $1,124 / $550 = 2 years until payback
</code></pre></div>

<h3 id="how-green-is-it">How green is it:</h3>

<p>Production footprint PV (<a href="https://sustainability.stackexchange.com/questions/8317/what-is-the-typical-embodied-energy-of-a-solar-photovoltaic-panel">source</a>):
<code>2,900kWhee/kW * 1.28kW = 3,712kWh embodied energy</code></p>

<p>Production footprint LiFePo4 battery (<a href="https://ris.utwente.nl/ws/portalfiles/portal/189571307/10.1016_j.procir.2019.01.099.pdf">source</a>):
<code>106kWhee/kWh * 2.4kWh = 254kWh embodied energy</code></p>

<p>Annual energy production system: 1100kWh/y
<code>Payback period: 3966kWh / 1100kWh/y = 3.5 year footprint payback</code></p>

<h3 id="faq">FAQ</h3>

<p>What’s the catch? Seems to good to be true? Well, this thing sits between your devices and the wall. So you need to neatly run extension cables from every room in the house to the “sun box”, and then run one cable from the box to the panels, and another to the wall (optional, just so it can fall back to pulling power from the wall). Photos of this are coming soon.</p>

<p>Will it ever push power back into the wall? Nope! It’ll only ever draw from the wall in the event that both the sun is down and the battery is dead (so your fridge won’t go off overnight for example).</p>

<p>Is this legal? Yes, see above. No difference to plugging your fridge into your wall, as far as the utility is concerned.</p>

    </div><section>
  <h2>Want some help?</h2>
  <p>Set up a call with us and we can plan your system!</p>
  <a href="https://sunboxlabs.com/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection#462e232a2a290635332824293e2a2724356825292b">Email Us</a>
</section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Harmful 5G Fast Lanes Are Coming; the FCC Needs to Stop Them (331 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://cyberlaw.stanford.edu/blog/2024/04/harmful-5g-fast-lanes-are-coming-fcc-needs-stop-them</link>
            <guid>40024062</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 16:09:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://cyberlaw.stanford.edu/blog/2024/04/harmful-5g-fast-lanes-are-coming-fcc-needs-stop-them">https://cyberlaw.stanford.edu/blog/2024/04/harmful-5g-fast-lanes-are-coming-fcc-needs-stop-them</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40024062">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div property="content:encoded"><p dir="ltr">The FCC is <a href="https://www.fcc.gov/april-2024-open-commission-meeting">set to vote on April 25</a> to restore its authority over the companies we pay to get online, and reinstate federal net neutrality protections that were jettisoned by the Trump administration in 2017.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">Net neutrality protections are supposed to ensure that we, not the internet service providers (ISPs) we pay to get online, get to decide what we do online.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The FCC released <a href="http://docs.fcc.gov/public/attachments/DOC-401676A1.pdf">its draft rules</a> early in April and there’s much to celebrate in them. Mobile carriers like T-Mobile, AT&amp;T and Verizon that have been degrading video quality for mobile users will have to stop. The FCC kept in place state neutrality protections like California’s net neutrality law, allowing for layers of enforcement. The FCC also made it harder for ISPs to evade net neutrality at the point where data enters their networks.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>However, there’s a huge problem: the proposed rules make it possible for mobile ISPs to start picking applications and putting them in a fast lane - where they’ll perform better generally and much better if the network gets congested.</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr"><a href="https://www.t-mobile.com/news/network/t-mobile-expands-worlds-first-network-slicing-beta-nationwide">T-Mobile</a>, <a href="https://www.lightreading.com/oss-bss-cx/at-t-tests-gaming-traffic-prioritization-amid-net-neutrality-debate">AT&amp;T</a> and <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/carriers-look-to-offer-fast-lane-access-on-5g-networks-0ab57bcc">Verizon</a> are all testing ways to create these 5G fast lanes for apps such as video conferencing, games, and video where the ISP chooses and controls what gets boosted. They use a technical feature in 5G called network slicing, where part of their radio spectrum gets used as a special lane for the chosen app or apps, separated from the usual internet traffic.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>The FCC’s draft order opens the door to these fast lanes, so long as the app provider isn’t charged for them.</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">That means we could soon see fast lane offerings like this:</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img alt="" src="https://cyberlaw.stanford.edu/sites/default/files/20240411-mobile2.png"></p>
<p dir="ltr">Or we could see add-ons like Enhanced Video Conferencing for $10 a month, or one-time 24-hour passes to have Prioritized Online Gaming.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img src="https://cyberlaw.stanford.edu/sites/default/files/20240411-mobile1.png"></p>
<p dir="ltr">This isn't imagination.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The ISPs write about this in their blogs and press releases. They talk about these efforts and dreams openly at conferences, and their equipment vendors plainly lay out how ISPs can chop up internet service into all manner of fast lanes.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>These kinds of ISP-controlled fast lanes violate core net neutrality principles and would limit user choice, distort competition, hamper startups, and help cement platform dominance.</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">Net neutrality means that we, the people who use the internet, get to decide what we do online, without interference from ISPs. ISPs do not get to interfere with our choices by blocking, speeding up or slowing down apps or kinds of apps. Apps compete on a level playing field, and users, not ISPs, determine which apps are successful.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">Letting ISPs decide which apps get to be in a fast lane violates these principles. Apps that are in a fast lane work better than those that are not, especially when the network is busy and apps in the regular lane start suffering. If HBO Max is in a fast lane, it will continue to work well even if the network is busy, while all other video is buffering.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Differences in performance, including relative differences in performance, matter. Even small differences in load times affect how long people stay on a site, how much they pay, and whether they’ll come back. Those differences also affect how high up sites show in search results.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Thus, letting ISPs choose which apps get to be in a fast lane lets them, not users, pick winners and losers online.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">And <a href="https://cyberlaw.stanford.edu/blog/2022/05/facebook-google-big-telecoms-want-keep-violating-net-neutrality-europe-regulators">as we’ve seen in the past</a>, programs like this favor the most popular apps, even when the program is supposedly open to all apps in a category and no apps are paying the ISP. So the biggest apps will end up in all the fast lanes, while most others would be left out. The ones left out would likely include messaging apps like Signal, local news sites, decentralized Fediverse apps like Mastodon and PeerTube, niche video sites like Dropout, indie music sites like Bandcamp, and the millions of other sites and apps in the long tail.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">Legislators, government agencies, attorneys general in states both red and blue, public interest groups, startups, and open-source technologists are all working to reduce the power and dominance of the biggest platforms. The FCC should be working to help that effort by creating a level playing field and banning these ISP-controlled 5G fast lanes.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Meaningful net neutrality protections prohibit ISPs from speeding up and slowing down apps and kinds of apps.&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">ISPs can pick winners and losers by putting winners in a fast lane or losers in a slow lane.</p>
<p dir="ltr">This is a what it would look like if an ISP put everything except YouTube and TikTok in a slow lane.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img src="https://cyberlaw.stanford.edu/sites/default/files/20240411-mobile4.png"></p>
<p dir="ltr">This is what it would look like if an ISP put YouTube and TikTok in a fast lane.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img p="" src="https://cyberlaw.stanford.edu/sites/default/files/20240411-mobile4.png"></p>
<p dir="ltr">It’s the same picture. The effect is the same. In either case, disfavored apps will find it harder to compete.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Meaningful net neutrality protections need to protect against both.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>This is not controversial.</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">President Obama’s <a href="https://obamawhitehouse.archives.gov/net-neutrality">November 2014 net neutrality proposal</a> included this protection:</p>
<p dir="ltr">“The rules I am asking for are simple, common-sense steps that reflect the Internet you and I use every day.” That included, he said, a brightline ban on ISPs “intentionally slow[ing] down some content or speed[ing] up others — through a process often called “throttling” — based on the type of service or your ISP’s preferences.”</p>
<p dir="ltr">Even proposed <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/115th-congress/house-bill/6393">Republican</a> <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/116th-congress/house-bill/1101/text?s=1&amp;r=98">net neutrality</a> <a href="https://cyberlaw.stanford.edu/sites/default/files/publication/files/RepublicanNetworkNeutralityBill-BILLS-114hr-PIH-OpenInternet.pdf">bills</a> prohibited ISPs from speeding up and slowing down apps and kinds of apps.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">Many, including me, <a href="https://www.fcc.gov/ecfs/document/104020490613577/2">thought the 2015 Order did so</a>, too.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Almost certainly, the millions of Americans who celebrated the 2015 Open Internet Order and fought the 2017 repeal think that net neutrality protections ban fast lanes and slow lanes.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>The draft order takes a different approach.&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">The no-throttling rule that the FCC proposed in October explicitly prohibited ISPs from slowing down apps and classes of apps; it was silent on whether the rule also applies to speeding up.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">Given the mobile ISPs’ public statements about their plans for 5G fast lanes, <a href="https://www.fcc.gov/ecfs/document/10328020156846/1">public</a> <a href="https://www.fcc.gov/ecfs/document/10401332717347/1">interest</a> <a href="https://www.fcc.gov/ecfs/document/10330745507976/1">groups</a>, <a href="https://www.fcc.gov/ecfs/document/1215041660232/1">startups</a>, and <a href="https://www.markey.senate.gov/imo/media/doc/letter_to_fcc_title_ii_4224.pdf">members of Congress</a> asked the FCC to clarify in the Order that the no-throttling rule also prohibits ISPs from speeding up apps and classes of apps.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>The draft order did not do that.&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">While <a href="https://docs.fcc.gov/public/attachments/DOC-401676A1.pdf">draft order</a> acknowledges that some speeding up of apps could violate the no-throttling rule, it added some unclear, nebulous language suggesting that the FCC would review any fast lanes case-by-case, without explaining how it would do that.<sup><a href="#one">1</a></sup> This language gives the FCC maximum flexibility to accept or reject specific fast lanes in the future as it sees fit.</p>
<p dir="ltr">According to the draft order, the agency “could” find a violation of the no-throttling rule, if:&nbsp;</p>
<ol>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr">an ISP speeds up specific apps (but not necessarily classes of apps), and</p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr">the decision to speed up is “unreasonably discriminatory,” and</p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr">the speeding up has the effect of “‘impair[ing] or degrad[ing]’ other … apps not given the same treatment.”&nbsp;</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>In other words, the proposed no-throttling rule is a bright line rule for slow lanes – ISPs can’t slow down apps or kinds of apps; but for fast lanes, it’s a fuzzy, unclear case-by-case standard.</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">For example, would it be “unreasonably discriminatory” to create a 5G fast lane that includes the most popular apps in a category since it responds to consumer preferences? Does an unreasonably discriminatory fast lane need to technically degrade or impair the apps that are not in the fast lane for the FCC to find a violation of the no-throttling rule?&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>There is no way to predict which kinds of fast lanes the FCC might ultimately find to violate the no-throttling rule. This gives ISPs cover to flood the market with various fast-lane offerings, arguing that their version does not violate the no-throttling rule and daring the FCC to enforce its rule.&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">And if the mobile ISPs do this, the cable companies will soon follow. Cable companies have the tech to build their own fast lanes, and increasingly they compete with 5G to the Home services. If T-Mobile and Verizon start selling home plans that have “enhanced streaming video,” you can bet the cable companies will launch their own version.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The FCC would then investigate these offerings case-by-case in lengthy and costly proceedings. In the meantime, apps that are not in the fast lane will suffer.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">Entrepreneurs and application providers that are not included in a fast lane will have to decide whether to try to get into the fast lane, file an FCC complaint, or just silently suffer.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">Companies that do file complaints will waste years litigating the meaning of “unreasonably discriminatory,” all the while going up against giant telecoms that stockpile lawyers and lobbyists.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Unless you are a high-paid telecom lawyer who bills by the hour, the proposed test for what’s a good or bad fast lane is a nightmare.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Not all 5G slices are harmful.&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">Just to be clear, net neutrality proponents are not asking the FCC to ban network slicing. There’s lots of ways for ISPs to use slices for things that are not normal internet service such as a dedicated slice for a farming operation using remote controlled tractors, slices for telemetry data and oversight of autonomous cars, or providing a slice for a stadium’s video system at a crowded game.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">There are good reasons to isolate this kind of traffic, and it can be done without reducing user choice or tilting the online playing field. Under the FCC’s draft order, such services would be so-called enterprise service offerings, to which the Open Internet protections don’t apply.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">But the 5G fast lanes ISPs are imagining for regular internet access – where ISPs decide which apps or kind of apps get a fast lane – would cause real harm and violate the core tenets of net neutrality.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">We don’t need our ISP deciding for us what’s important and what’s not; we want our ISP to let us decide and stick to the job of connecting our devices to the services we want to use.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">It’s not even clear why such fast lanes are necessary for consumer internet access. As one industry analyst noted, isn’t 5G already supposed to be the fast lane for everything?&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Luckily, there’s still time to fix this.</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">The FCC can and should edit the draft order ahead of the vote on April 24 and clarify in the Order that the no-throttling rule also prohibits ISPs from creating fast lanes for select apps or kinds of apps.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">The FCC just needs to put this fix in the fast lane to get it done before it votes on April 25.</p>
<hr>

<p><sup>1</sup> <a href="https://www.fcc.gov/document/promoting-fast-open-and-fair-internet">2024 Draft Order</a>, para. 492 (“Our interpretation of “throttling” encompasses a wide variety of conduct that could impair or degrade an end user’s ability to access content of their choosing; thus, we decline commenters’ request to modify the rule to explicitly include positive and negative discrimination of content. We agree, however, with Free Press that a BIAS provider’s “unreasonably discriminatory” decision to speed up specific content, applications, or services could “impair or degrade” other content, applications, or services not given the same treatment.” (footnotes omitted)).</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tree-shaking, the horticulturally misguided algorithm (174 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://wingolog.org/archives/2023/11/24/tree-shaking-the-horticulturally-misguided-algorithm</link>
            <guid>40023319</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 14:20:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://wingolog.org/archives/2023/11/24/tree-shaking-the-horticulturally-misguided-algorithm">https://wingolog.org/archives/2023/11/24/tree-shaking-the-horticulturally-misguided-algorithm</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40023319">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Let’s talk about tree-shaking!</p><h3>looking up from the trough</h3><p>But first, I need to talk about WebAssembly’s dirty secret: despite the
hype, WebAssembly has had limited success on the web.</p><p>There is
<a href="https://medium.com/@addyosmani/photoshop-is-now-on-the-web-38d70954365a">Photoshop</a>,
which does appear to be a real success.  5 years ago there was
<a href="https://www.figma.com/blog/figma-faster/">Figma</a>, though they don’t
talk much about Wasm these days.  There are quite a number of little NPM
libraries that use Wasm under the hood, usually compiled from C++ or
Rust.  I think
<a href="https://dotnet.microsoft.com/en-us/apps/aspnet/web-apps/blazor">Blazor</a>
probably gets used for a few in-house corporate apps, though I could be
fooled by their marketing.</p><p>You might recall the hyped demos of 3D first-person-shooter
games with Unreal engine again from 5 years ago, but that was the previous major release of
Unreal and was always experimental; the current Unreal 5 does not support targetting
WebAssembly.</p><p>Don’t get me wrong, I think WebAssembly is great.  It is having fine
success in off-the-web environments, and I think it is going to be a key
and growing part of the Web platform.  I suspect, though, that we are
only just now getting past the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gartner_hype_cycle">trough of
disillusionment</a>.</p><p>It’s worth reflecting a bit on the nature of web Wasm’s successes and
failures.  Taking Photoshop as an example, I think we can say that Wasm
does very well at bringing large C++ programs to the web.  I know that
it took quite some work, but I understand the end result to be
essentially the same source code, just compiled for a different target.</p><p>Similarly for the JavaScript module case, Wasm finds success in getting
legacy C++ code to the web, and as a way to write new web-targetting
Rust code.  These are often tasks that JavaScript doesn’t do very well
at, or which need a shared implementation between client and server
deployments.</p><p>On the other hand, WebAssembly has not been a Web success for DOM-heavy
apps.  Nobody is talking about rewriting the front-end of 
<a href="https://wordpress.com/">wordpress.com</a> in Wasm, for example.  Why is
that?  It may sound like a silly question to you: Wasm just isn’t good
at that stuff.  But <i>why</i>?  If you dig down a bit, I think it’s that the
programming models are just too different: the Web’s primary programming
model is JavaScript, a language with dynamic typing and managed memory,
whereas WebAssembly 1.0 was about static typing and linear memory.
Getting to the DOM from Wasm was a hassle that was overcome only by the
most ardent of the true Wasm faithful.</p><p>Relatedly, Wasm has also not really been a success for languages that
aren’t, like, C or Rust.  I am guessing that wordpress.com isn’t written
mostly in C++.  One of the sticking points for this class of language.
is that C#, for example, will want to ship with a garbage collector, and
that it is annoying to have to do this.  Check my <a href="https://wingolog.org/archives/2023/03/20/a-world-to-win-webassembly-for-the-rest-of-us">article from March
this year for more
details</a>.</p><p>Happily, this restriction is going away, as all browsers are going to
ship support for reference types and garbage collection within the next
months; Chrome and Firefox already ship Wasm GC, and Safari shouldn’t be
far behind thanks to the efforts from my colleague Asumu Takikawa.  This
is an extraordinarily exciting development that I think will kick off a
whole ‘nother Gartner hype cycle, as more languages start to update
their toolchains to support WebAssembly.</p><h3>if you don’t like my peaches</h3><p>Which brings us to the meat of today’s note: web Wasm will win where
compilers create compact code.  If your language’s compiler toolchain
can manage to produce useful Wasm in a file that is less than a handful
of over-the-wire kilobytes, you can win.  If your compiler can’t do that
yet, you will have to instead rely on hype and captured audiences for
adoption, which at best results in an unstable equilibrium until you
figure out what’s next.</p><p>In the JavaScript world, managing bloat and deliverable size is a huge
industry.  Bundlers like <a href="https://esbuild.github.io/">esbuild</a> are a
ubiquitous part of the toolchain, compiling down a set of JS modules to
a single file that should include only those functions and data types
that are used in a program, and additionally applying domain-specific
size-squishing strategies such as minification (making monikers more
minuscule).</p><p>Let’s focus on tree-shaking.  The visual metaphor is that you write a
bunch of code, and you only need some of it for any given page.  So you
imagine a tree whose, um, branches are the modules that you use, and
whose leaves are the individual definitions in the modules, and you then
violently shake the tree, probably killing it and also annoying any
nesting birds.  The only thing that’s left still attached is what is
actually needed.</p><p>This isn’t how trees work: holding the trunk doesn’t give you
information as to which branches are somehow necessary for the tree’s
mission.  It also <a href="https://pvk.ca/Blog/2012/02/19/fixed-points-and-strike-mandates/">primes your mind to look for the wrong fixed
point</a>,
removing unneeded code instead of keeping only the necessary code.</p><p>But, tree-shaking is an evocative name, and so despite its horticultural
and algorithmic inaccuracies, we will stick to it.</p><p>The thing is that maximal tree-shaking for languages with a thicker
run-time has not been a huge priority.  Consider Go: <a href="https://zchee.github.io/golang-wiki/WebAssembly/">according to the
golang wiki</a>, the most
trivial program compiled to WebAssembly from Go is 2 megabytes, and
adding imports can make this go to 10 megabytes or more.  Or look at
Pyodide, the Python WebAssembly port: the <a href="https://pyodide.org/en/stable/console.html">REPL
example</a> downloads about 20
megabytes of data.  These are fine sizes for technology demos or, in the
limit, very rich applications, but they aren’t winners for web
development.</p><h3>shake a different tree</h3><p>To be fair, both the built-in Wasm support for Go and the Pyodide port
of Python both derive from the upstream toolchains, where producing
small binaries is nice but not necessary: on a server, who cares how big
the app is?  And indeed when targetting smaller devices, we tend to see
alternate implementations of the toolchain, for example
<a href="https://micropython.org/">MicroPython</a> or
<a href="https://github.com/tinygo-org/tinygo">TinyGo</a>.  TinyGo has a Wasm
back-end that can apparently go down to less than a kilobyte, even!</p><p>These alternate toolchains often come with <a href="https://tinygo.org/docs/reference/lang-support/">some restrictions or
peculiarities</a>, and
although we can consider this to be an evil of sorts, it is to be
expected that the target platform exhibits some co-design feedback on
the language.  In particular, running in the sea of the DOM is
sufficiently weird that a Wasm-targetting Python program will
necessarily be different than a “native” Python program.  Still, I think
as toolchain authors we aim to provide the same language, albeit
possibly with a different implementation of the standard library.  I am
sure that the ClojureScript developers would prefer to remove their
<a href="https://clojurescript.org/about/differences">page documenting the differences with
Clojure</a> if they could, and
perhaps if Wasm becomes a viable target for Clojurescript, they will.</p><h3>on the algorithm</h3><p>To recap: now that it supports GC, Wasm could be a winner for web
development in Python and other languages.  You would need a different
toolchain and an effective tree-shaking algorithm, so that user
experience does not degrade.  So let’s talk about tree shaking!</p><p>I work on the <a href="https://gitlab.com/spritely/guile-hoot/">Hoot Scheme
compiler</a>, which targets Wasm
with GC.  We manage to get down to 70 kB or so right now, in the minimal
“main” compilation unit, and are aiming for lower; auxiliary compilation
units that import run-time facilities (the current exception handler and
so on) from the main module can be sub-kilobyte.  Getting here has been
tricky though, and I think it would be even trickier for Python.</p><p>Some background: <a href="https://wingolog.org/archives/2023/11/16/a-whiff-of-whiffle">like
Whiffle</a>,
the Hoot compiler prepends a
<a href="https://gitlab.com/spritely/guile-hoot/-/blob/main/module/hoot/prelude.scm">prelude</a>
onto user code.  Tree-shakind happens in a number of places:</p><ul><li><p><a href="https://git.savannah.gnu.org/cgit/guile.git/tree/module/language/tree-il/peval.scm">partial
evaluation</a>
will evaluate unused bindings for effect, possibly eliding them</p></li><li><p><a href="https://git.savannah.gnu.org/cgit/guile.git/tree/module/language/tree-il/fix-letrec.scm">fixing
letrec</a>
will do the same</p></li><li><p>CPS frequently traverses the program, following only referenced
function, value, and control edges, e.g. via
<a href="https://git.savannah.gnu.org/cgit/guile.git/tree/module/language/cps/renumber.scm">renumbering</a></p></li><li><p>There is an explicit <a href="https://git.savannah.gnu.org/cgit/guile.git/tree/module/language/cps/dce.scm">dead-code
elimination</a>
pass which tries to elide unused effect-free allocations, a situation
that can arise due to other optimizations</p></li><li><p>Finally there is a <a href="https://gitlab.com/spritely/guile-hoot/-/blob/main/module/hoot/stdlib.scm?ref_type=heads">standard library written in raw-ish
WebAssembly</a>,
whose definitions (globals, tables, imports, functions, etc) are
included in the residual binary <a href="https://gitlab.com/spritely/guile-hoot/-/blob/main/module/wasm/link.scm?ref_type=heads">only as
neeeded</a>.</p></li></ul><p>Generally speaking, procedure definitions (functions / closures) are the
easy part: you just include only those functions that are referenced by
the code.  In a language like Scheme, this gets you a long way.</p><p>However there are three immediate challenges.  One is that the
evaluation model for the definitions in the prelude is <tt>letrec*</tt>: the
scope is recursive but ordered.  Binding values can call or refer to
previously defined values, or capture values defined later.  If
evaluating the value of a binding requires referring to a value only
defined later, then that’s an error.  Again, for procedures this is
trivially OK, but as soon as you have non-procedure definitions,
sometimes the compiler won’t be able to prove this nice “only refers to
earlier bindings” property.  In that case the <a href="https://legacy.cs.indiana.edu/~dyb/pubs/letrec-reloaded-abstract.html">fixing <tt>letrec</tt>
(reloaded)</a>
algorithm will end up residualizing bindings that are <tt>set!</tt>, which of
all the tree-shaking passes above require the delicate DCE pass to
remove them.</p><p>Worse, some of those non-procedure definitions are <i>record types</i>, which
have vtables that define how to print a record, how to check if a value
is an instance of this record, and so on.  These vtable callbacks can
end up keeping a lot more code alive even if they are never used.  We’ll
get back to this later.</p><p>Similarly, say you print a string via
<a href="https://www.r6rs.org/final/html/r6rs-lib/r6rs-lib-Z-H-9.html#node_idx_832"><tt>display</tt></a>.
Well now not only are you bringing in the whole buffered I/O facility,
but you are also calling a highly polymorphic function: <tt>display</tt> can
print anything.  There’s a case for bitvectors, so you pull in code for
bitvectors.  There’s a case for pairs, so you pull in that code too.
And so on.</p><p>One solution is to instead call <tt>write-string</tt>, which only writes
strings and not general data.  You’ll still get the generic buffered I/O
facility (ports), though, even if your program only uses one kind of
port.</p><p>This brings me to my next point, which is that optimal tree-shaking is a
flow analysis problem.  Consider <tt>display</tt>: if we know that a program
will never have bitvectors, then any code in <tt>display</tt> that works on
bitvectors is dead and we can fold the branches that guard it.  But to
know this, we have to know what kind of arguments <tt>display</tt> is called
with, and for that we need <a href="https://wingolog.org/archives/2014/07/01/flow-analysis-in-guile">higher-level flow
analysis</a>.</p><p>The problem is exacerbated for Python in a few ways.  One, because
<a href="https://matt.might.net/articles/implementation-of-kcfa-and-0cfa/">object-oriented dispatch is higher-order
programming</a>.
How do you know what <tt>foo.bar</tt> actually means?  Depends on <tt>foo</tt>, which
means you have to thread around representations of what <tt>foo</tt> might be
everywhere and to everywhere’s caller and everywhere’s caller’s caller
and so on.</p><p>Secondly, lookup in Python is generally more dynamic than in Scheme: you
have <tt>__getattr__</tt> methods (is that it?; been a while since I’ve done
Python) everywhere and users might indeed use them.  Maybe this is not
so bad in practice and flow analysis can exclude this kind of dynamic
lookup.</p><p>Finally, and perhaps relatedly, the object of tree-shaking in Python is
a mess of modules, rather than a big term with lexical bindings.  This
is like JavaScript, but without the established ecosystem of
tree-shaking bundlers; Python has its work cut out for some years to go.</p><h3>in short</h3><p>With GC, Wasm makes it thinkable to do DOM programming in languages
other than JavaScript.  It will only be feasible for mass use, though,
if the resulting Wasm modules are small, and that means significant
investment on each language’s toolchain.  Often this will take the form
of alternate toolchains that incorporate experimental tree-shaking
algorithms, and whose alternate standard libraries facilitate the
tree-shaker.</p><p>Welp, I’m off to lunch.  Happy wassembling, comrades!</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[350 tons of of chocolate and wine arrive on world’s largest cargo sailboat (120 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://untappedcities.com/2024/04/12/grain-de-sail-ll/</link>
            <guid>40022801</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 12:45:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://untappedcities.com/2024/04/12/grain-de-sail-ll/">https://untappedcities.com/2024/04/12/grain-de-sail-ll/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40022801">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
<p>At&nbsp;<a href="https://untappedcities.com/2014/04/25/daily-what-south-street-seaport-mall-at-pier-17-demolition-fully-underway/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pier 17</a>&nbsp;in the South Street Seaport, New Yorkers can find the world’s largest cargo sailboat, <em>Grain de Sail&nbsp;ll</em>. The wind-powered ship arrived in New York on Wednesday with 350 tons of goods. Everything from Grain de Sail brand fine chocolates and organic coffee to cosmetic products, wine, and French fashion house luxury goods were on board.</p>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="533" data-attachment-id="590036" data-permalink="https://untappedcities.com/grain-de-sail-sailboat-untapped-new-york4/" data-orig-file="https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York4.jpg" data-orig-size="800,533" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;6.3&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;Untapped New York&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS Rebel T6s&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1712912553&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;113&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.005&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped New York4" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="<p>The Grain de Sail ll is the largest cargo sailboat. </p>
" data-medium-file="https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York4-300x200.jpg" data-large-file="https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York4.jpg" src="https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York4.jpg" alt="The Grain de Sail ll is the largest cargo sailboat." srcset="https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York4.jpg 800w, https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York4-300x200.jpg 300w, https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York4-768x512.jpg 768w, https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York4-560x373.jpg 560w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px"><figcaption>The Grain de Sail ll is the largest cargo sailboat. </figcaption></figure>
<p>“The best knowledge of what France is able to do is on this vessel,” said Jacques Barreau, CEO and Founder of Grain de Sail in France. <em>Grain de Sail ll </em>is the newest member of the company’s fleet of cargo sailboats. It stretches 52 meters, more than twice as long as <a href="https://untappedcities.com/2021/05/13/chocolate-wine-tasting-sailboat/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">its predecessor.</a> It can travel to New York from Saint-Malo, France in about 18 days. </p>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="533" data-attachment-id="590037" data-permalink="https://untappedcities.com/grain-de-sail-sailboat-untapped-new-york5/" data-orig-file="https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York5.jpg" data-orig-size="800,533" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;13&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;Untapped New York&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS Rebel T6s&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1712915734&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;50&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.005&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped New York5" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="<p>The Grain de Sail ll in New York City. </p>
" data-medium-file="https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York5-300x200.jpg" data-large-file="https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York5.jpg" src="https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York5.jpg" alt="The Grain de Sail ll in New York City." srcset="https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York5.jpg 800w, https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York5-300x200.jpg 300w, https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York5-768x512.jpg 768w, https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York5-560x373.jpg 560w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px"><figcaption>The Grain de Sail ll in New York City. </figcaption></figure>
<p>Grain de Sail’s cross-Atlantic voyages rely entirely on wind energy. The company’s mission is to empower zero-emission shipping with “retro-innovation,” blending ancestral technology with modern technology. This commitment to low emissions provides sustainable shipment options for Grain de Sail’s coffee, cacao, and wine brands, and other businesses that can now ship their products without contributing to worldwide maritime shipping’s global CO2 and methane emissions.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Compared to traditional cargo shipping, the process of unloading goods from Grain de Sail vessels averages about five days faster. This is because the sailboats have cranes directly on the deck. Thus, they can avoid harbor congestion and the long, strenuous process. Instead of taking 30-35 days to unload, Grain de Sail vessels take about 20 days.</p>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="533" data-attachment-id="590038" data-permalink="https://untappedcities.com/grain-de-sail-sailboat-untapped-new-york6/" data-orig-file="https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York6.jpg" data-orig-size="800,533" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;10&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;Untapped New York&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS Rebel T6s&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1712915477&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;35&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.004&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped New York6" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="<p>One of the sailboat’s mates works on the mast aboard the Grain de Sail ll. </p>
" data-medium-file="https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York6-300x200.jpg" data-large-file="https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York6.jpg" src="https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York6.jpg" alt="One of the sailboat's mates works on the mast aboard the Grain de Sail ll." srcset="https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York6.jpg 800w, https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York6-300x200.jpg 300w, https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York6-768x512.jpg 768w, https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York6-560x373.jpg 560w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px"><figcaption>One of the sailboat’s mates works on the mast aboard the Grain de Sail ll. </figcaption></figure>
<p>Grain de Sail was founded in 2010 by two twin brothers, Olivier and Jacques Barreau, who are renewable energy experts from France. The company’s inception stemmed from its goal to reduce the carbon footprint of maritime transportation.&nbsp;<a href="https://untappedcities.com/2020/08/20/schooner-apollonia-brings-freight-by-sail-to-nyc-for-first-time-in-a-century/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Wind</a>&nbsp;is a reliable, savvy alternative to the high environmental costs of fossil fuels. Grain de Sail also emphasizes its promise to preserve the quality of goods, so you’re introduced to one of the only floating wine cellars. To properly maintain the quality of the bottles, the vessel is fitted with temperature and humidity control features.&nbsp;</p>
<p>“We must shift our focus on the quality rather than quantity,” said Barreau. “We must change our mindset to products that last longer and generate less pressure on the environment.”</p>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="533" data-attachment-id="590034" data-permalink="https://untappedcities.com/grain-de-sail-sailboat-untapped-new-york2/" data-orig-file="https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York2.jpg" data-orig-size="800,533" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;9&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;Untapped New York&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS Rebel T6s&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1712915495&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;18&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.005&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped New York2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="<p>Jacques Barreau, CEO and Founder of Grain de Sail, on board the Grain de Sail ll. </p>
" data-medium-file="https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York2-300x200.jpg" data-large-file="https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York2.jpg" src="https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York2.jpg" alt="Jacques Barreau, CEO and Founder of Grain de Sail, on board the Grain de Sail ll." srcset="https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York2.jpg 800w, https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York2-300x200.jpg 300w, https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York2-768x512.jpg 768w, https://untappedcities.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Grain-de-Sail-Sailboat-Untapped-New-York2-560x373.jpg 560w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px"><figcaption>Jacques Barreau, CEO and Founder of Grain de Sail, on board the Grain de Sail ll. </figcaption></figure>
<p>In New York City,&nbsp;<a href="https://graindesail-overseas.com/search-retailers" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">several retailers</a>&nbsp;sell goods delivered from the Grain de Sail. Not only can you support local businesses, but your conscious buying is helping to decarbonize shipping.&nbsp;</p>
<p>After the ship leaves New York City on April 15, 2024, <em>Grain de Sail ll</em> will return to France, loaded with various goods. This is the first load of many for the <em>Grain de Sail ll</em>. In total, this vessel plans to sail the seas five times a year, trekking from France to New York and then down through the Caribbean, where the sailboat will dispatch humanitarian aid, working alongside local NGOs. The sailboat will also restock its coffee and cacao supply on its journey through the Caribbean. That supply is then brought back across the sea to France, where the coffee is roasted, and fine chocolates are produced.</p>
<p><strong>Next, check out <a href="https://untappedcities.com/2024/04/11/energy-observer-nyc/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">The Floating Energy Lab Docked in NYC for Earth Day</a></strong></p>


</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A disgruntled federal employee's 1980s desk calendar (2018) (131 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://internationaltimes.it/a-disgruntled-federal-employees-1980s-desk-calendar/</link>
            <guid>40022709</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 12:27:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://internationaltimes.it/a-disgruntled-federal-employees-1980s-desk-calendar/">https://internationaltimes.it/a-disgruntled-federal-employees-1980s-desk-calendar/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40022709">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://internationaltimes.it/a-disgruntled-federal-employees-1980s-desk-calendar/: Error: Request failed with status code 500]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Is .NET just miles ahead or am I delusional? (155 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://old.reddit.com/r/dotnet/comments/18gpl24/is_net_just_miles_ahead_or_am_i_delusional/</link>
            <guid>40021758</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 09:29:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/dotnet/comments/18gpl24/is_net_just_miles_ahead_or_am_i_delusional/">https://old.reddit.com/r/dotnet/comments/18gpl24/is_net_just_miles_ahead_or_am_i_delusional/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40021758">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Professionally I've only ever worked in c# code bases. Obviously a lot of projects had a js SPA frontend attached, but I wasnt on that side.</p>

<p>I'm branching out into other languages, I'm pretty involved in reading newest tech twitter stuff, articles, youtube videos etc.</p>

<p>I get hit by incredible "what is going on, I had this in .net for  years, i dont even know how any ecosystem exists without it" more and more recently. How do others feel about this?</p>

<p>Some examples: </p>

<p>I just watched this video <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zB9tEQYLPL4">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zB9tEQYLPL4</a>. Appearantly go + htmx have managed to recreate razor or blazor templates and people are gushing about how insane it is that they ALMOST make it typesafe. Its not really typesafe, more like typescript where its autocomplete, but not real.</p>

<p>I remember reading about one of the top javascript ORMs. Drizzle? People realized that it actually queried the entire database in the background and then did in memory query operations in its rust engine??? Generally I have to ignore any "ORM bad" comments people make, because I know their ORMs are actually bad. Its l ike using the original ef at best.</p>

<p>Build stuff and configuration in javascript specifically. In .net its so easy I don't even know what happens. It just works. I press F5 locally and I put it in whatever pipeline for production.Javascript mains just go babel webpack, they have conflicts, c make, i dont know whats going on...</p>

<p>The react server component meme a couple of months back where everyone was freaking out about either how insane it is or how insanely unsafe it is for sql injection. We had it in blazor for years.</p>

<p>Debugging... do I even need to say anything? There are unironic articles out there advocating for print debugging over attaching a debugger. Probably because it has actually some validity in other languages where you not just click the line number and smash F5.</p>

<p>I do like some things from other languages. I think just writing UIs in react, pressing strg s and instantly seeing the result is amazing. Much better than the blazor or razor dev experience.I like ... "hardcoded string options" as actual types. Its like enums but nicer I think. Dont know what that feature is actually called.</p>

<p>I also really like the typescript type magic. Autogenerating a type based on one object. Extending that type with 2 properties in 1 line and using that one. I miss that in c#. But in general these are small nice to haves, not "bro how do you even exist? How can some smart people not just steal ef core 1:1 for rust, go or js?"</p>

<p>I dont really know if I have a question. It just seems to me that these devs with a supposed breadth of knowledge are all missing the .net part. It feels like a weird island. It really feels like a waste.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ubisoft is stripping people's licences for The Crew weeks after its shutdown (174 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.pcgamer.com/games/racing/ubisoft-is-stripping-peoples-licences-for-the-crew-weeks-after-its-shutdown-nearly-squandering-hopes-of-private-servers-and-acting-as-a-stark-reminder-of-how-volatile-digital-ownership-is/</link>
            <guid>40020961</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 06:23:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.pcgamer.com/games/racing/ubisoft-is-stripping-peoples-licences-for-the-crew-weeks-after-its-shutdown-nearly-squandering-hopes-of-private-servers-and-acting-as-a-stark-reminder-of-how-volatile-digital-ownership-is/">https://www.pcgamer.com/games/racing/ubisoft-is-stripping-peoples-licences-for-the-crew-weeks-after-its-shutdown-nearly-squandering-hopes-of-private-servers-and-acting-as-a-stark-reminder-of-how-volatile-digital-ownership-is/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40020961">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-widget-type="contentparsed" id="content">

<section>
<div itemprop="image" itemscope="" itemtype="https://schema.org/ImageObject">
<div>
<picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-320-80.jpg.webp 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-480-80.jpg.webp 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-650-80.jpg.webp 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-970-80.jpg.webp 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-1024-80.jpg.webp 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-1200-80.jpg.webp 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-1920-80.jpg.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 600px, calc(100vw - 40px)"><img src="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-320-80.jpg" alt="Image for Ubisoft is stripping people's licences for The Crew weeks after its shutdown, nearly squandering hopes of fan servers and acting as a stark reminder of how volatile digital ownership is" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-320-80.jpg 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-480-80.jpg 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-650-80.jpg 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-970-80.jpg 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-1024-80.jpg 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-1200-80.jpg 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-1920-80.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 600px, calc(100vw - 40px)" data-original-mos="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296.jpg" data-pin-media="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296.jpg"></picture>
</div>
<meta itemprop="url" content="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296.jpg">
<meta itemprop="height" content="600">
<meta itemprop="width" content="338">
<figcaption itemprop="caption description">
<span itemprop="copyrightHolder">(Image credit: Ubisoft)</span>
</figcaption>
</div>

<div id="article-body">
<p>The downside of digital ownership has reared its ugly head for enjoyers of <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.pcgamer.com/uk/tag/ubisoft/" data-auto-tag-linker="true" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.pcgamer.com/uk/tag/ubisoft/">Ubisoft</a>'s open-world multiplayer racer The Crew. The publisher has revoked its licence for those who owned it on Ubisoft Connect, almost destroying fan ambitions to revive the game in both an offline and online format.</p><p><a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.pcgamer.com/the-crew-removed-from-sale-will-become-unplayable-after-april-1-we-understand-this-may-be-disappointing-for-players-still-enjoying-the-game/" target="_blank" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.pcgamer.com/the-crew-removed-from-sale-will-become-unplayable-after-april-1-we-understand-this-may-be-disappointing-for-players-still-enjoying-the-game/">The Crew was pulled from sale</a> back in December, with Ubisoft revealing that the servers would be shut down at the beginning of April. Frustratingly, despite a large portion of the game being doable in singleplayer, The Crew remained an online-only endeavour throughout its decade-long lifespan. That had already rendered the game unplayable, but it seems Ubisoft is determined to take things one step further to stamp out any attempts to continue playing it past its expiry date.</p><p>Fans began to notice earlier in the week that the licence to the game had been snatched away from them. A message at the top of the game's library page reads, "You no longer have access to this game. Why not check the Store to pursue your adventures?" It's also been moved to its own individual section in player libraries, listed under "inactive games". Apparently booting the game directly from the installation directory will still launch the game, but only in a demo mode.</p><p>The news has, unsurprisingly, gone down very poorly. "This was the saddest and most ruthless decision I've ever seen in gaming history," one Redditor <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Games/comments/1c1la9j/comment/kz59uec/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.reddit.com/r/Games/comments/1c1la9j/comment/kz59uec/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3">commented</a> after a screenshot began circulating on the site. "I will always fight for digital media, I love all the advantages it gives to users all around the world. But this… we need protection on the national or European level, that when we purchase something, we need to have lifetime access to it. No matter what."</p><figure data-bordeaux-image-check=""><div><p><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-320-80.jpg.webp 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-480-80.jpg.webp 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-650-80.jpg.webp 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-970-80.jpg.webp 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-1024-80.jpg.webp 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-1200-80.jpg.webp 1200w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 970px, calc(100vw - 40px)"><img src="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-320-80.jpg" alt="Ubisoft Connect's store which shows that the licence for The Crew has been revoked." srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-320-80.jpg 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-480-80.jpg 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-650-80.jpg 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-970-80.jpg 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-1024-80.jpg 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-1200-80.jpg 1200w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 970px, calc(100vw - 40px)" loading="lazy" data-original-mos="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi.jpg" data-pin-media="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi.jpg"></picture></p></div><figcaption itemprop="caption description"><span itemprop="copyrightHolder">(Image credit: Ubisoft)</span></figcaption></figure><p>A further Reddit user <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Games/comments/1c1la9j/comment/kz4rn3d/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.reddit.com/r/Games/comments/1c1la9j/comment/kz4rn3d/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3">called it</a> "really abhorrent behavior that needs to stop being legal," with another <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Games/comments/1c1la9j/comment/kz4q9er/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.reddit.com/r/Games/comments/1c1la9j/comment/kz4q9er/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3">writing</a>, "In an ideal world, revoking a license like this should entitle the buyer to a refund. I'm not sure why they're even bothering doing this. The game isn't playable anymore, so what exactly is the harm in keeping the game available for download for those who have purchased it? Server space? Is Ubisoft really that cheap?"</p><p>It's worth noting that it appears you can technically still download the game on Steam, but any attempt to play is followed-up with <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://imgur.com/WPOWIPc" target="_blank" data-url="https://imgur.com/WPOWIPc">a request to input a game key</a></p><p>Now it's one thing to just delist a game and still allow owners to download and boot it up if they want—even if the game is technically dead—but it's another thing to revoke the licence to the files entirely. It came very close to putting a dent in plans to bring fan servers to the game, but one project appears to still be chugging along.</p><div data-hydrate="true" id="slice-container-newsletterForm-articleInbodyContent-gMmpoeneCkWpxZH3cWJFGS"><section><p>Sign up to get the best content of the week, and great gaming deals, as picked by the editors.</p></section></div><blockquote><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/gaming/comments/1c1y7h3/ubisoft_revoking_licenses_for_the_crew_preventing" data-url="https://www.reddit.com/r/gaming/comments/1c1y7h3/ubisoft_revoking_licenses_for_the_crew_preventing">Ubisoft revoking licenses for The Crew, preventing owners who paid for the game from installing it.</a> from <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/gaming" data-url="https://www.reddit.com/r/gaming">r/gaming</a></blockquote><p>The Crew Unlimited Discord server is housing a project called The Crew Offline+Online Server Emulation, intended to bring the game back to a playable state "both offline locally and online" via a community server—no cracking or pirating involved. I asked project member ChemicalFlood how it had impacted their plans:</p><p><em>"We are deeply saddened by Ubisoft's choice to start revoking licences to this game when people have paid hard-earned cash for it," he told me. "In regard to the project, yes! We are currently working on a Server Emulator as opposed to cracking the game. Before the shutdown of the servers, we took the precaution of capturing Network Communications Data. Had we not done this, the project would [have] sadly fallen over and this game would [have] been lost forever.</em></p><p><em>"Thankfully, a server emulation is still possible. But no other patch is possible due to the high amount of DRM placed into the game by Ubisoft, which sadly has restricted our ability to work on a fix, but not impossible!"</em></p><p>I also asked ChemicalFlood how the news had gone down with fans and The Crew Unlimited Discord:&nbsp;</p><p><em>"Obviously, Ubisoft pulling the game licences has left a sour taste in every gamer's mouth and it has unfortunately made it so the game cannot even be launched without it turning into a restricted trial mode. However, we can bypass this new change made by them without having to modify the existing game files, so the project is still on track!</em></p><p><em>"It should go without saying that, by any means, the fact that the community has to implement something like this to continue playing something we all paid for is abysmal, especially something of this magnitude. We of course love the game and want it to be played for generations to come (my own son loved playing this on the <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.pcgamer.com/uk/tag/playstation/" data-auto-tag-linker="true" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.pcgamer.com/uk/tag/playstation/">PlayStation</a>, 'loved' being the keyword!) But Ubisoft should [have] implemented an offline mode and they could [have]! The offline mode already exists in the files, we just can't turn it on because of the DRM in place.</em></p><p><em>"We hope that the </em><a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.stopkillinggames.com/" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.stopkillinggames.com/"><em>Stopkillinggames</em></a><em> campaign will mean that the communities and fans of these games will not be expected to be able to restore every single online-only game like this."</em></p><figure data-bordeaux-image-check=""><div><p><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-320-80.jpg.webp 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-480-80.jpg.webp 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-650-80.jpg.webp 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-970-80.jpg.webp 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-1024-80.jpg.webp 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-1200-80.jpg.webp 1200w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 970px, calc(100vw - 40px)"><img src="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-320-80.jpg" alt="Ubisoft Connect's store which shows that the licence for The Crew has been revoked." srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-320-80.jpg 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-480-80.jpg 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-650-80.jpg 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-970-80.jpg 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-1024-80.jpg 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-1200-80.jpg 1200w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 970px, calc(100vw - 40px)" loading="lazy" data-original-mos="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui.jpg" data-pin-media="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui.jpg"></picture></p></div><figcaption itemprop="caption description"><span itemprop="copyrightHolder">(Image credit: Ubisoft)</span></figcaption></figure><p>I've requested comment from Ubisoft regarding the situation and will update if I hear back. I'll be interested to know if the publisher provides any solid reason for being extra thorough with its shutdown process. There's a good chance it has something to do with licensing—there are a good deal of licensed songs in The Crew, not to mention all of the real-world car manufacturers present, too. It could make for a sticky situation keeping the files around, and perhaps it was easier to try and kill the whole thing instead.&nbsp;</p><p>Regardless of the reason, it's an ever-looming reminder of how fragile digital ownership can be. A study by the Video Game History Foundation last year found that around <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.pcgamer.com/study-finds-over-87-percent-of-games-are-unplayable-without-resorting-to-piracy-scavenger-hunts-or-travelling-to-an-archive/" target="_blank" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.pcgamer.com/study-finds-over-87-percent-of-games-are-unplayable-without-resorting-to-piracy-scavenger-hunts-or-travelling-to-an-archive/">87% of games are unplayable</a> without diving into some kind of piracy or fan-created archive, and that number could even worsen as physical discs slowly die out. But preservation is becoming a bigger topic, one that's <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.pcgamer.com/gaming-industry/events-conferences/preserving-old-games-was-seen-as-a-non-commercial-art-project-until-recently-says-nightdive-director-they-were-great-then-and-theyre-great-now-and-companies-have-begun-to-realize-that/" target="_blank" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.pcgamer.com/gaming-industry/events-conferences/preserving-old-games-was-seen-as-a-non-commercial-art-project-until-recently-says-nightdive-director-they-were-great-then-and-theyre-great-now-and-companies-have-begun-to-realize-that/">now being taken more seriously</a> as a means of conserving the medium.</p><p>Earlier this month, YouTuber Ross Scott <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.pcgamer.com/gaming-industry/stop-killing-games-campaign/" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.pcgamer.com/gaming-industry/stop-killing-games-campaign/">launched a campaign</a> called "Stop Killing Games" with The Crew as its primary example. His hope is to eventually win a legal victory that would require publishers to keep their live service games playable in some form after they end support, such as by releasing private servers.</p>
</div>
<div id="slice-container-authorBio-gMmpoeneCkWpxZH3cWJFGS"><p>Mollie spent her early childhood deeply invested in games like Killer Instinct, Toontown and Audition Online, which continue to form the pillars of her personality today. She joined PC Gamer in 2020 as a news writer and now lends her expertise to write a wealth of features, guides and reviews with a dash of chaos. She can often be found causing mischief in Final Fantasy 14, using those experiences to write neat things about her favourite MMO. When she's not staring at her bunny girl she can be found sweating out rhythm games, pretending to be good at fighting games or spending far too much money at her local arcade. &nbsp;</p></div>




</section>


<div id="slice-container-relatedArticles"><p><h5>Most Popular</h5></p></div>







</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Arc Product-Market Fit Framework (133 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.sequoiacap.com/article/pmf-framework/</link>
            <guid>40020601</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 04:55:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.sequoiacap.com/article/pmf-framework/">https://www.sequoiacap.com/article/pmf-framework/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40020601">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main">
		<article>
	
<section><h2>The Arc Product-Market Fit Framework</h2></section>



<section>
<p>Finding product-market fit is the central quest of every early-stage startup. As we have seen over years of partnering with companies before they reached PMF, there are many ways of thinking about and approaching this quest. We walk founders through the following framework during <a href="https://www.sequoiacap.com/arc/">Arc</a>, our company-building immersion for pre-seed and seed stage companies. Rather than diagnosing whether you have product-market fit, this framework outlines three distinct archetypes of PMF which help you understand your product’s place in the market and determine how your company operates.</p>



<h2 id="h-3-archetypes-of-product-market-fit">3 Archetypes of Product-Market Fit</h2>



<p>Ultimately, product-market fit is about your product’s place in the world. There are different aspects to how your product fits into the world that you could hone in on—competitive landscape, the technical merits of your product, etc. We think the best way is to start by focusing on how the <strong><em>customer</em> <em>relates to the problem</em></strong><em> </em>your product solves.&nbsp;</p>



<p>There are different kinds of problems, and different ways customers relate to them. We see three basic archetypes, each with its own distinct customer-product relationship dynamics.</p>



<figure><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="304" height="210" src="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/03/HoF.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/03/HoF.png 304w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/03/HoF.png?resize=300,207 300w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/03/HoF.png?resize=217,150 217w" sizes="(max-width: 304px) 100vw, 304px"></figure>



<h3 id="h-hair-on-fire"><strong>Hair on Fire</strong></h3>



<p>You solve a problem that’s a clear, urgent need for customers. The demand is obvious. Because of this, your category is likely crowded with competitors vying for market share. Your customers are actively wrestling with the problem, and likely comparing existing products to solve it. To succeed in such a dynamic, you must rise above the noise. The only way to do so is by delivering the best-in-class solution. And best-in-class products stand out because they are different, not merely better. You can’t just be faster or cheaper—you need a truly differentiated customer experience to have a durable advantage.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" width="304" height="210" src="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/03/HF.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/03/HF.png 304w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/03/HF.png?resize=300,207 300w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/03/HF.png?resize=217,150 217w" sizes="(max-width: 304px) 100vw, 304px"></figure>



<h3 id="h-hard-fact"><strong>Hard Fact</strong></h3>



<p>You take a pain point universally accepted as a hard fact of life, and see that it’s merely a hard problem <em>that your product solves </em>for the customer. Your customers have resigned themselves to just living with the problem. They’re not urgently engaged with trying to solve it. The status quo is just how it is, and change doesn’t seem like an option. You upend how things are done with an unexpected approach: Facts can’t be changed—but problems can be solved. The challenge to overcome is force of habit. Customers will have to change their current behaviors, and inertia is powerful. You need an approach that’s novel enough, for a problem that <em>matters</em> enough, to be worth making a change.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" width="304" height="210" src="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/03/FV.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/03/FV.png 304w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/03/FV.png?resize=300,207 300w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/03/FV.png?resize=217,150 217w" sizes="(max-width: 304px) 100vw, 304px"></figure>



<h3 id="h-future-vision"><strong>Future Vision</strong></h3>



<p>You enable a new reality through visionary innovation. It sounds like science fiction to customers, either because the concept is familiar but sounds impossible (like abundant cheap energy from nuclear fusion) or because no one ever imagined it (like the iPhone). Customers are not only not trying to solve the problem, they are either oblivious to it or predisposed to think it’s a pipe dream. Either way, the obstacle is disbelief: Customers must believe that your product represents a whole new paradigm—often with its own ecosystem. (The iPhone wasn’t just a device; its App Store was a new way of interfacing with the internet. Tesla isn’t just a car; it’s a network of cameras and self-driving software that’s a new driving experience.) Customers must find the paradigm and its possibilities irresistible. As we’ll discuss below, this path is often long, and finding the right route with the right commercial opportunities along the way is usually critical.</p>
</section>



<figure><picture><source srcset="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Framework-mobile.png" media="(max-width: 767px)"><img decoding="async" width="2720" height="1530" src="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Framework-desktop.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Framework-desktop.png 2720w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Framework-desktop.png?resize=300,169 300w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Framework-desktop.png?resize=768,432 768w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Framework-desktop.png?resize=1024,576 1024w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Framework-desktop.png?resize=1536,864 1536w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Framework-desktop.png?resize=2048,1152 2048w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Framework-desktop.png?resize=220,124 220w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Framework-desktop.png?resize=1920,1080 1920w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Framework-desktop.png?resize=680,383 680w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Framework-desktop.png?resize=930,523 930w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Framework-desktop.png?resize=1440,810 1440w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Framework-desktop.png?resize=480,270 480w" sizes="(max-width: 2720px) 100vw, 2720px"></picture></figure>



<section>
<h2>How to Operate in Each Path&nbsp;</h2>



<p>Once you understand these archetypes, you can self-identify which path your company is on. Many founders we encounter in Arc assume they’re <em>supposed</em> to be in the Hair on Fire path. They have absorbed the adage to listen to what customers need. That’s good advice. But it often comes as a revelation that Hard Fact or Future Vision dynamics are viable options for finding PMF.</p>



<p>Hopefully you’re already working on a problem you have a unique advantage in solving. Your path, however, will be defined by how <em>your customer</em> relates to this problem (and how they feel about your solution). You can find success on any path—but each brings a distinct set of operating priorities that are essential to understand.</p>



<h3><mark>Path 1 –</mark> Hair on Fire</h3>



<p>The Hair on Fire path requires both a great product and a great go-to-market effort—in quick succession. This combination of solution, selling and speed is the key to overcoming the competition.&nbsp;</p>
</section>



<figure><a href="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hair-on-fire-desktop.png" data-pswp-width="2720" data-pswp-height="1530"><picture><source srcset="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hair-on-fire-mobile.png" media="(max-width: 767px)"><img decoding="async" width="2720" height="1530" src="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hair-on-fire-desktop.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hair-on-fire-desktop.png 2720w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hair-on-fire-desktop.png?resize=300,169 300w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hair-on-fire-desktop.png?resize=768,432 768w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hair-on-fire-desktop.png?resize=1024,576 1024w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hair-on-fire-desktop.png?resize=1536,864 1536w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hair-on-fire-desktop.png?resize=2048,1152 2048w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hair-on-fire-desktop.png?resize=220,124 220w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hair-on-fire-desktop.png?resize=1920,1080 1920w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hair-on-fire-desktop.png?resize=680,383 680w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hair-on-fire-desktop.png?resize=930,523 930w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hair-on-fire-desktop.png?resize=1440,810 1440w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hair-on-fire-desktop.png?resize=480,270 480w" sizes="(max-width: 2720px) 100vw, 2720px"></picture></a></figure>



<section>
<h3 id="h-hair-on-fire-case-studies">Hair on Fire<mark> –</mark> <mark>Case Studies</mark></h3>



<p>Along with product velocity, one hallmark of companies that break through to find success in the Hair on Fire path is the ability to aggressively out-maneuver the competition.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Assaf Rappaport and his Wiz co-founders had previously founded Adallom together. For their new company, they were intrigued by the problem of cloud infrastructure security—but it was already a crowded space with incumbents like Palo Alto Networks and startups like Orca Security offering products on the market. However, when they interviewed CISOs, the topic kept surfacing at the top of everyone’s wish list. There was evident demand in a large market—but it took some digging to find the opportunity for differentiation. Most cloud security products relied on agents, a piece of software that needs to be installed in every server in order to monitor it. Wiz conceived an “agentless” solution that not only reduced friction and headaches, but surfaced vulnerabilities more effectively. Even better, once connected it could surface those vulnerabilities in the course of a 15-minute customer demo. Assaf and his team found their advantage, and floored the accelerator, aggressively out-maneuvering the competition: engineers built the product during their workday Israel time, and worked double-duty as sales reps at night—daytime in the U.S. They went from $0 to $2.8M in a single quarter and reached $100M in ARR in 18 months, setting a new record for the fastest-growing software company, ever.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>When Parker Conrad founded Rippling, he was entering a large Hair on Fire market. Every company needs HR software, and this urgency was reflected in the steep competition: there were already at least half a dozen incumbents fighting for market share. In fact one of them was Parker’s <em>own</em> previous company Zenefits. Why bother? Because his deep expertise meant he knew what needed to be done differently: While other providers stitched together disparate datasets to offer a single platform for HR and benefits, Rippling’s approach was to build a unified database. This foundation layer for employee data could then “ripple” out to any aspect of the employee experience, from benefits to expenses to device management. Their technical advantage created a different experience for HR, finance and IT administrators, which allowed Rippling to stand out and quickly grow market share in a field of incumbents. And their strategy of bundling the widest set of employee experiences gave it pricing power even in a Hair on Fire dynamic where price leverage can be challenging for new entrants.</p>



<h3><mark>Path 2 –</mark> Hard Fact</h3>



<p>The Hard Fact path entails getting customers to re-evaluate and change the way they approach a current process. This requires first educating the market, and then capturing the opportunity.</p>
</section>



<figure><a href="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hard-Fact.png" data-pswp-width="2720" data-pswp-height="1530"><picture><source srcset="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hard-fact-mobile.png" media="(max-width: 767px)"><img decoding="async" width="2720" height="1530" src="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hard-Fact.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hard-Fact.png 2720w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hard-Fact.png?resize=300,169 300w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hard-Fact.png?resize=768,432 768w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hard-Fact.png?resize=1024,576 1024w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hard-Fact.png?resize=1536,864 1536w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hard-Fact.png?resize=2048,1152 2048w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hard-Fact.png?resize=220,124 220w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hard-Fact.png?resize=1920,1080 1920w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hard-Fact.png?resize=680,383 680w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hard-Fact.png?resize=930,523 930w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hard-Fact.png?resize=1440,810 1440w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Hard-Fact.png?resize=480,270 480w" sizes="(max-width: 2720px) 100vw, 2720px"></picture></a></figure>



<section>
<h3 id="h-hard-fact-case-studies">Hard Fact<mark> –</mark> <mark>Case Studies</mark></h3>



<p>Your novel approach may replace an existing market (like Salesforce moving CRM to the cloud) or it may create a new market (like Uber reimagining the taxi experience as a rideshare marketplace). Either way, you will likely face less competition on the Hard Fact path because the difficulty of changing the status quo has discouraged other founders from taking on the problem. To succeed, Uber had to not only convince legions of everyday people to drive strangers around, but also engage with taxi unions, local regulations and labor laws. Others’ natural aversion to such difficulty means you’ll likely get more of a greenfield opportunity.</p>



<p>When Block (then Square) first launched, the hard fact they were addressing was widely known and acknowledged: “cash only.” For many small businesses or at any farmers’ market, there was no way to accept credit cards. Consumers would trudge off to find ATMs and merchants would often miss out on sales. Jack Dorsey and Jim McKelvey’s unique insight was that smartphones, which were just becoming ubiquitous, could be effectively turned into mobile credit card terminals. Square realized that this supposed hard fact of life was actually a hard problem<em> that it could solve</em>. But finding success meant getting the world to see it no longer had to live with this pain point, and to trust Square’s solution enough to adopt their new way. In order to activate this epiphany and win over early adopters who would evangelize the product, Square made an early decision to give its hardware and software away for free to merchants and figure out a business model later. Eventually, Square became a new standard.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In 2006, marketing mainly consisted of advertising, mailers and telemarketing. This put small businesses at a disadvantage, as these were all high-cost channels. Brian Halligan and Dharmesh Shah realized there was a new way: small companies could leverage the properties of the fast-maturing internet—blogs, social media, SEO, email newsletters—to reach audiences at a fraction of the cost of traditional channels. HubSpot’s suite of content, SEO and email management tools solved this problem for customers. But in order for customers to <em>believe</em> in their approach and begin adopting their product, HubSpot needed to crystalize the new way in customers’ minds—to make them <em>aware</em> that the old way was broken and could be replaced with something better. They did this by coining a term for their new way—“inbound marketing”— and even wrote a book about it. They were so effective at educating the market that the idea caught on and started a marketing revolution in the small business world, propelling HubSpot to product-market fit and beyond.</p>



<h3><mark>Path 3 –</mark> Future Vision</h3>



<p>The Future Vision path has the most ways to fail and the fewest to succeed, but potentially the largest payoff. Taking this path requires endurance and the ability to attract and retain top talent for the long haul.</p>
</section>



<figure><a href="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Future-Vision.png" data-pswp-width="2720" data-pswp-height="1530"><picture><source srcset="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Future-vision-mobile.png" media="(max-width: 767px)"><img decoding="async" width="2720" height="1530" src="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Future-Vision.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Future-Vision.png 2720w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Future-Vision.png?resize=300,169 300w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Future-Vision.png?resize=768,432 768w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Future-Vision.png?resize=1024,576 1024w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Future-Vision.png?resize=1536,864 1536w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Future-Vision.png?resize=2048,1152 2048w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Future-Vision.png?resize=220,124 220w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Future-Vision.png?resize=1920,1080 1920w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Future-Vision.png?resize=680,383 680w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Future-Vision.png?resize=930,523 930w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Future-Vision.png?resize=1440,810 1440w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Future-Vision.png?resize=480,270 480w" sizes="(max-width: 2720px) 100vw, 2720px"></picture></a></figure>



<section>
<h3 id="h-future-vision-case-studies">Future Vision<mark> –</mark> <mark>Case Studies</mark></h3>



<p>Philosopher Søren Kierkegaard said, “Life can only be understood by looking backward, but it must be lived looking forward.” Future Vision founders like Nvidia’s Jensen Huang, who took a tortuous 30-year path to reach the company’s founding ambition, can probably relate.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Nvidia’s initial vision was to uplevel what PCs are capable of with a 3D graphics chip that would transform the experience of using a computer. When Nvidia released its first chip, it was so ahead of its time that no one knew what to do with it. It took six years and three product lines to find product-market fit in an industry where the GPU enabled irresistible new possibilities: video games. While Nvidia’s original ambition wasn’t limited to the video game industry, it became synonymous with gaming innovation, with its GPUs powering both PCs and Xboxes. Were it not for that very productive pit stop—which propelled Nvidia to profitability and IPO—the company never would have survived long enough to power today’s AI revolution. In fact, they were teetering on bankruptcy before finding PMF in gaming. Thirty years from its founding, Nvidia is enabling a new computing paradigm as GPUs transform everything from data centers to cloud computing.</p>



<p>Future Vision products that fail to find PMF are often described as being “too early.” For instance, 11 years after Google Glass launched, augmented reality still hasn’t gone mainstream. This is precisely why finding pit stops with <em>commercial traction along the way</em> is so critical. Assuming your vision is correct and you can find a viable path, time is on your side with the Future Vision archetype: You can amass an insurmountable headstart while the world comes around to your paradigm. But finding the right pit stops can be difficult. You must act with imperfect information—“live looking forward,” as Kierkegaard said—and the pitfalls are always more obvious in hindsight. Oftentimes finding the right path means embracing unexpected turns, both with the technology you produce and the market you serve.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>OpenAI is one of the most interesting Future Vision stories of our time. Its vision is to achieve artificial general intelligence (AGI)—long considered a pipe dream in technology circles—and to do so for the benefit of humanity. To achieve this, they started as a non-profit, since the founders thought the profit motive of a company would undermine their mission of human benefit. A few years into the journey, however, they realized that the cost of compute needed to innovate their large language models outstripped the fundraising capacity of even the best-connected non-profit. Their path required a turn into the for-profit sector. Adopting a more traditional startup structure brought funding as well as expectations for product launches—hence ChatGPT. It instantly found product-market fit in the iPhone paradigm of “<em>I couldn’t imagine wanting it until I saw it.</em>” Consumer demand for generative AI was nascent in 2022. In 2023, OpenAI generated $<a href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/openai-annualized-revenue-tops-16-billion-information-2023-12-30/">1.6B</a>. While ChatGPT achieved the fastest adoption of any consumer technology product ever, for OpenAI it’s the pit stop they need on the way toward their <em>real</em> ambition.</p>



<h3>Putting it All Together</h3>



<p>Using the framework of these three paths—and keeping in mind that one isn’t better than the others—you can reflect on your own product’s place in the world. What path are you on? How do customers relate to the problem you’re solving? Are you thinking about the right category dynamics? What are your operating priorities? Do you need to optimize for velocity and scale, land an epiphany with early adopters, or strategize the pit stops in your journey?</p>
</section>



<figure><a href="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Diagnostic-Desktop.png" data-pswp-width="2720" data-pswp-height="1530"><picture><source srcset="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Diagnostic-mobile.png" media="(max-width: 767px)"><img decoding="async" width="2720" height="1530" src="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Diagnostic-Desktop.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Diagnostic-Desktop.png 2720w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Diagnostic-Desktop.png?resize=300,169 300w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Diagnostic-Desktop.png?resize=768,432 768w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Diagnostic-Desktop.png?resize=1024,576 1024w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Diagnostic-Desktop.png?resize=1536,864 1536w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Diagnostic-Desktop.png?resize=2048,1152 2048w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Diagnostic-Desktop.png?resize=220,124 220w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Diagnostic-Desktop.png?resize=1920,1080 1920w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Diagnostic-Desktop.png?resize=680,383 680w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Diagnostic-Desktop.png?resize=930,523 930w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Diagnostic-Desktop.png?resize=1440,810 1440w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Diagnostic-Desktop.png?resize=480,270 480w" sizes="(max-width: 2720px) 100vw, 2720px"></picture></a></figure>



<section>
<h3 id="h-the-quest-continues-nbsp">The Quest Continues&nbsp;</h3>



<p>Practice is always messier than theory, and as you apply this thinking in the real world there are several important nuances to keep in mind:&nbsp;</p>



<p>Product-market relationship dynamics are fluid. Over time, many companies end up moving from one path to another as they introduce new products or as customer attitudes change about an existing product and underlying problem. Some companies straddle two paths at once. The point of this framework is not to irrevocably set your path in stone; it would be a mistake to identify yourself too narrowly with any one of them.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Apple, for instance, started as a Future Vision. The company’s initial memo to Sequoia in 1978 acknowledged that there was zero demand for household computers. “Apple management,” it stated, “believes that most potential customers of 1980 do not today have the slightest interest in purchasing a home computer.” As they captured imaginations and grew in popularity in the ’80s, however, the category of personal computers was no longer a Future Vision. By 1998, with the launch of iMac, Apple addressed a Hard Fact: computers, while increasingly ubiquitous, were impersonal. The iPhone instantly found PMF as a Future Vision when Steve Jobs unveiled it in 2007. The smartphone category then quickly shifted to Hair on Fire dynamics and a flood of new smartphones entered the market. Apple managed to retain its dominance by defining the category, being right and continuing to innovate. Today, Apple is introducing yet another Future Vision with Apple Vision Pro. The device leverages the 10X advancements in sensors developed for the iPhone: the fruits of one product’s PMF journey can create seeds for the next. Will Apple Vision Pro enable entirely new experiences we can’t yet imagine, and fall squarely in the Hair on Fire path a few years from now? Time will tell.</p>
</section>



<figure><a href="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Legacy.png" data-pswp-width="2720" data-pswp-height="1834"><img decoding="async" width="2720" height="1834" src="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Legacy.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Legacy.png 2720w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Legacy.png?resize=300,202 300w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Legacy.png?resize=768,518 768w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Legacy.png?resize=1024,690 1024w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Legacy.png?resize=1536,1036 1536w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Legacy.png?resize=2048,1381 2048w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Legacy.png?resize=220,148 220w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Legacy.png?resize=1920,1295 1920w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Legacy.png?resize=680,459 680w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Legacy.png?resize=930,627 930w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Legacy.png?resize=1440,971 1440w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/04/Legacy.png?resize=480,324 480w" sizes="(max-width: 2720px) 100vw, 2720px"></a></figure>



<section>
<p>Legendary companies string together multiple product lines that evolve through one path of product-market fit to another. While one product may plateau, the next product starts rising.</p>



<p>You can use this framework to orient yourself regardless of where you are in this cycle. PMF may seem like a destination you’re trying to reach—but keeping and expanding on it once you arrive is an ongoing quest that will last as long as your company does.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
</section>









<div data-columns="12">

					<p>
						JOIN OUR MAILING LIST					</p>

					<h2>
						Get the best stories from the Sequoia community.					</h2>

					
					
					

				</div>
</article>
	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>