(ignoring known css parsing error)
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 18:30:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AMD Ryzen 5 9600X and Ryzen 7 9700X Offer Excellent Linux Performance (107 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.phoronix.com/review/ryzen-9600x-9700x</link>
            <guid>41180976</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 13:01:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/review/ryzen-9600x-9700x">https://www.phoronix.com/review/ryzen-9600x-9700x</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41180976">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<p>This could quite well be my simplest review in the past twenty years of Phoronix. The AMD Ryzen 9000 series starting with the Ryzen 5 9600X and Ryzen 7 9700X launching tomorrow are some truly great desktop processors. The generational uplift is very compelling, even in single-threaded Linux workloads shooting ahead of Intel's 14th Gen Core competition, across nearly 400 benchmarks these new Zen 5 desktop CPUs impress, and these new Zen 5 desktop processors are priced competitively. I was already loving the Ryzen 7000 series performance on Linux with its AVX-512 implementation and performing so well across hundreds of different Linux workloads but now with the AMD Ryzen 9000 series, AMD is hitting it out of the ball park. That paired with the issues Intel is currently experiencing for the Intel Core 13th/14th Gen CPUs and the ~400 benchmark results makes this a home run for AMD on the desktop side with only some minor Linux caveats.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=amd-ryzen-5-9600x-ryzen-7-9700x&amp;image=amd_ryzen9600x9700x_1_lrg" target="_blank"><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=amd-ryzen-5-9600x-ryzen-7-9700x&amp;image=amd_ryzen9600x9700x_1_med" alt="AMD Ryzen 5 9600X and Ryzen 7 9700X retail packages"></a></p>
<p>The past two weeks I have been eagerly running many benchmarks of AMD <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/search/Zen+5">Zen 5</a> on Linux with Strix Point via the <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/review/amd-ryzen-ai-9-365">Ryzen AI 9 365</a> and <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/review/amd-ryzen-ai-9-hx-370">Ryzen AI 9 HX 370</a> with great results. That was fun, but now with Zen 5 desktop processors in hand, the benchmarking has been wild. Ahead of tomorrow's Ryzen 5 9600X and Ryzen 7 9700X availability, the review embargo on these processors lifts today. It's not until next week for the Ryzen 9 9900X and Ryzen 9 9950X availability and review embargo lift.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=amd-ryzen-5-9600x-ryzen-7-9700x&amp;image=amd_ryzen9600x9700x_2_lrg" target="_blank"><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=amd-ryzen-5-9600x-ryzen-7-9700x&amp;image=amd_ryzen9600x9700x_2_med" alt="AMD Ryzen Zen 5 bottom"></a></p>
<p>Given there were already the prior embargo lifts on the <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/review/amd-zen5-ryzen-9000">AMD Zen 5 client products</a> and <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/review/amd-zen-5-core">Zen 5 architecture details</a>, today's review is squarely focused on the Ryzen 5 9600X and Ryzen 7 9700X products.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=amd-ryzen-5-9600x-ryzen-7-9700x&amp;image=amd_ryzen9600x9700x_4_lrg" target="_blank"><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=amd-ryzen-5-9600x-ryzen-7-9700x&amp;image=amd_ryzen9600x9700x_4_med" alt="AMD Ryzen 5 9600X"></a></p>
<p>The Ryzen 5 9600X as a reminder is a 6-core / 12-thread Zen 5 processor with 3.9GHz base clock and 5.4GHz boost clock while having a 32MB L3 cache and a 65 Watt TDP rating. This processor is launching tomorrow at $279 USD... While the prior gen Ryzen 5 7600X today retails for around $200~220, back when it launched that Zen 4 6-core part was priced at $299 USD. So seeing the Ryzen 5 9600X launch less at $279 is rather competitive. The Intel Core i5 14600K competition meanwhile is priced at $299~339 USD as of writing.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=amd-ryzen-5-9600x-ryzen-7-9700x&amp;image=amd_ryzen9600x9700x_3_lrg" target="_blank"><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=amd-ryzen-5-9600x-ryzen-7-9700x&amp;image=amd_ryzen9600x9700x_3_med" alt="AMD Ryzen 7 9700X"></a></p>
<p>The Ryzen 7 9700X meanwhile is the 8-core / 16-thread Zen 5 desktop processor with a 3.8GHz base frequency, maximum boost clock of 5.5GHz, 32MB L3 cache, and a 65 Watt TDP. The Ryzen 7 9700X is launching at a suggested price of $359 USD. This too is priced very well considering the prior gen Ryzen 7 7700X launched at $399 USD and the Intel Core i7 14700K competition is priced at $399~419 USD.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=amd-ryzen-5-9600x-ryzen-7-9700x&amp;image=amd_ryzen9600x9700x_5_lrg" target="_blank"><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=amd-ryzen-5-9600x-ryzen-7-9700x&amp;image=amd_ryzen9600x9700x_5_med" alt="AMD Ryzen 7 9700X processor"></a></p>
<p>With the pricing covered, that leaves the two other main areas for the Phoronix focus: the Linux support and the performance.</p>
<p>When it comes to the Linux support for the Ryzen 9000 series, you should be in good shape with modern Linux distributions. With the Ryzen 9000 series working with existing AM5 motherboards after BIOS upgrade, there isn't any new platform kinks to really worry about or other Linux compatibility problems there. As I've shown in my several AMD Ryzen AI 300 series articles, the Zen 5 core support is in order. With the Ryzen 9000 series it's also simpler than with Strix Point given that there is the older cut-down RDNA2 integrated graphics if using the integrated graphics/display on the desktop CPUs and these are all full Zen 5 cores without any mix of Zen 5 and 5C.</p>
<p>All of the core support for the Ryzen 9000 series is good for end-users running the Ryzen 9000 series on modern distributions like Ubuntu 24.04 LTS, Fedora 40, Arch Linux, etc. There are a few caveats to note. First, while not relevant to most of you, if planning to use any RAPL/PowerCap sysfs monitoring the CPU power consumption that sadly isn't yet mainlined for Zen 5... Rather silly, but <a href="https://lore.kernel.org/linux-pm/20240719101234.50827-1-Dhananjay.Ugwekar@amd.com/">a one line patch is needed</a> that hasn't yet been upstreamed to add Family 1Ah to the PowerCap RAPL driver. It's sad that this one-liner wasn't merged months ago especially with the new Family ID for Zen 5 being known for months. But without this one line patch, you won't be able to enjoy any energy reporting for the CPU... Thus for my benchmarking of the Ryzen 9000 series I had to patch my kernel build. If you are on Linux 6.9+, you'll also need <a href="https://lore.kernel.org/linux-pm/20240730044917.4680-1-Dhananjay.Ugwekar@amd.com/T/#m7a59207d34b40a54971193b75d36c14dafee7824">this patch</a> to fix the AMD RAPL package energy counter scope. But again this isn't a feature used by the masses and for my purposes only ever of interest during benchmarking for power consumption monitoring and performance-per-Watt measurements. But frustrating nevertheless that the one line patch wasn't upstreamed months ago as part of the rest of the Zen 5 code but seemingly overlooked.</p>
<p>The other minor blemish for the AMD Zen 5 support is on the compiler side. <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/news/AMD-Zen-5-Znver5-Merged-GCC14">AMD did get the Znver5 target added for GCC 14.1 stable</a> that released back in April. Though it would have been even better if the support actually was out last year for GCC 13 given the annual release cadence and the likes of Ubuntu 24.04 LTS using GCC 13, not GCC 14. Intel typically does the better job here of trying to get their ISA enablement and new CPU targets added into the open-source compilers well ahead of release to avoid timing/alignment issues like this. But getting the Znver5 target into GCC 14 is at least better than sometimes where there hasn't been the support in a released compiler at launch day. But... Znver5 isn't yet in the LLVM/Clang compiler codebase. As of writing there is no Znver5 support upstreamed into the LLVM/Clang compiler. That's disappointing months after the GCC support was upstreamed. There is an imminent timing issue there as well with <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/news/LLVM-Clang-19-Feature-Freeze">LLVM Clang 19 releasing in September</a> and no Znver5 support yet. We'll see if it gets added and back-ported to the v19 release branch in the coming weeks or not.</p>
<p>So there still are some AMD Linux enablement quirks where they could improve upon for seeing better software support on launch-day, but for those not worrying about RAPL/PowerCap energy monitoring or spinning tuned-out binaries catered to Zen 5, the Linux support overall is in great shape for the Ryzen 9000 series.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: I've spent nearly 5y on a web app that creates 3D apartments (258 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://roometron.com</link>
            <guid>41180504</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 12:03:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://roometron.com">https://roometron.com</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41180504">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="mainContainer"><h3><span>ROO</span><span>M</span><span>ETRON</span></h3><div><h2><span>WE TRANSFORM&nbsp;</span><br><span>Floor&nbsp;</span> <span>PLANS</span></h2><h2><strong>Boost up your</strong> real estate <strong>marketing</strong><br>with eye-catching 3D visuals</h2></div></div><div id="aboutUsMobile"><h2>Roometron transforms floor plans into virtual 3D spaces</h2><p>We bring an amazing opportunity to <strong>enhance the visibility of your real estate projects</strong> and stand out among the others within any budget</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: BudgetFlow – Budget planning using interactive Sankey diagrams (138 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.budgetflow.cc/</link>
            <guid>41180441</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 11:56:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.budgetflow.cc/">https://www.budgetflow.cc/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41180441">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="page_content">
	<!-- <header>
		<h1>BudgetFlow: Visual Budget Management Made Easy</h1>
		<nav>
			<ul>
				<li><a href="">Home</a></li>
				<li><a href="">Features</a></li>
				<li><a href="">How It Works</a></li>
				<li><a href="">Pricing</a></li>
				<li><a href="">Blog</a></li>
			</ul>
		</nav>
	</header>
	-->
	
<!----------------------------------------------------------------------------->




<ui-container>
	<div id="top_bar">
	



		<div>

			<ui-button clear="" hx-get="/" hx-push-url="true" hx-select="#page_content" hx-target="#page_content" hx-swap="outerHTML">
				<img src="https://www.budgetflow.cc/static/images/logo6.png" alt="Logo">
			</ui-button>

			
		</div>

		

		<p id="align-right">
			
				<ui-button href="/register">
					Register
				</ui-button>
			
		</p>


</div>


</ui-container>


<ui-container>
	
	<p>
		Welcome to BudgetFlow, an app for managing your budget visually and interactively using flow charts.
		The website is currently in beta so feedback is highly appreciated.
	</p>
</ui-container>


<ui-container>
	<div>
		<div>
			<h5>Create Budgets</h5>
			<p>Create budgets and visualize them as sankey diagrams.</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<h5>Smart Pockets</h5>
			<p>Pockets can automatically send excess cash to another pocket or take missing cash from another pocket.</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<h5>Shared Budgets</h5>
			<p>Share budgets with other users like your roommates or partner. Collaborate on the budget together, and link it with your own budgets.</p>
		</div>
	</div>
</ui-container>






<!----------------------------------------------------------------------------->

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Uber tests its payment systems in production (137 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.alvaroduran.com/p/cringey-but-true-how-uber-tests-payments</link>
            <guid>41178959</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 07:16:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://news.alvaroduran.com/p/cringey-but-true-how-uber-tests-payments">https://news.alvaroduran.com/p/cringey-but-true-how-uber-tests-payments</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41178959">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><p>You are wasting most of the time you spend testing.</p><p>And I get it. You’d rather test things in staging, because it gives you a sense of control. Most engineers even cringe at the idea of testing in production. But I think that's because they think it’s either/or. It’s not.</p><p>You can test before deployment as much as you’d like. And then, you can test in production as much as you can. The trick is when to switch.&nbsp;</p><p><strong>You aren’t testing in production early enough.</strong></p><p>That’s why what Uber does is so intriguing.</p><p>But first, why is testing in production even necessary? Can’t we just try to write code as correctly as we can inside a no-stakes environment, rather than risking real money and real impact on real users?</p><p><span>You could. But </span><strong>if you’re doing your job right, you’ll quickly run out of bugs</strong><span> to find in such an environment. The easy ones. If you haven’t already.</span></p><p>Look, the systems you maintain, that most of us maintain, have been around for a few years. Some, even decades. That is because software is not like other machines. Most machines, in time, rot and decay. But software is just information: if it’s correct, it stays that way. Hardware does need replacement, but the correct software that runs on it keeps running.</p><p>Software, if you’re doing your job right, gets better over time.</p><p>What an amazing machine.</p><p><span>You probably call those systems </span><em>legacy</em><span> with disdain, because software gets more difficult to maintain over time. But there’s a reason legacy software is scary to change. We want it to keep doing what it's currently doing.</span></p><p><span>Hate it all you want, but </span><strong>legacy software works, even when it’s a mess</strong><span>.</span></p><p>There’s pretty much one way to produce high quality software. Use it, and fix all the bugs you can find in it. In time, the easy bugs are gone.&nbsp;</p><p>Unlike the human body, old software is so healthy. If that’s the only way to produce high quality software, the only illnesses you’re going to find are the exotic ones.</p><p><span>Payment systems are an extreme version of this. Moving money has always been </span><strong>the most obvious business use case for computers</strong><span>. And so, money software has been around for a long time.</span></p><p>That’s the kind of software that Uber, or any other merchant, has to deal with. What I find fascinating is that Uber is doing it in a way that makes many engineers cringe.</p><p><strong>Uber tests its payment systems in production</strong><span>. And in this article, I’m going to tell you how they do it, and why it’s a great idea.</span></p><p><span>I’m </span><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/alvaroduranbarata/" rel="">Alvaro Duran</a><span>, and this is </span><em>The Payments Engineer Playbook</em><span>. Scroll for five minutes on Youtube and you’ll find tons of tutorials that show you payment system designs that’ll help you pass interviews. But there’s not much that teaches you how to build this critical software for real users and real money.</span></p><p>The reason I know this is because I’ve built and maintained systems that handle close to 100,000 payments a day. And I’ve been able to see all types of interesting conversations about what works and what doesn't for payment systems behind closed doors.</p><p>These conversations are what inspired this newsletter.</p><p><span>In </span><em>The Payments Engineer Playbook</em><span>, we investigate the technology that transfers money. And we do that by cutting off one sliver of it and extract tactics from it.</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa77d5215-a5c5-4b71-b783-57e26c261a9f_1600x1097.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa77d5215-a5c5-4b71-b783-57e26c261a9f_1600x1097.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa77d5215-a5c5-4b71-b783-57e26c261a9f_1600x1097.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa77d5215-a5c5-4b71-b783-57e26c261a9f_1600x1097.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa77d5215-a5c5-4b71-b783-57e26c261a9f_1600x1097.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa77d5215-a5c5-4b71-b783-57e26c261a9f_1600x1097.jpeg" width="1456" height="998" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/a77d5215-a5c5-4b71-b783-57e26c261a9f_1600x1097.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:998,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;A Tour of Uber's New San Francisco Office - Officelovin&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="A Tour of Uber's New San Francisco Office - Officelovin" title="A Tour of Uber's New San Francisco Office - Officelovin" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa77d5215-a5c5-4b71-b783-57e26c261a9f_1600x1097.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa77d5215-a5c5-4b71-b783-57e26c261a9f_1600x1097.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa77d5215-a5c5-4b71-b783-57e26c261a9f_1600x1097.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa77d5215-a5c5-4b71-b783-57e26c261a9f_1600x1097.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>Uber offices in San Francisco</figcaption></figure></div><p>If you don’t want to test payments in production, your only choice is to use a staging environment.</p><p>And what do you have to do to set up a good one? Two things.</p><p>First, you have to copy all production data. It’s expensive, and a reckless breach in privacy and security, but it’s doable. And second, you must emulate all user activity. Staging must become a believable version of your production systems.</p><p><span>That reminds me of a </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Potemkin_village" rel="">Potemkin village</a><span>.</span></p><p><span>Staging environments are not as useful as you think they are. </span><strong>It is unrealistic to try to erect sophisticated replicas of the real world</strong><span>. Your tests will only be as good as your ability to do the job completely.</span></p><p><span>I really like </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DfAwKS1NShs" rel="">how Charity Majors put it</a><span>: “</span><strong>staging is just a glorified laptop</strong><span>”. Only production is production.</span></p><p><span>In fact, payment providers only do so much in their sandbox environments. As soon as you start digging deeper, </span><strong>you’ll notice a big gap between how sandbox behaves and all the surprises that production has for you</strong><span>.</span></p><p>But the lesson isn’t to demand better sandbox applications from your provider. They’re not going to comply, because it just doesn’t make a business difference to them.</p><p><span>Instead, the lesson should be this: </span><strong>to test your payment systems in sandbox for an amount of time that’s reasonable</strong><span>. And not a second more.</span></p><p>That’s how Uber does it.</p><p>Uber has outgrown the idea that defects can be completely solved at staging.</p><p>Rather than stressing out over a perfect release, Uber has put in place tools to detect production failures as early as possible, and to roll back to a known safe state quickly and easily.</p><p><span>These tools correspond to </span><strong>three key concepts</strong><span>: To roll out against business metrics, to carefully select a first rollout region, and to make these rollouts progressively.</span></p><p><span>Before he started </span><a href="https://newsletter.pragmaticengineer.com/" rel="">The Pragmatic Engineer</a><span>, Gergely Orosz worked as an engineer manager at Uber Money. In 2018, he gave a talk on </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yooCE5B0SRA" rel="">how Uber rolled out new payment methods</a><span>.</span></p><p><span>For Orosz, </span><strong>building and rolling out a new payment method are two sides of the same coin</strong><span>.</span></p><p>Sandbox testing is something you do early on, because it speeds up development. But as soon as you can, you move into real payments with real cards.</p><p>And for that, the right debugging tools are critical.</p><p>Orosz mentions Uber’s internal tools, Cerberus and Deputy, which are responsible for two important tasks when testing in production</p><ul><li><p>Making requests to real systems in a transparent way</p></li><li><p>Channeling the responses into your own laptop</p></li></ul><p>But to me, the most important point of his talk is this:</p><p>For Uber, every deployment is an experiment</p><p>What Orosz means is that Uber recognizes that nobody really knows how any deployment is really going to turn out. Every time out there is a guess, and your job is to make it an educated one.</p><p>Therefore, every deployment is a hypothesis on how certain business metrics will look like from the moment it goes live.</p><p><span>Which metrics to measure, and which monitors to put in place to do that varies from company to company. But </span><strong>a payment method that doesn’t help your company earn more or spend less is a wasted effort</strong><span>.</span></p><blockquote><p>I’m not going to name names but some large successful unicorns in this city still deploy all their Java WAR files to production at once. At once. And they have a reputation for going down a bunch. I have no idea why.</p><p><span>— Charity Majors, </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DfAwKS1NShs" rel="">Engineering Large Systems When You're Not Google Or Facebook</a></p></blockquote><p>Brazilians always get the new stuff from Facebook first.</p><p>This is by design. One of the corollaries of “every deployment is an experiment” is that you should mitigate any potential problems by exposing it to the smallest, but significant, subset of users possible. Only when you don’t see anything wrong, you expose it to more users.</p><p><span>The first experiment region is how you do that in the beginning. </span><strong>A way to contain the impact of a potential screw up</strong><span>.</span></p><p>When Uber rolled out GooglePay, they decided to focus their monitoring on Portugal.</p><p>It was a country</p><ul><li><p><strong>Small, but not tiny</strong><span>: Rolling out incrementally to 100% of the country’s traffic would be a significant number already</span></p></li><li><p><strong>In a close time region</strong><span> to where the team was based (Amsterdam): This made live monitoring so much convenient for them.</span></p></li><li><p><strong>With representative users</strong><span>: Most Portuguese pay on Uber through the Authorize flow, just like pretty much everyone globally.</span></p></li><li><p><strong>Where the provider’s dependencies are minimized</strong><span>: In Portugal, the old Android Pay had close to no penetration.</span></p></li></ul><p>Selecting a first experiment region can do wonders if you accept payments globally.</p><p>Done well, canary deployments make rollbacks more frequent, not less.</p><p>Like canaries in a coalmine, deploying to a subset of users is meant to be done frequently. You assume that the moment something doesn’t look good, you will pull back fast.</p><p><span>No deployment strategy is going to make each individual deployment safer. </span><strong>What canary deployments give you is the opportunity to trade SEV-1 outages for a few SEV-3 and SEV-4</strong><span>.</span></p><p>And guess what? That’s exactly what happened to Uber when they were rolling out GooglePay. Numbers didn’t add up in the beginning!</p><p>Rolling out cautiously in Portugal was a smart decision. It surfaced bugs in Google Pay.</p><blockquote><p>Our uncollected rate was huge. And we first just said “all right, are we stupid? Are we missing something here?” But no, everything seemed fine. Seemed like no mistakes.</p><p>So we searched it all with Google. First, we rolled back and we talked with Google. And, you know, It turns out there were some issues on their end, and there were some issues on our end, and we certainly fixed it. But it took quite a while.</p><p><span>— Gergely Orosz, </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yooCE5B0SRA" rel="">Payments Integration at Uber: A Case Study</a></p></blockquote><p>How on Earth are you going to find bugs in GooglePay from a staging environment?</p><p>You can’t. You just can’t.</p><p><span>And that’s what’s fascinating to me. On the one hand, you’ve got engineers who take every precaution possible </span><em>before rolling out</em><span> because payments are something you should never break.</span></p><p><span>And on the other hand, you’ve got companies like Uber, who take every precaution possible </span><em>after rolling out</em><span> because they understand that </span><strong>the game is resiliency</strong><span>, not never failing at anything.</span></p><p><span>That’s the lesson that I’m taking away from how Uber does things. </span><strong>Testing before production is fine, but returns diminish sharply</strong><span>.</span></p><p>At some point, you’re better off checking your work against real users, and real money.</p><p>This reminds me of algorithmic trading. You can develop a strategy that performs great with backtest data, in a no stakes environment. But the real test is the real thing with real stakes. Nothing else compares to it.</p><p>You should think of deployments as experiments. Only production is production. Anything else is a prelude.</p><p><span>All right, that’s it for this article of </span><em>The Payments Engineer Playbook</em><span>. See you next week.</span></p><p><strong>PS</strong><span>: Before you go, I have to be completely honest with you: this article and </span><a href="https://news.alvaroduran.com/p/stripe-made-the-obvious-choice-when" rel="">the one on Stripe</a><span> took A LOT of work. I’m not sure if I’m going to keep making these kind of articles anymore.</span></p><p>I need to know from you.</p><p>Are these articles useful? Then, you can do two things.</p><p>First, I want you to leave a comment, no matter if it’s negative or positive. Either way, I want you to let me know: do you want me to keep making these articles?</p><p>It’s a lot of work, but I’ll keep doing it if I know it’s making an impact on you. Otherwise, these ideas will stay private inside of my team.</p><p>The second thing I need from you is to tell a colleague. If you’re reading this, you probably work with someone who builds payments for a living. And you’ve been reading this newsletter long enough to tell if it’s going to be useful for them too.</p><p>And if you got this article from a colleague, do me a favor and subscribe. It’s a flex to be a reader of a well-known publication before it was cool.</p><p>I bet that’s how it feels to be a VC who led a series A on a startup at IPO day.</p><p><span>Make a bet on </span><em>The Payments Engineer Playbook</em><span>. I’ll see you around.</span></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[70% of new NPM packages in last 6 months were spam (207 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.phylum.io/the-great-npm-garbage-patch/</link>
            <guid>41178258</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 04:31:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.phylum.io/the-great-npm-garbage-patch/">https://blog.phylum.io/the-great-npm-garbage-patch/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41178258">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            
<!--kg-card-begin: html-->
    
<a href="https://www.phylum.io/black-hat-2024">
        <p><img src="https://www.blackhat.com/images/page-graphics-usa-15/logos/bh_logo_black_onwhite.png"></p>
        <p>Headed to Black Hat USA? Come talk to us in Start-Up City at SC203!</p>
    </a>
<!--kg-card-end: html-->
<p>In April of this year, the Phylum Research Team revealed the <a href="https://blog.phylum.io/digital-detritus-unintended-consequences-of-open-source-sustainability-platforms/" rel="noopener noreferrer">proliferation of spam packages in npm</a> associated with the Tea protocol, a decentralized initiative that promises to compensate software developers in cryptocurrency for their open-source contributions. Last month, we published our <a href="https://blog.phylum.io/q2-2024-evolution-of-software-supply-chain-security-report/" rel="noopener noreferrer">quarterly research report</a>, which estimated that approximately one out of every four packages published to npm in Q2 were associated with Tea, virtually all of which had no redeeming quality aside from gaming the protocol to inflate a software developer’s contribution artificially. With new research from a fresh perspective, our team can now report that the volume of these packages is likely larger than our initial estimates. Like the island of discarded plastic twice the size of Texas floating in the North Pacific Ocean, npm has accrued an astonishing amount of spam packages over the past six months. Join us as we take a fresh look at the pollution in this open-source ecosystem.</p><p>As detailed in <a href="https://blog.phylum.io/digital-detritus-unintended-consequences-of-open-source-sustainability-platforms/">our previous blog</a>, the Tea protocol perversely incentivizes software developers to exaggerate their contribution to open-source development. Using a modified PageRank called teaRank, software developers are rewarded based on their “Proof of Contribution”. As the early SEO spammers figured out how to game PageRank for their benefit, history repeats itself, and a few software developers have spammed open-source repositories with absurd amounts of worthless packages.</p><p>npm, the largest open-source ecosystem, has suffered the worst from this pollution from various actors. Some of the hallmarks of these spam packages are <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/mdanattagdaysrh?activeTab=code">gibberish package names</a>, packages named with <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/interesting-moccasin-pike?activeTab=code">random combinations of words</a> from a list, implausible <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/rusttool080059?activeTab=dependencies">lists of dependent packages</a>, a <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/random-job-selector?activeTab=dependents">dubious number of dependent packages</a>, and in this morass of transitive dependencies, the ubiquitous <code>tea.yaml</code> file that ultimately <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/hoadandi-27">identifies the code owner</a>. When Phylum first started investigating this situation in February, we were continually amazed at the sheer volume of packages that could be published, clearly due to automation. So, we turned our attention to trying to understand the full scope of this spam problem.</p><p>For a baseline, at the start of 2024, the total number of packages ingested into Phylum daily from npm was about 1,500 each business day and about half that on the weekends. Starting in February of 2024, Phylum began to notice a steady increase in npm package publications from a few thousand to tens of thousands. The high water mark of this increase occurred on 8 April 2024, with over 48,000 packages published to npm. This explosion of packages led us to our first discovery of the <a href="https://blog.phylum.io/digital-detritus-unintended-consequences-of-open-source-sustainability-platforms/">perverse incentives</a> of the Tea protocol.</p><p>Last month, in preparation for our quarterly report, we took a random sample from all npm packages published in Q2, and we manually triaged 1600 packages. If a package contained markers of Tea protocol abuse, as noted above, we marked it as spam. With these, we found a 95% confidence interval for the estimate of the percentage of spam packages in npm in Q2 between 21.25% and 25.5%, or in other words, over 500,000 spam packages.</p><p>Upon further reflection, we considered that many npm projects have nightly builds or alpha, beta, and canary versions. So, these legitimate packages that enjoy a robust development cycle might dilute the size of the true impact of spam. What if we restricted our search to new packages? Packages that have never been seen before in npm?</p><p>We widened our search in our npm data back to February, when we saw the first Tea protocol spam, and then removed all the packages that had at least one version published prior. This left us over 890,000 new, never-before-seen packages between February 2024 and the present. From this set, we took a random sample of 900 packages and applied the same criteria as before. From this new perspective, our 95% confidence interval for the estimate of Tea protocol spam in new packages over the past six months jumped to between 68.66% and 74.67%, or somewhere between 613,000 and 667,000 packages.</p><p>In other words, among all new packages published to npm in the past six months, about five out of every seven packages are Tea spam.</p><p>Followers of this blog know that most of our content focuses on exposing active malicious attacks against open-source software developers. In the spirit of full disclosure, Phylum has yet to discover evidence that these packages contain or lead to the usual kind of malice that we regularly report. But, as a general observation, this pollution is a kind of malice, and there are several dangerous avenues that this could turn into.</p><p>First, unlike malicious typosquatting campaigns, in which an unsuspecting developer might accidentally install <code>reaxt</code> instead of <code>react</code>, it is not at all likely that a developer would make the same mistake with, for example, <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/quasar-fig-0e1t?activeTab=dependencies">quasar-fig-0e1t</a>. However, a package like <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/web3-cover?activeTab=dependencies">web3-cover</a> is more plausible, where the developer would also get the 170 dependents along with the complete transitive dependency tree for each of those.</p><p>Next, because the AI hype train is at full steam, we must point out the obvious. AI models that are trained on these packages will almost certainly skew the outputs in unintended directions. These packages are ultimately garbage, and the mantra of “garbage in, garbage out” holds true.</p><p>Finally, these large-scale spam campaigns hinder the open-source package registry’s ability to reason through the safety of all packages in an ecosystem, despite the fact that no reasonable person would ever endeavor to install one of these spam packages. They raise the noise floor and create an environment in which an adversary could surreptitiously hide actual maliciousness.</p><p>Let’s start by taking a look at the following package, <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/sournoise" rel="noopener noreferrer">sournoise</a>. The npmjs website lists a single dependency on axios.</p><figure><img src="https://blog.phylum.io/content/images/2024/08/Screenshot-2024-08-05-at-17.55.22.png" alt="npmjs.org showing axios as a dependency of sournoise" loading="lazy" width="2000" height="1152" srcset="https://blog.phylum.io/content/images/size/w600/2024/08/Screenshot-2024-08-05-at-17.55.22.png 600w, https://blog.phylum.io/content/images/size/w1000/2024/08/Screenshot-2024-08-05-at-17.55.22.png 1000w, https://blog.phylum.io/content/images/size/w1600/2024/08/Screenshot-2024-08-05-at-17.55.22.png 1600w, https://blog.phylum.io/content/images/2024/08/Screenshot-2024-08-05-at-17.55.22.png 2000w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption><span>npmjs.org showing </span><code spellcheck="false"><span>axios</span></code><span> as a dependency of </span><code spellcheck="false"><span>sournoise</span></code></figcaption></figure><p>There is not a lot happening here. The package does not contain code, and according to npm, the only dependency is on the extremely popular Axios package. Is this package safe to install?</p><p>The <code>package.json</code> tells a different story.</p><figure><pre><code>{
  "name": "sournoise",
  "version": "1.0.1",
  "description": "",
  "main": "index.js",
  "scripts": {
    "test": "echo \"Error: no test specified\" &amp;&amp; exit 1"
  },
  "author": "",
  "license": "ISC",
  "dependencies": {
    "axios": "https://registry.npmjs.org/@putrifransiska/kwonthol36/-/kwonthol36-1.1.4.tgz"
  }
}</code></pre><figcaption><p><code spellcheck="false"><span>package.json</span></code><span> for </span><code spellcheck="false"><span>sournoise</span></code><span> shouting the spurious </span><code spellcheck="false"><span>axios</span></code><span> dependency</span></p></figcaption></figure><p>Contrary to what npm states, this package actually depends on one of our aforementioned spam packages. This is a by-product of how npm handles and displays dependencies to users on its website. There is no clear linkage to <code>@putrifransiska/kwonthol36</code>, <code>axios</code> lists <code>sournoise</code> as a dependent.</p><p>To say that you’d never install one of these spam packages is to ignore the complexity of the supply chain: transitive dependencies can pull in packages that the developer neither wants nor expects to receive.</p><p>Open-source software ecosystem pollution is a problem for everyone. The Tea protocol project is <a href="https://tea.xyz/blog/proof-of-contribution" rel="noopener noreferrer">taking steps to remediate this problem.</a> It would be unfair to legitimate participants in the Tea protocol to have their remuneration reduced because others are scamming the system. Also, npm has begun to take down <a href="https://github.com/advisories?query=type%3Amalware+zitterorg" rel="noopener noreferrer">some of these spammers</a>, but the take-down rate does not match the new publication rate. And this problem is not limited to npm alone. For example, <a href="https://packages.ecosyste.ms/api/v1/registries/rubygems.org/maintainers/188987/packages" rel="noopener noreferrer">this user</a> published nearly 1800 spam packages on Rubygems in late February and early March 2024. Phylum is actively researching this area, and we will continue to seek new ways to detect this spam as these actors adapt their tactics.</p>
        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Jeremy Rowley resigns from DigiCert due to mass-revocation incident (123 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1910322</link>
            <guid>41177161</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 00:54:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1910322">https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1910322</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41177161">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="wrapper">

 


<main id="bugzilla-body" tabindex="-1">



<div id="main-inner">













<div id="module-categories">
        <p><span id="field-value-component">
      <div>
        <p><span id="component-name" tabindex="0" role="button" aria-haspopup="menu" aria-controls="component-info">CA Certificate Compliance
          
        </span></p>
      </div>
        </span>
    </p></div>





































<meta name="firefox-versions" content="{&quot;FIREFOX_AURORA&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;FIREFOX_DEVEDITION&quot;:&quot;130.0b1&quot;,&quot;FIREFOX_ESR&quot;:&quot;115.14.0esr&quot;,&quot;FIREFOX_ESR_NEXT&quot;:&quot;128.1.0esr&quot;,&quot;FIREFOX_NIGHTLY&quot;:&quot;131.0a1&quot;,&quot;LAST_MERGE_DATE&quot;:&quot;2024-08-05&quot;,&quot;LAST_RELEASE_DATE&quot;:&quot;2024-08-06&quot;,&quot;LAST_SOFTFREEZE_DATE&quot;:&quot;2024-08-01&quot;,&quot;LAST_STRINGFREEZE_DATE&quot;:&quot;2024-08-02&quot;,&quot;LATEST_FIREFOX_DEVEL_VERSION&quot;:&quot;130.0b1&quot;,&quot;LATEST_FIREFOX_OLDER_VERSION&quot;:&quot;3.6.28&quot;,&quot;LATEST_FIREFOX_RELEASED_DEVEL_VERSION&quot;:&quot;130.0b1&quot;,&quot;LATEST_FIREFOX_VERSION&quot;:&quot;129.0&quot;,&quot;NEXT_MERGE_DATE&quot;:&quot;2024-09-02&quot;,&quot;NEXT_RELEASE_DATE&quot;:&quot;2024-09-03&quot;,&quot;NEXT_SOFTFREEZE_DATE&quot;:&quot;2024-08-29&quot;,&quot;NEXT_STRINGFREEZE_DATE&quot;:&quot;2024-08-30&quot;}">



<div id="c0" data-comment-id="17044133" data-ismarkdown="true"><p>User Agent: Mozilla/5.0 (Windows NT 10.0; Win64; x64) AppleWebKit/537.36 (KHTML, like Gecko) Chrome/126.0.0.0 Safari/537.36</p>
<p>Steps to reproduce:</p>
<p>We received a certificate problem report that indicated DigiCert might have an issue with our implementation of method 7 – DNS-based validation. We have been investigating the issue and discovered a path that could allow mis-issuance. We are still investigating the root cause and gathering a report on the certificates impacted. We will file a full report of our findings when we have the information.</p>
<p>For background, DigiCert supports multiple DNS-related verification processes:<br>
a)	Adding a random value or request token to a TXT record,<br>
b)	Adding a random value to a CNAME pointed to by _dcv.[domain] or another subdomain starting with a prefix as agreed upon with the subscriber,<br>
c)	Adding a random value or request token to a TXT record of a domain that is followed via CNAME,<br>
d)	Adding the random value with an underscore prefix to the CNAME as the sub domain of an authorization domain name,<br>
e)	Adding the random value to a CAA record, and<br>
f)	Adding the random value to a TXT record of a subdomain that includes a prefixed underscore.</p>
<p>Spot checks performed on each of the methods above showed accurate validation information, but we initiated a thorough code review on July 27th to confirm. This review found a potential issue under (d) on our current system.</p>
<p>The code review found one path where a certificate could issue when the random value was used as the host in a CNAME resource record without first pre-appending an underscore. Our preliminary investigation shows that the code that should have appended an underscore as a prefix to a random value when using the CNAME method was not working properly. The code worked in our original monolithic system but was not implemented properly when we moved to our micro-services systems. In some cases, underscores might not have been appended to random values used for CNAME verification where the random value was used as a sub domain.</p>
<p>We also found that the bug in the code was inadvertently remediated when engineering completed a user-experience enhancement project that collapsed multiple random value generation microservices into a single service. This service began including an underscore prefix before each random value, regardless of which validation method the user chose. This project allows DigiCert to simplify the random value generation process. This also reduced customer support calls related to the manual addition of underscore prefix, fixed a bug in our certificate management platform’s display of validation status, and inadvertently ensured that every CNAME-based verification included an underscore prefix to each random value.</p>
<p>We verified that after the UX modification certificate issuance is not possible without proper CNAME verification and reviewed recent issuance to confirm that certificates are not issuing without including an underscore as part of the random value.</p>
<p>The 24-hour revocation rule applies in this circumstance as the issue impacts domain validation. We are currently investigating the root cause and gathering a list of impacted certificate serial numbers. We will post this information in the full bug report along with a complete list of impacted certificates. The revocation process will begin as soon as we’ve identified the impacted serial numbers. We do not expect to have a delayed revocation in regard to this issue.</p>
</div><div id="a68164_661011"><p>Assignee: nobody → jeremy.rowley</p><p>Status: UNCONFIRMED → ASSIGNED</p><p>Type: defect → task</p><p>Ever confirmed: true</p><p>Whiteboard: [ca-compliance]</p></div><div id="c1" data-comment-id="17048384" data-ismarkdown="true"><p>Thank you for this report, Jeremy, and for the responsiveness exhibited by DigiCert. We’ve been getting inbound requests from various sources for guidance about this incident.</p>
<p>As you know, DigiCert, as a publicly trusted CA, has to comply with the CA/Browser Forum Baseline Requirements, which are written as a collaboration between CAs and Browsers, including DigiCert.</p>
<p>The Chrome Root Program does not have the authority to grant exceptions to the CA/Browser Forum TLS Baseline Requirements. However, we do recognize other programs include exceptions for delayed revocations in some exceptional circumstances.</p>
<p>As detailed in our <a href="https://www.chromium.org/Home/chromium-security/root-ca-policy/" rel="nofollow">policy</a>, we evaluate all incidents on a case-by-case basis and work to identify ecosystem-wide risk or potential improvements that can help prevent future incidents. The Chrome Root Program continuously points to the factors significant to our program when evaluating incidents which include (but are not limited to):</p>
<ul>
<li>a demonstration of understanding of the root causes of an incident,</li>
<li>a substantive commitment and timeline to changes that clearly and persuasively address the root cause,</li>
<li>past history by the Chrome Root Program Participant in its incident handling and its follow through on commitments, and,</li>
<li>the severity of the security impact of the incident.</li>
</ul>
<p>When evaluating an incident response, the Chrome Root Program’s primary concern is ensuring that Browsers, other CA Owners, users, and website developers have the necessary information to identify improvements, and that the Chrome Root Program Participant is responsive to addressing identified issues. Outside egregious cases (e.g., abject security failures), we do not make trust decisions on individual incidents, and always consider the wider context.</p>
<p>We note the ongoing <a href="https://groups.google.com/a/mozilla.org/g/dev-security-policy/c/-WC72Oa5DTI/m/ri0OF9v7AQAJ?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_source=footer" rel="nofollow">discussions</a> in community forums that seek to minimize impact for revocation activities, and will be looking for opportunities to strike the right balance between the security of the Web PKI and ecosystem considerations.</p>
</div><div id="c2" data-comment-id="17048396" data-ismarkdown="true"><p>I will note that currently there seems to be confusion on DigiCert's internal list of impacted certificates and how they are displayed to subscribers. I have heard directly from parties of email-validated certificates being impacted, so there is a high likelihood of an overbroad initial revocation.</p>
<p>While this is preferable to a partial revocation list, it would explain the high volume of customer outreach at present. There is also an additional complication of resellers not providing the revocation information to their subscribers. Please consider this internally as you analyze the situation and prepare a report.</p>
</div><div id="c3" data-comment-id="17048468" data-ismarkdown="true"><p>We wanted to update the community on the status of this issue. A full incident report is forthcoming. We have identified 83,267 certs impacting 6,807 subscribers. We are planning to begin revoking within the 24-hour time window. Some of these customers have been able to reissue their certificates. Unfortunately, many other customers operating critical infrastructure, vital telecommunications networks, cloud services, and healthcare industries are not in a position to be revoked without critical service interruptions. While we have deployed automation with several willing customers, the reality is that many large organizations cannot reissue and deploy new certificates everywhere in time. We note that other customers have also initiated legal action against us to block revocation.</p>
<p>We have been working around the clock with customers and remain committed to adhering to the BRs. We are aware of and are participating in the active industry discussion happening about the applicability of revocation timelines given the widespread impact and the relative severity of incidents. Our response to this incident to date reflects our commitment to comply with the BRs.  We also note that browsers have mentioned that delayed revocation might still be acceptable under “exceptional circumstances.” However, given no clear definition of what would constitute an exception circumstance, we are seeking root store feedback as soon as possible, as we are standing ready to begin revocations within the timeline.</p>
</div><div id="c4" data-comment-id="17048484" data-ismarkdown="true"><p>The 24 hour timer starts when the issue is notified to the CA, or when it is identified without a third-party report. I fear that DigiCert are acting under the impression that the timer begins when the final certificate list is generated, or when subscribers are informed?</p>
<p>I will not reiterate the discussion held in <a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1896053">#1896053</a>, but will note it is pertinent to this incident as well.</p>
</div><div id="c5"><p>For clarity, we expect customers will have all impacted certs remediated at 120 hours after we had serial numbers. For those ready sooner, we'll begin revocations.</p></div><div id="c6" data-comment-id="17048594" data-ismarkdown="true"><p>Can we have some more clarity on certificate count, please?<br>
"approximately 0.4% of the applicable domain validations we have in effect" - from your website and LinkedIn CEO post.</p>
<p>Can you confirm what 'applicable domain validations we have in effect' means, please?<br>
0.4% of all domain validations? 0.4% of all DNS-based? 0.4% of the specific method of DNS validations?</p>
<p>"We note that other customers have also initiated legal action against us to block revocation."<br>
Action with no legal basis, if the customers have agreed to your terms &amp; conditions and subscriber agreements, correct?<br>
How can legal action have merit when clearly stated in your legal documentation and industry guidelines?</p>
<p>If there are customers attempting to bypass these guidelines through legal means affecting all internet relying parties, they should be named.</p>
<p>"Unfortunately, many other customers operating critical infrastructure, vital telecommunications networks, cloud services, and healthcare industries are not in a position to be revoked without critical service interruptions. "<br>
Very specific details are needed. Customer names, certificate information, and explicit details as to why they cannot replace.</p>
<p>The suggestion from your own colleague:<br>
"For organizations that can’t, we would have transparent information about the existence of the issue, the nature of the problem, and the severity (feasible timeline). "<br>
"And furthermore, it would be better if these disclosures came directly from the subscribers, because they are the only ones in a position to know the ground truth.  Subscribers could be held publicly accountable for the accuracy and reasonableness of their determination and need."</p>
<p>...seems to imply this should be possible, no? Why not start now and lead by example?</p>
<p>"The 24-hour revocation rule applies in this circumstance as the issue impacts domain validation. "<br>
How are we now already talking about 120 revocation periods?</p>
</div><div id="c7"><p>Digicert, please note that if there is a delayed revocation happening to file a preliminary incident for that ASAP as the questions regarding this incident and why there’s a delay are going to be different. Also, we’re already seeing questions about the delayed revocation pop up.</p><div><p>Flags: needinfo?(jeremy.rowley)</p></div></div><div id="c8" data-comment-id="17048773" data-ismarkdown="true"><p>To answer everyone’s question:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I will note that currently there seems to be confusion on DigiCert's internal list of impacted certificates and how they are displayed to subscribers. I have heard directly from parties of email-validated certificates being impacted, so there is a high likelihood of an overbroad initial revocation.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The confusion is around mixed certificates where one domain was verified using a non-impacted method and another was verified using CNAME without an underscore. The data does overcount but only because some underscores were included in random values. We cannot distinguish between those that that had underscores and those that did not within the OEM system and are therefore revoking all of them.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>While this is preferable to a partial revocation list, it would explain the high volume of customer outreach at present. There is also an additional complication of resellers not providing the revocation information to their subscribers. Please consider this internally as you analyze the situation and prepare a report.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The total number of impacted certificates is 83,267. The primary source of confusion is the 24-hour notice that was done by email. We added an in-console message to alert users about the revocation but communicating this information in a short period of time outside of email proved difficult.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Can you confirm what 'applicable domain validations we have in effect' means, please?<br>
0.4% of all domain validations? 0.4% of all DNS-based? 0.4% of the specific method of DNS validations?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yes – DigiCert has one main validation system for high volume issuance (CDNs and Cloud providers specifically) and one for lower volume. The reason for the separation is the amount of control a user wants over their certificate process. 0.4% is the total over just OEM (the lower volume issuing system). We confirmed that the CNAME method in this higher volume issuance system worked correctly.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Action with no legal basis, if the customers have agreed to your terms &amp; conditions and subscriber agreements, correct?  How can legal action have merit when clearly stated in your legal documentation and industry guidelines?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Temporary Restraining Orders (TROs) are designed to be temporary while the facts are figured out. Courts routinely grant these to prevent material harm. TROs are legally binding. We did receive a TRO in connection with this revocation.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If there are customers attempting to bypass these guidelines through legal means affecting all internet relying parties, they should be named.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I will need to work my legal counsel to see if we can name them. I have no idea what’s allowed in these circumstances.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Unfortunately, many other customers operating critical infrastructure, vital telecommunications networks, cloud services, and healthcare industries are not in a position to be revoked without critical service interruptions. "  Very specific details are needed. Customer names, certificate information, and explicit details as to why they cannot replace.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This will be coming in the delayed revocation bug.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The suggestion from your own colleague:  "For organizations that can’t, we would have transparent information about the existence of the issue, the nature of the problem, and the severity (feasible timeline). "  "And furthermore, it would be better if these disclosures came directly from the subscribers, because they are the only ones in a position to know the ground truth. Subscribers could be held publicly accountable for the accuracy and reasonableness of their determination and need." ...seems to imply this should be possible, no? Why not start now and lead by example?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yes. I would love for them to jump in on Bugzilla. I think that information would be very beneficial to the community.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>How are we now already talking about 120 revocation periods?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That’s long-tail in the timeframe cited in discussions when all certificates can be revoked.  We will not be granting that timeline, but we need to untangle the mass revocation process before we can revoke the certificates that are not exceptional circumstances. We will provide a burn-down on the delayed revocation bug.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Digicert, please note that if there is a delayed revocation happening to file a preliminary incident for that ASAP as the questions regarding this incident and why there’s a delay are going to be different. Also, we’re already seeing questions about the delayed revocation pop up.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>We will be filing a preliminary delayed revocation bug today and are working on a draft.  Our systems were prepared to execute the entire revocation before 24-hour mark.</p>
</div><div id="c10" data-comment-id="17049050" data-ismarkdown="true"><p><a href="https://www.digicert.com/support/certificate-revocation-incident" rel="nofollow">DigiCert's public communication</a> about this incident (which has been quoted in <a href="https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/security/digicert-mass-revoking-tls-certificates-due-to-domain-validation-bug/" rel="nofollow">at least one news report</a>) gets the security impact of the noncompliance completely wrong:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The underscore prefix ensures that the random value cannot collide with an actual domain name that uses the same random value. While the odds of that happening are practically negligible, the validation is still deemed as non-compliant if it does not include the underscore prefix.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Failing to include the underscore is considered a security risk because there is potential for a collision between an actual domain and the subdomain used for verification. Although the chance of a collision is extremely low because the random value has at least 150 bits of entropy, there is still a chance. Because there is a finite chance of collision, revocation is strictly required per CABF rules.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The actual reason for the underscore is so that services which allow users to create DNS records at subdomains (e.g. dynamic DNS services) can block users from registering subdomains starting with an underscore and be safe from unwanted certificate issuance. It serves the same purpose that <code>/.well-known</code> does for Agreed-Upon Change To Website, and that admin/administrator/webmaster/hostmaster/postmaster do for Constructed Email to Domain Contact.  By using DNS records without underscores, DigiCert has violated a security-critical assumption that these services have made.</p>
<p><strong>Therefore, this is truly a security-critical incident</strong>, as there is a real risk (not a negligible 2^-150 risk as implied by DigiCert) that this flaw could have been exploited to get unauthorized certificates. <strong>Revocation of the improperly validated certificates is security-critical.</strong></p>
<p>It's troubling that DigiCert is no longer treating this with the urgency required by the Baseline Requirements.</p>
<p>It's also troubling that DigiCert has disseminated misinformation to the public that minimizes the security impact of the noncompliance.</p>
</div><div id="c11">

  <p>I had to split this into two parts as the size is too big for one file.</p></div><div id="c12">

  <p>I had to split this into two files</p></div><div id="c14"><p>Can we have a column with a human-readable attribute (such as the Common Name) in the CSV, so that not everyone has to open thousands of URLs by themselves on crt.sh?</p></div><div id="c15" data-comment-id="17050696" data-ismarkdown="true"><p>Has DigiCert confirmed whether this vulnerability has been exploited against major service providers that permit the creation of custom subdomains?</p>
<p>For instance, No-IP (<a href="https://www.noip.com/" rel="nofollow">https://www.noip.com</a>) allows the creation of arbitrary labels under their domains like ddns.net, enabling users to easily create subdomains such as <code>&lt;some_arbitrary_string&gt;.ddns.net</code> and map them as CNAMEs to any target.</p>
<p>In this scenario, this bug could have allowed an attacker to obtain a valid TLS certificate for <code>ddns.net</code>.</p>
</div><div id="c16" data-comment-id="17050963" data-ismarkdown="true"><p>In the provided CSV's by DigiCert there are 83_267 unique serials and 166_397 crt.sh links (137 have <code>#N/A</code> in the precert column).<br>
Please note that crt.sh is Precertificates heavy for DigiCert (see <a href="https://crt.sh/cert-populations?group=RootOwner" rel="nofollow">https://crt.sh/cert-populations?group=RootOwner</a>).<br>
I did a lookup of all serials and based on 84 batch requests to crt.sh between 2024-07-31T20:06:00Z and 2024-07-31T21:06:00Z this was the result:</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Precertificate</th>
<th>Leaf certificate</th>
<th>Count</th>
<th>Percentage</th>
<th>Note</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>-</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>137</td>
<td>0.16%</td>
<td>These all have <code>#N/A</code> in precert column</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2_105</td>
<td>2.53%</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>71_732</td>
<td>86.15%</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>9_293</td>
<td>11.16%</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>These are the match numbers based on the serial and sha256 fingerprint combination. Only 13.69% of the Leaf certificates are found, while 97.31% of Precertificates are found. Because of these numbers, it's not strange that the 137 certificates without Precertificates cannot be found.</p>
<p>All 92_423 can be found in this bzip2 compressed attachment in tab-separated values format.<br>
These are certificates for 172_047 unique domains, of which 20_702 are wildcard and 71 IP Addresses (63 IPv4 and 8 IPv6).</p>
</div><div id="c17"><div id="ct-17" data-comment-id="17051649" data-ismarkdown="true"><h2>Incident Report</h2>
<h3>Summary</h3>
<p>DigiCert verified domains using a random value in a CNAME without an underscore prefixed to the random value; the impact is limited to issuers utilizing DigiCert's OEM validation system. Validation paths through CertCentral and CIS, DigiCert’s high volume issuance engine for cloud providers, validated domains correctly and are unaffected.</p>
<h3>Impact</h3>
<p>83,267 valid certificates were issued based on this method. A list of active impacted certificates is attached as a CSV file to this bug report. We are revoking all certificates in the database listed as using CNAME-based DNS validation that are currently valid and issued before the date of the fix. This likely overcounts the number of certificates without an underscore, but the system controls in OEM did not adequately store information about whether an underscore was present.</p>
<h3>Timeline</h3>
<p>Executive Summary</p>
<p>DigiCert is continuously deploying changes to its RA system to consolidate and improve workflows. DigiCert deployed a change to its RA system to consolidate domain validation flows to reuse random values across multiple methods. This exposed the fact that one path through the system did not include the underscore when using CNAME verification. The issue was fixed with the consolidation but not found until a third party reported the issue. The root causes were siloing between engineering and compliance, a failure to take CPRs seriously if they did not include serial numbers, and a lack of engineering rigor.</p>
<p>Background</p>
<p>In 2019, DigiCert started creating a services-oriented architecture to extract all validation from the monolithic code. This plan separated the system into three components made up of different services: a front-end portal for customers (called CertCentral), two domain validation systems (CIS for high issuance and OEM for lower volume issuance), one org validation system, and a CA. CIS and OEM share some but not all services. In 2019, DNS CNAME was added to the services-oriented system. Both the monolithic system and service-oriented system ran in parallel while we measured performance and work flows to ensure 1:1 parity. The monolithic code included a function in the front-end that added an underscore if the customer requested a certificate for CNAME validation. The backend system did not check for the underscore, just the random value, and the underscore was not mandatory for any certificate issued through OEM.</p>
<p>Starting May 3, 2024, engineering initiated a project to consolidate and containerize domain validation to prepare for Multi-Perspective Validation (MPV). The goal was to execute on a directive from leadership made in January to open source our domain validation system for the community to use and deploy as needed to facilitate MPV from different global vantage points. This project also finalized the 2019 project by removing paths through our systems that are rarely used, cleaning up code, and consolidating similar processes. One of these processes consolidated the various method 7 steps to a single path. The last few months have been spent heavily on revising our validation system, which lead to confusion about what changes occurred and how the system worked.  The design goal behind these changes (per engineering) was to support a very large customer request from 2023 that wanted to pull all DNS records at each authorization domain name and check a single random value across CNAME, TXT, or CAA resource records. The following timeline discusses all relevant changes to the random value processing code and relevant to this incident.</p>
<p>All times are UTC</p>
<p>Dec 15, 2023 – Engineering architected a plan to consolidate domain methods into a streamlined process that included reusing the same random values across different methods, including non-DNS based methods as needed. This included a plan for making random value generation work uniformly regardless of method. This plan was part of a larger project and customer-requested project for a cloud provider where we wanted to be able to deploy our validation system easily to different regions. Part of this plan is to consolidate to one random value generation service that works with every validation workflow.</p>
<p>Jan 30, 2024 at 2:24 – Engineering created a plan to consolidate workflows into a single validation flow when random values are used. The project is scheduled for Q1 by leadership.</p>
<p>April 16, 2024 at 21:59 – Engineering makes a change to fix a display issue in CertCentral if a validation is originally requested using one method but later completed with another method.</p>
<p>May 1, 2024 at 21:34 – Engineering discusses how to update the DCV methods to use the same random values across domains if the domains are related. Random values being tied to specific validation types is identified as a blocker.</p>
<p>May 17, 2024 at 16:47 – Random value consolidation work starts with fixes to response codes that are causing issues in the API and UX.</p>
<p>May 18, 2024 – JIRA discussion on how to consolidate the user experience for file auth and DNS methods.</p>
<p>May 21, 2024 at 16:00 – During the weekly staff meeting, the team presents the RA consolidation architecture and plan to consolidate the random value process across methods. Compliance is not involved in the architecture design meetings.</p>
<p>May 29, 2024 at 17:00 – Sprint planning meeting to discuss operational changes required for consolidation.</p>
<p>May 29, 2024 at 23:18 – Modification of DCV checking strategy in preparation for consolidation of random value checking to a single process.</p>
<p>May 30, 2024 – Sprint where random value service change is planned begins.</p>
<p>June 4, 2024 at 16:12 – Globalsign sends a Digicert employee a personal email with a question on CNAME-based verification.</p>
<p>June 6, 2024 at 23:53 – Engineering deployed a change that consolidated random values to a single system that uses an underscore across all systems whether they require one or not. There were 7 processes that used a random value (File auth dynamic, File auth static, CNAME token, CNAME RND, TXT, DNS Token, CAA) processes subject to the plan. Although there is some overlap between CIS and OEM with these methods, each system had partially unique workflows that required consolidation. Random values are tied to the process and cannot be reused across methods. The underscore path was chosen as the consolidation because engineering understood that the random value was required in some cases but not others. There is no engineering documentation on which methods were understood as needing an underscore. Compliance was not consulted about this consolidation. After the deployment, random values can be used across different validation methods but random values without underscores cease functioning in the system. Engineering does not provide notice of change as the change is considered technical debt and non-customer impacting.</p>
<p>June 7, 2024 at 19:16 – I received the Globalsign email as the forwarding (on June 6) was missed due to multiple travel schedules. I investigated and found that certificates without an underscore could not issue. I thought the question was about documentation and requested more information from Globalsign. I spot checked random values in CIS and CC and found them included.</p>
<p>June 10, 2024 at 13:00, Globalsign confirmed that they could not issue, but that validation showed as complete.  I ask engineering to fix the UX bug associated with random values (based on the email from Globalsign). Engineering was not consulted on the Globalsign email nor brought into the investigation.  This is where a mistake was made as I should have investigated further on whether something changed.</p>
<p>June 11, 2024 at 11:24 – Engineering deployed a fix based on the UX request. Engineering also modified the random value format. These modifications were based on the Globalsign email but were not considered a compliance change. Engineering does not provide notice of change as customers are not expected to rely on the format of random values.</p>
<p>June 13, 2024 at 6:44 – Engineering merged code to remove DCV methods (ones that relied on the deprecated random value components) that were redundant and no longer necessary. Compliance was not consulted on this change. Notices are not made about the deprecation per DigiCert standard procedure (as no impact was expected).</p>
<p>June 18, 2024 – Our engineering team fixes another UX bug related to random values where the random value displayed to the customer is not the same as expected in the backend. Engineering fixes but does not provide notice of the change.</p>
<p>July 3, 2024 at 20:43 – Our support team received a certificate problem report from a researcher through <a href="mailto:revoke@digicert.com" rel="nofollow">revoke@digicert.com</a>. The researcher asked whether they needed to revoke their certificates that did not include an underscore as part of the random value. The question was not about CNAME-based verification, just random values in general.</p>
<p>July 4, 2024 at 11:24 - Our support team responded that engineering had made a UX change to show accurate random values in the console and requested serial numbers to investigate further. This support email was not escalated.</p>
<p>July 7, 2024 at 23:56 - The researcher asked for clarification on the random value change. The support team responded with information about the validation process and the underscore change that occurred on June 7.</p>
<p>July 9, 2024 at 23:41 – The researcher asked about our documentation that did not specify that an underscore was required in front of the random value. DigiCert support responded that the change was a trivial change to fix the UX to update the console. Support escalated to industry standards, who informed a browser representative about the questions and asked how to address the issue as we were unaware of an issue and could not get a serial number from the researcher. The standards team met to review the validation process and did not find an issue with respect to DNS records. The review included a demonstration of the CNAME process but showed the random value in the CNAME as retrieved from the base domain, not the authorization domain (e.g., - foo.example.com CNAME {_rnd}.dcv.digicert.com), and from an authorization domain with an underscore prefix (eg – [_rnd].domain.com CNAME dcv.digicert.com). No compliance issues were detected.</p>
<p>July 14, 2024 at 21:28 – The researcher responded to the request for serials stating that certificates on CertCentral are impacted and asked for clarification on what happened. No serial numbers are provided.</p>
<p>July 15, 2024 at 15:01 – Support again requests serial numbers and reiterates that the change was a user experience change that consolidated random values between various methods and internal workflows. </p>
<p>July 15, 2024 at 21:49 - The researcher responded asking for more information on what Digicert investigated but did not provide serial numbers.</p>
<p>July 16, 2024 at 15:40 – Support decides this is an industry standards or compliance question and escalates to me to answer.</p>
<p>July 17, 2024 at 16:33 - I ask questions about what’s going on to clarify exactly what the researcher is finding given the previous investigation and demo provided. Engineering is not consulted on the issue.</p>
<p>July 17, 2024 at 23:20 – The researcher resends a list of questions.</p>
<p>July 18, 2024 at 14:50 – Engineering deploys code to consolidate file auth and DNS methods into single process.</p>
<p>July 18, 2024 at 21:21 – I again tried to clarify the scope of issues as there’s confusion around why the researcher thinks that adding an underscore in front of all random values is a compliance issue. The CNAME aspect of the question is missed as random values are investigated across the methods.</p>
<p>July 18, 2024 at 23:16 - The researcher replied that they were upset that notice of the change was not sent to customers and that they were not getting the answers needed. Note that the researcher is correct that notice was not sent to customers. This is not an issue as notices are not typically sent for changes that are expected to have negligible impact. DigiCert’s CI/CD pipeline deploys changes daily and the review process only sends notices for material changes. The researcher claims the change was to comply with the Baseline Requirements. Spot checks were again performed on domain validation and found that the sampled certificates complied with the Baseline Requirements. Spot checks include verification of CNAME validation, TXT validation, and other types of validation that included random values as it’s still unclear whether CNAME is the issue.  The spot checks were primarily new certificates that had been issued after the consolidation change.</p>
<p>July 20, 2024 at 03:48 - I responded that the change should have been trivial as customers should not care about the contents of a random value and asked for more details. As DigiCert splits method 7 into 6 paths, there was ambiguity about which path might have an issue.</p>
<p>July 22, 2024 at 17:07– The researcher claimed a customer integration was broken (provides a link to the github pull where another third party commented on noticing the change with the addition of the underscore) because of the change made to the random value, citing a change to our onion process. This was not considered an issue because onions are not expected to have underscore characters but could have them at the start. Onions were not considered when evaluating the end-user impact of the change.</p>
<p>July 22, 2024 at 22:00 – I reply that I am unaware of an outage and ask for clarification of the outage so I can investigate. An outage was discovered with onion certs where the length of the random value changed.</p>
<p>July 24, 2024 at 22:42 – The researcher stated that they have serial numbers and this was a test to see if DigiCert would acknowledge that there was an issue with domain validation. DigiCert had not detected a mis-issuance, but we gave the other browsers notice that there was a potential issue and informed them that we were investigating. One browser rep offered to assist with understanding the ask from the researcher.</p>
<p>July 25, 2024 at 18:23 – I introduced the individual to the browser rep on the continuing email thread to help identify the issue.</p>
<p>July 26, 2024 at 09:33 - The browser rep helped establish a list of questions that narrow the scope and describe the issue.</p>
<p>July 27, 2024 at 07:36 – DigiCert began code reviews of DNS methods using random values and their paths through its validation system. This review was done on the code version that existed before the random value consolidation project. Engineering found a possible path on its service system that allowed certificates to issue without an underscore prefix using CNAME validation where the host is the random value. An underscore was required for all other subdomains (i.e., - _dcv.domain.com CNAME [rnd].dcv.digicert.com).  This issue is the method from our preliminary report.</p>
<p>July 28, 2024 at 03:56 – DigiCert engineering reported back the root cause and found that the service-oriented system had several paths through the system for random number generation. One of those (OEM) did not add the underscore. Consolidating the random value generator remediated the issue by ensuring that all paths included an underscore at the start of the random value, even if an underscore was not required.</p>
<p>July 29. 2024 at 02:17– DigiCert filed the preliminary incident report.</p>
<p>July 29, 2024 at 22:36 – DigiCert identified impacted certificates and sends notice about revocation.</p>
<p>July 30, 2024 at 2:10-12:56 – DigiCert informed the root stores on the impact of revocation. Based on the discussion, DigiCert decides these are exceptional circumstances.</p>
<p>July 30, 2024 at 19:01– The court granted the TRO prohibiting revocation. <a href="https://www.courtlistener.com/docket/68995396/alegeus-technologies-llc-v-digicert/" rel="nofollow">https://www.courtlistener.com/docket/68995396/alegeus-technologies-llc-v-digicert/</a>.</p>
<p>July 30, 2024 at 23:12 – DigiCert filed a delayed revocation bug.</p>
<h3>Root Cause Analysis</h3>
<p>In August 2019, we began modernizing our domain and organization validation systems towards a service-oriented architecture with a goal of improving performance and simplifying workflows. Legacy code in CertCentral (our TLS certificate management portal) automatically added an underscore prefix to random values if a customer selected CNAME-based verification. Our new architecture redirected all validation through separate services instead of the legacy monolithic code structure. The code adding an underscore prefix was removed from CertCentral and added to some paths in the updated system. The underscore prefix addition was not separated into a distinct service. One path through the updated system did not automatically add the underscore nor check to see if the random value had a pre-appended underscore.</p>
<p>We recently found the omission of an automatic underscore prefix was not caught during the cross-functional team reviews that occurred before deployment of the updated system. While we had regression testing in place, those tests failed to alert us to the change in functionality because the regression tests were scoped to workflows and functionality instead of the content/structure of the random value. Other paths through the system either added underscores automatically or required customers to manually add the random value before verification completed. Unfortunately, no reviews were done to compare the legacy random value implementations with the random value implementations in the new system. Had we conducted those evaluations, we would have learned earlier that the system was not automatically adding the underscore prefix to the random value.</p>
<p>On June 11, 2024, engineering completed a user-experience project that collapsed multiple random value generation microservices into a single service. This service began including an underscore prefix before each random value, regardless of which validation method the user intended to use. This project allows DigiCert to ignore the random value generation process when verifying a domain and only check whether a random value appears in an authorization domain name. This deployment also reduced customer support calls related to the manual addition of underscore characters, fixed a bug in CertCentral’s display of validation status, and inadvertently ensured that every CNAME-based verification included an underscore prefix to each random value. As before, we did not compare this UX change against the underscore flow in the legacy system.</p>
<p>Several weeks ago, a researcher contacted our problem report alias over email asking about random values used in validation. Although the reporter did not provide serial numbers for any certificates, DigiCert conducted a preliminary investigation. This initial investigation did not uncover any issues with random value generation or validation. After the reporter requested answers to their repeated questions without providing any certificate serial numbers, DigiCert sought guidance from external CABF participants, who suggested DigiCert conduct an additional review. Upon further review, DigiCert discovered an issue regarding the underscore prefix for random values. DigiCert then initiated this incident management process.</p>
<h3>Lessons Learned</h3>
<p>First, we need to have a compliance sign-off process in engineering. Engineering is expected to read and understand the standards. We also have a process for questions from engineering. However, there was not a sign-off process before RA or CA deployments, nor were compliance people included in the planning process.</p>
<p>Second, this would have been better handled if we’d moved the emails immediately from our certificate problem notification process to MDSP. The back and forth wasted valuable time and led to confusion on both the issue and process. The certificate problem reporting process is equipped to best handle reported serial numbers. Anything that is not a serial number needs to leave that queue as quickly as possible and move to MDSP.</p>
<p>Third, this incident and the last one made the fact our teams are badly siloed very apparent. Although we reorganized the compliance team to try and facilitate broader investigations, there is little communication between compliance and engineering. Had engineering sent the change to compliance for review, compliance would have known this was a critical change. Had compliance discussed the issue with engineering, the issue would have been caught in June. Compliance right now is verifying post change instead of pre-change, which is causing serious issues. Amit initiated a project to shift compliance left in the dev process during the last issue and we’ve made significant progress even though additional steps are needed. We will be adding additional remediation actions to this JIRA as we discuss internally how to ensure more technical and thorough compliance reviews that are a partnership with engineering.</p>
<h4>What went well</h4>
<p>We were ready to revoke at the 24-hour mark and could process that number of revocations in about 1.5 hours. The DigiCert team was aligned on the plan to revoke at the 24-hour mark, even if that plan was interrupted by additional information on the impact of the revocation.</p>
<p>We were able to organize on the weekend to investigate the issue.</p>
<p>We deployed code after the last bug that permitted customers to see whether they were impacted by the issue which helped with notification.</p>
<p>We notified browser representatives early.</p>
<h4>What didn't go well</h4>
<ul>
<li>
<p>We were unable to revoke all certificates within the 24-hour timeframe and unable to quickly detangle the customer list of those that had exceptional circumstances vs. those that did not.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>We never received an actionable certificate problem report. One problematic certificate would have simplified the scope. We rely too heavily on a serial for a certificate problem report and should have treated the allegation more seriously, despite not having any evidence of an issue.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Getting personal emails is not a good way to kickoff an investigation. Those are easily missed and were not investigated as they did not constitute a certificate problem report.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>We did not understand the original email about the issue and believed the issue was about the random value generator.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>We should have moved the discussion to the public earlier.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The 24-hour turn-around for certificate problem reports meant our responses were less ideal and didn’t have the research necessary to accurately answer the questions.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Our testing needs to focus as much on compliance checks as it does on customer workflow checks.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Notices of system changes should always be sent out, regardless of size or complexity but especially if the changes have any relevance to baseline requirements.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>The ultimate root cause ended up being me. I have led the compliance team for the past several years. The fact this went unnoticed in our many reviews during that time shows that we need a different approach to both our internal investigations and compliance controls. I also dropped the ball on the certificate problem report by failing to escalate the issue to engineering and give it the proper attention it deserved. Although I did some investigation, I failed to treat the allegations with sufficient seriousness based on what could have been wrong. I assumed I knew the systems and what was happening in them rather than deeply investigating the report. Finally, I didn’t do enough to eliminate the silos between compliance and engineering. We’ve done a lot to rectify those silos, including a complete reorganization in the compliance function. Unfortunately, those changes were too late to rectify the problem.</p>
<p>I apologize to the community and our customers for the events and circumstances that led to this incident. This incident made me realize that I am no longer the person for this role. As such, after consulting with Amit (CEO), we have agreed that the path forward is for me to tender my resignation at the company. I will definitely miss the community, browsers, and public interactions as the PKI ecosystem has been my home and life for such a long time.</p>
<p>Going forward, Amit has asked Tim Hollebeek to lead a task force to implement thorough technical compliance controls (that go above and beyond pkilint) and provide oversight to our engineering team and processes to ensure strict compliance. Tim has 25+ years of computer security experience and was a security architect before joining DigiCert. He is chair of several IETF working groups, has been involved with the CA/B forum for 10 years and is a leader in our industry. I have no doubt that with Tim’s background and Amit’s oversight, he and our other compliance and engineering colleagues will do what’s needed to ensure the rigor the community and our customers expect from DigiCert.</p>
<h4>Where we got lucky</h4>
<p>We patched the system without knowing it. That patch ultimately ended up exposing the issue, which lead to a researcher reporting the problem.</p>
<p>The number of certificates was relatively small compared to the overall scope (2.8% of the non-ACME DNS-based validations through OEM).</p>
<h3>Action Items</h3>
<p>Modify the certificate problem report process to create a Bugzilla discussion for all non-compromised certificate serial numbers. The current process is to wait until an issue is confirmed. Although this will result in more “Invalid” bugs filed, the extra transparency will be valuable. – In progress</p>
<p>Consolidation of random value generators. - Done </p>
<p>Ensure all random values are prefixed with an underscore. – Done</p>
<p>Ensure compliance is part of each architecture review meeting and has the technical expertise to provide solutions. Compliance now has the ability to access architecture meetings but the technical expertise is lacking. – In Progress; eta August 15.</p>
<p>Remove the ability of Product teams to self-identify changes that require a formal compliance review. All changes in the CA and RA systems require a compliance review. Compliance team members will be included in early stakeholder reviews with the RA sprint teams and will determine changes that require formal review. – In Progress; eta August 15.</p>
<p>Add all applicable tests (not just entropy and functionality) for random value content/structure in the context of all validation flows. – In Progress; eta August 15.</p>
<p>Complete review of DCV methods with Industry Standards Development team. – In Progress; eta of August 10th</p>
<p>Eliminate all infrequently used processes and funnel all users though a single flow for each method. – In Progress, eta of Nov 1</p>
<p>Open Source DCV system for community review – In Progress; eta of December 1.</p>
</div><div><p>Flags: <span>needinfo?(jeremy.rowley)</span></p></div></div><div id="c18" data-comment-id="17051714" data-ismarkdown="true"><p>Hello,</p>
<p>This is Tim.</p>
<p>We failed to live up to your expectations. Obviously, it is going to take a bit of time for me to get up to speed, but we're going to be doing things differently going forward. We have some amazing people here at DigiCert, and they've done some amazing things, but they don't always work together internally as well as they need to. And since literally the entire planet is relying on them, that's not acceptable and is going to change.</p>
<p>Right now, we're working hard to get all of these certificates replaced as soon as possible, but as you can see from the actions above, we take this very seriously, and have already initiated a variety of efforts to make sure our critical processes are as technically excellent and correct as you deserve them to be.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>-Tim</p>
</div><div id="c19" data-comment-id="17051920" data-ismarkdown="true"><p>Thank you for the incident report. This is quite detailed and really allows the reader to understand the full timeline and how this mistake was introduced. I have two passing thoughts here:</p>
<p>First:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The 24-hour turn-around for certificate problem reports meant our responses were less ideal and didn’t have the research necessary to accurately answer the questions.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>From my understanding, it is acceptable to say "We're going to be doing a deep look into this, and we'll update you again in 24 hours." to get more time to do a deeper analysis. I do not think the 24 hour time for CPRs explicitly say that you have to have it full done and complete by 24 hours. Just that you have to have <em>some</em> response by 24 hours, and that response could be a good-faith representation that you're looking further into it.</p>
<p>Maybe the community can correct my understanding here.</p>
<p>Second:</p>
<p>If I'm understanding this correctly, the security impact of this incident could be quite significant if an attacker knew about this flaw. Will there be an action item to go check DCVs since this bug was introduced in production to check for anomalies of DCVs? For example looking at the logs of DNS queries where the domain being queried didn't start with an <code>_</code> and seeing if there are anomalies in any of those issuance patterns?</p>
<p>I'd be interested if the community has any thoughts on how best a search like that can be executed.</p>
</div><div id="c20" data-comment-id="17051989" data-ismarkdown="true"><p>(Speaking personally, not on behalf of my employer.)</p>
<p>Thank you for this detailed and well-written incident report. The timeline is very clear and interesting, and I think the points about siloing between various compliance-critical departments within the same organization are very valuable insights that should be taken to heart by all CAs. The remediation items listed are clear, actionable, and make sense to me.</p>
<p>I believe strongly in <a href="https://sre.google/sre-book/postmortem-culture/" rel="nofollow">blameless postmortem culture</a>. Incidents like this are not the result of individual actions, but of years of systemic failures that have allowed incorrect actions to be taken. I believe this applies at all levels, from newly-hired line engineers to CISOs. Even when leadership changes do need to occur, I believe they should not be precipitated by -- nor announced as part of -- individual incidents. Doing so harms our industry, and sends the wrong message especially to junior employees.</p>
<p>Jeremy, if this resignation is your own idea, done for your own health and well-being, then I hope you know that the rest of this community does not hold you personally responsible or blame you for this incident. We wish you the best. If this resignation is at the prompting of DigiCert leadership, then I hope they recognize that this move reflects poorly upon them.</p>
<p>Thanks again for the report, and I sincerely look forward to reviewing DigiCert's open-source DCV system!</p>
</div><div id="c21" data-comment-id="17051995" data-ismarkdown="true"><p>(In reply to Aaron Gable from <a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1910322#c20" title="ASSIGNED - DigiCert: Random value in CNAME without underscore prefix">comment #20</a>)</p>
<blockquote>
<p>(Speaking personally, not on behalf of my employer.)</p>
<p>Thank you for this detailed and well-written incident report. The timeline is very clear and interesting, and I think the points about siloing between various compliance-critical departments within the same organization are very valuable insights that should be taken to heart by all CAs. The remediation items listed are clear, actionable, and make sense to me.</p>
<p>I believe strongly in <a href="https://sre.google/sre-book/postmortem-culture/" rel="nofollow">blameless postmortem culture</a>. Incidents like this are not the result of individual actions, but of years of systemic failures that have allowed incorrect actions to be taken. I believe this applies at all levels, from newly-hired line engineers to CISOs. Even when leadership changes do need to occur, I believe they should not be precipitated by -- nor announced as part of -- individual incidents. Doing so harms our industry, and sends the wrong message especially to junior employees.</p>
<p>Jeremy, if this resignation is your own idea, done for your own health and well-being, then I hope you know that the rest of this community does not hold you personally responsible or blame you for this incident. We wish you the best. If this resignation is at the prompting of DigiCert leadership, then I hope they recognize that this move reflects poorly upon them.</p>
<p>Thanks again for the report, and I sincerely look forward to reviewing DigiCert's open-source DCV system!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Thank you for saying this Aaron. I have similar feelings and didn’t really know what’s an appropriate way to put it into a comment.</p>
<p>I’d even go as far as saying I would like the CCADB incident response template specifically prohibiting these types of mentions in incident reports.</p>
<p>Personnel changes are not and have never been expected or appreciated as part of an incident response.</p>
</div><div id="c22"><p>Why? I think they are an important part of accountability. I decided to step down because of the incident. That's part of the incident report and something that should be disclosed. Knowing what changes are happening is part of transparency and ensuring accountability within the organization.</p></div><div id="c23" data-comment-id="17051998" data-ismarkdown="true"><p>(In reply to Jeremy Rowley from <a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1910322#c22" title="ASSIGNED - DigiCert: Random value in CNAME without underscore prefix">comment #22</a>)</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Why? I think they are an important part of accountability. I decided to step down because of the incident. That's part of the incident report and something that should be disclosed. Knowing what changes are happening is part of transparency and ensuring accountability within the organization.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>One reason: it can set inadvertently make it an expectation for other CAs to think they need to make personnel changes when an incident happens. It has a chilling effect for incident reporting even if that’s not the intention.</p>
</div><div id="c24" data-comment-id="17052062" data-ismarkdown="true"><p>(In reply to Jeremy Rowley from <a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1910322#c22" title="ASSIGNED - DigiCert: Random value in CNAME without underscore prefix">comment #22</a>)</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Why? I think they are an important part of accountability. I decided to step down because of the incident. That's part of the incident report and something that should be disclosed. Knowing what changes are happening is part of transparency and ensuring accountability within the organization.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Aaron laid out the <em>why</em> in his comment:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Incidents like this are not the result of individual actions, but of years of systemic failures that have allowed incorrect actions to be taken. I believe this applies at all levels, from newly-hired line engineers to CISOs.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Additionally, the lesson many people learn from shouldering blame, or from seeing blame shouldered, is to hide/bury mistakes instead of learning to uncover ways to make the mistakes easier to spot, earlier, and with more thorough understanding.</p>
<p>And I'd like to echo again Aaron's statement:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>if this is your own idea, done for your own health and well-being, then I hope you know that the rest of this community does not hold you personally responsible or blame you for this incident. We wish you the best.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Hundreds of other humans helping to run the PKI ecosystem upon which the current Web is built have a lot to learn from these reports; a lot to learn about improving the systems, policies and procedures that keep it going. We will all be digging into the technical details of the report and finding items that can help us improve - but learning to shoulder blame is not constructive in that regard.</p>
</div><div id="c25" data-comment-id="17052248" data-ismarkdown="true"><p>(In reply to Aaron Gable from <a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1910322#c20" title="ASSIGNED - DigiCert: Random value in CNAME without underscore prefix">comment #20</a>)</p>
<blockquote>
<p>(Speaking personally, not on behalf of my employer.)</p>
<p>Thank you for this detailed and well-written incident report. The timeline is very clear and interesting, and I think the points about siloing between various compliance-critical departments within the same organization are very valuable insights that should be taken to heart by all CAs. The remediation items listed are clear, actionable, and make sense to me.</p>
<p>I believe strongly in <a href="https://sre.google/sre-book/postmortem-culture/" rel="nofollow">blameless postmortem culture</a>. Incidents like this are not the result of individual actions, but of years of systemic failures that have allowed incorrect actions to be taken. I believe this applies at all levels, from newly-hired line engineers to CISOs. Even when leadership changes do need to occur, I believe they should not be precipitated by -- nor announced as part of -- individual incidents. Doing so harms our industry, and sends the wrong message especially to junior employees.</p>
<p>Jeremy, if this resignation is your own idea, done for your own health and well-being, then I hope you know that the rest of this community does not hold you personally responsible or blame you for this incident. We wish you the best. If this resignation is at the prompting of DigiCert leadership, then I hope they recognize that this move reflects poorly upon them.</p>
<p>Thanks again for the report, and I sincerely look forward to reviewing DigiCert's open-source DCV system!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Aaron you took every sentiment I was going to say privately and repeated them better than I could. I don't see a single piece of this incident that is a result of an individual failing, but a lack of support in getting them help. Jeremy I know you've made comments in the past that reflect you taking issues personally, but I see that more as you caring about doing your job properly. We need more people across the industry who care, so please reconsider. I see no one externally who thinks you were at all a problem throughout this, <a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1896053">or in prior incidents</a>.</p>
<p>Back to this incident: At least one organization has reached out regarding a certificate that is a single wildcard SAN that was email-verified but is in the revocation group, so I don't think the mixed-verification scenario explains the full story. Now unfortunately I can't name names, but I was being serious in prior comments. I realize the irony here when one unknown researcher was wasting everyone's time with an actual security incident and not providing serials - but that's where we are. I'd rather there be an overbroad search, but this will be why some subscribers are upset.</p>
<p>With regards to when the clock starts until we get stronger recommendations from CAB/F or Root Programs I am aiming to get CAs to be clearer on their methodology in incident reports. This makes it easier for people to review later, and reach a consensus across incidents.</p>
<p>I strongly appreciate there being an actual realistic time for revocation mentioned at 1.5h, rather than boldly claiming it can be done immediately. I am hesitant on the security of the CNAME underscore method itself, but if it is recognized in the industry then I don't see it relevant to this incident itself. I do think it is leaning too much on overlapping RFCs as a security property, but it is what it is.</p>
</div><div id="c26" data-comment-id="17052610" data-ismarkdown="true"><p>(In reply to Jeremy Rowley from <a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1910322#c22" title="ASSIGNED - DigiCert: Random value in CNAME without underscore prefix">comment #22</a>)</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Why? I think they are an important part of accountability. I decided to step down because of the incident. That's part of the incident report and something that should be disclosed. Knowing what changes are happening is part of transparency and ensuring accountability within the organization.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I wrote my thoughts about your decision to resign privately, and won’t restate them all here (roughly: oh god, what a blow to the web), but I want to respond to this point.</p>
<p>“Accountability” is not about punishment or scorekeeping or setting an example <em>pour encourager les autres</em>. It is about having appropriate attention paid to the things that caused a problem to occur, by making that reflection and transparency the responsibility of the person who was placed to observe those things and best understand how they happened. That reflection and transparency is <strong>only</strong> valuable to the extent that it changes the future handling of related situations. I know that in your place I would be watching the director’s commentary of <em>Looper</em> over and over to see if I could pull off time travel even <em>just once</em>, but alas that’s not one of the choices available. What matters now is what happens to the web, to DigiCert’s operations, and to Jeremy Rowley as a person and community member.</p>
<p>When DigiCert has another incident (and while I have tremendous faith in Tim, it will happen), I would rather that they have Jeremy Rowley with his wisdom and scar tissue around to guide their response and subsequent improvement. When another CA has a crisis related to domain validation, I want their panicked CISO to be able to reach out to Jeremy Rowley for help, and to see that these crises can be used as powerful tools for change. And, more personally, when DigiCert has rolled out its changes and demonstrated that is exactly the company that we need in such a critical role on the web, I want Jeremy Rowley to get the highest of fives at the after party. DigiCert and its customers and the web already have to pay the cost of this incident, and it would be so much better if we could also benefit maximally from what you’ve learned (so so painfully) along the way.</p>
<p>Of course, I have no right whatsoever to tell you that you can’t resign, Jeremy, or that you “shouldn’t” feel as you do. While I very much share Aaron’s love of blameless postmortem, I know that I can be caustic in these forums when I’m frustrated or disappointed; I hope that hasn’t contributed to you feeling that you should be punished or exiled. If this is your exit, please know that you will be missed.</p>
</div><div id="c27" data-comment-id="17053047" data-ismarkdown="true"><p>I have over 24 years of experience in the DNS (Domain Name System) space. I founded and developed DNS Made Easy in 2002 and have managed DNS Made Easy and Constellix since their inception. Initially, we handled DDNS (Dynamic DNS) entries for millions of hostnames before transitioning to the authoritative DNS space, focusing on the SMB and enterprise market. Over the past 24 years, I have been responsible for serving hundreds of millions of hostnames across millions of domains. For full transparency, DNS Made Easy and Constellix were acquired by DigiCert in May of 2022.</p>
<p>The current DNS-related issue centers on the ability for someone to create a CNAME (Canonical Name) record without being the domain owner. Historically, some services have allowed this due to the challenges of domain ownership at the time.</p>
<p>From a DNS perspective, it is crucial to understand that this issue arises from services that permit third parties to create hostnames within their domain names as a service or value to their customers. This is common among DDNS (dynamic DNS) providers, who typically allow users to map a name to a dynamic IP address, thus enabling the creation of A or AAAA records (IPv4 and IPv6 addresses, respectively). Most DDNS providers are not part of this conversation since they do not permit CNAME record creation by third parties.</p>
<p>However, a subset of DDNS providers do allow CNAME record creation for vanity reasons. Although the practice has diminished over the years, it still exists among a few companies. Within this group, the potential problem is further divided into those allowing CNAME records with hostnames starting with an underscore and those that do not. Providers allowing underscores inherently assume the risk of certificate creation for their root domain and are not part of this discussion. This risk can be mitigated with a properly secured domain using specific CAA (Certification Authority Authorization) records, but that is another conversation entirely.</p>
<p>Additionally, many providers do not allow the creation of CNAME records with hostnames of at least 32 characters, which further narrows the potentially affected group. After thoroughly investigating and testing notable DDNS services, it appears that No-IP allows CNAME record creation. While free accounts on their platform are limited to 19 characters, paid users can create longer CNAME records that would have allowed the 32 characters necessary for the CNAME validation.</p>
<p>Following discussions with the No-IP executive team and conducting an internal search, we were able to determine that none of these domains were affected by having a root certificate or a wildcard certificate created. Therefore, I can confidently say that none of the potentially affected domains were impacted. Based on a DNS-level understanding of this situation, no certificates were wrongfully or maliciously created.</p>
<p>Please note that all DDNS providers that allow the creation of A, AAAA, or CNAME records automatically permit certificates for individual hostnames since you can create certificates for them at any time. With any DDNS (or CNAME) provider, you have always been able to perform an "HTTP-01 challenge" to request a certificate for your individual hostname. The issue was whether you could create a certificate for other host names in the domain.</p>
<p>This overview is presented purely from a DNS perspective. I am not implying that the security policies of the appropriate agencies should not be followed. My goal is to assess the likelihood of such an occurrence and cross-reference this with known domains, finding zero collisions. From a DNS standpoint, I believe there is virtually a 0% chance that a domain certificate was wrongfully created.</p>
</div><div id="c28"><div id="ct-28" data-comment-id="17053081" data-ismarkdown="true"><p>First off, my peers at Sectigo and I want to echo others in applauding Jeremy for his contribution to this community and the WebPKI.  Thank you for being an esteemed colleague and a friend.</p>
<p>Now, on to this TRO.  I see that the TRO was filed on July 30, 2024.  As of posting time it’s August 2.  I can’t find any motion to dissolve on Pacer.</p>
<p><strong>Question 1</strong>:  Did you file a motion to dissolve?  Can you post it here?</p>
<p>The BRs require</p>
<blockquote>
<p>An acknowledgment and acceptance that the CA is entitled to revoke the certificate immediately if the Applicant were to violate the terms of the Subscriber Agreement or Terms of Use or if revocation is required by the CA’s CP, CPS, or these Baseline Requirements.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>Question 2</strong>:  Can you share the specific wording in your agreement with Alegeus that meets or was intended to meet this requirement?  This may be illuminating in understanding how to protect CAs from this kind of offense in the future.</p>
</div><div><p>Flags: needinfo?(tim.hollebeek)</p></div></div><div id="c29"><div id="ct-29" data-comment-id="17053732" data-ismarkdown="true"><p>On Saturday, August 3, 2024, 20:47 UTC, DigiCert completed the revocation of the 83,267 certificates affected by this bug, without exception. This was a large, coordinated effort across many organizations to get all certificates revoked within 5 days.  We’re very thankful to everyone for working with us on such a short timescale to make sure all impacted certificates could be revoked while minimizing impact to critical infrastructure and services. Faced with incidents of similar scale, many other CAs have simply let the affected certificates expire naturally. We originally planned to revoke all of these certificates within 24 hours, but a few legal and critical infrastructure related concerns, as well as the scale of the number of organizations we were dealing with, caused us to take a few more days to get everything resolved and revoked safely. Those concerns have now all been dealt with.</p>
<p>Obviously, the best outcome would have been for the validation method to have been implemented correctly, so improving the rigor of our approval processes and continuing to tighten up our technical controls is where we will be concentrating most of our efforts going forward. It’s unfortunate that this bug was exposed as a side-effect of us simplifying and coalescing our validation systems; we intend to provide more details going forward about our new, simpler validation architecture, and we even intend to open-source it so that we can benefit from community examination of the implementations.</p>
<p>We’ve had our DNS experts looking closely at whether any certificates were improperly issued due to this bug and have found no evidence that any of these certificates were issued to anyone other than the intended recipients. We’ve examined the list of affected domains and compared them to the theoretical attacks that have been suggested and found in most cases the suggested actions cannot be carried out successfully, and there’s no evidence anyone even attempted to do so. If people have additional scenarios or evidence that needs to be investigated, we can do so.</p>
<p>Questions have also been asked about whether any S/MIME certificates are affected by this validation bug, since the S/MIME Baseline Requirements include the TLS Baseline Requirement validation methods by reference, and Mozilla Policy has long required domain validation prior to the issuance of S/MIME certificates. We have investigated and found 1,308 S/MIME certificates which were based on flawed validations using this same method, and we will be revoking those as well. A list of affected serial numbers is attached.</p>
</div><div><p>Flags: <span>needinfo?(tim.hollebeek)</span></p></div></div>







<dialog id="att-overlay" aria-labelledby="att-overlay-title" data-attachment-count="4">
  
</dialog>

</div> 
</main> 
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Medieval (773 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://teenage.engineering/products/ep-1320</link>
            <guid>41176831</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 23:57:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://teenage.engineering/products/ep-1320">https://teenage.engineering/products/ep-1320</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41176831">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[MNT Pocket Reform first impressions and hardware (127 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://andypiper.co.uk/2024/08/06/mnt-pocket-reform-first-impressions/</link>
            <guid>41176817</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 23:56:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://andypiper.co.uk/2024/08/06/mnt-pocket-reform-first-impressions/">https://andypiper.co.uk/2024/08/06/mnt-pocket-reform-first-impressions/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41176817">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
		
<p>A couple of weeks ago I received something I’ve been eagerly expecting from a <a href="https://www.crowdsupply.com/mnt/pocket-reform" data-type="link" data-id="https://www.crowdsupply.com/mnt/pocket-reform">Crowd Supply crowd funding campaign</a>.</p>



<p><a href="https://mntre.com/about.html" data-type="link" data-id="https://mntre.com/about.html">MNT</a> have been making devices that aim to be “open source, accessible and modular” for a number of years. I didn’t get their original Reform laptop, but I’ve seen those around at events like FOSDEM and I’ve been following the team’s progress with interest. When the Pocket Reform was announced I was immediately intrigued – a smaller form factor, 7 inch full Linux system with open hardware that is easily portable.</p>







<p>I went for the Hyper edition, which came with a beautiful Piñatex sleeve, SSD, and printed manual. Purple, of course, because I want to be <a href="https://joinmastodon.org/branding" data-type="link" data-id="https://joinmastodon.org/branding">on brand</a> 🤓 and, also because I love it!</p>



<p>I posted a very brief <a href="https://makertube.net/w/fmCffr2EwC3kDE9fS4RycA" data-type="link" data-id="https://makertube.net/w/fmCffr2EwC3kDE9fS4RycA">unboxing video</a>. I’ve now had a couple of weeks to occasionally tinker, and I’ve been putting off writing about it all in part because there’s a lot of things to dig into! </p>



<p>One of the things I like, surprisingly, is the chunkiness of the machine. It is really well constructed, solid, and feels great. Fits in a small cross-body bag or satchel. It’s less than half the size of a 14 inch MacBook Pro – you can more than fit two of them side by side on top of the Mac – but it is about 3 times thicker – and that’s OK, because, it is in service of making the innards very accessible and user serviceable. It comes with a complete manual and schematic, which is something I’ve not had in a computer since the 8-bit machines of my youth! The top half contains the mainboard and display (all the ports are in the top half), and the bottom contains the battery cells and mechanical keyboard. The upper panel has a copper layer and acts as a large heatsink for the processor module.</p>



<figure data-carousel-extra="{&quot;blog_id&quot;:1,&quot;permalink&quot;:&quot;https:\/\/andypiper.co.uk\/2024\/08\/06\/mnt-pocket-reform-first-impressions\/&quot;}">
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="400" height="533" data-attachment-id="4691" data-permalink="https://andypiper.co.uk/2024/08/06/mnt-pocket-reform-first-impressions/img_3364/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3364-rotated.jpg?fit=3024%2C4032&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="3024,4032" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;2.2&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone 15 Pro&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1721388805&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;2.2200000286119&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;320&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.01&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_3364" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3364-rotated.jpg?fit=225%2C300&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3364-rotated.jpg?fit=400%2C533&amp;ssl=1" tabindex="0" role="button" data-id="4691" src="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3364.jpg?resize=400%2C533&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3364-rotated.jpg?resize=400%2C533&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3364-rotated.jpg?resize=225%2C300&amp;ssl=1 225w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3364-rotated.jpg?resize=113%2C150&amp;ssl=1 113w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3364-rotated.jpg?resize=768%2C1024&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3364-rotated.jpg?resize=1152%2C1536&amp;ssl=1 1152w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3364-rotated.jpg?resize=1536%2C2048&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3364-rotated.jpg?resize=900%2C1200&amp;ssl=1 900w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3364-rotated.jpg?resize=600%2C800&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3364-rotated.jpg?resize=450%2C600&amp;ssl=1 450w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3364-rotated.jpg?resize=300%2C400&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3364-rotated.jpg?resize=150%2C200&amp;ssl=1 150w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3364-rotated.jpg?resize=1200%2C1600&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3364-rotated.jpg?resize=1088%2C1451&amp;ssl=1 1088w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3364-rotated.jpg?w=1478&amp;ssl=1 1478w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3364-rotated.jpg?w=2217&amp;ssl=1 2217w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="400" height="300" data-attachment-id="4689" data-permalink="https://andypiper.co.uk/2024/08/06/mnt-pocket-reform-first-impressions/img_3368/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3368-rotated.jpg?fit=4032%2C3024&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="4032,3024" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;2.2&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone 15 Pro&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1721388929&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;2.2200000286119&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;80&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.01&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_3368" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3368-rotated.jpg?fit=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3368-rotated.jpg?fit=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1" tabindex="0" role="button" data-id="4689" src="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3368-400x300.jpg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3368-rotated.jpg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3368-rotated.jpg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3368-rotated.jpg?resize=150%2C113&amp;ssl=1 150w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3368-rotated.jpg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3368-rotated.jpg?resize=1536%2C1152&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3368-rotated.jpg?resize=2048%2C1536&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3368-rotated.jpg?resize=1200%2C900&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3368-rotated.jpg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3368-rotated.jpg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3368-rotated.jpg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3368-rotated.jpg?resize=1088%2C816&amp;ssl=1 1088w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3368-rotated.jpg?w=1478&amp;ssl=1 1478w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3368-rotated.jpg?w=2217&amp;ssl=1 2217w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="400" height="533" data-attachment-id="4688" data-permalink="https://andypiper.co.uk/2024/08/06/mnt-pocket-reform-first-impressions/img_3366/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3366-rotated.jpg?fit=3024%2C4032&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="3024,4032" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;2.2&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone 15 Pro&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1721388818&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;2.2200000286119&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;250&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.01&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_3366" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3366-rotated.jpg?fit=225%2C300&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3366-rotated.jpg?fit=400%2C533&amp;ssl=1" tabindex="0" role="button" data-id="4688" src="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3366.jpg?resize=400%2C533&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3366-rotated.jpg?resize=400%2C533&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3366-rotated.jpg?resize=225%2C300&amp;ssl=1 225w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3366-rotated.jpg?resize=113%2C150&amp;ssl=1 113w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3366-rotated.jpg?resize=768%2C1024&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3366-rotated.jpg?resize=1152%2C1536&amp;ssl=1 1152w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3366-rotated.jpg?resize=1536%2C2048&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3366-rotated.jpg?resize=900%2C1200&amp;ssl=1 900w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3366-rotated.jpg?resize=600%2C800&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3366-rotated.jpg?resize=450%2C600&amp;ssl=1 450w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3366-rotated.jpg?resize=300%2C400&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3366-rotated.jpg?resize=150%2C200&amp;ssl=1 150w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3366-rotated.jpg?resize=1200%2C1600&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3366-rotated.jpg?resize=1088%2C1451&amp;ssl=1 1088w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3366-rotated.jpg?w=1478&amp;ssl=1 1478w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3366-rotated.jpg?w=2217&amp;ssl=1 2217w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="739" height="554" data-attachment-id="4690" data-permalink="https://andypiper.co.uk/2024/08/06/mnt-pocket-reform-first-impressions/img_3486/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3486.jpg?fit=4032%2C3024&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="4032,3024" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;2.2&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone 15 Pro&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1722516372&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;2.2200000286119&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;1600&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.027777777777778&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_3486" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3486.jpg?fit=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3486.jpg?fit=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1" tabindex="0" role="button" data-id="4690" src="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3486.jpg?resize=739%2C554&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3486.jpg?w=4032&amp;ssl=1 4032w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3486.jpg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3486.jpg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3486.jpg?resize=150%2C113&amp;ssl=1 150w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3486.jpg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3486.jpg?resize=1536%2C1152&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3486.jpg?resize=2048%2C1536&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3486.jpg?resize=1200%2C900&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3486.jpg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3486.jpg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3486.jpg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3486.jpg?resize=1088%2C816&amp;ssl=1 1088w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3486.jpg?w=1478&amp;ssl=1 1478w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3486.jpg?w=2217&amp;ssl=1 2217w" sizes="(max-width: 739px) 100vw, 739px" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>
</figure>



<p>The keyboard is ortholinear, which means it is a direct grid layout rather than offset row-by-row. It’s the first time I’ve used this format, which – along with the smaller keycaps – has made it a little challenging to learn, but I’m doing pretty well now. The trackball is nice and responsive. The backlit keys are easy to adjust.</p>



<figure data-carousel-extra="{&quot;blog_id&quot;:1,&quot;permalink&quot;:&quot;https:\/\/andypiper.co.uk\/2024\/08\/06\/mnt-pocket-reform-first-impressions\/&quot;}">
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="400" height="300" data-attachment-id="4686" data-permalink="https://andypiper.co.uk/2024/08/06/mnt-pocket-reform-first-impressions/img_3357/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3357.jpg?fit=4032%2C3024&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="4032,3024" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;2.2&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone 15 Pro&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1721306672&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;2.2200000286119&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;320&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.02&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_3357" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3357.jpg?fit=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3357.jpg?fit=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1" tabindex="0" role="button" data-id="4686" src="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3357-400x300.jpg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3357.jpg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3357.jpg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3357.jpg?resize=150%2C113&amp;ssl=1 150w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3357.jpg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3357.jpg?resize=1536%2C1152&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3357.jpg?resize=2048%2C1536&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3357.jpg?resize=1200%2C900&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3357.jpg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3357.jpg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3357.jpg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3357.jpg?resize=1088%2C816&amp;ssl=1 1088w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3357.jpg?w=1478&amp;ssl=1 1478w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3357.jpg?w=2217&amp;ssl=1 2217w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="400" height="300" data-attachment-id="4685" data-permalink="https://andypiper.co.uk/2024/08/06/mnt-pocket-reform-first-impressions/img_3363/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3363-rotated.jpg?fit=4032%2C3024&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="4032,3024" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;2.2&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone 15 Pro&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1721332855&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;2.2200000286119&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;1600&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.026315789473684&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_3363" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3363-rotated.jpg?fit=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3363-rotated.jpg?fit=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1" tabindex="0" role="button" data-id="4685" src="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3363-400x300.jpg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3363-rotated.jpg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3363-rotated.jpg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3363-rotated.jpg?resize=150%2C113&amp;ssl=1 150w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3363-rotated.jpg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3363-rotated.jpg?resize=1536%2C1152&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3363-rotated.jpg?resize=2048%2C1536&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3363-rotated.jpg?resize=1200%2C900&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3363-rotated.jpg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3363-rotated.jpg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3363-rotated.jpg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3363-rotated.jpg?resize=1088%2C816&amp;ssl=1 1088w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3363-rotated.jpg?w=1478&amp;ssl=1 1478w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG_3363-rotated.jpg?w=2217&amp;ssl=1 2217w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>
</figure>



<p>The screen is excellent – bright, and sharp. Actually I think the screen is probably the aspect that has impressed me most so far.</p>



<p>In terms of ports and connectivity – I’ve yet to hook up to an additional screen via the micro-HDMI connector, but I’ve used the USB-C connections (one of which is used to charge / power the machine), and the micro SD slot. The industrial iX connector for ethernet is likely a good choice for the target niche, and certainly does give more space on the motherboard than an RJ45 socket would… but I’ve yet to put my hands on a passive adapter to enable me to plug in to a wired connection, so it’s currently not as useful to me.</p>



<p>There’s a lot more to talk about, primarily (but not exclusively) on the software side, and also around hardware enablement. Out-of-the-box the Pocket Reform runs Debian unstable from MMC, with some customisations to provide a nice getting started wizard. It is important to point out that this is a machine for hackers and tinkerers – although it works very nicely, it’s not all fully baked in places – for example, the firmware for the system controller (a Raspberry Pi RP2040 chip) is being tweaked and tested, and I’ve already tested one update to that which improved the charging behaviour. </p>



<p>The other day <a href="https://andypiper.co.uk/2024/08/03/messing-with-a-messy-nvme/" data-type="post" data-id="4615">I posted about some issues with an NVMe SSD</a> – that, unfortunately, was on this machine. I actually think there was a physical hardware issue with the drive, as I’ve now replaced it with a higher-performance NVMe and things are moving along nicely (while the problematic SSD continues to report errors when accessed in an adapter over USB). I also managed to temporarily brick the machine by corrupting the uboot in flash, and needed to rig it up with Dupont wires on headers and access the machine from another via USB to get back to where I wanted to be. Very Open Source! 😎 but, I’m comfortable with this, and knew what I was purchasing. The forums and IRC have proven to be useful so far and I’m enjoying learning as well as hopefully (!?) helping the MNT team via my feedback and bug reports. I have a huge amount of respect for what they have built, their ethos, and their commitment to making this as open hardware as they can.</p>



<p>I should be receiving a modem / WWAN card for the second internal expansion slot shortly. I’ve been both learning the Sway desktop environment and also working out how best to organise my setup, so there will be more to cover in future. I particularly want to play more with the onboard I2C, and other hardware opportunities, as well – for example, potentially swapping in a Raspberry Pi CM4 if that <a href="https://mntre.com/modularity.html" data-type="link" data-id="https://mntre.com/modularity.html">becomes a modular option in the future</a>.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="739" height="462" data-attachment-id="4701" data-permalink="https://andypiper.co.uk/2024/08/06/mnt-pocket-reform-first-impressions/screenshot-2024-08-06-15-49-30/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/screenshot-2024-08-06-15-49-30.png?fit=1920%2C1200&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="1920,1200" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="screenshot-2024-08-06-15-49-30" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/screenshot-2024-08-06-15-49-30.png?fit=300%2C188&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/screenshot-2024-08-06-15-49-30.png?fit=400%2C250&amp;ssl=1" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/screenshot-2024-08-06-15-49-30.png?resize=739%2C462&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/screenshot-2024-08-06-15-49-30.png?w=1920&amp;ssl=1 1920w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/screenshot-2024-08-06-15-49-30.png?resize=300%2C188&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/screenshot-2024-08-06-15-49-30.png?resize=400%2C250&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/screenshot-2024-08-06-15-49-30.png?resize=150%2C94&amp;ssl=1 150w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/screenshot-2024-08-06-15-49-30.png?resize=768%2C480&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/screenshot-2024-08-06-15-49-30.png?resize=1536%2C960&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/screenshot-2024-08-06-15-49-30.png?resize=1200%2C750&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/screenshot-2024-08-06-15-49-30.png?resize=1088%2C680&amp;ssl=1 1088w, https://i0.wp.com/andypiper.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/screenshot-2024-08-06-15-49-30.png?w=1478&amp;ssl=1 1478w" sizes="(max-width: 739px) 100vw, 739px" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>
			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How French Drains Work (304 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://practical.engineering/blog/2024/8/6/how-french-drains-work</link>
            <guid>41176461</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 23:07:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://practical.engineering/blog/2024/8/6/how-french-drains-work">https://practical.engineering/blog/2024/8/6/how-french-drains-work</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41176461">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-block-type="2" id="item-66b23daa88ea931bc7bcff1f" data-layout-label="Post Body" data-type="item" data-updated-on="1722957457318">
  <p><em>[Note that this article is a transcript of the video embedded above.]</em></p><p>In February of 2017, one of the largest spillways in the world, the one at Oroville Dam in northern California, was severely damaged during releases from heavy rain. You might remember this. I made a video about it, and then another one about the impressive feat of rebuilding the structure. In the forensic report following the incident, one of the contributing causes identified in the failure was the drainage system below the spillway. Rather than being installed below the concrete, each drain protruded into it, reducing the thickness of the concrete and making it more prone to cracking. But why do you need drains below a spillway in the first place? Put simply: water doesn’t just flow on the surface of earth. It also flows through the soil and rock below it. Water that gets underneath a structure creates pressure that can lift and move it. That’s especially true when the water is flowing. Dam Engineers deal with the challenge in two ways: make concrete structures like spillways massive (so gravity holds them in place) and use drains to relieve that pressure, giving the water a way out.</p><p>Even though we depend on it to live, water is the enemy of all kinds of structures. Pressure is far from the only problem it causes. Most of us have come face to face with it in some way or other. Water causes some soils to expand and contract. It freezes, promotes rot, erodes, and corrodes, wreaking all kinds of havoc on the things we build. On the surface, water is relatively easy to manage through channels and curbs and slopes. Below the ground, things get much more challenging. Subsurface drainage is a really interesting challenge, and it applies to everything from simple landscaping at your house to the biggest structures on Earth, and there are a lot of things that can go wrong if they’re not designed correctly. I’m Grady, and this is Practical Engineering. Today, we’re talking about French Drains.</p><p>The idea of a subsurface drain is really pretty simple. And I built a model here in the garage to show you how they work. This is just an acrylic box with a hole at the bottom. I filled the box with sand to simulate soil. And I left a small area of gravel in front of the hole. A few strategically-placed dye tablets will help with the visualization. When I turn on the rainfall simulator, watch what happens. Water percolating into the subsurface continues flowing within the sand. It moves toward the gravel, eventually flowing into the holes between the stones and out of the model. (Don’t pay attention to those dye traces on the left. Turns out there was a small leak in the box that was acting as a… secondary outlet to my drain). When the rain is over, the subsurface water continues to flow until the soil is mostly dries out.</p><p>This is a very simple model of what’s often referred to as a French drain. It’s not from France but named after an American farmer, lawyer, politician, and inventor Henry French whose 1846 book on Farm Drainage cataloged and described many of the practices being used around the world. Funny enough, he was explicit that he didn’t invent these drains, claiming “no great praise of originality in what is here offered to the public.” Still, I have to admit, after reading his book, I understand why he became the namesake of the drains he made famous. The man had a way with words:</p><p>“The art of removing superfluous water from land must be as ancient as the art of cultivation; and from the time when Noah and his family anxiously watched the subsiding of the waters into their appropriate channels to the present, men must have felt the ill effects of too much water, and adopted means, more or less effective, to remove it.” </p><p>Well before we worried about draining subsurface water to protect buildings and structures, farmers were doing it in one way or another to keep their fields from sogginess that affects the growth of crops and bogs down agricultural equipment. In fact, “tile drain” is another common term for subsurface drains because clay tiles were used to hold the drains open. And there are plenty of fields still drained using clay tiles today. But French pointed out that rocks sometimes work just as well:</p><p>“Providence has so liberally supplied the greater part of New England with stones, that it seems to the most inexperienced person to be a work of supererogation, almost, to manufacture tiles or any other draining material for our farms.”</p><p>He was mostly right, and gravel-filled trenches are used all over the place for simple and non-critical applications. The problem with rocks is that they clog up. You can kind of see how sand migrated into the spaces between the gravel in my demo. Since it’s sand, it’s not really a problem, but if this were a finer-grained soil, it would eventually reduce the drain’s ability to transport water, slowing down the drainage process. Tiles provided the benefit of holding open a clear space for water to flow. Over time, perforated or slotted pipes began to replace tiles for use in drains. You’ve probably seen these before; there are a hundred different styles and materials. Rather than flowing in through the joints between the tiles, the water just comes into the holes in the pipe. But which way should the holes face? Turns out it’s a debate as old as pipes themselves among engineers and contractors, and there are strong opinions on both sides.</p><p>If the holes are on the top, water has to fill the gravel to the top of the pipe before it can get in and be carried away. If the holes are on the bottom, the flow path isn’t smooth, so the water flows slower and is less likely to wash away any soil or debris that gets inside. From my research, it seems like most of the manufacturers recommend holes down so the gravel envelope doesn’t have to be completely saturated before water can enter the pipe. I think, in practice, it’s really not too important, and actually, a lot of perforated pipes you can buy for drainage have holes all the way around so you don’t even have to think about it. That’s the best kind of decision, in my book. But, if it seems counterintuitive to you to orient the holes downward, I can demonstrate it in my model.</p><p>With a pipe in the middle of the gravel layer, I can turn on the rain again. Just like before, water makes its way through the soil toward the drain, and eventually out of the model. Let’s watch that sped up. When the rain is off, the soil continues draining out until it’s no longer saturated. Hopefully it’s clear how beneficial this is. Without that drain, water will eventually dry out of the soil by flowing away or evaporating over time. But getting it out quickly, with a drain, gives it less opportunity to apply pressure to basement walls, freeze against a structure creating long-term movement, swell the soils, or cause rot and corrosion. </p><p>I’m using sand in my model to speed up these simulations, so this envelope of small gravel with a pipe inside is working pretty well to keep the soil in place. But, somewhat inconveniently, most places we want to drain aren’t overlain by playground sand. They have finer-grained soils, including silt and clay. These small stones are holding back the sand, but tinier particles would just flow right through the cracks. That can lead to erosion over time as water dislodges and carries soil particles away through the drain. Watch what happens when I try my French Drain model with large stones between the sand and the outlet. You can see the turbid water coming through the drain, indicating that soil particles are making their way out. And if you watch closely on the right side, you can see where they’re coming from. Eventually, enough sand washes through the rocks to create a sinkhole, and the rest of the water bursts through. Made a HECK of a mess (pardon my French drain). I’ve talked about internal erosion and sinkholes in a previous video, so check that one out if you want more details. This erosion can also result in clogging if the soil particles move into the gravel and pipe. In fact, clogging is the biggest problem with subsurface drains, so properly designed ones usually have some kind of filter.</p><p>The design you’re probably most familiar with if you’ve seen or installed a french drain yourself uses geotextile fabric. These are permeable sheets that have a wide variety of applications: separating different layers of soil or rock, protecting against erosion, adding reinforcement to backfill, and filtering soil particles out of flowing water. A typical french drain design uses geotextile fabric around the gravel envelope to keep the fines from migrating in. It’s sometimes known as a pipe-within-a-pipe. But geotextile has some limitations. It’s easy to damage during installation. It’s pretty much impossible to repair or replace once it’s in place. And it also gets clogged up. It’s just a thin mesh of fibers, after all, so once soil particles get stuck, they can quickly lead to a decrease in permeability and efficiency. But there is another option for filtration, and it’s most commonly used on dams.</p><p>It is hard to overstate the importance of properly filtered drains for dams. If you don’t believe me, take it from the Federal Emergency Management Agency in their 360-page report, Filters for Embankment Dams: Best Practices for Design and Construction. If that’s not enough, try the Bureau of Reclamation in their 400-page report, Drainage for Dams and Associated Structures. A civil engineer could spend an entire career just thinking about subsurface drains, and for good reason. Lots of high-profile dam failures have directly resulted from a lack of drains or ones that weren’t designed well, including the Oroville Spillway incident I mentioned. For embankment dams that are built from compacted soil, any movement of those soil particles can spell demise. And if you think about all the ways that water is terrible for structures, you can imagine how hard it is to design a structure whose literal job is to hold it back. That’s why they use filters of a different design. You can see it in bold right here in this FEMA status report: “It’s the policy of the National Dam Safety Review Board that geotextiles should not be used in locations that are critical to the safety of the dam.”</p><p>Instead, they use sand. Just like the gravel in my demonstration lets the water through while holding back the sand particles, sand can hold back smaller particles of silt and clay, acting as a filter. But it’s a little more complicated than that. Every soil consists of a variety of sizes of particles. I can show that pretty easily, again using sand as an example. I have a collection of sieves with different sizes of holes, each one finer than the one above. I put my sand in at the top. Then give it a little shake (a little razzle-dazzle). And when I open it back up, the sand is all sorted out. If you weigh out the fraction that got caught in each sieve and plot that on a graph, you get something like this: a grain size distribution curve, also called the soil’s gradation. Soils can have a wide variety of gradations. And it’s super important to understand in this case, because before you can design a filter, you have to know what you’re trying to filter out. Once you know the base soil’s grain size distribution, there are a number of engineering methods to find a material that will both allow water to flow while still holding the soil back. And in a lot of cases, that just happens to end up being some variation on the sand we’re used to using in concrete and sandboxes and demonstrations about french drains.</p><p>Actually, for dams, you often can get either the filtration you need or the capacity to let water through, but not both in the same material. So lots of dams use two-stage filters. The first stage filters the base soil material. The second stage filters the first stage, but lets water flow more freely. And then, you put a perforated pipe in the middle to get the water out of the drain as quickly as possible. So they look basically identical to the demonstration I built: sand, then gravel, then pipe.</p><p>As for dealing with the water once it’s out of the ground, there are really just two options. The easiest is to simply release it by gravity to the surface at some low point. But if you don’t have a low point on the surface nearby, the other alternative is to pump it. If you have a basement at your house, there’s a good chance you have a sump, which is just a low spot for drainage to collect, and if you have a sump, it’s a REALLY GOOD idea to have a sump pump, to move that water out and somewhere outside your house.</p><p>Of course, there’s a lot more to this. Dams have all kinds of drainage features depending on their design. Concrete dams often include a gallery or tunnel with vertical drains into the foundation. Embankment dams often feature a large internal drain called a chimney filter to keep water moving through cracks or pores from carrying soil along with it. And it’s not just dams. Plenty of structures, like retaining walls, rely on good subsurface drainage for protection against all the bad things that water does, not to mention their widespread use in agriculture. There are lots of interesting designs and maybe even more proprietary products on the market all trying to accomplish those two main tasks: get the water out without getting the soil out too. In the end, it’s all the same engineering whether you’re trying to protect a multi-million dollar structure or just keep your basement dry. I think Mr. French put it best: </p><p>“Indeed, the importance of this subject of drainage, seems all at once to have found universal acknowledgement throughout our country, not only from agriculturists, but from philosophers and men of general science.”</p><p>I don’t think anyone could reasonably call me a philosopher, but I do love drains, and I hope you agree that, from dams to fields to foundations of houses, they are pretty important.</p><p>French drains are one of those topics that be hard to sell in a pitch meeting, right? No studio executive would be like, “Yes, this is a million dollar idea!” But the thing I love about this channel is that it’s created a passionate community around seemingly mundane things like subsurface drains. TV used to be like that too: something for everyone. I loved the old History and Discovery channel shows. Now it’s all converged into reality shows and reruns, and I’ve found that pretty much everything I watch these days is done by passionate independent producers. If you feel the same way, I have a recommendation for you: The Getaway by my friend Sam at Wendover Productions.</p><p>It’s a gameshow with a hilarious premise, which is that all of the contestants (who are all big YouTubers, by the way) are snitches, but each one thinks they’re the only one. And it just leads to all these very funny situations where everyone is trying to secretly sabotage the contests. Plus the behind-the-scene cuts to the producers trying to keep all the confusion under control are wonderful. It’s such a great twist on a game show, and it’s one of those creative experiments that only works because it’s independently produced. The chaos of it is what makes it great, and that’s why it’s only available on Nebula.</p><p>I talk about Nebula a lot. It’s a streaming service built by and for independent creators, and it’s growing super fast. After the major overhaul of the home page, making it easier to find new stuff to love, we’ve leaned into producing really good original content, like The Getaway; basically allowing your favorite creators to make bigger budget videos without the fear of having it flop on YouTube’s algorithm. That means you get more creative, interesting, and thoughtful videos. My videos go live on Nebula before they come out here, and right now, a subscription is 40% off at the link in the description.</p><p>Plus if you already have a subscription, now you gift one to a friend. We have annual gift cards now. Give someone you love a year’s worth of thoughtful videos, podcasts, and classes from their favorite creators. It’s 40 percent off either way at nebula.tv/practicalengineering for yourself or gift.nebula.tv/practical-engineering for a friend. Thank you for watching, and let me know what you think!</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Please do not attempt to simplify this code (436 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/kubernetes/kubernetes/blob/60c4c2b2521fb454ce69dee737e3eb91a25e0535/pkg/controller/volume/persistentvolume/pv_controller.go</link>
            <guid>41175586</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 21:30:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/kubernetes/kubernetes/blob/60c4c2b2521fb454ce69dee737e3eb91a25e0535/pkg/controller/volume/persistentvolume/pv_controller.go">https://github.com/kubernetes/kubernetes/blob/60c4c2b2521fb454ce69dee737e3eb91a25e0535/pkg/controller/volume/persistentvolume/pv_controller.go</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41175586">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          <nav aria-label="Global">
            <ul>
                <li>
      
      <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;actions&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;actions_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/actions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Actions</p><p>
        Automate any workflow
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;packages&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;packages_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/packages">
      
      <div>
        <p>Packages</p><p>
        Host and manage packages
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;security&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;security_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/security">
      
      <div>
        <p>Security</p><p>
        Find and fix vulnerabilities
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;codespaces&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;codespaces_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/codespaces">
      
      <div>
        <p>Codespaces</p><p>
        Instant dev environments
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_copilot&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_copilot_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/copilot">
      
      <div>
        <p>GitHub Copilot</p><p>
        Write better code with AI
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;code_review&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;code_review_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/code-review">
      
      <div>
        <p>Code review</p><p>
        Manage code changes
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;issues&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;issues_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/issues">
      
      <div>
        <p>Issues</p><p>
        Plan and track work
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;discussions&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;discussions_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/discussions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Discussions</p><p>
        Collaborate outside of code
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
</li>

                  <li>
      
      
</li>

                  <li>
      
      <div>
                <p><span id="resources-explore-heading">Explore</span></p><ul aria-labelledby="resources-explore-heading">
                <li>
  <a target="_blank" data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;learning_pathways&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;learning_pathways_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://resources.github.com/learn/pathways">
      Learning Pathways

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a target="_blank" data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;white_papers_ebooks_webinars&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;white_papers_ebooks_webinars_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://resources.github.com/">
      White papers, Ebooks, Webinars

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;customer_stories&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;customer_stories_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/customer-stories">
      Customer Stories

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a target="_blank" data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;partners&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;partners_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://partner.github.com/">
      Partners

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
</li>


                <li>
      
      <div>
          <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_sponsors&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;open_source&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_sponsors_link_open_source_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/sponsors">
      
      <div>
        <p>GitHub Sponsors</p><p>
        Fund open source developers
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
          <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;the_readme_project&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;open_source&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;the_readme_project_link_open_source_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/readme">
      
      <div>
        <p>The ReadME Project</p><p>
        GitHub community articles
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
          
      </div>
</li>


                <li>
      
      <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;enterprise_platform&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;enterprise&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;enterprise_platform_link_enterprise_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/enterprise">
      
      <div>
        <p>Enterprise platform</p><p>
        AI-powered developer platform
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
</li>


                <li>
    <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;pricing&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;global&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;pricing_link_global_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/pricing">Pricing</a>
</li>

            </ul>
          </nav>

        <div>
                


<qbsearch-input data-scope="repo:kubernetes/kubernetes" data-custom-scopes-path="/search/custom_scopes" data-delete-custom-scopes-csrf="W_9cKzaBVObLcYkHVY1kdRD3QgD_wUef8TmL0FqYy_xAdRqYXFUsiy7qKKOH7Eb7r1RW2bhvQDzWlnETi1vSKw" data-max-custom-scopes="10" data-header-redesign-enabled="false" data-initial-value="" data-blackbird-suggestions-path="/search/suggestions" data-jump-to-suggestions-path="/_graphql/GetSuggestedNavigationDestinations" data-current-repository="kubernetes/kubernetes" data-current-org="kubernetes" data-current-owner="" data-logged-in="false" data-copilot-chat-enabled="false" data-nl-search-enabled="false">
  <div data-modal-dialog-overlay="" data-action="click:qbsearch-input#searchInputContainerClicked">
  <modal-dialog data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleClose" data-target="qbsearch-input.searchSuggestionsDialog" role="dialog" id="search-suggestions-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="search-suggestions-dialog-header" data-view-component="true">
      <h2 id="search-suggestions-dialog-header">Search code, repositories, users, issues, pull requests...</h2>
    
</modal-dialog></div>
  
  <div>
    
<dialog-helper>
  <dialog data-target="qbsearch-input.feedbackDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" id="feedback-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="feedback-dialog-title" aria-describedby="feedback-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="feedback-dialog-title">
        Provide feedback
      </h2>
        
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="feedback-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</dialog></dialog-helper>

    <custom-scopes data-target="qbsearch-input.customScopesManager">
    
<dialog-helper>
  <dialog data-target="custom-scopes.customScopesModalDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" id="custom-scopes-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="custom-scopes-dialog-title" aria-describedby="custom-scopes-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        Saved searches
      </h2>
        <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-description">Use saved searches to filter your results more quickly</h2>
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</dialog></dialog-helper>
    </custom-scopes>
  </div>
</qbsearch-input>

            

              <p><a href="https://github.com/signup?ref_cta=Sign+up&amp;ref_loc=header+logged+out&amp;ref_page=%2F%3Cuser-name%3E%2F%3Crepo-name%3E%2Fblob%2Fshow&amp;source=header-repo&amp;source_repo=kubernetes%2Fkubernetes" data-hydro-click="{&quot;event_type&quot;:&quot;authentication.click&quot;,&quot;payload&quot;:{&quot;location_in_page&quot;:&quot;site header menu&quot;,&quot;repository_id&quot;:null,&quot;auth_type&quot;:&quot;SIGN_UP&quot;,&quot;originating_url&quot;:&quot;https://github.com/kubernetes/kubernetes/blob/60c4c2b2521fb454ce69dee737e3eb91a25e0535/pkg/controller/volume/persistentvolume/pv_controller.go&quot;,&quot;user_id&quot;:null}}" data-hydro-click-hmac="564c48d6a3754f7a40049ef9e46bb8cca7808a986c548ee089aa5a617b2f103f" data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Sign up&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to sign up for account&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_page:/<user-name>/<repo-name>/blob/show;ref_cta:Sign up;ref_loc:header logged out&quot;}">
                Sign up
              </a>
        </p></div>
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Carvings at Gobekli Tepe may be oldest calendar (140 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1751696X.2024.2373876#abstract</link>
            <guid>41174979</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 20:30:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1751696X.2024.2373876#abstract">https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1751696X.2024.2373876#abstract</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41174979">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1751696X.2024.2373876#abstract: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to let go: Jake's life ends as his daughter's begins (108 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://jakeseliger.com/2024/08/06/how-to-let-go-one-life-ends-while-another-begins/</link>
            <guid>41174621</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 19:53:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://jakeseliger.com/2024/08/06/how-to-let-go-one-life-ends-while-another-begins/">https://jakeseliger.com/2024/08/06/how-to-let-go-one-life-ends-while-another-begins/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41174621">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
			<form action="https://subscribe.wordpress.com" method="post" accept-charset="utf-8" data-blog="221111" data-post_access_level="everybody" id="subscribe-blog">
				<p>Enter your email address to subscribe to this blog and receive notifications of new posts by email.</p>
				<p id="subscribe-email">
					<label id="subscribe-field-label" for="subscribe-field">
						Email Address:					</label>

									</p>

				
			</form>
							<p>
					Join 3,726 other subscribers				</p>
						</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[YC is doing a first ever Fall batch – applications due by 8/27 (178 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/yc-fall-2024#</link>
            <guid>41174281</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 19:21:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/yc-fall-2024#">https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/yc-fall-2024#</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41174281">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>In response to overwhelming demand, we are running a YC batch this fall. Applications are <a href="https://ycombinator.com/apply">now open</a>. The Fall 2024 batch will begin in San Francisco on Sunday, 9/29, and Demo Day will be in early December. We are excited to work with founders who want to begin YC right away rather than wait for the W25 batch.</p><p>In addition to YC’s standard deal investment of $500,000, YC companies have access to dedicated GPU clusters from <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/08/01/google-cloud-now-has-a-dedicated-cluster-of-nvidia-gpus-for-y-combinator-startups/">Google Cloud Platform</a> and <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/11/07/microsoft-partners-with-vcs-to-give-startups-free-ai-chip-access/">Microsoft Azure</a> along with exclusive credits worth over $1M from:</p><ul><li>Microsoft for startups</li><li>AWS AI/ML</li><li>Google Cloud</li><li>Open AI</li><li>Replicate</li><li>Scale AI</li><li>and many more</li></ul><figure><iframe width="200" height="113" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/9jOYX2pgTZk?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="" title="Apply To The F24 Batch!"></iframe></figure><div><p>This is a special moment to start a startup, and we want to be here to serve founders who know today is the day to take the plunge. To apply, please <a href="https://ycombinator.com/apply">submit an application</a> by Tuesday, 8/27 @ 9PM PT. </p><p>---</p></div><h2 id="faq">FAQ<br></h2><div><p><strong>Why is YC doing a fall batch?</strong><br>The opportunity for new startups is only growing, especially given the latest results we are seeing from the most recent YC batches where in aggregate companies are growing revenue by 4X or more in a single quarter during the YC batch itself.</p><p>The group partners got together and agreed it was time to grow the pie and do our first-ever Fall batch.</p></div><p><strong>Who is this for?</strong><br>There’s no special vertical focus or requirement for this batch. Like any other YC batch, we’re looking for great founders working on technology of all kinds that solve real problems for every market in the world. </p><p><strong>What are the terms of YC's investment?</strong><br>We invest on standard terms as described <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/deal">here</a>.</p><p><strong>Will the fall batch be different from the summer or winter batches?</strong><br>The fall batch is likely to have fewer companies than our Summer and Winter batches, but in every other respect it will be a “normal” batch.</p><p><strong>If I don't get selected for F24, will I be able to apply for W25?</strong><br>Yes, you will be able to apply for W25! Applications for the winter batch will open in early October and will be due late October. </p><p><strong>Will you do a new fall batch next year?</strong><br>YC is always updating how we do things because we want to serve founders to the best of our ability. We are considering adding new batches during the year and expect to have more to announce later in the year.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How not to say the wrong thing (2013) (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.latimes.com/nation/la-oe-0407-silk-ring-theory-20130407-story.html</link>
            <guid>41174014</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 18:54:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.latimes.com/nation/la-oe-0407-silk-ring-theory-20130407-story.html">https://www.latimes.com/nation/la-oe-0407-silk-ring-theory-20130407-story.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41174014">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-element="story-body" data-subscriber-content=""> <p>When Susan had breast cancer, we heard a lot of lame remarks, but our favorite came from one of Susan’s colleagues. She wanted, she needed, to visit Susan after the surgery, but Susan didn’t feel like having visitors, and she said so. Her colleague’s response? “This isn’t just about you.”</p><p>“It’s not?” Susan wondered. “My breast cancer is not about me? It’s about you?”<img src="https://articles.latimes.com/images/pixel.gif" alt="" width="1" height="1"></p><p>The same theme came up again when our friend Katie had a brain aneurysm. She was in intensive care for a long time and finally got out and into a step-down unit. She was no longer covered with tubes and lines and monitors, but she was still in rough shape. A friend came and saw her and then stepped into the hall with Katie’s husband, Pat. “I wasn’t prepared for this,” she told him. “I don’t know if I can handle it.”</p><p><b><a href="https://www.facebook.com/latimes" target="_blank">See more of our top stories on Facebook &gt;&gt;</a></b></p><p>This woman loves Katie, and she said what she did because the sight of Katie in this condition moved her so deeply. But it was the wrong thing to say. And it was wrong in the same way Susan’s colleague’s remark was wrong.</p><p>Susan has since developed a simple technique to help people avoid this mistake. It works for all kinds of crises: medical, legal, financial, romantic, even existential. She calls it the Ring Theory.</p><p>Draw a circle. This is the center ring. In it, put the name of the person at the center of the current trauma. For Katie’s aneurysm, that’s Katie. Now draw a larger circle around the first one. In that ring put the name of the person next closest to the trauma. In the case of Katie’s aneurysm, that was Katie’s husband, Pat. Repeat the process as many times as you need to. In each larger ring put the next closest people. Parents and children before more distant relatives. Intimate friends in smaller rings, less intimate friends in larger ones. When you are done you have a Kvetching Order. One of Susan’s patients found it useful to tape it to her refrigerator.</p><p>Here are the rules. The person in the center ring can say anything she wants to anyone, anywhere. She can kvetch and complain and whine and moan and curse the heavens and say, “Life is unfair” and “Why me?” That’s the one payoff for being in the center ring.</p><p>Everyone else can say those things too, but only to people in larger rings.</p><p>When you are talking to a person in a ring smaller than yours, someone closer to the center of the crisis, the goal is to help. Listening is often more helpful than talking. But if you’re going to open your mouth, ask yourself if what you are about to say is likely to provide comfort and support. If it isn’t, don’t say it. Don’t, for example, give advice. People who are suffering from trauma don’t need advice. They need comfort and support. So say, “I’m sorry” or “This must really be hard for you” or “Can I bring you a pot roast?” Don’t say, “You should hear what happened to me” or “Here’s what I would do if I were you.” And don’t say, “This is really bringing me down.”</p><p>If you want to scream or cry or complain, if you want to tell someone how shocked you are or how icky you feel, or whine about how it reminds you of all the terrible things that have happened to you lately, that’s fine. It’s a perfectly normal response. Just do it to someone in a bigger ring.</p><p>Comfort IN, dump OUT.</p><p><b><a href="https://www.latimes.com/popular/" target="_blank">See the most-read stories this hour &gt;&gt;</a></b></p><p>There was nothing wrong with Katie’s friend saying she was not prepared for how horrible Katie looked, or even that she didn’t think she could handle it. The mistake was that she said those things to Pat. She dumped IN.</p><p>Complaining to someone in a smaller ring than yours doesn’t do either of you any good. On the other hand, being supportive to her principal caregiver may be the best thing you can do for the patient.</p><p>Most of us know this. Almost nobody would complain to the patient about how rotten she looks. Almost no one would say that looking at her makes them think of the fragility of life and their own closeness to death. In other words, we know enough not to dump into the center ring. Ring Theory merely expands that intuition and makes it more concrete: Don’t just avoid dumping into the center ring, avoid dumping into any ring smaller than your own.</p><p>Remember, you can say whatever you want if you just wait until you’re talking to someone in a larger ring than yours.</p><p>And don’t worry. You’ll get your turn in the center ring. You can count on that.</p><p><i>Susan Silk is a clinical psychologist. Barry Goldman is an arbitrator and mediator and the author of “The Science of Settlement: Ideas for Negotiators.”</i></p><p><b>MORE FROM OPINION</b></p><p><b><a href="https://www.latimes.com/opinion/op-ed/la-oe-hemenway-guns-20150423-story.html#nt=outfit" target="_blank">There’s scientific consensus on guns -- and the NRA won’t like it</a></b></p><p><b><a href="https://www.latimes.com/opinion/livable-city/la-ol-automated-cars-mobility-plan-2035-parking-20151202-story.html#nt=outfit" target="_blank">How self-driving cars can transform Los Angeles, starting with its parking</a></b></p><p><b><a href="https://www.latimes.com/opinion/op-ed/la-oe-aubry-kaplan-black-battle-to-matter-20151129-story.html" target="_blank">The dehumanizing disregard I experienced at University of Redlands shows real equality has a ways to go</a></b></p><div data-list-id="0000018c-4558-d70f-adfc-c77d3e520002" data-module-id="0000018c-4558-d70f-adfc-c77d3e520002" data-click="enhancement" data-align-center="">  <p data-element="element-header" data-click="liZZListTitleCTA">  <h3 data-element="element-header-title" data-counter="3">More to Read </h3>  </p>      </div> </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>