<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 00:00:10 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[United Airlines inspections find loose bolts on several 737 Max 9 aircraft (129 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cnbc.com/2024/01/08/united-airlines-737-max-9-inspections-turn-up-loose-bolts.html</link>
            <guid>38918310</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 21:20:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/01/08/united-airlines-737-max-9-inspections-turn-up-loose-bolts.html">https://www.cnbc.com/2024/01/08/united-airlines-737-max-9-inspections-turn-up-loose-bolts.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38918310">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="RegularArticle-ArticleBody-6" data-module="ArticleBody" data-test="articleBody-2" data-analytics="RegularArticle-articleBody-6-2"><div id="ArticleBody-InlineImage-106807958" data-test="InlineImage"><p>A United Airlines Boeing 737 Max 9 aircraft lands at San Francisco International Airport in California on March 13, 2019.</p><p>Justin Sullivan | Getty Images</p></div><div><p><span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="RegularArticle-QuoteInBody-1"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/UAL/">United Airlines</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span> said Monday that it has found loose bolts on door plugs of several <span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="RegularArticle-QuoteInBody-2"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/BA/">Boeing</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span> 737 Max 9 planes during inspections spurred when a panel of that type <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/01/06/boeing-737-max-9-grounding-after-alaska-airlines-door-blows-midflight.html">blew out</a> during an <span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="RegularArticle-QuoteInBody-4"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/ALK/">Alaska Airlines</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span> flight using that type of aircraft last week.</p><p>The Federal Aviation Administration on Saturday grounded dozens of 737 Max 9s after the panel blew out midflight on Alaska Flight 1282, calling for inspections.</p><p>United has 79 of the Max 9 planes in its fleet and is the biggest operator of the jet model.</p><p>"Since we began preliminary inspections on Saturday, we have found instances that appear to relate to installation issues in the door plug — for example, bolts that needed additional tightening," United said in a statement. "These findings will be remedied by our Tech Ops team to safely return the aircraft to service."</p><p>Plane manufacturer Boeing said earlier Monday it <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/01/08/boeing-737-max-9-inspection-instructions-alaska-air-incident.html">issued instructions</a> to airlines to conduct the inspections of the Max 9s in their fleets. United had begun some preliminary inspection work in the past few days.</p><p>"We are committed to ensuring every Boeing airplane meets design specifications and the highest safety and quality standards," Boeing said in a statement Monday evening. "We regret the impact this has had on our customers and their passengers."</p><p>No one was seriously injured in the accident aboard the Alaska Airlines flight, though the blown-out panel produced a force so violent that some headrests and seatbacks were ripped from the cabin and the cockpit door was flung open, according to initial details of a federal safety investigation. No passengers were seated in the two seats next to the panel.</p><p>The National Transportation Safety Board said the accident would have been worse at cruising altitude when passengers and crews are walking around the cabin.</p><p>But the accident places <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/01/07/boeing-737-max-renewed-scrutiny.html">fresh scrutiny</a> on Boeing, which has spent years trying to clean up a host of quality defects, while also ramping up aircraft production, including of the 737 Max. CEO Dave Calhoun has spent months trying to assure airlines, investors and financial analysts that the company is improving its supply chain and working to resolve its quality problems.</p><p>Calhoun canceled a company leadership summit this week and plans to hold an all-employee call on Tuesday.</p><p>Alaska Airlines, which is set to inspect its fleet of more than 60 737 Max 9s, didn't immediately comment on whether it, too, has found loose bolts.</p><p>The FAA declined to comment on United's findings. Boeing didn't immediately respond to CNBC's request for comment.</p><div><p>The 737 Max is Boeing's best-selling aircraft, with more than 4,000 orders to fill. However, the more common Max 8, which is not affected by the grounding, makes up the majority of those orders.</p><p><em><strong>Don't miss these stories from CNBC PRO:</strong></em></p></div><ul><li><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/01/03/wall-street-loves-this-stock-so-much-that-5-analysts-named-it-a-top-pick-in-one-day.html"><em>There's one stock Wall Street loves so much for 2024 that five analysts in one day picked it as their favorite</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/01/06/morgan-stanley-names-its-top-stocks-for-2024-including-this-streaming-giant.html"><em>Morgan Stanley names its top stocks for 2024, including this streaming giant</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/01/07/investing-tips-from-warren-buffett-to-start-the-new-year-on-the-right-foot.html"><em>Investing tips from Warren Buffett to start the new year on the right foot</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/01/03/goldman-sees-50percent-gain-ahead-for-this-chinese-ev-stock-initiates-with-buy-rating.html"><em>Goldman sees a 50% gain ahead for this Chinese electric vehicle stock, initiates with buy rating</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/01/05/ritholtzs-josh-brown-stock-picks-shares-twice-as-cheap-as-the-sp-500.html"><em>'Twice as cheap': These stocks' discount to the S&amp;P 500 is double its average, Ritholtz's Brown says</em></a></li></ul></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Duolingo Cuts 10% of Contractors as It Uses More AI to Create App Content (187 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2024-01-08/duolingo-cuts-10-of-contractors-in-move-to-greater-use-of-ai</link>
            <guid>38918279</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 21:18:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2024-01-08/duolingo-cuts-10-of-contractors-in-move-to-greater-use-of-ai">https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2024-01-08/duolingo-cuts-10-of-contractors-in-move-to-greater-use-of-ai</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38918279">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section>
    <section>
        <h3>Why did this happen?</h3>
        <p>Please make sure your browser supports JavaScript and cookies and that you are not
            blocking them from loading.
            For more information you can review our <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/notices/tos">Terms of
                Service</a> and <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/notices/tos">Cookie Policy</a>.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
        <h3>Need Help?</h3>
        <p>For inquiries related to this message please <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/feedback">contact
            our support team</a> and provide the reference ID below.</p>
        <p>Block reference ID:</p>
    </section>
</section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[United finds loose bolts on plug doors during 737 Max 9 inspections (193 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://theaircurrent.com/feed/dispatches/united-finds-loose-bolts-on-plug-doors-during-737-max-9-inspections/</link>
            <guid>38917820</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 20:43:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://theaircurrent.com/feed/dispatches/united-finds-loose-bolts-on-plug-doors-during-737-max-9-inspections/">https://theaircurrent.com/feed/dispatches/united-finds-loose-bolts-on-plug-doors-during-737-max-9-inspections/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38917820">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
				<main>
		<article>
						<div>
																										<p><strong><em>Air safety reporting by The Air Current is provided without a subscription as a public service. Please</em> <a href="https://theaircurrent.memberful.com/join/?referrer=https%3A%2F%2Ftheaircurrent.com%2F">subscribe</a> to <em>gain full access to our all scoops, in-depth reporting and analyses.</em></strong></p>
<p>United Airlines has found loose bolts and other parts on 737 Max 9 plug doors as it inspects its fleet of Boeing jets following the Friday rapid depressurization aboard an Alaska Airlines jet of the same make, according to three people familiar with the findings.</p>
<p>The discrepant bolts and other parts on the plug doors have been found on at least five aircraft, one of the people told <em>The Air Current</em>.</p>
<p><span>A Boeing representative did not immediately respond to a request for comment. A spokeswoman for the Federal Aviation Administration declined to comment on the United findings, and pointed to the agency’s </span><a href="https://www.faa.gov/newsroom/updates-grounding-boeing-737-max-9-aircraft"><span>earlier statements</span></a><span>.</span></p>

<p><span>United confirmed the findings in a statement, saying, “Since we began preliminary inspections on Saturday, we have found instances that appear to relate to installation issues in the door plug – for example, bolts that needed additional tightening. These findings will be remedied by our Tech Ops team to safely return the aircraft to service.”</span></p>
<p><span>The findings aboard the five United aircraft will likely significantly widen the fall-out from the grounding, intensifying the focus on Boeing and Spirit AeroSystems. The pair together is responsible for the assembly, installation and quality checks of the aircraft structure.</span></p>
<p><b><i>Related: </i></b><a href="https://theaircurrent.com/industry-strategy/boeing-spirit-reintegration-ramp-up-special-report/"><b><i>Inside the strained union of Boeing and Spirit AeroSystems</i></b></a></p>
<p><span>Across the five aircraft, there is little consistency in the locations of the errant parts, according to documents reviewed by </span><i><span>The Air Current.</span></i><span> In one instance, United found that the bolts that affix the lower hinge of the plug door were not fully seated, and that the washers on the bolts could “spin”.&nbsp;</span></p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="ltr" lang="en">Following <a href="https://twitter.com/jonostrower?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@jonostrower</a>‘s scoop on United finding 737-9s with loose door plug screws, a source sent this image of one of the door plug’s lower hinge bracket with a note that 2 screws are not screwed all the way in. <a href="https://t.co/sz1d997PdL">https://t.co/sz1d997PdL</a> <a href="https://t.co/d6hgHAEb2u">pic.twitter.com/d6hgHAEb2u</a></p>
<p>— Edward Russell (@ByERussell) <a href="https://twitter.com/ByERussell/status/1744460136855294106?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 8, 2024</a></p></blockquote>

<p><span>Another aircraft was found to have loose bolts on the upper forward guide fitting on the plug and another on the forward guide roller that is an attachment point to the fuselage on the door frame. Additionally, screws that are part of the lower hinge bracket at the bottom of the plug on another aircraft were found to not be fully screwed in.</span></p>
<p><span>The five aircraft were delivered to United between November 2022 and September 2023, according to ch-aviation, and would likely not have been through a heavy maintenance C check that occurs every 4,000 to 6,000 hours or two to three years.</span></p>
<p><span>United is the only other U.S. airline to fly the 737 Max 9 and is the largest operator with 79 in its fleet. Alaska operates 65.</span></p>
<p><span>Boeing earlier Monday confirmed that it had formally distributed a Multi-Operator Message (MOM) to 737 Max 9 operators, prescribing the specific inspection criteria that would satisfy the <a href="https://theaircurrent.com/feed/dispatches/faa-orders-temporary-grounding-of-boeing-737-max-9-fleet/">emergency airworthiness directive</a> issued by the FAA on January 6, a day after the Alaska accident.</span></p>
<p><span>Alaska on Monday morning </span><a href="https://news.alaskaair.com/alaska-airlines/operations/as-1282/"><span>said</span></a><span> that before inspections could begin, the FAA would need to approve operators’ inspection processes to ensure compliance, and that the airline would need to develop detailed inspection instructions and processes for its maintenance technicians to follow. Alaska said that it canceled roughly 140 flights for Monday due to the 737 Max 9 grounding.</span></p>
<p><span>NTSB investigators announced late Sunday that they had recovered the plug that violently separated from the Alaska flight at 16,000 feet. No one was hurt in the accident.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>The board has not released any specific findings related to the door or said whether the accident was in any way caused by discrepancies in the plug installation.</span></p>
<p><i><span>Elan Head and Howard Slutsken also contributed to this article.</span></i></p>
									</div><!-- .entry-content -->
						<!-- .entry-footer -->
					</article><!-- #post-x -->
	</main><!-- .site-main -->
				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cells across the body talk to each other about aging (120 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.quantamagazine.org/cells-across-the-body-talk-to-each-other-about-aging-20240108/</link>
            <guid>38917749</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 20:37:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/cells-across-the-body-talk-to-each-other-about-aging-20240108/">https://www.quantamagazine.org/cells-across-the-body-talk-to-each-other-about-aging-20240108/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38917749">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Now, Dillin and his team have expanded that finding by discovering new details about how mitochondria in the brain communicate with cells across the worm’s body to extend life.</p>
<p>First, he had to understand why damage to the brain’s mitochondria could possibly have a beneficial effect on the organism. A mitochondrion’s process for generating energy requires exceedingly complex molecular machinery with dozens of different protein parts. When things go awry, such as when some components are missing or misfolded, mitochondria activate a stress response, known as the unfolded protein response, which delivers repair enzymes to help the complexes assemble properly and restore mitochondrial function. In this way, the unfolded protein response keeps cells healthy.</p>
<p>Dillin expected this process to unfold only inside the neurons with damaged mitochondria. Yet he observed that cells in other tissues of the worm’s body also turned on repair responses even though their mitochondria were intact.</p>

<p>It’s this repair activity that helped the worms live longer. Like taking a car to a mechanic regularly, the unfolded protein response seemed to keep cells in good running order and function as anti-aging detailing. What remained mysterious was how this unfolded protein response was communicated to the rest of the organism.</p>
<p>After some investigation, Dillin’s team discovered that the mitochondria in stressed neurons were using vesicles — bubblelike containers that move materials around the cell or between cells — to carry a signal called Wnt beyond the nerve cells to other cells in the body. Biologists already knew that Wnt plays a role in setting up the body pattern during early embryonic development, during which it also triggers repair processes like the unfolded protein response. Still, how could Wnt signaling, when turned on in an adult, avoid activating the embryonic program?</p>
<p>Dillin suspected that there had to be another signal that Wnt interacted with. After further work, the researchers discovered that a gene expressed in the mitochondria of the germline — and in no other mitochondria — can interrupt Wnt’s developmental processes. That result suggested to him that <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.08.21.554217v2">germline cells play critical roles</a> in relaying the Wnt signal between the nervous system and tissues throughout the rest of the body.</p>
<p>“The&nbsp;germline is absolutely essential&nbsp;for this,” Dillin said. It isn’t clear, however, whether the germline mitochondria act as amplifiers, receiving the signal from the brain’s mitochondria and transmitting it to other tissues, or if the receiving tissues are “listening” for signals from both sources.</p>
<p>Either way, the strength of the germline signal regulates the organism’s life span, Dillin said. As a worm ages, the quality of its eggs or sperm declines — what we refer to as the ticking of a biological clock. The decline is also reflected in the germ cells’ changing ability to transmit signals from the brain’s mitochondria, he suggested. As the worm grows older, its germline transmits the repair signal less effectively, and so its body declines, too.</p>

<p>Scientists don’t yet know whether these findings apply to humans and how we age. Still, the hypothesis makes sense from a broader evolutionary standpoint, Dillin said. As long as the germ cells are healthy, they send pro-survival signals to ensure that their host organism survives to reproduce. But as the quality of the germ cells declines, there is no evolutionary reason to keep extending life span further; from evolution’s perspective, life exists to reproduce itself.</p>
<p>The fact that mitochondria can talk among themselves might seem somewhat alarming, but there is an explanation. Long ago, mitochondria were free-living bacteria that joined forces with another type of primitive cell to work together in what became our modern complex cells. So, their ability to communicate is probably a relic from the free-living bacterial ancestor of mitochondria.</p>
<p>“This little thing that’s been ticking inside of cells for billions of years still retains its bacterial origins,” Dillin said. And if his research in worms holds up in more complex organisms like humans, it’s possible that your mitochondria are talking right now about your age.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The curious case of the Raspberry Pi in the network closet (2019) (216 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.haschek.at/2019/the-curious-case-of-the-RasPi-in-our-network.html</link>
            <guid>38917175</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 19:54:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.haschek.at/2019/the-curious-case-of-the-RasPi-in-our-network.html">https://blog.haschek.at/2019/the-curious-case-of-the-RasPi-in-our-network.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38917175">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
                    <div id="post-wrapper">
                            <p>Last week I got a message from my dad (who works with me at a client) with an image attached.</p>
<figure><img loading="lazy" src="https://pictshare.net/hdkhikv83m.png"><figcaption>Message from dad</figcaption></figure>
<p>I asked him to unplug it, store it in a safe location, take photos of all parts and to make an image from the SD card (since I mostly work remote). I have worked on many Raspberry Pi projects and I felt confident I could find out what it does.</p>
<p>At this point nobody thought it was going to be malicious, more like one of our staffers was playing around with something.</p>
<h2>The parts</h2>
<p>There were 3 parts: </p>
<ul>
<li>A Raspberry Pi b first generation</li>
<li>a mysterious USB dongle</li>
<li>a 16GB sd card (a fast one)</li>
</ul>
<figure><img loading="lazy" src="https://pictshare.net/gfss00puet.jpg"><figcaption>USB dongle and SD card</figcaption></figure>
<h2>First thing to do: Ask everybody who can access this network closet</h2>
<p>The number of people who can access this small cabinet is very limited. Only 4 people have a key for this room:</p>
<ol>
<li>The manager</li>
<li>The groundskeeper</li>
<li>My co-worker</li>
<li>Me</li>
</ol>
<p>None of them knew anything about this so I asked my IT colleagues and they were as baffled as I was. I heard of people getting paid to put things like this in places they shouldn't and for this reason I was very interested in finding out what it actually does.</p>
<h2>What is that USB dongle though?</h2>
<p>To help me solve this mistery <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/sysadmin/comments/9xveq5/rogue_raspberrypi_found_in_network_closet_need/">I asked reddit</a> and surely enough they identified the dongle as a microprocessor, almost as powerful as the Rasberry Pi itself: the <a href="https://wiki.makerdiary.com/nrf52832-mdk/">nRF52832-MDK</a>. A very powerful wifi, bluetooth and RFID reader.</p>
<figure><img loading="lazy" src="https://pictshare.net/lrc3fnqrl7.jpg"><figcaption>The nRF52832-MDK usb dongle</figcaption></figure>
<p>This was - no doubt - to give the old Raspberry Pi a wifi and bluetooth connection. Great so now this thing has wifi too..</p>
<h2>Time to dissect the SD card image</h2>
<p>The SD card has a few partitions. Most ext4 (linux) and one fat16 (boot)</p>
<figure><img loading="lazy" src="https://pictshare.net/htpg3y9xhu.png"><figcaption>GParted view of the image</figcaption></figure>
<p>Great, time to mount it.</p>
<p>My debian box told me the first big clue: It's a resin installation</p>
<figure><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.pictshare.net/wt9hqp.png"><figcaption>Resin partitions on the SD Card</figcaption></figure>
<h2>WTF is Resin?</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.balena.io/">Resin (now renamed to Balena)</a> is a paid <a href="https://www.balena.io/what-is-balena">IOT web service</a> where you can generate images for IOT devices, deploy those devices and get updates and data from and to resin.</p>
<p>Resin also installs a VPN on the device so the collected data is transferred securely. Obviously this device was meant to be picked up again since it leaves a trail as the service is a paid one.</p>
<h2>Closer look at the partitions</h2>
<p>First partition is called <strong>"resin-boot"</strong> </p>
<figure><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.pictshare.net/n7rq00.png"></figure>
<p>See something that catches your eye? We got a <code>config.json</code>. Quick jackpot?</p>
<figure><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.pictshare.net/y9tq3d93ru.png"><figcaption>config.json on the resin-boot partition</figcaption></figure>
<p>What we can extract from this file:</p>
<ol>
<li>The application deployed to this resin device is called <strong>"logger"</strong>. Not a good sign</li>
<li>We got a <strong>username</strong>. This seems to be the username for the resin account associated with this device</li>
<li>Confirmation that the device used a <strong>VPN</strong> via Port 443</li>
<li>A registration date. It was registered (or first deployed or set up?) on <strong>May 13th 2018</strong></li>
</ol>
<h3>About that username..</h3>
<p>When I googled the username found in the config.json file I found a person in the same town where this Pi was found. The company then checked their records for this person but found nothing.</p>
<p>Oddly enough I found a website from 2001 where parents of "gifted children" write articles about them and for some reason sign those articles with their home address and phone numbers. So I have a name and the address of this whole family.</p>
<figure><img loading="lazy" src="https://pictshare.net/800/9drvd1.jpg"><figcaption>Not the actual site but a similar one</figcaption></figure>
<p>This could be a wrong lead as usernames tend to be used by multiple people but let's just keep that name in mind.</p>
<h3>resin-data</h3>
<p>The data directory didn't have any data stored (as in: <em>collected data</em>) but there was a nodejs app which was heavily obfuscated and to this day I can't tell exactly what it was doing. It seems to talk via a serial connection to the dongle but I can't extract what data is actually collected. I can only assume that it collected movement profiles of bluetooth and wifi devices in the area (around the Managers office) and maybe raw wifi packets.</p>
<p>But I found something much more interesting: a <code>LICENSE.md</code> file</p>
<figure><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.pictshare.net/7ora0e.png"><figcaption>Screenshot of the LICENSE.md file</figcaption></figure>
<p>Odd.. Why would this nodejs app include a confidential piece of software? I googled the company from the copyright header and guess what? </p>
<h2>The guy from the username I found in the config file is a part owner</h2>
<p>It is beyond me why a co-founder of a company would distribute these devices around town but well..</p>
<hr>
<h2>Getting the attackers home address</h2>
<p>Another very interesting thing I found was a file on the third partition (<code>resin-state</code>) in the path <code>/root-overlay/etc/NetworkManager/system-connections/</code>. The file is called <strong>resin-wifi-01</strong> and guess what it contains?</p>
<figure><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.pictshare.net/8vdh9k.png"></figure>
<p>It contains the wifi credentials to the wifi that was used to set the device up (or to test it). Definitely not the wifi of the company. And what do we do, when we want to find out a location associated with a wifi name? We go to wigle.net, enter the SSID (=wifi name) and it tells us where on the world it is found.</p>
<figure><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.pictshare.net/6ztf78.png"><figcaption>not the actual name and not the actual location</figcaption></figure>
<p>And guess what? The address we found of that gifted persons parents? <strong>That's exactly where our Pi was set up</strong> according to Wigle.net</p>
<h2>Aftermath</h2>
<h2>How and when did the Pi even get there?</h2>
<p>I checked the DNS logs and found the exact date and time when the Pi was first seen in the network. I checked the RADIUS logs to see which employee was at the premises at that time and I saw multiple error messages that a deactivated account tried to connect to wifi.</p>
<p>That deactivated account belongs to an ex employee who (for some reason) made a deal with management that he could still have a key for a few months until he moved all his stuff out of the building (don't ask..).</p>
<h2>What now</h2>
<p>Legal has taken over, I did my part and the rest is over my pay grade.</p>
<p>For me it was a very interesting challenge and I'd like to thank every person on reddit who helped me with one piece of the puzzle.</p>
                            </div></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Solver Performance: 1989 vs. 2024 (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.solvermax.com/blog/solver-performance-1989-vs-2024</link>
            <guid>38916212</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 18:43:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.solvermax.com/blog/solver-performance-1989-vs-2024">https://www.solvermax.com/blog/solver-performance-1989-vs-2024</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38916212">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p>5 January 2024</p>
<p><img title="Blue steps" src="https://www.solvermax.com/images/blog/crossword/blue-steps.png" alt="Blue steps" width="300" height="180"></p>
<p>In our <a title="Optimal but not practical - Virtual machine" href="https://www.solvermax.com/blog/optimal-but-not-practical-virtual-machine">previous article</a>, we solved a mixed integer linear program (MILP) model with more than 8 million binary variables. Not long ago, a model of that size would have been unsolvable. Yet, once we had a computer with sufficient memory, the model was solved to optimality by an open source solver in 3 hours.</p>
<p>Of course, not all large models are solvable – even some small models are unsolvable, or at least hard to solve. Nonetheless, modern solvers, in association with modern computers, enable us to solve models that not-so-long-ago were beyond our capabilities.</p>
<p>In our next article, we'll look to compile crosswords using a MILP model. We're not the first to consider using a MILP model to compile crosswords. An article published in 1989 reported attempts to compile small crosswords using MILP models. The article's conclusion was very pessimistic, noting that:</p>
<blockquote><p>...the prospects of using integer programming for any type of puzzle of realistic size and with a substantial lexicon remain bleak.</p><span>Wilson, 1989, <a title="Crossword compilation using integer programming" href="https://academic.oup.com/comjnl/article-pdf/32/3/273/947308/320273.pdf">Crossword compilation using integer programming</a></span></blockquote>
<p>The problems Wilson encountered were insufficient computer memory and the time needed to solve a very small crossword grid, even though he was using a then state-of-the-art million dollar superminicomputer.</p>
<p>But a lot has changed in the 35 years since 1989. Computer hardware is many times faster, and memory capacity has increased enormously. In addition, optimization solver software has improved by orders of magnitude. Models that were difficult to solve in 1989 are now trivial. Solutions that were impossible to find in 1989 may now be within reach.</p>
<p>In this article, we estimate the magnitude of speed improvement for optimization solvers and computer hardware in the 35 years from 1989 to 2024. The results may be surprising.</p>
<h2>1989: Crossword compilation using integer programming</h2>
<figure>
<figcaption>Figure 1. 4x4 grid in Wilson's paper</figcaption>
<img title="4x4 grid" src="https://www.solvermax.com/images/blog/crossword/4x4.png" alt="4x4 grid" width="300" height="226">
</figure>
<p>As a motivating example, we consider an early attempt to compile crosswords using a mixed integer linear program (MILP). The paper <a title="Crossword compilation using integer programming" href="https://academic.oup.com/comjnl/article-pdf/32/3/273/947308/320273.pdf">Crossword compilation using integer programming</a>, was published in 1989 by J. M. Wilson. That article proposes two MILP model formulations for compiling crosswords:</p>
<figure>
<figcaption>Figure 2. Prime 750 superminicomputer</figcaption>
<img title="Prime 750 superminicomputer" src="https://www.solvermax.com/images/blog/crossword/prime750.jpg" alt="Prime 750 superminicomputer" width="468" height="400">

</figure>
<ul>
<li>Model 1, whole words. Model 1 attempts to fit whole words into a 4x4 fully interlocking puzzle (i.e. no black cells), as shown in Figure 1. With a lexicon of 100 4-letter words, the problem size was 800 variables and 524 constraints. A solution for this 4x4 <a title="double word square" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Word_square#Double_word_squares">double word square</a> puzzle was found in 1,800 seconds.</li>
<li>Model 2, individual letters. Model 2 attempts to place individual letters into a grid. It is more memory-efficient than Model 1, but it failed to find any solutions within 3,000 seconds, even for very small grids. In any case, Model 2 has a loose formulation that can create "words" that are not in the lexicon, so a solution (if found) may not be valid.</li>
</ul>
<p>From Wilson's experience, we observe that:</p>
<ul>
<li>A key modelling issue was memory usage, especially as the lexicon size increases. The models used a lexicon of 100 words, which is very limiting given that there are several thousand 4-letter English words.</li>
<li>Solutions were difficult to find, even for very small grids.</li>
<li>A model with 800 variables and 524 constraints is now considered to be small. In 1989 it was a large model.</li>
<li>Dense American-style puzzles (like Figure 1) are much harder to solve than sparser British-style crossword puzzles. This is likely because a dense grid has more word intersections. We'll explore this issue further in our next article.</li>
<li>The modelling was performed on a <a title="Prime 750 superminicomputer" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prime_Computer">Prime 750 superminicomputer</a>, an example of which is shown in Figure 2. The Prime 750 superminicomputer had up to 8 MB of RAM and it ran at 1 million instructions per second (MIPS). The Prime 750 was a state-of-the-art computer at the time. Depending on configuration, a <a title="THE EXECUTIVE COMPUTER; A Chip With Supercomputer Power" href="https://www.nytimes.com/1989/03/05/business/the-executive-computer-a-chip-with-supercomputer-power.html">system cost several hundred thousand US dollars</a> in the mid to late 1980s. That equates to about US\$1,000,000 today, <a title="U.S. Inflation Calculator" href="https://www.usinflationcalculator.com/">adjusted for inflation</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p>Wilson's paper refers to <a title="Crossword compilation with Horn clauses" href="https://academic.oup.com/comjnl/article/30/2/183/404335">another paper</a> that uses a lexicon of 1,000 4-letter words to compile crosswords using first-order predicate logic in the Prolog programming language, noting that, "This size of lexicon would present an almost impossible task for an integer programming model."</p>
<p>Overall, Wilson was pessimistic about using integer programming for compiling crosswords, considering it to be impractical, concluding that "the prospects of using integer programming for any type of puzzle of realistic size and with a substantial lexicon remain bleak".</p>
<p>So, integer programming was not a viable method for compiling crossword puzzles in 1989. But a lot has changed since then.</p>
<h2>Computers and solvers have improved enormously</h2>
<p>Wilson's paper was published in 1989. As we write this article in early 2024, that's 35 years ago. Since 1989, computers have become much faster, and they have a lot more memory. In addition, linear programming solvers have improved in both speed and sophistication.</p>
<p>In the following sections we attempt to estimate the magnitude of improvement in the 35 years since 1989.</p>
<h2>Computer improvements</h2>
<h3>Computer speed improvement: 1989-2024</h3>
<p>Computer processing speed has increased enormously over time. According to the <a title="50 years of microprocessor trend data" href="https://github.com/karlrupp/microprocessor-trend-data">50 years of microprocessor trend</a> data shown in Figure 3, single-thread Computer Processing Unit (CPU) performance (using the <a title="SpecINT benchmark" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SPECint">SpecINT benchmark</a>) improved from an average score of 67 in 1988-1989 to 105,300 in 2021. That equates to a factor of 1,572 times faster.</p>
<p>From 2021 to 2023, <a title="CPU single thread benchmark scores" href="https://www.cpubenchmark.net/singleThread.html">CPU single thread benchmark scores</a> improved by a further 10%, for a total factor from 1989 to 2023 of 1,729 times faster.</p>
<figure>
<figcaption>Figure 3. 50 years of microprocessor trend data</figcaption>
<img title="50 years of microprocessor trend data" src="https://www.solvermax.com/images/blog/crossword/cpu.png" alt="50 years of microprocessor trend data" width="769" height="446">
</figure>
<p>Until 2004, almost all CPUs had a single processing core. Since then, the number of logical CPU cores (i.e., physical cores and/or parallel threads within a physical core) has been increasing. A typical desktop computer now has at least several cores, with many having one or two dozen cores. Some CPUs have hundreds of cores. Graphics card GPUs typically have thousands of cores, though that is a different story.</p>
<p>Many solvers can use multiple CPU cores, to a greater or lesser extent. For example:</p>
<ul>
<li><a title="Gurobi" href="https://www.gurobi.com/documentation/current/refman/threads.html">Gurobi</a> and <a title="CPLEX" href="https://www.ibm.com/docs/en/icos/22.1.1?topic=parameters-parallel-mode-switch">CPLEX</a> use multiple cores, by default, when solving models.</li>
<li>The <a title="Octeract" href="https://octeract.gg/octeract-engine/">Octeract solver engine</a> relies on parallel processing for its high performance in solving non-linear models.</li>
<li>The open-source <a title="HiGHS" href="https://ergo-code.github.io/HiGHS/dev/parallel/#Future-plans">HiGHS</a> solver has "limited opportunities for exploiting parallel computing", though greater use of multiple CPU cores is planned soon.</li>
</ul>
<p>However, the speed improvement for multiple cores compared with a single core, according to <a title="Amdahl's law" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amdahl%27s_law">Amdahl's law</a>, is generally much less than a linear multiple of the number of cores.</p>
<p>For this analysis, we make the sweeping assumption that using multiple CPUs somewhat more than doubles the performance of a single CPU. That is, we estimate that total computer processing speed increased by a factor of about 4,000 times (= 2.3 x 1,729) from 1989 to 2024.</p>
<h3>Computers have a lot more memory</h3>
<p>The Prime 750 superminicomputer used by Wilson could have up to 8 MB of RAM (though some installations had only 2 or 4 MB of RAM). A modern desktop PC may have 8 GB of RAM – i.e., 1,024 times as much memory.</p>
<p>Though 8 GB of RAM is quite small for a computer in 2024. For example, the virtual machine we used in <a title="Optimal but not practical - Virtual machine" href="https://www.solvermax.com/blog/optimal-but-not-practical-virtual-machine">our previous article</a> has 128 GB of RAM – that's 16,384 times the maximum memory available in a million dollar computer in 1989.</p>
<p>Computer memory in 2024 is also many times faster than it was in 1989. We assume that the memory speed does not materially change our estimate of CPU speed increase.</p>
<h3>Computer costs has plummeted</h3>
<p>In this analysis, we're comparing a 1989 superminicomputer with a 2024 desktop PC – because those are the machines that would typically be used for optimization modelling in their respective eras. But this is not an entirely fair comparison, as the superminicomputer cost a million dollars (in today's money), while a high specification desktop computer now costs only a few thousand dollars – a reduction of more than 99%. If we maintained cost parity, then the performance of a 2024 computer would be even greater.</p>
<h3>Summary of computer hardware improvements</h3>
<p>Compared with 35 years ago, computers are thousands of times faster, with thousands of times more memory, and their cost has fallen by more than 99%.</p>
<h2>Solver improvements</h2>
<h3>Our estimate is based on aggregating separate estimates for periods of time</h3>
<p>The best estimate we can find of how much optimization solvers have improved is published by Gurobi. We start with an analysis by Gurobi estimating the <a title="Computation progress in linear and mixed integer programming" href="https://www.yumpu.com/en/document/read/54431495/computational-progress-in-linear-and-mixed-integer-programming">computation progress in linear and mixed integer programming</a> from 1991 to 2008. We then look at an updated analysis to 2020, which we extend to 2023.</p>
<h3>CPLEX performance improvement: 1991 to 2008</h3>
<figure>
<figcaption>Figure 4. CPLEX speed improvement for MILP from 1991 to 2008</figcaption>
<img title="CPLEX speed improvement" src="https://www.solvermax.com/images/blog/crossword/cplex-speedup.png" alt="CPLEX speed improvement" width="664" height="359">
</figure>
<p>Figure 4 shows Gurobi's assessment of speed improvement for the CPLEX solver when solving MILP models, for each major software version (bars) and cumulative (line), from 1991 to 2008.</p>
<p>The total cumulative speed improvement is a factor of almost 30,000 times faster (note the log scale for the right-hand axis).</p>
<p>Over those 17 years, this equates to about 1.8 times faster per annum, on average. Though improvements don't occur at a steady rate, with especially large improvements occurring in CPLEX versions 2.1-3.0 (inclusion of the dual simplex method) and in CPLEX versions 6.0-6.5 (many improvements gleaned from "mining" the academic literature).</p>
<p>Importantly, this estimate is just the improvement in solver software performance, not allowing for the speed increase of computer hardware over the same period.</p>
<p>Note that we ignore any improvement in solver performance from 1989 to 1991, as we don't have that information. But if the same rate of improvement (1.8 times per annum) had occurred in those 3 years, then we would have another factor of almost 6 times faster.</p>
<h3>Gurobi performance improvement: 2009 to 2023</h3>
<p>Dr. Bixby, one of the founders of Gurobi, presented an <a title="Optimization: Past, Present, Future with Dr. Robert Bixby" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_R8-nt5NyiE">updated analysis</a> of solver performance improvement in 2021, as shown in Figure 5.</p>
<figure>
<figcaption>Figure 5. Gurobi speed improvement for MILP from 2009 to 2020</figcaption>
<img title="Gurobi speed improvement" src="https://www.solvermax.com/images/blog/crossword/bixby-2021.png" alt="Gurobi speed improvement" width="639" height="348">
</figure>
<p>The figure states a cumulative improvement factor of 3,730,625 times, from CPLEX 1.2 to Gurobi 9.1 (released in 2020). Given the CPLEX improvement factor of 29,530 above, this implies an additional improvement for Gurobi of 126 times for the period 2009 to 2020.</p>
<p>Subsequent versions of Gurobi claim performance improvements for MILP models of:</p>
<ul>
<li><a title="Version 9.1 to 9.5" href="https://www.gurobi.com/wp-content/uploads/9.5-launch-Presentation.pdf">Version 9.1 to 9.5 (2021)</a>: 15%</li>
<li><a title="Version 9.5 to 10.0" href="https://www.gurobi.com/whats-new-gurobi-10-0/">Version 9.5 to 10.0 (2022)</a>: 13%</li>
<li><a title="Version 10.0 to 11.0" href="https://www.gurobi.com/whats-new-gurobi-11-0/">Version 10.0 to 11.0 (2023)</a>: 8.6%</li>
</ul>
<p>Combining these changes, we estimate that from 2009 to 2023 the Gurobi solver's speed improved by a factor of about 178 times.</p>
<p>A factor of 178 over 14 years equates to an average rate of about 1.45 times per annum. This is lower than the 1.8 times annual average rate from 1991 to 2009, but it is still impressive nonetheless.</p>
<h3>Solver performance improvement: 1989 to 2024</h3>
<p>Overall, by combining each of the solver-related steps above, we can estimate the cumulative improvement in solver performance over the last 35 years.</p>
<p>The result is that MILP solver performance improved by a factor of 5 million times (in round numbers) from 1989 to 2024. This is conservative estimate, as we exclude any improvement that may have occurred from 1989 to 1991, and from 2023 to 2024.</p>
<p>This improvement, assuming the same computer hardware, is equivalent to a model that takes 60 seconds to solve in 2023 taking 10 years to solve if started in 1989. That is, if it was possible to solve at all in 1989.</p>
<p>Note that our solver performance increase estimate is based on the commercial solvers CPLEX and Gurobi. An open-source solver, like HiGHS, is generally not as fast as CPLEX or Gurobi – perhaps by an order of magnitude, more-or-less, depending on the model. Though that hardly seems significant, given the magnitude of speed improvements over the past three+ decades.</p>
<h2>Solver + computer performance improvement: 1989 to 2024</h2>
<figure>
<figcaption>20 billion times faster</figcaption>
<p>Solving MILP models is about 20 billion times faster than it was 35 years ago.</p>
</figure>
<h3>Combined result</h3>
<p>Combining the computer hardware speed increase of 4,000 times with the solver software performance improvement of 5 million times, the total improvement from 1989 to 2024 is a factor of 20 billion times faster!</p>
<p>At that rate, a model that takes 60 seconds to solve in 2023 would have taken 38,000 years to solve if started in 1989.</p>
<h3>A grain of salt</h3>
<p>Of course, we shouldn't take these estimates too literally.</p>
<p>Firstly, there's substantial room for variation in our estimates. Some numbers are uncertain, while others are simply guesses. Also, aggregating the various factors in a multiplicative manner may not be entirely valid.</p>
<p>Secondly, there are many elements that contribute to how fast, or even whether, a MILP model can be solved, in addition to computer and solver raw speed. Other elements include memory size, programming language features, the fit between solver methodology and a model's specific characteristics, and changes in solver features.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, the magnitude of speed increases we've described in this article surely help in solving larger, more difficult MILP models. A lot.</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>In this article, we estimate the speed improvement in computer hardware and optimization solver software since 1989. This assessment is motivated by an academic paper by Wilson, published 35 years ago, describing an attempt to compile crossword puzzles using mixed integer linear programming (MILP). That attempt was largely unsuccessful, as the task was beyond the capability of MILP solvers at that time.</p>
<p>But both computers and MILP solvers have advanced enormously since 1989 – by a combined factor of around 20 billion time faster! That improvement should be enough to offset at least some of Wilson's pessimism about being able to compile crossword puzzles using MILP models. Likewise for many other optimization models.</p>
<p>In the next article, we attempt to formulate and solve a MILP to compile crossword puzzles. This is still a difficult problem, though given the improvement in computer and solver speed, there is some basis for optimism that the task is now possible.</p>
<p>If you would like help with your own models, then please <a href="https://www.solvermax.com/contact">contact us</a>.</p>
<h2>References</h2>
<p>The main references used in this article are listed below. Other information is linked within the article.</p>
<p>Gurobi Optimization, 2015. <a title="Computational progress in linear and mixed integer programming" href="https://www.yumpu.com/en/document/read/54431495/computational-progress-in-linear-and-mixed-integer-programming">Computational progress in linear and mixed integer programming</a>, accessed 13 December 2023.</p>
<p>Passmark Software, 2023. <a title="Single thread CPU performance" href="https://www.cpubenchmark.net/singleThread.html">Single thread CPU performance</a>, accessed 13 December 2023.</p>
<p>Rupp, K., 2023. <a title="Microprocessor trend data" href="https://github.com/karlrupp/microprocessor-trend-data">Microprocessor trend data</a>, accessed 13 December 2023.</p>
<p>Wilson, J.M., 1989. <a title="Crossword compilation using integer programming" href="https://academic.oup.com/comjnl/article-pdf/32/3/273/947308/320273.pdf">Crossword compilation using integer programming</a>, The Computer Journal, Volume 32, Number 3, Pages 273–275.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mario Maker 2 API (169 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://tgrcode.com/posts/mario_maker_2_api</link>
            <guid>38915775</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 18:08:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://tgrcode.com/posts/mario_maker_2_api">https://tgrcode.com/posts/mario_maker_2_api</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38915775">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://tgrcode.com/posts/mario_maker_2_api: Error: Request failed with status code 502]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OpenBSD KDE Plasma Desktop (218 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://rsadowski.de/posts/2024-01-09-openbsd-kde/</link>
            <guid>38915759</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 18:07:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://rsadowski.de/posts/2024-01-09-openbsd-kde/">https://rsadowski.de/posts/2024-01-09-openbsd-kde/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38915759">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          <p>Happy New Year, hackers! I started the new year 2024 with a personal milestone of mine.
<a href="https://kde.org/plasma-desktop/" target="_blank">
    The KDE Plasma 5.27</a> is available on OpenBSD -current and will be part of the next release 7.5.
I’m sure not very many people would understand how large this work. It started
so many years ago that I don’t even know how long I’ve been working on it.
Definitely years and not just 1 or 2. I remember that before I joined the OpenBSD community,
Vadim Zhukov did a lot of work in the Qt/KDE area. In the early days, it was
good to have someone to talk to, or just to know “you’re not alone”. This has
not been the case for a long time.  I’ve been doing it alone for years, just
like Vadim did it alone for years. It’s probably the burden of the project, we
are a super small team of OpenBSD kernel and ports developers.</p>
<p>It should be mentioned that last year kn@ - Klemens Nanni helped with a lot of
reviews and thus made it possible that we have KDE as packages.</p>
<p>I’m beginning to wonder as I write. What happens now? What happen next? Do I
have plans? Sure I could just continue to maintain the whole thing.
What will definitely be interesting is the KDE switch from Qt5 to Qt6. This
should not be a big challenge for OpenBSD. All dependencies like all Qt6
modules are ported. So this will just be a task of hard work.</p>
<p>Here are some thoughts on what we could work on.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/openbsd/ports/blob/master/meta/kde/pkg/README-plasma#L91" target="_blank">
    Fix KWin compositor</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/openbsd/ports/blob/master/meta/kde/pkg/README-plasma#L68" target="_blank">
    KDE Wayland</a></li>
<li><a href="https://networkmanager.dev/docs/libnm/latest/" target="_blank">
    NetworkManager</a> (It’s based on glib and GObject. I don’t like it)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/sddm/sddm" target="_blank">
    SDDM - QML based X11 and Wayland display manager </a> - Does that really still make sense?</li>
<li><a href="https://apps.kde.org/discover/" target="_blank">
    Discover</a> support for pkg_add(1)</li>
</ul>
<p>Perhaps it is normal that after such a big achievement, a period of reflection
begins. Let us be surprised what 2024 will bring.</p>
<p>OpenBSD KDE Plasma 5.27 Screenshots:</p>





<div data-te-carousel-item="" data-te-carousel-active="" id="carousel-0-1704733411954674175" data-te-carousel-init="" data-te-ride="carousel">
            <p><img src="https://rsadowski.de/posts/2024-01-09-openbsd-kde/images/1.png" alt="carousel image 0">
            </p>
        </div>

<p>You can super easy install KDE Plasma and KDE Gear on OpenBSD:</p>
<div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="bash"><span><span><span># KDE Gear</span>
</span></span><span><span>$ pkg_add kde
</span></span><span><span><span># KDE Plasma</span>
</span></span><span><span>$ pkg_add kde-plasma
</span></span><span><span><span># KDE Plasma extras like power management</span>
</span></span><span><span>$ pkg_add kde-plasma-extra
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>A special thanks to all who support my work with a small donation on <a href="https://github.com/sponsors/sizeofvoid/" target="_blank">
    GitHup</a>.</p>

        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Today we celebrate by announcing that Elixir is a gradually typed language (313 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/josevalim/status/1744395345872683471</link>
            <guid>38914407</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 16:29:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/josevalim/status/1744395345872683471">https://twitter.com/josevalim/status/1744395345872683471</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38914407">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://twitter.com/josevalim/status/1744395345872683471: Error: Request failed with status code 400]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tuna species popular in sashimi and poke bowls in sharp decline (142 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://phys.org/news/2024-01-tuna-species-popular-sashimi-bowls.html</link>
            <guid>38913649</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 15:47:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://phys.org/news/2024-01-tuna-species-popular-sashimi-bowls.html">https://phys.org/news/2024-01-tuna-species-popular-sashimi-bowls.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38913649">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
										
<div data-thumb="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2024/tuna-species-popular-i.jpg" data-src="https://scx2.b-cdn.net/gfx/news/hires/2024/tuna-species-popular-i.jpg" data-sub-html="Graphical abstract. Credit: <i>Ocean &amp; Coastal Management</i> (2023). DOI: 10.1016/j.ocecoaman.2023.106902">
        <figure>
            <img src="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/800a/2024/tuna-species-popular-i.jpg" alt="Tuna species popular in sashimi and poke bowls in sharp decline in the Indian Ocean" title="Graphical abstract. Credit: Ocean &amp; Coastal Management (2023). DOI: 10.1016/j.ocecoaman.2023.106902" width="800" height="392">
             <figcaption>
                Graphical abstract. Credit: <i>Ocean &amp; Coastal Management</i> (2023). DOI: 10.1016/j.ocecoaman.2023.106902
            </figcaption>        </figure>
    </div><p>The yellowfin tuna commonly enjoyed in sashimi, poke bowls and salad sandwiches may soon disappear from these dishes if current over-exploitation rates remain unchanged, especially in the Indian Ocean.</p>


										      
																																	<p>A <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ocecoaman.2023.106902">paper</a>, titled "Multiple lines of evidence highlight the dire straits of yellowfin <a href="https://phys.org/tags/tuna/" rel="tag">tuna</a> in the Indian Ocean," and published in <i>Ocean and Coastal Management</i> shows that since industrial exploitation started in 1950, the global biomass—the weight of a given <a href="https://phys.org/tags/population/" rel="tag">population</a> in the water—of yellowfin tuna has decreased, on average, by 54% across the four populations managed by tuna Regional Fisheries Management Organizations (RFMO). In the Indian Ocean, yellowfin tuna biomass has experienced a 70% decline in the past 70 years.</p>
<p>"If we look at more recent years, we can see that global yellowfin tuna populations continue to struggle. Biomass continues to decline everywhere except for stabilizing trends in the Western Pacific Ocean, prompted by management interventions," said Kristina Heidrich, lead author of the study and Ph.D. candidate with the Sea Around Us—Indian Ocean at the University of Western Australia (UWA).</p>
<p>"In most places, extractions have regularly surpassed the maximum sustainable yield or MSY limit, which is the level that would allow for the highest possible catches to be sustained over time, given that <a href="https://phys.org/tags/environmental+conditions/" rel="tag">environmental conditions</a> don't change much," added Dirk Zeller, co-author of the study and director of the Sea Around Us—Indian Ocean.</p>

																																						
																																			<p>To strengthen their evaluations, Heidrich and her co-authors used multiple methodologies. Since yellowfin tuna is normally assessed by RFMOs, they used the organizations' time series and assessment results of yellowfin tuna biomass to estimate its annual fluctuations from 1950 to 2020.</p>
<p>In parallel, they applied the CMSY++ approach, which relies mainly on time series of fisheries catches to assess the status of fish stocks. Finally, they analyzed 955 records of yellowfin tuna obtained from fisheries-independent sampling with Baited Remote Underwater Video Systems (BRUVS), which record biological and <a href="https://phys.org/tags/ecological+data/" rel="tag">ecological data</a> such as a species' size, biomass and how abundant it is in an area.</p>
<p>"The data collected with BRUVS provided a more holistic and fisheries-independent picture of the pelagic community and the status of the populations, which can complement fisheries-dependent data and analyses," said Jessica Meeuwig, co-author of the paper and director of UWA's Marine Futures Lab.</p>
<p>"These fisheries-independent BRUVS data suggest that, since 2014, yellowfin tuna in the Indian Ocean are the least common, least abundant, have the lowest biomass, and are the smallest yellowfin tuna in the existing dataset."</p>
<p>The CMSY++ approach, on the other hand, showed that even though yellowfin tuna exploitation rates slightly exceeded the MSY limit in the past decade in the eastern and western Pacific Ocean and in the Atlantic Ocean, these populations are not currently undergoing overfishing. That's not the case for the Indian Ocean, where overfishing is ongoing.</p>

																																			<p>"Beyond yellowfin tuna fisheries contributing more than US$16 billion to the <a href="https://phys.org/tags/global+economy/" rel="tag">global economy</a> yearly, the species is an <a href="https://phys.org/tags/apex+predator/" rel="tag">apex predator</a> that plays a critical role in the functioning, productivity and overall health of marine ecosystems," said Daniel Pauly, co-author of the study and principal investigator of the Sea Around Us initiative at the University of British Columbia.</p>
<p>"The risk of population collapse is high if current management does not adapt. Stringent management constraints must be implemented to reduce overall fishing capacity, rebuild overfished populations, and reduce the <a href="https://phys.org/tags/collateral+damage/" rel="tag">collateral damage</a> these fisheries cause to other species such as sharks."</p>
<p>The researchers note that, by using multiple lines of evidence that cross-validate each other, such as the ones they employed, management organizations can improve the confidence, transparency and accuracy of the information that guides their decisions. They also propose stricter management measures such as a reduction of fishing capacity, ensuring that the MSY limit is observed and implementing effective catch limits.</p>
<p>"In the Indian Ocean in particular, a catch reduction of 30% from 2020 levels is urgent to halt and reverse the decline in <a href="https://phys.org/tags/yellowfin+tuna/" rel="tag">yellowfin tuna</a> population," Heidrich said.</p>

																																																					
																				<p><strong>More information:</strong>
												Kristina N. Heidrich et al, Multiple lines of evidence highlight the dire straits of yellowfin tuna in the Indian Ocean., <i>Ocean &amp; Coastal Management</i> (2023). <a data-doi="1" href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ocecoaman.2023.106902" target="_blank">DOI: 10.1016/j.ocecoaman.2023.106902</a>
																						
																					</p>
                               											
																					
                              										                                        
										<!-- print only -->
										<div>
											 <p><strong>Citation</strong>:
												Tuna species popular in sashimi and poke bowls in sharp decline in the Indian Ocean (2024, January 8)
												retrieved 8 January 2024
												from https://phys.org/news/2024-01-tuna-species-popular-sashimi-bowls.html
											 </p>
											 <p>
											 This document is subject to copyright. Apart from any fair dealing for the purpose of private study or research, no
											 part may be reproduced without the written permission. The content is provided for information purposes only.
											 </p>
										</div>
                                        
									</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Dive: A tool for exploring a Docker image, layer contents and more (331 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/wagoodman/dive</link>
            <guid>38913425</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 15:35:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/wagoodman/dive">https://github.com/wagoodman/dive</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38913425">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          <nav aria-label="Global">
            <ul>
                <li>
      
      <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Actions&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Actions;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/actions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Actions</p><p>
        Automate any workflow
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Packages&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Packages;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/packages">
      
      <div>
        <p>Packages</p><p>
        Host and manage packages
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Security&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Security;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/security">
      
      <div>
        <p>Security</p><p>
        Find and fix vulnerabilities
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Codespaces&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Codespaces;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/codespaces">
      
      <div>
        <p>Codespaces</p><p>
        Instant dev environments
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Copilot&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Copilot;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/copilot">
      
      <div>
        <p>Copilot</p><p>
        Write better code with AI
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Code review&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Code review;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/code-review">
      
      <div>
        <p>Code review</p><p>
        Manage code changes
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Issues&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Issues;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/issues">
      
      <div>
        <p>Issues</p><p>
        Plan and track work
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Discussions&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Discussions;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/discussions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Discussions</p><p>
        Collaborate outside of code
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
</li>


                <li>
      
      
</li>


                <li>
      
      <div>
          <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Open Source&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to GitHub Sponsors&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:GitHub Sponsors;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/sponsors">
      
      <div>
        <p>GitHub Sponsors</p><p>
        Fund open source developers
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
          <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Open Source&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to The ReadME Project&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:The ReadME Project;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/readme">
      
      <div>
        <p>The ReadME Project</p><p>
        GitHub community articles
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
          
      </div>
</li>


                <li>
    <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header menu top item (logged out)&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Pricing&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Pricing;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/pricing">Pricing</a>
</li>

            </ul>
          </nav>

        <div>
                


<qbsearch-input data-scope="repo:wagoodman/dive" data-custom-scopes-path="/search/custom_scopes" data-delete-custom-scopes-csrf="cxRwDbVdgWeDDH77VkTVoQ6BSPl9Ky3rH886rDLkVuAvWvt4Um26BrrW4zIWGQL0AVHTSnhpV5nrwEU8kXS7Rg" data-max-custom-scopes="10" data-header-redesign-enabled="false" data-initial-value="" data-blackbird-suggestions-path="/search/suggestions" data-jump-to-suggestions-path="/_graphql/GetSuggestedNavigationDestinations" data-current-repository="wagoodman/dive" data-current-org="" data-current-owner="wagoodman" data-logged-in="false" data-copilot-chat-enabled="false" data-blackbird-indexed-repo-csrf="<esi:include src=&quot;/_esi/rails_csrf_token_form_hidden?r=yNrgLGbrtexIUJ7xuSyHxN%2BAZK7KpD7UaHzhYYFyuXDOf8MH5J412Vb%2F9pJ3JzFh9%2BV1N%2FFPFBTKWqL564KsthdHalZvbqfAHr31BtIF26o73qbU5lrrZyVhOHuvUwiPzFaUyWteeyLA0%2FfQxbOhZQLpAsZ6VW4ug5vgTXRwqzuP3pl4dqxuy2xLpASvEkBneCoUSuqBRhqpjzSvGpUdEUXIcSEyZgeVKgn%2FUf7AywBzOovZy3%2FSoo1e%2BmGATRq9W2qDucsq1nFDjQd02vaKzGaKy3RMZIy1oy9ArHS1ajdXSN9LL3uekbBWT1CJNNSNL5Kt6DSSSCQqV9wy2qgLRazRmXFiBXrYNMd7AE6wHw96I%2B%2BaaUoQcrOYWhmpMBfxEU7qK5qxA%2FwzRS%2Fg6FYOhzU7VbuQHUVU472UC6TUN43smSufQ5nxl9m0PSMuLYkLXEl6BQGVVAzPKowiTJBJc9mXo2KYcPURpY6s%2F8pvqP%2BpzdjpUJOGt1sOYDB1OcMOYU4xcVJeUrnYDA%3D%3D--npPi04dFXyg8%2BQ3b--PFlS002KpJtsJVg9%2Bt%2Fetg%3D%3D&quot; />">
  <div data-modal-dialog-overlay="" data-action="click:qbsearch-input#searchInputContainerClicked">
  <modal-dialog data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleClose" data-target="qbsearch-input.searchSuggestionsDialog" role="dialog" id="search-suggestions-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="search-suggestions-dialog-header" data-view-component="true">
      <h2 id="search-suggestions-dialog-header">Search code, repositories, users, issues, pull requests...</h2>
    
</modal-dialog></div>
  
  <div>
    
<div data-modal-dialog-overlay="">
  <modal-dialog data-target="qbsearch-input.feedbackDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" role="dialog" id="feedback-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-disabled="true" aria-labelledby="feedback-dialog-title" aria-describedby="feedback-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="feedback-dialog-title">
        Provide feedback
      </h2>
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="feedback-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</modal-dialog></div>

    <custom-scopes data-target="qbsearch-input.customScopesManager">
    
<div data-modal-dialog-overlay="">
  <modal-dialog data-target="custom-scopes.customScopesModalDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" role="dialog" id="custom-scopes-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-disabled="true" aria-labelledby="custom-scopes-dialog-title" aria-describedby="custom-scopes-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        Saved searches
      </h2>
        <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-description">Use saved searches to filter your results more quickly</h2>
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</modal-dialog></div>
    </custom-scopes>
  </div>
</qbsearch-input>

            <p><a href="https://github.com/signup?ref_cta=Sign+up&amp;ref_loc=header+logged+out&amp;ref_page=%2F%3Cuser-name%3E%2F%3Crepo-name%3E&amp;source=header-repo&amp;source_repo=wagoodman%2Fdive" data-hydro-click="{&quot;event_type&quot;:&quot;authentication.click&quot;,&quot;payload&quot;:{&quot;location_in_page&quot;:&quot;site header menu&quot;,&quot;repository_id&quot;:null,&quot;auth_type&quot;:&quot;SIGN_UP&quot;,&quot;originating_url&quot;:&quot;https://github.com/wagoodman/dive&quot;,&quot;user_id&quot;:null}}" data-hydro-click-hmac="e444211f9c374bb744cf5b1bdd70e4e14ac32368709b0206fd52796af07f44e9" data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Sign up&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to sign up for account&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_page:/<user-name>/<repo-name>;ref_cta:Sign up;ref_loc:header logged out&quot;}">
              Sign up
            </a>
        </p></div>
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Alaska 737 cockpit voice recorder data erasure renews safety debate (193 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.reuters.com/business/aerospace-defense/alaska-737-cockpit-voice-recorder-data-erasure-renews-industry-safety-debate-2024-01-08/</link>
            <guid>38913212</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 15:22:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.reuters.com/business/aerospace-defense/alaska-737-cockpit-voice-recorder-data-erasure-renews-industry-safety-debate-2024-01-08/">https://www.reuters.com/business/aerospace-defense/alaska-737-cockpit-voice-recorder-data-erasure-renews-industry-safety-debate-2024-01-08/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38913212">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.reuters.com/business/aerospace-defense/alaska-737-cockpit-voice-recorder-data-erasure-renews-industry-safety-debate-2024-01-08/: Error: Request failed with status code 401]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[95% of container ships are now going around the Southern Tip of Africa (271 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/typesfast/status/1743654060673093754</link>
            <guid>38912974</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 15:07:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/typesfast/status/1743654060673093754">https://twitter.com/typesfast/status/1743654060673093754</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38912974">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://twitter.com/typesfast/status/1743654060673093754: Error: Request failed with status code 400]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Jeff Lawson Steps Down as CEO of Twilio (351 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://investors.twilio.com/news/news-details/2024/Twilio-Announces-CEO-Transition/default.aspx</link>
            <guid>38912497</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 14:37:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://investors.twilio.com/news/news-details/2024/Twilio-Announces-CEO-Transition/default.aspx">https://investors.twilio.com/news/news-details/2024/Twilio-Announces-CEO-Transition/default.aspx</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38912497">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://investors.twilio.com/news/news-details/2024/Twilio-Announces-CEO-Transition/default.aspx: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[k on pdp11 (101 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ktye.github.io/pdp11/index.html</link>
            <guid>38912406</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 14:31:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ktye.github.io/pdp11/index.html">https://ktye.github.io/pdp11/index.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38912406">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Apple Vision Pro available in the U.S. on February 2 (285 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2024/01/apple-vision-pro-available-in-the-us-on-february-2/</link>
            <guid>38912032</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 14:03:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2024/01/apple-vision-pro-available-in-the-us-on-february-2/">https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2024/01/apple-vision-pro-available-in-the-us-on-february-2/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38912032">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">


	
    







 
<nav id="ac-localnav" lang="en-US" role="navigation" aria-label="Newsroom" data-analytics-region="local nav" data-sticky="">
	
    
    
        




    
    

</nav>



<main id="main" role="main"> 



<span id="opens-in-new-window">opens in new window</span>

	

<section>
<article data-analytics-activitymap-region-id="article">






    
    
    











    <div>
        

        <div>
                    
                    
                        <span>PRESS RELEASE</span>
                    
                    
                        <span>January 8, 2024</span>
                    
                    
                </div>

        <div>
                
                
                
                    <h2>
                        
    
        Apple Vision Pro available in the U.S. on February&nbsp;2
    

                    </h2>
                
            </div>

        <div>
                
                
                    The era of spatial computing is here — pre-orders begin Friday, January&nbsp;19
                
            </div>

        
            
    
    
    
    
    

        

    </div>







    
    
    






  
    
    
    
    
      <figure aria-label="Media, A woman wearing Apple Vision Pro.">
        <div>
             
              
              <div>
                Apple Vision Pro will be available beginning Friday, February 2, at all U.S. Apple Store locations and the U.S. Apple Store online.
              </div>
            
            
            
            
            <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/images/2024/01/apple-vision-pro-available-in-the-us-on-february-2/article/Apple-Vision-Pro-availability-hero.zip" download="" data-analytics-title="Download image" aria-label="Download media, A woman wearing Apple Vision Pro."></a>
          </div>
      </figure>
    
  






    
    
    


     
     
    
    
        <div>
             
                 <div><strong><span>CUPERTINO, CALIFORNIA</span></strong>&nbsp;Apple today announced Apple Vision Pro will be available beginning Friday, February 2, at all U.S. Apple Store locations and the U.S. Apple Store online. Vision Pro is a revolutionary spatial computer that transforms how people work, collaborate, connect, relive memories, and enjoy entertainment. Vision Pro seamlessly blends digital content with the physical world and unlocks powerful spatial experiences in visionOS, controlled by the most natural and intuitive inputs possible — a user’s eyes, hands, and voice. An all-new App Store provides users with access to more than 1 million compatible apps across iOS and iPadOS, as well as new experiences that take advantage of the unique capabilities of Vision Pro. Pre-orders for Apple Vision Pro begin Friday, January 19, at 5 a.m. PST.
</div>
                 
             
                 <div>“The era of spatial computing has arrived,” said Tim Cook, Apple’s CEO. “Apple Vision Pro is the most advanced consumer electronics device ever created. Its revolutionary and magical user interface will redefine how we connect, create, and explore.”
</div>
                 
             
                 <h2><strong>A Revolutionary Operating System and User Interface</strong>
</h2>
                 
             
                 <div>Apple Vision Pro is powered by visionOS, which is built on the foundation of decades of engineering innovation in macOS, iOS, and iPadOS. visionOS delivers powerful spatial experiences, unlocking new opportunities at work and at home. Featuring a brand-new three-dimensional user interface and input system controlled entirely by a user’s eyes, hands, and voice, navigation feels magical. Intuitive gestures allow users to interact with apps by simply looking at them, tapping their fingers to select, flicking their wrist to scroll, or using a virtual keyboard or dictation to type. With Siri, users can quickly open or close apps, play media, and more.
</div>
                 
             
         </div>
 

    
    
    


    
    <div data-component-list="ScrollAnimationDefault AutoPlayVideo">
        <div>visionOS features a brand-new three-dimensional user interface controlled entirely by a user’s eyes, hands, and voice.</div>
        
            <a aria-label="Download video: visionOS on Apple Vision Pro" data-analytics-title="Download video - visionOS on Apple Vision Pro" download="" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/videos/spatial-video-with-apple-vision-pro-available/downloads/Apple-Vision-Pro-availability-visionOS.zip">
            </a>
        
    </div>






    
    
    


     
     
    
    
        <div>Users can also immerse themselves in Environments — dynamic, beautiful landscapes like Haleakalā, Joshua Tree, and Yosemite national parks, and even the surface of the moon — to help them focus or reduce clutter in busy spaces. With Environments, a user’s world can grow beyond the dimensions of a physical room. With a twist of the Digital Crown, users can control how present or immersed they are in an environment.
</div>
 

    
    
    


    
    <div data-component-list="ScrollAnimationDefault AutoPlayVideo">
        <div>With Environments, a user’s world can grow beyond the dimensions of a physical room, using the Digital Crown to control how present or immersed they are.</div>
        
            <a aria-label="Download video: Apple Vision Pro Digital Crown" data-analytics-title="Download video - Apple Vision Pro Digital Crown" download="" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/videos/vision-pro-availability-environments/downloads/Apple-Vision-Pro-availability-Environments.zip">
            </a>
        
    </div>






    
    
    


     
     
    
    
        <div>
             
                 <h2><strong>Extraordinary Experiences</strong>
</h2>
                 
             
                 <div>Apple Vision Pro brings a new dimension to powerful, personal computing by changing the way users interact with their apps. The three-dimensional interface frees apps from the boundaries of a display so they can appear side by side at any scale, providing the ultimate workspace and creating an infinite canvas for multitasking and collaborating.
</div>
                 
             
                 <div>Since visionOS leverages existing developer frameworks, more than 1 million familiar apps across iOS and iPadOS are available on Apple Vision Pro and automatically work with the new input system. Vision Pro also has an all-new App Store where users can find apps that deliver spatial computing experiences unlike any other platform. Apps can be arranged anywhere and scaled to the perfect size, all while allowing the user to stay present in their space.
</div>
                 
             
                 <div><ul>
<li><strong>An infinite canvas for productivity</strong>:<strong> </strong>With key productivity and collaboration apps like Fantastical, Freeform, JigSpace, apps from Microsoft 365, and Slack, Apple Vision Pro is an ideal productivity tool for everyday tasks. Apps can appear side by side at any scale for incredible multitasking, and with support for Magic Keyboard and Magic Trackpad, users can create the perfect workspace. With Mac Virtual Display, users can even bring the powerful capabilities of their Mac into Vision Pro, creating an enormous, private, and portable 4K display, ideal for pro workflows.</li>
</ul>
</div>
                 
             
                 <div><ul>
<li><strong>The ultimate entertainment experience</strong>: Apple Vision Pro features ultra-high-resolution displays that deliver more pixels than a 4K TV for each eye, enabling users to watch movies and TV shows from Apple TV+, Disney+, Max, and other services on a screen that feels 100 feet wide with support for HDR content. Within the Apple TV app, users can access more than 150 3D titles with incredible depth wherever they are. Vision Pro also introduces Apple Immersive Video, a remarkable new entertainment format pioneered by Apple that puts users inside the action with&nbsp;180-degree,&nbsp;three-dimensional 8K recordings captured with Spatial&nbsp;Audio. Users can also enjoy new interactive experiences like Encounter Dinosaurs.</li>
</ul>
</div>
                 
             
                 <div><ul>
<li><strong>New gaming experiences</strong>: Players can access games on the App Store, including more than 250 titles on Apple Arcade. Hit games like NBA 2K24 Arcade Edition and Sonic Dream Team can be played on a screen as large as they want with incredible audio and support for popular game controllers. New spatial games, including Game Room, What the Golf?, and Super Fruit Ninja, take advantage of the powerful capabilities of Apple Vision Pro to transform the space around players, offering unique and engaging gameplay experiences.</li>
</ul>
</div>
                 
             
         </div>
 

    
    
    


    
    <div data-component-list="ScrollAnimationDefault AutoPlayVideo">
        <div>An all-new App Store on Apple Vision Pro features more than 1 million apps, including new experiences that take advantage of the unique capabilities of Vision Pro.</div>
        
            <a aria-label="Download video: App Store for Apple Vision Pro" data-analytics-title="Download video - App Store for Apple Vision Pro" download="" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/videos/vision-pro-visionos/downloads/Apple-Vision-Pro-availability-visionOS-home.zip">
            </a>
        
    </div>






    
    
    


     
     
    
    
        <div>
             
                 <h2><strong>Memories Brought to Life</strong>
</h2>
                 
             
                 <div>Apple Vision Pro enables users to capture and relive their favorite memories in entirely new ways. Spatial photos and videos transport users back to a special moment in time, and Spatial Audio makes the experience incredibly immersive. When users are on the go, they can capture spatial video on their iPhone 15 Pro or iPhone 15 Pro Max and relive them on Vision Pro. Users can also view all their photos and videos at a life-size scale with brilliant color and spectacular detail, including Panoramas that expand and wrap around the user, making them feel like they are right where it was taken.
</div>
                 
             
         </div>
 

    
    
    


    
    <div data-component-list="ScrollAnimationDefault AutoPlayVideo">
        <div>Spatial photos and videos transport users back to a special moment in time, and Spatial Audio makes the experience incredibly immersive.</div>
        
            <a aria-label="Download video: Apple Vision Pro Spatial Video" data-analytics-title="Download video - Apple Vision Pro Spatial Video" download="" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/videos/vision-pro-spatial-video/downloads/Apple-Vision-Pro-availability-Spatial-video.zip">
            </a>
        
    </div>






    
    
    


     
     
    
    
        <div>
             
                 <h2><strong>FaceTime Becomes Spatial</strong>
</h2>
                 
             
                 <div>FaceTime on Apple Vision Pro takes advantage of the space around the user so that everyone on a call appears life-size, while Spatial Audio makes it sound like each person’s voice comes from the location of their tile. If a user is wearing Vision Pro while on FaceTime, they appear as their Persona, while others joining from a Mac, iPad, or iPhone will appear in a tile.
</div>
                 
             
                 <div>Persona is an authentic spatial representation of an Apple Vision Pro user that enables others on a call to see their facial expressions and hand movements — all in real time.<sup>1</sup> Using machine learning techniques, a Persona can be created in just minutes using Vision Pro. Personas also work in third-party videoconferencing apps including Zoom, Cisco Webex, and Microsoft Teams.
</div>
                 
             
         </div>
 

    
    
    


    
    <div data-component-list="ScrollAnimationDefault AutoPlayVideo">
        <div>Persona is an authentic spatial representation of an Apple Vision Pro user that enables others on a call to see the user’s facial expressions and hand movements in real time.</div>
        
            <a aria-label="Download video: Persona on Apple Vision Pro" data-analytics-title="Download video - Persona on Apple Vision Pro" download="" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/videos/vision-pro-persona-creation/downloads/Apple-Vision-Pro-availability-Persona-creation.zip">
            </a>
        
    </div>






    
    
    


     
     
    
    
        <div>
             
                 <h2><strong>Breakthrough Design</strong>
</h2>
                 
             
                 <div>Apple Vision Pro builds on Apple innovation and experience designing high-performance products like Mac, iPhone, and wearables like Apple Watch, culminating in the most advanced personal electronics device ever. An astonishing amount of technology is packed into a beautiful, compact design that utilizes the most advanced materials possible to achieve ambitious goals for performance, mobility, and wearability.
</div>
                 
             
                 <div>Apple Vision Pro is designed as a modular system so users can personalize their fit. A singular piece of three-dimensionally formed, laminated glass gently curves around the user’s face and flows into the custom aluminum alloy frame. The Light Seal is made of a soft textile and comes in a range of shapes and sizes, flexing to conform to a user’s face for a precise fit. Flexible straps ensure audio remains close to the user’s ears, while the included Solo Knit Band and Dual Loop Band allow users to find the optimal fit for them. For those with vision correction needs, ZEISS Optical Inserts are available with a prescription or as readers that magnetically attach to Vision Pro, allowing users to take full advantage of the display’s incredible sharpness and clarity.<sup>2</sup>
</div>
                 
             
         </div>
 

    
    
    


    
    
        
        
        
            <div role="group" aria-label="gallery" data-component-list="MixinGallery" id="apple-vision-pro-design">
            <nav role="presentation">
                <ul role="tablist">
                    
                        <li role="presentation">
                            <a id="gallery-dotnav-8f9765a03f02c167f34a35b9be9cbfe2" href="#gallery-8f9765a03f02c167f34a35b9be9cbfe2" data-ac-gallery-trigger="gallery-8f9765a03f02c167f34a35b9be9cbfe2"><span>A side profile showing the modular components of Apple Vision Pro.</span></a>
                        </li>
                    
                        <li role="presentation">
                            <a id="gallery-dotnav-4fae60943d13b7e159832bb455614472" href="#gallery-4fae60943d13b7e159832bb455614472" data-ac-gallery-trigger="gallery-4fae60943d13b7e159832bb455614472"><span>The Dual Loop Band on Apple Vision Pro.</span></a>
                        </li>
                    
                        <li role="presentation">
                            <a id="gallery-dotnav-6d0bad6966f692309c103b01bdf6d067" href="#gallery-6d0bad6966f692309c103b01bdf6d067" data-ac-gallery-trigger="gallery-6d0bad6966f692309c103b01bdf6d067"><span>The Light Seal on Apple Vision Pro.</span></a>
                        </li>
                    
                </ul>
            </nav>
            <div>
                
                    
                        
                        <div id="gallery-8f9765a03f02c167f34a35b9be9cbfe2" aria-labelledby="gallery-dotnav-8f9765a03f02c167f34a35b9be9cbfe2" data-gallery-item="">
                            <figure role="presentation" data-analytics-activitymap-region-id="Gallery:modular-system">
                                
                                <div>
                                    <div>Apple Vision Pro utilizes the most advanced materials possible in a beautiful, compact design.</div>
                                    
                                    
                                    <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/images/2024/01/apple-vision-pro-available-in-the-us-on-february-2/article/Apple-Vision-Pro-availability-profile.zip" download="" data-analytics-title="Download image" aria-label="Download media, A side profile showing the modular components of Apple Vision Pro."></a>
                                </div>
                            </figure>
                        </div>
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                        <div id="gallery-4fae60943d13b7e159832bb455614472" aria-labelledby="gallery-dotnav-4fae60943d13b7e159832bb455614472" data-gallery-item="">
                            <figure role="presentation" data-analytics-activitymap-region-id="Gallery:dual-loop-band">
                                
                                <div>
                                    <div>Flexible straps ensure audio remains close to the user’s ears, while the included Solo Knit Band and Dual Loop Band allow users to find the optimal fit for them.</div>
                                    
                                    
                                    <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/images/2024/01/apple-vision-pro-available-in-the-us-on-february-2/article/Apple-Vision-Pro-availability-back-angle.zip" download="" data-analytics-title="Download image" aria-label="Download media, The Dual Loop Band on Apple Vision Pro."></a>
                                </div>
                            </figure>
                        </div>
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                        <div id="gallery-6d0bad6966f692309c103b01bdf6d067" aria-labelledby="gallery-dotnav-6d0bad6966f692309c103b01bdf6d067" data-gallery-item="">
                            <figure role="presentation" data-analytics-activitymap-region-id="Gallery:light-seal">
                                
                                <div>
                                    <div>The Light Seal is made of a soft textile and comes in a range of shapes and sizes, flexing to conform to a user’s face for a precise fit.</div>
                                    
                                    
                                    <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/images/2024/01/apple-vision-pro-available-in-the-us-on-february-2/article/Apple-Vision-Pro-availability-Digital-Crown.zip" download="" data-analytics-title="Download image" aria-label="Download media, The Light Seal on Apple Vision Pro."></a>
                                </div>
                            </figure>
                        </div>
                        
                    
                
            </div>
            
                
                
                <nav role="presentation">
                    
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    
                </nav>
            
        </div>
    


    
    
    


     
     
    
    
        <div>
             
                 <h2><strong>Unrivaled Innovation</strong>
</h2>
                 
             
                 <div>Apple Vision Pro is designed to deliver phenomenal compute performance in a compact wearable form factor. Featuring a breakthrough ultra-high-resolution display system built on top of Apple silicon, Vision Pro uses micro-OLED technology to pack 23 million pixels into two displays, each the size of a postage stamp, with wide color and high dynamic range. This technological breakthrough, combined with custom lenses that enable incredible sharpness and clarity, and advanced Spatial Audio, delivers jaw-dropping experiences.&nbsp;
</div>
                 
             
                 <div>Apple Vision Pro also features a high-performance eye tracking system that uses high-speed cameras and a ring of LEDs that project invisible light patterns onto the user’s eyes for responsive, intuitive input. And to help the user stay connected to the people around them, Apple designed a groundbreaking new feature called EyeSight. When a person approaches someone wearing Vision Pro, the device looks transparent — letting the user see them while also displaying the user’s eyes. When a user is immersed in an Environment or using an app, EyeSight gives visual cues to others about what the user is focused on.
</div>
                 
             
                 <div>The breakthrough display, advanced audio experiences, high-performance eye tracking system, and more are powered by Apple silicon in a unique dual-chip design. The M2 chip delivers powerful standalone performance, while the brand-new R1 chip processes input from 12 cameras, five sensors, and six microphones to ensure that content feels like it is appearing right in front of the user’s eyes.
</div>
                 
             
         </div>
 

    
    
    






  
    
    
    
    
      <figure aria-label="Media, A person wearing Apple Vision Pro while speaking with someone using the EyeSight feature that shows their eyes through the device.">
        <div>
             
              
              <div>
                Apple designed a groundbreaking new feature called EyeSight for Apple Vision Pro to help the user stay connected to the people around them, giving visual cues to others about what the user is focused on.
              </div>
            
            
            
            
            <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/images/2024/01/apple-vision-pro-available-in-the-us-on-february-2/article/Apple-Vision-Pro-availability-lifestyle-EyeSight.zip" download="" data-analytics-title="Download image" aria-label="Download media, A person wearing Apple Vision Pro while speaking with someone using the EyeSight feature that shows their eyes through the device."></a>
          </div>
      </figure>
    
  






    
    
    


     
     
    
    
        <div>
             
                 <h2><strong>Privacy and Security at Its Core</strong>
</h2>
                 
             
                 <div>Apple Vision Pro offers industry-leading privacy and security. Optic ID is a new authentication system that analyzes a user’s iris to unlock Vision Pro, autofill passwords, and complete payments with Apple Pay. Where a user looks stays private while navigating Vision Pro, and eye tracking information is not shared with Apple, third-party apps, or websites. EyeSight also includes a visual indicator that makes it clear to others when a user is capturing a spatial photo or video.
</div>
                 
             
                 <h2><strong>Accessibility in visionOS</strong>
</h2>
                 
             
                 <div>As with all Apple products, powerful accessibility features have been built right into visionOS. Key accessibility features like VoiceOver, Zoom, Switch Control, Guided Access, and more have been reimagined for spatial computing. Users can interact with Apple Vision Pro entirely with their eyes, hands, or voice, or any combination that works best for them. They can select a preferred input method such as their eyes, finger, or wrist using Pointer Control, pause on an element of visionOS for a few seconds to simulate a tap using Dwell Control, or simply use voice commands for activities across Vision Pro using Voice Control. If input from both eyes is not an option, visionOS also allows eye tracking with one dominant eye.
</div>
                 
             
                 <h2><strong>Apple Vision Pro and the Environment</strong>
</h2>
                 
             
                 <div>Apple Vision Pro is designed with the environment in mind, with 100 percent recycled rare earth elements in all magnets and 100 percent recycled tin soldering and gold plating in multiple printed circuit boards. The frame and battery enclosure contain 100 percent recycled aluminum, and the Light Seal and Solo Knit Band are each made with over 70 percent recycled yarn. Vision Pro meets Apple’s high standards for energy efficiency and is free of mercury, brominated flame retardants, PVC, and beryllium. The packaging is 100 percent fiber-based, bringing Apple closer to its goal of eliminating plastics in all packaging by 2025.
</div>
                 
             
                 <div>Today, Apple is carbon neutral for its global corporate operations, and by 2030, plans to be carbon neutral across the entire manufacturing supply chain and life cycle of every product.
</div>
                 
             
         </div>
 

    
    
    


     
     
    
    
        <div>
             
                 
                 
             
                 <div><ul>
<li>Apple Vision Pro will be available starting at<strong> $3,499</strong> (U.S.) with 256GB of storage. Pre-orders for Apple Vision Pro will begin on Friday, January 19, at 5 a.m. PST, with availability beginning Friday, February 2.</li>
</ul>
</div>
                 
             
                 <div><ul>
<li>Apple Vision Pro will be available at all U.S. Apple Store locations and the U.S. Apple Store online.</li>
</ul>
</div>
                 
             
                 <div><ul>
<li>ZEISS Optical Inserts — Readers will be available for <strong>$99</strong> (U.S.), and ZEISS Optical Inserts — Prescription will be available for <strong>$149</strong> (U.S.).</li>
</ul>
</div>
                 
             
                 <div><ul>
<li>Apple Vision Pro comes with a Solo Knit Band and Dual Loop Band — giving users two options for the fit that works best for them. Apple Vision Pro also includes a Light Seal, two Light Seal Cushions, an Apple Vision Pro Cover for the front of the device, Polishing Cloth, Battery, USB-C Charge Cable, and USB-C Power Adapter.</li>
</ul>
</div>
                 
             
         </div>
 

    
    
    




    
    
        
    


    
    
    



    
    
    




    




    
    
    





    
    
    <div>
            <ol>
<li>Persona is available in beta.</li>
<li>A valid prescription is required. Not all prescriptions are supported. Vision correction accessories are sold separately. ZEISS Optical Inserts are only available to purchase online.</li>
</ol>

        </div>



    
    
    






    
















	
	
	
		















	
	

</article>



</section>
</main>


	

</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What PWA Can Do Today (327 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://whatpwacando.today</link>
            <guid>38911791</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 13:44:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://whatpwacando.today">https://whatpwacando.today</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38911791">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div slot="body">
        <p>
          When motion sensors are not available on your device, you can follow these steps to enable them.
        </p>

        <h3>iOS</h3>
        <p>
          This only applies to iOS 12. You may need to remove and add the app to the home screen again for the changes
          to take effect.
        </p>
        <p>
          Open settings and scroll down to find Safari:
        </p>
        <p>
          <picture>
            <source srcset="https://whatpwacando.today/src/img/sensors-ios-step1.webp" type="image/webp">
            <source srcset="https://whatpwacando.today/src/img/sensors-ios-step1.png" type="image/png">
            <img src="https://whatpwacando.today/src/img/sensors-ios-step1.webp">
          </picture>
        </p>

        <p>
          Scroll down to find "Motion &amp; Orientation Access" and toggle the switch on:
        </p>
        <p>
          <picture>
            <source srcset="https://whatpwacando.today/src/img/sensors-ios-step2.webp" type="image/webp">
            <source srcset="https://whatpwacando.today/src/img/sensors-ios-step2.png" type="image/png">
            <img src="https://whatpwacando.today/src/img/sensors-ios-step2.webp">
          </picture>
        </p>

        <h3>Android</h3>
        <p>
          Open this site in Chrome browser for Android and open the main menu by tapping the icon in the top-right
          corner:
        </p>

        <p>
          <picture>
            <source srcset="https://whatpwacando.today/src/img/sensors-step1.webp" type="image/webp">
            <source srcset="https://whatpwacando.today/src/img/sensors-step1.png" type="image/png">
            <img src="https://whatpwacando.today/src/img/sensors-step1.webp">
          </picture>
        </p>

        <p>
          In the menu that opens, tap Settings:
        </p>

        <p>
          <picture>
            <source srcset="https://whatpwacando.today/src/img/sensors-step2.webp" type="image/webp">
            <source srcset="https://whatpwacando.today/src/img/sensors-step2.png" type="image/png">
            <img src="https://whatpwacando.today/src/img/sensors-step2.webp">
          </picture>
        </p>

        <p>
          In the Settings, tap Site settings:
        </p>

        <p>
          <picture>
            <source srcset="https://whatpwacando.today/src/img/sensors-step3.webp" type="image/webp">
            <source srcset="https://whatpwacando.today/src/img/sensors-step3.png" type="image/png">
            <img src="https://whatpwacando.today/src/img/sensors-step3.webp">
          </picture>
        </p>

        <p>
          In the Site settings menu, tap Motion sensors:
        </p>

        <p>
          <picture>
            <source srcset="https://whatpwacando.today/src/img/sensors-step4.webp" type="image/webp">
            <source srcset="https://whatpwacando.today/src/img/sensors-step4.png" type="image/png">
            <img src="https://whatpwacando.today/src/img/sensors-step4.webp">
          </picture>
        </p>

        <p>
          You can now enable Motion sensors:
        </p>

        <p>
          <picture>
            <source srcset="https://whatpwacando.today/src/img/sensors-step5.webp" type="image/webp">
            <source srcset="https://whatpwacando.today/src/img/sensors-step5.png" type="image/png">
            <img src="https://whatpwacando.today/src/img/sensors-step5.webp">
          </picture>
        </p>

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Aren't We Sieve-Ing? (221 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://brooker.co.za/blog/2023/12/15/sieve.html</link>
            <guid>38911740</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 13:39:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://brooker.co.za/blog/2023/12/15/sieve.html">https://brooker.co.za/blog/2023/12/15/sieve.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38911740">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post">
<h2 id="why-arent-we-sieve-ing">Why Aren’t We SIEVE-ing?</h2>

<p>Captain, we are being scanned!</p>

<p>Long-time readers of this blog will know that I have mixed feelings about caches. One on hand, caching is critical to the performance of systems at every layer, from CPUs to storage to whole distributed architectures. On the other hand, caching being this critical means that designers need to carefully consider what happens when the cache is emptied, and they don’t always do that well<sup><a href="#foot1">1</a></sup>.</p>

<p>Because of how important caches are, I follow the literature in the area fairly closely. Even to a casual observer, it’s obvious that there’s one group of researchers who’ve been on a bit of a tear recently, including Juncheng Yang, Yazhuo Zhang, K. V. Rashmi, and Yao Yue in various combinations. Their recent papers include <a href="https://www.usenix.org/system/files/osdi20-yang.pdf">a real-world analysis of cache systems at Twitter</a>, <a href="https://jasony.me/publication/hotos23-qdlp.pdf">an analysis of the dynamics of cache eviction</a>, and <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3600006.3613147">a novel FIFO-based cache design with some interesting properties</a>.</p>

<p>The most interesting one to me, which I expect anybody who enjoys a good algorithm will get a kick out of, is the eviction algorithm <a href="https://junchengyang.com/publication/nsdi24-SIEVE.pdf">SIEVE</a> (their paper is coming up at NSDI’24). SIEVE is an <em>eviction algorithm</em>, a way of deciding which cached item to toss out when a new one needs to be put in. There are hundreds of these in the literature. At least. Classics including throwing out the least recently inserted thing (FIFO), least recently accessed thing (LRU), thing that’s been accessed least often (LFU), and even just a random thing. Eviction is interesting because it’s a tradeoff between accuracy, speed (how much work is needed on each eviction and each access), and metadata size. The slower the algorithm, the less latency and efficiency benefit from caching. The larger the metadata, the less space there is to store actual data.</p>

<p>SIEVE performs well. In their words:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Moreover, SIEVE has a lower miss ratio than 9 state-of-the-art algorithms on more than 45% of the 1559 traces, while the next best algorithm only has a lower miss ratio on 15%.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What’s super interesting about SIEVE is that it’s both very effective, and an extremely simple change on top of a basic FIFO queue. Here’s Figure 1 from <a href="https://junchengyang.com/publication/nsdi24-SIEVE.pdf">their paper</a> with the pseudocode:</p>

<p><img src="https://brooker.co.za/blog/images/sieve_figure_1.png" alt=""></p>

<p>The only other change is to set <code>obj.visited</code> on access. Like the classic <a href="https://www.multicians.org/paging-experiment.pdf">CLOCK</a> (from the 1960s!), and unlike the classic implementation of LRU, SIEVE doesn’t require changing the queue order on access, which reduces the synchronization needed in a multi-tenant setting. All it needs on access is to set a <code>bool</code>, which is a simple atomic operation on most processors. That’s something of a big deal, for an algorithm that performs so well.</p>

<h2 id="why-arent-we-all-sieve-ing">Why aren’t we all SIEVE-ing?</h2>

<p>SIEVE raises an interesting question - if it’s so effective, and so simple, and so closely related to an algorithm that’s been around forever, why has nobody discovered it already? It’s possible they have, but I haven’t seen it before, and the authors say they haven’t either. Their hypothesis is an interesting one:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In block cache workloads, which frequently feature scans, popular objects often intermingle with objects from scans. Consequently, both types of objects are rapidly evicted after insertion.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>and</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We conjecture that not being scan-resistant is probably the reason why SIEVE remained undiscovered over the decades of caching research, which has been mostly focused on page and block accesses.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s believable. Scan resistance is important, and has been the focus of a lot of caching improvements over the decades<sup><a href="#foot2">2</a></sup>. Still, it’s hard to believe that folks kept finding this, and kept going <em>nah, not scan resistant</em> and tossing it out. Fascinating how these things are discovered.</p>

<p>Scan-resistance is important for block and file workloads because these workloads tend to be a mix of random access (<em>update that database page</em>, <em>move that file</em>) and large sequential access (<em>backup the whole database</em>, <em>do that unindexed query</em>). We don’t want the hot set of the cache that makes the random accesses fast evicted to make room for the sequential<sup><a href="#foot4">4</a></sup> pages that likely will never be accessed again<sup><a href="#foot3">3</a></sup>.</p>

<h2 id="a-scan-resistant-sieve">A Scan-Resistant SIEVE?</h2>

<p>This little historical mystery raises the question of whether there are similarly simple, but more scan-resistant, approaches to cache eviction. One such algorithm, which I’ll call SIEVE-k, involves making a small change to SIEVE.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Each item is given a small counter rather than a single access bit,</li>
  <li>On access the small counter is incremented rather than set, saturating at the value <code>k</code>,</li>
  <li>When the eviction <code>hand</code> goes past, the counter is decremented (saturating at 0), rather than reset.</li>
</ul>

<p>My claim here is that the eviction counter will go up for the most popular objects, causing them to be skipped in the round of evictions kicked off by the scan. This approach has some downsides. One is that eviction goes from worst-case <code>O(N)</code> to worst-case <code>O(kN)</code>, and the average case eviction also seems to go up by <code>k</code> (although I don’t love my analysis there). The other is that this could delay eviction of things that need to be evicted. Balancing these things, the most interesting variant of SIEVE-k is probably SIEVE-2 (along with SIEVE-1, which is the same as Zhang et al’s original algorithm).</p>

<h2 id="does-it-work">Does It Work?</h2>

<p>Yeah. Sort of. First, let’s consider a really trivial case of a Zipf-distributed <em>base</em> workload, and a periodic linear scan workload that turns on and off. In this simple setting SIEVE-2 out-performs SIEVE-1 across the board (lower miss rates are better).</p>

<p><img src="https://brooker.co.za/blog/images/sieve_k_results.png" alt=""></p>

<p>Clearly, with the 16MiB cache size here, SIEVE-2 and SIEVE-3 are doing a better job than SIEVE of keeping the scan from emptying out the cache. Beyond this magic size, it performs pretty much identically to SIEVE-1.</p>

<p>But the real-world is more complicated than that. Using the excellent open source <a href="https://github.com/cacheMon/libCacheSim">libCacheSim</a> I tried SIEVE-2 against SIEVE on a range of real-world traces. It was worse than SIEVE across the board on web-cache style KV workloads, as expected. Performance on block workloads<sup><a href="#foot5">5</a></sup> was a real mixed bag, with some wins and some losses. So it seems like SIEVE-k is potentially interesting, but isn’t a win over SIEVE more generally.</p>

<p>If you’d like to experiment some more, I’ve implemented SIEVE-k in <a href="https://github.com/mbrooker/libCacheSim">a fork of libCacheSim</a>.</p>

<h2 id="updates">Updates</h2>

<p><a name="updates"></a>The inimitable Keegan Carruthers-Smith writes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I believe there is an improvement on your worst case for SIEVE-k eviction from O(kN) to O(N):
When going through the list, keep track of the minimum counter seen.  Then if you do not evict on the first pass, decrement by that minimum value.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Which is, indeed, correct and equivalent to what my goofy k-pass approach was doing (only <code>k/2</code> times more efficient). He also pointed out that other optimizations are possible, but probably not that interesting for small <code>k</code>.</p>

<p>And, on the fediverse, Tobin Baker pointed out something important about SIEVE compared to FIFO and CLOCK: removing items from the middle of the list (rather than the head or tail only) means that the simple <code>circular array</code> approach doesn’t work. The upshot is needing <code>O(log N)</code> additional state<sup><a href="#foot6">6</a></sup> to keep a linked list. Potentially an interesting line of investigation for implementations that are very memory overhead sensitive or CPU cache locality sensitive (and scanning through entries in a random order rather than sequentially). Tobin then <a href="https://fediscience.org/@tobinbaker@discuss.systems/111660149084030363">pointed out an interesting potential fix</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A simple fix to the SIEVE algorithm to accommodate circular arrays would be to move the current tail entry into the evicted entry’s slot (much like CLOCK copies a new entry into the evicted entry’s slot). This is really not very different from the FIFO-reinsertion algorithm, except that its promotion method (moving promoted entries to evicted slots) preserves the SIEVE invariant of keeping new entries to the right of the “hand” and old entries to the left.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This one is interesting, and I don’t have a good intuition for how it would affect performance (or whether the analogy to FIFO-reinsertion is correct). Implementing it in libCacheSim would likely sort that out.</p>

<p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p>

<ol>
  <li><a name="foot1"></a> Partially because it’s hard to do. <a href="https://brooker.co.za/blog/2022/06/02/formal.html">We need better tools</a> for reasoning about system behavior.</li>
  <li><a name="foot2"></a> Including Betty O’Neil’s <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/pdf/10.1145/170036.170081">The LRU-K Page Replacement Algorithm For Database Disk Buffer</a>, a classic approach to scan resistance from the 90s database literature.</li>
  <li><a name="foot3"></a> It’s worth mentioning that some caches solve this by hoping that clients will let them know when data is only going to be accessed once (like with <code>POSIX_FADV_NOREUSE</code> and <code>POSIX_FADV_DONTNEED</code>). This can be super effective with the right discipline, but storage systems <em>in general</em> can’t make these kinds of assumptions (and often don’t have these kinds of interfaces at all).</li>
  <li><a name="foot4"></a> I say <em>sequential</em> here, but it’s really not sequential access that matters. What matters is that scans tend to happen at a high rate, and that they introduce a lot of <em>one hit wonders</em> (pages that are read once and never again, and therefore are not worth caching). Neither of those criteria need sequential access, but it happens to be true that they come along most often during sequential accesses.</li>
  <li><a name="foot5"></a> Block traces are interesting, because they tend to represent a kind of residue of accesses after the <em>easy</em> caching has already been done (by the database engine or OS page cache), and so represent a pretty tough case for cache algorithms in general.</li>
  <li><a name="foot6"></a> Which can be halved by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XOR_linked_list">committing unspeakable evil</a>.</li>
</ol>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[LinguaCafe: Self-hosted software for language learners to read foreign languages (169 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://simjanos-dev.github.io/LinguaCafeHome/</link>
            <guid>38911088</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 12:36:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://simjanos-dev.github.io/LinguaCafeHome/">https://simjanos-dev.github.io/LinguaCafeHome/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38911088">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Big Tech has already made enough money in 2024 to pay all its 2023 fines (196 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://proton.me/blog/big-tech-2023-fines-vs-revenue</link>
            <guid>38910731</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 11:53:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://proton.me/blog/big-tech-2023-fines-vs-revenue">https://proton.me/blog/big-tech-2023-fines-vs-revenue</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38910731">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><time datetime="2024-01-08T10:31:15">Published on January 8, 2024</time></p>
<p>Last year, Big Tech companies (Alphabet, Amazon, Apple, Meta, and Microsoft) received about<strong> $3.04 billion in fines for breaking laws on both sides of the Atlantic</strong>. <strong>As of seven days and three hours into 2024</strong><strong>, they had already earned enough revenue to pay it all off</strong>.</p>



<p>A little over a week of operations is all it would take if the companies tackled their fines one after another. If they each paid their fines simultaneously, Meta would be the last to finish after five days and 13 hours.&nbsp;</p>



<p>This shows how insignificant these fines are for companies whose revenues are often larger than countries’ GDPs. In fact, 2023 was the second straight year these five companies were <a rel="" target="_self" href="https://proton.me/blog/big-tech-three-billion-fines">fined over $3 billion<span>(new window)</span></a>, showing that they view fines as nothing more than the cost of doing business.&nbsp;</p>



<p>This also assumes these companies act in good conscience and pay their fines promptly. Unfortunately, there’s no late payment penalty for Big Tech — and they often delay for years. It’s just another instance of Big Tech using its overwhelming revenue to bend or avoid the rules that govern the rest of us. Clearly, the current remedies for antitrust and privacy breaches are not having the desired effect.&nbsp;</p>



<h2>Big Tech annual revenue dwarfs total fines</h2>



<p>We <a rel="" target="_self" href="https://proton.me/blog/big-tech-bigger-fines">published an article<span>(new window)</span></a> in August 2023 showing that the fines Big Tech companies received by that point in the year, some $2.3 billion, were inconsequential compared to their income. We thought it would be good to revisit those figures at the end of the year. We’ve calculated the average revenue earned per hour for each company using the latest figures reported. (We explain the sources we used for calculating this table at the bottom of this article.)</p>



<figure><table><thead><tr><th><strong>Company</strong></th><th><strong>Revenue earned per hour</strong></th><th><strong>How long it takes to earn $1 billion</strong></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank" href="https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1652044/000165204423000094/goog-20230930.htm">Alphabet<span>(new window)</span></a> (for the first three quarters of 2023)</td><td>$33.74 million&nbsp;</td><td>1 day, 5 hours, 35 minutes</td></tr><tr><td><a rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank" href="https://s2.q4cdn.com/299287126/files/doc_financials/2023/q3/AMZN-Q3-2023-Earnings-Release.pdf">Amazon<span>(new window)</span></a> (for the first three quarters of 2023)</td><td>$61.79 million</td><td>16 hours, 10 minutes</td></tr><tr><td><a rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank" href="https://s2.q4cdn.com/470004039/files/doc_earnings/2023/q4/filing/_10-K-Q4-2023-As-Filed.pdf">Apple<span>(new window)</span></a> (for the fiscal year ending Sept. 30, 2023)</td><td>$43.75 million</td><td>22 hours, 50 minutes</td></tr><tr><td><a rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank" href="https://d18rn0p25nwr6d.cloudfront.net/CIK-0001326801/29804645-5034-420a-82b6-54f869ec422b.html#">Meta<span>(new window)</span></a> (for the first three quarters of 2023)</td><td>$12.89 million</td><td>3 days, 3 hours, 35 minutes</td></tr><tr><td><a rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank" href="https://view.officeapps.live.com/op/view.aspx?src=https://c.s-microsoft.com/en-us/CMSFiles/MSFT_FY23Q4_10K.docx?version=d86a284d-dfce-35ee-366c-d754d90f9174">Microsoft<span>(new window)</span></a> (for the fiscal year ending June 30, 2023)</td><td>$24.19 million</td><td>1 day, 17 hours, 20 minutes</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<p>We also included fines these companies received in 2023 in the months after our article was published, such as a $700 million settlement in a case against Alphabet (Google) for how it <a rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank" href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/google-pay-700-million-us-043053930.html">illegally blocked competition on the Google Play Store<span>(new window)</span></a> that came out in December.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The updated table below shows the 2023 fine totals for each company, along with how long it would take them to pay off those fines with their 2023 average hourly revenue.</p>



<figure><table><thead><tr><th><strong>Company</strong></th><th><strong>2023 total fines</strong></th><th><strong>Company</strong></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Alphabet</td><td>$941 million</td><td>1 day, 3 hours, 55 minutes</td></tr><tr><td>Amazon</td><td>$111.7 million</td><td>1 hour, 50 minutes</td></tr><tr><td>Apple</td><td>$186.4 million</td><td>4 hours, 15 minutes</td></tr><tr><td>Meta</td><td>$1.72 billion</td><td>5 days, 13 hours, 25 minutes</td></tr><tr><td>Microsoft</td><td>$84 million</td><td>3 hours, 30 minutes</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Total fines</strong></td><td><strong>$3.04 billion</strong></td><td><strong>7 days, 3 hours</strong></td></tr></tbody></table><figcaption>For Apple and Microsoft, we calculated the average revenue per hour using the annual revenue amount in their 10-K report for their 2023 fiscal year (dates are noted in the table). We then divided that amount by 365 and then divided the resulting amount by 24 to reach the hourly average.<p>Alphabet (Google), Amazon, and Meta (Facebook) don’t release their annual financial statements until the beginning of February, so we calculated the average revenue per hour using the revenue they reported for the first nine months of 2023 in their September 10-Q report. We then divided that amount by 273 (the number of days in a year through Sept. 30) and then divided the resulting amount by 24 to reach the hourly average.</p></figcaption></figure>



<h2>Delay, delay, delay</h2>



<p>Big Tech companies can further water down the potential sting of these fines by <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://www.barrons.com/news/how-big-tech-generated-billions-in-fines-then-didn-t-pay-them-ab5d0a77">delaying payment for years<span>(new window)</span></a>. They’ve done this by filing appeals, counter-suing, or simply refusing to pay. Some notable examples include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Amazon continues to contest its <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://www.bbc.com/news/business-58024116">$886 million fine from the Luxembourg DPA in 2021<span>(new window)</span></a>.</li>



<li>Google somehow still arguing against $8 billion in antitrust fines from the EU in <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://ec.europa.eu/commission/presscorner/detail/es/MEMO_17_1785">2017<span>(new window)</span></a>, <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://www.theverge.com/2018/7/18/17580694/google-android-eu-fine-antitrust">2018<span>(new window)</span></a>, and <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://www.theverge.com/2019/3/20/18270891/google-eu-antitrust-fine-adsense-advertising">2019<span>(new window)</span></a>.</li>



<li>Google telling the Indian government that it <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://www.businesstoday.in/technology/news/story/google-refuses-to-pay-fine-in-india-even-though-it-paid-fine-in-same-case-in-europe-ccis-lawyer-360460-2023-01-16">simply refuses to pay their fines<span>(new window)</span></a>.</li>
</ul>



<p>Every company has the right to appeal, and privacy abuses and antitrust cases are notoriously complicated and often governed by laws that were written well before the internet was invented, meaning a great deal of interpretation is necessary. Still, it’s not a sign of a functioning justice system for appeals to take such a long time while people continue to suffer data abuses and unfair high prices. Those with the deepest pockets can often drag out litigation well after it’s clear they have no chance of winning, taking time and resources away from regulators’ efforts to create a level playing field in the market.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<h2>Weak fines are not a deterrent</h2>



<p>These paltry fines aren’t helpful if you think a fine should function as a punishment for poor corporate governance or an incentive for companies to change their behavior. If a company can pay off a fine with less than a week’s revenue or avoid paying it entirely for half a decade, then it won’t cause executives to tread cautiously.&nbsp;</p>



<p>For example, despite Meta racking up nearly $2 billion in fines and Google nearly $1 billion, both Mark Zuckerberg and Sundar Pichai remain secure in their CEO posts. While other CEOs might be ousted immediately if their companies were fined billions of dollars year after year, investors and board members are willing to accept them at Big Tech companies because $1 billion represents less than 1% of these company’s total revenue. They view these fines as nothing more than the cost of doing business under the surveillance capitalism business model. And as their balance sheets show, business remains good.</p>



<p>This is important because the internet has become one of the most (arguably the most) important pieces of global public infrastructure the world has ever seen. It connects billions of people to their friends and family, to gainful employment, to entertainment, to essential information, and more. Despite how essential it is to the global economy and society, governments around the world have allowed Big Tech to bend the internet to their will.</p>



<p>Big Tech believes the internet belongs to them, that they can use their size and wealth to <a rel="" target="_self" href="https://proton.me/blog/how-big-tech-tracks-users">gather people’s private information with impunity<span>(new window)</span></a> and <a rel="" target="_self" href="https://proton.me/blog/search-risk-google">block people from choosing competitors<span>(new window)</span></a> that might offer more privacy.</p>



<h2>We all must fight for a better internet</h2>



<p>Big Tech knows people want privacy. It’s why <a rel="" target="_self" href="https://proton.me/blog/google-privacy-washing">Google<span>(new window)</span></a> and Apple have launched major ad campaigns talking about how they give you control of your data. However, if you look at the features they’re producing, they continue to search for new ways to collect people’s data, from <a rel="" target="_self" href="https://proton.me/blog/privacy-metaverse">launching metaverses<span>(new window)</span></a> to <a rel="" target="_self" href="https://proton.me/blog/google-privacy-washing-android">following your activity in other apps<span>(new window)</span></a>, showing they aren’t taking regulators seriously.</p>



<p>If we want to take back control of the internet, several things must happen.&nbsp;</p>



<ul>
<li>First, governments must combat Big Tech. They must impose fines that get Big Tech’s attention for breaching user privacy and locking competitors out of the market.</li>



<li>But fines can only be part of the solution. Regulators, armed with strong antitrust legislation, must strongly challenge mergers that create massive monopolies. They must encourage competition and empower people to choose the service that is best for them.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p>There are several opportunities for legislators to empower regulators to ensure fair competition and protect people’s rights in the coming year, such as with the Digital Markets, Consumer and Competition Bill in the UK that’s currently going through Parliament. Similar legislative initiatives have started in South Korea and Japan, as well.</p>



<p>But until governments step in, you must protect your information yourself. If you remove your personal data from Big Tech’s reach, not only are you protecting your privacy, you’re also depriving Big Tech of the ability to sell targeted ads.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The best way to protect your information from Big Tech is to use end-to-end encrypted services. You can sign up for Proton today for free and join the over 100 million people who use our encrypted services to protect their <a href="https://proton.me/mail">emails</a>, <a href="https://proton.me/calendar">schedule details</a>, <a href="https://proton.me/drive">photos and files</a>, <a rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank" href="https://protonvpn.com/">online browsing<span>(new window)</span></a>, and <a href="https://proton.me/pass">passwords and online identity</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<hr>



<figure><table><thead><tr><th><strong>Company</strong></th><th><strong>Fine</strong></th><th><strong>Time to pay off fine</strong></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Alphabet (Google)</td><td>$160,000,000 (for <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-india-65120697">Android’s market dominance in India<span>(new window)</span></a>)</td><td>4 hours, 45 minutes</td></tr><tr><td>Apple</td><td>$8,000,000 (by <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://www.politico.eu/article/apple-fined-e8-million-in-privacy-case">the French DPA for privacy violations<span>(new window)</span></a>)</td><td>11 minutes</td></tr><tr><td>Apple</td><td>$17,000,000 (for <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/russian-anti-monopoly-agency-fines-apple-17-million-tass-2023-01-17">dominant market activity in Russia<span>(new window)</span></a>)</td><td>23 minutes</td></tr><tr><td>Meta (Facebook)</td><td>$5,950,000 (by the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://www.dataprotection.ie/en/news-media/data-protection-commission-announces-conclusion-inquiry-whatsapp">Irish DPA for breach of privacy laws<span>(new window)</span></a>)</td><td>28 minutes</td></tr><tr><td>Microsoft</td><td>$64,000,000 (by <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://www.competitionpolicyinternational.com/france-fines-microsoft-e60m-over-cookies">French DPA for Bing’s use of cookies)<span>(new window)</span></a></td><td>2 hours, 40 minutes</td></tr><tr><td>Meta (Facebook)</td><td>$414,000,000 (by Irish DPA <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/01/04/meta-fined-more-than-400-million-in-ireland-over-eu-privacy-breaches.html">for breaches of GDPR by both Meta and Instagram<span>(new window)</span></a>)</td><td>1 day, 8 hours, 7 minutes</td></tr><tr><td>Alphabet (Google)</td><td>$32,000,000 (by South Korea for <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://www.insiderintelligence.com/content/google-dinged-with-32m-fine-south-korea-blocking-mobile-games-on-rival-app-store">blocking mobile games on rival app stores<span>(new window)</span></a>)</td><td>55 minutes</td></tr><tr><td>Amazon</td><td>$30,000,000 (by <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/technology/amazon-faces-30-million-fine-over-ring-alexa-privacy-violations">FTC for privacy and data breaches relating to Ring and Alexa<span>(new window)</span></a>)</td><td>30 minutes</td></tr><tr><td>Meta (Facebook)</td><td>$1,300,000,000 (by <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/05/22/business/meta-facebook-eu-privacy-fine.html">Irish DPA for transfer of personal data to the USA<span>(new window)</span></a>)&nbsp;</td><td>4 days, 4 hours, 50 minutes</td></tr><tr><td>Alphabet (Google)</td><td>$47,000,000 (for <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/russian-court-slaps-additional-47-mln-fine-google-owner-alphabet-2023-06-27">anticompetitive activity in video hosting market in Russia<span>(new window)</span></a>)</td><td>1 hour, 23 minutes</td></tr><tr><td>Microsoft</td><td>$20,000,000 (by the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://sourcepoint.com/blog/ftc-fines-microsoft-over-childrens-privacy">FTC for violations of the Children’s Online Privacy Protection Act<span>(new window)</span></a>)</td><td>50 minutes</td></tr><tr><td>Amazon</td><td>$25,000,000 (by <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://variety.com/2023/digital/news/amazon-fine-alexa-settlement-doj-ftc-childrens-privacy-law-violation-1235675702">FTC for violations of the Children’s Online Privacy Protection Act)<span>(new window)</span></a></td><td>24 minutes</td></tr><tr><td>Alphabet (Google)</td><td>$2,000,000 (by <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://www.euronews.com/2023/07/04/google-fined-2m-in-france-over-search-engine-and-google-play">France for failure to provide search rank criteria on Google search and the Play Store<span>(new window)</span></a>)</td><td>4 minutes</td></tr><tr><td>Apple</td><td>$161,400,000 (by Spain, <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://edition.cnn.com/2023/07/18/tech/spain-antitrust-fine-apple-amazon/index.html">for price fixing Apple products on Amazon<span>(new window)</span></a>)</td><td>3 hours, 41 minutes</td></tr><tr><td>Amazon</td><td>$56,700,000 (by Spain, <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://edition.cnn.com/2023/07/18/tech/spain-antitrust-fine-apple-amazon/index.html">for price fixing Apple products on Amazon)<span>(new window)</span></a></td><td>55 minutes</td></tr><tr><td>Alphabet (Google)</td><td>$700,000,000 (in a settlement with all 50 states in the US <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/google-pay-700-million-us-043053930.html">for abusing its power in the Google Play Store<span>(new window)</span></a>)</td><td>20 hours, 45 minutes</td></tr></tbody><tfoot><tr><td><strong>Time to pay off fine</strong></td><td><strong>$3,043,050,000</strong></td><td><strong>7 days, 2 hours, 51 minutes</strong></td></tr></tfoot></table><figcaption>The above table is not an exhaustive list of all the fines these companies received in the 2023 calendar year. We included all the substantial fines we could find in major news sources, but there might be others. Also, this table excludes several censorship fines from Russia that seem motivated by Big Tech’s refusal to remove news about Russia’s invasion of Ukraine. Also, due to the fluctuation of foreign exchange rates, the dollar amounts might have shifted since this article was published.</figcaption></figure>




</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Phrase "No Evidence" Is a Red Flag for Bad Science Communication (2021) (264 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.astralcodexten.com/p/the-phrase-no-evidence-is-a-red-flag</link>
            <guid>38909735</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 09:14:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.astralcodexten.com/p/the-phrase-no-evidence-is-a-red-flag">https://www.astralcodexten.com/p/the-phrase-no-evidence-is-a-red-flag</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38909735">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><p><strong>Related to:</strong><span> </span><a href="https://www.overcomingbias.com/2008/08/doctor-there-ar.html" rel="">Doctor, There Are Two Types Of No Evidence</a><span>; </span><a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2020/04/14/a-failure-but-not-of-prediction/" rel="">A Failure, But Not Of Prediction</a><span>.</span></p><p><strong>I.</strong></p><p>Every single one of these statements that had “no evidence” is currently considered true or at least pretty plausible.</p><p>In an extremely nitpicky sense, these headlines are accurate. Officials were simply describing the then-current state of knowledge. In medicine, anecdotes or hunches aren’t considered “real” evidence. So if there hasn’t been a study showing something, then there’s “no evidence”. In early 2020, there hadn’t yet been a study proving that COVID could be airborne, so there was “no evidence” for it.</p><p><span>On the other hand, here is a recent headline: </span><a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/factcheck/2021/09/10/fact-check-no-evidence-vaccine-related-complications-killed-45-000/8256978002/" rel="">No Evidence That 45,000 People Died Of Vaccine-Related Complications</a><span>. Here’s another: </span><a href="https://www.msn.com/en-us/news/us/fact-check-no-evidence-pfizer-moderna-covid-19-vaccines-cause-miscarriage/ar-AARMn2d" rel="">No Evidence Vaccines Cause Miscarriage</a><span>. I don’t think the scientists and journalists involved in these stories meant to shrug and say that no study has ever been done so we can’t be sure either way. I think they meant to express strong confidence these things are false.</span></p><p>You can see the problem. Science communicators are using the same term - “no evidence” - to mean:</p><ol><li><p>This thing is super plausible, and honestly very likely true, but we haven’t checked yet, so we can’t be sure.</p></li><li><p>We have hard-and-fast evidence that this is false, stop repeating this easily debunked lie.</p></li></ol><p><span>This is </span><em>utterly corrosive</em><span> to anybody trusting science journalism. </span></p><p><span>Imagine you are John Q. Public. You read “no evidence of human-to-human transmission of coronavirus”, and then a month later it turns out such transmission is common. You read “no evidence linking COVID to indoor dining”, and a month later your governor has to shut down indoor dining because of all the COVID it causes. You read “no hard evidence new COVID strain is more transmissible”, and a month later everything is in panic mode because it was more transmissible after all. And </span><em>then</em><span> you read “no evidence that 45,000 people died of vaccine-related complications”. Doesn’t sound very reassuring, does it?</span></p><p><strong>II.</strong></p><p>Unfortunately, I don’t think this is just a matter of scientists and journalists using the wrong words sometimes. I think they are fundamentally confused about this. </p><p>In traditional science, you start with a “null hypothesis” along the lines of “this thing doesn’t happen and nothing about it is interesting”. Then you do your study, and if it gets surprising results, you might end up “rejecting the null hypothesis” and concluding that the interesting thing is true; otherwise, you have “no evidence” for anything except the null. </p><p>This is a perfectly fine statistical hack, but it doesn’t work in real life. In real life, there is no such thing as a state of “no evidence” and it’s impossible to even give the phrase a consistent meaning. EG:</p><p><strong>Is there "no evidence" that using a parachute helps prevent injuries when jumping out of planes?</strong><span> This was the conclusion of </span><a href="https://www.bmj.com/content/327/7429/1459?ijkey=c3677213eca83ff6599127794fc58c4e0f6de55a&amp;keytype2=tf_ipsecsha" rel="">a cute paper</a><span> in the </span><em>BMJ</em><span>, which pointed out that as far as they could tell, nobody had ever done a study proving parachutes helped. Their point was that "evidence" isn't the same thing as "peer-reviewed journal articles". So maybe we should stop demanding journal articles, and accept informal evidence as valid?</span></p><p><strong>Is there "no evidence" for alien abductions?</strong><span> There are hundreds of people who say they've been abducted by aliens! By legal standards, hundreds of eyewitnesses is </span><em>great</em><span> evidence! If a hundred people say that Bob stabbed them, Bob is a serial stabber - or, even if you thought all hundred witnesses were lying, you certainly wouldn't say the prosecution had “no evidence”! When we say "no evidence" here, we mean "no really strong evidence from scientists, worthy of a peer-reviewed journal article". But this is the opposite problem as with the parachutes - here we should stop accepting informal evidence, and demand more scientific rigor.</span></p><p><strong>Is there "no evidence" homeopathy works?</strong><span> No, </span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30202036/" rel="">here's a peer-reviewed study showing that it does</a><span>. Don't like it? I have </span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/9310601" rel="">eighty-nine more peer-reviewed studies showing that right here</a><span>. But a strong theoretical understanding of how water, chemicals, immunology, etc operate suggests homeopathy can't </span><em>possibly</em><span> work, so I assume all those pro-homeopathy studies are methodologically flawed and useless, the same way </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Replication_crisis#In_medicine" rel="">somewhere between 16% and 89%</a><span> of other medical studies are flawed and useless. Here we should reject </span><em>journal articles</em><span> because they disagree with </span><em>informal</em><span> evidence!</span></p><p><strong>Is there "no evidence" that King Henry VIII had a spleen?</strong><span> Certainly nobody has published a peer-reviewed article weighing in on the matter. And probably nobody ever dissected him, or gave him an abdominal exam, or collected any informal evidence. Empirically, this issue is just a complete blank, an empty void in our map of the world. Here we should ignore the absence of journal articles </span><em>and</em><span> the absence of informal evidence, and just assume it's true because </span><em>obviously</em><span> it’s true.</span></p><p><span>I challenge anyone to come up with a definition of "no evidence" that wouldn't be misleading in at least one of the above examples. If you can't do it, I think that's because the folk concept of "no evidence" doesn't match how real truth-seeking works. Real truth-seeking is </span><a href="https://www.yudkowsky.net/rational/bayes" rel="">Bayesian</a><span>. You start with a prior for how unlikely something is. Then you update the prior as you gather evidence. If you gather a lot of strong evidence, maybe you update the prior to somewhere very far away from where you started, like that some really implausible thing is nevertheless true. Or that some dogma you held unquestioningly is in fact false. If you gather only a little evidence, you mostly stay where you started.</span></p><p>I'm not saying this process is easy or even that I'm very good at it. I'm just saying that once you understand the process, it no longer makes sense to say "no evidence" as a synonym for “false”. </p><p><strong>III.</strong></p><p>Okay, but then what? “No Evidence That Snake Oil Works” is the bread and butter of science journalism. How do you express that concept without falling into the “no evidence” trap?</p><p>I think you have to go back to the basics of journalism: what story are you trying to cover? </p><p>If the story is that nobody has ever investigated snake oil, and you have no strong opinion on it, and for some reason that’s newsworthy, use the words “either way”: “No Evidence Either Way About Whether Snake Oil Works”. </p><p><span>If the story is that all the world’s top doctors and scientists believe snake oil doesn’t work, then say so. “Scientists: Snake Oil Doesn’t Work”. This doesn’t have the same faux objectivity as “No Evidence Snake Oil Works”. It centers the belief in fallible scientists, as opposed to the much more convincing claim that </span><em>there is literally not a single piece of evidence anywhere in the world</em><span> that anyone could use in favor of snake oil. Maybe it would sound less authoritative. Breaking an addiction to false certainty is as hard as breaking any other addiction. But the first step is admitting you have a problem.</span></p><p><span>But I think the most virtuous way to write this is to actually investigate. If it’s worth writing a story about why there’s no evidence for something, probably it’s because some people believe there </span><em>is</em><span> evidence. What evidence do they believe in? Why is it wrong? How do you know?</span></p><p>Some people thought masks helped slow the spread of COVID. You can type out "no evidence" and hit "send tweet". But what if you try to engage the argument? Why do people believe masks could slow spread? Well, because it seems intuitively obvious that if something is spread by droplets shooting out of your mouth, preventing droplets from shooting out of your mouth would slow the spread. Does that seem like basically sound logic? If so, are you sure your job as a science communicator requires you to tell people not to believe that? How do you know they're not smarter than you are? There's no evidence that they aren't!</p></div></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why use strace in 2023? [video] (133 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://media.ccc.de/v/all-systems-go-2023-228-why-would-you-still-want-to-use-strace-in-2023-</link>
            <guid>38908496</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 05:05:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://media.ccc.de/v/all-systems-go-2023-228-why-would-you-still-want-to-use-strace-in-2023-">https://media.ccc.de/v/all-systems-go-2023-228-why-would-you-still-want-to-use-strace-in-2023-</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38908496">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<div>
<p><a href="https://media.ccc.de/c/asg2023">
<img alt="conference logo" src="https://static.media.ccc.de/media/events/all_systems_go/2023/logo.png">
</a>
</p>

</div>
<p>
<span></span>
<a href="https://media.ccc.de/search?p=Eugene+Syromiatnikov">Eugene Syromiatnikov</a> and
<a href="https://media.ccc.de/search?p=Dmitry+Levin">Dmitry Levin</a>

</p>
<div data-aspect-ratio="16:9">

<!-- Mediaelement Player -->
<video controls="controls" data-id="12622" data-timeline="https://static.media.ccc.de/media/events/all_systems_go/2023/228-34203612-1025-5359-85f9-d42f13739426.timeline.jpg" height="100%" poster="https://static.media.ccc.de/media/events/all_systems_go/2023/228-34203612-1025-5359-85f9-d42f13739426_preview.jpg" preload="metadata" width="100%">
<source data-lang="eng" data-quality="high" src="https://cdn.media.ccc.de/events/all_systems_go/2023/h264-hd/asg2023-228-eng-Why_would_you_still_want_to_use_strace_in_2023_hd.mp4" title="eng 1080p" type="video/mp4">
<source data-lang="eng" data-quality="high" src="https://cdn.media.ccc.de/events/all_systems_go/2023/webm-hd/asg2023-228-eng-Why_would_you_still_want_to_use_strace_in_2023_webm-hd.webm" title="eng 1080p" type="video/webm">
<source data-lang="eng" data-quality="low" src="https://cdn.media.ccc.de/events/all_systems_go/2023/h264-sd/asg2023-228-eng-Why_would_you_still_want_to_use_strace_in_2023_sd.mp4" title="eng 576p" type="video/mp4">
<source data-lang="eng" data-quality="low" src="https://cdn.media.ccc.de/events/all_systems_go/2023/webm-sd/asg2023-228-eng-Why_would_you_still_want_to_use_strace_in_2023_webm-sd.webm" title="eng 576p" type="video/webm">
<track kind="metadata" label="thumbnails" src="https://static.media.ccc.de/media/events/all_systems_go/2023/228-34203612-1025-5359-85f9-d42f13739426.thumbnails.vtt" srclang="">

</video>


</div><p>
Playlists:
<a href="https://media.ccc.de/v/all-systems-go-2023-228-why-would-you-still-want-to-use-strace-in-2023-/playlist">'asg2023' videos starting here</a>
/
<a data-method="get" href="https://media.ccc.de/v/all-systems-go-2023-228-why-would-you-still-want-to-use-strace-in-2023-/audio">audio</a></p><ul>
<li>
<span></span>
26 min
</li>
<li>
<span title="event date"></span>
2023-09-13
</li>
<li>
<span title="release date"></span>
2023-09-14
</li>
<li>
<span></span>
4781
</li>
<li>
<span></span>
<a href="https://cfp.all-systems-go.io/all-systems-go-2023/talk/GUVYJ7/">Fahrplan</a>
</li>
</ul>
<!-- %h3 About -->
<p>strace is a traditional userspace tracer utility for Linux, implemented using ptrace API. Despite of the abundance of various kernel tracing interfaces nowadays, there are certain classes of tasks that are still better served by strace. In this talk the maintainer of strace will provide examples of such tasks.</p>

<h3>Download</h3>
<div>
<div>
<p>
<h4>Video</h4>
</p>
<div>
<ul role="tablist">
<li role="presentation">
<a aria-controls="mp4" data-toggle="tab" href="#mp4" role="tab">
MP4
</a>
</li>
<li role="presentation">
<a aria-controls="webm" data-toggle="tab" href="#webm" role="tab">
WebM
</a>
</li>
</ul>
<div>
<div id="mp4" role="tabpanel">
<div>
<a href="https://cdn.media.ccc.de/events/all_systems_go/2023/h264-hd/asg2023-228-eng-Why_would_you_still_want_to_use_strace_in_2023_hd.mp4">
<p>Download 1080p</p>
<span>eng</span>
<span>88 MB</span>
</a>
</div>
<div>
<a href="https://cdn.media.ccc.de/events/all_systems_go/2023/h264-sd/asg2023-228-eng-Why_would_you_still_want_to_use_strace_in_2023_sd.mp4">
<p>Download 576p</p>
<span>eng</span>
<span>40 MB</span>
</a>
</div>
</div>
<div id="webm" role="tabpanel">
<div>
<a href="https://cdn.media.ccc.de/events/all_systems_go/2023/webm-hd/asg2023-228-eng-Why_would_you_still_want_to_use_strace_in_2023_webm-hd.webm">
<p>Download 1080p</p>
<span>eng</span>
<span>121 MB</span>
</a>
</div>
<div>
<a href="https://cdn.media.ccc.de/events/all_systems_go/2023/webm-sd/asg2023-228-eng-Why_would_you_still_want_to_use_strace_in_2023_webm-sd.webm">
<p>Download 576p</p>
<span>eng</span>
<span>55 MB</span>
</a>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div>
<p>
<h4>Audio</h4>
</p>
<div>
<div>
<a href="https://cdn.media.ccc.de/events/all_systems_go/2023/mp3/asg2023-228-eng-Why_would_you_still_want_to_use_strace_in_2023_mp3.mp3">
<p>Download mp3</p>
<span>eng</span>
<span>24 MB</span>
</a>
</div>
<div>
<a href="https://cdn.media.ccc.de/events/all_systems_go/2023/opus/asg2023-228-eng-Why_would_you_still_want_to_use_strace_in_2023_opus.opus">
<p>Download opus</p>
<span>eng</span>
<span>15 MB</span>
</a>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- %h3 Embed/Share -->

<h3>Tags</h3>
<div>
<p><a href="https://media.ccc.de/c/asg2023/asg2023" rel="tag">asg2023</a>
<a href="https://media.ccc.de/tags/228" rel="tag">228</a>
<a href="https://media.ccc.de/tags/2023" rel="tag">2023</a>
</p></div>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How meta built the infrastructure for Threads (143 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://engineering.fb.com/2023/12/19/core-infra/how-meta-built-the-infrastructure-for-threads/</link>
            <guid>38908427</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 04:54:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://engineering.fb.com/2023/12/19/core-infra/how-meta-built-the-infrastructure-for-threads/">https://engineering.fb.com/2023/12/19/core-infra/how-meta-built-the-infrastructure-for-threads/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38908427">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

		<p><span>On July 5, 2023, Meta launched Threads, the newest product in our family of apps, to an unprecedented success that saw it garner </span><a href="https://www.threads.net/@zuck/post/CuhOXGmr74R"><span>over 100 million sign ups</span></a><span> in its first five days.</span></p>
<p><span>A small,</span><a href="https://engineering.fb.com/2023/09/07/culture/threads-inside-story-metas-newest-social-app/"> <span>nimble team of engineers built Threads</span></a><span> over the course of only five months of technical work. While the app’s production launch had been under consideration for some time, the business finally made the decision and informed the infrastructure teams to prepare for its launch with only two days’ advance notice. The decision was made with full confidence that Meta’s infrastructure teams can deliver based on their past track record and the maturity of the infrastructure. Despite the daunting challenges with minimal lead time, the infrastructure teams supported the app’s rapid growth exceptionally well.</span></p>
<p><span>The seamless scale that people experienced as they signed up by the millions came on the shoulders of over a decade of infrastructure and product development. This was not infrastructure purposely built for Threads, but that had been built over the course of Meta’s lifetime for many products. It had already been built for scale, growth, performance, and reliability, and it managed to exceed our expectations as Threads grew at a pace that no one could have predicted.</span></p>
<p><span>A huge amount of infrastructure goes into serving Threads. But, because of space limitations, we will only give examples of two existing components that played an important role:</span> <a href="https://engineering.fb.com/2021/08/06/core-infra/zippydb/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>ZippyDB</span></a><span>, our distributed key/value datastore, and</span> <a href="https://engineering.fb.com/2020/08/17/production-engineering/async/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>Async</span></a><span>, our aptly named asynchronous serverless function platform.</span></p>
<h2><span>ZippyDB: Scaling keyspaces for Threads</span></h2>
<p><span>Let’s zoom in on part of the storage layer, where we leveraged ZippyDB, a distributed key/value database that is run as a fully managed service for engineers to build on. It’s built from the ground up to leverage Meta’s infrastructure, and keyspaces hosted on it can be scaled up and down with relative ease and flexibly placed across any number of data centers. </span><a href="https://engineering.fb.com/2013/06/25/core-infra/tao-the-power-of-the-graph/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>TAO</span></a><span>, backed by </span><a href="https://engineering.fb.com/2023/05/16/data-infrastructure/mysql-raft-meta/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>MySQL</span></a><span>, is used for our social graph storage – thus you can find Threads posts and replies directly in that stack. ZippyDB is our key/value counterpart to MySQL, the relational part of our online data stack, and is used for counters, feed ranking/state, and search.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://engineering.fb.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/ZippyDb.1.psd.BodyImage1.jpg?resize=1024,576" width="1024" height="576"></p>
<p><span>The speed at which we can scale the capacity of a keyspace is made possible by two key features: First, the service runs on a common pool of hardware and is plugged into Meta’s overall capacity management framework. Once new capacity is allocated to the service, the machines are automatically added to the service’s pool and the load balancer kicks in to move data to the new machines. We can absorb thousands of new machines in a matter of a few hours once they are added to the service. While this is great, it is not enough since the end-to-end time in approving capacity, possibly draining it from other services and adding it to ZippyDB, can still be in order of a couple of days. We need to also be able to absorb a surge on shorter notice.</span></p>
<p><span>To enable the immediate absorption, we rely on the service architecture’s multi-tenancy and its strong isolation features. This allows for different keyspaces, potentially with complimentary load demands to share the underlying hosts, without worrying about their service level getting impacted when other workloads run hot. There is also slack in the hosts pool due to unused capacity of individual keyspaces as well as buffers for handling disaster recovery events. We can pull levers that shift unused allocations between keyspaces – dipping into any existing slack and letting the hosts run at a higher utilization level to let a keyspace ramp up almost immediately and sustain it over a short interval (a couple of days). All these are simple config changes with tools and automation built around them as they are fairly routine for day-to-day operations.</span></p>
<p><span>The combined effects of strong multi-tenancy and ability to absorb new hardware makes it possible for the service to scale more or less seamlessly, even in the face of a sudden large new demand.</span></p>
<h2><span>Optimizing ZippyDB for a product launch</span></h2>
<p><span>ZippyDB’s resharding protocol allows us to quickly and transparently increase the sharding factor (i.e., horizontal scaling factor) of a ZippyDB use case with zero downtime for clients, all while maintaining full consistency and correctness guarantees. This allows us to rapidly scale out use cases on the critical path of new product launches with zero interruptions to the launch, even if its load increases by 100x.</span></p>
<p><span>We achieve this by having clients hash their keys to logical shards, which are then mapped to a set of physical shards. When a use case grows and requires resharding, we provision a new set of physical shards and install a new logical-to-physical shard mapping in our clients through live configuration changes without downtime. Using hidden access keys on the server itself, and smart data migration logic in our resharding workers, we are then able to atomically move a logical shard from the original mapping to the new mapping. Once all logical shards have been migrated, resharding is complete and we remove the original mapping.</span></p>
<p><span>Because scaling up use cases is a critical operation for new product launches, we have invested heavily in our resharding stack to ensure ZippyDB scaling does not block product launches. Specifically, we have designed the resharding stack in a coordinator-worker model so it is horizontally scalable, allowing us to increase resharding speeds when needed, such as during the Threads launch. Additionally, we have developed a set of emergency operator tools to effortlessly deal with sudden use case growth.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>The combination of these allowed the ZippyDB team to effectively respond to the rapid growth of Threads. Often, when creating new use cases in ZippyDB, we start small initially and then reshard as growth requires. This approach prevents overprovisioning and promotes efficiency in capacity usage. As the viral growth of Threads began, it became evident that we needed to prepare Threads for a 100x growth by proactively performing resharding. With the help of automation tools developed in the past, we completed the resharding just in time as the Threads team opened up the floodgates to traffic at midnight UK time. This enabled delightful user experiences with Threads, even as its user base soared.</span></p>
<h2><span>Async: Scaling workload execution for Threads</span></h2>
<p><span>Async (also known as </span><a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/pdf/10.1145/3600006.3613155"><span>XFaaS</span></a><span>) is a serverless function platform capable of deferring computing to off-peak hours, allowing engineers at Meta to reduce their time from solution conception to production deployment. Async currently processes trillions of function calls per day on more than 100,000 servers and can support </span><a href="https://engineering.fb.com/2022/07/27/developer-tools/programming-languages-endorsed-for-server-side-use-at-meta/"><span>multiple programming languages</span></a><span>, including HackLang, Python, Haskell, and Erlang.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://engineering.fb.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/Async-Server-2.jpg?w=1024" alt="" width="1024" height="521" srcset="https://engineering.fb.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/Async-Server-2.jpg 1920w, https://engineering.fb.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/Async-Server-2.jpg?resize=916,466 916w, https://engineering.fb.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/Async-Server-2.jpg?resize=768,391 768w, https://engineering.fb.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/Async-Server-2.jpg?resize=1024,521 1024w, https://engineering.fb.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/Async-Server-2.jpg?resize=1536,782 1536w, https://engineering.fb.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/Async-Server-2.jpg?resize=96,49 96w, https://engineering.fb.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/Async-Server-2.jpg?resize=192,98 192w" sizes="(max-width: 992px) 100vw, 62vw"></p>
<p><span>The platform abstracts the details of deployment, queueing, scheduling, scaling, and disaster recovery and readiness, so that developers can focus on their core business logic and offload the rest of the heavy lifting to Async. By onboarding their code in this platform, their code automatically inherits hyperscale attributes. Scalability is not the only key feature of Async. Code uploaded to the platform also inherits guarantees on execution with configurable retries, time for delivery, rate limits, and capacity accountability.</span></p>
<p><span>The workloads commonly executed on Async are those that do not require blocking an active user’s experience with a product and can be performed anywhere from a few seconds to several hours after a user’s action. Async played a critical role in offering users the ability to build community quickly by choosing to follow people on Threads that they already follow on Instagram. Specifically, when a new user joins Threads and chooses to follow the same set of people they do on Instagram, the computationally expensive operation of executing the user’s request to follow the same social graph in Threads is conducted via Async in a scalable manner, which avoids blocking or negatively impacting the user’s onboarding experience.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>Doing this for 100 million users in five days required significant processing power. Moreover, many celebrities joined Threads, and when that happened millions of people could be queued up to follow them. Both this operation and the corresponding notifications also occurred in Async, enabling scalable operations in the face of a large number of users.</span></p>
<p><span>While the volume of Async jobs generated from the rapid Threads user onboarding was several orders of magnitude higher than our initial expectations, Async gracefully absorbed the increased load and queued them for controlled execution. </span><span>Specifically, the execution was managed within rate limits, which ensured that we were sending notifications and allowing people to make connections in a timely manner without overloading the downstream services that receive traffic from these Async jobs. Async automatically adjusted the flow of execution to match its capacity as well as the capacity of dependent services, such as the social graph database, all without manual intervention from either Threads engineers or infrastructure engineers.</span></p>
<h2><span>Where infrastructure and culture meet</span></h2>
<p><span>Threads’ swift development within a mere five months of technical work underscores the strengths of Meta’s infrastructure and engineering culture. Meta’s products leverage a shared infrastructure that has withstood the test of time, empowering product teams to move fast and rapidly scale successful products. The infrastructure boasts a high level of automation, ensuring that, except for efforts to secure capacity on short notice, the automatic redistribution, load balancing, and scaling up of workloads occurred smoothly and transparently.&nbsp;</span><span>Meta thrives on a move-fast engineering culture, wherein engineers take strong ownership and collaborate seamlessly to accomplish a large shared goal, with efficient processes that would take a typical organization months to coordinate. As an example, our</span><a href="https://atscaleconference.com/videos/metas-sev-culture-how-todays-sevs-create-tomorrows-reliability/"> <span>SEV incident-management culture</span></a><span> has been an important tool in getting the right visibility, focus, and action in places where we all need to coordinate and move fast. Overall, these factors combined to ensure the success of the Threads launch.</span></p>

		
	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Visualizing Ext4 (330 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://buredoranna.github.io/linux/ext4/2020/01/09/ext4-viz.html</link>
            <guid>38907821</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 03:13:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://buredoranna.github.io/linux/ext4/2020/01/09/ext4-viz.html">https://buredoranna.github.io/linux/ext4/2020/01/09/ext4-viz.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38907821">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      
<center><h2>What does ext4 look like?</h2></center>


<div><p>That is... if I start with a blank drive, a drive made completely of 0x00s, and then do mkfs.ext4, what does the drive, now embossed with ext4, look like?</p></div>

<div><p>I mean, what I wanted to see, is what it takes to transmogrify a bunch 0x00s, from "nothing" into the purposeful assemblage of bytes that is an ext4 filesystem.</p></div>

<div><p>At first I figured I’d try visualizing a live drive, like /dev/sda... but quickly figured 'dd' + 'live drive' could get me into trouble, so opted for adding a small secondary drive to my VM.</p></div>

<div><p>Then I thought, even with a virtual machine, working with 'dd' and /dev/sdX would be more trouble than it was worth. I then remembered I didn’t have to use drives at all, virtual or otherwise, I could just work with a regular file, configured as a loop device.</p></div>

<div><p>And it turns out mount/umount have evolved since I last experimented with loop devices... you don’t have to 'losetup' the loop device anymore just a simple:</p></div>

<pre># mount -o loop &lt;foo_file&gt; &lt;bar_dir&gt;
# umount &lt;bar_dir&gt;
</pre>



<div><p>Using a loop device simplified my efforts, and diminished the likelihood of a<br><a href="https://askubuntu.com/questions/982552/accidentally-did-dd-dev-sda">dd accident</a>.</p></div>

<div><p>So a little about what we’re looking at.</p></div>

<p>I always start with a blank file... that is a file created with 'dd' and a source of '/dev/zero'... the calculated size of the file correspond to a final image with eight blocks, each 64-pixels/bytes high, and 1024-pixels/bytes wide.<br></p>

<pre>$ dd if=/dev/zero of=blockfile.ext4 bs=$((64 * 1024)) count=8
</pre>

<p>The output of this is predictable<br></p>
<pre>$ od -x -A x blockfile.ext4
000000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
*
080000
</pre>

<div><p>But I wanted to see the difference between a zero file, and one with whatever structure mkfs.ext4 adds to the drive...</p></div>

<div><p>Of note: the size of drive I’m working with is too small for a journal... but thats okay... Doing a visualization which includes a journal I’m leaving for a future project.</p></div>

<p>So now the output of 'od' of the blockfile which mkfs.ext4 is run against, is a little more interesting... here we begin to see structure:<br></p>

<pre>$ od -x -Ax blockfile.ext4
000000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
*
000400 0040 0000 0200 0000 0019 0000 01e2 0000
000410 0035 0000 0001 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
000420 2000 0000 2000 0000 0040 0000 0000 0000
000430 c737 5e10 0000 ffff ef53 0001 0001 0000
000440 c737 5e10 0000 0000 0000 0000 0001 0000
000450 0000 0000 000b 0000 0080 0000 0038 0000
000460 02c2 0000 046b 0000 927f 9037 d060 5e4c
000470 1b83 287a 7389 0001 0000 0000 0000 0000
000480 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
*
0004c0 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0003
0004d0 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
0004e0 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 7da5 5d6c
0004f0 72c1 5b42 719d b2ee 63d5 d142 0001 0040
000500 000c 0000 0000 0000 c737 5e10 0000 0000
000510 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
*
000560 0001 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
000570 0000 0000 0104 0000 0015 0000 0000 0000
000580 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
*
0007f0 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 7d3f 9ace
000800 0006 0000 0016 0000 0026 0000 01e2 0035
000810 0002 0004 0000 0000 c571 4e0a 0035 4797
000820 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
000830 0000 0000 0000 0000 96a2 c509 0000 0000
000840 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
*
001800 ffff 002f 1fe0 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
001810 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
*
001830 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 8000
001840 ffff ffff ffff ffff ffff ffff ffff ffff
*
001c00 0002 0000 000c 0201 002e 0000 0002 0000
001c10 000c 0202 2e2e 0000 000b 0000 03dc 020a
001c20 6f6c 7473 662b 756f 646e 0000 0000 0000
001c30 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
*
001ff0 0000 0000 0000 0000 000c de00 e669 11f0
002000 000b 0000 000c 0201 002e 0000 0002 0000
002010 03e8 0202 2e2e 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
002020 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
*
0023f0 0000 0000 0000 0000 000c de00 0f7a 7b5d
002400 0000 0000 03f4 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
002410 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
*
0027f0 0000 0000 0000 0000 000c de00 3e04 8f88
002800 0000 0000 03f4 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
002810 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
*
002bf0 0000 0000 0000 0000 000c de00 3e04 8f88
002c00 0000 0000 03f4 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
002c10 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
*
002ff0 0000 0000 0000 0000 000c de00 3e04 8f88
003000 0000 0000 03f4 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
003010 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
*
0033f0 0000 0000 0000 0000 000c de00 3e04 8f88
003400 0000 0000 03f4 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
003410 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000
*
[... snip ...]
</pre>

<div><p>But at the byte density provided by the output of 'od', trying to visualize the ext4 structure is like trying to visualize the structure of three deciduous forests by examining the leaves of a single tree... I wanted a picture which would let me "zoom out", giving me a better idea of what I was looking at...</p></div>

<div><p>So I came up with this... each blue block is 1024 pixels wide, and 64 pixels high... each pixel represents a single byte... Nothing much to see here, except a drive made entirely of 0x00s.</p></div>

<p><img src="https://buredoranna.github.io/assets/images/blockfile.nulls.ext4.png" alt="I miss you, image =("></p>

<div><p>It starts to get interesting after creating the ext4 filesystem, and see this...</p></div>

<p><img src="https://buredoranna.github.io/assets/images/blockfile.nouserdata.ext4.png" alt="I miss you, image"></p>

<div><p>With this image we can can see the structure added by mkfs.ext4, and where on the drive the ext4 data is located.</p></div>

<p>Its worth noting this image doesn’t actually differentiate between "ext4 bytes" and "non-ext4 bytes". That is, there could be bytes owned by ext4, but if they are 0x00s they are color coded the same as any other 0x00... But even with this limitation, the image is interesting.
<br></p>

<div><p>But I still wanted an image which differentiated between ext4 data and "user" data. My solution was to create a file 1024 bytes in size from /dev/urandom, and copy that file to the mounted loop device. Then, in my visualization code, when reading the blockfile, I test if "the next 1024 bytes to be read" match "the 1024 bytes of the reference file", and if they match, color code those 1024 pixels accordingly.</p></div>

<div><p>And with user data copied to the drive, we get this:</p></div>

<p><img src="https://buredoranna.github.io/assets/images/blockfile.ext4.120.png" alt="I miss you, image"></p>

<div><p>Which I find very satisfying... But still, I wanted an animation. So I built an animated GIF.</p></div>

<div><p>Between each frame, the "user data" file is copied to the drive three times... so there are three copies written each frame... This makes for a more expressive animation and a smaller GIF than if each frame was a single 'cp' of the file.</p></div>

<div><p>I hope you enjoy this as much as I do.</p></div>



<div><p>And by way of comparison, here is a similar animation, but with ext2</p></div>


<hr>

<p><br>Here begins the ext4 rabbit hole...<br>
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ext4">Wikipedia</a>
<a href="https://ext4.wiki.kernel.org/index.php/Main_Page">ext4 wiki</a><a></a>
<a href="https://www.kernel.org/doc/html/latest/admin-guide/ext4.html">Admin Guide</a>
<a href="http://e2fsprogs.sourceforge.net/">e2fsprogs</a>
<a href="https://www.kernel.org/doc/html/latest/filesystems/ext4/index.html">ext4 Data Structures and Algorithms</a></p>



    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Database of 16,000 Artists Used to Train Midjourney AI Goes Viral (144 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.artnews.com/art-news/news/midjourney-ai-artists-database-1234691955/</link>
            <guid>38907729</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 02:57:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.artnews.com/art-news/news/midjourney-ai-artists-database-1234691955/">https://www.artnews.com/art-news/news/midjourney-ai-artists-database-1234691955/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38907729">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post-1234691955">
		<header>
			<div>
	<nav data-dropdown="">

	
	<ul data-dropdown-list="">
					<li data-dropdown-list-item="">
				<span>
	<a href="https://www.artnews.com/">

	Home
	</a>
</span>
			</li>
					<li data-dropdown-list-item="">
				<span>
	<a href="https://www.artnews.com/c/art-news/">

	ARTnews
	</a>
</span>
			</li>
					<li data-dropdown-list-item="">
				<span>
	<a href="https://www.artnews.com/c/art-news/news/">

	News
	</a>
</span>
			</li>
			</ul>
</nav>
</div>

		</header>

		

		

		<div>

			<article>
				<div>
	

<figure>

			
<div>
	
			<p><img src="https://www.artnews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/4f6e27fd85d4a899633e2228d076124f_1920_KR-wide.jpg?w=2000" alt="Metalwork Colossus by Hyan Tran, age 6, for a special drop of Magic the Gathering benefitting the Seattle Children's Hospital in 2021." srcset="https://www.artnews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/4f6e27fd85d4a899633e2228d076124f_1920_KR-wide.jpg 2800w, https://www.artnews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/4f6e27fd85d4a899633e2228d076124f_1920_KR-wide.jpg?resize=400,183 400w" sizes="(min-width: 87.5rem) 1000px, (min-width: 78.75rem) 681px, (min-width: 48rem) 450px, (max-width: 48rem) 250px" height="" width="" decoding="async">
			
			</p>
	
	</div>
	
			
			
<figcaption>
	
					<span>A database shows this image by Hyan Tran, age 6, was also scraped by Midjourney for its AI image generator.</span>
		
									<cite>©2023 Scalefast Inc.
Courtesy of Magic the Gathering Secret Lair</cite>
					
	</figcaption>

			
</figure>

</div>

				<div>
					<p>
	For many, a new year includes resolutions to do better and build better habits. For <a href="https://www.artnews.com/t/midjourney/" id="auto-tag_midjourney" data-tag="midjourney">Midjourney</a>, the start of 2024 meant having to deal with a circulating list of artists whose work the company used to train its generative artificial intelligence program.</p>



<p>
	During the New Year’s weekend, artists linked to a Google Sheet on the social media platforms X (formerly known as Twitter) and Bluesky, alleging that it showed how Midjourney developed a database of time periods, styles, genres, movements, mediums, techniques, and thousands of artists to train its AI text-to-image generator. Jon Lam, a senior storyboard artist at Riot Games, also posted several screenshots of Midjourney software developers discussing the creation of a database of artists to train its AI image generator to emulate.

	</p>
<section>
	

	<h2 id="section-heading">

	
		Related Articles
	
	</h2>


	
</section>




<p>
	https://x.com/JonLamArt/status/1741545927435784424?s=20</p>



<p>
	The 24-page list of artists’ names used by Midjourney as the training foundation for its AI image generator (Exhibit J) includes modern and contemporary blue-chip names,as well as commercially successfully illustrators for companies like Hasbro and Nintendo. Notable artists include Cy Twombly, Andy Warhol, Anish Kapoor, Yayoi Kusama, Gerhard Richter, Frida Kahlo, Andy Warhol, Ellsworth Kelly, Damien Hirst, Amedeo Modigliani, Pablo Picasso, Paul Signac, Norman Rockwell, Paul Cézanne, Banksy, Walt Disney, and Vincent van Gogh.

</p>



<p>
	Midjourney’s dataset also includes artists who contributed art to the popular trading card game Magic the Gathering, including Hyan Tran, a six-year-old child and one-time art contributor who <a rel="nofollow" href="https://secretlair.wizards.com/us/en/product/694985/extra-life-2021" target="_blank">participated in a fundraiser for the Seattle Children’s Hospital in 2021</a>. </p>



<p>
	<a rel="nofollow" href="https://bsky.app/profile/thephilfoglio.bsky.social/post/3khxc4wqgmt2e" target="_blank">Phil Foglio</a> encouraged other artists to search the list to see if their names were included and to seek legal representation if they did not already have a lawyer. </p>



<p>
	Access to the Google file was soon restricted, but <a rel="nofollow" href="https://web.archive.org/web/20231231203837/https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1MEglfejpqgVcaf-I-cgZ5ngV_MlaOTeGXAoBPJO69FM/htmlview#" target="_blank">a version has been uploaded to the Internet Archive</a>. </p>



<p>
	The list of 16,000 artists was included as part of a lawsuit amendment to a class-action complaint<a href="https://www.artnews.com/art-news/news/artists-class-action-lawsuit-against-ai-image-generator-midjourney-stability-deviantart-1234653892/"> targeted at Stability AI, Midjourney, and DeviantArt </a>and the submission of <a rel="nofollow" href="https://stablediffusionlitigation.com/pdf/00201/1-1-stable-diffusion-complaint-exhibits.pdf" target="_blank">455-pages of supplementary evidence</a> filed on November 29 last year. </p>



<p>
	The amendment was filed after a judge in California federal court <a href="https://www.artnews.com/art-news/news/judge-dismisses-several-copyright-allegations-against-ai-companies-in-artist-class-action-1234685299/">dismissed several claims</a> brought forth by a group of artists against Midjourney and DeviantArt on October 30. 

</p>



<p>
	The class-action copyright lawsuit was<a href="https://www.artnews.com/art-news/news/artists-class-action-lawsuit-against-ai-image-generator-midjourney-stability-deviantart-1234653892/"> first filed almost a year ago</a> in the United States District Court of the Northern District of California.</p>



<p>
	Last September, the US Copyright Review Board decided that an image generated using Midjourney’s software could not be copyright due to how it was produced. Jason M. Allen’s image had garnered the $750 top prize in the digital category for art at the Colorado State Fair in 2022. The win went viral online, but <a href="https://www.artnews.com/art-news/news/colorado-state-fair-ai-generated-artwork-controversy-1234638022/">prompted intense worry and anxiety among artists</a> about the future of their careers. </p>



<p>
	Concern about artworks being scraped without permission and used to train AI image generators also prompted researchers from the University of Chicago to create a digital tool for artists <a href="https://www.artnews.com/art-news/news/new-data-poisoning-tool-enables-artists-to-fight-back-against-image-generating-ai-companies-1234684663/">to help “poison” massive image sets</a> and destabilize text-to-image outputs.</p>



<p>
	At publication time, Midjourney did not respond to requests for comment from <em>ARTnews</em>.</p>










				</div>

				<div>
	<nav data-dropdown="">

						<h4 data-dropdown-list-item=""> Read More About:</h4>
			
	
</nav>
</div>
	

			</article>

			
		</div>
	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[iPhone that fell from hole in Alaska 737 MAX flight is found, still open to Mail (506 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/SeanSafyre/status/1744138937239822685</link>
            <guid>38907620</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 02:34:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/SeanSafyre/status/1744138937239822685">https://twitter.com/SeanSafyre/status/1744138937239822685</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38907620">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://twitter.com/SeanSafyre/status/1744138937239822685: Error: Request failed with status code 400]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[MotorOS: a Rust-first operating system for x64 VMs (306 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/moturus/motor-os</link>
            <guid>38907568</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 02:24:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/moturus/motor-os">https://github.com/moturus/motor-os</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38907568">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-target="readme-toc.content">
            <article itemprop="text"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Motūrus OS</h2>
<p dir="auto">Motūrus project builds a simple, fast, and secure operating system (Motūrus OS) for the cloud.</p>
<p dir="auto">In more specific terms, Motūrus OS (sometimes called Motor OS),
is a new operating system targeting virtual machine-based workloads such as web serving, "serverless", edge caching, etc.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/moturus/motor-os/blob/main/docs/screenshot.md">Screenshot</a></p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Why?</h2>
<p dir="auto">At the moment, most virtualized production workloads run Linux.
While Linux has many advanced features that in many
situations mean it is the only reasonable OS choice, there are
several complications that make it not ideal, in theory,
for some virtualized workloads:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Linux is optimized for baremetal, which leads to inefficiencies
when it is used inside a VM that is running on a Linux host:
<ul dir="auto">
<li>duplicate block caches</li>
<li>duplicate page table walks</li>
<li>the host scheduler can preempt the VCPU holding a spinlock in the VM's kernel</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Linux is difficult to use:
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Docker, Nix OS, "serverless", etc. all exist because of Linux's complexity</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Linux has, historically, not been very secure</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">A new operating system built from ground-up with the focus
on virtualized workloads can be made much simpler and more
secure than Linux, while matching or exceeding its
performance and/or efficiency.</p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What?</h2>
<p dir="auto">Motūrus OS is a microkernel-based operating system, built in
Rust, that targets virtualized workloads exclusively. It
currently supports x64 KVM-based virtual machines, and can
run in either Qemu or Cloud Hypervisor.</p>
<p dir="auto">Rust is <em>the</em> language of Motūrus OS: not only it is
implemented in Rust, it also exposes its ABI in Rust, not C.</p>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What works</h3>
<p dir="auto">While at the moment most of the subsystems are working in only
POC/MVP mode, they <strong>are</strong> working, and you can run, say, a web
server.</p>
<p dir="auto">More specifically, these things work:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>boots via MBR (Qemu) or PVH (Cloud Hypervisor) in about 200ms</li>
<li>himem micro-kernel</li>
<li>scheduling:
<ul dir="auto">
<li>a simple multi-processor round robin (SMP)</li>
<li>in-kernel scheduling is cooperative
<ul dir="auto">
<li>the kernel is very small and does not block, so does not need to be preemptible</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>the userspace is preemptible</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>memory management:
<ul dir="auto">
<li>only 4K pages at the moment</li>
<li>stacks are guarded</li>
<li>page faults in the userspace work and are properly handled (only stack memory allocations are currently lazy)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I/O subsystem (in the userspace)
<ul dir="auto">
<li>VirtIO-BLK and VirtIO-NET <a href="https://github.com/moturus/motor-os/tree/main/src/lib/virtio">drivers</a></li>
<li>two simple filesystems
(<a href="https://crates.io/crates/srfs" rel="nofollow">srfs</a> and
<a href="https://crates.io/crates/flatfs" rel="nofollow">flatfs</a>)</li>
<li><a href="https://crates.io/crates/smoltcp" rel="nofollow">smoltcp</a>-based networking (TCP only at the moment)
<ul dir="auto">
<li>a simple <a href="https://github.com/moturus/motor-os/tree/main/src/bin/httpd">httpd</a> is provided</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>the userspace:
<ul dir="auto">
<li>multiple processes, with preemption</li>
<li>threads, TLS</li>
<li>Rust's standard library <a href="https://github.com/moturus/rust/tree/moturus-2023-12-16">mostly ported</a>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Rust programs that use Rust standard library and do not
depend, directly or indirectly, on Unix or Windows FFI,
will cross-compile for Motūrus OS and run, subject to
"what does not work" below</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>a simple <a href="https://github.com/moturus/rush">unix-like shell</a> in the serial console</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What does not work</h3>
<p dir="auto">Most pieces are not yet ready for production use. No security
audit has been made. It is very easy to hit a "not implemented"
panic in sys-io (the userspace I/O subsystem).</p>
<p dir="auto">More specifically:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Filesystem: most Rust std::fs APIs have been implemented as
proof-of-concept, but are slow (synchronous) and will
have to be reimplemented using Motūrus async I/O</li>
<li>Networking:
<ul dir="auto">
<li>std::net::TcpStream is mostly implemented, but there are
todo! panics</li>
<li>other protocols are not implemented yet</li>
<li>performance can (and will) be better</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The ecosystem outside Rust std:
<ul dir="auto">
<li>crates like rand or rustls can be compiled and used
with minor tweaks</li>
<li>crates depending on async runtimes (e.g.
<a href="https://tokio.rs/" rel="nofollow">Tokio</a>) will not compile at the moment
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/tokio-rs/mio">Tokio Mio</a> should be
not too difficult to port</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>crates that are wrappers around native Linux or Windows APIs
will not work, obviously</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How can I build/run it?</h2>
<p dir="auto">See <a href="https://github.com/moturus/motor-os/blob/main/docs/build.md">docs/build.md</a>.</p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Thanks</h2>
<p dir="auto">Big thanks to Philipp Oppermann for his great <a href="https://os.phil-opp.com/" rel="nofollow">Writing an OS in Rust</a> blog series - it has inspired a lot of people to experiment in this space.</p>
</article>
          </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: I made a HTMX Playground 100% in the browser (434 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lassebomh.github.io/htmx-playground/</link>
            <guid>38906989</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 01:03:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lassebomh.github.io/htmx-playground/">https://lassebomh.github.io/htmx-playground/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38906989">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="popup-top">
        <main id="popup">
            <article>
                
                
                <p>
                    A simple code sandbox for playing around with HTMX. No setup needed!
                </p>
                <p>
                    It allows you to write code in a backend-like environment, running entirely inside the browser. You can define endpoints within server.js and render your own templates. It will run a mock server that intersepts outgoing requests from HTMX. The request handling and templating engine should be very familiar to people who use Django. In principle, this project isn't specific to HTMX, so you are free to try out other libraries as well.
                </p>
                
                <p>
                    Check out the examples! I've adapted them from the original <a href="https://htmx.org/examples/">htmx.org examples</a>.
                </p>
                <h2>Saving &amp; sharing</h2>
                <ol>
                    <li>Press "Copy as JSON" in the top right.</li>
                    <li>Upload the contents as a Gist, and enter the raw URL in "Load Playground"</li>
                    <li>The URL on this page will update, and can now be shared.</li>
                </ol>
                <p>
                    The code is available <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/lassebomh/htmx-playground">on GitHub</a>.
                </p>

                <h2>Limitations</h2>
                <ul>
                    <li>No page navigation</li>
                    <li>Limited mobile support</li>
                </ul>

                <h2>Libraries used</h2>
                <ul>
                    <li>Svelte</li>
                    <li>Ace (code editor)</li>
                    <li>PollyJS (mock server)</li>
                    <li>Nunjucks (templating engine)</li>
                </ul>
                
            </article>
        </main>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I made an app that runs Mistral 7B 0.2 LLM locally on iPhone Pros (278 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://apps.apple.com/us/app/offline-chat-private-ai/id6474077941</link>
            <guid>38906966</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 01:00:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/offline-chat-private-ai/id6474077941">https://apps.apple.com/us/app/offline-chat-private-ai/id6474077941</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38906966">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
  
<!---->
<!---->
<!---->
    


<!---->
    


  <div dir="" data-test-bidi=""><p>Introducing Offline Chat, the next-generation AI ChatBot that runs entirely on your device without the Internet.&nbsp;You can use it anywhere, and your data stays private and secure.</p><p>While Offline Chat might not match the prowess of top-tier online models due to inherent memory and processing constraints, it stands out as an engaging and versatile tool. It's perfect for sparking creativity and assisting in various tasks such as writing, though it's advisable to verify facts independently.</p><p>The app requires a Pro iPhone with a minimum of 6GB of RAM. Only the following devices meet the requirement:</p><p>- iPhone 15 Pro, iPhone 14 Pro, iPhone 13 Pro, iPhone 12 Pro.<br>- iPads: Please check. RAM varies based on model and year. </p><p>For the technically oriented, the AI is a fine tuned large language model based on Mistral 7B 0.1, quantized to 3-bit.</p></div>

<!---->
  <section>
    <div>
      <h2>What’s New</h2>
        

    </div>
    <div>
          <p dir="false" data-test-bidi="">Updated model to Mistral 7B 0.2. This new model is truly extraordinary considering its size.</p>


      </div>
  </section>

      <section>
      <p>
        <h2>
          Ratings and Reviews
        </h2>

        <!---->
      </p>

        


      

<!---->    </section>


<!---->
<!---->
<!---->
  <section>
  <div>
    <h2>
      App Privacy
    </h2>

    


  </div>

  <p>
    The developer, <span>Opus Noma LLC</span>, indicated that the app’s privacy practices may include handling of data as described below. For more information, see the <a href="http://opusnoma.com/privacy">developer’s privacy policy</a>.
  </p>

  <div>
        
        <h3>Data Not Collected</h3>
        <p>The developer does not collect any data from this app.</p>
<!---->      </div>

    <p>Privacy practices may vary, for example, based on the features you use or your age. <a href="https://apps.apple.com/story/id1538632801">Learn&nbsp;More</a></p>
</section>


<section>
  <div>
    <h2>Information</h2>
    <dl>
        <p>
          <dt>Seller</dt>
          <dd>
              Opus Noma LLC
          </dd>
        </p>
        <p>
          <dt>Size</dt>
          <dd aria-label="3.3 gigabytes">3.3 GB</dd>
        </p>
        <p>
          <dt>Category</dt>
          <dd>
              <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/genre/id6000" data-metrics-click="{&quot;actionType&quot;:&quot;navigate&quot;,&quot;actionUrl&quot;:&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/genre/id6000&quot;,&quot;targetType&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;targetId&quot;:&quot;GenrePage&quot;}">
                Business
              </a>
          </dd>
        </p>
      <div>
        <dt>Compatibility</dt>
          <dd>
              <dl>
                <dt>
                  iPhone
                </dt>
                <dd>Requires iOS 17.0 or later.
                </dd>
              </dl>
              <dl>
                <dt>
                  iPad
                </dt>
                <dd>Requires iPadOS 17.0 or later.
                </dd>
              </dl>
              <dl>
                <dt>
                  Mac
                </dt>
                <dd>Requires macOS&nbsp;14.0 or later and a Mac with Apple&nbsp;M1&nbsp;chip or later.
                </dd>
              </dl>
          </dd>
      </div>
<!---->      
      <p>
        <dt>Age Rating</dt>
        <dd>
             12+
              <span>Infrequent/Mild Medical/Treatment Information</span>
              <span>Infrequent/Mild Mature/Suggestive Themes</span>
        </dd>
      </p>
<!---->      <p>
        <dt>Copyright</dt>
        <dd>© 2023 Opus Noma LLC</dd>
      </p>
        <p>
          <dt>Price</dt>
          <dd>$1.99</dd>
        </p>
<!---->
    </dl>
  </div>
  <div>
    <ul>
<!---->        <li>
          <a data-metrics-click="{&quot;actionType&quot;:&quot;navigate&quot;,&quot;targetType&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;targetId&quot;:&quot;LinkToAppSupport&quot;}" href="http://opusnoma.com/">
            App Support
          </a>
        </li>
<!---->        <li>
          <a data-metrics-click="{&quot;actionType&quot;:&quot;navigate&quot;,&quot;targetType&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;targetId&quot;:&quot;LinkToPrivacyPolicy&quot;}" href="http://opusnoma.com/privacy">
            Privacy Policy
          </a>
        </li>
    </ul>
  </div>
</section>

<section>
  <ul>
<!---->      <li>
        <a data-metrics-click="{&quot;actionType&quot;:&quot;navigate&quot;,&quot;targetType&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;targetId&quot;:&quot;LinkToAppSupport&quot;}" href="http://opusnoma.com/">
          App Support
        </a>
      </li>
<!---->      <li>
        <a data-metrics-click="{&quot;actionType&quot;:&quot;navigate&quot;,&quot;targetType&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;targetId&quot;:&quot;LinkToPrivacyPolicy&quot;}" href="http://opusnoma.com/privacy">
          Privacy Policy
        </a>
      </li>
  </ul>
</section>

  <section>
    <p>
      <h2>Supports</h2>
    </p>
    <ul>
        <li>
          <img src="https://apps.apple.com/assets/images/supports/supports-FamilySharing@2x-f58f31bc78fe9fe7be3565abccbecb34.png" alt="" role="presentation">
          <div>
              <h3 dir="ltr">
    Family Sharing
</h3>


              <h4 dir="">
        

                    <p data-test-bidi="">Up to six family members can use this app with Family&nbsp;Sharing enabled.</p>

    


<!----></h4>


          </div>
        </li>
    </ul>
  </section>

<!---->
    <section>
      <p>
        <h2>
          More By This Developer
        </h2>
        <!---->
      </p>

      
    </section>

    <section>
      <p>
        <h2>
          You Might Also Like
        </h2>
        <!---->
      </p>

      
    </section>


<!---->

<!----></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How An ASML Lithography Machine Moves a Wafer [video] (170 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1fOA85xtYxs</link>
            <guid>38906881</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 00:46:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1fOA85xtYxs">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1fOA85xtYxs</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38906881">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How We Handle Cap Table Information (117 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://henrysward.medium.com/how-we-handle-captable-information-c98d85d79277</link>
            <guid>38906749</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 00:31:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://henrysward.medium.com/how-we-handle-captable-information-c98d85d79277">https://henrysward.medium.com/how-we-handle-captable-information-c98d85d79277</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38906749">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><a rel="noopener follow" href="https://henrysward.medium.com/?source=post_page-----c98d85d79277--------------------------------"><div aria-hidden="false"><p><img alt="Henry Ward" src="https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fill:88:88/1*-fzeFCY7lgBp4RqEXdKdVw.jpeg" width="44" height="44" loading="lazy" data-testid="authorPhoto"></p></div></a></div><p id="9bd8">On Friday we had an internal policy violation that affected three companies. I’ve been in touch with the founders and I’m appalled we made that mistake and it should never have happened. It is unacceptable and we’ve dealt with the violation on Saturday morning and are continuing the investigation to make sure it never happens again.</p><p id="dba1">Let me share our framework on data privacy and access controls to hopefully address concerns from this weekend. For a deeper dive, I will bucket data privacy into four buckets with different rules that I will cover separately.</p><p id="779c">1. <strong>Public Disclosures:</strong> We can only publish <em>aggregate and anonymous data</em>. So we can say things like there are 34K startups on Carta, or the average Series A startup has 25 employees, etc… However, we cannot say Acme Startup has 41 shareholders or the PPS is $13.24. You will see this type of aggregate anonymous information frequently in our data reports.</p><p id="8e1c">2. <strong>Internal Systems Disclosures:</strong> We can use cap table data for onboarding and internal systems development. So for example, we can load cap table data into dashboards for audit, we can write health checks to make sure cap table reports are correct, we can run machine learning algorithms to predict when you need a 409A, etc… We can use cap table data <em>to help us improve the software or customer experience</em>. This also includes things like when support teams access cap tables (through an approval and audit system) or when a customer needs help correcting or updating their cap table. All human access to cap tables is tracked and audited.</p><p id="e651">3. <strong>Sales &amp; Marketing:</strong> Lastly, we can market to our customers and users. For example, we can offer new products to help companies with employee compensation, taxes, and expense reporting. Occasionally we have offered products directly to employee shareholders. For example, in the past we have offered stock based loan products to employees of certain companies where employees can access loans to exercise their stock. But when we offer these products to employees we only do it in collaboration with the company. The company has to approve the program for their employees for us to offer it.</p><p id="5023"><strong>4. CartaX: </strong>CartaX is a separate product that operates as an opt-in marketplace where investors are invited to enter bids and asks on different companies. At any given time we have about one hundred companies that are in the marketplace. Where CartaX and the cap table business converge is if we match a trade in the marketplace, we go to the company and ask if they will allow it. If the company allows it, we use their cap table to execute the trade. If the company doesn’t allow it, we stop the trade. We do not and will never trade without company consent.</p><p id="81c5">In the case of Linear and two other companies, we had an internal breach of protocol and we contacted someone directly on the cap table. That never should have happened and is absolutely a breach of our privacy protocols. And we have addressed it over the weekend.</p><p id="2c11">The second mistake might be whether we are too close to the cap table business to be helping on liquidity. We started CartaX five years ago to help founders and companies with liquidity and it has mostly been a net positive for founders, employees, and shareholders. But even if we do everything perfectly and make zero mistakes, perhaps just the appearance of being in the liquidity business makes us seem compromised. Everything we do must be grounded in trust and if being in the liquidity business compromises that trust, perhaps we need to reevaluate that offering.</p><p id="62dc">I will think about this and come back with more thoughts in the coming months. If you have a perspective on whether Carta should be helping companies with liquidity, please reach out to me. I’d love to hear them.</p><p id="83f6">I’m sorry for scaring everybody about this. After ten years of managing cap tables across 40,000 startups, I promise we aren’t compromising anyone’s data. We won’t be here if you don’t trust us. Trust, transparency, and integrity is our most important currency. If you would like to chat with me more one-on-one, please email me at <a href="mailto:henry.ward@carta.com" rel="noopener ugc nofollow" target="_blank">henry.ward@carta.com</a> and we can set up a zoom.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Buffett once bet $1M that he could beat a group of hedge funds over 10 years (118 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://finance.yahoo.com/news/warren-buffett-once-bet-1m-113000485.html</link>
            <guid>38906586</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 00:07:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/warren-buffett-once-bet-1m-113000485.html">https://finance.yahoo.com/news/warren-buffett-once-bet-1m-113000485.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38906586">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><figure><div><p><img alt="Warren Buffett once bet $1M that he could beat a group of fancy hedge funds over 10 years — and he crushed them with a technique requiring absolutely no investing skill. Here's what he did" src="https://s.yimg.com/ny/api/res/1.2/PAPJyRp1wWXzoalzy.3PIA--/YXBwaWQ9aGlnaGxhbmRlcjt3PTk2MDtoPTQyNw--/https://media.zenfs.com/en/moneywise_327/2ced5299e5954d8176723c1e63fb13e7" data-src="https://s.yimg.com/ny/api/res/1.2/PAPJyRp1wWXzoalzy.3PIA--/YXBwaWQ9aGlnaGxhbmRlcjt3PTk2MDtoPTQyNw--/https://media.zenfs.com/en/moneywise_327/2ced5299e5954d8176723c1e63fb13e7"></p></div><p><figcaption>Warren Buffett once bet $1M that he could beat a group of fancy hedge funds over 10 years — and he crushed them with a technique requiring absolutely no investing skill. Here's what he did</figcaption></p></figure><p>Known for their complex investment strategies, hedge funds are typically seen as exclusive options for the ultra-rich. However, you don’t have to be among the elite to achieve comparable, or even superior, returns.</p><p>According to legendary investor Warren Buffett, there’s a very simple strategy that has the potential to outperform these complex hedge funds. Buffett was at one point so confident about this strategy that he was willing to wager a million dollars on its effectiveness.</p><h2>Don’t miss</h2><ul><li><p>Commercial real estate has outperformed the S&amp;P 500 over 25 years. Here's how to diversify your portfolio <a href="https://moneywise.com/investing/alternative-investments/hedge-your-portfolio-with-commercial-real-estate?throw=C1DM1&amp;utm_source=syn_oath_mon&amp;utm_medium=Z&amp;utm_campaign=38715&amp;utm_content=oath_mon_38715_without+the+headache+of+being+a+landlord" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:without the headache of being a landlord;elm:context_link;itc:0">without the headache of being a landlord</a></p></li><li><p>Finish 2023 stronger than you started: <a href="https://moneywise.com/retirement/retirement/alt-5-money-moves-you-should-make-before-the-end-of-2023?throw=C1DM2&amp;utm_source=syn_oath_mon&amp;utm_medium=Z&amp;utm_campaign=38715&amp;utm_content=oath_mon_38715_5+money+moves+you+should+make+before+the+end+of+th" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:5 money moves you should make before the end of the year;elm:context_link;itc:0">5 money moves you should make before the end of the year</a></p></li><li><p>The US dollar has lost 87% of its purchasing power since 1971 — <a href="https://moneywise.com/investing/alternative-investments/gold-ira-secure-financial-future?throw=C1DM3&amp;utm_source=syn_oath_mon&amp;utm_medium=Z&amp;utm_campaign=38715&amp;utm_content=oath_mon_38715_invest+in+this+stable+asset+before+you+lose+your+r" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:invest in this stable asset before you lose your retirement fund;elm:context_link;itc:0">invest in this stable asset before you lose your retirement fund</a></p></li></ul><p>In 2007, <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/money/markets/2018/01/02/warren-buffett-bet-against-hedge-funds-girls-charity/996993001/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:Buffett bet a million dollars;elm:context_link;itc:0">Buffett bet a million dollars</a> that over the course of a decade, a simple S&amp;P 500 index fund would outperform a basket of hand-picked hedge funds. He picked the Vanguard 500 Index Fund Admiral Shares (VFIAX).</p><p>Hedge fund manager Ted Seides from Protégé Partners accepted the bet and picked five funds-of-funds. A fund-of-funds is a portfolio of funds that charges two layers of management fees.</p><p>The outcome? Buffett triumphed decisively.</p><p>Buffett <a href="https://www.berkshirehathaway.com/letters/2017ltr.pdf" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:shared;elm:context_link;itc:0">shared</a> the final scorecard of the bet in his 2017 shareholder letter. The S&amp;P 500 index fund he selected delivered a total gain of 125.8% during the decade, while the five funds-of-funds reported respective gains of 21.7%, 42.3%, 87.7%, 2.8% and 27.0% during the same period.</p><p>Buffett gave all proceeds to charity — and Girls Inc. of Omaha turned out to be the biggest winner of the bet.</p><h2>High returns, low fees</h2><p>This decade-long bet challenged the notion that complex and expensive investment methods always yield the best results.</p><p>After all, anyone can replicate Buffett’ strategy at a very low cost. The Vanguard index fund he picked has an expense ratio of just 0.04%.</p><p>The hedge funds, Buffett pointed out, come at a much higher cost to investors.</p><p>“Even if the funds lost money for their investors during the decade, their managers could grow very rich,” he wrote in the shareholder letter. “That would occur because fixed fees averaging a staggering 2.5% of assets or so were paid every year by the fund-of-funds’ investors, with part of these fees going to the managers at the five funds-of-funds and the balance going to the 200-plus managers of the underlying hedge funds.”</p><p>In the investing world, fees should not be overlooked — they can eat into your returns. In an op-ed for Bloomberg titled “Why I Lost My Bet With Warren Buffett,” Seides agreed with Buffett on the subject of hedge funds’ management fees.</p><p>“He is correct that hedge-fund fees are high, and his reasoning is convincing. Fees matter in investing, no doubt about it,” he <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/view/articles/2017-05-03/why-i-lost-my-bet-with-warren-buffett" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:wrote;elm:context_link;itc:0">wrote</a>.</p><p><strong>Read more:</strong> 'It's not taxed at all': Warren Buffett shares the <a href="https://moneywise.com/life/lifestyle/hybrid-its-not-taxed-at-all?throw=C1HALF&amp;utm_source=syn_oath_mon&amp;utm_medium=Z&amp;utm_campaign=38715&amp;utm_content=oath_mon_38715_%27best+investment%27+you+can+make+when+battling+infla" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:'best investment' you can make when battling inflation;elm:context_link;itc:0">'best investment' you can make when battling inflation</a></p><p>These days, many ETFs enable investors to track benchmark indices at minimal costs. For instance, the Vanguard S&amp;P 500 ETF (VOO), which follows the S&amp;P 500, has a low expense ratio of 0.03%. Similarly, the SPDR S&amp;P 500 ETF Trust (SPY) tracks the same index and carries an expense ratio of 0.0945%.</p><p>Does that mean every investor should abandon stock-picking and put all their money into index funds?</p><p>The answer varies based on the individual.</p><p>For someone like Buffett, making their own investment decisions could lead to significantly greater success. Consider this: from 1964 to 2022, Buffett’s Berkshire Hathaway <a href="https://www.berkshirehathaway.com/letters/2022ltr.pdf" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:delivered;elm:context_link;itc:0">delivered</a> an astounding overall gain of 3,787,464%, substantially outperforming the S&amp;P 500’s already impressive 24,708% return in the same timeframe.</p><h2>What to read next</h2><ul><li><p>Thanks to Jeff Bezos, you can now <a href="https://moneywise.com/investing/real-estate/invest-vacation-rental-homes?throw=C1WTRN1&amp;utm_source=syn_oath_mon&amp;utm_medium=Z&amp;utm_campaign=38715&amp;utm_content=oath_mon_38715_cash+in+on+prime+real+estate" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:cash in on prime real estate;elm:context_link;itc:0">cash in on prime real estate</a> — without the headache of being a landlord. Here's how</p></li><li><p>Worried about the economy? Here are <a href="https://moneywise.com/top/alternative-investments?throw=C1WTRN2&amp;utm_source=syn_oath_mon&amp;utm_medium=Z&amp;utm_campaign=38715&amp;utm_content=oath_mon_38715_the+best+shock-proof+assets" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:the best shock-proof assets;elm:context_link;itc:0">the best shock-proof assets</a> for your portfolio. (They’re all outside of the stock market.)</p></li><li><p>Rising prices are throwing off Americans' retirement plans — here’s <a href="https://moneywise.com/managing-money/retirement-planning/how-to-retire-early?throw=C1WTRN3&amp;utm_source=syn_oath_mon&amp;utm_medium=Z&amp;utm_campaign=38715&amp;utm_content=oath_mon_38715_how+to+get+your+savings+back+on+track" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:how to get your savings back on track;elm:context_link;itc:0">how to get your savings back on track</a></p></li></ul><p><em>This article provides information only and should not be construed as advice. It is provided without warranty of any kind.</em></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>