<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 23:30:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[US hospital told family their daughter had checked out when in fact she'd died (142 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/article/2024/aug/21/sacramento-hospital-patient-death-checked-out</link>
            <guid>41313740</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 20:07:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/article/2024/aug/21/sacramento-hospital-patient-death-checked-out">https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/article/2024/aug/21/sacramento-hospital-patient-death-checked-out</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41313740">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p>Jessie Peterson’s family spent a year searching for her after they were told that she had checked herself out of a <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/california" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">California</a> hospital against medical advice – before they learned that she had been dead all along.</p><p>The 31-year-old died in the care of Mercy San Juan medical center in Sacramento in April 2023. The hospital shipped her body to a storage facility and did not inform her mother and sisters. The family only learned her fate the following April after months of trying to find her, according to a civil lawsuit against the hospital.</p><p>In the lawsuit, filed earlier this month, the family described the hospital’s conduct as “malicious and outrageous” and accused the facility of negligence, the negligent handling of a corpse and negligent infliction of emotional distress.</p><p>“Mercy San Juan hospital failed in its most fundamental duty to notify Jessie’s family of her death,” the lawsuit states. “Mercy San Juan stored<strong> </strong>Jessie in an off-site warehouse morgue and she was left to decompose for nearly a year while her family relentlessly inquired about her whereabouts.”</p><p>Peterson, whom her family described in the lawsuit as “loving and energetic”, had type 1 diabetes. She was experiencing a diabetic episode when she was admitted to Mercy San Juan on 6 April 2023. Her mother, Ginger Congi, stated that Peterson had called her two days later asking for a ride because she would be leaving the hospital, according to the lawsuit.</p><p>Congi was later told that Peterson had left the hospital against medical advice, and her medical records indicate she was discharged on 8 April. After her sudden disappearance, the family spent months “relentlessly” searching for her, posting flyers, speaking with unhoused residents in the area, and contacting police and the coroner’s office, according to the lawsuit.</p><p>On 12 April 2024, more than a year after Peterson was last seen, the Sacramento county detective’s office informed the family that she had been found dead at Mercy San Juan, the suit states. According to her death certificate, which was completed in April 2024, Peterson died of cardiopulmonary arrest at age 31.</p><figure id="4fa9fbba-5a61-436c-a35b-3aac46440d98" data-spacefinder-role="showcase" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-2"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/40cc543f18f79dd497ebea63faf0894d5fa95c2e/0_405_6016_3611/master/6016.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 1300px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1300px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/40cc543f18f79dd497ebea63faf0894d5fa95c2e/0_405_6016_3611/master/6016.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 1300px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/40cc543f18f79dd497ebea63faf0894d5fa95c2e/0_405_6016_3611/master/6016.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 1140px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1140px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/40cc543f18f79dd497ebea63faf0894d5fa95c2e/0_405_6016_3611/master/6016.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 1140px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/40cc543f18f79dd497ebea63faf0894d5fa95c2e/0_405_6016_3611/master/6016.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 980px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 980px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/40cc543f18f79dd497ebea63faf0894d5fa95c2e/0_405_6016_3611/master/6016.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 980px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/40cc543f18f79dd497ebea63faf0894d5fa95c2e/0_405_6016_3611/master/6016.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/40cc543f18f79dd497ebea63faf0894d5fa95c2e/0_405_6016_3611/master/6016.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/40cc543f18f79dd497ebea63faf0894d5fa95c2e/0_405_6016_3611/master/6016.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/40cc543f18f79dd497ebea63faf0894d5fa95c2e/0_405_6016_3611/master/6016.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/40cc543f18f79dd497ebea63faf0894d5fa95c2e/0_405_6016_3611/master/6016.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/40cc543f18f79dd497ebea63faf0894d5fa95c2e/0_405_6016_3611/master/6016.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="Outside of building." src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/40cc543f18f79dd497ebea63faf0894d5fa95c2e/0_405_6016_3611/master/6016.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" width="445" height="267.10355718085106" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption data-spacefinder-role="inline"><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>Mercy medical center.</span> Photograph: Chris Allan/Alamy</figcaption></figure><p>Peterson’s sister went to the coroner’s office seeking her remains, but a worker told her that the office did not have Peterson’s body and directed her to contact the hospital. Mercy San Juan was not responsive to efforts to contact them, according to the lawsuit, and a mortuary eventually informed Congi that Peterson’s body had been found in one of the hospital’s off-site storage facilities.</p><p>Her body was so decomposed the family could not obtain her fingerprints or hold an open casket funeral, and an autopsy that could have indicated whether there had been medical malpractice associated with her death was “rendered impossible”, according to the lawsuit.</p><p>“Defendants’ failure to issue a timely certificate of death, failure to notify Jessie’s next of kin, failure to allow an autopsy, and mishandling of Jessie’s remains [was] negligent, careless, and heartless,” the lawsuit states. “Defendants violated their own promise of dignity and respect for the people in their care. Defendants’ conduct is so egregious and malicious to shock the conscious and punitive damages should be awarded.”</p><p>The family is seeking more than $5m in damages, as well as “five times the jury’s award of actual damages to punish defendants for their outrageous and inexcusable negligence” and attorneys’ fees.</p><p>Dignity Health, which operates Mercy San Juan, said in a statement: “We extend our deepest sympathies to the family during this difficult time. We are unable to comment on pending litigation.”</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Linux desktop market share climbs to 4.45% (271 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ostechnix.com/linux-market-share-july-2024-report/</link>
            <guid>41312883</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 18:32:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ostechnix.com/linux-market-share-july-2024-report/">https://ostechnix.com/linux-market-share-july-2024-report/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41312883">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://ostechnix.com/linux-market-share-july-2024-report/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Midjourney web experience is now open to everyone (176 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.midjourney.com/</link>
            <guid>41312225</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 17:11:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.midjourney.com/">https://www.midjourney.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41312225">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.midjourney.com/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Code review antipatterns (105 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/code-review-antipatterns/</link>
            <guid>41312084</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 16:55:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/code-review-antipatterns/">https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/quasiblog/code-review-antipatterns/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41312084">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
    
    <p>[Simon Tatham, 2024-08-21]</p>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <a href="#intro">Introduction</a>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="#antipatterns">The antipatterns</a>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <a href="#round-trips">The Death of a Thousand Round Trips</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="#ransom-note">The Ransom Note</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="#double-team">The Double Team</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="#guessing-game">The Guessing Game</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="#priority-inversion">The Priority Inversion</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="#late-design">The Late-Breaking Design Review</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="#catch-22">The Catch-22</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="#flip-flop">The Flip Flop</a>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="#the-point">But seriously, folks …</a>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <a href="#authority">Authority</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="#types">Gatekeeping code review</a>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="#disclaimer">Disclaimer</a>
      </li>
    </ul>
    <h2 id="intro">Introduction</h2>
    <p>Code review seems like a great idea, right? Two developers
      looking at the same code means two chances to spot problems; it
      spreads understanding of the way the project is evolving; the
      reviewer can learn useful tricks from reading the author’s code
      in detail, or spot opportunities to teach the author a useful
      trick that they didn’t know already.</p>
    <p>But that’s only for ‘light side’ code reviewers, who use it to
      try to improve the code base and the developers’ collective
      skills. Code review can also be a powerful tool for totally
      different purposes. When a code reviewer turns to the dark side,
      they have a huge choice of ways to obstruct or delay
      improvements to the code, to annoy patch authors or discourage
      them completely, or to pursue other goals of their own.</p>
    <p>If you’ve only recently turned to the dark side, you might not
      have thought of all the possibilities yet. So here’s a list of
      code-review antipatterns, for the dark-side code reviewer who’s
      running out of ideas.</p>
    <h2 id="antipatterns">The antipatterns</h2>

    <h3 id="round-trips">The Death of a Thousand Round Trips</h3>
    <p>You start reading the code. As soon as you see a nitpick, you
      add a review comment pointing it out. Then you stop reading.</p>
    <p>The developer conscientiously fixes your nitpick, and submits a
      revised patch.</p>
    <p>You start reading that version. You spot another nitpick,
      independent of the first. You <em>could</em> perfectly well have
      mentioned it the first time, but you didn’t, because you didn’t
      get that far. So you point that out – and stop reading
      again.</p>
    <p>And so on. Iterate until the developer loses hope.</p>
    <p>If you’re in a very different time zone from the developer, you
      get a natural 24-hour round-trip time, so that the patch evolves
      as slowly as possible. If you’re in a nearby time zone, or the
      same one, then to delay the patch properly, you’ll have to
      arrange to be busy with several other things, so you have a good
      excuse for it taking you a day or two to get round to looking at
      each new version.</p>
    <p>Resist the temptation to make any remarks like ‘This is
      looking much better now.’ If you hint that you’re getting closer
      to being satisfied, you’ll give them reason to keep trying!</p>

    <h3 id="ransom-note">The Ransom Note</h3>
    <p>This particular patch seems <em>especially</em> important to
      the developer who submitted it. (Maybe they said that outright,
      as part of their argument trying to persuade you to take the
      patch. Or maybe you just read between the lines.)</p>
    <p>But this patch isn’t especially vital to you – so you’re in a
      position of power! Now you can hold the change they need hostage
      until they do lots of extra tangentially related work, which
      doesn’t really need to be in the same commit, but which is
      important to <em>you</em>.</p>
    <p>‘If you ever want to see your beloved patch again …’</p>

    <h3 id="double-team">The Double Team</h3>
    <p>One patch. Two reviewers.</p>
    <p>Every time one of you demands a change, the developer
      obediently makes it – and now the other one can complain
      instead!</p>
    <p>Keep taking turns to make incompatible demands. But always
      direct your comments at the developer. Avoid arguing directly
      with <em>each other</em> on the review thread, and don’t
      acknowledge any suggestion from the patch author that the two of
      you should talk to each other and come to a consensus about what
      the patch is supposed to look like.</p>
    <p>See how many times you can ping-pong the developer back and
      forth before they give up.</p>
    <p>(In a real emergency, if you can’t find an accomplice, you can
      try contradicting <em>your own</em> previous review comments.
      But normally someone will notice. It works better with two
      reviewers.)</p>

    <h3 id="guessing-game">The Guessing Game</h3>
    <p>There’s a problem, and lots of different possible ways to
      solve it. A developer has picked one solution and submitted a
      patch.</p>
    <p>Criticise that <em>particular</em> solution, on some grounds
      that don’t relate to whether or not it solves the problem. Keep
      your criticism vague and woolly: violation of an obscure design
      principle, perhaps, or incompatibility with some vapourware plan
      for future development in the same area. Make the criticism as
      irrelevant as possible to the thing they were really trying to
      achieve.</p>
    <p>If you make it vague enough, the developer won’t be able to
      think of any way to adapt their existing patch that they’re
      confident will address your criticisms. Their best bet is to
      choose a totally <em>different</em> solution to the original
      problem, and try implementing that instead.</p>
    <p>So now you can smack that one down too, in just as unhelpful a
      way!</p>
    <p>Don’t let the developer trap you into any conversation like
      ‘ok, how do you think this problem <em>should</em> be solved?’,
      or give any hint at a solution you’d be happy with. Sooner or
      later, they’ll lose the will to keep guessing.</p>

    <h3 id="priority-inversion">The Priority Inversion</h3>
    <p>In your first code review passes, pick small and simple nits.
      Variable names are a bit unclear; comments have typos in.</p>
    <p>Wait for the developer to fix those, and <em>then</em> drop
      your bombshell: there’s a much more fundamental problem with the
      patch, that needs a chunk of it to be completely rewritten –
      which means throwing away a lot of the nitpick fixes you’ve
      already made the developer do in that part of the patch.</p>
    <p>Nothing says ‘your work is not wanted, and your time is not
      valued’ better than making someone do a lot of work and then
      making them throw it away. This might be enough to make the
      developer give up, all by itself.</p>

    <h3 id="late-design">The Late-Breaking Design Review</h3>
    <p>An enormously complicated piece of work has been ongoing for
      weeks or months, in lots of separate patches. Half the work is
      already committed.</p>
    <p>You personally don’t agree with the design of the entire piece
      of work, but you weren’t consulted in the original discussions.
      Or maybe you were, but you were on the losing side of the
      debate.</p>
    <p>But now you’ve been asked to review a minor but important thing
      in the middle of it, like an easy fix for a bug that’s blocking
      lots of developers. This is your opportunity!</p>
    <p>Demand justification for the entire design of the work so far.
      If the developer doesn’t know the answers, because they’re just
      working on one small part of the overall job, then shrug –
      that’s not your problem, and you’re not hitting the ‘Approve’
      button until you’re satisfied.</p>
    <p>If you’re really lucky, perhaps you can even manipulate this
      developer into undoing some of the already-done work, by giving
      a plausible excuse why it’s necessary. Carefully avoid letting
      them know where to find the design discussions that contradict
      you.</p>

    <h3 id="catch-22">The Catch-22</h3>
    <p>If there’s one big patch, then it’s too hard to read! Demand it
      be split up into self-contained sub-pieces.</p>
    <p>On the other hand, if there are lots of little patches, then
      some of them make no sense on their own! So insist that they be
      glued back together.</p>
    <p>With any large enough piece of work you can surely find a
      reason to make <em>one</em> of those complaints; it’s just a
      matter of deciding which.</p>
    <p>It doesn’t have to be ‘number of patches in the pull request’.
      You can do this one with any kind of tradeoff that seems
      relevant in the particular case. For example, if the code is
      written legibly, it probably has unacceptably poor performance –
      or if it’s well optimised, it’s unreadable and hard to
      maintain.</p>

    <h3 id="flip-flop">The Flip Flop</h3>
    <p>There’s a type of change that people commonly make to the same
      part of the code, like adding an extra thing to a list. You’ve
      reviewed several of these changes before. Another one has just
      come along: the author has looked at the prior changes,
      carefully followed the existing pattern, and chosen you as a
      code reviewer because you’re clearly used to this area.</p>
    <p>Keep everybody on their toes by suddenly objecting to an aspect
      of the change that you’ve never had a problem with before.
      Following the existing pattern just isn’t good enough! The
      author ought to have anticipated that you’ve recently changed
      your mind about what this type of change should look like.</p>
    <p>What if the author points out your inconsistency, by showing
      the previous three identical changes where you didn’t raise this
      objection?</p>
    <p>Then you say ‘You’re right, those should be changed too.’ Be
      careful not to take any personal responsibility
      – <em>you’re</em> not volunteering to change all the existing
      cases. If you’re really lucky the developer will interpret this
      as instructions to change the existing cases themself, and then
      you’ve saved yourself a lot of effort.</p>

    <h2 id="the-point">But seriously, folks …</h2>
    <p>Up to here, this article has been a joke.</p>
    <p>(I’d hope I don’t even have to say that at all, but I’m
      sure <em>somebody</em> would have misunderstood otherwise.)</p>
    <p>I’m not <em>really</em> intending to encourage code reviewers
      to be annoying and obstructive. And I’m not even really
      suggesting that code reviewers <em>do</em> do all these bad
      things, at least on purpose, at least most of the time. Most of
      the descriptions above are exaggerations of what the reviewer
      really does. Or not even that: just an exaggeration of what
      it <em>feels</em> like, when you’re the frustrated patch
      submitter, and your patch has been stuck in review for weeks,
      and doesn’t feel as if it’s getting any closer.</p>
    <p>I really mean: <em>don’t</em> do these things! Try to minimise
      round trips, rather than maximising them. Ask for important
      rewrites (if needed) <em>before</em> picking all the trivial
      nits. When you criticise the patch, make constructive
      suggestions about what version of it you <em>would</em> accept.
      If you have opinions about the code base as a whole, raise them
      with all the developers in a general discussion, rather than
      being petty with the one developer whose patch you’re assigned
      to review. And if you do any of these things <em>by
      accident</em>, have some self-awareness about it: notice that
      you’ve made the developer’s life extra difficult by mistake,
      apologise, and try to compensate by being extra helpful. (Maybe
      even help to improve the actual code, either by writing your own
      revised version of this patch, or doing extra polishing in a
      followup patch of your own.)</p>
    
    <p>But if there’s a serious point to make here, I think it’s this.
      When one developer becomes the code reviewer for another one’s
      patch, that relationship creates temporary <em>authority</em>.
      The reviewer has the power to prevent that particular patch
      being committed, even if they don’t have any kind of authority
      over the patch submitter the rest of the time.</p>
    <p>With authority comes responsibility. You’re supposed to use the
      authority only for its intended purpose, and only as much as
      necessary. In this case, that’s to make the patch as good as
      possible, according to whatever definition of ‘good’ the
      development team as a whole has agreed on.</p>
    <p>So most of these antipatterns (or the milder behaviours that
      they’re caricaturing) are <em>abuses of authority</em>. The
      reviewer is using that temporary power over another developer as
      leverage to pursue some other personal agenda, perhaps
      independent of the goodness of the patch, or perhaps actively
      opposed to it.</p>
    <p>The personal agenda in question varies between these
      antipatterns. It could be some unrelated piece of work the
      reviewer is in favour of; it could be personal stylistic
      preferences that the reviewer hasn’t been able to get the rest
      of the team to adopt; it could be laziness, taking advantage of
      the opportunity to write a one-line description of what you want
      and let someone else do the hard work; it could just be plain
      resistance to change, or perhaps even a personal dislike of the
      patch submitter.</p>
    <p>And that dislike might be quite justifiable, if the patch
      submitter has done any of these bad behaviours when it was
      last <em>their</em> turn to be the code reviewer! That’s another
      reason you should use the code reviewer’s authority sparingly.
      If developers manage to get locked into a cycle of revenge
      against each other, your software project is doomed.</p>
    <h3 id="types">Gatekeeping code review</h3>
    <p>Up to this point, I’ve been focused on <em>peer</em> code
      review. The code reviewer and the patch submitter are
      colleagues; neither is in charge of the other; neither has the
      final say over the code base in general. That’s why the
      authority you get in a code review is <em>temporary</em>:
      tomorrow, after this patch lands, you won’t have it any more.
      The day after that, it might be the other way round.</p>
    <p>Also, in peer review situations, the code reviewer and the
      author are supposed to have basically the same goal. If there’s
      any serious disagreement about what features should go into the
      code at all, or how polished something needs to be before
      approval, or what the acceptable coding style is, it’s supposed
      to be dealt with outside the context of the code review.</p>
    <p>But in other kinds of code review situation, that’s not quite
      the way it works. In particular, if an outsider to your software
      project sends you an unsolicited patch, that’s very different.</p>
    <p>(This scenario usually comes up in free software, since anyone
      in the world can modify your source code, and some of them will
      try sending the changes back to you. But it can happen in other
      situations too – inside a company developing proprietary code, a
      developer in one team might try their luck sending a patch to
      another team’s project, if they particularly want a feature or
      fix that the other team hasn’t found effort for.)</p>
    <p>In this situation, there’s a much bigger chance that the
      receiver of the patch will be unwilling to accept it at all,
      either because they don’t think that change should be made in
      the first place, or they disagree completely with the way it was
      done. And in this case, that’s <em>not</em> an abuse of the
      temporary authority granted by being a peer reviewer: it’s a
      legitimate exercise of the <em>permanent</em> authority of being
      the person or team in charge of the project. It’s my software
      project – I get to decide what direction it goes in.</p>
    <p>When the code reviewer is in this ‘gatekeeping’ role, it’s not
      always wrong to criticise the patch on the grounds that it
      violates an existing general design principle or requirement
      (<a href="#guessing-game">The Guessing Game</a>), without
      suggesting how the same problem could be solved better. Maybe I
      don’t <em>know</em> how that problem could be solved in a way
      that’s consistent with the requirement. In fact, maybe that’s
      precisely the hard part, and the only reason why I haven’t
      already made the same change myself!</p>
    <p>But even in a gatekeeping context, it’s rude to deploy ‘The
      Guessing Game’ <em>without explaining</em>. When I do this, I
      generally try to explain how the developer has overlooked the
      hard part, and if I don’t know the answer myself, I’ll say so.</p>
    <p>And, of course, there’s still no excuse
      for <em>passive-aggressive</em> obstructiveness
      like <a href="#round-trips">The Death of a Thousand Round
      Trips</a>. If you genuinely don’t want the patch in the code at
      all, and you’re in a gatekeeping role with the legitimate
      authority to make that decision, you can <em>say so</em> in
      words, so the submitter doesn’t waste any more time on it!</p>
    <h2 id="disclaimer">Disclaimer</h2>
    <p>I’ve been collecting notes towards this article for many years,
      from code reviews I’ve participated in (on <em>both</em> sides),
      code reviews I’ve observed between others, and code reviews I’ve
      only heard about in conversation.</p>
    <p>So it’s not aimed at any specific person who’s reviewed my code
      recently!</p>
  

</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mimalloc Cigarette: Losing one week of my life catching a memory leak (Rust) (111 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://pwy.io/posts/mimalloc-cigarette/</link>
            <guid>41311071</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 15:09:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://pwy.io/posts/mimalloc-cigarette/">https://pwy.io/posts/mimalloc-cigarette/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41311071">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post">
        

        <p>
          One of applications at my work has always been RAM-bound - it's a
          pricing engine that basically loads tons of hotels, builds some
          in-memory indices and then allows you to issue queries like
          <i>find me the cheapest hotel in berlin, pronto</i>.
        </p>

        <p>
          A pricing engine's main purpose is to price <s>engines</s> hotels, but
          in order to do that effectively, there's a lot of "meta work"
          involved, like:
        </p>

        <ul>
          <li>Where do we load the data from, how do we do it?</li>
          <li>Do we load the entire dataset or just some parts of it?</li>
          <li>
            Should we precalculate prices in order to speed-up the most popular
            queries?
          </li>
        </ul>

        <p>
          Such an engine poses an interesting technical challenge, even greater
          so when one day it starts OOMing on production, even though the entire
          dataset should fit in the memory multiple times...
        </p>

        <h2 id="hello-world"><a href="#hello-world"> Hello, World! </a></h2>

        <p>Simplifying <s>a bit</s> a lot, what we're dealing with is:</p>

        

        <div>
          <pre><span></span><span>struct</span> <span>State</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>    </span><span>hotels</span>: <span>Vec</span><span>&lt;</span><span>Hotel</span><span>&gt;</span><span>,</span>
<span>}</span>

<span>struct</span> <span>Hotel</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>    </span><span>prices</span>: <span>Vec</span><span>&lt;</span><span>f32</span><span>&gt;</span><span>,</span>
<span>}</span>

<span>// ---</span>

<span>impl</span><span> </span><span>State</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>    </span><span>fn</span> <span>new</span><span>()</span><span> </span>-&gt; <span>Self</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>        </span><span>Self</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>            </span><span>hotels</span>: <span>load_hotels</span><span>().</span><span>collect</span><span>(),</span>
<span>        </span><span>}</span>
<span>    </span><span>}</span>

<span>    </span><span>fn</span> <span>refresh</span><span>(</span><span>&amp;</span><span>mut</span><span> </span><span>self</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>        </span><span>for</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>id</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>hotel</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>in</span><span> </span><span>load_hotels</span><span>().</span><span>enumerate</span><span>()</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>            </span><span>self</span><span>.</span><span>hotels</span><span>[</span><span>id</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>hotel</span><span>;</span>
<span>        </span><span>}</span>
<span>    </span><span>}</span>
<span>}</span>

<span>fn</span> <span>load_hotels</span><span>()</span><span> </span>-&gt; <span>impl</span><span> </span><span>Iterator</span><span>&lt;</span><span>Item</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>Hotel</span><span>&gt;</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>    </span><span>(</span><span>0</span><span>..</span><span>1_000</span><span>).</span><span>map</span><span>(</span><span>|</span><span>_</span><span>|</span><span> </span><span>Hotel</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>        </span><span>prices</span>: <span>(</span><span>0</span><span>..</span><span>1_000_000</span><span>).</span><span>map</span><span>(</span><span>|</span><span>n</span><span>|</span><span> </span><span>n</span><span> </span><span>as</span><span> </span><span>f32</span><span>).</span><span>collect</span><span>(),</span>
<span>    </span><span>})</span>
<span>}</span>

<span>// ---</span>

<span>fn</span> <span>main</span><span>()</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>    </span><span>let</span><span> </span><span>state</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>Arc</span>::<span>new</span><span>(</span><span>RwLock</span>::<span>new</span><span>(</span><span>State</span>::<span>new</span><span>()));</span>

<span>    </span><span>// Spawn a separate thread responsible for checking which hotels have</span>
<span>    </span><span>// changed and need to be refreshed etc.</span>
<span>    </span><span>thread</span>::<span>spawn</span><span>({</span>
<span>        </span><span>let</span><span> </span><span>state</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>Arc</span>::<span>clone</span><span>(</span><span>&amp;</span><span>state</span><span>);</span>

<span>        </span><span>move</span><span> </span><span>||</span><span> </span><span>loop</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>            </span><span>thread</span>::<span>sleep</span><span>(</span><span>Duration</span>::<span>from_secs</span><span>(</span><span>5</span><span>));</span>
<span>            </span><span>state</span><span>.</span><span>write</span><span>().</span><span>unwrap</span><span>().</span><span>refresh</span><span>();</span>
<span>        </span><span>}</span>
<span>    </span><span>});</span>

<span>    </span><span>// Now in reality we start a Rocket server here, but for practical</span>
<span>    </span><span>// purposes stalling the main thread will be sufficient.</span>
<span>    </span><span>loop</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>        </span><span>thread</span>::<span>sleep</span><span>(</span><span>Duration</span>::<span>from_secs</span><span>(</span><span>1</span><span>));</span>
<span>    </span><span>}</span>
<span>}</span>
</pre>
        </div>

        <p>
          Of course IRL there's <kbd>ArcSwap</kbd> instead of <kbd>RwLock</kbd>,
          every hotel contains much more information (like taxes, discounts or
          supplements) etc., but we've got a reasonably good approximation here.
        </p>

        <p>
          Now, what if I told you that this code has <i>totally</i> different
          memory characteristics depending on which allocator you use?
        </p>

        <h2 id="practical-reasons">
          <a href="#practical-reasons"> Practical Reasons </a>
        </h2>

        <p>
          Memory allocator is the piece of software invoked whenever your
          program needs to get hands on extra memory, like when you're calling
          <kbd>Box::new()</kbd>. And memory allocation is quite a complex topic,
          with different solutions offering different trade-offs.
        </p>

        <p>
          Say, when implementing a firmware you might pick an allocator that
          works slower, because its implementation is just simpler and doesn't
          occupy much space in the final binary.
        </p>

        <p>
          (some would argue that embeddeed programs shouldn't allocate, yadda
          yadda, but you get the idea -- replace <i>firmware</i> with
          <i>wasm</i> and you end up with the same problem.)
        </p>

        <p>
          <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/mimalloc">mimalloc</a> is an
          allocator that fights tooth and nail for performance - and while most
          applications don't have to worry about allocation performance, in our
          case internal benchmarks have proven it gives us extra 10% for free;
          when your response times have to be within milliseconds, this matters.
        </p>

        <p>But there's a catch.</p>

        <h2 id="desenchantee"><a href="#desenchantee"> Désenchantée </a></h2>

        <p>
          That program from before, on my x86_64 Linux machine it allocates
          around 4 GB of memory and it remains on this level through the
          refreshing.
        </p>

        <p>
          This makes sense, right? We're using lazy iterators, replacing stuff
          in place one-by-one, there's no reason we'd need more RAM.
        </p>

        <p>But if you use mimalloc:</p>

        <div>
          <pre><span></span><span>use</span><span> </span><span>mimalloc</span>::<span>MiMalloc</span><span>;</span>

<span>#[global_allocator]</span>
<span>static</span><span> </span><span>GLOBAL</span>: <span>MiMalloc</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>MiMalloc</span><span>;</span>
</pre>
        </div>

        <p>
          ... the program will first allocate 4 GB and then allocate
          <i>extra</i> 4 GB during the refreshing, oh noes!
        </p>

        <p>
          Getting to this point already took three days of my life - believe me
          or not, when faced with 200k lines of Arc-ridden Rust code that
          <i>seems</i> to generate a memory leak, one's first thought is not
          "let's try with different allocator", but rather "probably something's
          holding onto an Arc for too long".
        </p>

        <p>
          And so I've valgrind-ed. I've perf-ed. I've analyzed assembly. I've
          headbanged and I've cried.
        </p>

        <p>No more.</p>

        <p>
          From now on I'm always assuming it's someone else's fault - it's the
          allocator, it's the compiler, it's that crate Mike pulled last night.
          WHY DO YOU HATE ME MIKE, WHY ARE YOU PULLING RANDOM CRATES TO MY PURE
          <span>~~~tv noise~~~</span>
        </p>

        <h2 id="remede"><a href="#remede"> Remède </a></h2>

        <p>
          Allocators have different characteristics for a reason - they do some
          things differently between each other. What do you think mimalloc does
          that could account for this behavior?
        </p>

        <p>
          Let me give you two hints, two pieces of code that solve the problem,
          but feel cursed:
        </p>

        <div>
          <pre><span></span><span>// Approach 1:</span>
<span>fn</span> <span>main</span><span>()</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>    </span><span>let</span><span> </span><span>state</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>thread</span>::<span>spawn</span><span>(</span><span>||</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>        </span><span>Arc</span>::<span>new</span><span>(</span><span>RwLock</span>::<span>new</span><span>(</span><span>State</span>::<span>new</span><span>()))</span>
<span>    </span><span>}).</span><span>join</span><span>().</span><span>unwrap</span><span>();</span>

<span>    </span><span>/* ... */</span>
<span>}</span>

<span>// Approach 2:</span>
<span>fn</span> <span>main</span><span>()</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>    </span><span>/* ... */</span>

<span>    </span><span>loop</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>        </span><span>Box</span>::<span>new</span><span>(</span><span>1234</span><span>);</span>
<span>    </span><span>}</span>
<span>}</span>
</pre>
        </div>

        <p>Any ideas? Last chance to win a plushie polar bear!</p>

        <p>
          Alright then, the issue is that mimalloc assumes that
          <b>every thread allocates every now and then</b>.
        </p>

        <p>
          Every now and then during <kbd>malloc()</kbd> mimalloc performs some
          internal bookkeeping, so when a thread goes to sleep (say, because it
          delegates handling HTTP requests into a separate thread pool...), this
          bookkeeping doesn't happen (for that particular thread).
        </p>

        <p>
          The most nasty edge case that can happen here, and the one that we've
          stumbled upon, is when your thread allocates a lot of data, then
          launches other threads to work on that data, and then goes to sleep.
          As other threads work on memory and override stuff, Rust destructors
          <i>are</i> launched properly, but the underlying memory blocks simply
          get marked as "to be released".
        </p>

        <p>
          Under normal conditions, these blocks get processed a moment later,
          during a call to <kbd>malloc()</kbd> on the thread that created them -
          but if that thread is asleep, those blocks never become available
          again (unless the thread dies, of course).
        </p>

        <p>
          To be sure, the problem is not that the memory is not returned to the
          kernel - that's alright. It's that unless this bookkeeping happens,
          mimalloc can't even use the memory <i>for itself</i> - all this free
          estate just lays there, dormant:
        </p>

        <ul>
          <li>
            <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/mimalloc/issues/537">https://github.com/microsoft/mimalloc/issues/537</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/mimalloc/issues/214">https://github.com/microsoft/mimalloc/issues/214</a>
          </li>
        </ul>

        <p>
          Anyway, the solution we went with was to keep all refreshing on the
          same thread - when program starts, we spawn a dedicated
          refreshing-thread and use channels to let it know to do its thing.
        </p>

        <p>
          So yeah, that was fun; and health-wise probably more like seven
          cigarettes.
        </p>
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to Build a 50K Ton Forging Press (218 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.construction-physics.com/p/how-to-build-a-50000-ton-forging</link>
            <guid>41310384</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 14:00:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.construction-physics.com/p/how-to-build-a-50000-ton-forging">https://www.construction-physics.com/p/how-to-build-a-50000-ton-forging</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41310384">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F58b0c742-762b-4cf4-870c-eeec69206c55_1434x1239.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F58b0c742-762b-4cf4-870c-eeec69206c55_1434x1239.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F58b0c742-762b-4cf4-870c-eeec69206c55_1434x1239.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F58b0c742-762b-4cf4-870c-eeec69206c55_1434x1239.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F58b0c742-762b-4cf4-870c-eeec69206c55_1434x1239.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F58b0c742-762b-4cf4-870c-eeec69206c55_1434x1239.png" width="1434" height="1239" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/58b0c742-762b-4cf4-870c-eeec69206c55_1434x1239.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1239,&quot;width&quot;:1434,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F58b0c742-762b-4cf4-870c-eeec69206c55_1434x1239.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F58b0c742-762b-4cf4-870c-eeec69206c55_1434x1239.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F58b0c742-762b-4cf4-870c-eeec69206c55_1434x1239.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F58b0c742-762b-4cf4-870c-eeec69206c55_1434x1239.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a><figcaption>Alcoa 50,000 ton forging press.</figcaption></figure></div><p><span>In the late 1940s and early 1950s, a revolution took place in American military aircraft design. The invention of the jet engine made it possible for aircraft to fly far higher and faster than ever before. While the fastest propeller-driven aircraft of World War II topped out at slightly less than 500 miles per hour in level flight, jet-powered aircraft in the mid-1950s were flying at over </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convair_B-58_Hustler#Specifications_(B-58A)" rel="">1,300 miles per hour</a><span>, twice the speed of sound, with </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_American_XB-70_Valkyrie" rel="">even faster aircraft</a><span> on the horizon. Achieving this level of performance required not only powerful jet engines, but a whole host of new aircraft technologies: materials like </span><a href="https://www.construction-physics.com/p/building-apollo" rel="">inconel</a><span> and </span><a href="https://www.construction-physics.com/p/the-story-of-titanium" rel="">titanium</a><span>, and manufacturing methods that could produce far stronger and lighter aircraft parts.&nbsp;</span></p><p>One promising technological advance was to use large forged or extruded parts. Forging is a manufacturing method that shapes metal by applying pressure, usually by hammering it or squeezing it with large presses. Extruding is a similar process that shapes metal by squeezing it through an opening of the proper shape. At the time, both forging and extrusion were used to produce aircraft parts, but parts were limited in size and needed to be stitched together with hundreds or thousands of fasteners. By using very large forgings and extrusions to replace many smaller parts, components could be thinner, lighter, and stronger. Aerodynamic surfaces could be smoothed, and seals could be tightened. And by eliminating so many individual parts (along with the time and effort to attach them together), large forgings and extrusions could potentially reduce the time and cost required to build an aircraft. While there were a variety of different methods for making very large parts, such as casting and machining from plate or billet, forging and extrusion had several distinct advantages.</p><blockquote><p><em><span>…Machining from plate or billet requires tremendous machines and many machine-hours. A part machined from plate or billet is not as consistent in its mechanical properties as a part forged or extruded to finished or nearly finished dimensions. Mechanical properties in the center of thick plate or billet are questionable. Forgings have the added advantage of variable grain direction which generally can be tailored to the stress patterns of a specific design. The large percentage of stock going into chips [in machining] is unfavorable. Casting materials do not have sufficiently high physical properties, nor have casting techniques developed to the point where efficient metal distribution and thin sections can be obtained. –&nbsp; </span><a href="https://archive.org/details/sim_american-society-of-mechanical-engineers-transactions_1953-11_75_8" rel="">Symposium on Heavy Presses</a></em></p></blockquote><p>But the size of forgings or extrusions was limited by the size of the presses used to make them. Very large forgings or extrusions would require building presses of unprecedented size. Machines would need to be ten stories tall and capable of exerting hundreds of millions of pounds of force.&nbsp;</p><p>In the 1950s, the Department of Defense undertook a program to build such presses. Known as the Heavy Press Program, it funded the construction of four large forging presses and six extrusion presses. Upon completion, the largest of them were the largest presses in the world.</p><p>The program was an enormous success. Not only did the large parts produced by the presses greatly reduce the cost and increase the performance of military aircraft, but the presses proved useful for making parts for things like helicopters, submarines, spacecraft, and commercial jets. Within roughly a decade the presses had returned more than double their investment in reduced manufacturing costs, and they continued to produce complex, high quality forged and extruded parts over the subsequent decades. Six of the ten presses are still operational today.</p><p>The origins of the Heavy Press Program can be traced to Germany in the 1920s. As a condition of the Treaty of Versailles, Germany was forced to give up many of its western iron-producing regions, creating a chronic shortage of iron and steel. This drove Germany to make greater use of other metals, like magnesium and aluminum. Germany was the first country to produce magnesium on a commercial scale, starting in the 1880s, and it was an early leader in the development and use of high-strength aluminum alloys.&nbsp;</p><p>It was found that while aluminum and magnesium responded poorly to being shaped by hammering (they tended to shatter, particularly magnesium), good results could be achieved by squeezing them in hydraulic presses. As a result, Germany built a series of increasingly large presses in the years following WWI&nbsp; to make large forgings and extrusions from magnesium and aluminum. For forgings, it built a 7,000-ton press, followed by three 16,500-ton presses, followed by a 33,000 ton press, with plans for an even larger 55,000 ton press. Progress in extrusion presses was similar: by the end of WWII, Germany had four 12,000-ton extrusion presses in various stages of completion, and a 25,000-ton press on the drawing board. (“tons” refers to the pressure capacity of a press, not its weight. So a 7,000-ton press is capable of exerting 7,000 tons of force.)</p><p>The U.S. became aware of Germany’s large press capabilities as early as 1942, when inspection of the wreckage of German aircraft revealed forgings far larger than anything the U.S. could produce. The U.S. responded by starting work on a large, 18,000 ton forging press at the Wyman-Gordon plant in Massachusetts, but it wouldn’t be completed until 1946.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb7cec4ed-894c-4416-98a2-35a3394afa8a_1166x487.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb7cec4ed-894c-4416-98a2-35a3394afa8a_1166x487.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb7cec4ed-894c-4416-98a2-35a3394afa8a_1166x487.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb7cec4ed-894c-4416-98a2-35a3394afa8a_1166x487.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb7cec4ed-894c-4416-98a2-35a3394afa8a_1166x487.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb7cec4ed-894c-4416-98a2-35a3394afa8a_1166x487.png" width="1166" height="487" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/b7cec4ed-894c-4416-98a2-35a3394afa8a_1166x487.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:487,&quot;width&quot;:1166,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb7cec4ed-894c-4416-98a2-35a3394afa8a_1166x487.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb7cec4ed-894c-4416-98a2-35a3394afa8a_1166x487.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb7cec4ed-894c-4416-98a2-35a3394afa8a_1166x487.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb7cec4ed-894c-4416-98a2-35a3394afa8a_1166x487.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption><span>German large aircraft forging (left) vs same assembly made from multiple smaller parts, via </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iZ50nZU3oG8" rel="">USAF</a></figcaption></figure></div><p><span>Following Germany’s surrender, the U.S. and the Soviet Union divided up its large press capabilities as well as its </span><a href="https://www.construction-physics.com/p/building-apollo" rel="">rocket scientists</a><span>. The U.S. dismantled four German presses and had them shipped back to the states, while the Soviet Union secured the 33,000-ton press, the designs for the 55,000-ton press, and a number of German metallurgical experts.</span></p><p>By the late 1940s, a confluence of factors was pushing the U.S. towards building its own series of large presses. Rapidly improving aircraft performance was creating a need for lighter, stronger aircraft parts. The Germans had shown what could be achieved by using very large aircraft forgings and extrusions, and the U.S. had several years of experience from operating its own 18,000-ton press. The Soviet Union had taken the largest of the German presses and was presumably building more of its own, creating the risk that the U.S. might fall behind in aircraft manufacturing capabilities.</p><p><span>The Air Force studied seventeen different aircraft then under production, surveyed several different aircraft manufacturers, and concluded there were large potential benefits from building very large presses for forgings and extrusions.</span><em> </em><span>In 1950, the Department of Defense initiated a program to build 17 large presses: 9 die-forging (where hot metal was squeezed into a mold) and 8 extrusion. The expected cost, including presses and necessary supporting facilities, was $389 million. This was later cut down to 10 presses: 4 extrusion and 6 forging (in addition to the 18,000-ton Wyman-Gordon and the four presses taken from Germany), which would ultimately cost $239 million ($2.8 billion in 2024 dollars).</span></p><p>The program would be funded by the Department of Defense and managed by the Air Force, but the presses themselves would be leased to and operated by private industry (a choice that was controversial at the time). In return for very attractive lease rates, the companies would be responsible for any costs associated with maintaining and operating them, and the government would receive 4 to 5% of the revenue made from their operation.</p><p>This arrangement required some degree of selling on the part of the government. Private industry had to be convinced to participate, and that the presses would be sources of revenue and not simply a constant drain due to maintenance costs. Aircraft designers likewise had to be convinced that the presses would be available, and to design parts to take advantage of them. (Historically, aircraft designers had been reluctant to design parts that could only be made in a limited number of facilities.)</p><p>Construction on the presses began in 1952 and was a monumental undertaking. The largest, the 50,000-ton forging presses, were behemoths: each was the size of a ten-story building, and could exert enough force to lift an entire battleship. The 35,000-ton forging presses weren’t much smaller. Even the 12,000-ton extrusion presses were 120 feet long, with parts twice as tall as a man, and more than twice the capacity of the previous largest American extrusion presses.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb4c68b9-7afe-4a73-b5f0-a17afd568ffb_940x592.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb4c68b9-7afe-4a73-b5f0-a17afd568ffb_940x592.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb4c68b9-7afe-4a73-b5f0-a17afd568ffb_940x592.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb4c68b9-7afe-4a73-b5f0-a17afd568ffb_940x592.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb4c68b9-7afe-4a73-b5f0-a17afd568ffb_940x592.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb4c68b9-7afe-4a73-b5f0-a17afd568ffb_940x592.png" width="618" height="389.20851063829787" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/bb4c68b9-7afe-4a73-b5f0-a17afd568ffb_940x592.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:592,&quot;width&quot;:940,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:618,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb4c68b9-7afe-4a73-b5f0-a17afd568ffb_940x592.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb4c68b9-7afe-4a73-b5f0-a17afd568ffb_940x592.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb4c68b9-7afe-4a73-b5f0-a17afd568ffb_940x592.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb4c68b9-7afe-4a73-b5f0-a17afd568ffb_940x592.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption><span>Loewy 12,000 ton extrusion press, via </span><a href="https://archive.org/details/sim_industry-week_1955-02-07_136_6/page/68/mode/2up?q=%22heavy+press+program%22" rel="">Steel</a><span>.</span></figcaption></figure></div><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4a80505d-a835-4c46-872d-b057dc01a748_611x414.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4a80505d-a835-4c46-872d-b057dc01a748_611x414.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4a80505d-a835-4c46-872d-b057dc01a748_611x414.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4a80505d-a835-4c46-872d-b057dc01a748_611x414.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4a80505d-a835-4c46-872d-b057dc01a748_611x414.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4a80505d-a835-4c46-872d-b057dc01a748_611x414.png" width="611" height="414" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/4a80505d-a835-4c46-872d-b057dc01a748_611x414.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:414,&quot;width&quot;:611,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4a80505d-a835-4c46-872d-b057dc01a748_611x414.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4a80505d-a835-4c46-872d-b057dc01a748_611x414.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4a80505d-a835-4c46-872d-b057dc01a748_611x414.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4a80505d-a835-4c46-872d-b057dc01a748_611x414.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption><span>Cast steel component for a 12,000-ton Lombard extrusion press, via </span><a href="https://archive.org/details/sim_industry-week_1955-05-02_136_18/page/64/mode/2up?q=%22heavy+press+program%22" rel="">Steel</a></figcaption></figure></div><p>Most of the forging presses themselves would be underground, and required a 100-foot deep hole lined with concrete walls 13 feet thick. The forging and extrusion presses alike were made up of massive iron and steel components that were some of the largest metal parts ever produced: 200-ton cross beams, 90-ton cylinder supports, 145-ton tie rods. The parts were so large that special manufacturing and transportation methods were devised to handle them. Special furnaces needed to be built to fabricate the 108-foot tie rods for the forging presses, and multiple cranes were needed to move them. Some press components exceeded the weight limit for what a single rail car could support, and so were carried by multiple rail cars at once. Parts were produced by American fabricators like Bethlehem Steel, but also came from all over the world: England, Scotland, France, and Japan.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F46449d3f-01a8-4258-b299-06002e191051_651x820.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F46449d3f-01a8-4258-b299-06002e191051_651x820.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F46449d3f-01a8-4258-b299-06002e191051_651x820.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F46449d3f-01a8-4258-b299-06002e191051_651x820.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F46449d3f-01a8-4258-b299-06002e191051_651x820.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F46449d3f-01a8-4258-b299-06002e191051_651x820.png" width="483" height="608.3870967741935" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/46449d3f-01a8-4258-b299-06002e191051_651x820.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:820,&quot;width&quot;:651,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:483,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F46449d3f-01a8-4258-b299-06002e191051_651x820.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F46449d3f-01a8-4258-b299-06002e191051_651x820.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F46449d3f-01a8-4258-b299-06002e191051_651x820.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F46449d3f-01a8-4258-b299-06002e191051_651x820.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>275 ton steel ingot prior to being forged into part of a steel column for the Loewy 50,000 ton forging press.&nbsp;</figcaption></figure></div><p>The huge presses required equally huge supporting infrastructure. Hydraulic systems for the presses required water tanks thousands of gallons in size, and complex pumping systems that could pressurize water up to 7000 psi. Huge new furnaces had to be built, along with new, larger tools like saws and stretching devices. Mills had to figure out how to produce larger ingots of metals like aluminum to feed the large presses. At Alcoa, an entire 500,000 square foot factory was built in Cleveland to accommodate the 50,000- and 35,000-ton forging presses being installed.&nbsp;</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7cafb18f-45a8-44f2-9553-1fbe1e1411e1_771x594.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7cafb18f-45a8-44f2-9553-1fbe1e1411e1_771x594.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7cafb18f-45a8-44f2-9553-1fbe1e1411e1_771x594.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7cafb18f-45a8-44f2-9553-1fbe1e1411e1_771x594.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7cafb18f-45a8-44f2-9553-1fbe1e1411e1_771x594.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7cafb18f-45a8-44f2-9553-1fbe1e1411e1_771x594.png" width="558" height="429.8988326848249" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/7cafb18f-45a8-44f2-9553-1fbe1e1411e1_771x594.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:594,&quot;width&quot;:771,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:558,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7cafb18f-45a8-44f2-9553-1fbe1e1411e1_771x594.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7cafb18f-45a8-44f2-9553-1fbe1e1411e1_771x594.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7cafb18f-45a8-44f2-9553-1fbe1e1411e1_771x594.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7cafb18f-45a8-44f2-9553-1fbe1e1411e1_771x594.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>Turning a steel column for the 50,000 ton Mesta press on a 110 inch lathe.</figcaption></figure></div><p>By 1954 the first heavy presses were operational, and by 1956 they had all been completed. The presses quickly proved their worth, greatly reducing aircraft part counts and manufacturing costs. In one case, four forgings replaced a collection of 272 individual parts held together by 2,700 rivets. In another case, nine large extrusions replaced 81 smaller parts and eliminated more than 9,000 fasteners, reducing part cost by 30% and weight by 6%. And the new presses were also faster, further increasing production efficiencies.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0fd46d0d-e945-4246-bd9e-5474e24eeefc_1307x522.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0fd46d0d-e945-4246-bd9e-5474e24eeefc_1307x522.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0fd46d0d-e945-4246-bd9e-5474e24eeefc_1307x522.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0fd46d0d-e945-4246-bd9e-5474e24eeefc_1307x522.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0fd46d0d-e945-4246-bd9e-5474e24eeefc_1307x522.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0fd46d0d-e945-4246-bd9e-5474e24eeefc_1307x522.png" width="1307" height="522" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/0fd46d0d-e945-4246-bd9e-5474e24eeefc_1307x522.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:522,&quot;width&quot;:1307,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0fd46d0d-e945-4246-bd9e-5474e24eeefc_1307x522.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0fd46d0d-e945-4246-bd9e-5474e24eeefc_1307x522.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0fd46d0d-e945-4246-bd9e-5474e24eeefc_1307x522.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0fd46d0d-e945-4246-bd9e-5474e24eeefc_1307x522.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption><span>Reducing in machining on part for the B-52 by using heavy presses, via </span><a href="https://archive.org/details/sim_american-machinist_1957-09-09_101_18/page/175/mode/1up?q%3D%E2%80%9CAlcoa%E2%80%9D%2B%E2%80%9C50%252C000%2Bton=&amp;q=50%2C000" rel="">American Machinist</a><span>.</span></figcaption></figure></div><p>The presses eliminated machining time as well as parts and fasteners. Typically, a forging or extrusion didn’t come out of a press perfectly accurate, which required machining to carve the part down to its final dimensions. Likewise, very large parts had often needed to be cut down from large pieces of plate or billet. While machining wasn’t totally eliminated by the heavy presses, their ability to produce thin and complex parts near in size to the final shape required meant that machining time was greatly reduced. In one case, a part that started weighing 1,600 pounds and had more than 1,200 pounds removed by machining, at a cost of $18,000, was replaced by a part that started at just 321 pounds and required $500 worth of machining. Another part went from needing 23 pounds of material removed to just 2 pounds removed.</p><p>These savings had a significant effect on the total cost of aircraft being produced. Savings on the Convair F-102A were estimated to be $20,000, around 1.6% of the cost of the aircraft. The savings on a heavy bomber was estimated to be even greater, around 5-10% of its total cost; savings on the B-52 alone were estimated to be greater than the entire cost of the Heavy Press Program. By the 1960s, the heavy presses had saved the government an estimated $500 million in reduced manufacturing costs.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31df45e9-0ff5-42ff-8b37-23fb204471b3_775x474.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31df45e9-0ff5-42ff-8b37-23fb204471b3_775x474.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31df45e9-0ff5-42ff-8b37-23fb204471b3_775x474.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31df45e9-0ff5-42ff-8b37-23fb204471b3_775x474.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31df45e9-0ff5-42ff-8b37-23fb204471b3_775x474.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31df45e9-0ff5-42ff-8b37-23fb204471b3_775x474.png" width="775" height="474" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/31df45e9-0ff5-42ff-8b37-23fb204471b3_775x474.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:474,&quot;width&quot;:775,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31df45e9-0ff5-42ff-8b37-23fb204471b3_775x474.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31df45e9-0ff5-42ff-8b37-23fb204471b3_775x474.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31df45e9-0ff5-42ff-8b37-23fb204471b3_775x474.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31df45e9-0ff5-42ff-8b37-23fb204471b3_775x474.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>Aircraft components that could be made on the heavy presses, via Aviation Week.</figcaption></figure></div><p>And it wasn’t just aircraft that were able to take advantage of the new press capabilities; parts from the presses were used in ballistic missiles, nuclear submarines, and armored vehicles for the Army. The presses were used to forge the beryllium heat shield on the Mercury space capsule, and the huge aluminum “anchors” that attached the Saturn V rocket to the launch pad. In 1956, the presses were first used to produce parts for commercial aircraft, and by the 1960s this was common — a 4,000-pound titanium beam made on the heavy presses to support the landing gear on the Boeing 747 was the largest titanium forging that had ever been produced.</p><p>Partly this broad range of uses for the heavy presses came from expanding the range of materials used in them. Originally the presses were designed to make parts from aluminum and magnesium, but by the 1960s they were not only pressing aluminum and magnesium but steel, titanium, nickel, copper, columbium, beryllium, and a variety of other metals.</p><p>The heavy presses have been described as “the most rapid and far reaching advance in metal processing in industrial history,” as well as the biggest leap for aircraft manufacturing in industry history. By the early 2000s, parts from the heavy presses were in every U.S. military aircraft in service, and every airplane built by Airbus and Boeing. The two 50,000-ton forging presses remained the largest closed-die forging presses in the U.S. until 2018, when they were surpassed by an even larger 60,000-ton press.</p><p><span>The Heavy Press Program is a classic example of military technological spillovers, and the potential returns from government investment in technological capabilities. The heavy presses were built specifically for military purposes — making lighter and stronger parts for supersonic aircraft — but once they were built, they proved useful for all sorts of other things, from spacecraft to power systems to commercial aircraft. The U.S. has accrued the benefits of the presses for 70 years and counting, and at least part of America’s success in commercial aircraft manufacturing can be attributed to their existence. Some have gone so far as to say that the entire modern American aerospace industry </span><a href="https://riancwhitton.substack.com/p/start-the-presses" rel="">owes its existence to the heavy presses</a><span>.</span></p><p><span>The Heavy Press Program also shows the importance of manufacturing improvements for technological progress. The sorts of </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Design_for_manufacturability" rel="">design for manufacturing</a><span> optimizations that the presses made possible — replacing a large number of parts and fasteners with a smaller number of larger components, reducing machining time — not only reduce manufacturing costs, but they changed the economic calculus as to what sorts of technologies are commercially viable, and thus get further developed. The heavy presses made it possible to build strong, precise, lightweight aircraft components more cheaply than other manufacturing methods, making things feasible that otherwise might not have been. An official Air Force statement from 1964 states that “to catalogue the significant accomplishments of the heavy press program is almost to relate the history of our modern advanced aircraft,” and credits it for making things like aircraft wet wings (where the wing of the airplane holds the fuel) inexpensive enough to be viable.</span><span><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-1-147930799" href="https://www.construction-physics.com/p/how-to-build-a-50000-ton-forging#footnote-1-147930799" target="_self" rel="">1</a></span></p><p><span>We can see a modern, obvious parallel between the Air Force Heavy Press Program and Tesla, which has created a similar revolution in car manufacturing by using large aluminum castings to replace dozens or hundreds of smaller parts. Like the Heavy Press, using large castings required building new, larger capacity machinery, in the form of “Giga-casting” machines of unprecedented size. Tesla was the first car manufacturer to adopt large castings, but the savings were so significant — an estimated 20 to 40% reduction in the cost of a car body — that they’re being adopted by many other car manufacturers, particularly Chinese ones. Large, complex castings have been described as a key tool for not only reducing cost but also </span><a href="https://www.diecasting-mould.com/news/the-casting-expert-behind-byd-and-xpengs-components" rel="">good EV charging performance</a><span>.</span></p><p><span>The experience of Tesla with large castings suggest that there’s still opportunities available to push technology forward by making large, complex parts in a single step. Even with large presses, we may not have exhausted the possibilities. The largest closed-die forging presses have now reached 80,000 tons (in China, naturally), but as early as the 1950s experts were speculating that presses of up to 200,000 tons might be useful for aircraft manufacturing. Experience developing the SR-71 led Kelly Johnson to believe that the U.S. needed even larger, 250,000-ton presses, and in the 1980s the Army studied </span><a href="https://archive.org/details/DTIC_ADA132398/mode/1up?q%3D%E2%80%9CAlcoa%E2%80%9D%2B%E2%80%9C50%252C000%2Bton=" rel="">whether presses</a><span> of up to 200,000 tons might be useful. But no such presses were ever built, either in the U.S. or elsewhere.</span></p><p>And in fact, recent experience suggests the U.S. might no longer be willing or able to take advantage of this type of opportunity. Much of the experience in building machinery of this magnitude has been lost, or has migrated elsewhere. The original heavy presses were built by American companies like Loewy Hydropress and Mesta, but when the 50,000-ton Alcoa press was refurbished in the early 2000s, the parts came from German company SMS, the same company that built the 60,000-ton forging press. And while American car manufacturers are using large Giga-casting machines in their manufacturing operations, those machines themselves are overwhelmingly built by Chinese or Chinese-owned companies like IDRA.</p><p>Technological progress means building things that have never been built before, which often means pushing the boundaries of manufacturing technology forward. Fail to do this, and you risk being outcompeted by people who do.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Rye and Uv: August Is Harvest Season for Python Packaging (138 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lucumr.pocoo.org/2024/8/21/harvest-season/</link>
            <guid>41309072</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 11:12:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lucumr.pocoo.org/2024/8/21/harvest-season/">https://lucumr.pocoo.org/2024/8/21/harvest-season/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41309072">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        
  

  
  <p>written on Wednesday, August 21, 2024
  

  </p><p>It has been a few months since I wrote about <a href="https://rye.astral.sh/">Rye</a> here last.  You might remember that in
February I passed over stewardship of my Rye packaging too to <a href="https://astral.sh/">Astral</a>.  The folks over there have been super busy in
building a lot of amazing tooling for Python packaging in the last few
months.  If you have been using Rye in the last few months you will have
noticed that the underlying resolver and installer <a href="https://docs.astral.sh/uv/">uv</a> got a lot better and faster.</p>
<p>As of the most recent release, <cite>uv</cite> also gained a lot of functionality that
previously required Rye such as manipulating <cite>pyproject.toml</cite> files,
workspace support, local package references and script installation.  It
now also can manage Python installations for you so it's getting much
closer.</p>
<p>If you are using Rye today, consider this blog post as a reminder that you
should probably starting having a closer look at <cite>uv</cite> and <a href="https://github.com/astral-sh/rye/discussions/1342">give feedback to
the Astral folks</a>.</p>
<p>I gave a talk just recently in Prague at EuroPython about my current view
of the Python packaging, the lessons I learned when creating Rye and one
of the things I mentioned there is that the goal of a packaging tool has
to be that it will dominate the space.  The tool that absolutely everybody
uses has to be the best tool: it's the thing any new person to Python gets
to see when they start their programming journey.  After that talk a lot
of people walked up to me and had a lot of questions about that in
particular.</p>
<p>Python in the last two years has become an incredibly hot and popular
platform for many new developers.  That has in part been fueled by all the
investments and interest that went into AI and ML.  I really want
everybody who gets to learn and experience Python not to remember it as an
old language with bad tooling, but as an amazing language with a stellar
developer experience.  Unfortunately that's not the case today because
there is so much choice, so many tools that are not quite compatible, and
by the inconsistency everywhere.  I have seen people walk down one tool,
just to re-emerge moving their entire stack to conda and back because they
hit some wall.</p>
<p>Domination is a goal because it means that most investment will go into
one stack.  I can only re-iterate my wish and desire that Rye (and with it
a lot of other tools in the space) should cease to exist once the
dominating tool has been established.  For me <cite>uv</cite> is poised to be that
tool.  It's not quite there today yet for all cases, but it will be in no
time, and now is the moment to step up as a community and start to start
to rally around it.  That doesn't mean that this tool will be the tool
forever.  Things come and go and maybe there is a future for some other
tool.</p>
<p>But today I'm looking forward to the moment when there will be a final
release of Rye that is no remaining functionality other than to just
largely alias to uv, that retires Rye specific functionality and migrates
you over to uv.</p>
<p>However I <em>only have the power to retire one tool, and that won't be
enough</em>.  Today we are using so many other package managing solutions for
Python and we should be advertising fewer.  I understand how much time and
effort went into many of those, and everybody's contributions are
absolutely appreciated.  Software like Rye and uv were built on the
advancements of the ecosystem underneath it.  They leverage years and
years of work that went into migrating the Python ecosystems from setup.py
files to eggs and finally wheels.  From not having a metadata standard to
having one.  From coupled to decoupled build systems.  Much of what makes
Rye so enjoyable were individuals that worked towards making
redistributable and downloadable Python binaries a possibility.  There was
a lot of work that was put into building out an amazing ecosystem of Rust
crates and Python libraries needed to make these tools work.  All of that
brought us to that point where we are today.</p>
<p>But it is my believe that we need to take the next step and be willing to
say as a community that some tools are no longer recommended.  Maybe not
today, but that moment will come quicker than we think.  I remember a time
when many of us who maintained Python libraries pointed new developers to
using <cite>ez_setup.py</cite> and <cite>easy_install</cite> in our onboarding guides.  Years
later we removed the mentions of <cite>ez_setup.py</cite> from our guides to replace
them with <cite>pip</cite>.  Some of us have pointed developers at <cite>pip-tools</cite>, at
<cite>poetry</cite> or <cite>PDM</cite>.  Many projects today even show 5 different installation
guides because of that wild variety of tools available because they no
longer feel like they can recommend one.</p>
<p>If you maintain an important Python project I would ask you to give <cite>uv</cite> a
try and ask yourself if you would consider pointing people towards it.  I
think that this is our best shot in the community at finding ourselves in
a much better position than we have ever been.</p>
<p>Have a look at the blog post that Charlie from Astral wrote about what <a href="https://astral.sh/blog/uv-unified-python-packaging">uv
can do today</a>.
It's a true accomplishment worth celebrating and enjoying.</p>
<hr>
<p><small><p><strong>Postscriptum:</strong> there is an elephant in the room which is that Astral is a
VC funded company.  What does that mean for the future of these tools?
Here is my take on this: for the community having someone pour money into
it can create some challenges.  For the PSF and the core Python project
this is something that should be considered.  However having seen the code
and what uv is doing, even in the worst possible future this is a very
forkable and maintainable thing.  I believe that even in case Astral shuts
down or were to do something incredibly dodgy licensing wise, the
community would be better off than before uv existed.</p>
</small></p><p>This entry was tagged
    
      <a href="https://lucumr.pocoo.org/tags/announcement/">announcement</a>, 
      <a href="https://lucumr.pocoo.org/tags/python/">python</a> and 
      <a href="https://lucumr.pocoo.org/tags/rye/">rye</a>
  

      </p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I've Built My First Successful Side Project, and I Hate It (894 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://switowski.com/blog/i-have-built-my-first-successful-side-project-and-i-hate-it/</link>
            <guid>41308599</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 09:59:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://switowski.com/blog/i-have-built-my-first-successful-side-project-and-i-hate-it/">https://switowski.com/blog/i-have-built-my-first-successful-side-project-and-i-hate-it/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41308599">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>

<div>
<p>In 2020, I built my first side project. I <em>scratched my own itch</em>, then started selling it, and since then, the project has earned me over $15,000. But a few months after releasing it, I was so tired of the maintenance that I wanted to shut it down. Here is a story about my short entrepreneurial adventure.</p>
<figure>
<picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/rBpbw8Pkd4-250.webp 250w, https://switowski.com/img/rBpbw8Pkd4-600.webp 600w, https://switowski.com/img/rBpbw8Pkd4-920.webp 920w, https://switowski.com/img/rBpbw8Pkd4-1280.webp 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/rBpbw8Pkd4-250.jpeg 250w, https://switowski.com/img/rBpbw8Pkd4-600.jpeg 600w, https://switowski.com/img/rBpbw8Pkd4-920.jpeg 920w, https://switowski.com/img/rBpbw8Pkd4-1280.jpeg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><img alt="Gumroad dashboard with the earnings from my project" loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://switowski.com/img/rBpbw8Pkd4-250.jpeg" width="1280" height="990"></picture>
<figcaption>Gumroad dashboard with the earnings from my project</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>In the second part of 2020, I had some spare time. I just finished a project for a client, and I've decided to dedicate a few months to making a <a href="https://modernpythonprojects.com/">Python course</a> – just to try something new. At the same time, I became interested in using technical analysis to trade stocks. Following one of the "internet investment gurus" (yes, I know how bad it sounds), I started day-trading stocks following some "mystical knowledge" on how to leverage price formation called "harmonic patterns" to figure out when to buy or sell (look, I'm sorry, I also cringe when I write those words).</p>
<p>Like many <s>traders</s> investors, I was using <a href="https://www.tradingview.com/">TradingView</a>, the most popular free platform for technical analysis. Compared to the tools offered by stock brokers at that time, TradingView was far superior with its user-friendly web interface and a plethora of tools. You could even write your own scripts using an abomination of a scripting language called PineScript to implement all sorts of additional tools, graphs, and metrics for your charts.</p>
<p>But there was no script that would draw harmonic patterns for me, and after a few days of drawing them manually, I got tired and decided to automate the process. It took me a few weeks to learn the language and implement a script to automatically draw harmonic patterns on the chart. The script significantly decreased the time I had to spend searching for stocks to trade. Then, I wrote another script - one that was drawing potential future patterns.</p>
<p><em>Great! If those scripts work for me, maybe someone will pay money to use them too.</em> After all, the idea of harmonic patterns wasn't new – the earliest harmonic pattern, the "Gartley Pattern", was first described in 1935. There are books, articles, and videos on this topic, so for sure, I wasn't the only one using them.</p>
<p>Luckily for me, TradingView supports selling access to scripts, although in a slightly convoluted way. With the most expensive subscription, if you publish your script with "invite only" access, you can control which users can use it. So, I bought that subscription and created a landing page connected to Gumroad to accept payments for monthly and yearly subscriptions.</p>

<p>Now, I needed to find a way to tell TradingView's users about my scripts, as those "invite only" scripts are not easy to find. TradingView doesn't promote them in the search results; instead, it prioritizes free-to-use scripts with publicly available source code. And even if someone found my scripts or my website, I needed to convince them that my scripts are useful and do what they are supposed to do. Even though I offered a 14-day money-back guarantee on any subscription, people were reluctant to give their credit card details on some random website.</p>
<p>So, I've created a couple of smaller scripts by reusing large chunks of code from the existing scripts. Their source code was still hidden, but people could use the scripts for free - with limited functionality:</p>
<ul>
<li>you could find only some types of price formations</li>
<li>there was a limit to how many past days you could check</li>
<li>there were no automatic notifications when a new pattern appeared</li>
</ul>
<p>Still, people liked them and started using them. When they asked about missing features like the notifications or detecting more patterns, I directed them to the paid scripts.</p>
<p>Then, I published some "ideas" on TradingView - screenshots of popular stocks with drawings of the existing and potential future harmonic patterns generated with my scripts. Finally, I created a YouTube channel where I published videos showing all the features of my scripts (this was partially so I didn't have to explain over and over again how they work).</p>
<p>And I started waiting for the cash to roll in.</p>
<p>Nothing happened for the first two weeks, but then I got my first sale! Someone bought access to one of the scripts for a month. For the first time in my life, I got paid for selling something on the internet. It felt amazing! Later, they requested a refund because they didn't find the script helpful, but to this day, I clearly remember the excitement of laying on the sofa in the evening and getting an email from Gumroad saying, "Hey, someone just paid you $9 for the thing you've built".</p>
<figure>
<picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/om8PY3JLxn-250.webp 250w, https://switowski.com/img/om8PY3JLxn-600.webp 600w, https://switowski.com/img/om8PY3JLxn-920.webp 920w, https://switowski.com/img/om8PY3JLxn-1280.webp 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/om8PY3JLxn-250.jpeg 250w, https://switowski.com/img/om8PY3JLxn-600.jpeg 600w, https://switowski.com/img/om8PY3JLxn-920.jpeg 920w, https://switowski.com/img/om8PY3JLxn-1280.jpeg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><img alt="Dashboard with earnings from the first months" loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://switowski.com/img/om8PY3JLxn-250.jpeg" width="1280" height="602"></picture>
<figcaption>The first sale felt more rewarding than any other that followed, although hitting a $1,000 revenue per month was also a nice milestone.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Slowly, more people started using my free scripts, and some also bought the paid ones. To strike while the iron was still hot, I posted a message saying that anyone interested can leave a comment under the paid scripts, and I will give them a free 1-week trial. So people started doing that, and each time, I would log in to TradingView and manually grant them access for a week. Some of those trials turned into paid subscriptions, but most didn't. Slowly but steadily, the number of subscribers started increasing.</p>
<h2 id="needy-customers-checked-fraud-checked-next-stop-the-burn-out-station" tabindex="-1">Needy customers? Checked. Fraud? Checked. Next stop - the "burn out" station </h2>
<p>As more people used my scripts, I started getting more emails with questions and requests for new features. Many of the emails contained requests for free access to the scripts. Others had very basic questions, answers to which were given in the description of each script.</p>
<p>Some people wanted to buy the source code:
<picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/4IoNUoQmrC-250.webp 250w, https://switowski.com/img/4IoNUoQmrC-600.webp 600w, https://switowski.com/img/4IoNUoQmrC-920.webp 920w, https://switowski.com/img/4IoNUoQmrC-1133.webp 1133w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/4IoNUoQmrC-250.jpeg 250w, https://switowski.com/img/4IoNUoQmrC-600.jpeg 600w, https://switowski.com/img/4IoNUoQmrC-920.jpeg 920w, https://switowski.com/img/4IoNUoQmrC-1133.jpeg 1133w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><img alt="Email from someone who wants to buy the source code of my scripts" loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://switowski.com/img/4IoNUoQmrC-250.jpeg" width="1133" height="248"></picture></p>
<p>Or get access to it for free. Of course, for <em>personal use</em>.</p>
<figure>
<picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/54Cf6CwS-z-250.webp 250w, https://switowski.com/img/54Cf6CwS-z-600.webp 600w, https://switowski.com/img/54Cf6CwS-z-920.webp 920w, https://switowski.com/img/54Cf6CwS-z-1087.webp 1087w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/54Cf6CwS-z-250.jpeg 250w, https://switowski.com/img/54Cf6CwS-z-600.jpeg 600w, https://switowski.com/img/54Cf6CwS-z-920.jpeg 920w, https://switowski.com/img/54Cf6CwS-z-1087.jpeg 1087w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><img alt="Email from someone who wants to get free access to the source code" loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://switowski.com/img/54Cf6CwS-z-250.jpeg" width="1087" height="354"></picture>
<figcaption>Sure thing random person from the Internet, I totally trust that you won't share or publish my script as your own.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>There were people requesting that I add some very specific features because someone they watched on YouTube recommended it.
<picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/nsHIXzL6mt-250.webp 250w, https://switowski.com/img/nsHIXzL6mt-600.webp 600w, https://switowski.com/img/nsHIXzL6mt-920.webp 920w, https://switowski.com/img/nsHIXzL6mt-1430.webp 1430w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/nsHIXzL6mt-250.jpeg 250w, https://switowski.com/img/nsHIXzL6mt-600.jpeg 600w, https://switowski.com/img/nsHIXzL6mt-920.jpeg 920w, https://switowski.com/img/nsHIXzL6mt-1430.jpeg 1430w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><img alt="Email requesting to add some specific feature" loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://switowski.com/img/nsHIXzL6mt-250.jpeg" width="1430" height="490"></picture></p>
<p>Or that I add <em>some kind of feature</em> that I could not really understand, but it surely made a lot of sense in <em>their</em> mind:
<picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/4NVDxL98Jg-250.webp 250w, https://switowski.com/img/4NVDxL98Jg-600.webp 600w, https://switowski.com/img/4NVDxL98Jg-920.webp 920w, https://switowski.com/img/4NVDxL98Jg-1430.webp 1430w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/4NVDxL98Jg-250.jpeg 250w, https://switowski.com/img/4NVDxL98Jg-600.jpeg 600w, https://switowski.com/img/4NVDxL98Jg-920.jpeg 920w, https://switowski.com/img/4NVDxL98Jg-1430.jpeg 1430w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><img alt="Email requesting I add some very weird feature" loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://switowski.com/img/4NVDxL98Jg-250.jpeg" width="1430" height="518"></picture></p>
<p>Quite a few folks were asking for some "hot tips" on how to trade <em>something</em> or if that <em>something</em> was going to go up or down (almost always, this <em>something</em> was cryptocurrencies or forex).
<picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/rVwhZjW8Kx-250.webp 250w, https://switowski.com/img/rVwhZjW8Kx-600.webp 600w, https://switowski.com/img/rVwhZjW8Kx-744.webp 744w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/rVwhZjW8Kx-250.jpeg 250w, https://switowski.com/img/rVwhZjW8Kx-600.jpeg 600w, https://switowski.com/img/rVwhZjW8Kx-744.jpeg 744w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><img alt="Someone asking for advice" loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://switowski.com/img/rVwhZjW8Kx-250.jpeg" width="744" height="204"></picture></p>
<p><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/5-VIdNzhN9-250.webp 250w, https://switowski.com/img/5-VIdNzhN9-600.webp 600w, https://switowski.com/img/5-VIdNzhN9-756.webp 756w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/5-VIdNzhN9-250.jpeg 250w, https://switowski.com/img/5-VIdNzhN9-600.jpeg 600w, https://switowski.com/img/5-VIdNzhN9-756.jpeg 756w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><img alt="Another person asking for advice" loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://switowski.com/img/5-VIdNzhN9-250.jpeg" width="756" height="294"></picture></p>
<p>Even worse, sometimes such requests were accompanied by a backstory like "I'm a poor student and want to make some money" or "I've lost some money trading, but your script looks very cool, and I will use it to make money back". Why on earth would you bet your money on some random tool you don't even understand? And then ask some random stranger on the internet for financial advice?! This was sad. I built a tool for people who knew what harmonic patterns were. People who had an investment strategy and only needed a tool to automate the drawing of the charts that they would normally draw by hand. Not some gung-ho <em>investors</em> whose entire investment strategy consists of "this random script I found five minutes ago says that stock X will go up, so I buy."</p>
<p>Sometimes, I would get a job offer. Yay! For writing PineScript for a living. Nay!</p>
<figure>
<picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/gVllKEsxoN-250.webp 250w, https://switowski.com/img/gVllKEsxoN-600.webp 600w, https://switowski.com/img/gVllKEsxoN-920.webp 920w, https://switowski.com/img/gVllKEsxoN-1596.webp 1596w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/gVllKEsxoN-250.jpeg 250w, https://switowski.com/img/gVllKEsxoN-600.jpeg 600w, https://switowski.com/img/gVllKEsxoN-920.jpeg 920w, https://switowski.com/img/gVllKEsxoN-1596.jpeg 1596w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><img alt="Job offer email" loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://switowski.com/img/gVllKEsxoN-250.jpeg" width="1596" height="420"></picture>
<figcaption>Writing PineScript full time? No, thanks.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Or a collaboration proposal from someone who had a "large group of active traders":</p>
<figure>
<picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/pEAwY8UCOf-250.webp 250w, https://switowski.com/img/pEAwY8UCOf-600.webp 600w, https://switowski.com/img/pEAwY8UCOf-920.webp 920w, https://switowski.com/img/pEAwY8UCOf-1448.webp 1448w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/pEAwY8UCOf-250.jpeg 250w, https://switowski.com/img/pEAwY8UCOf-600.jpeg 600w, https://switowski.com/img/pEAwY8UCOf-920.jpeg 920w, https://switowski.com/img/pEAwY8UCOf-1448.jpeg 1448w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><img alt="Email from someone with a large group of traders" loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://switowski.com/img/pEAwY8UCOf-250.jpeg" width="1448" height="226"></picture>
<figcaption>Somehow all those claims from 'people with large communities' never materialized beyond testing the trial.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>I even had a chance to practice foreign languages!
<picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/CUwZF8NE39-250.webp 250w, https://switowski.com/img/CUwZF8NE39-600.webp 600w, https://switowski.com/img/CUwZF8NE39-920.webp 920w, https://switowski.com/img/CUwZF8NE39-1448.webp 1448w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/CUwZF8NE39-250.jpeg 250w, https://switowski.com/img/CUwZF8NE39-600.jpeg 600w, https://switowski.com/img/CUwZF8NE39-920.jpeg 920w, https://switowski.com/img/CUwZF8NE39-1448.jpeg 1448w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><img alt="Message in a foreign language" loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://switowski.com/img/CUwZF8NE39-250.jpeg" width="1448" height="265"></picture></p>
<h3 id="disputes" tabindex="-1">Disputes </h3>
<p>Sometimes, people would open a "dispute". A dispute means someone complained to PayPal that their credit card was wrongfully charged and then it's up to PayPal to decide if they are right (and refund them the full amount of money + charge me additional $20 for "chargeback fees") or if they are not (then I get to keep the payment).</p>
<p>In general, I try to be as accommodating to customers as possible. I'm selling software, so unlike with a physical product, I have unlimited stock of my products; producing new copies costs me nothing, and I don't have costs related to handling shipments or returns. So if someone writes to me and asks, "Hey, I forgot to cancel my subscription, and it renewed for another month", or "It's past the 14-day money-back guarantee, but it turns out that the script is not useful for me", I give them their money back. I want to be nice to people. I started selling those tools to help others. I don't want to charge them for a product they don't like.</p>
<p>But I also don't want people to open disputes. If you have too many disputes, you risk that PayPal will freeze your account.</p>
<p>Sometimes, being nice to people is not enough. Especially if you don't get a chance to show your goodwill because you're sleeping. My first dispute came from a customer who sent me a message in the middle of the night asking how to cancel their subscription and, half an hour later, proceeded to open a dispute. Even though all they had to do was check the emails from Gumroad that contained a link to manage their subscription. And those are short emails with a few lines of text, so it's not that the link is hidden somewhere - at least other people who wanted to cancel their subscription managed to find it. Or they could at least send me an email without opening a dispute right away.</p>
<p>Luckily, after I explained that I could (and wanted to) refund their payment, provided they closed the dispute first, the customer cooperated with me. So we closed the dispute, and shortly afterwards, they got their money back.</p>
<p>A few more disputes happened throughout the years but were less thrilling. Usually, someone would open a dispute through PayPal, not answer my messages (or PayPal's), and then PayPal would dismiss that dispute as unfounded.</p>
<h3 id="and-yes-fraud" tabindex="-1">And yes, fraud </h3>
<p>Being polite and accommodating will take you a long way and make your online interactions much more enjoyable.</p>
<p>It also means that, at some point, someone will try to take advantage of you.</p>
<p>For me, it happened three times. Most of the time, someone tried using a stolen credit card, but Gumroad caught that and cancelled the payment. But the first time a fraud happened, it caught me a bit off guard. I don't have many screenshots left because that person deleted their TradingView account, but here's how it went.</p>
<p>First, Mr. Scammer (that's not his real name 😉) asked for free access to the script. That's not uncommon - sometimes, people send me requests like that. When I kindly but firmly denied his request, he tried to pay, but his payment was declined with a message saying he should contact Gumroad. Again, this didn't sound like a red flag, more like a technical issue. Eventually, I got a confirmation email that he had paid for the subscription.</p>
<p>Two months later, a "sale has been disputed" email dropped. The dispute was initiated by Mr. Scammer. I asked him why he initiated the dispute because he never mentioned wanting to cancel his subscription or getting a refund. This is when things started to be very fishy:</p>
<p><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/NrBw1iXww8-250.webp 250w, https://switowski.com/img/NrBw1iXww8-473.webp 473w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/NrBw1iXww8-250.jpeg 250w, https://switowski.com/img/NrBw1iXww8-473.jpeg 473w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><img alt="Screenshot of me asking the scammer about the dispute" loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://switowski.com/img/NrBw1iXww8-250.jpeg" width="473" height="400"></picture></p>
<p>Weird grammar errors were not a red flag. They are common in emails I get from existing and potential customers, so it doesn't automatically mean an email is a scam. But a story of your wife controlling the finances and you forgetting to tell her about buying a script for TradingView, which made her open a dispute? That's even weirder than the "I'm a student who can't afford $15, but I <em>really</em> need this script for my day-trading" emails I sometimes get.</p>
<p>While waiting for the dispute to be resolved, Mr. Scammer tried to buy the subscription one more time, this time with less success:
<picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/vlwB-CFoFG-250.webp 250w, https://switowski.com/img/vlwB-CFoFG-600.webp 600w, https://switowski.com/img/vlwB-CFoFG-920.webp 920w, https://switowski.com/img/vlwB-CFoFG-1228.webp 1228w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/vlwB-CFoFG-250.jpeg 250w, https://switowski.com/img/vlwB-CFoFG-600.jpeg 600w, https://switowski.com/img/vlwB-CFoFG-920.jpeg 920w, https://switowski.com/img/vlwB-CFoFG-1228.jpeg 1228w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><img alt="Email about fraud attempt from Mr. Scammer" loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://switowski.com/img/vlwB-CFoFG-250.jpeg" width="1228" height="1065"></picture></p>
<p>So, was his "wife" not only controlling the finances but also using stolen credit cards? I wrote him that he's permanently banned from buying any scripts from me, and the next time he tries, I will immediately revoke his access. That stopped any further attempts.</p>
<p>That was the most interesting case of fraud. Usually, when people got caught, they ignored my messages instead of coming up with a creative story:
<picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/dI8l5KzDb--250.webp 250w, https://switowski.com/img/dI8l5KzDb--600.webp 600w, https://switowski.com/img/dI8l5KzDb--742.webp 742w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://switowski.com/img/dI8l5KzDb--250.jpeg 250w, https://switowski.com/img/dI8l5KzDb--600.jpeg 600w, https://switowski.com/img/dI8l5KzDb--742.jpeg 742w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) calc(100vw - 32px), (max-width: 767px) 608px, (max-width: 960px) calc(100vw - 40px), 920px"><img alt="Message to another scammer that was ignored by them." loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://switowski.com/img/dI8l5KzDb--250.jpeg" width="742" height="356"></picture></p>
<h3 id="burn-out" tabindex="-1">Burn out </h3>
<p>Answering emails and checking TradingView comments to give out trial access took a bit of time every day. Not much, but I tried to answer at least every day. It was a minor annoyance when I wasn't working full-time. But when I had to do this after a full day of work, and I got yet another email asking to add some <em>magical</em> method for determining take profit levels that was invented by a crypto-trading YouTuber with 50 followers<sup><a href="#fn1" id="fnref1">[1]</a></sup>, I had enough.</p>
<p>The worst part was that after a few months, I wasn't even using those scripts anymore. I had fun day trading when I wasn't working full-time. It was a nice break from recording videos and a motivation to learn about financial markets. But when a new contract started, I stopped day trading due to the lack of time.</p>
<p>But I still had existing customers that I needed to take care of and potential new customers asking me all sorts of questions. I was growing tired of maintaining this project. Sometimes, I would spend an hour answering many detailed questions from a potential customer only to never hear back from them. At times, someone would leave a 1-star review on Gumroad because I didn't want to add some weird functionality they requested. On days like that, I wanted to close down this project, refund the money to the existing clients, and delete my TradingView account.</p>
<p>Still, the project was bringing in a bit of money every month. I didn't want to kill the goose that laid tiny golden eggs. So, I've decided that I'm going to sell my "goose".</p>
<h2 id="selling-my-project-well-trying-to" tabindex="-1">Selling my project. Well, trying to... </h2>
<p>I looked for platforms where I could list my project for sale. I found a few and decided to submit an ad to <a href="https://indiemaker.co/">IndieMaker</a> and <a href="https://transferslot.com/">Transferslot</a> (which looked much more active three years ago). I prepared a detailed description of the project and shared details like the number of views on my YouTube channel, unique visitors to the website, the number of followers and subscribers on various platforms, and, of course, the revenue. I even shared some ideas on how to move this project forward. For example, getting one of the free scripts promoted in the weekly TradingView newsletter could accelerate the sales of paid scripts.</p>
<p>Then, following some random advice on the internet, I came up with a number to ask for that was around 5x the revenue from last year. I then sent my ad for publication.</p>
<p>IndieMaker published my ad, and shortly after, I received an inquiry from a potential buyer. But after answering questions about the Monthly Recurring Revenue growth and what assets come with the project, there was no follow-up. I got more messages later, but those were just spam ("Hey, I'm interested in your project, send us a list of your inventory"). Transferslot never published my ad. I think the website was already abandoned when I submitted it.</p>
<p>If you have any experience selling projects online (and if you don't, <a href="https://training.kalzumeus.com/newsletters/archive/selling_software_business">this article</a> from Patrick McKenzie is the best way to understand how it works), you're probably shaking your head by now. People buying software businesses look for <strong>simple, low-risk, boring-tech projects</strong> with a proven track record of stable or increasing profits. No one wants to buy a project written in an esoteric language (PineScript) running on a proprietary platform (TradingView) that targets a very specific niche of traders.</p>
<p>After a couple of weeks with no more replies, I had to decide what to do next. I could submit my ad to bigger platforms like <a href="https://flippa.com/">Flippa</a> and pay to have it listed there. But I felt that this project was so niche that I wouldn't find a potential buyer on other platforms either. Especially a potential buyer who knew the PineScript language necessary to maintain and improve the scripts' source code.</p>
<p>While waiting for more bids from potential buyers, I started thinking about what I could do to ease the burden of this project. I'm an engineer, goddamit! We're not meant to click buttons in the browser or send the same email over and over again!</p>
<h2 id="turning-the-autopilot-on" tabindex="-1">Turning the autopilot on </h2>
<p>I checked my options and decided to automate the following parts of my work:</p>
<ul>
<li>Gumroad payment should automatically grant access to the script on TradingView and send a "welcome" email. This would cover the most time-critical part of my work, so I didn't have to start my day from logging in to TradingView and granting access to people who bought subscriptions during the night.</li>
<li>A chatbot to manage subscriptions so that I could do all the manual work (removing access from people who cancelled subscriptions, extending trial access, etc.) with simple commands from my phone without logging in to TradingView.</li>
<li>Finally, I could create an online form where people could request trial access by leaving their TradingView username. This form would then trigger a Python script granting them one week's access to the selected TradingView script.</li>
</ul>
<p>I implemented all those features using <a href="https://n8n.io/">n8n</a> to connect various services together - webhooks, a Telegram bot, Python scripts, sending emails, etc. I will write a separate article describing this setup's technical details.</p>
<p>Once I had the automation in place, users could request free trial access through an online form or buy a subscription on Gumroad, and everything would be handled automatically. From time to time, when they cancelled their subscription, I had to send a short message to my Telegram bot to set an expiration date for their access.</p>
<p>The hardest part was to stop caring so much about this project and disconnect myself. I like helping people. That's why I became a programmer - to build things that help me or help others. When I get an email, I try to answer it as best as I can. Years of working with clients taught me to explain things in a simple and easy-to-understand way. So, I spent hours patiently answering questions from potential customers only to never hear back from them. And even though I posted a link to the form where people could request trial access, plenty of folks didn't bother reading the description and kept commenting or sending me messages requesting trials.</p>
<p>This had to stop. I started by checking TradingView messages only on the weekends and granting trial access in bulk. For every comment about trial access, I replied "I gave you access now, but it would have been faster if you used the form I posted", hoping that others would see my reply and use the form next time. I still paid special attention to my existing clients and answered their emails every evening. But if someone was not an existing client, I would only respond to their questions on weekends. Eventually, I stopped checking the TradingView comments or messages. If people really wanted a trial, they would eventually read the two-sentence instruction, click the link, and fill in the form.</p>
<p>Did this affect my sales significantly? I don't think so. Most of the people asking basic questions would never convert to paying customers anyway. They were window shopping. They found a script that seemed to predict price changes, and they wanted to know how to make money with it. And the theory behind how it works and why it's supposed to work? Nah, they didn't care. They had ten more random scripts to test out today.</p>
<p>Did disconnecting from my project affect my sanity? Oh, hell yes! The project went on autopilot, and it no longer felt like a dreaded chore when I was checking my emails or logging in to my TradingView account. It lost a lot of traction because I stopped updating it, so people think it's not useful anymore (even though it does its job as well as it did a few years ago). Its revenue declined in the past years. But I don't care. I'm happy again.</p>
<p>What's next for this project? I guess I will keep running it until I decide that including it in my monthly accounting is not worth the effort, which is when I will shut it down. But for now, the $200 I get every month with almost no work is a nice passive income.</p>
<h2 id="things-i-ve-learned" tabindex="-1">Things I've learned </h2>
<h3 id="don-t-let-a-side-project-burn-you-out" tabindex="-1">Don't let a side project burn you out </h3>
<p>The dreaded truth that most programmers learn the hard way is that releasing a product is just the beginning. Once it's out there, you have to maintain it: fix bugs, implement new features, deal with disputes or frauds, and answer a LOT of emails (often from curious window shoppers who never convert to paying customers).</p>
<p>This maintenance is easier if you have more products and you do support in bulk. Or if your project can replace your full-time job and maintaining it is the only thing you do during the day. But if you do this on top of your regular job, it's a terrible time sink. You need to set some boundaries. Otherwise, working on your project will take all your available time.</p>
<p>Working on a side project is much more fun if you're also one of its users and genuinely want to keep improving it. It's incredibly smooth if you love your project, and the perspective of working on it full-time sounds like a dream job. And accordingly, it's much harder to support a project when you move on to doing something else and you're no longer interested in maintaining it, but you still have existing customers you need to keep happy.</p>
<p>If your side project is not a source of genuine joy and you have other priorities, it's important to set some boundaries. I've decided to focus my support only on the paying customers. I also stopped adding new features and told myself that unless my scripts break, I'm not touching the code. Even though I still had a list of additional improvements I wanted to make one day, I deleted that list. I already had paying customers, which means people find value in what I've built. Sure, I can add new features to attract new customers. But that means even more coding and maintenance for a <em>chance</em> to attract new customers.</p>
<h3 id="use-a-merchant-of-record" tabindex="-1">Use a merchant of record </h3>
<p>If you're planning to sell products globally, consider using a "merchant of record" like Gumroad or Paddle. This way, you won't have to figure out how much tax to charge for each country (basically, you only sell to Gumroad, and they resell your product to the final customer). Figuring out taxes was the last thing I wanted to do when selling my products. I went with Gumroad, which - at the time of writing - charges a 10% fee, plus around 3% of PayPal/Stripe fees on top of that.</p>
<p>There might be cheaper options, so do your research before choosing one. Once you get some recurring payments rolling in, you can't easily move your existing customers to a different company. When the Gumroad fees increased throughout the years, I always thought that migrating to another service was too much of a hassle, so that's why I'm still using Gumroad.</p>
<h3 id="selling-stuff-to-customers-is-hard" tabindex="-1">Selling stuff to customers is hard </h3>
<p>I had this one guy where the conversation looked like this:</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Hey, amazing script, I rated it 5 stars! Can you implement the take profit levels for me?</li>
<li>I'm sorry, but I can't. The original methodology doesn't specify exact take profit levels. It also doesn't make sense because take profits should be manually determined, for example, based on support or resistance levels visible on the chart. Different people will use different take profit levels based on their risk appetite.</li>
<li>Ok, but can you please put them for me? I follow this [insert some YouTube crypto day-trader], and he uses [some very specific take profit levels]. I would like the script to draw them for me.</li>
<li>Look, I can't do this. Those take profit levels are very specific to your trading system. They won't work for most other people, but they will slow down the script for everyone.</li>
<li>Ok, bro.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>He cancelled his subscription a few days later and lowered his 5-star review to 2 stars.</p>
<p>Business-to-consumer (B2C) is difficult (not that business-to-business is much easier - it has a different set of challenges). But this doesn't mean that B2C is not worth pursuing. There are many people who did great selling to customers. One of the most well-known is Pieter Levels (<a href="https://twitter.com/levelsio">@levelsio</a>), creator of projects like NomadList, RemoteOK, and, more recently, PhotoAI. According to his Twitter profile stats, he makes an astonishing $200k Monthly Recurring Revenue from his projects. But B2C, while easier to get into than establishing a relationship with a company in a B2B business model, means that you will need many more customers to have the revenue levels that B2B can bring. And more customers mean more work.</p>
<h3 id="be-nice" tabindex="-1">Be nice </h3>
<p>Try to be nice to people. I mean, being nice to people in general will make the world a better place. But when dealing with customers, never assume they do something in bad faith. Sure, some folks will try to take advantage of you. But many "problems" are just a matter of misunderstanding. People will request a chargeback because they think it's the only way to get a refund for a subscription they forgot about. If someone asks me for a refund, then no matter what's the reason, I give them their money back and wish them good luck with their investments. Fighting disgruntled customers over $20 is not a good way to spend time.</p>
<p>If you're nice to people, they are more likely to use and recommend your products. One of the reasons why Amazon got so popular early in the days was because of its extraordinary customer support. Ten years ago, when my Kindle stopped turning on (which might or might not have been caused by accidental yet excessive force applied to it), Amazon's support said "no worries, we'll send you a new one for free". Someone would send me a free product instead of requesting to prove that it broke by itself? This blew me away! Especially since I was living in Poland, where the strong post-communism roots mean that if a seller is not mean to you, then this already counts as them being nice.😉</p>
<p>So, I wanted to do the same with my customers. I tried to accommodate their needs, write detailed explanations to their questions, and generously issue refunds or even discounts when requested. When someone complained that something didn't work because it didn't work the way <em>they</em> wanted, I suggested alternative scripts and offered refunds. And that paid back. I received a lot of nice messages from customers, and even though I was getting tired of supporting my project, getting positive feedback from time to time kept me going for all those years.</p>
<hr>
<p>And that's the story of my first side project. It was fun at the beginning, frustrating in the middle, and now it's mostly a passive income that will eventually dry up.</p>
<p>Was it worth the money? Not really. Spending equal time working for a client would probably earn me more. But the experience I gained from this side project will be invaluable when I build the next one.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for the next article, where I describe the technical setup I used to automate most of this project.</p>
<hr>
<section>
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>It was always the crypto or forex crowd that was asking for weird stuff. <a href="#fnref1">↩︎</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
</div>
</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Handwriter.ttf – Handwriting Synthesis with Harfbuzz WASM (130 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/hsfzxjy/handwriter.ttf</link>
            <guid>41307815</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 07:47:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/hsfzxjy/handwriter.ttf">https://github.com/hsfzxjy/handwriter.ttf</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41307815">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">handwriter.ttf</h2><a id="user-content-handwriterttf" aria-label="Permalink: handwriter.ttf" href="#handwriterttf"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><b> ✍️ A Handwriting Synthesizer by abusing <a href="https://github.com/harfbuzz/harfbuzz/blob/main/docs/wasm-shaper.md">Harfbuzz WASM Shaper</a>.</b></p>
<p dir="auto"><b> 🔗 Check more stupid stuff at <a href="https://github.com/hsfzxjy/Harfbuzz-WASM-Fantasy">Harfbuzz-WASM-Fantasy</a>.</b></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Introduction</h2><a id="user-content-introduction" aria-label="Permalink: Introduction" href="#introduction"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">During the hype of <a href="https://github.com/fuglede/llama.ttf">llama.ttf</a> months ago, I was speculating the potential of WASM shaper for even crazier purpose, one that fitter to a font shaper's duty -- to synthesize font at runtime. This project as proof-of-concept implements a synthesizer that generates and rasterizes handwriting-style font, backed by <a href="https://github.com/X-rayLaser/pytorch-handwriting-synthesis-toolkit/blob/main/my-app/synthesis_network_52.onnx">a super-lightweight RNN model</a> (~14MiB).</p>
<p dir="auto">The project must be run in an application linked against <code>libharfbuzz</code> with the experimental WASM shaper enabled, which does not hold for any products currently. Considering that it's not easy to build such a library from scratch, I prebuilt a Docker image <code>hsfzxjy/harfbuzz-wasm-handwriting-synthesis</code> which contains both the TTF file and a modified version of <code>gedit</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Usage</strong> You may try out this project with the following steps:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>On a Linux system with X11 (WSL is fine), run <code>GIT_LFS_SKIP_SMUDGE=1 git clone https://github.com/hsfzxjy/handwriter.ttf</code>;</li>
<li>In directory <code>handwriter.ttf</code>, run <code>make run</code>, which fetches Docker image <code>hsfzxjy/harfbuzz-wasm-handwriting-synthesis</code> and starts the <code>gedit</code> application inside;</li>
<li>Start typing in the pop-up gedit window. Each line should prefixed by <code>#</code> to trigger the shaper, e.g., typing <code>#hello world</code>.</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto">Some strokes might look cursed due to the limitation of the model, appending a space <code> </code> should make it better.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://youtu.be/IjObhagKnY8" rel="nofollow">Watch on Youtube</a></p>
<details open="">
  <summary>
    
    <span aria-label="Video description 2024-08-21.13-31-43.mp4">2024-08-21.13-31-43.mp4</span>
    <span></span>
  </summary>

  <video src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/4702188/359766819-ea5e1b61-fcb3-4950-8621-af2499c96493.mp4?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjQyNjg5MDEsIm5iZiI6MTcyNDI2ODYwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii80NzAyMTg4LzM1OTc2NjgxOS1lYTVlMWI2MS1mY2IzLTQ5NTAtODYyMS1hZjI0OTljOTY0OTMubXA0P1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI0MDgyMSUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNDA4MjFUMTkzMDAxWiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9ZmYwZTA1MDk2YTUxMzgxOTBhYzI4MGEzOTYwNmEwN2I5Y2IwYTkyMmYxYzNhODY1ZjlhMTg0OGI4YjAzY2ZhNSZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QmYWN0b3JfaWQ9MCZrZXlfaWQ9MCZyZXBvX2lkPTAifQ.wvq21KOznWurQlCk3GY50gmZU9ijuDH2CwrFCoGLAzI" data-canonical-src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/4702188/359766819-ea5e1b61-fcb3-4950-8621-af2499c96493.mp4?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjQyNjg5MDEsIm5iZiI6MTcyNDI2ODYwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii80NzAyMTg4LzM1OTc2NjgxOS1lYTVlMWI2MS1mY2IzLTQ5NTAtODYyMS1hZjI0OTljOTY0OTMubXA0P1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI0MDgyMSUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNDA4MjFUMTkzMDAxWiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9ZmYwZTA1MDk2YTUxMzgxOTBhYzI4MGEzOTYwNmEwN2I5Y2IwYTkyMmYxYzNhODY1ZjlhMTg0OGI4YjAzY2ZhNSZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QmYWN0b3JfaWQ9MCZrZXlfaWQ9MCZyZXBvX2lkPTAifQ.wvq21KOznWurQlCk3GY50gmZU9ijuDH2CwrFCoGLAzI" controls="controls" muted="muted">

  </video>
</details>

<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Technical Details</h2><a id="user-content-technical-details" aria-label="Permalink: Technical Details" href="#technical-details"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Algorithm</h3><a id="user-content-algorithm" aria-label="Permalink: Algorithm" href="#algorithm"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The project follows Alex Graves's paper <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1308.0850" rel="nofollow">Generating Sequences With Recurrent Neural Networks</a> and adopts an RNN model for handwriting synthesis. Shortly, the generation process undergoes multiple steps to produce a series of strokes given the input text. At each step the model predicts the next pen position given the current one. Afterwards, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bresenham%27s_line_algorithm" rel="nofollow">Bresenham's line algorithm</a> rasterizes the strokes into pixel locations, which are set as the offsets for an array of "black-box" glyphs.</p>
<p dir="auto">I've tried some more recent models, but their runtime latency is unaffordable.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Performance</h3><a id="user-content-performance" aria-label="Permalink: Performance" href="#performance"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The final TTF file is highly optimized, reaching the speed of 0.08 sec/character on Intel Ultra 125H. Each text run's generation time is proportional to the text length.</p>
<p dir="auto">The journey to perfect optimization is interesting, which I shall introduce in blog posts later. Some important notes:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Use <a href="https://github.com/robertknight/rten">rten</a> as inference backend to make sure neural ops are executed with SIMD instructions.</li>
<li>Pre-transpose the RHS of MatMul to make them col-major, improving the performance by ~15%.</li>
<li>To run modules containing SIMD instructions, <a href="https://github.com/bytecodealliance/wasm-micro-runtime">wasm-micro-runtime</a> should be compiled with <code>-DWAMR_BUILD_SIMD=1</code> and WASM file must be AOT-compiled by <a href="https://github.com/bytecodealliance/wasm-micro-runtime/tree/main/wamr-compiler">wamrc</a>.</li>
<li>Enable specific optimization in <code>wamrc</code> (<code>--opt-level=3</code>, <code>--enable-segue=i32.load,f32.load,i32.store,f32.store</code> and <code>--enable-tail-call</code>), improving the performance by ~55%.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This project is licensed under the <a href="https://github.com/hsfzxjy/handwriter.ttf/blob/master/LICENSE">Apache 2.0 LICENSE</a>. Copyright (c) 2024 hsfzxjy.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PS4 Emulator for Windows,Linux,macOS (329 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4</link>
            <guid>41307195</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 05:58:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4">https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41307195">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text">
<div dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">
  <br>
  <a href="https://shadps4.net/" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/raw/main/.github/shadps4.png" width="220"></a>
  <br>
  <b>shadPS4</b>
  <br>
</h2><a id="user-content---------shadps4--" aria-label="Permalink: shadPS4" href="#--------shadps4--"></a></div>

<p dir="auto">
  <a href="https://shadps4.net/" rel="nofollow">
  <img src="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/raw/main/documents/Screenshots/Sonic%20Mania.png" width="400">
  <img src="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/raw/main/documents/Screenshots/Bloodborne.png" width="400">
  <img src="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/raw/main/documents/Screenshots/Undertale.png" width="400">
  <img src="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/raw/main/documents/Screenshots/We%20are%20DOOMED.png" width="400">
</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">shadPS4</h2><a id="user-content-shadps4" aria-label="Permalink: shadPS4" href="#shadps4"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">shadPS4 is an early <strong>PlayStation 4</strong> emulator for <strong>Windows</strong>, <strong>Linux</strong> and <strong>macOS</strong> written in C++</p>
<p dir="auto">If you encounter problems or have doubts, do not hesitate to look at the <a href="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/blob/main/documents/Quickstart/Quickstart.md"><strong>Quickstart</strong></a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">To verify that a game works, you can look at <a href="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadps4-game-compatibility"><strong>shadPS4 Game Compatibility</strong></a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">To discuss shadPS4 development or suggest ideas, join the <a href="https://discord.gg/MyZRaBngxA" rel="nofollow"><strong>Discord server</strong></a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">To get the latest news, go to our <a href="https://x.com/shadps4" rel="nofollow"><strong>X (twitter)</strong></a> or our <a href="https://shadps4.net/" rel="nofollow"><strong>website</strong></a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Status</h2><a id="user-content-status" aria-label="Permalink: Status" href="#status"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">In development, small games are working like <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AAHoNzhHyCU" rel="nofollow"><strong>Sonic Mania</strong></a>, <a href="https://youtu.be/5zIvdy65Ro4" rel="nofollow"><strong>Undertale</strong></a>, <a href="https://youtu.be/b9xzhLBdESE" rel="nofollow"><strong>Dysmantle</strong></a> and others...</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Why</h2><a id="user-content-why" aria-label="Permalink: Why" href="#why"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The project started as a fun project. Due to limited free time, it will probably take a while before shadPS4 is able to run anything decent, but we're trying to make small, regular commits.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Build</h2><a id="user-content-build" aria-label="Permalink: Build" href="#build"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Windows</h2><a id="user-content-windows" aria-label="Permalink: Windows" href="#windows"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Check the build instructions for <a href="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/blob/main/documents/building-windows.md"><strong>Windows</strong></a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Linux</h2><a id="user-content-linux" aria-label="Permalink: Linux" href="#linux"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Check the build instructions for <a href="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/blob/main/documents/building-linux.md"><strong>Linux</strong></a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Build status</h2><a id="user-content-build-status" aria-label="Permalink: Build status" href="#build-status"></a></p>
<details>
<summary><b>Windows</b></summary>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Windows</th>
<th>Build status</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Windows SDL Build</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/actions/workflows/windows.yml"><img src="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/actions/workflows/windows.yml/badge.svg" alt="Windows-sdl"></a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Windows Qt Build</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/actions/workflows/windows-qt.yml"><img src="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/actions/workflows/windows-qt.yml/badge.svg" alt="Windows-qt"></a></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
</details>
<details>
<summary><b>Linux</b></summary>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Linux</th>
<th>Build status</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Linux SDL Build</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/actions/workflows/linux.yml"><img src="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/actions/workflows/linux.yml/badge.svg" alt="Linux-sdl"></a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Linux Qt Build</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/actions/workflows/linux-qt.yml"><img src="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/actions/workflows/linux-qt.yml/badge.svg" alt="Linux-qt"></a></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
</details>
<details>
<summary><b>macOS</b></summary>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>macOS</th>
<th>Build status</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>macOS SDL Build</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/actions/workflows/macos.yml"><img src="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/actions/workflows/macos.yml/badge.svg" alt="macOS-sdl"></a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>macOS Qt Build</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/actions/workflows/macos-qt.yml"><img src="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/actions/workflows/macos-qt.yml/badge.svg" alt="macOS-qt"></a></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
</details>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Keyboard Mapping</h2><a id="user-content-keyboard-mapping" aria-label="Permalink: Keyboard Mapping" href="#keyboard-mapping"></a></p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Controller button</th>
<th>Keyboard</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>LEFT AXIS UP</td>
<td>W</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LEFT AXIS DOWN</td>
<td>S</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LEFT AXIS LEFT</td>
<td>A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LEFT AXIS RIGHT</td>
<td>D</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RIGHT AXIS UP</td>
<td>I</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RIGHT AXIS DOWN</td>
<td>K</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RIGHT AXIS LEFT</td>
<td>J</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RIGHT AXIS RIGHT</td>
<td>L</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TRIANGLE</td>
<td>Numpad 8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CIRCLE</td>
<td>Numpad 6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CROSS</td>
<td>Numpad 2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SQUARE</td>
<td>Numpad 4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PAD UP</td>
<td>UP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PAD DOWN</td>
<td>DOWN</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PAD LEFT</td>
<td>LEFT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PAD RIGHT</td>
<td>RIGHT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>OPTIONS</td>
<td>RETURN</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TOUCH PAD</td>
<td>SPACE</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>L1</td>
<td>Q</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>R1</td>
<td>U</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>L2</td>
<td>E</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>R2</td>
<td>O</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>L3</td>
<td>X</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>R3</td>
<td>M</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Main team</h2><a id="user-content-main-team" aria-label="Permalink: Main team" href="#main-team"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/georgemoralis"><strong>georgemoralis</strong></a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/raphaelthegreat"><strong>raphaelthegreat</strong></a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/psucien"><strong>psucien</strong></a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/skmp"><strong>skmp</strong></a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/wheremyfoodat"><strong>wheremyfoodat</strong></a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/raziel1000"><strong>raziel1000</strong></a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Logo is done by <a href="https://github.com/Xphalnos"><strong>Xphalnos</strong></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing</h2><a id="user-content-contributing" aria-label="Permalink: Contributing" href="#contributing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If you want to contribute, please look the <a href="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/blob/main/CONTRIBUTING.md"><strong>CONTRIBUTING.md</strong></a> file.</p>
<p dir="auto">Open a PR and we'll check it :)</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributors</h2><a id="user-content-contributors" aria-label="Permalink: Contributors" href="#contributors"></a></p>
<a href="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/graphs/contributors">
  <img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/150710c902fab9adbc4861eb4357e0b2e5845c19adaa91641e8f98875b513ee7/68747470733a2f2f636f6e747269622e726f636b732f696d6167653f7265706f3d736861647073342d656d752f73686164505334266d61783d3135" data-canonical-src="https://contrib.rocks/image?repo=shadps4-emu/shadPS4&amp;max=15">
</a>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Sister Projects</h2><a id="user-content-sister-projects" aria-label="Permalink: Sister Projects" href="#sister-projects"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/wheremyfoodat/Panda3DS"><strong>Panda3DS</strong></a>: A multiplatform 3DS emulator from our co-author wheremyfoodat.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/hydra-emu/hydra"><strong>hydra</strong></a>: A multisystem, multiplatform emulator (chip-8, GB, NES, N64) from Paris.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/blob/main/LICENSE"><strong>GPL-2.0 license</strong></a></li>
</ul>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Australian government approves AAPowerLink project to export solar to Singapore (138 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.pv-tech.org/australian-government-approves-aapowerlink-project-to-export-solar-to-singapore/</link>
            <guid>41307166</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 05:52:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.pv-tech.org/australian-government-approves-aapowerlink-project-to-export-solar-to-singapore/">https://www.pv-tech.org/australian-government-approves-aapowerlink-project-to-export-solar-to-singapore/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41307166">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-id="510fd0e" data-element_type="section" data-settings="{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_list&quot;:[{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;_id&quot;:&quot;24f6673&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_tablet&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_mobile&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_speed&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;%&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:50,&quot;sizes&quot;:[]},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_type&quot;:&quot;scroll&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_fx_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_z_index&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size&quot;:&quot;auto&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_animation_prop&quot;:&quot;transform&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_on&quot;:[&quot;desktop&quot;,&quot;tablet&quot;]}]}" data-elementor-type="single-post" data-elementor-id="1361" data-elementor-post-type="elementor_library">
<div data-id="67e85e8" data-element_type="column">






<div data-id="613081b" data-element_type="section" data-settings="{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_list&quot;:[{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;_id&quot;:&quot;8251f3b&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_tablet&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_mobile&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_speed&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;%&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:50,&quot;sizes&quot;:[]},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_type&quot;:&quot;scroll&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_fx_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_z_index&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size&quot;:&quot;auto&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_animation_prop&quot;:&quot;transform&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_on&quot;:[&quot;desktop&quot;,&quot;tablet&quot;]}]}">
<div data-id="9be277d" data-element_type="column">
<div data-id="54bad55" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="heading.default">
<p>
<h2>Latest</h2> </p>
</div>
<div data-id="14335fb" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="jet-listing-grid.default" data-settings="{&quot;columns&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-elementor-type="jet-listing-items" data-elementor-id="30276" data-elementor-post-type="jet-engine" data-post-id="141984" data-queried-id="141921|WP_Post" data-nav="{&quot;enabled&quot;:false,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;more_el&quot;:null,&quot;query&quot;:[],&quot;widget_settings&quot;:{&quot;lisitng_id&quot;:30276,&quot;posts_num&quot;:10,&quot;columns&quot;:1,&quot;columns_tablet&quot;:1,&quot;columns_mobile&quot;:1,&quot;is_archive_template&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;post_status&quot;:[&quot;publish&quot;],&quot;use_random_posts_num&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;max_posts_num&quot;:9,&quot;not_found_message&quot;:&quot;No data was found&quot;,&quot;is_masonry&quot;:false,&quot;equal_columns_height&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;use_load_more&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;load_more_id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;load_more_type&quot;:&quot;click&quot;,&quot;load_more_offset&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:0,&quot;sizes&quot;:[]},&quot;use_custom_post_types&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;custom_post_types&quot;:[],&quot;hide_widget_if&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;carousel_enabled&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;slides_to_scroll&quot;:&quot;1&quot;,&quot;arrows&quot;:&quot;true&quot;,&quot;arrow_icon&quot;:&quot;fa fa-angle-left&quot;,&quot;dots&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;autoplay&quot;:&quot;true&quot;,&quot;pause_on_hover&quot;:&quot;true&quot;,&quot;autoplay_speed&quot;:5000,&quot;infinite&quot;:&quot;true&quot;,&quot;center_mode&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;effect&quot;:&quot;slide&quot;,&quot;speed&quot;:500,&quot;inject_alternative_items&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;injection_items&quot;:[],&quot;scroll_slider_enabled&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;scroll_slider_on&quot;:[&quot;desktop&quot;,&quot;tablet&quot;,&quot;mobile&quot;],&quot;custom_query&quot;:false,&quot;custom_query_id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;_element_id&quot;:&quot;&quot;}}" data-page="1" data-pages="2305" data-listing-source="posts" data-listing-id="30276" data-query-id="">
<p><span>Features</span><span>,</span> <span>Editors' Blog</span><span>,</span> <span>Interviews</span><span>,</span> <span>Long Reads</span></p> </div>
</div>
<div data-id="efbb6f5" data-element_type="column">

<div data-id="c85d89e" data-element_type="widget" id="post-content" data-widget_type="theme-post-content.default">
<div>
<figure><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="614" src="https://www.pv-tech.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Sun-Cable-1024x614.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.pv-tech.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Sun-Cable-1024x614.jpg 1024w, https://www.pv-tech.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Sun-Cable-300x180.jpg 300w, https://www.pv-tech.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Sun-Cable-768x461.jpg 768w, https://www.pv-tech.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Sun-Cable.jpg 1279w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption>A model of the solar panels initially planned to be built for the Sun Cable project. Credit: Sun Cable</figcaption></figure>
<p>Renewable energy developer Sun Cable has secured approval from the Australian government for the Australian element of its <a href="https://www.pv-tech.org/australian-power-export-project-will-unlock-solars-potential-developer-sun-cable-says/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Australia-Asia Power Link (AAPowerLink)</a> interconnector.</p>
<p>In a statement made today (21 August), Sun Cable said the project has been assessed and approved by Tanya Plibersek, the Commonwealth’s minister for the Environment and Water, under the Environment Protection and Biodiversity Conservation Act (EPBC). This approval follows the previous one <a href="https://www.pv-tech.org/suncable-lands-approval-for-aapowerlink-project-set-to-unlock-20gw-of-solar-in-australia/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">secured from the Northern Territory government and NT Environment Protection Authority</a> for the interconnector last month.</p></div><div><div><p>This article requires <span>Premium Subscription</span><span>Basic (FREE) Subscription</span></p>
<h2>Unlock unlimited access for 12 whole months of distinctive global analysis</h2>
<h4>Photovoltaics International is now included.</h4>

<ul>
<li><span></span><span>Regular insight and analysis of the industry’s biggest developments</span></li>
<li><span></span><span>In-depth interviews with the industry’s leading figures</span></li>
<li><span></span><span>Unlimited digital access to the PV Tech Power journal catalogue</span></li>
<li><span></span><span>Unlimited digital access to the Photovoltaics International journal catalogue</span></li>
<li><span></span><span>Access to more than 1,000 technical papers</span></li>
<li><span></span><span>Discounts on Solar Media’s portfolio of events, in-person and virtual</span></li>
</ul>

<div data-wk-call-status-user="guest">
<h3>Or continue reading this article for free</h3>

</div></div><div>
<p>Sun Cable said that the approval “signifies the Australian government’s confidence that Sun Cable can deliver this nationally important project within appropriate approval conditions”.</p>
<p>Cameron Garnsworthy, Sun Cable Australia’s managing director, said the approval was a landmark moment in the project’s journey. The company will now focus on achieving a final investment decision by 2027.</p>
<p>“Today’s announcement is a vote of confidence in the project and Sun Cable itself as responsible stewards of the local Northern Territory environment. Sun Cable will now focus its efforts on the next stage of planning to advance the project towards a final investment decision targeted by 2027,” Garnsworthy said.</p>
<p>It is worth noting that the project <a href="https://www.pv-tech.org/multi-gigawatt-australian-solar-storage-sun-cable-project-clears-further-hurdle/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">received approval from Indonesian authorities in 2021</a>.</p>
<h2 id="h-aapowerlink-to-couple-large-scale-solar-and-energy-storage-deployment"><strong>AAPowerLink to couple large-scale solar and energy storage deployment</strong></h2>
<p>The AAPowerLink project is set to deploy between 17GW and 20GW of solar capacity and between 36.42GWh and 42GWh of energy storage to connect Australia’s Northern Territory with Singapore via 4,300km of subsea cable and supply power to the territory’s capital, Darwin, and the surrounding region.</p>
<p>The project aims to deliver up to 4GW of green electricity to Darwin’s green industrial customers over two stages of development. 900MW will be provided in stage one and approximately 3GW in stage two. 1.75GW will also be supplied to customers in Singapore.</p>
<p>Once complete, it will be capable of delivering up to 15% of Singapore’s total electricity needs via a 2GW high-voltage direct current (HVDC) subsea cable, Sun Cable said. Electricity supply is anticipated to commence in the early 2030s.</p>
<p>Sun Cable will also invest further in communities in the Northern Territory, Singapore, and Indonesia to help progress the project to the next stage. Indeed, the organisation is continuing negotiations of Indigenous Land Use Agreements (ILUAs) with Traditional Owners across the project footprint in the Northern Territory.</p>
<p>In Singapore, Sun Cable is working with the Singapore Energy Market Authority on the conditional approval application for the project’s subsea cable interconnector component. Sun Cable is also engaging with the Indonesian government on regulatory and permitting matters to prove that the subsea route includes knowledge and hydrographic data sharing.</p>
<p>Speaking exclusively to&nbsp;<em>PV Tech </em>in 2022, Andrew Barton, project director of the Australia-Asia PowerLink, said the project would&nbsp;“<a href="https://www.pv-tech.org/australian-power-export-project-will-unlock-solars-potential-developer-sun-cable-says/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">use proven technologies that have been deployed at projects around the world</a>” before adding that it “will unlock solar’s potential”.</p>
</div></div> </div>

<div data-id="83d4478" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="jet-listing-grid.default" data-settings="{&quot;columns&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-elementor-type="jet-listing-items" data-elementor-id="29814" data-elementor-post-type="jet-engine" data-post-id="94270" data-queried-id="141921|WP_Post" data-nav="{&quot;enabled&quot;:false,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;more_el&quot;:null,&quot;query&quot;:[],&quot;widget_settings&quot;:{&quot;lisitng_id&quot;:29814,&quot;posts_num&quot;:6,&quot;columns&quot;:1,&quot;columns_tablet&quot;:1,&quot;columns_mobile&quot;:1,&quot;is_archive_template&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;post_status&quot;:[&quot;publish&quot;],&quot;use_random_posts_num&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;max_posts_num&quot;:9,&quot;not_found_message&quot;:&quot;No data was found&quot;,&quot;is_masonry&quot;:false,&quot;equal_columns_height&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;use_load_more&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;load_more_id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;load_more_type&quot;:&quot;click&quot;,&quot;load_more_offset&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:0,&quot;sizes&quot;:[]},&quot;use_custom_post_types&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;custom_post_types&quot;:[],&quot;hide_widget_if&quot;:&quot;empty_query&quot;,&quot;carousel_enabled&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;slides_to_scroll&quot;:&quot;1&quot;,&quot;arrows&quot;:&quot;true&quot;,&quot;arrow_icon&quot;:&quot;fa fa-angle-left&quot;,&quot;dots&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;autoplay&quot;:&quot;true&quot;,&quot;pause_on_hover&quot;:&quot;true&quot;,&quot;autoplay_speed&quot;:5000,&quot;infinite&quot;:&quot;true&quot;,&quot;center_mode&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;effect&quot;:&quot;slide&quot;,&quot;speed&quot;:500,&quot;inject_alternative_items&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;injection_items&quot;:[],&quot;scroll_slider_enabled&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;scroll_slider_on&quot;:[&quot;desktop&quot;,&quot;tablet&quot;,&quot;mobile&quot;],&quot;custom_query&quot;:false,&quot;custom_query_id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;_element_id&quot;:&quot;&quot;}}" data-page="1" data-pages="1" data-listing-source="posts" data-listing-id="29814" data-query-id=""><p>PV Tech has been running PV ModuleTech Conferences since 2017. PV ModuleTech USA, on 17-18 June 2025, will be our fourth PV ModulelTech conference dedicated to the U.S. utility scale solar sector. The event will gather the key stakeholders from solar developers, solar asset owners and investors, PV manufacturing, policy-making and and all interested downstream channels and third-party entities. The goal is simple: to map out the PV module supply channels to the U.S. out to 2026 and beyond.</p></div>

</div>
</div>

<div data-id="bca8549" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="heading.default">
<p>
<h2>Read Next</h2> </p>
</div>
<div data-queried-id="141921|WP_Post" data-nav="{&quot;enabled&quot;:false,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;more_el&quot;:null,&quot;query&quot;:[],&quot;widget_settings&quot;:{&quot;lisitng_id&quot;:5281,&quot;posts_num&quot;:6,&quot;columns&quot;:1,&quot;columns_tablet&quot;:1,&quot;columns_mobile&quot;:1,&quot;is_archive_template&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;post_status&quot;:[&quot;publish&quot;],&quot;use_random_posts_num&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;max_posts_num&quot;:9,&quot;not_found_message&quot;:&quot;No data was found&quot;,&quot;is_masonry&quot;:false,&quot;equal_columns_height&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;use_load_more&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;load_more_id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;load_more_type&quot;:&quot;click&quot;,&quot;load_more_offset&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:0,&quot;sizes&quot;:[]},&quot;use_custom_post_types&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;custom_post_types&quot;:[],&quot;hide_widget_if&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;carousel_enabled&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;slides_to_scroll&quot;:&quot;1&quot;,&quot;arrows&quot;:&quot;true&quot;,&quot;arrow_icon&quot;:&quot;fa fa-angle-left&quot;,&quot;dots&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;autoplay&quot;:&quot;true&quot;,&quot;pause_on_hover&quot;:&quot;true&quot;,&quot;autoplay_speed&quot;:5000,&quot;infinite&quot;:&quot;true&quot;,&quot;center_mode&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;effect&quot;:&quot;slide&quot;,&quot;speed&quot;:500,&quot;inject_alternative_items&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;injection_items&quot;:[],&quot;scroll_slider_enabled&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;scroll_slider_on&quot;:[&quot;desktop&quot;,&quot;tablet&quot;,&quot;mobile&quot;],&quot;custom_query&quot;:false,&quot;custom_query_id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;_element_id&quot;:&quot;&quot;}}" data-page="1" data-pages="616" data-listing-source="posts" data-listing-id="5281" data-query-id="" data-id="9bad793" data-element_type="widget" data-settings="{&quot;columns&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-widget_type="jet-listing-grid.default"><div data-id="cf529fb" data-element_type="section" data-settings="{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_list&quot;:[{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;_id&quot;:&quot;291e5ab&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_tablet&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_mobile&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_speed&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;%&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:50,&quot;sizes&quot;:[]},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_type&quot;:&quot;scroll&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_fx_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_z_index&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size&quot;:&quot;auto&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_animation_prop&quot;:&quot;transform&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_on&quot;:[&quot;desktop&quot;,&quot;tablet&quot;]}]}" data-elementor-type="jet-listing-items" data-elementor-id="5281" data-elementor-post-type="jet-engine" data-post-id="141951">
<div data-id="fff57e3" data-element_type="column" data-widget_type="image.default">
<p><a href="https://www.pv-tech.org/fraunhofer-csp-to-protect-european-solar-ip/">
<img src="https://www.pv-tech.org/wp-content/uploads/elementor/thumbs/03_Eroeffnung-Module-TEC_Copyright_Fraunhofer-ISE_Foto_Myriam-Kaiser-qohdxxzh13lucjqk9wzlpyjoh5fekdkoxc7z03d7k8.jpg" title="03_Eroeffnung-Module-TEC_Copyright_Fraunhofer-ISE_Foto_Myriam-Kaiser" alt="The new facility was opened earlier this week at an ex-solar manufacturing facility. Image: Fraunhofer ISE" loading="lazy"> </a>
</p>
</div>
<div data-id="2dd429f" data-element_type="column" data-widget_type="jet-listing-dynamic-field.default"><p>A new research project, announced this week, will seek to bolster intellectual property (IP) and patent protection for European companies developing new solar cell technologies.</p></div>
</div><div data-id="cf529fb" data-element_type="section" data-settings="{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_list&quot;:[{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;_id&quot;:&quot;291e5ab&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_tablet&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_mobile&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_speed&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;%&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:50,&quot;sizes&quot;:[]},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_type&quot;:&quot;scroll&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_fx_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_z_index&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size&quot;:&quot;auto&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_animation_prop&quot;:&quot;transform&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_on&quot;:[&quot;desktop&quot;,&quot;tablet&quot;]}]}" data-elementor-type="jet-listing-items" data-elementor-id="5281" data-elementor-post-type="jet-engine" data-post-id="141927">
<div data-id="fff57e3" data-element_type="column" data-widget_type="image.default">
<p><a href="https://www.pv-tech.org/australia-transgrid-to-investigate-three-inland-renewable-energy-zones-in-western-nsw/">
<img src="https://www.pv-tech.org/wp-content/uploads/elementor/thumbs/transgrid-550kv-line_vni-west-768x401-1-qohe0cgmhuw80o8y8yda3cq34ll68j3zx88n5jszns.jpg" title="transgrid-550kv-line_vni-west-768×401" alt="transgrid-550kv-line_vni-west-768x401" loading="lazy"> </a>
</p>
</div>
<div data-id="2dd429f" data-element_type="column" data-widget_type="jet-listing-dynamic-field.default"><p>Australian transmission system operator Transgrid&nbsp;has signalled in a new report that remote inland renewable energy zones (REZ) could provide an additional renewable energy source, such as solar PV, in the mid-2030s.</p></div>
</div><div data-id="cf529fb" data-element_type="section" data-settings="{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_list&quot;:[{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;_id&quot;:&quot;291e5ab&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_tablet&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_mobile&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_speed&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;%&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:50,&quot;sizes&quot;:[]},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_type&quot;:&quot;scroll&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_fx_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_z_index&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size&quot;:&quot;auto&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_animation_prop&quot;:&quot;transform&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_on&quot;:[&quot;desktop&quot;,&quot;tablet&quot;]}]}" data-elementor-type="jet-listing-items" data-elementor-id="5281" data-elementor-post-type="jet-engine" data-post-id="141913">
<div data-id="fff57e3" data-element_type="column" data-widget_type="image.default">
<p><a href="https://www.pv-tech.org/us-manufacturers-seek-retroactive-tariffs-on-solar-import-surge/">
<img src="https://www.pv-tech.org/wp-content/uploads/elementor/thumbs/Solar_cells_from_Thalheim_Image_Meyer_Burger-qohe4njztisj8bzo3beq0rl556cqil7pijvrc7f154.jpg" title="Solar_cells_from_Thalheim_Image_Meyer_Burger" alt="Meyer Burger is further expanding its Germany plant to reach 1.4GW module production for 2023. Image: Meyer Burger." loading="lazy"> </a>
</p>
</div>
<div data-id="2dd429f" data-element_type="column" data-widget_type="jet-listing-dynamic-field.default"><p>The American Alliance for Solar Manufacturing Trade Committee claims that imports from Vietnam and Thailand have "accelerated" since April's AD/CVD petition, and has alleged Critical Circumstances.</p></div>
</div><div data-id="cf529fb" data-element_type="section" data-settings="{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_list&quot;:[{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;_id&quot;:&quot;291e5ab&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_tablet&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_mobile&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_speed&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;%&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:50,&quot;sizes&quot;:[]},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_type&quot;:&quot;scroll&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_fx_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_z_index&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size&quot;:&quot;auto&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_animation_prop&quot;:&quot;transform&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_on&quot;:[&quot;desktop&quot;,&quot;tablet&quot;]}]}" data-elementor-type="jet-listing-items" data-elementor-id="5281" data-elementor-post-type="jet-engine" data-post-id="141869">
<div data-id="fff57e3" data-element_type="column" data-widget_type="image.default">
<p><a href="https://www.pv-tech.org/engie-reaches-financial-close-for-250mw-solar-project-in-victoria-australia/">
<img src="https://www.pv-tech.org/wp-content/uploads/elementor/thumbs/Engie-India-qohfqqyw7wbisplruxfmmltqvi0f94uh63f44va2ko.jpg" title="ENGIE-Solar-Power-Plant-Gujarat" alt="An 200MW project in the Indian state of Gujarat. Image: Engie." loading="lazy"> </a>
</p>
</div>
<div data-id="2dd429f" data-element_type="column" data-widget_type="jet-listing-dynamic-field.default"><p>Utility giant Engie’s Australian division has reached financial close on its 250MW Goorambat East Solar Farm project in northern Victoria.</p></div>
</div><div data-id="cf529fb" data-element_type="section" data-settings="{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_list&quot;:[{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;_id&quot;:&quot;291e5ab&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_tablet&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_mobile&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_speed&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;%&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:50,&quot;sizes&quot;:[]},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_type&quot;:&quot;scroll&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_fx_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_z_index&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size&quot;:&quot;auto&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_animation_prop&quot;:&quot;transform&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_on&quot;:[&quot;desktop&quot;,&quot;tablet&quot;]}]}" data-elementor-type="jet-listing-items" data-elementor-id="5281" data-elementor-post-type="jet-engine" data-post-id="141848">
<div data-id="fff57e3" data-element_type="column" data-widget_type="image.default">
<p><a href="https://www.pv-tech.org/bloombergnef-australia-needs-290gw-solar-pv-and-wind-by-2050-for-net-zero/">
<img src="https://www.pv-tech.org/wp-content/uploads/elementor/thumbs/degrussa_australia_neoen_1gw_solar_for_web-qohejdoyw2y94elm3okb31t46hrr3vobjftm09kzns.jpg" title="degrussa_australia_neoen_1gw_solar_for_web" alt="A solar PV module array in Australia deployed in a Neoen-managed project." loading="lazy"> </a>
</p>
</div>
<div data-id="2dd429f" data-element_type="column" data-widget_type="jet-listing-dynamic-field.default"><p>Analyst firm BloombergNEF has cautioned that Australia requires around A$2.4 trillion (US$1.6 trillion) investment to reach net zero, with solar PV and wind installations to reach 290GW by 2050.</p></div>
</div><div data-id="cf529fb" data-element_type="section" data-settings="{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_list&quot;:[{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;_id&quot;:&quot;291e5ab&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_tablet&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_mobile&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_speed&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;%&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:50,&quot;sizes&quot;:[]},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_type&quot;:&quot;scroll&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_fx_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_z_index&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size&quot;:&quot;auto&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_animation_prop&quot;:&quot;transform&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_on&quot;:[&quot;desktop&quot;,&quot;tablet&quot;]}]}" data-elementor-type="jet-listing-items" data-elementor-id="5281" data-elementor-post-type="jet-engine" data-post-id="141860">
<div data-id="fff57e3" data-element_type="column" data-widget_type="image.default">
<p><a href="https://www.pv-tech.org/origin-energy-cancels-204mw-of-solar-pv-projects-in-australia-due-to-unfavourable-conditions/">
<img src="https://www.pv-tech.org/wp-content/uploads/elementor/thumbs/photo_tall_solar-farm-768x432-Image-Origin-qsvfdirpbo60qdvgsszxuyaq5lsuvi3ko4geepc614.jpg" title="photo_tall_solar-farm-768×432.jpg Image Origin" alt="Origin Energy's largest solar PV project is its proposed 900MW Yarrabee site in New South Wales. Image: Origin Energy." loading="lazy"> </a>
</p>
</div>
<div data-id="2dd429f" data-element_type="column" data-widget_type="jet-listing-dynamic-field.default"><p>Australia's Origin Energy has cancelled its 130MW Morgan and 74MW Carisbrook solar PV projects due to “unfavourable conditions”.</p></div>
</div></div>

</div>
<div data-id="e11b756" data-element_type="column">
<div data-id="18951a6" data-element_type="section" data-widget_type="heading.default" data-settings="{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_list&quot;:[{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;_id&quot;:&quot;1c41e47&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_tablet&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_mobile&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_speed&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;%&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:50,&quot;sizes&quot;:[]},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_type&quot;:&quot;scroll&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_fx_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_z_index&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size&quot;:&quot;auto&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_animation_prop&quot;:&quot;transform&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_on&quot;:[&quot;desktop&quot;,&quot;tablet&quot;]}]}">
<p>
<h2>Subscribe to Newsletter</h2> </p>
</div>

<div data-id="6271dee" data-element_type="section" data-widget_type="heading.default" data-settings="{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_list&quot;:[{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;_id&quot;:&quot;1c41e47&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_tablet&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_mobile&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_speed&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;%&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:50,&quot;sizes&quot;:[]},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_type&quot;:&quot;scroll&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_fx_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_z_index&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size&quot;:&quot;auto&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_animation_prop&quot;:&quot;transform&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_on&quot;:[&quot;desktop&quot;,&quot;tablet&quot;]}]}">
<p>
<h2>Most Read</h2> </p>
</div>

<div data-id="785e82d" data-element_type="section" data-settings="{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_list&quot;:[{&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;_id&quot;:&quot;1c41e47&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_tablet&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_image_mobile&quot;:{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:&quot;&quot;},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_speed&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;%&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:50,&quot;sizes&quot;:[]},&quot;jet_parallax_layout_type&quot;:&quot;scroll&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_fx_direction&quot;:null,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_z_index&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_x_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y&quot;:50,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_y_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size&quot;:&quot;auto&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_tablet&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_bg_size_mobile&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_animation_prop&quot;:&quot;transform&quot;,&quot;jet_parallax_layout_on&quot;:[&quot;desktop&quot;,&quot;tablet&quot;]}]}">
<div data-id="3788039" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="heading.default">
<p>
<h2>Upcoming Events</h2> </p>
</div>
<div data-id="7924a19" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="jet-listing-grid.default" data-settings="{&quot;columns&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-elementor-type="jet-listing-items" data-elementor-id="5885" data-elementor-post-type="jet-engine" data-post-id="141637" data-queried-id="141921|WP_Post" data-nav="{&quot;enabled&quot;:false,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;more_el&quot;:null,&quot;query&quot;:[],&quot;widget_settings&quot;:{&quot;lisitng_id&quot;:5885,&quot;posts_num&quot;:5,&quot;columns&quot;:1,&quot;columns_tablet&quot;:1,&quot;columns_mobile&quot;:1,&quot;is_archive_template&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;post_status&quot;:[&quot;publish&quot;],&quot;use_random_posts_num&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;max_posts_num&quot;:9,&quot;not_found_message&quot;:&quot;No data was found&quot;,&quot;is_masonry&quot;:false,&quot;equal_columns_height&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;use_load_more&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;load_more_id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;load_more_type&quot;:&quot;click&quot;,&quot;load_more_offset&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;size&quot;:0,&quot;sizes&quot;:[]},&quot;use_custom_post_types&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;custom_post_types&quot;:[],&quot;hide_widget_if&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;carousel_enabled&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;slides_to_scroll&quot;:&quot;1&quot;,&quot;arrows&quot;:&quot;true&quot;,&quot;arrow_icon&quot;:&quot;fa fa-angle-left&quot;,&quot;dots&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;autoplay&quot;:&quot;true&quot;,&quot;pause_on_hover&quot;:&quot;true&quot;,&quot;autoplay_speed&quot;:5000,&quot;infinite&quot;:&quot;true&quot;,&quot;center_mode&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;effect&quot;:&quot;slide&quot;,&quot;speed&quot;:500,&quot;inject_alternative_items&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;injection_items&quot;:[],&quot;scroll_slider_enabled&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;scroll_slider_on&quot;:[&quot;desktop&quot;,&quot;tablet&quot;,&quot;mobile&quot;],&quot;custom_query&quot;:false,&quot;custom_query_id&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;_element_id&quot;:&quot;&quot;}}" data-page="1" data-pages="6" data-listing-source="posts" data-listing-id="5885" data-query-id=""><p>Huntington Place Detroit, MI</p></div>
</div>

</div>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Being on The Semantic Web is easy, and, frankly, well worth the bother (416 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://csvbase.com/blog/13</link>
            <guid>41307011</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 05:22:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://csvbase.com/blog/13">https://csvbase.com/blog/13</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41307011">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <!-- Being on The Semantic Web is easy, and, frankly, well worth the bother -->
<p>The Semantic Web is the <em>old</em> Web 3.0.  Before "Web 3.0" meant
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web3">crypto-whatnot</a>, it meant
"machine-readable websites".</p>
<p>I thought this concept hadn't really gone anywhere but it turns out that The
Semantic Web (best read in a very deep voice) is now very widely adopted.</p>
<p>The Semantic Web is so widely adopted in fact that I think it's fair to say
that we're already on Web 3.0.  It's not the future, it's the present.  I
suppose that means the blockchain crowd will need to argue their case to get
all that crypto stuff into the next major version.  Good luck to them,
<a href="https://calpaterson.com/blockchain.html">really</a>.</p>
<p>If Web 3.0 is already here, where is it, then?  Mostly, it's hidden in the
markup.</p>
<h2>JSON-LD for a <code>BlogPosting</code></h2>
<p>A worked example might help.  Here's how Semantic Web metadata is added for a
blog post, for example the one you're reading now.</p>
<p>You include a special <code>&lt;script type="application/ld+json"&gt;</code> element inside the
<code>&lt;head&gt;</code> of an HTML page.  Inside that element is some
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JSON-LD">JSON-LD</a>.</p>
<p>JSON-LD (JSON "for Linked Data") is the leading format for encoding Sematic Web
metadata.  It's <em>just JSON</em>, really.  There are schemas that lay out the
"types" you can use to describe the stuff on your page.  For a blog post, the
right type is <a href="https://schema.org/BlogPosting">BlogPosting</a>.  Here's a (mildly
truncated) example of a <code>BlogPosting</code>:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>{</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>"@context"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"https://schema.org"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>"@type"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"BlogPosting"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>"headline"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"From Shell to Excel - with a little bit of HTTPS"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>"url"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"https://csvbase.com/blog/10"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>"description"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"Write once, read everywhere"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>"author"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span>
<span>        </span><span>"@type"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"Person"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>        </span><span>"name"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"Cal Paterson"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>        </span><span>"email"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"cal@calpaterson.com"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>        </span><span>"url"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"https://calpaterson.com/about.html"</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>},</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>"image"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"https://csvbase.com/blog-static/excel.png"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>"datePublished"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"2024-08-12"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>"dateCreated"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"2024-08-12"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>"dateModified"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"2024-08-12"</span><span></span>
<span>}</span><span></span>
</pre></div>
<p>It's all pretty self expanatory:</p>
<ul>
<li>
keys starting with <code>@</code> are metadata (meta-metadata?)<ul>
<li><code>@context</code> is the namespace.  Usually it's schema.org</li>
<li><code>@type</code> is the class, <code>BlogPosting</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>the other keys are just things <a href="https://schema.org/BlogPosting">allowed in the <code>BlogPosting</code> type</a></li>
<li>the values of keys can be other types, eg <code>Person</code> for the <code>author</code> key in
this case</li>
</ul>
<h2>What's in it for me?</h2>
<p>Does anyone actually read all that stuff?  Yes, a lot of bots are out there
parsing JSON-LD metadata.  Nice things tend to happen to blog posts that
include the Semantic Web metadata:</p>
<p>Social media sites (Twitter/Discord/Facebook/WhatsApp/etc) start showing that
<strong>nice link preview</strong> with an image for your links.  Link previews usually look
a bit like this:</p>
<p><a href="https://fosstodon.org/@calpaterson/112953513297517114">
<img alt="screenshot of a mastodon link preview" src="https://csvbase.com/blog-static/mastodon-link-preview.png">
</a></p><p>People do click on these link previews more often than on "bare urls", which is
something that drives adoption of the Semantic Web.</p>
<p>Search engine web crawlers also make use of this metadata both to <strong>crawl a bit
more intelligently</strong> but also to show <strong>more information in search results</strong>
(for example: who the author is).  Again, people are more likely to click on
such "enhanced" search results, which is another thing that has driven
adoption.</p>
<p>Automated link aggregators <strong>show your post</strong> to their users.  I once woke to
many many nice emails from people who normally wouldn't have read my blog.
After being initially puzzled I eventually learned that Android had decided,
all on its own, to show my blog post on its on-phone news screen.  All possible
because of Semantic Web metadata.</p>
<p>Many other, usually nice, things can happen.  The joy of The Semantic Web is
that it is <em>permissionless</em> as well as "vendor-neutral".  Anyone can take the
metadata and run with it.  That's cool, that's the web spirit.</p>
<h2>Is it really hard?</h2>
<p>Not really, no.  A bit of JSON, containing things already on the page anyway,
just laid out in a way for computers to read.  If people can write <a href="https://infrequently.org/series/reckoning/">enormous
frontend apps</a> I think they can
figure out JSON-LD.</p>
<h2>JSON-LD for other stuff</h2>
<p>There are other JSON-LD "types" than just <code>BlogPosting</code>.  A lot more.  Some
well supported ones:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://schema.org/Event"><code>Event</code></a></li>
<li><a href="https://schema.org/LocalBusiness"><code>LocalBusiness</code></a></li>
<li><a href="https://schema.org/JobPosting"><code>JobPosting</code></a></li>
<li><a href="https://schema.org/Product"><code>Product</code></a></li>
<li><a href="https://schema.org/Recipe"><code>Recipe</code></a></li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://csvbase.com/about">csvbase</a> is a website full of table data
(tinder-for-dogs style pitch: "Github, for data tables"), so it uses the
<a href="https://schema.org/Dataset"><code>Dataset</code></a> type to describe each of tables
(<a href="https://csvbase.com/meripaterson/stock-exchanges">for example</a>) in a
machine-readable way.  Here's an example of the JSON-LD csvbase includes on
each table page:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>{</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>"@context"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span></span>
<span>        </span><span>"https://schema.org"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>        </span><span>{</span><span></span>
<span>            </span><span>"csvw"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"https://www.w3.org/ns/csvw#"</span><span></span>
<span>        </span><span>}</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>],</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>"@type"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"Dataset"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>"name"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"stock-exchanges"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>"url"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"https://csvbase.com/meripaterson/stock-exchanges"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>"isAccessibleForFree"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>true</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>"distribution"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span></span>
<span>        </span><span>{</span><span></span>
<span>            </span><span>"@type"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"DataDownload"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>            </span><span>"contentUrl"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"https://csvbase.com/meripaterson/stock-exchanges.csv"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>            </span><span>"encodingFormat"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"text/csv"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>            </span><span>"contentSize"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"16222"</span><span></span>
<span>        </span><span>},</span><span></span>
<span>        </span><span>{</span><span></span>
<span>            </span><span>"@type"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"DataDownload"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>            </span><span>"contentUrl"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"https://csvbase.com/meripaterson/stock-exchanges.parquet"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>            </span><span>"encodingFormat"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"application/parquet"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>            </span><span>"contentSize"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"10751"</span><span></span>
<span>        </span><span>},</span><span></span>
<span>        </span><span>{</span><span></span>
<span>            </span><span>"@type"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"DataDownload"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>            </span><span>"contentUrl"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"https://csvbase.com/meripaterson/stock-exchanges.xlsx"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>            </span><span>"encodingFormat"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>            </span><span>"contentSize"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"15500"</span><span></span>
<span>        </span><span>},</span><span></span>
<span>        </span><span>{</span><span></span>
<span>            </span><span>"@type"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"DataDownload"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>            </span><span>"contentUrl"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"https://csvbase.com/meripaterson/stock-exchanges.jsonl"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>            </span><span>"encodingFormat"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"application/x-jsonlines"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>            </span><span>"contentSize"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"38627"</span><span></span>
<span>        </span><span>}</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>],</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>"dateCreated"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"2022-04-25T13:43:24.746075+01:00"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>"dateModified"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"2023-04-02T20:27:33.255648+01:00"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>"maintainer"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span>
<span>        </span><span>"@type"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"Person"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>        </span><span>"name"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"meripaterson"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>        </span><span>"url"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"https://csvbase.com/meripaterson"</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>},</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>"description"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"The world's stock exchanges..."</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>"mainEntity"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span>
<span>        </span><span>"@type"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"csvw:Table"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>        </span><span>"csvw:tableSchema"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span>
<span>            </span><span>"csvw:columns"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span></span>
<span>                </span><span>{</span><span></span>
<span>                    </span><span>"csvw:name"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"csvbase_row_id"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>                    </span><span>"csvw:datatype"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"integer"</span><span></span>
<span>                </span><span>},</span><span></span>
<span>                </span><span>{</span><span></span>
<span>                    </span><span>"csvw:name"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"Continent"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>                    </span><span>"csvw:datatype"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"string"</span><span></span>
<span>                </span><span>},</span><span></span>
<span>                </span><span>{</span><span></span>
<span>                    </span><span>"csvw:name"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"Country"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>                    </span><span>"csvw:datatype"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"string"</span><span></span>
<span>                </span><span>},</span><span></span>
<span>                </span><span>{</span><span></span>
<span>                    </span><span>"csvw:name"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"Name"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>                    </span><span>"csvw:datatype"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"string"</span><span></span>
<span>                </span><span>},</span><span></span>
<span>                </span><span>{</span><span></span>
<span>                    </span><span>"csvw:name"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"MIC"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>                    </span><span>"csvw:datatype"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"string"</span><span></span>
<span>                </span><span>},</span><span></span>
<span>                </span><span>{</span><span></span>
<span>                    </span><span>"csvw:name"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"Last changed"</span><span>,</span><span></span>
<span>                    </span><span>"csvw:datatype"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"date"</span><span></span>
<span>                </span><span>}</span><span></span>
<span>            </span><span>]</span><span></span>
<span>        </span><span>}</span><span></span>
<span>    </span><span>}</span><span></span>
<span>}</span><span></span>
</pre></div>
<p>There's a lot of stuff in there.  From basic things like the last time the
data was changed (personal bugbear of mine) to some more complicated stuff.</p>
<p>Several <code>DataDownload</code> objects are included, to help bots understand where
people can go to just download the data, without having the visit the site.
Hopefully that's nice for people viewing tables through data-specific search
engines, like Google's <a href="https://datasetsearch.research.google.com/">Dataset
Search</a>.  Save them a click.</p>
<p>There's also some more advanced stuff.  The JSON-LD document actually includes
<em>two</em> schemas.  One is the ordinary "schema.org" one (<code>Dataset</code>) but the other
is a schema called <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/tabular-data-primer/">"CSV on the
Web"</a>, which allows you to describe
the columns and the types of those columns --- as well as other more detailed
data I haven't sorted out yet.</p>
<p>I haven't direct evidence that anyone is yet doing much with these CSVW types
yet but Google do <a href="https://developers.google.com/search/docs/appearance/structured-data/dataset#tabular">document that they read
it</a>
so perhaps there is more to come on this in the future from them.  And of
course, there is nothing to stop anyone else using it.  It's all standardised
stuff.</p>
<h2>It is really necessary?  "Doesn't AI solve this?"</h2>
<p>It would of course be possible to sic
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ChatGPT">Chatty-Jeeps</a> on the raw markup and
have it extract all of this stuff automatically.  But there are some good
reasons why not.</p>
<p>The first is that large language models (LLMs) routinely get stuff wrong.
If you want bots to get it right, provide the metadata to ensure that they do.</p>
<p>The second is that requiring an LLM to read the web is throughly
disproportionate and exclusionary.  Everyone parsing the web would need to be
paying for pricy GPU time to parse out the meaning of the web.  It would feel
bizarre if "technological progress" meant that fat GPUs were required for
computers to read web pages.</p>
<h2>Alternatives</h2>
<p>JSON-LD is not the only form of Semantic Web metadata, though it's increasingly
got the most momentum.  There is some overlap between the various schemes and
many bots will parse whatever they can find.  Here's a quick overview of the
alternatives:</p>
<p>At some point Facebook created the <a href="https://ogp.me/">Open Graph Protocol</a>, a
standard based on using special <code>&lt;meta&gt;</code> tags.  It's widely used and supported
but only covers the kinds of things you might post to Facebook: articles,
songs, videos, etc.  What zoomers call "Content".</p>
<p>There is also <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microdata_(HTML)">"microdata"</a>.
It's very simple but I think quite hard to parse out.  Bits of it are well
supported.</p>
<p>Twitter published a spec for <a href="https://developer.x.com/en/docs/twitter-for-websites/cards/overview/abouts-cards">"Twitter
Cards"</a>
which pretty much just lets you describe how you want your thing to appear on
Twitter.  It's pretty limited - but Twitter is popular - so this is widely
implemented.</p>
<p>Before JSON-LD there was a nest of other, more XMLy, standards emitted by the
various web steering groups.  These actually have very, very deep support in
many places (for example in library and archival systems) but on the open web
they are not a goer.</p>
<h2>Boring technology</h2>
<p>It is surprising how low-key The Semantic Web is.  Thousands of sites are
already setting this metadata.  The Semantic Web is already widespread, it's
just that there was no moment of victory.</p>
<hr>
<p>If you think csvbase is cool:</p>
<ul>
<li>become <a href="https://csvbase.com/billing/pricing">a supporter</a></li>
<li>star <a href="https://github.com/calpaterson/csvbase">the github repo</a></li>
<li>follow me <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@calpaterson">on mastodon</a></li>
<li><a href="mailto:cal@calpaterson.com">write me an email</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2>Notes</h2>
<p>Googlers, if you're reading this, JSON-LD could have the same level of public
awareness as RSS if only you could release, and then shut down, some kind of
app or service in this area.  Please, for the good of the web: consider it.</p>
<p>Semantic Web information on websites is a bit of a "living document".  You tend
publish something, then have a look to see what people have parsed (or failed
to parse) it and then you try to improve it a bit.  If you have ideas for ways
that csvbase can improve its metadata, please <a href="https://github.com/calpaterson/csvbase/issues">open an issue on the github
repo</a>.</p>

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Calling All Hackers (509 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://phrack.org/issues/71/17.html#article</link>
            <guid>41306128</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 02:08:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://phrack.org/issues/71/17.html#article">https://phrack.org/issues/71/17.html#article</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41306128">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://phrack.org/issues/71/17.html#article: Error: unable to verify the first certificate]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ares Industries – Building low-cost cruise missiles (132 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ycombinator.com/launches/Ler-ares-industries-building-low-cost-cruise-missiles</link>
            <guid>41305736</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 01:04:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/launches/Ler-ares-industries-building-low-cost-cruise-missiles">https://www.ycombinator.com/launches/Ler-ares-industries-building-low-cost-cruise-missiles</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41305736">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/media/?type=post&amp;id=83257&amp;key=user_uploads/1087615/dea0086b-00cd-4322-b4ba-d670c17a85f8"></p>
<p>Hello, we’re Alex and Devan, and we’re building the low-cost cruise missiles the United States needs!</p>
<p><strong>What we’re building</strong></p>
<p>Ares is building a new class of anti-ship cruise missiles. We are going to deliver the capabilities that the DoD wants in a form factor that’s 10x smaller and 10x cheaper.</p>
<p>Our missiles will be compatible with existing launch platforms, deliver smaller payloads at high subsonic speeds, and take out ships hundreds of miles away. We’re focusing on ground and ship-launched variants to start but will expand into air-launched versions, as well as versions with extended ranges and different payloads.</p>
<p><strong>Why we’re doing this</strong></p>
<p>A war with China in the Taiwan Strait would look nothing like what we've seen in Ukraine or the Middle East. Wargames within DoD and military experts are in agreement that the most useful weapons in such a conflict would be long range anti-ship weapons or cruise missiles.</p>
<p>The United States is not adequately prepared. In a potential conflict, our stockpiles will run out in weeks, and we currently don’t have the industrial capacity to build at a rate that could win a war, much less deter China. Higher-ups in DoD are waking up to the problem, and generals such as Major General Cameron Holt and officials such as Chairman of the House Select Committee on China Mike Gallagher have echoed this sentiment.</p>
<p>Recent conflicts in the Middle East and Ukraine have shown that our weapons are too large, too expensive for the wars of today. Existing anti-ship cruise missiles are low-volume, multi-million dollar, 3,000 lb behemoths meant to take out large cruisers and destroyers.</p>
<p>But Chinese shipbuilding capability is far superior to ours, and we can’t make enough anti-ship missiles to counter. In addition, huge missiles aren’t needed to take out the smaller corvettes and frigates that make up the People’s Liberation Army Navy. And $3M missiles make even less sense to take out swarms of $200k small, unmanned surface vessels.</p>
<p>The DoD needs smaller, less expensive cruise missiles, and lots of them! But no one has delivered on that promise yet.</p>
<p><strong>How we know how to do this</strong></p>
<p>Both of us have worked at multiple defense and munitions startups.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/devanplantamura">Devan</a> is an Army Psychological Operations and Navy combat veteran and has deep experience in operations and business development at well-funded defense startups.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/alextseng1/">Alex</a> was the first engineering hire at an earlier missile startup, built autonomous systems at Rivian and Stanford, and worked on turbojets at CSULB.</p>
<p><strong>Where we’re at now</strong></p>
<p>We spent the summer building multiple prototypes and flight-testing them in the Mojave. In 11 weeks, we went from starting the company to flight testing with our own design. We are on track to deliver early working missile systems to our first customers by mid-2025.</p>
<p>We believe our vision for anti-ship cruise missiles can help fill the munitions gap that the US faces. At Ares, we would never wish for a war to occur. But by helping to rebuild our defense industrial base, we can make sure the United States is prepared to stop a conflict and save countless lives.</p>
<p><strong>Our Ask</strong></p>
<p>We are looking for extremely talented aerospace engineers to help bring our prototypes to fruition. If you know any aerodynamics, propulsion, or GNC engineers who are interested in building something incredibly cool and want to make a positive difference in geopolitics, please send them our way!</p>
<p><img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/media/?type=post&amp;id=83257&amp;key=user_uploads/1087615/44076741-cbe9-4762-af9b-84e96db0c32e"></p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[US judge throws out FTC's ban on non-compete agreements (310 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ft.com/content/56770a82-3c3f-4739-9895-e2f97b6202b4</link>
            <guid>41305591</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 00:38:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/56770a82-3c3f-4739-9895-e2f97b6202b4">https://www.ft.com/content/56770a82-3c3f-4739-9895-e2f97b6202b4</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41305591">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><a data-trackable="a11y-skip-to-help" href="https://www.ft.com/accessibility">Accessibility help</a><a data-trackable="a11y-skip-to-navigation" href="#site-navigation">Skip to navigation</a><a data-trackable="a11y-skip-to-content" href="#site-content">Skip to content</a><a data-trackable="a11y-skip-to-footer" href="#site-footer">Skip to footer</a></p><div id="barrier-page">
<div data-component="electionsHeader" data-component-unique-name="CHE-Print"><h2>US Elections 2024</h2></div>
<div data-component="electionsHeroOffer" data-component-unique-name="CHE-Print"><div><div data-o-grid-colspan="12 XL6"><p><span></span><span></span><span></span><span>Register to unlock this article</span><span></span></p></div><section data-o-grid-colspan="12 XL6"><h2><blockquote>US judge throws out FTC’s ban on non-compete agreements</blockquote></h2></section><div data-o-grid-colspan="12 XL5"><p><h2><strong>Continue reading and get the indispensable US Election Countdown newsletter for free.</strong></h2></p></div></div><p><img src="https://www.ft.com/__origami/service/image/v2/images/raw///financial-times-financial-times.cdn.zephr.com/assets/images/us_election_2024/hero_banner_us_election_2024_usa_flag.png?source=next-barrier-page" data-color_variant="usa" alt="US presidential election 2024"></p></div>
<div data-component="electionsFeatures" data-component-unique-name="CHE-Print"><h2>We've got you covered</h2><div><div><p><img alt="" src="https://www.ft.com/__origami/service/image/v2/images/raw///financial-times-financial-times.cdn.zephr.com/assets/images/us_election_2024/feature_countdown.png?source=next-barrier-page"></p><h3>US Election Countdown newsletter</h3><p>Register for your free guide to the twists and turns of the 2024 presidential election.</p></div><div><p><img alt="" src="https://www.ft.com/__origami/service/image/v2/images/raw///financial-times-financial-times.cdn.zephr.com/assets/images/us_election_2024/feature_hub_2024.png?source=next-barrier-page"></p><h3>US Presidential Election 2024 hub</h3><p>Discover the FT's latest news, analysis and polling data from this year's election.</p></div><div><p><img alt="" src="https://www.ft.com/__origami/service/image/v2/images/raw///financial-times-financial-times.cdn.zephr.com/assets/images/us_election_2024/feature_expert_opinion_analysis.png?source=next-barrier-page"></p><h3>Democracy 2024</h3><p>See the bigger picture. Discover FT perspectives, analysis, opinion and film on the political year ahead.</p></div><div><p><img alt="" src="https://www.ft.com/__origami/service/image/v2/images/raw///financial-times-financial-times.cdn.zephr.com/assets/images/us_election_2024/feature_democracy_2024.png?source=next-barrier-page"></p><h3>Expert Opinion &amp; Analysis</h3><p>Decode the impact on business, politics and beyond with updates from our worldwide network of 700+ journalists. </p></div></div><div><div><p><img alt="" src="https://www.ft.com/__origami/service/image/v2/images/raw///financial-times-financial-times.cdn.zephr.com/assets/images/us_election_2024/feature_countdown.png?source=next-barrier-page"></p><h3>US Election Countdown newsletter</h3><p>Register for your free guide to the twists and turns of the 2024 presidential election.</p></div><div><p><img alt="" src="https://www.ft.com/__origami/service/image/v2/images/raw///financial-times-financial-times.cdn.zephr.com/assets/images/us_election_2024/feature_hub_2024.png?source=next-barrier-page"></p><h3>US Presidential Election 2024 hub</h3><p>Discover the FT's latest news, analysis and polling data from this year's election.</p></div><div><p><img alt="" src="https://www.ft.com/__origami/service/image/v2/images/raw///financial-times-financial-times.cdn.zephr.com/assets/images/us_election_2024/feature_expert_opinion_analysis.png?source=next-barrier-page"></p><h3>Democracy 2024</h3><p>See the bigger picture. Discover FT perspectives, analysis, opinion and film on the political year ahead.</p></div><div><p><img alt="" src="https://www.ft.com/__origami/service/image/v2/images/raw///financial-times-financial-times.cdn.zephr.com/assets/images/us_election_2024/feature_democracy_2024.png?source=next-barrier-page"></p><h3>Expert Opinion &amp; Analysis</h3><p>Decode the impact on business, politics and beyond with updates from our worldwide network of 700+ journalists. </p></div></div></div>
<div id="recommendedOffers-CHE-Print" data-component="recommendedOffers" data-component-unique-name="CHE-Print"><p><h2 data-tiles="" data-o-grid-colspan="12">Explore more offers.</h2></p><div data-o-grid-colspan="12"><div data-offer-type="epaper" data-o-grid-colspan="12" data-tile=""><div><p><img src="https://www.ft.com/__origami/service/image/v2/images/raw///financial-times-financial-times.cdn.zephr.com/assets/icons/primary_product_icon_epaper.svg?source=next-barrier-page&amp;format=svg" alt=""></p><p data-offer-type="epaper"><h3>Standard Digital</h3><h3>Weekend Print + Standard Digital</h3></p></div><div><p><span><span>was</span></span><span><span>now</span> CHF36 </span><span>per 3 months</span></p></div><p>The new FT Digital Edition: today’s FT, cover to cover on any device. This subscription does not include access to ft.com or the FT App.</p></div><div data-offer-type="standard" data-o-grid-colspan="12" data-tile=""><div><p><img src="https://www.ft.com/__origami/service/image/v2/images/raw///financial-times-financial-times.cdn.zephr.com/assets/icons/primary_product_icon_standard.svg?source=next-barrier-page&amp;format=svg" alt=""></p><p data-offer-type="standard"><h3>Standard Digital</h3><h3>Weekend Print + Standard Digital</h3></p></div><p>Essential digital access to quality FT journalism on any device. Pay a year upfront and save 20%.</p></div><div data-offer-type="premium" data-o-grid-colspan="12" data-tile=""><div><p><img src="https://www.ft.com/__origami/service/image/v2/images/raw///financial-times-financial-times.cdn.zephr.com/assets/icons/primary_product_icon_premium.svg?source=next-barrier-page&amp;format=svg" alt=""></p><p data-offer-type="premium"><h3>Standard Digital</h3><h3>Weekend Print + Standard Digital</h3></p></div><p>Complete digital access to quality FT journalism with expert analysis from industry leaders. Pay a year upfront and save 20%.</p></div></div></div>
<div data-component="subscriptionOptionsV2" data-component-unique-name="UK-Print"><h2>Explore our full range of subscriptions.</h2></div>
<div data-component="whyFT" data-component-unique-name="default"><div><h2>Why the FT?</h2><p>See why over a million readers pay to read the Financial Times.</p></div><p><a href="https://subs.ft.com/whytheft">Find out why</a></p></div>


</div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>