<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 17:30:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The shadows lurking in the equations (148 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://gods.art/articles/equation_shadows.html</link>
            <guid>45823141</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 14:21:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://gods.art/articles/equation_shadows.html">https://gods.art/articles/equation_shadows.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45823141">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
						<!-- START CONTENT -->

                        

                        <p>
                        <img src="https://gods.art/images/articles/slashdot_comparison.gif" alt="Slash Dot Equation comparison">
                        For all the history of computational mathematical visualization, <span>graphing equations has been done in binary mode</span> - where graphs show only where an equation is EXACTLY equal. But when you only see in black-and-white, some things are invisible. For all this time, lurking beneath the error == 0 surface, <span>mathematical shadows</span> have been lurking in the equations.</p>
                        <p>FuzzyGraph, on the other hand, <span>visualizes equations in Non-Binary mode</span> - showing not only where an equation are exactly equal, but also where the equation <span>nearly equal</span> and where the equation is <span>far from equal</span> (where the error is high). Sometimes, these high error areas form clear visual shadow-like features.</p>

                        <p>Let's look at some examples...</p>

                        <h2 id="slashdot">Example 1: Slash Dot Equation</h2>

                        <p>Here is the "Slash Dot" Equation ( \( \frac{y}{x^2+y^2} = \frac{x+1}{x^2+y^2} \)) as both a conventional and fuzzy graph...</p>

                        

                        <p>Note the giant black hole that is present in the Fuzzy/Non-Binary graph, but invisible in conventional/Binary graphing. This "black hole" feature represents a region of high error in the equation.</p>


                        <h2 id="quasar">Example 2: Quasar Equation</h2>

                        <p>Let's look at another example: \(y = \frac{x}{x^2 + y^2} \)

                        </p>

                        <p>Notice that the <span>black hole eye-looking features are COMPLETELY INVISIBLE</span> in the conventional/binary mode of graphing.</p>


                        <h2 id="simple-black-hole">Example 3: Simple Star and Black Hole</h2>

                        <p>To get a better idea of what these black hole things are, let's look at a simpler example. First let's look at the opposite of a black hole - a simple star/particle example: \( x^2 + y^2 = 0 \). For this equation, there is only 1 solution: (0, 0). So if you <a href="https://www.desmos.com/calculator/tkzm7jpjaf">graph this in a conventional graphing app</a>, it will only show a single dot at (0, 0). But in FuzzyGraph, it looks like a fuzzy particle or something.</p>

                        

                        <p>But now, let's invert this to get the "Black Hole Equation": \( \frac{1}{x^2+y^2} = 0 \)...</p>

                        

                        <p>In this case, there is absolutely nothing to show on a conventional graph, as there are actual solutions to this equations. However, there is still a mathematical <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Topography">topography</a> which can be visualized (as can be seen in the fuzzy graph).</p>


                        <h2 id="shadow-lines">Example 4: Shadow Line</h2>

                        <p>Not all of the <span>Shadows</span> are like black holes.</p>
                        
                        <p>In this example, let's start by combining 2 lines together: \(y=x\) and \(y=-x\).</p>
                        <p>We can visually add 2 equations together by refactoring them so they are both equal to 0, and then multiplying the two refactored equations together. \(y=x\) can be changed to \(y-x=0\), and \(y=-x\) can be refactored to \(y+x=0\).</p>
                        <p>We can then combine 2 into a single equation these like this: \( (y-x) \times (y+x) = 0 \)</p>

                        

                        <p>And now, <span>let's invert one of the equations using division</span>: \( \frac{x-y}{x+y} = 0 \)</p>

                        

                        <p>So as you can see, the line that was inverted (under the division line) is now a <span>Shadow Line</span>. And this seems like a more "correct" way to visualize this than as the conventional graph shows it (which is indistinguishable from the simpler equation, \(y-x=0\)).</p>

                        <h2 id="phi-equation">Example 5: Phi Equation</h2>

                        <p>This equation works almost exactly as the previous. And like before, let's start with multiplication to combine 2 equations (in this case, a circle and a vertical line equation): \( x \times (x^2+y^2-1) = 0 \). </p>

                        

                        <p>But now, let's <span>invert the circle by using division</span>, which makes the equation: \( \frac{x}{x^2+y^2-1} = 0 \).</p>

                        

                        <p>Note that the <span>Shadow Circle is invisible in the conventional graph</span>. In fact, the conventional graph looks identical to a conventional graph of the \(x=0\) equation (as if the denominator was not there).</p>


                        <h2 id="underwater-islands">Example 6: Underwater Islands</h2>

                        <p>In all of these previous examples, the "shadows" have represented areas of high error. But in this last example, we'll see some hidden details that represent areas of low error - areas that are <span>nearly</span> solutions to the equation.</p>

                        <p>Consider the equation, \( y=4 sin(x)+ sin(2.7y) \), as both a conventional graph and a fuzzy graph:</p>

                        

                        <p>Note the floating dots in the fuzzy graph version that are not there in the conventional/binary graph. These are like underwater islands - underwater mountains that are just below the surface of the water (or in this case, the \( error == 0 \) surface). These hidden islands represent area that are near-solutions to the equation (which are only visible in FuzzyGraph).</p>
                        <p>Their presense hints that we can tweak the equation slightly to cause them to burst above the surface of the water (which should also make them visible in conventional graphs).</p>
                        <p>So let's change the equation from: <br>  \( y=4 sin(x)+ sin(2.7y) \) to: <br> \( y=4 sin(x)+ sin(2.8y) \)...</p>

                        

                        <p>And as you can see, <span>those previously-hidden islands are now visible in the conventional graph</span>. </p><p>So Fuzzy/non-binary graphing can help us see features of the mathematical topography that are completely invisible with conventional/binary.</p>

						<hr>
                        <p>Date published: 2025-11-05</p>
                        <!-- END CONTENT -->

                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Radiant Computer (103 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://radiant.computer</link>
            <guid>45822559</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 13:22:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://radiant.computer">https://radiant.computer</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45822559">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
  <p>Radiant Computer</p>

  <p>
    <img src="https://radiant.computer/assets/images/cabin.12.webp">
  </p>

  <p>Radiant's purpose is to explore what personal computing could be when
  designed from <a href="https://radiant.computer/principles">first principles</a>.</p><p>

  We believe the current trajectory of personal computing is leading us to a
  less free world, and that only a new computing movement rooted in human
  dignity, creation and autonomy can change its course.

  </p><hr>

  <p><strong>Radiant is a computer reimagined from the ground up</strong>, a
  <em>clean-slate</em> design free from the historical baggage that plagues
  modern systems, and free from Big Tech's influence.</p>

  <p>It's a computer designed to help you learn, create, play, and explore.
  It's a space to focus, free from distractions. A return to the simple
  joy of computing: just you and your ideas.</p>

  <p><strong>Computers today are designed around engagement</strong> and
  surveillance business models rather than user needs. App stores are filled
  with adware. Operating systems prioritize data collection over user agency.
  Social media algorithms optimize for addiction. Big Tech fundamentally
  reshaped computing from a tool for human empowerment into an attention
  extraction machine.</p>

  <p><strong>Radiant proposes an alternative vision for computing</strong>. It
  doesn't ship with a web browser; it has its own network reminiscent of the
  early Internet: no social media, no scripts, no trackers. It's a from-scratch
  system that doesn't retrace the footsteps of the contemporary OS. It's a
  new paradigm for personal computing that uses modern advances mindfully and
  deliberately. It's fully open, from hardware to software. It's an
  offline-first space, designed for focus and creation.</p>

  <p><strong>Code is computing's native medium</strong>; the material you shape
  to build your own tools, stories, and spaces. Radiant is designed to make
  that accessible to everyone. It's a tool for personal computing where every
  application and every surface, exists as code you can read, edit, and extend.
  It's a system you can truly own. One that is designed to bring the joy of
  computing to everyone.</p>

  <p><strong>Writing software doesn't have to be daunting</strong>, but the
  platforms and tools we're stuck with make it so. Radiant aims to change that
  and truly empower users to create. Furthermore, advances in generative A.I.
  will make coding accessible to a much broader audience. One of our goals is
  to explore how an A.I.-native computer system can enhance the creative
  process, all while keeping data private.</p>

  <p>Radiant belongs to a more humane future: a personal computer that welcomes
  curiosity, invites experimentation, and keeps the power in your hands. This
  is personal computing for the next generation.</p>

  <hr>

  <p>Find out more about the Radiant <a href="https://radiant.computer/system">system</a>, or read our
  design <a href="https://radiant.computer/principles">principles</a> and <a href="https://radiant.computer/tenets">tenets</a>.</p>

  <hr>
  <p>
  Radiant is an ongoing research project in personal computing.
  If this resonates with you, write us at 📧 <a href="mailto:letters@radiant.computer">letters@radiant.computer</a>
  or follow us on 🦋 Bluesky <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/radiant.computer">@radiant.computer</a>.
</p>

  <p>You can learn more about Radiant by browsing our
  <a href="https://radiant.computer/log">log</a> or <a href="https://radiant.computer/notes">notes</a>.</p>
  <hr>
  <p>
  © 2025 The Radiant Computer Team
</p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[iOS 26.2 to allow third-party app stores in Japan ahead of regulatory deadline (195 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.macrumors.com/2025/11/05/ios-26-2-third-party-app-stores-japan/</link>
            <guid>45822302</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 12:51:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/11/05/ios-26-2-third-party-app-stores-japan/">https://www.macrumors.com/2025/11/05/ios-26-2-third-party-app-stores-japan/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45822302">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div role="main" id="maincontent"><article expanded="true"><div data-io-article-url="/2025/11/05/ios-26-2-third-party-app-stores-japan/"><p>Apple on Tuesday released the first beta of iOS 26.2 to developers, and it appears that the software will allow users in Japan to install alternative app marketplaces on their devices when it is released to the public in December.</p>
<p><img src="https://images.macrumors.com/t/9gZqzwr4izpakGd18cqwpi88XnM=/400x0/article-new/2025/11/iOS-26.2-Glass-Feature.jpg?lossy" srcset="https://images.macrumors.com/t/9gZqzwr4izpakGd18cqwpi88XnM=/400x0/article-new/2025/11/iOS-26.2-Glass-Feature.jpg?lossy 400w,https://images.macrumors.com/t/_mA3cq1Fdd3jxJpkxQEbA0OJGXE=/800x0/article-new/2025/11/iOS-26.2-Glass-Feature.jpg?lossy 800w,https://images.macrumors.com/t/WTNj-dgPJPyHH_muE2tXmo2SFec=/1600x0/article-new/2025/11/iOS-26.2-Glass-Feature.jpg 1600w,https://images.macrumors.com/t/tPjenoS1N4o_FFVviRVgZYzj2-w=/2500x0/filters:no_upscale()/article-new/2025/11/iOS-26.2-Glass-Feature.jpg 2500w" sizes="(max-width: 900px) 100vw, 697px" alt="iOS 26" width="2500" height="1406"><br>According to a <a href="https://x.com/Tzzlala/status/1985857946082070604">post shared on X by @Tzzlala</a>, iPhones running the beta in Japan are able to install alternative app stores like AltStore PAL and Epic Games, and download apps from them, though Fortnite in-app purchases are currently region-blocked by Epic. </p>
<p>Apple only lets iPhone and iPad users based in the EU to install apps using alternative app marketplaces in addition to the App Store. The ability was introduced in iOS 17.4 and iPadOS 18 in order to comply with the Digital Markets Act, and Apple does not currently allow it in any regions outside the 27-member bloc. However, that's set to change. </p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2024/06/14/japan-passes-law-to-allow-third-party-app-stores/">June 2024</a>, the Japanese parliament approved and enacted legislation that requires Apple to allow third-party app stores and payment providers on the iPhone. The law seeks to curb the dominance of major tech firms like Apple in the smartphone market.</p>
<p>More recently, in August 2025, the Japan Fair Trade Commission established the <a href="https://www.jftc.go.jp/file/MSCA_Guidelines_tentative_translation.pdf">Mobile Software Competition Act Guidelines</a>. Under the new guidelines, platform operators like Apple and Google are banned from blocking or restricting the availability of alternative app stores and payment systems on their mobile operating systems. </p>
<p>The guidelines are set to come into effect by December 18, 2025, while Apple is expected to release iOS 26.2 in December, sometime between December 9 and December 16. Epic Games has already announced plans to bring Fortnite and its game store platform to iOS in Japan by late 2025.</p>
</div></article><p><h2>Popular Stories</h2></p><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/11/02/apple-to-launch-these-new-products-in-2026/">Report: Apple to Launch These New Products in 2026</a></h3><p>Apple is planning to launch at least 15 new products in 2026, according to Bloomberg's Mark Gurman.
Gurman outlined what to expect from Apple in 2026 in the latest edition of his "Power On" newsletter. He said the company is heading "into one of its most pivotal years in recent memory," with the rollout of major new Apple Intelligence features, intense regulatory pressure on the App Store,...</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/11/02/new-version-of-siri-to-lean-on-google-gemini/">New Version of Siri to 'Lean' on Google Gemini</a></h3><p>In his "Power On" newsletter, Bloomberg's Mark Gurman today provided an update on the status of Apple Intelligence and the plans for it in 2026.
Apple is still planning to roll out its revamped version of Siri around March of next year. The release should be accompanied by the release of a new smart home display product with speaker-base and wall-mount options. A new Apple TV and HomePod...</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/11/02/new-apple-tv-and-homepod-mini-launching-soon/">New Apple TV and HomePod Mini Likely Launching Soon</a></h3><p>A new Apple TV and HomePod mini could launch as soon as this month, Bloomberg's Mark Gurman today suggested.
In today's "Power On" newsletter, Gurman said that Apple retail stores are planning an overnight refresh on the evening of November 11, where changes will be made after closing, such as refreshing displays and placing new products for the following day.
The timing of the overnight...</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/11/02/best-early-black-friday-apple-deals-2025/">The Best Early Black Friday Apple Deals</a></h3><p>We're officially in the month of Black Friday, which will take place on Friday, November 28 in 2025. As always, this will be the best time of the year to shop for great deals, including popular Apple products like AirPods, iPad, Apple Watch, and more. In this article, the majority of the discounts will be found on Amazon.
Note: MacRumors is an affiliate partner with some of these vendors. When ...</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/11/03/ios-26-1-available-tomorrow/">iOS 26.1 Available Today With These 8 New Features</a></h3><p>Update: Apple has released iOS 26.1.
Following more than a month of beta testing, Apple is expected to release iOS 26.1 this Monday, November 3. The update includes a handful of new features and changes, including the ability to adjust the look of Liquid Glass and more.
Below, we outline key details about iOS 26.1.
Liquid Glass Toggle
iOS 26.1 lets you choose your preferred look for ...</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/10/31/iphone-fold-release-pricing-features-foldable/">iPhone Fold: Launch, Pricing, and What to Expect From Apple's Foldable</a></h3><p>Friday October 31, 2025 8:52 am PDT by <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/author/tim-hardwick/" rel="author">Tim Hardwick</a></p><p>Apple is expected to launch a new foldable iPhone next year, based on multiple rumors and credible sources. The long-awaited device has been rumored for years now, but signs increasingly suggest that 2026 could indeed be the year that Apple releases its first foldable device.
Below, we've collated an updated set of key details that have been leaked about Apple's foldable iPhone so far.
Ove...</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/11/03/apple-one-new-logo/">Apple One Gets New Colorful Logo Following Apple TV Rebrand [Updated]</a></h3><p>Monday November 3, 2025 3:22 pm PST by <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/author/juli-clover/" rel="author">Juli Clover</a></p><p>Apple updated the logo and name for its Apple TV streaming service today, and it looks like Apple One might be next. On the revamped Apple TV website, there's a new, more colorful Apple One logo available.
The logo features an Apple icon that's split into six slices, and each slice includes the color that Apple uses for one of the services included in Apple One Premium.
Apple One is...</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[YouTube erased more than 700 videos documenting Israeli human rights violations (317 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://theintercept.com/2025/11/04/youtube-google-israel-palestine-human-rights-censorship/</link>
            <guid>45822018</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 12:13:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://theintercept.com/2025/11/04/youtube-google-israel-palestine-human-rights-censorship/">https://theintercept.com/2025/11/04/youtube-google-israel-palestine-human-rights-censorship/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45822018">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    
    <p><span>A documentary featuring</span> mothers surviving Israel’s genocide in Gaza. A video investigation uncovering Israel’s role in the killing of a Palestinian American journalist. Another video revealing Israel’s destruction of Palestinian homes in the occupied West Bank.</p>
<p>YouTube surreptitiously deleted all these videos in early October by wiping the accounts that posted them from its website, along with their channels’ archives. The accounts belonged to three prominent Palestinian human rights groups: Al-Haq, Al Mezan Center for Human Rights, and the Palestinian Centre for Human Rights.</p>
<p>The move came in response to a U.S. government campaign to stifle accountability for alleged Israeli war crimes against Palestinians in Gaza and the West Bank.</p>
<p>The Palestinian groups’ YouTube channels hosted hours of footage documenting and highlighting alleged Israeli government violations of international law in both Gaza and the West Bank, including the killing of Palestinian civilians.</p>
<!-- BLOCK(cta)[0](%7B%22componentName%22%3A%22CTA%22%2C%22entityType%22%3A%22SHORTCODE%22%2C%22optional%22%3Atrue%7D)(%7B%7D) -->


<!-- END-BLOCK(cta)[0] -->
<p>“I’m pretty shocked that YouTube is showing such a little backbone,” said Sarah Leah Whitson, executive director of Democracy for the Arab World Now. “It’s really hard to imagine any serious argument that sharing information from these Palestinian human rights organizations would somehow violate sanctions. Succumbing to this arbitrary designation of these Palestinian organizations, to now censor them, is disappointing and pretty surprising.”</p>
<p>After the International Criminal Court <a href="https://theintercept.com/2024/11/21/icc-netanyahu-arrest-us-war-crimes/">issued arrest warrants</a> and charged Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu and former Israeli Defense Secretary Yoav Gallant with war crimes in Gaza, the Trump administration escalated its defense of Israel’s actions by sanctioning ICC officials and targeting people and organizations that work with the court.</p>
<!-- BLOCK(pullquote)[0](%7B%22componentName%22%3A%22PULLQUOTE%22%2C%22entityType%22%3A%22SHORTCODE%22%2C%22optional%22%3Atrue%7D)(%7B%22pull%22%3A%22right%22%7D) --><blockquote data-shortcode-type="pullquote" data-pull="right"><!-- CONTENT(pullquote)[0] -->“YouTube is furthering the Trump administration’s agenda to remove evidence of human rights violations and war crimes.”<!-- END-CONTENT(pullquote)[0] --></blockquote><!-- END-BLOCK(pullquote)[0] -->
<p>“It is outrageous that YouTube is furthering the Trump administration’s agenda to remove evidence of human rights violations and war crimes from public view,” said Katherine Gallagher, a senior staff attorney at the Center for Constitutional Rights. “Congress did not intend to allow the president to cut off the flow of information to the American public and the world — instead, information, including documents and videos, are specifically exempted under the statute that the president cited as his authority for issuing the ICC sanctions.”</p>
<h2 id="h-alarming-setback"><strong>“Alarming Setback</strong>”</h2>
<p>YouTube, which is owned by Google, confirmed to The Intercept that it deleted the groups’ accounts as a direct result of State Department <a href="https://theintercept.com/2025/09/16/trump-sanctions-palestine-human-rights-israel/">sanctions</a> against the group after a review. The Trump administration leveled the sanctions against the organizations in September over their work with the International Criminal Court in cases charging Israeli officials of war crimes.</p>
<p>“Google is committed to compliance with applicable sanctions and trade compliance laws,” YouTube spokesperson Boot Bullwinkle said in a statement.</p>
<p>According to Google’s <a href="https://support.google.com/publisherpolicies/answer/11128499?hl=en">Sanctions Compliance</a> publisher policy, “Google publisher products are not eligible for any entities or individuals that are restricted under applicable trade sanctions and export compliance laws.”</p>
<p>Al Mezan, a human rights organization in Gaza, told The Intercept that its YouTube channel was abruptly terminated this year on October 7 without prior notification.</p>
<p>“Terminating the channel deprives us from reaching what we aspire to convey our message to, and fulfill our mission,” a spokesperson for the group said, “and prevents us from achieving our goals and limits our ability to reach the audience we aspire to share our message with.”</p>
<p>The West Bank-based Al-Haq’s channel was deleted on October 3, a spokesperson for the group said, with a message from YouTube that its “content violates our guidelines.”</p>

<p>“YouTube’s removal of a human rights organisation’s platform, carried out without prior warning, represents a serious failure of principle and an alarming setback for human rights and freedom of expression,” the Al-Haq spokesperson said in a statement. “The U.S. Sanctions are being used to cripple accountability work on Palestine and silence Palestinian voices and victims, and this has a ripple effect on such platforms also acting under such measures to further silence Palestinian voices.”</p>
<p>The Palestinian Center for Human Rights, which the U.N. <a href="https://www.ohchr.org/en/press-releases/2024/09/attacks-against-human-rights-defenders-and-obliteration-civic-space-gaza">describes</a> as the oldest human rights organization in Gaza, said in a statement that YouTube’s move “protects perpetrators from accountability.”</p>
<p>“YouTube’s decision to close PCHR’s account is basically one of many consequences that we as an organisation have faced since the decision of the US government to sanction our organisations for our legitimate work,” said Basel al-Sourani, an international advocacy officer and legal advisor for the group. “YouTube said that we were not following their policy on Community Guidelines, when all our work was basically presenting factual and evidence-based reporting on the crimes committed against the Palestinian people especially since the start of the ongoing genocide on 7 October.”</p>
<p>“By doing this, YouTube is being complicit in silencing the voices of Palestinian victims,” al-Sourani added.</p>
<h2 id="h-looking-outside-the-u-s">Looking Outside the U.S.</h2>
<p>The three human rights groups’ account terminations cumulatively amount to the erasure of more than 700 videos, according to an Intercept tally.</p>
<p>The deleted videos range in scope from investigations, such as an <a href="https://web.archive.org/whttps:/www.youtube.com/watch?v=BXjVDKILC3s">analysis</a> of the Israeli killing of American journalist <a href="https://theintercept.com/2022/09/20/shireen-abu-akleh-killing-israel/">Shireen Abu Akleh</a>, to <a href="https://pchrgaza.org/shattered-futures-testimonies-of-torture-and-genocide-in-gaza/">testimonies</a> of Palestinians tortured by Israeli forces and documentaries like “<a href="https://mezan.org/en/post/42336/-the-beach-----%D8%A7%D9%84%D8%B4%D8%A7%D8%B7%D8%A6">The Beach</a>,” about children playing on a beach who were killed by an Israeli strike.</p>
<p>Some videos are still available through copies saved on the Internet Archive’s <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20250108193449/http:/www.youtube.com/watch?v=BXjVDKILC3s">Wayback Machine</a> or on alternate platforms, such as <a href="https://www.facebook.com/watch/?v=2564706803864135">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://vimeo.com/faiu">Vimeo</a>. The wiping only affected the group’s official channels; videos which were produced by the nonprofits but hosted on alternate YouTube channels remain <a href="https://www.mezan.org/en/post/33676/Death-Permit----%D8%AA%D8%B5%D8%A7%D8%B1%D9%8A%D8%AD-%D8%A7%D9%84%D9%85%D9%88%D8%AA">active</a>. No cumulative index of videos deleted by YouTube is available, however, and many appear to not be available elsewhere online.</p>
<!-- BLOCK(promote-post)[0](%7B%22componentName%22%3A%22PROMOTE_POST%22%2C%22entityType%22%3A%22SHORTCODE%22%2C%22optional%22%3Atrue%7D)(%7B%22slug%22%3A%22chilling-dissent%22%2C%22crop%22%3A%22promo%22%7D) -->  
<!-- END-BLOCK(promote-post)[0] -->
<p>Videos posted elsewhere online, the groups fear, could soon be targeted for deletion because many of the platforms hosting them are also U.S.-based services. The ICC itself began <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/europe/us-could-hit-entire-international-criminal-court-with-sanctions-soon-2025-09-22/">exploring</a> <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/10/31/international_criminal_court_ditches_office/">using</a> service providers outside the U.S.</p>
<p>Al-Haq said it would also be looking for alternatives outside of U.S. companies to host their work.</p>
<p>YouTube isn’t the only U.S. tech company blocking Palestinian rights groups from using its services. The Al-Haq spokesperson said Mailchimp, the mailing list service, also deleted the group’s account in September. (Mailchimp and its parent company, Intuit, did not immediately respond to a request for comment.)</p>
<h2 id="h-caving-to-trump-s-demand"><strong>Caving to Trump’s Demand</strong></h2>
<p>Both the U.S. and Israeli governments have long <a href="https://theintercept.com/2024/11/21/icc-netanyahu-arrest-us-war-crimes/">shielded</a> themselves from the ICC and accountability for their alleged war crimes. <a href="https://theintercept.com/2021/08/23/samantha-power-icc-sudan/">Neither country</a> is party to the Rome Statute, the international treaty that established the court.</p>
<p>In November 2024, the ICC prosecutors<a href="https://theintercept.com/2024/11/21/icc-netanyahu-arrest-us-war-crimes/"> issued arrest warrants</a> for Netanyahu and Gallant, charging the leaders with intentionally starving civilians by blocking aid from entering into Gaza. Both the Biden and Trump administrations rejected the legitimacy of the warrants.</p>

<p>Since his reelection, Trump has taken a more aggressive posture against accountability for Israel. In the early days of his second term, Trump renewed sanctions against the ICC and issued new, more severe measures against court officials and anyone accused of aiding their efforts. In September, in a new order, he specifically <a href="https://theintercept.com/2025/09/16/trump-sanctions-palestine-human-rights-israel/">sanctioned the three Palestinian groups</a>.</p>
<p>The U.S. moves followed Israel’s own designation of Al-Haq as a “<a href="https://www.ohchr.org/en/press-releases/2022/04/israelpalestine-un-experts-call-governments-resume-funding-six-palestinian">terrorist organization</a>” in 2021 and an online <a href="https://www.ohchr.org/en/press-releases/2024/09/attacks-against-human-rights-defenders-and-obliteration-civic-space-gaza">smear campaign</a> by pro-Israeli activists attempting to link Palestinian Centre for Human Rights with militant groups.</p>
<p>The sanctions freeze the organizations’ assets in the U.S. and bar sanctioned individuals from traveling to the country. Federal judges have already&nbsp;issued preliminary injunctions in&nbsp;<a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/federal/district-courts/new-york/nysdce/1:2025cv03114/640571/70/">two cases&nbsp;</a>in favor of plaintiffs who argued the sanctions had violated their First Amendment rights.</p>
<p>“The Trump administration is focused on contributing to the censorship of information about Israeli atrocities in Palestine and the sanctions against these organizations is very deliberately designed to make association with these organizations frightening to Americans who will be concerned about material support laws,” said Whitson, of DAWN, which <a href="https://www.hrw.org/news/2025/10/17/joint-statement-us-sanctions-on-palestinian-human-rights-organizations-erodes">joined a coalition</a> of groups in September to demand the Trump administration drop its sanctions.</p>
<!-- BLOCK(newsletter)[0](%7B%22componentName%22%3A%22NEWSLETTER%22%2C%22entityType%22%3A%22SHORTCODE%22%2C%22optional%22%3Atrue%7D)(%7B%7D) -->

<!-- END-BLOCK(newsletter)[0] -->
<p>Like many tech firms, YouTube has shown a ready willingness to comply with demands from both the Trump administration and Israel. YouTube coordinated with a campaign organized by Israeli tech workers to remove social media content<a href="https://theintercept.com/2024/01/10/israel-disinformation-social-media-iron-truth/"> deemed critical of Israel</a>. At home, Google, YouTube’s parent company, secretly <a href="https://theintercept.com/2025/09/16/google-facebook-subpoena-ice-students-gaza/">handed over</a> personal Gmail account information to U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement in an effort to detain a pro-Palestinian student organizer.</p>
<p>Even before Israel’s genocidal campaign in Gaza, YouTube had been <a href="https://al-shabaka.org/briefs/youtubes-violation-of-palestinian-digital-rights-what-needs-to-be-done/">accused</a> of unevenly applying its community guidelines to censor Palestinian voices while withholding similar scrutiny from <a href="https://al-shabaka.org/policy-memos/the-rise-in-hate-speech-targeting-palestinians-in-israeli-social-media/">pro-Israeli content</a>. Such trends continued during the war, according to a Wired <a href="https://archive.ph/4U1iU">report</a>.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, YouTube shut down the official <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/addameer21">account</a> of the <a href="https://addameer.ps/">Addameer Prisoner Support and Human Rights Association</a>. The move came after pressure from <a href="https://www.uklfi.com/addameers-youtube-channel-shut-down">UK Lawyers for Israel</a>, which wrote to YouTube to point out that the organization had been <a href="https://home.treasury.gov/news/press-releases/sb0162">sanctioned</a> by the State Department.</p>
<p>Whitson warned that YouTube’s capitulation could set a precedent, pushing other tech companies to bend to censorship.</p>
<p>“They are basically allowing the Trump administration to dictate what information they share with the global audience,” she said. “It’s not going to end with Palestine.”</p>
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I’m worried that they put co-pilot in Excel (318 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Nov/5/brenda/</link>
            <guid>45820872</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 08:54:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Nov/5/brenda/">https://simonwillison.net/2025/Nov/5/brenda/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45820872">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<blockquote cite="http://www.tiktok.com/@belligerentbarbies/video/7568380008633257271"><p>I'm worried that they put co-pilot in Excel because Excel is the beast that drives our entire economy and do you know who has tamed that beast?</p>
<p>Brenda.</p>
<p>Who is Brenda?</p>
<p>She is a mid-level employee in every finance department, in every business across this stupid nation and the Excel goddess herself descended from the heavens, kissed Brenda on her forehead and the sweat from Brenda's brow is what allows us to do capitalism. [...]</p>
<p>She's gonna birth that formula for a financial report and then she's gonna send that financial report to a higher up and he's gonna need to make a change to the report and normally he would have sent it back to Brenda but he's like oh I have AI and AI is probably like smarter than Brenda and then the AI is gonna fuck it up real bad and he won't be able to recognize it because he doesn't understand Excel because AI hallucinates.</p>
<p>You know who's not hallucinating?</p>
<p>Brenda.</p></blockquote>
<p>— <a href="https://www.tiktok.com/@belligerentbarbies/video/7568380008633257271">@belligerentbarbies</a>, <span>on TikTok</span></p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Hacker’s Manifesto (1986) (110 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://phrack.org/issues/7/3</link>
            <guid>45820715</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 08:28:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://phrack.org/issues/7/3">https://phrack.org/issues/7/3</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45820715">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<table>
   <tbody>
      <tr><td><a href="https://phrack.org/issues/7/1.html#article">Intro/Index</a></td><td>Taran King</td></tr>

<tr><td><a href="https://phrack.org/issues/7/2.html#article">Phrack Pro-Phile of Scan Man</a></td><td>Taran King</td></tr>

<tr><td><a href="https://phrack.org/issues/7/3.html#article">Hacker's Manifesto</a></td><td>The Mentor</td></tr>

<tr><td><a href="https://phrack.org/issues/7/4.html#article">Hacking Chilton's Credimatic</a></td><td>Ryche</td></tr>

<tr><td><a href="https://phrack.org/issues/7/5.html#article">Hacking RSTS Part 1</a></td><td>The Seker</td></tr>

<tr><td><a href="https://phrack.org/issues/7/6.html#article">How to Make TNT</a></td><td>The Radical Rocker</td></tr>

<tr><td><a href="https://phrack.org/issues/7/7.html#article">Trojan Horses in Unix</a></td><td>Shooting Shark</td></tr>

<tr><td><a href="https://phrack.org/issues/7/8.html#article">Phrack World News VI Part 1</a></td><td>Knight Lightning</td></tr>

<tr><td><a href="https://phrack.org/issues/7/9.html#article">Phrack World News VI Part 2</a></td><td>Knight Lightning</td></tr>

<tr><td><a href="https://phrack.org/issues/7/10.html#article">Phrack World News VI Part 3</a></td><td>Knight Lightning</td></tr>

   </tbody>
</table>

<p><strong>Title</strong> : Hacker's Manifesto</p>
<p><strong>Author</strong> : The Mentor</p>
<pre>                               ==Phrack Inc.==

                    Volume One, Issue 7, Phile 3 of 10

=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=
The following was written shortly after my arrest...

                       \/\The Conscience of a Hacker/\/

                                      by

                               +++The Mentor+++

                          Written on January 8, 1986
=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=

        Another one got caught today, it's all over the papers.  "Teenager
Arrested in Computer Crime Scandal", "Hacker Arrested after Bank Tampering"...
        Damn kids.  They're all alike.

        But did you, in your three-piece psychology and 1950's technobrain,
ever take a look behind the eyes of the hacker?  Did you ever wonder what
made him tick, what forces shaped him, what may have molded him?
        I am a hacker, enter my world...
        Mine is a world that begins with school... I'm smarter than most of
the other kids, this crap they teach us bores me...
        Damn underachiever.  They're all alike.

        I'm in junior high or high school.  I've listened to teachers explain
for the fifteenth time how to reduce a fraction.  I understand it.  "No, Ms.
Smith, I didn't show my work.  I did it in my head..."
        Damn kid.  Probably copied it.  They're all alike.

        I made a discovery today.  I found a computer.  Wait a second, this is
cool.  It does what I want it to.  If it makes a mistake, it's because I
screwed it up.  Not because it doesn't like me...
                Or feels threatened by me...
                Or thinks I'm a smart ass...
                Or doesn't like teaching and shouldn't be here...
        Damn kid.  All he does is play games.  They're all alike.

        And then it happened... a door opened to a world... rushing through
the phone line like heroin through an addict's veins, an electronic pulse is
sent out, a refuge from the day-to-day incompetencies is sought... a board is
found.
        "This is it... this is where I belong..."
        I know everyone here... even if I've never met them, never talked to
them, may never hear from them again... I know you all...
        Damn kid.  Tying up the phone line again.  They're all alike...

        You bet your ass we're all alike... we've been spoon-fed baby food at
school when we hungered for steak... the bits of meat that you did let slip
through were pre-chewed and tasteless.  We've been dominated by sadists, or
ignored by the apathetic.  The few that had something to teach found us will-
ing pupils, but those few are like drops of water in the desert.

        This is our world now... the world of the electron and the switch, the
beauty of the baud.  We make use of a service already existing without paying
for what could be dirt-cheap if it wasn't run by profiteering gluttons, and
you call us criminals.  We explore... and you call us criminals.  We seek
after knowledge... and you call us criminals.  We exist without skin color,
without nationality, without religious bias... and you call us criminals.
You build atomic bombs, you wage wars, you murder, cheat, and lie to us
and try to make us believe it's for our own good, yet we're the criminals.

        Yes, I am a criminal.  My crime is that of curiosity.  My crime is
that of judging people by what they say and think, not what they look like.
My crime is that of outsmarting you, something that you will never forgive me
for.

        I am a hacker, and this is my manifesto.  You may stop this individual,
but you can't stop us all... after all, we're all alike.

                               +++The Mentor+++
_______________________________________________________________________________
</pre>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Epic vs. Google settlement: Opening up Android (104 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/TimSweeneyEpic/status/1985920786545123613</link>
            <guid>45818973</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 04:12:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/TimSweeneyEpic/status/1985920786545123613">https://twitter.com/TimSweeneyEpic/status/1985920786545123613</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45818973">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="ScriptLoadFailure"><form action="" method="GET"><div><p><span>Something went wrong, but don’t fret — let’s give it another shot.</span></p><p><img alt="⚠️" draggable="false" src="https://abs-0.twimg.com/emoji/v2/svg/26a0.svg"><span> Some privacy related extensions may cause issues on x.com. Please disable them and try again.</span></p></div></form></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hypothesis: Property-Based Testing for Python (186 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://hypothesis.readthedocs.io/en/latest/</link>
            <guid>45818562</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 03:15:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://hypothesis.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">https://hypothesis.readthedocs.io/en/latest/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45818562">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="furo-main-content" role="main">
<!-- adapted from https://docs.django-cms.org/en/release-4.1.x/, with thanks -->
<section id="welcome-to-hypothesis">
<h2>Welcome to Hypothesis!<a href="#welcome-to-hypothesis" title="Link to this heading">¶</a></h2>
<p>Hypothesis is the property-based testing library for Python. With Hypothesis, you write tests which should pass for all inputs in whatever range you describe, and let Hypothesis randomly choose which of those inputs to check - including edge cases you might not have thought about. For example:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>from</span> <span>hypothesis</span> <span>import</span> <a href="https://hypothesis.readthedocs.io/en/latest/reference/api.html#hypothesis.given" title="hypothesis.given"><span>given</span></a><span>,</span> <span>strategies</span> <span>as</span> <span>st</span>

<a href="https://hypothesis.readthedocs.io/en/latest/reference/api.html#hypothesis.given" title="hypothesis.given"><span>@given</span></a><span>(</span><a href="https://hypothesis.readthedocs.io/en/latest/reference/strategies.html#hypothesis.strategies.lists" title="hypothesis.strategies.lists"><span>st</span><span>.</span><span>lists</span></a><span>(</span><a href="https://hypothesis.readthedocs.io/en/latest/reference/strategies.html#hypothesis.strategies.integers" title="hypothesis.strategies.integers"><span>st</span><span>.</span><span>integers</span></a><span>()</span> <span>|</span> <a href="https://hypothesis.readthedocs.io/en/latest/reference/strategies.html#hypothesis.strategies.floats" title="hypothesis.strategies.floats"><span>st</span><span>.</span><span>floats</span></a><span>()))</span>
<span>def</span> <span>test_sort_correct</span><span>(</span><span>lst</span><span>):</span>
    <span># hypothesis generates random lists of numbers to test</span>
    <span>assert</span> <span>my_sort</span><span>(</span><span>lst</span><span>)</span> <span>==</span> <a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/functions.html#sorted" title="sorted"><span>sorted</span></a><span>(</span><span>lst</span><span>)</span>

<span>test_sort_correct</span><span>()</span>
</pre></div>
<p>You should start with the <a href="https://hypothesis.readthedocs.io/en/latest/tutorial/index.html"><span>tutorial</span></a>, or alternatively the more condensed <a href="https://hypothesis.readthedocs.io/en/latest/quickstart.html"><span>quickstart</span></a>.</p>
<section id="tutorial">
<h2><a href="https://hypothesis.readthedocs.io/en/latest/tutorial/index.html"><span>Tutorial</span></a><a href="#tutorial" title="Link to this heading">¶</a></h2>
<p>An introduction to Hypothesis.</p>
<p>New users should start here, or with the more condensed <a href="https://hypothesis.readthedocs.io/en/latest/quickstart.html"><span>quickstart</span></a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-to-guides">
<h2><a href="https://hypothesis.readthedocs.io/en/latest/how-to/index.html"><span>How-to guides</span></a><a href="#how-to-guides" title="Link to this heading">¶</a></h2>
<p>Practical guides for applying Hypothesis in specific scenarios.</p>
</section>
<section id="explanations">
<h2><a href="https://hypothesis.readthedocs.io/en/latest/explanation/index.html"><span>Explanations</span></a><a href="#explanations" title="Link to this heading">¶</a></h2>
<p>Commentary oriented towards deepening your understanding of Hypothesis.</p>
</section>
<section id="api-reference">
<h2><a href="https://hypothesis.readthedocs.io/en/latest/reference/index.html"><span>API Reference</span></a><a href="#api-reference" title="Link to this heading">¶</a></h2>
<p>Technical API reference.</p>


</section>
</section>
</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What Happened to Piracy? Copyright Enforcement Fades as AI Giants Rise (103 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.leefang.com/p/what-happened-to-piracy-copyright</link>
            <guid>45818483</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 03:01:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.leefang.com/p/what-happened-to-piracy-copyright">https://www.leefang.com/p/what-happened-to-piracy-copyright</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45818483">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!uL9M!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55733038-d09b-4337-9fe5-c119ddfacbe5_2384x1257.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!uL9M!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55733038-d09b-4337-9fe5-c119ddfacbe5_2384x1257.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!uL9M!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55733038-d09b-4337-9fe5-c119ddfacbe5_2384x1257.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!uL9M!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55733038-d09b-4337-9fe5-c119ddfacbe5_2384x1257.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!uL9M!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55733038-d09b-4337-9fe5-c119ddfacbe5_2384x1257.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!uL9M!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55733038-d09b-4337-9fe5-c119ddfacbe5_2384x1257.jpeg" width="1456" height="768" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/55733038-d09b-4337-9fe5-c119ddfacbe5_2384x1257.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:768,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:1149976,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.leefang.com/i/178020077?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55733038-d09b-4337-9fe5-c119ddfacbe5_2384x1257.jpeg&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!uL9M!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55733038-d09b-4337-9fe5-c119ddfacbe5_2384x1257.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!uL9M!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55733038-d09b-4337-9fe5-c119ddfacbe5_2384x1257.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!uL9M!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55733038-d09b-4337-9fe5-c119ddfacbe5_2384x1257.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!uL9M!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55733038-d09b-4337-9fe5-c119ddfacbe5_2384x1257.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>The artificial intelligence revolution threatens to uproot entire professions, replace millions of workers, and reshape industrial relations. Much ink has been spilled on the ways in which AI influence has already taken root. Wall Street and Washington, D.C., are both betting on the technology to power the future of American innovation.</p><p>But little has been said about how the industry has already seized control over key components of American governance. Look no further than the quiet shifts in the application of copyright law.</p><p><span>Since the mid-nineties, software giants led by Microsoft have waged a global war against copyright infringement and online piracy. They bankrolled groups like the Business Software Alliance to </span><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/19/business/software-group-enters-fray-over-proposed-piracy-law.html" rel="">demand increased penalties</a><span> for copyright violations and </span><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/19/business/software-group-enters-fray-over-proposed-piracy-law.html" rel="">pressured FBI agents</a><span> to raid foreign hosts accused of harboring illicit content-sharing servers. For the old software model, duplicated Microsoft Office disks and fake software licenses posed the greatest risk.</span></p><p><span>Then-Microsoft Deputy General Counsel Brad Smith, in a 2001 interview with the Wall Street Journal, championed the crusade against digital theft as part of a </span><a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB986164716595422714?gaa_at=eafs&amp;gaa_n=ASWzDAhbHT-g5t6PFu1BZ2abmPRcd-2sRJr9bJqkFuXX1wmGZnzDsql6Rwc5Z7hCW74%3D&amp;gaa_ts=68b8b5da&amp;gaa_sig=QipzGOBnMm9GSirdh76EfUFCX_ZyF_4XoGeY8yZki1bRFz6OdW0VJyzstd9MBH5kNwCQJb28Es_kVKvRx7KtKw%3D%3D" rel="">sprawling battle</a><span> against “organized criminal enterprises.” The company and its allies marshaled their resources to encourage the federal government to crack down on foreign piracy sites, especially illegal file-sharing firms based in Russia, Hong Kong, and Brazil.</span></p><p><span>In a case that signified this old era of aggressive copyright enforcement, the Justice Department in 2011 </span><a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/217117-united-states-of-america-v-aaron-swartz/?mode=document&amp;q=copyright#document/p7" rel="">pursued</a><span> criminal charges against Aaron Swartz, a young open internet activist, for downloading JSTOR’s repository of scholarly papers without authorization. Faced with the prospect of decades in prison, he died by suicide during the prosecution.</span></p><p>Much has changed since advances in artificial intelligence have made the technology the focal point of Silicon Valley innovation. Smith is now president of Microsoft, and the company and its partner OpenAI—which exclusively runs on Microsoft’s Azure cloud computing network and was backed with $13.75 billion in investment funds from Microsoft—are at the center of a very different type of copyright dispute. This time, as the power of the tech industry still looms over Washington, D.C., prosecutors are less interested in going after those suspected of engaging in illegal downloads of copyrighted work.</p><p>That is because it is now the tech giants that are accused of exploiting pirated content on an industrial scale. Meta, Anthropic, Microsoft, Google, xAI, and OpenAI are competing to vacuum up as much data as humanly possible in a race to develop their respective AI models. The most prized training data, it turns out, are vast quantities of copyrighted material, largely in the form of published works such as academic articles, novels, and nonfiction books.</p><p>After decades of FBI warnings about copyright violations and the dangers of piracy, suddenly the federal government is no longer interested in such crimes. That has left law enforcement in the hands of civil litigation class actions, many of which have been filed by authors and writers noting that tech giants are now plundering their works for AI training without authorization, payment, or notification.</p><p>The court cases have cast a spotlight on a stratospheric level of hypocrisy. Microsoft, which once cast peer-to-peer and dark web piracy sites as an existential threat that cost the economy billions of dollars in damages, allegedly taps the very same types of illicit forums for a huge range of copyrighted academic articles, novels, and nonfiction.</p><p>The AI giants have all but admitted that they have developed their most advanced models by tapping into mass piracy. The lawsuit Kadrey et al. v. Meta Platforms revealed that Meta, the parent company of Facebook, used a mirror of Library Genesis, a notorious library of pirated books hosted on Russian servers, to train its generative AI systems.</p><p>Tech executives have pressed for licensing deals with some publishers—but in many cases have gone ahead with simply stealing millions of books and articles via known piracy sites on the dark web and other illicit forums. The litigation produced emails and documents showing Meta employees admitting that “torrenting from a [Meta-owned] corporate laptop doesn’t feel right 😃.” In one exchange, engineers noted that use of the illegal content had been escalated to Meta CEO Mark Zuckerberg (referred to as “MZ”) and that the decision was “approved to use.”</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Zohran Mamdani wins the New York mayoral race (723 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/elections/new-york-city-mayor-election-winner-2025-race-rcna238909</link>
            <guid>45818421</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 02:50:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/elections/new-york-city-mayor-election-winner-2025-race-rcna238909">https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/elections/new-york-city-mayor-election-winner-2025-race-rcna238909</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45818421">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p id="anchor-1bc85f">Zohran Mamdani has won New York’s mayoral race, NBC News projects, after the 34-year-old democratic socialist energized progressives in the city and across the country while generating intense backlash from President Donald Trump and Republicans, as well as some Democratic moderates.</p><p id="anchor-54393e">Mamdani, the Democratic nominee, on Tuesday handily defeated former New York Gov. Andrew Cuomo — who ran as a third-party candidate after having lost the Democratic primary — and Republican nominee Curtis Sliwa. Mayor Eric Adams, who mounted a third-party campaign for re-election after he won as a Democrat in 2021, dropped out of the race in September and endorsed Cuomo last month.</p><p id="anchor-2b7649"><a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/elections/live-blog/election-day-2025-nyc-mayor-governor-race-live-updates-rcna241592" target="_blank"><em><strong>Follow the election live here</strong></em></a></p><p id="anchor-031319">The victory caps a meteoric rise through New York politics for Mamdani since he launched his campaign roughly one year ago, transforming him from a virtually unknown state assemblyman who barely registered in polling to the incoming leader of America’s largest city. </p><p id="anchor-c4feca">Along the way, he pushed aside the heir to one of New York’s most iconic political dynasties not once but twice within five months.</p><p id="anchor-d59229">Now a nationally known political figure, Mamdani will attempt to enact the sweeping policy platform that inspired his supporters while managing an enormous municipal bureaucracy — and influencing national politics, as one of the most prominent democratic socialists and Democrats in the country. Among other goals, Mamdani wants to freeze rent on rent-stabilized units, enact universal child care, create a free bus program and launch city-run grocery stores.</p><p id="anchor-165e09">“It is tempting to believe that this moment was always destined,” Mamdani said before thousands at a rally in Queens late last month, before he noted that when he started his campaign, “there was not a single television camera there to cover it.”</p><p id="anchor-e54466">“Four months later and as recently as this February, our support had reached eye-watering heights of 1%,” Mamdani continued. “We were tied with noted candidate ‘someone else.’”</p><p id="anchor-7f8818">Mamdani’s victory is sure to reverberate not just throughout New York City but around the nation.</p><p id="anchor-8b107e">In New York, Mamdani’s next challenge will be the tall task of uniting leaders in Albany and on the City Council — many of whom were not eager to line up behind him — to advance his ambitious agenda.</p><p id="anchor-106b97">Nationally, many Democrats will examine his rise from obscurity, his successful messaging on social media and his focus on affordability for clues about how to navigate their own races.</p><p id="anchor-e2060e">Meanwhile, Republicans are eager to turn Mamdani’s left-wing platform into a wedge issue in competitive races far beyond New York City’s borders.</p><figure id="anchor-8edf15"><picture data-testid="picture" data-flavor="fit" data-original-height="1667" data-original-width="2500"><source media="(min-width: 1000px)" srcset="https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_fit-560w,f_avif,q_auto:eco,dpr_2/rockcms/2025-10/251031-election-zohran-mamdani-ew-530p-558899.jpg 2x, https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_fit-560w,f_auto,q_auto:best/rockcms/2025-10/251031-election-zohran-mamdani-ew-530p-558899.jpg 1x"><source media="(min-width: 320px)" srcset="https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_fit-760w,f_avif,q_auto:eco,dpr_2/rockcms/2025-10/251031-election-zohran-mamdani-ew-530p-558899.jpg 2x, https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_fit-760w,f_auto,q_auto:best/rockcms/2025-10/251031-election-zohran-mamdani-ew-530p-558899.jpg 1x"><img loading="lazy" src="https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_fit-760w,f_auto,q_auto:best/rockcms/2025-10/251031-election-zohran-mamdani-ew-530p-558899.jpg" alt="Zohran Mamdani speaking at his campaign office on Oct. 30, 2025 in New York." height="1667" width="2500"></picture><figcaption data-testid="caption"><span data-testid="caption__container">Zohran Mamdani speaking at his campaign office on Oct. 30, 2025 in New York.</span><span data-testid="caption__source">Laurel Golio for NBC News</span></figcaption></figure><p id="anchor-7c0f40">NBC News exit polling found that Mamdani won across racial demographics — with white, Black, Latino, Asian and voters of other races all backing his candidacy over Cuomo’s and Sliwa’s.</p><p id="anchor-59815a">Younger voters overwhelmingly backed Mamdani, with NBC News exit polling showing that voters under 45 years old favored him over Cuomo by 43 points. Voters over 45, meanwhile, backed Cuomo by a 10-point margin.</p><p id="anchor-5d083c">Education played a big role, too, the exit polling showed. And <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/elections/new-york-city-divide-shaping-contentious-mayoral-race-rcna233912" target="_blank">one of the biggest divides</a> in the election was between New Yorkers who were born in the city and those who had moved to New York within the last 10 years.</p><p id="anchor-037249">Meanwhile, with Mamdani’s pro-Palestinian activism having become a key issue in the race, NBC News exit polling found that Jewish voters favored Cuomo over Mamdani by 29 points, 60% to 31%.</p><p id="anchor-50e30c">The closing weeks of the race turned into a brawl between Mamdani and Cuomo, the onetime front-runner who spent the general election trying to play catch-up. The two had heated debates in recent weeks, with Cuomo calling Mamdani a “divisive force in New York” while Mamdani painted Cuomo as Trump’s “puppet.”</p><p id="anchor-2e99c4">Trump made a late jump into the race Monday night, endorsing Cuomo on social media and saying a vote for Sliwa, the Republican nominee, was essentially a vote for Mamdani in the split general election field.</p><p id="anchor-746b05">Interestingly, exit polling showed self-identified Republicans favored Cuomo over Sliwa, with 61% of Republicans him while just 35% backed Sliwa.</p><p id="anchor-cbec83">Late last month, Mamdani delivered an emotional address condemning what he slammed as “racist, baseless” attacks he has faced for his Muslim faith. He will be the first Muslim mayor in New York City history. His unapologetically pro-Palestinian stance energized progressives who oppose Israel’s war in Gaza, as pro-Israel Democrats and donors grew anxious about his rise.</p><p id="anchor-8e888e">At a rally alongside Rep. Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez, D-N.Y., and Sen. Bernie Sanders, I-Vt., days later, Mamdani said Cuomo, Adams and Sliwa possess only “the playbook of the past.”</p><p id="anchor-1fd5a1">“They have sought to make this election a referendum not on the affordability crisis that consumes New Yorkers’ lives,” he said, “but on the faith I belong to and the hatred they seem to normalize.”</p></div><div data-activity-map="expanded-byline-article-bottom"><div data-testid="byline-thumbnail"><a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/author/allan-smith-ncpn925861" tabindex="-1"><picture data-testid="picture" data-flavor="focal" data-original-height="48" data-original-width="48"><source media="(min-width: 320px)" srcset="https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_focal-60x60,f_avif,q_auto:eco,dpr_2/newscms/2024_26/3653035/190618-allan-smith.jpg 2x, https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_focal-60x60,f_auto,q_auto:best/newscms/2024_26/3653035/190618-allan-smith.jpg 1x"><img loading="lazy" src="https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_focal-60x60,f_auto,q_auto:best/newscms/2024_26/3653035/190618-allan-smith.jpg" alt="" height="48" width="48"></picture></a></div><p>Allan Smith is a political reporter for NBC News.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Direct File won't happen in 2026, IRS tells states (301 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nextgov.com/digital-government/2025/11/direct-file-wont-happen-2026-irs-tells-states/409309/</link>
            <guid>45818319</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 02:30:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nextgov.com/digital-government/2025/11/direct-file-wont-happen-2026-irs-tells-states/409309/">https://www.nextgov.com/digital-government/2025/11/direct-file-wont-happen-2026-irs-tells-states/409309/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45818319">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Munich's surfers left stunned after famed river wave vanishes (132 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/world/2025/nov/04/munichs-surfers-left-stunned-after-famed-river-wave-vanishes</link>
            <guid>45818123</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 01:51:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2025/nov/04/munichs-surfers-left-stunned-after-famed-river-wave-vanishes">https://www.theguardian.com/world/2025/nov/04/munichs-surfers-left-stunned-after-famed-river-wave-vanishes</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45818123">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p>The “mother of all river waves” in a German canal that is often credited as the birthplace of freshwater surfing has mysteriously disappeared after decades of flowing smoothly, leaving enthusiasts dumbfounded.</p><p>The famous stationary wave in the southern city of Munich is known as the Eisbach, or “ice brook”, for its frigid temperatures, and has become a pilgrimage site for surfers worldwide.</p><p>Unlike ocean surfing, its freshwater cousin takes place on a “standing wave”, which is often human-made, with currents often flowing over a concrete slab that manipulates the water into a permanent wave.</p><p>The sport’s origin is often cited as dating back to the early 1970s, when rule-breaking daredevils rode the naturally forming wave in Munich for the first time.</p><p>Today, river surfing has a global following, including in the River Severn in the United Kingdom, where surfers ride tidal bores, a phenomenon in which incoming tides form waves that move up a river.</p><p>In Hawaii, surfers also make river waves by digging a trench between a river and the ocean, with water flowing violently over the sand.</p><p>The Eisbach wave was originally believed to be formed by gravel, but the Munich surfing community later installed wooden planks that helped artificially stabilise the wave. Over the decades, it has become <a href="https://www.munich.travel/en/pois/sports-leisure/eisbachwelle" data-link-name="in body link">a major tourist</a> draw for Bavaria’s state capital.</p><p>Largest during the winter months – when ice melt can push the wave up to one metre high – the river is now officially managed, including being drained once a year to clean away debris and inspect the streambed.</p><figure id="bfa32c70-4b17-433b-b4b8-e30d66ab0293" data-spacefinder-role="inline" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-2"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/88b089083a2d4374607e3a79a42d475b5b5335d2/241_0_3839_3072/master/3839.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/88b089083a2d4374607e3a79a42d475b5b5335d2/241_0_3839_3072/master/3839.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/88b089083a2d4374607e3a79a42d475b5b5335d2/241_0_3839_3072/master/3839.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/88b089083a2d4374607e3a79a42d475b5b5335d2/241_0_3839_3072/master/3839.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/88b089083a2d4374607e3a79a42d475b5b5335d2/241_0_3839_3072/master/3839.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/88b089083a2d4374607e3a79a42d475b5b5335d2/241_0_3839_3072/master/3839.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="People look at the spot where there once was the Eisbach wave " src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/88b089083a2d4374607e3a79a42d475b5b5335d2/241_0_3839_3072/master/3839.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" width="445" height="356.09273248241726" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption data-spacefinder-role="inline"><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>People look at the spot where there once was the Eisbach wave in Munich.</span> Photograph: Michael Nguyen/NurPhoto/Shutterstock</figcaption></figure><p>But after torrents were released back into the canal following its cleanup on Friday, the Eisbach wave did not form as usual, instead leaving unstable white water rapids.</p><p>“We’re at a loss,” surfer Klaus Rudolf <a href="https://www.stern.de/sport/sportwelt/eisbachwelle--so-funktioniert-die-stehende-welle--normalerweise--36188344.html" data-link-name="in body link">told Stern magazine</a>. “I was standing at the edge with my board on Friday evening and couldn’t believe it.”</p><p>Authorities were looking into the cause of the wave’s disappearance, including whether it could be due to the cleaning or a lack of water.</p><p>“No structural changes were made to the Eisbach wave or its banks during the cleanup,” the city said. An inspection of the site on Monday also did not reveal any damage.</p><p>On Tuesday, Mayor Dieter Reiter said in a statement that the city administration was “working with the Water Management Office and surfers to find a quick solution so that the famous surf wave will soon be available again as usual”.</p><p>Officials now plan to divert more water into the canal in hopes of a reappearance of the Eisbach, which SurferToday.com <a href="https://www.surfertoday.com/surfing/eisbach-the-mother-of-all-river-waves" data-link-name="in body link">describes</a> as “the mother of all river waves”. Standing waves require delicately balanced water levels and speeds.</p><p>The Eisbach wave closed earlier this year for several months after the death of a 33-year-old Munich woman who became trapped under the surface at night. Since it reopened, new rules have banned night-time surfing.</p><p><em>Agence France-Presse contributed to this report</em></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[FDA described as a "clown show" amid latest scandal; top drug regulator is out (147 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/health/2025/11/fda-described-as-a-clown-show-amid-latest-scandal-top-drug-regulator-is-out/</link>
            <guid>45817308</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 23:53:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/health/2025/11/fda-described-as-a-clown-show-amid-latest-scandal-top-drug-regulator-is-out/">https://arstechnica.com/health/2025/11/fda-described-as-a-clown-show-amid-latest-scandal-top-drug-regulator-is-out/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45817308">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          
          
<p>In September, Tidmarsh went after Tang’s Aurinia and its drug voclosporin that treats lupus nephritis, a disease in which the immune system attacks the kidneys. In a startling post on his LinkedIn account, Tidmarsh claimed that the FDA-approved drug had not been shown to provide “hard” clinical benefit and that the drugmaker had not performed necessary trials.</p>
<p>Such a post from the FDA’s top drugmaker turned heads. Aurinia claims its share price fell 20 percent in a matter of hours, dropping $350 million in market value.</p>
<h2>“Embarrassing”</h2>
<p>Aurinia pushed back in the lawsuit, saying that the drug had undergone a full FDA approval process—not an abbreviated one—and been assessed based on a validated surrogate endpoint that is known to predict clinical outcomes. Further, the drug has been approved for use in 36 other countries in addition to the US.</p>
<p>On Sunday, Tidmarsh offered his resignation, but on Monday, pharmaceutical industry publication <a href="https://endpoints.news/day-after-resigning-tidmarsh-now-says-hell-fight-exit-from-fda/">Endpoints News reported</a> that Tidmarsh had notified FDA staff that he planned to fight the investigation and was reconsidering his decision to resign.</p>
<p>If the allegations in Aurinia’s lawsuit are true, Tidmarsh’s behavior would be egregious for a federal regulator. But already, the claims and other scandals have outsiders concerned that the high-stakes “soap opera” is destroying the agency’s credibility, <a href="https://www.statnews.com/2025/11/04/fda-in-disarray-expert-analysis-george-tidmarsh-scandal/">as Stat reported Tuesday</a>.</p>
<p>“We are witnessing nothing less than a clown show at FDA right now,” one venture capital investor told the outlet. “For the sake of patients, we need a stable and consistent FDA!”</p>
<p>“What’s happening at the top of the FDA is embarrassing,” a portfolio manager at a large biotech fund added. “How am I supposed to convince people, other investors, that this sector is doing important work when the leaders of the FDA are acting this way?”</p>


          
                  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Uncle Sam wants to scan your iris and collect your DNA, citizen or not (341 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theregister.com/2025/11/04/dhs_wants_to_collect_biometric_data/</link>
            <guid>45817167</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 23:35:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/11/04/dhs_wants_to_collect_biometric_data/">https://www.theregister.com/2025/11/04/dhs_wants_to_collect_biometric_data/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45817167">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="body">
<p>If you're filing an immigration form - or helping someone who is - the Feds may soon want to look in your eyes, swab your cheek, and scan your face. The US Department of Homeland Security wants to greatly expand biometric data collection for immigration applications, covering immigrants and even some US citizens tied to those cases.</p>
<p>DHS, through its component agency US Citizenship and Immigration Services, on Monday <a href="https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2025/11/03/2025-19747/collection-and-use-of-biometrics-by-us-citizenship-and-immigration-services" rel="nofollow">proposed</a> a sweeping expansion of the agency's collection of biometric data. While ostensibly about verifying identities and preventing fraud in <a href="https://www.nilc.org/resources/table_ovrw_fedprogs/" rel="nofollow">immigration benefit</a> applications, the proposed rule goes much further than simply ensuring applicants are who they claim to be.</p>
<p>First off, the rule proposes expanding when DHS can collect biometric data from immigration benefit applicants, as "submission of biometrics is currently only mandatory for certain benefit requests and enforcement actions." DHS wants to change that, including by requiring practically everyone an immigrant is associated with to submit their biometric data.&nbsp;</p>

    

<p>"DHS proposes in this rule that any applicant, petitioner, sponsor, supporter, derivative, dependent, beneficiary, or individual filing or associated with a benefit request or other request or collection of information, including U.S. citizens, U.S. nationals and lawful permanent residents, and without regard to age, must submit biometrics unless DHS otherwise exempts the requirement," the rule proposal said.&nbsp;</p>

        


        

<p>DHS also wants to require the collection of biometric data from "any alien apprehended, arrested or encountered by DHS."&nbsp;</p>
<p>It's not explicitly stated in the rule proposal why US citizens associated with immigrants who are applying for benefits would have to have their biometric data collected. DHS didn't answer questions to that end, though the rule stated that US citizens would also be required to submit biometric data "when they submit a family-based visa petition."&nbsp;</p>
<h3>Give me your voice, your eye print, your DNA samples</h3>
<p>In addition to expanded collection, the proposed rule also changes the definition of what DHS considers to be valid biometric data.&nbsp;</p>
<p>"Government agencies have grouped together identifying features and actions, such as fingerprints, photographs, and signatures under the broad term, biometrics," the proposal states. "DHS proposes to define the term 'biometrics' to mean 'measurable biological (anatomical, physiological or molecular structure) or behavioral characteristics of an individual,'" thus giving DHS broad leeway to begin collecting new types of biometric data as new technologies are developed.</p>

        

<p>The proposal mentions several new biometric technologies DHS wants the option to use, including ocular imagery, voice prints and DNA, all on the table per the new rule.&nbsp;</p>
<p>"The rule proposes to grant DHS express authority to require, request, or accept raw DNA or DNA test results," DHS said, including "to prove or disprove … biological sex" in situations where that can affect benefit eligibility.&nbsp;</p>
<p>DHS wants to use all that data for identity enrollment, verification and management of the immigration lifecycle, national security and criminal history checks, "the production of secure identity documents," to prove familial relationships, and to perform other administrative functions, the rule states.</p>
<ul>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/08/18/facial_recognition_benchmarks/">Facial recognition works better in the lab than on the street, researchers show</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/10/14/eu_biometric_border_system_launches/">EU biometric border system launch hits inevitable teething problems</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/02/20/vietnam_id_cards_dna/">Vietnam to collect biometrics - even DNA - for new ID cards</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/05/04/sam_altman_startup_world/">Altman's eyeball-scanning biometric blockchain orbs officially come to America</a></li>
</ul>
<p>As we noted in our story last week about DHS' <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/10/29/us_foreigner_facial_scans/">new rule</a> expanding biometric data collection on&nbsp;entry into and exit from the US, biometric technology - especially the often-used facial recognition scan - is ripe for misuse and prone to errors.&nbsp;</p>
<p>This new proposed rule goes far beyond subjecting immigrants to algorithmic identification tech prone to <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/09/30/remote_identity_verification_biased/">misidentifying non-white individuals</a>, however, and reaches a new level of surveillance, with DHS seeking to collect and keep DNA test results - including partial profiles - from immigrants and some US citizens to verify family ties or biological sex when relevant. It's not much more assuring that DHS also wants to collect new forms of biometric data like voice records, which are <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/03/10/ai_voice_cloning_safeguards/">increasingly easy to spoof</a> with AI.</p>

        

<p>When we asked DHS questions about its biometric expansion proposal, it only sent us a statement identical to the one it sent last week when we inquired about the new entry/exit biometric requirements. The agency didn't respond when we asked for a statement pertaining to this latest proposed rule.&nbsp;</p>
<p>DHS is taking comments on the proposal until January 2; so far the <a href="https://www.regulations.gov/document/USCIS-2025-0205-0002/comment" rel="nofollow">submissions</a> are nearly entirely negative, with posters decrying the plan as government overreach, comparing the proposal to communist China, and calling it a violation of Constitutional guarantees against unreasonable search and seizure.&nbsp;®</p>                                
                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Bluetui – A TUI for managing Bluetooth on Linux (229 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/pythops/bluetui</link>
            <guid>45817114</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 23:29:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/pythops/bluetui">https://github.com/pythops/bluetui</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45817114">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><div dir="auto">
  <p><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/pythops/bluetui/blob/master/assets/bluetui-logo-anim.svg"><img height="125" src="https://github.com/pythops/bluetui/raw/master/assets/bluetui-logo-anim.svg"></a></p><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"> TUI for managing bluetooth on Linux </h2><a id="user-content--tui-for-managing-bluetooth-on-linux-" aria-label="Permalink:  TUI for managing bluetooth on Linux " href="#-tui-for-managing-bluetooth-on-linux-"></a></p>
  <p><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/57548585/504375101-f937535d-5675-4427-b347-8086c8830e23.gif?jwt=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3NjIzMzE3MDEsIm5iZiI6MTc2MjMzMTQwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii81NzU0ODU4NS81MDQzNzUxMDEtZjkzNzUzNWQtNTY3NS00NDI3LWIzNDctODA4NmM4ODMwZTIzLmdpZj9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNTExMDUlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjUxMTA1VDA4MzAwMVomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPWYzYmQwYzUwM2E1ZjE3ZWQ3MTdlMDBjZGNjNTdiZmJkMTFiODdiMTNhYzdlN2NjNzNhODc2MjE0NDgwMDI5Y2EmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0In0.p3YUVgKKF_rvvSlsAm4aYWIfHpcJPjTAceml7p_bx6s"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/57548585/504375101-f937535d-5675-4427-b347-8086c8830e23.gif?jwt=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3NjIzMzE3MDEsIm5iZiI6MTc2MjMzMTQwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii81NzU0ODU4NS81MDQzNzUxMDEtZjkzNzUzNWQtNTY3NS00NDI3LWIzNDctODA4NmM4ODMwZTIzLmdpZj9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNTExMDUlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjUxMTA1VDA4MzAwMVomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPWYzYmQwYzUwM2E1ZjE3ZWQ3MTdlMDBjZGNjNTdiZmJkMTFiODdiMTNhYzdlN2NjNzNhODc2MjE0NDgwMDI5Y2EmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0In0.p3YUVgKKF_rvvSlsAm4aYWIfHpcJPjTAceml7p_bx6s" data-animated-image=""></a>
</p></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">💡 Prerequisites</h2><a id="user-content--prerequisites" aria-label="Permalink: 💡 Prerequisites" href="#-prerequisites"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">A Linux based OS with <a href="https://www.bluez.org/" rel="nofollow">bluez</a> installed.</p>
<div dir="auto"><p dir="auto">Note</p><p dir="auto">You might need to install <a href="https://www.nerdfonts.com/" rel="nofollow">nerdfonts</a> for the icons to be displayed correctly.</p>
</div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🚀 Installation</h2><a id="user-content--installation" aria-label="Permalink: 🚀 Installation" href="#-installation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">📥 Binary release</h3><a id="user-content--binary-release" aria-label="Permalink: 📥 Binary release" href="#-binary-release"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">You can download the pre-built binaries from the release page <a href="https://github.com/pythops/bluetui/releases">release page</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">📦 crates.io</h3><a id="user-content--cratesio" aria-label="Permalink: 📦 crates.io" href="#-cratesio"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">You can install <code>bluetui</code> from <a href="https://crates.io/crates/bluetui" rel="nofollow">crates.io</a></p>

<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🐧 Arch Linux</h3><a id="user-content--arch-linux" aria-label="Permalink: 🐧 Arch Linux" href="#-arch-linux"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">You can install <code>bluetui</code> from the <a href="https://archlinux.org/packages/extra/x86_64/bluetui/" rel="nofollow">extra repository</a>:</p>

<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🐧 Gentoo</h3><a id="user-content--gentoo" aria-label="Permalink: 🐧 Gentoo" href="#-gentoo"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">You can install <code>bluetui</code> from the <a href="https://gpo.zugaina.org/net-wireless/bluetui" rel="nofollow">lamdness Gentoo Overlay</a>:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="sudo eselect repository enable lamdness
sudo emaint -r lamdness sync
sudo emerge -av net-wireless/bluetui"><pre>sudo eselect repository <span>enable</span> lamdness
sudo emaint -r lamdness sync
sudo emerge -av net-wireless/bluetui</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🧰 X-CMD</h3><a id="user-content--x-cmd" aria-label="Permalink: 🧰 X-CMD" href="#-x-cmd"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If you are a user of <a href="https://x-cmd.com/" rel="nofollow">x-cmd</a>, you can run:</p>

<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">⚒️ Build from source</h3><a id="user-content-️-build-from-source" aria-label="Permalink: ⚒️ Build from source" href="#️-build-from-source"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Run the following command:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/pythops/bluetui
cd bluetui
cargo build --release"><pre>git clone https://github.com/pythops/bluetui
<span>cd</span> bluetui
cargo build --release</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">This will produce an executable file at <code>target/release/bluetui</code> that you can copy to a directory in your <code>$PATH</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🪄 Usage</h2><a id="user-content--usage" aria-label="Permalink: 🪄 Usage" href="#-usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Global</h3><a id="user-content-global" aria-label="Permalink: Global" href="#global"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><code>Tab</code>: Switch between different sections.</p>
<p dir="auto"><code>j</code> or <code>Down</code> : Scroll down.</p>
<p dir="auto"><code>k</code> or <code>Up</code>: Scroll up.</p>
<p dir="auto"><code>s</code>: Start/Stop scanning.</p>
<p dir="auto"><code>?</code>: Show help.</p>
<p dir="auto"><code>esc</code>: Dismiss the help pop-up.</p>
<p dir="auto"><code>ctrl+c</code> or <code>q</code>: Quit the app.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Adapters</h3><a id="user-content-adapters" aria-label="Permalink: Adapters" href="#adapters"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><code>p</code>: Enable/Disable the pairing.</p>
<p dir="auto"><code>o</code>: Power on/off the adapter.</p>
<p dir="auto"><code>d</code>: Enable/Disable the discovery.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Paired devices</h3><a id="user-content-paired-devices" aria-label="Permalink: Paired devices" href="#paired-devices"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><code>u</code>: Unpair the device.</p>
<p dir="auto"><code>Space or Enter</code>: Connect/Disconnect the device.</p>
<p dir="auto"><code>t</code>: Trust/Untrust the device.</p>
<p dir="auto"><code>e</code>: Rename the device.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">New devices</h3><a id="user-content-new-devices" aria-label="Permalink: New devices" href="#new-devices"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><code>Space or Enter</code>: Pair the device.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Custom keybindings</h2><a id="user-content-custom-keybindings" aria-label="Permalink: Custom keybindings" href="#custom-keybindings"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Keybindings can be customized in the default config file location <code>$HOME/.config/bluetui/config.toml</code> or from a custom path with <code>-c</code></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# Possible values: &quot;Legacy&quot;, &quot;Start&quot;, &quot;End&quot;, &quot;Center&quot;, &quot;SpaceAround&quot;, &quot;SpaceBetween&quot;
layout = &quot;SpaceAround&quot;

# Window width
# Possible values: &quot;auto&quot; or a positive integer
width = &quot;auto&quot;

toggle_scanning = &quot;s&quot;

[adapter]
toggle_pairing = &quot;p&quot;
toggle_power = &quot;o&quot;
toggle_discovery = &quot;d&quot;

[paired_device]
unpair = &quot;u&quot;
toggle_trust = &quot;t&quot;
rename = &quot;e&quot;"><pre><span><span>#</span> Possible values: "Legacy", "Start", "End", "Center", "SpaceAround", "SpaceBetween"</span>
<span>layout</span> = <span><span>"</span>SpaceAround<span>"</span></span>

<span><span>#</span> Window width</span>
<span><span>#</span> Possible values: "auto" or a positive integer</span>
<span>width</span> = <span><span>"</span>auto<span>"</span></span>

<span>toggle_scanning</span> = <span><span>"</span>s<span>"</span></span>

[<span>adapter</span>]
<span>toggle_pairing</span> = <span><span>"</span>p<span>"</span></span>
<span>toggle_power</span> = <span><span>"</span>o<span>"</span></span>
<span>toggle_discovery</span> = <span><span>"</span>d<span>"</span></span>

[<span>paired_device</span>]
<span>unpair</span> = <span><span>"</span>u<span>"</span></span>
<span>toggle_trust</span> = <span><span>"</span>t<span>"</span></span>
<span>rename</span> = <span><span>"</span>e<span>"</span></span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">⚖️ License</h2><a id="user-content-️-license" aria-label="Permalink: ⚖️ License" href="#️-license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">GPLv3</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">✍️ Credits</h2><a id="user-content-️-credits" aria-label="Permalink: ✍️ Credits" href="#️-credits"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Bluetui logo: <a href="https://github.com/Bugg4">Marco Bulgarelli</a></p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google Removed 749M Anna's Archive URLs from Its Search Results (344 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://torrentfreak.com/google-removed-749-million-annas-archive-urls-from-its-search-results/</link>
            <guid>45816968</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 23:11:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://torrentfreak.com/google-removed-749-million-annas-archive-urls-from-its-search-results/">https://torrentfreak.com/google-removed-749-million-annas-archive-urls-from-its-search-results/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45816968">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

          <p>    
                 <!-- Breadcrumb NavXT 7.4.1 -->
<span property="itemListElement" typeof="ListItem"><a property="item" typeof="WebPage" title="Go to TorrentFreak." href="https://torrentfreak.com/"><span property="name">Home</span></a><meta property="position" content="1"></span> &gt; <span property="itemListElement" typeof="ListItem"><a property="item" typeof="WebPage" title="Go to the Anti-Piracy category archives." href="https://torrentfreak.com/category/anti-piracy/"><span property="name">Anti-Piracy</span></a><meta property="position" content="2"></span> &gt; <span></span>
	</p>

        <p>
                      <span> </span>
                    Popular shadow library Anna's Archive has become a top target for copyright holders. In just three years, publishers and authors have prompted Google to remove 749 million of the site's URLs from its search results. Despite this immense takedown campaign, which accounts for 5% of all URLs reported to Google on copyright grounds, the site itself remains easily discoverable through the search engine.
        </p>
      </div><div>
        <p><picture loading="lazy" decoding="async">
<source type="image/webp" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/archives.png.webp 547w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/archives-300x243.png.webp 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px">
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://torrentfreak.com/images/archives.png" alt="archive" width="300" height="243" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/archives.png 547w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/archives-300x243.png 300w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/archives-150x121.png 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px">
</picture>
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anna%27s_Archive">Anna’s Archive</a> is a meta-search engine for shadow libraries that allows users to find pirated books and other related sources.</p>
<p>The site launched in <a href="https://torrentfreak.com/annas-archive-opens-the-door-to-z-library-and-other-pirate-libraries-221118/">the fall of 2022</a>, just days after Z-Library was targeted in a U.S. criminal crackdown, to ensure continued availability of ‘free’ books and articles to the broader public. </p>
<p>In the three years since then, Anna’s Archive has built up quite the track record. The site has been <a href="https://torrentfreak.com/german-pirate-site-blockades-target-annas-archive-fitgirl-and-rpg-only/">blocked</a> in various countries, was <a href="https://torrentfreak.com/lawsuit-accuses-annas-archive-of-hacking-worldcat-stealing-2-2-tb-data-240207/">sued in the U.S.</a> after it scraped WorldCat, and actively <a href="https://torrentfreak.com/annas-archive-urges-ai-copyright-overhaul-to-protect-national-security-250201/">provides assistance to AI researchers</a> who want to use its library for model training. </p>
<p>Despite legal pressure, Annas-archive.org and the related .li and .se domains remain operational. This is a thorn in the side of publishers who are actively trying to take the site down. In the absence of options to target the site directly, they ask third-party intermediaries such as Google to lend a hand. </p>
<h2>749 Million URLs</h2>
<p>Google and other major search engines allow rightsholders to request removal of allegedly infringing URLs. The aim is to ensure that pirate sites no longer show up in search results when people search for books, movies, music, or other copyrighted content. </p>
<p>The Pirate Bay, for example, has been a popular target; Google has removed more than 4.2 million thepiratebay.org URLs over the years in response to copyright holder complaints. While this sounds like a sizable number, it pales in comparison to the volume of takedowns targeting Anna’s Archive.</p>
<p>Google’s <a href="https://transparencyreport.google.com/copyright/overview">transparency report</a> reveals that rightsholders asked Google to remove 784 million URLs, divided over the three main Anna’s Archive domains. A small number were rejected, mainly because Google didn’t index the reported links, resulting in 749 million confirmed removals. </p>
<p>The comparison to sites such as The Pirate Bay isn’t fair, as Anna’s Archive has many more pages in its archive and uses multiple country-specific subdomains. This means that there’s simply more content to take down. That said, in terms of takedown activity, the site’s three domain names clearly dwarf all pirate competition. </p>
<center><em>Top targeted domains (Google)</em></center><br><center><picture loading="lazy" decoding="async">
<source type="image/webp" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/takedown-domains.png.webp 1045w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/takedown-domains-300x192.png.webp 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px">
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://torrentfreak.com/images/takedown-domains.png" alt="Top targeted domains (Google)" width="600" height="384" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/takedown-domains.png 1045w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/takedown-domains-300x192.png 300w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/takedown-domains-600x384.png 600w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/takedown-domains-150x96.png 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px">
</picture>
</center>
<h2>5% of All Google Takedowns, Ever</h2>
<p>Since Google published its first transparency report in May 2012, rightsholders have flagged 15.1 billion allegedly infringing URLs. That’s a staggering number, but the fact that 5% of the total targeted Anna’s Archive URLs is remarkable.</p>
<p>Penguin Random House and John Wiley &amp; Sons are the most active publishers targeting the site, but they are certainly not alone. According to Google data, more than 1,000 authors or publishers have sent DMCA notices targeting Anna’s Archive domains.</p>
<p>Yet, there appears to be no end in sight. Rightsholders are reporting roughly 10 million new URLs per week for the popular piracy library, so there is no shortage of content to report. </p>
<p>With these DMCA takedown notices, publishers are aiming to make it as difficult as possible for people to find books on the site using Google. This works, as many URLs are now delisted while others are actively being demoted by the search engine for book-related queries.</p>
<p>That said, the Anna’s Archive website is certainly not unfindable. Searching for the site’s name in Google still shows the main domain as the top search result. </p>
<center><em>Search: Anna’s Archive</em></center><br><center><picture loading="lazy" decoding="async">
<source type="image/webp" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/annasgoogle.png.webp 1136w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/annasgoogle-300x184.png.webp 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px">
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://torrentfreak.com/images/annasgoogle.png" alt="Search: Anna's Archive" width="600" height="369" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/annasgoogle.png 1136w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/annasgoogle-300x184.png 300w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/annasgoogle-600x369.png 600w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/annasgoogle-150x92.png 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px">
</picture>
</center>

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[UPS plane crashes near Louisville airport (293 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cbsnews.com/news/ups-plane-crash-louisville-kentucky/</link>
            <guid>45816963</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 23:10:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/ups-plane-crash-louisville-kentucky/">https://www.cbsnews.com/news/ups-plane-crash-louisville-kentucky/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45816963">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                    
                                                                                                                                
                                                                            
<article id="article-0" data-index="0" data-path="/news/ups-plane-crash-louisville-kentucky/">
  <!-- lil observer -->
      <span></span>
    




  <div id="article-header" data-sort-time="1762315786000" data-update-time="1762315786000">
    <header>
                                      
          

      

      
      
      <div>

                
  

          <p>
            <time datetime="2025-11-04T23:02:00-0500">Updated on:  November 4, 2025 / 11:02 PM EST</time>
            / CBS News
          </p>
        </div>

    </header>
  </div>


  <section>
    <p>At least seven people were killed and several others injured after a UPS plane crashed shortly after takeoff near the Louisville International Airport on Tuesday, officials said. &nbsp;</p><p>The number of fatalities is expected to increase, Kentucky Gov. Andy Beshear <a href="https://x.com/GovAndyBeshear/status/1985908287422767542" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">wrote</a> on social media Tuesday night. At least 11 people were injured, officials said earlier.</p><p>Louisville Mayor Craig Greenberg confirmed at a news conference Tuesday night that at least four people had been killed on the ground.</p><p>UPS Flight 2976 crashed around 5:15 p.m. local time after it departed from the Louisville airport, according to the Federal Aviation Administration. The aircraft was headed to Daniel K. Inouye International Airport in Honolulu, Hawaii, when it went down three miles south of the airfield, Louisville airport public safety officer Jonathan Biven said at a news conference.</p><p>Beshear said there was no hazardous cargo onboard the plane that would create environmental issues around the crash site, but urged residents to follow any shelter-in-place orders.</p>

    

<p>The Louisville Metro Police Department described the scene as active with "fire and debris," warning residents to stay away from Fern Valley and Grade Lane, an intersection located on the south side of the airport, which serves as the hub of UPS. More than 100 firefighters responded to the crash and were still battling hot spots as of Tuesday night, Greenberg said. Louisville Fire Chief Brian O'Neill noted the fire was "almost entirely contained."&nbsp;</p><p>O'Neill said the fire had been extinguished enough to allow a formal grid search for any possible victims in the area.</p><p>Videos of the crash showed the aircraft partially on fire as it sped down the runway before it burst into flames.</p><figure>
    
                                    
      <span><img src="https://assets2.cbsnewsstatic.com/hub/i/r/2025/11/04/6fdbb254-e6f5-4657-a830-ddc300fb8eff/thumbnail/620x349/767c42b8b1f55d5c7f4fd7c777c006e7/wlky-louisville-plane-crash-rem326-frame-8785.jpg#" alt="Aerial footage shows the aftermath of a plane crash in Louisville, Kentucky, Nov. 4, 2025. " height="349" width="620" srcset="https://assets2.cbsnewsstatic.com/hub/i/r/2025/11/04/6fdbb254-e6f5-4657-a830-ddc300fb8eff/thumbnail/620x349/767c42b8b1f55d5c7f4fd7c777c006e7/wlky-louisville-plane-crash-rem326-frame-8785.jpg 1x, https://assets2.cbsnewsstatic.com/hub/i/r/2025/11/04/6fdbb254-e6f5-4657-a830-ddc300fb8eff/thumbnail/1240x698/9e0976f3d25998f92741dad25ba42f1e/wlky-louisville-plane-crash-rem326-frame-8785.jpg 2x" loading="lazy"></span>

      
          <figcaption>
        
        
                  <span>Aerial footage shows the aftermath of a plane crash in Louisville, Kentucky, Nov. 4, 2025.</span>
        
                  <span>
            
                WLKY-TV

                          </span>
              </figcaption>
      </figure>
<p>A shelter-in-place order has been reduced to a one-mile radius of the crash site, authorities said. The police department also urged those in the area to turn off any air intake systems as soon as possible due to the smoke in the area.</p>

    
    

<p>"Anybody who has seen the images and the video knows how violent this crash is, and there are a lot of families that are gonna be waiting and wondering for a period of time. We're going to try to get them that information as fast as we can," Beshear said.</p><p>UPS said in a statement that it was notified of an incident involving one of its aircraft. Three UPS crewmembers were on board, the company said. It didn't immediately provide more details.</p><p>"We do not at the moment have the status of the crew," Beshear said. "Watching that video, I think we're all very, very worried about them."</p><p>Businesses in the area were heavily impacted by the crash, including Kentucky Petroleum Recycling and Grade A Auto Parts, the governor said.</p><p>All arriving and departing flights at the Louisville airport were temporarily suspended. The airport will remain closed Tuesday night, but is expected to reopen Wednesday morning, Greenberg said.</p><figure>
    
                                    
      <span><img src="https://assets3.cbsnewsstatic.com/hub/i/r/2025/11/04/c7cb0f24-0d09-4d6b-9b8c-f5210b353dc8/thumbnail/620x349/38b28c02652e44ac5b403c2ba36c603e/wlky-louisville-plane-crash-rem326-frame-31344.jpg#" alt="Firefighters are seen in aerial footage battling a massive blaze after a plane crash in Louisville, Kentucky, Nov. 4, 2025. " height="349" width="620" srcset="https://assets3.cbsnewsstatic.com/hub/i/r/2025/11/04/c7cb0f24-0d09-4d6b-9b8c-f5210b353dc8/thumbnail/620x349/38b28c02652e44ac5b403c2ba36c603e/wlky-louisville-plane-crash-rem326-frame-31344.jpg 1x, https://assets3.cbsnewsstatic.com/hub/i/r/2025/11/04/c7cb0f24-0d09-4d6b-9b8c-f5210b353dc8/thumbnail/1240x698/11f9b7018be07db68627e04f3e66ea2e/wlky-louisville-plane-crash-rem326-frame-31344.jpg 2x" loading="lazy"></span>

      
          <figcaption>
        
        
                  <span>Firefighters are seen in aerial footage battling a massive blaze after a plane crash in Louisville, Kentucky, Nov. 4, 2025.</span>
        
                  <span>
            
                WLKY-TV

                          </span>
              </figcaption>
      </figure>
<p>According to preliminary flight data from FlightRadar24, the plane appeared to hit 175 feet in altitude briefly after takeoff. It would have been full of fuel for the flight to Hawaii, which likely led to the significant fire as seen from <a href="https://www.wlky.com/article/plane-crash-explosion-louisville-airport/69255042" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">CBS affiliate WLKY-TV</a>'s chopper.</p><p>The three-engine McDonnell Douglas MD-11 was manufactured in 1991, according to FAA data.</p>

    
    

<p>It was carrying approximately 38,000 gallons of fuel, which weighs about 233,000 pounds, Louisville Fire Chief Brian O'Neill said. The area affected by the crash is about a city block wide, he said, but it has been difficult to contain the fire due to surrounding hazardous materials.&nbsp;</p><p>Greenberg urged any residents who find debris on their property not to touch it, and instead report it through a website that should be live by Wednesday.</p><figure>
    
                                    
      <span><img src="https://assets1.cbsnewsstatic.com/hub/i/r/2025/11/04/55579509-b29a-40b0-a811-b297fe5b82e5/thumbnail/620x413/b86d154bf882a320c21b3cd3d3e58aec/ap25308836563310.jpg#" alt="APTOPIX Louisville UPS Plane Crash " height="413" width="620" srcset="https://assets1.cbsnewsstatic.com/hub/i/r/2025/11/04/55579509-b29a-40b0-a811-b297fe5b82e5/thumbnail/620x413/b86d154bf882a320c21b3cd3d3e58aec/ap25308836563310.jpg 1x, https://assets3.cbsnewsstatic.com/hub/i/r/2025/11/04/55579509-b29a-40b0-a811-b297fe5b82e5/thumbnail/1240x826/72d1b41d81f4784488537fd3625cf9e8/ap25308836563310.jpg 2x" loading="lazy"></span>

      
          <figcaption>
        
        
                  <span>A fireball erupts near airport property after reports of a plane crash at the Louisville International Airport on Tuesday, Nov. 4, 2025, in Kentucky.</span>
        
                  <span>
            
                Jon Cherry / AP

                          </span>
              </figcaption>
      </figure>
<p>The crash is where <a href="https://www.jobs-ups.com/us/en/ups-worldport" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">UPS Worldport</a>, an international air hub for the parcel service, is located. UPS said it was halting package sorting operations at Worldport on Tuesday night.</p><p>"This is a UPS town," Louisville Metro Councilwoman Betsy Ruhe, whose district is part of the crash site, said during the news conference Tuesday night. "We all know somebody who works at UPS, and they're all texting their friends, their family, trying to make sure everyone is safe. Sadly, some of those texts are probably going to go unanswered."</p><p>The 5.2 million-square-foot facility processes more than 400,000 packages an hour and is home to 20,000 UPS workers and 300 daily flights, according to the company.</p><p>"My team and I are closely monitoring the plane crash near Louisville Muhammad Ali International Airport," Kentucky Sen. Rand Paul said. "We continue to pray for the safety of the aircrew, everyone in the area, and for the first-responders on the scene."</p><p>The National Transportation Safety Board will lead the investigation into the crash. A team of 28 investigators is expected to arrive Wednesday, Greenberg said.</p>

    
    

<p>All public schools in the Jefferson County School District, the largest school district in Kentucky with a little under 100,000 students, will be closed Wednesday, Greenberg said.</p>

    <section>
        
            <p>
                                        
                                  <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/team/kris-van-cleave/" data-invalid-url-rewritten-http="">Kris  Van Cleave</a>
                  
        contributed to this report.
    </p>
  
    </section>

                    
        
  
          
  <!-- data-recirc-source="queryly" -->
  



  
    
    <section>
  <h2>In:</h2>
  <ul>
          <li><a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/tag/louisville-international-airport/">Louisville International Airport</a></li>
          <li><a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/tag/kentucky/">Kentucky</a></li>
          <li><a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/tag/ups/">UPS</a></li>
      </ul>
</section>
  </section>

  

  
  </article>
            

                                                                                            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mr Tiff (881 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/mr-tiff/</link>
            <guid>45816853</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 22:57:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/mr-tiff/">https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/mr-tiff/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45816853">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <p>For as long as I have published my books, one of my overarching goals was to give credit to those who actually invented the hardware and software that we use. </p><p>I have spent 10,000+ hours to create an&nbsp;accurate record of their work but I'm not complaining. The 'as-close-to-possible' truth of invention by individuals or teams meant identifying the work, educating myself, writing questions, and sending emails. And after that process, I set up a chat because it all gets down to talking to someone on the other side of the world, about something that happened 30 or 40 years ago. </p><p>If the invention involves a team, I try to interview more than one person, so I can cross-check the facts. Not to call anyone out, it’s just that, given time, we all forget the facts. And everyone adds their personal take. It’s because of that, for example, that I know the English musician Peter Gabriel really did visit Apple's research labs as they tested the Apple Sound Chip, and gave the team his personal approval to use the song 'Red Rain' for the Macintosh II launch. Wil Oxford, Steve Perlman, Mike Potel, Mark Lentczner and Steve Milne told me so.</p><p>As I was wrapping up Version 2.3 of <a href="https://books.by/john-buck/inventing-the-future?ref=inventingthefuture.ghost.io" rel="noreferrer">Inventing the Future</a>, I spoke with Steve M and Mark about the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Audio_Interchange_File_Format?ref=inventingthefuture.ghost.io" rel="noreferrer">AIFF</a> (Audio Interchange File Format) audio standard that they built around the same time as their VIP visit. They did so as professional programmers, amateur musicians and electronic music experts. Milne and Lentczner knew users needed a standard file format to make their work lives easier and to fend off confusion in the nascent MIDI marketplace. But it didn't exist. So Steve and Mark consulted with users and manufacturers in the Apple cafeteria after hours. This work is interesting on its own but it also underpinned other research. The AIFF, Apple Sound Chip, and MIDI Manager work scaffolded QuickTime and its extensible video formats and programs in 1991. Senior engineer Toby Farrand told me:</p><p><em>Audio drove the development of QuickTime more than anything.</em></p><p>So who or what drove the development of AIFF?</p><p>Steve and Mark referred me to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interchange_File_Format?ref=inventingthefuture.ghost.io" rel="noreferrer">IFF</a> (Interchange File Format&nbsp;(IFF) and the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TIFF?ref=inventingthefuture.ghost.io" rel="noreferrer">TIFF</a> (Tag Image File Format) that were built before AIFF, in 1985 and 1986 respectively. These file formats were the benchmark for open media standards. My search pivoted, as it always does, to understand those inventions. I expected to be able to find the engineer or engineers names, track them down and interview them. It has worked around 100 times before. </p><p>Jerry Morrison created IFF while working at Electronic Arts and then went to Apple, where he liaised with the AIFF team. I could easily background his work.</p><figure><img src="https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/2025/10/Screenshot-2025-10-29-at-10.56.52---am-1.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1760" height="472" srcset="https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/Screenshot-2025-10-29-at-10.56.52---am-1.png 600w, https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/Screenshot-2025-10-29-at-10.56.52---am-1.png 1000w, https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/Screenshot-2025-10-29-at-10.56.52---am-1.png 1600w, https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/2025/10/Screenshot-2025-10-29-at-10.56.52---am-1.png 1760w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>So I turned my attention to TIFF, built initially as an image standard for desktop publishing. TIFF was able to store monochrome, grayscale, and color images, alongside metadata such as size, compression algorithms, and color space information. In many ways, it was a lot like AIFF so I was keen to know more. But I couldn't find a TIFF creator. No matter how I enquired, Aldus created TIFF. </p><p>To be clear, while a search for AIFF will offer up a company (Apple) not a person, I was able to&nbsp;find Milne and Lentczner in part because of their unique names and because Apple publicised the AIFF work and those publications are archived. </p><p>All I had was Aldus, an American company that created desktop publishing with the help of Apple and Adobe. In fact, Paul Brainerd, the cofounder of Aldus coined the term 'desktop publishing' to quickly explain the technicality of what they were doing to potential investors. But Aldus and their seminal product, PageMaker, are long <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1994/03/16/business/company-news-adobe-and-aldus-plan-a-500-million-merger.html?ref=inventingthefuture.ghost.io" rel="noreferrer">gone</a>, and there were no breadcrumbs for TIFF's creation.  </p><p>Finally, after a day-long trawl through MacWeek back issues, I found Steve Carlson. (below)</p><figure><img src="https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/2025/10/carslonmacweek.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1280" height="663" srcset="https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/carslonmacweek.png 600w, https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/carslonmacweek.png 1000w, https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/2025/10/carslonmacweek.png 1280w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Then I ran a similar length search through the Computer History Museum’s amazing Oral Histories transcriptions.&nbsp;Brainerd mentioned Carlson's name in an interview. (below)</p><figure><img src="https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/2025/10/carslonchm.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1096" height="314" srcset="https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/carslonchm.png 600w, https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/carslonchm.png 1000w, https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/2025/10/carslonchm.png 1096w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>But it was too brief an explanation so I kept looking. Then the trail went cold. </p><p>And that was because, folks had misspelt his name when quoting&nbsp;him and then that was copied into magazines, and reviews and so forth.&nbsp;Brainerd's CHM interview transcript was wrong. But I didn’t know that. </p><p>I just kept looking for Steve Carlson. </p><p>I found other inventors because they had unique middle or last names or by random methods such as searching glider pilot licences in the Napa Valley after a tip from a former colleague that 'so and so' was a pilot in retirement. I had no tips, no links, nothing.</p><p>Why couldn’t I find Steve Carlson? </p><p>All the while, the answer was right under my nose. I had downloaded the final Aldus TIFF specifications document, hoping to find the author’s name. However, the name is seemingly written in white text on white paper - making it invisible. What? </p><p>See below where I have highlighted the region with a blue block over the text.</p><figure><img src="https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/2025/10/TIFF-blue.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="948" height="1234" srcset="https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/TIFF-blue.png 600w, https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/2025/10/TIFF-blue.png 948w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>For a reason I can’t recall, I downloaded a plain text version and typed in Carlson to see if he was mentioned, but I must have paused at ‘Carls...' and the search functionality automatically filled in the rest. Suddenly I was staring at:</p><p><em>Author/Editor/Arbitrator: Steve Carlsen.</em></p><p>‘Carls-EN’</p><p>A quick trip to Google patents, and a search for <em>Steve Carlsen, Stephen Carlsen.</em>  Bingo! Stephen E. Carlsen’s patents at Aldus (and Adobe) in Issaquah, WA.</p><figure><img src="https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/2025/10/Screenshot-2025-10-27-at-5.08.25---pm.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1066" height="542" srcset="https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/Screenshot-2025-10-27-at-5.08.25---pm.png 600w, https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/Screenshot-2025-10-27-at-5.08.25---pm.png 1000w, https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/2025/10/Screenshot-2025-10-27-at-5.08.25---pm.png 1066w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>I checked the geography, as most folks of a certain age do not stray far from the addresses filed in their patents, and typed Stephen’s correctly spelled surname into the online US White Pages for Washington State. There was ‘a’ Stephen Carlsen listed in a retirement&nbsp;village in WA. His age matched, but there were no public facing email addresses. </p><p>I searched bulletin boards on the topic of TIFF, as I had found a former Apple engineer that way. Don had picked an abbreviation of his initials and numbers to post on BBS in his college days and then carried that same combination into adulthood. Many of us did. I took a punt pasting his unique prefix into hotmail, gmail etc. and found Don and interviewed him, but - Stephen Carlsen did not show up in a BBS. So, no email to try.</p><p>My ‘last straw' method for finding someone is a stamped envelope. I wrote, printed and mailed a one-page letter to Stephen's listed address, and crossed my fingers.&nbsp;Four months later he popped up in my email. </p><p>It was a surprise and a relief. We swapped a few emails, and he confirmed the TIFF catalyst story. For Stephen it was 'no big deal'. Once he had built the initial TIFF, Aldus needed to convince 3rd party developers and scanner manufacturers to agree to TIFF as a standard.</p><p><em>“We had to define and promote an industry standard for storing and processing scanned images,&nbsp;so that we wouldn't have to write import filters for every model of every scanner that would soon&nbsp;be entering the budding desktop scanner market."</em></p><p>Stephen himself did much of the evangelizing as Paul Brainerd later pointed out:</p><p><em>“(Steve) developed the standard, and then we went out and promoted it in a series of meetings with specific companies - as well as some workshops we ran in Seattle and the Bay Area during the Seybold shows and the MacWorld shows.”</em> </p><p>I sent Stephen a draft of what I had written and he sent a prompt reply saying -&nbsp;<em>‘Looks good’.</em></p><p>I followed up asking him how he ended up at a tiny startup in Seattle called Aldus. </p><p><em>At that time, I was interviewing for a graphics position at Boeing Computer Services in Seattle, and noticed a small wanted ad that sounded really interesting, and seemed to be an excellent match for my background and interests. I interviewed with Paul and the 5-person mostly-ex-Atex engineering team, and I was hired.</em></p><p>Out of curiosity I put Stephen's email address, now that I knew it, into a Duck Duck search and found him helping people online with TIFF queries long after Aldus had been acquired by Adobe. He also contributed to a Google Group called tiffcentral. </p><p>Having interviewed so many people across more than a decade, I’ve got pretty good at judging those who would like to talk or type, those who are verbose and those that are not. I knew Stephen had said what he was going to say. I added his pioneering work on TIFF to the AIFF story and moved on. </p><p>Two years had flown by when I received an email yesterday.&nbsp;His ex-wife Peggy found my paper letter and wrote to me. Stephen passed away earlier this year.</p><p><em>Thank you for your interest in and support of Stephen’s brilliant work creating TIFF. I’m not surprised Stephen didn’t finish corresponding with you, as he had begun to struggle with using his&nbsp;computer and phone. Some days were better than others for him, but he began to lose touch with people&nbsp;during those months you were reaching out to him. He was a humble man, and I guess never pushed to be recognized, although I believe those who worked&nbsp;with him knew the truth.&nbsp;His last week was in my home, where he was never left alone.</em></p><p>Peggy finished the email with,&nbsp;<em>‘I called him Mr TIFF up to his last moment.'</em></p><p>The 10,000+ hours of book research disappeared in an instant. As sad as it was, I could see clearly that all of my work was worth it. Every single second. Because of this email. </p><p>Mr TIFF.</p><p>Last night, as everyone in my house went to sleep, I took a deep breath and edited the Wikipedia page for TIFF, the Tag Image File Format.&nbsp;</p><p>It no longer reads&nbsp;<em>‘created by Aldus’</em>, it reads&nbsp;<em>‘…created by Stephen Carlsen, an engineer at Aldus'</em></p><figure><img src="https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/2025/10/TIFF-Fixed.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="2000" height="1228" srcset="https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/TIFF-Fixed.png 600w, https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/TIFF-Fixed.png 1000w, https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/TIFF-Fixed.png 1600w, https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/content/images/2025/10/TIFF-Fixed.png 2004w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure>
        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Grayskull: A tiny computer vision library in C for embedded systems, etc. (159 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/zserge/grayskull</link>
            <guid>45816673</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 22:35:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/zserge/grayskull">https://github.com/zserge/grayskull</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45816673">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🏰 Grayskull</h2><a id="user-content--grayskull" aria-label="Permalink: 🏰 Grayskull" href="#-grayskull"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Grayskull is a minimalist, dependency-free computer vision library designed for microcontrollers and other resource-constrained devices. It focuses on <strong>grayscale</strong> images and provides modern, practical algorithms that fit in a few kilobytes of code. Single-header design, integer-based operations, pure C99.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Features</h2><a id="user-content-features" aria-label="Permalink: Features" href="#features"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Image operations: copy, crop, resize (bilinear), downsample</li>
<li>Filtering: blur, Sobel edges, thresholding (global, Otsu, adaptive)</li>
<li>Morphology: erosion, dilation</li>
<li>Geometry: connected components, perspective warp</li>
<li>Features: FAST/ORB keypoints and descriptors (object tracking)</li>
<li>Local binary patterns: LBP cascades to detect faces, vehicles etc</li>
<li>Utilities: PGM read/write</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">As usual, no dependencies, no dynamic memory allocation, no C++, no surprises. Just a single header file under 1KLOC.</p>
<p dir="auto">Check out the <a href="https://github.com/zserge/grayskull/blob/main/examples">examples</a> folder for more!</p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://zserge.com/grayskull/" rel="nofollow">Online demo</a>: try Grayskull in your browser.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Quickstart</h2><a id="user-content-quickstart" aria-label="Permalink: Quickstart" href="#quickstart"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="#include &quot;grayskull.h&quot;

struct gs_image img = gs_read_pgm(&quot;input.pgm&quot;);
struct gs_image blurred = gs_alloc(img.w, img.h);
struct gs_image binary = gs_alloc(img.w, img.h);

gs_blur(blurred, img, 2);
gs_threshold(binary, blurred, gs_otsu_theshold(blurred));

gs_write_pgm(binary, &quot;output.pgm&quot;);
gs_free(img);
gs_free(blurred);
gs_free(binary);"><pre><span>#include</span> <span>"grayskull.h"</span>

<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>img</span> <span>=</span> <span>gs_read_pgm</span>(<span>"input.pgm"</span>);
<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>blurred</span> <span>=</span> <span>gs_alloc</span>(<span>img</span>.<span>w</span>, <span>img</span>.<span>h</span>);
<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>binary</span> <span>=</span> <span>gs_alloc</span>(<span>img</span>.<span>w</span>, <span>img</span>.<span>h</span>);

<span>gs_blur</span>(<span>blurred</span>, <span>img</span>, <span>2</span>);
<span>gs_threshold</span>(<span>binary</span>, <span>blurred</span>, <span>gs_otsu_theshold</span>(<span>blurred</span>));

<span>gs_write_pgm</span>(<span>binary</span>, <span>"output.pgm"</span>);
<span>gs_free</span>(<span>img</span>);
<span>gs_free</span>(<span>blurred</span>);
<span>gs_free</span>(<span>binary</span>);</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><em>Note that <code>gs_alloc</code>/<code>gs_free</code> are optional helpers; you can allocate image pixel buffers any way you like.</em></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">API Reference</h2><a id="user-content-api-reference" aria-label="Permalink: API Reference" href="#api-reference"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="struct gs_image { unsigned w, h; uint8_t *data; };
struct gs_rect { unsigned x, y, w, h; }; // ROI
struct gs_point { unsigned x, y; }; // corners

uint8_t gs_get(struct gs_image img, unsigned x, unsigned y);
void gs_set(struct gs_image img, unsigned x, unsigned y, uint8_t value);
void gs_crop(struct gs_image dst, struct gs_image src, struct gs_rect roi);
void gs_copy(struct gs_image dst, struct gs_image src);
void gs_resize(struct gs_image dst, struct gs_image src);
void gs_downsample(struct gs_image dst, struct gs_image src);

// Thresholding
void gs_histogram(struct gs_image img, unsigned hist[256]);
void gs_threshold(struct gs_image img, uint8_t threshold);
uint8_t gs_otsu_threshold(struct gs_image img);
void gs_adaptive_threshold(struct gs_image dst, struct gs_image src, unsigned radius, int c);

// Filters
void gs_blur(struct gs_image dst, struct gs_image src, unsigned radius);
void gs_erode(struct gs_image dst, struct gs_image src);
void gs_dilate(struct gs_image dst, struct gs_image src);
void gs_sobel(struct gs_image dst, struct gs_image src);

// Blobs (connected components) and contours
typedef uint16_t gs_label;
struct gs_blob { gs_label label; unsigned area; struct gs_rect box; struct gs_point centroid; };
struct gs_contour { struct gs_rect box; struct gs_point start; unsigned length; };
unsigned gs_blobs(struct gs_image img, gs_label *labels, struct gs_blob *blobs, unsigned nblobs);
void gs_blob_corners(struct gs_image img, gs_label *labels, struct gs_blob *b, struct gs_point c[4]);
void gs_perspective_correct(struct gs_image dst, struct gs_image src, struct gs_point c[4]);
void gs_trace_contour(struct gs_image img, struct gs_image visited, struct gs_contour *c);

// FAST/ORB
struct gs_keypoint { struct gs_point pt; unsigned response; float angle; uint32_t descriptor[8]; };
struct gs_match { unsigned idx1, idx2; unsigned distance; };
unsigned gs_fast(struct gs_image img, struct gs_image scoremap, struct gs_keypoint *kps, unsigned nkps, unsigned threshold);
float gs_compute_orientation(struct gs_image img, unsigned x, unsigned y, unsigned r);
void gs_brief_descriptor(struct gs_image img, struct gs_keypoint *kp);
unsigned gs_orb_extract(struct gs_image img, struct gs_keypoint *kps, unsigned nkps, unsigned threshold, uint8_t *scoremap_buffer);
unsigned gs_match_orb(const struct gs_keypoint *kps1, unsigned n1, const struct gs_keypoint *kps2, unsigned n2, struct gs_match *matches, unsigned max_matches, float max_distance);

// LBP cascades
struct gs_lbp_cascade { uint16_t window_w, window_h; uint16_t nfeatures, nweaks, nstages; const int8_t *features; /* [nfeatures * 4] */ const uint16_t *weak_feature_idx; const float *weak_left_val, *weak_right_val; const uint16_t *weak_subset_offset, *weak_num_subsets; const int32_t *subsets; const uint16_t *stage_weak_start, *stage_nweaks; const float *stage_threshold; };
void gs_integral(struct gs_image src, unsigned *ii);
unsigned gs_lbp_window(const struct gs_lbp_cascade *c, const unsigned *ii, unsigned iw, unsigned ih, int x, int y, float scale);
unsigned gs_lbp_detect(const struct gs_lbp_cascade *c, const unsigned *ii, unsigned iw, unsigned ih, struct gs_rect *rects, unsigned max_rects, float scale_factor, float min_scale, float max_scale, int step);

// Optional:
struct gs_image gs_alloc(unsigned w, unsigned h);
void gs_free(struct gs_image img);
struct gs_image gs_read_pgm(const char *path);
int gs_write_pgm(struct gs_image img, const char *path);"><pre><span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> { <span>unsigned</span> <span>w</span>, <span>h</span>; <span>uint8_t</span> <span>*</span><span>data</span>; };
<span>struct</span> <span>gs_rect</span> { <span>unsigned</span> <span>x</span>, <span>y</span>, <span>w</span>, <span>h</span>; }; <span>// ROI</span>
<span>struct</span> <span>gs_point</span> { <span>unsigned</span> <span>x</span>, <span>y</span>; }; <span>// corners</span>

<span>uint8_t</span> <span>gs_get</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>img</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>x</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>y</span>);
<span>void</span> <span>gs_set</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>img</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>x</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>y</span>, <span>uint8_t</span> <span>value</span>);
<span>void</span> <span>gs_crop</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>dst</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>src</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_rect</span> <span>roi</span>);
<span>void</span> <span>gs_copy</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>dst</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>src</span>);
<span>void</span> <span>gs_resize</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>dst</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>src</span>);
<span>void</span> <span>gs_downsample</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>dst</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>src</span>);

<span>// Thresholding</span>
<span>void</span> <span>gs_histogram</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>img</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>hist</span>[<span>256</span>]);
<span>void</span> <span>gs_threshold</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>img</span>, <span>uint8_t</span> <span>threshold</span>);
<span>uint8_t</span> <span>gs_otsu_threshold</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>img</span>);
<span>void</span> <span>gs_adaptive_threshold</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>dst</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>src</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>radius</span>, <span>int</span> <span>c</span>);

<span>// Filters</span>
<span>void</span> <span>gs_blur</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>dst</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>src</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>radius</span>);
<span>void</span> <span>gs_erode</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>dst</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>src</span>);
<span>void</span> <span>gs_dilate</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>dst</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>src</span>);
<span>void</span> <span>gs_sobel</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>dst</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>src</span>);

<span>// Blobs (connected components) and contours</span>
<span>typedef</span> <span>uint16_t</span> <span>gs_label</span>;
<span>struct</span> <span>gs_blob</span> { <span>gs_label</span> <span>label</span>; <span>unsigned</span> <span>area</span>; <span>struct</span> <span>gs_rect</span> <span>box</span>; <span>struct</span> <span>gs_point</span> <span>centroid</span>; };
<span>struct</span> <span>gs_contour</span> { <span>struct</span> <span>gs_rect</span> <span>box</span>; <span>struct</span> <span>gs_point</span> <span>start</span>; <span>unsigned</span> <span>length</span>; };
<span>unsigned</span> <span>gs_blobs</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>img</span>, <span>gs_label</span> <span>*</span><span>labels</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_blob</span> <span>*</span><span>blobs</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>nblobs</span>);
<span>void</span> <span>gs_blob_corners</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>img</span>, <span>gs_label</span> <span>*</span><span>labels</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_blob</span> <span>*</span><span>b</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_point</span> <span>c</span>[<span>4</span>]);
<span>void</span> <span>gs_perspective_correct</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>dst</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>src</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_point</span> <span>c</span>[<span>4</span>]);
<span>void</span> <span>gs_trace_contour</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>img</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>visited</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_contour</span> <span>*</span><span>c</span>);

<span>// FAST/ORB</span>
<span>struct</span> <span>gs_keypoint</span> { <span>struct</span> <span>gs_point</span> <span>pt</span>; <span>unsigned</span> <span>response</span>; <span>float</span> <span>angle</span>; <span>uint32_t</span> <span>descriptor</span>[<span>8</span>]; };
<span>struct</span> <span>gs_match</span> { <span>unsigned</span> <span>idx1</span>, <span>idx2</span>; <span>unsigned</span> <span>distance</span>; };
<span>unsigned</span> <span>gs_fast</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>img</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>scoremap</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_keypoint</span> <span>*</span><span>kps</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>nkps</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>threshold</span>);
<span>float</span> <span>gs_compute_orientation</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>img</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>x</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>y</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>r</span>);
<span>void</span> <span>gs_brief_descriptor</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>img</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_keypoint</span> <span>*</span><span>kp</span>);
<span>unsigned</span> <span>gs_orb_extract</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>img</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_keypoint</span> <span>*</span><span>kps</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>nkps</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>threshold</span>, <span>uint8_t</span> <span>*</span><span>scoremap_buffer</span>);
<span>unsigned</span> <span>gs_match_orb</span>(<span>const</span> <span>struct</span> <span>gs_keypoint</span> <span>*</span><span>kps1</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>n1</span>, <span>const</span> <span>struct</span> <span>gs_keypoint</span> <span>*</span><span>kps2</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>n2</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_match</span> <span>*</span><span>matches</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>max_matches</span>, <span>float</span> <span>max_distance</span>);

<span>// LBP cascades</span>
<span>struct</span> <span>gs_lbp_cascade</span> { <span>uint16_t</span> <span>window_w</span>, <span>window_h</span>; <span>uint16_t</span> <span>nfeatures</span>, <span>nweaks</span>, <span>nstages</span>; <span>const</span> <span>int8_t</span> <span>*</span><span>features</span>; <span>/* [nfeatures * 4] */</span> <span>const</span> <span>uint16_t</span> <span>*</span><span>weak_feature_idx</span>; <span>const</span> <span>float</span> <span>*</span><span>weak_left_val</span>, <span>*</span><span>weak_right_val</span>; <span>const</span> <span>uint16_t</span> <span>*</span><span>weak_subset_offset</span>, <span>*</span><span>weak_num_subsets</span>; <span>const</span> <span>int32_t</span> <span>*</span><span>subsets</span>; <span>const</span> <span>uint16_t</span> <span>*</span><span>stage_weak_start</span>, <span>*</span><span>stage_nweaks</span>; <span>const</span> <span>float</span> <span>*</span><span>stage_threshold</span>; };
<span>void</span> <span>gs_integral</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>src</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>*</span><span>ii</span>);
<span>unsigned</span> <span>gs_lbp_window</span>(<span>const</span> <span>struct</span> <span>gs_lbp_cascade</span> <span>*</span><span>c</span>, <span>const</span> <span>unsigned</span> <span>*</span><span>ii</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>iw</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>ih</span>, <span>int</span> <span>x</span>, <span>int</span> <span>y</span>, <span>float</span> <span>scale</span>);
<span>unsigned</span> <span>gs_lbp_detect</span>(<span>const</span> <span>struct</span> <span>gs_lbp_cascade</span> <span>*</span><span>c</span>, <span>const</span> <span>unsigned</span> <span>*</span><span>ii</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>iw</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>ih</span>, <span>struct</span> <span>gs_rect</span> <span>*</span><span>rects</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>max_rects</span>, <span>float</span> <span>scale_factor</span>, <span>float</span> <span>min_scale</span>, <span>float</span> <span>max_scale</span>, <span>int</span> <span>step</span>);

<span>// Optional:</span>
<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>gs_alloc</span>(<span>unsigned</span> <span>w</span>, <span>unsigned</span> <span>h</span>);
<span>void</span> <span>gs_free</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>img</span>);
<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>gs_read_pgm</span>(<span>const</span> <span>char</span> <span>*</span><span>path</span>);
<span>int</span> <span>gs_write_pgm</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>gs_image</span> <span>img</span>, <span>const</span> <span>char</span> <span>*</span><span>path</span>);</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This project is licensed under the MIT License. Feel free to use in research, products, and your next embedded vision project!</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I took all my projects off the cloud, saving thousands of dollars (421 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://rameerez.com/send-this-article-to-your-friend-who-still-thinks-the-cloud-is-a-good-idea/</link>
            <guid>45816041</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 21:22:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://rameerez.com/send-this-article-to-your-friend-who-still-thinks-the-cloud-is-a-good-idea/">https://rameerez.com/send-this-article-to-your-friend-who-still-thinks-the-cloud-is-a-good-idea/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45816041">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope="" itemprop="author">
<p><img alt="" src="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/themes/rameerez-yuuta/assets/images/avatar-200px.webp" data-lazy-type="image" data-lazy-src="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/themes/rameerez-yuuta/assets/images/avatar-200px.webp" data-lazy-srcset="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/themes/rameerez-yuuta/assets/images/avatar-200px.webp 2x" itemprop="image" loading="lazy" srcset="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/themes/rameerez-yuuta/assets/images/avatar-200px.webp 2x" width="100" height="100">
</p>
<p>
I'm , maker of <a href="https://prompthero.com/?ref=rameerez">PromptHero</a>, <a href="https://gohustl.co/?ref=rameerez">Hustl</a>, <a href="https://jobician.com/?ref=rameerez">Jobician</a>, and <a href="https://rameerez.com/projects">other products</a> that are used by millions of people across the globe. My work has been featured in The Washington Post, The Wall Street Journal, Vox, Fast Company and <a href="https://rameerez.com/press">others</a>.
</p>
</div><div>
<p id="breadcrumbs"><span><span><a href="https://rameerez.com/">Home</a> » <span><a href="https://rameerez.com/category/blog/">Blog</a> » <span aria-current="page">Send this article to your friend who still thinks the cloud is a good idea</span></span></span></span></p>
<p>I recently took all my projects off the cloud, saving 10x in monthly AWS costs and thousands of dollars:</p>
<div>
<blockquote><div lang="en" dir="ltr"><p>I FINALLY got everything off the cloud</p><p>I’m now paying 10x LESS money for BETTER infrastructure</p><p>My AWS bill was ~$1,400/mo</p><p>I got it down to less than $120/mo for literally better, beefier servers</p><p>Fear of managing servers has a price: 10x your monthly infra bill <a href="https://t.co/X8ezjo0CV1">pic.twitter.com/X8ezjo0CV1</a></p></div>— rameerez (@rameerez) <a href="https://twitter.com/rameerez/status/1841451179609370748?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">October 2, 2024</a></blockquote>  
</div>

<p>This tweet got viral, and I found out <strong>two things</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>One</strong> – many developers were tempted to do the same, and therefore curious on how I did it myself, so I wrote a blogpost explaining exactly <a href="https://rameerez.com/how-i-exited-the-cloud/">how I exited the cloud</a>.</p>
<p><strong>And two</strong> – the most important one: the majority of people commenting were not only <strong>not tempted</strong> by the idea, but <strong>highly confrontational</strong> about it.</p>
<p>Interesting behavior –I thought– because I genuinely believe I did something <em>good</em> from both a technical and business point of view: I managed to decrease costs 10x <a href="https://x.com/rameerez/status/1841457055686656511">while getting a 2x performance speedup</a> for free, and freeing myself from vendor lock-in – who wouldn’t want that for their business?</p>
<p>I have more money in my pocket, I’m more free, and I managed to do so while providing a better service for my users. </p>
<p>Well, turns out many people had strong opinions about it.</p>
<h2>I’m sorry, but you’ve been scammed</h2>
<p>You’ve been scammed, likely not out of your own money, but your employer’s money – and that’s why you don’t give a crap.</p>
<p>See, I noticed something interesting. Most people complaining about what I did happen to have “devops”, “cloud engineer”, “serverless guy”, “AWS certified”, or something similar in their bio.</p>
<p>None of these people have any skin in the game.</p>
<p>They don’t run their own projects in the cloud, they don’t pay a single dollar of the cloud bill at the end of the month, and they couldn’t care less about their employer’s AWS bill. They don’t <em>feel</em> the <strong>pain</strong> of being scammed out of thousands and thousands of dollars by cloud providers month after month. With someone else’s money, everyone’s brave.</p>
<p>To them, it’s way too convenient to be on AWS: not only it solves their problem, but it’s also a shiny object. It’s technically complex, it makes them look smart in front of other devs, it creates dependencies and lock-in effects so they’re not easily replaceable as employees, and most importantly – being on the cloud yields them a fat paycheck at the end of the month. They don’t have any incentive to make the most efficient decision for the business they work for, on the contrary – they depend on the business’ infrastructure being as complex and convoluted as possible, or they’ll be out of a job.</p>
<p>So don’t count on any of them telling you the truth – the truth that <strong>servers are not actually expensive</strong>.</p>
<h2>You can just rent servers for cheap</h2>
<p>I made my move from AWS to a company called Hetzner. I don’t get paid by them or have any affiliation to them, they just happen to offer cheap servers. I’ve used Digital Ocean in the past, loved them and considered them this time, but Hetzner prices are just better.</p>
<p>How good are the prices? Well, let’s take a look:</p>
<div>
<figure><picture>
<source type="image/webp" srcset="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1-1024x646.png.webp 1024w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1-300x189.png.webp 300w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1-768x484.png.webp 768w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1-1536x969.png.webp 1536w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1-1400x883.png.webp 1400w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1.png.webp 1716w" sizes="(max-width: 773px) 100vw, 773px">
<img src="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1-1024x646.png" alt="" width="773" height="487" srcset="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1-1024x646.png 1024w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1-300x189.png 300w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1-768x484.png 768w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1-1536x969.png 1536w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1-1400x883.png 1400w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1.png 1716w" sizes="(max-width: 773px) 100vw, 773px">
</picture>
</figure></div>
<p>You can rent bare-metal servers with 80 cores for under $190 a month. I repeat: <strong>eighty cores for one-hundred-ninety dollars a month</strong>.</p>
<p>For comparison, compute-heavy instances in AWS of the C5-C6 families with comparable number of vCPUs cost between $2,500 and $3,500 a month – which is between 13x and 18x more expensive. Sure, you can get reserved instances, and that brings the price down to ~$1,300/mo, which is still 7x more expensive, plus you’d need to pay $46k upfront and be locked to a 3-year contract. I don’t know, Rick…</p>
<p>Say you don’t need such a big server. You don’t need, or you don’t want, to pay for the 79EUR one-time setup fee. It’s understandable, you only want to run your little projects, or you want a bit more flexibility. Let’s look at the VPS options:</p>
<div>
<figure><picture loading="lazy">
<source type="image/webp" srcset="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-2-1024x562.png.webp 1024w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-2-300x165.png.webp 300w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-2-768x422.png.webp 768w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-2-1536x844.png.webp 1536w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-2-2048x1125.png.webp 2048w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-2-1400x769.png.webp 1400w" sizes="(max-width: 798px) 100vw, 798px">
<img loading="lazy" src="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-2-1024x562.png" alt="" width="798" height="438" srcset="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-2-1024x562.png 1024w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-2-300x165.png 300w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-2-768x422.png 768w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-2-1536x844.png 1536w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-2-2048x1125.png 2048w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-2-1400x769.png 1400w" sizes="(max-width: 798px) 100vw, 798px">
</picture>
</figure></div>
<p>You still can get a 48-vCPU machine for around $300/mo, without setup fees, without 3-year contracts, and with full flexibility to scale it down if needed.</p>
<p>Or a more-than-enough 8-core, 32GB RAM machine for around $50 a month that will probably be able to run <strong>all</strong> your projects at once, as long as they’re not getting literal millions of requests per day.</p>
<h2>You can buy servers for even cheaper</h2>
<p>But say this is still not cheap enough for you.</p>
<p>You’re not worried about monthly costs, you’re looking to save <em>for the long run</em>. Well, turns out buying your own servers is even cheaper in a long enough time frame:</p>

<p>You can buy a decent rack-mounted server, with 44 CPUs, 256GB RAM, 2TB NVMe SSD and a bunch of other features for under $1k. Think about it. You could probably run your app for <em>years</em> – for less than what you probably pay a month in cloud services.</p>
<p>Now, of course, you can buy the server but you still to account for the electricity costs, internet costs, cooling costs, rack costs, etc. I’m not going to get to that level of detail. The bottom line is that good servers are <em>cheap</em>.</p>
<p>You can also choose to rent rack space in a datacenter, and they’ll provide you with reliable electricity, internet, cooling, security, etc. You can look for datacenters in your area using websites like <a href="https://www.datacentermap.com/">DatacenterMap</a>:</p>
<div>
<figure><picture loading="lazy">
<source type="image/webp" srcset="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-8-1024x686.png.webp 1024w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-8-300x201.png.webp 300w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-8-768x515.png.webp 768w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-8-1536x1029.png.webp 1536w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-8-2048x1372.png.webp 2048w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-8-1400x938.png.webp 1400w" sizes="(max-width: 807px) 100vw, 807px">
<img loading="lazy" src="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-8-1024x686.png" alt="" width="807" height="540" srcset="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-8-1024x686.png 1024w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-8-300x201.png 300w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-8-768x515.png 768w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-8-1536x1029.png 1536w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-8-2048x1372.png 2048w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-8-1400x938.png 1400w" sizes="(max-width: 807px) 100vw, 807px">
</picture>
</figure></div>
<p>The way it works is: you call the datacenter and they provide you with either shared space or a whole secure room for your servers, called datacenter cage, like this one:</p>
<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" src="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-9-1024x768.png" alt="" width="637" height="478" srcset="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-9-1024x768.png 1024w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-9-300x225.png 300w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-9-768x576.png 768w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-9.png 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 637px) 100vw, 637px"></figure></div>
<p>And then you buy and ship your racks, and switches, and cables, and servers to the datacenter, load all the boxes in a little warehouse cart, transport everything into your cage and start building the racks and putting your servers in them:</p>
<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" src="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-10.png" alt="" width="407" height="611" srcset="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-10.png 600w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-10-200x300.png 200w" sizes="(max-width: 407px) 100vw, 407px"></figure></div>
<p>BUT – all of this is WAY too complex for small developers. You’d probably need to hire an engineer to help you set everything right, you’d need to be in sales calls with the datacenter to negotiate the price and all that – it’s way too cumbersome. Not worth it.</p>
<p>I’m just documenting it so you get a notion of how things actually work. I’ve never done this myself, it’s usually aimed at medium-to-big companies and enterprises that want to build their own infrastructure, and it’s pretty unusual that small teams do this.</p>
<p>Datacenter operations are quite interesting, I recommend you go <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PVubvo6H8Oc">watch some videos</a> to get a better understanding of how the internet actually works. This is literally how AWS works under the hood. It’s all datacenters. The whole internet is just cold, noisy rooms filled with metal boxes. Always has been.</p>
<p>Now, instead of renting an entire datacenter cage, you can just rent some available rack space in a shared rack, and then place your server there.</p>
<p>But you’d still need to physically go and install your server – and the end result is in practice THE SAME as just renting an already mounted server off a company like Hetzner, as I already described. And Hetzner takes care of replacing server parts when they go faulty, and they take all that hardware weight off your shoulders, quite literally.</p>
<h2>bUt ISn’T tHat sTilL tHe clOUD</h2>
<p>One of the most common critiques I got while I was trying to make the points above was something along the lines of: “but isn’t that still the cloud?”, “you didn’t actually exit the cloud, you just changed cloud providers”</p>
<div>
<figure><picture loading="lazy">
<source type="image/webp" srcset="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-4.png.webp 583w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-4-300x211.png.webp 300w" sizes="(max-width: 570px) 100vw, 570px">
<img loading="lazy" src="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-4.png" alt="" width="570" height="402" srcset="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-4.png 583w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-4-300x211.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 570px) 100vw, 570px">
</picture>
</figure></div>
<p>Look, first of all, you’re as unique as the other 1000 peanut gallery enjoyers that have made the same astute observation before you. Congratulations. But you’re absolutely missing the point.</p>
<p>The point here is that there’s value in managing your own servers VS just accepting the cloud as a given truth. The point is you can start paying 10x-100x less money by running a little Linux machine instead of using managed AWS services. The point is most developers are scared of servers, and they just need a little push and encouragement to realize they can just set up their own servers for cheap to replace money-burners like RDS. The point is almost no one in the real world needs the cloud’s expensive managed services, and can do just fine with regular software running on a couple Linux boxes.</p>
<p>At the end of the day, the only hard truth is whether you managed to keep more dollars in your pocket or you gave them away to Amazon’s stockholders’ pockets.</p>
<p>The whole debate of “is this still the cloud or not” is nonsense to me. You’re just getting lost in naming conventions. VPS, bare metal, on-prem, colo, who cares what you call it. You need to put your servers <em>somewhere</em>. Sure, have a computer running in your mom’s basement if that makes you feel like you’re <em>exiting the cloud more</em>, I’ll have mine in a datacenter and both will be happy.</p>
<p>I don’t care if the server is physically in my building. I don’t need to touch it, I need to <code>ssh</code> into it. In fact, if I had bought a physical server instead of renting one off Hetzner, I would still need to rent rack space to host it. At which point, you’re just doing the exact same thing as renting a server off Hetzner, only more expensive and less convenient if you’re a small developer.</p>
<p>It seems to me that people pushing for the “this is still the cloud” mindset are essentially gatekeepers. “You’re not doing it correctly, you need to purchase your own switches, build your own rack, hook the ethernet cable yourself…” – boss, how far do you wanna take this argument? Do you etch your own circuits too? This whole thing is like saying “I’m the only one who knows how to do it right and you’re not puritan enough to belong in this exclusive club”. It’s not only toxic, but it’s also the most lazy argumentation one could make. It’s choosing to get nuclear over a superficial nuance, instead of trying to refute the central argument.</p>
<p>The central argument is servers are not actually expensive, and whoever is telling you otherwise is probably trying to sell you a cloud managed service.</p>
<p>Companies like AWS or Vercel are charging you a 10x to 100x markup.</p>
<h2>You’re not using the cloud wrong, it’s just expensive</h2>
<p>They will try to gaslight you.</p>
<p>They will not only try to convince you you’re not exiting the cloud, but they’ll go as far as gaslighting you. They will make you believe you were not smart enough to <em>get</em> the cloud.</p>
<p>“You’re using the cloud wrong”, “It’s expensive because you’re doing it poorly”, “You just need to know how to use the cloud”.</p>
<p>You will hear a bunch of crap from people that have literally never tried the alternative. People with no real hands-on experience managing servers for their own projects for any sustained period of time. People trying to offer expert-level advice but that end up just spewing out generic, bland, off-the-shelve clichés and vague notions about how they think the cloud should work. People not only without skin in the game, but whose first job was straight into the cloud. People that go literally silent when you ask them: “so, what have you personally built lately, how many users does it serve, and how much are you paying for it?” They just don’t know better, and they’ll try to save face by defending themselves like a cat with its back against the wall – even if that means gaslighting you.</p>
<p>I’m definitely not an expert but I know my way around AWS. Hell, I’ve even studied AWS certs. I made sure my infra was not overprovisioned. I made sure I was not paying for services I was not using in regions I might have used only once or twice. I had already spent countless hours optimizing AWS costs, and even had some success in doing so (I even managed to cut my monthly AWS bill in more than half last year – it was north of $5k/mo before!)</p>
<p>I already did all that. I do know about serverless computing. I do know about reserved instances. I had reserved instances, in fact. (Don’t purchase reserved instances, they only make the problem worse: they create vendor lock-in, and they essentially go against everything I’ve been trying to argue. The least thing you want when you’re considering getting off the cloud because it keeps getting more and more expensive is to lock yourself into it with a 3-year contract. Yes, I also do know you can resell RIs, thanks, my argument still stands).</p>
<p>I tried all that, I tried as hard as I could, and the only conclusion I arrived to after many, many frustrations was that the cloud is simply way too expensive.</p>
<p>You can try yourself, by all means be my guest and try to prove me wrong, but I’ve already been there, done that, and I’m pretty sure of what I’m saying. So I’d suggest you just don’t listen to the fearmongering cloud cult folks that keep repeating gaslighting mantras like a broken record.</p>
<h2>You won’t make friends proposing all this</h2>
<p>All this backlash was interesting. Why do all these people care if I save more money or not?</p>
<p>I arrived at two main conclusions: 1) their livelihood depends on it; and 2) because of this fear, the conversation turns irrational.</p>
<p><strong>One – their livelihoods depend on it</strong>.</p>
<p>If they’re wrong, and if I and more people like me manage to convince enough people that they’re wrong, they may be out of a job soon.</p>
<p>It’s as simple as that.</p>
<p>We come from a decade-long trend where the cool thing was to build things in the cloud, which in turn created thousands if not millions of “devops” and “cloud engineers”; and we’re now switching to a trend where the cool thing is to keep things off the cloud, which may terminate the careers of many cloud experts. It’s just another cycle, but people get understandably very defensive about it.</p>
<p>I’m sure many developers secretly know the cloud is not as good as they initially promised, and they hold that conflicting thought in their head day in and day out as they go about their job. There’s just no way those bright engineers look at their employer’s AWS spending realizing it’s 10x what it should be and go like: “ah, this is fine”.</p>
<p>But no one wants to do the work, and risk getting their managers upset and getting thrown under the bus. They don’t want to risk the political cost of not being in the same page as the most vocal person in the team. Or they just don’t know better. Many entered the industry after the cloud was already mainstream. People used to run their own servers, it used to be absolutely normal and just the thing to do, but Amazon’s marketing team managed to flip the market, so newcomers haven’t touched anything but cloud in their entire careers – and AWS evangelists convinced whoever seniors were left.</p>
<p><strong>Two – it’s not a rational discussion</strong>. As a result, developers that are currently balls deep into this whole cloud thing have developed some sort of Stockholm syndrome about the cloud. It’s essentially sunk cost fallacy, but it turns them into very irrational creatures.</p>
<p>AWS has a strong cult-like following. They teach you the doctrine via certifications where they make you memorize actual sales pages and product offerings, they have literal <em>evangelists</em>, they instruct you to stop listening to the rational voices around you that push for pragmatism instead of dogmatism, they instill fear of the outside world in you (servers are dangerous! things don’t scale!), they make you adopt “cloud engineer” as your whole new identity, they make it really easy to get in but really difficult to get out, etc. I’m not saying it’s an <em>actual</em> cult, of course, just that things get irrational pretty quick. More so when people’s livelihoods are on the line.</p>
<p>The end result is AWS followers, whenever confronted, get caught up in dogma and just start throwing irrational arguments left and right, repeating the AWS sales landing pages’ talking points one by one, and don’t even stop to think about what they really need or if those things are even of use to them. They got tricked into believing something, and once you touch upon belief systems, people get irrational.</p>
<p>I could never win this irrational discussion with rational arguments. It doesn’t matter how good my optimizations were. I could have cut costs 100x instead of just 10x – or I could have claimed something outrageous like I got to run all my infrastructure for just $1. It just doesn’t matter.</p>
<p>These people would still be ranting and arguing that I’m doomed because now I don’t have things like “infinite scalability capabilities” or “automated failovers with automated replica recovery”. These are things that I’ve never needed or used, things that I’m sure 99% of people in the thread never needed or used either, but that they throw at you in a vain attempt to build an argument.</p>
<p>When people are cornered, arguments quickly turn into dogma – and fear:</p>
<p>Hackers will break in. Your servers will get full of malware. Your hardware will fail and you won’t be able to restore it. Your switches will break and your customers will leave while your server is down. You will need to pay someone to maintain and upgrade your server, there’s no way around it! And you need a plethora of busywork to “do it properly”: failure scenarios! Recovery plans! Managing availability! Infosec! Monsters, spiders and zombies! All of them, coming for you! Be afraid, very afraid! How dare you not be afraid of all this scary stuff!</p>
<p>Well, either the last 15 years of my life –and the lives of most <em>webmasters</em> on the internet– have been a lie, or you don’t actually need any of that to run a server online.</p>
<h2>How did we get here?</h2>
<p>The majority of devs are clueless, or have forgotten, about how we got here.</p>
<p>Everyone used to run their own servers. Either VPSs, or hosting services, or bare metal in datacenters, or in a dark room in their companies, or at home. Everyone was familiar and comfortable <code>ssh</code>ing into machines.</p>
<p>I remember very clearly how the cloud marketing psyops campaign started in the early 2010s. It was a deliberate move by companies to try to shill their enterprise technology to early-stage startups, trying to get them locked in as early as possible so they could milk them as they raised rounds.</p>
<p>I remember when AWS started to give out credits specifically for startups only. They would literally make the rounds, going from startup accelerator to startup accelerator, trying to get everyone on board.</p>
<p>The trick is easy: you make it extremely cheap (free!) for startups to build on your infrastructure, then make everything extremely expensive as they grow, and enjoy the show because they’re so locked in most will struggle to escape the ecosystem by them.</p>
<p>AWS was not the only one. I remember attending an IBM cloud event in 2014. I was the CTO of a small startup at the time. They were very specifically targeting startups; in fact, we got the invitation via our startup accelerator.</p>
<p>We ran everything on Heroku at the time, and it worked just fine. I remember thinking: “what the hell is all this cloud stuff and how do I use it?” I vividly remember feeling like they were trying to sell us something that was not designed for us. I spent some time looking into it and just couldn’t wrap my head around this whole cloud thing. All of it sounded so alien to us.</p>
<p>But all these companies poured literal millions upon millions of dollars into this cloud shilling campaign over the following years, tricking early startups into adopting enterprise technology.</p>
<p>They ended up being successful at it – and the aftermath is the current state of web development in 2024. Zero interest rates through most of the last decade definitely helped in getting us here.</p>
<p>There is now a counterculture movement, mainly led by <a href="https://x.com/dhh">@dhh</a> and the Rails community, and this feels like something fundamentally fresh, right, and aligned with the reality of MOST software businesses on Earth.</p>
<h2>You don’t need the cloud</h2>
<p>Some people are absolutely out of touch with what most software businesses look like in the real world.</p>
<p>They think in terms of Fortune 500; they truly believe enterprise is the norm. They think the average business needs all the bells and whistles the cloud has to offer: high availability, multi-zone replication, automatic failovers, distributed Kubernetes clusters…</p>
<p>The reality is only a teeny tiny fraction of all software businesses need something like this.</p>
<p>Most businesses are and will always be small, by a simple rule of power law.</p>
<div>
<figure><picture loading="lazy">
<source type="image/webp" srcset="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-5.png.webp 800w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-5-300x232.png.webp 300w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-5-768x594.png.webp 768w" sizes="(max-width: 710px) 100vw, 710px">
<img loading="lazy" src="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-5.png" alt="" width="710" height="549" srcset="https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-5.png 800w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-5-300x232.png 300w, https://rameerez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-5-768x594.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 710px) 100vw, 710px">
</picture>
<figcaption>Representation of a power law distribution. Actual phenomenon depicted is mostly unrelated, but it shows what a power law is: a very small number of companies are actually big – while the vast majority of companies in the long tail are small. In the United States, small businesses account for 99.9% of all businesses. In the European Union, SMEs (defined as having fewer than 250 employees) represent 99% of all businesses. Similar patterns are observed in many other countries around the world. Your little app is (most probably) not part of that 0.1%.</figcaption></figure></div>
<p>Most business are small, and the ones that need actual computing power can do incredibly well without the cloud up until a very high point. Scaling vertically can get you very, very far nowadays.</p>
<p>Most devs wildly overestimate scaling requirements. They have such a low bar for what “high traffic” means.</p>
<p>Here’s a reference point: my current two-server setup serves millions of requests a day for millions of monthly visitors. So is the case for many other indie makers, like <a href="https://x.com/levelsio/">@levelsio</a>, who even managed to get everything down to one single server. Most devs have never tried running a project of their own, with actual users and actual production traffic, on a single server – and it shows.</p>
<p>Devs also wildly overestimate other technical requirements. Again, only a tiny fraction of software businesses need the bells and whistles. Of course they exist, but they’re rare, and they usually have very good reasons for their technical decisions.</p>
<p>Like Netflix, needing to transcode and stream enormous amounts of video to customers all over the world. That’s where you need distributed systems, CDNs, edge computing, all of that stuff. Your little app with one thousand users that just sends some JSON objects around does definitely not need that.</p>
<p>I feel like most devs have this magical notion in their heads that their project is something like Netflix. It’s wishful thinking, and I get it – you want to be as successful as Netflix. But it makes you make the wrong technical decisions, and all of a sudden they think they need to have distributed servers all over the world because their users will somehow notice a few milliseconds difference in latency when they tap a button. It’s wild.</p>
<p>I remember a random conversation I had with a young entrepreneur a couple years ago. He ran a mobile app. I don’t remember what exactly it did, but it was of the “upload things and follow people” category of apps. I asked: “what’s the biggest challenge your facing in your startup?”, and he replied: “well, that’d be estimating monthly AWS costs. They’re high and unpredictable”. I held my breath and took a step back, as one does when someone makes a claim bold enough to make you reconsider if you might be in front of a billionaire or a super-successful entrepreneur you’ve never heard about, and respectfully asked: “how many users does your app have?”. “Oh, about a thousand now” – he replied.</p>
<p>Bro, just get a server. You don’t need the cloud.</p>
<h2>Your servers are going to be okay</h2>
<p>Something I discovered is that a lot of people have magical ideas about how datacenters actually work.</p>
<p>They think servers in datacenters are fragile and volatile. Like things that can just vanish into thin air.</p>
<p><a href="https://x.com/rameerez/status/1841602037949026585">Someone even thought a lightning strike can take down an entire datacenter</a> and nuke your business out of existence.</p>
<p>The reality is modern datacenters already account for all these problems and are equipped with many protections: not only against things as mundane as lightning, but against pretty much anything that can compromise uptime.</p>
<p>They have plenty of redundant systems: redundant power sources, redundant cooling, redundant internet connections, redundant fire suppresion systems, redundant security sustems and tons of physical security… Everything in a datacenter is designed with resiliency and redundancy in mind (N+1 redundancy at minimum, sometimes 2N) to guarantee uptime.</p>
<p>These are mostly fear-driven opinions, the result of a successful cloud marketing and psyops campaign. Where do you think AWS stores their machines, in a magical place under the rainbow? And how exactly would AWS machines be the only ones magically protected against problems that other datacenters also have?</p>
<p>Disasters can happen (<a href="https://www.datacenterdynamics.com/en/analysis/ovhcloud-fire-france-data-center/">OVH 2021</a>), sure, and you should have backups to recover from them – but in my experience of ~15 years running servers I think they’re rare, and I’ve never had any downtime of more than a few minutes.</p>
<p>Your server is probably going to be okay.</p>
<h2>You won’t have to spend your days managing servers</h2>
<p>Anyone who has managed servers for long enough knows you spend most time in the initial setup; then servers tend to be relatively stable.</p>
<p>Hardware failures are relatively rare, and once a server is up and running it usually runs flawlessly for years without much intervention.</p>
<p>Managing your own servers is not a full-time job.</p>
<p>You don’t need to employ a 5-person devops team. You don’t even need to hire a server guy: you can just do things yourself! It’s not that difficult.</p>
<p>Claude and ChatGPT usually have a good understanding of Linux systems and how to manage them, ask them for help.</p>
<p>When I posted the tweet, people thought this was my first time running servers and claimed I was overly optimistic in what running a server actually means.</p>
<p>It’s difficult to say these things without coming across as arrogant, but I’ve been managing servers since 2006.</p>
<p>I started, as many did, editing PHP scripts and uploading them to my FTP server. I first had to learn how to install WordPress, then ventured a bit and started editing WP templates, then everything else followed.</p>
<p>It was an invaluable experience for me. It taught me the basics.</p>
<p>It taught me what Linux was, how to navigate it, and by 2007 I was requesting Canonical for Ubuntu CD-ROMs that would arrive in the mail and that I would use to install in a partition in my parents’ computer to learn more about Linux.</p>
<p>Those early experiences taught me the basics of web development; everything else is built on top of it. Which leads me to my next point:</p>
<h2>You will learn how to use Linux, and that’s a good thing</h2>
<p>I think the new generations of devs (genz devs, alpha devs, etc.) are absolutely out of touch with the hardware that runs their software.</p>
<p>They lack these kinds of foundational experiences.</p>
<p>They were born in an era where a random guy on Youtube shilled them one specific vendor and taught them to run one very specific command that magically solved all their infrastructure problems. It’s only reasonable they have magical assumptions about what servers are and how they work.</p>
<p>They rant and rant about how you can just do things “serverless” without realizing they’re just running their code in many different boxes. Of course, many of them go on to learn more about Linux and servers, but the average bootcamp grad, let’s say, lacks the hands-on Linux experience that FTP hackers would have had 20 years ago.</p>
<p>I’m not making moral judgements about this: I’m not arguing it’s good or bad – it is what it is. The current state of web dev.</p>
<p>But the result is companies like Vercel are making literal millions of dollars by capitalizing on this new generation of developers that generally don’t know what they’re doing and have never ran a server of their own in their life.</p>
<div>
<blockquote><div lang="en" dir="ltr"><p>Vercel pricing is absolutely insane, it blows my mind</p><p>Data transfer starts at $150/TB with 1TB included</p><p>Hetzner gives 20TB free, and then it’s €1.19/TB</p><p>So 20TB on Vercel is $2850, on Hetzner it’s free (included with VPS)</p><p>And then you have to pay extra per request?</p><p>Perhaps…</p></div>— Daniel Lockyer (@DanielLockyer) <a href="https://twitter.com/DanielLockyer/status/1841920964164026635?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">October 3, 2024</a></blockquote> 
</div>

<p>Ignorance has a double price: being ignorant in itself; and the price you pay for people exploiting that ignorance of yours. Not knowing how things work will actually cost you money.</p>
<h2>You’ll be fine</h2>
<p>Even if you’ve never managed your own server and you’re scared of everything that smells of backend, you’ll be fine.</p>
<p>In fact, <strong>there has never been a better time to get good at servers</strong>. Claude and ChatGPT are both extremely knowledgeable about Linux, and can guide your steps like it’s never been possible before in the history of technology. Not only to set things up and understand how they work, but whenever you need to make a change you can just ask them, and follow the steps without needing to hire anyone. It’s not as scary as it seems, and you won’t have to do it that often.</p>
<p>Plus, in the time of AI where code generation is the norm and code might even become a commodity, knowing how to put that code in cheap production servers, and make it actually useful to end users might be a key differentiator for you as a developer.</p>
<p>You will now need to worry about things like security, sure. Don’t listen to those arguing that running your own server is somehow less secure than running AWS’s servers, as if EC2 instances were magically protected against hackers or something.</p>
<p>The reality is it’s not that difficult to set things up right, just follow <a href="https://gist.github.com/rameerez/7771f4f949eddd8b0832c4652429c1ff">my guide and setup scripts</a> for example. There are many devs, more experienced than you, doing things in production way worse than what you could do when equiped with AI. Ask ChatGPT how to harden your Linux server and follow best security practices (like: don’t use password auth, only strong ssh keys) and you’re 90<em>% </em>there. Just take the plunge and go for it.</p>
<p>Something like Cloudflare can get you really far, too.</p>
<p>After locking your Linux box you can run Cloudflare on top of everything for an extra layer of protection: proxy the IP of your server on their DNS so you don’t expose it and you’re golden. And you get DDoS protection, edge caching, and a top-tier DNS for essentially free.</p>
<p>You’ll be fine.</p>
<!-- <hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /> -->
<p>
P.S.: <a href="https://twitter.com/intent/follow?original_referer=https%3A%2F%2Frameerez.com&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&amp;region=follow_link&amp;screen_name=rameerez&amp;tw_p=followbutton">Follow me on Twitter</a> to stay in the loop. I'm writing a book called <a href="https://boldhackers.com/">Bold Hackers</a> on making successful digital products as an indie hacker. <a href="https://rameerez.com/blog">Read other stories</a> I've written. Subscribe below to get an alert when I publish a new post:
</p>
<div id="mc_embed_signup">


<p>No spam ever, unsubscribe with one single click. </p>
</div>
<!-- DEBUG: Including Turnstile script block -->


</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[We're open-sourcing the successor of Jupyter notebook (175 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://deepnote.com/blog/were-open-sourcing-the-successor-of-jupyter-notebook</link>
            <guid>45813994</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 18:06:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://deepnote.com/blog/were-open-sourcing-the-successor-of-jupyter-notebook">https://deepnote.com/blog/were-open-sourcing-the-successor-of-jupyter-notebook</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45813994">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><p>The traditional Jupyter experience has felt outdated for a while now. We’re <strong>open‑sourcing its successor</strong>.</p><p>Teams need notebooks that are reactive, collaborative, and AI‑ready. If your workflow still depends on tools that are not ready for the next decade, your tools are holding you back.</p><p><strong>Today, we’re announcing that Deepnote is going open source.</strong></p><p>We’re doing this as a way to share our learnings over past 7 years of working to power the worfklows of 500,000 data professionals and over 21% of Fortune 500.</p><p>We’re also doing this because the center of gravity has moved: from single‑player JSON scrolls to <strong>reactive, AI‑ready projects</strong> that humans and agents can co‑author, review, and deploy. We’re opening the format and the building blocks so the community has a standard that is purpose-built for AI.</p><h2>First principles: we still love notebooks</h2><p>We are big believers in notebooks — full stop. They are:</p><ul><li><p><strong>Perfect for data exploration</strong></p></li><li><p><strong>Perfect for collaborating with AI agents</strong></p></li><li><p><strong>Perfect for bringing technical and non‑technical users together</strong></p></li></ul><p>In other words, they are the <strong>universal computational medium</strong> we’ve been all looking for.</p><h2>Why companies are leaving Jupyter</h2><p>You already know the papercuts because you live with them: <strong>no native integrations, confusing UX, shaky collaboration and versioning, brittle reproducibility, spotty visualization support, and no first‑class AI</strong>. On a small project you can squint; at team scale, those are blockers.</p><p>Meanwhile, the <strong>market is voting with its feet</strong>. Across the Fortune 1000, job postings that mention and require Jupyter knowledge are down sharply; the most recent month was deep in the red YTD.</p><img src="https://us-west-2.graphassets.com/AaDC4FvhQQq2MDrtSUqtMz/cmhkgffun5yx809lq24yqut8d" alt="Nov 4 Screenshot from Blogpost.png" title="Nov 4 Screenshot from Blogpost.png" width="1252" height="1100"><p>On the other side, there’s slow activity in core Jupyter repos. If look at the contributions graph, you’ll see low commit velocity and very few unique contributors, including multi‑month holidays with no commits.<br></p><img src="https://us-west-2.graphassets.com/AaDC4FvhQQq2MDrtSUqtMz/cmhkggpdh5zea09lqgsnoyh2o" alt="Blogpost Image (3).png" title="Blogpost Image (3).png" width="1784" height="710"><h2>What’s wrong with the old notebooks</h2><p>Let’s start with the expensive elephant: <strong>internal data platforms built on top of Jupyter</strong>.&nbsp;The <strong>single‑player notebook model turns you into a platform vendor</strong>. That’s not your job. Lots of teams did the sensible thing in 2019–2023: stand up JupyterHub, glue on extensions, wire auth, deploy it on a k8s cluster, and call it a “platform.” It worked - until it didn’t. We see this in the wild. The <strong>total cost of ownership</strong> is now eating the roadmap for those teams, making them less nimble in the age where speed is everything. Rather than using cutting-edge software, the users are stuck with a platform that didn’t change since 2019.</p><p><strong>Where the cost hides (and compounds):</strong></p><ul><li><p><strong>People tax</strong>: Platform/SRE/Sec/DS‑ops spend cycles maintaining JupyterHub, kernels,</p></li><li><p><strong>Productivity stall</strong>: Teams are still using pre‑AI, single‑player tooling, so output doesn’t compound year‑over‑year; you can't even slap AI and call it a day - agether data nor the rest of collaboration infra is AI-ready.</p></li><li><p><strong>People tax</strong>: Platform/SRE/Sec/DS‑ops spend cycles maintaining JupyterHub, kernels, proxies, extensions, images, and brittle auth. Every upgrade is a change‑freeze prayer circle.</p></li><li><p><strong>Connector upkeep</strong>: Building data connectors, rotating and sharing creds, chase schema drift, and re‑testing pipelines on every vendor change.</p></li><li><p><strong>Collaboration debt</strong>: No first‑class versioning/comments/reviews; unreadable diffs; flaky reproducibility; ghost kernel state. “Run All” becomes ceremony—and a source of incidents.</p></li><li><p><strong>Compliance drag</strong>: Audit trails, RBAC, data residency, PII egress checks, and access reviews get bolted on per team.</p></li><li><p><strong>Compute waste</strong>: Idle kernels and full‑notebook re‑runs burn budgets; without a reactive dependency graph, every tweak reheats the whole pipeline.</p></li><li><p><strong>AI bolt‑ons</strong>: Chat helpers that can’t see state, can’t run tools, and can’t re‑run downstream safely; you end up owning fragile agent plumbing.</p></li><li><p><strong>Opportunity cost</strong>: Your best engineers ship platform fixes instead of features. The backlog grows while competitors move.</p></li></ul><h3>Real‑world TCO snapshots</h3><p><strong>Fintech, 50‑person data org (self‑hosted JupyterHub)</strong></p><ul><li><p>Platform: ~3 FTE (platform/SRE/security/enablement) ≈ <strong>$2.0M</strong> fully‑loaded over 3 years.</p></li><li><p>Glue: 14 custom extensions + 9 connectors maintained across repos; ~6 hrs/week/analyst on environment drift and re‑runs.</p></li><li><p>Incidents: 4 auth/secret‑rotation breakages per year; 2 post‑mortems tied to stale kernel state.</p></li><li><p>After adopting Deepnote format + reactive execution: <strong>35–45%</strong> fewer re‑runs; <strong>1.5 FTE</strong> reallocated to product work; <strong>~$180k/year</strong> infra savings from fewer idle kernels.</p></li></ul><p>This is also where skeptics usually jump in:</p><ul><li><p><strong>“But Jupyter is the standard.”</strong> <em>It was.</em> Standards stay standards only if they keep TCO low while meeting reality: mixed‑skill teams, CI, governance, and agents that lint, refactor, and re‑run.</p></li><li><p><strong>“Is this a marketing gimmick?”</strong><br>Hold us to the implementation: an <strong>open, human‑readable project</strong> you can diff and automate, <strong>round‑trippable</strong> with <code>.ipynb</code>, shaped in public by a very large community. That’s the opposite of lock‑in.</p></li><li><p><strong>“AI assistants don’t belong in notebooks.”</strong><br>They already work there—badly—when the substrate is wrong. With reactive blocks and explicit structure, agents become safe and useful instead of noisy.</p></li></ul><p>Your next data project shouldn’t start by typing “import numpy as np…”. It should start with the description of the problem and AI scaffolding the project for you.</p><img src="https://us-west-2.graphassets.com/AaDC4FvhQQq2MDrtSUqtMz/cmhkgikkc5kpq07n1v2yadaec" alt="Blogpost Image (2).png" title="Blogpost Image (2).png" width="3380" height="2308"><h2>What you get (at a glance)</h2><ul><li><p><strong>AI agents</strong> (single‑player authoring coming soon)</p></li><li><p><strong>One workspace</strong> for technical and non‑technical users together</p></li><li><p><strong>Seamless collaboration</strong>: native versioning, comments, reviews; <strong>human‑readable projects</strong> with clean diffs</p></li><li><p><strong>Blocks that go beyond code</strong>: SQL queries, Python/R code blocks, charts, tables, inputs (text/number/select/slider/date), file upload, buttons/actions, layout/app pages, reusable modules</p></li><li><p><strong>Beautiful apps:</strong> deploy your notebooks as interactive dashboards or data apps in a single click</p></li><li><p><strong>100+ native integrations</strong> with governed secrets</p></li><li><p><strong>Reactive execution</strong> so downstream blocks update automatically</p></li></ul><p>All of this is open and designed to work across your stack. While the best experience is in Deepnote, we’re backporting key pieces so you can use them in Jupyter, VS Code, Cursor, or Windsurf.</p><img src="https://us-west-2.graphassets.com/AaDC4FvhQQq2MDrtSUqtMz/cmhkgk19n5lro07n1pqd0y136" alt="Blogpost Image (1).png" title="Blogpost Image (1).png" width="3380" height="2308"><p><strong>Why it matters (no fluff):</strong></p><ul><li><p>Spend engineering time on product — not platform plumbing. Deepnote gives you the core out of the box.</p></li><li><p>Fewer re‑runs and less compute waste (reactive graph)</p></li><li><p>Less glue code and secret sprawl (native integrations)</p></li><li><p>Faster reviews and cleaner audits (diff‑able projects, governed workspaces)</p></li><li><p>No lock‑in (open standard; export as <code>.ipynb</code> where and if you need it)</p></li><li><p>Pure developer experience and happiness. Having data workspace you're looking forward to open could be a night and day in dev productivity.</p></li></ul><h2>What we opened — in English, not a changelog</h2><p><strong>A notebook format ready for the next decade.</strong><br>Goodbye messy JSON with random metadata. Deepnote projects use a  human‑and AI-readable text file you can review in Git and automate in CI. It’s <strong>extensible for blocks of the future</strong> — not just code and markdown, but SQL, headings, bullet lists, charts, inputs, KPIs, and more. It’s also <strong>AI‑readable</strong>: explicit structure and dependencies so agents can safely reason, edit, and re‑run. And when you need it, <strong>portability</strong> is built in — round‑trip to <code>.ipynb</code> without lock‑in.</p><p><strong>A format without a lock-in</strong><br>You can move between <code>.ipynb</code> and the Deepnote format as needed. Keep your pipelines. Keep your habits. Keep your exit. We’re allergic to lock‑in because standards outlast companies.</p><p><strong>Reactive by default.</strong><br>Change a parameter, and downstream blocks update — like spreadsheets, except it’s your real analysis, not a shadow model. No more "Run All" and pray. This is how notebooks become apps, not demos.</p><p><strong>AI that understands your work, not just your prompt.</strong><br>Copilot helps you write SQL and Python <em>in context</em>. The next step is inevitable: <strong>a single‑player Agent</strong> that goes from a prompt to a whole notebook — code, queries, charts, inputs — then iterates as you nudge.</p><p>With open-sourcing Deepnote, we’re doing the responsible thing: <strong>supporting the community</strong> while opening the path forward. If you’re all‑in on classic notebooks, keep them — you can convert anytime for want sleeker UI, data integrations,&nbsp;and AI, SQL, and collaboration as first-class citizens. If you’re ready to move, you can bring your team with one simple command.</p><img src="https://us-west-2.graphassets.com/AaDC4FvhQQq2MDrtSUqtMz/cmhkgo8pe631k09lqe2ss3bty" alt="Blogpost Image.png" title="Blogpost Image.png" width="3380" height="2308"><h2>An open invitation</h2><p>With gratitude to Jupyter, we've built the Jupyter notebook for the AI era, and the enterprise context. In this spirit, we're building the open standard for AI notebooks, data dashboards and apps. An open standard that is human‑readable, diff‑able, AI‑ready, and fully compatible with <code>.ipynb</code>.</p><p>But an open standard isn't open without feedback from you, as a community - that's why we welcome you to check out our GitHub repo and create your first .deepnote notebook today.</p><p>We decided to build Deepnote to bring beautiful yet powerful notebooks for the data science community. Along the way, we solved a lot of the problems that still exist in Jupyter today.</p><p>Today, Deepnote serves as a mature, enterprise-grade replacement of existing Jupyter deployments based on an open standard that’s human-readable, AI-native and ready for the next decade.</p><p>An open standard isn’t truly open without the community. We’re committed to maintaining and developing the standard, but we need feedback from you, the community, to tell us what you’re missing. Go and check out our GitHub repos, create your first .deepnote notebook today, and help us define the future of data notebooks.</p><h2>Get started today</h2><p><a title="https://github.com/deepnote/deepnote/" href="https://github.com/deepnote/deepnote/">Deepnote Open Source</a><br><a title="https://github.com/deepnote/vscode-deepnote/" href="https://github.com/deepnote/vscode-deepnote/">Deepnote VS Code extension</a><br><a title="https://pypi.org/project/jupyterlab-deepnote/" href="https://pypi.org/project/jupyterlab-deepnote/">Deepnote in Jupyterlab</a></p></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Codemaps: Understand Code, Before You Vibe It (297 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://cognition.ai/blog/codemaps</link>
            <guid>45813767</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 17:47:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://cognition.ai/blog/codemaps">https://cognition.ai/blog/codemaps</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45813767">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="blog-post__body"> <blockquote><em>“Your code is your understanding of the problem you’re exploring. So it’s <strong>only when you have your code in your head</strong> that you really understand the problem.”</em> — <a href="https://paulgraham.com/head.html?utm_source=chatgpt.com">Paul Graham</a></blockquote><p>Software development only becomes <em>engineering</em> with <strong>understanding</strong>. Your ability to reason through your most challenging coding tasks is constrained by your mental model of how things work — in other words, how quickly and how well you <strong>onboard</strong> to any codebase for solving any problem. However most AI vibe coding tools are aimed at relieving you of that burden by reading → thinking → writing the code for you, <strong>increasing the separation from you and your code</strong>. This is fine for low value, commodity tasks, but absolutely unacceptable for the hard, sensitive, and high value work that defines real engineering.</p><p><strong>We all need more AI that turns your brain ON, not OFF.</strong></p><p>Today we are announcing <strong>Windsurf Codemaps</strong>, which are first-of-its-kind AI-annotated structured maps of your code, powered by <a href="https://cognition.ai/blog/swe-1-5">SWE-1.5</a> and Claude Sonnet 4.5. Building on our popular work from <a href="https://cognition.ai/blog/deepwiki">DeepWiki</a> and <a href="https://docs.devin.ai/work-with-devin/ask-devin">Ask Devin</a>, Codemaps is the next step in hyper-contextualized codebase understanding, grounded in precise code navigation.</p><p><a href="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/2mc9cv2v/production/d1d8909494354ce8236620e1e57781ed2782a594-2232x1230.png" target="_blank"><img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/2mc9cv2v/production/d1d8909494354ce8236620e1e57781ed2782a594-2232x1230.png" alt="" loading="lazy"></a></p><h2>Why Codemaps?</h2><p>Every engineering task — debugging, refactors, new features — starts with <em>understanding</em>. Great engineers aren’t just good at writing code; they’re good at <em>reading</em> it, building mental models that span files, layers, and systems.</p><p>But modern codebases are sprawling: hundreds of files, multiple services, dense abstractions. Based on own experience and deep conversations with our customers across the Fortune 500, even top engineers spend much of their deep-work time <em>finding</em> and <em>remembering</em> what matters.</p><p>It’s a huge tax on productivity:</p><ul><li>New engineers take <strong>3–9 months</strong> to fully ramp (<a href="https://hackernoon.com/engineer-onboarding-the-ugly-truth-about-ramp-up-time-7e323t9j?utm_source=chatgpt.com">estimates</a>) </li><li>Senior engineers lose <strong>5+ hours per week</strong> onboarding others (<a href="https://decode.agency/article/hidden-costs-hiring-in-house-developers/">source</a>) </li><li>Stripe found legacy maintenance to be the #1 drag on productivity on their customers (<a href="https://stripe.com/files/reports/the-developer-coefficient.pdf?utm_source=chatgpt.com#page=6.66">source</a>)</li></ul><p><strong>This is the frontier that AI coding tools haven’t yet solved.</strong> Onboarding isn’t even a onetime cost, you pay it every time you switch context and codebases. The faster and better you understand your codebase, the faster and better you’ll be able to fix it yourself, or prompt agents to do it.</p><p><a href="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/2mc9cv2v/production/aebd2028ee20ba20f3a43fdb70885f0a02178276-1345x905.png" target="_blank"><img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/2mc9cv2v/production/aebd2028ee20ba20f3a43fdb70885f0a02178276-1345x905.png" alt="" loading="lazy"></a></p><p>Until today, the standard approach by Copilot, Claude Code, Codex, and even Windsurf Cascade, was to have you ask questions of a generalist agent with access to your code in a typical chat experience. But those solutions don’t solve focused onboarding and strongly grounded navigation to onboard, debug, and better context engineer for your codebase.</p><p>At Cognition, we’ve been investing far more deeply in understanding:</p><ul><li><strong>Ask Devin</strong> <a href="https://docs.devin.ai/work-with-devin/ask-devin">introduced</a> focused agents that reason through real codebases. </li><li><strong>DeepWiki</strong> <a href="https://cognition.ai/blog/deepwiki">made that reasoning transparent</a>, turning your repos into browsable, linked documentation.</li><li><strong>Windsurf</strong> <a href="https://docs.windsurf.com/windsurf/deepwiki">brought</a> these capabilities into the IDE.</li></ul><p>Codemaps is our next investment in tooling that makes engineers the best versions of themselves.</p><h2>Our solution: Just-in-Time mapping for any problem</h2><p>When you first open Codemaps (click the new maps icon or <strong>Cmd+Shift+C</strong> in Windsurf) with a codebase opened in Windsurf, you can enter in a prompt for the task you are trying to do, or take one of the automatic suggestions. You can choose a <strong>Fast</strong> (SWE-1.5) or <strong>Smart</strong> (Sonnet 4.5) model to generate your Codemap. Every Codemap is snapshots your code and respects ZDR.</p><p><a href="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/2mc9cv2v/production/8cbebdcf68b3099afbd2c9ea0196fcfc37ed339a-1080x510.png" target="_blank"><img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/2mc9cv2v/production/8cbebdcf68b3099afbd2c9ea0196fcfc37ed339a-1080x510.png" alt="" loading="lazy"></a></p><p>Based on our demos to customers, you will experience Codemaps best on your own codebase and asking a question about how or where some functionality works. In our dogfooding, we find particular effectiveness tracing through client-server problems or a data pipeline or debugging auth/security issues:</p><p><a href="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/2mc9cv2v/production/cbdd13ef52a6237d08d69d598ee8fbedcf7c7183-1116x2090.png" target="_blank"><img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/2mc9cv2v/production/cbdd13ef52a6237d08d69d598ee8fbedcf7c7183-1116x2090.png" alt="" loading="lazy"></a></p><p>If all you wanted was to quickly jump through grouped and nested parts of your code that related to your question, this is already an improvement compared to asking the same question in Cascade, where answers are not as densely linked to the exact lines of code.</p><p>You can also toggle over to a visually drawn Codemap, which performs the same functions when you click on individual nodes: they send you to the exact part of the codebase you clicked on.</p><p><a href="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/2mc9cv2v/production/a10c9f829feb0566341b024f1bf6d26c4825a6b5-2848x2046.png" target="_blank"><img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/2mc9cv2v/production/a10c9f829feb0566341b024f1bf6d26c4825a6b5-2848x2046.png" alt="" loading="lazy"></a></p><p>However, if you want a little more context, then you can hit “See more” in any section to expand our “trace guide” that gives a more descriptive explanation of what groups the discovered lines together.</p><p><a href="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/2mc9cv2v/production/57fa1bc99ab9afd5ac160c59576261c6217b1097-2536x1560.png" target="_blank"><img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/2mc9cv2v/production/57fa1bc99ab9afd5ac160c59576261c6217b1097-2536x1560.png" alt="" loading="lazy"></a></p><p>Finally, inside Cascade you can also reference a codemap for the agent with <code>@{codemap}</code> (all of it, or a particular subsection) in your prompt to provide more specific context and dramatically improve the performance of your agent for your task.</p><p><a href="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/2mc9cv2v/production/2558ea0c9dafe8c93810fc7ea2f2cf04f5a7dc8d-1594x2006.png" target="_blank"><img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/2mc9cv2v/production/2558ea0c9dafe8c93810fc7ea2f2cf04f5a7dc8d-1594x2006.png" alt="" loading="lazy"></a></p><h2>Fight back against Vibeslop</h2><p>We feel that the popular usage of “vibe coding” has strayed far from the original intent, into a blanket endorsement of plowing through any and all AI generated code slop. If you look at the difference between the most productive vs the problematic AI-assisted coders, the productive ones can surf the vibes of code that they understand well, whereas <strong>people get into trouble when the code they generate and maintain starts to outstrip their ability to understand it</strong>.</p><p><a href="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/2mc9cv2v/production/a0bfa8a930936a0bdadd1c771d46b4ec7df099db-1712x634.png" target="_blank"><img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/2mc9cv2v/production/a0bfa8a930936a0bdadd1c771d46b4ec7df099db-1712x634.png" alt="" loading="lazy"></a></p><p><strong>To understand is to be accountable.</strong> As AI takes on more of the easy work, the hard problems left to humans are the ones that demand real comprehension: debugging complex systems, refactoring legacy code, making architecture decisions. In this new era, <strong>the engineer’s role shifts from <em>authoring</em> to <em>accountability</em> — you might not write every line, but you’re still responsible for what ships.</strong> That accountability depends on understanding what the AI produced, why it changed, and whether it’s safe. Codemaps closes that gap by giving both the human and the AI a <em>shared picture</em> of the system: how it’s structured, how data flows, where dependencies live. Codemaps is our latest Fast Agent, but as we discussed in <a href="https://cognition.ai/blog/swe-grep#fast-context-as-the-first-step-to-fast-agents">the Semi-Async Valley of Death</a>, our goal isn't just about speed, it is to help your human engineers stay in flow, stay on top of their code, and to move faster and more confidently on the hardest problems, never shipping slop that they don't understand.</p><p><strong>Augment engineers for high value work, relieve them of low value work</strong>. The other local minima that the coding agent industry has gotten stuck in is in the general messaging of replacing engineers for low value work and not having any solutions for the hardest tasks apart from “pls ultrathink high, no mistakes”, which only gives autonomy to the agent, at the expense of the engineer. The long history of human-machine collaboration teaches us that we can always do more with the synergy rather than humans-alone or AI-alone. Our view is that the AI product that engineers will love most is the one that makes them better at their job, not the one that tries to replace them with a sloppy facsimile of themselves.</p><h2>What’s Next</h2><p>With Codemaps, we are now exposing to humans some of the indexing and analysis we do inside of our coding agents. These artifacts are sharable today across teams for learning and discussion, but we have yet to benchmark how much better they can make our coding agents like Devin and Cascade in solving challenging tasks on their own. We also see opportunities for connecting and annotating codemaps, as well as defining an open <code>.codemap</code> protocol that can be used by other code agents and custom tooling built by you. Complementing our <strong>Fast Context feature</strong>, this is an advancement in human-readable <strong>automatic context engineering</strong>.</p><p>You can try Codemaps on the latest versions of Windsurf, or DeepWiki!</p> </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Michael Burry a.k.a. "Big Short",discloses $1.1B bet against Nvidia&Palantir (183 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://sherwood.news/markets/michael-burry-big-short-discloses-1-1-billion-options-bet-against-nvidia-palantir-puts/</link>
            <guid>45813734</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 17:44:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://sherwood.news/markets/michael-burry-big-short-discloses-1-1-billion-options-bet-against-nvidia-palantir-puts/">https://sherwood.news/markets/michael-burry-big-short-discloses-1-1-billion-options-bet-against-nvidia-palantir-puts/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45813734">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-post-id="4EPAdOoOrJ3oOA3uk67W6I" id="__next"><header><div><a href="https://sherwood.news/"><div><p><img alt="Markets" src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAIAAAAAAAP///yH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAIBRAA7" decoding="async"></p></div></a></div></header><div><article><div><a href="https://sherwood.news/markets/"><div><p><img alt="markets" src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAIAAAAAAAP///yH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAIBRAA7" decoding="async"></p></div></a><div><div><p>“The Big Short” investor Michael Burry, famous for predicting the 2008 housing crash — and a number of crashes since that haven’t materialized quite as spectacularly — has placed massive bets against <span><a href="https://robinhood.com/us/en/stocks/NVDA/?source=sherwood"><span>Nvidia</span></a></span> and <span><a href="https://robinhood.com/us/en/stocks/PLTR/?source=sherwood"><span>Palantir</span></a></span>, according to a new regulatory <a href="https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1649339/000164933925000007/xslForm13F_X02/infotable.xml" target="_blank" rel="noopener">filing</a> for the quarter ended September 30.</p></div><p>The 13-F filing released Monday discloses that Burry<!-- -->’<!-- -->s fund, Scion Asset Management, bought put options on roughly 5 million Palantir shares worth <b>$912 million</b>, and 1 million Nvidia shares worth <b>$187 million</b>. Together, the two positions make up <b>80%</b> of Scion<!-- -->’<!-- -->s disclosed US equity holdings, per the 13-F.</p><div><p>Burry’s move follows a surge in both stocks amid record AI enthusiasm and rising tech valuations: <span><a href="https://robinhood.com/us/en/stocks/NVDA/?source=sherwood"><span>Nvidia</span></a></span> jumped 50% this year and <a href="https://sherwood.news/markets/nvidia-crosses-usd5-trillion-market-cap-as-batmmaan-dominates-ai/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">crossed</a> the <b>$5 trillion</b> mark in market cap for the first time, while <span><a href="https://robinhood.com/us/en/stocks/PLTR/?source=sherwood"><span>Palantir</span></a></span> is up a whopping 176% on the year, with the company just <a href="https://sherwood.news/markets/palantir-posts-ninth-straight-earnings-beat-stock-surges/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">posting</a> its ninth straight earnings beat and raising full-year revenue guidance to nearly $4.4 billion.</p><p>Burry’s bets, as well as wider concerns about the company’s stretched valuation, appear to be weighing on Palantir, which has <a href="https://sherwood.news/markets/the-negative-reaction-to-palantirs-earnings-is-spreading-to-other-volatile/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">gone into reverse</a> since posting its numbers and is now trading 6.86% lower as of 10:03 a.m. ET on Tuesday.</p><p>Nvidia was 1.8% lower as of 10:03 a.m. ET.</p><p>Last week, Burry <a href="https://x.com/michaeljburry/status/1984067754270319052?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw%7Ctwcamp%5Etweetembed%7Ctwterm%5E1984067754270319052%7Ctwgr%5E88455fa94f9397003a79266a2d1ad35bdddb43e8%7Ctwcon%5Es1_&amp;ref_url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.businessinsider.com%2Fbig-short-michael-burry-bubble-warning-x-account-scion-crash-2025-10" target="_blank" rel="noopener">warned</a> of market “bubbles” on X, writing that “sometimes the only winning move is not to play.” Scion also disclosed call options on Pfizer and Halliburton, alongside holdings in Lululemon, Bruker, Molina Healthcare, and Sallie Mae. </p></div></div><p>The 13-F filing released Monday discloses that Burry<!-- -->’<!-- -->s fund, Scion Asset Management, bought put options on roughly 5 million Palantir shares worth <b>$912 million</b>, and 1 million Nvidia shares worth <b>$187 million</b>. Together, the two positions make up <b>80%</b> of Scion<!-- -->’<!-- -->s disclosed US equity holdings, per the 13-F.</p><div><p>Burry’s move follows a surge in both stocks amid record AI enthusiasm and rising tech valuations: <span><a href="https://robinhood.com/us/en/stocks/NVDA/?source=sherwood"><span>Nvidia</span></a></span> jumped 50% this year and <a href="https://sherwood.news/markets/nvidia-crosses-usd5-trillion-market-cap-as-batmmaan-dominates-ai/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">crossed</a> the <b>$5 trillion</b> mark in market cap for the first time, while <span><a href="https://robinhood.com/us/en/stocks/PLTR/?source=sherwood"><span>Palantir</span></a></span> is up a whopping 176% on the year, with the company just <a href="https://sherwood.news/markets/palantir-posts-ninth-straight-earnings-beat-stock-surges/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">posting</a> its ninth straight earnings beat and raising full-year revenue guidance to nearly $4.4 billion.</p><p>Burry’s bets, as well as wider concerns about the company’s stretched valuation, appear to be weighing on Palantir, which has <a href="https://sherwood.news/markets/the-negative-reaction-to-palantirs-earnings-is-spreading-to-other-volatile/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">gone into reverse</a> since posting its numbers and is now trading 6.86% lower as of 10:03 a.m. ET on Tuesday.</p><p>Nvidia was 1.8% lower as of 10:03 a.m. ET.</p><p>Last week, Burry <a href="https://x.com/michaeljburry/status/1984067754270319052?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw%7Ctwcamp%5Etweetembed%7Ctwterm%5E1984067754270319052%7Ctwgr%5E88455fa94f9397003a79266a2d1ad35bdddb43e8%7Ctwcon%5Es1_&amp;ref_url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.businessinsider.com%2Fbig-short-michael-burry-bubble-warning-x-account-scion-crash-2025-10" target="_blank" rel="noopener">warned</a> of market “bubbles” on X, writing that “sometimes the only winning move is not to play.” Scion also disclosed call options on Pfizer and Halliburton, alongside holdings in Lululemon, Bruker, Molina Healthcare, and Sallie Mae. </p></div></div></article></div><div><div><a href="https://sherwood.news/markets/"><div><p><img alt="markets" src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAIAAAAAAAP///yH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAIBRAA7" decoding="async"></p></div></a><div><a href="https://sherwood.news/markets/fermi-secures-preliminary-approval-for-a-low-emissions-natural-gas-plant-to/"><h2><span>Fermi secures preliminary approval for a low-emissions natural gas plant to meet AI power demands</span></h2></a><p>Power provider <span><a href="https://robinhood.com/stocks/FRMI/?source=sherwood"><span>Fermi</span></a></span> <a href="https://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/fermi-america-and-the-state-of-texas-announce-preliminary-approval-for-first-6-gw-of-one-of-the-worlds-largest-clean-natural-gas-facilities-on-project-matadors-11-gw-private-hypergrid-campus-302603582.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">said</a> it has received preliminary approval from the Texas Commission on Environmental Quality for the planned 6 gigawatts of natural gas generation that’s part of its “Project Matador” to meet the ever-growing power demands of the AI boom. </p><p>“At Fermi, our private grid model ensures that the growing demand for AI is met privately,” Fermi America CEO and cofounder Toby Neugebauer said.</p><p>Final approval is still subject to a formal meeting and public comment.</p><p>The initial gas generators are already en route to the campus, with plans to have these installed and online in 2026, Fermi said.</p><p>Microsoft CEO Satya Nadella <a href="https://sherwood.news/markets/iren-surges-9-7-billion-deal-provide-ai-cloud-capacity-microsoft-dell-supply/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">recently remarked</a> that “the ability to get the builds done fast enough close to power” is the biggest constraint he faces, just ahead of an announced deal with IREN to purchase power-secured cloud computing capacity.</p></div></div><div><a href="https://sherwood.news/markets/"><div><p><img alt="markets" src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAIAAAAAAAP///yH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAIBRAA7" decoding="async"></p></div></a><div><a href="https://sherwood.news/markets/the-negative-reaction-to-palantirs-earnings-is-spreading-to-other-volatile/"><h2><span>The negative reaction after Palantir’s earnings is spreading to other volatile retail favorites</span></h2></a><p>Palantir is the poster child for a richly valued, retail darling, megacap momentum stock. It’s going down on <a href="https://sherwood.news/markets/stocks-are-getting-speed-checked/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">largely good news</a>, and that’s cascading to hit smaller, volatile segments of the market also beloved by the retail community.</p><ul><li><p>Fuel cell company <span><a href="https://robinhood.com/stocks/BE/?source=sherwood"><span>Bloom Energy</span></a></span> and no-revenues nuclear company <span><a href="https://robinhood.com/us/en/stocks/OKLO/?source=sherwood"><span>Oklo</span></a></span> are both off about 5% or more in early trading.</p></li><li><p>Neoclouds <span><a href="https://robinhood.com/stocks/NBIS/?source=sherwood"><span>Nebius</span></a></span> and <span><a href="https://robinhood.com/stocks/CRWV/?source=sherwood"><span>CoreWeave</span></a></span> are facing significant selling pressure.</p></li><li><p>The quantum space is getting rocked, with <span><a href="https://robinhood.com/stocks/QBTS?source=sherwood"><span>D-Wave Quantum</span></a></span>,  <span><a href="https://robinhood.com/us/en/stocks/RGTI/?source=sherwood"><span>Rigetti</span></a></span>, <span><a href="https://robinhood.com/stocks/IONQ?source=sherwood"><span>IonQ</span></a></span>, and <span><a href="https://robinhood.com/stocks/QUBT/?source=sherwood"><span>Quantum Computing</span></a></span> all down between 3% and 5% as of 9:42 a.m. ET.</p></li><li><p>Other story stocks deep in the red include <span><a href="https://robinhood.com/stocks/SOUN?source=sherwood"><span>SoundHound AI</span></a></span>, <span><a href="https://robinhood.com/us/en/stocks/RKLB/?source=sherwood"><span>Rocket Lab</span></a></span>, and <span><a href="https://robinhood.com/stocks/open?source=sherwood"><span>Opendoor Technologies</span></a></span>.</p></li></ul><p>Goldman Sachs baskets that track retail favorites and nonprofitable tech stocks are down more than 2% and 3% as of 9:43 a.m. ET, respectively, while the Invesco S&amp;P 500 High Beta ETF is also off more than 2%. </p></div></div><div><a href="https://sherwood.news/markets/stocks-are-getting-speed-checked/"><div><p><img alt="Long Island highway patrol officer using radar to check speed" src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAIAAAAAAAP///yH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAIBRAA7" decoding="async"></p></div><h2><span><span>Stocks are getting speed checked</span></span></h2></a><p>A retail favorite failing to build momentum even when it “deserves” to, the most important part of the stock market being told it’s overheating, and the heads of banks warning of a broader pullback.</p></div><div><a href="https://sherwood.news/markets/"><div><p><img alt="markets" src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAIAAAAAAAP///yH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAIBRAA7" decoding="async"></p></div></a><div><a href="https://sherwood.news/markets/spotify-whipsaws-reporting-strong-active-user-numbers-and-improved/"><h2><span>Spotify notches another quarter of strong active user growth and improved profitability</span></h2></a><p><span><a href="https://robinhood.com/us/en/stocks/SPOT/?source=sherwood"><span>Spotify</span></a></span> shares are up 3.25% as of 6:45 a.m. ET as investors digest the streaming giant’s Q3 earnings, in which the company reported that it added more than 70 million monthly active users, posted revenues that were up 7% from last year, and improved profitability. </p><p>Total revenues climbed to €4.27 billion, or around $4.91 billion, for the quarter, while net income came in at €899 million ($1.03 billion), which translated into adjusted earnings per share of €3.28 — ahead of the ~€1.96 that analysts had expected, per FactSet figures cited by <a href="https://www.wsj.com/business/earnings/spotify-spot-q3-earnings-report-2025-5483bcee" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Wall Street Journal</a>. Spotify now counts a whopping 713 million monthly active users, including 281 million premium subscribers, compared to 640 million and 252 million, respectively, on the same quarter last year. </p><p>The boosted figures come on the back of a host of new features that the streaming platform’s introduced, such as “<a href="https://newsroom.spotify.com/2025-09-10/lossless-listening-arrives-on-spotify-premium-with-a-richer-more-detailed-listening-experience/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lossless listening</a>,” <a href="https://newsroom.spotify.com/2025-09-22/mixed-playlists-debut-martin-garrix-pinkpantheress-sofi-tukker/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">playlist mixing controls</a>, and <a href="https://newsroom.spotify.com/2025-08-26/introducing-messages-a-new-way-to-share-what-you-love-on-spotify-with-friends-and-family/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">direct messages</a>. The company is now forecasting that its total monthly active users will climb to 745 million by the end of the fourth quarter.</p><p>With the latest gains today, Spotify is now up ~48% year to date, even as cofounder Daniel Ek announced <a href="https://newsroom.spotify.com/2025-09-30/spotify-announcement-daniel-ek-executive-chairman/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in September</a> that he’d be stepping down as CEO at the end of the year, almost 20 years on from the company’s inception. </p></div></div></div><section><p><h3>Latest Stories</h3></p></section><div><p>Sherwood Media, LLC produces fresh and unique perspectives on topical financial news and is a fully owned subsidiary of Robinhood Markets, Inc., and any views expressed here do not necessarily reflect the views of any other Robinhood affiliate, including Robinhood Markets, Inc., Robinhood Financial LLC, Robinhood Securities, LLC, Robinhood Crypto, LLC, or Robinhood Money, LLC.</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>