<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 10:30:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Operating System in 1,000 Lines – Intro (195 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://operating-system-in-1000-lines.vercel.app/en</link>
            <guid>42631873</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 07:18:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://operating-system-in-1000-lines.vercel.app/en">https://operating-system-in-1000-lines.vercel.app/en</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42631873">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Hey there! In this book, we're going to build a small operating system from scratch, step by step.</p>
<p>You might get intimidated when you hear OS or kernel development, the basic functions of an OS (especially the kernel) are surprisingly simple. Even Linux, which is often cited as a huge open-source software, was only 8,413 lines in version 0.01. Today's Linux kernel is overwhelmingly large, but it started with a tiny codebase, just like your hobby project.</p>
<p>We'll implement basic context switching, paging, user mode, a command-line shell, a disk device driver, and file read/write operations in C. Sounds like a lot, however, it's only 1,000 lines of code!</p>
<p>One thing you should remember is, it's not easy as it sounds. The tricky part of creating your own OS is debugging. You can't do <code>printf</code> debugging until you implement it. You'll need to learn different debugging techniques and skills you've never needed in application development. Especially when starting "from scratch", you'll encounter challenging parts like boot process and paging. But don't worry! We'll also learn "how to debug an OS" too!</p>
<p>The tougher the debugging, the more satisfying it is when it works. Let's dive into exciting world of OS development!</p>
<ul>
<li>You can download the implementation examples from <a href="https://github.com/nuta/operating-system-in-1000-lines">GitHub</a>.</li>
<li>This book is available under the <a href="https://creativecommons.jp/faq">CC BY 4.0 license</a>. The implementation examples and source code in the text are under the <a href="https://opensource.org/licenses/MIT">MIT license</a>.</li>
<li>The prerequisites are familiarity with C language and with UNIX-like environment. If you've <code>gcc hello.c &amp;&amp; ./a.out</code>, you're good to go!</li>
<li>This book was originally written as an appendix of my book <em><a href="https://www.shuwasystem.co.jp/book/9784798068718.html">Design and Implementation of Microkernels</a></em> (written in Japanese).</li>
</ul>
<p>Happy OS hacking!</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Annual 'winners' for most egregious US healthcare profiteering announced (129 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/jan/07/annual-awards-healthcare-profiteering</link>
            <guid>42630030</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 01:48:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/jan/07/annual-awards-healthcare-profiteering">https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/jan/07/annual-awards-healthcare-profiteering</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42630030">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p>The 2024 “winners” of the annual <a href="https://lowninstitute.org/projects/2024-shkreli-awards/" data-link-name="in body link">Shkreli awards</a>, given each year to perpetrators of the most egregious examples of profiteering and dysfunction within the healthcare industry, have been released from the Lown Institute, an independent healthcare thinktank.</p><p>The recipients are chosen by a panel made up of health policy experts, clinicians, journalists and advocates. The awards are named after <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/martin-shkreli" data-link-name="in body link">Martin Shkreli</a>, the infamous “pharma bro” who rose to international notoriety after increasing the price of lifesaving anti-parasitic drug Daraprim 50-fold.</p><p>“All these stories paint a picture of a healthcare industry in desperate need of transformation. In 2024, healthcare practices were put in the spotlight,” Vikas Saini, president of the Lown Institute, said during the ceremony.</p><p>“But doing these awards every year shows us that this is nothing new. We’re hoping that these stories illuminate what changes are needed.”</p><p>The No 10 spot this year went to the University of North Texas health science center in Fort Worth for allegedly neglecting to notify next of kin before selling body parts of deceased people.</p><p>An <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/university-north-texas-corpses-dissected-unclaimed-bodies-rcna170478" data-link-name="in body link">NBC News</a> investigation uncovered that the school did not properly receive consent from the deceased or their family members before dissecting and distributing unclaimed bodies, despite the network finding that said family members were fairly easy to identify and contact.</p><p>The ninth spot was given to the outdated practice of baby tongue-tie cutting, which continues to be falsely touted as a cure for several ailments, from sleep apnea to nursing trouble, according to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/07/29/health/tongue-tie-releases-aap.html#:~:text=One%20study%20estimated%20an%20800,Serious%20complications%20are%20rare." data-link-name="in body link">the New York Times</a>.</p><p>Shady billing practices from Zynex Medical, a company specializing in nerve-stimulation devices used for pain management, took the No 8 slot. Patients received Zynex devices understanding the expense would be covered by insurance, according to a report from <a href="https://www.statnews.com/2024/06/04/zynex-medical-pain-patient-tens-unit-batteries-electrodes-bills/" data-link-name="in body link">Stat News</a>. Users then got unsolicited supplies of items like batteries and electrode pads delivered to them (often excessive quantities), which they ultimately got charged for. The report states<em> </em>that almost 70% of Zynex’s $184m in revenue in 2023 came from batteries and electrode pads.</p><p>“This is just classic over-billing. It’s fraud,” Patricia Kelmar, a senior director at the research group US Pirg and judge on the panel, said. “The patients feel that they owe the money because they already received the supplies. We see a lot of this kind of abuse within the pain-management field.”</p><p>The seventh spot was given to Sara England and her infant son, Amari Vaca. After the three-month-old experienced severe respiratory distress two months after open-heart surgery, doctors at Natividad medical center in Salinas, California, chose to have him <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/health-coverage-medical-debt-air-ambulance-kff-sara-england-amari/" data-link-name="in body link">transferred via air ambulance</a> to a medical center in San Francisco. He recovered and Cigna later deemed the service “not medically necessary”. The family was given a $97,599 bill.</p><p>“This is happening everywhere,” Kelmar said. “The insurance denial here is that it should have been a ground ambulance instead of air, but how is the patient supposed to know that? This is a mother taking medical advice from the doctors.”</p><p>At No 6 was Medicare’s mass billing for urinary catheters. As many as 450,000 beneficiaries had bills for catheters submitted on their behalf in 2023, representing an 800% increase over previous years. Just <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/texas/news/i-team-texas-company-connected-to-alleged-scheme-that-billed-medicare-3b-for-urinary-catheters/" data-link-name="in body link">seven suppliers</a> were responsible for $2bn of these suspicious charges.</p><p>Taking the No 5 spot was Memorial medical center (a former non-profit turned for-profit) in Las Cruces, New Mexico, for allegations of <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/health/cancer/cancer-patients-say-new-mexico-hospital-turned-them-away-rcna147184" data-link-name="in body link">refusing cancer treatment to patients</a> or demanding upfront payments, even from those with insurance.</p><p>ProPublica’s uncovering of a once-celebrated oncologist’s pattern of <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/thomas-weiner-montana-st-peters-hospital-oncology" data-link-name="in body link">malpractice and trails of suspicious deaths</a> came in at No 4. Dr Thomas C Weiner of Helena, Montana, reportedly subjected one patient to unnecessary cancer treatments for more than a decade, amid a myriad of other shocking revelations.</p><p>Lumakras, a cancer drug from Amgen that was <a href="https://kffhealthnews.org/news/article/amgen-cancer-drug-sotorasib-lumakras-high-dosage-fda-dosing-trials/" data-link-name="in body link">granted accelerated FDA approval</a> at a daily dose of 960mg, despite findings that a 240mg dose offered similar efficacy with reduced toxicity and risk of side effects, grabbed the third spot.</p><p>“Pharma companies have that same incentive to get a return on profits,” said Kelmar. “The healthcare industry is a business, and businesses will try to get the highest profits possible.”</p><p>At No 2 was the <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2024/dec/14/unitedhealth-group-chief-andrew-witty-new-york-times-essay" data-link-name="in body link">behemoth that is UnitedHealth</a> and how it’s become the fourth-largest business in the nation. Doctors for United have reported pressure to reduce time spent with patients, and make patients seem as sick as possible through aggressive medical coding tactics.</p><p>In a highly competitive year, the top spot went to Steward Health Care, whose CEO, Ralph de la Torre, is accused of <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2024/sep/25/ralph-de-la-torre-congress-criminal-contempt" data-link-name="in body link">prioritizing private-equity profits</a> over patient care. His financial scheming led to bankruptcy, leaving hospitals in shambles, employees laid off and communities with less healthcare access.</p><p>“I want to say that this is our backyard,” said Saini.</p><p>“What was going on here was on the grapevine for many years. And if we knew about it, then we have to ask: ‘Where are the regulators? Where are the people who should’ve known better?”</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Oracle Will Not Voluntarily Withdraw JavaScript Trademark (124 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/deno_land/status/1876728474666217739</link>
            <guid>42629256</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:01:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/deno_land/status/1876728474666217739">https://twitter.com/deno_land/status/1876728474666217739</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42629256">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A day in the life of a prolific voice phishing crew (151 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://krebsonsecurity.com/2025/01/a-day-in-the-life-of-a-prolific-voice-phishing-crew/</link>
            <guid>42629163</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 23:51:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2025/01/a-day-in-the-life-of-a-prolific-voice-phishing-crew/">https://krebsonsecurity.com/2025/01/a-day-in-the-life-of-a-prolific-voice-phishing-crew/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42629163">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
												<p>Besieged by scammers seeking to phish user accounts over the telephone, <strong>Apple</strong> and <strong>Google</strong> frequently caution that they will never reach out unbidden to users this way. However, new details about the internal operations of a prolific voice phishing gang show the group routinely abuses legitimate services at Apple and Google to force a variety of outbound communications to their users, including emails, automated phone calls and system-level messages sent to all signed-in devices.</p>
<div id="attachment_69859"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-69859" decoding="async" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/thumb-mobile.png" alt="" width="701" height="413"></p><p id="caption-attachment-69859">Image: Shutterstock, iHaMoo.</p></div>
<p>KrebsOnSecurity recently told the saga of a cryptocurrency investor named <strong>Tony</strong> who was robbed of more than $4.7 million in <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2024/12/how-to-lose-a-fortune-with-just-one-bad-click/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an elaborate voice phishing attack</a>. In Tony’s ordeal, the crooks appear to have initially contacted him via <strong>Google Assistant</strong>, an AI-based service that can engage in two-way conversations. The phishers also abused legitimate Google services to send Tony an email from google.com, and to send a Google account recovery prompt to all of his signed-in devices.</p>
<p>Today’s story pivots off of Tony’s heist and new details shared by a scammer to explain how these voice phishing groups are abusing a legitimate Apple telephone support line to generate “account confirmation” message prompts from Apple to their customers.</p>
<p>Before we get to the Apple scam in detail, we need to revisit Tony’s case. The phishing domain used to steal roughly $4.7 million in cryptocurrencies from Tony was <strong>verify-trezor[.]io</strong>. This domain was featured in <a href="https://www.lookout.com/threat-intelligence/article/cryptochameleon-fcc-phishing-kit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a writeup from February 2024</a> by the security firm <strong>Lookout</strong>, which found it was one of dozens being used by a prolific and audacious voice phishing group it dubbed “<strong>Crypto Chameleon</strong>.”</p>
<p>Crypto Chameleon was brazenly trying to voice phish employees at the <strong>U.S. Federal Communications Commission</strong> (FCC), as well as those working at the cryptocurrency exchanges <strong>Coinbase</strong> and <strong>Binance</strong>. Lookout researchers discovered multiple voice phishing groups were using a new phishing kit that closely mimicked the single sign-on pages for <strong>Okta</strong> and other authentication providers.</p>
<p>As we’ll see in a moment, that phishing kit is operated and rented out by a cybercriminal known as “<strong>Perm</strong>” a.k.a. “<strong>Annie</strong>.” Perm is the current administrator of <strong>Star Fraud</strong>, one of the more consequential cybercrime communities on Telegram and one that has emerged as a foundry of innovation in voice phishing attacks.</p>
<p>A review of the many messages that Perm posted to Star Fraud and other Telegram channels showed they worked closely with another cybercriminal who went by the handles “<strong>Aristotle</strong>” and just “<strong>Stotle</strong>.”</p>
<p>It is not clear what caused the rift, but at some point last year Stotle decided to turn on his erstwhile business partner Perm, sharing extremely detailed videos, tutorials and secrets that shed new light on how these phishing panels operate.</p>
<p>Stotle explained that the division of spoils from each robbery is decided in advance by all participants. Some co-conspirators will be paid a set fee for each call, while others are promised a percentage of any overall amount stolen. The person in charge of managing or renting out the phishing panel to others will generally take a percentage of each theft, which in Perm’s case is 10 percent.</p>
<p>When the phishing group settles on a target of interest, the scammers will create and join a new <strong>Discord</strong> channel. This allows each logged on member to share what is currently on their screen, and these screens are tiled in a series of boxes so that everyone can see all other call participant screens at once.</p>
<p>Each participant in the call has a specific role, including:</p>
<p>-The Caller: The person speaking and trying to social engineer the target.<br>
-The Operator: The individual managing the phishing panel, silently moving the victim from page to page.<br>
-The Drainer: The person who logs into compromised accounts to drain the victim’s funds.<br>
-The Owner: The phishing panel owner, who will frequently listen in on and participate in scam calls.</p>
<h2>‘OKAY, SO THIS REALLY IS APPLE’</h2>
<p>In one video of a live voice phishing attack shared by Stotle, scammers using Perm’s panel targeted a musician in California. Throughout the video, we can see Perm monitoring the conversation and operating the phishing panel in the upper right corner of the screen.</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" title="YouTube video player" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/F44un1_y2fs?si=fmYxbcLS3TDtHjrs" width="750" height="315" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"><span data-mce-type="bookmark" style="display: inline-block; width: 0px; overflow: hidden; line-height: 0;" class="mce_SELRES_start">﻿</span></iframe></p>
<p>In the first step of the attack, they <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2024/03/recent-mfa-bombing-attacks-targeting-apple-users/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">peppered the target’s Apple device with notifications from Apple</a> by attempting to reset his password. Then a “<strong>Michael Keen</strong>” called him, spoofing Apple’s phone number and saying they were with Apple’s account recovery team.</p>
<p>The target told Michael that someone was trying to change his password, which Michael calmly explained they would investigate. Michael said he was going to send a prompt to the man’s device, and proceeded to place a call to an automated line that answered as Apple support saying, “I’d like to send a consent notification to your Apple devices. Do I have permission to do that?”</p>
<p>In this segment of the video, we can see the operator of the panel is calling the real Apple customer support phone number <strong>800-275-2273</strong>, but they are doing so by spoofing the target’s phone number (the victim’s number is redacted in the video above). That’s because calling this support number from a phone number tied to an Apple account and selecting “1” for “yes” will then send an alert from Apple that displays the following message on all associated devices:</p>
<div id="attachment_70000"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-70000" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/appleconfirmation.png" alt="" width="393" height="448"></p><p id="caption-attachment-70000">Calling the Apple support number 800-275-2273 from a phone number tied to an Apple account will cause a prompt similar to this one to appear on all connected Apple devices.</p></div>
<p>KrebsOnSecurity asked two different security firms to test this using the caller ID spoofing service shown in Perm’s video, and sure enough calling that 800 number for Apple by spoofing my phone number as the source caused the Apple Account Confirmation to pop up on all of my signed-in Apple devices.</p>
<p>In essence, the voice phishers are using an automated Apple phone support line to send notifications from Apple and to trick people into thinking they’re really talking with Apple. The phishing panel video leaked by Stotle shows this technique fooled the target, who felt completely at ease that he was talking to Apple after receiving the support prompt on his iPhone.</p>
<p>“Okay, so this really is Apple,” the man said after receiving the alert from Apple. “Yeah, that’s definitely not me trying to reset my password.”</p>
<p>“Not a problem, we can go ahead and take care of this today,” Michael replied. “I’ll go ahead and prompt your device with the steps to close out this ticket. Before I do that, I do highly suggest that you change your password in the settings app of your device.”</p>
<p>The target said they weren’t sure exactly how to do that. Michael replied “no problem,” and then described how to change the account password, which the man said he did on his own device. At this point, the musician was still in control of his iCloud account.</p>
<p>“Password is changed,” the man said. “I don’t know what that was, but I appreciate the call.”</p>
<p>“Yup,” Michael replied, setting up the killer blow. “I’ll go ahead and prompt you with the next step to close out this ticket. Please give me one moment.”</p>
<p>The target then received a text message that referenced information about his account, stating that he was in a support call with Michael. Included in the message was a link to a website that mimicked Apple’s iCloud login page — <strong>17505-apple[.]com</strong>. Once the target navigated to the phishing page, the video showed Perm’s screen in the upper right corner opening the phishing page from their end.</p>
<p>“Oh okay, now I log in with my Apple ID?,” the man asked.</p>
<p>“Yup, then just follow the steps it requires, and if you need any help, just let me know,” Michael replied.</p>
<p>As the victim typed in their Apple password and one-time passcode at the fake Apple site, Perm’s screen could be seen in the background logging into the victim’s iCloud account.</p>
<p>It’s unclear whether the phishers were able to steal any cryptocurrency from the victim in this case, who did not respond to requests for comment. However, shortly after this video was recorded, someone leaked several music recordings stolen from the victim’s iCloud account.</p>
<p>At the conclusion of the call, Michael offered to configure the victim’s Apple profile so that any further changes to the account would need to happen in person at a physical Apple store. This appears to be one of several scripted ploys used by these voice phishers to gain and maintain the target’s confidence.</p>
<p>A tutorial shared by Stotle titled “Social Engineering Script” includes a number of tips for scam callers that can help establish trust or a rapport with their prey. When the callers are impersonating Coinbase employees, for example, they will offer to sign the user up for the company’s free security email newsletter.</p>
<p>“Also, for your security, we are able to subscribe you to Coinbase Bytes, which will basically give you updates to your email about data breaches and updates to your Coinbase account,” the script reads. “So we should have gone ahead and successfully subscribed you, and you should have gotten an email confirmation. Please let me know if that is the case. Alright, perfect.”</p>
<p>In reality, all they are doing is entering the target’s email address into Coinbase’s public email newsletter signup page, but it’s a remarkably effective technique because it demonstrates to the would-be victim that the caller has the ability to send emails from Coinbase.com.</p>
<p>Asked to comment for this story, Apple said there has been no breach, hack, or technical exploit of iCloud or Apple services, and that the company is continuously adding new protections to address new and emerging threats. For example, it said it has implemented rate limiting for multi-factor authentication requests, which <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2024/03/recent-mfa-bombing-attacks-targeting-apple-users/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have been abused by voice phishing groups to impersonate Apple</a>.</p>
<p>Apple said its representatives will never ask users to provide their password, device passcode, or two-factor authentication code or to enter it into a web page, even if it looks like an official Apple website. If a user receives a message or call that claims to be from Apple, <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/120569" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here is what the user should expect</a>.</p>

<h2>AUTODOXERS</h2>
<p>According to Stotle, the target lists used by their phishing callers originate mostly from a few crypto-related data breaches, including the 2022 and <a href="https://blog.trezor.io/trezor-security-update-stay-vigilant-against-potential-phishing-attack-bb05015a21f8?gi=4a9e1da3b8b2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2024 breaches</a> involving user account data stolen from cryptocurrency hardware wallet vendor <strong>Trezor</strong>.</p>
<p>Perm’s group and other crypto phishing gangs rely on a mix of homemade code and third-party data broker services to refine their target lists. Known as “<strong>autodoxers</strong>,” these tools help phishing gangs quickly automate the acquisition and/or verification of personal data on a target prior to each call attempt.</p>
<div id="attachment_69998"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-69998" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/vbals-autodoxer.png" alt="" width="748" height="592" srcset="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/vbals-autodoxer.png 1067w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/vbals-autodoxer-768x607.png 768w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/vbals-autodoxer-782x619.png 782w" sizes="(max-width: 748px) 100vw, 748px"></p><p id="caption-attachment-69998">One “autodoxer” service advertised on Telegram that promotes a range of voice phishing tools and services.</p></div>
<p>Stotle said their autodoxer used a Telegram bot that leverages hacked accounts at consumer data brokers to gather a wealth of information about their targets, including their full Social Security number, date of birth, current and previous addresses, employer, and the names of family members.</p>
<p>The autodoxers are used to verify that each email address on a target list has an active account at Coinbase or another cryptocurrency exchange, ensuring that the attackers don’t waste time calling people who have no cryptocurrency to steal.</p>
<p>Some of these autodoxer tools also will check the value of the target’s home address at property search services online, and then sort the target lists so that the wealthiest are at the top.</p>
<h2>CRYPTO THIEVES IN THE SHARK TANK</h2>
<p>Stotle’s messages on Discord and Telegram show that a phishing group renting Perm’s panel voice-phished tens of thousands of dollars worth of cryptocurrency from the billionaire <strong>Mark Cuban</strong>.</p>
<p>“I was an idiot,” Cuban told KrebsOnsecurity when asked about <a href="https://www.dallasnews.com/business/2024/06/23/mark-cubans-public-email-was-hacked-after-receiving-call-from-a-fake-google-rep/?outputType=amp" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the June 2024 attack</a>, which he first disclosed in a short-lived post on Twitter/X. “We were shooting Shark Tank and I was rushing between pitches.”</p>
<div id="attachment_70008"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-70008" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/sharktank.png" alt="" width="749" height="435" srcset="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/sharktank.png 780w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/sharktank-768x446.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 749px) 100vw, 749px"></p><p id="caption-attachment-70008">Image: Shutterstock, ssi77.</p></div>
<p>Cuban said he first received a notice from Google that someone had tried to log in to his account. Then he got a call from what appeared to be a Google phone number. Cuban said he ignored several of these emails and calls until he decided they probably wouldn’t stop unless he answered.</p>
<p>“So I answered, and wasn’t paying enough attention,” he said. “They asked for the circled number that comes up on the screen. Like a moron, I gave it to them, and they were in.”</p>
<p>Unfortunately for Cuban, somewhere in his inbox were the secret “seed phrases” protecting two of his cryptocurrency accounts, and armed with those credentials the crooks were able to drain his funds. All told, the thieves managed to steal roughly $43,000 worth of cryptocurrencies from Cuban’s wallets — a relatively small heist for this crew.</p>
<p>“They must have done some keyword searches,” once inside his Gmail account, Cuban said. “I had sent myself an email I had forgotten about that had my seed words for 2 accounts that weren’t very active any longer. I had moved almost everything but some smaller balances to Coinbase.”</p>
<h2>LIFE IS A GAME: MONEY IS HOW WE KEEP SCORE</h2>
<p>Cybercriminals involved in voice phishing communities on Telegram are universally obsessed with their crypto holdings, mainly because in this community one’s demonstrable wealth is primarily what confers social status. It is not uncommon to see members sizing one another up using a verbal shorthand of “figs,” as in figures of crypto wealth.</p>
<p>For example, a low-level caller with no experience will sometimes be mockingly referred to as a 3fig or 3f, as in a person with less than $1,000 to their name. Salaries for callers are often also referenced this way, e.g. “Weekly salary: 5f.”</p>
<div id="attachment_70058"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-70058" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/howitstartedhowitsgoing.png" alt="" width="749" height="416" srcset="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/howitstartedhowitsgoing.png 1265w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/howitstartedhowitsgoing-768x426.png 768w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/howitstartedhowitsgoing-782x434.png 782w" sizes="(max-width: 749px) 100vw, 749px"></p><p id="caption-attachment-70058">This meme shared by Stotle uses humor to depict an all-too-common pathway for voice phishing callers, who are often minors recruited from gaming networks like Minecraft and Roblox. The image that Lookout used in its blog post for Crypto Chameleon can be seen in the lower right hooded figure.</p></div>
<p>Voice phishing groups frequently require new members to provide “proof of funds” — screenshots of their crypto holdings, ostensibly to demonstrate they are not penniless — before they’re allowed to join.</p>
<p>This proof of funds (POF) demand is typical among thieves selling high-dollar items, because it tends to cut down on the time-wasting inquiries from criminals who can’t afford what’s for sale anyway. But it has become so common in cybercrime communities that there are now several services designed to create fake POF images and videos, allowing customers to brag about large crypto holdings without actually possessing said wealth.</p>
<p>Several of the phishing panel videos shared by Stotle feature audio that suggests co-conspirators were practicing responses to certain call scenarios, while other members of the phishing group critiqued them or tried disrupt their social engineering by being verbally abusive.</p>
<p>These groups will organize and operate for a few weeks, but tend to disintegrate when one member of the conspiracy decides to steal some or all of the loot, referred to in these communities as “snaking” others out of their agreed-upon sums. Almost invariably, the phishing groups will splinter apart over the drama caused by one of these snaking events, and individual members eventually will then re-form a new phishing group.</p>
<p><strong>Allison Nixon</strong> is the chief research officer for <a href="https://www.unit221b.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Unit 221B</a>, a cybersecurity firm in New York that has worked on a number of investigations involving these voice phishing groups. Nixon said the constant snaking within the voice phishing circles points to a psychological self-selection phenomenon that is in desperate need of academic study.</p>
<p>“In short, a person whose moral compass lets them rob old people will also be a bad business partner,” Nixon said. “This is another fundamental flaw in this ecosystem and why most groups end in betrayal. This structural problem is great for journalists and the police too. Lots of snitching.”</p>
<h2>POINTS FOR BRAZENNESS</h2>
<p>Asked about the size of Perm’s phishing enterprise, Stotle said there were dozens of distinct phishing groups paying to use Perm’s panel. He said each group was assigned their own subdomain on Perm’s main “command and control server,” which naturally uses the domain name <strong>commandandcontrolserver[.]com</strong>.</p>
<p>A review of that domain’s history via <strong>DomainTools.com</strong> shows there are at least 57 separate subdomains scattered across commandandcontrolserver[.]com and two other related control domains — <strong>thebackendserver[.]com</strong> and <strong>lookoutsucks[.]com</strong>. That latter domain was created and deployed shortly after Lookout published its blog post on Crypto Chameleon.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://urlscan.io/search/#page.url%3A%22captcha%3Forigin%3D%22" target="_blank" rel="noopener">dozens of phishing domains that phone home to these control servers</a> are all kept offline when they are not actively being used in phishing attacks. A social engineering training guide shared by Stotle explains this practice minimizes the chances that a phishing domain will get “redpaged,” a reference to the default red warning pages served by Google Chrome or Firefox whenever someone tries to visit a site that’s been flagged for phishing or distributing malware.</p>
<p>What’s more, while the phishing sites are live their operators typically place a CAPTCHA challenge in front of the main page to prevent security services from scanning and flagging the sites as malicious.</p>
<p>It may seem odd that so many cybercriminal groups operate so openly on instant collaboration networks like Telegram and Discord. After all, this blog is replete with stories about cybercriminals getting caught thanks to personal details they inadvertently leaked or disclosed themselves.</p>
<p>Nixon said the relative openness of these cybercrime communities makes them inherently risky, but it also allows for the rapid formation and recruitment of new potential co-conspirators. Moreover, today’s English-speaking cybercriminals tend to be <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2024/10/lamborghini-carjackers-lured-by-243m-cyberheist/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more afraid of getting home invaded or mugged by fellow cyber thieves</a> than they are of being arrested by authorities.</p>
<p>“The biggest structural threat to the online criminal ecosystem is not the police or researchers, it is fellow criminals,” Nixon said. “To protect them from themselves, every criminal forum and marketplace has a reputation system, even though they know it’s a major liability when the police come. That is why I am not worried as we see criminals migrate to various ‘encrypted’ platforms that promise to ignore the&nbsp;police. To protect themselves better against the&nbsp;law, they have to ditch their protections against fellow&nbsp;criminals and that’s not going to happen.”</p>
											</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Servo Revival: 2023-2024 (150 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blogs.igalia.com/mrego/servo-revival-2023-2024/</link>
            <guid>42628414</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 22:25:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blogs.igalia.com/mrego/servo-revival-2023-2024/">https://blogs.igalia.com/mrego/servo-revival-2023-2024/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42628414">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="skip">
				






<ul>
	<li><time datetime="2024-11-15">15 November 2024</time></li>
	<li><a href="https://blogs.igalia.com/mrego/tags/english/">English</a></li>
	<li><a href="https://blogs.igalia.com/mrego/tags/planet/">Planet</a></li>
	<li><a href="https://blogs.igalia.com/mrego/tags/servo/">Servo</a></li>
</ul>

<p>As many of you already know, <strong><a href="https://www.igalia.com/">Igalia</a> took over the maintenance of the <a href="https://servo.org/">Servo</a> project in January 2023</strong>.
We’ve been working hard on bringing the project back to life again, and this blog post is a summary of our achievements so far.</p>
<h2 id="some-history-first" tabindex="-1">Some history first <a href="#some-history-first">#</a></h2>
<p><em>You can skip this this section if you already know about the Servo project.</em></p>
<p>Servo is an experimental browser engine created by <a href="https://www.mozilla.org/">Mozilla</a> in 2012.
From the very beginning, it was developed alongside the Rust language, like a showcase for the new language that Mozilla was developing.
Servo has always aimed to be a <strong>performant and secure web rendering engine</strong>, as those are also main characteristics of the Rust language.</p>
<p><strong>Mozilla was the main force behind Servo’s development for many years</strong>, with some other companies like Samsung collaborating too.
Some of Servo’s components, like Stylo and WebRender, were adopted and used in Firefox releases by 2017, and continue to be used there today.</p>
<p><strong>In 2020</strong>, Mozilla laid off the whole Servo team, and <a href="https://www.linuxfoundation.org/press/press-release/open-source-web-engine-servo-to-be-hosted-at-linux-foundation"><strong>the project moved to the Linux Foundation</strong></a>.
Despite some initial interest in the project, by the end of 2020 there was barely any active work on the project, and 2021 and 2022 weren’t any better.
At that point, many considered the Servo project to be abandoned.</p>
<h2 id="2023-igalia-takes-over-maintenance-of-servo" tabindex="-1">2023: Igalia takes over maintenance of Servo <a href="#2023-igalia-takes-over-maintenance-of-servo">#</a></h2>
<p>Things changed in 2023, when <strong>Igalia</strong> got external funding to work on Servo and get the project moving again.
We have previous experience working on Servo during the Mozilla years, and we also have a wide experience working on other web rendering engines.</p>
<p>To explore new markets and grow a stable community, the <a href="https://linuxfoundation.eu/newsroom/servo-web-rendering-engine-joins-linux-foundation-europe"><strong>Servo project joined Linux Foundation Europe</strong></a> in September 2023, and is now one of the most active projects there.
LF Europe is an umbrella organization that hosts the Servo project, and provides us with opportunities to showcase Servo at several events.</p>
<p>Over the last two years, Igalia has had a team of around <strong>five engineers working full-time</strong> on the Servo project.
We’re taking care of the project maintenance, communication, community governance, and a large portion of development.
We have also been looking for new partners and organizations that may be interested in the Servo project, and can devote resources or money towards moving it forward.</p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://blogs.igalia.com/mrego/files/2024/11/servo-talk.jpg" alt="Picture of the Servo Project Updates talk at Linux Foundation Europe Member Summit 2024. In the picture you can see a room with a group of people sitting watching the presentation. On the projector there is a slide about Servo usage exmaples showing Tauri, Qt WebView, Blitz and Verso. Manuel Rego is giving the talk at the right of the projector.">
  <figcaption>Servo Project Updates talk at Linux Foundation Europe Member Summing 2024 (<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/linuxfoundation/54033006044/in/album-72177720320738433">Picture by Linux Foundation</a>)</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="achievements" tabindex="-1">Achievements <a href="#achievements">#</a></h2>
<p>Two years is not a lot of time for a project like Servo, and we’re very proud of what we’ve achieved in this period.
Some highlights, including work from Igalia and the wider Servo community:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Maintenance</strong>: General project maintenance, tooling, documentation, community, and governance work.
Lots of work has been put in upgrading Servo dependencies, specially the big ones (<a href="https://github.com/servo/mozjs">SpiderMonkey</a>, <a href="https://github.com/servo/stylo">Stylo</a> and <a href="https://github.com/servo/webrender">WebRender</a>).
There have been improvements in Servo’s CI and tooling.
We now have a <a href="https://book.servo.org/">Servo book</a>, the Servo community has been growing, and <a href="https://github.com/servo/project/blob/main/governance/tsc/README.md">the Technical Steering Committee (TSC) is running periodic meetings every month</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Communications</strong>: The project is alive again and we want the world to know it, so we’ve been doing <a href="https://servo.org/blog/">monthly blog posts</a>, weekly updates on social media, plus <a href="https://servo.org/about/#presentations">conference talks</a> and booths at several events.
The project is more popular than ever, and our <a href="https://star-history.com/#servo/servo">GitHub stars haven’t stopped growing</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Layout engine</strong>: Servo had two layout engines: its original one, and a newer one started around 2020, which follows specs more closely but was in very early stages.
After <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/wiki/Servo-Layout-Engines-Report">some analysis</a>, we decided to go with the new layout engine and start to implement features in it like floats, tables, flexbox, fonts, right-to-left, etc.
We now pass 1.4 million subtests (1,401,889 at the time of publishing this blog post) in the <a href="https://wpt.fyi/results/?product=servo">Web Platform Tests</a>.
And of the tests we run today, <a href="https://wpt.servo.org/">our overall pass rate</a> has gone from 40.8% in April 2023 to 62.0% (+21.2). 📈</li>
<li><strong>New platforms</strong>: Servo used to support Linux, macOS, and Windows.
That’s still the case, but we’ve also added support for Android and OpenHarmony, helping us reach a wide range of mobile devices. 📱</li>
<li><strong>Embedded experiments</strong>: We’ve been working with the developers of <a href="https://github.com/tauri-apps/wry/tree/servo-wry-demo">Tauri</a>, making Servo easier to embed and creating a first prototype of <a href="https://servo.org/blog/2024/01/19/embedding-update/">using Servo as web engine in WRY</a>.
Our community has also experimented with integrating Servo in other projects, including <a href="https://github.com/DioxusLabs/blitz">Blitz</a>, <a href="https://github.com/KDABLabs/cxx-qt-servo-webview">Qt WebView</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/versotile-org/verso/">Verso</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Outreachy</strong>: <a href="https://www.outreachy.org/">Outreachy</a> is an internship program for getting people from underrepresented groups into our industry via FOSS, and we’ve rejoined the program in 2024.
Our intern in the May cohort, <a href="https://github.com/eerii">@eerii</a>, <a href="https://servo.org/blog/2024/09/20/devtools/">brought DevTools support back to Servo</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p>Of course, it’s impossible to summarize all of the work that happened in so much time, with so many people working together to achieve these great results.
<strong>Big thanks to everyone that has collaborated on the project! 🙏</strong></p>
<figure>
  <video src="https://blogs.igalia.com/mrego/files/2024/11/servoshell.webm" controls="" title="Screencast of Servo browsing the servo.org website and some Wikipedia articles">
    Screencast of Servo browsing the servo.org website and some Wikipedia articles.
  </video>
  <figcaption>Screencast of Servo browsing the servo.org website and some Wikipedia articles</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="some-numbers" tabindex="-1">Some numbers <a href="#some-numbers">#</a></h2>
<p>While it’s hard to list all of our achievements, we can take a look at some stats.
Numbers are always tricky to draw conclusions from, but we’ve been taking a look at the number of PRs merged in <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo">Servo’s main repository</a> since 2018, to understand how the project is faring.</p>
<div>
  <table>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th></th>
        <th>2018</th>
        <th>2019</th>
        <th>2020</th>
        <th>2021</th>
        <th>2022</th>
        <th>2023</th>
        <th>2024</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td><strong>PRs</strong></td>
        <td>1,188</td>
        <td>986</td>
        <td>669</td>
        <td>118</td>
        <td>65</td>
        <td>776</td>
        <td>1,771</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><strong>Contributors</strong></td>
        <td>27.33</td>
        <td>27.17</td>
        <td>14.75</td>
        <td>4.92</td>
        <td>2.83</td>
        <td>11.33</td>
        <td>26.33</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><strong>Contributors ≥ 10</strong></td>
        <td>2.58</td>
        <td>1.67</td>
        <td>1.17</td>
        <td>0.08</td>
        <td>0.00</td>
        <td>1.58</td>
        <td>4.67</td>
    </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</div>
<ul>
<li><strong>PRs</strong>: total numbers of PRs merged.
We’re now doing more than we were doing in 2018-2019.</li>
<li><strong>Contributors</strong>: average number of contributors per month.
We’re getting very close to the numbers of 2018-2019, it looks like a good number.</li>
<li><strong>Contributors ≥ 10</strong>: average number of contributors that have merged more than 10 PRs per month.
In this case we already have bigger numbers than in 2018-2019.</li>
</ul>



<p>As a clarification, these numbers don’t include PRs from bots (<code>dependabot</code> and <code>Servo WPT Sync</code>).</p>
<p>Our participation in Outreachy has also made a marked difference.
During each month-long contribution period, we get a huge influx of new people contributing to the project.
This year, we participated in both the May and December cohorts, and the contribution periods are very visible in our March and October 2024 stats:</p>
<div>
  <table>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th></th>
        <th>Jan</th>
        <th>Feb</th>
        <th>Mar</th>
        <th>Apr</th>
        <th>May</th>
        <th>Jun</th>
        <th>Jul</th>
        <th>Aug</th>
        <th>Sep</th>
        <th>Oct</th>
        <th>Nov</th>
        <th>Dec</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td><strong>PRs</strong></td>
        <td>103</td>
        <td>97</td>
        <td>255</td>
        <td>111</td>
        <td>71</td>
        <td>96</td>
        <td>103</td>
        <td>188</td>
        <td>167</td>
        <td>249</td>
        <td>170</td>
        <td>161</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><strong>Contributors</strong></td>
        <td>19</td>
        <td>22</td>
        <td>32</td>
        <td>27</td>
        <td>23</td>
        <td>22</td>
        <td>30</td>
        <td>31</td>
        <td>24</td>
        <td>37</td>
        <td>21</td>
        <td>28</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><strong>Contributors ≥ 10</strong></td>
        <td>2</td>
        <td>3</td>
        <td>9</td>
        <td>3</td>
        <td>2</td>
        <td>2</td>
        <td>2</td>
        <td>6</td>
        <td>5</td>
        <td>8</td>
        <td>7</td>
        <td>7</td>
    </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</div>



<p>Anyway overall, we think <strong>these numbers ratify that the project is back to life</strong>, and the community is growing and engaging with the project.
We’re very happy about them.</p>
<h2 id="donations" tabindex="-1">Donations <a href="#donations">#</a></h2>
<p><a href="https://servo.org/blog/2024/03/12/sponsoring-servo/">Early this year</a> we set up the <a href="https://opencollective.com/servo"><strong>Servo Open Collective</strong></a> and <a href="https://github.com/sponsors/servo"><strong>GitHub Sponsors</strong></a>, where many people and organizations have since been donating to the project.
We decide how to spend this money transparently in the TSC, and so far we’ve used it to cover the project’s infrastructure costs, like self-hosted runners to speed up CI times.</p>
<p>We’re very grateful to everyone donating money to the project, so far adding up to <strong>over $24,500 from more than 500 donors</strong>.
<strong>Thank you! 🙏</strong></p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://blogs.igalia.com/mrego/files/2024/11/servo-booth.jpg" alt="Picture of the Servo booth at Linux Foundation Europe Member Summit 2024. It's a talbe with a TV on the left showing a video of Servo running on Raspberry Pi, there's also a smaller screen on the right, showing a presentation about Servo. Behind the table there's a Servo banner. Over the table there is a Raspberry Pi, a Rockchip board and an Android phone. There are also stikcers and flyers.">
  <figcaption>Servo booth at Linux Foundation Europe Member Summing 2024 (<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/linuxfoundation/54031806317/in/album-72177720320738433">Picture by Linux Foundation</a>)</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="about-the-future" tabindex="-1">About the future <a href="#about-the-future">#</a></h2>
<p>Servo has a lot of potential.
Several things make it a very special project:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Independent</strong>: Servo is managed under Linux Foundation Europe with an open governance model, which we believe is very important for the open web ecosystem as a whole.</li>
<li><strong>Performant</strong>: Servo is the only web rendering engine that uses parallel layout for web content.
Though Servo is not yet faster than other web engines that are already production-ready, we’re exploring new ways to render web content that take advantage of modern CPUs with many cores.</li>
<li><strong>Secure</strong>: Servo is written in Rust, which prevents many security vulnerabilities by design, such as memory safety bugs.
Other kinds of unsoundness, such as concurrency bugs, are also easier to manage in Rust.</li>
</ul>
<p>Of course, the project has some challenges too:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Experimental</strong>: Servo is still in an experimental phase and is not a production-ready product.
We still lack several features that are important for web content.</li>
<li><strong>Competition</strong>: The dominant web rendering engines have huge teams behind them, working on making them better, faster, and more complete.
Catching up with them is a really complex task.</li>
<li><strong>Funding</strong>: This is a key topic for any open source project, and Servo is no different in this regard.
We need organizations from public and private sectors to join efforts with us, and grow a healthy ecosystem around the project.</li>
</ul>
<p>To finish on a positive note, we also have some key opportunities:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Single web apps</strong>: Servo may excel at rendering specific web apps in embedded scenarios, where the HTML and CSS features are known in advance.</li>
<li><strong>UI frameworks</strong>: UI frameworks in the Rust ecosystem could start using Servo as web engine to render their contents.</li>
<li><strong>Web engine</strong>: Servo could become the default web engine for any Rust application.</li>
<li><strong>Web browser</strong>: In the future, we could grow into being able to develop a full-featured web browser.</li>
</ul>
<p>The future of Servo, as with many other open source projects, is still uncertain.
We’ll see how things go in the coming years, but we would love to see that the Servo project can keep growing.</p>
<p>Servo is a huge project.
To keep it alive and making progress, we need continuous funding on a bigger scale than crowdfunding can generally accomplish.
If you’re interested in contributing to the project or sponsoring the development of specific functionality, please contact us at <a href="mailto:join@servo.org">join@servo.org</a> or <a href="https://www.igalia.com/contact/">igalia.com/contact</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Let’s hope we can walk this path together and keep working on Servo for many years ahead. 🤞</strong></p>
<p><em>PS: Special thanks to my colleague <a href="https://www.azabani.com/">Delan Azabani</a> for proofreading and copyediting this blog post. 🙏</em></p>

<ul><li>Previous: <a href="https://blogs.igalia.com/mrego/servo-at-fosdem-2024/">Servo at FOSDEM 2024</a></li>
</ul>

			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Laid off for the first time in my career, and twice in one year (234 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://dillonshook.com/laid-off/</link>
            <guid>42627567</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 21:14:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://dillonshook.com/laid-off/">https://dillonshook.com/laid-off/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42627567">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-pagefind-body=""><p>So, I got laid off again… This time it was the week before Christmas, last time it was a week into paternity leave. Both great timing, I know. Last time I didn’t feel like writing about it since it was a swirl of emotions with a new baby in the house and the first time I had been laid off in my career, 13 years in at that point. But this time I’m ready to get it out in a post that’s cathartic for me to write and something you might relate to. If you don’t relate now, I hope it stays that way. Hopefully this post will give you a bit of perspective if you ever do unexpectedly lose your job.</p><h2 id="the-indigo-story">The Indigo Story<a href="#the-indigo-story"><span data-pagefind-ignore="">#</span></a></h2><p>For both my stories you’re not going to find any shit-talking here for a number of reasons. First, that’s not the kind of person I am. Second, I feel fairly treated given both companies circumstances. And third, I want to keep good relationships with the people both that were laid off at the same time and the people still at both companies. Keeping good connections with your coworkers and not burning bridges is one of the most important things I think you can do in your career.</p><p>So with that out of the way, let’s talk about the Indigo story a bit.</p><p>One week into paternity leave delirious with sleep deprivation and all the emotions of now caring and loving for such a tiny helpless little baby I remember getting a text from a coworker saying I should probably check my email. A bunch of thoughts and feels rushed in seemingly all at once. What’s going on? Am I getting laid off? I knew there was a chance since the company had multiple rounds of layoffs before but it wasn’t really happening to me on leave right? What was going to happen to our health insurance? Did I do something wrong? How many more people were getting laid off? It felt like ages till the HR call was scheduled and I found out some of the details.</p><p>A wave of relief took over after hearing I would get paid out for my paternity leave with severance on top so I could take a deep breath, relax, and enjoy being with my wife and daughter for her first few weeks on the planet we call Earth.</p><p>After a week or two when it felt like we were starting to form something resembling a routine it was time to crack back open the resume. This always feels daunting after being at a company for awhile. How do you succinctly summarize and highlight all you’ve done there? Luckily I had some notes from my own self review one year to help but I also made a mental note to myself to start writing down accomplishments as they happen to make this easier next time.</p><p>Once I was happy with the updates I got right into the most difficult job search process I’d experienced since trying to find my first software engineering job out of college. I was being selective and only applying for places I’d realistically want to work for and also screening out companies that didn’t seem to have a viable business model which narrowed the field by more than half.</p><p>Ultimately it’s a pipeline numbers game though so I kept applying, kept interviewing, and kept persisting until I found a match. My funnel ended up looking like this</p><p><img alt="Job Hunt" src="https://dillonshook.com/_astro/jobhunt.CgaTHyCX_oANgU.webp" decoding="async" height="597" loading="lazy" width="999"></p><p>It’s easy to get <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39615097&amp;ref=dillonshook.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">disheartened by the process</a> when you’re in the middle of it and you get through so many interviews with a company you really want to work for only to be told a lame reason why you’re not getting an offer at the end. I really wish companies would start giving honest feedback even if it’s hard for the candidates to heard at first. It would be a much better way for candidates to improve themselves and we’re all adults here and can take the feedback.</p><h2 id="the-pryon-story">The Pryon Story<a href="#the-pryon-story"><span data-pagefind-ignore="">#</span></a></h2><p>The Pryon story is much shorter just like my employment was. I don’t feel like going into any of the details since they don’t feel that important now. It was an 85% surprise to me that it happened at all, and 100% surprise for how deep they cut without many signs the company was struggling. I can only speculate what the reasons were, but someone screwed up to hire dozens of people just to lay them off 6 months later. The shock and whirlwind of thoughts and feelings came and went much quicker this time around. Going through the process once before builds your resilience and you take it less personally.</p><h2 id="how-to-tell-a-layoff-is-coming">How to Tell a Layoff is Coming<a href="#how-to-tell-a-layoff-is-coming"><span data-pagefind-ignore="">#</span></a></h2><p>Based on my N=2 experience and the posts I’ve read here are some warning signs to look out for:</p><ul><li>The product org is struggling to set a vision</li><li>Many distractions and lack of focus</li><li>Low products usage</li><li>Perks being cut, cancelled onsite meetings, signs of financial troubles</li></ul><p>And last but certainly most telling:</p><ul><li>There’s a “company update” meeting unexpectedly scheduled four hours from now</li></ul><h2 id="what-to-do-if-youve-been-laid-off">What to Do if You’ve Been Laid Off<a href="#what-to-do-if-youve-been-laid-off"><span data-pagefind-ignore="">#</span></a></h2><p>First, take a deep breath, this is going to be stressful. But it’s also a new opportunity to find an even better job, meet new amazing people, and expand your skill set.</p><h3 id="update-and-improve-your-resume">Update and Improve your Resume<a href="#update-and-improve-your-resume"><span data-pagefind-ignore="">#</span></a></h3><p>Depending on how long you’ve been at your last job you might have a lot or a little to add. Regardless though, you should try and improve the design a little bit each time you update it. Your resume is highly personal and should reflect some of your personality while still looking as professional as possible, so I use any templates or resume builders myself. Just 100% artisanal HTML and CSS for me baby. I want it to stand out from the hundreds and hundreds of other resumes out there in the application pool.</p><p>Try some new <a href="https://fontjoy.com/#?ref=dillonshook.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">font pairings</a>. Add a touch of iconography. Improve the spacing. Refine, refine, refine.</p><h3 id="file-for-unemployement-benefits">File for Unemployement Benefits<a href="#file-for-unemployement-benefits"><span data-pagefind-ignore="">#</span></a></h3><p>Don’t feel any stigma for filing for unemployment after you’ve been laid off. Your pay your taxes into the system and deserve to get money back when you’re unemployed. I didn’t file after the first time since I had a long period of severance and didn’t want to deal with the overhead but I’ve already filed this time.</p><h3 id="start-searching-for-jobs">Start Searching for Jobs<a href="#start-searching-for-jobs"><span data-pagefind-ignore="">#</span></a></h3><p>The best places I’ve found to look in the past are:</p><ul><li>Stack Overflow jobs (<a href="https://meta.stackoverflow.com/questions/415293/sunsetting-jobs-developer-story?ref=dillonshook.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">RIP</a>)</li><li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42575537&amp;ref=dillonshook.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Monthly Hacker News Who’s Hiring Thread</a></li><li>Networking and local meetups. This is much more hit and miss for finding a job quickly but it’s playing the long game to grow your network in your local community that is well worth the effort.</li><li>LinkedIn. I don’t apply to jobs directly since they’re flooded with applicants. Instead I find places I want to work at that have jobs posted on their company website then reach out to employees in the department and try to make a connection and get an introduction.</li><li>Recruiters. Don’t discount or blow them off. They have a vested interest in getting you hired and 3 of my jobs have been found through them.</li></ul><p>Some other site’s I’ve used with mixed results are <a href="https://hiring.cafe/?ref=dillonshook.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hiring Cafe</a>, <del>Otta</del> <a href="https://employers.welcometothejungle.com/en/introducing-our-new-brand?ref=dillonshook.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Welcome To The Jungle</a> (weird rebrand name), and <a href="https://www.unlistedjobs.com/?ref=dillonshook.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Unlisted Jobs</a>.</p><p>As I mentioned before, when you’re looking for jobs and you want to avoid a layoff in the future it pays to understand the business model and how the company you’re applying to makes money. Ask where the company is in its profitability journey. How many customers do they have? Are they B2B (selling to other business) or B2C (selling directly to consumers)? How long is the sales or conversion process for each customer? How much money does each customer spend? How many rounds of funding has the company raised and for how much? Is the company visibly blowing a lot of money? One place I interviewed for flew its employees across the Atlantic for on sites once a quarter. You’re not going to get an exact answer to all these questions but you should be getting a sense in your head of how financially stable a company is while you’re interviewing.</p><h3 id="keep-track-of-the-jobs-you-applied-for">Keep Track of the Jobs you Applied For<a href="#keep-track-of-the-jobs-you-applied-for"><span data-pagefind-ignore="">#</span></a></h3><p>You’re likely going to have to do this for the unemployment benefits anyways but it also serves the purpose of making sure you don’t apply to a place twice (more likely than you think with the number of applications you’re going to have to send out), and tracking your progress through all the stages. You might be able to find patterns with what worked and what didn’t by tracking as well but for me it’s felt like there’s too many variables at play with each application to find much commonality.</p><h3 id="work-on-a-project">Work on a Project<a href="#work-on-a-project"><span data-pagefind-ignore="">#</span></a></h3><p>While you’re unemployed I’ve found it very helpful to have a side project to work on at the same time. It helps keep me sane through the process of looking through hundreds of job posts. Doing that for 8 hours a day will just make your eyes bleed and brain rot. It could be an idea you’ve had in the back of your head for awhile and never had the time to work on till now or it could be an open source project you’ve used and want to improve. Working on an actual project will keep your skills fresh, break up the days, and you’ll have something to show and talk about during the interview process. With any luck the project might even lead to finding job opportunities directly.</p><h3 id="keep-at-it">Keep At It<a href="#keep-at-it"><span data-pagefind-ignore="">#</span></a></h3><p>The software engineering job market today is very different than it has been prior to (and during Covid). If you haven’t searched for a job since then it will surprise you how much more of <a href="https://newsletter.pragmaticengineer.com/p/state-of-eng-market-2024?ref=dillonshook.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an employers market</a> it is now. Ultimately though, if you’ve got the skills you will find a job if you play the game long enough and stay positive through the process. You got this.</p><h2 id="the-takeaway">The Takeaway<a href="#the-takeaway"><span data-pagefind-ignore="">#</span></a></h2><p>Layoffs are increasingly becoming part of the normal tech industry experience. More than <a href="https://layoffs.fyi/?ref=dillonshook.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">150,000 layoffs were reported</a> in 2024 and a whopping 264,000 in 2023. And those are just the reported ones. During the process the first time around I distinctly remember feeling some guilt/shame as if I hadn’t done enough to prove my worth and avoid the axe for the fourth (or more depending on how you count) time. But ultimately it’s not my fault or decision it happened, just like it’s very likely it’s not your fault if it happens to you. I’m not the one deciding to spend over 400 million dollars on spaghetti to see what sticks to the wall. Not yet at least :)</p><p>An important part of the process is also learning to <a href="https://cruciallearning.com/blog/retaking-your-pen-learning-to-author-your-worth/?ref=dillonshook.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">retake your pen</a>. This is a concept from the book Crucial Conversations I read recently that’s all about learning to define your own self worth and your story in your own words. Don’t let other people tell your story for you or define success for you. In our society where we place such emphasis on your profession, a job loss can mean a shaken self identity. It’s up to you to tell your (truthful of course) side of the story and define yourself separately from any single employer.</p><p>I think it’ll still be a while longer before we can start to say the dust has settled in the tech industry from the end of ZIRP and the disruption AI tools are bringing. So keep your chin up and keep learning!</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Magic/tragic email links: don't make them the only option (518 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://recyclebin.zip/posts/annoyinglinks/</link>
            <guid>42627453</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 21:06:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://recyclebin.zip/posts/annoyinglinks/">https://recyclebin.zip/posts/annoyinglinks/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42627453">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><p><time>2025-01-07</time></p><div><p>The term “Magic Links” once meant a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magic_Link">futuristic PDA</a>. Nowdays, companies like <a href="https://auth0.com/docs/authenticate/passwordless/authentication-methods/email-magic-link">Auth0</a> use it to refer to the slightly-magical feat of including a login link in an email.</p><p>Last week, the great website you should subscribe to if you haven’t already (it’s great, when you’re not logged out), <a href="https://www.404media.co/">404 Media</a>, posted <a href="https://www.404media.co/we-dont-want-your-password-3/">“We Don’t Want Your Password”</a> in defense of so-called magic links.</p><p>Of course, as stated in the article, such email links are harder to phish than passwords, can’t lead to a breach of passwords, and protect the site itself against users who might reuse passwords previously compromised.</p><p>The article even covers some of my annoyances with this system, but throws out this sentence:</p><blockquote><p><a href="https://www.404media.co/we-dont-want-your-password-3/">We find this to be a much easier login process and wish it was more common across the web where appropriate.</a></p></blockquote><p>Easier than what? Easier than a long password, without a password manager? Easier than a passkey? Easier than an OTP sent to the same email address?</p><p>This sentence reads to me as one written by someone mostly working and <em>living</em> from a single laptop and mobile device. The second part of the sentence, calling for more sites to do this is why I am writing this.</p><p>For any scenario with a minimal amount of complexity, like users with multiple computers, and you’re looking at a scenario where the site’s unwillingness to deal with other login methods shoves friction on the end-user.</p><h3 id="what-makes-them-tragic">What makes them tragic:<a href="#what-makes-them-tragic" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h3><ol><li>Multiple devices. Who doesn’t use at least a few computers weekly? I don’t have my email on my gaming PC, nor do I have it on my work laptops.</li><li>Slower. From 2 seconds slower to minutes slower, depending on SMTP delays as well as how awkward it is to get the link to the right browser.</li><li>Anti-mobile. As mentioned by 404 in their own article, this breaks the ability to use in-app browsers, which is quite annoying especially for RSS reader type apps. It makes interacting with any local link in the RSS feed extremely annoying.</li><li>Indirect security downsides. Pushing people to access personal email on work devices (or vice-versa) isn’t exactly a win for security.</li></ol><p>Another annoying <em>passwordless</em> system is to email or SMS an OTP the end user can type in.</p><p>While this sucks, it at least allows you to easily log in in situations where you don’t have a clear and easy copy/paste path from the email client to the browser you want to log in to.</p><p><a href="https://stratechery.com/">Stratechery</a>, powered by <a href="https://passport.online/">Passport</a>, uses this type of scheme (click link OR type in OTP), which is still shifting annoyances onto end-users to free developers from implementing passkeys, but at least has a bit more of an appreciation for end-users.</p><p>If you insist on using magic/tragic links by default, at least consider offering a robust alternative, such as <a href="https://fidoalliance.org/passkeys/">passkeys</a>, especially if your audience is technical and privacy-focused.</p></div></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mistakes engineers make in large established codebases (489 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.seangoedecke.com/large-established-codebases/</link>
            <guid>42627227</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 20:44:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.seangoedecke.com/large-established-codebases/">https://www.seangoedecke.com/large-established-codebases/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42627227">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section><p>Working in large established codebases is one of the hardest things to learn as a software engineer. You can’t practice it beforehand (no, open source does not give you the same experience). Personal projects can never teach you how to do it, because they’re necessarily small and from-scratch. For the record, when I say “large established codebases”, I mean:</p>
<ul>
<li>Single-digit million lines of code (~5M, let’s say)</li>
<li>Somewhere between 100 and 1000 engineers working on the same codebase</li>
<li>The first working version of the codebase is at least ten years old</li>
</ul>
<p>I’ve now spent a decade working in these codebases. Here’s what I wish I’d known at the start.</p>
<h3>The cardinal mistake is inconsistency</h3>
<p>There’s one mistake I see more often than anything else, and it’s absolutely deadly: ignoring the rest of the codebase and just implementing your feature in the most sensible way. In other words, limiting your touch points with the existing codebase in order to keep your nice clean code uncontaminated by legacy junk. For engineers that have mainly worked on small codebases, this is very hard to resist. But you must resist it! In fact, you must sink as deeply into the legacy codebase as possible, <strong>in order to maintain consistency.</strong></p>
<p>Why is consistency so important in large codebases? Because it protects you from nasty surprises, it slows down the codebase’s progression into a mess, and it allows you to take advantage of future improvements.</p>
<p>Suppose you’re building an API endpoint for a particular type of user. You could put some “return 403 if current user isn’t of that type” logic in your endpoint. But you should first go and look to see what other API endpoints in the codebase do for auth. If they use some specific set of helpers, you should also use that helper (even if it’s ugly, hard to integrate with, or seems like overkill for your use case). <strong>You must resist the urge to make your little corner of the codebase nicer than the rest of it.</strong></p>
<p>The main reason to do this is because large codebases have a lot of landmines in them. For instance, you might not know that the codebase has a concept of “bots”, which are like users but not quite, and require special treatment for auth. You might not know that the internal support tooling in the codebase allows an engineer to sometimes authenticate on behalf of a user, which requires special treatment for auth. There’s definitely another hundred things you might not know. Existing functionality represents a safe path through the minefield. If you do your auth like other API endpoints that have stuck around for a long time, you can follow that path without having to know all the surprising things that the codebase does.</p>
<p>On top of that, lack of consistency is the primary long-term killer of large codebases, because it makes it impossible to make any general improvements. Sticking with our auth example, if you want to ever introduce a new type of user, a consistent codebase lets you update the existing set of auth helpers to accommodate that. In an inconsistent codebase, where some API endpoints are doing things differently, you’ll have to go and update and test every one of those implementations. In practice, that means that the general change does not happen, or that the hardest 5% of endpoints to update are just left out of scope - which in turn decreases consistency further, because now you have a user type that works for most-but-not-all API endpoints.</p>
<p>So when you sit down to implement anything in a large codebase, you should always first go and look around for prior art, and follow that if at all possible.</p>
<h3>Is anything else important?</h3>
<p>Consistency is the most important thing. Let me quickly run through some other concerns as well, though:</p>
<p>You need to develop a good sense of how the service is used in practice (i.e. by users). Which endpoints are hit the most often? Which endpoints are the most crucial (i.e. are used by paying customers and cannot gracefully degrade)? What latency guarantees must the service obey, and what code gets run in the hot paths? One common large-codebase mistake is to make a “tiny tweak” that is unexpectedly in the hot path for a crucial flow, and thus causes a big problem.</p>
<p>You can’t rely on your ability to test the code in development like you can in a small project. Any large project accumulates state over time (for instance, how many kinds of user do you think GMail supports?) At a certain point, you can’t test every combination of states, even with automation. Instead, you have to test the crucial paths, code defensively, and rely on slow rollouts and monitoring to catch problems.</p>
<p>Be very, very reluctant to introduce new dependencies. In large codebases, code often lives forever. Dependencies introduce an ongoing cost in security vulnerabilities and package updates that will almost certainly outlive your tenure at the company. If you have to, make sure you pick dependencies that are widely-used and reliable, or that are easy to fork if needed. </p>
<p>For related reasons, if you ever get the chance to remove code, take it with both hands. This is some of the riskiest work in large codebases, so don’t half-ass it: first instrument the code to identify callers in production and drive them down to zero, so you can be absolutely certain it’s safe to remove. But it’s still worth doing. There are few things in a large codebase more worthwhile than safely removing code.</p>
<p>Work in small PRs and front-load the changes that affect other teams’ code. This one is important in small projects too, but it’s critical in large ones. That’s because you’ll often be relying on the domain experts in other teams to anticipate things you’ve missed (since large projects are just too complex to anticipate it all yourself). If you keep your changes to risky areas small and easy-to-read, those domain experts have a much better chance of noticing problems and saving you from an incident.</p>
<h3>Why bother?</h3>
<p>Finally, I want to take a second to defend these codebases in general. One common take I’ve heard goes like this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Why would you ever decide to work in the legacy mess? Spending time knee-deep in spaghetti code might be hard, but it isn’t good engineering. When faced with a large established codebase, our job should be to shrink it by splitting out small elegant services instead of wading in and making the mess larger.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think this is totally wrong-headed. The main reason is that, as a general rule, <strong>large established codebases produce 90% of the value</strong>. In any big tech company, the majority of the revenue-producing activity (i.e. the work that actually pays your engineering salary) comes from a large established codebase. If you work at a big tech company and don’t think this is true, maybe you’re right, but I’ll only take that opinion seriously if you’re deeply familiar with the large established codebase you think isn’t providing value. I’ve seen multiple cases where a small elegant service powers some core feature of a high-revenue product, but all the actual productizing code (settings, user management, billing, enterprise reporting, etc) still lives in the large established codebase.</p>
<p>So you should know how to work in the “legacy mess” because that’s what your company actually does. Good engineering or not, <em>it’s your job</em>. </p>
<p>The other reason is that <strong>you cannot split up a large established codebase without first understanding it</strong>. I have seen large codebases successfully split up, but I have never seen that done by a team that wasn’t already fluent at shipping features inside the large codebase. You simply cannot redesign any non-trivial project (i.e. a project that makes real money) from first-principles. There are too many accidental details that support tens of millions of dollars of revenue.</p>
<h3>Summary</h3>
<ul>
<li>Large codebases are worth working in because they usually pay your salary</li>
<li>By far the most important thing is consistency</li>
<li>Never start a feature without first researching prior art in the codebase</li>
<li>If you don’t follow existing patterns, you better have a very good reason for it</li>
<li>Understand the production footprint of the codebase</li>
<li>Don’t expect to be able to test every case - instead, rely on monitoring</li>
<li>Remove code any chance you get, but be very careful about it</li>
<li>Make it as easy as possible for domain experts to catch your mistakes</li>
</ul></section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Online Behavioral Ads Fuel the Surveillance Industry (141 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2025/01/online-behavioral-ads-fuel-surveillance-industry-heres-how</link>
            <guid>42627090</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 20:33:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2025/01/online-behavioral-ads-fuel-surveillance-industry-heres-how">https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2025/01/online-behavioral-ads-fuel-surveillance-industry-heres-how</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42627090">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <article role="article">
  
  
  <div><p><span>A </span><a href="https://www.404media.co/inside-global-phone-spy-tool-patternz-nuviad-real-time-bidding/"><span>global spy tool</span></a><span> exposed the locations of billions of people to anyone willing to pay. A Catholic group </span><a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/dc-md-va/2023/03/09/catholics-gay-priests-grindr-data-bishops/"><span>bought location data about gay dating app users</span></a><span> in an effort to out gay priests. A location data broker </span><a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/2023196mobilewallacomplaint.pdf"><span>sold lists of people who attended political protests</span></a><span>.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>What do these privacy violations have in common? They share a source of data that’s shockingly pervasive and unregulated: the technology powering nearly every ad you see online.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>Each time you see a targeted ad, your personal information is exposed to </span><a href="https://www.iccl.ie/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/Americas-hidden-security-crisis.pdf"><span>thousands of advertisers and data brokers</span></a><span> through a process called “real-time bidding” (RTB). This process does more than deliver ads—it fuels government surveillance, poses national security risks, and gives data brokers easy access to your online activity. RTB might be the most privacy-invasive surveillance system that you’ve never heard of.</span></p>
<h3><b>What is Real-Time Bidding?</b></h3>
<p><span>RTB is the process used to select the targeted ads shown to you on nearly every website and app you visit. The ads you see are the winners of milliseconds-long auctions that expose your personal information to </span><a href="https://www.iccl.ie/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/Americas-hidden-security-crisis.pdf"><span>thousands of companies a day</span></a><span>. Here’s how it works:</span></p>
<ol>
<li><span>The moment you visit a website or app with ad space, it asks a company that runs ad auctions to determine which ads it will display for you. This involves sending information about you and the content you’re viewing to the ad auction company.</span></li>
<li><span>The ad auction company packages all the information they can gather about you into a “bid request” and broadcasts it to thousands of potential advertisers.&nbsp;</span></li>
<li><span>The bid request may contain personal information like your </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2022/05/how-disable-ad-id-tracking-ios-and-android-and-why-you-should-do-it-now"><span>unique advertising ID</span></a><span>, location, IP address, device details, interests, and demographic information. The information in bid requests is called “bidstream data” and can </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2023/11/debunking-myth-anonymous-data"><span>easily be linked to real people</span></a><span>.</span><i><span>&nbsp;</span></i></li>
<li><span>Advertisers use the personal information in each bid request, along with data profiles they’ve built about you over time, to decide whether to bid on ad space.&nbsp;</span></li>
<li><span>Advertisers, and their ad buying platforms, can store the personal data in the bid request regardless of whether or not they bid on ad space.&nbsp;</span></li>
</ol>
<p><span>A key vulnerability of real-time bidding is that while only one advertiser wins the auction, all participants receive the data. Indeed, anyone posing as an ad buyer can access a stream of sensitive data about the billions of individuals using websites or apps with targeted ads. That’s a big way that RTB puts personal data into the hands of data brokers, who sell it to basically anyone willing to pay. Although some ad auction companies have </span><a href="https://www.google.com/intl/en/authorizedbuyers/guidelines/"><span>policies against selling bidstream data</span></a><span>, the practice </span><a href="https://www.iccl.ie/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/Americas-hidden-security-crisis.pdf"><span>remains widespread</span></a><span>.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>RTB doesn’t just allow companies to harvest your data—it also incentivizes it. </span><a href="https://headerbidding.co/bid-request/"><span>Bid requests containing more personal data attract higher bids</span></a><span>, so websites and apps are financially motivated to harvest as much of your data as possible. RTB further incentivizes data brokers to track your online activity because advertisers </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/wp/behind-the-one-way-mirror#Real-time-bidding"><span>purchase data from data brokers to inform their bidding decisions</span></a><span>.</span></p>
<p><span>Data brokers don’t need any direct relationship with the apps and websites they’re collecting bidstream data from. While some data collection methods require web or app developers to </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2021/03/apple-and-google-kicked-two-location-data-brokers-out-their-app-stores-good-now"><span>install code from a data broker</span></a><span>, RTB is facilitated by ad companies that are already plugged into most websites and apps. This allows data brokers to collect data at a staggering scale. </span><a href="https://www.iccl.ie/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Mass-data-breach-of-Europe-and-US-data-1.pdf"><span>Hundreds of billions of RTB bid requests</span></a><span> are broadcast every day. For each of those bids, thousands of real or fake ad buying platforms may receive data. As a result, </span><a href="https://www.wired.com/story/how-pentagon-learned-targeted-ads-to-find-targets-and-vladimir-putin/"><span>entire businesses have emerged</span></a><span> to harvest and sell data from online advertising auctions.</span></p>
<h3><b>First FTC Action Against Abuse of Real-Time Bidding Data</b></h3>
<p><span>A recent </span><a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/12/ftc-takes-action-against-mobilewalla-collecting-selling-sensitive-location-data"><span>enforcement action</span></a><span> by the Federal Trade Commission (FTC) shows that the dangers of RTB are not hypothetical—data brokers actively rely on RTB to collect and sell sensitive information. The FTC found that data broker Mobilewalla was collecting personal data—including precise location information—from RTB auctions without placing ads.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>Mobilewalla collected data on over a billion people, with an estimated </span><a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/2023196mobilewallacomplaint.pdf"><span>60% sourced directly from RTB auctions</span></a><span>. The company then sold this data for </span><a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/2023196mobilewallacomplaint.pdf"><span>a range of invasive purposes</span></a><span>, including tracking union organizers, tracking people at Black Lives Matter protests, and compiling home addresses of healthcare employees for recruitment by competing employers. It also </span><a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/2023196mobilewallacomplaint.pdf"><span>categorized people into custom groups for advertisers</span></a><span>, such as “pregnant women,” “Hispanic churchgoers,” and “members of the LGBTQ+ community.”</span></p>
<p><span>The FTC concluded that Mobilewalla's practice of collecting personal data from RTB auctions where they didn’t place ads </span><a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/statement-khan-bedoya-slaughter-mobilewalla.pdf"><span>violated the FTC Act’s</span></a><span> prohibition of unfair conduct. The FTC’s proposed settlement order bans Mobilewalla from collecting consumer data from RTB auctions for any purposes other than participating in those auctions. This action marks </span><a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/statement-khan-bedoya-slaughter-mobilewalla.pdf"><span>the first time</span></a><span> the FTC has targeted the abuse of bidstream data. While we celebrate this significant milestone, the dangers of RTB go far beyond one data broker.&nbsp;</span></p>
<h3><b>Real-Time Bidding Enables Mass Surveillance&nbsp;</b></h3>
<p><span>RTB is regularly exploited for government surveillance. As early as 2017, </span><a href="https://adint.cs.washington.edu/ADINT.pdf"><span>researchers demonstrated</span></a><span> that $1,000 worth of ad targeting data could be used to track an individuals’ locations and glean sensitive information like their religion and sexual orientation. Since then, data brokers have been caught selling bidstream data to government intelligence agencies. For example, the data broker Near Intelligence collected data about more than a billion devices from RTB auctions and </span><a href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/cybersecurity/how-ads-on-your-phone-can-aid-government-surveillance-943bde04"><span>sold it to the U.S. Defense Department</span></a><span>. Mobilewalla </span><a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/mobilewalla-says-data-it-gathered-from-consumers-cellphones-ended-up-with-government-11637242202"><span>sold bidstream data</span></a><span> to another data broker, Gravy Analytics, whose subsidiary, Venntell, likewise has </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2022/06/how-federal-government-buys-our-cell-phone-location-data"><span>sold location data to the FBI, ICE, CBP, and other government agencies</span></a><span>.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>In addition to buying raw bidstream data, governments buy surveillance tools that rely on the same advertising auctions. The </span><a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2023-05-11/surveillance-company-turns-ad-data-into-government-tracking-tool"><span>surveillance company Rayzone</span></a><span> posed as an advertiser to acquire bidstream data, which it repurposed into tracking tools sold to governments around the world. Rayzone’s tools could identify phones that had been in specific locations and link them to people's names, addresses, and browsing histories. </span><a href="https://www.404media.co/inside-global-phone-spy-tool-patternz-nuviad-real-time-bidding/"><span>Patternz</span></a><span>, another surveillance tool built on bidstream data, was advertised to security agencies worldwide as a way to track people's locations. The CEO of Patternz highlighted the connection between surveillance and advertising technology when he suggested his company could track people through “</span><a href="https://www.404media.co/inside-global-phone-spy-tool-patternz-nuviad-real-time-bidding/"><span>virtually any app that has ads</span></a><span>.”</span></p>
<p><span>Beyond the privacy harms from RTB-fueled government surveillance, RTB also creates national security risks. </span><a href="https://www.iccl.ie/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/Americas-hidden-security-crisis.pdf"><span>Researchers have warned</span></a><span> that RTB could allow foreign states and non-state actors to obtain compromising personal data about American defense personnel and political leaders. In fact, </span><a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/google-russia-rutarget-sberbank-sanctions-ukraine"><span>Google’s ad auctions sent sensitive data to a Russian ad company</span></a><span> for months after it was sanctioned by the U.S. Treasury.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>The privacy and security dangers of RTB are inherent to its design, and not just a matter of misuse by individual data brokers. The process broadcasts torrents of our personal data to thousands of companies, hundreds of times per day, with no oversight of how this information is ultimately used. This indiscriminate sharing of location data and other personal information is dangerous, regardless of whether the recipients are advertisers or surveillance companies in disguise. Sharing sensitive data with advertisers enables exploitative advertising, such as </span><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2022/mar/13/google-profiting-from-predatory-loan-adverts-promising-instant-cash"><span>predatory loan companies targeting people in financial distress</span></a><span>. RTB is a surveillance system at its core, presenting corporations and governments with limitless opportunities to use our data against us.</span></p>
<h3><b>How You Can Protect Yourself</b></h3>
<p><span>Privacy-invasive ad auctions occur on nearly every website and app, but there are steps you can take to protect yourself:</span></p>
<ul>
<li><span>For apps: Follow </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2024/11/creators-police-location-tracking-tool-arent-vetting-buyers-heres-how-protect"><span>EFF’s instructions</span></a><span> to disable your mobile advertising ID and audit app permissions. These steps will reduce the personal data available to the RTB process and make it harder for data brokers to create detailed profiles about you.</span></li>
<li><span>For websites: Install </span><a href="https://privacybadger.org/"><span>Privacy Badger</span></a><span>, a free browser extension built by EFF to block online trackers. Privacy Badger automatically blocks tracking-enabled advertisements, preventing the RTB process from beginning.</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span>These measures will help protect your privacy, but advertisers are </span><a href="https://democraticmedia.org/assets/cdd-ctv-report-oct24-1.1.pdf"><span>constantly</span></a> <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/how-transportation-car-data-advertisers-personalized-experiences-drivers-2021-9"><span>finding</span></a> <a href="https://www.twipla.com/en/blog/how-to-track-cookieless"><span>new</span></a> <a href="https://themarkup.org/privacy/2023/02/16/forget-milk-and-eggs-supermarkets-are-having-a-fire-sale-on-data-about-you"><span>ways</span></a><span> to collect and exploit your data. This is just one more reason why individuals shouldn’t bear the sole responsibility of defending their data every time they use the internet.</span></p>
<h3><b>The Real Solution: Ban Online Behavioral Advertising</b></h3>
<p><span>The best way to prevent online ads from fueling surveillance is to </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2022/03/ban-online-behavioral-advertising"><span>ban online behavioral advertising</span></a><span>. This would end the practice of targeting ads based on your online activity, removing the primary incentive for companies to track and share your personal data. It would also prevent your personal data from being broadcast to data brokers through RTB auctions. Ads could still be targeted contextually—based on the content of the page you’re currently viewing—without collecting or exposing sensitive information about you. This shift would not only protect individual privacy but also reduce the power of the surveillance industry. Seeing an ad shouldn’t mean surrendering your data to thousands of companies you’ve never heard of. It’s time to end online behavioral advertising and the mass surveillance it enables.</span></p>

</div>

          </article>
    </div><div>
          <h2>Join EFF Lists</h2>
        
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Streets GL – 3D OpenStreetMap (132 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://streets.gl/#47.35245,8.50958,21.25,42.00,459.10</link>
            <guid>42626964</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 20:20:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://streets.gl/#47.35245,8.50958,21.25,42.00,459.10">https://streets.gl/#47.35245,8.50958,21.25,42.00,459.10</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42626964">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Microsoft disguises Bing as Google to fool inattentive searchers (269 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.pcworld.com/article/2568916/microsoft-disguises-bing-as-google-to-fool-inattentive-searchers.html</link>
            <guid>42626431</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 19:37:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.pcworld.com/article/2568916/microsoft-disguises-bing-as-google-to-fool-inattentive-searchers.html">https://www.pcworld.com/article/2568916/microsoft-disguises-bing-as-google-to-fool-inattentive-searchers.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42626431">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="link_wrapped_content">




<p>Microsoft would really, really, <em>really</em> like you to use Bing, its self-branded search engine that competes against Google’s monopoly. Not only is it <a href="https://www.pcworld.com/article/2509630/how-the-windows-search-uses-google-instead-of-bing.html">hardwired into much of Windows</a> and other Microsoft products like the Edge browser, it also employs a lot of sneaky visual tricks to steer you away from Google itself. But the company’s latest trick is more, well, tricky — in fact, it’s just straight-up Google camouflage.</p>



<p>This morning, users are discovering that if they search for “Google” in the primary Bing interface, they’re shown a special Bing search page. Before you scroll down to the actual search results, you’re presented with an all-white page with a centered, unbranded search bar and a multicolored doodle above it that’s heavy on yellow, red, blue, and green.</p>



<p>It is, in a very practical and (in this writer’s opinion) deliberate sense, a clone of the familiar Google search page. If you aren’t paying attention, you might put in a search or two in this disguised bar without ever realizing that you haven’t actually left Bing itself. You’ll have to scroll up or down to notice something’s off, if you haven’t immediately seen that it’s basically a knock-off Google doodle.</p>



<p>The change was <a href="https://go.skimresources.com/?id=111346X1569483&amp;xs=1&amp;url=https://www.windowslatest.com/2025/01/06/microsoft-bing-is-trying-to-spoof-google-ui-when-people-search-google-com/&amp;xcust=2-1-2568916-1-0-0-0-0&amp;sref=https://www.pcworld.com/article/2568916/microsoft-disguises-bing-as-google-to-fool-inattentive-searchers.html" rel="nofollow" data-subtag="2-1-2568916-1-0-0-0-0" data-domain-name="windowslatest" target="_blank">noted by  Windows Latest</a> (via <a href="https://go.skimresources.com/?id=111346X1569483&amp;xs=1&amp;url=https://9to5google.com/2025/01/06/bing-trick-users-google/&amp;xcust=2-1-2568916-1-0-0-0-0&amp;sref=https://www.pcworld.com/article/2568916/microsoft-disguises-bing-as-google-to-fool-inattentive-searchers.html" rel="nofollow" data-subtag="2-1-2568916-1-0-0-0-0" data-domain-name="9to5google" target="_blank">9to5Google</a>), which also points out that this page appears whether you’re going to Bing.com directly or searching from the Edge combined search/URL bar. The only place it <em>doesn’t</em> appear is if you’re searching from an Edge tab in which you’ve already signed into a Microsoft account. A little testing on my part verifies these parameters. (I’m seeing the “I can’t believe it’s not Google” search page in Vivaldi, even though I’m signed into my work Outlook account.)</p>

		
			
			


<p>This dedicated “I can’t believe it’s not Google” search page does not seem to appear for any searches less specific than “google,” “google search,” etc. Even something only slightly less immediate, like “google mail,” gives you the regular Bing interface and results.</p>



<p>The intent seems pretty obvious here, and it’s a very desperate look on the part of Microsoft. Not that I blame anyone for feeling a little desperate in the face of Google’s search dominance. I didn’t call it the Google monopoly idly, because that’s <a href="https://www.pcworld.com/article/2418714/googles-search-business-ruled-an-illegal-monopoly.html">the official determination of a United States federal court</a>. Google controlled an astonishing <a href="https://go.skimresources.com/?id=111346X1569483&amp;xs=1&amp;url=https://www.statista.com/statistics/1358006/worldwide-mobile-market-share-of-search-engines/&amp;xcust=2-1-2568916-1-0-0-0-0&amp;sref=https://www.pcworld.com/article/2568916/microsoft-disguises-bing-as-google-to-fool-inattentive-searchers.html" rel="nofollow" data-subtag="2-1-2568916-1-0-0-0-0" data-domain-name="statista" target="_blank">95 percent of the mobile search marketplace</a> as of 2024 according to Statista, a number that has barely moved since 2015, with Bing claiming less than one percent despite 15 years of Microsoft backing. The results are slightly less bleak if you look at the desktop search market, where Google has “only” 82 percent to Bing’s growing 10.51 percent share <a href="https://go.skimresources.com/?id=111346X1569483&amp;xs=1&amp;url=https://www.statista.com/statistics/216573/worldwide-market-share-of-search-engines/&amp;xcust=2-1-2568916-1-0-0-0-0&amp;sref=https://www.pcworld.com/article/2568916/microsoft-disguises-bing-as-google-to-fool-inattentive-searchers.html" rel="nofollow" data-subtag="2-1-2568916-1-0-0-0-0" data-domain-name="statista" target="_blank">as of early 2024</a>.</p>



<p>So, yeah, I don’t envy the Bing team’s task of slaying giants. But that being said, if a user wants Google and they search Bing to get it, deliberately obfuscating the search seems like a failure of a search engine’s sole task. Microsoft is putting its business goals above its users, a strategy that never endears users to the product.</p>



<p>Considering how poorly Microsoft’s push to <a href="https://www.pcworld.com/article/2548424/microsofts-wins-fails-and-wtf-moments-of-2024.html">move people off of Windows 10 is going</a>, I wonder if they might benefit from a bit of serious introspection on this approach. </p>

</div><div data-ga="article-footer-author">
								<p><img src="https://www.pcworld.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/author_photo_Michael-Crider_1635298804-1.jpg?quality=50&amp;strip=all&amp;w=150&amp;h=150&amp;crop=1" height="125" width="125">
				</p>
								<p>Michael is a 10-year veteran of technology journalism, covering everything from Apple to ZTE. On PCWorld he's the resident keyboard nut, always using a new one for a review and building a new mechanical board or expanding his desktop "battlestation" in his off hours. Michael's previous bylines include Android Police, Digital Trends, Wired, Lifehacker, and How-To Geek, and he's covered events like CES and Mobile World Congress live. Michael lives in Pennsylvania where he's always looking forward to his next kayaking trip.</p>
				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Anthropic raising funding valuing it at $60B (105 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wsj.com/tech/ai/ai-startup-anthropic-raising-funding-valuing-it-at-60-billion-19d0605a</link>
            <guid>42625497</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 18:19:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/ai/ai-startup-anthropic-raising-funding-valuing-it-at-60-billion-19d0605a">https://www.wsj.com/tech/ai/ai-startup-anthropic-raising-funding-valuing-it-at-60-billion-19d0605a</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42625497">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.wsj.com/tech/ai/ai-startup-anthropic-raising-funding-valuing-it-at-60-billion-19d0605a: Error: Request failed with status code 401]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tax Heaven 3000, a dating SIM that prepares your federal taxes (112 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://taxheaven3000.com</link>
            <guid>42625425</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 18:13:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://taxheaven3000.com">https://taxheaven3000.com</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42625425">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-v-df642fc4="" id="manifesto" data-v-4762ba8b=""><div data-v-df642fc4=""><p data-v-df642fc4="">Hi there! Iris here~</p> <p data-v-df642fc4="">
          It’s always been a dream of mine to meet that special someone…and
          file their tax return. Join me and we’ll search for deductions while
          searching for love!
        </p> <p data-v-df642fc4="">
          But be careful! We’re not alone. Corporate tax filing services like
          TurboTax are (by dint of extensive lobbying) predatory, parasitic
          bottlenecks that deliberately complicate the tax filing process in
          order to make it unnavigable by ordinary people. They feed us their
          poison so that we buy their medicine!
        </p></div> <div data-v-df642fc4=""><p data-v-df642fc4="">
          Most wealthy countries make tax filing free, if the burden of
          preparation is even passed along to individuals at all. TurboTax
          actively seeks to backdoor the regulatory structure that could
          otherwise seek to rein it in. And it works! The villainous
          corporation that controls the government from the shadows is a sadly
          mundane reality. It’s the most boring industry imaginable.
        </p> <p data-v-df642fc4="">
          TurboTax, per its own internal documents, is built on the “Fear,
          Uncertainty, and Doubt” that ordinary people have about their taxes.
          Against this, we pit free software instead built on parasocial
          desire for intimacy and benign horniness! If TurboTax is Dark UI,
          TH3K is Pink UI, the nightcore of tax software.
        </p></div> <div data-v-df642fc4=""><p data-v-df642fc4="">
          Videogames are, at the end of the day, pieces of
          software–ontologically akin to Microsoft Word. All of TurboTax’s
          cutesy loading animations are fake graphics; TH3K simply makes the
          fiction the point. For some reason the game-to-real-life interface
          has tended to remain in the purview of corporate metaverse fictions.
          TH3K is a dongle that adapts from a visual novel to the IRS.
        </p> <p data-v-df642fc4="">
          Come on, let’s get started! I can already tell I’m going to like you
          ♥ And remember,
          <span data-v-df642fc4="">if you die in the game you die in real life</span>
          if you file your taxes in the game, you file your taxes in real
          life.
        </p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Physicists Magnetize a Material with Light (134 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.mit.edu/2024/physicists-magnetize-material-using-light-1218</link>
            <guid>42625219</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 17:54:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://news.mit.edu/2024/physicists-magnetize-material-using-light-1218">https://news.mit.edu/2024/physicists-magnetize-material-using-light-1218</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42625219">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
          

            <p>MIT physicists have created a new and long-lasting magnetic state in a material, using only light.</p><p>In a study <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-08226-x" target="_blank">appearing today in <em>Nature</em></a>, the researchers report using a terahertz laser — a light source that oscillates more than a trillion times per second — to directly stimulate atoms in an antiferromagnetic material. The laser’s oscillations are tuned to the natural vibrations among the material’s atoms, in a way that shifts the balance of atomic spins toward a new magnetic state.</p><p>The results provide a new way to control and switch antiferromagnetic materials, which are of interest for their potential to advance information processing and memory chip technology.</p><p>In common magnets, known as ferromagnets, the spins of atoms point in the same direction, in a way that the whole can be easily influenced and pulled in the direction of any external magnetic field. In contrast, antiferromagnets are composed of atoms with alternating spins, each pointing in the opposite direction from its neighbor. This up, down, up, down order essentially cancels the spins out, giving antiferromagnets a net zero magnetization that is impervious to any magnetic pull.</p><p>If a memory chip could be made from antiferromagnetic material, data could be “written” into microscopic regions of the material, called domains. A certain configuration of spin orientations (for example, up-down) in a given domain would represent the classical bit “0,” and a different configuration (down-up) would mean “1.” Data written on such a chip would be robust against outside magnetic influence.</p><p>For this and other reasons, scientists believe antiferromagnetic materials could be a more robust alternative to existing magnetic-based storage technologies. A major hurdle, however, has been in how to control antiferromagnets in a way that reliably switches the material from one magnetic state to another.</p><p>“Antiferromagnetic materials are robust and not influenced by unwanted stray magnetic fields,”&nbsp;says Nuh Gedik, the Donner Professor of Physics at MIT. “However, this robustness is a double-edged sword; their insensitivity to weak magnetic fields makes these materials difficult to control.”</p><p>Using carefully tuned terahertz light, the MIT team was able to controllably&nbsp;switch an antiferromagnet to a new magnetic state. Antiferromagnets could be incorporated into future memory chips that store and process more data while using less energy and taking up a fraction of the space of existing devices, owing to the stability of magnetic domains.</p><p>“Generally, such antiferromagnetic materials are not easy to control,” Gedik says. “Now we have some knobs to be able to tune and tweak them.”</p><p>Gedik is the senior author of the new study, which also includes MIT co-authors Batyr Ilyas, Tianchuang Luo, Alexander von Hoegen, Zhuquan Zhang, and Keith Nelson, along with collaborators at the Max Planck Institute for the Structure and Dynamics of Matter in Germany, University of the Basque Country in Spain, Seoul National University, and the Flatiron Institute in New York.</p><p><strong>Off balance</strong></p><p>Gedik’s group at MIT develops techniques to manipulate quantum materials in which interactions among atoms can give rise to exotic phenomena.</p><p>“In general, we excite materials with light to learn more about what holds them together fundamentally,” Gedik says. “For instance, why is this material an antiferromagnet, and is there a way to perturb microscopic interactions such that it turns into a ferromagnet?”</p><p>In their new study, the team worked with FePS<sub>3</sub> — a material that transitions to an antiferromagnetic phase at a critical temperature of around 118 kelvins (-247 degrees Fahrenheit).</p><p>The team suspected they might control the material’s transition by tuning into its atomic vibrations.</p><p>“In any solid, you can picture it as different atoms that are periodically arranged, and between atoms are tiny springs,” von Hoegen explains. “If you were to pull one atom, it would vibrate at a characteristic frequency which typically occurs in the terahertz range.”</p><p>The way in which atoms vibrate also relates to how their spins interact with each other. The team reasoned that if they could stimulate the atoms with a terahertz source that oscillates at the same frequency as the atoms’ collective vibrations, called phonons, the effect could also nudge the atoms’ spins out of their perfectly balanced, magnetically alternating alignment. Once knocked out of balance, atoms should have larger spins in one direction than the other, creating a preferred orientation that would shift the inherently nonmagnetized material into a new magnetic state with finite magnetization.</p><p>“The idea is that you can kill two birds with one stone: You excite the atoms’ terahertz vibrations, which also couples to the spins,” Gedik says.</p><p><strong>Shake and write</strong></p><p>To test this idea, the team worked with a sample of FePS<sub>3</sub> that was synthesized by colleages at Seoul National University. They placed the sample in a vacuum chamber and cooled it down to temperatures at and below 118 K. They then generated a terahertz pulse by aiming a beam of near-infrared light through an organic crystal, which transformed the light into the terahertz frequencies. They then directed this terahertz light toward the sample.</p><p>“This terahertz pulse is what we use to create a change in the sample,” Luo says. “It’s like ‘writing’ a new state into the sample.”</p><p>To confirm that the pulse triggered a change in the material’s magnetism, the team also aimed two near-infrared lasers at the sample, each with an opposite circular polarization. If the terahertz pulse had no effect, the researchers should see no difference in the intensity of the transmitted infrared lasers.</p><p>“Just seeing a difference tells us the material is no longer the original antiferromagnet, and that we are inducing a new magnetic state, by essentially using terahertz light to shake the atoms,” Ilyas says.</p><p>Over repeated experiments, the team observed that a terahertz pulse successfully switched the previously antiferromagnetic material to a new magnetic state — a transition that persisted for a surprisingly long time, over several milliseconds, even after the laser was turned off.</p><p>“People have seen these light-induced phase transitions before in other systems, but typically they live for very short times on the order of a picosecond, which is a trillionth of a second,” Gedik says.</p><p>In just a few milliseconds, scientists now might have a decent window of time during which they could probe the properties of the temporary new state before it settles back into its inherent antiferromagnetism. Then, they might be able to identify new knobs to tweak antiferromagnets and optimize their use in next-generation memory storage technologies.</p><p>This research was supported, in part, by the U.S. Department of Energy, Materials Science and Engineering Division, Office of Basic Energy Sciences, and the Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation.&nbsp;</p>        

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Type 2 Diabetes and cardiovascular disease attributable to sugar beverages (342 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-024-03345-4</link>
            <guid>42625193</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 17:51:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-024-03345-4">https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-024-03345-4</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42625193">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-024-03345-4: Error: Request failed with status code 406]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Tramway SDK – The Unholy Union Between Half-Life and Morrowind Engines (557 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://racenis.github.io/tram-sdk/why.html</link>
            <guid>42624116</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 16:22:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://racenis.github.io/tram-sdk/why.html">https://racenis.github.io/tram-sdk/why.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42624116">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
					<!-- PAGE_TITLE: Why Tramway SDK | Tramway Drifting and Dungeon Exploration Simulator Software Development Kit -->



<hr>

<p>
	<b>Tramway SDK</b> (heavy metal spelling –
	T̈ra̦m̊ẅa̦ÿ SD̈K) is a graphics
	package/framework/game engine that I have been working on for the past
	3 years.
</p>

<p>
	In this article I attempt to turn you against mainstream engines and I will
	explain, in detail, why Tramway SDK is not as awful as them.
</p>

<h2>
	Unreasonable system requirements due to Turbobloat
</h2>

<hr>

<p>
	Unity needs very powerful hardware and consumes enough power to burn down a
	rainforest. Godot is slightly better, but you still need relatively capable
	hardware.
</p>

<p>
	But what if all that you really want to make is just a lowpoly horror
	roguelite deckbuilder simulator? 15 year old hardware is more than capable
	of running a game like that, but not if you use a mainstream engine, due to
	Turbobloat.
</p>

<p>
	Tramway SDK can run on virtually any hardware from the last 15 years, since
	it is not Turbobloated. It doesn't even need a graphics card, since it can
	be switched to use software rasterization, making it perfect for displaying
	graphics on	toasters and fridges.
</p>

<p>
	Some might say "just get a better computer". This is why getting a better
	computer is bad:
</p>

<ol>
	<li>
		<h4>
			Affordance
		</h4>
		
		<p>
			A lot of people, especially from 3rd world countries are very poor
			and can't afford to buy hardware to run Turbobloat.
		</p>
	</li>
	
	<li>
		<h4>
			e-Waste
		</h4>
		
		<p>
			Producing computer chips is very bad on the environment. If modern
			software wasn't Turbobloated you would buy new hardware only when
			the previous hardware broke and wasn't repairable.
		</p>
	</li>
	
	<li>
		<h4>
			Not putting up with Turbobloat
		</h4>
		
		<p>
			Why spend money on another computer if you already have one that
			works perfectly fine? Just because of someone else's turbobloat? 
			You could buy 1000 cans of Dr. Pepper instead.
		</p>
	</li>
</ol>

<h2>
	Nodes are bad
</h2>

<hr>

<p>
	A thing should be a thing. It should not be a bunch of things pretending to
	be a single thing. With nodes you have to pretend that a collection of
	things is a single thing.
</p>

<p>
	Also when creating things with nodes, you have to go back and forth between
	node GUI and code. 
</p>

<p>
	In Tramway SDK you just subclass the Entity class and write the code. After
	that you make a level using the level editor. No going back and forth. No 
	nodes, just entities.
</p>

<h2>
	Monolithism
</h2>

<hr>

<p>
	All of the mainstream engines have a monolithic game editor. It doesn't
	matter how many features you use from it, you still have to wait 10 minutes
	for all of them to load in.
</p>

<p>
	Tramway SDK has editors, but all of them are optional. If you just want to
	use it as a framework, you can use only the C++ runtime. If you want to
	build levels, you can use only the level editor and no other GUI tool.
</p>

<p>
	Data files are stored as whitespace-seperated-values, so you could even edit
	all of the data files by hand, without using a single editor.
</p>

<h2>
	Bad graphics
</h2>

<hr>

<p>
	Most Unity games look like very bad, even with fancy shaders, normal mapping
	and other techniques.
</p>

<p>
	Look at what Tramway SDK can do with just lightmapping and Gouraud shading:
</p>

<center>
	<a target="_blank" href="https://racenis.github.io/tram-sdk/images/article/why/photorealism.png">
		<img src="https://racenis.github.io/tram-sdk/images/article/why/photorealism.png">
	</a><br>
	<i>
		This could be rendered on a Direct3D 7 level graphics card with a
		fixed-function pipeline.
	</i>
</center>

<h2>
	Quake level editors
</h2>

<hr>

<p>
	Brush based level geometry is very good and you can prototype levels with it
	very quickly. Tramway SDK has a <code>.map</code> file converter, which
	converts brushes into triangle meshes.
</p>

<center>
	<a target="_blank" href="https://racenis.github.io/tram-sdk/images/article/why/trenchbroom.png">
		<img src="https://racenis.github.io/tram-sdk/images/article/why/trenchbroom.png">
	</a><br>
	<i>Level being created in the Trenchbroom map editor.</i>
</center>

<br>

<center>
	<a target="_blank" href="https://racenis.github.io/tram-sdk/images/article/why/leveleditor.png">
		<img src="https://racenis.github.io/tram-sdk/images/article/why/leveleditor.png">
	</a><br>
	<i>Level being set up in the Tramway SDK level editor.</i>
</center>

<br>

<center>
	<a target="_blank" href="https://racenis.github.io/tram-sdk/images/article/why/inengine.png">
		<img src="https://racenis.github.io/tram-sdk/images/article/why/inengine.png">
	</a><br>
	<i>Level with lightmaps being rendered in-engine.</i>
</center>

<p>
	Wow! Look at this very fancy level. Not only can we create brush-based
	levels, we even have an input/output system like in Source to set up 
	interactions between entities in levels.
</p>

<center>
	<a target="_blank" href="https://racenis.github.io/tram-sdk/images/article/why/signals.png">
		<img src="https://racenis.github.io/tram-sdk/images/article/why/signals.png">
	</a><br>
	<i>Very fancy interaction editor.</i>
</center>

<p>
	In the future I will be implementing all of the Source logic entities, so
	that you can do visual scripting right in the level editor.
</p>

<h2>
	Framework for RPGs
</h2>

<hr>

<p>
	I think that it is very interesting to see the different kinds of games that
	can be created in a tool like RPG Maker. There's also tons of mods, even
	total conversions based on Morrowind. You can do a lot of stuff by changing
	the data, even in the RPG mechanics have already preprogrammed.
</p>

<center>
	<a target="_blank" href="https://racenis.github.io/tram-sdk/images/article/why/kitchensink.png">
		<img src="https://racenis.github.io/tram-sdk/images/article/why/kitchensink.png">
	</a><br>
	<i>Editor for the RPG framework.</i>
</center>

<p>
	Since the engine was designed to support level streaming from the very
	beginning, it should make the creation of open-world RPG-ish games very
	quick and very easy.
</p>

<center>
	<a target="_blank" href="https://racenis.github.io/tram-sdk/images/article/why/rpg.png">
		<img src="https://racenis.github.io/tram-sdk/images/article/why/rpg.png">
	</a><br>
	<i>
		Everyone always says that you "shouldn't create an open-world RPG", but
		that's just because they have never tried using the Trawmay SDK.
	</i>
</center>

<h2>
	TL; DR
</h2>

<hr>

<p>
	Tramway SDK is a game engine based on Quake/Source style entities, supports
	open-world streaming, comes with optional extensions, like the RPG framework
	that is sort like RPG Maker, but for 3D.
</p>

<p>
	This project is still in very early development. APIs are unstable, stuff
	breaks or just doesn't work, a lot of things still haven't been implemented,
	but it's getting better very quickly.
</p>

<center>
	<a href="https://github.com/racenis/tram-sdk">
		Click here for the Github repo!
	</a>
</center>




				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: HipScript – Run CUDA in the Browser with WebAssembly and WebGPU (231 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://hipscript.lights0123.com/</link>
            <guid>42623593</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 15:44:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://hipscript.lights0123.com/">https://hipscript.lights0123.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42623593">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><h2>HipScript</h2> <p>Online compiler for HIP and NVIDIA® CUDA® code to WebGPU</p> <p>By Ben Schattinger • <a href="https://lights0123.com/blog/2025/01/07/hip-script/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Learn More</a></p> <p><small>Load sample code:</small> </p><!--[!--><details open=""><summary>Select GPU</summary>  <p>GPU Information</p> <ul><!--[--><!--]--></ul></details> <!--]--> <!--[!--><!--]--> <!--[!--><!--]--></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Federal Reserve Bank of NY "Doomsday Book" 2022 via FOIA [pdf] (276 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.crisesnotes.com/content/files/2023/12/NYFRB-2006.--Doomsday-Book--Searchable.pdf</link>
            <guid>42623144</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 15:09:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.crisesnotes.com/content/files/2023/12/NYFRB-2006.--Doomsday-Book--Searchable.pdf">https://www.crisesnotes.com/content/files/2023/12/NYFRB-2006.--Doomsday-Book--Searchable.pdf</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42623144">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Building Ultra Long Range Toslink (220 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.benjojo.co.uk/post/sfp-experiment-ultra-long-range-toslink</link>
            <guid>42621766</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 12:39:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.benjojo.co.uk/post/sfp-experiment-ultra-long-range-toslink">https://blog.benjojo.co.uk/post/sfp-experiment-ultra-long-range-toslink</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42621766">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://blog.benjojo.co.uk/post/sfp-experiment-ultra-long-range-toslink: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ending our third party fact-checking program and moving to Community Notes model (705 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://about.fb.com/news/2025/01/meta-more-speech-fewer-mistakes/</link>
            <guid>42621627</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 12:15:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://about.fb.com/news/2025/01/meta-more-speech-fewer-mistakes/">https://about.fb.com/news/2025/01/meta-more-speech-fewer-mistakes/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42621627">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
		<p><span>Meta’s platforms are built to be places where people can express themselves freely. That can be messy. On platforms where billions of people can have a voice, all the good, bad and ugly is on display. But that’s free expression.</span></p>
<p><span>In his 2019 speech at Georgetown University, Mark Zuckerberg argued that free expression has been the driving force behind progress in American society and around the world and that inhibiting speech, however well-intentioned the reasons for doing so, often reinforces existing institutions and power structures instead of empowering people. He said: “Some people believe giving more people a voice is driving division rather than bringing us together. More people across the spectrum believe that achieving the political outcomes they think matter is more important than every person having a voice. I think that’s dangerous.”</span></p>
<p><span>In recent years we’ve developed increasingly complex systems to manage content across our platforms, partly in response to societal and political pressure to moderate content. This approach has gone too far. As well-intentioned as many of these efforts have been, they have expanded over time to the point where we are making too many mistakes, frustrating our users and too often getting in the way of the free expression we set out to enable. Too much harmless content gets censored, too many people find themselves wrongly locked up in “Facebook jail,” and we are often too slow to respond when they do.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>We want to fix that and return to that fundamental commitment to free expression. Today, we’re making some changes to stay true to that ideal.</span></p>
<h2>Ending Third Party Fact Checking Program, Moving to Community Notes</h2>
<p><span>When we launched our independent fact checking program in 2016, we were very clear that we didn’t want to be the arbiters of truth. We made what we thought was the best and most reasonable choice at the time, which was to hand that responsibility over to independent fact checking organizations. The intention of the program was to have these independent experts give people more information about the things they see online, particularly viral hoaxes, so they were able to judge for themselves what they saw and read.</span></p>
<p><span>That’s not the way things played out, especially in the United States. Experts, like everyone else, have their own biases and perspectives. This showed up in the choices some made about what to fact check and how. Over time we ended up with too much content being fact checked that people would understand to be legitimate political speech and debate. Our system then attached real consequences in the form of intrusive labels and reduced distribution. A program intended to inform too often became a tool to censor.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>We are now changing this approach. We will end the current third party fact checking program in the United States and instead begin moving to a Community Notes program. We’ve seen this approach work on X – where they empower their community to decide when posts are potentially misleading and need more context, and people across a diverse range of perspectives decide what sort of context is helpful for other users to see. We think this could be a better way of achieving our original intention of providing people with information about what they’re seeing – and one that’s less prone to bias.</span></p>
<ul>
<li><span>Once the program is up and running, Meta won’t write Community Notes or decide which ones show up. They are written and rated by contributing users.&nbsp;</span></li>
<li><span>Just like they do on X, Community Notes will require agreement between people with a range of perspectives to help prevent biased ratings.</span></li>
<li><span>We intend to be transparent about how different viewpoints inform the Notes displayed in our apps, and are working on the right way to share this information.</span></li>
<li><span>People can sign up today (</span><a href="https://www.facebook.com/help/contact/1914298425761977"><span>Facebook</span></a><span>, </span><a href="https://help.instagram.com/contact/1223551615403090"><span>Instagram</span></a><span>, </span><a href="https://help.instagram.com/contact/1638078013752611"><span>Threads</span></a><span>) for the opportunity to be among the first contributors to this program as it becomes available.&nbsp;</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span>We plan to phase in Community Notes in the US first over the next couple of months, and will continue to improve it over the course of the year. As we make the transition, we will get rid of our fact-checking control, stop demoting fact checked content and, instead of overlaying full screen interstitial warnings you have to click through before you can even see the post, we will use a much less obtrusive label indicating that there is additional information for those who want to see it.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p>
<h2>Allowing More Speech</h2>
<p><span>Over time, we have developed complex systems to manage content on our platforms, which are increasingly complicated for us to enforce. As a result, we have been over-enforcing our rules, limiting legitimate political debate and censoring too much trivial content and subjecting too many people to frustrating enforcement actions.</span></p>
<p><span>For example, in December 2024, we removed millions of pieces of content every day. While these actions account for less than 1% of content produced every day, we think one to two out of every 10 of these actions may have been mistakes (i.e., the content may not have actually violated our policies). This does not account for actions we take to tackle large-scale adversarial spam attacks. We plan to expand our transparency reporting to share numbers on our mistakes on a regular basis so that people can track our progress. As part of that we’ll also include more details on the mistakes we make when enforcing our spam policies.</span></p>
<p><span>We want to undo the mission creep that has made our rules too restrictive and too prone to over-enforcement. We’re getting rid of a number of restrictions on topics like immigration, gender identity and gender that are the subject of frequent political discourse and debate. It’s not right that things can be said on TV or the floor of Congress, but not on our platforms. These policy changes may take a few weeks to be fully implemented.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>We’re also going to change how we enforce our policies to reduce the kind of mistakes that account for the vast majority of the censorship on our platforms. Up until now, we have been using automated systems to scan for all policy violations, but this has resulted in too many mistakes and too much content being censored that shouldn’t have been. So, we’re going to continue to focus these systems on tackling illegal and high-severity violations, like terrorism, child sexual exploitation, drugs, fraud and scams. For less severe policy violations, we’re going to rely on someone reporting an issue before we take any action. We also demote too much content that our systems predict might violate our standards. We are in the process of getting rid of most of these demotions and requiring greater confidence that the content violates for the rest. And we’re going to tune our systems to require a much higher degree of confidence before a piece of content is taken down. As part of these changes, we will be moving the trust and safety teams that write our content policies and review content out of California to Texas and other US locations.</span></p>
<p><span>People are often given the chance to appeal our enforcement decisions and ask us to take another look, but the process can be frustratingly slow and doesn’t always get to the right outcome. We’ve added extra staff to this work and in more cases, we are also now requiring multiple reviewers to reach a determination in order to take something down. We are working on ways to make recovering accounts more straightforward and testing facial recognition technology, and we’ve started using AI large language models (LLMs) to provide a second opinion on some content before we take enforcement actions.</span></p>
<h2>A Personalized Approach to Political Content</h2>
<p><span>Since 2021, we’ve made changes to reduce the amount of civic content people see – posts about elections, politics or social issues – based on the feedback our users gave us that they wanted to see less of this content. But this was a pretty blunt approach. We are going to start phasing this back into Facebook, Instagram and Threads with a more personalized approach so that people who want to see more political content in their feeds can.</span></p>
<p><span>We’re continually testing how we deliver personalized experiences and have recently conducted testing around civic content. As a result, we’re going to start treating civic content from people and Pages you follow on Facebook more like any other content in your feed, and we will start ranking and showing you that content based on explicit signals (for example, liking a piece of content) and implicit signals (like viewing posts) that help us predict what’s meaningful to people. We are also going to recommend more political content based on these personalized signals and are expanding the options people have to control how much of this content they see.</span></p>
<p><span>These changes are an attempt to return to the commitment to free expression that Mark Zuckerberg set out in his Georgetown speech. That means being vigilant about the impact our policies and systems are having on people’s ability to make their voices heard, and having the humility to change our approach when we know we’re getting things wrong.</span></p>
		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Getty Images and Shutterstock to Merge (167 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://newsroom.gettyimages.com/en/getty-images/getty-images-and-shutterstock-to-merge-creating-a-premier-visual-content-company</link>
            <guid>42621544</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 12:00:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://newsroom.gettyimages.com/en/getty-images/getty-images-and-shutterstock-to-merge-creating-a-premier-visual-content-company">https://newsroom.gettyimages.com/en/getty-images/getty-images-and-shutterstock-to-merge-creating-a-premier-visual-content-company</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42621544">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div> <ul><li><em>Merged company will be well‑positioned to meet the evolving needs of creative, media, and advertising industries through combined investment in content creation, event coverage, and product and technology innovation &nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</em></li><li><em>Expected annual cost synergies between $150 million and $200 million by year three</em></li><li><em>Expected to be accretive to earnings and cash flow beginning in year two</em></li><li><em>Companies will hold conference call to discuss the transaction with investment community today at 8.30a.m. EST</em></li></ul><p><strong>NEW YORK, January 7, 2025</strong> – Getty&nbsp;Images Holdings, Inc. (NYSE: GETY) and Shutterstock (NYSE: SSTK) today announced that they entered into a definitive merger agreement to combine in a merger of equals transaction, creating a premier visual content company. The combined company, which would have an enterprise value of approximately $3.7 billion[i], will be named Getty&nbsp;Images Holdings, Inc and will continue to trade on the New York Stock Exchange under the ticker symbol “GETY”.&nbsp;</p><p>As a combined company, Getty&nbsp;Images and Shutterstock will offer a content library with greater depth and breadth for the benefit of customers, expanded opportunities for its contributor community and a reinforced commitment to the adoption of inclusive and representative content. Furthermore, the stronger financial profile of the combined company is expected to create increased capacity for product investment and innovation for customers in a fast‑evolving and highly competitive environment. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p><p>&nbsp;“Today’s announcement is exciting and transformational for our companies, unlocking multiple opportunities to strengthen our financial foundation and invest in the future—including enhancing our content offerings, expanding event coverage, and delivering new technologies to better serve our customers,” said Craig Peters, CEO, Getty&nbsp;Images. “With the rapid rise in demand for compelling visual content across industries, there has never been a better time for our two businesses to come together. By combining our complementary strengths, we can better address customer opportunities while delivering exceptional value to our partners, contributors, and stockholders.”</p><p>“We are excited by the opportunities we see to expand our creative content library and enhance our product offering to meet diverse customer needs,” said Paul Hennessy, CEO, Shutterstock. “We expect the merger to produce value for the customers and stockholders of both companies by capitalizing on attractive growth opportunities to drive combined revenues, accelerating product innovation, realizing significant cost synergies and improving cash flow. We look forward to working closely with the Getty&nbsp;Images management team to complete the transaction and drive the next chapter of growth.”</p><p><strong>Strategic and Financial Benefits</strong></p><ul><li><em>Cutting‑edge innovation:</em> Facilitates greater investment in innovative content creation, expanded event coverage, and customer‑facing technologies and capabilities such as search, 3D imagery and generative AI. &nbsp; &nbsp;</li><li><em>Complementary portfolios:&nbsp;</em>Creates a broader set of visual content products across still imagery, video, music, 3D and other asset types.</li><li><em>Expanded opportunities for content creators:&nbsp;</em>Provides contributors substantially greater opportunities to reach customers around the world.</li><li><em>Strengthened balance sheet and greater cash flow generation:</em> By deleveraging the combined balance sheet through the transaction and driving more robust cash flow, the combined company will be well positioned to accelerate debt repayment, reduce borrowing costs, and capitalize on new opportunities to create value for customers and stockholders.</li><li><em>Significant synergies:&nbsp;</em>Drives expected run rate synergies across SG&amp;A and CAPEX between $150 million and $200 million achieved within the first three years post‑close, with approximately two‑thirds expected to be delivered within the first twelve to twenty‑four months.</li><li><em>Compelling Financial Profile:</em>On a pro forma 2024 basis the combined company would have an attractive financial profile:<ul><li>Revenue of between $1,979 million and $1,993 million, including 46% of subscription revenue</li><li>Pre‑synergy EBITDA of between $569 million and $574 million</li><li>Pre‑synergy Adjusted EBITDA less capital expenditures of between $461 million and $466 million</li><li>Pre‑synergy net leverage of 3.0x pro forma 2024 pre‑synergy EBITDA</li></ul></li></ul><p><strong>Leadership and Governance</strong><br>At close, Getty&nbsp;Images’s CEO, Craig Peters, will serve as CEO of the combined company. The combined company will have an eleven‑member Board of Directors, comprised of Getty&nbsp;Images CEO Craig Peters, six directors designated by Getty&nbsp;Images and four directors designated by Shutterstock, including Paul Hennessy, Shutterstock CEO. The Chairman of the Board of Directors of the combined company will be Mark Getty, currently Chairman of Getty&nbsp;Images.</p><p><strong>Transaction Details</strong><br>Under the terms of the agreement, which was unanimously approved by the Boards of Directors of both companies, Shutterstock stockholders at close can elect to receive one of the following:</p><ul><li>$28.84870 per share in cash for each share of Shutterstock common stock they own;</li><li>13.67237 shares of Getty&nbsp;Images common stock for each share of Shutterstock common stock they own; or</li><li>a mixed consideration of 9.17 shares of Getty&nbsp;Images common stock plus $9.50 in cash for each share of Shutterstock common stock they own.</li></ul><p>Shutterstock shareholder elections at close are subject to proration to ensure that the aggregate consideration payable by Getty&nbsp;Images consist of $9.50 in cash per Shutterstock share as of immediately before close and 9.17 shares of Getty&nbsp;Images stock per Shutterstock share as immediately before close.</p><p>Based on the common shares outstanding as of the signing date, the aggregate consideration payable by Getty&nbsp;Images would consist of $331 million in cash and 319.4 million shares of Getty&nbsp;Images stock. These figures do not include the impact of unvested Shutterstock equityholders as of the signing date and do not assume any vesting of currently‑unvested Shutterstock equity holdings between signing and close.</p><p>Shutterstock equityholders with unvested RSU and PSU grants at close will only be eligible to receive the mixed consideration noted above upon vesting with respect to such grants. Shutterstock option holders will have their options and strike prices adjusted by a ratio equal to the sum of (i) 9.17 and (ii) $9.50 divided by the 10‑day average closing stock price of Getty&nbsp;Images common stock for the period ending two (2) business days prior to the closing as quoted on NYSE. Equity treatment will take into account any employment contracts in place at the close of the transaction. Aggregate cash and share amounts are estimates and are subject to change between signing and close.</p><p>At close, Getty&nbsp;Images stockholders will own approximately 54.7% and Shutterstock stockholders will own approximately 45.3% of the combined company on a fully diluted basis. Shutterstock will, at the discretion of its Board of Directors, continue to declare and pay quarterly cash dividends, in accordance with its dividend policy, pending the close of the transaction.</p><p><strong>Timing and Closing</strong><br>The transaction is subject to the satisfaction of customary closing conditions, including receipt of required regulatory approvals, the approval of Getty&nbsp;Images and Shutterstock stockholders and the extension or refinancing of Getty&nbsp;Images’ existing debt obligations. &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</p><p><strong>Advisors</strong><br>Berenson &amp; Company, LLC is acting as lead financial advisor and J.P. Morgan Securities LLC is acting as a financial advisor to Getty&nbsp;Images and Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher &amp; Flom LLP is serving as legal advisor. Allen &amp; Company LLC is acting as exclusive financial advisor to Shutterstock and White &amp; Case LLP is serving as legal advisor.</p><p><strong>Conference Call</strong><br>Getty&nbsp;Images and Shutterstock will hold a conference call to discuss the transaction today, January 7, 2025, at 8:30 a.m. Eastern Time. The live webcast will be accessible through the Investor Relations section of the each company’s website at <a href="https://investors.gettyimages.com/" target="_blank">https://investors.gettyimages.com/</a> and&nbsp;<a href="https://investor.shutterstock.com/" target="_blank">https://investor.shutterstock.com</a>.</p><p>To access the call through a conference line, dial 1‑800‑445‑7795 (in the U.S.) or 1‑785‑424‑1699 (international callers). The conference ID for the call is GETTY. A replay of the conference call will be posted shortly after the call and will be available for fourteen days following the call. To access the replay, dial 1‑844‑512‑2921 (in the U.S.) or 1‑412‑317‑6671 (international callers). The access code for the replay is 11156500.</p><p><strong>Investor Contact Getty&nbsp;Images:</strong><br>Steven Kanner<br><a href="mailto:Investorrelations@gettyimages.com">Investorrelations@gettyimages.com</a></p><p>&nbsp;<strong>Media Contact Getty&nbsp;Images:</strong><br>Anne Flanagan<br><a href="mailto:Anne.flanagan@gettyimages.com">Anne.flanagan@gettyimages.com</a></p><p>&nbsp;<strong>Investor Contact Shutterstock:</strong><br>Chris Suh<br><a href="mailto:csuh@shutterstock.com">csuh@shutterstock.com</a></p><p>&nbsp;<strong>Media Contact Shutterstock:</strong><br>Lori Rodney<br><a href="mailto:lrodney@shutterstock.com">lrodney@shutterstock.com</a></p><p><strong>About Getty&nbsp;Images</strong><br>Getty&nbsp;Images (NYSE: GETY) is a preeminent global visual content creator and marketplace that offers a full range of content solutions to meet the needs of any customer around the globe, no matter their size. Through its <a href="http://www.gettyimages.com/" target="_blank">Getty&nbsp;Images</a>, <a href="https://www.istockphoto.com/" target="_blank">iStock</a> and <a href="https://unsplash.com/" target="_blank">Unsplash</a> brands, websites and APIs, Getty&nbsp;Images serves customers in almost every country in the world and is the first‑place people turn to discover, purchase and share powerful visual content from the world’s best photographers and videographers. Getty&nbsp;Images works with over 576,000 content creators and more than 340 content partners to deliver this powerful and comprehensive content. Each year Getty&nbsp;Images covers more than 160,000 <a href="http://www.gettyimages.com/editorialimages/news" target="_blank">news</a>, <a href="http://www.gettyimages.com/editorialimages/sport" target="_blank">sport</a> and <a href="http://www.gettyimages.com/editorialimages/entertainment" target="_blank">entertainment</a> events providing depth and breadth of coverage that is unmatched. Getty&nbsp;Images maintains one of the largest and best privately‑owned&nbsp;<a href="http://www.gettyimages.com/editorialimages/archival" target="_blank">photographic archives</a> in the world with millions of images dating back to the beginning of photography.</p><p>Through its <a href="https://www.gettyimages.com/creative" target="_blank">best‑in‑class creative library</a> and <a href="https://www.gettyimages.com/enterprise/custom-content" target="_blank">Custom Content</a> solutions, Getty&nbsp;Images helps customers elevate their creativity and entire end‑to‑end creative process to find the right visual for any need. With the adoption and distribution of generative AI technologies and tools trained on permissioned content that include indemnification and perpetual, worldwide usage rights, <a href="https://www.gettyimages.com/ai" target="_blank">Getty&nbsp;Images&nbsp;</a>and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.istockphoto.com/ai" target="_blank">iStock</a> customers can use text to image generation to ideate and create commercially safe compelling visuals, further expanding Getty&nbsp;Images capabilities to deliver exactly what customers are looking for.</p><p>For company news and announcements, visit our&nbsp;<a href="https://newsroom.gettyimages.com/" target="_blank">Newsroom</a>.</p><p><strong>About Shutterstock, Inc.</strong><br>Shutterstock, Inc. (NYSE:&nbsp;<a href="https://markets.financialcontent.com/prnews/quote?Symbol=SSTK" target="_blank">SSTK</a>) is a premier partner for transformative brands, digital media and marketing companies, empowering the world to create with confidence. Fueled by millions of creators around the world and a fearless approach to product innovation, Shutterstock is the leading global platform for licensing from the most extensive and diverse collection of high‑quality 3D models, videos, music, photographs, vectors and illustrations. From the world's largest content marketplace, to breaking news and A‑list entertainment editorial access, to all‑in‑one content editing platform and studio production service—all using the latest in innovative technology—Shutterstock offers the most comprehensive selection of resources to bring storytelling to life.</p><p>Learn more at <a href="https://www.shutterstock.com/" target="_blank">www.shutterstock.com</a> and follow us on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/shutterstock/" target="_blank">LinkedIn</a>, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/shutterstock/" target="_blank">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://x.com/shutterst" target="_blank">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/Shutterstock/" target="_blank">Facebook</a> and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCmhVYUCCOm0D5bT12MOr5_w" target="_blank">YouTube</a>.</p><p><strong>Additional Information about the Acquisition and Where to Find It</strong><br>In connection with the proposed transaction, Getty&nbsp;Images intends to file with the Securities and Exchange Commission (the “SEC”) a registration statement on Form S‑4 that will include an information statement of Getty&nbsp;Images and a proxy statement of Shutterstock and that also will constitute a prospectus with respect to shares of Getty&nbsp;Images’ common stock to be issued in the transaction (the “joint proxy and information statement/prospectus”). Each of Getty&nbsp;Images and Shutterstock may also file with or furnish to the SEC other relevant documents regarding the proposed transaction. This press release is not a substitute for the joint proxy and information statement/prospectus or any other document that Getty&nbsp;Images or Shutterstock may file with or furnish to the SEC. The definitive joint proxy and information statement/prospectus (if and when available) will be mailed to stockholders of Getty&nbsp;Images and Shutterstock. BEFORE MAKING ANY VOTING OR INVESTMENT DECISION, INVESTORS AND SECURITY HOLDERS ARE URGED TO READ THE JOINT PROXY AND INFORMATION STATEMENT/PROSPECTUS (WHEN AVAILABLE) AND ALL OTHER RELEVANT DOCUMENTS THAT ARE OR WILL BE FILED WITH OR FURNISHED TO THE SEC, AS WELL AS ANY AMENDMENTS OR SUPPLEMENTS TO THESE DOCUMENTS, CAREFULLY AND IN THEIR ENTIRETY BECAUSE THEY CONTAIN OR WILL CONTAIN IMPORTANT INFORMATION ABOUT THE PROPOSED TRANSACTION AND RELATED MATTERS. Investors and security holders will be able to obtain free copies of the joint proxy and information statement/prospectus (if and when available) and other documents containing important information about Getty&nbsp;Images, Shutterstock and the proposed transaction, once such documents are filed with or furnished to the SEC through the website maintained by the SEC at www.sec.gov. Copies of the documents filed with or furnished to the SEC by Getty&nbsp;Images will be available free of charge on Getty&nbsp;Images’ website at investors.gettyimages.com or by contacting Getty&nbsp;Images’ Investor Relations department by email at <a href="mailto:investorrelations@gettyimages.com">investorrelations@gettyimages.com</a>. Copies of the documents filed with or furnished to the SEC by Shutterstock will be available free of charge on Shutterstock’s website at investor. shutterstock.com or by contacting Shutterstock’s Investor Relations department by email at&nbsp;<a href="mailto:IR@Shutterstock.com">IR@Shutterstock.com</a>.</p><p><strong>Participants in the Solicitation</strong><br>This communication is not a solicitation of proxies in connection with the proposed transaction. Getty&nbsp;Images, Shutterstock and certain of their respective directors and executive officers and other members of their respective management and employees may be deemed to be participants in the solicitation of proxies in respect of the proposed transaction. Information about the directors and executive officers of Getty&nbsp;Images, including a description of their direct or indirect interests, by security holdings or otherwise, is set forth in Getty&nbsp;Images’ proxy statement for its 2024 annual meeting of stockholders, which was filed with the SEC on April 24, 2024. Information about the directors and executive officers of Shutterstock, including a description of their direct or indirect interests, by security holdings or otherwise, is set forth in Shutterstock’s proxy statement for its 2024 annual meeting of stockholders, which was filed with the SEC on April 26, 2024. Other information regarding the participants in the proxy solicitations and a description of their direct and indirect interests, by security holdings or otherwise, will be contained in the joint proxy and information statement/prospectus and other relevant materials to be filed with or furnished to the SEC regarding the proposed transaction. You may obtain free copies of these documents using the sources indicated above.</p><p><strong>No Offer or Solicitation</strong><br>This communication is not intended to and shall not constitute an offer to buy or sell or the solicitation of an offer to buy or sell any securities, or a solicitation of any vote or approval, nor shall there be any sale of securities in any jurisdiction in which such offer, solicitation or sale would be unlawful prior to registration or qualification under the securities laws of any such jurisdiction. No offer of securities shall be made, except by means of a prospectus meeting the requirements of Section 10 of the Securities Act of 1933, as amended.</p><p><strong>Forward Looking Statements</strong><br>The statements in this press release, and any related oral statements, include forward‑looking statements concerning Getty&nbsp;Images, Shutterstock, the proposed transaction described herein and other matters. All statements, other than historical facts, are forward‑looking statements. Forward‑looking statements may discuss goals, intentions and expectations as to future plans, trends, events, results of operations or financial condition, financings or otherwise, based on current beliefs and involve numerous risks and uncertainties that could cause actual results to differ materially from expectations. Forward‑looking statements speak only as of the date they are made or as of the dates indicated in the statements and should not be relied upon as predictions of future events, as there can be no assurance that the events or circumstances reflected in these statements will be achieved or will occur or the timing thereof. Forward‑looking statements can often, but not always, be identified by the use of forward‑looking terminology including “believes,” “expects,” “may,” “will,” “should,” “could,” “might,” “seeks,” “intends,” “plans,” “pro forma,” “estimates,” “anticipates,” “designed,” or the negative of these words and phrases, other variations of these words and phrases or comparable terminology, but not all forward‑looking statements include such identifying words. Forward‑looking statements are based upon current plans, estimates and expectations that are subject to risks, uncertainties and assumptions. Should one or more of these risks or uncertainties materialize, or should underlying assumptions prove incorrect, actual results may vary. The forward‑looking statements in this press release relate to, among other things, obtaining applicable regulatory and stockholder approvals on a timely basis or otherwise, satisfying other closing conditions to the proposed transaction, on a timely basis or otherwise, the expected tax treatment of the transaction, the expected timing of the transaction, and the integration of the businesses and the expected benefits, cost savings, accretion, synergies and growth to result therefrom. Important factors that could cause actual results to differ materially from such forward‑looking statements include, among other things: failure to obtain applicable regulatory or stockholder approvals in a timely manner or otherwise; interloper risk; failure to satisfy other closing conditions to the transaction or to complete the transaction on anticipated terms and timing (or at all); negative effects of the announcement of the transaction on the ability of Shutterstock or Getty&nbsp;Images to retain and hire key personnel and maintain relationships with customers, suppliers and others who Shutterstock or Getty&nbsp;Images does business, or on Shutterstock or Getty&nbsp;Images’ operating results and business generally; risks that the businesses will not be integrated successfully or that the combined company will not realize expected benefits, cost savings, accretion, synergies and/or growth, as expected (or at all), or that such benefits may take longer to realize or may be more costly to achieve than expected; the risk that disruptions from the transaction will harm business plans and operations; risks relating to unanticipated costs of integration; significant transaction and/or integration costs, or difficulties in connection with the transaction and/or unknown or inestimable liabilities; restrictions during the pendency of the transaction that may impact the ability to pursue certain business opportunities or strategic transactions; potential litigation associated with the transaction; the potential impact of the announcement or consummation of the transaction on Getty&nbsp;Images’, Shutterstock’s or the combined company’s relationships with suppliers, customers, employers and regulators; demand for the combined company’s products; potential changes in the Getty&nbsp;Images stock price that could negatively impact the value of the consideration offered to the Shutterstock stockholders; the occurrence of any event that could give rise to the termination of the proposed transaction; and Getty&nbsp;Images’ ability to complete any refinancing of its debt or new debt financing on a timely basis, on favorable terms or at all. A more fulsome discussion of the risks related to the proposed transaction will be included in the joint proxy and information statement/prospectus. For a discussion of factors that could cause actual results to differ materially from those contemplated by forward‑looking statements, see the section captioned “Risk Factors” in each of Getty&nbsp;Images’ and Shutterstock’s Annual Report on Form 10‑K for the fiscal year ended December 31, 2023, subsequent Quarterly Reports on Form 10‑Q and other filings with the SEC. Should one or more of these risks or uncertainties materialize, or should underlying assumptions prove incorrect, actual results may vary materially from those indicated or anticipated by such forward looking statements. While the list of factors presented here is, and the list of factors presented in the joint proxy and information statement/prospectus will be, considered representative, no such list should be considered to be a complete statement of all potential risks and uncertainties. Unlisted factors may present significant additional obstacles to the realization of forward looking statements. Neither Getty&nbsp;Images nor Shutterstock assumes, and each hereby disclaims, any obligation to update forward‑looking statements, except as may be required by law.</p><p>&nbsp;[i] Pro‑Forma Combined Enterprise Value is based on closing share prices as of January 6, 2025.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Nvidia announces $3k personal AI supercomputer called Digits (123 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theverge.com/2025/1/6/24337530/nvidia-ces-digits-super-computer-ai</link>
            <guid>42621332</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 11:11:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2025/1/6/24337530/nvidia-ces-digits-super-computer-ai">https://www.theverge.com/2025/1/6/24337530/nvidia-ces-digits-super-computer-ai</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42621332">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>If you were looking for your own personal AI supercomputer, Nvidia has you covered.</p><p>The chipmaker announced <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2025/1/4/24307731/ces-2025-tvs-gaming-smart-home-wearables-news">at CES</a> it’s launching a personal AI supercomputer called Project Digits in May. The heart of Project Digits is the new GB10 Grace Blackwell Superchip, which packs enough processing power to run sophisticated AI models while being compact enough to fit on a desk and run from a standard power outlet (this kind of processing power used to require much larger, more power-hungry systems). This desktop-sized system can handle AI models with up to 200 billion parameters, and has a starting price of $3,000. The product itself looks <a href="https://www.theverge.com/24289730/apple-mac-mini-m4-review">a lot like a Mac Mini</a>.</p><p>“AI will be mainstream in every application for every industry. With Project Digits, the Grace Blackwell Superchip comes to millions of developers,” Nvidia CEO Jensen Huang said in a press release. “Placing an AI supercomputer on the desks of every data scientist, AI researcher and student empowers them to engage and shape the age of AI.”</p><div><div role="button" aria-label="Zoom" tabindex="0"><figure><div><p><span><img alt="Project Digits looks like a mini PC." loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 744px" srcset="https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1319x741/376x211/filters:focal(660x371:661x372):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820689/chrome_HV8SYeFAav.png 376w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1319x741/384x216/filters:focal(660x371:661x372):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820689/chrome_HV8SYeFAav.png 384w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1319x741/415x233/filters:focal(660x371:661x372):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820689/chrome_HV8SYeFAav.png 415w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1319x741/480x270/filters:focal(660x371:661x372):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820689/chrome_HV8SYeFAav.png 480w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1319x741/540x303/filters:focal(660x371:661x372):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820689/chrome_HV8SYeFAav.png 540w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1319x741/640x360/filters:focal(660x371:661x372):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820689/chrome_HV8SYeFAav.png 640w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1319x741/750x421/filters:focal(660x371:661x372):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820689/chrome_HV8SYeFAav.png 750w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1319x741/828x465/filters:focal(660x371:661x372):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820689/chrome_HV8SYeFAav.png 828w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1319x741/1080x607/filters:focal(660x371:661x372):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820689/chrome_HV8SYeFAav.png 1080w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1319x741/1200x674/filters:focal(660x371:661x372):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820689/chrome_HV8SYeFAav.png 1200w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1319x741/1440x809/filters:focal(660x371:661x372):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820689/chrome_HV8SYeFAav.png 1440w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1319x741/1920x1079/filters:focal(660x371:661x372):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820689/chrome_HV8SYeFAav.png 1920w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1319x741/2048x1151/filters:focal(660x371:661x372):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820689/chrome_HV8SYeFAav.png 2048w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1319x741/2400x1348/filters:focal(660x371:661x372):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820689/chrome_HV8SYeFAav.png 2400w" src="https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1319x741/2400x1348/filters:focal(660x371:661x372):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820689/chrome_HV8SYeFAav.png" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAIAAAAAAAP///yH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAIBRAA7"></span></p></div></figure></div><div><figcaption><em>Project Digits looks like a mini PC.</em></figcaption> <p><cite>Image: Nvidia</cite></p></div></div><p>Each Project Digits system comes equipped with 128GB of unified, coherent memory (by comparison, a good laptop might have 16GB or 32GB of RAM) and up to 4TB of NVMe storage. For even more demanding applications, two Project Digits systems can be linked together to handle models with up to 405 billion parameters (Meta’s best model, Llama 3.1,  <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/7/23/24204055/meta-ai-llama-3-1-open-source-assistant-openai-chatgpt">has 405 billion parameters</a>).</p><p>The GB10 chip delivers up to 1 petaflop of AI performance (which means it can perform 1 quadrillion AI calculations per second) at FP4 precision (which helps make the calculations faster by making approximations), and the system features Nvidia’s latest-generation CUDA cores and fifth-generation Tensor Cores, connected via NVLink-C2C to a Grace CPU containing 20 power-efficient Arm-based cores. MediaTek, known for their Arm-based chip designs, collaborated on the GB10’s development to optimize its power efficiency and performance.</p><div><div role="button" aria-label="Zoom" tabindex="0"><figure><div><p><span><img alt="The Digits supercomputer specs." loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 744px" srcset="https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1322x733/376x208/filters:focal(661x367:662x368):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820687/chrome_NP3LJVKJfM.png 376w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1322x733/384x213/filters:focal(661x367:662x368):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820687/chrome_NP3LJVKJfM.png 384w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1322x733/415x230/filters:focal(661x367:662x368):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820687/chrome_NP3LJVKJfM.png 415w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1322x733/480x266/filters:focal(661x367:662x368):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820687/chrome_NP3LJVKJfM.png 480w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1322x733/540x299/filters:focal(661x367:662x368):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820687/chrome_NP3LJVKJfM.png 540w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1322x733/640x355/filters:focal(661x367:662x368):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820687/chrome_NP3LJVKJfM.png 640w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1322x733/750x416/filters:focal(661x367:662x368):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820687/chrome_NP3LJVKJfM.png 750w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1322x733/828x459/filters:focal(661x367:662x368):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820687/chrome_NP3LJVKJfM.png 828w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1322x733/1080x599/filters:focal(661x367:662x368):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820687/chrome_NP3LJVKJfM.png 1080w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1322x733/1200x665/filters:focal(661x367:662x368):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820687/chrome_NP3LJVKJfM.png 1200w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1322x733/1440x798/filters:focal(661x367:662x368):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820687/chrome_NP3LJVKJfM.png 1440w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1322x733/1920x1065/filters:focal(661x367:662x368):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820687/chrome_NP3LJVKJfM.png 1920w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1322x733/2048x1136/filters:focal(661x367:662x368):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820687/chrome_NP3LJVKJfM.png 2048w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1322x733/2400x1331/filters:focal(661x367:662x368):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820687/chrome_NP3LJVKJfM.png 2400w" src="https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:1322x733/2400x1331/filters:focal(661x367:662x368):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25820687/chrome_NP3LJVKJfM.png" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAIAAAAAAAP///yH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAIBRAA7"></span></p></div></figure></div><div><figcaption><em>The Digits supercomputer specs.</em></figcaption> <p><cite>Image: Nvidia</cite></p></div></div><p>Users will also get access to Nvidia’s AI software library, including development kits, orchestration tools, and pre-trained models available through the Nvidia NGC catalog. The system runs on Linux-based Nvidia DGX OS and supports popular frameworks like PyTorch, Python, and Jupyter notebooks. Developers can fine-tune models using the Nvidia NeMo framework and accelerate data science workflows with Nvidia RAPIDS libraries.</p><p>Users can develop and test their AI models locally on Project Digits, then deploy them to cloud services or data center infrastructure using the same Grace Blackwell architecture and Nvidia AI Enterprise software platform.</p><p>Nvidia offers a range of similar devices in the same <a href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/ai/nvidia-introduces-device-aimed-at-small-companies-hobbyists-3972ae41">accessibility</a> style — in December, it announced a $249 version of its Jetson computer for AI applications, targeting hobbyists and startups, called the Jetson Orin Nano Super (it handles models <a href="https://gigazine.net/gsc_news/en/20241218-nvidia-jetson-orin-nano-super/?utm_source=chatgpt.com">up to 8 billion parameters</a>).</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>