<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 23:00:06 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OpenAI's board has fired Sam Altman (2525 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://openai.com/blog/openai-announces-leadership-transition</link>
            <guid>38309611</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 20:28:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://openai.com/blog/openai-announces-leadership-transition">https://openai.com/blog/openai-announces-leadership-transition</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38309611">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content"><p><em>Chief technology officer Mira Murati appointed interim CEO to lead OpenAI; Sam Altman departs the company. </em></p><p><em>Search process underway to identify permanent successor.</em></p><p><br>The board of directors of OpenAI, Inc., the 501(c)(3) that acts as the overall governing body for all OpenAI activities, today announced that Sam Altman will depart as CEO and leave the board of directors. Mira Murati, the company’s chief technology officer, will serve as interim CEO, effective immediately.</p><p>A member of OpenAI’s leadership team for five years, Mira has played a critical role in OpenAI’s evolution into a global AI leader. She brings a unique skill set, understanding of the company’s values, operations, and business, and already leads the company’s research, product, and safety functions.&nbsp;Given her long tenure and close engagement with all aspects of the company, including her experience in AI governance and policy, the board believes she is uniquely qualified for the role and anticipates a seamless transition while it conducts a formal search for a permanent CEO.</p><p>Mr. Altman’s departure follows a deliberative review process by the board, which concluded that he was not consistently candid in his communications with the board, hindering its ability to exercise its responsibilities. The board no longer has confidence in his ability to continue leading OpenAI.</p><p>In a statement, the board of directors said: “OpenAI was deliberately structured to advance our mission: to ensure that artificial general intelligence benefits all humanity. The board remains fully committed to serving this mission. We are grateful for Sam’s many contributions to the founding and growth of OpenAI. At the same time, we believe new leadership is necessary as we move forward. As the leader of the company’s research, product, and safety functions, Mira is exceptionally qualified to step into the role of interim CEO. We have the utmost confidence in her ability to lead OpenAI during this transition period.”</p><p>OpenAI’s board of directors consists of OpenAI chief scientist Ilya Sutskever, independent directors Quora CEO Adam D’Angelo, technology entrepreneur Tasha McCauley, and Georgetown Center for Security and Emerging Technology’s Helen Toner.</p><p>As a part of this transition,&nbsp;Greg Brockman will be stepping down as chairman of the board and will remain in his role at the company, reporting to the CEO.</p><p>OpenAI was founded as a non-profit in 2015 with the core mission of ensuring that artificial general intelligence benefits all of humanity. In 2019, OpenAI restructured to ensure that the company could raise capital in pursuit of this mission, while preserving the nonprofit's mission, governance, and oversight. The majority of the board is independent, and the independent directors do not hold equity in OpenAI. While the company has experienced dramatic growth, it remains the fundamental governance responsibility of the board to advance OpenAI’s mission and preserve the principles of its Charter.<br></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Half-Life 25th Anniversary Update (377 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.half-life.com/en/halflife25/</link>
            <guid>38307889</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 18:35:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.half-life.com/en/halflife25/">https://www.half-life.com/en/halflife25/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38307889">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent">
                        <section id="updateincludes">
                            <h2 id="updateincludeshead">The 25th Anniversary Update <br>for Half-Life Includes:</h2>
                        </section>
                        <section id="uplink">
                            <h3>Half-Life Uplink</h3>
                            <p>Originally released as a CD exclusive for magazines and hardware manufacturers, this mini-campaign was built by the Half-Life team right after the game went gold. As this was many people's first experience with Half-Life, we thought it was finally time to bundle it with the main game—no sound card purchase necessary.</p>
                            <p><a data-lightbox="uplink" href="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/uplink_1.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/uplink_1thumb.jpg"></a>
                                <a data-lightbox="uplink" href="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/uplink_2.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/uplink_2thumb.jpg"></a>
                            </p>
                        </section>
                        <section id="maps">
                            <h3>4 New Multiplayer Maps</h3>
                            <p>Built by Valve level designers, these new maps push the limits of what's possible in the Half-Life engine.</p>
                            <div>
                                <div>
                                    <p><a data-lightbox="maps" href="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/map_contamination.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/map_contamination_thumb.jpg"></a></p><h6>Contamination</h6>
                                    <p>Two-foot-thick steel doors block off access to this contaminated waste facility, which has questionable scientific goals at best. Strap on a gluon gun and roast all intruders.</p>
                                </div>
                                <div>
                                    <p><a data-lightbox="maps" href="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/map_pool_party.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/map_pool_party_thumb.jpg"></a></p><h6>Pool Party</h6>
                                    <p>Enjoy a relaxing stay at this abandoned Xen outpost built around a cluster of soothing healing pools free-floating in space. How do you breathe here? It doesn't matter!</p>
                                </div>
                                <div>
                                    <p><a data-lightbox="maps" href="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/map_disposal.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/map_disposal_thumb.jpg"></a></p><h6>Disposal</h6>
                                    <p>Processing Area 3, a massive radioactive waste plant gone quiet. Tons of room for you and your colleagues to do experiments with a Tau Cannon or some hand grenades.</p>
                                </div>
                                <div>
                                    <p><a data-lightbox="maps" href="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/map_rocket_frenzy.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/map_rocket_frenzy_thumb.jpg"></a></p><h6>Rocket Frenzy</h6>
                                    <p>The creaking weight of this decaying orbital satellite launch facility somehow feels familiar… If we could switch on the oxygen lines, power, and fuel, we might just be able to light this candle.</p>
                                </div>
                            </div>
                        </section>
                        <section id="graphics">
                            <h3>Updated Graphics Settings</h3>
                            <p>Play the game the way it looked in 1998, but on a modern monitor.</p>
                            <ul>
                                <li>Widescreen field of view!</li>
                                <li>Option to disable texture smoothing on the GL renderer!</li>
                                <li>Lighting fixes including the long-lost GL Overbright support!</li>
                                <li>Software rendering on Linux! Crisp colors, animated water, and unfiltered textures!</li>
                            </ul>
                        </section>
                        <section id="loader">
                            <video id="loadervideo" preload="" autoplay="" muted="" playsinline="" loop="" poster="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/loader.png">
                                <source type="video/webm" src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/loader.webm">
                            </video>
                            
                        </section>
                        <section id="multiplayer">
                            <h3>Controller and Steam Networking Support</h3>
                            <ul>
                                <li>A proper gamepad config out of the box!</li>
                                <li>Added support for Steam Networking! Invite your friends or join games instantly with no fuss.</li>
                            </ul>
                        </section>
                        <section id="deck">
                            <h3>Steam Deck Support!</h3>
                            <p>We finally put our game through our own “Verified” tests, and... we failed super hard. So we fixed it! After re-testing the game, Half-Life gets to officially wear the green checkmark.</p><p>Now you can play Half-Life on the best handheld gaming computer in the world in glorious 800p with improved controls and UI.</p>
                            <video id="deckvideo" preload="" autoplay="" muted="" playsinline="" loop="" poster="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/deck.jpg">
                                <source type="video/webm" src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/deck.webm">
                            </video>
                        </section>
                        <section id="scaling">
                            <h3>UI Scaling Support for Higher Resolutions</h3>
                            <div>
                                <p><a data-lightbox="scaling" href="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/hud_scale_before.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/hud_scale_before_thumb.jpg"></a>
                                </p>
                                <p><a data-lightbox="scaling" href="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/hud_scale_after.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/hud_scale_after_thumb.jpg"></a>
                                </p>
                            </div>
                            <p>The entire UI has been reworked to scale at larger screen sizes. We built most of this stuff for 640x480 CRTs and apparently some of you have upgraded since then.</p>
                        </section>
                        <section id="icky">
                            <video id="ickyvideo" preload="" autoplay="" muted="" playsinline="" loop="" poster="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/icky.png">
                                <source type="video/webm" src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/icky.webm">
                            </video>
                            
                        </section>
                        <section id="restored">
                            <h2>Restored Content</h2>
                            <p>We brought back the classic Valve logo video with its iconic music and reskinned the menu to match the 1998 build.</p>
                            <div>
                                <p>
									<video id="mainmenu" poster="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/mainmenu.jpg" preload="" autoplay="" muted="" playsinline="" loop="">
										<source type="video/webm" src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/mainmenu_thumb.webm">
                                        <source type="video/mp4" src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/mainmenu_thumb.mp4">
									</video>
                                    <h6>Original Main Menu Artwork</h6>
                                </p>
                                <p>
									<video id="valve_guy" poster="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/valve_guy.jpg" autoplay="" loop="" playsinline="" preload="" muted="">
										<source type="video/webm" src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/valve_guy_thumb.webm">
                                        <source type="video/mp4" src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/valve_guy_thumb.mp4">
									</video>
                                    <h6>Valve Logo Intro Video</h6>
                                </p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <p><a data-lightbox="restored" href="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/ivan_and_bbbbarney.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/ivan_and_bbbbarney_thumb.jpg"></a>
                                </p>
                                <div>
                                    <h6>Ivan the Space Biker and Proto-Barney</h6>
                                    <p>After all this time we finally shipped the original heroes from the alpha builds of Half-Life, available as multiplayer skins!</p>
                                </div>
                            </div>
                        </section>
                        <section id="hound">
                            <video id="houndvideo" preload="" autoplay="" muted="" playsinline="" loop="" poster="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/hound.png">
                                <source type="video/webm" src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/hound.webm">
                            </video>
                            
                        </section>
                        
                        <section id="furthermaps">
                            <h3>Three Multiplayer Maps</h3>
                            <div>
                                <div>
                                    <p><a data-lightbox="furthermaps" href="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/further_data_map_1.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/further_data_map_1_thumb.jpg"></a></p><h6>Double Cross</h6>
                                </div>
                                <div>
                                    <p><a data-lightbox="furthermaps" href="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/further_data_map_2.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/further_data_map_2_thumb.jpg"></a></p><h6>Rust Mill</h6>
                                </div>
                                <div>
                                    <p><a data-lightbox="furthermaps" href="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/further_data_map_3.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/further_data_map_3_thumb.jpg"></a></p><h6>Xen DM</h6>
                                </div>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <p><a data-lightbox="models" href="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/further_data_player_models.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/further_data_player_models_thumb.jpg"></a>
                                </p>
                                <div>
                                    <h6>Two MP Player Models</h6>
                                    <p>The Half-Life: Further Data CD also included some multiplayer skins made by the original team; we've brought back this incredible skeleton (now with tintable eyes!) and fan-favorite <a href="https://www.shannonleowheeler.com/">Too Much Coffee Man</a>.</p>
                                </div>
                            </div>
                        </section>
                        <section id="sprays">
                            <h3>Dozens of Sprays</h3>
                            <p><a data-lightbox="models" href="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/sprays.png"><img src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/sprays.png"></a>
                            </p>
                            <p>While playing a bunch of multiplayer matches we kept wanting more sprays... So we grabbed several megabytes of them from the Further Data release!</p>
                        </section>
                        <section id="fixes">
                            
                            <h2>Bug Fixes and Change Notes</h2>
                            <ul aria-label="New Content">
                                <li>Now Verified on the Steam Deck (and our native Linux runtime has been set as the default).</li>
                                <li>Half-Life: Uplink — the original standalone Half-Life demo — has been added to the game, and is accessible through the "New Game" menu.</li>
                                <li>Added four all-new Half-Life Deathmatch maps: contamination, pool_party, disposal, and rocket_frenzy</li>
                                <li>Added three old Half-Life Deathmatch maps formerly available only on the "Half-Life: Further Data" CD: doublecross, rust_mill, xen_dm.</li>
                                <li>Added Ivan the Space Biker, Prototype Barney, Skeleton, and Too Much Coffee Man as player models to Half-Life Deathmatch.</li>
                                <li>Added dozens of new sprays formerly available only on the "Half-Life: Further Data" CD.</li>
                                <li>Added support for Steam Networking, allowing easy multiplayer via Steam's Join Game and Invite features.</li>
                                <li>Added support for Steam Friends Rich Presence, allowing your friends to follow your journey through Black Mesa.</li>
                            </ul>
                            <ul aria-label="Nostalgia">
                                <li>Brought back the original Valve Intro video. Can be skipped with the "-novid" launch command.</li>
                                <li>Updated main menu to a design inspired by the game's original 1998 main menu.</li>
                                <li>Changed the default models to the original (non "HD") models.</li>
                            </ul>
                            <ul aria-label="Gameplay Changes">
                                <li>Improved physics for throwing grenades.</li>
                                <li>Improved randomness for initial spawn points in multiplayer.</li>
                                <li>Improved satchel charge controls: primary fire now always throws a new satchel, and secondary fire always detonates.</li>
                                <li>Fixed push-able entity movement being based on framerate.</li>
                                <li>Fixed players with high framerates freezing in place on death in multiplayer.</li>
                                <li>Fixed some cases where the player could get stuck in place on level transitions.</li>
                                <li>Fixed some cases where characters would interrupt important dialogue with their "greetings" dialogue.</li>
                                <li>Fixed weapon view-bob angles.</li>
                                <li>Fixed red barrels at the start of Surface Tension not launching as intended.</li>
                                <li>Fixed Snarks attacking FL_WORLDBRUSH entities (such as func_walls).</li>
                                <li>Fixed players sometimes failing to deploy a snark while crouching and looking down.</li>
                                <li>Fixed certain convars ("pausable" and "sv_maxspeed") being set to incorrect values when entering a singleplayer game after a multiplayer game.</li>
                                <li>Fixed singleplayer auto-aim setting being changed when entering a multiplayer game that disallows auto-aim.</li>
                                <li>Fixed the flashlight HUD showing empty after loading a savegame.</li>
                                <li>Fixed rockets in CONTENTS_SKY not always detonating.</li>
                                <li>Fixed incorrect bullet impact sounds for NPCs.</li>
                                <li>Fixed gauss gun making a loud static noise if it was charged across level transitions.</li>
                                <li>Fixed a crash in mods that display keybinds in their UI.</li>
                                <li>Fixed singleplayer weapons not auto-switching away when exhausted (grenades / snarks / satchels / etc)</li>
                                <li>Fixed interpolation artifacts when animated models are moved by other entities.</li>
                                <li>Fixed some buffer overflow exploits.</li>
                            </ul>
                            <ul aria-label="UI Changes">
                                <li>Main-menu background and buttons have been reskinned, and now scale based upon screen resolution without stretching, supporting background image layouts up to 3840x1600.</li>
                                <li>In-Game HUD now uses double or triple sized sprites when playing at higher resolutions.</li>
                                <li>UI dialogs and in-game fonts now scale to improve readability at high screen resolutions.</li>
                                <li>In-Game HUD HEV suit display has been shifted to the left of the screen, and no longer changes position at larger screen resolutions.</li>
                                <li>Added an "Enable texture filtering" setting.</li>
                                <li>Added an "Allow widescreen Field of View" setting to correct non-anamorphic FOVs, for widescreen and ultrawide displays.</li>
                                <li>Re-organized all the Settings screens to improve legibility, and support controller navigation.</li>
                                <li>Updated the Pause menu to be aware of the current gameplay mode.</li>
                                <li>The default server name and multiplayer player name are now based on the player's Steam Persona.</li>
                                <li>The Steam platform menu has been removed, now that all its features are in Steam itself.</li>
                                <li>Fixed application icon rendering incorrectly when using the software renderer.</li>
                                <li>Fixed player and spray images not updating their coloring on the settings screen.</li>
                                <li>Removed the now very unnecessary "Low video quality. Helps with slower video cards." setting.</li>
                            </ul>
                            <ul aria-label="Input Changes">
                                <li>Improved support for keyboard and controller navigation everywhere.</li>
                                <li>Added "Lower Input Latency" option: Synchronizes the CPU and GPU to reduce the time between input and display output.</li>
                                <li>Fixed issues that caused jerky mouse / joystick input.</li>
                                <li>(We basically rewrote it all - if you've got a custom Steam Input controller configuration, you should rebuild it from our newly published Official Configuration).</li>
                            </ul>
                            <ul aria-label="Multiplayer Balancing">
                                <li>Increased the 357 damage from 40 → 50.</li>
                                <li>Hive Hand reload time has been reduced from 0.5s → 0.3s per shot, and it will be selected at higher priority than the pistol on pickup.</li>
                                <li>MP5 now always starts it with full ammo when picked up.</li>
                                <li>Players no longer drop empty weapons, and any that are dropped are reloaded by what's in the dying player's backpack.</li>
                                <li>Improved client-side prediction to reduce "ghost shots".  Like Counter-Strike, consider hitboxes and not just bounding boxes for hits on the client.</li>
                                <li>Fixed network predicted crowbar swing damage being incorrect.</li>
                            </ul>
                            <ul aria-label="Rendering">
                                <li>Added supported for UI Sprites and Texture files larger than 256x256.</li>
                                <li>Added support for UI Font special render modes: "blur" and "additive".</li>
                                <li>Added setting to turn off texture filtering when using the OpenGL renderer.</li>
                                <li>Default resolution is now based on the resolution of the desktop, instead of a 640x480 window.</li>
                                <li>Default gamma has been decreased from 2.5 → 2.2, now that we aren't all playing on CRTs.</li>
                                <li>Software renderer will now correctly filter out incompatible resolutions, unless there is only 1 resolution available on the display.</li>
                                <li>Restored OpenGL overbright support.</li>
                                <li>Fixed fullscreen software renderer crashing on systems that don't support 16-bit color.</li>
                                <li>Fixed software renderer being stretched when using widescreen resolutions.</li>
                                <li>Fixed skyboxes and sky color incorrectly carrying over when transitioning maps in multiplayer.</li>
                                <li>Fixed the game appearing too dark after modifying video settings.</li>
                                <li>Fixed MSAA in windowed mode.</li>
                                <li>Fixed mipmap rendering on studio models.</li>
                                <li>Fixed gluon gun sprite rendering in multiplayer.</li>
                                <li>Fixed gluon gun sinusoidal noise being incorrect.</li>
                                <li>Various optimizations to support the newly increased engine limits.</li>
                                <li>OpenGL optimizations for the Steam Deck.</li>
                            </ul>
                            <ul aria-label="Engine Improvements for Mod Makers">
                                <li>Increased maximum limit of dynamic sound channels from 8 → 32.</li>
                                <li>Increased maximum limit of sentences in the sentences.txt file from 1536 → 2048.</li>
                                <li>Increased maximum number of entities (MAX_EDICTS) from 900 → 1200.</li>
                                <li>Increased MAX_PACKET_ENTITIES increased from 256 → 1024.</li>
                                <li>Increased MAX_GLTEXTURES from 4800 → 10000.</li>
                                <li>Increased software renderer geometry limits: max spans 3000 → 6000, max surfaces 2000 → 4000, and max edges 7200 → 14400.</li>
                                <li>Cycler and func_button entities can now be the entity target for scripted_sentence entities, and are allowed to speak in multiplayer.</li>
                                <li>Incorporated func_vehicle entity support from Counter-Strike, for mod-makers to use. Full SDK update will come later, but level designers can use it now.</li>
                            </ul>
                            <ul aria-label="Native Linux Build">
                                <li>Added support for the software renderer.</li>
                                <li>Improved font rendering.</li>
                                <li>Many stability and behavior fixes.</li>
                            </ul>
                            <ul aria-label="Other">
                                <li>Localization files updated.</li>
                                <li>Miscellaneous security fixes.</li>
                            </ul>
                            <ul aria-label="Notes">
                                <li>The previous version of the game has been archived to a publicly visible Beta branch named "steam_legacy", with the description "Pre-25th Anniversary Build." If a mod or feature is behaving in an unexpected way, you may need to run this archived build until the issue is resolved in the default build.</li>
                                <li>We now consider this anniversary version of Half Life to be the definitive version, and the one we'll continue to support going forward. Therefore, we'll be reducing the visibility of Half Life: Source on the Steam Store. We know Half-Life: Source's assets are still being used by the Source engine community, so it'll remain available, but we'll be encouraging new Half-Life players to play this version instead.</li>
                            </ul>
                                                    </section>
                        <section id="wallpapers">
                            <h3>Wallpapers</h3>
                            <p>Celebrate 25 years of Half-life by decorating your desktop and mobile phone.</p>
                            
                        </section>
                        
                        <p><img src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/headcrab_dead.png" id="deadheadcrab">
                        <img id="bottomgrunge" src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/half-life.com/images/halflife25/decayconstant_end.png">
                    </p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Swedish dockworkers are refusing to unload Teslas at ports in broad boycott move (120 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://text.npr.org/1213157550</link>
            <guid>38307538</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 18:12:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://text.npr.org/1213157550">https://text.npr.org/1213157550</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38307538">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <p>At the Malmo port in southern Sweden, a cargo ship looms over row after row of shiny new cars — Volkswagens, Volvos, Mercedes.</p><p>Notably missing are Teslas. That's because dockworkers are refusing to unload them.</p><p>Goran Larsson, a cargo ship inspector, said he's informing the crew on each arriving vessel of the labor action and assessing whether any Teslas are on board.</p><p>"We want there to be good regulation in Sweden — law and order all around the workplaces," Larsson said. "And this is the first step that we will do."</p><p>Tesla has long fended off efforts to unionize its workforce around the world. But in Sweden, the electric vehicle maker is facing its first formal labor action over its anti-union stance, with potential ripple effects for the company globally.</p><p>The Swedish metal and industrial workers union, IF Metall, which represents Tesla's roughly 120 workers, launched a walkout at the company in late October.</p><p>And now, Swedish workers of all stripes – dockworkers, electricians, cleaners and others – are banding together to boycott the U.S. company in solidarity.</p><p>The strike is a response to the company's refusal to sign a collective bargaining agreement for its employees, almost all of them mechanics, because Tesla doesn't have a manufacturing plant in Sweden.</p><h3>Even postal workers will stop delivering mail to Tesla</h3><p>About 90% of the entire Swedish workforce belong to trade unions and they are covered by contracts with their employers, which standardize pay rates, insurance and pensions, among other work conditions, in each sector.</p>
      <hr><p>
      Related Story: <a href="https://text.npr.org/1209109868">Why workers are resorting to more strikes this year to pressure companies </a></p><hr><p>"This is the way we regulate working conditions in Sweden and has been for a long, long time," said IF Metall spokesperson Jesper Pettersson. "It has been very beneficial for both parties – both for employers and for employees."</p><p>The Swedish labor movement is rallying behind the relatively small group of Tesla mechanics, who repair Tesla vehicles at service centers.</p><p>Thousands of workers are refusing to touch any Teslas until the company signs a contract. And the boycott keeps expanding. Postal workers have said they will stop delivering mail addressed to the company if there's no deal by Nov. 20.</p><h3>Trade unions are part of the fabric of the Swedish economy</h3><p>They see the American EV maker's efforts to circumvent collective bargaining as an affront to the entire Swedish labor system, where trade unions are part of the fabric of the economy.</p><p>Dockworkers represented by Sweden's transport workers' union have been blocking all imports of Teslas at Sweden's four main ports since last week. And this Friday, they're set to expand their blockade to the entire country.</p><p>Tommy Wreeth, chairman of the transport workers' union, said the Swedish labor system is based on collective bargaining agreements, which Tesla, led by the staunchly anti-union Elon Musk, is reluctant to embrace.</p>
      <hr><p>
      Related Story: <a href="https://text.npr.org/1198938942">Sky-high CEO pay is in focus as workers everywhere are demanding higher wages</a></p><hr><p>"It's very important to protect our model – it's a fight for the model, not just for the Tesla workers," Wreeth said, referring to his union's solidarity boycott.</p><p>Tesla did not respond to NPR's requests for comment. A Tesla representative told Sweden's TT News Agency that the company is choosing not to enter into a collective agreement.</p><p>"We already offer equivalent or better agreements than those covered by collective bargaining and find no reason to sign any other agreement," Tesla told TT.</p><p>A Tesla mechanic in Gothenburg, who requested anonymity due to concern about retaliation by the company, said he thinks a union agreement would provide a financial safety net that "allows us as employees to be able to have security."</p><h3>"Symbolically important" fight</h3><p>Despite the broad nature of the protests lodged by the unions, they have an uphill battle on their hands. Sweden is a relatively small market for Tesla – its fifth biggest in Europe this year. And Tesla doesn't manufacture any cars in the Nordic country, meaning it could theoretically decide to leave the country altogether.</p>
      <hr><p>
      Related Story: <a href="https://text.npr.org/1206209107">UAW members aren't all assembling cars. More and more are unionized grad students</a></p><hr><p>But German Bender, a labor market analyst at Stockholm think tank Arena Idé, said it's unlikely Tesla will leave Sweden. And he doubts the Swedish unions will give up anytime soon – their fight, he said, is "too symbolically important" to abandon.</p><p>"And it becomes more symbolically important the longer the strike goes on," Bender said.</p><h3>Europe's one Tesla factory in Germany also has a union drive</h3><p>The strike is, at its core, a domestic issue – it's about a foreign company at odds with Sweden's labor norms and values.</p><p>But the labor action comes as unions in bigger markets are also challenging Tesla. Musk is facing, for instance, a union drive at its factory in Germany.</p><p>It is Tesla's only factory in Europe: the Berlin-Brandenburg Gigafactory, one of six such plants worldwide.</p><p>In the United States, the Texas-based automaker has so far thwarted all attempts to unionize its workforce. But the United Auto Workers union has set its sights on Tesla, after negotiating major deals with the Detroit Three automakers.</p><p>"If the Tesla workers in Sweden would manage to sign the first collective agreement ever with Tesla, I think that could have a symbolic importance in other markets," Bender said.</p><p>Atle Hoie, general secretary of IndustriALL Global Union which represents industrial workers around the world, said large-scale strikes like this one are rare in Sweden. He said the solidarity from Swedish unions across sectors, including from dockworkers, is a "big blow to Tesla" both within and beyond the Nordic country, sending the message that Tesla "is not immune to organizing."</p><p>Anders Gustafsson, a former dockworker who now works for the Swedish transport workers' union, said his union has received messages of support from unions in other countries, including in the U.S. and Canada.</p><p>"We hope that Tesla workers all around the world actually take that fight," Gustafsson said. "Somebody needs to be first."</p>
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Rocket v0.5: Stable, Async (105 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://rocket.rs/v0.5/news/2023-11-17-version-0.5/</link>
            <guid>38306540</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 17:14:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://rocket.rs/v0.5/news/2023-11-17-version-0.5/">https://rocket.rs/v0.5/news/2023-11-17-version-0.5/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38306540">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><p><strong>Posted by <a href="https://sergio.bz/">Sergio Benitez</a> on Nov 17, 2023</strong></p><p>Four years, four release candidates, a thousand commits, and over a thousand issues, discussions, and PRs later, I am <del>relieved</del> thrilled to announce the general availability of Rocket v0.5.</p><blockquote><p><strong>Rocket</strong> is an async backend web framework for Rust with a focus on usability, security, extensibility, and speed. Rocket makes it simple to write secure web applications without sacrificing productivity or performance.</p></blockquote><p>We encourage all users to upgrade. For a guided migration from Rocket v0.4 to Rocket v0.5, please consult the newly available <a href="https://rocket.rs/v0.5/guide/upgrading">upgrading guide</a>. Rocket v0.4 will continue to be supported and receive security updates until the time Rocket v0.6 is released.</p><div><p><span><b>Note:</b> This is a co-announcement <a href="https://rocket.rs/v0.5/news/2023-11-17-rwf2-prelaunch/">along with the prelaunch</a> of <a href="https://rwf2.org/">RWF2</a>.</span></p><p>We're addressing the community's concerns regarding the pace of Rocket's development, leadership, and release cadence in a separate announcement. Please see the accompanying <a href="https://rocket.rs/v0.5/news/2023-11-17-rwf2-prelaunch/">RWF2 prelaunch announcement</a> to learn more and see how you can get involved.</p></div><h3 id="whats-new">What's New?<a href="#whats-new" title="perma link">#</a></h3><p>Almost every bit has been reevaluated with a focus on usability and developer productivity, security, and consistency across the library and <a href="https://rocket.rs/v0.5/guide/faq/#releases">broader ecosystem</a>. The changes are numerous, so we focus on the most noteworthy changes here and encourage everyone to read the <a href="https://github.com/SergioBenitez/Rocket/blob/v0.5.0/CHANGELOG.md">CHANGELOG</a> for a complete list. For answers to frequently asked questions, see the new <a href="https://rocket.rs/v0.5/guide/faq">FAQ</a>.</p><h4 id="support-for-stable-rustc-since-rc1">⚓ Support for Stable <code>rustc</code><badge>since <code>rc.1</code></badge><a href="#support-for-stable-rustc-since-rc1" title="perma link">#</a></h4><p>Rocket v0.5 compiles and builds on Rust stable. You can now compile and build Rocket applications with <code>rustc</code> from the stable release channel and remove all <code>#![feature(..)]</code> crate attributes. The complete canonical example with a single <code>hello</code> route becomes:</p><div><table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><div><pre><span></span><span>#[macro_use]</span><span> </span><span>extern</span><span> </span><span>crate</span><span> </span><span>rocket</span><span>;</span>

<span>#[get(</span><span>"/&lt;name&gt;/&lt;age&gt;"</span><span>)]</span>
<span>fn</span> <span>hello</span><span>(</span><span>name</span>: <span>&amp;</span><span>str</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>age</span>: <span>u8</span><span>)</span><span> </span>-&gt; <span>String</span> <span>{</span>
<span>    </span><span>format!</span><span>(</span><span>"Hello, {} year old named {}!"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>age</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>name</span><span>)</span>
<span>}</span>

<span>#[launch]</span>
<span>fn</span> <span>rocket</span><span>()</span><span> </span>-&gt; <span>_</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>    </span><span>rocket</span>::<span>build</span><span>().</span><span>mount</span><span>(</span><span>"/hello"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>routes</span><span>!</span><span>[</span><span>hello</span><span>])</span>
<span>}</span>
</pre></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div><details><summary>See a <code>diff</code> of the changes from v0.4.</summary><div><table><tbody><tr><td><div><pre><span> 1</span>
<span> 2</span>
<span> 3</span>
<span> 4</span>
<span> 5</span>
<span> 6</span>
<span> 7</span>
<span> 8</span>
<span> 9</span>
<span>10</span>
<span>11</span>
<span>12</span>
<span>13</span>
<span>14</span>
<span>15</span>
<span>16</span>
<span>17</span></pre></div></td><td><div><pre><span></span><span>- #![feature(proc_macro_hygiene, decl_macro)]</span>
<span>-</span>
<span> </span>#[macro_use] extern crate rocket;

<span> </span>#[get("/&lt;name&gt;/&lt;age&gt;")]
<span>- fn hello(name: String, age: u8) -&gt; String {</span>
<span>+ fn hello(name: &amp;str, age: u8) -&gt; String {</span>
<span> </span>    format!("Hello, {} year old named {}!", age, name)
}

<span>- fn main() {</span>
<span>-     rocket::ignite().mount("/hello", routes![hello]).launch();</span>
<span>- }</span>
<span>+ #[launch]</span>
<span>+ fn rocket() -&gt; _ {</span>
<span>+     rocket::build().mount("/hello", routes![hello])</span>
<span>+ }</span>
</pre></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div></details><p>Note the new <a href="https://api.rocket.rs/master/rocket/attr.launch.html"><code>launch</code></a> attribute, which simplifies starting an <code>async</code> runtime for Rocket applications. See the <a href="https://rocket.rs/v0.5/guide/upgrading">migration guide</a> for more on transitioning to a stable toolchain.</p><h4 id="async-io-since-rc1">📥 Async I/O<badge>since <code>rc.1</code></badge><a href="#async-io-since-rc1" title="perma link">#</a></h4><p>Rocket's core request handling was rebuilt in v0.5 to take advantage of the latest <code>async</code> networking facilities in Rust. Backed by <code>tokio</code>, Rocket automatically multiplexes request handling across <code>async</code> tasks on all of the available cores on the machine. As a result, route handlers can now be declared <code>async</code> and make use of <code>await</code> syntax:</p><div><table><tbody><tr><td><div><pre><span> 1</span>
<span> 2</span>
<span> 3</span>
<span> 4</span>
<span> 5</span>
<span> 6</span>
<span> 7</span>
<span> 8</span>
<span> 9</span>
<span>10</span>
<span>11</span>
<span>12</span></pre></div></td><td><div><pre><span></span><span>use</span><span> </span><span>rocket</span>::<span>tokio</span><span>;</span>
<span>use</span><span> </span><span>rocket</span>::<span>data</span>::<span>{</span><span>Data</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>ToByteUnit</span><span>};</span>

<span>#[post(</span><span>"/debug"</span><span>, data = </span><span>"&lt;data&gt;"</span><span>)]</span>
<span>async</span><span> </span><span>fn</span> <span>debug</span><span>(</span><span>data</span>: <span>Data</span><span>&lt;'</span><span>_</span><span>&gt;</span><span>)</span><span> </span>-&gt; <span>std</span>::<span>io</span>::<span>Result</span><span>&lt;</span><span>()</span><span>&gt;</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>    </span><span>// Stream at most 512KiB all of the body data to stdout.</span>
<span>    </span><span>data</span><span>.</span><span>open</span><span>(</span><span>512.</span><span>kibibytes</span><span>())</span>
<span>        </span><span>.</span><span>stream_to</span><span>(</span><span>tokio</span>::<span>io</span>::<span>stdout</span><span>())</span>
<span>        </span><span>.</span><span>await</span><span>?</span><span>;</span>

<span>    </span><span>Ok</span><span>(())</span>
<span>}</span>
</pre></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div><p>See the <a href="https://rocket.rs/guide/upgrading#blocking-io">Blocking I/O</a> section of the upgrading guide for complete details on the <code>async</code> I/O transition.</p><h4 id="sentinels-since-rc1">💂 Sentinels<badge>since <code>rc.1</code></badge><a href="#sentinels-since-rc1" title="perma link">#</a></h4><p>Rocket v0.5 introduces <a href="https://api.rocket.rs/master/rocket/trait.Sentinel.html">sentinels</a>. Entirely unique to Rocket, sentinels offer an automatic last line of defense against runtime errors by enabling any type that appears in a route to abort application launch under invalid conditions. For example, the <a href="https://api.rocket.rs/master/rocket/struct.State.html"><code>&amp;State&lt;T&gt;</code></a> guard in v0.5 is a <a href="https://api.rocket.rs/master/rocket/trait.Sentinel.html"><code>Sentinel</code></a> that aborts launch if the type <code>T</code> is not in managed state, thus preventing associated runtime errors.</p><p><a href="https://api.rocket.rs/master/rocket/trait.Sentinel.html"><code>Sentinel</code></a>s can be implemented outside of Rocket, too, and you should seek to do so whenever possible. For instance, the <a href="https://api.rocket.rs/master/rocket_dyn_templates/struct.Template.html"><code>Template</code></a> type from <a href="https://api.rocket.rs/master/rocket_dyn_templates/index.html"><code>rocket_dyn_templates</code></a> is a sentinel that ensures templates are properly registered. As another example, consider a <code>MyResponder</code> that expects:</p><ul><li>A specific type <code>T</code> to be in managed state.</li><li>An catcher to be registered for the <code>400</code> status code.</li></ul><p>Making <code>MyResponder</code> a sentinel that guards against these conditions is as simple as:</p><div><table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><div><pre><span></span><span>use</span><span> </span><span>rocket</span>::<span>{</span><span>Rocket</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>Ignite</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>Sentinel</span><span>};</span>

<span>impl</span><span> </span><span>Sentinel</span><span> </span><span>for</span><span> </span><span>MyResponder</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>    </span><span>fn</span> <span>abort</span><span>(</span><span>r</span>: <span>&amp;</span><span>Rocket</span><span>&lt;</span><span>Ignite</span><span>&gt;</span><span>)</span><span> </span>-&gt; <span>bool</span> <span>{</span>
<span>        </span><span>r</span><span>.</span><span>state</span>::<span>&lt;</span><span>T</span><span>&gt;</span><span>().</span><span>is_none</span><span>()</span><span> </span><span>||</span><span> </span><span>!</span><span>r</span><span>.</span><span>catchers</span><span>().</span><span>any</span><span>(</span><span>|</span><span>c</span><span>|</span><span> </span><span>c</span><span>.</span><span>code</span><span> </span><span>==</span><span> </span><span>Some</span><span>(</span><span>400</span><span>))</span>
<span>    </span><span>}</span>
<span>}</span>
</pre></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div><h4 id="streams-and-sse-since-rc1">☄️ Streams and SSE<badge>since <code>rc.1</code></badge><a href="#streams-and-sse-since-rc1" title="perma link">#</a></h4><p>Powered by the new asynchronous core, Rocket v0.5 introduces real-time, typed <code>async</code> <a href="https://api.rocket.rs/master/rocket/response/stream/index.html">streams</a>. The new <a href="https://rocket.rs/guide/responses/#async-streams">async streams</a> section of the guide contains further details, and we encourage all interested parties to see the new real-time, multi-room <a href="https://github.com/SergioBenitez/Rocket/tree/master/examples/chat">chat example</a>.</p><p>As a taste of what's possible, the following <code>stream</code> route emits a <code>"pong"</code> Server-Sent Event every <code>n</code> seconds, defaulting to <code>1</code>:</p><div><table><tbody><tr><td><div><pre><span> 1</span>
<span> 2</span>
<span> 3</span>
<span> 4</span>
<span> 5</span>
<span> 6</span>
<span> 7</span>
<span> 8</span>
<span> 9</span>
<span>10</span>
<span>11</span>
<span>12</span>
<span>13</span></pre></div></td><td><div><pre><span></span><span>use</span><span> </span><span>rocket</span>::<span>tokio</span>::<span>time</span>::<span>{</span><span>interval</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>Duration</span><span>};</span>
<span>use</span><span> </span><span>rocket</span>::<span>response</span>::<span>stream</span>::<span>{</span><span>Event</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>EventStream</span><span>};;</span>

<span>#[get(</span><span>"/ping?&lt;n&gt;"</span><span>)]</span>
<span>fn</span> <span>stream</span><span>(</span><span>n</span>: <span>Option</span><span>&lt;</span><span>u64</span><span>&gt;</span><span>)</span><span> </span>-&gt; <span>EventStream</span><span>!</span><span>[]</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>    </span><span>EventStream</span><span>!</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>        </span><span>let</span><span> </span><span>mut</span><span> </span><span>timer</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>interval</span><span>(</span><span>Duration</span>::<span>from_secs</span><span>(</span><span>n</span><span>.</span><span>unwrap_or</span><span>(</span><span>1</span><span>)));</span>
<span>        </span><span>loop</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>            </span><span>yield</span><span> </span><span>Event</span>::<span>data</span><span>(</span><span>"pong"</span><span>);</span>
<span>            </span><span>timer</span><span>.</span><span>tick</span><span>().</span><span>await</span><span>;</span>
<span>        </span><span>}</span>
<span>    </span><span>}</span>
<span>}</span>
</pre></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div><h4 id="websockets-since-rc4">🔌 WebSockets<badge>since <code>rc.4</code></badge><a href="#websockets-since-rc4" title="perma link">#</a></h4><p>Rocket v0.5 introduces support for HTTP connection upgrades via a new <a href="https://api.rocket.rs/master/rocket/response/struct.Response.html#upgrading">upgrade API</a>. The API allows responders to assume control of raw I/O with the client in an existing HTTP connection, thus allowing HTTP connections to be <em>upgraded</em> to any protocol, including WebSockets!</p><p>The newly introduced <a href="https://api.rocket.rs/master/rocket_ws"><code>rocket_ws</code></a> library takes advantage of the new API to implement first-class support for WebSockets entirely outside of Rocket's core. Working with <code>rocket_ws</code> to implement an echo server looks like this:</p><div><table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><div><pre><span></span><span>use</span><span> </span><span>rocket_ws</span>::<span>{</span><span>WebSocket</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>Stream</span><span>};</span>

<span>#[get(</span><span>"/echo"</span><span>)]</span>
<span>fn</span> <span>echo_compose</span><span>(</span><span>ws</span>: <span>WebSocket</span><span>)</span><span> </span>-&gt; <span>Stream</span><span>!</span><span>[</span><span>'</span><span>static</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>    </span><span>ws</span><span>.</span><span>stream</span><span>(</span><span>|</span><span>io</span><span>|</span><span> </span><span>io</span><span>)</span>
<span>}</span>
</pre></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div><p>Just like the newly introduced <code>async</code> streams, <code>rocket_ws</code> also supports using generator syntax for WebSocket messages:</p><div><table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><div><pre><span></span><span>use</span><span> </span><span>rocket_ws</span>::<span>{</span><span>WebSocket</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>Stream</span><span>};</span>

<span>#[get(</span><span>"/echo"</span><span>)]</span>
<span>fn</span> <span>echo_stream</span><span>(</span><span>ws</span>: <span>WebSocket</span><span>)</span><span> </span>-&gt; <span>Stream</span><span>!</span><span>[</span><span>'</span><span>static</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>    </span><span>Stream</span><span>!</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span> </span><span>ws</span><span> </span><span>=&gt;</span>
<span>        </span><span>for</span><span> </span><span>await</span><span> </span><span>message</span><span> </span><span>in</span><span> </span><span>ws</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>            </span><span>yield</span><span> </span><span>message</span><span>?</span><span>;</span>
<span>        </span><span>}</span>
<span>    </span><span>}</span>
<span>}</span>
</pre></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div><p>For complete usage details, see the <a href="https://api.rocket.rs/master/rocket_ws"><code>rocket_ws</code></a> documentation.</p><h4 id="comprehensive-forms-since-rc1">📝 Comprehensive Forms<badge>since <code>rc.1</code></badge><a href="#comprehensive-forms-since-rc1" title="perma link">#</a></h4><p>Rocket v0.5 entirely revamps <a href="https://rocket.rs/guide/requests#forms">forms</a> with support for <a href="https://rocket.rs/guide/requests#multipart">multipart uploads</a>, <a href="https://rocket.rs/guide/requests#collections">arbitrary collections</a> with <a href="https://rocket.rs/guide/requests#nesting">arbitrary nesting</a>, <a href="https://rocket.rs/guide/requests#ad-hoc-validation">ad-hoc validation</a>, and an improved <a href="https://api.rocket.rs/master/rocket/derive.FromForm.html"><code>FromForm</code> derive</a>, obviating the need for nearly all custom implementations of <code>FromForm</code> or <code>FromFormField</code>. Rocket's new wire protocol for forms allows applications to express <em>any structure</em> with <em>any level of nesting and collection</em> without any custom code, eclipsing what's offered by other web frameworks.</p><p>As an illustrative example, consider the following structures:</p><div><table><tbody><tr><td><div><pre><span> 1</span>
<span> 2</span>
<span> 3</span>
<span> 4</span>
<span> 5</span>
<span> 6</span>
<span> 7</span>
<span> 8</span>
<span> 9</span>
<span>10</span>
<span>11</span>
<span>12</span>
<span>13</span>
<span>14</span>
<span>15</span>
<span>16</span>
<span>17</span>
<span>18</span>
<span>19</span></pre></div></td><td><div><pre><span></span><span>use</span><span> </span><span>rocket</span>::<span>form</span>::<span>FromForm</span><span>;</span>

<span>#[derive(FromForm)]</span>
<span>struct</span> <span>MyForm</span><span>&lt;'</span><span>r</span><span>&gt;</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>    </span><span>owner</span>: <span>Person</span><span>&lt;'</span><span>r</span><span>&gt;</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>pet</span>: <span>Pet</span><span>&lt;'</span><span>r</span><span>&gt;</span><span>,</span>
<span>}</span>

<span>#[derive(FromForm)]</span>
<span>struct</span> <span>Person</span><span>&lt;'</span><span>r</span><span>&gt;</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>    </span><span>name</span>: <span>&amp;</span><span>'</span><span>r</span> <span>str</span>
<span>}</span>

<span>#[derive(FromForm)]</span>
<span>struct</span> <span>Pet</span><span>&lt;'</span><span>r</span><span>&gt;</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>    </span><span>name</span>: <span>&amp;</span><span>'</span><span>r</span> <span>str</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>#[field(validate = eq(true))]</span>
<span>    </span><span>good_pet</span>: <span>bool</span><span>,</span>
<span>}</span>
</pre></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div><p>To parse request data into a <code>MyForm</code>, a form with fields of <code>owner.name</code>, <code>pet.name</code>, and <code>pet.good_pet</code> must be submitted. The ad-hoc validation on <code>good_pet</code> validates that <code>good_pet</code> parses as <code>true</code>. Such a form, URL-encoded, may look like:</p><div><table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><div><pre><span></span><span>"owner.name=Bob&amp;pet.name=Sally&amp;pet.good_pet=yes"</span>
</pre></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div><p>Rocket's derived <code>FromForm</code> implementation for <code>MyForm</code> will automatically parse such a submission into the correct value:</p><div><table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><div><pre><span></span><span>MyForm</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>    </span><span>owner</span>: <span>Person</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>        </span><span>name</span>: <span>"Bob"</span><span>.</span><span>into</span><span>()</span>
<span>    </span><span>},</span>
<span>    </span><span>pet</span>: <span>Pet</span><span> </span><span>{</span>
<span>        </span><span>name</span>: <span>"Sally"</span><span>.</span><span>into</span><span>(),</span>
<span>        </span><span>good_pet</span>: <span>true</span><span>,</span>
<span>    </span><span>}</span>
<span>}</span>
</pre></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div><p>The rewritten <a href="https://rocket.rs/guide/requests/#forms">forms guide</a> provides complete details on revamped forms support.</p><h4 id="and-so-much-more">🚀 And so much more!<a href="#and-so-much-more" title="perma link">#</a></h4><p>Rocket v0.5 introduces over <strong>40</strong> new features and major improvements! We encourage everyone to review the <a href="https://github.com/SergioBenitez/Rocket/blob/v0.5.0/CHANGELOG.md">CHANGELOG</a> to learn about them all. Here are a few more we don't want you to miss:</p><ul><li>An automatically enabled <a href="https://api.rocket.rs/master/rocket/shield/struct.Shield.html"><code>Shield</code></a>: security and privacy headers for all responses.</li><li><a href="https://api.rocket.rs/master/rocket/config/struct.Shutdown.html#summary">Graceful shutdown</a> with configurable grace periods, <a href="https://api.rocket.rs/master/rocket/struct.Shutdown.html">notification</a>, and <a href="https://api.rocket.rs/master/rocket/fairing/trait.Fairing.html#shutdown">shutdown fairings</a>.</li><li>An entirely new, flexible and robust <a href="https://rocket.rs/guide/configuration/#configuration">configuration system</a> based on <a href="https://docs.rs/figment/">Figment</a>.</li><li>Type-system enforced <a href="https://rocket.rs/guide/requests/#streaming">incoming data limits</a> to mitigate memory-based DoS attacks.</li><li>Support for <a href="https://rocket.rs/guide/configuration/#mutual-tls">mutual TLS</a> and client <a href="https://api.rocket.rs/master/rocket/mtls/struct.Certificate.html"><code>Certificate</code></a>s.</li><li>Asynchronous database pooling support via <a href="https://api.rocket.rs/master/rocket_db_pools/index.html"><code>rocket_db_pools</code></a>.</li><li>Compile-time URI literals via a fully revamped <a href="https://api.rocket.rs/master/rocket/macro.uri.html"><code>uri!</code></a> macro.</li></ul><h3 id="whats-next">What's Next?<a href="#whats-next" title="perma link">#</a></h3><p>We think Rocket provides the most productive and confidence-inspiring web development experience in Rust today, but as always, there's room for improvement. To that end, here's what's on the docket for the next major release:</p><ol><li><p><strong>Migration to RWF2</strong></p><p>Discussed further in the <a href="https://rocket.rs/v0.5/news/2023-11-17-rwf2-prelaunch/">RWF2 prelaunch announcement</a>, Rocket will transition to being managed by the newly formed Rocket Web Framework Foundation: <em>RWF2</em>. The net effect is increased development transparency, including public roadmaps and periodic updates, financial support for high-quality contributions, and codified pathways into the project's governance.</p></li><li><p><strong>Pluggable Connection Listeners</strong></p><p>Rocket currently expects and enjoins connection origination via TCP/IP. While sufficient for the common case, it excludes other desirable interfaces such as Unix Domain Sockets (UDS).</p><p>In the next major release, Rocket will expose [an interface for implementing and plugging-in custom connection listeners]. Rocket itself will make use of this interface to expose more common mediums out-of-the-box, such as the aforementioned UDS.</p></li><li><p><strong>Native <code>async</code> Traits</strong></p><p>Given the <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/pull/115822">stabilization of <code>async fn</code> in traits</a>, the next major release will seek to eliminate Rocket's dependence on <code>#[async_trait]</code> opting instead for native <code>async</code> traits. This will greatly improve our documentation, which currently calls out the attribute for each affected trait, as well as offer modest performance improvements.</p></li><li><p><a href="https://github.com/SergioBenitez/Rocket/issues/749"><strong>Typed Catchers</strong></a></p><p>Today's catchers cannot receive strictly typed error data. This results in workarounds where error data is queried for well-typedness at runtime. While it <em>has</em> been possible to implement a form of typed error catching prior, doing so necessitated limiting error data to <code>'static</code> values, as other Rust web frameworks do, a concession we're unwilling to make.</p><p>After much experimentation, we have an approach that is ergonomic to use, safe, and correct, all without the <code>'static</code> limitation. This will allow error catchers to "pattern match" against error types at compile-time. At runtime, Rocket will match emerging error types against the declared catchers and call the appropriate catcher with the fully-typed value.</p></li><li><p><strong>Short-Circuitable Request Processing</strong></p><p>Whether with success or failure, fairings and guards cannot presently terminate request processing early. The rationale for forbidding this functionality was that it would allow third-party crates and plugins to dictate responses without offering any recourse to the top-level application.</p><p>With the advent of typed catchers, however, we now have a mechanism by which a top-level application can intercept early responses via their type, resolving the prior concern. As such, in the next major release, fairings and guards will be able to respond to requests early, and catchers will be able to intercept those early responses at will.</p></li><li><p><strong>Associated Resources</strong></p><p>Often a set of routes will share a set requirements. For example, they may share a URI prefix, subset of guards, and some managed state. In today's Rocket, these common requirements must be repeatedly specified for each route. While this is by design (we <em>want</em> a route's requirements to be obvious), the repetition is arduous and potentially error prone.</p><p>In an upcoming major release, Rocket will introduce new mechanisms by which a set of routes can share an explicitly declared set of requirements. Their <em>explicit</em> and <em>declarative</em> nature results in requirements that are simultaneously obvious <em>and</em> declared once.</p><p>We're really excited about this upcoming change and will be announcing more in the near future.</p></li><li><p><strong>Performance Improvements</strong></p><p>Rocket appears to lag behind other Rust web frameworks in benchmarks. This is partly due to <a href="https://rocket.rs/guide/faq/#performance">poor benchmarking</a>, partly due to security-minded design decisions, and partially due to unexploited opportunities. In the next release, we'll be addressing the latter points. Specifically:</p><ul><li><p><em>Explore making work stealing optional.</em></p><p>Rocket currently defaults to using tokio's multithreaded, work-stealing scheduler. This avoids tail latency issues when faced with irregular and heterogeneous tasks at the expense of throughput due to higher bookkeeping costs associated with work stealing. Other Rust web frameworks instead opt to use tokio's single-threaded scheduler, which while theoretically suboptimal, may yield better performance results in practice, especially when benchmarking homogeneous workloads.</p><p>While we believe work-stealing schedulers are the right choice for the majority of applications desireing robust performance characteristics, we also believe the choice should be the user's. We'll seek to make this choice easier in the next release.</p></li><li><p><em>Reduce conversions from external to internal HTTP types.</em></p><p>Rocket revalidates and sometimes copies incoming HTTP request data. In Rocket v0.5, we began transitioning to a model where we revalidate security insensitive data in debug mode only, allowing for bugs to be caught and reported while reducing performance impacts in production. In the next release, we seek to extend this approach.</p></li></ul></li></ol><h3 id="thank-you">❤️ Thank You<a href="#thank-you" title="perma link">#</a></h3><p>A very special thank you to <a href="https://github.com/SergioBenitez/Rocket/commits?author=jebrosen">Jeb Rosen</a>, Rocket's maintainer from v0.4 to v0.5-rc.1, without whom Rocket v0.5 wouldn't exist. Jeb is responsible for leading the migration to <code>async</code> and Rust stable along with tireless efforts to improve Rocket's documentation and address the community. Rocket is better for having had Jeb along for the ride. Thank you, Jeb.</p><p>A special thank you to all of Rocket's users, especially those who diligently waded through all four release candidates, raised issues, and participated on <a href="https://github.com/SergioBenitez/Rocket">GitHub</a> and the <a href="https://chat.mozilla.org/#/room/#rocket:mozilla.org">Matrix channel</a>. You all are an awesome, kind, and thoughtful bunch. Thank you.</p><p>A heartfelt <em>thank you</em> as well to <em>all</em> <strong>148</strong> who contributed to Rocket v0.5:</p><ul><li>Aaron Leopold</li><li>Abdullah Alyan</li><li>Aditya</li><li>Alex Macleod</li><li>Alex Sears</li><li>Alexander van Ratingen</li><li>ami-GS</li><li>Antoine Martin</li><li>arctic-alpaca</li><li>arlecchino</li><li>Arthur Woimbée</li><li>atouchet</li><li>Aurora</li><li>badoken</li><li>Beep LIN</li><li>Ben Sully</li><li>Benedikt Weber</li><li>Benjamin B</li><li>BlackDex</li><li>Bonex</li><li>Brenden Matthews</li><li>Brendon Federko</li><li>Brett Buford</li><li>Cedric Hutchings</li><li>Cezar Halmagean</li><li>Charles-Axel Dein</li><li>Compro Prasad</li><li>cui fliter</li><li>Daniel Wiesenberg</li><li>David Venhoek</li><li>Dimitri Sabadie</li><li>Dinu Blanovschi</li><li>Dominik Boehi</li><li>Doni Rubiagatra</li><li>Edgar Onghena</li><li>Edwin Svensson</li><li>est31</li><li>Felix Suominen</li><li>Fenhl</li><li>Filip Gospodinov</li><li>Flying-Toast</li><li>Follpvosten</li><li>Francois Stephany</li><li>Gabriel Fontes</li><li>gcarq</li><li>George Cheng</li><li>Giles Cope</li><li>Gonçalo Ribeiro</li><li>hiyoko3m</li><li>Howard Su</li><li>hpodhaisky</li><li>Ian Jackson</li><li>IFcoltransG</li><li>Indosaram</li><li>inyourface34456</li><li>J. Cohen</li><li>Jacob Pratt</li><li>Jacob Sharf</li><li>Jacob Simpson</li><li>Jakub Dąbek</li><li>Jakub Wieczorek</li><li>James Tai</li><li>Jason Hinch</li><li>Jeb Rosen</li><li>Jeremy Kaplan</li><li>Jieyou Xu</li><li>Joakim Soderlund</li><li>Johannes Liebermann</li><li>John-John Tedro</li><li>Jonah Brüchert</li><li>Jonas Møller</li><li>Jonathan Dickinson</li><li>Jonty</li><li>Joscha</li><li>Joshua Nitschke</li><li>JR Heard</li><li>Juhasz Sandor</li><li>Julian Büttner</li><li>Juraj Fiala</li><li>Kenneth Allen</li><li>Kevin Wang</li><li>Kian-Meng Ang</li><li>Konrad Borowski</li><li>Leonora Tindall</li><li>Lev Kokotov</li><li>lewis</li><li>Lionel G</li><li>Lucille Blumire</li><li>Mai-Lapyst</li><li>Manuel</li><li>Manuel Transfeld</li><li>Marc Schreiber</li><li>Marc-Stefan Cassola</li><li>Marshall Bowers</li><li>Martin1887</li><li>Martinez</li><li>Matthew Pomes</li><li>Maxime Guerreiro</li><li>meltinglava</li><li>Michael Howell</li><li>Mikail Bagishov</li><li>mixio</li><li>multisn8</li><li>Necmettin Karakaya</li><li>Ning Sun</li><li>Nya</li><li>Paolo Barbolini</li><li>Paul Smith</li><li>Paul van Tilburg</li><li>Paul Weaver</li><li>pennae</li><li>Petr Portnov</li><li>philipp</li><li>Pieter Frenssen</li><li>PROgrm_JARvis</li><li>Razican</li><li>Redrield</li><li>Riley Patterson</li><li>Rodolphe Bréard</li><li>Roger Mo</li><li>RotesWasser</li><li>rotoclone</li><li>Ruben Schmidmeister</li><li>Rudi Floren</li><li>Rémi Lauzier</li><li>Samuele Esposito</li><li>Scott McMurray</li><li>Sergio Benitez</li><li>Silas Sewell</li><li>Soham Roy</li><li>Steven Murdoch</li><li>Stuart Hinson</li><li>Thibaud Martinez</li><li>Thomas Eckert</li><li>ThouCheese</li><li>Tilen Pintarič</li><li>timando</li><li>timokoesters</li><li>toshokan</li><li>TotalKrill</li><li>Unpublished</li><li>Vasili</li><li>Vladimir Ignatev</li><li>Wesley Norris</li><li>xelivous</li><li>YetAnotherMinion</li><li>Yohannes Kifle</li><li>Yusuke Kominami</li></ul><h3 id="get-involved">Get Involved<a href="#get-involved" title="perma link">#</a></h3><p>Looking to help with Rocket? To contribute code, head over to <a href="https://github.com/SergioBenitez/Rocket">GitHub</a>. To get involved with the project, see the <a href="https://rocket.rs/v0.5/news/2023-11-17-rwf2-prelaunch/">RWF2 prelaunch announcement</a>. We'd love to have you.</p></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[With trillions at play, Pentagon fails audit for sixth year in a row (207 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://breakingdefense.com/2023/11/with-trillions-at-play-pentagon-fails-audit-for-sixth-year-in-a-row/</link>
            <guid>38306174</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 16:52:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://breakingdefense.com/2023/11/with-trillions-at-play-pentagon-fails-audit-for-sixth-year-in-a-row/">https://breakingdefense.com/2023/11/with-trillions-at-play-pentagon-fails-audit-for-sixth-year-in-a-row/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38306174">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="entry-322353">
<div id="attachment_322365"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-322365" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" src="https://sites.breakingmedia.com/uploads/sites/3/2023/11/pentagon3-scaled.jpg" alt="The Pentagon" width="2560" height="1396" srcset="https://sites.breakingmedia.com/uploads/sites/3/2023/11/pentagon3-scaled.jpg 2560w, https://sites.breakingmedia.com/uploads/sites/3/2023/11/pentagon3-350x191.jpg 350w, https://sites.breakingmedia.com/uploads/sites/3/2023/11/pentagon3-1024x558.jpg 1024w, https://sites.breakingmedia.com/uploads/sites/3/2023/11/pentagon3-768x419.jpg 768w, https://sites.breakingmedia.com/uploads/sites/3/2023/11/pentagon3-1536x837.jpg 1536w, https://sites.breakingmedia.com/uploads/sites/3/2023/11/pentagon3-2048x1116.jpg 2048w, https://sites.breakingmedia.com/uploads/sites/3/2023/11/pentagon3-1070x583.jpg 1070w" sizes="(max-width: 2560px) 100vw, 2560px"></p><p id="caption-attachment-322365">The Pentagon released its latest audit this week. (US Army/Sgt. 1st Class Marisol Walker)</p></div>
<p><span>WASHINGTON — For the sixth year in a row, the Pentagon has failed its </span><a href="https://breakingdefense.com/tag/audit/"><span>annual audit</span></a><span>, while contending it made incremental, year-over-year progress.</span></p>
<p><span>“Auditing the Department’s $3.8 trillion in assets and $4.0 trillion in liabilities is a massive undertaking… but the improvements and changes we are making every day as a result of these audits positively affect every soldier, sailor, airman, marine, guardian, and DoD civilian,” Michael McCord, the Department of Defense (DoD) Under Secretary of Defense and Chief Financial Officer, wrote in a statement Wednesday.</span></p>
<p>The department unveiled its latest audit on Wednesday and, similar to<a href="https://breakingdefense.com/2022/11/not-the-progress-i-would-have-hoped-for-pentagon-fails-latest-financial-audit/"> last year’s</a>, it examined 29 standalone entities, from the Military Retirement Fund to different military agencies. Of those it gave only seven an “unmodified opinion,” or clean audit, in which auditors determined their financial statements were presented fairly and that they adhered to accounting principles.</p>

<p><span>Only one audit, the Medicare-Eligible Retiree Health Care Fund, received an “qualified opinion” this year, meaning auditors determined there were misstatements, or potentially undetected misstatements, but those did not adversely influence the financial statements.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>While there are still three outstanding audits not yet wrapped up, the DoD reported that the remaining 18 failed, including the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency and National Security Agency.<br>
</span></p>

<p><span>“We are working hard to address audit findings as well as recommendations from the </span><span>Government Accountability Office,” McCord wrote. “The components are making good progress resulting in meaningful benefits, but we must do more, and we cannot do this alone.”&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>The department has now failed every audit since 2018, the year the first audit took place. The audit is conducted by the DoD’s Office of Inspector General along with an independent public accounting firm.<br>
</span></p>


<p><span> In 2020, then-Acting Comptroller Thomas Harker signaled that by 2027 the Pentagon could begin to pass its annual audit, an ascertain </span><span>McCord </span><a href="https://breakingdefense.com/2021/11/as-most-military-agencies-fail-annual-audit-comptroller-claims-steady-progress/"><span>previously stated </span></a><span>might not be viable.</span></p>
<p><span>While there is a lot of heavy lifting to do to get to a clean audit, McCord noted several steps forward this year and outlined additional ones that can be taken to help achieve a passing grade.</span></p>
<p><span>Those additional steps include:</span></p>
<ul>
<li aria-level="1"><span>An Oct. 13 memo from Dense Secretary Lloyd Austin to the service secretaries and principal staff assistants emphasizing and reinforcing expectations for supporting the DoD financial statement audits;</span></li>
<li aria-level="1"><span>More collaboration across DoD’s planners and programmers, the DoD financial management community, DoD leadership, the Office of Management and Budget, and Congress “to ensure alignment of priorities and resources;”&nbsp;</span></li>
<li aria-level="1"><span>A call for lawmakers to pass annual budgets on time and avoid continuing resolutions and shutdowns; and&nbsp;</span></li>
<li aria-level="1"><span>Asking defense contractors to pitch in by introducing “innovative, time-saving enterprise solutions,” and bringing their property into audit compliance.</span></li>
</ul>
<p>The call for congressional help is a timely one, coming just hours after lawmakers agreed on a new continuing resolution that pushes the DoD’s budget battle to February next year — a regular source of frustration for senior Pentagon officials.</p>



</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A game about staring into the eyes of a stranger (173 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://stranger.video/</link>
            <guid>38305787</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 16:30:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://stranger.video/">https://stranger.video/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38305787">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="whatIsThisBox">
        <p><span>this site lets you and a stranger see each other's faces</span>.
        it doesn't do much else.</p>
        <ul id="whatIsThisList">
            <li>all video is cropped to show just faces</li>
            <li>no text chat, no audio. just faces</li>
            <li>video stops when one of you blinks</li>
        </ul>
        <p>it uses <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/WebRTC_API">webrtc</a> and <a href="https://developers.google.com/mediapipe">mediapipe</a> for the hard parts. i blogged about it <a href="https://eieio.games/nonsense/game-12-stranger-video/">here</a></p>
        <p>want to chat? email me at <a href="mailto:eieiogames@gmail.com?subject=the%20staring%20game!%20ah,%20the%20staring%20game.%20i%20love%20the%20hole%20in%20my%20computer%20where%20i%20look%20at%20strangers.%20thank%20you">eieiogames@gmail.com</a></p>
        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Amazon cuts 'several hundred' jobs in Alexa division (110 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cnbc.com/2023/11/17/amazon-cuts-several-hundred-jobs-in-alexa-division.html</link>
            <guid>38305097</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 15:43:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/11/17/amazon-cuts-several-hundred-jobs-in-alexa-division.html">https://www.cnbc.com/2023/11/17/amazon-cuts-several-hundred-jobs-in-alexa-division.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38305097">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="RegularArticle-ArticleBody-6" data-module="ArticleBody" data-test="articleBody-2" data-analytics="RegularArticle-articleBody-6-2"><div id="ArticleBody-InlineImage-107335764" data-test="InlineImage"><p>Visitors at Amazon Alexa boot during the international electronics and innovation fair IFA in Berlin on September 10, 2019.</p><p>Nurphoto | Getty Images</p></div><div><p><span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="RegularArticle-QuoteInBody-1"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/AMZN/">Amazon</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span> on Friday began laying off "several hundred" people in its Alexa division as part of broader belt-tightening that's been underway since last year, the company confirmed.</p><p>Daniel Rausch, Amazon's vice president of Alexa and Fire TV, sent a note to staffers informing them of the job cuts, according to a copy of the memo shared by an Amazon spokesperson.</p><p>"As we continue to invent, we're shifting some of our efforts to better align with our business priorities, and what we know matters most to customers — which includes maximizing our resources and efforts focused on generative AI," Rausch wrote in the memo, which was reported earlier by <a href="https://www.geekwire.com/2023/amazon-will-cut-several-hundred-more-jobs-on-alexa-team-as-it-discontinues-some-initiatives/" target="_blank">GeekWire</a>. "These shifts are leading us to discontinue some initiatives, which is resulting in several hundred roles being eliminated."</p><p>Amazon didn't specify which Alexa initiatives it's winding down as a result of the move.</p><p>The company will reach out on Friday to employees in the U.S. and Canada who were affected. Staffers in India will be notified next week, while timing in other regions is dependent on local regulations, Rausch said.</p><p>Amazon CEO Andy Jassy <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2022/10/12/amazon-cost-cuts-under-andy-jassy-reflect-new-reality-after-25-years.html">has been in cost-cutting mode</a> since last year as the company reckons with an economic downturn and slowing growth in its core retail business. The company initiated the largest layoffs in its history, cutting more than 27,000 jobs, and axed many of its more unprofitable initiatives. Amazon previously cut employees <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2022/11/16/amazon-lays-off-some-devices-employees-read-the-memo.html">in its devices and services division</a>, which includes Alexa.</p><p>Since its launch in 2014, Amazon has made big investments in Alexa and assigned top talent to grow the technology, largely at the direction of Jeff Bezos, who first pitched Alexa and strongly believed voice would play a key role in how people interact with computers in the future. At one point, Amazon&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2017/09/27/amazon-has-5000-people-on-echo-and-alexa-more-than-fitbit-and-gopro.html">had 5,000 people</a>&nbsp;working on Alexa and Echo.</p><p>Alexa and digital assistants like it were once groundbreaking technology, but they face increasing competition from generative artificial intelligence and chatbots like OpenAI's ChatGPT. In September, Amazon <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/09/20/amazon-event-2023-heres-everything-the-company-just-announced.html">teased updates</a> to Alexa that are tied to generative AI, such as composing messages on behalf of users. The unit overseeing Alexa also has a new leader, after longtime devices head Dave Limp <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/09/25/blue-origin-ceo-bob-smith-out-replaced-by-outgoing-amazon-exec-dave-limp.html">left to join</a> Bezos' rocket company Blue Origin. Limp <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/09/27/amazon-hires-former-microsoft-product-chief-to-oversee-devices-unit.html">was succeeded by</a> veteran Microsoft executive Panos Panay.</p><p>Rausch said Amazon remains "encouraged by the progress we're making with Alexa," noting that users have interacted with the virtual assistant "tens of millions of times every hour," and there are more than 500 million Alexa devices in consumers' homes.</p><p><strong>WATCH: </strong><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/video/2023/11/14/amazon-partners-with-snap-to-feature-shopping-ads-on-the-app.html">Amazon partners with Snap to feature shopping ads</a></p></div><div id="Placeholder-ArticleBody-Video-107333715" data-test="VideoPlaceHolder" role="region" tabindex="0" data-vilynx-id="7000322537" aria-labelledby="Placeholder-ArticleBody-Video-107333715"><p><img src="https://image.cnbcfm.com/api/v1/image/107333716-16999882791699988276-32025931418-1080pnbcnews.jpg?v=1699988278&amp;w=750&amp;h=422&amp;vtcrop=y" alt="Amazon partners with Snap to feature shopping ads on the app"><span></span><span></span></p></div><div><p><em><strong>Don't miss these stories from CNBC PRO:</strong></em></p><ul><li><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/11/06/warren-buffett-is-selling-stocks-including-chevron-and-hoarding-record-cash.html"><em>Warren Buffett has been selling stocks including Chevron and hoarding a record level of cash</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/11/07/bernsteins-stock-picks-to-play-the-expected-bitcoin-etf-and-halving.html"><em>Bernstein says to buy these crypto stocks to play the expected bitcoin ETF and halving</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/11/08/bank-of-america-says-there-are-two-things-that-will-drive-the-next-bull-run-in-stocks.html"><em>Bank of America says there are two things that will drive the next bull run in stocks</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/11/06/zweig-breadth-thrust-rare-market-buy-signal.html"><em>The market just triggered a rare signal that has meant higher returns a year later 100% of the time</em></a></li></ul></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[280M e-bikes and mopeds are cutting demand for oil far more than electric cars (582 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://theconversation.com/the-worlds-280-million-electric-bikes-and-mopeds-are-cutting-demand-for-oil-far-more-than-electric-cars-213870</link>
            <guid>38304485</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 15:02:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://theconversation.com/the-worlds-280-million-electric-bikes-and-mopeds-are-cutting-demand-for-oil-far-more-than-electric-cars-213870">https://theconversation.com/the-worlds-280-million-electric-bikes-and-mopeds-are-cutting-demand-for-oil-far-more-than-electric-cars-213870</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38304485">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
    <p>We hop in the car to get groceries or drop kids at school. But while the car is convenient, these short trips add up in terms of emissions, pollution and petrol cost.  </p>

<p>Close to half (44%) of all Australian commuter trips are by car –&nbsp;and under 10km. Of Perth’s 4.2 million daily car trips, 2.8 are for distances of less than 2km.   </p>

<p>This is common in wealthier countries. In the United States, a staggering 60% of all car trips cover <a href="https://www.urbanismnext.org/resources/summary-of-travel-trends-2017-national-household-travel-survey">less than 10km</a>. </p>

<p>So what’s the best solution? You might think switching to an electric vehicle is the natural step. In fact, for short trips, an electric bike or moped might be better for you –&nbsp;and for the planet. That’s because these forms of transport – collectively known as electric micromobility – are cheaper to buy and run. </p>

<p>But it’s more than that –&nbsp;they are actually displacing <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2023-09-26/the-rise-of-the-electric-two-wheeler">four times as much demand for oil</a> as all the world’s electric cars at present, due to their staggering uptake in China and <a href="https://www.dailykos.com/stories/2023/9/16/2192859/-EVs-are-cutting-the-world-demand-for-oil-but-not-in-the-way-you-may-think">other nations</a> where mopeds are a common form of transport. </p>

<figure>
            <a href="https://images.theconversation.com/files/559542/original/file-20231115-17-wb6yq4.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=1000&amp;fit=clip"><p><img alt="family on electric moped in Beijing, China" data-src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/559542/original/file-20231115-17-wb6yq4.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip" data-srcset="https://images.theconversation.com/files/559542/original/file-20231115-17-wb6yq4.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=600&amp;h=450&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=1 600w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/559542/original/file-20231115-17-wb6yq4.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=30&amp;auto=format&amp;w=600&amp;h=450&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=2 1200w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/559542/original/file-20231115-17-wb6yq4.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=15&amp;auto=format&amp;w=600&amp;h=450&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=3 1800w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/559542/original/file-20231115-17-wb6yq4.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;h=565&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=1 754w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/559542/original/file-20231115-17-wb6yq4.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=30&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;h=565&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=2 1508w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/559542/original/file-20231115-17-wb6yq4.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=15&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;h=565&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=3 2262w" sizes="(min-width: 1466px) 754px, (max-width: 599px) 100vw, (min-width: 600px) 600px, 237px" src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/559542/original/file-20231115-17-wb6yq4.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip"></p></a>
            <figcaption>
              <span>Electric mopeds have surged in popularity –&nbsp;especially in China.</span>
              <span><span>Shutterstock</span></span>
            </figcaption>
          </figure>

<h2>How can that be?</h2>

<p>On the world’s roads last year, there were over 20 million electric vehicles and 1.3 million commercial EVs such as buses, delivery vans and trucks. </p>

<p>But these numbers of four or more wheel vehicles are wholly eclipsed by two- and three-wheelers. There were over 280 million electric mopeds, scooters, motorcycles and three-wheelers on the road last year. Their sheer popularity is already cutting demand for oil by a million barrels of oil a day –&nbsp;about 1% of the world’s total oil demand, according to estimates by <a href="https://bnef.turtl.co/story/evo-2022/page/2/1">Bloomberg New Energy Finance</a>. </p>

<p>What about electric vehicles, you ask? After all, EVs have been heralded as a silver bullet for car emissions and air pollution in cities, as their tailpipe emissions are zero. If charged with renewable power, they get even greener. </p>

<p>But to see them as an inarguable good is an error. They are cleaner cars, but they are still cars, taking up space on the roads and requiring a lot of electricity to power them. Their batteries make them heavier than a traditional car, and draw heavily on the extraction of rare earth elements. While EVs are <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/03/02/climate/electric-vehicles-environment.html">overall much greener</a> than internal combustion engine cars, battery manufacture can undermine <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/j.1530-9290.2012.00532.x">some of the gains</a>.</p>

<p>On the plus side, petrol cars cost about <a href="https://www.carsguide.com.au/ev/advice/do-electric-cars-actually-save-you-money-83060">A$0.14 per kilometre</a> in fuel, or about $1,820 in fuel annually for the <a href="https://www.abs.gov.au/statistics/industry/tourism-and-transport/survey-motor-vehicle-use-australia/latest-release">average car doing 12,000km</a>. Maintenance averages at $910 a year, bringing the total to $2,730 for a petrol car.</p>

<p>By contrast, charging an EV would cost around $480 for that distance. Maintenance of $240 takes annual running costs to $720. So EVs are much cheaper to run. But they are expensive to buy.   </p>

<hr>
<p>
  <em>
    <strong>
      Read more:
      <a href="https://theconversation.com/five-years-on-brisbanes-e-scooters-and-e-bikes-are-winning-over-tourists-and-residents-as-they-open-up-the-city-212464">Five years on, Brisbane's e-scooters and e-bikes are winning over tourists and residents as they open up the city</a>
    </strong>
  </em>
</p>
<hr>


<h2>What advantages do electric mopeds and bikes have?</h2>

<p>The electric transport revolution is a great chance to rethink how we move through our cities –&nbsp;and whether we even need a car at all. </p>

<p>Cars, after all, often have only one occupant. You’re expending a lot of energy to transport yourself. </p>

<p>By contrast, electric mopeds and bikes use a lot less energy to transport one or two people. They’re also a lot cheaper to buy and run than electric cars. </p>

<p>If you commute on an e-bike 20km a day, five days a week, your charging cost would be about $20 – annually. </p>

<p>In Australia, electric bikes are very rapidly going from a hobbyist pursuit to a serious mode of urban transport. Over 100,000 e-bikes <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/2023/oct/08/its-also-just-fun-why-a-growing-number-of-australia-families-are-ditching-cars-for-e-bikes">were sold here</a> last year.</p>

<p>Of course, you’re unlikely to use electric mopeds or bikes to drive from Sydney to Melbourne. Their real value is in short-hop trips –&nbsp;the school run, the milk and bread run or even the commute –&nbsp;where they take roughly the same time or shorter than a car. </p>

<figure>
            <a href="https://images.theconversation.com/files/559546/original/file-20231115-19-pc1wdl.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=1000&amp;fit=clip"><p><img alt="man standing near stacked oil barrels" data-src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/559546/original/file-20231115-19-pc1wdl.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip" data-srcset="https://images.theconversation.com/files/559546/original/file-20231115-19-pc1wdl.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=600&amp;h=400&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=1 600w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/559546/original/file-20231115-19-pc1wdl.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=30&amp;auto=format&amp;w=600&amp;h=400&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=2 1200w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/559546/original/file-20231115-19-pc1wdl.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=15&amp;auto=format&amp;w=600&amp;h=400&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=3 1800w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/559546/original/file-20231115-19-pc1wdl.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;h=503&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=1 754w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/559546/original/file-20231115-19-pc1wdl.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=30&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;h=503&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=2 1508w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/559546/original/file-20231115-19-pc1wdl.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=15&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;h=503&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=3 2262w" sizes="(min-width: 1466px) 754px, (max-width: 599px) 100vw, (min-width: 600px) 600px, 237px" src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/559546/original/file-20231115-19-pc1wdl.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip"></p></a>
            <figcaption>
              <span>E-bikes and electric mopeds are cutting oil demand more than electric vehicles.</span>
              <span><span>Shutterstock</span></span>
            </figcaption>
          </figure>

<p>Smaller electric options like scooters and skateboards also offer a way to overcome the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Last_mile_(transportation)">last kilometre problem</a> which plagues public  transport systems. This, in short, is the <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2015-09-16/study-working-near-public-transit-is-more-important-to-non-car-commuters-than-living-near-it">inconvenient distance</a> between your home and the station or bus stop. Being able to cover this distance fast can be a game-changer for public transport. </p>

<p>If taken up, electric micromobility can cut urban emissions. A study of e-scooter riders in the United Kingdom found <a href="https://www.voi.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/UCL-C_Emissions-Savings-Emissions-from-Shared-E-Scooters.pdf">these trips produced</a> up to 45% less carbon dioxide than alternatives. </p>

<p>US researchers estimate that if e-bike trips expanded to 11% of all vehicle trips, transport emissions <a href="https://www.itdp.org/2019/09/24/e-bikes-e-scooters-drivers-of-climate-action/">would fall by about 7%</a>. </p>

<p>As petrol prices increase and battery prices fall, the cheaper running costs of electric vehicles and even cheaper running costs of electric mopeds, bikes and scooters will keep eating away at the demand for oil. </p>

<p>Global oil demand is now <a href="https://www.instituteforenergyresearch.org/international-issues/iea-forecasts-global-oil-demand-peaking-by-2028">projected to peak</a> in 2028 at 105.7 million barrels per day –&nbsp;and then begin to fall, according to the International Energy Agency. </p>

<p>Electric vehicles will play a role in cutting oil demand. But it may well be that electric micromobility cuts demand faster, given how fast these cheaper, more plentiful options are being taken up. </p>

<h2>What does this mean for me?</h2>

<p>If you’re looking to go electric, it’s worth taking a close look at your transport needs. If you live in an outer suburb or regional towns, you may find the longer range and larger capacity of an electric car is better suited.</p>

<p>But for many people, it’s likely you’ll have a range of options. You might have one electric vehicle for longer trips, or group trips, as well as an e-bike for the school run or groceries. </p>

<hr>
<p>
  <em>
    <strong>
      Read more:
      <a href="https://theconversation.com/beyond-electric-cars-how-electrifying-trucks-buses-tractors-and-scooters-will-help-tackle-climate-change-182055">Beyond electric cars: how electrifying trucks, buses, tractors and scooters will help tackle climate change</a>
    </strong>
  </em>
</p>
<hr>

  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Electric vehicle battery prices are falling faster than expected (222 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.goldmansachs.com/intelligence/pages/electric-vehicle-battery-prices-falling.html</link>
            <guid>38304405</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 14:57:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.goldmansachs.com/intelligence/pages/electric-vehicle-battery-prices-falling.html">https://www.goldmansachs.com/intelligence/pages/electric-vehicle-battery-prices-falling.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38304405">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article> 
     <div> 
       <p> <img alt="" src="https://www.goldmansachs.com/intelligence/pages/electric-vehicle-battery-prices-falling-f/800x450.png"></p> 
       <p> It wasn’t long ago rising demand and component shortages sparked concern that <a href="https://www.goldmansachs.com/intelligence/pages/batteries-the-greenflation-challenge-2.html">“greenflation” would drive up prices</a> for the batteries used in electric vehicles. That’s subsiding as prices cool for battery metals, which could help make EVs more competitive with traditional cars more quickly.&nbsp;</p> 
        
       <p> Goldman Sachs Research now expects battery prices to fall to $99 per kilowatt hour (kWh) of storage capacity by 2025 — a 40% decrease from 2022 (the previous forecast was for a 33% decline). Our analysts estimate that almost half of the decline will come from declining prices of <a href="https://www.goldmansachs.com/intelligence/pages/infographics/green-metals/index.html">EV raw materials</a> such as lithium, nickel, and cobalt. Battery pack prices are now expected to fall by an average of 11% per year from 2023 to 2030, writes Nikhil Bhandari, co-head of Goldman Sachs Research’s Asia-Pacific Natural Resources and Clean Energy Research, in the team’s report.</p> 
       <p> As battery prices fall, Goldman Sachs Research estimates the EV market could achieve cost parity, without subsidies, with internal combustion engine (ICE) vehicles around the middle of this decade on a total-cost-of-ownership basis.&nbsp;</p> 
        
       <div><p> “The reduction in battery costs could lead to more competitive EV pricing, more extensive consumer adoption, and further growth in the total addressable markets for EVs and batteries,” says Bhandari.</p><p>  The EV market was initially driven by regulatory support around the world, but global EV penetration is starting to retreat from recent highs, a potential driver of which could be governments in Europe and China cutting back on subsidies.</p></div> 
        
       <p> Still, our analysts see the EV market transitioning to a new phase that is more heavily influenced by consumer adoption than government largesse as battery prices drop. The team’s base case estimate for global EV penetration jumps to 17% in 2025 from just 2% in 2020, and to 35% and 63% by 2030 and 2040, respectively. But its “hyper adoption” scenario sees EVs accounting for 21% of total global vehicle sales by 2025, 47% by 2030, and 86% by 2040.&nbsp;</p> 
        
       <p> So far China is leading the way — its EVs are more competitively priced against ICEs in its local market relative to Europe and the US. While EV sales there have been subsidized by Chinese EV producers, which are selling EVs at a loss, the Goldman Sachs Research expects this to eventually change in around the middle of the decade, when battery price declines and a scale-up in EV sales volumes lead to a significant reduction in EV costs. And whereas Chinese consumers are seeing more options of competitively priced EVs, carmakers in the US and Europe have so far focused on larger and more luxurious EV models.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> 
       <p> “We believe the EV market in China could be the closest to a consumer-led EV adoption phase,” Bhandari says.</p> 
       <p> Our analysts also credit new battery technologies for their forecast of a more rapid decline in battery prices. The report highlights a handful of EV battery innovations that could be commercialized this decade, creating “pockets of strength” along the battery value chain. These include novel anode materials featuring silicon that replace or blend with graphite and improve energy density. Bhandari also notes there are new battery structures such as those that increase the size of each battery cell (large cylindrical batteries) that help simplify the pack manufacturing process, “leading to a meaningful savings of labor and machine time.”&nbsp;</p> 
       <hr> 
       <p> <em>This article is being provided for educational purposes only. The information contained in this article does not constitute a recommendation from any Goldman Sachs entity to the recipient, and Goldman Sachs is not providing any financial, economic, legal, investment, accounting, or tax advice through this article or to its recipient. Neither Goldman Sachs nor any of its affiliates makes any representation or warranty, express or implied, as to the accuracy or completeness of the statements or any information contained in this article and any liability therefore (including in respect of direct, indirect, or consequential loss or damage) is expressly disclaimed.</em></p> 
      </div> 
    </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Wikidata, with 12B facts, can ground LLMs to improve their factuality (187 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/WikiResearch/status/1723966761962520824</link>
            <guid>38304290</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 14:44:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/WikiResearch/status/1723966761962520824">https://twitter.com/WikiResearch/status/1723966761962520824</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38304290">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="ScriptLoadFailure"><form action="" method="GET"><div><p><span>Something went wrong, but don’t fret — let’s give it another shot.</span></p><br></div></form></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[FCC Is Trying to Stop Discrimination in Broadband Deployment. Telecoms Are Mad (114 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.techdirt.com/2023/11/17/the-fcc-is-trying-to-stop-discrimination-in-broadband-deployment-telecoms-and-republicans-are-big-mad-about-it/</link>
            <guid>38304109</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 14:32:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/2023/11/17/the-fcc-is-trying-to-stop-discrimination-in-broadband-deployment-telecoms-and-republicans-are-big-mad-about-it/">https://www.techdirt.com/2023/11/17/the-fcc-is-trying-to-stop-discrimination-in-broadband-deployment-telecoms-and-republicans-are-big-mad-about-it/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38304109">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="storywrap-425463">


<h3>from the <i>gop-living-down-to-its-reputation</i> dept</h3>

<p>For decades, big ISPs like AT&amp;T have refused to upgrade low income and poor communities to fiber, despite billions in subsidies, regulatory favors, and tax breaks that were supposed to accomplish <em>precisely that</em>. Groups like the National Digital Inclusion Alliance (NDIA) have released studies on cities like <a href="https://www.digitalinclusion.org/blog/2017/03/10/atts-digital-redlining-of-cleveland/">Cleveland</a> and <a href="https://www.digitalinclusion.org/blog/2017/09/06/more-digital-redlining-att-deployment-and-poverty-in-detroit-and-toledo/">Detroit</a>, documenting how this discrimination lines up with <a href="https://www.npr.org/2017/05/03/526655831/a-forgotten-history-of-how-the-u-s-government-segregated-america">30s “redlining” efforts</a>. </p>
<p>Section 60506 of the 2021 infrastructure bill dedicated $65 billion in new broadband subsidies. But it also tasked the FCC with creating rules that would prevent future broadband deployment discrimination. The FCC came in just under the wire for Congress’ November 15 deadline, <a href="https://www.fcc.gov/document/fcc-adopts-rules-prevent-eliminate-digital-discrimination">finally unveiling its full rules yesterday</a>. </p>
<p>I’ve spent much of the last few weeks talking to consumer groups, activists, and telecom policy experts about the rules.</p>
<p>The general consensus is that it’s a hugely welcome and long overdue improvement, even though the FCC stubbornly refuses to name and shame ISPs with long histories of clear discrimination (wouldn’t want to upset <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/2015/08/17/new-leaks-confirm-ats-position-as-nsas-favorite-telco-partner/">key domestic surveillance allies</a>), the complaint process isn’t transparent, and many are worried that this FCC, with its sketchy track record on consumer protection, won’t consistently enforce them.</p>
<p>FCC boss Jessica Rosenworcel <a href="https://docs.fcc.gov/public/attachments/DOC-398477A2.pdf">had this to say about the new rules</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>“These rules are strong. When you consider Congress explicitly directed us to “prevent”<br>and “eliminate” digital discrimination of access, they had better be. But I would also argue that they are fair and reasonable.”</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Again, these rules are a welcome and long overdue admission by the government that minority and low income Americans have been systematically discriminated against when it comes to broadband deployment, something that’s documentable and indisputably true, despite industry denials. </p>
<p>Late last year you’ll recall <a href="https://themarkup.org/still-loading/2022/10/19/dollars-to-megabits-you-may-be-paying-400-times-as-much-as-your-neighbor-for-internet-service">The Markup released a story</a> showing that not only do big ISPs systematically discriminate in deployment, they charge low income and minority customers more money for slower service than less diverse, more affluent neighborhoods. It’s not really a debate. </p>
<p>One thing consumer groups are happy about: the rules govern both “disparate treatment” (spotty broadband deployment caused by active, provable discrimination) and “disparate impact” (spotty broadband deployment that falls along discriminatory lines regardless of intent). Telecom execs don’t often put discriminatory intent in emails to staff, so proving discriminatory intent isn’t always possible. Other agencies like the NTIA had <a href="https://www.ntia.gov/press-release/2023/ntia-calls-strong-digital-discrimination-rules#:~:text=NTIA's%20filing%20urges%20the%20FCC,an%20ISP%20against%20a%20group.">advised the FCC adopt this broader approach</a>. </p>
<p>“Strong rules are needed to identify and remedy unequal access to Internet service, no matter what the cause may be,” NTIA Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information Alan Davidson wrote<strong>.</strong>&nbsp;“Rules that combat these inequities will bring lasting relief for vulnerable communities that historically have been left behind online.”</p>
<p>Giant incumbent telecom monopolies with decades of discrimination under their belt are unsurprisingly upset. Key trade groups have already <a href="https://www.lightreading.com/broadband/industry-hints-at-possible-legal-challenges-to-fcc-s-digital-discrimination-rules?mc_cid=e3190e9f79&amp;mc_eid=eb527a594e">threatened to sue</a> over the rules, and <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2023/11/internet-providers-say-the-fcc-should-not-investigate-broadband-prices/">seem particularly chaffed</a> that the rules govern discrimination in broadband pricing. They insist the rules interfere with “the practical business choices and profit-related decisions that sustain a vibrant and dynamic free enterprise system.”</p>
<p>Here in reality, U.S. broadband is anything but a vibrant and dynamic free enterprise system. It’s a failed market, dominated by a handful of politically powerful regional mono/duopolies, who hoover up untold billions in taxpayer subsidies for networks they routinely fail to fully deploy. All protected by layers upon layers of state and federal corruption policymakers like to pretend doesn’t exist.</p>
<p>Enter the GOP, which was quick to hyperventilate about the rules at industry’s prompt. Senator Ted Cruz and <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/2023/11/14/fcc-commish-brendan-carr-takes-a-break-from-crying-about-tiktok-to-lie-about-his-agencys-plan-to-combat-racism-in-broadband-deployment/">FCC Commissioner Brendan Carr</a> were particularly incensed, and quickly got to work <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/politics/fcc-commissioner-blasts-bidens-digital-equity-plan-unlawful-power-grab">peppering the media with false claims</a> that the rules were a dystopian Biden administration attempt to <a href="https://www.nexttv.com/news/gop-to-fcc-back-off-from-overbroad-digital-equity-rules">exert “government control over virtually all aspects of the Internet</a>,” despite it being a congressional mandate. </p>
<p>Recall, Republicans largely voted against the infrastructure bill, despite the fact that they <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/2023/04/27/republicans-keep-taking-credit-for-billions-in-broadband-subsidies-only-made-possible-by-the-covid-relief-and-infrastructure-bills-they-vehemently-opposed/">still take credit for the numerous broadband projects it’s funding</a> among local constituents. </p>
<p>Again, I’m not particularly sure this FCC will consistently enforce the rules (assuming they survive industry legal challenge) or bring any meaningful penalties against big companies, since that’s never been the agency’s strong suit. And the FCC’s failure to name and shape specific ISPs or address very clear past discrimination is a bit feckless. Also, with FCC leadership shifting every election, it’s extremely unlikely that a Trump-run FCC would ever bother to enforce the rules. </p>
<p>At the same time, absolutely <strong>any</strong> effort to hold big telecom accountable for shitty behavior is treated by the GOP as if it’s some kind of dystopian hellscape of government overreach (though this is the same GOP that wants to abuse FCC authority to bully social media companies that moderate, however sloppily, the party’s race-baiting political propaganda). </p>
<p>Still, simply having the U.S. government overtly acknowledge a generation of discrimination in broadband deployment remains a big deal. It at least <strong>attempts</strong> to begin to rebalance the scales after generations of redlining and government apathy, something predatory regional monopolies and their loyal puppies in Congress clearly aren’t too keen on. </p>
<p>
Filed Under: <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/broadband/" rel="tag">broadband</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/corruption/" rel="tag">corruption</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/digital-discrimination/" rel="tag">digital discrimination</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/digital-divide/" rel="tag">digital divide</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/discrimination/" rel="tag">discrimination</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/gop/" rel="tag">gop</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/high-speed-internet/" rel="tag">high speed internet</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/infrastructure-bill/" rel="tag">infrastructure bill</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/ndia/" rel="tag">ndia</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/racism/" rel="tag">racism</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/redlining/" rel="tag">redlining</a>
<br>
</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Volvo delivers 74-tonne electric truck (101 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.volvotrucks.com/en-en/news-stories/press-releases/2023/jun/volvo-delivers-74-tonne-electric-truck.html</link>
            <guid>38302844</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 12:55:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.volvotrucks.com/en-en/news-stories/press-releases/2023/jun/volvo-delivers-74-tonne-electric-truck.html">https://www.volvotrucks.com/en-en/news-stories/press-releases/2023/jun/volvo-delivers-74-tonne-electric-truck.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38302844">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-nc="Text">
      <p>More and more hauliers are now starting to invest in electric trucks, also for heavy transport. Mattson Åkeri in Gothenburg, Sweden is one of them, and the company has now bought three heavy electric Volvo FH trucks from Volvo.<br>
&nbsp;</p>
<p>For the past few weeks, testing has been ongoing on one of the trucks in container traffic in the port area of ​​Arendal in Gothenburg. The test is a so-called HCT (High-Capacity Transport) project. The truck with two trailers is 32 m long and can handle a gross combination weight of 74 tonnes.<br>
&nbsp;</p>
<p>“We want to show that all-electric solutions also work in applications with high total weights and a high utilization rate. Together with Mattson Åkeri, the Swedish Transport Administration and several other partners, we are now looking at how we can optimize the operation of the electric truck, including how charging should take place in the most efficient way,” explains Lena Larsson, project manager of the HCT project within Volvo's technology organization.<br>
&nbsp;</p>
<p>The electric truck being tested is a Volvo FH Electric 6X4 and is charged with green electricity at the two fast 180 kW chargers that Mattsson Åkeri has installed in the company's depot in Arendal. In the long term, the truck will also run between Gothenburg and the city of Borås, 70 km from Gothenburg.<br>
&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>In operation 12 hours a day</b></p>
<p>“Driving long and heavy loads using electricity works very well so far, and we can carry as much cargo as a diesel truck,” says Jan-Olof Mattsson, CEO of Mattson Åkeri. “The truck runs 12 hours a day, with a stop for charging when the driver takes a break. We charge with green electricity and thus get no CO2 emissions. Silent, electric operation also means a better working environment for the driver.”<br>
&nbsp;</p>
<div><p>Since Volvo Trucks started production of all-electric trucks in 2019, the company has sold nearly 5,000 electric trucks in 40 countries around the world. Volvo today offers the industry's widest product range with six electric models in series production that meet a broad range of needs for transport in and between cities. Globally, Volvo Trucks has set the target that half of all trucks sold are electric by 2030.</p></div>
<p><b>High-Capacity Transports</b><br>
High-Capacity Transports (HCT) means that the vehicle's length and/or gross weight is allowed to increase, which allows for a larger load to be transported per vehicle. HCT can be applied on all types of drivelines. The idea is that HCT will contribute to lower transport costs, reduced environmental impact, higher traffic safety, reduced road wear and lower maintenance costs. In Europe there are a number of ongoing and planned HCT projects. One example is Finland, where it is permitted to drive with 76 tonnes of total weight and 34,5m truck combinations on most roads. Another is Sweden, where it is allowed to drive 74 tonnes (BK4 road network) and test, with permission from authorities, truck combinations of up to 34,5m and 100 tonnes on a defined road network.</p>

<p><b><a href="https://images.volvotrucks.com/search?querylabel=PRHL0613_1&amp;querystring=(%22%7Baf4b2e0c-5f6a-11d2-8f20-0000c0e166dc%7D:Categories%22%20?%20%22:13363:%22)" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LINK</a></b> to high-resolution images<br>
</p>

  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Almost No One Pays a 6% Real-Estate Commission–Except Americans (309 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wsj.com/personal-finance/real-estate-buying-home-charts-6dc40caa</link>
            <guid>38302780</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 12:48:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wsj.com/personal-finance/real-estate-buying-home-charts-6dc40caa">https://www.wsj.com/personal-finance/real-estate-buying-home-charts-6dc40caa</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38302780">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><div> <p>By </p><p><a data-testid="author-link" href="https://www.wsj.com/news/author/veronica-dagher" target="_blank" aria-label="Author page for Veronica Dagher"><span><span>Veronica Dagher</span></span></a></p></div><div><p>Nov. 16, 2023 9:00 pm ET</p></div></div><div aria-label="Utility Bar" role="toolbar" data-block="doNotPrint"></div><section><div data-type="image" data-inset_type="" data-sub_type="" data-layout="inline"><figure><picture><img alt="" sizes="(max-width: 639px) 100vw, (max-width: 979px) 620px, (max-width: 1299px) 540px, 700px" srcset="https://images.wsj.net/im-888257?width=540&amp;size=1.5005861664712778 540w, https://images.wsj.net/im-888257?width=620&amp;size=1.5005861664712778 620w, https://images.wsj.net/im-888257?width=639&amp;size=1.5005861664712778 639w, https://images.wsj.net/im-888257?width=700&amp;size=1.5005861664712778 700w, https://images.wsj.net/im-888257?width=700&amp;size=1.5005861664712778&amp;pixel_ratio=1.5 1050w, https://images.wsj.net/im-888257?width=700&amp;size=1.5005861664712778&amp;pixel_ratio=2 1400w, https://images.wsj.net/im-888257?width=700&amp;size=1.5005861664712778&amp;pixel_ratio=3 2100w" width="700" height="466" src="https://images.wsj.net/im-888257?width=700&amp;height=466"></picture></figure><figcaption><span>The U.S. has more real-estate agents than any other country, by a wide margin.</span> <span><span>Photo: </span>Getty Images</span></figcaption></div><p data-type="paragraph">The way we buy and sell homes in the U.S. isn’t normal—at least not compared with the rest of the world.</p><p data-type="paragraph">The commission on a home sale here is typically around 5% to 6%, usually split between the seller’s and buyer’s agents. In most countries, the commissions are substantially smaller.</p></section><p>Copyright ©<!-- -->2023<!-- --> Dow Jones &amp; Company, Inc. All Rights Reserved. 87990cbe856818d5eddac44c7b1cdeb8</p><div><div id="cx-snippet-overlay"><p><img src="https://sts3.wsj.net/iweb/images/wsj-logo-big-black.svg" title="The Wall Street Journal" alt=""></p><p>Continue reading your article with<br>a WSJ subscription</p><p><a href="https://subscribe.wsj.com/wsjsnippet">Subscribe Now</a></p></div><p>Already a subscriber? <a href="https://www.wsj.com/client/login?target=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.wsj.com%2Fpersonal-finance%2Freal-estate-buying-home-charts-6dc40caa">Sign In</a></p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Oops! We Automated Bullshit (333 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cst.cam.ac.uk/blog/afb21/oops-we-automated-bullshit</link>
            <guid>38302635</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 12:34:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cst.cam.ac.uk/blog/afb21/oops-we-automated-bullshit">https://www.cst.cam.ac.uk/blog/afb21/oops-we-automated-bullshit</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38302635">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div property="content:encoded"><p>ChatGPT is a bullshit generator. To understand AI, we should think harder about bullshit</p>
<p>This post appears in a blog created in 2019 to focus on AI in Africa. Long before the release of ChatGPT, many wondered why AI would be relevant to Africans. But I’m writing in a week when US President Biden published an executive order on AI, and British PM Rishi Sunak listened enthusiastically to Elon Musk promising a magical AI future where nobody needs to work. When the richest man in the world talks up a storm with NATO leaders, Africa will get blown around in those political and economic winds.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Since my fieldwork in Africa, I’ve learned to ask different questions about AI, and in recent months, I’ve started to feel like the boy who questions the emperor’s new clothes. The problem I see, apparently not reported in coverage of Sunak’s AI Summit, is that AI <em>literally produces bullshit</em>. (Do I mean “literally”? My friends complain that I take everything literally, but I’m not a kleptomaniac).&nbsp;</p>
<p>MIT Professor of AI Rodney Brooks summarises the working principle of ChatGPT as “it just makes up stuff that sounds good”. This is mathematically accurate, where “sounds good” is an algorithm to imitate text found on the internet, while “makes up” is the basic randomness of relying on predictive text rather than logic or facts. Other leading researchers and professors of AI say the same things, with more technical detail, as in the famous “stochastic parrots” paper by Emily Bender, Timnit Gebru and their colleagues, or Murray Shanahan’s explanation of the text prediction principles (references below).</p>
<p>“Godfather of AI” Geoff Hinton, in recent public talks, explains that one of the greatest risks is not that chatbots will become super-intelligent, but that they will generate text that is super-persuasive without being intelligent, in the manner of Donald Trump or Boris Johnson. In a world where evidence and logic are not respected in public debate, Hinton imagines that systems operating without evidence or logic could become our overlords by becoming superhumanly persuasive, imitating and supplanting the worst kinds of political leader.</p>
<p>If this isn’t about evidence or logic, what is the scientific principle involved? Quite simply, we are talking about bullshit. Philosopher Harry Frankfurt, in his classic text <em>On Bullshit</em>, explains that the bullshitter “does not reject the authority of truth, as the liar does […] He pays no attention to it at all.” This is exactly what senior AI researchers such as Brooks, Bender, Shanahan and Hinton are telling us, when they explain how ChatGPT works. The problem, as Frankfurt explains, is that “[b]y virtue of this, bullshit is a greater enemy of the truth than lies are.” (p. 61). At a time when a public enquiry is reporting the astonishing behaviour of our most senior leaders during the Covid pandemic, the British people wonder how we came to elect such such bullshitters to lead us. But as Frankfurt observes, “Bullshit is unavoidable whenever circumstances require someone to talk without knowing what he is talking about” (p.63)</p>
<p>Perhaps this explains why the latest leader of the same government is so impressed by AI, and by billionaires promoting automated bullshit generators? But Frankfurt’s book is not the only classic text on bullshit. David Graeber’s famous analysis of <em>Bullshit Jobs</em> explains precisely why Elon Musk’s claim to the British PM is so revealing of the true nature of AI. Graeber revealed that over 30% of British workers believe their own job contributes nothing of any value to society. These are people who spend their lives writing pointless reports, relaying messages from one person to another, or listening to complaints they can do nothing about. Every part of their job could easily be done by ChatGPT.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Graeber observes that aspects of university education prepare young people to expect little more from life, training them to submit to bureaucratic processes, while writing reams of text that few will ever read. In the kind of education that produces a Boris Johnson, verbal fluency and entertaining arguments may be rewarded more highly than close attention to the truth. As Graeber says, we train people for bullshit jobs by training them to generate bullshit. So is Elon Musk right, that nobody will have to work any more once AI is achieved? Perhaps so, if producing bullshit is the only kind of work we need - and you can see how the owner of (eX)Twitter might see the world that way.</p>
<p>AI systems like ChatGPT are trained with text from Twitter, Facebook, Reddit, and other huge archives of bullshit, alongside plenty of actual facts (including Wikipedia and text ripped off from professional writers). But there is no algorithm in ChatGPT to check which parts are true. The output is literally bullshit, exactly as defined by philosopher Harry Frankfurt, and as we would expect from Graeber’s study of bullshit jobs. Just as Twitter encourages bullshitting politicians who don’t care whether what they say is true or false, the archives of what they have said can be used to train automatic bullshit generators.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The problem isn’t AI. What we need to regulate is the bullshit. Perhaps the next British PM should convene a summit on bullshit, to figure out whose jobs are worthwhile, and which ones we could happily lose?</p>
<p>If you'd like to read more, my new book on <em>Designing Alternatives to AI,</em> to be published by MIT Press in 2024, is available as an <a href="https://moralcodes.pubpub.org/">online free preview</a>.<br>
&nbsp;</p>
<h3>References</h3>
<p>Emily M. Bender, &nbsp;Timnit Gebru, Angelina McMillan-Major, and Shmargaret Shmitchell, "On the Dangers of Stochastic Parrots: Can Language Models Be Too Big?" in Proceedings of the 2021 ACM conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency (March 2021), 610-623.</p>
<p>Harry G. Frankfurt, On Bullshit. Princeton University Press, 2005.</p>
<p>David Graeber, Bullshit Jobs: A Theory. Penguin Books, 2019.</p>
<p>Murray Shanahan, Talking About Large Language Models. (2022). arXiv preprint <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03551">arXiv:2212.03551</a>.</p>
<p>Glenn Zorpette, &nbsp;"Just Calm Down About GPT-4 Already. And stop confusing performance with competence, says Rodney Brooks," <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/gpt-4-calm-down">IEEE Spectrum (17 May 2023).</a></p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[YouTube Copyright ID Scammers Must Pay Artists $3.3M Restitution (206 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://torrentfreak.com/youtube-copyright-id-scammers-must-pay-artists-3-3m-restitution-231116/</link>
            <guid>38302634</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 12:34:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://torrentfreak.com/youtube-copyright-id-scammers-must-pay-artists-3-3m-restitution-231116/">https://torrentfreak.com/youtube-copyright-id-scammers-must-pay-artists-3-3m-restitution-231116/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38302634">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p>

<span property="itemListElement" typeof="ListItem"><a property="item" typeof="WebPage" title="Go to TorrentFreak." href="https://torrentfreak.com/"><span property="name">Home</span></a><meta property="position" content="1"></span> &gt; <span property="itemListElement" typeof="ListItem"><a property="item" typeof="WebPage" title="Go to the Lawsuits category archives." href="https://torrentfreak.com/category/lawsuits/"><span property="name">Lawsuits</span></a><meta property="position" content="2"></span> &gt; <span></span>
</p>
<p>
<span> </span>
By masquerading as legitimate music rightsholders, two men managed to extract over $23 million in revenue from YouTube's Content ID system. Both were arrested and sentenced to prison. In the wake of the criminal proceeding, hundreds of disadvantaged artists came forward, and the court has now ordered the scammers to pay $3.3 million in restitution.
</p>
</div><div>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://torrentfreak.com/images/youtubehappy.png" alt="YouTube" width="230" height="158" data-old-src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg'%20viewBox='0%200%20230%20158'%3E%3C/svg%3E" data-lazy-src="https://torrentfreak.com/images/youtubehappy.png">In 2021, the US Department of Justice launched a <a href="https://torrentfreak.com/u-s-indicts-two-men-for-running-a-20-million-youtube-content-id-scam-211203/">criminal proceeding</a> against two men suspected of running a massive YouTube Content ID scam.</p>
<p>YouTube’s flagship anti-piracy system is supposed to protect rightsholders but, in this case, it was used to exploit them.</p>
<h2>Multi-Million Dollar Scam</h2>
<p>The scammers’ company, MediaMuv LLC., wasn’t a direct member of the Content ID program. Instead, it operated through a trusted third-party company, which had access to the platform.</p>
<p>By falsely claiming to own the rights to more than 50,000 copyrighted songs, the scammers generated more than $23 million in revenue.</p>
<p>In 2022, the first defendant confessed to his part in the copyright swindle by pleading guilty. Webster Fernandez admitted it was a simple scheme: find Latin music that wasn’t yet monetized on YouTube and claim the content as their own.</p>
<p>In February of this year, the second defendant pleaded guilty. Jose Teran signed a plea agreement admitting that he was part of the conspiracy, engaging in wire fraud and money laundering.</p>
<h2>Prison Sentences</h2>
<p>The guilty pleas may have helped to reduce their sentences but the defendants didn’t get off easily. This summer, a federal court in Arizona handed a <a href="https://torrentfreak.com/court-sentences-youtube-content-id-scammer-to-over-five-years-in-prison-230629/">70 month prison term</a> to Mr. Teran, to be followed by three years of probation. </p>
<p>A few weeks later, the same court sentenced Mr. Fernandez to <a href="https://torrentfreak.com/lead-youtube-content-id-scammer-sentenced-to-46-months-230821/">46 months in prison</a> for his role in the conspiracy, to be followed by three years of supervised release.</p>
<p>In addition to the jail time, both convicts had to forfeit multiple possessions related to their crimes, including bank accounts, several pieces of real estate, and cars.</p>
<h2>$3.3 Million Restitution</h2>
<p>At the time of the sentencing, the authorities requested victims of the YouTube Content ID scam to come forward, as they are entitled to restitution. The MediaMuv operation mostly targeted Spanish language artists, who were not monetizing their content on YouTube yet. </p>
<p>Over the past several weeks, hundreds of these artists submitted their claims, ranging from a few dozen dollars, to well over $100,000. Some of these artists were represented by lawyers or their label and the RIAA submitted a claim on behalf of artists as well. </p>
<p>All told, the U.S. Attorney’s Office and defense attorneys agreed to a total restitution amount of more than $3.3 million, which is due immediately. </p>
<p>“The United States, counsel for Webster Batista, and counsel for Jose Teran, respectfully stipulate to the restitution amount of $3,365,352.85,” the stipulation reads.</p>
<p>“Along with the other standard conditions concerning the repayment of restitution, the parties agree that Webster Batista and Jose Teran will be jointly and severally liable for the restitution, restitution is due immediately, and Batista and Teran be ordered to make minimum monthly payments..” </p>
<center><img decoding="async" src="https://torrentfreak.com/images/jointstip.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="525" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/jointstip.jpg 1070w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/jointstip-300x262.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" data-old-src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg'%20viewBox='0%200%20600%20525'%3E%3C/svg%3E" data-lazy-srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/jointstip.jpg 1070w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/jointstip-300x262.jpg 300w" data-lazy-src="https://torrentfreak.com/images/jointstip.jpg"></center>
<p>A quick tally shows that roughly 800 affected artists came forward. One of the largest claims comes from Cecilia Ramirez, widow of the Mexican singer-songwriter <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agust%C3%ADn_Ram%C3%ADrez_(singer)">Agustín Ramírez</a>, who was the frontman of the band Los Caminantes. Ramírez passed away last year.</p>
<center><img decoding="async" src="https://torrentfreak.com/images/restit.jpg" alt="restti" width="600" height="567" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/restit.jpg 1059w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/restit-300x283.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" data-old-src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg'%20viewBox='0%200%20600%20567'%3E%3C/svg%3E" data-lazy-srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/restit.jpg 1059w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/restit-300x283.jpg 300w" data-lazy-src="https://torrentfreak.com/images/restit.jpg"></center>
<p>The RIAA’s claim totals $1,247,719.76 and is based on falsely claimed music of hundreds of artists, as detailed in this <a href="https://torrentfreak.com/images/webster-judg-c.pdf">57-page exhibit</a>. </p>
<p>Both convicted defendants are jointly and severally liable for the restitution payments. How long it will take to repay the affected artists will depend on their income and available funds. </p>
<p>A copy of the joint stipulation on the restitution amount is available <a href="https://torrentfreak.com/images/mediamuvrest.pdf">here (pdf)</a>. The amount was agreed upon by all parties and granted by the Arizona federal court earlier this week.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Unauthorized "David Attenborough" AI clone narrates developer's life, goes viral (201 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2023/11/unauthorized-david-attenborough-ai-clone-narrates-developers-life-goes-viral/</link>
            <guid>38302319</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 11:57:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2023/11/unauthorized-david-attenborough-ai-clone-narrates-developers-life-goes-viral/">https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2023/11/unauthorized-david-attenborough-ai-clone-narrates-developers-life-goes-viral/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38302319">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <h4>
      21st century nature documentary    —
</h4>
            
            <h2 itemprop="description">"We observe the sophisticated <em>Homo sapiens</em> engaging in the ritual of hydration."</h2>
                    </div><div itemprop="articleBody">
                                    
<figure>
  <img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/attenborough_hero-800x519.jpg" alt="Screen capture from a demo video of a fake, unauthorized David Attenborough narrating a developer's video feed.">
      <figcaption><p><a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/attenborough_hero.jpg" data-height="720" data-width="1110">Enlarge</a> <span>/</span> Screen capture from a demo video of an AI-generated unauthorized David Attenborough voice narrating a developer's video feed.</p><p>Charlie Holtz</p></figcaption>  </figure>

  




<!-- cache hit 96:single/related:1dc28c1f58c95231268f5b6413365080 --><!-- empty -->
<p>On Wednesday, Replicate developer Charlie Holtz <a href="https://x.com/charliebholtz/status/1724815159590293764?s=20">combined</a> GPT-4 Vision (commonly called GPT-4V) and ElevenLabs voice cloning technology to create an unauthorized AI version of the famous naturalist <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Attenborough">David Attenborough</a> narrating Holtz's every move on camera. As of Thursday afternoon, the <a href="https://x.com/charliebholtz/status/1724815159590293764?s=20">X post</a> describing the stunt had garnered over 21,000 likes.</p>

<p>"Here we have a remarkable specimen of <em>Homo sapiens</em> distinguished by his silver circular spectacles and a mane of tousled curly locks," the false Attenborough says in the demo as Holtz looks on with a grin. "He's wearing what appears to be a blue fabric covering, which can only be assumed to be part of his mating display."</p>
<p>"Look closely at the subtle arch of his eyebrow," it continues, as if narrating a BBC wildlife documentary. "It's as if he's in the midst of an intricate ritual of curiosity or skepticism. The backdrop suggests a sheltered habitat, possibly a communal feeding area or watering hole."</p>
<figure>
    
    </figure>
<p>How does it work? Every five seconds, a Python script called "narrator" takes a photo from Holtz's webcam and feeds it to <a href="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2023/09/chatgpt-goes-multimodal-with-image-recognition-and-speech-synthesis/">GPT-4V</a>—the version of OpenAI's language model that can process image inputs—via an API, which has a special prompt to make it create text in the style of Attenborough's narrations. Then it feeds that text into an <a href="https://elevenlabs.io/">ElevenLabs</a> AI voice profile trained on audio samples of Attenborough's speech. Holtz provided <a href="https://github.com/cbh123/narrator">the code</a> (called "narrator") that pulls it all together on GitHub, and it requires API tokens for OpenAI and ElevenLabs that cost money to run.</p>                                            
                                                        
<p>While some of these capabilities have been available separately for some time, developers have recently begun to experiment with combining these capabilities together thanks to API availability, which can create surprising demonstrations like this one.</p>
<p>During the demo video, when Holtz holds up a cup and takes a drink, the fake Attenborough narrator says, "Ah, in its natural environment, we observe the sophisticated <em>Homo sapiens</em> engaging in the critical ritual of hydration. This male individual has selected a small cylindrical container, likely filled with life-sustaining H<sub>2</sub>O, and is tilting it expertly towards his intake orifice. Such grace, such poise."</p>

<p>In a different demo <a href="https://x.com/skirano/status/1724944550790135926?s=20">posted on X</a> by Pietro Schirano, you can hear the cloned voice of Steve Jobs critiquing designs created in Figma, a design app. Schirano used a similar technique, with an image being streamed to GPT-4V via API (which was prompted to reply in the style of Jobs), then fed into an ElevenLabs clone of Jobs' voice.</p>
<p>We've <a href="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2022/09/james-earl-jones-signed-darth-vader-voice-rights-to-disney-for-ai-use/">previously</a> <a href="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2023/01/microsofts-new-ai-can-simulate-anyones-voice-with-3-seconds-of-audio/">covered</a> <a href="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2022/09/with-koe-recast-you-can-change-your-voice-as-easily-as-your-clothing/">voice cloning</a> technology, which is fraught with ethical and legal concerns where the software creates convincing deepfakes of a person's voice, making them "say" things the real person never said. This has legal implications regarding a celebrity's publicity rights, and it has already been used to <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2023/03/rising-scams-use-ai-to-mimic-voices-of-loved-ones-in-financial-distress/">scam people</a> by faking the voices of loved ones seeking money. ElevenLabs' <a href="https://elevenlabs.io/terms">terms of service</a> prohibit people from making clones of other people's voices in a way that would violate "Intellectual Property Rights, publicity rights and Copyright," but it's a rule that can be difficult to enforce.</p>
<p>For now, while some people expressed deep discomfort from someone imitating Attenborough's voice without permission, many others seem bemused by the demo. "Okay, I'm going to get David Attenborough to narrate videos of my baby learning how to eat broccoli," <a href="https://x.com/JeremyNguyenPhD/status/1724837709158731887?s=20">quipped</a> Jeremy Nguyen in an X reply.</p>

                                                </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google News is shutting down purchased magazine content, offering refunds (141 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/11/google-news-will-stop-hosting-already-purchased-magazines-next-month/</link>
            <guid>38302306</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 11:56:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/11/google-news-will-stop-hosting-already-purchased-magazines-next-month/">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/11/google-news-will-stop-hosting-already-purchased-magazines-next-month/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38302306">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <h4>
      Imagine being a magazine company in 2023! Who would do that?    —
</h4>
            
            <h2 itemprop="description">Google offers static PDF downloads for some content, refunds for others. </h2>
                    </div><div itemprop="articleBody">
                                    
<figure>
  <img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/Google-News-800x534.jpg" alt="Google News is shutting down purchased magazine content, offering refunds">
      <figcaption><p>Google / Ron Amadeo</p></figcaption>  </figure>

  




<!-- cache hit 101:single/related:37da5cc2bfd65206587bab305050774c -->

<p>Google News is known to most people as a big pile of web links, but it actually hosts magazines, too. Before the days of the Internet, a "magazine" was a big bundle of paper full of articles you could get shipped to your door, sort of like if you printed out a website. For a time, you could pay cold, hard cash for a digital copy of a paper magazine through Google and then view that content through whatever the latest Google magazine/news app was.</p>
<p>Magazine content sales were shut down <a href="https://www.androidpolice.com/2020/01/03/google-news-killing-digital-magazines-refunds-subscriptions/">in 2020</a>, though, and soon, Google's magazine content will no longer be hosted online. The <a href="https://support.google.com/googlenews/thread/243673441/an-update-to-google-news-magazine-support">company announced</a> on a support page that purchased content will be shut down starting December 18. You can see if you have purchased (or freebie) magazines at <a href="https://news.google.com/my/magazines">this link</a>.</p>
<p>Let's see if we can put on our "Google archeology" hats and figure out where this all came from. Google started selling magazines in 2012 with "<a href="https://www.androidpolice.com/2012/06/27/google-play-store-updated-to-bring-new-tv-shows-magazines-and-movies-for-purchase/">Google Play Magazines</a>." You could buy individual magazine issues for around $8 or subscribe yearly for $11. These were all hosted by Google, with access available through the app and web. One year later, in 2013, Play Magazines was merged with another Google news app, Google Currents, to create <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2013/11/google-launches-play-newsstand-a-hybrid-magazine-store-and-rss-reader/">Google Play Newsstand</a>. Newsstand featured paid magazines and free website content. Google spent 2013–2016 rolling out purchasing support across more and more countries.</p>                                            
                                                        
<figure><a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/floorp_gdyDUPo63u.jpg" data-height="1011" data-width="1622" alt="A magazine on Google News."><img alt="A magazine on Google News." src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/floorp_gdyDUPo63u-980x611.jpg" width="980" height="611"></a><figcaption><p><a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/floorp_gdyDUPo63u.jpg" data-height="1011" data-width="1622">Enlarge</a> <span>/</span> A magazine on Google News.</p><p>Google</p></figcaption></figure>
<p>By 2018, Play Newsstand <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2018/05/the-revamped-google-news-app-is-now-available-on-iphones-and-ipads/">was replaced</a> by the first "Google News" app, a long-overdue entry in the Google app portfolio given how much of a powerhouse Google News has been online. The new app focused more on online content but kept a spot for your magazine subscriptions. The Android Google News app still has the same package name from 2012: "com.google.android.apps.magazines."</p>
<p>With sales of new magazines dead in 2020, it was only a matter of time until Google shut down the hosting of old, purchased magazine content. The good news is that you can download a PDF of your purchased magazine before December 18. Anyone who has purchased magazine content should be getting an email with an option to download or, for some magazines, request a refund.</p>
<p>Google says that some magazines will be refund-eligible because they "contain interactive elements that cannot be downloaded and saved for future access." December 18 isn't just the date for the hosting shutdown, but also the deadline for downloads or refund requests.</p>
<p>Offering a PDF download is better than nothing, but static PDFs are a lot more cumbersome and miserable than the slick user experience Google's original magazine offering had across all your devices. Remember, all online content purchases are really just rentals.</p>

                                                </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ethernet Is Still Going Strong After 50 Years (313 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://spectrum.ieee.org/ethernet-ieee-milestone</link>
            <guid>38302283</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 11:53:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/ethernet-ieee-milestone">https://spectrum.ieee.org/ethernet-ieee-milestone</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38302283">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-headline="Ethernet is Still Going Strong After 50 Years" data-elid="2666289566" data-post-url="https://spectrum.ieee.org/ethernet-ieee-milestone" data-authors="Joanna Goodrich" data-page-title="Ethernet is Still Going Strong After 50 Years - IEEE Spectrum"><p>The <a href="https://www.xerox.com/en-us" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Xerox</a>&nbsp;<a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/xerox-parc" target="_self">Palo Alto Research Center</a> in California has spawned many pioneering computer technologies including the <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/xerox-alto" target="_self">Alto</a>—the first personal computer to use a graphical user interface—and the first laser printer.</p><p>The PARC facility also is known for the invention of <a href="https://ethw.org/Ethernet" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Ethernet</a>, a networking technology that allows high-speed data transmission over coaxial cables. Ethernet has become the standard wired local area network around the world, and it is widely used in businesses and homes. It was honored this year as an <a href="https://ieeemilestones.ethw.org/Milestone-Proposal:Ethernet_Local_Area_Network_(LAN),_1973-1985" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">IEEE Milestone</a>, a half century after it was born.</p><h2>Connecting PARC’s Alto computers</h2><p> Ethernet’s development began in 1973, when <a href="https://amturing.acm.org/award_winners/thacker_1336106.cfm" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Charles P. Thacker</a>—who was working on the design of the Alto computer—envisioned a network that would allow Altos to communicate with each other, as well as with laser printers and with PARC’s gateway to the <a href="https://ethw.org/ARPANET" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">ARPANET</a>. PARC researcher <a href="https://ethw.org/Robert_M._Metcalfe" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Robert M. Metcalfe</a>, an IEEE Fellow, took on the challenge of creating the technology. Metcalfe soon was joined by computer scientist <a href="https://ethw.org/David_Boggs" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">David Boggs</a>.</p><p>Metcalfe and Boggs had two criteria: The network had to be fast enough to support their laser printer, and it had to connect hundreds of computers within the same building.</p><p>The Ethernet design was inspired by the <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/alohanet-introduced-random-access-protocols-to-the-computing-world" target="_self">Additive Links On-line Hawaii Area network</a> (ALOHAnet), a radio-based system at the <a href="https://www.hawaii.edu/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">University of Hawai’i</a>. Computers transmitted packets, prefaced by the addresses of the recipients, over a shared channel as soon as they had information to send. If two messages collided, the computers that had sent them would wait a random interval and try again. </p><p>Metcalfe outlined his proposal, then called the Alto Aloha Network, in a <a href="https://ieeemilestones.ethw.org/w/images/a/af/Ref1_PARC_Ethernet_Memo_1973.pdf" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">now-famous memo</a> to his colleagues. Using coaxial cables rather than radio waves would allow faster transmission of data and limit interference. The cables also meant that users could join or exit the network without having to shut off the entire system, Metcalfe said in a 2004 <a href="https://ethw.org/Oral-History:Robert_Metcalfe" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">oral history</a> conducted by the <a href="https://www.ieee.org/about/history-center/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">IEEE History Center</a>.</p><p>“There was something called a cable television tap, which allows one to tap into a coax without cutting it,” Metcalfe said. “Therefore, [Boggs and I] chose coax as our means of communication. In [the] memo, I described the principles of operation—very distributed, no central control, a single piece of ‘ether.’”</p><p>Metcalfe and Boggs designed the first version of what is now known as Ethernet in 1973. It sent data at up to 2.94 megabits per second and was “fast enough to feed the laser printer and easy to send through the coax,” Metcalfe told the IEEE History Center.</p><p>A 9.5-millimeter thick and stiff coaxial cable was laid in the middle of a hall in the PARC building. The 500-meter cable had 100 transceiver nodes attached to it with N connectors, known as vampire taps. Each of the taps—small boxes with a hard shell—had two probes that “bit” through the cable’s outer insulation to contact its copper core. Thus new nodes could be added while existing connections were live.</p><p>Each vampire tap had a D-type connector socket in it, consisting of a plug with nine pins that matched to a socket with nine jacks. The sockets allowed Alto computers, printers, and file servers to attach to the network.</p><p>To enable the devices to communicate, Metcalfe and Boggs created the first high-speed network interface card (NIC)—a circuit board that is connected to a computer’s motherboard. It included what is now known as an Ethernet port.</p><p>The researchers changed the name from the original Alto Aloha Network to Ethernet to make it clearer that the system could support any computer. It reflected a comment Thacker had made early on, that “coaxial cable is nothing but captive ether,” PARC researcher <a href="https://amturing.acm.org/award_winners/kay_3972189.cfm" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Alan Kay</a>&nbsp;<a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/xerox-parc" target="_self">recalled</a>.</p><p>Metcalfe, Boggs, Thacker, and <a href="https://amturing.acm.org/award_winners/lampson_1142421.cfm" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Butler W. Lampson</a> were granted a U.S. patent in 1978 for their invention.</p><p>They continued to develop the technology and, in 1980, PARC released Ethernet that ran at 10 Mb/s. The update was done in collaboration with researchers at <a href="https://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/homepage.html" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Intel</a> and the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_Equipment_Corporation" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Digital Equipment Corp.</a> (DEC) to create a version of Ethernet for broad industry use, according to the Milestone entry.</p><h2>Becoming an IEEE standard</h2><p>Ethernet became commercially available in 1980 and quickly grew into the industry LAN standard. To provide computer companies with a framework for the technology, in June 1983 Ethernet was adopted as a standard by the <a href="https://grouper.ieee.org/groups/802/es-ecsg/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">IEEE 802 Local Area Network Standards Committee</a>.</p><p>Currently, the <a href="https://www.ieee802.org/#:~:text=The%20IEEE%20802%20LAN%2FMAN,them%20on%20a%20global%20basis." rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">IEEE 802</a> family consists of 67 published standards, with 49 projects under development. The committee works with standards agencies worldwide to publish certain IEEE 802 standards as international guidelines. </p><p>A plaque recognizing the technology is displayed outside the PARC facility. It reads:</p><p><em>Ethernet wired LAN was invented at Xerox Palo Alto Research Center (PARC) in 1973, inspired by the ALOHAnet packet radio network and the ARPANET. In 1980 Xerox, DEC, and <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/intel">Intel</a> published a specification for 10 Mbps Ethernet over coaxial cable that became the IEEE 802.3-1985 Standard. Later augmented for higher speeds, and twisted-pair, optical, and wireless media, Ethernet became ubiquitous in home, commercial, industrial, and academic settings worldwide.</em></p><p>Administered by the IEEE History Center and <a href="https://www.ieeefoundation.org/donate_history" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">supported by donors</a>, the Milestone program recognizes outstanding technical developments around the world.</p><p>The <a href="https://ieeescv.org/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">IEEE Santa Clara Valley Section</a> sponsored the nomination. At press time, the dedication ceremony was still being planned.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Chrome Users Beware: Manifest V3 Is Deceitful and Threatening – EFF (405 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2021/12/chrome-users-beware-manifest-v3-deceitful-and-threatening</link>
            <guid>38301801</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 10:46:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2021/12/chrome-users-beware-manifest-v3-deceitful-and-threatening">https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2021/12/chrome-users-beware-manifest-v3-deceitful-and-threatening</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38301801">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <article role="article">
  
  
  <div><p><span>Manifest V3, Google Chrome’s soon-to-be definitive basket of changes to the world of web browser extensions, has been framed by its authors as “a step in the direction of privacy, security, and performance.” But we think these changes are a raw deal for users.&nbsp; </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2019/07/googles-plans-chrome-extensions-wont-really-help-security" title="We've said that"><span>We’ve said that</span></a><span> since Manifest V3 was announced, and </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/am/deeplinks/2021/11/manifest-v3-open-web-politics-sheeps-clothing"><span>continue to say so</span></a><span> as its implementation is now imminent. Like </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2021/03/googles-floc-terrible-idea"><span>FLoC</span></a><span> and </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2019/08/dont-play-googles-privacy-sandbox-1"><span>Privacy Sandbox</span></a><span> before it, Manifest V3 is another example of the inherent conflict of interest that comes from Google controlling both the dominant web browser and one of the largest internet advertising networks.</span></p>
<p><span>Manifest V3, or Mv3 for short, is outright harmful to privacy efforts. It will restrict the capabilities of web extensions—especially those that are designed to monitor, modify, and compute alongside the conversation your browser has with the websites you visit. Under the new specifications, extensions like these– like some privacy-protective tracker blockers– will have greatly reduced capabilities. Google’s efforts to limit that access is concerning, especially considering that </span><a href="https://spreadprivacy.com/biggest-tracker-networks/"><span>Google has trackers installed on 75% of the top one million websites</span></a><span>.</span></p>
<p><span>It’s also doubtful Mv3 will do much for security. Firefox maintains the largest extension market that’s not based on Chrome, and the company has said it will adopt Mv3 in the interest of cross-browser compatibility. Yet, at the </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tpDFS-GUytg&amp;t=416s"><span>2020 AdBlocker Dev Summit</span></a><span>, Firefox’s Add-On Operations Manager said about the extensions security review process: “For malicious add-ons, we feel that for Firefox it has been at a manageable level....since the add-ons are mostly interested in grabbing bad data, they can still do that with the current webRequest API that is not blocking.” In plain English, this means that when a malicious extension sneaks through the security review process, it is usually interested in simply observing the conversation between your browser and whatever websites you visit. The malicious activity happens elsewhere, after the data has already been read. A more thorough review process could improve security, but Chrome hasn’t said they’ll do that. Instead, their solution is to restrict capabilities for all extensions.</span></p>
<p><span>As for Chrome’s other justification for Mv3– performance– </span><a href="https://kevin.borgolte.me/files/pdf/www2020-privacy-extensions.pdf"><span>a 2020 study by researchers at Princeton and the University of Chicago revealed that privacy extensions</span></a><span>, the very ones that will be hindered by Mv3, actually improve browser performance. <br></span></p>
<p><span>The development specifications of web browser extensions may seem in the weeds, but the broader implications should matter to all internet citizens: it’s another step towards Google defining how we get to live online. Considering that Google has been </span><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/media/2017/may/02/google-and-facebook-bring-in-one-fifth-of-global-ad-revenue"><span>the world’s largest advertising company</span></a><span> for years now, these new limitations are paternalistic and downright creepy.</span></p>
<p><span><a id="MV3quotes"></a>But don’t just take our words for it. Here are some thoughts from technologists, privacy advocates, and extension developers who share our concern over Manifest V3:</span></p>
<blockquote><p><i><span>"A web browser is supposed to act on behalf of the user and respect the user's interests. Unfortunately, Chrome now has a track record as a Google agent, not a user agent. It is the only major web browser that lacks meaningful privacy protections by default, shoves users toward linking activity with a Google Account, and implements invasive new advertising capabilities. Google's latest changes will break Chrome privacy extensions, despite academic research demonstrating that no change is necessary. These user-hostile decisions are all directly attributable to Google's surveillance business model and enabled by its dominance of the desktop browser market." <br></span></i></p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><span>Jonathan Mayer, Princeton University</span></li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><i><span>“Manifest V3 positions Chrome as the all-powerful arbiter of what software lives and what dies, shattering the ideal of a diverse array of extensions serving the legitimate preferences and values of equally diverse users. In 2017, when </span></i><a href="https://adnauseam.io/free-adnauseam.html"><i><span>Google banned AdNauseam</span></i></a><i><span> from the Chrome store, it summarily cut off tens of thousands of users from data they had accumulated, and deprived them of a free and open-source extension to counter online profiling and manipulation. In hindsight, AdNauseam was the canary in the coal mine, as Mv3 is now poised to cut off users from a range of invaluable privacy tools (including ad blockers) that thousands if not millions rely on. A browser that plays favorites to advance its owners’ interests effectively chokes out innovative, independent developers, while shrinking the options for individuals to shape their online experiences.”</span></i></p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><span>Helen Nissenbaum and Daniel Howe (creators of AdNauseam and TrackMeNot)</span></li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><i><span>“Manifest V3 is a detrimental step back for internet privacy.”</span></i></p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.ghostery.com/blog/manifest-v3-the-ghostery-perspective"><span>Ghostery</span></a><span> company blog</span><span></span></li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><em><span>“</span><span>Manifest V3 is an opinionated specification; it enforces limitations to improve user experience. That looks good on paper, but the reality is quite different. We at Ghostery believe that Google's Manifest V3 harms privacy protecting extensions.</span></em></p>
<p><em><span>Instead of requiring service workers and removing blocking webRequest, Google should make service workers and declarativeNetRequest optional, providing solutions fit for different use cases. Ultimately, this is about user choice and innovation.</span></em></p>
<p><em><span>Instead of having to reinvent the wheel, we at Ghostery would like to focus on finding new ways to prevent tracking. This is after all what browser extensions are and should be, a playing field for innovation and the express lane for browser enhancement.</span><span>”</span></em></p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><span>Krzysztof Modras, director of engineering and product at </span><a href="https://www.ghostery.com/"><span>Ghostery</span></a></li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><i><span>“Nearly all browser extensions as you know them today will be affected in some way: the more lucky ones will ‘only’ experience problems, some will get crippled, and some will literally cease to exist.”</span></i></p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><span>Andrey Meshkov, </span><a href="https://adguard.com/en/blog/manifestv3-timeline.html"><span>AdGuard</span></a><span> company blog</span><span></span></li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><em><span>“</span><span>Of all the browser extension API revolutions I've seen in 16 years of NoScript development, Manifest V3 is the worst offender by a long shot: a huge step backwards, and a poorly justified one. Manifest V3 shrinks extension capabilities and Web users' freedom to customize their browsing experience.</span></em></p>
<p><em><span>While there are many reasons to doubt the claimed privacy improvements and the theoretical performance gains, the disruption for existing extensions is painfully real: non-trivial extensions will need to be rewritten, in cases forced to abandon fundamental features.</span></em></p>
<p><em><span>But even worse is the severe crunch on browser extensions developers' ability to innovate, and, in the case of privacy and security extensions, to respond to emerging threats promptly and creatively. The net loss is huge, for developers but most importantly for web users' online safety and freedom of choice.</span><span><i>”</i></span></em></p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><span>Giorgio Maone, author of </span><a href="https://noscript.net/"><span>NoScript</span></a></li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><i><span>“For SingleFile, I consider the migration to Manifest V3 to be a major regression from a functional and technical point of view. It also undermines some of the work done. Unfortunately, it doesn't bring any gains in return for the users. It is the very example of the collateral damage the Manifest V3 can cause.”</span></i></p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><span>Gildas, author of </span><a href="https://github.com/gildas-lormeau/SingleFile"><span>SingleFile</span></a></li>
</ul>

<h4><strong>More Information</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2021/12/googles-manifest-v3-still-hurts-privacy-security-innovation">Google’s Manifest V3 Still Hurts Privacy, Security, and Innovation</a></li>
<li>

</li>
<li>

</li>
</ul>

</div>

          </article>
    </div><div>
          <h2>Join EFF Lists</h2>
        
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Lack of Compensation in Open Source Software Is Unsustainable (223 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://trstringer.com/oss-compensation-broken/</link>
            <guid>38301710</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 10:33:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://trstringer.com/oss-compensation-broken/">https://trstringer.com/oss-compensation-broken/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38301710">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>It’s 11:43pm on a Monday night. My 6-week-old son is asleep in my office so my wife can get some uninterrupted rest for the first half of the night. He’s finally asleep now, and I probably should be also after a full day of work. But I’m not done for the day. Even though I’m a software engineer by trade, I’m also a computer programmer by hobby and passion. So I do what I’ve been doing for well over a decade now: I boot up my computer to write some code.</p><p>What to do, what to do… Learn something new? Maybe. Write a blog post? Well… here I am. But… in the back of my mind I know that I have open source projects that need some attention. One happens to be heavily used. I’m nearly 3/4 million downloads, and it’s something that people seem to think has some level of usefullness. Those are the good parts. The bad parts are that there’s a dozen issues that I haven’t even reviewed much less triaged, investigated, and fixed. There are a few PRs from the community that I need to look through. There are dependencies that need to be updated. The list goes on and on. This project has hit a not-so-uncommon OSS milestone: Maintainer burnout.</p><h2 id="what-compels-all-software-builders">What compels all software builders</h2><p>I’m certainly not alone in my pursuits of writing software. And with the fear of overgeneralizing a massive group of us software craftspeople, I think the effort we put into software is a simple equation:</p><p><code>time = passion + money</code></p><p>Every hour we spend writing code is because of some combination of passion and money. Both of those can be zero, but the other part must be great enough to compensate the zeroed value. Let’s see me as an example:</p><p><img src="https://trstringer.com/images/oss-is-broken1.png" alt="Time and money"></p><p>My job as a software engineer is great. They give me money to write code. I’m also super lucky that I have a high level of passion for the code I write and the things I build. There’s also a high level of demand on my work. That’s a massive win! I’m lucky. Others may have low or no passion for their work, but their compensation keeps them coming back on Monday morning at 9am. That’s totally fine too!</p><p>Let’s see some of my other current projects. My blog, this blog, is one of them. I don’t get money, but I have a bit of passion with it and that matches the demand well enough. Then there is <code>passion project</code>, which I get no money from but I’m pretty stoked about so my motivation is pretty high. And there’s no demand, so I go at my own pace and take it whatever direction I want!</p><p>And then finally, there’s my <code>uninteresting (to me) OSS project</code>. What once resembled <code>passion project</code> is now unrecognizable from a motivation perspective. But the demand is high. There are lots of users, many in a corporate sense using my software to further progress their organization. And the bad news is, I get no money at all from it. So motivation is essentially nonexistent at this point. Where passion is falling short, money <em>could</em> motivate me to routinely work on this product.</p><h2 id="whats-really-going-on">What’s really going on?</h2><p>This all boils down to a situation where you have many profit-generating companies using software that some programmer volunteered to write. That software contributes to that company making even more money. But the developer sees none of it because they are just an author on some git commits, and aren’t on the company’s payroll.</p><p>This is Volunteering as a Service (VaaS). It is quite literally a free lunch at the expense of hard-working individuals.</p><p>That’s pretty dark, so let me bring that back a little bit. It is not all companies treating OSS this way. And even the ones that are, I would be willing to bet that 99% of these companies don’t neglect compensation out of malice. The OSS system is just entirely not equipped to facilitate these companies to pay contributors.</p><h2 id="whats-the-solution">What’s the solution?</h2><p>So that problem statement isn’t new. It has bounced around often and in many forms. So what do <em>I</em> think could be a solution? Open source software developers should have compensation that follows this:</p><p><code>money = contributions * usage</code></p><p>If you are an active contributor on a product with high utilization, the payout should reflect that. Likewise, if you’ve submitted a couple of commits on a product that nobody uses, the money (or lack thereof) should represent that. But it’s not that simple, because there are different types of open source software developers out there. Some write OSS code as part of their employment, in which case they are likely already compensated for their contributions. It comes in their checks twice a month. But the other type of OSS developer is the one that is making those OSS contributors after hours and not affiliated with an organization.</p><p>OSS-using companies should be funding these projects. After all, they are using them. And even though they aren’t forced to buy licenses from SomeClosedSourceSoftwareCompany, that doesn’t mean that they <em>shouldn’t</em> be contributing.</p><h2 id="how-can-companies-contribute">How can companies contribute?</h2><p>The obvious answer is money. The less obvious answer is with developer time. This is quite common. Companies might have employees full or part time contributing to open source software projects. A great example of this is <a href="https://k8s.devstats.cncf.io/d/9/companies-table?orgId=1">Kubernetes, and all the developers that contribute to Kubernetes on company time</a>. Those companies in that list (Google, Red Hat, VMware, and Microsoft to name the top ones) <em>are</em> contributing to the success of those projects. They’re giving developer time.</p><p>When a company doesn’t contribute any or enough developer time to the projects, they should be supplementing with money that is distributed to those OSS developers that <em>aren’t</em> representing their company. Enterprise compensation should resemble the following:</p><p><code>compensation = developers + money</code></p><p>Here’s another way to look at this:</p><p><img src="https://trstringer.com/images/oss-is-broken2.png" alt="OSS is broken"></p><p>All three of these companies are responsibly contributing to the OSS product, but in different ways. <code>company1</code> contributes both money and developer time, <code>company2</code> sends just money, and finally <code>company3</code> provides adequate developers to the project. <code>company3</code> is the Googles or Microsofts of Kubernetes.</p><h2 id="how-do-dependencies-get-compensated">How do dependencies get compensated?</h2><p>Quick, name all the dependencies of Kubernetes. You can’t, and I can’t either. There’s just too many. It shouldn’t be only end user facing products that get appropriate compensation. It should be these products that send a portion of their contributions (money and developer time) down to these dependencies in a big happy tree of contributions.</p><h2 id="why-is-this-so-hard">Why is this so hard?</h2><p>There is a lot of challenges to this. And these are only the things I <em>thought</em> of. I’m sure in reality it’s even more complicated. That’s why I don’t think the moral reponsibility at the moment falls on these companies. There needs to be a system in place that handles the contributions from users and distributes them to projects and dependency projects. It’s just too complicated to do otherwise. <code>company2</code> can wake up one day and say “I want to do the right thing and compensate OSS developers.” But… uhhhh… where do they send the money to? I have no clue. There is nobody to send it to without adding a <em>ton</em> of overhead, which isn’t fair to anybody. And no, I don’t think GitHub Sponsors is the answer to this.</p><h2 id="summarizing">Summarizing</h2><p>Hopefully one day we do figure out how to fairly compensate open source software builders. It’s the right thing to do, and I don’t know anybody (including these companies) that would argue that point. We’re all in this big software world together.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA['Energy independent' Uruguay runs on 100% renewables for four straight months (321 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://theprogressplaybook.com/2023/10/19/energy-independent-uruguay-runs-on-100-renewables-for-four-straight-months/</link>
            <guid>38301480</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 09:52:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://theprogressplaybook.com/2023/10/19/energy-independent-uruguay-runs-on-100-renewables-for-four-straight-months/">https://theprogressplaybook.com/2023/10/19/energy-independent-uruguay-runs-on-100-renewables-for-four-straight-months/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38301480">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-id="74b4dcf" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="theme-post-content.default">
			
<p>Renewables alone have powered the Uruguayan economy for nearly four straight months.</p>



<p>In the three months to end-September 2023, the South American nation generated all of its electricity from renewable sources — with wind the single-biggest contributor, according to data from the country’s electricity market operator. And as of October 25, it’s on track to extend that streak by another month.</p>



<p>Uruguay hit the same milestone in 2022 during the spring months. But it had to turn back to fossil fuels — in the form of imported oil — over the summer period when a historic drought curbed hydro output. The polluting fuel accounted for roughly 10% of the power mix through 2022.</p>



<p><strong>How it got here:</strong>&nbsp;Uruguay used to rely almost entirely on hydro- and oil &amp; gas-based power. But as the economy grew and electricity demand threatened to overtake supply from the early 2010s, it needed to add additional generating capacity, and fast. New hydro wasn’t an option as it had already made the most of that resource.</p>



<p>To chart the way forward, the president appointed Ramón Méndez Galain, a particle physicist from the private sector, as the country’s director of energy — a position he held until 2015.</p>



<p>In a&nbsp;<a href="https://kleinmanenergy.upenn.edu/podcast/how-uruguay-went-almost-completely-fossil-fuel-free/">podcast discussion</a>&nbsp;with the Kleinman Center for Energy Policy, Méndez Galain said one of his primary goals was to make Uruguay less reliant on volatile imported oil &amp; gas. The quest for energy independence made him rule out nuclear power, which would’ve require uranium imports.</p>



<p>A decision was ultimately made to better exploit the country’s ample solar, wind, water and biomass waste resources.</p>



<p>Because the state couldn’t fund a massive energy programme alone, it ran a series of clean power auctions, where it offered project developers 20-year contracts to sell electricity into the national grid at guaranteed rates.</p>



<p>In just five years, $6 billion was invested in renewable energy — the equivalent of 12% of Uruguay’s GDP.</p>



<p><strong>The results:</strong>&nbsp;Power production costs have declined “by almost half”, according to Méndez Galain. And the clean energy sector has created 50,000 new jobs — the equivalent of 3% of the labour force. Further, Uruguay has become a net exporter of electricity.</p>



<p>The rapid increase in wind power capacity has largely displaced oil use, even as electricity demand has steadily grown. Between 2017 and 2020, renewables made up 97% of the electricity mix and oil &amp; gas just 3%.</p>



<p>“You become independent of all these kinds of wars or other geopolitical events,” Méndez Galain said.</p>



<p>“Ask me what was the impact on the electricity sector in Uruguay after this tragic war in Europe — zero. We have no impact because we’re not dependent on energy commodities.”</p>
		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[UnitedHealth uses AI model with 90% error rate to deny care, lawsuit alleges (145 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/health/2023/11/ai-with-90-error-rate-forces-elderly-out-of-rehab-nursing-homes-suit-claims/</link>
            <guid>38299921</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 05:25:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/health/2023/11/ai-with-90-error-rate-forces-elderly-out-of-rehab-nursing-homes-suit-claims/">https://arstechnica.com/health/2023/11/ai-with-90-error-rate-forces-elderly-out-of-rehab-nursing-homes-suit-claims/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38299921">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <header>
            <h4>
      despicable     —
</h4>
            
            <h2 itemprop="description">For the largest health insurer in the US, AI's error rate is like a feature, not a bug.</h2>
                    </header>
        <section>
            <div itemprop="articleBody">
                                    
<figure>
  <img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/GettyImages-1543156724-800x533.jpeg" alt="UnitedHealthcare (UHC) health insurance company signage is displayed on an office building in Phoenix on July 19, 2023.">
      <figcaption><p><a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/GettyImages-1543156724-scaled.jpeg" data-height="1707" data-width="2560">Enlarge</a> <span>/</span> UnitedHealthcare (UHC) health insurance company signage is displayed on an office building in Phoenix on July 19, 2023.</p></figcaption>  </figure>

  




<!-- cache hit 92:single/related:1370c992e84e2c6e4e3bcb4cfc8a7d63 --><!-- empty -->
<p>UnitedHealthcare, the largest health insurance company in the US, is allegedly using a deeply flawed AI algorithm to override doctors' judgments and wrongfully deny critical health coverage to elderly patients. This has resulted in patients being kicked out of rehabilitation programs and care facilities far too early, forcing them to drain their life savings to obtain needed care that should be covered under their government-funded Medicare Advantage Plan.</p>
<p>That's all according to <a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/class-action-v-unitedhealth-and-navihealth-1.pdf">a lawsuit</a> filed this week in the US District Court for the District of Minnesota. The lawsuit is brought by the estates of two deceased people who were denied health coverage by UnitedHealth. The suit also seeks class-action status for similarly situated people, of which there may be tens of thousands across the country.</p>
<p>The lawsuit lands alongside <a href="https://www.statnews.com/2023/11/14/unitedhealth-algorithm-medicare-advantage-investigation/">an investigation by Stat News</a> that largely backs the lawsuit's claims. The investigation's findings stem from internal documents and communications the outlet obtained, as well as interviews with former employees of NaviHealth, the UnitedHealth subsidiary that developed the AI algorithm called nH Predict.</p>
<p>"By the end of my time at NaviHealth I realized: I'm not an advocate, I'm just a moneymaker for this company," Amber Lynch, an occupational therapist and former NaviHealth case manager, told Stat. "It's all about money and data points," she added. 'It takes the dignity out of the patient, and I hated that."</p>
<h2>AI-based denials</h2>
<p>According to the lawsuit, UnitedHealth started using nH Predict in at least November 2019, and it is still in use. The algorithm estimates how much post-acute care a patient on a Medicare Advantage Plan will need after an acute injury, illness, or event, like a fall or a stroke. Post-acute care can include things like therapy and skilled care from home health agencies, skilled nursing homes, and inpatient rehabilitation centers.</p>                                            
                                                        
<p>It's unclear how nH Predict works exactly, but it reportedly estimates post-acute care by pulling information from a database containing medical cases from 6 million patients. NaviHealth case managers plug in certain information about a given patient—including age, living situation, and physical functions—and the AI algorithm spits out estimates based on similar patients in the database. The algorithm estimates medical needs, length of stay, and discharge date.</p>
<p>But Lynch noted to Stat that the algorithm doesn't account for many relevant factors in a patient's health and recovery time, including comorbidities and things that occur during stays, like if they develop pneumonia while in the hospital or catch COVID-19 in a nursing home.</p>
<p>According to the Stat investigation and the lawsuit, the estimates are often draconian. For instance, on a Medicare Advantage Plan, patients who stay in a hospital for three days are typically entitled to up to 100 days of covered care in a nursing home. But with nH Predict, patients rarely stay in nursing homes for more than 14 days before receiving payment denials from UnitedHealth.</p>
<p>When patients or their doctors have requested to see nH Predict's reports, UnitedHealth has denied their requests, telling them the information is proprietary, according to the lawsuit. And, when prescribing physicians disagree with UnitedHealth's determination of how much post-acute care their patients need, their judgments are overridden.</p>
<h2>Favorable failings</h2>
<p>The use of faulty AI is not new for the health care industry. While AI chatbots and image generators are currently grabbing headlines and causing alarm, the health care industry in the US has a longer record of problematic AI use, including establishing <a href="https://www.healthaffairs.org/content/forefront/medical-algorithms-failing-communities-color">algorithmic racial bias</a> in patient care. But, what sets this situation apart is that the dubious estimates nH Predict spits out seem to be a feature, not a bug, for UnitedHealth.</p>
<p>Since UnitedHealth acquired NaviHealth in 2020, former employees told Stat that the company's focus shifted from patient advocacy to performance metrics and keeping post-acute care as short and lean as possible. Various statements by UnitedHealth executives echoed this shift, Stat noted. In particular, the UnitedHealth executive overseeing NaviHealth, Patrick Conway, was quoted in a company podcast saying: "If [people] go to a nursing home, how do we get them out as soon as possible?"</p>

                                                </div>

            
                            <nav>Page: <span>1 <a href="https://arstechnica.com/health/2023/11/ai-with-90-error-rate-forces-elderly-out-of-rehab-nursing-homes-suit-claims/2/">2</a> <a href="https://arstechnica.com/health/2023/11/ai-with-90-error-rate-forces-elderly-out-of-rehab-nursing-homes-suit-claims/2/"><span>Next <span>→</span></span></a></span></nav>
            
        </section>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I analyzed Stack Overflow for secrets (187 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://matan-h.com/analyze-stackoverflow</link>
            <guid>38299888</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 05:18:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://matan-h.com/analyze-stackoverflow">https://matan-h.com/analyze-stackoverflow</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38299888">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      
        <header>
          
          

  <p>
    

    

    
      
      

      <span>
        
        
          3 minute read
        
      </span>
    
  </p>


        </header>
      

      <section itemprop="text">
        
        

<h2 id="backstory">backstory</h2>

<p>I read hackernews sometimes, and articles like <a href="https://py-code.org/stats">I mirrored all the code from PyPI to GitHub and analysed it</a> made me think, maybe there are less obvious places with leaked information.</p>

<p>This was in the back of my mind until recently, when I tried to <a href="https://github.com/kivy/buildozer/pull/1709">contribute</a> to the <a href="https://github.com/kivy/buildozer">buildozer</a> project. 
I implemented rich logs, and I felt like I understood buildozer, so I searched for <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/tags/buildozer">stackoverflow</a> questions about it. Then I discovered that buildozer, <a href="https://github.com/beeware/briefcase/blob/4db325af8381789ad5e049fb80bb4f03d1810208/src/briefcase/console.py#L402">unlike beeware</a> , actually dumps the <a href="https://github.com/kivy/buildozer/blob/dda7eaaf94d56813f48570b277752318555301f6/buildozer/logger.py#L81">full</a> environment when a command fails (for example output, see <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/66628535/facing-buildozer-error-stating-command-failed">this</a> old question), and thought “what if this user built the app with a sensitive api ?”</p>

<p><img src="https://matan-h.com/assets/images/stackoverflow-random-data2.webp" alt="screenshot of stackoverflow quistion with random (fake) ghp tokens instead of the buildozer logs. "></p>

<h2 id="parsing">parsing</h2>

<p>So, I downloaded stackOverflow from the <a href="https://archive.org/download/stackexchange">stackexchange archive.org dump</a>, and started to think how to parse it. It’s a huge (103G) XML file, where each line is a question or answer.</p>

<p>I tried different “leak detect” tools, most of them crashed or taking too much cpu:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>gitleaks : <code>fatal error: runtime: out of memory</code></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>truffleHog : Actually works (and takes 100% cpu), but giving very poor results (e.g. a simple <code>%s</code> is considered a SQL server base64 encoded: <code>Detector Type: SQLServer,Decoder Type: BASE64,Raw result: %s</code> ).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>ripsecrets : no output 1 hour after I run it.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>(Yelp) detect-secrets: <code>Traceback (most recent call last): ... MemoryError</code></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>ripgrep : freeze my system after few minutes.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>So I ended up returning to my zsh and doing <code>grep</code>  , and even writing a my own rust script to do the searches.</p>

<h2 id="results">results</h2>

<p>As I suspected , there are a lot of leaks in stackoverflow (on the graph, only unique and not junk data is displayed. click on a label to hide it ):</p>




<p>As you can see, a lot of data.</p>

<p>Then, I asked myself, what could an attacker do with this information? Turns out, most of it is useless:</p>

<p>For using most data, you need more information than just the api key. For example, for stripe , you need the customer ID. For grafana, an instance url. For aws, a site url.</p>

<p>And even if you have an api key which goes to a centralized location without need for a “username”, most of the data is old. All the JWTs (<a href="https://jwt.io/">JSON Web Tokens</a>) - forget about them, the average life of a JWT is a month.</p>

<p>Until I run a simple scan (again using the best hacking tools : <code>xargs</code> and <code>curl</code> ) against all the 74 real looking GitHub user tokens (which is a token that grants access to pretty much the full GitHub user) and discovered that 6 of them are actually valid.</p>

<p>Still, only 2 of them actually have bio and email, but one of them (a c/c++ developer)  has a repo with <code>3.4k</code> stars. So I finally found the path an attacker would take.</p>

<p>I sent both developers an email (I told them about this research and referred them to the question where they leak the token, with a little “if you find this message helpful, you can <a href="https://www.buymeacoffee.com/matanh">buy me a coffee</a>” at the end) and they both revoked the tokens (and both actually bought me a coffee, the first time I got money since I opened this buymeacoffee account in March 2021!).</p>

<p>I obviously couldn’t verify all the secrets. From most of them I’ll probably be banned,  so I stooped here.</p>

<h2 id="cause">cause</h2>

<p>Unlike PyPi and GitHub leaks articles, this article is not because of people leaving the password in their <code>deploy-to-server.py</code> and accidentally committing it (well, sometimes they copy <code>deploy-to-server-example.py</code> into stackoverflow and forget to mask the id …).</p>

<p>Most leaks are in the output of tools, a long output that people like to copy/paste right into stackoverflow, without actually looking at it,  because of people publish <strong>the output/ the tool config file</strong> of the tool they using (e.g. did you know that <code>curl -v</code> also displays your request with the headers, or that a long <code>package.json</code> with private dependencies can contain <code>git+your-private-gh-token</code> ? )</p>

<div>

  <pre><code>why is this not working?  I run this command curl -v --path-as-is 'https://matan-h.com/[redundant]'
and I get this output:
*   Trying 185.199.108.153:80...
* Connected to matan-h.com (185.199.108.153) port 80 (#0)
&gt; GET /404/../ddebug/../my-windows-shell/../list-of-online-converter-tools/../exec_python_code_super_secret_4h0a4b?code=print("hi") HTTP/1.1
&gt; Host: matan-h.com
&gt; User-Agent: curl/40.4.0
&gt; Accept: */*
&gt; Accept-Encoding: deflate, gzip, br
&gt;
&lt; HTTP/1.1 301 Moved Permanently
</code></pre>

</div>

<p>I hope you enjoyed the article, and pay more attention to what you copy/paste in StackOverflow.</p>

        
      </section>

      

      


      
  

    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[No Bing, no Edge, no upselling: De-crufted Windows 11 coming to Europe soon (289 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/11/europeans-can-soon-strip-bing-edge-other-microsoft-cruft-from-windows-11/</link>
            <guid>38298918</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 03:03:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/11/europeans-can-soon-strip-bing-edge-other-microsoft-cruft-from-windows-11/">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/11/europeans-can-soon-strip-bing-edge-other-microsoft-cruft-from-windows-11/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38298918">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <h4>
      Digital Markets Act    —
</h4>
            
            <h2 itemprop="description">Some changes will arrive for non-EU users, too, but not the easy removals.</h2>
                    </div><div itemprop="articleBody">
                                    
<figure>
  <img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/win11-exhausting-800x450.jpg" alt="Windows 11 with a number of advertising pushes opened simultaneously">
      <figcaption><div><p><a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/win11-exhausting.jpg" data-height="1440" data-width="2560">Enlarge</a> <span>/</span> Users in the extended European Economic Area will soon be able to avoid most of the things that <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/11/europeans-can-soon-strip-bing-edge-other-microsoft-cruft-from-windows-11/%22https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/08/windows-11-has-made-the-clean-windows-install-an-oxymoron/%22">feel so exhausting about Windows 11</a>.</p></div><p>Andrew Cunningham</p></figcaption>  </figure>

  




<!-- cache hit 92:single/related:f82ceea55f6993117421e828afee04b9 --><!-- empty -->
<p>Using Windows these days means putting up with <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/08/windows-11-has-made-the-clean-windows-install-an-oxymoron/">many, many pitches to use and purchase other Microsoft products</a>. Some are subtle, like the built-in Edge browser suggesting you use its "recommended settings" after each major update. Some are not so subtle, like testing a "quiz" that made some users <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/11/microsoft-pulls-onedrive-update-that-would-quiz-you-before-letting-you-quit/">explain why they're trying to quit the OneDrive app</a>.</p>
<p>Those living in the <a href="https://www.gov.uk/eu-eea">European Economic Area (EEA)</a>—which includes the EU and adds Iceland, Liechtenstein, and Norway—will soon get the volume turned down on their Windows 11 systems. To meet the demands of <a href="https://digital-markets-act.ec.europa.eu/index_en">the European Commission's Digital Markets Act</a>—slated to be enforced in March 2024—Microsoft must make its apps easier to uninstall, its default settings easier to change, and its attempts at steering people toward its services easier to avoid.</p>
<p>Microsoft <a href="https://blogs.windows.com/windows-insider/2023/11/16/previewing-changes-in-windows-to-comply-with-the-digital-markets-act-in-the-european-economic-area/">writes in a blog post</a> that many of these changes will be available in a preview update of Windows 11 (version 23H2) this month. Windows 10 will get similar changes "at a later date." A couple of changes affect all Windows 10 and 11 users:</p>
<ul>
<li>Apps that are critical to Windows will be labeled with a "System" tag in Settings, the Start menu, and search results</li>
<li>Camera, Cortana, and Photos can now be uninstalled</li>
</ul>                                            
                                                        
<p>In the EEA, much more is on the way:</p>
<ul>
<li>Bing's web search from the Start menu and the Edge browser can be uninstalled</li>
<li>Third parties can add to the Windows Widgets Board feeds</li>
<li>Third parties, like Google or DuckDuckGo, can provide the built-in web search results that Bing once had exclusively</li>
<li>Windows users who choose to sync their Microsoft accounts will have their pinned apps and preferences synced, seemingly keeping their EEA-enabled choices</li>
<li>Windows will now "always use customers' configured app default settings for link and file types"</li>
</ul>
<p>Microsoft's post notes that Windows uses the region picked during Windows install to offer the EEA-exclusive options. Only a PC reset can undo the options. EEA Windows devices will also not get the <a href="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2023/11/bing-chat-is-now-microsoft-copilot-in-potentially-confusing-rebranding-move/">Microsoft Copilot preview</a> that is rolling out in other markets.</p>
<p>The Digital Markets Act's impending arrival <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2022/03/eu-to-regulate-gatekeepers-in-crackdown-on-google-apple-amazon-facebook/">will impact other major tech firms</a> that are considered "gatekeepers" providing "core platform services" that are "most prone to unfair business practices." Google has recently pitched the European Union on the idea of <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/11/google-argues-imessage-should-be-regulated-by-the-eus-digital-markets-act/">forcing Apple to make iMessage interoperable</a> under the Act. Apple has reportedly worked on changes to iOS that <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2022/12/report-apple-engineers-are-working-on-third-party-app-store-support-in-ios/">would allow "sideloading" apps</a> outside Apple's own App Store, while another provision in the Digital Markets Act would demand developers be able to use their preferred payments systems.</p>
<p>A companion piece of legislation focused on online platforms, the Digital Services Act, <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2023/04/google-runs-5-of-the-19-platforms-that-must-follow-eus-new-internet-rules/">will impact 19 platforms</a>, including five Google services, Meta-owned Facebook and Instagram, and Microsoft's Bing search engine. On Wednesday, Meta became the first platform to <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2023/11/meta-tiktok-fight-eu-gatekeeper-status-to-avoid-opening-up-services-to-rivals/">appeal its gatekeeper status</a> for its Messenger and Marketplace services, <a href="https://newsroom.tiktok.com/en-eu/appealing-our-gatekeeper-designation-under-the-digital-markets-act">followed shortly thereafter by TikTok</a>.</p>

                                                </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HTML Web Components: An Example (117 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.jim-nielsen.com/2023/html-web-components-an-example/</link>
            <guid>38298694</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 02:40:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.jim-nielsen.com/2023/html-web-components-an-example/">https://blog.jim-nielsen.com/2023/html-web-components-an-example/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38298694">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          
          <p>In <a href="https://blog.jim-nielsen.com/2023/html-web-components/">my article on HTML web components</a>, I said:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>But the unique power of web components (in the browser) is that they can render before JavaScript. React components cannot do this — full stop.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There’s a lot in there I wanted to explain more in-depth, but I just never go to it.</p>
<p>Then a reader kindly emailed me and asked:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>what do you mean? As far as I know, web components need a JS API to be defined. How can they run before JS?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That is a great question. Allow me to explain my thinking.</p>
<p>There are different ways to use web components.</p>
<p>One way of using them requires JavaScript in order for them to “run” and display anything in the browser.</p>
<p>An alternate way of using them allows you to display information/content in the browser before any JavaScript executes, and then you use web component structured JavaScript<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1">[1]</a></sup> to enhance what’s already on display.</p>
<p>In an attempt to explain this more, let’s use an simplified example.</p>
<p>Imagine we want to build a component for displaying a user’s avatar. It will be an image and, when hovered, it will display a tooltip that shows their full name.</p>
<p><img src="https://cdn.jim-nielsen.com/blog/2023/user-avatar-end-result.png" width="220" height="220" alt="Screenshot of a profile photo with a mouse cursor hovering over it and dispaying a name.">

</p><p>If you were building this in React, you could imagine a typical implementation looking something like this:</p>
<pre><code><span>import</span> <span>Tooltip</span> <span>from</span> <span>"3rd-party-tooltip-on-npm"</span>;

<span>function</span> <span>UserAvatar</span>(<span>{ src, name }</span>) {
  <span>const</span> [showTooltip, setShowTooltip] = <span>useState</span>(<span>false</span>);
  <span>return</span> (
    <span><span>&lt;<span>div</span>&gt;</span>
      <span>&lt;<span>img</span>
        <span>src</span>=<span>{src}</span>
        <span>alt</span>=<span>{</span>`<span>Profile</span> <span>photo</span> <span>of</span> ${<span>name</span>}`}
        <span>width</span>=<span>"32"</span>
        <span>height</span>=<span>"32"</span>
      /&gt;</span>
      {showTooltip &amp;&amp; <span>&lt;<span>Tooltip</span>&gt;</span>{name}<span>&lt;/<span>Tooltip</span>&gt;</span>}
    <span>&lt;/<span>div</span>&gt;</span></span>
  )
}

<span>/**
 * Example usage:
 *
 * &lt;UserAvatar
 *   src="https://www.jim-nielsen.com/.well-known/avatar"
 *   name="Jim Nielsen"
 * /&gt;
 */</span>
</code></pre>
<p>This is nice enough. But the point is: it requires JavaScript (React, <code>3rd-party-tooltip-on-npm</code>, your JS code) before <em>anything</em> will render in the browser. It’s an all-or-nothing approach. If any JavaScript fails to download, parse, and run, the end user will see absolutely nothing. This is what it will look like:</p>
<p><img src="https://cdn.jim-nielsen.com/blog/2023/user-avatar-blank.png" width="220" height="220" alt="Screenshot of a mouse cursor on a blank white screen.">

</p><p>Now, since this is a “component” and the web has components, couldn’t you port it to a web component and remove the dependency on React? Yes, you could. (Note: this code is not meant to be production ready, but illustrative.)</p>
<pre><code><span>&lt;<span>user-avatar</span>
  <span>src</span>=<span>"https://www.jim-nielsen.com/.well-known/avatar"</span>
  <span>name</span>=<span>"Jim Nielsen"</span>
&gt;</span><span>&lt;/<span>user-avatar</span>&gt;</span>

<span>&lt;<span>script</span>&gt;</span><span><span>
  class UserAvatar extends HTMLElement {
    connectedCallback() {
      const src = this.getAttribute("src");
      const name = this.getAttribute("name");
      this.innerHTML = `
        <span>&lt;<span>div</span>&gt;</span>
          <span>&lt;<span>img</span>
            <span>src</span>=<span>"${src}"</span>
            <span>alt</span>=<span>"Profile photo of ${name}"</span>
            <span>width</span>=<span>"32"</span>
            <span>height</span>=<span>"32"</span>
          /&gt;</span>
          <span>&lt;!-- Markup/code for the tooltip --&gt;</span>
        <span>&lt;/<span>div</span>&gt;</span>
      `;
    }
  }
  customElements.define('user-avatar', UserAvatar);
</span></span><span>&lt;/<span>script</span>&gt;</span>
</code></pre>
<p>You can see we have a web component that does something very similar to the React component but it doesn’t require React.</p>
<p>It does, however, still require JavaScript. If the user’s browser fails to download, parse, and run any JavaScript, nothing will display on screen. This is what they’ll see:</p>
<p><img src="https://cdn.jim-nielsen.com/blog/2023/user-avatar-blank.png" width="220" height="220" alt="Screenshot of a mouse cursor on a blank white screen.">

</p><p>This kind of approach to building web components, per the original question, has a dependence on JavaScript. This web component cannot display anything on screen without JavaScript. It is what I meant in <a href="https://blog.jim-nielsen.com/2023/html-web-components/">my original article</a> when I said “JavaScript web components”.</p>
<p>But there’s another approach to building web components.</p>
<p>This approach is what Jeremy called <a href="https://adactio.com/journal/20618">“HTML web components”</a>. It does not require JavaScript in order to provide basic functionality. But it does require the author of the component to step back and ask, “What am I trying to build here and how can I do it in a way that progressively enhances the end user’s experience?”</p>
<p>What we want to show to is a profile picture of the user. That shouldn’t require JavaScript, it’s just an <code>&lt;img&gt;</code>.</p>
<p>Is there a way for us to provide the basic functionality of <code>&lt;user-avatar&gt;</code> so that, before JavaScript loads (if it loads at all), the user still sees something?</p>
<p>With an approach that considers the idea of HTML web components, you can! Starting with the HTML, you could write something like this:</p>
<pre><code><span>&lt;<span>img</span>
  <span>src</span>=<span>"https://www.jim-nielsen.com/.well-known/avatar"</span>
  <span>alt</span>=<span>"Profile photo of Jim Nielsen"</span>
  <span>width</span>=<span>"32"</span>
  <span>height</span>=<span>"32"</span>
  <span>title</span>=<span>"Jim Nielsen"</span>
/&gt;</span>
</code></pre>
<p>Given this HTML, we have a profile photo with some meta information. Note the <code>title</code> attribute: this will display a tooltip on hover (in browsers that support it). So before any JavaScript has been downloaded, parsed, and run, a desktop browser could display something like:</p>
<p><img src="https://cdn.jim-nielsen.com/blog/2023/user-avatar-base.png" width="220" height="220" alt="Screenshot of a profile photo with a mouse cursor hovering over it displaying a browser-native tooltip.">

</p><p>Is it what we want our end result to look like? No. Will that tooltip work everywhere? No. Is this The Best Thing Ever™️? No.</p>
<p>But that’s not the point. The point is we’re starting with a baseline, core experience that will provide basic functionality and content to a wide array of user agents before any JavaScript is required.</p>
<p>Once you’ve done everything you can in vanilla HTML to provide core elements of your baseline experience, you can begin enhancing the existing markup with additional functionality.</p>
<p>This is where HTML web components shine. You can wrap that basic functionality in a custom element and then, <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Web_components/Using_custom_elements">using the JavaScript APIs of web components</a>, enhance the markup.</p>
<pre><code><span>&lt;<span>user-avatar</span>&gt;</span>
  <span>&lt;<span>img</span>
    <span>src</span>=<span>"https://www.jim-nielsen.com/.well-known/avatar"</span>
    <span>alt</span>=<span>"Profile photo of Jim Nielsen"</span>
    <span>width</span>=<span>"32"</span>
    <span>height</span>=<span>"32"</span>
    <span>title</span>=<span>"Jim Nielsen"</span>
  /&gt;</span>
<span>&lt;/<span>user-avatar</span>&gt;</span>
<span>&lt;<span>script</span>&gt;</span><span>
  <span>class</span> <span>UserAvatar</span> <span>extends</span> <span>HTMLElement</span> {
    <span>connectedCallback</span>(<span></span>) {
      <span>// Get the data for the component from exisiting markup</span>
      <span>const</span> $img = <span>this</span>.<span>querySelector</span>(<span>"img"</span>);
      <span>const</span> src = $img.<span>getAttribute</span>(<span>"src"</span>);
      <span>const</span> name = $img.<span>getAttribute</span>(<span>"title"</span>);

      <span>// Create the markup and event listeners for tooltip...</span>

      <span>// Append it to the DOM</span>
      <span>this</span>.<span>insertAdjacentHTML</span>(
        <span>'beforeend'</span>, 
        <span>'&lt;!-- code for tooltip here --&gt;'</span>
      );
    }
  }
  customElements.<span>define</span>(<span>'user-avatar'</span>, <span>UserAvatar</span>);
</span><span>&lt;/<span>script</span>&gt;</span>
</code></pre>
<p>Again, this code is for illustration purposes, but it shows how you can leverage HTML to provide the basic functionality of a component and then you enhance it with JavaScript.</p>
<p>Now you have something that works pretty decent. It displays <em>something</em> before JavaScript without any layout shift<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2">[2]</a></sup>. And if/when JavaScript loads, you get that nice experience we wanted from the get go.</p>
<p><img src="https://cdn.jim-nielsen.com/blog/2023/user-avatar-both.png" width="520" height="220" alt="Screenshot of a basic HTML profile photo with a `title` tooltip on the left, and an enhanced tooltip with a profile photo on the right.">

</p><p>Hopefully this answers the question of, “I thought web components required JavaScript? How can they run before JavaScript?”</p>
<p>It’s all about approach. Web components give you an approach of augmentation, where you can provide basic functionality and then progressively enhance the experience depending on the end user’s capabilities.</p>
<p>Endnote: I know, I know, there’s a whole lot more that could be said about all the above. For example, a JS framework like <a href="https://remix.run/">Remix</a> allows you to do something very similar to the above: provide basic HTML over the wire and then enhance (i.e. hydrate) that experience with JavaScript (i.e. React). RSC looks like it’ll do something similar — but that’s all a discussion for another day.</p>
<hr><ol><li id="fn:1">I wrote about <a href="https://blog.jim-nielsen.com/2023/web-components-icon-galleries/">how I used custom elements to structure my JavaScript and enhance markup</a>. Then Eric wrote <a href="https://meyerweb.com/eric/thoughts/2023/11/01/blinded-by-the-light-dom/">a thoughtful, lengthy post</a> on the same idea, but going way, way deeper into how web components can serve to structure and enhance your HTML, CSS, and JS. <a href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">↩</a></li><li id="fn:2"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=R4Ri4ft7bXY">Zach’s talk</a> is a great introduction to this idea of building web components in a way that delivers something useful in the initial HTML while also preventing layout shift as JavaScript enhances the markup with additional functionality — a very important UX detail IMO. <a href="#fnref:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text.">↩</a></li></ol>
        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google confirms they will disable uBlock Origin in Chrome in 2024 (216 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://old.reddit.com/r/uBlockOrigin/comments/17wu2gz/google_confirms_they_will_disable_ublock_origin/</link>
            <guid>38298502</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 02:17:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/uBlockOrigin/comments/17wu2gz/google_confirms_they_will_disable_ublock_origin/">https://old.reddit.com/r/uBlockOrigin/comments/17wu2gz/google_confirms_they_will_disable_ublock_origin/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38298502">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Yes, but ublock origin lite lacks a lot of features that actually makes ublock the best:</p>

<p><a href="https://preview.redd.it/lbgozpmljr0c1.png?width=649&amp;format=png&amp;auto=webp&amp;s=33863c01942ae5fda6de2a6e95995e76e3a29241" target="_blank">&lt;image&gt;</a></p>

<p>Source: <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/uBlockOrigin/comments/1067als/eli5_ublock_lite_vs_ublock_origin/">https://www.reddit.com/r/uBlockOrigin/comments/1067als/eli5_ublock_lite_vs_ublock_origin/</a></p>

<p>Not being able to update the filters without having to update the extension itself is a really big deal! I mean when ublock 1.53 came out, it took google almost a freaking week to finally allow the new version.</p>

<p>Why is that a big deal? Imagine that you have a site that you use a lot, that site then implements a way to detect adblock but you are stuck with ublock origin lite, in other words, you can't craft your own filter to by pass that site anti-adblocking(if you have the know how), you can't also come to ubo reddit to ask someone else to craft them for you and with that instantly solve the issue and you also don't have access to element picker which could also solve problem!</p>

<p>Now, the only thing you can do? Report the problem to ubo team, then wait until they add the new filter which will bypass the antiblock to the new version of ubo lite which you don't know when its getting released and after that you will have to wait until google authorizes the new update to be released which like I've said, takes several days!</p>

<p>Another example is youtube itself, if we were stuck with <strong>ubo lite</strong> right now, we would be losing the war against youtube anti-adblock badly! Because the only reason ubo is kinda able to keep up with youtube anti-adblocking is because after youtube updates their blocking script(which is every 12 hours), ubo team then updates their filters and then we as users just need to run the update manually inside the extension and boom we are back on business! Which won't be possible with ubo lite at all.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Portugal just ran on 100% renewables for six days in a row (332 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.canarymedia.com/articles/clean-energy/portugal-just-ran-on-100-renewables-for-six-days-in-a-row</link>
            <guid>38297805</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 00:49:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.canarymedia.com/articles/clean-energy/portugal-just-ran-on-100-renewables-for-six-days-in-a-row">https://www.canarymedia.com/articles/clean-energy/portugal-just-ran-on-100-renewables-for-six-days-in-a-row</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38297805">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p dir="ltr">One recent autumn afternoon, I&nbsp;watched the Atlantic gusts collide with the cliffs that rise above Nazaré, Portugal. Rain pelted down, and the world-renowned swells rose into walls of water that even the most <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GJc4Ir78KdE" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">death-defying surfers</a> reach only via Jet Ski. For me, this looked like a&nbsp;rained-out, late-season beach getaway, but for the sliver of Iberia that is Portugal, it looked like a&nbsp;bright future. That weekend, the nation of <span>10</span> million <a href="https://www.ren.pt/en-gb/media/news/portugal-has-been-using-green-electricity-for-over-24-hours" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ran on nothing but wind, solar and hydropower.&nbsp;</a></p>
<p dir="ltr">As it turned out, those rainy, blustery days were just a&nbsp;warmup. Portugal produced more than enough renewable power to serve all its customers for <a href="https://www.ren.pt/en-gb/media/news/renewable-energy-production-sets-new-records" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">six straight days</a>, from October <span>31</span> to November <span>6</span>.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><span>“</span>The gas plants were there, waiting to dispatch energy, should it be needed. It was not, because the wind was blowing; it was raining a&nbsp;lot,” said Hugo Costa, who oversees Portugal for <span>EDP</span> Renewables, the renewables arm of the state utility, which was <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/economy_finance/publications/occasional_paper/2012/pdf/ocp95_en.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">privatized in <span>2012</span></a>. <span></span>​<span>“</span>And we were producing with a&nbsp;positive impact to the consumers because the prices have dropped dramatically, almost to&nbsp;zero.”</p>
<p dir="ltr">To hit Paris Agreement climate goals by <span>2050</span>, nations need to run their grids without carbon emissions not just for three or six days, but year-round. A&nbsp;handful of countries already do this, thanks to generous endowments of hydropower, largely developed well before the climate crisis drove investment decisions for power plants. Others score highly on carbon-free power thanks to big fleets of nuclear plants.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Portugal falls into a&nbsp;different, more relatable bucket: It started its decarbonization journey with some legacy hydropower, but no nuclear capacity nor plans to build any. That meant it had to figure out how to cut fossil fuel use by maximizing new renewables.</p>
<p dir="ltr">How did Portugal make this happen? It committed to building renewables early and often, pledging a&nbsp;<span>2050</span> deadline for net-zero carbon emissions <a href="https://unfccc.int/sites/default/files/resource/RNC2050_EN_PT%20Long%20Term%20Strategy.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">in <span>2016</span></a>, several years before the European Union as a&nbsp;whole found the conviction to <a href="https://www.france24.com/en/20191213-european-union-brussels-carbon-neutral-green-deal-2050-poland-climate-change" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">take that step</a>. Portugal’s last coal plants shut down in <span>2022</span>, leaving (imported) fossil gas as the backstop for on-demand power.</p>

<p dir="ltr"><span>“</span>The key conclusion, in my opinion, is that it shows that the Portuguese grid is prepared for very high shares of renewable electricity and for its expected variation: We were able to manage both the sharp increase of hydro and wind production, and also the return to a&nbsp;lower share of renewables, when natural-gas power plants were requested again to supply some of the country’s demand,” said <a href="https://expresso.pt/autores/2015-05-02-Miguel-Prado-14b44dbf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Miguel Prado</a>, who covers Portugal’s energy sector for <em>Expresso</em> newspaper.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The task ahead for Portugal’s grid decarbonization is to reduce and ultimately eliminate the number of hours when the country needs to burn gas to keep the lights on. Leaders want gas generation, which made up <a href="https://www.ren.pt/en-gb/media/news/renewables-supplied-67-of-the-electricity-consumed-in-october" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span>21</span>% of electricity consumption</a> from January through October, to <a href="https://www.reuters.com/sustainability/climate-energy/portugal-doubles-2030-goals-solar-hydrogen-capacity-2023-07-03/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">end completely by <span>2040</span></a>.</p>
<p dir="ltr">To reach its climate goals, Portugal has focused on diversification of renewable resources; instead of depending primarily on wind, water or sun, it blends each into the portfolio and finds ways to make them more complementary. The country’s power companies are now chasing major additional offshore wind opportunities, expanding solar installations and repowering older onshore wind projects to get more out of the best locations.</p>
<h2><strong>Anatomy of a&nbsp;six-day clean energy streak</strong></h2>
<p dir="ltr">After the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carnation_Revolution" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">overthrow of the authoritarian Estado Novo dictatorship</a> in <span>1974</span>, the newly formed state utility Energias de Portugal constructed a&nbsp;series of hydroelectric dams on the once-wild rivers that rushed from the eastern mountains to the western coast. The company built its first onshore wind projects in the <span>1990</span>s, when solar simply couldn’t compete economically, and solar installations have only recently started to catch&nbsp;up.</p>
<p dir="ltr">That’s why the gray skies didn’t hurt overall renewable production during the country’s recent record-setting stretch, as they would have in, say, California or Hawaii. The wind and hydro were cranking, and that’s what mattered.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Any milestone in the rapidly evolving clean energy sector should come with specific parameters. So what exactly did the Portuguese grid accomplish earlier this&nbsp;month?</p>
<p dir="ltr">The six-day record refers to the <a href="https://www.ren.pt/en-gb/media/news/renewable-energy-production-sets-new-records" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span>149</span> consecutive hours</a> in which <span></span>​<span>“</span>energy from renewable sources exceeded the industrial and household consumption needs across the country.” The country’s previous record for that metric was <span>131</span>&nbsp;hours (a little over five days), achieved in <span>2019</span>. That doesn’t mean that fossil fuel plants weren’t operating — just that the overall renewable generation more than met customer needs.</p>
<p dir="ltr">But Portugal also just set a&nbsp;national record for meeting the entire electricity system’s needs <span></span>​<span>“</span>without resorting to conventional thermal power generation.” This gas-free stretch started Halloween night and ran for <span>131</span> consecutive hours, about <span>5</span>&nbsp;days, nearly tripling Portugal’s previous record of <span>56</span>&nbsp;hours straight in <span>2021</span>. And for <span>95</span> of those consecutive hours, Portugal exported clean electricity to Spain, because it consistently had more than it needed — again without burning gas.</p>
<p dir="ltr">That trendline is the thing to watch. Renewables-friendly weather will come and go, and shoulder months are ripe for renewables to outpace consumer demand because heating or cooling needs are lower than in the summer and winter. But the last time Portugal had ideal conditions for a&nbsp;renewables record, it only lasted one-third as long without burning gas. As more wind and solar capacity comes online, Portugal expands its arsenal for running entirely on renewables.</p>
<p dir="ltr">This particular week stood out, but it exemplifies a&nbsp;historic shift in energy sources. Natural-gas use for Portugal’s electricity production <a href="https://www.ren.pt/en-gb/media/news/renewables-supplied-67-of-the-electricity-consumed-in-october" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">fell <span>39</span>% year-over-year</a> for the period from January to October, according to <span>REN</span>. That brought overall gas use to its lowest level since&nbsp;<span>2006</span>.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Portugal has made grid decarbonization perfectly tangible for itself. To reach its climate goals, it needs to take the playbook from this one week in November and run it for longer periods of time, until eventually it doesn’t even need gas on standby. And it has to do so even in the parts of the year when the winds and the rain don’t lash the off-season traveler who’d heard so much about a&nbsp;climate reminiscent of Southern California.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Tesla Semi from an Insider's View After One Year: "Hot Mess" (155 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://bradmunchen.substack.com/p/scoop-the-tesla-semi-from-an-insiders</link>
            <guid>38297765</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 00:44:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://bradmunchen.substack.com/p/scoop-the-tesla-semi-from-an-insiders">https://bradmunchen.substack.com/p/scoop-the-tesla-semi-from-an-insiders</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38297765">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg" width="548" height="364" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:364,&quot;width&quot;:548,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:39763,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><span>After a nearly 5 years since being announced in 2017, the Tesla Semi was finally launched with great fanfare to its first customer, PepsiCo, on December 1, 2022. But, there was absolutely no data was given on pricing, Autopilot use, battery pack size, or Tesla’s original 1 million-mile guarantee of lifetime range. In fact, the status of the Tesla Semi has been classified as “pilot production” in Tesla’s Shareholder Deck for the past year since its launch and Tesla Semi drivers are forbidden (most likely by non-disclosure agreements) from speaking about the Semi, as CNBC reported </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l-BVM673pDs&amp;t=828s&amp;ab_channel=CNBC" rel="">here</a><span> (watch from 8:20). </span></p><p>This is why it was with great fortune to receive the details below, which were told to a trusted automotive source of mine by a PepsiCo employee who happened to have time for my friend’s questions about the Semi at a charging station the other day (my friend has owned a Tesla and many other EVs). </p><p>But let’s first look at what Tesla promised about the Semi back in 2017, when they first revealed the new product and said it would be in production by 2019: </p><ul><li><p>500-mile range (800 km) at a maximum load of 82,000 lbs or 37,195 kg</p></li><li><p>0-60 mph in 5 seconds vs 20 seconds for a diesel semi</p></li><li><p>100,000 in output by 2022 (only 90 Semis have been produced through October 2023, according to InsideEVs)</p></li></ul><p>And after one year since its first deliveries to PepsiCo, Tesla has yet to divulge any data on the Tesla Semi except for a tweet from Elon Musk saying that the battery efficiency was 1.7 kWh per mile (a useful number to have with the details from PepsiCo below).  </p><p>Below are the comments from a PepsiCo employee about the Tesla Semi. Please note that the text within parentheses are my comments, not that of the PepsiCo employee who provided the comments. </p><ul><li><p><strong>PepsiCo only gets 400 miles at best with a full payload of 82,000 lbs (37,195 kg) on their Tesla Semis</strong><span> [</span><em>this implies a much smaller battery pack than expected, as Musk said battery efficiency for the Semi is 1.7 kWh per mile, which implies a battery pack size of only around 700 kWh; at a 500-mile range, the assumption was the Semi had a battery pack size of at least 1,000 kWh</em><span>]. </span></p></li><li><p><strong>The constant use of the battery pack is unprecedented and is causing reliability problems for Tesla and other EV truck makers</strong><span> [s</span><em>imilar claims coming from Uber drivers who use their Teslas over 300 miles per day, i.e., their batteries are dying quickly. This is a hidden cost that that Tesla Semi customers need to account for; if a 100 kWh battery pack for a Model S costs roughly $25,000 to replace, the Semi’s battery pack should be at least $170,000]</em><span>.&nbsp; </span></p></li><li><p><strong>PepsiCo did a 500-mile trip with the Tesla Semi from California to Phoenix, but it was just for PR purposes. The batteries completely burned out, which is why on PR trips like this, they bring three Tesla Semis, with two being towed on a diesel Semi truck, only to be swapped out when the battery dies the other two Semis on the 500-mile drive</strong><span> [</span><em>this is why Tesla classifies the Semi as being in “pilot production”: the battery pack is not strong enough to deliver all the specs on range, etc. which Tesla promised in 2017</em><span>].&nbsp; </span></p></li></ul><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg" width="1425" height="805" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/fc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:805,&quot;width&quot;:1425,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:101522,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg" width="1380" height="716" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:716,&quot;width&quot;:1380,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:109033,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><ul><li><p><strong>The PepsiCo employee said that the Tesla Semi is using “pouch” battery cells made in Nevada</strong><span> [</span><em>this is odd, as all cells made by Panasonic in Nevada are cylindrical cells, but Tesla could be importing these pouches from overseas and packaging them at their Nevada plant. Pouches are lighter than cylindrical cells, so better to be used for the Semi</em><span>]</span></p></li><li><p><strong>The Tesla Semi’s pouch-style battery pack appears to be problematic, as they were easily damaged during a spate of heavy rain showers in California this year</strong><span>. </span></p></li><li><p><strong>All Tesla Semis and other electric trucks are subsidized by California state and the Megacharger station alone cost around $6 million</strong><span> [</span><em>these mega chargers can power up to 28,000 homes</em><span>].&nbsp; </span></p></li><li><p><strong>During the installation process, the Megachargers took down the power grid for a good chunk of the city</strong><span> [</span><em>imagine what happens when 100% of ICE vehicles have switched over to BEV in California by 2035</em><span>]. </span></p></li><li><p><strong>Tesla isn’t using special-grade truck parts for the Tesla Semi</strong><span> (i.e. weight and energy-grade heavy-duty parts).&nbsp; </span><strong>Tesla is using car parts on the Semi, which is why it breaks down so often given the range at which PepsiCo is driving its fleet</strong><span>.  </span></p></li><li><p><strong>There is a team of Tesla engineers on call 24 hours a day, ready to fly out and fix anything wrong with the Tesla Semis. No one at PepsiCo is allowed to fix the Semi</strong><span>.&nbsp; </span></p></li><li><p><strong>Tesla is using a double wishbone suspension on the Semi which the PepsiCo employee said makes zero sense and shows how Tesla simply threw car parts—not heavy-duty truck parts—into the Tesla Semi</strong><span>.&nbsp; </span></p></li><li><p><strong>Center seating, which looks cool in the Tesla Semi launch video, is actually not practical and not well liked by PepsiCo’s drivers</strong><span>.</span></p></li><li><p><strong>There is no consideration for battery longevity, which is another reason why the batteries keep dying and Tesla Semis need to be towed away</strong><span> [</span><em>the Megachargers used for the Semi release 750 kW and only require 50 minutes for a 400-mile charge; that’s a ton of energy that will wear the batteries out quickly, but cost isn’t a consideration it appears; just performance</em><span>]. &nbsp; </span></p></li><li><p><strong>None of the Tesla Semi drivers care about the fact that the Semi can accelerate to 60 mph (96 kph) in 20 seconds. People commenting on the Tesla Semi say it might help in passing other trucks, but PepsiCo’s employee said nobody cared</strong><span> [</span><em>Tesla uses the the tri-motor system from the Models S/X Plaid on one axle of the Semi, which seems both dangerous and needless, given the lack of concern among Semi users for quick acceleration</em><span>].</span></p></li><li><p><strong>Pepsi is “all in” on the Tesla Semi despite all the problems </strong><span>[</span><em>this is no surprise, given that California taxpayers are paying for all of the absurd costs of this project</em><span>].</span></p></li></ul><p>All of the above tidbits on the Tesla Semi from inside PepsiCo make sense and some of it was speculated over by Jason Fenske, the brilliant man behind the YouTube channel, “Engineering Explained”. </p><p><span>Specifically, he said that the 500-mile test drive of the Semi was suspect, as the size of the battery pack couldn’t support a drive that long at 60 miles per hour (96 kph) of constant speed. He showed that the Tesla-filmed test drive of the Semi revealed that the Semi’s odometer was only at 60 mph for 15% of the haul (full video </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hvg_i0GE0Vo&amp;ab_channel=EngineeringExplained" rel="">here</a><span>).  </span></p><p>Why is PepsiCo going to all this trouble to use such ineffective vehicles to transport their products? Because they need all the ESG points they can get by using electric vehicles (they also use Volvos, Fords &amp; others) to transport the poison they peddle: PepsiCo’s food and beverage products are a major cause of the rising obesity problems in the US. The image below is roughly half of PepsiCo’s top products (full disclosure: I love many of them, but stopped eating them years ago).  </p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg" width="1035" height="835" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/d9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:835,&quot;width&quot;:1035,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:93895,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Why is Tesla screwing around with the Semi despite it not being a viable product and Tesla having more pressing needs with other new models? Because Elon needed a pump for Tesla’s stock back in 2017. Keep in mind that Tesla was close to bankruptcy due to troubles with the Model 3 launch between 2017 to 2019, but Elon Musk’s own admission. </p><p>And Musk recently said in June that the Semi won’t see higher-volume production until late 2024 “due to battery supply constraints”. This was a blatant lie. Recent earnings calls at Panasonic and LG Energy Solutions revealed that the two battery cell makers are seeing excess capacity as their customers’ EV models are seeing a slowdown in sales (Tesla Models S/X) and others are pushing out their EV capex to 2025 (Ford and GM). </p><p>The Semi was simply another pump that never came to fruition, somewhat like battery pack swapping back in 2014 at Tesla. It would be no surprise to see the Tesla Semi discontinued or simply not mentioned anymore after 2024 unless battery packs become as cheap as ICE vehicle engines. For now, I believe it’s safe to say that electric Semis are a joke. And Elon Musk is the master joker.   </p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg" width="1015" height="931" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:931,&quot;width&quot;:1015,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:118310,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><em>Nothing in this report is investment advice. The Tesla Semi is a small part of Tesla’s overall costs. </em></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Anomalous propagation and the sinking of the Russian warship Moskva (135 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://journals.ametsoc.org/view/journals/bams/aop/BAMS-D-23-0113.1/BAMS-D-23-0113.1.xml</link>
            <guid>38297349</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 23:51:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://journals.ametsoc.org/view/journals/bams/aop/BAMS-D-23-0113.1/BAMS-D-23-0113.1.xml">https://journals.ametsoc.org/view/journals/bams/aop/BAMS-D-23-0113.1/BAMS-D-23-0113.1.xml</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38297349">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section id="container-56968-item-56938"><h2 id="d25885642e184">Abstract</h2><p>On 13 April 2022, the Russian warship <em>Moskva</em> was hit by two Ukrainian <em>Neptune</em> anti-ship missiles in the Black Sea, leading to its demise. Before launching an anti-ship missile, a target must first be detected and positioned, for example by an accompanying radar system. However, when the missiles hit the <em>Moskva</em> she was well beyond the normal radar horizon of any ground-based radar system, making the ship undetectable under normal circumstances. Using meteorological reanalysis data, we show that at the time of the missile launch the prevailing weather conditions allowed a ground-based radar to detect targets far beyond the normal radar horizon through anomalous propagation conditions. During such conditions, the atmospheric index of refraction decreases rapidly with height, making electromagnetic radiation bend downward to, partly or fully, compensate the curvature of the Earth. The results show that atmospheric conditions must be considered carefully, even during warfare, as their impact on radar wave propagation can be considerable.</p></section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Justice Dept Says Collusion Suit Against Apartment Owners Should Move Forward (281 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wsj.com/us-news/law/justice-department-clears-the-way-for-collusion-suit-against-apartment-owners-e545f260</link>
            <guid>38297203</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 23:35:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wsj.com/us-news/law/justice-department-clears-the-way-for-collusion-suit-against-apartment-owners-e545f260">https://www.wsj.com/us-news/law/justice-department-clears-the-way-for-collusion-suit-against-apartment-owners-e545f260</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38297203">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><p>Updated Nov. 16, 2023 6:27 pm ET</p></div><section><div data-type="image" data-inset_type="" data-sub_type="" data-layout="inline"><figure><picture><img alt="" sizes="(max-width: 639px) 100vw, (max-width: 979px) 620px, (max-width: 1299px) 540px, 700px" srcset="https://images.wsj.net/im-888279?width=540&amp;size=1.5005861664712778 540w, https://images.wsj.net/im-888279?width=620&amp;size=1.5005861664712778 620w, https://images.wsj.net/im-888279?width=639&amp;size=1.5005861664712778 639w, https://images.wsj.net/im-888279?width=700&amp;size=1.5005861664712778 700w, https://images.wsj.net/im-888279?width=700&amp;size=1.5005861664712778&amp;pixel_ratio=1.5 1050w, https://images.wsj.net/im-888279?width=700&amp;size=1.5005861664712778&amp;pixel_ratio=2 1400w, https://images.wsj.net/im-888279?width=700&amp;size=1.5005861664712778&amp;pixel_ratio=3 2100w" width="700" height="466" src="https://images.wsj.net/im-888279?width=700&amp;height=466"></picture></figure><figcaption><span>Tenants earlier this year filed a complaint in a Tennessee federal court alleging RealPage, and landlords that use its algorithmic pricing system to set rents, are violating antitrust laws.</span> <span><span>Photo: </span>Matt Rourke/Associated Press</span></figcaption></div><p data-type="paragraph">A lawsuit alleging that <a data-type="link" href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/thoma-bravo-agrees-to-buy-realpage-for-9-6-billion-11608526860" rel="">real-estate software company RealPage</a> illegally fixes rents at millions of apartments should go forward, the U.S. Justice Department said in a court filing.</p><p data-type="paragraph">Tenants earlier this year <a data-type="link" href="https://www.wsj.com/real-estate/commercial/thanks-to-big-data-landlords-know-how-to-squeeze-the-most-out-of-renters-eb7e5f02" rel="">filed a complaint</a> in a Tennessee federal court alleging RealPage and landlords that use its algorithmic pricing system to set rents are violating antitrust laws. The use of this pricing system has limited competition in the housing market and resulted in higher rents for tenants, the complaint alleges.&nbsp;</p></section><p>Copyright ©<!-- -->2023<!-- --> Dow Jones &amp; Company, Inc. All Rights Reserved. 87990cbe856818d5eddac44c7b1cdeb8</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>