<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 17:30:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to pwn a billion dollar VC firm using inspect element (421 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.kibty.town/blog/a16z/</link>
            <guid>41016768</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 14:33:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.kibty.town/blog/a16z/">https://www.kibty.town/blog/a16z/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41016768">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><div><h2>background</h2>
<p>i like to do this thing where i search twitter, looking for companies, and then try giving them a quick pentest. i've done a lot of my hacks this way and its more effective than you think it is.</p>
<p>on this search, i use the "Relevant People" tab more often than you think, this is how i got to a16z</p>
<ul>
<li>crypto bullshit -&gt; venture capital firms for crypto -&gt; a16z crypto -&gt; a16z</li>
</ul>
<h2>the hack</h2>
<p>while looking into a16z, i did a usual subdomain scan and used tooling from <a href="https://lunchcat.dev/">lunchcat</a> which does common checks on domains, scanning for secrets in js files, etc.</p>
<p>in this search, i came across <code>portfolio.a16z.com</code>, a site that seems like a portfolio management tool for companies that are in a16z. while doing cursory checks like i usually do, lunchcat seemed to catch a AWS key referenced somewhere in the website.</p>
<p>i confirmed this and what i saw in the js, was this.</p>
<pre><code>{
    <span>MARKETPLACE_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>DATABASE_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SALESFORCE_CLIENT_ID</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SALESFORCE_SECURITY_TOKEN</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>npm_config_user_agent</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SALESFORCE_CLIENT_SECRET</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SALESFORCE_USERNAME</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>OKTA_CLIENT_ID</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>OKTA_CLIENT_SECRET</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SESSION_SECRET</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>API_USERNAME</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>GOOGLE_CLIENT_ID_DEVELOPMENT</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>CLIENT_TOKEN_SECRET</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>GOOGLE_CLIENT_SECRET_DEVELOPMENT</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>AWS_BUCKET_NAME</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>npm_config_prefix</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>REACT_APP_SENTRY_DSN</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>AWS_BUCKET_TEAM_PAGES</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>MAILGUN_API_KEY</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>GOOGLE_CLIENT_ID</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>AWS_LOGO_BUCKET_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SALESFORCE_KEY</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>GOOGLE_CLIENT_SECRET</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>PAPERTRAIL_API_TOKEN</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>MAILGUN_PASSWORD</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>OKTA_CALLBACK_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SALESFORCE_PASSWORD</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>MAILGUN_USER</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>PNPM_CONFIG_CACHE</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>MAILGUN_DOMAIN</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>GOOGLE_CALLBACK_URL_DEVELOPMENT</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>API_PASSWORD</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SENTRY_DSN</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SALESFORCE_LOGIN_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>COOKIE_SECRET</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>OKTA_DOMAIN</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>NODE_MODULES_CACHE</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>GOOGLE_CALLBACK_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,,
    <span>NODE_ENV</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>HEROKU_POSTGRESQL_CRIMSON_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>TALENTPLACE_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
}
</code></pre>
<p>this was. horrifying, it was the entire <code>process.env</code> of a heroku instance, in the JS. put in dynamically.</p>
<p>i did a quick valid look of the credentials and they didnt seem like fake credentials. they. were. real. and all someone had to do find them was go to the sources tab of inspect element.</p>
<h2>impact</h2>
<p>the compromised list of services:</p>
<ul>
<li>their database (containing PII)</li>
<li>their AWS</li>
<li>their salesforce (never checked, account may be limited)</li>
<li>mailgun (arbitrary emails from a16z domains, and also could read older emails)</li>
<li>... and probably more</li>
</ul>
<h2>reward</h2>
<p>a16z did not give me any bug bounty on this because of the fact i publicly reached out instead of trying to reach out privately. the only reason i did it this way was because:</p>
<ul>
<li>there was no available contact on their main site</li>
<li>the email i could find <code>engineering@a16z.com</code> bounced my emails</li>
</ul>
<p>so, i dunno. imo this is unfair.</p>
<h2>related</h2>
<p>techcrunch article (lorenzo reached out to me seeing my tweet trying to get in contact with them and wrote a piece!): https://techcrunch.com/2024/07/18/researcher-finds-flaw-in-a16z-website-that-exposed-some-company-data/</p>
</div></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[No Uptime Hosting – Guaranteed Server Downtime (196 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nouptime.com/</link>
            <guid>41016290</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 13:21:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nouptime.com/">https://nouptime.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41016290">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content">


<p>

	- 200Kb of Storage<br>

	- 10Mb of Bandwidth<br>

	- PHP 4, 5 and 6<br>

	- MySQL, SQL and Oracle<br>

	- Dedicated Dedication<br>

	- Host Up To 6.8 Sites<br>

	- Free Identity Theft

</p>



<p>

	- Lots of Storage<br>

	- 10Kb of Bandwidth<br>

	- PHP 5, 6 and 7<br>

	- MySQL and ReiserFS<br>

	- 2 Glow Sticks<br>

	- Free Broken Toaster<br>

	- 24/8 Email Support

</p>



<p>

	- 200Gb of Storage<br>

	- 10 Bytes of Path Bandwidth<br>

	- Ruby on Railroads<br>

	- Dedicated Support Geek<br>

	- Dedicated Win 3.11<br>

	- Steve Ballmer<br>

	- Ruby on Boats

</p>



<p>

	Currently Hosting Over <b>5,568,120</b> Websites

</p><!--sites-hosted-->



<p>

	Hosting Websites Since <b>1969</b>!

</p>



<br clear="all">



<div>

	<p><img id="graph" src="https://nouptime.com/images/graph.gif" alt="Downtime Graph"></p>

	<p>We are constantly working to improve our server downtime.</p>

	<p>Keeping you awake at night is our #1 priority.</p><br>

	<h2>Clusters and Scalability</h2>

	<p>If your websites go down we'll make sure to confuse</p>

	<p>you with technical terms and instructions. It's our</p>

	<p>job to keep you aggravated, and we never disappoint.<br clear="all"></p>

</div>



<div>

	<p><img id="testimonials" src="https://nouptime.com/images/testimonials.gif" alt="Testimonials"></p><p>We have over <b>359</b> testimonials from happy customers around the world:</p>

	<!--testimonial-box-->

	

</div>



<!--? include("bottom.php");?--></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Public toilets are vanishing and that's a civic catastrophe (136 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://psyche.co/ideas/public-toilets-are-vanishing-and-thats-a-civic-catastrophe</link>
            <guid>41015731</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 11:37:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://psyche.co/ideas/public-toilets-are-vanishing-and-thats-a-civic-catastrophe">https://psyche.co/ideas/public-toilets-are-vanishing-and-thats-a-civic-catastrophe</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41015731">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="articleContent"><h2>New research shows it is a nightmare for all of us, but especially for people with health issues and marginalised groups</h2><p>The most terrifying moments often unfold in mundane situations. My own taste of horror emerges every time I enter a bar and I’m met with a prolonged silence after asking: ‘Can I use the toilet, please?’ In supposedly affluent Western nations, the dire state or absence of public toilets has become a universal nightmare, impacting the health and quality of life of all of us, but particularly for marginalised groups.</p>
<p>What I find most scary is that we seem to be accepting this cruel reality without confronting it. It is like there is a monster in the city that is affecting the life of everyone, but the people who can make a difference don’t even care.</p>
<p>I have been aware of the monster since 2013 when I was diagnosed with ulcerative colitis. This is a chronic inflammatory bowel disease that causes long-lasting inflammation and ulcers in the digestive tract and affects life in different ways, such as needing the toilet frequently, pain and fatigue. That’s when I realised the impact a simple toilet can have, not only on an individual’s health but also on public health. This is the story of the <em>shitty</em> life that the poor quality of public toilets confers <span>upon us</span>.</p>
<p>Making public bathrooms accessible and appropriate is a matter of human dignity</p>
<p><strong>Toilets were one of the biggest steps</strong> forward for humanity: they allowed us to <a href="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/8/8/779" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">create</a> cleaner spaces, reducing death and improving health. By the <span>19th century</span>, in Western countries, bathrooms with toilets were increasingly included in home design, catering to essential human needs, such as urination, defecation and personal cleaning. With the emergence of new hygiene standards through the <span>20th century</span>, the focus of bathrooms shifted further towards convenience and cleanliness. In contemporary times, the role of domestic bathrooms has <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.2752/174063109X12462745321345" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">expanded</a> beyond their practical utility to symbolise places of wellbeing, with more affluent homes including features such as hot tubs and toilets with hi-tech and luxury functions.</p>
<p>And yet, the vast majority of public restrooms have not yet embraced this aspect of wellbeing. On the contrary, the poor state of them often elicits disgust and repulsion. In severe situations, for some people, these adverse psychological responses can escalate to pathological levels, including incontinence, urinary problems, anxiety, and significant alterations to their normal social life.</p>
<p>For many people, most of the time, the state of restrooms is something they think about only when they fail, if they are unusable or unavailable, or there simply aren’t any. Yet toilets often fail when you need them the most. And it’s in such moments you realise that these invisible parts of our cities are fundamental. So, why are restrooms typically tucked away at the back of establishments, hidden both literally and metaphorically? We all must keep in mind that the use of public bathrooms is inevitable, and that making them accessible and appropriate is a matter of human dignity.</p>
<p><strong>The toilet problem has two differentiable</strong> branches. The first is the global sanitation crisis in developing countries and in extreme situations such as refugee camps, which provokes disease and death. The second branch pertains to the problems in developed countries, causing issues in daily life and negatively impacting quality of life.</p>
<p>Fear of public bathrooms will be greater in those most disadvantaged by society</p>
<p>Worldwide, the World Bank highlights three critical <a href="https://blogs.worldbank.org/en/water/3-hard-truths-about-global-sanitation-crisis" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">facts</a>: a quarter of the world’s population lacks access to decent toilets, only <span>39 per cent</span> of human waste is safely managed worldwide, and the global cost of inadequate sanitation reaches <span>$260 billion</span> annually. These facts emphasise the severe health, economic and environmental impacts of inadequate sanitation. Lack of access to toilets is a silent global burden: people die as disease spreads due to the lack of sanitation.</p>
<p>The problem is different when looking to Western, educated, industrialised, rich and democratic (WEIRD) countries. Here we often take adequate sewage disposal for granted. And yet free access to toilets is gradually <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/langas/article/PIIS2468-1253(21)00438-6/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">disappearing</a>. As the journalist Lezlie Lowe <a href="https://chbooks.com/Books/N/No-Place-To-Go" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">documents</a> in <em>No Place to Go</em> (2018), institutions are retiring from ensuring the availability of public toilets. This withdrawal of support for basic sanitary facilities has left many people, especially in urban areas, struggling to find accessible restrooms when needed. For instance, data collected in the United Kingdom in 2018 showed that the number of public toilets had dropped by <span>39 per cent</span> over the previous two decades. Quite simply, Lowe was right: there is often no place <span>to go</span>.</p>
<p>Yet, having access to toilets is essential for everyone’s dignity and to help support everyone’s mental, physical and social health. When women can’t easily use public toilets, it harms their <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31510038/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">wellbeing</a> and denies their <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0282917" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">basic rights</a>. The list of problems associated with public restrooms doesn’t end there. For instance, transgender and gender-nonconforming individuals <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6747507/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">face</a> <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10964-017-0652-1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">difficulties</a> accessing restrooms due to transphobia. There is also a noticeable rise in urogenital issues due to holding in the urge to use the restroom at <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28671729/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">work</a> or due to <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/15987005/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">schools</a> not adapting to the needs of children. Everyone can easily find a reason to fear public bathrooms, although these fears will be greater in those most disadvantaged by society.</p>
<p>For those of us with gastrointestinal problems, our minds always reserve a considerable space for public restrooms: we often worry about when we’ll have to use them, if we’ll find one, and if it will meet minimum standards. Dependency reshapes your reality: you are no longer concerned about whether you can park at the beach, but whether there will be a nearby restroom; you are not so worried about being late for the bus, but suddenly having an urgency in a <span>45-minute</span>-long journey. Life changes when you are dependent on toilets. Note that everyone can find themselves toilet dependent, even if only temporarily – like that week after you ate a meal that upset your stomach.</p>
<p>Women reported more negative incidents with public restrooms than men</p>
<p><strong>These thoughts drove me to conduct</strong> some scientific studies on what people face with public toilets and how it affects their daily lives. Our studies started with interviews with the true experts in public restrooms: patients with bowel diseases (such as Crohn’s disease, ulcerative colitis or irritable bowel syndrome). In our case, these were people from Spain, and with their help we <a href="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/17/21/7817" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">developed</a> some assessment tools to use in surveys. We confirmed what we suspected: people struggle with public toilets because they are dirty, don’t offer any privacy, and lack the basic things needed to use them. The ideal public toilet – the one with the adequate levels of cleanliness, privacy and usability – is hard to find. Another <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/nau.25118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> from our team showed that, for people who are toilet dependent, these negative situations can increase the shame they feel about their illness. This illness-related shame is associated with poorer health outcomes, such as reduced seeking of help or support from others.</p>
<p>When we asked people about the struggles they face with public toilets, such as ‘being unable to find an open unoccupied public toilet’ or ‘feeling unsafe or exposed in a public toilet’, we <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/sjop.12914" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">found</a> that the more often they experienced these negative events, the lower their quality of life (even after accounting for any differences in their health or socioeconomic status). What’s more, we found that people from poorer and less educated backgrounds had more of these negative toilet experiences – probably because they usually live further from work and in places with fewer available high-quality toilets. Consistent with previous research, we found that gender also influences (negative) experiences with public restrooms: women reported more negative incidents than men, perhaps due to distinct needs that are so often ignored.</p>
<p>Considering the data and experiences, it might seem we’re losing the battle for quality public toilets. There is just cause for anger, which should be channelled into action. Yet, there’s also reason to hope for a future with better toilets that restore our dignity. Some public administrations are taking the availability of quality public restrooms seriously in their facilities. Increasingly, patient and consumer associations are initiating campaigns for universal access to public toilets. For instance, in my country of Spain, there is the ‘I can’t wait!’ <a href="https://www.nopucesperar.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">campaign</a> in Catalonia, and the <a href="https://cecu.es/publicaciones/informe-sobre-la-presencia-de-banos-publicos-y-fuentes-de-agua/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">report</a> about public bathrooms from the Spanish Federation of Consumers and Users, which called for their greater availability.</p>
<p>Recognising this issue and assessing the situation is the initial stride toward a future where everyone can access high-quality restrooms tailored to their individual needs. One thing is clear: we need to talk about public restrooms openly, not in secret. Loudly, not whispering. We need to assert our fundamental right to access a restroom without having to wait until we’re back home.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Typst: An easy to learn alternative for LaTex (244 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/typst/typst</link>
            <guid>41014941</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 08:14:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/typst/typst">https://github.com/typst/typst</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41014941">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><div dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/17899797/226108480-722b770e-6313-40d7-84f2-26bebb55a281.png"><img alt="Typst" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/17899797/226108480-722b770e-6313-40d7-84f2-26bebb55a281.png"></a>
</h2><a id="user-content---" aria-label="Permalink: " href="#--"></a></div>
<p dir="auto">
  <a href="https://typst.app/docs/" rel="nofollow">
    <img alt="Documentation" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/d4ce973908547985ad235179c01636c81ff82a006036dea43e9f0732a7588b63/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f776562736974653f646f776e5f6d6573736167653d6f66666c696e65266c6162656c3d646f63732675705f636f6c6f723d3030376166662675705f6d6573736167653d6f6e6c696e652675726c3d687474707325334125324625324674797073742e617070253246646f6373" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/website?down_message=offline&amp;label=docs&amp;up_color=007aff&amp;up_message=online&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Ftypst.app%2Fdocs"></a>
  <a href="https://typst.app/" rel="nofollow">
    <img alt="Typst App" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/8f217dbac20c3a22ec5d60735e5cf9c364e453dcb1cebd0612aa3d5efb1226eb/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f776562736974653f646f776e5f6d6573736167653d6f66666c696e65266c6162656c3d74797073742e6170702675705f636f6c6f723d3233396461642675705f6d6573736167653d6f6e6c696e652675726c3d687474707325334125324625324674797073742e617070" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/website?down_message=offline&amp;label=typst.app&amp;up_color=239dad&amp;up_message=online&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Ftypst.app"></a>
  <a href="https://discord.gg/2uDybryKPe" rel="nofollow">
    <img alt="Discord Server" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/301accc7fe35bd2e5c40fb032c781bf753eca60c1d6478cf445527c6ed3e9c92/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f646973636f72642f313035343434333732313937353932323734383f636f6c6f723d353836354632266c6162656c3d646973636f7264266c6162656c436f6c6f723d353535" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/discord/1054443721975922748?color=5865F2&amp;label=discord&amp;labelColor=555"></a>
  <a href="https://github.com/typst/typst/blob/main/LICENSE">
    <img alt="Apache-2 License" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/5e717e166730c9f15db9cd416e0dbcf68c10baf29f6208b6ee1c8cbfdc108ead/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f6c6963656e73652d417061636865253230322d627269676874677265656e" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/license-Apache%202-brightgreen"></a>
  <a href="https://typst.app/jobs/" rel="nofollow">
    <img alt="Jobs at Typst" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/f605de5d6651c518139aec45f5183c54376710fd1423b6499798ee774b096ea3/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f64796e616d69632f6a736f6e3f75726c3d687474707325334125324625324674797073742e61707025324661737365747325324664617461253246736869656c64732e6a736f6e2671756572793d2532342e6a6f62732e74657874266c6162656c3d6a6f627326636f6c6f723d2532334135363146462663616368655365636f6e64733d31383030" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/dynamic/json?url=https%3A%2F%2Ftypst.app%2Fassets%2Fdata%2Fshields.json&amp;query=%24.jobs.text&amp;label=jobs&amp;color=%23A561FF&amp;cacheSeconds=1800"></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto">Typst is a new markup-based typesetting system that is designed to be as powerful
as LaTeX while being much easier to learn and use. Typst has:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Built-in markup for the most common formatting tasks</li>
<li>Flexible functions for everything else</li>
<li>A tightly integrated scripting system</li>
<li>Math typesetting, bibliography management, and more</li>
<li>Fast compile times thanks to incremental compilation</li>
<li>Friendly error messages in case something goes wrong</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">This repository contains the Typst compiler and its CLI, which is everything you
need to compile Typst documents locally. For the best writing experience,
consider signing up to our <a href="https://typst.app/" rel="nofollow">collaborative online editor</a> for free. It is
currently in public beta.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Example</h2><a id="user-content-example" aria-label="Permalink: Example" href="#example"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">A <a href="https://typst.app/docs/tutorial/" rel="nofollow">gentle introduction</a> to Typst is available in our documentation.
However, if you want to see the power of Typst encapsulated in one image, here
it is:</p>
<p dir="auto">
 <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/17899797/228031796-ced0e452-fcee-4ae9-92da-b9287764ff25.png"><img alt="Example" width="900" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/17899797/228031796-ced0e452-fcee-4ae9-92da-b9287764ff25.png"></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto">Let's dissect what's going on:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto">We use <em>set rules</em> to configure element properties like the size of pages or
the numbering of headings. By setting the page height to <code>auto</code>, it scales to
fit the content. Set rules accommodate the most common configurations. If you
need full control, you can also use <a href="https://typst.app/docs/reference/styling/#show-rules" rel="nofollow">show rules</a> to completely redefine
the appearance of an element.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">We insert a heading with the <code>= Heading</code> syntax. One equals sign creates a top
level heading, two create a subheading and so on. Typst has more lightweight
markup like this, see the <a href="https://typst.app/docs/reference/syntax/" rel="nofollow">syntax</a> reference for a full list.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://typst.app/docs/reference/math/" rel="nofollow">Mathematical equations</a> are enclosed in dollar signs. By adding extra
spaces around the contents of an equation, we can put it into a separate block.
Multi-letter identifiers are interpreted as Typst definitions and functions
unless put into quotes. This way, we don't need backslashes for things like
<code>floor</code> and <code>sqrt</code>. And <code>phi.alt</code> applies the <code>alt</code> modifier to the <code>phi</code> to
select a particular symbol variant.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">Now, we get to some <a href="https://typst.app/docs/reference/scripting/" rel="nofollow">scripting</a>. To input code into a Typst document, we can
write a hash followed by an expression. We define two variables and a
recursive function to compute the n-th fibonacci number. Then, we display the
results in a center-aligned table. The table function takes its cells
row-by-row. Therefore, we first pass the formulas <code>$F_1$</code> to <code>$F_8$</code> and then
the computed fibonacci numbers. We apply the spreading operator (<code>..</code>) to both
because they are arrays and we want to pass the arrays' items as individual
arguments.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<details>
  <summary>Text version of the code example.</summary>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="#set page(width: 10cm, height: auto)
#set heading(numbering: &quot;1.&quot;)

= Fibonacci sequence
The Fibonacci sequence is defined through the
recurrence relation $F_n = F_(n-1) + F_(n-2)$.
It can also be expressed in _closed form:_

$ F_n = round(1 / sqrt(5) phi.alt^n), quad
  phi.alt = (1 + sqrt(5)) / 2 $

#let count = 8
#let nums = range(1, count + 1)
#let fib(n) = (
  if n <= 2 { 1 }
  else { fib(n - 1) + fib(n - 2) }
)

The first #count numbers of the sequence are:

#align(center, table(
  columns: count,
  ..nums.map(n => $F_#n$),
  ..nums.map(n => str(fib(n))),
))"><pre><span>#set</span> <span>page</span>(<span>width</span>: <span>10cm</span>, <span>height</span>: <span>auto</span>)
<span>#set</span> <span>heading</span>(<span>numbering</span>: <span><span>"</span>1.<span>"</span></span>)

<span>= <span>Fibonacci sequence</span></span>
The Fibonacci sequence is defined through the
recurrence relation <span><span>$</span>F_n = F_(n-1) + F_(n-2)<span>$</span></span>.
It can also be expressed in <span>_closed form:_</span>

<span><span>$</span> F_n = round(1 / sqrt(5) phi.alt^n), quad</span>
<span>  phi.alt = (1 + sqrt(5)) / 2 <span>$</span></span>

<span>#let</span> <span>count</span> <span>=</span> <span>8</span>
<span>#let</span> <span>nums</span> <span>=</span> <span>range</span>(<span>1</span>, <span>count</span> <span>+</span> <span>1</span>)
<span>#let</span> <span>fib</span>(<span>n</span>) <span>=</span> (
  <span>if</span> <span>n</span> <span>&lt;=</span> <span>2</span> { <span>1</span> }
  <span>else</span> { <span>fib</span>(<span>n</span> <span>-</span> <span>1</span>) <span>+</span> <span>fib</span>(<span>n</span> <span>-</span> <span>2</span>) }
)

The first <span>#count</span> numbers of the sequence are:

<span>#align</span>(center, table(
  columns: count,
  ..nums.map(n =&gt; <span><span>$</span>F_#n<span>$</span></span>),
  ..nums.map(n =&gt; str(fib(n))),
))</pre></div>
</details>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h2><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Typst's CLI is available from different sources:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto">You can get sources and pre-built binaries for the latest release of Typst
from the <a href="https://github.com/typst/typst/releases/">releases page</a>. Download the archive for your platform and
place it in a directory that is in your <code>PATH</code>. To stay up to date with future
releases, you can simply run <code>typst update</code>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">You can install Typst through different package managers. Note that the
versions in the package managers might lag behind the latest release.</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Linux: View <a href="https://repology.org/project/typst/versions" rel="nofollow">Typst on Repology</a></li>
<li>macOS: <code>brew install typst</code></li>
<li>Windows: <code>winget install --id Typst.Typst</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">If you have a <a href="https://rustup.rs/" rel="nofollow">Rust</a> toolchain installed, you can install</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>the latest released Typst version with
<code>cargo install --locked typst-cli</code></li>
<li>a development version with
<code>cargo install --git https://github.com/typst/typst --locked typst-cli</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">Nix users can</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>use the <code>typst</code> package with <code>nix-shell -p typst</code></li>
<li>build and run a development version with
<code>nix run github:typst/typst -- --version</code>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">Docker users can run a prebuilt image with
<code>docker run -it ghcr.io/typst/typst:latest</code>.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h2><a id="user-content-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Usage" href="#usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Once you have installed Typst, you can use it like this:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# Creates `file.pdf` in working directory.
typst compile file.typ

# Creates PDF file at the desired path.
typst compile path/to/source.typ path/to/output.pdf"><pre><span><span>#</span> Creates `file.pdf` in working directory.</span>
typst compile file.typ

<span><span>#</span> Creates PDF file at the desired path.</span>
typst compile path/to/source.typ path/to/output.pdf</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">You can also watch source files and automatically recompile on changes. This is
faster than compiling from scratch each time because Typst has incremental
compilation.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# Watches source files and recompiles on changes.
typst watch file.typ"><pre><span><span>#</span> Watches source files and recompiles on changes.</span>
typst watch file.typ</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Typst further allows you to add custom font paths for your project and list all
of the fonts it discovered:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# Adds additional directories to search for fonts.
typst compile --font-path path/to/fonts file.typ

# Lists all of the discovered fonts in the system and the given directory.
typst fonts --font-path path/to/fonts

# Or via environment variable (Linux syntax).
TYPST_FONT_PATHS=path/to/fonts typst fonts"><pre><span><span>#</span> Adds additional directories to search for fonts.</span>
typst compile --font-path path/to/fonts file.typ

<span><span>#</span> Lists all of the discovered fonts in the system and the given directory.</span>
typst fonts --font-path path/to/fonts

<span><span>#</span> Or via environment variable (Linux syntax).</span>
TYPST_FONT_PATHS=path/to/fonts typst fonts</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">For other CLI subcommands and options, see below:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# Prints available subcommands and options.
typst help

# Prints detailed usage of a subcommand.
typst help watch"><pre><span><span>#</span> Prints available subcommands and options.</span>
typst <span>help</span>

<span><span>#</span> Prints detailed usage of a subcommand.</span>
typst <span>help</span> watch</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">If you prefer an integrated IDE-like experience with autocompletion and instant
preview, you can also check out the <a href="https://typst.app/" rel="nofollow">Typst web app</a>, which is currently in
public beta.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Community</h2><a id="user-content-community" aria-label="Permalink: Community" href="#community"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The main place where the community gathers is our <a href="https://discord.gg/2uDybryKPe" rel="nofollow">Discord server</a>.
Feel free to join there to ask questions, help out others, share cool things
you created with Typst, or just to chat.</p>
<p dir="auto">Aside from that there are a few places where you can find things built by
the community:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>The official <a href="https://typst.app/docs/packages" rel="nofollow">package list</a></li>
<li>The <a href="https://github.com/qjcg/awesome-typst">Awesome Typst</a> repository</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">If you had a bad experience in our community, please <a href="https://typst.app/contact" rel="nofollow">reach out to us</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing</h2><a id="user-content-contributing" aria-label="Permalink: Contributing" href="#contributing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">We would love to see contributions from the community. If you experience bugs,
feel free to open an issue. If you would like to implement a new feature or bug
fix, please follow the steps outlined in the <a href="https://github.com/typst/typst/blob/main/CONTRIBUTING.md">contribution guide</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">To build Typst yourself, first ensure that you have the
<a href="https://rustup.rs/" rel="nofollow">latest stable Rust</a> installed. Then, clone this repository and build the
CLI with the following commands:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/typst/typst
cd typst
cargo build --release"><pre>git clone https://github.com/typst/typst
<span>cd</span> typst
cargo build --release</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">The optimized binary will be stored in <code>target/release/</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Another good way to contribute is by <a href="https://github.com/typst/packages/">sharing packages</a> with the
community.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Pronunciation and Spelling</h2><a id="user-content-pronunciation-and-spelling" aria-label="Permalink: Pronunciation and Spelling" href="#pronunciation-and-spelling"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">IPA: /taɪpst/. "Ty" like in <strong>Ty</strong>pesetting and "pst" like in Hi<strong>pst</strong>er. When
writing about Typst, capitalize its name as a proper noun, with a capital "T".</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Design Principles</h2><a id="user-content-design-principles" aria-label="Permalink: Design Principles" href="#design-principles"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">All of Typst has been designed with three key goals in mind: Power,
simplicity, and performance. We think it's time for a system that matches the
power of LaTeX, is easy to learn and use, all while being fast enough to realize
instant preview. To achieve these goals, we follow three core design principles:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Simplicity through Consistency:</strong>
If you know how to do one thing in Typst, you should be able to transfer that
knowledge to other things. If there are multiple ways to do the same thing,
one of them should be at a different level of abstraction than the other. E.g.
it's okay that <code>= Introduction</code> and <code>#heading[Introduction]</code> do the same thing
because the former is just syntax sugar for the latter.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Power through Composability:</strong>
There are two ways to make something flexible: Have a knob for everything or
have a few knobs that you can combine in many ways. Typst is designed with the
second way in mind. We provide systems that you can compose in ways we've
never even thought of. TeX is also in the second category, but it's a bit
low-level and therefore people use LaTeX instead. But there, we don't really
have that much composability. Instead, there's a package for everything
(<code>\usepackage{knob}</code>).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Performance through Incrementality:</strong>
All Typst language features must accommodate for incremental compilation.
Luckily we have <a href="https://github.com/typst/comemo/"><code>comemo</code></a>, a system for incremental compilation which does
most of the hard work in the background.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google's shortened links will stop working next year (119 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theverge.com/2024/7/19/24201734/google-url-link-shortening-service-shut-down-support</link>
            <guid>41014089</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 04:36:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/7/19/24201734/google-url-link-shortening-service-shut-down-support">https://www.theverge.com/2024/7/19/24201734/google-url-link-shortening-service-shut-down-support</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41014089">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>If you ever used Google’s URL shortening service goo.gl before it was shut down in 2019, be warned — those links will stop working on August 25th, 2025. Google <a href="https://developers.googleblog.com/en/google-url-shortener-links-will-no-longer-be-available/">announced in a blog post</a> that “the time has come to turn off the serving portion of Google URL Shortener” and that any links in the https://goo.gl/* format will respond with a 404 error next year.</p><p>Ahead of the shutdown, goo.gl links will start showing an interstitial page on August 23rd, 2024, notifying users that “this link will no longer work in the near future.” This message will initially appear for a “percentage of existing links,’’ which will increase as the deadline draws closer. Google is encouraging developers to update impacted links as soon as possible, however, as this interstitial page may cause disruptions to link redirections.</p><div><div role="button" aria-label="Zoom" tabindex="0"><figure><div><p><span><img alt="The interstitial page that will appear on goo.gl links after August 23rd." loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 744px" srcset="https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/376x167/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 376w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/384x170/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 384w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/415x184/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 415w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/480x213/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 480w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/540x240/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 540w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/640x284/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 640w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/750x333/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 750w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/828x368/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 828w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/1080x479/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 1080w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/1200x533/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 1200w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/1440x639/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 1440w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/1920x852/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 1920w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/2048x909/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 2048w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/2400x1065/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 2400w" src="https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/2400x1065/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAIAAAAAAAP///yH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAIBRAA7"></span></p></div></figure></div><div><figcaption><em>Here’s the interstitial page that will start popping up on goo.gl links after August 23rd.</em></figcaption> <p><cite>Image: Google</cite></p></div></div><p>When <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2018/3/31/17184164/google-alphabet-url-shortening-service-closed">Google announced in 2018</a> that it was shutting down goo.gl, the company encouraged developers to migrate to Firebase Dynamic Links (FDL) — which has also since been <a href="https://firebase.google.com/support/dynamic-links-faq">deprecated</a>. </p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Technical Details on Today's Outage (107 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.crowdstrike.com/blog/technical-details-on-todays-outage/</link>
            <guid>41013198</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 01:19:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.crowdstrike.com/blog/technical-details-on-todays-outage/">https://www.crowdstrike.com/blog/technical-details-on-todays-outage/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41013198">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<h2><span>What Happened?</span></h2>
<p><span>On July 19, 2024 at 04:09 UTC, as part of ongoing operations, CrowdStrike released a sensor configuration update to Windows systems. Sensor configuration updates are an ongoing part of the protection mechanisms of the Falcon platform. This configuration update triggered a logic error resulting in a system crash and blue screen (BSOD) on impacted systems.</span></p>
<p><span>The sensor configuration update that caused the system crash was remediated on Friday, July 19, 2024 05:27 UTC.</span></p>
<p><span>This issue is not the result of or related to a cyberattack.</span></p>
<h2><span>Impact</span></h2>
<p><span>Customers running Falcon sensor for Windows version 7.11 and above, that were online between Friday, July 19, 2024 04:09 UTC and Friday, July 19, 2024 05:27 UTC, may be impacted.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>Systems running Falcon sensor for Windows 7.11 and above that downloaded the updated configuration from 04:09 UTC to 05:27 UTC – were susceptible to a system crash.</span></p>
<h2><span>Configuration File Primer</span></h2>
<p><span>The configuration files mentioned above are referred to as “</span><a href="https://supportportal.crowdstrike.com/s/article/ka16T000000wuddQAA"><span>Channel Files</span></a><span>” and are part of the behavioral protection mechanisms used by the Falcon sensor. Updates to Channel Files are a normal part of the sensor’s operation and occur several times a day in response to novel tactics, techniques, and procedures discovered by CrowdStrike. This is not a new process; the architecture has been in place since Falcon’s inception.</span></p>
<h2><span>Technical Details</span></h2>
<p><span>On Windows systems, Channel Files reside in the following directory:</span></p>
<p><code><span>C:\Windows\System32\drivers\CrowdStrike\</span></code></p>
<p><span>and have a file name that starts with “</span><code><span>C-</span></code><span>”. Each channel file is assigned a number as a unique identifier. The impacted Channel File in this event is 291 and will have a filename that starts with “</span><code><span>C-00000291-</span></code><span>” and ends with a </span><code><span>.sys</span></code><span> extension. Although Channel Files end with the SYS extension, </span><span><span>they are not kernel drivers</span></span><span>.</span></p>
<p><span>Channel File 291 controls how Falcon evaluates named pipe<sup>1</sup></span><span> execution on Windows systems. Named pipes are used for normal, interprocess or intersystem communication in Windows.</span></p>
<p><span>The update that occurred at 04:09 UTC was designed to target newly observed, malicious named pipes being used by common C2 frameworks in cyberattacks. The configuration update triggered a logic error that resulted in an operating system crash.&nbsp;</span></p>
<h2><span>Channel File 291</span></h2>
<p><span>CrowdStrike has corrected the logic error by updating the content in Channel File 291. No additional changes to Channel File 291 beyond the updated logic will be deployed. Falcon is still evaluating and protecting against the abuse of named pipes.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>This is not related to null bytes contained within Channel File 291 or any other Channel File.&nbsp;</span></p>
<h2><span>Remediation</span></h2>
<p><span>The most up-to-date remediation recommendations and information can be found on our </span><a href="https://www.crowdstrike.com/blog/statement-on-falcon-content-update-for-windows-hosts/"><span>blog</span></a><span> or in the </span><a href="https://supportportal.crowdstrike.com/s/article/Tech-Alert-Windows-crashes-related-to-Falcon-Sensor-2024-07-19"><span>Support Portal</span></a><span>.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>We understand that some customers may have specific support needs and we ask them to contact us directly.</span></p>
<p><span>Systems that are </span><span>not</span><span> currently impacted will continue to operate as expected, continue to provide protection, and have </span><span>no risk</span><span> of experiencing this event in the future.</span></p>
<p><span>Systems running Linux or macOS do not use Channel File 291 and were not impacted.&nbsp;</span></p>
<h2><span>Root Cause Analysis</span></h2>
<p><span>We understand how this issue occurred and we are doing a thorough root cause analysis to determine how this logic flaw occurred. This effort will be ongoing. We are committed to identifying any foundational or workflow improvements that we can make to strengthen our process. We will update our findings in the root cause analysis as the investigation progresses.</span></p>

<p><sup>1 </sup>https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/win32/ipc/named-pipes</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Doom on Playdate (138 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://devforum.play.date/t/doom-on-playdate/852</link>
            <guid>41013159</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 01:10:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://devforum.play.date/t/doom-on-playdate/852">https://devforum.play.date/t/doom-on-playdate/852</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41013159">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/DiscussionForumPosting">
      <meta itemprop="headline" content="Doom on Playdate">
      
      <meta itemprop="datePublished" content="2020-05-25T21:50:30Z">
        <meta itemprop="articleSection" content="Games">
      <meta itemprop="keywords" content="">
      


          <div itemprop="text" id="post_1">
              <p>Last week end I finally started to work on porting Doom on the Playdate.</p>
<p>This is a very early result, just to run the game, but that was the hardest part for me. Dealing with makefiles and compiler is really not my cup of tea so having the game running means that now I can focus on the game control, presentation and optimization.</p>
<p><img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/ad0bca29eb788fe9bfed240366cd41ee2a4639bf.gif" alt="04" data-base62-sha1="oGPRqp9vmPbukHgOoJDHnql4w8v" width="400" height="240"></p>
<p>This is a gif from the simulator but I got the game running on the hardware too.</p>
<p><img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/7c0f0a9386f96b3029520f6f76648db93a399eb6.gif" alt="05" data-base62-sha1="hHtqNnHnN2GfthLDtz2yS3xf5Rk" width="400" height="225"></p>
<p>The most difficult part was to deal with the linker that was complaining about some missing references in libc. After spending two evenings chasing every libc functions that might be problematic, I found out that there is some magical linker option.</p>
<p>I've added the following line in CMakeLists.txt<br>
<code>add_link_options(-specs=nano.specs -specs=nosys.specs)</code></p>
<p>Since the linker was complaining about the symbol end missing, I've added it to the link_map.ld in the playdate SDK</p>
<pre><code>	.bss :
	{
		. = ALIGN(4);
		__bss_start__ = .;
		*(.bss*)
		*(COMMON)
		. = ALIGN(4);
		__bss_end__ = .;
		end = __bss_end__;

	} &gt; EXTRAM
</code></pre>
            </div>
          <div id="post_2" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/matt"><span itemprop="name">matt</span></a>
                (gingerbeardman)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-25T22:33:56Z">
                    May 25, 2020, 10:33pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-25T22:33:56Z">
              <span itemprop="position">2</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <div itemprop="text">
              <p>Nic! You're crazy. In a good way.</p>
<p>Awesome</p>
            </div>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_3" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/ast-rsk"><span itemprop="name">ast-rsk</span></a>
                
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-25T23:07:57Z">
                    May 25, 2020, 11:07pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-25T23:07:57Z">
              <span itemprop="position">3</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <p>This officially makes the playdate a viable product! If it can run doom, it's a solid device <img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/3c05b67d820920114bafac96e31bfbefd6a4944d.png?v=12" title=":playdate:" alt=":playdate:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_4" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/squirrelboy"><span itemprop="name">squirrelboy</span></a>
                (Jake White)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-25T23:25:39Z">
                    May 25, 2020, 11:25pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-25T23:25:39Z">
              <span itemprop="position">4</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <p>Woah. I already wanted to make a Wolfenstein/Doom style game on this, but now even more.</p>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_5" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/dustin"><span itemprop="name">dustin</span></a>
                (Dustin Mierau)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-26T00:00:20Z">
                    May 26, 2020, 12:00am
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-26T00:00:20Z">
              <span itemprop="position">5</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <p><img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/d04cb21f40800c547fa08bc80d3c8dff0bc580c6.png?v=12" title=":playdate_shocked:" alt=":playdate_shocked:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"> <img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/f444a5a65c415828c203bcb1b25076709723e907.png?v=12" title=":playdate_heart:" alt=":playdate_heart:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_6" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/Dreezn"><span itemprop="name">Dreezn</span></a>
                (Dries Vienne)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-26T07:30:21Z">
                    May 26, 2020,  7:30am
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-26T07:30:21Z">
              <span itemprop="position">6</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <p>I love you man.<br>
This is beautiful <img src="https://devforum.play.date/images/emoji/apple/smiling_face_with_three_hearts.png?v=12" title=":smiling_face_with_three_hearts:" alt=":smiling_face_with_three_hearts:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_7" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/SamanthaZero"><span itemprop="name">SamanthaZero</span></a>
                (Samantha Kalman)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-26T08:39:28Z">
                    May 26, 2020,  8:39am
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-26T08:39:28Z">
              <span itemprop="position">7</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <p>very cool! <img src="https://devforum.play.date/images/emoji/apple/clap.png?v=12" title=":clap:" alt=":clap:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"> <img src="https://devforum.play.date/images/emoji/apple/clap.png?v=12" title=":clap:" alt=":clap:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"> <img src="https://devforum.play.date/images/emoji/apple/clap.png?v=12" title=":clap:" alt=":clap:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_8" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <div>
              <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/Nic"><span itemprop="name">Nic</span></a>
                (Nic Magnier)
              </span></p>

              <p><span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-26T10:01:16Z">
                    May 26, 2020, 10:01am
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-26T10:01:16Z">
              <span itemprop="position">8</span>
              </span>
            </p></div>
            <div itemprop="text">
              <p>Wow thank you all <img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/f444a5a65c415828c203bcb1b25076709723e907.png?v=12" title=":playdate_heart:" alt=":playdate_heart:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p>
<p>But I have to say that this is possible mostly because the Doom engine is extremely well done and organized and can be easily ported. It is not a mystery why this is the game that is always ported everywhere.</p>
<p>Something I forgot to mention is that I used STM32Doom for the port which itself in based on chocolate doom. I will share the source when I am a bit further and after cleaning some code (If anyone want to source already, feel free to DM me).</p>

<p>For anyone interested, I also recommend the book from Fabien Sanglard which analyze the source code. That was the book that pick my interest in porting the game.<br>
<a href="https://fabiensanglard.net/gebbdoom/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://fabiensanglard.net/gebbdoom/index.html</a></p>
            </div>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_9" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/Dreezn"><span itemprop="name">Dreezn</span></a>
                (Dries Vienne)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-26T12:02:57Z">
                    May 26, 2020, 12:02pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-26T12:02:57Z">
              <span itemprop="position">9</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <div itemprop="text">
              <p>Wow thanks for sharing!</p>
<p>I didn't know that book existed <img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/3c05b67d820920114bafac96e31bfbefd6a4944d.png?v=12" title=":playdate:" alt=":playdate:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"> . Although I never attempted porting, I dove into the source a few times to get inspiration for various clones and such. This makes my week!</p>
<p>What next steps are you planning, now that you got it up and running?</p>
            </div>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_10" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/DJLink"><span itemprop="name">DJLink</span></a>
                (David)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-29T20:39:52Z">
                    May 29, 2020,  8:39pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-29T20:39:52Z">
              <span itemprop="position">10</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <p>wow this is so cool, thanks for sharing</p>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_11" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <div>
              <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/Nic"><span itemprop="name">Nic</span></a>
                (Nic Magnier)
              </span></p>

              <p><span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-30T17:12:32Z">
                    May 30, 2020,  5:12pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-30T17:12:32Z">
              <span itemprop="position">11</span>
              </span>
            </p></div>
            <div itemprop="text">
              <p>I was not able to work on the port so much this week. This is still a gif of the rolling demo and this is not playable yet.</p>
<p><img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/45a72288f2aaca1680556bcc2edfabb22b71cd51.gif" alt="06" data-base62-sha1="9Wb1SCfukHAEAsvNGWkQLwoF6Gl" width="400" height="240"></p>
<p>This is still pretty rough. I tried to add controls but now the game crashes in the simulator when I try to launch the proper game. I also have a new crash on device, a totally different one. It will be (not) fun to track them down.</p>
<p><img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/831f4a1754fb7fb0e96227829fa4be398b4e78a9.jpeg" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="iHXAkc5VIVpibnRjHfObJxDlL29" width="300" height="225"></p>
<p>At least the rendering is a bit better. I use a dithering map texture which indicate which part of the screen is blue noise, ordered of just threshold. On the long term the key will be to add contrast to make some element like enemies pop more.</p>
<p><img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/bd8bb0089cf2a258971e14d7d7738d44d34cbc5e.png" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="r2NwjONof7FsOhFRe46a25dlW5U" width="320" height="200"></p>
<p>But now I went back to the blue noise rabbit hole and started to experiment generating my own blue noise textures. That will be interesting to improve the picture quality (and I have an idea that might force me to go back to my video experiments)</p>
            </div>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_12" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/donald.hays"><span itemprop="name">donald.hays</span></a>
                (Donald Hays)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-30T23:50:22Z">
                    May 30, 2020, 11:50pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-30T23:50:22Z">
              <span itemprop="position">12</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <div itemprop="text">
              <p>That is amazingly awesome.</p>
<p>I don't want to throw extra work on your plate, but this made me think about <a href="https://forums.tigsource.com/index.php?topic=40832.msg1363742#msg1363742" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">a post about dithering in Return of the Obra Dinn</a>, and how the dither pattern was rotated with the camera. Since you're working with Doom's source directly, I would imagine this means you have easy access to the camera rotation angle, yes? If so, I wonder how easy it would be to scroll the blue noise texture correspondingly, and if it would make the scene look any better or worse?</p>
            </div>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_13" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/Nic"><span itemprop="name">Nic</span></a>
                (Nic Magnier)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-31T05:08:14Z">
                    May 31, 2020,  5:08am
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-31T05:08:14Z">
              <span itemprop="position">13</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <p>That’s an excellent idea!<br>
I will look into it but it shouldn’t be too hard indeed.</p>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_14" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <div>
              <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/Nic"><span itemprop="name">Nic</span></a>
                (Nic Magnier)
              </span></p>

              <p><span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-06-01T21:27:41Z">
                    June 1, 2020,  9:27pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-06-01T21:27:41Z">
              <span itemprop="position">14</span>
              </span>
            </p></div>
            <div itemprop="text">
              <p>So if you don't go on the discord you might not have seen that Poom is kind of playable. I say kind of because I still have a lot of random crashes when navigating the menus. I am waiting to be able to debug on the simulator figure out what is the issue.</p>
<p>And because of popular demand I've added using the crank to use the Gatling. <img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/d04cb21f40800c547fa08bc80d3c8dff0bc580c6.png?v=12" title=":playdate_shocked:" alt=":playdate_shocked:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p>
<p><img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/62f76ee198cb00799bf45990690c10531b8f6d7f.gif" alt="DoomGatlingMini.2020-06-01 23_25_12" data-base62-sha1="e7uUJNqPr1l5EejChDvwKfT8oub" width="330" height="220"></p>
<p>We also had a discussion about Chex Quest and I don't think my code can support it so I am considering switch fully to Doom Chocolate. That would be an opportunity to clean up the code I did.</p>
<p>The early results are encouraging but there is still so much to do. <img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/d5fcf966698d4f0ed1188749a3aca4707508f293.png?v=12" title=":playdate_dizzy:" alt=":playdate_dizzy:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p>
            </div>

            

            

                
          </div>
          <div id="post_15" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/dustin"><span itemprop="name">dustin</span></a>
                (Dustin Mierau)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-06-01T22:25:24Z">
                    June 1, 2020, 10:25pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-06-01T22:25:24Z">
              <span itemprop="position">15</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <p>SO FREAKING GOOD <img src="https://devforum.play.date/images/emoji/apple/smiley.png?v=12" title=":smiley:" alt=":smiley:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_16" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/ast-rsk"><span itemprop="name">ast-rsk</span></a>
                
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-06-01T23:27:32Z">
                    June 1, 2020, 11:27pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-06-01T23:27:32Z">
              <span itemprop="position">16</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <div itemprop="text">
              <p>Incredible progress!</p>
<p>A couple friends of mine who don't know anything about playdate or that I'm in the preview, individually shared your update tweet with me saying how cool it is and how the device is so unique and looks fun.</p>
            </div>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_17" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/Drarok"><span itemprop="name">Drarok</span></a>
                
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-06-02T20:04:47Z">
                    June 2, 2020,  8:04pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-06-02T20:04:47Z">
              <span itemprop="position">17</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <div itemprop="text">
              <p>This is absolutely nuts in a brilliant way.</p>
<p>How's the music sound? <img src="https://devforum.play.date/images/emoji/apple/grimacing.png?v=12" title=":grimacing:" alt=":grimacing:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p>
            </div>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_18" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/Nic"><span itemprop="name">Nic</span></a>
                (Nic Magnier)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-06-02T21:11:39Z">
                    June 2, 2020,  9:11pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-06-02T21:11:39Z">
              <span itemprop="position">18</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <div itemprop="text">
              <p>No sound or music yet.</p>
<p>This is not my specialty so I didn't even look at it yet. Especially since this seem to have been the least portable part of the original doom. But I will come to that [art eventually.</p>
            </div>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_19" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/HaitoH3"><span itemprop="name">HaitoH3</span></a>
                (Jason A. Huff)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-07-01T05:08:37Z">
                    July 1, 2020,  5:08am
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-07-01T05:08:37Z">
              <span itemprop="position">19</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <p>oh man so good... i'll just start over now</p>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_20" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/spencer"><span itemprop="name">spencer</span></a>
                (spencer cap)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-07-21T07:33:23Z">
                    July 21, 2020,  7:33am
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-07-21T07:33:23Z">
              <span itemprop="position">20</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <p>Great job with this! would love to try out how it feels to shoot using the crank. do you have a pdx avail to play test?</p>

            

            

          </div>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Garage: Open-Source Distributed Object Storage (367 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/</link>
            <guid>41013004</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 00:40:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/">https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41013004">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      <div>
        <h2>Our Goals</h2>
        
        <p>We made it lightweight and kept the efficiency in mind:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <span>Self-contained</span>
            <p>We ship a single dependency-free binary that runs on all Linux distributions</p>
          </li>
          
          <li>
            <span>Fast to deploy, safe to operate</span>
            <p>We are sysadmins, we know the value of operator-friendly software</p>
          </li>
          
          <li>
            <span>Deploy everywhere on every machine</span>
            <p>We do not have a dedicated backbone, and neither do you,<br>
              so we made software that run over the Internet across multiple datacenters</p>
          </li>
          
          <li>
            Highly resilient
            <p><span>to network failures</span>,
              <span>network latency</span>,
              <span>disk failures</span>,
              <span>sysadmin failures</span>
            </p>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </div>

      <div>
        <h2>Keeping requirements low</h2>
        
        <p>
          We worked hard to keep requirements as low as possible:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <p><img src="https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/icons/cpu.svg" width="24">
              <span>CPU</span>
            </p>
            <span>Any x86_64 CPU from the last 10 years, ARMv7 or ARMv8</span>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p><img src="https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/icons/ram.svg" width="24">
              <span>RAM</span>
            </p>
            <span>1 GB</span>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p><img src="https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/icons/disk.svg" width="24">
              <span>Disk space</span>
            </p>
            <span>At least 16 GB</span>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p><img src="https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/icons/network.svg" width="24">
              <span>Network</span>
            </p>
            <span>200 ms or less, 50 Mbps or more</span>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p><img src="https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/icons/hardware.svg" width="24">
              <span>Heterogeneous hardware</span>
            </p>
            <span>Build a cluster with whatever second-hand machines are available</span>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </div>

      <div>
        <h2>Data resiliency for everyone</h2>
        
        <p>
          We built Garage to suit your existing infrastructure:
        </p>
        <p>
          Garage implements the Amazon S3 API<br>and thus is already compatible with many applications.
        </p>
        
      </div>

      <div>
        <h2>Standing on the shoulders of giants</h2>
        
        <p>
          Garage leverages insights from recent research in distributed systems:
        </p>
        
      </div>
    </div><div>
        <h2>Sponsors and funding</h2>
        <p>Garage has received funding from <a href="https://pointer.ngi.eu/" target="_blank">NGI POINTER</a> (3 full-time employees for one year, in 2021-2022),
          and from <a href="https://nlnet.nl/entrust/" target="_blank">NLnet / NGI0 Entrust</a> (1 full-time employee for one year, in 2023-2024).
        </p>
        <p>If you want to participate in funding Garage development,
          either through donation or support contract,
          please <a href="mailto:garagehq@deuxfleurs.fr">get in touch with us</a>.
        </p>
        <p>
          <img src="https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/images/ngi-pointer-eu.png" alt="NGI Pointers">
        </p>
        <p>
         <img src="https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/images/nlnet.svg" alt="NLnet logo">
         <img src="https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/images/NGI0Entrust_tag.svg" alt="NGI0 Entrust logo">
        </p>
        <p>This project has received funding from the European Union's Horizon 2021 research and innovation programme
          within the framework of the NGI-POINTER Project funded under grant agreement N° 871528.</p>
        <p>This project has received funding from the NGI0
          Entrust Fund, a fund established by NLnet with financial support from the
          European Commission's Next Generation Internet programme, under the aegis of DG
          Communications Networks, Content and Technology under grant agreement No
          101069594.
        </p>
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I mapped almost every USA traffic death in the 21st century (657 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://roadway.report</link>
            <guid>41012443</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 23:16:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://roadway.report">https://roadway.report</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41012443">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://roadway.report: Error: connect ECONNREFUSED 2600:3c00::f03c:94ff:fe0d:a614:443]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Multisatellite data depicts a record-breaking methane leak from a well blowout (296 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.estlett.4c00399</link>
            <guid>41012193</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 22:42:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.estlett.4c00399">https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.estlett.4c00399</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41012193">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.estlett.4c00399: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Academics shocked after T&F sells access to their research to Microsoft AI (110 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.thebookseller.com/news/academic-authors-shocked-after-taylor--francis-sells-access-to-their-research-to-microsoft-ai</link>
            <guid>41011779</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 21:53:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.thebookseller.com/news/academic-authors-shocked-after-taylor--francis-sells-access-to-their-research-to-microsoft-ai">https://www.thebookseller.com/news/academic-authors-shocked-after-taylor--francis-sells-access-to-their-research-to-microsoft-ai</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41011779">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div> <p>Authors have expressed their shock after the news that academic publisher Taylor &amp; Francis, which owns Routledge, had sold access to its authors’ research as part of an Artificial Intelligence (AI) partnership with Microsoft—a deal worth almost £8m ($10m) in its first year.</p>
<p>The agreement with Microsoft was included in a trading update by the publisher’s parent company in May this year.&nbsp;However, academics published by the group claim they have not been told about the AI deal, were not given the opportunity to opt out and are receiving no extra payment for the use of their research by the tech company.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The Society of Authors said it is "concerned to see publishers signing deals with tech companies without consulting authors and creators first".</p>
<p>Dr Ruth Alison Clemens, a lecturer in modern English literature whose work has been published by Taylor &amp; Francis and Routledge, claimed authors hadn’t been contacted about the AI deal.</p>
<p>Clemens told&nbsp;<em>The Bookseller </em>: "I only found out about this via word of mouth in the past few days. I was shocked that they had not publicised this more widely to their authors, as the use of AI and LLMs is a prominent concern for academic researchers today."</p>
<p>A spokesman from the Taylor &amp; Francis group, which is owned by Informa—a FTSE 100 international B2B Events, B2B Digital Services and Academic Markets group—confirmed to <em>The Bookseller </em>that "it is providing Microsoft non-exclusive access to advanced learning content and data to help improve relevance and performance of AI systems".</p>
<p>The&nbsp;<a href="https://www.informa.com/globalassets/documents/investor-relations/2024/informa-plc---market-update.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">agreement</a>, details of which were published by Informa during a trading update in May, states that Informa will be paid $10m+ for "an initial data access" of the works it has the rights to, with a recurring payment of an undisclosed sum to be made over the subsequent three years. &nbsp;</p>
<p>When contacted by <em>The Bookseller, </em>Taylor &amp; Francis said it is "protecting the integrity of our authors’ work and limits on verbatim text reproduction, as well as authors’ rights to receive royalty payments in accordance with their author contracts".</p>
<p>Informa is expecting revenues to reach just shy of £3.5bn in the current financial year, up from £3.2bn in 2023.</p>
<p>Taylor &amp; Francis, with its portfolio of specialist publishing brands (Routledge, CRC Press, F1000),&nbsp;<a href="https://www.thebookseller.com/news/taylor--francis-revenues-up-43-in-strong-trading-performance%3Ca%20href=" https:="" www.thebookseller.com="" news="" taylor--francis-revenues-up-43-in-strong-trading-performance"="" target="_blank">www.thebookseller.com/news/taylor--francis-revenues-up-43-in-strong-trading-performance</a>" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;revealed in March that its revenues went up 4.3% for 2023 to £619m, with adjusted operating profit up 4.4% to £217.9m.</p>
<p>One of the biggest concerns raised by Clemens is over whether it is possible for Taylor &amp; Francis’ authors to opt out of the AI partnership with Microsoft. Clemens told&nbsp;<em>The Bookseller</em>: "There is no clarity from Taylor &amp; Francis about whether an opt-out policy is in place or on the cards. But as they did not inform their authors about the deal in the first place, any opt-out policy is now not functional."</p> </div><div> <p><em>The Bookseller</em> asked Taylor &amp; Francis if it was possible to opt out and requested clarification over whether authors had been told about the AI deal. The publisher’s spokesman said he couldn’t comment further. <em>The Bookseller</em> has also contacted Microsoft for comment.</p>
<p>Clemens told&nbsp;<em>The Bookseller </em>the response from the academic community following her post on X shows the issue has "struck a nerve, and authors around the world are rightfully concerned".</p>
<p>"We are at a crossroads in the production and dissemination of research knowledge, and in my view the biggest problem with this deal is the reduction of academic research into raw content from which data can be extracted and repackaged as knowledge," Clemens said.</p>
<p>Mia Gray, professor of economic geography at the University of Cambridge, wrote on X: "This is disturbing and an increasingly important issue for academics."</p>
<p>James McConnachie, author and journalist posted on X: "Authors: check your contracts! Ask your publisher about their AI policy."</p>
<p>Ambre Morvan, senior policy manager and contracts advisor at the Society of Authors, told&nbsp;<em>The Bookseller</em>: “The Society of Authors is concerned to see publishers signing deals with tech companies without consulting authors and creators first."</p>
<p>She added: "There are copyright, moral rights and data protection questions that need to be carefully considered, as well as questions about transparency and fairness of payment from (authorised) uses by tech companies. The impact of such uses on traditional sales of the author’s work and the author’s professional future more widely must also be considered. Creators are the backbone of our world-leading creative industries, and we cannot emphasise enough the vital need to protect them."</p>
<p>The Society of Authors (SoA) urged authors who "find their work has been used without their consent" to contact them for guidance and encouraged authors to complete <a href="https://www.alcs.co.uk/news/alcs-launches-survey-on-ai-licenses/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a survey currently being conducted by the Authors’ Licensing and Collecting Society</a> (ALCS) around collective licensing options for authors.</p>
<p>ALCS’s c.e.o Barbara Hayes, told <em>The Bookseller:</em> "We know that developments in generative AI technologies are happening at speed with deals between publishers and technology companies the subject of regular media reports. We believe it’s imperative that the interests and rights of authors are fully represented within these discussions and negotiations which is unfortunately often the step missing at present."</p>
<p><span dir="ltr">Earlier this week the Copyright Clearance Centre announced the availability of AI re-use rights within its&nbsp;<a title="https://gbr01.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3a%2f%2fwww.copyright.com%2fsolutions-annual-copyright-license%2f&amp;data=05%7c02%7cmatilda.battersby%40thebookseller.com%7c8d60b159185e4d4723f208dca7d0a573%7c681bf9290a374aebb6da197c32182db1%7c0%7c0%7c638569761768939727%7cunknown%7ctwfpbgzsb3d8eyjwijoimc4wljawmdailcjqijoiv2lumziilcjbtii6ik1hawwilcjxvci6mn0%3d%7c0%7c%7c%7c&amp;sdata=yqt%2bv6lxusxjfigo%2bg53f%2b6iqugfi9xid8ggklpibho%3d&amp;reserved=0" href="https://gbr01.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.copyright.com%2Fsolutions-annual-copyright-license%2F&amp;data=05%7C02%7CMatilda.Battersby%40thebookseller.com%7C8d60b159185e4d4723f208dca7d0a573%7C681bf9290a374aebb6da197c32182db1%7C0%7C0%7C638569761768939727%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=YQt%2BV6lXuSxJfigO%2Bg53F%2B6IQUGfi9xID8GgKlpiBho%3D&amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" rel="noopener" aria-label="Link Annual Copyright License">Annual Copyright License</a> (ACL) — which it claims is "the first-ever collective licensing solution for the internal use of copyrighted materials in AI systems." The license will provides holders with rights and remuneration for new uses of their content.&nbsp;</span></p> </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The European Union must keep funding free software (133 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://pad.public.cat/lettre-NCP-NGI</link>
            <guid>41010458</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 19:57:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://pad.public.cat/lettre-NCP-NGI">https://pad.public.cat/lettre-NCP-NGI</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41010458">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
    <nav>
    <!-- Brand and toggle get grouped for better mobile display -->
    <div>
        
        
        <p><a href="https://pad.public.cat/" title="HedgeDoc">
            <img src="https://pad.public.cat/banner/banner_h_bw.svg" alt="HedgeDoc">
            <img src="https://pad.public.cat/banner/banner_h_wb.svg" alt="HedgeDoc">
        </a></p><div>
            <ul role="menu" aria-labelledby="menu">
                <li role="presentation"><a role="menuitem" tabindex="-1" href="https://pad.public.cat/new" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><i></i> New</a>
                </li>
                <li role="presentation"><a role="menuitem" tabindex="-1" href="https://pad.public.cat/#" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> Publish</a>
                </li>
                <li></li>
                <li>Extra</li>
                <li role="presentation"><a role="menuitem" tabindex="-1" data-toggle="modal" data-target="#revisionModal"><i></i> Revision</a>
                </li>
                <li role="presentation"><a role="menuitem" tabindex="-1" href="https://pad.public.cat/#" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><i></i> Slide Mode</a>
                </li>
                
                <li></li>
                <li>Import</li>
                <li role="presentation"><a role="menuitem" tabindex="-1" href="https://pad.public.cat/#" target="_self"><i></i> Dropbox</a>
                </li>
                <li role="presentation"><a role="menuitem" href="https://pad.public.cat/#" data-toggle="modal" data-target="#gistImportModal"><i></i> Gist</a>
                </li>
                
                <li role="presentation"><a role="menuitem" href="https://pad.public.cat/#" data-toggle="modal" data-target="#clipboardModal"><i></i> Clipboard</a>
                </li>
                <li></li>
                <li>Download</li>
                <li role="presentation"><a role="menuitem" tabindex="-1" href="https://pad.public.cat/#" target="_self"><i></i> Markdown</a>
                </li>
                <li role="presentation"><a role="menuitem" tabindex="-1" href="https://pad.public.cat/#" target="_self"><i></i> HTML</a>
                </li>
                <li role="presentation"><a role="menuitem" tabindex="-1" href="https://pad.public.cat/#" target="_self"><i></i> Raw HTML</a>
                </li>
                <li></li>
                <li role="presentation"><a role="menuitem" href="https://pad.public.cat/#" data-toggle="modal" data-target=".help-modal"><i></i> Help</a>
                </li>
            </ul>
            
            </div>
    </div>
    <div>
        <ul>
            
            
            <span title="Help" data-toggle="modal" data-target=".help-modal">
                <i></i>
            </span>
        </ul>
        <ul>
            <li id="online-user-list">
                <a data-toggle="dropdown">
                    <span><i></i> OFFLINE</span>
                </a>
                <ul role="menu" aria-labelledby="menu">
                </ul>
            </li>
        </ul>
        <ul>
            <li>
                <a href="https://pad.public.cat/new" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
                    <i></i> New
                </a>
            </li>
            <li>
                <a href="https://pad.public.cat/#" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
                     Publish
                </a>
            </li>
            <li>
                <a data-toggle="dropdown">
                    Menu <i></i>
                </a>
                <ul role="menu" aria-labelledby="menu">
                    <li>Extra</li>
                    <li role="presentation"><a role="menuitem" tabindex="-1" data-toggle="modal" data-target="#revisionModal"><i></i> Revision</a>
                    </li>
                    <li role="presentation"><a role="menuitem" tabindex="-1" href="https://pad.public.cat/#" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><i></i> Slide Mode</a>
                    </li>
                    
                    <li></li>
                    <li>Import</li>
                    <li role="presentation"><a role="menuitem" tabindex="-1" href="https://pad.public.cat/#" target="_self"><i></i> Dropbox</a>
                    </li>
                    <li role="presentation"><a role="menuitem" href="https://pad.public.cat/#" data-toggle="modal" data-target="#gistImportModal"><i></i> Gist</a>
                    </li>
                    
                    <li role="presentation"><a role="menuitem" href="https://pad.public.cat/#" data-toggle="modal" data-target="#clipboardModal"><i></i> Clipboard</a>
                    </li>
                    <li></li>
                    <li>Download</li>
                    <li role="presentation"><a role="menuitem" tabindex="-1" href="https://pad.public.cat/#" target="_self"><i></i> Markdown</a>
                    </li>
                    <li role="presentation"><a role="menuitem" tabindex="-1" href="https://pad.public.cat/#" target="_self"><i></i> HTML</a>
                    </li>
                    <li role="presentation"><a role="menuitem" tabindex="-1" href="https://pad.public.cat/#" target="_self"><i></i> Raw HTML</a>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </li>
        </ul>
    </div>
</nav>


    
<!-- clipboard modal -->

<!-- locked modal -->

<!-- limit modal -->

<!-- message modal -->

<!-- gist import modal -->

<!-- snippet import modal -->

<!-- snippet export modal -->

<!-- delete modal -->

<!-- refresh modal -->


<!-- signin modal -->


<!-- help modal -->



<!-- revision modal -->


    








</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AI paid for by Ads – the GPT-4o mini inflection point (272 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://batchmon.com/blog/ai-cheaper-than-ads/</link>
            <guid>41010188</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 19:28:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://batchmon.com/blog/ai-cheaper-than-ads/">https://batchmon.com/blog/ai-cheaper-than-ads/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41010188">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Article"><header><p>July 18, 2024</p></header><section itemprop="articleBody"><p>OpenAI <a href="https://openai.com/index/gpt-4o-mini-advancing-cost-efficient-intelligence/">recently announced</a> their gpt-4o mini model, at a price of $0.15 per 1 million input tokens, and $0.60 per 1 million output tokens.</p>
<p>This extremely low cost AI model has just passed an inflection point.</p>
<p>It's now possible to build dynamic, AI generated content entirely supported by ads.</p>
<center>
<blockquote><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Introducing GPT-4o mini! It’s our most intelligent and affordable small model, available today in the API. GPT-4o mini is significantly smarter and cheaper than GPT-3.5 Turbo.<a href="https://t.co/sqJsFEYHWq">https://t.co/sqJsFEYHWq</a> <a href="https://t.co/g6jMttp1mF">pic.twitter.com/g6jMttp1mF</a></p>— OpenAI Developers (@OpenAIDevs) <a href="https://twitter.com/OpenAIDevs/status/1813990748406317221?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">July 18, 2024</a></blockquote>
</center>
<h3>How much do publishers earn from ad impressions?</h3>
<p>The amount of money an ad impression generates varies significantly across display mediums and content categories.</p>
<p>But we can get a good heuristic from <a href="https://adsense.google.com/start/#calculator">Google's AdSense estimated revenue calculator</a>.</p>
<p>The calculator gives you an estimate for your annual ad revenue potential based upon your content category (Finance, Games, Health, etc...) and your monthly page views.</p>
<p>For example, putting in 50k page views a month, with a Finance category, gives a potential yearly earnings of $2,000.</p>
<p>I'm going to take the <strong>median</strong> across all categories, which is an estimated annual revenue of $1,550 for 50,000 monthly page views.</p>
<p>This is approximately <strong>~$0.00022 earned per page view</strong>.</p>
<h3>How much does it cost to generate AI content?</h3>
<p>Let's invent a blog that generates content in response to whatever the user types in the search bar.</p>
<p>We'll generate the article the user is looking for, on the fly. Will it be mostly nonsense? Probably. But let's go for it anyway, just to illustrate a point.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>user: "how to have my macbook audibly greet me whenever I flip it open"</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In order to facilitate this, we'll wrap the user's query around a prompt.</p>
<p>Below is the prompt we'll use.</p>
<div data-language="text"><pre><code>You are an excellent blog writer. You write blogs that rank well in search engines because you know about SEO and how to use highly relevant and popular keywords. Your blog posts are informative, and help users achieve what they are looking for.

You will receive queries from users searching for blog posts. You will create blog posts that matches their query, that are helpful, and that answer or are relevant to whatever they are searching for.

Respond with only the blog post.</code></pre></div>
<p>With this prompt, and the user query, we have <strong>119 input tokens</strong> according to <a href="https://platform.openai.com/playground/chat?models=gpt-4o-mini">OpenAI's Playground</a>.</p>
<p>The response generated by gpt4o-mini, is only <strong>829 output tokens</strong>.</p>
<div data-language="text"><pre><code># How to Make Your MacBook Audibly Greet You When You Flip It Open

If you want your MacBook to greet you with a chime or a specific sound every time you flip it open, it’s a fun way to personalize your device and make your daily interactions a bit more exciting. While macOS doesn’t come with a built-in feature to audibly greet you immediately upon opening the lid, there are a few creative workarounds to achieve a similar effect. In this blog post, we will discuss a couple of methods you can set up for your MacBook to greet you audibly.

## Method 1: Setting Up a Startup Sound

1. **System Preferences:**
   - Go to the Apple menu in the upper-left corner of your screen.
   - Select **System Preferences**.
   - Click on **Sound** and then navigate to the **Sound Effects** tab.
   
2. **Enable Startup Sound:**
   - Make sure the option “Play sound on startup” is checked. This way, your MacBook will play the selected sound every time you start it up.
   - Note: This method will only play sound when the MacBook is fully powered down and then opened again.

While this method does not greet you specifically upon opening the lid from sleep mode, it’s effective for a full startup.

## Method 2: Create an Automator App for a Custom Greeting

For more customization, you can use the Automator app to create your own greeting sound that plays when the MacBook wakes from sleep.

### Steps to Create Your Greeting:

1. **Open Automator:**
   - Search for **Automator** in Spotlight Search or find it in the Applications folder.

2. **Create New Document:**
   - Choose **New Document** and select **Application**.

3. **Use the Run Shell Script Action:**
   - In the sidebar, find **Utilities** and drag the **Run Shell Script** action to the main area.

4. **Enter the AppleScript Command:**
   - Replace the default script with the following:
     ```bash
     osascript -e 'tell app "System Events" to say "Welcome back!"'
     ```

5. **Choose Your Sound:**
   - If you want a specific sound file instead of a spoken greeting, use the following command instead:
     ```bash
     afplay /path/to/your/soundfile.mp3
     ```
   - Make sure you replace `/path/to/your/soundfile.mp3` with the actual file path of your chosen audio file.

6. **Save Your Application:**
   - Go to **File &gt; Save**, and name it something like “Greeting Sound.” Ensure it is saved in the Applications folder.

### Automating the Greeting Sound:

1. **Open System Preferences:**
   - Go to **System Preferences** and select **Users &amp; Groups**.

2. **Select Your User Account:**
   - Click on your username and select the **Login Items** tab.

3. **Add Your Automator App:**
   - Click the **“+”** button and navigate to the Greeting Sound app you created. Add it to the list.

Now, whenever your MacBook wakes from sleep, your personalized greeting sound will play.

## More Personalization Options

- **Use a Different Voice:** If you used the text-to-speech option, you can change the voice in **System Preferences** &gt; **Accessibility** &gt; **Spoken Content**.
- **Add More Sounds:** You can repeat the process for multiple sounds or greetings by creating separate Automator apps.

## Conclusion

By using the methods outlined above, you can add a personal touch to your MacBook experience. Whether you choose the simple startup sound or get creative with an Automator app, these options allow you to greet your MacBook (and yourself) every time you open it. So, go ahead and set it up, and enjoy your daily welcome back! 

Feel free to share your own unique greeting sounds or any additional tips in the comments below!</code></pre></div>
<p>Let's calculate how much we paid for this article.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Token Type</th>
<th>Number of Tokens</th>
<th>Cost per 1 Million Tokens</th>
<th>Calculated Cost</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Input Tokens</td>
<td>119</td>
<td>$0.15</td>
<td>$0.00001785</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Output Tokens</td>
<td>829</td>
<td>$0.60</td>
<td>$0.0004974</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Total Cost</strong></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td><strong>$0.00051525</strong></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The cost to generate the article was <strong>$0.00051525</strong>. And it wasn't half-bad.</p>
<h3>Ad impression vs AI cost.</h3>
<p>You can probably see where I'm going with this now.</p>
<p>For that blog post, we might earn <strong>~$0.00022</strong> for the single page impression from the user that requested it.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the blog post itself, had a cost of <strong>$0.00051525</strong> to generate.</p>
<p>We made a net profit of $0.00022 - $0.00051525 = <strong>$-0.00029525</strong>!</p>
<p>Woohoo, we lost money! We're going to be rich!</p>
<p>Joking aside, let's imagine that blog post receives <strong>only 5 page views</strong> throughout its entire lifetime, which is a pretty conservative estimate to make.</p>
<p>Now, we'll earn $0.00022 * 5 = <strong>$0.0011</strong>.</p>
<p>Subtracting our cost, $0.0011 - $0.00051525 = <strong>$0.00058475</strong>.</p>
<p>That's <strong>5.8 hundreths of a penny</strong>. Don't go spending it all in one place.</p>
<h2>Is this going to actually happen?</h2>
<p>Will the future of the internet be entirely dynamically generated AI blogs in response to user queries?</p>
<p>I don't know. I hope not. But the internet has been on a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enshittification">downward trend for a while now</a>.</p>
<p>Most of the internet is probably already SEO content blogspam generated by cheap copywriters.</p>
<h2>Is anyone doing this now?</h2>
<p>In a fun way, yes, check out <a href="https://websim.ai/">Websim</a> which uses LLMs to dynamically generate an alternative internet. It's a "web simulator" brought to you by AI.</p>
<p>They're not making money though. There aren't any ads (yet).</p></section><hr></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Never Update Anything (170 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.kronis.dev/articles/never-update-anything</link>
            <guid>41009942</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 19:07:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.kronis.dev/articles/never-update-anything">https://blog.kronis.dev/articles/never-update-anything</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41009942">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section id="blog-hero">
    
    <section>
        
<p>Here's a fair warning: this article is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reductio_ad_absurdum">reductio ad absurdum</a>, therefore you shouldn't take it as gospel. However, i do believe that this point of view is extreme enough that it usually gets shut down immediately, yet doesn't have any frank discussion about it, which makes it the perfect subject for me to write about! To reiterate, i'm not suggesting that you go out there after reading this and never update any of your production software, merely consider the points that are offered here.</p>
<p>So, as the article title suggests, you should never update anything. Not your OS. Not your libraries in your software project. Not your tools. What would make someone come to this controversial idea? Actually trying to do that, of course! </p>
<p>When you're telling your colleagues that you can't really work because Windows or JetBrains IDEs need to install some updates, they'll give you understanding, yet annoyed glances. When you tell clients that you cannot ship software because first you need to spend a few days or weeks refactoring software to keep up with the latest library releases, they will express their displeasure at you and will probably look elsewhere for someone who won't care about updates. When your company won't be the first to market, because about 20% of your total development capacity needs to spent on keeping up with the technical debt, which is slowly forced upon by the industry, while another 20% of the effort needs to go to writing and maintaining a test suite, the company will suffer as a result. And once you actually do get the buy-in to update the components and when it turns out that migrating from Spring to Spring Boot is actually a herculean effort that means carrying over about 50 dependencies of a legacy Java project that has about 1 million SLoC, during which you also discover that at least 20-30 of those are painfully out of date, then you'll just start writing blog posts like this.</p>
<p>My premise is that updates are a massive waste of time, most of the time. Obviously, someone will jump out and say that "Hey, if you don't update, your Windows XP installation will get added to a botnet in less than a week," and they'll also be right at the same time. </p>
<h3>Types of updates are the problem</h3>
<p>The problem here is that we never differentiate between the types of updates properly: </p>
<ul>
<li>major leaps in the development of the software which add new features</li>
<li>security updates that don't change any actual functionality apart from the security fix</li>
<li>bug fixes that should not alter any functionality in significant ways</li>
<li>small backwards compatible feature updates that are essentially opt in</li>
</ul>
<p>There are plenty of things that you might want to feasibly change and update without any of the other functionality being altered. Actually, the situation is so bad in that regard, that most if not all of our modern software only ever has feature updates which sooner or later will have breaking changes in them. Otherwise, if you wanted to eliminate the possibility of running into breaking changes entirely, the development of any library would look like this:</p>
<p><img alt="how updates would look" src="https://blog.kronis.dev/images/h/o/w/-/u/how-updates-would-look-aff7472e.jpeg"></p>
<p>In the image, we see that we have major releases (with the "V" prefix), for example, we'd have MySQL 5, that would eventually be updated to MySQL 6, MySQL 7 and MySQL 8 (which is funny, if you know anything about how that actually worked out). Esentially, you'd have a few large releases, that represent both new features being added, as well as breaking changes. Then, you have the minor versions which introduce new functionaly (with the "f" prefix) and patches (with the "s" prefix) which in this case would mean security fixes. </p>
<p>Essentially, i'm describing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_versioning">semantic versioning</a>, where this scheme would be approximately <code>V.f.s</code>, where you have a clear distinction between the major, minor and patch versions. However, instead of abandoning minor releases, you'd have to keep them up to date, since in practice different minor releases are not always compatible. If you wanted to support all of the versions of your software without forcing your users to use the new features, it would mean maintaining a new instance of your codebase for every minor release in existence. And in this case we're also simplifying things, because we assume that the patch versions will never break anything, which would probably mean that we need to preserve non-security related bugs and only fix them across minor releases.</p>
<p>You'd have to backport any and all security fixes from your newest versions, should the older ones also be affected. For example, if you discover a problem in V5.2.15 and fix it in V5.2.16, then you'd have to port these changes back to the current V5.1.X version and V5.0.X version, which is probably doable when you have 3 releases, but less so with 30.</p>
<p>And it goes the other way around, if you discover a problem in one of your older releases and the newer ones are also affected, then you have to port the changes forwards. For example, if you discover a problem in V5.0.14 and fix it in V5.0.15, then you'd have to port these changes forwards to the current V5.1.X and V5.2.X versions, where you run into the same problem as above.</p>
<p>In practice, things almost never work like that because that necessitates too much work. If you tried doing that, your issue tracking software could look like this:</p>
<pre><code>Issue: MYSOFT-3401
Description: Security breakage in $FOO module.
Assignee: You
Status: Ready to test

Versions affected:
- V7.6.245
- V7.5.267
- ... (down to V7.0.X)
- V6.10.315
- V6.9.326
- ... (down to V6.0.X)
- V5.14.421
- V5.13.442
- ... (down to V5.0.X)

Fixed in:
- V7.6.246
- V7.5.268
- ... (down to V7.0.X)
- V6.10.316
- V6.9.327
- ... (down to V6.0.X)
- V5.14.422
- V5.13.443
- ... (down to V5.0.X)</code></pre>
<p>Of course, testing all of that would be interesting, as would fixing further issues. Imagine having to do this for every single bug report and change. You'd spend days if not weeks fixing even trivial bugs if you'd have to support every single release of your software. That's why a lot of companies just drop support for older packages and leave people with no updates at all in cases where a minor version actually does break something, which isn't as much solving the problem, as it is simply sweeping it under the rug. </p>
<p>I'm sure that some of them would perhaps want to update their older versions, but it simply isn't feasible, perhaps apart from supporting the major version as a whole and forcing people to update to the newest minor versions to keep getting support. So in reality, the list of supported versions would indeed be just the last minor releases in the first example above, which would look a bit like the following:</p>
<p><img alt="actual updates are more like" src="https://blog.kronis.dev/images/a/c/t/u/a/actual-updates-are-more-like-e7f2dfac.jpeg"></p>
<p>More doable, but still not good enough in my mind - minor versions are for new features, which you don't necessarily want. My experience shows that oftentimes these new and supposedly backwards compatible features still break old functionality. Perhaps it's due to some refactoring that was needed, other times there were bugs fixed that old code relied upon and assumed to be the right way to do things. </p>
<p>My pain is that you'll never actually know how far you can update, seeing as the breaking changes will get you sooner or later, even if it's supposed to just be a bug fix. In reality, you might find that you can only run your software with a subset of the released versions (orange being what you have now, green what you can update to without breakages, red being everything that won't work):</p>
<p><img alt="how far you can update without breakages" src="https://blog.kronis.dev/images/h/o/w/-/f/how-far-you-can-update-before-breakages-618dd6ac.jpeg"></p>
<p>Now, the understandable argument here is: "Breaking changes are inevitable, you should just update your code." which is fair, but at the same time kind of useless. The industry shows that there are still plenty of projects that are stuck with JDK 8 and MySQL 5.7, or even a better example, old PHP versions like 5.6.40 and realistically cannot be updated and eventually will receive no security updates either, because all of that is simply too hard. And good luck with trying to tell your clients that now you'll probably need to alter or rewrite a huge portion of your code that uses the now deprecated or removed packages - oftentimes they simply won't understand that code rots with time.</p>
<p>Worse yet, those that don't care about semantic versioning don't even attempt to keep track of all of this stuff - i've seen projects out there in the wild, where V6.9.0 is always followed by V7.0.0 and V7.0.1 is code for "we screwed up the previous release, so this is just a hotfix", plenty of people and orgs out there just look at version numbers like something to put in Jira and get paid for, rather than a measure of what the software is compatible with.</p>
<h3>Noone wants updates</h3>
<p>But that's just the tip of the iceberg. I think i've briefly described while backporting security fixes and such is pretty hard, even though some operating systems still try to do that. Now, here's a story about why updates are actually bad. In a word: breaking changes. In the aforementioned Spring migration, i updated the <a href="https://flywaydb.org/">Flyway</a> version and ran into the following message:</p>
<pre><code>org.flywaydb.core.internal.license.FlywayEditionUpgradeRequiredException: Flyway Teams Edition or Oracle upgrade required: Oracle OLD_VERSION is no longer supported by Flyway Community Edition, but still supported by Flyway Teams Edition.</code></pre>
<p>I think that this is the inevitable future of software. "Want support for older versions of stuff that you're stuck with because of organizational reasons beyond your control? Sure, pay us!" If you look at the pricing page, you actually see that you'd need to part with 3000 USD for that sort of a license:</p>
<p><img alt="flyway costs" src="https://blog.kronis.dev/images/f/l/w/a/y/flway-costs-0bd2cc78.jpeg"></p>
<p>Now, i'm using this as an example for intentionally breaking support for older versions in a way that will hopefully (from the company's point of view) lead to them dying off and therefore the companies won't need to explicitly support them for a long time, thus attempting to solve the problem above. However, there are also plenty of cases out there, where updates introduce other breaking changes, oftentimes being forced upon the user against their will!</p>
<p>For example, i want to use Flyway, but i don't want to be forced to use a version, which drops support for the DB that i need to use. And yet, i wasn't even consulted about this, since the newest version is mandated by Spring Boot:</p>
<pre><code>&lt;dependency&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;org.flywaydb&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;flyway-core&lt;/artifactId&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;</code></pre>
<p>There are plenty of cases out there like this as well! For example, Docker Desktop doesn't let you decide whether you want updates or not, unless you pay them:</p>
<p><img alt="docker desktop updates" src="https://blog.kronis.dev/images/d/o/c/k/e/docker-desktop-updates-6f750760.png"></p>
<p>And i'm sure that we've all also heard plenty of other horror stories of this very same trend, be it <a href="https://www.howtogeek.com/670084/what-you-need-to-know-about-snaps-on-ubuntu-20.04/">Ubuntu forcing updates with snap packages</a>, or Windows 7 forcefully upgrading to newer releases when people step away from their computers for a bit.</p>
<p>In a word, the way how companies approach updates nowadays suck, especially when they break things!</p>
<h3>Updates are bad</h3>
<p>All you need to do is go to the "Everything is Broken" section of my blog and you will see plenty of cases of updates breaking things. In the current year, it's gotten to the point where i treat every update like a possibly completely clean wipe and install from nothing. Therefore, backups are of the utmost importance and every update needs to have at least an hour or two set aside for when things will inevitably go wrong, as they oftentimes have in the past.</p>
<p>But here's the thing - if i don't want to rely on <a href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/who-does-that-server-really-serve.html">SaaSS</a>, then i have to host and manage my software by myself. If i want to do that, then i need to handle the updates myself as well. Every update takes a significant amount of time and potentially can break things. And, even more importantly, if there are any non-standard configuration changes done (even the theme of this very blog), then things become more likely to break and waste my time. But i don't have unlimited amounts of time. </p>
<p>Actually, i don't have enough time to do my day job, learn new technologies for when it inevitably becomes stale and would otherwise lead to my career death, to also help my aging parents around the countryside estate with various chores, at the same time educate myself on both things in the industry and news in the world, as well as spend anywhere between 1-2 hours working out every day (a weight loss and personal wellness effort which seems to be working and about which i'll write a post some day) and have any sort of enjoyment of life in general, for example, by reading a sci-fi book in the evenings.</p>
<p>Ergo, i cannot update. Ergo, companies cannot ship features AND handle all of the updates, without having enough tests to catch all of the problems, which they will never be able to do no matter how good their tests are without slowing down their development pace to the point where they are no longer competitive.</p>
<p>Breaking feature updates of any sort are a nuisance and a direct impediment to progress more often than they're not and the more updates there are to be done, the less will be done. So don't update!</p>
<p>For example, to see why we shouldn't update software, let's take a look at <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/react">React</a>. To date, it has over 500 versions that have been released. No, not development snapshots (even though some experimental new versions are included), publically released versions that need to be installed, managed and coped with:</p>
<p><img alt="react versions" src="https://blog.kronis.dev/images/r/e/a/c/t/react-versions-1c6d1bd1.jpeg"></p>
<p>But once again, that's not the full story. Creating a simple React app with <code>create-react-app</code> makes us fetch an absolutely absurd amount of code, files and folders under <code>node_modules</code>:</p>
<p><img alt="node-modules" src="https://blog.kronis.dev/images/n/o/d/e/-/node-modules-4f8c2cd7.jpeg"></p>
<p>The idea of anyone ever understanding what's going on in there, or even auditing the security of all of it, is simply absurd! Don't believe me? Have a look at a dependency graph of this newly created "Hello world" project:</p>
<p><img alt="dependencies for a simple project" src="https://blog.kronis.dev/images/d/e/p/e/n/dependencies-for-a-simple-app-3da0fdaf.jpeg"></p>
<p>There are almost 1500 different modules in there! Many of those will have updates eventually. Many of those will also have breaking changes. You will run into problems with that. And even if you don't, the chances of something malicious getting in there, or for the development stack to get too large for you to be able to explore it is a question of time, rather one of probability. Once again, do not update!</p>
<h3>A more stable world without updates</h3>
<p>Let's look at some software that's the exact opposite. It's stable, doesn't have many breaking changes, and comes with "batteries included". No, i'm not talking about Angular, because even that's a mess in comparison, i'm talking about the <a href="https://www.lazarus-ide.org/">Lazarus IDE</a>, the modern and perhaps the only way to write Pascal code!</p>
<p><img alt="lazarus ide" src="https://blog.kronis.dev/images/l/a/z/a/r/lazarus-ide-e66e70cb.jpeg"></p>
<p>But it's not just a tool for writing code, instead, it does something a bit more amazing and peculiar. It also includes the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lazarus_Component_Library">Lazarus Component Library</a>, a large package of components and classes that concern not only GUI development (which, by the way, is abstracted away from the platforms entirely), but also offers lots of useful functionality that would otherwise need to be installed separately in almost any other tech stack out there:</p>
<p><img alt="lazarus component library" src="https://blog.kronis.dev/images/l/a/z/a/r/lazarus-component-library-ec79c91c.png"></p>
<p>Consider a scenario in which you want a MySQL driver for your app. In npm, you install it with bunches of dependencies. In Java, you pull it down with Maven or Gradle. In Python, you probably mess around with native extensions and have to install additional packages for your OS/container for it to even work. But with Lazarus, you drop it from the component palette into your application and are on your way. More platforms should be like that! Only support a known and trusted subset of software packages, keep them in tree and update them with the larger software package, in this case, the IDE.</p>
<p>Some of you might realize that what i'm describing is actually a lot like the <a href="https://docs.freebsd.org/en/books/handbook/ports/">FreeBSD approach to packages</a> - a stable enclave of "good software", that's optionally built upon by "ports", external and less table packages which the user will have to install themselves while being aware that those aren't supported. This sort of discouragement is exactly what most of the developers behind npm should have experienced more of! Same for React, Angular and most other technologies out there!</p>
<p>What i'm saying is that most of the integrations, dependencies and other software should be kept "in-tree" for most tools and packages out there. To hell with dynamic linking, use stable and minimalistic packages where needed, much like Windows does instead of Linux. Not only that, but put anything and everything you will ever need within the standard library or one or two large additional libraries. When eventually people will want to do more, provide pushback and curb their enthusiasm, make them do less instead of more. Slow down their pace of development and therefore also updates, preferring stable and good software in 5 to 10 years, as opposed to a half baked SaaS trap in 2 years, which will stop being supported in 4. Yes, at this point i'm getting into why this probably won't be possible in our current society, but my thoughts on the subject are unchanged by this reality.</p>
<h3>It's already happening</h3>
<p>But that's not to say that large, breaking releases aren't already happening and that people aren't sticking with the more stable stuff. Just look at <a href="https://snyk.io/blog/developers-dont-want-to-leave-java-8-as-64-hold-firm-on-their-preferred-release/">JDK versions that are used</a> in the industry:</p>
<p><img alt="java versions" src="https://blog.kronis.dev/images/j/a/v/a/-/java-versions-dca7d97c.jpeg"></p>
<p>The majority of existing projects out there are stuck with JDK 8, either due to their dependencies, their requirements, the ecosystem surrounding them, people not knowing about the benefits of the newer versions or simply not caring, or maybe the whole migration process being so time consuming, complicated and expensive that most companies out there simply don't want to touch the idea of doing that with a 10 foot pole. Essentially, what i described above is happening, but for all of the wrong reasons!</p>
<p>That brings me to the next point - situations like that are unavoidable. Sooner or later, there will be a significant amount of projects out there that will be stuck on old versions. There will be plenty of .NET 2.0 projects out there that will be running on dated installations of Windows Server 2012, instead of running the latest cross platform .NET Core or nowadays just .NET 5+. There will be plenty of old Java projects out there, or old PHP 5 projects out there and so on.</p>
<p>And my argument is not that this should be the expected outcome, but rather that it's something inevitable. Therefore, we should prepare for the eventual mess of legacy software, with entire languages possibly dying out and there being <a href="https://www.shrm.org/hr-today/news/hr-news/pages/desperate-need-for-cobol-programmers-underlines-importance-of-workforce-planning.aspx">significant issues in finding developers for them</a>, once it's discovered that there's actually software that's mission critical running in some old forgotten server room. And the easier we'll make dealing with old code for ourselves, the easier our lives will be - the more focus we'll put on truly non-breaking security updates that keep your dated software alive and running well, the better our future will be.</p>
<p>To that end, it's actually imperative that we slow down our development and the speed of updates, which add new features.</p>
<h3>Forcing things to slow down</h3>
<p>It's important that code written 20 years in the future remain vaguely similar to what we have now, so that old codebases can be recognized. Think Java Streams API, over syntactic sugar that changes how the actual language works. Think more along the lines of a stable base, that's well documented, thoroughly tested and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lFRKrHE8oPo&amp;t=518s">helps you use it with its discoverability</a>, instead of making you do some long forgotten Maven rituals that are like something out of Warhammer 40k, because noone bothered to write documentation in the pursuit of agility.</p>
<p>Bring back the old days where we engineered software to be used long term, instead of the current day world of: "Move fast and break things... oh, and don't bother thinking about what'll happen in 10 years, because your CV will be full of bleeding edge stuff, your bank account will be loaded and the troubles with most of the projects behind you won't be the slightest of your concerns." Realistically, you probably don't care about this stuff, but on the grand scale of things, perhaps you should.</p>
<p>I don't know about you, but i think that we shouldn't even need containers for reproducible environments in the first place. We should take a page out of the BSD operating system group book, instead of the GNU/Linux distros that are patched together out of bunches of different pieces of software of vastly varying quality. We shouldn't bend to the whims of the businesses which want things done yesterday. We should strive for the standards of engineering, where we are in control of the stacks that we work with and actually know what's going on inside of them.</p>
<p>Why do we need a new Java version every year and to only support the LTS ones for 5 years? Why do we need multiple Ubuntu releases per year and to only support the LTS ones for 5 years? Why not a new release every 5 years with everything else between being just patches and non breaking changes and a new major release every 20 years instead?</p>
<p>If things don't work out that way, then eventually we'll just have bunches of clueless code monkeys that execute npm commands that they don't understand to use frameworks and mechanisms which they have no hope of understanding to create as much value as quickly possible in the short period before all of that goes to hell and there's the eventual breakdown of nothing working and noone having any idea of why. I'm exaggerating slightly, but sooner or later software projects out there will exceed the cognitive capabilities of any single person - the only question is whether that will happen in 50 or 500 years.</p>
<h3>What to actually do now?</h3>
<p>Don't choose <a href="https://vimeo.com/156706113">Clusterpoint</a> for your project, which actually died in just a few years and now needs to be maintained in one of the legacy projects that i'm stuck in. Instead, pick <a href="https://www.postgresql.org/">PostgreSQL</a> and use it for <a href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/release/">more than 20 years</a>. Realistically, you can't avoid updates entirely, but you can at least try to decrease the frequency of them that you'll run into and will have to deal with.</p>
<p>Use self contained packages and only use them for the things that they are good for - for example, Ruby on Rails for a simple webapp will be a better choice than stitching together 20 different libraries. Having the freedom of choice in the library case will cause more problems than its worth.</p>
<p>And lastly, <a href="http://boringtechnology.club/">choose boring technology</a>. Only use software that you're sure will be supported in 10 years. Only use software, which has very few "unknown unknowns". Only use software, where the development pace has slowed down to a reasonable degree, as opposed to React pulling a sneaky on everyone and introducing hooks, which was a pretty bad move, especially if you needed to migrate to them. </p>
<p>Use maintenance mode software:</p>
<ul>
<li>Debian over Fedora</li>
<li>Docker Swarm over Kubernetes</li>
<li>Java over Go</li>
<li>Angular over React</li>
</ul>
<p>Of course, this only applies to projects that you're about to start. Chances are, that if you're working in the industry and will have to handle codebases written by others, then <a href="https://earthly.dev/blog/brown-green-language/">preferring brownfield technologies will make you less happy</a>, given that there will be more bad ones out there. Your mileage may vary and don't expect all of the answers here.</p>
<p>As for the actual updates: the above approaches should decrease the frequency at which they need to be done. That said, the title of the article is not entirely honest - do install security updates and do install updates to the LTS software that you're using, be it Ubuntu LTS, Unity LTS, Java 11, or anything else... Just be sure that you have backups that work before doing that!</p>
<h3>Update</h3>
<p>I've cleaned the text up a little bit and have decided to extract an idea about a versioning scheme out of the main body of text.</p>
<p>I believe that software could benefit from something more finely grained than semantic versioning. </p>
<p>Perhaps an alternate scheme, that goes more into detail about what's included in any given release:</p>
<ul>
<li>major new functionality changes</li>
<li>minor, backwards compatible'ish functionality additions</li>
<li>patch, bug fixes that could still break code that's written with them in mind</li>
<li>security, fixes that should not affect code bugs as long as those do not concern security exploits</li>
</ul>
<p>Maybe it would be possible to have those patch versions be globally unique, so that you'd know that your software <code>V5.152.4567.7213</code> has had 5 major versions released so far, 152 feature releases across those major versions, 4567 bug fixes to date and 7213 security fixes? Thus, you could tie them to Jira ticket numbers or what have you, though it would probably break some ordering of these versions somewhere, so i'm not entirely sure about that. Granted, i can't actually tell whether adding that sort of complexity would actually be good for anyone, seeing as people seem to have trouble keeping themselves to the standards set forth by semantic versioning already. </p>
<h3>Update #2</h3>
<p>I've actually written <a href="https://blog.kronis.dev/articles/stable-software-release-system">a separate article about how software versioning could be done</a>, with a larger focus on stability and backwards compatibility. I still think that i'm quite there yet in regards to the quality of my writing, but it should serve as a conceptual alternative to semver, maybe it's worth a look at?</p>
<p>Someone actually posted this article on Hacker News, though sadly i missed it due to being busy with my work. Nonetheless, you can go to the thread and <a href="https://bit.ly/30i6Eep">read my comment</a>, which should provide a real world example of why breaking changes and large generational shifts can be a very time consuming thing.</p>
<p>To sum up everything above in a single sentence:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In my eyes it could be pretty nice to have a framework version that's supported for 10-20 years and is so stable that it can be used with little to no changes for the entire expected lifetime of a system.</p>
</blockquote>
    </section>
    <i id="to-start"></i>
</section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What Happened to Bert and T5? (222 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.yitay.net/blog/model-architecture-blogpost-encoders-prefixlm-denoising</link>
            <guid>41009803</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 18:54:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.yitay.net/blog/model-architecture-blogpost-encoders-prefixlm-denoising">https://www.yitay.net/blog/model-architecture-blogpost-encoders-prefixlm-denoising</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41009803">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-0370f11da47205b70fe2">
  <p>The people who worked on language and NLP about 5+ years ago are left scratching their heads about where all the encoder models went. If BERT worked so well, why not scale it? What happened to encoder-decoders or encoder-only models?&nbsp;</p><p>Today I try to unpack all that is going on, in this new era of LLMs. I Hope this post will be helpful. </p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1721063358593_12105">
  <p>Few months ago I was also writing a long tweet-reply to this <a href="https://x.com/srush_nlp/status/1779938508578165198" target="_blank">tweet</a> by <a href="https://x.com/srush_nlp" target="_blank">@srush_nlp</a> at some point. Then the tweet got deleted because I closed the tab by accident.¯\_(ツ)_/¯  I promised to write it as a blog post some day. <br></p><div><p>So here it is!</p><p>This will be the first part of a series of blog posts I plan to write about model architectures in the era of LLMs (I hope).&nbsp;</p></div><h4><strong>A quick primer  (Skip connection to next section if you feel confident)</strong></h4><p>There are mainly three overarching paradigms of model architectures in the past couple of years. Encoder-only models (<em>e.g., BERT</em>), Encoder-Decoder models (<em>e.g., T5</em>) and decoder-only models (e.g., <em>GPT series</em>). People get confused a lot about this and people often have tons of misconceptions about these dichotomies and architectures so I’m hoping this post will help.</p><p>The first thing to really understand is that encoder-decoder models are actually still autoregressive models. A decoder in an encoder-decoder model is literally and fundamentally still a causal decoder. Instead of pre-filling a decoder model, some text can be offloaded to an encoder, which is then sent to the decoder via cross-attention. Yes, T5 models are also language models!</p><p>A variant of this is a Prefix Language model or PrefixLM <strong>architecture</strong>, which does almost the same thing minus the cross attention (<em>and some other small details like sharing weights between encoder/decoder plus not having no encoder bottleneck</em>). PrefixLMs are also sometimes known as non-casual decoders. In short, encoder-decoders, decoder-only models and PrefixLMs are not that different altogether!</p><p>In the latest excellent lecture by Hyung Won, he masterfully gave explanations about the relationship between these models. You can check it out <a href="https://x.com/hwchung27/status/1800676312916656592" target="_blank">here</a>. Good stuff.</p><p>Meanwhile, encoder-only models such as the OG BERT does denoising differently (i.e., in-place) and to some extent, rely on classification “task” heads to do anything useful with the base model after pretraining. Denoising objective was later adopted in models like T5 in an “adapted style” using the sequence to sequence format.</p><p>To this end, it is worth noting that denoising in T5 is not exactly a new objective function per se (in the machine learning sense) but rather a data transformation across inputs, i.e., you can also train span corruption objective with a causal decoder too by the way!</p><p>People always assume encoder decoder models have to be denoising models partly because of the <em>overly representative</em> T5 model. However, <em>this is not always true.</em> You can train an encoder-decoder with a regular language modeling task (i.e.m, CLM). Conversely you can also train a causal decoder with the span corruption task. As I’ve said earlier, this is mostly a data transformation.</p><div><p>It is also worth to note that, generally speaking, an Encoder-Decoders of 2N parameters has the same compute cost as a decoder-only model of N parameters which gives it a different FLOP to parameter count ratio. This is just like “model sparsity” that is split across inputs and targets.</p><p>This is nothing new, and I didn’t come up with anything new here. It’s already in the 2019 T5 paper and reemphasized in the UL2 paper.&nbsp;</p></div><p>For now, glad to get this out of the way. Now onto objectives.</p><h4>On the denoising objective (does it not work? does it not scale? is it too easy?)</h4><p>The denoising objective I’m referring to is any variation of the “span corruption” task. This is sometimes known as “infilling” or “fill in the blank”. There are variations on how to express it (i.e., span length, randomness, sentinel tokens etc). But you get the gist.&nbsp;</p><p>While the denoising objective in BERT style models are mostly “in-place”, (e.g., classification head on top of mask tokens), the slightly more modern way is to do it “T5-style”, <em>ala</em> data transformation that can be processed by an encoder-decoder or decoder-only model. In such a data transformation, masked tokens are just “moved to the back” for the model for prediction.</p><p>The primary goal of pretraining is to build a useful internal representation that can be aligned for downstream tasks in the most efficient and effective way possible. The better the internal representations, the easier to use these learned representations for anything useful later. The simple next word prediction&nbsp; “causal language modeling” objective is known to do this very well and has served as the bread and butter of the LLM revolution. The question now at hand is whether the denoising objective is just as good.</p><p>From publicly available information, we know that T5-11B works pretty well even after being aligned/SFT-ed (Flan-T5 XXL’s MMLU score is 55+, which is more than decent for a model of this scale and of that time). Hence, we can make some conclusion that the transfer process (pretraining -&gt; alignment) of the denoising objective works relatively reasonably well at this scale.</p><p>My take is that denoising objectives are great but pretty insufficient as a standalone objective. A big drawback is because of a reason which we could call less “loss exposure”. In denoising objectives, only a small amount of tokens are being masked and gets learned as a result (i.e., taken into account in the loss). Conversely, in regular language modeling, this is close to 100%. This makes for pretty low sample efficiency per FLOP which makes denoising objectives hugely disadvantaged on a flop-basis comparison.&nbsp;</p><p>Another drawback is that denoising objectives are more unnatural than regular language modeling since it reformats the input/output in a strange way, making them a little awkward for few-shot learning. (It’s still possible to massage these models to do reasonably okay on few-shot tasks though). Hence, I believe denoising objectives should pretty much only be used as a complementary objective to regular language modeling.</p><h4>The early days of unification and why xBERTs went extinct</h4><p>The gradual phasing out of BERT-like models was an interesting phase that not many people talk about these days. It was subtle. This could also explain why we don’t see any mega large scale BERT models running around anymore. The reason? It was largely a matter of unification and shift in task/modeling paradigms. BERT-style models are cumbersome, but the real deprecation of BERT models was because people wanted to do all tasks at once, which led to a better way of doing denoising - using autoregressive models.</p><p>During 2018-2021, there was an implicit paradigm shift of single task finetuning to massively multi-task models. This slowly gravitated us towards the unified “SFT” models that we see today that are universal and general purpose. It was simply so hard to do this with BERT. I don’t think this has anything much to do with “denoising” at all. People simply found a way to re-express denoising pretraining tasks if they wanted to use such a model (i.e., T5) which made BERT-style models pretty much deprecated at this point because there is a strictly better alternative.</p><p>To be even more concrete, encoder-decoder and decoder-only models were able to express multiple tasks at once without the need for task specific classification heads. For Encoder-Decoders, if the decoder was getting in the way, researchers and engineers also began to find out that yanking out the encoder performed just as competitive as a BERT encoder. Moreover, it also retains the same bidirectional attention benefit that made BERT competitive over GPT models at small (often production) scale.&nbsp;</p><h4>The value of denoising objectives</h4><p>Denoising pretraining objective also learns to predict the next word in a similar way to regular language modeling. However, different from regular causal language modeling, a data transformation is applied to the sequence such that the model learns to “fill in the blanks” instead of simply predicting the naturally occuring left-to-right text.&nbsp;</p><p>Notably, denoising objectives are sometimes also called “infilling tasks” that are sometimes mashed together into pretraining together with regular language modeling tasks.</p><div><p>While the exact configuration and implementation details can vary, modern LLMs today may use a combination of language modeling and infilling in some capacity. It is actually interesting how this mixture of LM + infilling seemed to have been propagated around the same time (e.g., <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.05131"><span>UL2</span></a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.14255"><span>FIM</span></a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02414"><span>GLM</span></a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2201.07520"><span>CM3</span></a>), with many groups bringing their own flavor of this mixture in some way. On a side note, the largest publicly disclosed &amp; reported model trained in this style is likely the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.10403"><span>PaLM-2 model</span></a>.</p><p>It is also worth noting that pretraining task mixtures could be also stacked sequentially and does not necessarily have to be mixed concurrently, i.e., Flan-T5 originally trains on 1T span corruption tokens and switches out to 100B tokens of prefix language modeling objective before flan instruction tuning. To some extent, this qualifies as a mixed denoised/LM objective model. To be clear, prefix language modeling objective (not to be confused with architecture) is simply casual language modeling with a split point randomly determined and sent to the input side (with no loss and non-casual masking). </p><p>On a side’s note, infilling could have originated from the world of code LLMs, where filling in the blank was more of a feature desired by coding applications. Meanwhile, UL2 was motivated more by unifying the class of tasks that denoising objectives and bidirectional LLMs do well on with inherently generative tasks (such as summarization or open-ended generation). An advantage of this autoregressive style of denoising “shift to the back” is that it allows the model to not only learn longer range dependencies but also implicitly benefit from <em>non-explicit</em> bidirectional attention (since you would already have seen the future in order to fill in the blank).</p><p>Anecdotal experience is that denoising objectives learn representations that are better at certain classes of tasks, sometimes in a more sample efficient way. In the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.11399"><span>U-PaLM</span></a> paper, we showed how a small amount of span corruption up-training changes behavior and emergence on a set of BIG-Bench tasks. On top of that, finetuning models trained with this objective generally result in better supervised fine-tuning models, especially at smaller scale.</p><p>When it comes to single-task finetuning, you can see the OG <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.02311" target="_blank">PaLM-1</a> 62B model gets defeated by a much smaller T5 model. Bidirectional attention + denoising objective packs a punch at a relatively small scale! I’m sure many practitioners see this happen these days as well, especially in production.</p></div><h4>What about bidirectional attention?</h4><div><p>Bidirectional attention is an interesting “inductive bias” for language models - one that is commonly conflated with objectives and model backbones. The usefulness of inductive biases changes at different compute regions and could have different effects on scaling curves at different compute regions. That said, it could be true that bidirectional doesn’t seem to matter that much at larger scales compared to smaller scales, or have different impacts on different tasks or modalities. For instance, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07726v1" target="_blank">PaliGemma</a> makes use of PrefixLM architectures.</p><p>As Hyung won also points out in his <a href="https://x.com/hwchung27/status/1800676312916656592" target="_blank">lecture</a>, PrefixLM models (decoder-only models with bidirectional attention) also have an issue with caching and are an intrinsic drawback with this type of architecture. However, I think there are many ways to work around this flaw which is out of scope for this post.</p></div><h4>Pros and Cons of Encoder-Decoder architectures</h4><div><p>Encoder-decoder architectures actually have some pros vs regular decoder-only models. The first case is where the encoder side is not restricted by a causal mask. To some extent, you can go crazy with the attention layers by doing aggressive pooling or any form of linear attention without worrying about the autoregressive design restriction. This is a good way to offload not so important “context” to an encoder. You can also make the encoder smaller, which is neat. </p><p>One example of how encoder-decoder architecture was necessary was in <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.12672" target="_blank">Charformer</a>, where we could go crazy on the encoder and mitigate the speed drawbacks of byte-level models. Encoder-side innovations allow quick wins without worrying about major resigns of the causal mask.&nbsp;</p></div><p>Meanwhile, one negative point of the encoder-decoder versus PrefixLM is that inputs and targets have to have fixed allocated budgets. For instance, if the input budget is 1024 tokens, the encoder side has to be padded to this value which causes a lot of potential for wasted compute. Conversely, in PrefixLM, input and targets can just be directly concatenated which mitigates this problem.</p><h4>Relevance to models today and key takeaways</h4><p>The ability to reason with inductive biases both at architectural and from a pre-training perspective is a critical aspect of being a competent LLM researcher and practitioner today. Understanding the fundamental nuances helps one to extrapolate and continue to innovate.</p><p>Here are my key takeaways:</p><ol data-rte-list="default"><li><p>Encoder-decoder and decoder-only models are both autoregressive models that have implementation-level differences and pros/cons. They are subtly different inductive biases. Optimal usage really depends on downstream use-case and pretty much application constraints. Meanwhile, for most LLM usage and niche use-cases aside, BERT style encoder models are mostly considered deprecated.</p></li><li><p>Denoising objectives are mostly complementary to CLM. They have just found their way as “supporting objectives” in pretraining. Training CLM with denoising objectives usually helps in some way. While this happens very frequently in code models (i.e., code infilling), it is not uncommon (though not mandatory) for general purpose models today still pretrain with CLM with some denoising objective.</p></li><li><p>Bidirectional attention helps a lot at smaller scales but is generally optional at larger scales. This is mostly anecdotal. I see bidirectional attention has a form of inductive bias, just like many other types of modifications to Transformer models.</p></li></ol><p>Finally, on to recap, we don’t see any scaled up xBERTs running around: BERT models got deprecated in favor of more flexible forms of denoising (autoregressive) T5 models. This is largely due to paradigm unification where people would like to perform any task with a general purpose model (as opposed to task specific model). Meanwhile, autoregressive denoising gets sometimes folded as side objectives to casual language models.&nbsp;</p><h4>Final words &amp; Acknowledgements</h4><div><p>It’s really fun to write about model architecture. I hope to write more about LLMs and AI research in general. </p><p>I thank Hyung Won Chung and Vinh Tran for feedback on this post.</p></div>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The CrowdStrike file that broke everything was full of null characters (285 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/jeremyphoward/status/1814364640127922499</link>
            <guid>41009740</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 18:47:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/jeremyphoward/status/1814364640127922499">https://twitter.com/jeremyphoward/status/1814364640127922499</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41009740">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Opinion: I'd rather have a headphone jack and a microSD slot than AI in my phone (116 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41009359</link>
            <guid>41009359</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 18:14:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41009359">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <tbody><tr id="41009454"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41009454" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41009454&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I agree 100%. And when people inevitably claim that the reason for eliminating the headphone jack is so you could have a phone that could withstand being dropped in water, I think back to the Samsung Galaxy S5 that I bought 10 years ago. It has a headphone jack, a microSD slot, and a user-removable battery, plus an IP67 rating.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41009730"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41009730" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41009730&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I'll also add that the S5 was a much more convenient size than the enormous phones they make these days, some of probably wouldn't even fit in my pocket.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41011459"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41011425"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41011425" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41011425&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p><a href="http://phandroid.com/2014/04/19/galaxy-s5-water-damage/amp/" rel="nofollow">http://phandroid.com/2014/04/19/galaxy-s5-water-damage/amp/</a></p><p>&gt; The Galaxy S5 is very good about reminding you close your charger door snugly and make sure your battery cover is snapped on COMPLETELY before continuing. This is a message you shouldn’t dismiss (although it allows you to) because the reminder is a good one. I can say with confidence that during both water tests my phone back cover and battery port were completely secured.</p><p>&gt; Somehow, though, water snuck its way into my battery.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41009607"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41009607" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41009607&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>To offer an alternative data point, I don't really want any of the above. Just make it cheaper, smaller, and with guaranteed security updates for as long as possible.</p><p>The only wired headphones I own are high-impedance """audiophile""" headphones, that a phone couldn't really drive in the first place.</p><p>As for storage, I don't do a whole lot on my phone except for messaging and looking things up on-the-go, none of which needs much in terms of storage space. I've had my current phone (iPhone SE3, 128GB) for over 2 years, and I've never even had to delete anything (and when the day comes, I'll transfer the contents of the photo gallery over to external storage).</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41010181"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41010181" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41010181&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>3.5mm jack, microSD and removable batteries is the holy grail.</p><p>The only reason these aren't included anymore on flagship phones is because companies think they can upsell you on BT headphones, cloud storage plans and extended warranties. They're building for shareholder value, not the customer.</p><p>Plenty of midrange and low end phones still come with the jack and microSD, but removable batteries seem to be extinct.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41013741"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41013741" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41013741&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Sony is making high end phones that have all these features, like the xperia line. The UI is a little wonky, and you have to degoogle the phone, but after that its pretty solid.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41010200"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41012479"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41012479" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41012479&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Maybe we should carry our phones around less often.</p><p>I carry a media player, like an iPod. 500GB sd card, balanced and unbalanced headphone outs, and actual physical buttons and knobs for control.</p><p>Phones can do everything, but there are too many compromises. Ebook readers, and media players do one thing very well.</p><p>You also get a lot of peace when you disconnect from apps, scrolling and notifications and just enjoy your music out in the world.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41010028"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41010028" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41010028&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I've got a Sony Xperia phone from last year. It's got a headphone jack and sdcard slot, waterproof, latest chipset etc. Plus a very close to vanilla Android. Yet they sold so few that Sony are pulling out of the US phone market. It seems to me that folks who say they want those things don't actually want them that much.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41013593"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41013593" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41013593&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I definitely do, I have never bought a phone without a headphone jack. I feel like that will end soon though, as the line of phones I'm using seems to be dying, and it's the last of its kind.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41010951"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41010951" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41010951&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; It seems to me that folks who say they want those things don't actually want them that much.</p><p>On the contrary, we do. There's just not enough of us.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41013010"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41010197"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41010197" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41010197&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Sony hasn't been relevant in the phone industry since the transition to smartphones. Samsung, Huawei, Lenovo and others sell millions of phones with these features, but the flagship models still exclude them.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41010435"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41010435" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41010435&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>The early Sony Android phones were available in stores. I remember the first smartphone I got was a Sony, and, compared to a friend's Samsung, it was really lovely, great screen, better feeling build quality. Maybe they never competed on price? I didn't even think about the brand back then, just chose the nicest one in the store.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41013439"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41013439" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41013439&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Nobody wants a high-end android cameraphone where the camera firmware self-destructs when you unlock the bootloader.</p><p>For better or for worse, the android world is reliant on custom roms if you want long-term software support. Wiping the camera firmware is unacceptable given that reality.</p><p>Again, the whole custom rom thing is a bandaid patch on a shitty, user-hostile OS model that makes it nearly impossible to perform a vital function of the computing system (updates). The inability to deliver updates effectively is itself a symptom of a product defect here.  It would be better if we could require all companies to provide useful first-party support lifecycles for the products they release.</p><p>But sony is <i>deliberately</i> gutting the device’s functionality to prevent you from unlocking it and that’s unacceptable even among android devices. <i>If</i> you’re going to do this shitty custom rom model, vendors that decide to kill even the ability to try and use that bandaid are going to suffer poor sales.</p><p>I would love a high-end cameraphone, the Xperia lineup was a serious consideration when I bought my last phone. But I could never get over the hump of buying a device that would have less than 2 years of updates by the time I got it, <i>and</i> that would deliberately self-destruct if I attempted to extend it beyond that.</p><p>I got an iPhone instead. Much less user-hostile. Forcing me to use a custom rom is already user-hostile, but to then <i>punish me for doing it</i> is unconscionable.</p><p>Oddly enough, there’s not nearly as much emphasis on banging the EU’s door down to stop that kind of waste and really honestly intentional/malicious damage, as there is about whatever apple thing people are whining about this week. Oh no the pelican case full of oem phone repair tooling that apple lets you rent (or buy) is too big/heavy… or Sony phones deliberately self-destruct themselves when you unlock the bootloader… somehow the “we can do both!” reply-guys never get around to doing both. Curious.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41011852"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41013297"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41013297" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41013297&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Ok. I paid more than that. What you're saying is I want x y and z, and also to be this cheap. But they're obviously catering for a niche market so you have to compromise and can't then just comment with "why can't they..." They would bring those features to cheaper phones if people were buying expensive phones for those features. You don't think it's worth the extra, so they don't think it's worth the effort.</p><p>I'm happy to pay a bit more, I use my phone all the time. I would like a folding phone but I don't consider those ready yet, but I'm not posting that all phones should be folding for $200 because they can do it in that model for 1800</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="41009916"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41009916" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41009916&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>How about the option to totally remove google without installing a custom rom.</p><p>you start your brand new phone and a pop up appears:</p><p>Would you like to remove google and all the other bloatware to start with a blank phone and choose to install exactly what you need and want.</p><p>Please click here.</p><p>I would then seriously consider buying a new phone instead of slightly older phones I can install custom roms on.</p><p>now that would be a thing.</p><p>In a perfect world</p><p>I have an old Samsung S4 2013 (android 11) and an old Motorola G3 (android 11). I keep the G3 to listen to FM radio as modern phones dont have the FMradio.</p><p>My main phone is a onplus 5T with android 14. A superb phone, 8 years old and still runs better than any modern phone my friends own. Cost me £75</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41010328"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41010328" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41010328&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>My Librem 5 has a 3.5mm jack, microSD slot, removable battery, even removable modem and smartcard, and an OS I fully control. Couldn't be happier. The only thing that bothers me is that it's soon going to be 5 years old and there's still nothing better on the market, and even though it's still usable it's at a point where I expect it to start showing its age rather sooner than later.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41011467"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41011467" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41011467&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>My librem 5 has about 3.5mm of dust on it because the phone is unusable. I appreciate that they made a linux phone, but they didn't make a phone people would actually want to use. Abysmal battery life where "carry a 2nd battery" is actual advice for every-day use. Very slow user interface. So large and heavy that I could murder someone with it. Questionable cellular support where the modem randomly disconnecting in the middle of a phone call can happen.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41011524"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41011524" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41011524&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>The battery lasts up to a single day, which is short but enough for me. I recognize that it's not a phone for everyone and it has its quirks, but "unusable" is not how I'd describe it after daily driving it for years. Overall I see more advantages than disadvantages when compared to mainstream devices, which is why I continue to use it.</p><p>&gt; where the modem randomly disconnecting in the middle of a phone call can happen</p><p>Fixed 1.5 years ago. It's a fun story BTW: <a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3200-universal-serial-bug-a-tale-of-spontaneous-modem-resets/" rel="nofollow">https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3200-univ...</a></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41013404"><td></td></tr>
                              <tr id="41009478"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41009478" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41009478&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Next you are telling me you want to go back to the time when mobiles needed a whole week to go through a charge. How outdated!</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41012474"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41012474" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41012474&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Not that I use android smart phones that much any more in the capacity to replace what a laptop might do, since google's ugly head all too often places too much hindrance on the apps I prefer to use, however I do still use unencrypted microSD for times when bluetooth isn't doing what it's supposed to do to transfer photos or it's just faster to put the card into  a reader and look at the contents on a laptop.</p><p>AI might seem useful - but sadly on a phone and prepackaged, I only see it becoming a <i>minder</i> in a short time - no thanks.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41011649"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41011833"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41009639"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41009437"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41009437" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41009437&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I have so many tablets and cheap phones that don't have the storage to play high-end mobile games,  it would make a difference to me if I could expand my memory easily.  (Edit: some folks got excited because I said "memory" when I meant "storage")</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41009474"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41009498"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41009561"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41009561" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41009561&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>SD cards do not increase the memory available to user applications. They are storage devices, even if the technology behind them has the word memory in the name.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41009843"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41009843" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41009843&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>It's not the memory that's the problem,  it's that games like FGO require 10GB or more of flash storage which is most of a 16GB device particularly when you consider overhead for software updates.  It's not like the game has high memory requirements but it sure has a lot of levels, textures and stuff.</p><p>It's amusing the the IBM Mainframe world still uses the word "storage" to describe RAM.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                                    <tr id="41011054"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41011054" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41011054&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I love bluetooth headphones for listening to video or even talking, but it has too much latency for realtime music performance (e.g. music making apps, or using your phone as a MIDI instrument with a controller). Having the wired headphone jack without the latency that (any) wireless protocol necessarily introduces is a huge deadlbreaking feature and I never see people defending bluetooth headsets mention it.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41009902"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41009902" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41009902&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I agree, that's why I am daily driving Samsung Galaxy S10 (exynos version) on LineageOS.</p><p>I miss 2010-2015 smartphone market, it was much more innovative than it's now :(</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41009578"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41010074"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41009435"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41010259"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41010259" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41010259&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Thinking like this is how we end up with gadgets that can be barely be called pocket computers.</p><p>Thank God that the computer industry came of age before iOSsification began. Need to connect to wired headphones? Buy a dongle. Need more storage? Pay for iCloud. Want to program on your iPad? Jump through a million hoops and end up using a remote desktop solution.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41009512"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41009512" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41009512&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I can understand the upgrade required for extra storage and AI subscriptions, but what revenue is earned from the elimination of the headphone jack? I can only see the marginal costs of adding one in, but for consumers who want it, it'd be a sales tactic.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41010121"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41010121" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41010121&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Bluetooth earphones are devices with a really limited lifespan.</p><p>You can use like 2 charges in a day easily and that a lifespan of one to 2 years.</p><p>For a lot if vendors it isn't a notable difference, for apple with the air pods it's MASSIVE</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41009462"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41009521"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41009521" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41009521&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I recently bought a NOS Samsung Note 10 Lite. A quarter the price of the S24, has the wonderful S-Pen and a headphone jack. And even though the battery is ostensibly not user replaceable, it is an easy job that can be done in five minutes without risking breaking anything else.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41009714"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41009714" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41009714&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Similarly, I now have a Samsung Galaxy A52, which has a headphone jack and a microSD slot (but no user-replaceable battery).</p><p>I'm not particularly price conscious, so I feel like Samsung lost out on an opportunity to sell me a flagship phone because those no longer have these features I care about. Luckily, this much cheaper phone still has the two that are most important to me. When they stop offering them at all, I'll be done with Samsung.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41009809"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41009809" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41009809&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>You just explained something that I've been noticing more and more lately. A decade ago, the early adopters and nerds would have the flagship phones, and everybody else would have the cheap phone. Today the power users are using the absolute cheapest phones and the general public has the flagships.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                                    <tr id="41011789"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41011789" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41011789&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>My device has a headphone jack and a microSD slot and I've never used either of them.</p><p>In regards of AI I find transcription, summarization, translation and predictive text to be very useful.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41010122"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41010122" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41010122&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; Curious how others feel about this.</p><p>I would rather have none of these things, but if I had to choose, AI sounds more useful.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41010211"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41010211" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41010211&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>"sounds" being the operative word. I don't consider being able to erase something on a photo, or add something to be a compelling enough use case. The AI demos I've seen have been pretty pathetic relative to the hype they're trying to build.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41010272"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41010272" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41010272&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I agree for the most part. I'm pretty bearish on most AI stuff, I was not interested in the Apple Intelligence stuff announced at WWDC beyond having a Siri that might be able to answer a question directly instead of sending me to a Wikipedia article.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="41009477"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41009562"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41009562" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41009562&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>This was the defining feature of the best MP3 player I ever owned. (I believe it was a Sanyo Sansa.) I wound up using it way more than the MP3 functionality. I was spoiled, living in NYC at the time, but there was/still is so much good content out there, if you spend the time to look (college, community, pirate, etc.).</p><p>It's depressing that such functionality is missing from modern devices. Entertainment value aside, it can be a lifeline in times of crisis/emergencies.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41009484"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41010063"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41011084"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41010154"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41010154" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41010154&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Alternative in what sense? I think most, if not all, modern Xperias have both headphone jacks and microSD slots. I'm not sure how they are when it comes to android updates though.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41010956"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41010956" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41010956&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Worst. 2 years only with awful track record even for the security updates.</p><p>And the price is around 1400 eur.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41011218"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="41010085"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41010085" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41010085&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>For me, the microSD slot is the important part, and the Galaxy A54 still has one.  No headphone jack, though.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41011037"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41011782"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41011782" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41011782&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Huh, the reviews I read seemed to say that the camera was a huge step up.  (But maybe they were mostly comparing to the A53, which seemed uniformly to be regarded as a regression.)  If not, then I feel quite stupid for paying the extra to "upgrade" to an A54, instead of an A52, from my A50.</p><p>(Also, though it's easy for me to believe this random search result is dodgy, and with the understanding that benchmarks don't mean much, Googling around for a chip comparison turned up <a href="https://gadgetversus.com/processor/qualcomm-sm7125-snapdragon-720g-vs-samsung-exynos-1380/" rel="nofollow">https://gadgetversus.com/processor/qualcomm-sm7125-snapdrago...</a> , which seems to suggest that the Exynos 1380 in the A54 wins over the Snapdragon 720G in the A52 in many benchmarks.)</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                              <tr id="41009513"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41009513" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41009513&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Headphone jack I’ve not really needed.</p><p>But I want a smartphone with a removable battery.  Same with laptops.</p><p>Let me kill the power.  Let me replace the batteries easily.</p><p>Give me thicker devices!</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41010086"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41012068"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41012068" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41012068&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>"Some people say give the customers what they want, but that's not my approach. Our job is to figure out what they're going to want before they do. I think Henry Ford once said, 'If I'd ask customers what they wanted, they would've told me a faster horse.' People don't know what they want until you show it to them. That's why I never rely on market research. Our task is to read things that are not yet on the page."</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41009646"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41010489"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41009445"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41010060"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41010060" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41010060&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Sony Xperia phones have this combination, including the just released version. Just nobody buys them.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41011882"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41009690"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41011185"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41011185" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41011185&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>My Zenfone 9 has a headphone jack. No SD card slot though, which I don't need.</p><p>So yeah, I voted for this position with my dollars, and will continue to do so.</p><p>Any phone with mandatory AI crap is Hard Pass.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41009739"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41011330"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41009464"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41009464" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41009464&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Yeah but how does Google/Apple make money off of cloud storage when you don't need it?</p><p>In some ways it's better to just get a usb-c fob for this functionality...have a problem with your headphone jack or microSD slot? Throw it out and replace it.</p><p>I'd rather see TB+ storage on my phone.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41010093"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41010093" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41010093&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>i would much rather have AI to do routine tasks on my phone for me and change settings without me having to dig through menus</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41009539"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41009539" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41009539&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I don't know if we need 8k video, but if it's going to be a feature it sure feels like we should have sd cards. This write-up is talking about 33GB/hr. Given the dinky ass 128GB that seems to be common, and given that the base install is often 30GB+, like, yeah, we need more storage. <a href="https://www.androidauthority.com/pixel-9-8k-more-storage-3462002/" rel="nofollow">https://www.androidauthority.com/pixel-9-8k-more-storage-346...</a></p><p>MicroSD cards are fantastic &amp; I'd want them anywhere. But man it's just so preposterous that they have so drastically outpaced phone's builtin storage. 0.5 or 1TB are basically unheard of on phones, but there's plenty of whole SSDs with far more components and cost selling for $50 or less. It's wild. What a supply side economics setup, so many companies all keeping the whole mobile market back, deliberately.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41013281"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41013281" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41013281&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I think Apple's aware of the storage limitations with 8k recording and so they won't bother to ship it in software for another couple years.</p><p>The utility gap between 4k and 8k video is tiny. I was eager to move from a giant 1080p TV to a giant 4k TV, but I have no desire to buy 8k.</p><p>Neither 8k TVs nor 8k monitors have occupied a meaningful amount of the market, and there appears to be not much demand for them. On the gaming side, the latest graphics cards still can't max out settings on most AAA games at 4k/60fps.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41011469"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41010295"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41009485"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41009485" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41009485&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I'm going to side with Apple on this one. Transistors are basically free and ports are expensive and unreliable. I'm happy they've been moving to eSIMs. I'd be fine if my next iPhone only supported wireless charging.</p><p>No ports is better.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41011147"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41011147" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41011147&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I've certainly have had ports fail, but software is worse, and bluetooth is a lot of software. My spouse's phone was able to connect to our van for some time, then a phone software update broke it, and it took 3 months for them to push a new one that fixed it. If it was a wired 4-pin connection for handsfree audio and either port failed, it would probably take less time to get it fixed. (Yes, a 4-pin connection probably leaves out features from Bluetooth, but no  agency to fix problems is worse)</p><p>I've yet to have a SIM fail on me, and I don't see why I would want to lose out on the convenience of removing the SIM from old phone, and inserting it into the new one. Moving an eSIM requires interaction with the carrier as I understand it.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41009609"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41009774"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41009774" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41009774&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41009359"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>If they weren't burning cash on AI, they'd be burning it on something equally useless. Smartphones have been more or less feature-complete for years now.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        </tbody></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Kompute – Vulkan Alternative to CUDA (161 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/KomputeProject/kompute</link>
            <guid>41009023</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 17:43:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/KomputeProject/kompute">https://github.com/KomputeProject/kompute</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41009023">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/8f872dee052b7c84233f785769c7e17ccfdbff17a05ebb774c2f3755d50ebf0e/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f56657273696f6e2d302e372e302d677265656e2e737667"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/8f872dee052b7c84233f785769c7e17ccfdbff17a05ebb774c2f3755d50ebf0e/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f56657273696f6e2d302e372e302d677265656e2e737667" alt="GitHub" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/Version-0.7.0-green.svg"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/b8c3ea661caa26d6e0bad0e0cf08250dcee72f166dc0ca80005fac186c0f8e9b/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f432b2b2d313425453225383025393432302d707572706c652e737667"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/b8c3ea661caa26d6e0bad0e0cf08250dcee72f166dc0ca80005fac186c0f8e9b/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f432b2b2d313425453225383025393432302d707572706c652e737667" alt="GitHub" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/C++-14%E2%80%9420-purple.svg"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/a931e304cb2822ce527ed9230da8fed82e1f6972ff0674706ff06fe5a4ac333c/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f4275696c642d636d616b652d7265642e737667"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/a931e304cb2822ce527ed9230da8fed82e1f6972ff0674706ff06fe5a4ac333c/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f4275696c642d636d616b652d7265642e737667" alt="GitHub" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/Build-cmake-red.svg"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/ca62ec82651f12fc0f1cd5c027a061794b6bf2199fe9130be61cbab90ae8002e/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f507974686f6e2d332e37254532253830253934332e392d626c75652e737667"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/ca62ec82651f12fc0f1cd5c027a061794b6bf2199fe9130be61cbab90ae8002e/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f507974686f6e2d332e37254532253830253934332e392d626c75652e737667" alt="GitHub" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/Python-3.7%E2%80%943.9-blue.svg"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/266f5c100f8205bd1421e45d36346c42927736082dc1d7b8409d0850e4764eaa/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f4c6963656e73652d4170616368652d626c61636b2e737667"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/266f5c100f8205bd1421e45d36346c42927736082dc1d7b8409d0850e4764eaa/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f4c6963656e73652d4170616368652d626c61636b2e737667" alt="GitHub" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/License-Apache-black.svg"></a>
<a href="https://bestpractices.coreinfrastructure.org/projects/4834" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/bd6283e527078fd79a22cbe272515776ac1c20c801ff86f65181d558cf478673/68747470733a2f2f626573747072616374696365732e636f7265696e6672617374727563747572652e6f72672f70726f6a656374732f343833342f6261646765" alt="CII Best Practices" data-canonical-src="https://bestpractices.coreinfrastructure.org/projects/4834/badge"></a></p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KomputeProject/kompute/master/docs/images/kompute.jpg"><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KomputeProject/kompute/master/docs/images/kompute.jpg"></a>
</td>
<td>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Kompute</h2><a id="user-content-kompute" aria-label="Permalink: Kompute" href="#kompute"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">The general purpose GPU compute framework for cross vendor graphics cards (AMD, Qualcomm, NVIDIA &amp; friends)</h3><a id="user-content-the-general-purpose-gpu-compute-framework-for-cross-vendor-graphics-cards-amd-qualcomm-nvidia--friends" aria-label="Permalink: The general purpose GPU compute framework for cross vendor graphics cards (AMD, Qualcomm, NVIDIA &amp; friends)" href="#the-general-purpose-gpu-compute-framework-for-cross-vendor-graphics-cards-amd-qualcomm-nvidia--friends"></a></p>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Blazing fast, mobile-enabled, asynchronous, and optimized for advanced GPU acceleration usecases.</h4><a id="user-content-blazing-fast-mobile-enabled-asynchronous-and-optimized-for-advanced-gpu-acceleration-usecases" aria-label="Permalink: Blazing fast, mobile-enabled, asynchronous, and optimized for advanced GPU acceleration usecases." href="#blazing-fast-mobile-enabled-asynchronous-and-optimized-for-advanced-gpu-acceleration-usecases"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">💬 <a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/community.html" rel="nofollow">Join the Discord &amp; Community Calls</a> 🔋 <a href="https://kompute.cc/" rel="nofollow">Documentation</a> 💻 <a href="https://medium.com/@AxSaucedo/machine-learning-and-data-processing-in-the-gpu-with-vulkan-kompute-c9350e5e5d3a" rel="nofollow">Blog Post</a> ⌨ <a href="#more-examples">Examples</a> 💾</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h5 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Kompute is backed by the Linux Foundation as a <a href="https://lfaidata.foundation/blog/2021/08/26/kompute-joins-lf-ai-data-as-new-sandbox-project/" rel="nofollow">hosted project</a> by the LF AI &amp; Data Foundation.</h5><a id="user-content-kompute-is-backed-by-the-linux-foundation-as-a-hosted-project-by-the-lf-ai--data-foundation" aria-label="Permalink: Kompute is backed by the Linux Foundation as a hosted project by the LF AI &amp; Data Foundation." href="#kompute-is-backed-by-the-linux-foundation-as-a-hosted-project-by-the-lf-ai--data-foundation"></a></p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Principles &amp; Features</h2><a id="user-content-principles--features" aria-label="Permalink: Principles &amp; Features" href="#principles--features"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="#your-first-kompute-python">Flexible Python module</a> with <a href="#your-first-kompute-c">C++ SDK</a> for optimizations</li>
<li><a href="#asynchronous-and-parallel-operations">Asynchronous &amp; parallel processing</a> support through GPU family queues</li>
<li><a href="#mobile-enabled">Mobile enabled</a> with examples via Android NDK across several architectures</li>
<li>BYOV: <a href="#motivations">Bring-your-own-Vulkan design</a> to play nice with existing Vulkan applications</li>
<li>Explicit relationships for GPU and host <a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/memory-management.html" rel="nofollow">memory ownership and memory management</a></li>
<li>Robust codebase with <a href="https://kompute.cc/codecov/" rel="nofollow">90% unit test code coverage</a></li>
<li>Advanced use-cases on <a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/machine-learning-and-data-processing-in-the-gpu-with-vulkan-kompute-c9350e5e5d3a" rel="nofollow">machine learning 🤖</a>, <a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/gpu-accelerated-machine-learning-in-your-mobile-applications-using-the-android-ndk-vulkan-kompute-1e9da37b7617" rel="nofollow">mobile development 📱</a> and <a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/supercharging-game-development-with-gpu-accelerated-ml-using-vulkan-kompute-the-godot-game-engine-4e75a84ea9f0" rel="nofollow">game development 🎮</a>.</li>
<li>Active community with <a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/community.html" rel="nofollow">monthly calls, discord chat and more</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KomputeProject/kompute/master/docs/images/komputer-logos.gif"><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KomputeProject/kompute/master/docs/images/komputer-logos.gif" alt="" data-animated-image=""></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Projects using Kompute ❤️  🤖</h2><a id="user-content-projects-using-kompute-️--" aria-label="Permalink: Projects using Kompute ❤️  🤖" href="#projects-using-kompute-️--"></a></p>

<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Getting Started</h2><a id="user-content-getting-started" aria-label="Permalink: Getting Started" href="#getting-started"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Below you can find a GPU multiplication example using the C++ and Python Kompute interfaces.</p>
<p dir="auto">You can <a href="https://discord.gg/MaH5Jv5zwv" rel="nofollow">join the Discord</a> for questions / discussion, open a <a href="https://github.com/KomputeProject/kompute/issues/new">github issue</a>, or read <a href="https://kompute.cc/" rel="nofollow">the documentation</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Your First Kompute (C++)</h3><a id="user-content-your-first-kompute-c" aria-label="Permalink: Your First Kompute (C++)" href="#your-first-kompute-c"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The C++ interface provides low level access to the native components of Kompute, enabling for <a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/async-parallel.html" rel="nofollow">advanced optimizations</a> as well as <a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/reference.html" rel="nofollow">extension of components</a>.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="
void kompute(const std::string&amp; shader) {

    // 1. Create Kompute Manager with default settings (device 0, first queue and no extensions)
    kp::Manager mgr; 

    // 2. Create and initialise Kompute Tensors through manager

    // Default tensor constructor simplifies creation of float values
    auto tensorInA = mgr.tensor({ 2., 2., 2. });
    auto tensorInB = mgr.tensor({ 1., 2., 3. });
    // Explicit type constructor supports uint32, int32, double, float and bool
    auto tensorOutA = mgr.tensorT<uint32_t>({ 0, 0, 0 });
    auto tensorOutB = mgr.tensorT<uint32_t>({ 0, 0, 0 });

    std::vector<std::shared_ptr<kp::Tensor>> params = {tensorInA, tensorInB, tensorOutA, tensorOutB};

    // 3. Create algorithm based on shader (supports buffers &amp; push/spec constants)
    kp::Workgroup workgroup({3, 1, 1});
    std::vector<float> specConsts({ 2 });
    std::vector<float> pushConstsA({ 2.0 });
    std::vector<float> pushConstsB({ 3.0 });

    auto algorithm = mgr.algorithm(params,
                                   // See documentation shader section for compileSource
                                   compileSource(shader),
                                   workgroup,
                                   specConsts,
                                   pushConstsA);

    // 4. Run operation synchronously using sequence
    mgr.sequence()
        ->record<kp::OpTensorSyncDevice>(params)
        ->record<kp::OpAlgoDispatch>(algorithm) // Binds default push consts
        ->eval() // Evaluates the two recorded operations
        ->record<kp::OpAlgoDispatch>(algorithm, pushConstsB) // Overrides push consts
        ->eval(); // Evaluates only last recorded operation

    // 5. Sync results from the GPU asynchronously
    auto sq = mgr.sequence();
    sq->evalAsync<kp::OpTensorSyncLocal>(params);

    // ... Do other work asynchronously whilst GPU finishes

    sq->evalAwait();

    // Prints the first output which is: { 4, 8, 12 }
    for (const float&amp; elem : tensorOutA->vector()) std::cout << elem << &quot;  &quot;;
    // Prints the second output which is: { 10, 10, 10 }
    for (const float&amp; elem : tensorOutB->vector()) std::cout << elem << &quot;  &quot;;

} // Manages / releases all CPU and GPU memory resources

int main() {

    // Define a raw string shader (or use the Kompute tools to compile to SPIRV / C++ header
    // files). This shader shows some of the main components including constants, buffers, etc
    std::string shader = (R&quot;(
        #version 450

        layout (local_size_x = 1) in;

        // The input tensors bind index is relative to index in parameter passed
        layout(set = 0, binding = 0) buffer buf_in_a { float in_a[]; };
        layout(set = 0, binding = 1) buffer buf_in_b { float in_b[]; };
        layout(set = 0, binding = 2) buffer buf_out_a { uint out_a[]; };
        layout(set = 0, binding = 3) buffer buf_out_b { uint out_b[]; };

        // Kompute supports push constants updated on dispatch
        layout(push_constant) uniform PushConstants {
            float val;
        } push_const;

        // Kompute also supports spec constants on initalization
        layout(constant_id = 0) const float const_one = 0;

        void main() {
            uint index = gl_GlobalInvocationID.x;
            out_a[index] += uint( in_a[index] * in_b[index] );
            out_b[index] += uint( const_one * push_const.val );
        }
    )&quot;);

    // Run the function declared above with our raw string shader
    kompute(shader);
}
"><pre><span>void</span> <span>kompute</span>(<span>const</span> std::string&amp; shader) {

    <span><span>//</span> 1. Create Kompute Manager with default settings (device 0, first queue and no extensions)</span>
    kp::Manager mgr; 

    <span><span>//</span> 2. Create and initialise Kompute Tensors through manager</span>

    <span><span>//</span> Default tensor constructor simplifies creation of float values</span>
    <span>auto</span> tensorInA = mgr.<span>tensor</span>({ <span>2</span>., <span>2</span>., <span>2</span>. });
    <span>auto</span> tensorInB = mgr.<span>tensor</span>({ <span>1</span>., <span>2</span>., <span>3</span>. });
    <span><span>//</span> Explicit type constructor supports uint32, int32, double, float and bool</span>
    <span>auto</span> tensorOutA = mgr.<span>tensorT</span>&lt;<span>uint32_t</span>&gt;({ <span>0</span>, <span>0</span>, <span>0</span> });
    <span>auto</span> tensorOutB = mgr.<span>tensorT</span>&lt;<span>uint32_t</span>&gt;({ <span>0</span>, <span>0</span>, <span>0</span> });

    std::vector&lt;std::shared_ptr&lt;kp::Tensor&gt;&gt; params = {tensorInA, tensorInB, tensorOutA, tensorOutB};

    <span><span>//</span> 3. Create algorithm based on shader (supports buffers &amp; push/spec constants)</span>
    kp::Workgroup <span>workgroup</span>({<span>3</span>, <span>1</span>, <span>1</span>});
    std::vector&lt;<span>float</span>&gt; <span>specConsts</span>({ <span>2</span> });
    std::vector&lt;<span>float</span>&gt; <span>pushConstsA</span>({ <span>2.0</span> });
    std::vector&lt;<span>float</span>&gt; <span>pushConstsB</span>({ <span>3.0</span> });

    <span>auto</span> algorithm = mgr.<span>algorithm</span>(params,
                                   <span><span>//</span> See documentation shader section for compileSource</span>
                                   <span>compileSource</span>(shader),
                                   workgroup,
                                   specConsts,
                                   pushConstsA);

    <span><span>//</span> 4. Run operation synchronously using sequence</span>
    mgr.<span>sequence</span>()
        -&gt;<span>record</span>&lt;kp::OpTensorSyncDevice&gt;(params)
        -&gt;<span>record</span>&lt;kp::OpAlgoDispatch&gt;(algorithm) <span><span>//</span> Binds default push consts</span>
        -&gt;<span>eval</span>() <span><span>//</span> Evaluates the two recorded operations</span>
        -&gt;<span>record</span>&lt;kp::OpAlgoDispatch&gt;(algorithm, pushConstsB) <span><span>//</span> Overrides push consts</span>
        -&gt;<span>eval</span>(); <span><span>//</span> Evaluates only last recorded operation</span>

    <span><span>//</span> 5. Sync results from the GPU asynchronously</span>
    <span>auto</span> sq = mgr.<span>sequence</span>();
    sq-&gt;<span>evalAsync</span>&lt;kp::OpTensorSyncLocal&gt;(params);

    <span><span>//</span> ... Do other work asynchronously whilst GPU finishes</span>

    sq-&gt;<span>evalAwait</span>();

    <span><span>//</span> Prints the first output which is: { 4, 8, 12 }</span>
    <span>for</span> (<span>const</span> <span>float</span>&amp; elem : tensorOutA-&gt;<span>vector</span>()) std::cout &lt;&lt; elem &lt;&lt; <span><span>"</span>  <span>"</span></span>;
    <span><span>//</span> Prints the second output which is: { 10, 10, 10 }</span>
    <span>for</span> (<span>const</span> <span>float</span>&amp; elem : tensorOutB-&gt;<span>vector</span>()) std::cout &lt;&lt; elem &lt;&lt; <span><span>"</span>  <span>"</span></span>;

} <span><span>//</span> Manages / releases all CPU and GPU memory resources</span>

<span>int</span> <span>main</span>() {

    <span><span>//</span> Define a raw string shader (or use the Kompute tools to compile to SPIRV / C++ header</span>
    <span><span>//</span> files). This shader shows some of the main components including constants, buffers, etc</span>
    std::string shader = (<span><span>R"(</span></span>
<span>        #version 450</span>
<span></span>
<span>        layout (local_size_x = 1) in;</span>
<span></span>
<span>        // The input tensors bind index is relative to index in parameter passed</span>
<span>        layout(set = 0, binding = 0) buffer buf_in_a { float in_a[]; };</span>
<span>        layout(set = 0, binding = 1) buffer buf_in_b { float in_b[]; };</span>
<span>        layout(set = 0, binding = 2) buffer buf_out_a { uint out_a[]; };</span>
<span>        layout(set = 0, binding = 3) buffer buf_out_b { uint out_b[]; };</span>
<span></span>
<span>        // Kompute supports push constants updated on dispatch</span>
<span>        layout(push_constant) uniform PushConstants {</span>
<span>            float val;</span>
<span>        } push_const;</span>
<span></span>
<span>        // Kompute also supports spec constants on initalization</span>
<span>        layout(constant_id = 0) const float const_one = 0;</span>
<span></span>
<span>        void main() {</span>
<span>            uint index = gl_GlobalInvocationID.x;</span>
<span>            out_a[index] += uint( in_a[index] * in_b[index] );</span>
<span>            out_b[index] += uint( const_one * push_const.val );</span>
<span>        }</span>
<span>    <span>)"</span></span>);

    <span><span>//</span> Run the function declared above with our raw string shader</span>
    <span>kompute</span>(shader);
}
</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Your First Kompute (Python)</h3><a id="user-content-your-first-kompute-python" aria-label="Permalink: Your First Kompute (Python)" href="#your-first-kompute-python"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The <a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/python-package.html" rel="nofollow">Python package</a> provides a <a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/python-reference.html" rel="nofollow">high level interactive interface</a> that enables for experimentation whilst ensuring high performance and fast development workflows.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="
from .utils import compile_source # using util function from python/test/utils

def kompute(shader):
    # 1. Create Kompute Manager with default settings (device 0, first queue and no extensions)
    mgr = kp.Manager()

    # 2. Create and initialise Kompute Tensors through manager

    # Default tensor constructor simplifies creation of float values
    tensor_in_a = mgr.tensor([2, 2, 2])
    tensor_in_b = mgr.tensor([1, 2, 3])
    # Explicit type constructor supports uint32, int32, double, float and bool
    tensor_out_a = mgr.tensor_t(np.array([0, 0, 0], dtype=np.uint32))
    tensor_out_b = mgr.tensor_t(np.array([0, 0, 0], dtype=np.uint32))

    params = [tensor_in_a, tensor_in_b, tensor_out_a, tensor_out_b]

    # 3. Create algorithm based on shader (supports buffers &amp; push/spec constants)
    workgroup = (3, 1, 1)
    spec_consts = [2]
    push_consts_a = [2]
    push_consts_b = [3]

    # See documentation shader section for compile_source
    spirv = compile_source(shader)

    algo = mgr.algorithm(params, spirv, workgroup, spec_consts, push_consts_a)

    # 4. Run operation synchronously using sequence
    (mgr.sequence()
        .record(kp.OpTensorSyncDevice(params))
        .record(kp.OpAlgoDispatch(algo)) # Binds default push consts provided
        .eval() # evaluates the two recorded ops
        .record(kp.OpAlgoDispatch(algo, push_consts_b)) # Overrides push consts
        .eval()) # evaluates only the last recorded op

    # 5. Sync results from the GPU asynchronously
    sq = mgr.sequence()
    sq.eval_async(kp.OpTensorSyncLocal(params))

    # ... Do other work asynchronously whilst GPU finishes

    sq.eval_await()

    # Prints the first output which is: { 4, 8, 12 }
    print(tensor_out_a)
    # Prints the first output which is: { 10, 10, 10 }
    print(tensor_out_b)

if __name__ == &quot;__main__&quot;:

    # Define a raw string shader (or use the Kompute tools to compile to SPIRV / C++ header
    # files). This shader shows some of the main components including constants, buffers, etc
    shader = &quot;&quot;&quot;
        #version 450

        layout (local_size_x = 1) in;

        // The input tensors bind index is relative to index in parameter passed
        layout(set = 0, binding = 0) buffer buf_in_a { float in_a[]; };
        layout(set = 0, binding = 1) buffer buf_in_b { float in_b[]; };
        layout(set = 0, binding = 2) buffer buf_out_a { uint out_a[]; };
        layout(set = 0, binding = 3) buffer buf_out_b { uint out_b[]; };

        // Kompute supports push constants updated on dispatch
        layout(push_constant) uniform PushConstants {
            float val;
        } push_const;

        // Kompute also supports spec constants on initalization
        layout(constant_id = 0) const float const_one = 0;

        void main() {
            uint index = gl_GlobalInvocationID.x;
            out_a[index] += uint( in_a[index] * in_b[index] );
            out_b[index] += uint( const_one * push_const.val );
        }
    &quot;&quot;&quot;

    kompute(shader)
"><pre><span>from</span> .<span>utils</span> <span>import</span> <span>compile_source</span> <span># using util function from python/test/utils</span>

<span>def</span> <span>kompute</span>(<span>shader</span>):
    <span># 1. Create Kompute Manager with default settings (device 0, first queue and no extensions)</span>
    <span>mgr</span> <span>=</span> <span>kp</span>.<span>Manager</span>()

    <span># 2. Create and initialise Kompute Tensors through manager</span>

    <span># Default tensor constructor simplifies creation of float values</span>
    <span>tensor_in_a</span> <span>=</span> <span>mgr</span>.<span>tensor</span>([<span>2</span>, <span>2</span>, <span>2</span>])
    <span>tensor_in_b</span> <span>=</span> <span>mgr</span>.<span>tensor</span>([<span>1</span>, <span>2</span>, <span>3</span>])
    <span># Explicit type constructor supports uint32, int32, double, float and bool</span>
    <span>tensor_out_a</span> <span>=</span> <span>mgr</span>.<span>tensor_t</span>(<span>np</span>.<span>array</span>([<span>0</span>, <span>0</span>, <span>0</span>], <span>dtype</span><span>=</span><span>np</span>.<span>uint32</span>))
    <span>tensor_out_b</span> <span>=</span> <span>mgr</span>.<span>tensor_t</span>(<span>np</span>.<span>array</span>([<span>0</span>, <span>0</span>, <span>0</span>], <span>dtype</span><span>=</span><span>np</span>.<span>uint32</span>))

    <span>params</span> <span>=</span> [<span>tensor_in_a</span>, <span>tensor_in_b</span>, <span>tensor_out_a</span>, <span>tensor_out_b</span>]

    <span># 3. Create algorithm based on shader (supports buffers &amp; push/spec constants)</span>
    <span>workgroup</span> <span>=</span> (<span>3</span>, <span>1</span>, <span>1</span>)
    <span>spec_consts</span> <span>=</span> [<span>2</span>]
    <span>push_consts_a</span> <span>=</span> [<span>2</span>]
    <span>push_consts_b</span> <span>=</span> [<span>3</span>]

    <span># See documentation shader section for compile_source</span>
    <span>spirv</span> <span>=</span> <span>compile_source</span>(<span>shader</span>)

    <span>algo</span> <span>=</span> <span>mgr</span>.<span>algorithm</span>(<span>params</span>, <span>spirv</span>, <span>workgroup</span>, <span>spec_consts</span>, <span>push_consts_a</span>)

    <span># 4. Run operation synchronously using sequence</span>
    (<span>mgr</span>.<span>sequence</span>()
        .<span>record</span>(<span>kp</span>.<span>OpTensorSyncDevice</span>(<span>params</span>))
        .<span>record</span>(<span>kp</span>.<span>OpAlgoDispatch</span>(<span>algo</span>)) <span># Binds default push consts provided</span>
        .<span>eval</span>() <span># evaluates the two recorded ops</span>
        .<span>record</span>(<span>kp</span>.<span>OpAlgoDispatch</span>(<span>algo</span>, <span>push_consts_b</span>)) <span># Overrides push consts</span>
        .<span>eval</span>()) <span># evaluates only the last recorded op</span>

    <span># 5. Sync results from the GPU asynchronously</span>
    <span>sq</span> <span>=</span> <span>mgr</span>.<span>sequence</span>()
    <span>sq</span>.<span>eval_async</span>(<span>kp</span>.<span>OpTensorSyncLocal</span>(<span>params</span>))

    <span># ... Do other work asynchronously whilst GPU finishes</span>

    <span>sq</span>.<span>eval_await</span>()

    <span># Prints the first output which is: { 4, 8, 12 }</span>
    <span>print</span>(<span>tensor_out_a</span>)
    <span># Prints the first output which is: { 10, 10, 10 }</span>
    <span>print</span>(<span>tensor_out_b</span>)

<span>if</span> <span>__name__</span> <span>==</span> <span>"__main__"</span>:

    <span># Define a raw string shader (or use the Kompute tools to compile to SPIRV / C++ header</span>
    <span># files). This shader shows some of the main components including constants, buffers, etc</span>
    <span>shader</span> <span>=</span> <span>"""</span>
<span>        #version 450</span>
<span></span>
<span>        layout (local_size_x = 1) in;</span>
<span></span>
<span>        // The input tensors bind index is relative to index in parameter passed</span>
<span>        layout(set = 0, binding = 0) buffer buf_in_a { float in_a[]; };</span>
<span>        layout(set = 0, binding = 1) buffer buf_in_b { float in_b[]; };</span>
<span>        layout(set = 0, binding = 2) buffer buf_out_a { uint out_a[]; };</span>
<span>        layout(set = 0, binding = 3) buffer buf_out_b { uint out_b[]; };</span>
<span></span>
<span>        // Kompute supports push constants updated on dispatch</span>
<span>        layout(push_constant) uniform PushConstants {</span>
<span>            float val;</span>
<span>        } push_const;</span>
<span></span>
<span>        // Kompute also supports spec constants on initalization</span>
<span>        layout(constant_id = 0) const float const_one = 0;</span>
<span></span>
<span>        void main() {</span>
<span>            uint index = gl_GlobalInvocationID.x;</span>
<span>            out_a[index] += uint( in_a[index] * in_b[index] );</span>
<span>            out_b[index] += uint( const_one * push_const.val );</span>
<span>        }</span>
<span>    """</span>

    <span>kompute</span>(<span>shader</span>)</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Interactive Notebooks &amp; Hands on Videos</h3><a id="user-content-interactive-notebooks--hands-on-videos" aria-label="Permalink: Interactive Notebooks &amp; Hands on Videos" href="#interactive-notebooks--hands-on-videos"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">You are able to try out the interactive Colab Notebooks which allow you to use a free GPU. The available examples are the Python and C++ examples below:</p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto">You can also check out the two following talks presented at the FOSDEM 2021 conference.</p>
<p dir="auto">Both videos have timestamps which will allow you to skip to the most relevant section for you - the intro &amp; motivations for both is almost the same so you can skip to the more specific content.</p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Architectural Overview</h2><a id="user-content-architectural-overview" aria-label="Permalink: Architectural Overview" href="#architectural-overview"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The core architecture of Kompute includes the following:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/reference.html#manager" rel="nofollow">Kompute Manager</a> - Base orchestrator which creates and manages device and child components</li>
<li><a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/reference.html#sequence" rel="nofollow">Kompute Sequence</a> - Container of operations that can be sent to GPU as batch</li>
<li><a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/reference.html#algorithm" rel="nofollow">Kompute Operation (Base)</a> - Base class from which all operations inherit</li>
<li><a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/reference.html#tensor" rel="nofollow">Kompute Tensor</a> - Tensor structured data used in GPU operations</li>
<li><a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/reference.html#algorithm" rel="nofollow">Kompute Algorithm</a> - Abstraction for (shader) logic executed in the GPU</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">To see a full breakdown you can read further in the <a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/reference.html" rel="nofollow">C++ Class Reference</a>.</p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<tbody><tr><th>
Full Architecture
</th>
<th>
Simplified Kompute Components
</th>
</tr><tr>
<td>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KomputeProject/kompute/master/docs/images/kompute-vulkan-architecture.jpg"><img width="100%" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KomputeProject/kompute/master/docs/images/kompute-vulkan-architecture.jpg"></a>
<p>

(very tiny, check the <a href="https://ethicalml.github.io/vulkan-kompute/overview/reference.html" rel="nofollow">full reference diagram in docs for details</a>)
</p><p>

<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KomputeProject/kompute/master/docs/images/suspicious.jfif"><img width="100%" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KomputeProject/kompute/master/docs/images/suspicious.jfif"></a></p></td>
<td>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KomputeProject/kompute/master/docs/images/kompute-architecture.jpg"><img width="100%" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KomputeProject/kompute/master/docs/images/kompute-architecture.jpg"></a>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Asynchronous and Parallel Operations</h2><a id="user-content-asynchronous-and-parallel-operations" aria-label="Permalink: Asynchronous and Parallel Operations" href="#asynchronous-and-parallel-operations"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Kompute provides flexibility to run operations in an asynrchonous way through vk::Fences. Furthermore, Kompute enables for explicit allocation of queues, which allow for parallel execution of operations across queue families.</p>
<p dir="auto">The image below provides an intuition on how Kompute Sequences can be allocated to different queues to enable parallel execution based on hardware. You can see the <a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/advanced-examples.html#parallel-operations" rel="nofollow">hands on example</a>, as well as the <a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/async-parallel.html" rel="nofollow">detailed documentation page</a> describing how it would work using an NVIDIA 1650 as an example.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KomputeProject/kompute/master/docs/images/queue-allocation.jpg"><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KomputeProject/kompute/master/docs/images/queue-allocation.jpg" alt=""></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Mobile Enabled</h2><a id="user-content-mobile-enabled" aria-label="Permalink: Mobile Enabled" href="#mobile-enabled"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Kompute has been optimized to work in mobile environments. The <a href="#build-overview">build system</a> enables for dynamic loading of the Vulkan shared library for Android environments, together with a working <a href="https://github.com/KomputeProject/kompute/tree/master/vk_ndk_wrapper_include">Android NDK wrapper</a> for the CPP headers.</p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">More examples</h2><a id="user-content-more-examples" aria-label="Permalink: More examples" href="#more-examples"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Simple examples</h3><a id="user-content-simple-examples" aria-label="Permalink: Simple examples" href="#simple-examples"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/advanced-examples.html#simple-shader-example" rel="nofollow">Simple multiplication example</a></li>
<li><a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/advanced-examples.html#record-batch-commands" rel="nofollow">Record batch commands with a Kompute Sequence</a></li>
<li><a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/advanced-examples.html#asynchronous-operations" rel="nofollow">Run Asynchronous Operations</a></li>
<li><a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/advanced-examples.html#parallel-operations" rel="nofollow">Run Parallel Operations Across Multiple GPU Queues</a></li>
<li><a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/advanced-examples.html#your-custom-kompute-operation" rel="nofollow">Create your custom Kompute Operations</a></li>
<li><a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/advanced-examples.html#logistic-regression-example" rel="nofollow">Implementing logistic regression from scratch</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">End-to-end examples</h3><a id="user-content-end-to-end-examples" aria-label="Permalink: End-to-end examples" href="#end-to-end-examples"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/machine-learning-and-data-processing-in-the-gpu-with-vulkan-kompute-c9350e5e5d3a" rel="nofollow">Machine Learning Logistic Regression Implementation</a></li>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/parallelizing-heavy-gpu-workloads-via-multi-queue-operations-50a38b15a1dc" rel="nofollow">Parallelizing GPU-intensive Workloads via Multi-Queue Operations</a></li>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/gpu-accelerated-machine-learning-in-your-mobile-applications-using-the-android-ndk-vulkan-kompute-1e9da37b7617" rel="nofollow">Android NDK Mobile Kompute ML Application</a></li>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/supercharging-game-development-with-gpu-accelerated-ml-using-vulkan-kompute-the-godot-game-engine-4e75a84ea9f0" rel="nofollow">Game Development Kompute ML in Godot Engine</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Python Package</h2><a id="user-content-python-package" aria-label="Permalink: Python Package" href="#python-package"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Besides the C++ core SDK you can also use the Python package of Kompute, which exposes the same core functionality, and supports interoperability with Python objects like Lists, Numpy Arrays, etc.</p>
<p dir="auto">The only dependencies are Python 3.5+ and Cmake 3.4.1+. You can install Kompute from the <a href="https://pypi.org/project/kp/" rel="nofollow">Python pypi package</a> using the following command.</p>

<p dir="auto">You can also install from master branch using:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="pip install git+git://github.com/KomputeProject/kompute.git@master"><pre><code>pip install git+git://github.com/KomputeProject/kompute.git@master
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">For further details you can read the <a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/python-package.html" rel="nofollow">Python Package documentation</a> or the <a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/python-reference.html" rel="nofollow">Python Class Reference documentation</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">C++ Build Overview</h2><a id="user-content-c-build-overview" aria-label="Permalink: C++ Build Overview" href="#c-build-overview"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The build system provided uses <code>cmake</code>, which allows for cross platform builds.</p>
<p dir="auto">The top level <code>Makefile</code> provides a set of optimized configurations for development as well as the docker image build, but you can start a build with the following command:</p>

<p dir="auto">You also are able to add Kompute in your repo with <code>add_subdirectory</code> - the <a href="https://github.com/KomputeProject/kompute/blob/7c8c0eeba2cdc098349fcd999102bb2cca1bf711/examples/android/android-simple/app/src/main/cpp/CMakeLists.txt#L3">Android example CMakeLists.txt file</a> shows how this would be done.</p>
<p dir="auto">For a more advanced overview of the build configuration check out the <a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/build-system.html" rel="nofollow">Build System Deep Dive</a> documentation.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Kompute Development</h2><a id="user-content-kompute-development" aria-label="Permalink: Kompute Development" href="#kompute-development"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">We appreciate PRs and Issues. If you want to contribute try checking the "Good first issue" tag, but even using Kompute and reporting issues is a great contribution!</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing</h3><a id="user-content-contributing" aria-label="Permalink: Contributing" href="#contributing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Dev Dependencies</h4><a id="user-content-dev-dependencies" aria-label="Permalink: Dev Dependencies" href="#dev-dependencies"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Testing
<ul dir="auto">
<li>GTest</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Documentation
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Doxygen (with Dot)</li>
<li>Sphynx</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Development</h4><a id="user-content-development" aria-label="Permalink: Development" href="#development"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Follows Mozilla C++ Style Guide <a href="https://www-archive.mozilla.org/hacking/mozilla-style-guide.html" rel="nofollow">https://www-archive.mozilla.org/hacking/mozilla-style-guide.html</a>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Uses post-commit hook to run the linter, you can set it up so it runs the linter before commit</li>
<li>All dependencies are defined in vcpkg.json</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Uses cmake as build system, and provides a top level makefile with recommended command</li>
<li>Uses xxd (or xxd.exe windows 64bit port) to convert shader spirv to header files</li>
<li>Uses doxygen and sphinx for documentation and autodocs</li>
<li>Uses vcpkg for finding the dependencies, it's the recommended set up to retrieve the libraries</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">If you want to run with debug layers you can add them with the <code>KOMPUTE_ENV_DEBUG_LAYERS</code> parameter as:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="export KOMPUTE_ENV_DEBUG_LAYERS=&quot;VK_LAYER_LUNARG_api_dump&quot;"><pre><code>export KOMPUTE_ENV_DEBUG_LAYERS="VK_LAYER_LUNARG_api_dump"
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h5 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Updating documentation</h5><a id="user-content-updating-documentation" aria-label="Permalink: Updating documentation" href="#updating-documentation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To update the documentation you will need to:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Run the gendoxygen target in the build system</li>
<li>Run the gensphynx target in the build-system</li>
<li>Push to github pages with <code>make push_docs_to_ghpages</code></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h5 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Running tests</h5><a id="user-content-running-tests" aria-label="Permalink: Running tests" href="#running-tests"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Running the unit tests has been significantly simplified for contributors.</p>
<p dir="auto">The tests run on CPU, and can be triggered using the ACT command line interface (<a href="https://github.com/nektos/act">https://github.com/nektos/act</a>) - once you install the command line (And start the Docker daemon) you just have to type:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="$ act

[Python Tests/python-tests] 🚀  Start image=axsauze/kompute-builder:0.2
[C++ Tests/cpp-tests      ] 🚀  Start image=axsauze/kompute-builder:0.2
[C++ Tests/cpp-tests      ]   🐳  docker run image=axsauze/kompute-builder:0.2 entrypoint=[&quot;/usr/bin/tail&quot; &quot;-f&quot; &quot;/dev/null&quot;] cmd=[]
[Python Tests/python-tests]   🐳  docker run image=axsauze/kompute-builder:0.2 entrypoint=[&quot;/usr/bin/tail&quot; &quot;-f&quot; &quot;/dev/null&quot;] cmd=[]
..."><pre><code>$ act

[Python Tests/python-tests] 🚀  Start image=axsauze/kompute-builder:0.2
[C++ Tests/cpp-tests      ] 🚀  Start image=axsauze/kompute-builder:0.2
[C++ Tests/cpp-tests      ]   🐳  docker run image=axsauze/kompute-builder:0.2 entrypoint=["/usr/bin/tail" "-f" "/dev/null"] cmd=[]
[Python Tests/python-tests]   🐳  docker run image=axsauze/kompute-builder:0.2 entrypoint=["/usr/bin/tail" "-f" "/dev/null"] cmd=[]
...
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">The repository contains unit tests for the C++ and Python code, and can be found under the <code>test/</code> and <code>python/test</code> folder.</p>
<p dir="auto">The tests are currently run through the CI using Github Actions. It uses the images found in <code>docker-builders/</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto">In order to minimise hardware requirements the tests can run without a GPU, directly in the CPU using <a href="https://github.com/google/swiftshader">Swiftshader</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">For more information on how the CI and tests are setup, you can go to the <a href="https://kompute.cc/overview/ci-tests.html" rel="nofollow">CI, Docker and Tests Section</a> in the documentation.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Motivations</h2><a id="user-content-motivations" aria-label="Permalink: Motivations" href="#motivations"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This project started after seeing that a lot of new and renowned ML &amp; DL projects like Pytorch, Tensorflow, Alibaba DNN, Tencent NCNN - among others - have either integrated or are looking to integrate the Vulkan SDK to add mobile (and cross-vendor) GPU support.</p>
<p dir="auto">The Vulkan SDK offers a great low level interface that enables for highly specialized optimizations - however it comes at a cost of highly verbose code which requires 500-2000 lines of code to even begin writing application code. This has resulted in each of these projects having to implement the same baseline to abstract the non-compute related features of the Vulkan SDK. This large amount of non-standardised boiler-plate can result in limited knowledge transfer, higher chance of unique framework implementation bugs being introduced, etc.</p>
<p dir="auto">We are currently developing Kompute not to hide the Vulkan SDK interface (as it's incredibly well designed) but to augment it with a direct focus on the Vulkan SDK's GPU computing capabilities. <a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/machine-learning-and-data-processing-in-the-gpu-with-vulkan-kompute-c9350e5e5d3a" rel="nofollow">This article</a> provides a high level overview of the motivations of Kompute, together with a set of hands on examples that introduce both GPU computing as well as the core Kompute architecture.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A search engine by and for the federal government (209 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://search.gov/</link>
            <guid>41009021</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 17:43:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://search.gov/">https://search.gov/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41009021">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main-container">
    <main id="main-content">
    

    
    <div>
          <h4>New report — 2023 in review</h4>
          <p>
            Search.gov supports one third of federal government domains. Learn what the public was searching for on these websites last year. <a href="https://search.gov/about/updates/year-in-review/2023-year-in-review/overview.html">Read the report</a>
            <!-- <a class="usa-link" href="javascript:void(0);">Read the report.</a> -->
          </p>
        </div>

<div>
      <h2>A search engine by and for the federal government
      </h2>
      <p>Powering search results on more than 2,000 websites. Free, effective, and simple—Search.gov has all you need to get search right on your website!</p>
      <p><a href="https://search.gov/get-started/">Get started today</a>
    </p></div>

<div>
        
        <p><strong>Built for government —</strong> Secure, compliant, designed around the unique circumstances of government web publishing.</p>
        <p><strong>Highly configurable —</strong> No developers required - use our easy interface to design your search experience yourself.</p>
        <p><strong>Hands-on customer service —</strong> We're here to help you, from implementation to SEO.</p>
        <p><strong>No barriers to entry —</strong> Getting started with Search.gov is friction free.</p>
        <p><a href="https://search.gov/about/why-choose-searchgov.html">Learn more</a>
    </p></div>

<div>
    <h2><strong>How do I get search right</strong> on my website?</h2>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <div>
          
          <p>Curious about how to properly index your federal agency website? We can help you get started with our training and resources on indexing.</p>
          
        </div>
      </li>
      <li>
        <div>
          
          <p>Want to improve your results? Having trouble with results missing? Learn more about how to improve your search experience.</p>
          
        </div>
      </li>
      <li>
        <div>
          
          <p>Making improvements to your site can be exciting but also daunting. We created a guide to help you keep your search working well on the new site.</p>
          
        </div>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </div>

<div>
        <h2>How do I...</h2>
        
    </div>


    </main>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>