<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 21:30:04 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Elon Musk wanted an OpenAI for-profit (146 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://openai.com/index/elon-musk-wanted-an-openai-for-profit/</link>
            <guid>42411608</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 19:36:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://openai.com/index/elon-musk-wanted-an-openai-for-profit/">https://openai.com/index/elon-musk-wanted-an-openai-for-profit/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42411608">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://openai.com/index/elon-musk-wanted-an-openai-for-profit/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[MarkItDown: Python tool for converting files and office documents to Markdown (154 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/microsoft/markitdown</link>
            <guid>42410803</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 18:02:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/markitdown">https://github.com/microsoft/markitdown</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42410803">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">MarkItDown</h2><a id="user-content-markitdown" aria-label="Permalink: MarkItDown" href="#markitdown"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The MarkItDown library is a utility tool for converting various files to Markdown (e.g., for indexing, text analysis, etc.)</p>
<p dir="auto">It presently supports:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>PDF (.pdf)</li>
<li>PowerPoint (.pptx)</li>
<li>Word (.docx)</li>
<li>Excel (.xlsx)</li>
<li>Images (EXIF metadata, and OCR)</li>
<li>Audio (EXIF metadata, and speech transcription)</li>
<li>HTML (special handling of Wikipedia, etc.)</li>
<li>Various other text-based formats (csv, json, xml, etc.)</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">The API is simple:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="from markitdown import MarkItDown

markitdown = MarkItDown()
result = markitdown.convert(&quot;test.xlsx&quot;)
print(result.text_content)"><pre><span>from</span> <span>markitdown</span> <span>import</span> <span>MarkItDown</span>

<span>markitdown</span> <span>=</span> <span>MarkItDown</span>()
<span>result</span> <span>=</span> <span>markitdown</span>.<span>convert</span>(<span>"test.xlsx"</span>)
<span>print</span>(<span>result</span>.<span>text_content</span>)</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing</h2><a id="user-content-contributing" aria-label="Permalink: Contributing" href="#contributing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This project welcomes contributions and suggestions.  Most contributions require you to agree to a
Contributor License Agreement (CLA) declaring that you have the right to, and actually do, grant us
the rights to use your contribution. For details, visit <a href="https://cla.opensource.microsoft.com/" rel="nofollow">https://cla.opensource.microsoft.com</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">When you submit a pull request, a CLA bot will automatically determine whether you need to provide
a CLA and decorate the PR appropriately (e.g., status check, comment). Simply follow the instructions
provided by the bot. You will only need to do this once across all repos using our CLA.</p>
<p dir="auto">This project has adopted the <a href="https://opensource.microsoft.com/codeofconduct/" rel="nofollow">Microsoft Open Source Code of Conduct</a>.
For more information see the <a href="https://opensource.microsoft.com/codeofconduct/faq/" rel="nofollow">Code of Conduct FAQ</a> or
contact <a href="mailto:opencode@microsoft.com">opencode@microsoft.com</a> with any additional questions or comments.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Trademarks</h2><a id="user-content-trademarks" aria-label="Permalink: Trademarks" href="#trademarks"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This project may contain trademarks or logos for projects, products, or services. Authorized use of Microsoft
trademarks or logos is subject to and must follow
<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/legal/intellectualproperty/trademarks/usage/general" rel="nofollow">Microsoft's Trademark &amp; Brand Guidelines</a>.
Use of Microsoft trademarks or logos in modified versions of this project must not cause confusion or imply Microsoft sponsorship.
Any use of third-party trademarks or logos are subject to those third-party's policies.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Imposter Attack – Among Us-themed infrared game made with ESP32 (111 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.langworth.com/imposter-attack</link>
            <guid>42410229</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 17:00:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.langworth.com/imposter-attack">https://blog.langworth.com/imposter-attack</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42410229">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article> <figure><img src="https://blog.langworth.com/assets/imposter-attack/main-1200.jpg" alt="A custom gaming setup featuring Among Us-themed glowing targets in various designs, a laptop displaying the game &quot;Imposter Attack&quot; with a high score of 4900, and infrared components, all illuminated under colorful lighting." loading="eager"></figure>
<p>At Legoland California this past summer I rode <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lost_Kingdom_Adventure">a Lego-styled ancient Egyptian adventure ride</a> where you travel through a tomb and shoot as many snakes and mummies and things as you can with a laser gun. Two things occurred to me while riding: the fact that Legoland thought it a good idea to equip kids with lasers, and the thought that I could make a shooting gallery game like this that people would like.</p>
<p>Making games is fun. Games are the reason lots of people get into programming, including me. Some people even make a profession out of them. Even though this was months before Halloween, the game that appeared in my mind was a fun, shoot-em-up carnival-style game, and maybe I could inspire a few kids with software and hardware along the way.</p>
<p>But this wasn’t just a “this will be fun” idea. I’ve noticed a pattern about myself and it’s been the basis of many of my projects or even companies. I see bits of technology and how they fit together, especially those that have become recently available or economical. If the result is novel product or game that nobody else has created before, I’m locked in, and I tend to not shut up about it.</p>
<p>In this case, I had recently learned about inexpensive programmable microprocessors, particularly the <a href="https://esp32.com/">ESP32</a>, and I finally had an excuse to get into rudimentary electrical engineering. I was stunned at how cheap and accessible electronic components had become, and the online learning resources seemed infinite. I googled around and couldn’t find anything too similar to what I wanted to build, and thus this goofy and fun idea took hold.</p>
<h2 id="what-the-heck-is-esp32">What the heck is ESP32?</h2>
<p>One of the greatest fears as a homeowner is uncontrolled running water. A great product to deal with this fear is <a href="https://flumewater.com/">Flume</a>, an internet-connected water meter that gives you reports and alerts you to leaks. Flume had recently informed me that my old unit was defective and sent me a free replacement, so naturally I took apart the old one to see what was inside. Made of two components, a reader and base station that communicate wirelessly, opening them revealed that they were powered by a versatile, programmable chip called ESP32.</p>
<p>As someone who hadn’t been following makers, Arduino, or any kind of hardware, the ESP32 platform was astounding. It has a dual-core CPU that runs at up to 240 MHz, it can do wifi and Bluetooth, and it’s got about forty pins that can be used for all sorts of stuff. You can program it with the free <a href="https://www.arduino.cc/en/software">Arduino IDE</a> and a USB cable, and they <a href="https://amazon.com/s?k=esp32">cost about $6 per board</a>. For someone who wanted to experiment efficiently <em>and</em> knew that they’d probably set one or two prototypes on fire, this was perfect.</p>
<p>I watched <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLUhbm0oyg91ZyRa5XK_S947yB354VmN8W">a <em>lot</em> of videos on electronics basics and Arduino</a> and figured out what I’d need to buy to start learning. Initially I bought a single board and some LEDs from <a href="https://www.sparkfun.com/">SparkFun</a>, which is a popular site, but the lengthy ship times made me impatient. I turned to Amazon — yes, I’m sorry — where I could get components much more quickly and cheaply, and spent a few dollars on <a href="https://a.co/d/a7I6lh6">a few ESP-WROOM-32 boards</a> and <a href="https://a.co/d/6HOSekd">a breadboard starter kit</a>. Learning the Arduino IDE was pretty quick, and before long I had some LEDs blinking and was reading infrared signals from a soundbar remote I had lying around.</p>
<lite-vimeo data-id="1038078166" data-params="loop=true&amp;autoplay=1&amp;dnt=1"> <a href="https://vimeo.com/1038078166" aria-label="Play"></a> </lite-vimeo> 
<p>The game started to solidify in my head, and the idea of zapping aliens seemed reasonably fun. I decided to create <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Among_Us">Among Us</a>-style characters for the target faces since every kid loves that game (mine do) and the characters are very recognizable. So I decided to build out the first version of a Node.js game server with a web-driven scoreboard, and I had the ESP32 target connect to my wifi and communicate “hits” over UDP:</p>
<figure><lite-vimeo data-id="1038081093" data-params="autoplay=1&amp;dnt=1"> <a href="https://vimeo.com/1038081093" aria-label="Play"></a> </lite-vimeo> <figcaption>It’s basically done, right?</figcaption></figure>
<h2 id="moving-to-micropython">Moving to MicroPython</h2>
<p>While working on the game I used my newfound ESP32 skills to do some other projects, such as automating the remote-controlled blinds in our bedroom as well as a motion sensor that would send <a href="https://pushover.net/">Pushover</a> notifications to my phone. I started to run into issues with keeping time and went down rabbit holes of using NTP and <a href="https://a.co/d/h8FzOZ5">DS3231 realtime clock modules</a>. Online friends convinced me to look at <a href="https://micropython.org/">MicroPython</a><sup><a href="#user-content-fn-2" id="user-content-fnref-2" data-footnote-ref="" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup>, which seemed to have a better ecosystem than Arduino, so I switched.</p>
<p>I was hesitant to switch to MicroPython because I wanted to stay low-level and better understand the hardware. But I quickly discovered that iterating with MicroPython was <em>much</em> faster. Python is a much easier language to work with, of course, but the real win was that there was no compilation or flashing step. In theory, you simply copy files to the board and reset it with the <a href="https://docs.micropython.org/en/latest/reference/mpremote.html"><code>mpremote</code> command</a>. This was <em>mostly</em> true, but watching <code>main.py</code> for changes, copying the files, and monitoring the serial port for output gets cumbersome and buggy, so I built <a href="https://github.com/statico/imposter-attack-2024/blob/main/devtool/devtool.py">a tool</a> to automate this. It worked most of the time but still occasionally required unplugging and reconnecting the board.</p>
<p>The switch to MicroPython really paid off later when I started using <a href="https://github.com/mkomon/uota">uOTA</a>, an over-the-air updater framework. By hosting a tarball on my laptop and sending the targets an “update” command, I was able to update all 15 devices wirelessly without connecting them via USB. More on that later.</p>
<h2 id="infrared">Infrared</h2>
<p>Sending and receiving infrared (IR) signals with microcontrollers is well-documented with a handful of protocols. After some experimentation I found all of the remotes I had used <a href="http://exploreembedded.com/wiki/NEC_IR_Remote_Control_Interface_with_8051">NEC</a>, which basically sends one long pulse, then a space, then bits of data with some simple error checking.</p>
<figure><img src="https://blog.langworth.com/assets/imposter-attack/ir-nec.png" alt="Diagram illustrating the NEC infrared remote control signal protocol" loading="lazy"><figcaption><p>NEC infrared remote control signal protocol from <a href="https://exploreembedded.com/wiki/NEC_IR_Remote_Control_Interface_with_8051">Explore
Embedded</a></p></figcaption></figure>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/Arduino-IRremote/Arduino-IRremote">IRremote library for Arduino</a> is great. It’s well-documented, has lots of examples, and decodes the IR protocol automatically. Even though I didn’t use it, one of the best features is how it creates a 4-byte hash of any incoming IR command, which makes it trivial to check for button presses on an IR remote.</p>
<p>For inputs, I was definitely set on using <a href="https://a.co/d/21eXs0B">the cheapest IR laser tag guns I could find</a>, which use IR despite being called “laser” tag. I also had an <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CZkqtpVFRTE">“MagiQuest” wand</a> from a local water park with a <em>definitely-not-Harry-Potter</em> game where you wave a wand to collect points. Importantly, I felt the wand would be more appropriate to use the wand at a school event.</p>
<p>Neither the pistols nor the MagiQuest wand used any known protocol<sup><a href="#user-content-fn-1" id="user-content-fnref-1" data-footnote-ref="" aria-describedby="footnote-label">2</a></sup>, so I had to parse the raw timing data and look for patterns there. I discovered that there was a particular tolerance needed when decoding an IR signal as they tend to get more corrupted or “wrong” the farther away you are and how accurately you’re aiming the transmitter at the receiver. I assume IR signals are bright and bouncy to allow the changing TV channels from a hundred feet away, but other than that I haven’t really researched the physics as to why this happens. Regardless, I was able to use this property to more accurately detect hits from the laser guns and wands.</p>
<figure><img src="https://blog.langworth.com/assets/imposter-attack/pistols-and-wand.jpg" alt="Two toy laser tag pistols in blue and red lightning designs and a wooden wand with tan grip wrappings, arranged on a green cutting mat. A small clear plastic case containing electronic components and a USB cable is also visible." loading="lazy"><figcaption>A proper alien-blasting arsenal</figcaption></figure>
<p>Around this time I also switched to MicroPython and began using <a href="https://github.com/peterhinch/micropython_ir">Peter Hinch’s micropython_ir libraries</a>. I decided that a <code>1</code> bit was any burst longer than 750µs for the laser guns and 500µs for the wand. The entire receiving code ended up looking like this:</p>
<pre tabindex="0" data-language="python"><code><span><span># `burst` is an array of IR pulse lengths</span></span>
<span><span>bits </span><span>=</span><span> ""</span></span>
<span><span>if</span><span> burst</span><span>[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span> &gt;</span><span> 1200</span><span> and</span><span> burst</span><span>[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span> &lt;</span><span> 1800</span><span>:</span></span>
<span><span>  # Laser gun</span></span>
<span><span>  for</span><span> i</span><span>,</span><span> value </span><span>in</span><span> enumerate</span><span>(</span><span>burst</span><span>):</span></span>
<span><span>    if</span><span> i </span><span>==</span><span> 0</span><span>:</span></span>
<span><span>      continue</span></span>
<span><span>    if</span><span> i </span><span>%</span><span> 2</span><span> ==</span><span> 1</span><span>:</span></span>
<span><span>      bits </span><span>+=</span><span> "</span><span>1</span><span>"</span><span> if</span><span> value </span><span>&gt;</span><span> 750</span><span> else</span><span> "</span><span>0</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>else</span><span>:</span></span>
<span><span>  # Wand or anything else</span></span>
<span><span>  for</span><span> i</span><span>,</span><span> value </span><span>in</span><span> enumerate</span><span>(</span><span>burst</span><span>):</span></span>
<span><span>    bits </span><span>+=</span><span> "</span><span>1</span><span>"</span><span> if</span><span> value </span><span>&gt;</span><span> 500</span><span> else</span><span> "</span><span>0</span><span>"</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span># Wand is acting strangely. Trim any leading 10+</span></span>
<span><span>bits</span><span>.</span><span>replace</span><span>(</span><span>"</span><span>1</span><span>"</span><span> +</span><span> "</span><span>0</span><span>"</span><span> *</span><span> (</span><span>len</span><span>(</span><span>bits</span><span>)</span><span> -</span><span> len</span><span>(</span><span>bits</span><span>.</span><span>lstrip</span><span>(</span><span>"</span><span>0</span><span>"</span><span>))),</span><span> ""</span><span>,</span><span> 1</span><span>)</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span>if</span><span> len</span><span>(</span><span>bits</span><span>)</span><span> ==</span><span> 20</span><span> and</span><span> bits</span><span>[:</span><span>8</span><span>]</span><span> ==</span><span> "</span><span>00001111</span><span>"</span><span>:</span></span>
<span><span>  print</span><span>(</span><span>"</span><span>hit (pistol)</span><span>"</span><span>)</span></span>
<span><span>  handle_hit</span><span>()</span></span>
<span><span>elif</span><span> len</span><span>(</span><span>bits</span><span>)</span><span> &gt;=</span><span> 12</span><span> and</span><span> bits</span><span>[:</span><span>12</span><span>]</span><span> ==</span><span> "</span><span>100101010101</span><span>"</span><span>:</span></span>
<span><span>  print</span><span>(</span><span>"</span><span>hit (wand)</span><span>"</span><span>)</span></span>
<span><span>  handle_hit</span><span>()</span></span>
<span><span>else</span><span>:</span></span>
<span><span>  print</span><span>(</span><span>f</span><span>"unknown IR signal: </span><span>{</span><span>bits</span><span>}</span><span>"</span><span>)</span></span></code></pre>
<h2 id="lighting">Lighting</h2>
<p>My vision was to have 10-15 targets that, once the game started, would all light up at random intervals to signal that they were ready to be shot. I wanted the targets to flash if shot, but also flicker and turn off if the player didn’t shoot them as it’s a common mechanic in platformer games to flicker and remove items if they’re not picked up in time. Since this game was going to be played by kids on Halloween, I figured that UV (blacklight) against neon paper would fit the spooky motif. Thus, I needed two LEDs: one UV for the “ready” light and something else for the “shot” light.</p>
<p>One of the first real challenges I had was figuring out how much light I could produce with an ESP32. The GPIO pins produce 3.3V, but the maximum current is a little mysterious even though the datasheets say something like 40mA. I really wanted to drive the LEDs right from the board and avoid any extra components to keep things simple and reliable. A relay or step-up voltage converter would mean lots of extra soldering for fifteen targets, and another part meant another thing that could fail.</p>
<p>I ordered a few different types of LED components to experiment with and decided that <a href="https://a.co/d/5ve473u">3W 420nm UV</a> and <a href="https://a.co/d/6pGWnzx">1W white LED</a> “lamp chips” would be sufficient as long as the LED was oriented correctly. I made a prototype with a little stalk to angle the LEDs properly and a little tin foil reflector to help add the light. The reflector doubled as a shield to prevent me from looking at the UV light, which left yellow spots in my vision for a few minutes. I’m sure that that’s totally safe.</p>
<figure><lite-vimeo data-id="1038439862" data-params="loop=true&amp;autoplay=1&amp;dnt=1"> <a href="https://vimeo.com/1038439862" aria-label="Play"></a> </lite-vimeo> <figcaption><p>Glow-in-the-dark paint didn’t look nearly as cool as I thought it would</p></figcaption></figure>
<p>This was before I discovered the world of RGB lighting and WS2812B strips, which I’ll cover in a later post when I talk about my holiday lights project. In the future, I might use one or more 5V WS2812B LED lamp chips which, in theory, could be driven using the full 5V from the power supply and controlled via a data pin. Noted for next year!</p>
<h2 id="power">Power</h2>
<p>Power was another big question. I wasn’t sure whether I should keep each device plugged with long USB cables or use battery power. Long cables meant I wouldn’t have to worry about battery life and swapping out batteries during an event, but I also imagined a tripping hazard, and I worried about voltage drop. Instead, I decided to give batteries a try.</p>
<p>I learned about the ubiquitous <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/18650masterrace/">18650 li-ion “flashlight battery”</a>, a form factor that is apparently in everything rechargeable from power tools to <a href="https://insideevs.com/news/587455/batteries-tesla-using-electric-cars/">Teslas</a>. In fact, I already had a few left over from when I fixed the battery pack in a handheld vacuum cleaner. Since they’re unprotected and can cause fires if overcharged, undercharged, or looked at menacingly,<sup><a href="#user-content-fn-3" id="user-content-fnref-3" data-footnote-ref="" aria-describedby="footnote-label">3</a></sup> a charging and discharging protection circuit is necessary. Luckily, <a href="https://a.co/d/8J2QXgp">TP4056 charging modules</a> are cheap and abundant.</p>
<p>With power figured out, my prototype was now complete hardware-wise.</p>
<figure><img src="https://blog.langworth.com/assets/imposter-attack/prototype.jpg" alt="Back and front of the target prototype. Pictured is an 18650 battery connected to a TP4056 li-ion protection circuit, which is powering a D1 Mini ESP32 board via USB." loading="lazy"><figcaption>Back and front of the target prototype</figcaption></figure>
<p>Once the charging components arrived, I made a prototype of my first battery-powered self-contained ESP-NOW powered target and it worked! The only glitch was that the TP4056 required a repeat insertion of the battery. It seemed like something needed to be powered up for the charging component to activate, and only with the second battery insertion did they begin to provide 5V continuously. The modules were meant to drive USB battery packs, so I’m guessing this behavior is related to that somehow. In the future I’ll either add a power switch to make the process easier or I’ll find a way to circumvent it completely.</p>
<h2 id="communication">Communication</h2>
<p>I was still worried about power consumption, and this led me to discover <a href="https://randomnerdtutorials.com/esp-now-esp32-arduino-ide/">ESP-NOW</a>, a UDP-like 2.4 GHz communication protocol available on ESP32 systems. Not connecting to wifi sounded much more efficient since the CPU wouldn’t need to waste valuable cycles and energy processing packets and such. Also, I was already disappointed to find that UDP retransmission was necessary even on my private and quiet home network. The only downside was that I would need yet another ESP32 plugged into my laptop to act as an ESP32-NOW bridge.<sup><a href="#user-content-fn-4" id="user-content-fnref-4" data-footnote-ref="" aria-describedby="footnote-label">4</a></sup></p>
<p>When manufactured, each ESP32 gets a unique MAC address. I was already using this as a device identifier when communicating over UDP, so converting the code to use ESP-NOW was simple. I used an extra <a href="https://www.sparkfun.com/products/23484">ESP32-C3</a> I had ordered since it fit nicely into a plastic battery box and could stick to my laptop with blue tak. Testing them demonstrated communication distances of over 200 feet <em>without retransmission</em>, which was impressive. ESP-NOW became an easy win.</p>
<p>I wasn’t finished with wifi, though. I plumbed in <a href="https://github.com/mkomon/uota">uOTA</a>, a MicroPython framework that does over-the-air updates over wifi, and updated the targets to only connect to wifi once they received a special “update” command over ESP-NOW. Once connected, they would check for updates from a web server running on my laptop with a fixed IP, update themselves, and reboot. This ended up working <em>perfectly</em>, and later it became the primary way I made changes to the target code.</p>
<h2 id="more-target-work">More target work</h2>
<p>With the prototype working, I thought carefully on how construct fifteen of these targets in the most foolproof, reliable, and easily-debuggable way. I decided on the following:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://a.co/d/aer4OII">18650 li-ion batteries</a> with <a href="https://a.co/d/2RUgmFJ">holders</a> and <a href="https://a.co/d/9qqIEh4">TP4056 charging modules</a> as the power source</li>
<li><a href="https://a.co/d/jeLaDBc">D1 Mini ESP-WROOM-32</a> boards since they were the cheapest and, not having any header pins soldered, the most versatile</li>
<li><a href="https://a.co/d/72jX1Bq">Neon project paper</a> on which to print the target faces, <a href="https://a.co/d/fARe4w1">spray-gluing</a> them to cardboard to make them sturdy, and punching a hole with an awl for the IR received to peek through</li>
<li>Small pieces of <a href="https://a.co/d/83qRSb8">mirror paper</a> to act as reflectors</li>
<li><a href="https://a.co/d/6rqoSjI">Clear plastic storage cases</a> to protect the components and make handling easier</li>
<li>Simple wood T’s, black spray paint, and hot glue as a frame</li>
<li><a href="https://a.co/d/aOjW3op">Blu-Tak putty</a> to stick components to the case and frame</li>
<li><a href="https://a.co/d/2fd04dm">3M Command Strips</a> (like velcro) to stick the case to the frame and the target to the case</li>
<li><a href="https://a.co/d/9AyDcFh">Stick-on hangers</a> so the targets could be hung easily, such as with <a href="https://a.co/d/7hlgE0m">strong magnetic hangers</a> on a garage door</li>
<li>Dupont jumper wires (<a href="https://a.co/d/7y3kHFk">1</a>, <a href="https://a.co/d/8y4yhWP">2</a>, <a href="https://a.co/d/6jH10Aw">3</a>) instead of soldering in order to make service and assembly easier</li>
<li>My own 4- or 5-pin jumper bridges created from soldering extra headers as a common ground</li>
</ul>
<p>Making the targets modular — a case, a target face, and frame — let them be easily constructed and serviceable. With the command strips, if a target face seemed off-center or unbalanced, I could take it off and reposition it. Also, all of the targets packed up neat and tidy in a box when no longer in use.</p>
<figure><img src="https://blog.langworth.com/assets/imposter-attack/prototype2.jpg" alt="Two game targets on a workbench, one facing front and one facing back. The front-facing one shows an orange neon sign with an Among Us imposter graphic and the back of the reflector attached to a T-frame on the bottom. The one facing back shows the clear case with the ESP32, battery holder, and charging module inside, with connectors going out to the IR receiver and LEDs." loading="lazy"><figcaption>Two more prototypes using the new parts</figcaption></figure>
<p>Using Dupont jumper wires for everything had mixed results. On one hand, I liked the idea of making the ESP32 boards reusable. On the other hand, jumper wires tend to work themselves free, and I ended up adding blu-tak to all of them. Also, the project boxes weren’t quite tall enough, so repeated pressure from handling and inserting batteries tended to knock the wires loose. Despite this, everything mostly worked, and figuring out why something wasn’t working was usually a matter of fixing a loose connection.</p>
<p>Using some Among Us clip art and <a href="https://www.iconfinder.com/iconsets/halloween-01">a Halloween icon pack</a>, I made fifteen graphics in Figma to use for target faces. I wanted to use a local shop to print the targets but, for some reason, couldn’t find one that would do it. One shop owner said to just use my own laser printer with the “thick paper” setting, which is what I did. Some neon paper colors held toner better than others, and all of the target faces had some amount of ghosting. The toner also tended to rub off after printing, so every print was sprayed down with aerosol Minwax polycrylic to seal it up.</p>
<figure><div data-astro-cid-juhulabb=""> <p><img src="https://blog.langworth.com/assets/imposter-attack/build1.jpg" alt="Brightly colored Among Us characters with tools, printed on fluorescent paper, scattered on a workbench." loading="lazy"></p><p><img src="https://blog.langworth.com/assets/imposter-attack/build2.jpg" alt="Small breadboard with a mounted breakout board, secured by a rubber band on a green cutting mat." loading="lazy"></p><p><img src="https://blog.langworth.com/assets/imposter-attack/build3.jpg" alt="A pile of blue breakout boards with scattered components on a workbench." loading="lazy"></p><p><img src="https://blog.langworth.com/assets/imposter-attack/build4.jpg" alt="Neatly organized multicolored wires and LED modules on top of clear plastic storage boxes." loading="lazy"></p><p><img src="https://blog.langworth.com/assets/imposter-attack/build5.jpg" alt="A green cutting mat with multiple black-painted, T-shaped wood pieces arranged in a pattern." loading="lazy"></p><p><img src="https://blog.langworth.com/assets/imposter-attack/build6.jpg" alt="A small project setup featuring an ESP32 board, battery pack, and connected LEDs on a workbench." loading="lazy"></p><p><img src="https://blog.langworth.com/assets/imposter-attack/build7.jpg" alt="Prototyping station with a plastic container holding electronics, including a sensor module and wires." loading="lazy"></p><p><img src="https://blog.langworth.com/assets/imposter-attack/build8.jpg" alt="The backs of three targets showing different states of assembly placed in front of four target faces." loading="lazy"></p><p><img src="https://blog.langworth.com/assets/imposter-attack/build9.jpg" alt="Targets that have been deconstructed and are ready for storage." loading="lazy"></p> </div>  <figcaption>Various progress pictures</figcaption></figure>
<p>After a few nights of doing everything 15-20 times (I needed redundancy for every step of course), I had fifteen working targets ready to go! I strung up some rope in the garage and hung them all for easy testing.</p>
<figure><lite-vimeo data-id="1038463145" data-params="loop=true&amp;autoplay=1&amp;dnt=1"> <a href="https://vimeo.com/1038463145" aria-label="Play"></a> </lite-vimeo> <figcaption>Thirteen targets flashing in “test” mode</figcaption></figure>
<p>The final idea to implement was a “boss” target that would have special sounds and take more hits to destroy. Originally I had intended the boss target to be bigger and scarier, but since I had to print the targets myself I settled for a unique face and just told players which target was “special.” Since I didn’t want to have a unique version of the code for bosses, I designated a single pin as a pull-up resistor which the code could read to determine whether it was a regular or boss target, and on the special target I connected that pin to ground.</p>
<pre tabindex="0" data-language="python"><code><span><span>imposter_pin </span><span>=</span><span> Pin</span><span>(</span><span>16</span><span>,</span><span> Pin</span><span>.</span><span>IN</span><span>,</span><span> Pin</span><span>.</span><span>PULL_UP</span><span>)</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span># ...</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span>def</span><span> is_imposter</span><span>():</span></span>
<span><span>  return</span><span> imposter_pin</span><span>.</span><span>value</span><span>()</span><span> ==</span><span> 0</span></span></code></pre>
<h2 id="the-big-day-or-days">The big day (or days)</h2>
<p>The first trial run was at our elementary school’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trunk-or-treating">“Trunk or Treat”</a> event, where people parked cars at the school and made Halloween-themed exhibits.</p>
<figure><img src="https://blog.langworth.com/assets/imposter-attack/trunk.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"></figure>
<p>Everyone had a blast! About 115 kids played, with a few making second or third attempts at breaking the high score. I was told that I had the <em>second biggest</em> crowd, second only to a Pokémon bean bag game (which did look pretty cool). Some adults were curious, but most importantly, a handful of questions from kids who wanted to know how I built it. It was especially rewarding to show one off one of the extra targets I brought. One kid even recognized the ESP32 chips and said, “Oh, these are the ones you can make drones out of!”</p>
<figure><lite-vimeo data-id="1038824565" data-params="autoplay=1&amp;dnt=1"> <a href="https://vimeo.com/1038824565" aria-label="Play"></a> </lite-vimeo> <figcaption>Example gameplay with the wand</figcaption></figure>
<p>Halloween, however, was the <em>big</em> show. I set up a table in front of our garage and used [magnetic hooks] to mount the targets, of which only 13 were working. Having learned from the event at the school, I taped off a line for people to stand behind so they’d have the best chance at shooting the targets. I also added a counter to track how many games were played, and it came out to almost 90. A handful of people came back to try and get the high score, which I think was around 5,200.</p>
<figure><lite-vimeo data-id="1038824555" data-params="autoplay=1&amp;dnt=1"> <a href="https://vimeo.com/1038824555" aria-label="Play"></a> </lite-vimeo> <figcaption>Example gameplay with the laser guns</figcaption></figure>
<h2 id="improvements-for-next-time">Improvements for next time</h2>
<p>People really liked the game, and I’ve set it up a few more times for other events. However, there’s a host of improvements that need to be made to make the game more fun and reliable.</p>
<ul>
<li>An on/off switch — Popping batteries in and out was a lot of toil because the targets were so fragile.</li>
<li>Better target faces — Surely I can find a local sign shop to do coroplast signs. And I might try a different theme than Among Us.</li>
<li>Better lighting — WS2812B LEDs might be the solution since I can drive a few at once as well as change the colors for different effects and events.</li>
<li>Custom boards — Using something like <a href="https://www.pcbway.com/">PCBWay</a> to print my own boards might be a good idea. I could make sockets to drop the ESP32s and other components into and use headers to get rid of the unreliable jumper wires.</li>
</ul>
<p>Until next time, please enjoy the videos. You can checkout the <a href="https://github.com/statico/imposter-attack-2024">source code for the entire project</a> on GitHub.</p>
<section data-footnotes="">
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-2">
<p>I also considered CircuitPython, and choosing between that and MicroPython was difficult. I decided that CircuitPython is more focused on pushing people into the Adafruit branded hardware ecosystem, so I stuck with the more organic-feeling MicroPython. <a href="#user-content-fnref-2" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-1">
<p>There does appear to be <a href="https://github.com/patricknevindwyer/arduino-magiquest">a project</a> where someone decodes the wand ID and shake magnitude of MagiQuest wands with Arduino. <a href="#user-content-fnref-1" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 2">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-3">
<p>The biggest problem with 18650 batteries appears to be <a href="https://youtube.com/watch?v=rammyIePuGc&amp;t=167">their design</a>. The negative pole makes up most of the case while the positive “button” is a thin cap at the top. The gap between the two parts is small, so if they get dropped or damaged in the right way, those terminals can touch. This leads to thermal runaway, scary moments, and insurance claims. <a href="#user-content-fnref-3" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 3">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-4">
<p>Maybe there’s a way to send ESP-NOW packets from a regular wifi NIC, but I couldn’t figure this out. <a href="https://www.instructables.com/ESPNow-a-Deeper-Look-Unicast-Vs-Broadcast-ACKs-Ret/">Wireshark can sniff ESP-NOW packets</a>, though, so maybe? If you know, let me know. <a href="#user-content-fnref-4" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 4">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section> </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Feds help health insurers hide their dirty secret: denials on the rise (141 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nypost.com/2024/12/12/opinion/feds-help-health-insurers-hide-dirty-secret-rising-denials/</link>
            <guid>42408925</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 14:51:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nypost.com/2024/12/12/opinion/feds-help-health-insurers-hide-dirty-secret-rising-denials/">https://nypost.com/2024/12/12/opinion/feds-help-health-insurers-hide-dirty-secret-rising-denials/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42408925">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
							


<p>The <a href="https://nypost.com/2024/12/05/us-news/anthem-blue-cross-blue-shield-to-impose-limits-on-surgical-anesthesia/">health insurance industry’s</a> dirty secret is that it’s no longer selling insurance: It’s selling a crapshoot.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The risk of having your health insurance claim denied is roughly 10 times what it was a decade ago.</p>



<p>Back then, insurers seldom rejected claims.&nbsp;</p>





<p>UnitedHealthcare nixed 1.1%, Humana 1.9%, Aetna 1.5% in 2013, per the American Medical Association.</p>



<p>By 2022, major insurers were refusing to pay, on average, 15% of claims, according to a national survey of hospitals and health-care providers by Premier, an insurance consultant.</p>






<p>The&nbsp;figure&nbsp;continues to shoot&nbsp;upward, with some companies today denying almost <em>half</em> of all claims, according to researchers at the Kaiser Family Foundation.&nbsp;</p>



<p>But you can’t find out <em>which</em> companies, and that makes choosing a plan a high-stakes gamble. </p>



<p>If you’re seriously ill and need costly care, a denied claim could push you into bankruptcy. &nbsp;</p>



<p>The&nbsp;<a href="https://nypost.com/2024/08/16/us-news/trump-shares-promises-for-affordable-care-act-social-security-medicare/">Affordable Care Act </a>of 2010 requires the Department of Health and Human Services to monitor claims denials and provide the information to the public.</p>



<p>But government officials — coopted by the industry — simply don’t do it.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Consumers be damned.</p>



<p>Uncle Sam is allowing claims denial to become a major profit center for insurers.</p>



<p>The assassination of UnitedHealthcare CEO Brian Thompson is igniting an outpouring of vitriol against insurers.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Alleged killer Luigi Mangione railed in a manifesto against the&nbsp;<a href="https://nypost.com/2024/12/09/us-news/luigi-mangione-unitedhealthcare-ceo-brian-thompsons-suspected-killer-expresses-disdain-for-health-insurance-industry-in-manifesto/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">“corruption and greed”</a> of the industry.</p>



<p>No industry malfeasance could ever excuse murder.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Period.</p>



<p>Even so, it’s past time for companies’ denial rates to be made public. </p>



<p>You aren’t really insured if your insurer can deny valid claims with impunity.</p>



<p>That is what’s happening,&nbsp;based on information that Kaiser researchers&nbsp;were able get about plans sold on the Affordable Care Act exchanges.</p>



<p>ACA plans on average refuse to pay 17% of claims. </p>



<p>But the researchers found that numerous insurers nix 30% or more, including&nbsp;Meridian Health Plan of Michigan, United Healthcare of Arizona, and Optimum Choice in Virginia.</p>



<p>Celtic Insurance Company in Florida refused 42%&nbsp;of claims in 2021.&nbsp;</p>



<p>You can’t really call that insurance.</p>



<p>The problem is not unique to ACA plans.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Premier’s March 2024 survey found that insurers overall denied 15.7% of Medicare Advantage claims, 15.1% of Medicaid managed care claims and 13.9% of claims from non-government plans.&nbsp;</p>



<p>That staggering denial rate should be the first fact any consumer sees <a href="https://nypost.com/2024/10/02/lifestyle/americans-would-rather-do-these-annoying-things-than-pick-an-insurance-plan/">when choosing a plan</a>, and plan ratings should include denial rates. </p>



<p>Hiding them is an outrage.</p>



<p>Insurers&nbsp;cite lack&nbsp;of medical necessity for under 2% of denials,&nbsp;lack of prior authorization for 8%, and about 13.5% for the service not being covered under the plan.</p>



<p>But the major reason for denials — “other,” accounting for 76% of them — is a big black hole. Anybody’s guess.</p>



<p>Patients rarely appeal — only 0.2% of the time, per Kaiser.</p>



<p>An appeal means coaxing your doctor and staff to spend hours filling out forms and making repeated phone calls to joust with an insurance company employee.</p>



<div>
			
			<div>
				<h3>
					Start and end your day informed with our newsletters				</h3>
				<p>
					Morning Report and Evening Update: Your source for today's top stories				</p>
			</div>
			<p>
				<h3>
					Thanks for signing up!				</h3>
			</p>
		</div>



<p>Few doctors are eager to take on this ordeal.&nbsp;</p>



<p>But appeals pay off. In the ACA plans,&nbsp;Kaiser reports that&nbsp;41% of turn-downs get reversed&nbsp;— an&nbsp;indication that plenty of necessary care covered by plans is being denied.</p>



<p>Employers and their workers should be able to get information on how often insurers deny claims, and so should Medicare Advantage plan users.&nbsp;</p>



<p>But federal regulators&nbsp;have capitulated to pushback from the industry, and refuse to collect the information.</p>



<p>State regulators aren’t any better. </p>



<p>State insurance commissioners collect denial data, but with the exception of Connecticut and Vermont,&nbsp;they don’t disclose that information, a ProPublica investigation found.&nbsp;</p>



<p>New York state publicizes the number of complaints against insurers, but not actual denial rates — which would be more telling.</p>



<p>Nationwide, health coverage for a family of four topped $25,000 this year — a staggering amount. Young families will likely never meet their annual deductible.</p>



<p>All they’re getting for their premium is peace of mind — the knowledge that if a terrible illness or accident happens, they’re covered.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Truth is, they may <em>not</em> be covered. </p>



<p>They may be insured by a company that denies a third or more of all claims. </p>



<p>And they won’t know it until it’s too late.</p>



<p>Transparency is the only way to make the insurance market fair.&nbsp;</p>



<p>President-elect Trump’s health nominees have argued that there’s <a href="https://nypost.com/2024/11/14/us-news/trump-to-nominate-rfk-jr-to-head-department-of-health-and-human-services-sources/">too much coziness</a> between industry and the federal bureaucracy, with the public paying the price. </p>



<p>They’re right — and this is an odious example.</p>



<p>Federal regulators need to do what the law requires: Expose companies that take our money and then deny legitimate claims. </p>







<p>No new law is needed. </p>



<p>Just an order from the top.&nbsp; </p>



<p>President Trump, are you listening?</p>



<p><em>Betsy McCaughey is a former lieutenant governor of New York and co-founder of the </em><a href="https://www.saveourcityny.org/"><em>Committee to Save Our City</em></a><em>.</em></p>
						</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Web Origami, for making websites where you can understand how they're made (137 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://weborigami.org</link>
            <guid>42408819</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 14:43:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://weborigami.org">https://weborigami.org</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42408819">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://weborigami.org: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Noninvasive imaging method can penetrate deeper into living tissue (133 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.mit.edu/2024/noninvasive-imaging-method-can-penetrate-deeper-living-tissue-1211</link>
            <guid>42408271</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 13:34:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://news.mit.edu/2024/noninvasive-imaging-method-can-penetrate-deeper-living-tissue-1211">https://news.mit.edu/2024/noninvasive-imaging-method-can-penetrate-deeper-living-tissue-1211</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42408271">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://news.mit.edu/2024/noninvasive-imaging-method-can-penetrate-deeper-living-tissue-1211: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Test (341 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.defense.gov/News/News-Stories/Article/Article/4000004/test/</link>
            <guid>42408202</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 13:23:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.defense.gov/News/News-Stories/Article/Article/4000004/test/">https://www.defense.gov/News/News-Stories/Article/Article/4000004/test/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42408202">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.defense.gov/News/News-Stories/Article/Article/4000004/test/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Donald Bitzer has died (131 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://computerhistory.org/blog/in-memoriam-donald-bitzer-1934-2024/</link>
            <guid>42406158</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 05:32:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://computerhistory.org/blog/in-memoriam-donald-bitzer-1934-2024/">https://computerhistory.org/blog/in-memoriam-donald-bitzer-1934-2024/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42406158">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://computerhistory.org/blog/in-memoriam-donald-bitzer-1934-2024/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The age of average (2023) (226 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.alexmurrell.co.uk/articles/the-age-of-average</link>
            <guid>42405999</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 04:50:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.alexmurrell.co.uk/articles/the-age-of-average">https://www.alexmurrell.co.uk/articles/the-age-of-average</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42405999">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="page" role="main">
        
          
<article id="sections" data-page-sections="5e1378631e7192005deefed0">
  
  
    
    


  
  


<div data-content-field="main-content" data-item-id="" data-test="page-section" data-section-theme="" data-section-id="5e1378631e7192005deefed2" data-controller="SectionWrapperController" data-current-styles="{
                      &quot;imageOverlayOpacity&quot;: 0.15,
                      &quot;backgroundWidth&quot;: &quot;background-width--full-bleed&quot;,
                      &quot;sectionHeight&quot;: &quot;section-height--medium&quot;,
                      &quot;horizontalAlignment&quot;: &quot;horizontal-alignment--center&quot;,
                      &quot;verticalAlignment&quot;: &quot;vertical-alignment--middle&quot;,
                      &quot;contentWidth&quot;: &quot;content-width--wide&quot;,
                      &quot;sectionTheme&quot;: &quot;&quot;,
                      &quot;sectionAnimation&quot;: &quot;none&quot;,
                      &quot;backgroundMode&quot;: &quot;image&quot;
                    }" data-current-context="{
                      &quot;video&quot;: {
                        &quot;playbackSpeed&quot;: 0.5,
                        &quot;filter&quot;: 1,
                        &quot;filterStrength&quot;: 0,
                        &quot;zoom&quot;: 0,
                        &quot;videoSourceProvider&quot;: &quot;none&quot;
                      },
                      &quot;backgroundImageId&quot;: null,
                      &quot;backgroundMediaEffect&quot;: null,
                      &quot;divider&quot;: null,
                      &quot;typeName&quot;: &quot;blog-side-by-side&quot;
                    }" data-animation="none">
  <article id="article-">
  
    
    
    
    <div data-layout-label="Post Body" data-type="item" id="item-641626ac586ffe734c19233e"><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-916df3e46586a65faff0">
  <h3>Introduction:</h3><p>In the early 1990s, two Russian artists named Vitaly Komar and Alexander Melamid took the unusual step of hiring a market research firm. Their brief was simple. Understand what Americans desire most in a work of art.</p><p>Over 11 days the researchers at Marttila &amp; Kiley Inc. asked 1,001 US citizens a series of survey questions.</p><p>What’s your favourite colour? Do you prefer sharp angles or soft curves? Do you like smooth canvases or thick brushstrokes? Would you rather figures that are nude or clothed? Should they be at leisure or working? Indoors or outside? In what kind of landscape?&nbsp;</p><p>Komar and Melamid then set about painting a piece that reflected the results. The pair repeated this process in a number of countries including Russia, China, France and Kenya.</p><p>Each piece in the series, titled “People’s Choice”, was intended to be a unique a collaboration with the people of a different country and culture.</p><p>But it didn’t quite go to plan.</p><p>Describing the work in his book <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Playing-Gallery-Contemporary-Struggle-Understood/dp/0141979615/ref=sr_1_1?crid=3UOQSPFWMD6YD&amp;keywords=playing+to+the+gallery&amp;qid=1675784020&amp;sprefix=playing+to+the+gallery%2Caps%2C84&amp;sr=8-1"><span>Playing to the Gallery</span></a>, the artist Grayson Perry said:</p><p>“In nearly every country all people really wanted was a landscape with a few figures around, animals in the foreground, mainly blue.”</p><p>Despite soliciting the opinions of over 11,000 people, from 11 different countries, each of the paintings looked almost exactly the same. </p>
</div><div data-test="image-block-inline-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_266561">

      

      
        <figure>
          
        
        

        
          
            
          <div data-animation-role="image">
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/14b4aa2e-c990-481b-b710-83ce32052a0a/Most+Wanted.jpg" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/14b4aa2e-c990-481b-b710-83ce32052a0a/Most+Wanted.jpg" data-image-dimensions="4961x2787" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/14b4aa2e-c990-481b-b710-83ce32052a0a/Most+Wanted.jpg" width="4961" height="2787" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/14b4aa2e-c990-481b-b710-83ce32052a0a/Most+Wanted.jpg?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/14b4aa2e-c990-481b-b710-83ce32052a0a/Most+Wanted.jpg?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/14b4aa2e-c990-481b-b710-83ce32052a0a/Most+Wanted.jpg?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/14b4aa2e-c990-481b-b710-83ce32052a0a/Most+Wanted.jpg?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/14b4aa2e-c990-481b-b710-83ce32052a0a/Most+Wanted.jpg?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/14b4aa2e-c990-481b-b710-83ce32052a0a/Most+Wanted.jpg?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/14b4aa2e-c990-481b-b710-83ce32052a0a/Most+Wanted.jpg?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            </p>
          </div>
        
          
        

        
          
          <figcaption>
            <p>Komar and Melamid, People’s Choice</p>
          </figcaption>
        
      
        </figure>
      

    </div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_270163">
  <p>After completing the work, Komar quipped:</p><p>“We have been travelling to different countries, engaging in dull negotiations with representatives of polling companies, raising money for further polls, receiving more or less the same results, and painting more or less the same blue landscapes. Looking for freedom, we found slavery.”&nbsp;</p><p>This, however, was the point. The art was not the paintings themselves, but the comment they made. We like to think that we are individuals, but we are much more alike that we wish to admit.</p><p>30 years after People’s Choice, it seems the landscapes which Komar and Melamid painted have become the landscapes in which we live.</p><p>This article argues that from film to fashion and architecture to advertising, creative fields have become dominated and defined by convention and cliché. Distinctiveness has died. In every field we look at, we find that everything looks the same.</p><p>Welcome to the age of average.</p><p>Let’s dive in.</p><h3>Interiors all look the same</h3><p>In 2011, Laurel Schwulst was planning to redecorate her New York apartment when she began searching the internet for interior design inspiration.</p><p>Before long, the designer had stumbled on the perfect research tool: AirBnB. From the comfort of her home the app gave her a window into thousands of others. She could travel the world, and view hundreds of rooms, without leaving her chair.</p><p>Schwulst began sharing images to her Tumblr, “<a href="https://modernlifespace.tumblr.com/">Modern Life Space</a>”. The blog became an ever-expanding gallery of interior design inspiration. But something wasn’t right.</p><p><a href="https://www.theverge.com/2016/8/3/12325104/airbnb-aesthetic-global-minimalism-startup-gentrification">Laurel Schwulst:</a></p><p>“The Airbnb experience is supposed to be about real people and authenticity. But so many of them were similar, whether in Brooklyn, Osaka, Rio de Janeiro, Seoul, or Santiago.”</p><p>Schwulst had identified an AirBnB design aesthetic that had organically emerged and was quickly spreading through the platform’s properties. White walls. Raw wood. Nespresso machines. Eames chairs. Bare brick. Open shelving. Edison bulbs. The style combines the rough-hewn rawness of industrialism with the elegant minimalism of mid-century design.</p>
</div><div data-test="image-block-inline-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_287237">

      

      
        <figure>
          
        
        

        
          
            
          <div data-animation-role="image">
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/44325ee7-602e-46ab-89bc-bc37c7f58d62/The+Age+of+Average_0009_Interiors+-+Homes.jpg" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/44325ee7-602e-46ab-89bc-bc37c7f58d62/The+Age+of+Average_0009_Interiors+-+Homes.jpg" data-image-dimensions="4961x2787" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/44325ee7-602e-46ab-89bc-bc37c7f58d62/The+Age+of+Average_0009_Interiors+-+Homes.jpg" width="4961" height="2787" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/44325ee7-602e-46ab-89bc-bc37c7f58d62/The+Age+of+Average_0009_Interiors+-+Homes.jpg?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/44325ee7-602e-46ab-89bc-bc37c7f58d62/The+Age+of+Average_0009_Interiors+-+Homes.jpg?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/44325ee7-602e-46ab-89bc-bc37c7f58d62/The+Age+of+Average_0009_Interiors+-+Homes.jpg?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/44325ee7-602e-46ab-89bc-bc37c7f58d62/The+Age+of+Average_0009_Interiors+-+Homes.jpg?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/44325ee7-602e-46ab-89bc-bc37c7f58d62/The+Age+of+Average_0009_Interiors+-+Homes.jpg?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/44325ee7-602e-46ab-89bc-bc37c7f58d62/The+Age+of+Average_0009_Interiors+-+Homes.jpg?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/44325ee7-602e-46ab-89bc-bc37c7f58d62/The+Age+of+Average_0009_Interiors+-+Homes.jpg?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            </p>
          </div>
        
          
        

        
          
          <figcaption>
            <p>International Airbnb Style</p>
          </figcaption>
        
      
        </figure>
      

    </div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_287591">
  <p>But Schwulst wasn’t the only one to identify the trend. <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2016/8/3/12325104/airbnb-aesthetic-global-minimalism-startup-gentrification">Aaron Taylor Harvey</a>, the Executive Creative Director of Environments at Airbnb had spotted something similar:</p><p>“You can feel a kind of trend in certain listings. There’s an International Airbnb Style that’s starting to happen. I think that some of it is really a wonderful thing that gives people a sense of comfort and immediate belonging when they travel, and some of it is a little generic. It can go either way.”</p><p>This “Modern Life Space” or “International AirBnB Style” goes by a number of other names. It’s known as the Brooklyn Look, or according to the journalist Kyle Chayka, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/aug/06/hipster-aesthetic-taking-over-world">AirSpace</a>:</p><p>“I called this style “AirSpace”. It’s marked by an easily recognisable mix of symbols – like reclaimed wood, Edison bulbs, and refurbished industrial lighting – that’s meant to provide familiar, comforting surroundings for a wealthy, mobile elite, who want to feel like they’re visiting somewhere “authentic” while they travel, but who actually just crave more of the same: more rustic interiors and sans-serif logos and splashes of cliche accent colours on rugs and walls.”</p><p>Perhaps this seems inevitable. Isn’t it obvious that a global group of hosts all trying to present their properties to a global group of travellers would converge on a single, optimal, appealing yet inoffensive style?</p><p>AirSpace, however, isn’t just limited to residential interiors. The same tired tropes have spread beyond the spaces where we live, and taken over the spaces where we work, eat, drink and relax.</p><p>In an in-depth investigation for <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/aug/06/hipster-aesthetic-taking-over-world">The Guardian</a>, Chayka documents how the AirSpace style of interior decor has become the dominant design style of coffee shops:</p><p>“Go to Shoreditch Grind, near a roundabout in the middle of London’s hipster district. It’s a coffee shop with rough-hewn wooden tables, plentiful sunlight from wide windows, and austere pendant lighting. Then head to Takk in Manchester. It’s a coffee shop with a big glass storefront, reclaimed wood furniture, and hanging Edison bulbs. Compare the two: You might not even know you’re in different spaces. It’s no accident that these places look similar. Though they’re not part of a chain and don’t have their interior design directed by a single corporate overlord, these coffee shops have a way of mimicking the same tired style, a hipster reduction obsessed with a superficial sense of history and the remnants of industrial machinery that once occupied the neighbourhoods they take over.”</p><p>And this isn’t just a trend that we can see in British coffee culture. The same trend has been identified in cities from Bangkok to Beijing and from Seoul to San Francisco.</p>
</div><div data-test="image-block-inline-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_307432">

      

      
        <figure>
          
        
        

        
          
            
          <div data-animation-role="image">
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/5f34eabb-d900-4bca-a9a5-751e192b7b3f/The+Age+of+Average_0010_Interiors+-+Coffee+shops.jpg" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/5f34eabb-d900-4bca-a9a5-751e192b7b3f/The+Age+of+Average_0010_Interiors+-+Coffee+shops.jpg" data-image-dimensions="4961x2787" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/5f34eabb-d900-4bca-a9a5-751e192b7b3f/The+Age+of+Average_0010_Interiors+-+Coffee+shops.jpg" width="4961" height="2787" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/5f34eabb-d900-4bca-a9a5-751e192b7b3f/The+Age+of+Average_0010_Interiors+-+Coffee+shops.jpg?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/5f34eabb-d900-4bca-a9a5-751e192b7b3f/The+Age+of+Average_0010_Interiors+-+Coffee+shops.jpg?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/5f34eabb-d900-4bca-a9a5-751e192b7b3f/The+Age+of+Average_0010_Interiors+-+Coffee+shops.jpg?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/5f34eabb-d900-4bca-a9a5-751e192b7b3f/The+Age+of+Average_0010_Interiors+-+Coffee+shops.jpg?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/5f34eabb-d900-4bca-a9a5-751e192b7b3f/The+Age+of+Average_0010_Interiors+-+Coffee+shops.jpg?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/5f34eabb-d900-4bca-a9a5-751e192b7b3f/The+Age+of+Average_0010_Interiors+-+Coffee+shops.jpg?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/5f34eabb-d900-4bca-a9a5-751e192b7b3f/The+Age+of+Average_0010_Interiors+-+Coffee+shops.jpg?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            </p>
          </div>
        
          
        

        
          
          <figcaption>
            <p>AirSpace</p>
          </figcaption>
        
      
        </figure>
      

    </div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_307794">
  <p>According to <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2016/8/3/12325104/airbnb-aesthetic-global-minimalism-startup-gentrification">The Verge</a>:</p><p>“The coffee roaster Four Barrel in San Francisco looks like the Australian Toby’s Estate in Brooklyn looks like The Coffee Collective in Copenhagen looks like Bear Pond Espresso in Tokyo. You can get a dry cortado with perfect latte art at any of them, then Instagram it on a marble countertop and further spread the aesthetic to your followers.”</p><p>Once this interior design style became dominant in the world’s coffee shops, it began to spread throughout the wider hospitality sector. </p><p>Anne Quito, for example, writes about how the hipster makeover has made its way to restaurants in <a href="https://qz.com/764853/the-brooklyn-look-is-sweeping-the-world-to-designers-dismay-and-business-owners-delight/">Quartz</a>:</p><p>“Established restaurants are getting the hipster makeover. Traditional restaurants like Dickey’s Barbecue in Dallas, eateries in Toronto’s Chinatown and even the 47-year-old roadside diner chain Cracker Barrel—in the guise of its new biscuit joint Holler &amp; Dash—are embracing chalkboard menus and reclaimed wood look to attract the affluent, design-savvy millennial.”</p><p>So, the interiors of our homes, coffee shops and restaurants have begun to converge upon a single style. But when we move outside, the story doesn’t get much better.</p><h3>Architecture all looks the same</h3><p>The anthropologist Marc Augé coined the term “non-place” to describe built environments that are defined by their transience and anonymity. Non-places, such as airports, service stations and hotels, tend towards utilitarian sterility. They prioritise function and efficiency over a softer sense of human expression and social connection.</p><p>In 1995, the Professor of Architecture and Urban Design at Harvard University, Rem Koolhaas, published an essay titled The Generic City:</p><p>“Is the contemporary city like the contemporary airport— ‘all the same’? Is it possible to theorise this convergence? And if so, to what ultimate configuration is it aspiring? Convergence is possible only at the price of shedding identity. That is usually seen as a loss. But at the scale at which it occurs it must mean something. What are the disadvantages of identity, and conversely, what are the advantages of blankness? What if this seemingly accidental, and usually regretted, homogenization was an intentional process, a conscious movement away from difference toward similarity?”</p><p>That opening question takes Augé’s idea of the sterile non-place and applies it to the city as a whole. Koolhaas, in effect, is arguing that soulless is becoming the default design direction of all urban architecture.</p>
</div><div data-test="image-block-inline-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_334264">

      

      
        <figure>
          
        
        

        
          
            
          <div data-animation-role="image">
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/22c63688-9507-4a98-ab95-02017ef800c2/The+Age+of+Average_0011_Exteriors+-+Skylines.jpg" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/22c63688-9507-4a98-ab95-02017ef800c2/The+Age+of+Average_0011_Exteriors+-+Skylines.jpg" data-image-dimensions="4961x2787" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/22c63688-9507-4a98-ab95-02017ef800c2/The+Age+of+Average_0011_Exteriors+-+Skylines.jpg" width="4961" height="2787" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/22c63688-9507-4a98-ab95-02017ef800c2/The+Age+of+Average_0011_Exteriors+-+Skylines.jpg?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/22c63688-9507-4a98-ab95-02017ef800c2/The+Age+of+Average_0011_Exteriors+-+Skylines.jpg?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/22c63688-9507-4a98-ab95-02017ef800c2/The+Age+of+Average_0011_Exteriors+-+Skylines.jpg?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/22c63688-9507-4a98-ab95-02017ef800c2/The+Age+of+Average_0011_Exteriors+-+Skylines.jpg?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/22c63688-9507-4a98-ab95-02017ef800c2/The+Age+of+Average_0011_Exteriors+-+Skylines.jpg?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/22c63688-9507-4a98-ab95-02017ef800c2/The+Age+of+Average_0011_Exteriors+-+Skylines.jpg?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/22c63688-9507-4a98-ab95-02017ef800c2/The+Age+of+Average_0011_Exteriors+-+Skylines.jpg?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            </p>
          </div>
        
          
        

        
          
          <figcaption>
            <p>The generic city</p>
          </figcaption>
        
      
        </figure>
      

    </div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_334625">
  <p>Almost 30 years after the publication of The Generic City I think it’s clear Koolhaas’ fears were well founded. Architecture’s march towards blank homogeneity is perhaps most obvious in the quick build, low-cost apartment blocks that have rapidly spread across the United States.</p><p>Justin Fox writing for <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/features/2019-02-13/why-america-s-new-apartment-buildings-all-look-the-same">Bloomberg</a>:</p><p>“Cheap stick framing has led to a proliferation of blocky, forgettable mid-rises. (…) These buildings are in almost every U.S. city. They range from three to seven stories tall and can stretch for blocks. They’re usually full of rental apartments, but they can also house college dorms, condominiums, hotels, or assisted-living facilities. Close to city centers, they tend toward a blocky, often colorful modernism; out in the suburbs, their architecture is more likely to feature peaked roofs and historical motifs. Their outer walls are covered with fiber cement, metal, stucco, or bricks.”</p><p>This architectural style, characterised by boxy forms and unconvincing cladding, goes by names such as Fast-Casual Architecture and McUrbanism. But perhaps most commonly, these buildings are known as five-over-ones.</p><p>When Justin Fox drove across the US, he realised that they were not specific to one city or state. They were everywhere. And they were proliferating:&nbsp; </p><p>“In 2017, 187,000 new housing units were completed in buildings of 50 units or more in the U.S., the most since the Census Bureau started keeping track in 1972. By my informal massaging of the data, well over half of those were in blocky mid-rises.”</p><p>But why is this the case? Why are the majority of large American buildings succumbing to the same style?</p><p>Coby Lefkowitz offers four reasons in his essay, “<a href="https://marker.medium.com/why-everywhere-looks-the-same-248940f12c4">Why Everywhere Looks the Same</a>”. First, unlike in the early 20th century, developers are increasingly constrained by building codes. Second, rapidly rising land costs cause developers to pack as many properties as possible into every site. Third, the rising barriers to entry have caused the industry to consolidate. And fourth, developers seek to reduce their costs by reusing the same plans across multiple sites:</p><p>“It would be disappointing enough to fail in gracing a land as physically beautiful as the US with the built companions it deserves. But it’s downright shameful that we deprive ourselves of living in interesting, meaningful, and wonderful places, given the thousands of precedents for inspiration worldwide, and many hundreds within our borders. Instead, we’ve copied and pasted our society from the most anodyne, the most boring, and the most bleh. We’ve all seen them. Covered with fiber cement, stucco, and bricks or brick-like material. They’ve shown up all over the country, indifferent to their surroundings. Spreading like a non-native species.”</p>
</div><div data-test="image-block-inline-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_350558">

      

      
        <figure>
          
        
        

        
          
            
          <div data-animation-role="image">
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/624d1c73-6f4e-43ea-b3fd-d3ebd144ac00/The+Age+of+Average_0012_Exteriors+-+Apartments.jpg" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/624d1c73-6f4e-43ea-b3fd-d3ebd144ac00/The+Age+of+Average_0012_Exteriors+-+Apartments.jpg" data-image-dimensions="4961x2787" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/624d1c73-6f4e-43ea-b3fd-d3ebd144ac00/The+Age+of+Average_0012_Exteriors+-+Apartments.jpg" width="4961" height="2787" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/624d1c73-6f4e-43ea-b3fd-d3ebd144ac00/The+Age+of+Average_0012_Exteriors+-+Apartments.jpg?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/624d1c73-6f4e-43ea-b3fd-d3ebd144ac00/The+Age+of+Average_0012_Exteriors+-+Apartments.jpg?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/624d1c73-6f4e-43ea-b3fd-d3ebd144ac00/The+Age+of+Average_0012_Exteriors+-+Apartments.jpg?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/624d1c73-6f4e-43ea-b3fd-d3ebd144ac00/The+Age+of+Average_0012_Exteriors+-+Apartments.jpg?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/624d1c73-6f4e-43ea-b3fd-d3ebd144ac00/The+Age+of+Average_0012_Exteriors+-+Apartments.jpg?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/624d1c73-6f4e-43ea-b3fd-d3ebd144ac00/The+Age+of+Average_0012_Exteriors+-+Apartments.jpg?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/624d1c73-6f4e-43ea-b3fd-d3ebd144ac00/The+Age+of+Average_0012_Exteriors+-+Apartments.jpg?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            </p>
          </div>
        
          
        

        
          
          <figcaption>
            <p>America’s five-over-one architecture</p>
          </figcaption>
        
      
        </figure>
      

    </div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_350920">
  <p>Cities once felt rooted in time and place. The Victorian grandeur of London. The Art Deco glamour of New York. The neon modernity of Tokyo. But with anodyne architecture spreading across the United States, cities are beginning to lose their contextual identities. They are all starting to look the same:</p><p>“Institutional developers march forward, ignorant of what makes Portland, Maine different from Portland, Oregon, or Philadelphia from Kansas City. Unique local traditions? Completely different climates? Hah! Joke’s on us. A box fits just as well in any of these places.”</p><p>And it isn’t just the design of our residential buildings but our professional ones as well.</p><p>In an article for <a href="https://grist.org/business-technology/why-do-all-office-parks-look-the-same/">Grist</a>, Heather Smith describes the homogeneity of the office parks she’d pass on the way to her mother’s place of work and how present day Silicon Valley feels so similar.</p><p>“All the offices and factories along the way to my mom’s office were smaller versions of the same thing — set back from the road, behind deep rectangles of rolling green lawn, no sidewalks. Sometimes clusters of begonias added accent marks, or regimented little bushes pruned into spheres or squares.”</p><p>Smith continues:</p><p>“I thought about this recently when I went driving through Silicon Valley, because I was surprised at how similar it was to the neighborhoods that I had grown up in. Not that it was an exact replica (…). But the architecture was the same — the same low-slung buildings, set back from the street by parking lots, each complex its own self-contained bubble, separated from the road by a row of trees.”</p><p>So, the places where we live and work have begun to converge upon a single style, but we’re also seeing the same trend occur in the way we travel between them.</p><h3>Cars all looks the same</h3><p>In 2015, the ex-Chairman of BBH London, <a href="https://www.jimcarrollsblog.com/blog/2015/2/24/wind-tunnel-marketing-in-todays-campaign">Jim Carroll</a> recalled his realisation 32 years earlier that aerodynamic tests had begun to make all cars look alike:</p><p>“Some of you will recall the day in 1983 when we woke up and noticed that the cars all looked the same. There was a simple explanation. They’d all been through the same wind tunnel. We nodded assent at the evident improvement in fuel efficiency, but we could not escape a weary sigh of disappointment. Modern life is rubbish.”</p><p>In Carroll’s opinion, because all vehicles underwent the same wind tunnel tests, manufacturers were independently converging on the same optimal set of forms, proportions and dimensions. And as a result, homogeneity in car design was increasing.</p><p>What Carroll didn’t realise was that things were about to get a lot worse.</p><p>Sat at a red light, <a href="https://www.roadandtrack.com/car-culture/a36715409/why-does-every-new-car-look-like-every-other-new-car/">Drew Magary</a> took the opportunity to scope out some new car ideas. Suddenly he saw an SUV that looked attractive. But he couldn’t quite see the badge. Another car was blocking his line of sight:</p><p>“Maybe it’s a Bimmer,” I said to the dog. “It kinda looks like one.” It wasn’t. It was a Hyundai Santa Fe, which kinda resembles the Acura RDX, which kinda resembles the Volvo XC60, which kinda resembles the BMW X3. (…) These four models are all 75 inches wide, 66 inches high (save for the Volvo, which is 65), and they only differ in length by a maximum of three inches. They all have rear quarter windows smaller than a porthole on a submarine. They all have chrome accents to increase the glam factor by, like, five percent. And they all abhor right angles, (…). They’re spiritual clones, and they’re not exceptions in being so.”</p>
</div><div data-test="image-block-inline-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_401954">

      

      
        <figure>
          
        
        

        
          
            
          <div data-animation-role="image">
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/9afc9fcc-13dc-4522-8efc-8755bb4cca7f/The+Age+of+Average_0008_Cars+-+Form.jpg" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/9afc9fcc-13dc-4522-8efc-8755bb4cca7f/The+Age+of+Average_0008_Cars+-+Form.jpg" data-image-dimensions="4961x2787" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/9afc9fcc-13dc-4522-8efc-8755bb4cca7f/The+Age+of+Average_0008_Cars+-+Form.jpg" width="4961" height="2787" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/9afc9fcc-13dc-4522-8efc-8755bb4cca7f/The+Age+of+Average_0008_Cars+-+Form.jpg?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/9afc9fcc-13dc-4522-8efc-8755bb4cca7f/The+Age+of+Average_0008_Cars+-+Form.jpg?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/9afc9fcc-13dc-4522-8efc-8755bb4cca7f/The+Age+of+Average_0008_Cars+-+Form.jpg?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/9afc9fcc-13dc-4522-8efc-8755bb4cca7f/The+Age+of+Average_0008_Cars+-+Form.jpg?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/9afc9fcc-13dc-4522-8efc-8755bb4cca7f/The+Age+of+Average_0008_Cars+-+Form.jpg?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/9afc9fcc-13dc-4522-8efc-8755bb4cca7f/The+Age+of+Average_0008_Cars+-+Form.jpg?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/9afc9fcc-13dc-4522-8efc-8755bb4cca7f/The+Age+of+Average_0008_Cars+-+Form.jpg?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            </p>
          </div>
        
          
        

        
          
          <figcaption>
            <p>The wind tunnel effect (Source: Adrian Hanft, User Zero)</p>
          </figcaption>
        
      
        </figure>
      

    </div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_402330">
  <p>But why do so many modern cars look the same? </p><p>Jim Carroll’s wind-tunnel theory is certainly one reason. Another is that the automotive giants increasingly share vehicle “platforms” between the many brands that they operate. And <a href="https://www.roadandtrack.com/car-culture/a36715409/why-does-every-new-car-look-like-every-other-new-car/">Ian Callum</a>, who led design at Jaguar-Land Rover for two decades, provides a third theory.</p><p>“There was a time when you could identify the country the car came from. But today, basically every company makes cars for basically every country (…). Cars are now designed for the broadest possible audience, across the broadest number of countries, to be manufactured in the most efficient possible way.”</p><p>Callum continues:</p><p>“Before the typical car designer can even begin sketching out a model, they’re given specs from the packaging department (…). The measurements might vary within millimetres. These strict dimensions are agonisingly chosen to please the needs of the wind tunnel, to adhere to government safety regulations, to properly accommodate the average American family’s collective weight of 78,000 lbs., and to allow for enough cargo space for all their crap.”</p><p>These three theories explain why the three-dimensional design of cars has been converging over time. But they don’t explain why the colour of cars has converged as well.</p><p>According to data shared by <a href="https://twitter.com/jokull/status/1413941573285519360?s=46&amp;t=wqhUUXYC6rJ-1raSoFy_Og">Jökull Solberg</a>, around 40% of cars sold in 1996 were monochromatic (black, white, silver or grey). 20 years later that figure had increased to 80%.</p><p>There are many suggestions for why this might be. Perhaps these colours come as standard and everything else is an optional upgrade. Perhaps brighter colours fade more quickly. Maybe people buy less vibrant colours when times are more turbulent. Maybe the resale market for monochromatic cars is more buoyant. Or maybe the pared-back design of smartphones informed stylistic trends in the auto industry.&nbsp;</p><p>Regardless, the result is the same. Where once carparks were a kaleidoscope of reds, blues and greens, today they capture a sea of desaturation.</p><p>And what’s more? The visual identities of car brands seem to be following suit. In September 2020, Vauxhall released a modernised, minimal marque. According to Henry Wong at <a href="https://www.designweek.co.uk/issues/28-september-4-october/whats-driving-so-many-car-brands-to-redesign-their-identity/">Design Week</a>:</p><p>“Vauxhall unveiled its new logo last week, a “confidently British” look, which reworks the griffin icon and introduces a blue-and-red colour scheme. Most prominent is its new flat styling — a simplified version of the logo’s previous 3D look. Vauxhall calls the redesign the “progressive face of the brand”.”</p>
</div><div data-test="image-block-inline-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_454787">

      

      
        <figure>
          
        
        

        
          
            
          <div data-animation-role="image">
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/b0a5f012-0cd4-41be-a2f5-4910ebda8495/The+Age+of+Average_0007_Cars+-+Logos.jpg" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/b0a5f012-0cd4-41be-a2f5-4910ebda8495/The+Age+of+Average_0007_Cars+-+Logos.jpg" data-image-dimensions="4961x2787" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/b0a5f012-0cd4-41be-a2f5-4910ebda8495/The+Age+of+Average_0007_Cars+-+Logos.jpg" width="4961" height="2787" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/b0a5f012-0cd4-41be-a2f5-4910ebda8495/The+Age+of+Average_0007_Cars+-+Logos.jpg?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/b0a5f012-0cd4-41be-a2f5-4910ebda8495/The+Age+of+Average_0007_Cars+-+Logos.jpg?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/b0a5f012-0cd4-41be-a2f5-4910ebda8495/The+Age+of+Average_0007_Cars+-+Logos.jpg?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/b0a5f012-0cd4-41be-a2f5-4910ebda8495/The+Age+of+Average_0007_Cars+-+Logos.jpg?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/b0a5f012-0cd4-41be-a2f5-4910ebda8495/The+Age+of+Average_0007_Cars+-+Logos.jpg?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/b0a5f012-0cd4-41be-a2f5-4910ebda8495/The+Age+of+Average_0007_Cars+-+Logos.jpg?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/b0a5f012-0cd4-41be-a2f5-4910ebda8495/The+Age+of+Average_0007_Cars+-+Logos.jpg?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            </p>
          </div>
        
          
        

        
          
          <figcaption>
            <p>The “blanding” of automotive brand identities</p>
          </figcaption>
        
      
        </figure>
      

    </div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_455153">
  <p>Vauxhall had ditched a logo that looked like a chrome sculpted bonnet badge and replaced it with a flatter, thinner, altogether simpler execution. But they weren’t the only one. As Wong says, at least five other major manufacturers had charted a similar course:</p><p>“It’s a familiar story within car branding of late. Audi first unveiled a minimalist-inspired rebrand in 2018, but it’s been followed by a host of other marques in the past year. Volkswagen, BMW, Toyota, Nissan have all revealed new branding and each with a flat logo.”</p><p>So, the cars we drive, their colours and their logos have begun to converge upon a single style, but we’re also seeing the same trend occur in the way we look ourselves.</p><h3>People all look the same</h3><p>In December 2019 the journalist <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/culture/decade-in-review/the-age-of-instagram-face">Jia Tolentino</a> set about investigating a troubling trend. Many celebrities and influencers had started to resemble each other.&nbsp;</p><p>“This past summer, I booked a plane ticket to Los Angeles with the hope of investigating what seems likely to be one of the oddest legacies of our rapidly expiring decade: the gradual emergence, among professionally beautiful women, of a single, cyborgian face. It’s a young face, of course, with poreless skin and plump, high cheekbones. It has catlike eyes and long, cartoonish lashes; it has a small, neat nose and full, lush lips. It looks at you coyly but blankly, as if its owner has taken half a Klonopin and is considering asking you for a private-jet ride to Coachella.”</p><p>The look that Tolentino is describing is the result of (at least) three conspiring trends. The growing market for injectable treatments is driving a trend for physical enhancements. The rise of apps such as FaceTune is driving a trend for digital enhancements. And make-up techniques such as “strobing” and “contouring” are driving a trend for cosmetic enhancements. Over the last decade, these trends have developed in parallel, each feeding and fueling the other.</p><p>Starting at the top, Tolentino discusses the rising accessibility of beauty treatments such as Botox and fillers:</p><p>“Twenty years ago, plastic surgery was a fairly dramatic intervention: expensive, invasive, permanent, and, often, risky. But, in 2002, the Food and Drug Administration approved Botox for use in preventing wrinkles; a few years later, it approved hyaluronic-acid fillers, such as Juvéderm and Restylane, which at first filled in fine lines and wrinkles and now can be used to restructure jawlines, noses, and cheeks. These procedures last for six months to a year and aren’t nearly as expensive as surgery. (…) You can go get Botox and then head right back to the office.”</p><p>But the cost of achieving this look, which has become known as “Instagram Face”, is even lower than one may imagine. Whilst the average price per syringe of filler is $683, social sharers can now use apps to achieve similar results.</p>
</div><div data-test="image-block-inline-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_489938">

      

      
        <figure>
          
        
        

        
          
            
          <div data-animation-role="image">
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/ce2887b1-08ed-4561-b0df-9de2050f0d6e/The+Age+of+Average_0005_People+-+Celebrities.jpg" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/ce2887b1-08ed-4561-b0df-9de2050f0d6e/The+Age+of+Average_0005_People+-+Celebrities.jpg" data-image-dimensions="4961x2787" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/ce2887b1-08ed-4561-b0df-9de2050f0d6e/The+Age+of+Average_0005_People+-+Celebrities.jpg" width="4961" height="2787" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/ce2887b1-08ed-4561-b0df-9de2050f0d6e/The+Age+of+Average_0005_People+-+Celebrities.jpg?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/ce2887b1-08ed-4561-b0df-9de2050f0d6e/The+Age+of+Average_0005_People+-+Celebrities.jpg?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/ce2887b1-08ed-4561-b0df-9de2050f0d6e/The+Age+of+Average_0005_People+-+Celebrities.jpg?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/ce2887b1-08ed-4561-b0df-9de2050f0d6e/The+Age+of+Average_0005_People+-+Celebrities.jpg?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/ce2887b1-08ed-4561-b0df-9de2050f0d6e/The+Age+of+Average_0005_People+-+Celebrities.jpg?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/ce2887b1-08ed-4561-b0df-9de2050f0d6e/The+Age+of+Average_0005_People+-+Celebrities.jpg?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/ce2887b1-08ed-4561-b0df-9de2050f0d6e/The+Age+of+Average_0005_People+-+Celebrities.jpg?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            </p>
          </div>
        
          
        

        
          
          <figcaption>
            <p>Instagram Face</p>
          </figcaption>
        
      
        </figure>
      

    </div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_490301">
  <p>Rebecca Jennings writing for <a href="https://www.vox.com/the-goods/2020/2/13/21125464/brow-lift-botox-bella-hadid-ariana-grande-kylie-jenner">Vox</a>:</p><p>“Instagram Face is so ubiquitous that there are now special filters that give you the look digitally if you can’t afford the real thing. (…) Almost no one is born with Instagram Face — by virtue of it being associated with a digital platform, the look is always mediated and performed — and even those who have it naturally still use tools like FaceTune to enhance their already algorithmically perfect features.”</p><p>Finally, these physical and digital enhancements are complemented by a third, altogether less dystopian, trend: cosmetic enhancements. Here make-up, and an almost endless supply of YouTube tutorials, are used to alter the perceived bone structure of a face.</p><p><a href="https://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/entry/instagram-influencers-beauty_n_5aa13616e4b002df2c6163bc">Julia Brucculieri</a> for the Huffington Post:</p><p>“Social media influencers these days are starting to look like beauty clones. You know the look: a full pout, perfectly arched eyebrows, maybe some expertly applied eyeliner, topped off with a healthy dose of highlighter and cheek contouring. With a few makeup brushes, a contour palette and some matte lip color, you can be well on your way to looking like everyone else.”</p><p>So where did all of this begin?</p><p>According to the make-up artist <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/culture/decade-in-review/the-age-of-instagram-face">Colby Smith</a>, Kim Kardashian is patient-zero of Instagram face. Ultimately, he says, every social media star’s goal is to look like her.</p><p>And Smith isn’t the only one to hold this opinion. Writing for <a href="https://www.thecut.com/2016/06/instagram-makeup-making-us-all-beauty-clones.html">The Cut</a>, Kathleen Hou offers a similarly provocative opinion.</p><p>“Instagram’s beauty posters tend to look like they’re all the same woman, and that woman is Kim Kardashian. Thanks to hundreds of “Get the Look” tutorials, it’s never been easier to strobe and contour yourself into a facsimile of the star. So, no wonder there’s a cloning effect.”</p><p>This may seem like an exaggeration. There is, however, a truth at the centre of the assertion.</p><p>When <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/culture/decade-in-review/the-age-of-instagram-face">The New Yorker</a> interviewed Beverley Hills based plastic surgeon Jason Diamond, he claimed around a third of all his patients aspire to become a Kardashian doppelgänger:</p><p>“I’d say that thirty percent of people come in bringing a photo of Kim, or someone like Kim—there’s a handful of people, but she’s at the very top of the list, and understandably so.”</p><p>And we haven’t only started to look alike from the neck up. <a href="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/femail/article-2103601/Vivienne-Westwood-Everyone-looks-clothes-ugly.html">Dame Vivienne Westwood</a>, the late fashion designer best known for bringing the counter-cultural punk scene onto the catwalk, comments on the way clothing has started to conform: </p><p>“Everybody looks like clones and the only people you notice are my age. I don’t notice anybody unless they look great, and every now and again they do, and they are usually 70. We are so conformist, nobody is thinking. We are all sucking up stuff, we have been trained to be consumers and we are all consuming far too much. I’m a fashion designer and people think, what do I know? But I’m talking about all this disposable crap.”</p><p>So, the way we look and the way we dress has begun to converge upon a single style. But when we look at the content we consume, the story doesn’t get much better.</p><h3>Media all looks the same</h3><p>In the early 2010s, French blogger <a href="https://www.boredpanda.com/movie-poster-cliches/?utm_source=google&amp;utm_medium=organic&amp;utm_campaign=organic">Christophe Courtois</a> began curating movie posters that conformed to strikingly similar formulas.</p><p>Rom-coms often used a guy and a girl standing back-to-back against a white background. Horror films featured a close up of an eye. Action films opting for a lone character, dressed in black with their back to the camera.</p><p>Courtois’ series perfectly illustrates how, in the 21st Century, every genre of film sticks to a relatively narrow set of clichés, codes and conventions that promoters slavishly abide by.</p>
</div><div data-test="image-block-inline-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_547656">

      

      
        <figure>
          
        
        

        
          
            
          <div data-animation-role="image">
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/8ed3f2bb-b5e9-40b0-b25e-3a8decfc32a5/The+Age+of+Average_0004_Films.jpg" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/8ed3f2bb-b5e9-40b0-b25e-3a8decfc32a5/The+Age+of+Average_0004_Films.jpg" data-image-dimensions="4961x2787" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/8ed3f2bb-b5e9-40b0-b25e-3a8decfc32a5/The+Age+of+Average_0004_Films.jpg" width="4961" height="2787" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/8ed3f2bb-b5e9-40b0-b25e-3a8decfc32a5/The+Age+of+Average_0004_Films.jpg?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/8ed3f2bb-b5e9-40b0-b25e-3a8decfc32a5/The+Age+of+Average_0004_Films.jpg?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/8ed3f2bb-b5e9-40b0-b25e-3a8decfc32a5/The+Age+of+Average_0004_Films.jpg?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/8ed3f2bb-b5e9-40b0-b25e-3a8decfc32a5/The+Age+of+Average_0004_Films.jpg?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/8ed3f2bb-b5e9-40b0-b25e-3a8decfc32a5/The+Age+of+Average_0004_Films.jpg?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/8ed3f2bb-b5e9-40b0-b25e-3a8decfc32a5/The+Age+of+Average_0004_Films.jpg?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/8ed3f2bb-b5e9-40b0-b25e-3a8decfc32a5/The+Age+of+Average_0004_Films.jpg?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            </p>
          </div>
        
          
        

        
          
          <figcaption>
            <p>Christophe Courtois’ cinematic clichés</p>
          </figcaption>
        
      
        </figure>
      

    </div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_548040">
  <p>In Hadley Freeman’s book <a href="https://amzn.eu/d/0cB2krS">Life Moves Pretty Fast</a>, Oscar winning director Steven Soderbergh argues that this is the natural result of testing:</p><p>“If you've ever wondered why every poster and every trailer and every TV spot looks exactly the same, it's because of testing. It's because anything interesting scores poorly and gets kicked out. (…) I've tried to argue that maybe the thing that's making it distinctive, and score poorly, actually would stick out if you presented it to these people the way the real world presents it. And I’ve never won that argument.”</p><p>But is the homogenisation of Hollywood a new phenomenon?</p><p>To find out <a href="https://experimentalhistory.substack.com/p/pop-culture-has-become-an-oligopoly">Adam Mastroianni</a> analysed the top 20 grossing films in every year since 1977 and coded whether each was part of a “multiplicity” (i.e. a sequel, prequel, franchise, spin-off, reboot etc.).</p><p>What he found was surprising:&nbsp;</p><p>“Until the year 2000, about 25% of top-grossing movies were prequels, sequels, spinoffs, remakes, reboots, or cinematic universe expansions. Since 2010, it’s been over 50% ever year. In recent years, it’s been close to 100%.”</p><p>Mastroianni continues:</p><p>“In 2021, only one of the ten top-grossing films (the Ryan Reynolds vehicle Free Guy) was an original. There were only two originals in 2020’s top 10, and none at all in 2019.”</p><p>A further finding for the research was that the revenue generated by the top 20 movies was, until 2015, around 40% of that generated by the top 200. Since then however that 40% figure has begun to climb even higher, crossing the 60% threshold in 2021.</p><p>In short, the top 20 films are becoming both bigger and more alike.</p><p>But this isn’t just happening in film. In every corner of pop culture, a smaller number of “blockbusters” is claiming a larger share of the market. What were once creative powerhouses have become factories of the familiar.</p><p>Take books.</p><p>“It used to be pretty rare for one author to have multiple books in the top 10 in the same year. Since 1990, it’s happened almost every year. No author ever had three top 10 books in one year until Danielle Steel did it 1998. In 2011, John Grisham, Kathryn Stockett, and Stieg Larsson all had two chart-topping books each. (…) In the 1950s, a little over half of the authors in the top 10 had been there before. These days, it’s closer to 75%.”</p><p>You can see this creative convergence for yourself when you next visit a bookstore. In fiction you’ll see many popular books following a “girl with…” naming convention. Of course, there’s Larsson’s “The Girl with the Dragon Tattoo”, but we’ve also seen Paula Hawkins’ “The Girl on the Train”, M. R. Carey’s “The Girl With all the Gifts” and A. J. Grayson’s “The Girl in the Water”.</p><p>In non-fiction, if you visit the self-help category, you’ll notice that every book title seems to include a swear word. We have Mark Manson’s “The Subtle Art of not Giving a Fuck”, Sarah Knight’s “The Life Changing Magic of Not Giving a Fuck” and Alexis Rockley’s “Find your Fuck Yeah.”</p>
</div><div data-test="image-block-inline-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_581357">

      

      
        <figure>
          
        
        

        
          
            
          <div data-animation-role="image">
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/b7838ce0-218d-46ca-aff4-cda5c6dc6941/The+Age+of+Average_0002_Books+-+Non-fiction.jpg" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/b7838ce0-218d-46ca-aff4-cda5c6dc6941/The+Age+of+Average_0002_Books+-+Non-fiction.jpg" data-image-dimensions="4961x2787" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/b7838ce0-218d-46ca-aff4-cda5c6dc6941/The+Age+of+Average_0002_Books+-+Non-fiction.jpg" width="4961" height="2787" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/b7838ce0-218d-46ca-aff4-cda5c6dc6941/The+Age+of+Average_0002_Books+-+Non-fiction.jpg?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/b7838ce0-218d-46ca-aff4-cda5c6dc6941/The+Age+of+Average_0002_Books+-+Non-fiction.jpg?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/b7838ce0-218d-46ca-aff4-cda5c6dc6941/The+Age+of+Average_0002_Books+-+Non-fiction.jpg?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/b7838ce0-218d-46ca-aff4-cda5c6dc6941/The+Age+of+Average_0002_Books+-+Non-fiction.jpg?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/b7838ce0-218d-46ca-aff4-cda5c6dc6941/The+Age+of+Average_0002_Books+-+Non-fiction.jpg?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/b7838ce0-218d-46ca-aff4-cda5c6dc6941/The+Age+of+Average_0002_Books+-+Non-fiction.jpg?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/b7838ce0-218d-46ca-aff4-cda5c6dc6941/The+Age+of+Average_0002_Books+-+Non-fiction.jpg?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            </p>
          </div>
        
          
        

        
          
          <figcaption>
            <p>Sweary self-help books</p>
          </figcaption>
        
      
        </figure>
      

    </div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_581733">
  <p>Video games are no different.</p><p>In the late 1990s, 75% or less of the best-selling video games were franchise instalments. Since 2005, it’s been closer to 100%.</p><p>I’ll quote Keith Stuart, writing for <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/games/2022/jun/14/pushing-buttons-why-every-big-video-game-looks-the-same">The Guardian</a>, at length:</p><p>“The absence of the E3 expo in Los Angeles for the past two years has left a gigantic vacuum in the video game calendar. Last week, the industry did its best to fill that gaping content maw with three online events – the Summer Game fest, the Xbox and Bethesda showcase and the PC gaming show. They were underwhelming for many seasoned players. Major reveals included a remake of The Last of Us, a remake of Call of Duty: Modern Warfare II, Street Fighter 6, Final Fantasy XVI and news about the reimagining of the classic role-player System Shock.”</p><p>So, our movies, books and video games have all begun to look the same. But it’s not just the content we consume. When we look at the content brands produce the story doesn’t get much better.</p><h3>Brands all look the same</h3><p>In 1982 the American fashion photographer Irving Penn shot an ad for Clinique that became known as “the shelfie”. The advert is simply a photograph of the inside of a medicine cabinet. A bright white background. Glass shelves. Bottles of pills. And a few well branded Clinique products.</p><p>Since this iconic 80s ad, many other brands have created their own shelfies, including Selfridges, e. l. f. and Billie. But this isn’t the only tried and tested trope.</p><p>Here’s <a href="https://eyeondesign.aiga.org/all-advertising-looks-the-same-these-days-blame-the-moodboard/">AIGA Eye on Design</a>:</p><p>“There are many more oft-mimicked setups like the shelfie currently bouncing around the zeitgeist; one omnipresent shot includes objects placed on a mirror reflecting the sky, giving the illusion of a product floating in midair. Another example uses a dense pattern of water droplets to refract a single item into a series of psychedelic miniatures, while yet another places subjects in front of faux scenic backdrops reminiscent of a low-budget Sears photo studio. Each of these distinct setups is utilized broadly and across industries, with the same composition and concept seen on the Instagram feeds of a major beverage syndicate and an indie skincare brand alike.”</p>
</div><div data-test="image-block-inline-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_594083">

      

      
        <figure>
          
        
        

        
          
            
          <div data-animation-role="image">
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/4a65c0b3-9da3-4672-983a-94a4d579cd5b/The+Age+of+Average_0001_Brands+-+Cosmetics.jpg" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/4a65c0b3-9da3-4672-983a-94a4d579cd5b/The+Age+of+Average_0001_Brands+-+Cosmetics.jpg" data-image-dimensions="4961x2787" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/4a65c0b3-9da3-4672-983a-94a4d579cd5b/The+Age+of+Average_0001_Brands+-+Cosmetics.jpg" width="4961" height="2787" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/4a65c0b3-9da3-4672-983a-94a4d579cd5b/The+Age+of+Average_0001_Brands+-+Cosmetics.jpg?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/4a65c0b3-9da3-4672-983a-94a4d579cd5b/The+Age+of+Average_0001_Brands+-+Cosmetics.jpg?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/4a65c0b3-9da3-4672-983a-94a4d579cd5b/The+Age+of+Average_0001_Brands+-+Cosmetics.jpg?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/4a65c0b3-9da3-4672-983a-94a4d579cd5b/The+Age+of+Average_0001_Brands+-+Cosmetics.jpg?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/4a65c0b3-9da3-4672-983a-94a4d579cd5b/The+Age+of+Average_0001_Brands+-+Cosmetics.jpg?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/4a65c0b3-9da3-4672-983a-94a4d579cd5b/The+Age+of+Average_0001_Brands+-+Cosmetics.jpg?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/4a65c0b3-9da3-4672-983a-94a4d579cd5b/The+Age+of+Average_0001_Brands+-+Cosmetics.jpg?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            </p>
          </div>
        
          
        

        
          
          <figcaption>
            <p>Shelfies</p>
          </figcaption>
        
      
        </figure>
      

    </div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_594445">
  <p>In an article for The Cut, titled <a href="https://www.thecut.com/2020/03/will-the-millennial-aesthetic-ever-end.html">The Tyranny of Terrazzo</a>, Molly Fischer pushes this thought one step further.</p><p>Whilst there is the shelfie trope and the mirror trope and the water droplet trope, these layouts all seem to share a surprisingly consistent style of art direction. They might be compositionally different, but they are conceptually alike:</p><p>“And then there are advertisements, making up a visual world of their own. The products on view (cookware, supplements, stretchy clothes) occupy blank pastel landscapes manipulated by a diversity of hands. These aren’t ads that bellow or hector; they whisper, in restrained sans-serif fonts, or chastely flirt, in letters with curves and bounce. They’re ads, sure, but they’re so well designed. In this era, you come to understand, design was the product. Whatever else you might be buying, you were buying design, and all the design looked the same.”&nbsp;</p><p>Whilst Clinique’s original Shelfie hails from the 80s, it wasn’t until the 2010s that it became a more widely adopted style. And the majority of companies who did so were digital-first, DTC brands.</p><p><a href="https://eyeondesign.aiga.org/all-advertising-looks-the-same-these-days-blame-the-moodboard/">Elizabeth Goodspeed</a> argues this is because these brands are more likely to draw inspiration from the same vast online sources. The result, she says, is a “moodboard effect”:&nbsp;</p><p>“This kind of visual homogeneity is a common occurrence in the art direction world, where ubiquitous styles operate less like trends and more like memes; remixed and diluted until they become a single visual mass. In today’s extremely-online world, the vast availability of reference imagery has, perhaps counterintuitively, led to narrower thinking and shallower visual ideation. It’s a product of what I like to call the “moodboard effect”.”</p><p>So, designers use the same online platforms, draw inspiration from the same sorts of imagery and, in turn, create broadly the same types of adverts.</p><p>But it isn’t just advertising that is causing brands to all look the same. Their visual identities are converging as well.</p><p>In December 2018, Thierry Brunfaut and Tom Greenwood published an article in <a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/90276496/the-hottest-branding-trend-of-the-year-is-also-the-worst">Fast Company</a> where they coined a new word: Blanding.</p><p>“The worst branding trend (…) is the one you probably never noticed. I call it blanding. The main offenders are in tech, where a new army of clones wears a uniform of brand camouflage. The formula is sort of a brand paint-by-numbers. Start with a made-up-word name. Put it in a sans-serif typeface. Make it clean and readable, with just the right amount of white space. Use a direct tone of voice. Nope, no need for a logo. Maybe throw in some cheerful illustrations. Just don’t forget the vibrant colors. Bonus points for purple and turquoise. Blah blah blah.”</p><p>Companies like AirBnB, Spotify and eBay have all dropped colourful logos with expressive typography for a straighter, stricter, altogether more muted, alternative.</p>
</div><div data-test="image-block-inline-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_624022">

      

      
        <figure>
          
        
        

        
          
            
          <div data-animation-role="image">
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/2dc85b51-d3f5-439f-9c20-3b6486454d95/The+Age+of+Average_0000_Brands+-+Toothbrushes.jpg" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/2dc85b51-d3f5-439f-9c20-3b6486454d95/The+Age+of+Average_0000_Brands+-+Toothbrushes.jpg" data-image-dimensions="4961x2787" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/2dc85b51-d3f5-439f-9c20-3b6486454d95/The+Age+of+Average_0000_Brands+-+Toothbrushes.jpg" width="4961" height="2787" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/2dc85b51-d3f5-439f-9c20-3b6486454d95/The+Age+of+Average_0000_Brands+-+Toothbrushes.jpg?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/2dc85b51-d3f5-439f-9c20-3b6486454d95/The+Age+of+Average_0000_Brands+-+Toothbrushes.jpg?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/2dc85b51-d3f5-439f-9c20-3b6486454d95/The+Age+of+Average_0000_Brands+-+Toothbrushes.jpg?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/2dc85b51-d3f5-439f-9c20-3b6486454d95/The+Age+of+Average_0000_Brands+-+Toothbrushes.jpg?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/2dc85b51-d3f5-439f-9c20-3b6486454d95/The+Age+of+Average_0000_Brands+-+Toothbrushes.jpg?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/2dc85b51-d3f5-439f-9c20-3b6486454d95/The+Age+of+Average_0000_Brands+-+Toothbrushes.jpg?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/2dc85b51-d3f5-439f-9c20-3b6486454d95/The+Age+of+Average_0000_Brands+-+Toothbrushes.jpg?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            </p>
          </div>
        
          
        

        
          
          <figcaption>
            <p>The homogeneity of modern brands</p>
          </figcaption>
        
      
        </figure>
      

    </div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_624377">
  <p>Ben Schott writing for <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2020-09-07/welcome-to-your-bland-new-world-of-consumer-capitalism">Bloomberg</a>:</p><p>“Visually, blands are simple, neutral and flat. The palette is plain and pastel (with the occasional vibrant splash); the mood is upbeat and happy, or pensive and cool, but never truly real; the dress-code is smart-casual. Bland people are stock-photo attractive (or quirkily jolie laide). (…) Complex products and technical processes are illustrated by cute cartoons or Noun Project icons. Bland logos are confident but cute, utilizing an array of tweaks and twists to provoke the all-important “smile in the mind”.”</p><p>While the tech sector has led the way on blanding, we see the trend towards flatter, more lifeless, identities playing out in categories from the high-end world of fashion to the more mass world of personal care.</p><p>In a November 2021 article, title <a href="https://www.contagious.com/news-and-views/distinction-rebellion-twitter-report">Distinction Rebellion</a>, Contagious claimed that more and more brands seem content to drift along in a sea of sameness:</p><p>“Look up any new corporate brand identity unveiled over the past decade and you will almost certainly find yourself staring at a flattened and simplified version of the company’s old logo. The aesthetic has become so ubiquitous that it’s acquired its own name – blanding.”</p><p>So, advertising and brand identities are becoming more and more alike. But so too are the taglines brands employ.</p><p>Shai Idelson, Strategy Director at ad agency BBH, collected a list of 27 brands whose taglines follow the “Find Your X” sentence structure. These include Lucozade’s “Find Your Flow”, Rightmove’s “Find Your Happy” and Volvic’s “Find Your Volcano”.</p><p><a href="https://www.bbh-labs.com/have-we-lost-the-ability-to-make-what-we-make-interesting">Idelson</a> says:</p><p>“I love end-lines. The delicate art of capturing a meaningful thought about a brand or a product in as few words as possible. A great end-line will touch my heart and stay in my memory forever. I still remember some from my childhood. But in the last few years, something happened to end-lines. (…) The linguistic similarity is staggering.”&nbsp;</p><p>The same “insight” that sits behind the 27 taglines (that young consumers celebrate individuality above all else) has also led to the “X, Your Way” end line construction. We have Nespresso’s “Indulge, Your Way”, Sonos’ “Sound, Your Way”, Dunelm’s “Dun, Your Way” and many, many more.</p><p>And so brand adverts, identities and taglines are all starting to look the same. But where does this all leave us?</p><h3>Conclusion</h3><p>So, there you have it. The interiors of our homes, coffee shops and restaurants all look the same. The buildings where we live and work all look the same. The cars we drive, their colours and their logos all look the same. The way we look and the way we dress all looks the same. Our movies, books and video games all look the same. And the brands we buy, their adverts, identities and taglines all look the same.</p><p>But it doesn’t end there. In the age of average, homogeneity can be found in an almost indefinite number of domains.</p><p>The <a href="https://www.instagram.com/insta_repeat">Instagram</a> pictures we post, the <a href="https://qz.com/590581/everyone-has-the-same-personality-online">tweets</a> we read, the <a href="https://experimentalhistory.substack.com/p/pop-culture-has-become-an-oligopoly">TV</a> we watch, the <a href="https://twitter.com/rossstevens_uk/status/1361952724695277573?s=46&amp;t=TmI-eK0yCGuxiS_qulQy5A">app icons</a> we click, the <a href="https://twitter.com/culturaltutor/status/1539993526053773316?s=46&amp;t=eUaL2qL7ilKuvgyDzBcEOQ">skylines</a> we see, the <a href="https://twitter.com/wakefield00/status/1361374931993378818?s=46&amp;t=SUddHZRJK8nqI64JIVsszQ">websites</a> we visit and the <a href="https://qz.com/quartzy/1728767/why-editorial-illustrations-look-so-similar-these-days">illustrations</a> which adorn them all look the same. The list goes on, and on, and on.</p>
</div><div data-test="image-block-inline-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_628720">

      

      
        <figure>
          
        
        

        
          
            
          <div data-animation-role="image">
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/495db714-2e33-43a9-a869-df5ce4118b49/The+Age+of+Average_0006_People+-+Influencers.jpg" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/495db714-2e33-43a9-a869-df5ce4118b49/The+Age+of+Average_0006_People+-+Influencers.jpg" data-image-dimensions="4961x2787" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/495db714-2e33-43a9-a869-df5ce4118b49/The+Age+of+Average_0006_People+-+Influencers.jpg" width="4961" height="2787" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/495db714-2e33-43a9-a869-df5ce4118b49/The+Age+of+Average_0006_People+-+Influencers.jpg?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/495db714-2e33-43a9-a869-df5ce4118b49/The+Age+of+Average_0006_People+-+Influencers.jpg?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/495db714-2e33-43a9-a869-df5ce4118b49/The+Age+of+Average_0006_People+-+Influencers.jpg?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/495db714-2e33-43a9-a869-df5ce4118b49/The+Age+of+Average_0006_People+-+Influencers.jpg?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/495db714-2e33-43a9-a869-df5ce4118b49/The+Age+of+Average_0006_People+-+Influencers.jpg?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/495db714-2e33-43a9-a869-df5ce4118b49/The+Age+of+Average_0006_People+-+Influencers.jpg?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13762b05aeab4478a071d5/495db714-2e33-43a9-a869-df5ce4118b49/The+Age+of+Average_0006_People+-+Influencers.jpg?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            </p>
          </div>
        
          
        

        
          
          <figcaption>
            <p>UGC all looks the same (Source: Insta Repeat)</p>
          </figcaption>
        
      
        </figure>
      

    </div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1679173293279_629082">
  <p>There are many reasons why this might have happened.</p><p>Perhaps when times are turbulent, people seek the safety of the familiar. Perhaps it’s our obsession with quantification and optimisation. Or maybe it’s the inevitable result of inspiration becoming globalised.</p><p>Regardless of the reasons, it seems that just as Komar and Melamid produced the “people’s choice” in art, contemporary companies produce the people’s choice in almost every category of creativity.</p><p>But it’s not all bad news.</p><p>I believe that the age of average is the age of opportunity.</p><p>When every supermarket aisle looks like a sea of sameness, when every category abides by the same conventions, when every industry has converged on its own singular style, bold brands and courageous companies have the chance to chart a different course. To be different, distinctive and disruptive.</p><p>So, this is your call to arms. Whether you’re in film or fashion, media or marketing, architecture, automotive or advertising, it doesn’t matter. Our visual culture is flatlining and the only cure is creativity.</p><p>It’s time to cast aside conformity. It’s time to exorcise the expected. It’s time to decline the indistinguishable.</p><p>For years the world has been moving in the same stylistic direction. And it’s time we reintroduced some originality.</p><p>Or as the ad agency BBH says.</p><p>When the world zigs. Zag.</p><h3>Notes</h3><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p>A big thank you to <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/tobyososki/" target="_blank">Toby Ososki</a> for his guidance and support on this piece.</p></li><li><p>This article is based on a talk I gave at the <a href="https://www.alexmurrell.co.uk/talks/wedfresh-the-age-of-average">West of England Design Forum</a> in November 2022.</p></li><li><p>To demonstrate how AI tools will only make this trend worse, Tim O’Neill asked Midjourney to output images in the categories covered in this article. The <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/timoneill_the-age-of-average-a-great-article-by-activity-7044602177952108544-R5JC?utm_medium=member_ios&amp;utm_source=share">results</a> are surprising.</p></li><li><p>This article featured in newsletters from <a href="https://mailchi.mp/onlydeadfish/weekly-fish-food-episode-551?e=0e2dab96f3">Neil Perkin</a>, <a href="https://stratscraps.substack.com/p/strat-scraps_v105">Alex Morris</a>, <a href="https://www.notboring.co/p/weekly-dose-of-optimism-36">Packy McCormick</a>, <a href="https://ritholtz.com/2023/04/10-friday-am-reads-402/">Barry Ritholtz</a>, Tim Ferris and <a href="https://thebrowser.com/free/bicycle-age/">The Browser</a>. Thank you all.</p></li><li><p>This article was referenced in articles by <a href="https://www.thedrum.com/opinion/2023/03/30/ai-or-bs-how-tell-if-marketing-tool-really-uses-artificial-">Samuel Scott</a> at The Drum and <a href="https://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2023/03/alex-murrell-the-age-of-average.html">Tyler Cowen</a> at Marginal Revolution. It’s also been covered by <a href="https://www.vice.com/en/article/qjvbpx/this-week-online-the-age-of-average">Vice</a>, <a href="https://www.inc.com/jessica-stillman/buildings-cars-brands-even-people-are-starting-to-look-same-that-makes-standing-out-even-more-valuable.html">Inc</a> and <a href="https://uk.news.yahoo.com/why-does-everything-look-same-210039368.html">Yahoo!</a></p></li><li><p>This article was referenced in talks by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/unpacking-age-average-monik-ladha-qkbuc/" target="_blank">Chris Barth</a> at the Most Contagious 2024 conference and by both <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:7209878445034512386/" target="_blank">Lisa Smith</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:7209878445034512386?commentUrn=urn%3Ali%3Acomment%3A%28activity%3A7209878445034512386%2C7210282718608134144%29&amp;dashCommentUrn=urn%3Ali%3Afsd_comment%3A%287210282718608134144%2Curn%3Ali%3Aactivity%3A7209878445034512386%29" target="_blank">Adam Morgan</a> at Cannes Festival of Creativity in 2024.</p></li><li><p>This article was referenced in System 1 Group’s report, <a href="https://The Extraordinary Cost Of Dull " target="_blank">The Extraordinary Cost of Dull</a>.</p></li><li><p>Kurt Anderson’s essay <a href="https://archive.vanityfair.com/article/2012/1/you-say-you-want-a-devolution">You Say You Want A Devolution</a>, in Vanity Fair, and Jason Farago’s article <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/10/10/magazine/stale-culture.html">Why Culture Has Come To A Standstill</a>, in The New York Times, are excellent.</p></li><li><p><a href="https://lindynewsletter.beehiiv.com/p/refinement-culture">Paul Skallas</a> (‘refinement culture’) and <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/newsletters/archive/2022/10/sabermetrics-analytics-ruined-baseball-sports-music-film/671924/">Derek Thompson</a> (’moneyballification’) do a great job of exploring how different sports teams have gradually adopted a narrower set of playing styles.</p></li><li><p>Since writing this article I’ve come across related ideas in economics (hotelling’s law), geography (central place theory), politics (median voter theory) and sociology (mimetic isomorphism).</p></li></ul>
</div></div>
  
</article>

</div>

  
</article>


          

          
            
              

            
          
        
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Amid cuts to basic research, New Zealand scraps all support for social sciences (218 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.science.org/content/article/amid-cuts-basic-research-new-zealand-scraps-all-support-social-sciences</link>
            <guid>42405956</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 04:38:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.science.org/content/article/amid-cuts-basic-research-new-zealand-scraps-all-support-social-sciences">https://www.science.org/content/article/amid-cuts-basic-research-new-zealand-scraps-all-support-social-sciences</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42405956">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.science.org/content/article/amid-cuts-basic-research-new-zealand-scraps-all-support-social-sciences: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A transformer supply crisis bottlenecks energy projects (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://spectrum.ieee.org/transformer-shortage</link>
            <guid>42405795</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 03:53:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/transformer-shortage">https://spectrum.ieee.org/transformer-shortage</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42405795">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>At a solar facility in Georgia, Silicon Ranch stores substation transformers it expects to deploy in the region in one to two years. </p><div data-headline="This Essential Element of the Power Grid Is in Critically Short Supply"><p><strong>To Nick de Vries,</strong> chief technology officer at the solar-energy developer <a href="https://www.siliconranch.com/" target="_blank">Silicon Ranch</a>, a transformer is like an interstate on-ramp: It boosts the voltage of the electricity that his solar plants generate to match the voltage of grid transmission lines. “They’re your ticket to ride,” says de Vries. “If you don’t have your high-voltage transformer, you don’t have a project.”
</p><p>
	Recently, this ticket has grown much harder to come by. The demand for transformers has spiked worldwide, and so the wait time to get a new transformer has doubled from 50 weeks in 2021 to nearly two years now, according to a 
	<a href="https://www.woodmac.com/news/opinion/supply-shortages-and-an-inflexible-market-give-rise-to-high-power-transformer-lead-times/" target="_blank">report</a> from <a href="https://www.woodmac.com/" target="_blank">Wood MacKenzie</a>, an energy-analytics firm. The wait for the more specialized large power transformers (LPTs), which step up voltage from power stations to transmission lines, is up to four years. Costs have also climbed by <a href="https://www.woodmac.com/news/opinion/supply-shortages-and-an-inflexible-market-give-rise-to-high-power-transformer-lead-times/" target="_blank">60 to 80 percent</a> since 2020.
</p><p>
	About five years ago, de Vries grew worried that transformer shortages would postpone his solar projects from coming online, so he began ordering transformers years before they’d actually be needed. Silicon Ranch, based in Nashville, now has a pipeline of custom transformers to make sure supply chain problems don’t stall its solar projects.
</p><p>
	The company isn’t alone in its quandary. A quarter of the world’s renewable-energy projects may be delayed while awaiting transformers to connect them to local grids, according to the Wood MacKenzie report. In India, the wait for 220-kilovolt transformers has 
	<a href="https://www.mercomindia.com/shortage-power-transformers-india-solar" target="_blank">leaped</a> from 8 to 14 months, potentially holding up nearly 150 gigawatts of new solar development.
</p><p>
	And it’s not just renewable-energy projects. The transformer shortage touches utilities, homeowners, businesses, rail systems, EV charging stations—anyone needing a grid connection. In Clallam County, the part of Washington state where the 
	<em><em>Twilight</em></em> movies are set, officials in May 2022 began to deny new home-construction requests because they couldn’t get enough pad-mounted transformers to step down voltage to homes. To address the backlog of customers who had already paid for new electrical service, the utility scrounged up refurbished transformers, or “ranch runners,” which helped but likely won’t last as long as new ones.
</p><p>
	The ripple effects of the shortage touch both public policy and safety. When a transformer fails from wear and tear, gets hit by a storm, or is 
	<a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/transformer-stockpiles" target="_blank">damaged</a> by war or sabotage, the inability to quickly replace it increases the risk of a power outage. The <a href="https://commission.europa.eu/strategy-and-policy/priorities-2019-2024/european-green-deal/energy-and-green-deal_en#:~:text=Decarbonising%20the%20EU's%20energy%20system,based%20largely%20on%20renewable%20sources" target="_blank">European Green Deal</a>, which plans for an enormous build-out of Europe’s transmission network by 2030 to accelerate electrification, is imperiled by the protracted wait times for transformers, says <a href="https://research.ugent.be/web/person/joannes-laveyne-0/en" target="_blank">Joannes Laveyne</a>, an electrical engineer and energy-systems expert at Ghent University, in Belgium.
</p><p>
	For power engineers, this crisis is also an opportunity. They’re now reworking transformer designs to use different or less sought-after materials, to last longer, to include power electronics that allow the easy conversion between AC and DC, and to be more standardized and less customized than the transformers of today. Their innovations could make this critical piece of infrastructure not only more resistant to supply chain weaknesses, but also better suited to the power grids of the future.
</p><h2>How Transformers Work</h2><p>
	A transformer is a 
	<a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/the-transformers-superheroes-of-electrical-inventions" target="_blank">simple thing</a>—and an old one, too, invented in the 1880s. A typical one has a two-sided core made of iron or steel with copper wire wrapped around each side. The sets of wires, called windings, aren’t connected, but through electromagnetic induction across the core, current transfers from one coil to the other. By changing the number of times the wire wraps around each side of the core, engineers can change the voltage that emerges from the device so that it is higher or lower than what entered.
</p><p>
	This basic setup underlies transformers in a wide range of sizes. An LPT can weigh as much as two blue whales and might be used to step up the electricity that emerges from a fossil fuel or <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/nuclear-power">nuclear power</a> plant—typically in the thousands of volts—to match the hundreds of thousands of volts running through transmission lines. When the electricity on those lines arrives at a city, it meets a power substation, which has transformers that step down the voltage to tens of thousands of volts for local distribution. Distribution transformers, which are smaller, decrease the voltage further, eventually to the hundreds of volts that can be used safely in homes and businesses.</p><p>
	The simplicity of the design has been its strength, says 
	<a href="https://ece.gatech.edu/directory/deepakraj-m-divan" target="_blank">Deepak Divan</a>, an electrical engineer and director of the Georgia Tech Center for Distributed Energy. Transformers are big, bulky devices built to endure for decades. Their very durability shoulders the grid. </p><p>
	But they’re a little like the gears and chain of a bicycle—adept at their simple conversion task, and little else. For example, traditional transformers that work only with AC can’t switch to DC without extra components. That AC-DC conversion is important because a host of technologies that aim to be a part of the cleaner energy future, including the electrolyzers that create hydrogen fuel, EV charging stations, and energy storage, all require lots of transformers, and they all need DC power. Solid-state power electronics, on the other hand, can seamlessly handle AC-DC conversions. “Wouldn’t it be nice to have a power-electronic replacement for the transformer?” Divan says. “It gives you control. And, in principle, it could become smaller if you really do it right.”
</p><p>
	The idea of a solid-state transformer has been 
	<a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/smart-transformers-will-make-the-grid-cleaner-and-more-flexible" target="_blank">kicking around</a> in academia and industry for years. Divan and his team call their version a modular controllable transformer (MCT). It uses <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/topic/semiconductors/">semiconductors</a> and active electronic components to not only transform electricity to other voltages but also invert the current between DC and AC in a single stage. It’s also built with novel insulations and other measures to protect it from lightning strikes and power surges. Divan and his team received an <a href="https://ece.gatech.edu/news/2023/12/ece-team-honored-groundbreaking-transformer-design" target="_blank">award</a> in 2023 from <em><em>IEEE Transactions on Power Electronics </em></em>for one of their designs.
</p><p>
	Divan’s modular transformer doesn’t have to be custom-built for each application, which could ease manufacturing bottlenecks. But as an emerging technology, it’s more expensive and fragile than a conventional transformer. For example, today’s semiconductors can’t survive electrical loads greater than about 1.7 kV. A device connected to the grid would need to endure at minimum 13 kV, which would mean stacking these transformer modules and hoping the whole group can withstand whatever the real world throws its way, Divan says.
</p><p>
	“If I have 10 converter modules stacked in series to withstand the high voltage, what happens if one fails? What happens if one of them gets a signal that is delayed by 200 nanoseconds? Does the whole thing collapse on you? These are all very interesting, challenging problems,” Divan says.
</p><p><img alt="A soccer ball-size machine next to a bookcase-size machine" data-rm-shortcode-id="dfb981375fb3d81305b543709d22dbd0" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" data-runner-src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/a-soccer-ball-size-machine-next-to-a-bookcase-size-machine.jpg?id=55156664&amp;width=980" height="3000" id="40fc5" lazy-loadable="true" src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/a-soccer-ball-size-machine-next-to-a-bookcase-size-machine.jpg?id=55156664&amp;width=980" width="4860"><small placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">Researchers at Oak Ridge National Laboratory’s GRID-C developed a next-generation transformer that is much smaller than previous generations and has the same capabilities. </small><small placeholder="Add Photo Credit...">Alonda Hines/ORNL/U.S. Dept. of Energy </small></p><p>
	At Oak Ridge National Laboratory’s Grid Research Integration and Deployment Center, or GRID-C, 
	<a href="https://www.ornl.gov/staff-profile/madhu-sudhan-chinthavali" target="_blank">Madhu Chinthavali</a> is also evaluating new technologies for next-gen transformers. Adding power electronics could enable transformers to manage power flow in ways that conventional ones cannot, which could in turn aid in <a href="https://www.ornl.gov/news/grid-electronics-research-bridge-gap-cleaner-more-reliable-power" target="_blank">adding more solar and wind power</a>. It could also enable transformers to put information into action, such as instantaneously responding to an outage or failure on the grid. Such advanced transformers aren’t the right solution everywhere but using them in key places will help add more loads to the grid. Equipping them with smart devices that relay data would give grid operators better real-time information and increase overall grid resilience and durability, says Chinthavali, who directs GRID-C.
</p><p>
	New kinds of power-electronic transformers, if they can be made affordable and reliable, would be a breakthrough for solar energy, says Silicon Ranch’s de Vries. They would simplify the chore of regulating the voltage going from solar plants to transmission lines. At present, operators must do that voltage regulation constantly because of the variable nature of the sun’s energy—and that task wears down inverters, capacitors, and other components.
</p><h2>Why Is There a Transformer Shortage?</h2><p>
	Driving the transformer shortage are market forces stemming from electricity demand and material supply chains. For example, nearly all transformer cores are made of grain-oriented electrical steel, or GOES—a material 
	<a href="https://www.electric.coop/nreca-urges-biden-to-prioritize-u-s-steel-production-for-electric-grid" target="_blank">also used</a> in <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/electric-motors">electric motors</a> and EV chargers. The expansion of those adjacent industries has intensified the demand for GOES and diverted much of the supply.
</p><p>
	On top of this, transformer manufacturing generally slowed after a boom period about 20 years ago. 
	<a href="https://www.hitachienergy.com/us/en/news-and-events/press-releases/2024/04/hitachi-energy-to-invest-additional-1-5-billion-to-ramp-up-global-transformer-production-by-2027" target="_blank">Hitachi Energy</a>, <a href="https://www.siemens-energy.com/us/en/home/press-releases/siemens_energy_addresses_shortage_US_powertransformers_invests_new_factory.html" target="_blank">Siemens Energy</a>, and <a href="https://www.vatransformer.com/about-us/our-locations/p2-chihuahua-mexico/" target="_blank">Virginia Transformers</a> have announced plans to scale up production with new facilities in Australia, China, Colombia, Finland, Germany, Mexico, the United States, and Vietnam. But those efforts won’t ease the logjam soon.
</p><p>
	At the same time, the demand for transformers has skyrocketed over the last two years by as much as 
	<a href="https://www.energy.gov/sites/default/files/2024-10/EXEC-2022-001242%20-%20Large%20Power%20Transformer%20Resilience%20Report%20signed%20by%20Secretary%20Granholm%20on%207-10-24.pdf" target="_blank">70 percent</a> for some U.S. manufacturers. Global demand for LPTs with voltages over 100 kV has grown more than 47 percent since 2020, and is expected to increase another 30 percent by 2030, according to research by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/wilfried-breuer/?trk=public_post_follow-articles" target="_blank">Wilfried Breuer</a>, managing director of German electrical equipment manufacturer <a href="https://www.reinhausen.com/" target="_blank">Maschinenfabrik Reinhausen,</a> in Regensburg. Aging grid infrastructure, new renewable-energy generation, expanding electrification, increased <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/the-ev-transition-explained-2659602311" target="_blank">EV charging stations,</a> and new data centers all contribute to the rising demand for these machines.
</p><p>
	Compounding the problem is that a typical LPT doesn’t just roll off an assembly line. Each is a bespoke creation, says 
	<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/b-vaagensmith/" target="_blank">Bjorn Vaagensmith</a>, a power-systems researcher at Idaho National Laboratory. In this low-volume industry, “a factory will make maybe 50 of these things a year,” he says.
</p><p>
	The LPT’s design is dictated by the layout of the substation or power plant it serves, as well as the voltage needs and the orientation of the incoming and outgoing power lines. For example, the bushings, which are upward-extending arms that connect the transformer to power lines, must be built in a particular position to intercept the lines.
</p><p>
	Such customization slows manufacturing and increases the difficulty of replacing a failed transformer. It’s also the reason why many energy companies don’t order LPTs ahead of time, says Laveyne at Ghent. “Imagine you get the transformer delivered but the permitting process ends up in a stall, or delay, or even a cancellation [of the project]. Then you’re stuck with a transformer you can’t really use.”
</p><p><img alt="A large transformer machine at a utility substation connected to power lines" data-rm-shortcode-id="1fc67bac3540d056dedc3ca0dc96705d" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" data-runner-src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/a-large-transformer-machine-at-a-utility-substation-connected-to-power-lines.jpg?id=55156578&amp;width=980" height="3024" id="4e242" lazy-loadable="true" src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/a-large-transformer-machine-at-a-utility-substation-connected-to-power-lines.jpg?id=55156578&amp;width=980" width="4032"><small placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">GE Vernova Advanced Research developed a flexible large power transformer that it has been field-testing at a substation in Columbia, Miss., since 2021. </small><small placeholder="Add Photo Credit...">Cooperative Energy </small></p><p>
	Less customized, more one-size-fits-all transformers could ease supply chain problems and reduce power outages. To that end, a team at 
	<a href="https://www.gevernova.com/research" target="_blank">GE Vernova Advanced Research (GEVAR)</a> helped develop a “flexible LPT.” In 2021, the team began field-testing a 165-kV version at a substation operated by <a href="https://cooperativeenergy.com/" target="_blank">Cooperative Energy</a> in Mississippi, where it remains active.
</p><p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ibrahima-ndiaye-b2892825/" target="_blank">Ibrahima Ndiaye</a>, a senior principal engineer at GEVAR who led the project, says the breakthrough was figuring out how to give a conventional transformer the capability to change its impedance (that is, its resistance to electricity flow) without changing any other feature in the transformer, including its voltage ratio.
</p><p>
	Impedance and voltage ratio are both critical features of a transformer that ordinarily must be tailored to each use case. If you can tweak both factors independently, then you can modify the transformer for various uses. But altering the impedance without also changing the transformer’s voltage ratio initially seemed impossible, Ndiaye says.
</p><p>
	The solution turned out to be surprisingly straightforward. The engineer added the same amount of windings to both sides of the transformer’s core, but in opposite directions, cancelling out the voltage increase and thereby allowing him to tweak one factor without automatically changing the other. “There is no [other] transformer in the world that has a capability of that today,” Ndiaye says.
</p><p>
	The flexible LPT could work like a universal spare, filling in for LPTs that fail, and negating the need to keep a custom spare for every transformer, Ndiaye says. This in turn would reduce the demand for these types of transformers and crucial materials such as GOES. The flexible LPT also lets the grid operate reliably even when there are variable renewable resources, or large variable loads such as a bank of EV charging stations.
</p><p><img alt="Three tractor-trailers lined up in parallel and each carrying a large machine" data-rm-shortcode-id="689444ecd79c0151b495ce61404efc48" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" data-runner-src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/three-tractor-trailers-lined-up-in-parallel-and-each-carrying-a-large-machine.jpg?id=55156634&amp;width=980" height="2745" id="90ba5" lazy-loadable="true" src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/three-tractor-trailers-lined-up-in-parallel-and-each-carrying-a-large-machine.jpg?id=55156634&amp;width=980" width="3118"><small placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">Avangrid’s mobile transformer has multivoltage capabilities and can be trucked to any of Avangrid’s onshore solar or wind projects within a couple of months. </small><small placeholder="Add Photo Credit...">Hitachi Energy and Avangrid </small></p><p>
	Similarly, 
	<a href="https://www.siemens-energy.com/us/en/home/press-releases/siemens-energy-installs-worlds-first-leased-rapid-response-transformers-allowing-large.html" target="_blank">Siemens Energy</a> has been developing what it calls “rapid response transformers”—plug-and-play backups that could replace a busted transformer within weeks. And the renewable-energy company <a href="https://www.avangrid.com/" target="_blank">Avangrid</a> this year <a href="https://www.avangrid.com/w/avangrid-boosts-resiliency-and-reliability-of-onshore-portfolio-with-first-mobile-transformer" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">introduced a mobile transformer</a> that can be trucked to any of its solar or wind projects within a couple of months.
</p><h2>Transformers Designed for Longevity</h2><p>
	There is room to improve, rather than replace, the century-old design of the traditional transformer, says 
	<a href="https://www.uni-stuttgart.de/en/press/experts/Prof.-Stefan-Tenbohlen/" target="_blank">Stefan Tenbohlen</a>, an energy researcher at the University of Stuttgart, in Germany. He cofounded the <a href="http://www.university-transformer-research.com/" target="_blank">University Transformer Research Alliance</a>, to connect international researchers who are tinkering with conventional designs. A chief goal is to make sure new transformers last even longer than the older generation did.
</p><p>
	One approach is to try different insulation techniques. Copper windings are typically insulated by paper and mineral oil to protect them from overheating. New approaches replace the mineral oil with natural esters to allow the interior of the transformer to safely reach higher temperatures, prolonging the device’s lifespan in the process. Vaagensmith at Idaho National Lab has experimented with ceramic paper—a thin, lightweight, ultra-heat-resistant material made of alumina silicate fibers—as insulation. “We cooked it up to a thousand degrees Celsius, which is ridiculously high for a transformer, and it was fine,” he says.
</p><p><img alt="Metal formed into geometric shapes" data-rm-shortcode-id="0c85be4be11a220b940823f630a8ddfe" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" data-runner-src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/metal-formed-into-geometric-shapes.png?id=55156732&amp;width=980" height="764" id="667c6" lazy-loadable="true" src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/metal-formed-into-geometric-shapes.png?id=55156732&amp;width=980" width="2298"><small placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">Researchers at Oak Ridge National Laboratory built hollow transformer cores made of electrical steel using additive manufacturing. </small><small placeholder="Add Photo Credit...">Alex Plotkowski/ORNL </small></p><p>
	Changing other materials used in LPTs could also help. Hollow-core transformers, for example, use far less steel. Scientists at Oak Ridge, in Tennessee, 
	<a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0264127520304287" target="_blank">have been testing</a> 3D printing of hollow cores made of electrical steel. Switching to hollow cores and being able to 3D print them would ease demand for the material in the United States, where there’s just one company that produces GOES steel for transformers, according to a 2022 <a href="https://www.energy.gov/sites/default/files/2022-02/Electric%20Grid%20Supply%20Chain%20Report%20-%20Final.pdf" target="_blank">report</a> from the U.S. Department of Energy.
</p><h2>Transformer Industry Faces Capacity Crunch</h2><p>
	Transformer manufacturing used to be a cyclical business where demand ebbed and flowed—a longstanding pattern that created an ingrained way of thinking. Consequently, despite clear signs that electrical infrastructure is set for a sustained boom and that the old days aren’t coming back, many transformer manufacturers have been hesitant to increase capacity, says 
	<a href="https://www.publicpower.org/people/adrienne-lotto" target="_blank">Adrienne Lotto</a>, senior vice president of grid security, technical, and operations services for the American Public Power Association, in Arlington, Va. She sums up their attitude: “If the demand is again going to simply fall off, why invest millions of dollars’ worth of capital into your manufacturing facility?”
</p><p>
	But greater demand for electricity 
	<a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tsmc-energy-choices" target="_blank">is coming</a>. The recent book <a href="https://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-3-031-49417-8" target="_blank"><em><em>Energy 2040</em></em></a> (Springer), coauthored by Georgia Tech’s Divan, lays out some of the staggering numbers. The capacity of all the energy projects waiting to connect to the U.S. grid amounts to 2,600 GW—more than double the nation’s entire generation capacity currently. An average estimate of U.S. EV adoption suggests the country will have 125 million <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/evs">EVs</a> by 2040. The electricity demands of U.S. data centers may <a href="https://www.epri.com/research/products/3002028905" target="_blank">double</a> by the end of this decade because of the boom in <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/topic/artificial-intelligence/">artificial intelligence</a>. The <a href="https://www.nrel.gov/news/program/2024/how-many-transformers-will-the-us-distribution-grid-need-by-2050.html" target="_blank">National Renewable Energy Lab</a> found that U.S. transformer capacity will need to increase by as much as 260 percent by 2050 to handle all the extra load.
</p><p>
	Globally, electricity supplied 20 percent of the world’s energy needs in 2023, and may reach 30 percent by 2030 as countries turn to electrification as a way to decarbonize, 
	<a href="https://www.iea.org/reports/electricity-2024/executive-summary" target="_blank">according to the International Energy Agency</a>. India and China are expected to see the fastest demand growth in that time. India installed <a href="https://www.mercomindia.com/product/q1-2024-india-solar-market-update" target="_blank">more solar capacity</a> in the first quarter of 2024 than in any quarter previously, and yet, as mentioned, the wait time to get those solar projects running is growing because of the <a href="https://www.mercomindia.com/shortage-power-transformers-india-solar" target="_blank">transformer shortage</a>.
</p><p>
	The world’s power systems are not accustomed to such upheaval, Divan says. Because longstanding technologies like the transformer change so slowly, utilities spend very little—perhaps 0.1 percent of their budgets—on R&amp;D. But they must prepare for a sea change, Divan says. “Utilities are not going to be able to stop this tsunami that’s coming. And the pressure is on.” <span></span></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mathematicians uncover a new way to count prime numbers (175 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.quantamagazine.org/mathematicians-uncover-a-new-way-to-count-prime-numbers-20241211/</link>
            <guid>42405733</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 03:38:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/mathematicians-uncover-a-new-way-to-count-prime-numbers-20241211/">https://www.quantamagazine.org/mathematicians-uncover-a-new-way-to-count-prime-numbers-20241211/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42405733">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.quantamagazine.org/mathematicians-uncover-a-new-way-to-count-prime-numbers-20241211/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A new video captures a 1968 demo of IBM’s Executive Terminal (304 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://spectrum.ieee.org/ibm-demo</link>
            <guid>42405462</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 02:30:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/ibm-demo">https://spectrum.ieee.org/ibm-demo</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42405462">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-headline="When IBM Built a War Room for Executives"><p>
	It seems to me that every item in the 
	<a href="https://computerhistory.org/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Computer History Museum</a>’s collection has a biography of sorts—a life before CHM, a tale about how it came to us, and a life within the museum. The chapters of that biography include the uses made of it, and the historical and interpretive stories it can be made to tell. This then is a biography of one item that recently entered the museum’s collection—an early Memorex videotape containing a recording from 1968—and the historical discovery it has afforded.
</p><p>
	Our biography begins in May 2020, with an email. Debra Dunlop, a 
	<a href="https://www.nec.edu/news/dr-debra-dunlop-is-honored-by-new-england-college" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">dean at New England College</a>, wrote to the museum about a large collection of documents, audiovisual materials, and a rare computer, a Xerox Star, in New Hampshire. These were the professional papers of Debra’s father, Robert Dunlop, and she knew how dearly he valued the collection. She was helping her father move to an assisted living facility, and she had to make a plan for this extensive collection. What did the museum think?</p><p><img alt="Black and white photo of a smiling man wearing glasses and a suit." data-rm-shortcode-id="985be946e0c9327ec3efbf8f9815408c" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" data-runner-src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/black-and-white-photo-of-a-smiling-man-wearing-glasses-and-a-suit.jpg?id=55267761&amp;width=980" height="625" id="091e7" lazy-loadable="true" src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/black-and-white-photo-of-a-smiling-man-wearing-glasses-and-a-suit.jpg?id=55267761&amp;width=980" width="833"><small placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">Industrial psychologist Robert Dunlop spent his career at high-tech companies, including <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/ibm">IBM</a>, RCA, and Xerox.</small><small placeholder="Add Photo Credit...">Computer History Museum</small></p><p>For me, the Dunlop collection was a light in the darkness. It was still early days in the pandemic, and the death toll in the United States from Covid-19 was nearing 100,000, with a vaccine shot for me still months in the future. I was working from home in Massachusetts but I was nervous because the museum—like all places that depend in part on ticket sales—faced <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/what-we-lose-when-we-lose-museums" target="_self">strong financial pressures</a>, and I didn’t know how long it could go on with its doors closed. The Dunlop collection sounded interesting. Robert Dunlop had been an industrial psychologist who spent his career at large, high-technology U.S. firms—first IBM, then RCA, and finally Xerox. The collection wasn’t far away, and perhaps there was a way I could safely go and have a look.</p><p>I learned more about Robert Dunlop’s career from Debra. She and her family moved the collection to a garage where, after we let it sit for a week, we felt it would be safe for me to review the materials alone, wearing a mask, with the garage doors open.</p><p>
	After the visit, I discussed what I had seen with my colleagues, and we agreed that I would return and select, pack, and ship out a substantial portion of it. Debra and her family very kindly made a financial donation to the museum to help with the shipping expenses in that difficult time for CHM. And as my colleagues and I would eventually discover, Dunlop’s collection offered an extraordinary glimpse into a transformative time in advanced computing, and a fascinating project that had been wholly unknown to the <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/history-of-computing">history of computing</a> until now.
</p><h2>A Discovery</h2><p><img alt="Photo of a garage with stacks of boxes on a folding table." data-rm-shortcode-id="c8e2237d7202df4e4b6c1e7af5597dd5" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" data-runner-src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/photo-of-a-garage-with-stacks-of-boxes-on-a-folding-table.jpg?id=55269376&amp;width=980" height="4032" id="9543d" lazy-loadable="true" src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/photo-of-a-garage-with-stacks-of-boxes-on-a-folding-table.jpg?id=55269376&amp;width=980" width="3024"><small placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">In May 2020, the author visited Dunlop’s home to go through documents, photos, and audiovisual recordings related to his work. Much of the material now resides at the Computer History Museum.</small><small placeholder="Add Photo Credit...">David C. Brock</small></p><p>
	As I went through the collection in that New Hampshire garage, one item intrigued me. It was an early video recording, made in 1968, that clearly had great meaning for Robert Dunlop. The 1-inch format tape on an open reel had been carefully packaged and included an explanatory note by Dunlop taped to the outside, along with a longer letter from him tucked inside. Both notes told of an inventive computer system at IBM headquarters that I’d never heard of. According to the notes, a demo of the system was captured on the long obsolete video.
</p><p>
	In 1995, when Dunlop wrote the notes, he had despaired of finding any working equipment to recover the recording. As the tape rested in my hands, I wondered the same thing—should I even collect this if it’s impossible to watch? But then I thought, “Perhaps we can figure something out. And if not us, maybe something could happen in the future.” I decided to take my chances and collect it.
</p><p><img alt="Photo of a reel of old recording tape and its packaging, with Memorex on the outside." data-rm-shortcode-id="deef6ca479999ee00e0c1c1d4b743593" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" data-runner-src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/photo-of-a-reel-of-old-recording-tape-and-its-packaging-with-memorex-on-the-outside.jpg?id=55269763&amp;width=980" height="2139" id="81d14" lazy-loadable="true" src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/photo-of-a-reel-of-old-recording-tape-and-its-packaging-with-memorex-on-the-outside.jpg?id=55269763&amp;width=980" width="3422"><small placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">To recover the recording from the obsolete tape, the museum turned to George Blood LP, a company that specializes in archival audio and video. </small><small placeholder="Add Photo Credit...">Penny Ahlstrand</small></p><p>
	The Dunlop collection started its new life in the museum, carefully rehoused into archival storage boxes and added to our backlog for archival processing. In 2023, a grant to the museum from the 
	<a href="https://moore.org/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation</a> presented an opportunity to digitize some of the audiovisual materials in our collection. When I was consulted about priorities, one of the items I selected was Dunlop’s 1968 video recording. Could we give it a try?
</p><p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/massimo-petrozzi-phd-573367102/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Massimo Petrozzi</a>, CHM’s Director of Archives and Digital Initiatives, reached out to his networks to see if there was someone who could help. A contact in Europe pointed back to the States, to George Blood and his firm <a href="https://www.georgeblood.com/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">George Blood LP</a> outside of Philadelphia. The company is a major provider of audio and moving-picture preservation services, boasting an enormous collection of equipment—including, as it happens, an Ampex video unit capable of recovering video from Dunlop’s tape, which Blood called a “very early technology.” Blood and his colleagues made painstaking adjustments and experiments and were finally able to recover and digitize Dunlop’s silent video, fulfilling Robert Dunlop’s long hopes. Sadly, Dunlop did not live to see his recording again. He died in July 2020.
</p><h2>A Competing Vision of Computing</h2><p>
	The recording reveals a story as interesting as it is seemingly forgotten.
</p><p>
	You may already be aware of the “<a href="https://dougengelbart.org/content/view/209/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Mother of All Demos</a>” presented by Doug Engelbart and the members of his Stanford Research Institute center at the close of 1968. This presentation, with Engelbart on stage at a major computing conference in San Francisco, displayed the features and capabilities of his group’s “oN-Line System,” known as NLS. The system included many elements that were extraordinarily novel, even for the assembled computing professionals: networked computers, video conferencing, graphical interfaces, hypertext, collaborative word processing, and even a new input device, the computer mouse.
</p><p>
	This remarkable 1968 demonstration of the NLS was, much to our benefit, recorded on videotape. Although relatively early in video technology, the quality of the surviving recording is excellent and readily available online today.
</p><p><span data-rm-shortcode-id="c9384988d9582a867826ea2003b8696c"><iframe frameborder="0" height="auto" type="lazy-iframe" scrolling="no" data-runner-src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UhpTiWyVa6k?rel=0&amp;start=1" width="100%"></iframe></span></p><p>
	The NLS was driven by a particular vision for the future use and practice of computing: a vision that centered on the notion of alliance. In this vision, individuals would join together into teams and organizations, directly using new computing tools and approaches for creating and using knowledge, and in doing so, “augmenting human intellect” to better solve complex problems.
</p><p>
	Dunlop’s video recording, it turned out, also contained a demonstration of another advanced computing system that also took place in 1968. This second demo occurred on the East Coast, at IBM’s corporate headquarters in Armonk, N.Y., and was motivated by a far different—perhaps one could go so far as to say an opposite—vision for the future of computing. This vision centered not on alliance, but rather on the concept of rank. The system was known as the IBM Corporate Headquarters Information Center, and it was the culmination of Dunlop’s experiments with executive-computer interaction at the company.
</p><p>
	Dunlop’s career at IBM across the 1960s coincided with a truly remarkable period of growth for the firm. From 1964—the year IBM announced its 
	<a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/building-the-system360-mainframe-nearly-destroyed-ibm" target="_self">new System/360 line of digital computers</a>—to 1970, the firm’s headcount and revenues both doubled.
</p><p>
	To contend with this extraordinary growth, Dunlop worked on what he and others there called “management information systems”—computer systems serving the informational needs of IBM managers.
</p><p>
	As Dunlop noted in an unpublished talk, IBM managers were increasingly embracing information processing in the form of the company’s own timesharing computer products. Several internal IBM systems gave users remote access to timesharing computers, with modified electric typewriters serving as the user “terminals.” A sophisticated messaging system allowed employees to send one another telegram-like messages from one terminal to another, at the rate of 25,000 messages per day. A mathematical utility, QUIKTRAN, let users perform simple as well as sophisticated calculations from their terminals. There was a proliferation of systems for storing documents and formatting them in complex ways, with a single computer supporting up to 40 typewriter terminal users. Lastly, there were what today we would call database systems, containing information about the business and the organization, with a query language and financial models, again available from the users’ typewriter terminals.
</p><h2>IBM’s Executive War Room</h2><p>
	As these systems were increasingly adopted by what Dunlop called “operational and middle managers,” he led a series of projects to see if IBM could create terminals and management information systems that could be productively used by IBM’s “top executives.” The systems would allow the executives to make strategic decisions for the company in new ways afforded by the computer. His initial efforts all failed.
</p><p>
	First, Dunlop experimented with providing high-ranking executives—VPs and the like— with typewriter terminals directly linked to real-time data, financial models, and summary documents about the firm. The terminals went untouched, quickly migrating to the desks of the executives’ secretaries.
</p><p>
	Dunlop then tried using IBM’s new CRT-based terminal, the 2250, with a simplified keypad for input. The result was unchanged. Through interviews and surveys, he concluded that the failure was due to the executives’ “self-role concept.” They held themselves to be “very high status” decision-makers who got information from subordinates; any direct use of a typewriter or keyboard would “demean” them.
</p><p>
	From his failed experiments, Dunlop concluded that the state-of-the-art in computing technology was inadequate for creating a terminal-based management system for top management. However, those same top managers had noticed that middle managers around the firm had established “war rooms,” in which staff integrated information from all the various terminal-based systems: messaging, text, and database. At IBM corporate headquarters, the top executives wanted a war room of their own.
</p><p>
	This desire led Dunlop and others to create the IBM Headquarters Information Center. Here, “information specialists” would respond to inquiries by high-ranking executives. The specialists had access to messaging, text, database, and financial modeling systems accessed through typewriter and CRT terminals, as well as an array of printed materials, microform holdings, and audiovisual materials. In short, the information center was a reference library, staffed with reference librarians, of the sort that would become commonplace in the 1980s.
</p><p><img alt="Photo of a battered square cardboard package with typewritten notes taped to the front." data-rm-shortcode-id="3c72236f1d0f3539dfd67bf18adcaa4c" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" data-runner-src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/photo-of-a-battered-square-cardboard-package-with-typewritten-notes-taped-to-the-front.jpg?id=55269718&amp;width=980" height="2913" id="50058" lazy-loadable="true" src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/photo-of-a-battered-square-cardboard-package-with-typewritten-notes-taped-to-the-front.jpg?id=55269718&amp;width=980" width="2976"><small placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">An old recording with typed notes from Dunlop turned out to contain a previously unknown 1968 demonstration of an IBM system called the Executive Terminal. </small><small placeholder="Add Photo Credit...">Penny Ahlstrand</small></p><p>
	With the new IBM Headquarters Information Center in place, Dunlop saw the opportunity to run another experiment in 1967-68, which he called the “Executive Terminal.” The lead information specialist in the information center would sit at a video-mixing and control console, equipped with a video camera, microphone, and even lighting. Meanwhile, the executive user would be in their office with their Executive Terminal, a modified television set with an audio and video connection to the console in the information center.
</p><p>
	The executive pressed a button to summon the information specialist and their live video image to the screen. Remaining unseen, the executive could then place an inquiry. The information specialist would direct other staff in the information center to gather the appropriate information to answer the request: Models were run on CRT terminals, documents and data were gathered on typewriter terminals, microform could be loaded into a video reader, paper documents could be placed on a video capture unit. Once the results were assembled, the information specialist conveyed all this information to the executive, cutting from one video feed to another, guided by the executive’s interest and direction.
</p><p>
	Dunlop’s 1968 video demonstration of the Executive Terminal and the Information Center proceeds in three acts.
</p><p>
	The first 10 minutes of the video show the information specialist and other staff responding to an executive’s request, finding and preparing all the materials for video presentation, using the typewriter and CRT terminals, and even engaging in video conferencing with another employee:
</p><p><span data-rm-shortcode-id="d9d2a2051467f3b510f4f8dbb43ee21f"><iframe frameborder="0" height="auto" type="lazy-iframe" scrolling="no" data-runner-src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EUZMWGoB-Ug?rel=0&amp;start=2" width="100%"></iframe></span></p><p>
	The next five minutes show the executive using the Executive Terminal to receive the results and directing the display and flow of the information:
</p><p><span data-rm-shortcode-id="8e6a3c38963a4e2263022b8d1f826891"><iframe frameborder="0" height="auto" type="lazy-iframe" scrolling="no" data-runner-src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZnH7blyDLRw?rel=0" width="100%"></iframe></span></p><p>
	The final few minutes show the information specialist working on an IBM 2260 video computer terminal, at the time still a novelty that was used for database and model access:
</p><p><span data-rm-shortcode-id="4a42a78a92508fec8f51d00e2098e6ff"><iframe frameborder="0" height="auto" type="lazy-iframe" scrolling="no" data-runner-src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rH1rd6l8mbk?rel=0" width="100%"></iframe></span></p><h2>Restoring History</h2><p>
	It’s unclear what ultimately became of IBM’s Executive Terminal and the Information Center, as they appear to have left little to no historical traces beyond a few documents—including the unpublished talk—some photographs, and Dunlop’s 1968 video recording.
</p><p>
	With Engelbart’s and Dunlop’s 1968 demo videos, we now have a remarkable and contrasting snapshot of two very different directions in advanced computing. Engelbart’s Mother of All Demos showed how advanced computing could create a shared, collaborative environment of allied individuals, all direct users of the same system, befitting of a laboratory of computer enthusiasts in Menlo Park, Calif. Dunlop’s Executive Terminal demo showed how many of these same advanced technologies could be directed along another path, that of a strictly hierarchical organization, highly attuned to rank and defined roles and specialties. While these were very different and perhaps opposing directions, they shared a common commitment to the use of advanced computing for organizing and analyzing information, and taking action.
</p><p><img alt="Blurry photo of a room containing old-fashioned computer equipment, with two men standing at the back with their backs to the camera." data-rm-shortcode-id="42496d934cd18d2030264f5c5c2e0e52" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" data-runner-src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/blurry-photo-of-a-room-containing-old-fashioned-computer-equipment-with-two-men-standing-at-the-back-with-their-backs-to-the-ca.jpg?id=55270168&amp;width=980" height="2224" id="2aa91" lazy-loadable="true" src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/blurry-photo-of-a-room-containing-old-fashioned-computer-equipment-with-two-men-standing-at-the-back-with-their-backs-to-the-ca.jpg?id=55270168&amp;width=980" width="2966"><small placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">In the Information Center at IBM Headquarters, in Armonk, N.Y., information specialists were on call to answer questions from users.</small><small placeholder="Add Photo Credit...">The Dunlop Collection</small></p><p>
	Engelbart held that his system was for the “augmentation of the human intellect,” so that users might better address complex problems. For Dunlop, the Executive Terminal was an answer to his question, “Can we make better decisions, at higher levels, through better information processes?”
</p><p>
	There are echoes of Engelbart’s Mother of All Demos around us every day—the hyperlinks of the Web, the scuttling of computer mice on desktops, the editing of online documents, and more. But just as evident are the echoes of Dunlop’s Executive Terminal demo, such as the video conferencing and screen-sharing practices so familiar in Zooms, Teams, and Meets today.</p><p>
	The Computer History Museum is pleased to make public the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DWhZ8ELDM8c&amp;t=2s" target="_blank">entire video recording</a> of Robert Dunlop’s 1968 demonstration, and with its release, to restore a forgotten chapter in the history of computing. <span></span></p><p><em><em>Editor’s note: This post originally appeared on the blog of the </em></em><a href="https://computerhistory.org/stories/the-biography-of-a-discovery/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><em>Computer History Museum</em></a><em><em>.</em></em></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Rust’s Incremental Compiler Architecture (110 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lwn.net/Articles/997784/</link>
            <guid>42405357</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 02:03:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/997784/">https://lwn.net/Articles/997784/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42405357">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://lwn.net/Articles/997784/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: I designed an espresso machine and coffee grinder (699 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://velofuso.com</link>
            <guid>42405046</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 01:03:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://velofuso.com">https://velofuso.com</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42405046">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-fluid-engine="true"><div data-animation-role="image" data-test="image-block-fluid-outer-wrapper" data-aspect-ratio="41.37931034482759" data-block-type="5" id="block-4672c01ea1048caf2408">
                
            
            
            
            
            
            
            <p><img data-stretch="true" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/642b16caa701311a34f57545/59acc4cf-a57f-45eb-bc72-560fe271f8e9/Subtracted+Front.png" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/642b16caa701311a34f57545/59acc4cf-a57f-45eb-bc72-560fe271f8e9/Subtracted+Front.png" data-image-dimensions="5771x3847" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/642b16caa701311a34f57545/59acc4cf-a57f-45eb-bc72-560fe271f8e9/Subtracted+Front.png" width="5771" height="3847" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/642b16caa701311a34f57545/59acc4cf-a57f-45eb-bc72-560fe271f8e9/Subtracted+Front.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/642b16caa701311a34f57545/59acc4cf-a57f-45eb-bc72-560fe271f8e9/Subtracted+Front.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/642b16caa701311a34f57545/59acc4cf-a57f-45eb-bc72-560fe271f8e9/Subtracted+Front.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/642b16caa701311a34f57545/59acc4cf-a57f-45eb-bc72-560fe271f8e9/Subtracted+Front.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/642b16caa701311a34f57545/59acc4cf-a57f-45eb-bc72-560fe271f8e9/Subtracted+Front.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/642b16caa701311a34f57545/59acc4cf-a57f-45eb-bc72-560fe271f8e9/Subtracted+Front.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/642b16caa701311a34f57545/59acc4cf-a57f-45eb-bc72-560fe271f8e9/Subtracted+Front.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs"></p>
          
              </div><div data-blend-mode="NORMAL" data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-07f50155ef0eb0539444">

<p>
  <h2>TREFOLO ESPRESSO MACHINE</h2>
</p>




















  
  



</div><div data-blend-mode="NORMAL" data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1715156589882_9946">

<p>
  <h3>A MINIMALIST REIMAGINING OF THE ESPRESSO MACHINE </h3>
</p>




















  
  



</div><div data-animation-role="button" data-alignment="center" data-button-size="medium" data-button-type="primary" data-block-type="53" id="block-7e94b02023c9ffdf5cc2">
  <p><a href="https://velofuso.com/trefolo" target="_blank">
    SEE TREFOLO
  </a>
</p></div><div data-animation-role="image" data-test="image-block-fluid-outer-wrapper" data-aspect-ratio="41.37931034482759" data-block-type="5" id="block-7a4c525688de104728e1">
                
            
            
            
            
            
            
            <p><img data-stretch="true" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/642b16caa701311a34f57545/73a38f34-0386-47c8-8503-650534af114c/Cover+Front.jpg" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/642b16caa701311a34f57545/73a38f34-0386-47c8-8503-650534af114c/Cover+Front.jpg" data-image-dimensions="3859x3898" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/642b16caa701311a34f57545/73a38f34-0386-47c8-8503-650534af114c/Cover+Front.jpg" width="3859" height="3898" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/642b16caa701311a34f57545/73a38f34-0386-47c8-8503-650534af114c/Cover+Front.jpg?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/642b16caa701311a34f57545/73a38f34-0386-47c8-8503-650534af114c/Cover+Front.jpg?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/642b16caa701311a34f57545/73a38f34-0386-47c8-8503-650534af114c/Cover+Front.jpg?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/642b16caa701311a34f57545/73a38f34-0386-47c8-8503-650534af114c/Cover+Front.jpg?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/642b16caa701311a34f57545/73a38f34-0386-47c8-8503-650534af114c/Cover+Front.jpg?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/642b16caa701311a34f57545/73a38f34-0386-47c8-8503-650534af114c/Cover+Front.jpg?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/642b16caa701311a34f57545/73a38f34-0386-47c8-8503-650534af114c/Cover+Front.jpg?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs"></p>
          
              </div><div data-blend-mode="NORMAL" data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-2884aca7b72517f726f3">

<p>
  <h2><span>Turbina  COFFEE GRINDER</span></h2>
</p>




















  
  



</div><div data-blend-mode="NORMAL" data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-0589d937ef2c78a466f5">

<p>
  <h3><span>THE FIRST cylindrical burr coffee grinder</span></h3>
</p>




















  
  



</div><div data-animation-role="button" data-alignment="center" data-button-size="medium" data-button-type="primary" data-block-type="53" id="block-d3fb51620e3f89a6ca59">
  <p><a href="https://velofuso.com/turbina" target="_blank">
    SEE TURBINA
  </a>
</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Clio: A system for privacy-preserving insights into real-world AI use (117 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.anthropic.com/research/clio</link>
            <guid>42404447</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 23:22:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/research/clio">https://www.anthropic.com/research/clio</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42404447">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.anthropic.com/research/clio: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Elixir/Erlang Hot Swapping Code (208 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://kennyballou.com/blog/2016/12/elixir-hot-swapping/index.html</link>
            <guid>42404411</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 23:16:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://kennyballou.com/blog/2016/12/elixir-hot-swapping/index.html">https://kennyballou.com/blog/2016/12/elixir-hot-swapping/index.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42404411">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://kennyballou.com/blog/2016/12/elixir-hot-swapping/index.html: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Taming LLMs – A Practical Guide to LLM Pitfalls with Open Source Software (161 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.souzatharsis.com/tamingLLMs/markdown/toc.html</link>
            <guid>42404202</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 22:45:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.souzatharsis.com/tamingLLMs/markdown/toc.html">https://www.souzatharsis.com/tamingLLMs/markdown/toc.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42404202">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.souzatharsis.com/tamingLLMs/markdown/toc.html: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Carta is making it too difficult to cancel subscriptions, some founders say (206 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://techcrunch.com/2024/12/12/carta-is-making-it-too-difficult-to-cancel-subscriptions-some-founders-say/</link>
            <guid>42404144</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 22:37:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/12/12/carta-is-making-it-too-difficult-to-cancel-subscriptions-some-founders-say/">https://techcrunch.com/2024/12/12/carta-is-making-it-too-difficult-to-cancel-subscriptions-some-founders-say/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42404144">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://techcrunch.com/2024/12/12/carta-is-making-it-too-difficult-to-cancel-subscriptions-some-founders-say/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What every systems programmer should know about concurrency (2020) [pdf] (154 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://assets.bitbashing.io/papers/concurrency-primer.pdf</link>
            <guid>42403744</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 21:46:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://assets.bitbashing.io/papers/concurrency-primer.pdf">https://assets.bitbashing.io/papers/concurrency-primer.pdf</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42403744">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://assets.bitbashing.io/papers/concurrency-primer.pdf: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>