<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 19:30:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Right Kind of Stubborn (126 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://paulgraham.com/persistence.html</link>
            <guid>40907155</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 17:05:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://paulgraham.com/persistence.html">https://paulgraham.com/persistence.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40907155">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div width="435"><tbody><tr><td><img src="https://s.turbifycdn.com/aah/paulgraham/the-right-kind-of-stubborn-1.gif" width="221" height="18" alt="The Right Kind of Stubborn"><span size="2" face="verdana">July 2024<p>Successful people tend to be persistent. New ideas often don't work
at first, but they're not deterred. They keep trying and eventually
find something that does.</p><p>Mere obstinacy, on the other hand, is a recipe for failure. Obstinate
people are so annoying. They won't listen. They beat their heads
against a wall and get nowhere.</p><p>But is there any real difference between these two cases? Are
persistent and obstinate people actually behaving differently? Or
are they doing the same thing, and we just label them later as
persistent or obstinate depending on whether they turned out to be
right or not?</p><p>If that's the only difference then there's nothing to be learned
from the distinction. Telling someone to be persistent rather than
obstinate would just be telling them to be right rather than wrong,
and they already know that. Whereas if persistence and obstinacy
are actually different kinds of behavior, it would be worthwhile
to tease them apart.
</p><span color="#dddddd">[<a href="#f1n"><span color="#dddddd">1</span></a>]</span><p>I've talked to a lot of determined people, and it seems to me that
they're different kinds of behavior. I've often walked away from a
conversation thinking either "Wow, that guy is determined" or "Damn,
that guy is stubborn," and I don't think I'm just talking about
whether they seemed right or not. That's part of it, but not all
of it.</p><p>There's something annoying about the obstinate that's not simply
due to being mistaken. They won't listen. And that's not true of
all determined people. I can't think of anyone more determined than
the Collison brothers, and when you point out a problem to them,
they not only listen, but listen with an almost predatory intensity.
Is there a hole in the bottom of their boat? Probably not, but if
there is, they want to know about it.</p><p>It's the same with most successful people. They're never <i>more</i>
engaged than when you disagree with them. Whereas the obstinate
don't want to hear you. When you point out problems, their eyes
glaze over, and their replies sound like ideologues talking about
matters of doctrine.
</p><span color="#dddddd">[<a href="#f2n"><span color="#dddddd">2</span></a>]</span><p>The reason the persistent and the obstinate seem similar is that
they're both hard to stop. But they're hard to stop in different
senses. The persistent are like boats whose engines can't be throttled
back. The obstinate are like boats whose rudders can't be turned.
</p><span color="#dddddd">[<a href="#f3n"><span color="#dddddd">3</span></a>]</span><p>In the degenerate case they're indistinguishable: when there's only
one way to solve a problem, your only choice is whether to give up
or not, and persistence and obstinacy both say no. This is presumably
why the two are so often conflated in popular culture. It assumes
simple problems. But as problems get more complicated, we can see
the difference between them. The persistent are much more attached
to points high in the decision tree than to minor ones lower down,
while the obstinate spray "don't give up" indiscriminately over the
whole tree.</p><p>The persistent are attached to the goal. The obstinate are attached
to their ideas about how to reach it.</p><p>Worse still, that means they'll tend to be attached to their <i>first</i>
ideas about how to solve a problem, even though these are the least
informed by the experience of working on it. So the obstinate aren't
merely attached to details, but disproportionately likely to be
attached to wrong ones.</p><p>Why are they like this? Why are the obstinate obstinate? One
possibility is that they're overwhelmed. They're not very capable.
They take on a hard problem. They're immediately in over their head.
So they grab onto ideas the way someone on the deck of a rolling
ship might grab onto the nearest handhold.</p><p>That was my initial theory, but on examination it doesn't hold up.
If being obstinate were simply a consequence of being in over one's
head, you could make persistent people become obstinate by making
them solve harder problems. But that's not what happens. If you
handed the Collisons an extremely hard problem to solve, they
wouldn't become obstinate. If anything they'd become less obstinate.
They'd know they had to be open to anything.</p><p>Similarly, if obstinacy were caused by the situation, the obstinate
would stop being obstinate when solving easier problems. But they
don't. And if obstinacy isn't caused by the situation, it must come
from within. It must be a feature of one's personality.</p><p>Obstinacy is a reflexive resistance to changing one's ideas. This
is not identical with stupidity, but they're closely related. A
reflexive resistance to changing one's ideas becomes a sort of
induced stupidity as contrary evidence mounts. And obstinacy is a
form of not giving up that's easily practiced by the stupid. You
don't have to consider complicated tradeoffs; you just dig in your
heels. It even works, up to a point.</p><p>The fact that obstinacy works for simple problems is an important
clue. Persistence and obstinacy aren't opposites. The relationship
between them is more like the relationship between the two kinds
of respiration we can do: aerobic respiration, and the anaerobic
respiration we inherited from our most distant ancestors. Anaerobic
respiration is a more primitive process, but it has its uses. When
you leap suddenly away from a threat, that's what you're using.</p><p>The optimal amount of obstinacy is not zero. It can be good if your
initial reaction to a setback is an unthinking "I won't give up,"
because this helps prevent panic. But unthinking only gets you so
far. The further someone is toward the obstinate end of the continuum,
the less likely they are to succeed in solving hard problems.
</p><span color="#dddddd">[<a href="#f4n"><span color="#dddddd">4</span></a>]</span><p>Obstinacy is a simple thing. Animals have it. But persistence turns
out to have a fairly complicated internal structure.</p><p>One thing that distinguishes the persistent is their energy. At the
risk of putting too much weight on words, they persist rather than
merely resisting. They keep trying things. Which means the persistent
must also be imaginative. To keep trying things, you have to keep
thinking of things to try.</p><p>Energy and imagination make a wonderful combination. Each gets the
best out of the other. Energy creates demand for the ideas produced
by imagination, which thus produces more, and imagination gives
energy somewhere to go.
</p><span color="#dddddd">[<a href="#f5n"><span color="#dddddd">5</span></a>]</span><p>Merely having energy and imagination is quite rare. But to solve
hard problems you need three more qualities: resilience, good
judgement, and a focus on some kind of goal.</p><p>Resilience means not having one's morale destroyed by setbacks.
Setbacks are inevitable once problems reach a certain size, so if
you can't bounce back from them, you can only do good work on a
small scale. But resilience is not the same as obstinacy. Resilience
means setbacks can't change your morale, not that they can't change
your mind.</p><p>Indeed, persistence often requires that one change one's mind.
That's where good judgement comes in. The persistent are quite
rational. They focus on expected value. It's this, not recklessness,
that lets them work on things that are unlikely to succeed.</p><p>There is one point at which the persistent are often irrational
though: at the very top of the decision tree. When they choose
between two problems of roughly equal expected value, the choice
usually comes down to personal preference. Indeed, they'll often
classify projects into deliberately wide bands of expected value
in order to ensure that the one they want to work on still qualifies.</p><p>Empirically this doesn't seem to be a problem. It's ok to be
irrational near the top of the decision tree. One reason is that
we humans will work harder on a problem we love. But there's another
more subtle factor involved as well: our preferences among problems
aren't random. When we love a problem that other people don't, it's
often because we've unconsciously noticed that it's more important
than they realize.</p><p>Which leads to our fifth quality: there needs to be some overall
goal. If you're like me you began, as a kid, merely with the desire
to do something great. In theory that should be the most powerful
motivator of all, since it includes everything that could possibly
be done. But in practice it's not much use, precisely because it
includes too much. It doesn't tell you what to do at this moment.</p><p>So in practice your energy and imagination and resilience and good
judgement have to be directed toward some fairly specific goal. Not
too specific, or you might miss a great discovery adjacent to what
you're searching for, but not too general, or it won't work to
motivate you.
</p><span color="#dddddd">[<a href="#f6n"><span color="#dddddd">6</span></a>]</span><p>When you look at the internal structure of persistence, it doesn't
resemble obstinacy at all. It's so much more complex. Five distinct
qualities — energy, imagination, resilience, good judgement, and
focus on a goal — combine to produce a phenomenon that seems a bit
like obstinacy in the sense that it causes you not to give up. But
the way you don't give up is completely different. Instead of merely
resisting change, you're driven toward a goal by energy and resilience,
through paths discovered by imagination and optimized by judgement.
You'll give way on any point low down in the decision tree, if its
expected value drops sufficiently, but energy and resilience keep
pushing you toward whatever you chose higher up.</p><p>Considering what it's made of, it's not surprising that the right
kind of stubbornness is so much rarer than the wrong kind, or that
it gets so much better results. Anyone can do obstinacy. Indeed,
kids and drunks and fools are best at it. Whereas very few people
have enough of all five of the qualities that produce right kind
of stubbornness, but when they do the results are magical.</p><p>
<b>Notes</b></p><p>[</p><a name="f1n"><span color="#000000">1</span></a>]
I'm going to use "persistent" for the good kind of stubborn
and "obstinate" for the bad kind, but I can't claim I'm simply
following current usage. Conventional opinion barely distinguishes
between good and bad kinds of stubbornness, and usage is correspondingly
promiscuous. I could have invented a new word for the good kind,
but it seemed better just to stretch "persistent."<p>[</p><a name="f2n"><span color="#000000">2</span></a>]
There are some domains where one can succeed by being obstinate.
Some political leaders have been notorious for it. But it won't
work in situations where you have to pass external tests. And indeed
the political leaders who are famous for being obstinate are famous
for getting power, not for using it well.<p>[</p><a name="f3n"><span color="#000000">3</span></a>]
There will be some resistance to turning the rudder of a
persistent person, because there's some cost to changing direction.<p>[</p><a name="f4n"><span color="#000000">4</span></a>]
The obstinate do sometimes succeed in solving hard problems.
One way is through luck: like the stopped clock that's right twice
a day, they seize onto some arbitrary idea, and it turns out to be
right. Another is when their obstinacy cancels out some other form
of error. For example, if a leader has overcautious subordinates,
their estimates of the probability of success will always be off
in the same direction. So if he mindlessly says "push ahead regardless"
in every borderline case, he'll usually turn out to be right.<p>[</p><a name="f5n"><span color="#000000">5</span></a>]
If you stop there, at just energy and imagination, you get
the conventional caricature of an artist or poet.<p>[</p><a name="f6n"><span color="#000000">6</span></a>]
Start by erring on the small side. If you're inexperienced
you'll inevitably err on one side or the other, and if you err on
the side of making the goal too broad, you won't get anywhere.
Whereas if you err on the small side you'll at least be moving
forward. Then, once you're moving, you expand the goal.<span color="888888"><b>Thanks</b> to Trevor Blackwell, 
Jessica Livingston, Jackie McDonough,
Courtenay Pipkin, Harj Taggar, and Garry Tan for reading drafts of
this.</span></span></td></tr></tbody></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Reverse Engineering Ticketmaster's Rotating Barcodes (639 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://conduition.io/coding/ticketmaster/</link>
            <guid>40906148</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 15:14:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://conduition.io/coding/ticketmaster/">https://conduition.io/coding/ticketmaster/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40906148">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
    <p><em>“Screenshots won’t get you in”, but Chrome DevTools will.</em></p>
<p><a href="#Reverse-Engineering">Click here to skip the rant and go straight to the nerdy stuff.</a></p>
<p>I recently purchased tickets to a concert from TicketMaster. If they had issued me normal, printable PDF tickets I could save offline to my phone, this article would’ve never been penned. But of course this is 2024: Nothing we do online can be simple anymore.</p>
<p>After finalizing the purchase, TicketMaster discloses that I can’t print off tickets for this event. Instead, they issue tickets via a system called Mobile Entry, AKA <em>SafeTix.</em> This takes the form of a rotating barcode displayed inside TicketMaster’s web-app or android/ios app.</p>
<p><img src="https://conduition.io/images/ticketmaster/safetix-barcode.gif"></p><p>Perhaps I’m getting old, but I remember a time when printable tickets were ubiquitous. One could print off tickets after buying them online or even (gasp) <em>in-person,</em> and bring these paper tickets to get entry into the event when you arrive. They can be saved as PDFs and viewed on pretty much any device on the planet. PDF tickets work even if your phone loses internet connection. Paper tickets work even if you don’t have a phone. If you bought the ticket off the event’s official ticketing agency (not a sketchy reseller), you know for sure that they’re real. There’s no risk that your ticket won’t get you in. You can easily send them to a friend over WhatsApp, iMessage, Signal, email, or even by-hand with printed tickets.</p>
<p>These rotating barcodes on the other hand are far from perfect. I experienced this first-hand last year when I attended another <em>very popular</em> concert where they used a similar rotating-QR-code-ticket system. Numerous people including myself and my friends were floundering at the entry gate citing a bevy of broken barcode problems. The #1 was:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>My phone has no internet connection, so my QR code won’t load.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The venue was so crowded that cell-towers and WiFi were overloaded. Internet access was spottier than a Dalmatian with chickenpox.</p>
<p>The company responsible for this ticketing nightmare (I can’t remember their name) obviously had no phone support line, and even if they did it probably wouldn’t have worked. The venue employees were completely helpless. Our only hope was to keep refreshing the ticket app, wildly waving our phones in the air in the hopes we might catch a brief moment of cell-network coverage with which to fetch and then display the ticket QR codes to the venue staff.</p>
<p>In the end, I luckily caught some cell-service and loaded our ticket QR codes. We left behind a slew of other ticketholders waving their phones around at the gate. I have no idea whether they ever got through.</p>
<p>I paid three hundred US dollars for this high-tech experience.</p>
<h2 id="The-Marketing"><a href="#The-Marketing" title="The Marketing"></a>The Marketing</h2><p>TicketMaster markets their SafeTix technology as a cure-all for scammers and scalpers.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>SafeTix™ are powered by a new and unique barcode that automatically refreshes every few seconds so it cannot be stolen or copied, keeping your tickets safe and secure.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Ticketmaster SafeTix are powered by a new and unique barcode that automatically refreshes every 15 seconds. This greatly reduces the risk of ticket fraud from stolen or illegal counterfeit tickets.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><sub><a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://www.ticketmaster.com/safetix">Source</a></sub></p>
<blockquote>
<p>Our secure ticket technology reduces the risk of ticket fraud, eliminating the possibilities of theft or counterfeiting. Once you’ve purchased your mobile tickets on Ticketmaster, you can always rest assured you’re getting the seats you paid for.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><sub><a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://blog.ticketmaster.com/mobile-ticketing-an-essential-for-safe-entry/">Source</a></sub></p>
<p>There’s also this gem:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If you take a closer look at your ticket, you may notice that it has a gliding movement, making it in a sense, alive. That movement is our ticket technology actively working to safeguard you every second.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Bullshit, TicketMaster. It’s a CSS animation. Get over yourself.</p>
<p>The part that got me worried:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The barcode on your mobile ticket includes technology to protect it, which means screenshots or printouts of your ticket will not be scannable.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This triggered flashbacks to the concert last year, and I pictured myself once more haphazardly waving my phone around, praying for service like Saul Goodman in the desert.</p>
<p><img src="https://conduition.io/images/ticketmaster/saul-goodman-1.webp">
  <img src="https://conduition.io/images/ticketmaster/saul-goodman-2.webp">
</p>

<p>But TicketMaster was prepared for this anxiety:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Concerned about cell phone service at venues? This ticket has you covered. Once you view it in our App, your ticket is automatically saved so it’s always ready.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Great, so as long as I trust their app not to have a seizure on the day of the concert, I should be fine. Too bad I really don’t trust that, besides the fact that I don’t want to install their spyware on my phone.</p>
<h2 id="Motivations"><a href="#Motivations" title="Motivations"></a>Motivations</h2><p>It’s pretty clear why TicketMaster is pushing this technology:</p>
<ul>
<li>SafeTix makes it harder for people to resell tickets outside of TicketMaster’s closed, high-margin ticket-resale marketplace, where they make a boatload of money by buying low and selling high to customers with no alternative.</li>
<li>It pushes users to install TicketMaster’s proprietary closed-source app, which gives TicketMaster more insight into their users’ devices and behavior.</li>
<li>People can’t save and transfer tickets outside of Ticketmaster. This forces ticketholders to surrender their friends’ contact information to TicketMaster, who can use this data to build social graphs, or conduct other privacy-invasive practices.</li>
</ul>
<p>TicketMaster will never admit to these motivations, but it cannot be doubted that these effects have manifested regardless of TicketMaster’s intent, and they’re all good news for TicketMaster’s shareholders, if not for their customers.</p>
<h2 id="The-Contradiction"><a href="#The-Contradiction" title="The Contradiction"></a>The Contradiction</h2><p>If you have any experience with computers and software, then having read all of TicketMaster’s marketing, you might come to the same question I did.</p>
<p><strong>How can tickets be saved offline if they can’t also be transferred outside of TicketMaster?</strong></p>
<p>This ticket is digital. Saving data offline is the same as copying it to your hard drive. If data can be copied, it can be transmitted. If it can be transmitted, it can be shared. If it can be shared, <em>it can be sold.</em></p>
<p>This is a contradiction in TicketMaster’s marketing. They can’t have robust DRM on their tickets if those tickets can still be viewed offline.</p>
<p>So what is TicketMaster really doing to create these rotating barcodes?</p>
<h2 id="Reverse-Engineering"><a href="#Reverse-Engineering" title="Reverse Engineering"></a>Reverse Engineering</h2><p>My first order of business was inspecting the barcodes themselves to see what I could learn. Their format is quite simple. They are <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PDF417">PDF417</a> barcodes which encode <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UTF-8">UTF-8 text</a>. As I mentioned earlier, that blue bar which sweeps across the barcode is just a gimmicky <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://www.w3schools.com/css/css3_animations.asp">CSS animation</a>: It doesn’t actually prevent screenshots of the barcode from scanning, because PDF417 has error correction properties built-in.</p>
<p>It seems like some older barcodes encode different formats of text, but the barcodes my TicketMaster web-app was generating embed data which looks like this:</p>
<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><pre><span>1</span><br></pre></td><td><pre><span>B4cq2BdFCpFl90TDuYD3pWfRDSO6eQ3bR0YQqsDnyfciuVFkKp+m0zI+a2lgfonY::140013::481994::1707070843</span><br></pre></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>

<p><sub>Disclaimer: This isn’t from a real SafeTix barcode. I don’t want TicketMaster to be able to identify and harass me.</sub></p>
<p>This looks like four distinct pieces of data, delimited by colons. First, there is some <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Base64">Base64</a>-encoded data, followed by two six-digit numbers, with a <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix_time">unix timestamp</a> trailing at the end.</p>
<p>When the barcode rotates every 15 seconds, its content changes slightly. The base64 data remains static, but both 6-digit numbers and the timestamp change.</p>
<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><pre><span>1</span><br></pre></td><td><pre><span>B4cq2BdFCpFl90TDuYD3pWfRDSO6eQ3bR0YQqsDnyfciuVFkKp+m0zI+a2lgfonY::358190::038184::1707070859</span><br></pre></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>

<p>These six-digit numbers behave a lot like <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time-based_One-Time_Password">Time-based One-Time Passwords (TOTPs)</a> - This is what powers 2FA apps like <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://authy.com/">Authy</a> or <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.google.android.apps.authenticator2">Google Authenticator</a>. These are rotating 6-digit codes which can be generated from a shared secret and a timestamp.</p>
<p>My instinct was that the first two numbers are indeed TOTPs, generated from different secrets, using the unix timestamp appended at the end of the barcode data. This makes sense: TicketMaster wouldn’t want to reinvent the wheel with this system, so they used a tried and tested cryptographic tool as a building block.</p>
<p>The base64 data was still a mystery. Decoding it into its constituent 48 bytes, it doesn’t seem to contain any meaningful data structures that I could discern. It seems more or less like random data, and since it doesn’t change when the barcode rotates, it’s probably some kind of random bearer token which identifies the ticketholder and their ticket.</p>
<p>When the ticket is scanned at the venue, TicketMaster (or perhaps the venue) looks up the ticket metadata using that bearer token, and then validates the two OTPs against two secrets stored in its database. If both steps pass, then your ticket is valid and the staff can let you in.</p>
<h2 id="Here’s-the-Secret"><a href="#Here’s-the-Secret" title="Here’s the Secret"></a>Here’s the Secret</h2><p>TOTPs are very customizable, but generally the software industry has settled on a set of common defaults for TOTP standardization. You really only need to have two things to generate a TOTP:</p>
<ul>
<li>The shared secret, which is just a byte array.</li>
<li>A working clock.</li>
</ul>
<p>If you have both of those, you can generate as many TOTPs as you’d like, <em>entirely offline.</em></p>
<p>There are two TOTPs in the barcode data, so there are probably two shared secrets I need to find. If I have both of those, plus the bearer token, I can create as many valid barcodes as I want.</p>
<p>So now my goal is much clearer: I need to find out where these tokens &amp; secrets come from.</p>
<h2 id="Debugging-the-Web-App"><a href="#Debugging-the-Web-App" title="Debugging the Web App"></a>Debugging the Web App</h2><p>I booted up an Android phone and connected its Chrome browser to the Chrome DevTools on my desktop computer. This gives me a view into TicketMaster’s API and source code.</p>
<p>By <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://developer.chrome.com/docs/devtools/network/reference/">recording network requests</a> as I loaded the TicketMaster barcode viewer, I found one particularly interesting request:</p>
<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><pre><span>1</span><br></pre></td><td><pre><span>POST /api/render-ticket/secure-barcode?time=1707071877481&amp;amid=XXXXXXXXXXXXXXX&amp;_format=json</span><br></pre></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>

<p>Its response data:</p>
<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><pre><span>1</span><br><span>2</span><br><span>3</span><br><span>4</span><br><span>5</span><br><span>6</span><br><span>7</span><br><span>8</span><br><span>9</span><br><span>10</span><br><span>11</span><br><span>12</span><br><span>13</span><br><span>14</span><br><span>15</span><br><span>16</span><br><span>17</span><br><span>18</span><br><span>19</span><br><span>20</span><br><span>21</span><br><span>22</span><br><span>23</span><br><span>24</span><br><span>25</span><br><span>26</span><br><span>27</span><br><span>28</span><br><span>29</span><br><span>30</span><br><span>31</span><br><span>32</span><br></pre></td><td><pre><span><span>{</span></span><br><span>  <span>"deviceId"</span><span>:</span> <span>"8f651107-acad-42a4-b3a6-019aaac41960"</span><span>,</span></span><br><span>  <span>"deviceType"</span><span>:</span> <span>"WEB"</span><span>,</span></span><br><span>  <span>"deviceOs"</span><span>:</span> <span>"ANDROID"</span><span>,</span></span><br><span>  <span>"userAgent"</span><span>:</span> <span>"Mozilla/5.0 (Linux; Android 10; K) XXXXXXXXXXXXXXX"</span><span>,</span></span><br><span>  <span>"nfcCapableDevice"</span><span>:</span> <span><span>true</span></span><span>,</span></span><br><span>  <span>"tickets"</span><span>:</span> <span>[</span></span><br><span>    <span>{</span></span><br><span>      <span>"eventId"</span><span>:</span> <span>"myevent.50.38991943985838B9"</span><span>,</span></span><br><span>      <span>"section"</span><span>:</span> <span>"3"</span><span>,</span></span><br><span>      <span>"row"</span><span>:</span> <span>"A"</span><span>,</span></span><br><span>      <span>"seat"</span><span>:</span> <span>"1"</span><span>,</span></span><br><span>      <span>"barcode"</span><span>:</span> <span>"481848590102K"</span><span>,</span></span><br><span>      <span>"addedValue"</span><span>:</span> <span><span>false</span></span><span>,</span></span><br><span>      <span>"generalAdmission"</span><span>:</span> <span><span>false</span></span><span>,</span></span><br><span>      <span>"fan"</span><span>:</span> <span><span>null</span></span><span>,</span></span><br><span>      <span>"token"</span><span>:</span> <span>"eyJiIjoiNDgxODQ4NTkwMTAySyIsInQiOiJUR1JMWUNxQWYyQ1MvQmxILzh5dThZdkhoV055TW8xUW9CYTI5UTVqVkN4V2xBcE5NbnczSlJkeU9UcFVVWUFDIiwiY2siOiJiOTg0MzJlZDIzYjhmMmJkYTgyMzQ4MjE2MjI5ZjRkMjdjZTlkMDYzIiwiZWsiOiJiMzUxOTM2NGUwYzc5MTRjMWY5ZDU5ZDM1NjUyYTA0MDY3ZDJmNjQ3IiwicnQiOiJyb3RhdGluZ19zeW1ib2xvZ3kifQ=="</span><span>,</span></span><br><span>      <span>"renderType"</span><span>:</span> <span>"rotating_symbology"</span><span>,</span></span><br><span>      <span>"passData"</span><span>:</span> <span>{</span></span><br><span>        <span>"android"</span><span>:</span> <span>{</span></span><br><span>          <span>"jwt"</span><span>:</span> <span>"eyJhbGciOiJSUzI1NiJ9.XXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXX.YYYYYYYYYYYYYYYYYYYYYYYYYY"</span></span><br><span>        <span>}</span></span><br><span>      <span>}</span><span>,</span></span><br><span>      <span>"bindingRequired"</span><span>:</span> <span><span>true</span></span><span>,</span></span><br><span>      <span>"deviceKeyBindingRequired"</span><span>:</span> <span><span>false</span></span><span>,</span></span><br><span>      <span>"deviceSignatureRequired"</span><span>:</span> <span><span>false</span></span><span>,</span></span><br><span>      <span>"segmentType"</span><span>:</span> <span>"NFC_ROTATING_SYMBOLOGY"</span><span>,</span></span><br><span>      <span>"ticketId"</span><span>:</span> <span>"50.3.A.1"</span></span><br><span>    <span>}</span></span><br><span>  <span>]</span><span>,</span></span><br><span>  <span>"globalUserId"</span><span>:</span> <span>"k39Fj4lNfOS4Zq481bxIWg"</span></span><br><span><span>}</span></span><br></pre></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>

<p><sub>Disclaimer: Identifying data has been scrambled to protect the guilty.</sub></p>
<p>Note the <code>token</code> property in the object in the <code>tickets</code> array. I base64-decoded it, and I found it was actually just a another JSON object:</p>
<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><pre><span>1</span><br><span>2</span><br><span>3</span><br><span>4</span><br><span>5</span><br><span>6</span><br><span>7</span><br></pre></td><td><pre><span><span>{</span></span><br><span>  <span>"b"</span><span>:</span> <span>"481848590102K"</span><span>,</span></span><br><span>  <span>"t"</span><span>:</span> <span>"TGRLYCqAf2CS/BlH/8yu8YvHhWNyMo1QoBa29Q5jVCxWlApNMnw3JRdyOTpUUYAC"</span><span>,</span></span><br><span>  <span>"ck"</span><span>:</span> <span>"b98432ed23b8f2bda82348216229f4d27ce9d063"</span><span>,</span></span><br><span>  <span>"ek"</span><span>:</span> <span>"b3519364e0c7914c1f9d59d35652a04067d2f647"</span><span>,</span></span><br><span>  <span>"rt"</span><span>:</span> <span>"rotating_symbology"</span></span><br><span><span>}</span></span><br></pre></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>

<ul>
<li>The <code>b</code> property seems to be the same as the <code>barcode</code> property on the ticket object.</li>
<li>The <code>rt</code> property seems to be the same as the <code>renderType</code> property on the main ticket object.</li>
<li>The <code>t</code> property is a base64-encoded byte array, 48 bytes long.</li>
<li>The <code>ck</code> and <code>ek</code> properties are both hex-encoded byte arrays, each 20 bytes long.</li>
</ul>
<p>I re-scanned the latest barcode shown on the TicketMaster web-app:</p>
<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><pre><span>1</span><br></pre></td><td><pre><span>TGRLYCqAf2CS/BlH/8yu8YvHhWNyMo1QoBa29Q5jVCxWlApNMnw3JRdyOTpUUYAC::492436::240860::1707074879</span><br></pre></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>

<p>Nice. So <code>t</code> is the static bearer token. I wonder if <code>ck</code> and <code>ek</code> are the TOTP secrets I’m after.</p>
<p>Upon some further investigation into TicketMaster’s minified website source code, in a file called <code>presence-secure-entry.js</code>, I found the actual function the web-app uses to generate barcode data, which is labeled <code>generateSignedToken</code>.</p>
<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><pre><span>1</span><br><span>2</span><br><span>3</span><br><span>4</span><br><span>5</span><br><span>6</span><br><span>7</span><br><span>8</span><br><span>9</span><br><span>10</span><br><span>11</span><br><span>12</span><br><span>13</span><br><span>14</span><br><span>15</span><br><span>16</span><br><span>17</span><br><span>18</span><br><span>19</span><br><span>20</span><br><span>21</span><br><span>22</span><br><span>23</span><br><span>24</span><br><span>25</span><br><span>26</span><br><span>27</span><br><span>28</span><br><span>29</span><br><span>30</span><br><span>31</span><br><span>32</span><br></pre></td><td><pre><span><span>key</span>: <span>"generateSignedToken"</span>,</span><br><span><span>value</span>: <span>function</span>(<span>t</span>) {</span><br><span>    <span>var</span> e = <span>arguments</span>.<span>length</span> &gt; <span>1</span> &amp;&amp; <span>void</span> <span>0</span> !== <span>arguments</span>[<span>1</span>] &amp;&amp; <span>arguments</span>[<span>1</span>];</span><br><span>    <span>if</span> (<span>this</span>.<span>displayType</span> === l.<span>ROTATING</span>) {</span><br><span>        <span>var</span> n = [<span>this</span>.<span>eventKey</span>, <span>this</span>.<span>customerKey</span>]</span><br><span>          , a = t;</span><br><span>        <span>if</span> (<span>this</span>.<span>eventKey</span>) {</span><br><span>            <span>var</span> u = <span>new</span> <span>Date</span>(a);</span><br><span>            a = u <span>instanceof</span> <span>Date</span> &amp;&amp; <span>"Invalid Date"</span> !== <span>""</span>.<span>concat</span>(u) ? u : <span>new</span> <span>Date</span></span><br><span>        }</span><br><span>        <span>var</span> A = n.<span>reduce</span>((<span>function</span>(<span>t, n</span>) {</span><br><span>            <span>if</span> (n) {</span><br><span>                <span>var</span> u;</span><br><span>                <span>try</span> {</span><br><span>                    u = i.<span>b32encode</span>(o.<span>a</span>.<span>hexToByteString</span>(n))</span><br><span>                } <span>catch</span> (t) {</span><br><span>                    u = <span>""</span></span><br><span>                }</span><br><span>                <span>var</span> A = r.<span>a</span>(u, <span>15</span>).<span>now</span>(a, e);</span><br><span>                t.<span>push</span>(A)</span><br><span>            }</span><br><span>            <span>return</span> t</span><br><span>        }</span><br><span>        ), [<span>this</span>.<span>rawToken</span>]);</span><br><span>        <span>if</span> (<span>this</span>.<span>eventKey</span>) {</span><br><span>            <span>var</span> s = <span>Math</span>.<span>floor</span>(a.<span>getTime</span>() / <span>1e3</span>);</span><br><span>            A.<span>push</span>(s)</span><br><span>        }</span><br><span>        <span>return</span> A.<span>join</span>(<span>"::"</span>)</span><br><span>    }</span><br><span>    <span>return</span> <span>this</span>.<span>barcode</span></span><br><span>}</span><br></pre></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>

<p>The minification makes it a bit harder to read, but it seems like <code>ek</code> and <code>ck</code> probably refer to the <code>eventKey</code> and <code>customerKey</code> respectively, while the bearer token <code>t</code> is referenced as <code>rawToken</code> in the above code.</p>
<p>It appears the two TOTPs are generated with a 15-second time step interval, but are otherwise constructed in the same way as the ubiquitous industry-standard SHA-1 TOTPs we see in any mobile 2FA app. The first one is generated with the <code>eventKey</code>, and the second with the <code>customerKey</code>. Finally, the unix timestamp used for both TOTPs is appended to help with verification on the server-side.</p>
<p>To verify my interpretation, I installed <code>oathtool</code>, a TOTP command-line tool. I plugged <code>ck</code>, <code>ek</code> and the unix timestamp into a SHA-1 TOTP generator with a 15-second step interval:</p>
<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><pre><span>1</span><br><span>2</span><br><span>3</span><br><span>4</span><br><span>5</span><br><span>6</span><br><span>7</span><br></pre></td><td><pre><span><span>$ </span><span>sudo apt install oathtool -y</span></span><br><span>...</span><br><span><span>$ </span><span><span>date</span>=$(python3 -c <span>'import datetime; print(datetime.datetime.fromtimestamp(1707074879).isoformat())'</span>)</span></span><br><span><span>$ </span><span>oathtool --totp --time-step-size 15s -N <span>"<span>$date</span>"</span> b3519364e0c7914c1f9d59d35652a04067d2f647</span></span><br><span>492436</span><br><span><span>$ </span><span>oathtool --totp --time-step-size 15s -N <span>"<span>$date</span>"</span> b98432ed23b8f2bda82348216229f4d27ce9d063</span></span><br><span>240860</span><br></pre></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>

<p>Bingo! 🎉 This matches the TOTPs in the barcode:</p>
<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><pre><span>1</span><br></pre></td><td><pre><span>TGRLYCqAf2CS/BlH/8yu8YvHhWNyMo1QoBa29Q5jVCxWlApNMnw3JRdyOTpUUYAC::492436::240860::1707074879</span><br></pre></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>

<p>The <code>eventKey</code> is probably unique to the particular event that is being ticketed, and <code>customerKey</code> is probably unique to the ticketholder. They don’t appear to change at all, unlike the <code>rawToken</code> which seems to rotate every time I refresh the TicketMaster web-app. However, if I leave the page alone for several hours, the <code>rawToken</code> doesn’t change, suggesting it should remain valid even after closing the web-app.</p>
<p><sub>What about the <code>passData.android.jwt</code> field? Does that come into play anywhere? I’ll save you some work on that front. Turns out it’s not actually needed for ticket verification at all, but rather just an authentication token used for saving the ticket to a user’s <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://wallet.google/">Google Wallet</a>. I don’t use Google Wallet. Being a rather privacy-conscious individual, I stay well clear of Google services as much as possible.</sub></p>
<h2 id="Pirating-Tickets"><a href="#Pirating-Tickets" title="Pirating Tickets"></a>Pirating Tickets</h2><p>I now know everything I would need to duplicate TicketMaster’s barcodes in a custom app, or even resell a ticket outside of TicketMaster’s closed marketplace. All I would need to do is extract the base64 <code>token</code> property from the <code>/api/render-ticket/secure-barcode</code> API endpoint, or engineer a way to fetch that token dynamically using TicketMaster session credentials.</p>
<p>That base64 <code>token</code> string <em><strong>IS</strong></em> the ticket, as far as the venue staff at the gates are concerned. If you have a valid <code>rawToken</code>, <code>eventKey</code>, and <code>customerKey</code>, you can generate valid <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PDF417">PDF417 barcodes</a>, indistinguishable from the official TicketMaster app. Short of checking photo IDs at the entry gate, the venue staff can’t tell whether the person at the gate is the same person who the ticket is registered to on TicketMaster.</p>
<p>Quite hilariously, TicketMaster actually makes token-extraction easy on us: The <code>token</code> is logged to the browser console automatically when the barcode renderer component is mounted on the web page.</p>
<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><pre><span>1</span><br><span>2</span><br><span>3</span><br><span>4</span><br><span>5</span><br><span>6</span><br></pre></td><td><pre><span>r.<span>a</span>.<span>log</span>(</span><br><span>  <span>"'render' called on '"</span>.<span>concat</span>(</span><br><span>    <span>"pseview-"</span>.<span>concat</span>(J.<span>get</span>(<span>this</span>)),</span><br><span>    <span>"' with token '"</span>, <span>this</span>.<span>token</span>, <span>"'"</span></span><br><span>  )</span><br><span>)</span><br></pre></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>

<p>This means we don’t even need to mess around injecting custom user-scripts into the page to get the <code>token</code> out. You can just open your SafeTix barcode on the TicketMaster web-app, <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://developer.chrome.com/blog/devtools-mobile/">connect your phone’s Chrome instance to your laptop’s Chrome DevTools</a>, and open the console. You’ll see the <code>token</code> printed right there. You can copy and use it wherever you’d like.</p>
<h2 id="Lifetimes"><a href="#Lifetimes" title="Lifetimes"></a>Lifetimes</h2><p>The only unknown factor here is the <code>rawToken</code> lifetime. It’s difficult to know for sure how TicketMaster’s backend server uses <code>rawToken</code> to look up the ticket. It’s likely that a new <code>rawToken</code> is generated every time the client contacts the <code>/api/render-ticket/secure-barcode</code> endpoint.</p>
<p>I have no idea how long each <code>rawToken</code> remains valid. It’s possible that only a single <code>rawToken</code> could be valid for a given TicketMaster account at a time. Indeed TicketMaster devs probably designed the system that way to prevent extracting multiple tickets which are concurrently valid.</p>
<p>If multiple <code>token</code>s are valid concurrently, one person could buy dozens of tickets, extract however many ticket <code>token</code>s they’d like, and resell them under-the-table. I would really love if TicketMaster didn’t think of that, because then I could extract the ticket <code>token</code>s for my friends and distribute them without having to go through TicketMaster’s data-harvesting pipeline.</p>
<p>The only authoritative source I could find on this is <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://developer.ticketmaster.com/products-and-docs/apis/partner/safetix/">an obscure document on TicketMaster’s developer API docs website</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Partners will need to refresh the token 20 hours prior to the start of the event and whenever the ticket is displayed in your app.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>FAQ</p>
<ol>
<li>How often must the token be refreshed? You should refresh the token anytime a fan opens and views a ticket within your app and 20 hours prior to the event. If you are unable to refresh the token when the fan views the ticket at the gate, then the SDK would attempt to use the token refreshed 20 hours prior. The token should still be valid. You do not need to refresh the token every 20 hours.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>Based on this, it might be reasonable to assume the <code>rawToken</code> is only valid for a 20 hour period, which would mean you’d need to fetch the <code>rawToken</code> at most 20 hours before the event to be able to resell or transfer it without TicketMaster’s permission. However, if all you want to do is save a ticket offline, this is more than adequate. I even built a little <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://expo.dev/">Expo</a> app I call <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://github.com/conduition/ticketgimp"><em>TicketGimp</em></a> which renders SafeTix barcodes if you give it a <code>token</code>.</p>
<p><img src="https://conduition.io/images/ticketmaster/ticketgimp.png"></p><p>I look forward to testing it out when my concert comes around.</p>
<h2 id="Conclusion"><a href="#Conclusion" title="Conclusion"></a>Conclusion</h2><p>I think we can all agree: <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://duckduckgo.com/?q=fuck+ticketmaster&amp;ia=web">Fuck TicketMaster</a>. I hope their sleazy product managers and business majors read this and throw a tantrum. I hope their devs read this and feel embarrassed. It’s rare that I feel genuine malice towards other developers, but to those who designed this system, I say: <em>Shame.</em></p>
<p>Shame on you for abusing your talent to <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://www.ticketnews.com/2021/07/mobile-only-ticketing-push-leaving-many-without-smartphones-behind/">exclude the technologically-disadvantaged</a>.</p>
<p>Shame on you for letting the marketing team <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://business.ticketmaster.com/business-solutions/safetix-the-game-changer-in-digital-ticketing/">dress this dark-pattern as a safety measure</a>.</p>
<p>Shame on you for supporting a company with <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/business/business-news/live-nation-ticketmaster-class-action-1235070131/">such cruel business practices</a>.</p>
<p>Software developers are the wizards and shamans of the modern age. We ought to use our powers with the austerity and integrity such power implies. You’re using them to exclude people from entertainment events.</p>
<p>Have fun refactoring your ticket verification system.</p>
<p><a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://www.breakupticketmaster.com/">Break up TicketMaster</a>.</p>

  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[For the first time in more than 150 years, Alberta's electricity is coal free (161 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theglobeandmail.com/canada/alberta/article-for-the-first-time-in-more-than-150-years-albertas-electricity-is-coal/</link>
            <guid>40905706</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 14:23:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theglobeandmail.com/canada/alberta/article-for-the-first-time-in-more-than-150-years-albertas-electricity-is-coal/">https://www.theglobeandmail.com/canada/alberta/article-for-the-first-time-in-more-than-150-years-albertas-electricity-is-coal/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40905706">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="content-gate" data-sophi-feature="article body"><figure><a href="https://www.theglobeandmail.com/resizer/v2/QKC5TQXHIZGSXF6QKOI6THRCKI.jpg?auth=eb580dbce4c76beaf22c1ef51fea442435e53654bfdebf72c561830fa9775ed3&amp;width=600&amp;quality=80" aria-haspopup="true" data-photo-viewer-index="0"><span>Open this photo in gallery:</span><p><img alt="" height="431" sizes="(min-width: 80rem) 940px,(min-width: 48rem) 690px,100vw" src="https://www.theglobeandmail.com/resizer/v2/QKC5TQXHIZGSXF6QKOI6THRCKI.jpg?auth=eb580dbce4c76beaf22c1ef51fea442435e53654bfdebf72c561830fa9775ed3&amp;width=600&amp;quality=80" srcset="https://www.theglobeandmail.com/resizer/v2/QKC5TQXHIZGSXF6QKOI6THRCKI.jpg?auth=eb580dbce4c76beaf22c1ef51fea442435e53654bfdebf72c561830fa9775ed3&amp;width=1200&amp;quality=80 1200w,https://www.theglobeandmail.com/resizer/v2/QKC5TQXHIZGSXF6QKOI6THRCKI.jpg?auth=eb580dbce4c76beaf22c1ef51fea442435e53654bfdebf72c561830fa9775ed3&amp;width=900&amp;quality=80 900w,https://www.theglobeandmail.com/resizer/v2/QKC5TQXHIZGSXF6QKOI6THRCKI.jpg?auth=eb580dbce4c76beaf22c1ef51fea442435e53654bfdebf72c561830fa9775ed3&amp;width=600&amp;quality=80 600w" width="600" fetchpriority="high"></p></a><figcaption><div><p><span>Unit 2 at the Genesee Generating Station west of Edmonton went offline on June 16. It was the last remaining electricity-generation facility in Alberta to rely exclusively on coal.</span><span>Capital Power</span></p></div></figcaption></figure><p>At 10:57 p.m. on Sunday, June 16, Alberta’s last coal plant went offline. An official announcement shortly followed, quietly signalling the end of coal-fired electricity in Alberta.</p><p>Many organizations contributed to this successful campaign through advocacy and research. The Canadian Association of Physicians for the Environment, the Lung Association and the Asthma Society of Canada were instrumental in highlighting the health impacts associated with air pollution from coal-fired electricity. The Pembina Institute, an Alberta-based clean-energy think tank, first intervened in a coal plant regulatory process in the late 1990s and, in 2009, published the first major proposal that showed the province could move to an unabated coal-free grid by 2030. Our research was ahead of its time and criticized as idealistic.</p><p><a href="https://www.theglobeandmail.com/topics/coal/" target="_blank">Coal </a>accounted for 80 per cent of Alberta’s electricity grid in the early 2000s and it still amounted to 60 per cent just 10 years ago. When phasing out coal was just an idea being batted around, many said it couldn’t be done. This is not dissimilar to the rhetoric today around decarbonizing the grid. But Alberta’s experience phasing out coal shows environmental progress of this magnitude is possible.</p><p>In 2012, then-prime minister Stephen Harper mandated a nationwide phase-out of coal by 2061. A far-off target date that, nonetheless, provided certainty to the provinces and got the ball rolling. In <a href="https://www.theglobeandmail.com/topics/alberta/" target="_blank">Alberta</a>, the Wildrose Party, then led by now United Conservative Party Premier <a href="https://www.theglobeandmail.com/topics/danielle-smith/" target="_blank">Danielle Smith</a>, included a coal phase-out commitment in its 2012 election platform.</p><p>When the New Democratic Party came to power after the 2015 provincial election, they got to work delivering on a plan to accelerate the elimination of coal. This included strengthening Alberta’s industrial carbon pricing system, a commitment to 30-per-cent renewables by 2030 and a target date for phasing out coal by 2030 – a target built through consultation with experts and industry. The current federal government made a similar national commitment in 2016.</p><p>At the time, there were concerns about the impact this would have on jobs. We learned that workers benefit from new investments in cleaner electricity – if included in strategic planning from the start. Federal and provincial programs to support workers during this transition were made available, while community economic diversification and growth in jobs in other sectors have helped to offset some of this change. Research also shows there are opportunities in clean energy, such as from increased land revenues and municipal taxes.</p><p>Phasing out coal in Alberta was supported by good policy design driven by carbon pricing and regulations with clear targets that offered necessary certainty to the industry and stakeholders. Rapidly growing, low-cost renewable energy further supported the phase-out, along with companies investing in gas-fired electricity. All these actions accelerated the transition away from coal at a faster rate than anticipated.</p><p>So, for the first time in 150 years, coal is no longer part of Alberta’s electricity mix. It is important to celebrate and reflect on these milestones, while recognizing there is no time to rest before redoubling our efforts and looking to what’s next.</p><p>As Pembina Institute’s latest research shows, many countries are striving to be the first to decarbonize their electricity system and a decarbonized electricity system by 2035 is within reach in Canada. It would save households hundreds of dollars on their electricity bills, enhance the competitiveness of our industries, and attract more investments into Canada as industries all look to secure clean power. But, as with coal, powerful incumbents want to maintain the status quo. Neither Albertans nor our climate can afford to be locked in to burning greenhouse gas-emitting natural gas when we have better, lower-cost alternatives.</p><p>Renewable energy is already the most cost-effective form of new electricity generation, and costs continue to drop. However, we still need to bring more wind and solar energy online, along with storage. Historically a leader in renewable energy, Alberta’s seven-month renewables moratorium, new restrictions unique to renewables, and a market restructuring have chilled project development. Restoring certainty should be a priority for the government. Alberta also already has enough existing and planned gas on its grid to meet its electricity needs.</p><p>The future is abundant, affordable, zero-emissions electricity. But we also need to invest in updating our infrastructure to meet our modern-day needs. Alberta is behind on demand-side management measures – a tactic that has reduced energy demand by 15 per cent in Ontario. Canada is also behind on building interties between jurisdictions – an approach that supports resilient systems and allows us to benefit from our complementary strengths across the country in hydro and other renewables.</p><p>We urgently need to continue to reduce emissions and we have the tools to achieve this. As the coal example shows, success takes time – sometimes over the course of decades – and relentless fact-based advocacy.</p><p><i>Chris Severson-Baker is the executive director of the Pembina Institute.</i></p></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Open-sourced Webflow for your own app (221 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/onlook-dev/studio</link>
            <guid>40904862</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 12:36:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/onlook-dev/studio">https://github.com/onlook-dev/studio</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40904862">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text">




<p dir="auto"><a href="https://discord.gg/hERDfFZCsH" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/b34dddc0d45b289f47c2c99aa412b80a10ab31ada4098f32d84d1effb4a9f4a6/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f2d446973636f72642d626c61636b3f6c6f676f3d646973636f726426636f6c6f72423d353535" alt="Discord" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/-Discord-black?logo=discord&amp;colorB=555"></a>
<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/onlook-dev" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/ae07a475769d11377cad3f842a91f70e631d8a59e05145c861ac1f747366daa4/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f2d4c696e6b6564496e2d626c61636b2e7376673f6c6f676f3d6c696e6b6564696e26636f6c6f72423d353535" alt="LinkedIn" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/-LinkedIn-black.svg?logo=linkedin&amp;colorB=555"></a>
<a href="https://x.com/onlookdev" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/29c5ce1a545500c27435ab309753fd4f0681965c6784bfab139a5ed00f3a1416/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f2d547769747465722d626c61636b3f6c6f676f3d7826636f6c6f72423d353535" alt="Twitter" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/-Twitter-black?logo=x&amp;colorB=555"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://youtu.be/RSX_3EaO5eU" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://github.com/onlook-dev/studio/raw/main/readme/assets/brand.png" alt="Onlook Screen Shot"></a></p>
<div dir="auto">
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Onlook</h3><a id="user-content-onlook" aria-label="Permalink: Onlook" href="#onlook"></a></p>
  
</div>

<details>
  <summary>Table of Contents</summary>
  <ol dir="auto">
    <li> <a href="#about">About</a> </li>
    <li><a href="#installation">Installation</a></li>
    <li><a href="#usage">Usage</a></li>
    <li><a href="#roadmap">Roadmap</a></li>
    <li><a href="#contributing">Contributing</a></li>
    <li><a href="#contact">Contact</a></li>
    <li><a href="#acknowledgments">Acknowledgments</a></li>
    <li><a href="#license">License</a></li>
  </ol>
</details>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">About</h2><a id="user-content-about" aria-label="Permalink: About" href="#about"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Build your UI visually. Supports any React + TailwindCSS app.</p>
<details open="">
  <summary>
    
    <span aria-label="Video description Onlook.Studio.Preview.mp4">Onlook.Studio.Preview.mp4</span>
    <span></span>
  </summary>

  <video src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/31864905/346226317-ea429342-03bc-40b2-8a94-d3955f638015.mp4?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjA0NTI5MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcyMDQ1MjYwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii8zMTg2NDkwNS8zNDYyMjYzMTctZWE0MjkzNDItMDNiYy00MGIyLThhOTQtZDM5NTVmNjM4MDE1Lm1wND9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDA3MDglMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQwNzA4VDE1MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTMyZTU0YzhlOGU3Yzk4YWY4NTI2OTdkMWM5NTczZDQ5NjkwNmQxZWE4YmU2MWZkYWYwODhmZmY4M2EyNmYwZTgmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0JmFjdG9yX2lkPTAma2V5X2lkPTAmcmVwb19pZD0wIn0.J5VCfUjrVrfM3KtGgU3LAixz7NL4JKvTVm9btF8Pa-g" data-canonical-src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/31864905/346226317-ea429342-03bc-40b2-8a94-d3955f638015.mp4?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjA0NTI5MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcyMDQ1MjYwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii8zMTg2NDkwNS8zNDYyMjYzMTctZWE0MjkzNDItMDNiYy00MGIyLThhOTQtZDM5NTVmNjM4MDE1Lm1wND9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDA3MDglMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQwNzA4VDE1MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTMyZTU0YzhlOGU3Yzk4YWY4NTI2OTdkMWM5NTczZDQ5NjkwNmQxZWE4YmU2MWZkYWYwODhmZmY4M2EyNmYwZTgmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0JmFjdG9yX2lkPTAma2V5X2lkPTAmcmVwb19pZD0wIn0.J5VCfUjrVrfM3KtGgU3LAixz7NL4JKvTVm9btF8Pa-g" controls="controls" muted="muted">

  </video>
</details>

<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Built With</h3><a id="user-content-built-with" aria-label="Permalink: Built With" href="#built-with"></a></p>

<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h3><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Clone the repo
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/onlook-dev/studio.git"><pre>git clone https://github.com/onlook-dev/studio.git</pre></div>
</li>
<li>Navigate to app folder

</li>
<li>Install NPM packages

</li>
<li>Run the project

</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h2><a id="user-content-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Usage" href="#usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Trying with demo project</h3><a id="user-content-trying-with-demo-project" aria-label="Permalink: Trying with demo project" href="#trying-with-demo-project"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">We have a few demo projects included in the <code>demos</code> folder. These inside are a standard React app and a Next.js React app.</p>
<p dir="auto">These are already set up with the Onlook plugins and have code written to them directly.</p>
<p dir="auto">To run, follow the following steps:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Run the demo project
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="cd demos/next &amp;&amp; npm install &amp;&amp; npm run dev"><pre><span>cd</span> demos/next <span>&amp;&amp;</span> npm install <span>&amp;&amp;</span> npm run dev</pre></div>
</li>
<li>Open Onlook studio</li>
<li>Point to <code>http://localhost:3000</code></li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto">For more examples, please refer to the <a href="https://docs.onlook.dev/" rel="nofollow">Documentation</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Using your own React project</h3><a id="user-content-using-your-own-react-project" aria-label="Permalink: Using your own React project" href="#using-your-own-react-project"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To try with your own React + TailwindCSS project, follow the following steps:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Install the corresponding Onlook plugins for your React framework:
<ol dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/@onlook/nextjs" rel="nofollow">Nextjs</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/@onlook/babel-plugin-react" rel="nofollow">Babel (webpack, esbuild, vite, etc.)</a></li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Run your project in dev mode</li>
<li>Open Onlook studio to where your project is running locally. For example <code>http://localhost:3000</code></li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto">The code for the plugins are under <code>plugins</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Roadmap</h2><a id="user-content-roadmap" aria-label="Permalink: Roadmap" href="#roadmap"></a></p>
<ul>
<li> Browser</li>
<li> Editor</li>
<li> Write-to-code</li>
<li> Components</li>
<li> Variables</li>
<li> Code Editor</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">See the <a href="https://github.com/onlook-dev/studio/blob/main/readme/ROADMAP.md">roadmap</a> for a detailed list of project goals and improvements.</p>
<p dir="auto">See the <a href="https://github.com/onlook-dev/studio/issues">open issues</a> for a full list of proposed features (and known issues).</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing</h2><a id="user-content-contributing" aria-label="Permalink: Contributing" href="#contributing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If you have a suggestion that would make this better, please fork the repo and create a pull request. You can also <a href="https://github.com/onlook-dev/studio/issues">open issues</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">See the <a href="https://github.com/onlook-dev/studio/blob/main/readme/CONTRIBUTING.md">CONTRIBUTING.md</a> for instructions and code of conduct.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contact</h2><a id="user-content-contact" aria-label="Permalink: Contact" href="#contact"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Onlook Team - <a href="https://twitter.com/onlookdev" rel="nofollow">@onlookdev</a> - <a href="mailto:contact@onlook.com">contact@onlook.com</a></li>
<li>Project Link: <a href="https://github.com/onlook-dev/studio">https://github.com/onlook-dev/studio</a></li>
<li>Website: <a href="https://onlook.dev/" rel="nofollow">https://onlook.dev</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Acknowledgments</h2><a id="user-content-acknowledgments" aria-label="Permalink: Acknowledgments" href="#acknowledgments"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/GoogleChromeLabs/ProjectVisBug">Project Visbug</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/responsively-org/responsively-app">Responsively App</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Distributed under the Apache 2.0 License. See <a href="https://github.com/onlook-dev/studio/blob/main/LICENSE.md">LICENSE.md</a> for more information.</p>

</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Xpra: Persistent Remote Applications for X11 (163 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra</link>
            <guid>40903870</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 09:15:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra">https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40903870">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><ol dir="auto">
<li><a href="#about">About</a></li>
<li><a href="#installation">Installation</a></li>
<li><a href="#usage">Usage</a></li>
<li><a href="#documentation">Documentation</a></li>
<li><a href="#help">Help</a></li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">About</h2><a id="user-content-about" aria-label="Permalink: About" href="#about"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Xpra is known as <em>"screen for X"</em> : its <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/Usage/Seamless.md">seamless mode</a> allows you to run X11 programs,
usually on a remote host, direct their display to your local machine,
and then to disconnect from these programs and reconnect from the same or another machine(s),
without losing any state.
Effectively giving you remote access to individual graphical applications.
It can also be used to
<a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/Usage/Shadow.md">access existing desktop sessions</a> and <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/Usage/Desktop.md">start remote desktop sessions</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Xpra is <em>open-source</em> (<a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/COPYING">GPLv2+</a>) with clients available for <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/wiki/Platforms">many supported platforms</a>
and the server includes a built-in <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra-html5">HTML5 client</a>.
Xpra is usable over a wide variety of <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/Network/README.md">network protocols</a> and does its best to adapt to any network conditions.</p>
<p dir="auto">Xpra forwards and synchronizes many extra desktop features which allows remote applications
to integrate transparently into the client's desktop environment:
<a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/Features/Audio.md">audio input and output</a>, <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/Features/Printing.md">printers</a>, <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/Features/Clipboard.md">clipboard</a>,
<a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/Features/System-Tray.md">system trays</a>, <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/Features/Notifications.md">notifications</a>, <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/Features/Webcam.md">webcams</a>, etc</p>
<p dir="auto">It can also <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/Features/File-Transfers.md">open documents and URLs remotely</a>,
display <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/Features/Image-Depth.md">high bit depth content</a>,
and it will try honour the <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/Features/DPI.md">display's DPI</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Here's what a seamless session with two windows (an <code>xterm</code> and <code>glxspheres</code>)
looks like when attached from an MS Windows 11 desktop client:
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/images/screenshots/win11-glxspheres.png"><img src="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/raw/master/docs/images/screenshots/win11-glxspheres.png" alt="Windows11-client"></a>
(the windows may look like native windows, but they are running on a remote Linux server)</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h2><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Official stable downloads</h2><a id="user-content-official-stable-downloads" aria-label="Permalink: Official stable downloads" href="#official-stable-downloads"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Microsoft Windows: <a href="https://xpra.org/dists/windows/Xpra-x86_64_Setup.exe" rel="nofollow">EXE</a>, <a href="https://xpra.org/dists/windows/Xpra.zip" rel="nofollow">ZIP</a>, <a href="https://xpra.org/dists/windows/Xpra-x86_64.msi" rel="nofollow">MSI</a></li>
<li>MacOS <code>x86_64</code> <a href="https://xpra.org/dists/MacOS/x86_64/Xpra.dmg" rel="nofollow">DMG</a> / <a href="https://xpra.org/dists/MacOS%3E/x86_64/Xpra.pkg" rel="nofollow">PKG</a>, <code>arm64</code> <a href="https://xpra.org/dists/MacOS/arm64/Xpra.dmg" rel="nofollow">DMG</a> / <a href="https://xpra.org/dists/MacOS/arm64/Xpra.pkg" rel="nofollow">PKG</a></li>
<li>Linux: <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/wiki/Download#-for-rpm-distributions">RPM</a>, <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/wiki/Download#-for-debian-based-distributions">DEB</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">All the packages are signed. There are also <a href="https://xpra.org/beta" rel="nofollow">beta builds</a> available.
For more information, see <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/wiki/Download">xpra downloads</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Build from source</h2><a id="user-content-build-from-source" aria-label="Permalink: Build from source" href="#build-from-source"></a></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra; cd xpra
python3 ./setup.py install"><pre><code>git clone https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra; cd xpra
python3 ./setup.py install
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">For more details, see <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/tree/master/docs/Build">building from source</a>.
To contribute to the project, please try to use pull-requests and follow our <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/CODE_OF_CONDUCT.md">code of conduct</a>.
Unit test status:
<a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/actions/workflows/test.yml"><img src="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/actions/workflows/test.yml/badge.svg" alt="xpra"></a></p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h2><a id="user-content-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Usage" href="#usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Initial requirements</h2><a id="user-content-initial-requirements" aria-label="Permalink: Initial requirements" href="#initial-requirements"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><code>xpra</code> must be installed on the client and the host.</p>
<p dir="auto">You can use the <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra-html5">html5 client</a> in which case xpra is only required on the host.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Seamless Mode</h2><a id="user-content-seamless-mode" aria-label="Permalink: Seamless Mode" href="#seamless-mode"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Run <code>xterm</code> on a remote host, display and iteract with it locally (from the client machine):</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="xpra start ssh://USER@HOST/ --start=xterm
# hint: xterm must be installed on the HOST."><pre><code>xpra start ssh://USER@HOST/ --start=xterm
# hint: xterm must be installed on the HOST.
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">For more examples, see <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/Usage/README.md">usage</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Shadow</h2><a id="user-content-shadow" aria-label="Permalink: Shadow" href="#shadow"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">View an existing desktop session running on a remote host:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="xpra shadow ssh://USER@HOST/"><pre><code>xpra shadow ssh://USER@HOST/
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Network Access</h2><a id="user-content-network-access" aria-label="Permalink: Network Access" href="#network-access"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Xpra servers can support <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/Network/README.md">many different types of connections</a> using a single TCP port:
<a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/Network/SSL.md">SSL</a>, <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/Network/SSH.md">SSH</a>, (secure) http / websockets, RFB, etc..<br>
Connections can be secured using <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/Network/Encryption.md">encryption</a> and <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/Usage/Authentication.md">many authentication modules</a>.<br>
Sessions can be automatically announced on LANs using <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/Network/Multicast-DNS.md">multicast DNS</a>
so that clients can connect more easily using a GUI (ie: <code>xpra mdns-gui</code>).<br>
Its flexible <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/Usage/Proxy-Server.md">proxy server</a> can be used as a relay or front end for multiple server sessions.</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Documentation</h2><a id="user-content-documentation" aria-label="Permalink: Documentation" href="#documentation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">There is extensive documentation <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs">right here</a> for the current development version.
This documentation is also included with each release.</p>
<p dir="auto">For more generic version-agnostic information, checkout <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/wiki">the wiki</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Help</h2><a id="user-content-help" aria-label="Permalink: Help" href="#help"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Make sure to check the <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/blob/master/docs/FAQ.md">FAQ</a>, your question may already be answered there.
You can ask your questions on the <a href="https://github.com/orgs/Xpra-org/discussions">github discussions</a>, or on the IRC channel <code>#xpra</code> on <a href="https://libera.chat/" rel="nofollow"><code>libera.chat</code></a>
or <a href="https://discord.gg/2mtC6cDv6Q" rel="nofollow">using discord</a>.
If you have hit a bug (sorry about that!), please see <a href="https://github.com/Xpra-org/xpra/wiki/Reporting-Bugs">reporting bugs</a>.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Zed Editor automatically downloads binaries and NPM packages without consent (218 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://old.reddit.com/r/programming/comments/1dxmroj/zed_editor_automatically_downloads_binaries_and/</link>
            <guid>40902826</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 05:26:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/programming/comments/1dxmroj/zed_editor_automatically_downloads_binaries_and/">https://old.reddit.com/r/programming/comments/1dxmroj/zed_editor_automatically_downloads_binaries_and/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40902826">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>In order to provide support for language servers and various tools, Zed automatically downloads binaries from the internet without user approval.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>I noticed that Zed automatically downloads the NodeJS binary from <a href="https://nodejs.org/">https://nodejs.org</a> without asking or even informing the user about it. Right after starting it and opening a file, without doing anything else. And there’s no option to disable it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>...</p>

<blockquote>
<p>EDIT: Now I found that it downloads (here) even some proprietary binary from <a href="https://supermaven.com/">https://supermaven.com</a>, i.e. unaudited and unauditable code, without any verification (except TLS)! At least this is not downloaded by default… I hope…</p>

<p>EDIT2: Zed also automatically downloads and executes prebuilt language servers for C#, Clojure, Deno, Elixir, Gleam, GLSL, Lua, Terraform, Toml and Zig. It automatically resolves the latest version available on GitHub and downloads it, again, without any verification.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>-- jirutka</p>

<p>The Zed Team does not currently plan to change their approach:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>We do not have plans to abandon this approach since there's so much code written to support various frontend tools already, that rewriting those in Rust will take an eternity, so not sure what is actionable here, hence closing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>-- <a href="https://github.com/zed-industries/zed/issues/7054#issuecomment-1916315391">https://github.com/zed-industries/zed/issues/7054#issuecomment-1916315391</a></p>

<p>Edit:</p>

<p>I created an issue that hopes to improve the situation to an extent: <a href="https://github.com/zed-industries/zed/issues/13918">https://github.com/zed-industries/zed/issues/13918</a></p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Boeing to plead guilty to criminal fraud charge stemming from 737 MAX crashes (469 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cnbc.com/2024/07/08/boeing-to-plead-guilty-to-criminal-fraud-charge-stemming-from-737-max-crashes.html</link>
            <guid>40902749</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 05:06:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/07/08/boeing-to-plead-guilty-to-criminal-fraud-charge-stemming-from-737-max-crashes.html">https://www.cnbc.com/2024/07/08/boeing-to-plead-guilty-to-criminal-fraud-charge-stemming-from-737-max-crashes.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40902749">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="RegularArticle-ArticleBody-5" data-module="ArticleBody" data-test="articleBody-2" data-analytics="RegularArticle-articleBody-5-2"><div id="ArticleBody-InlineImage-105786668" data-test="InlineImage"><p>Rescuers work at the scene of an Ethiopian Airlines flight crash near Bishoftu, or Debre Zeit, south of Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, Monday, March 11, 2019.</p><p>Mulugeta Ayene | Reuters</p></div><div><p><span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="RegularArticle-QuoteInBody-1"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/BA/">Boeing</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span> agreed to plead guilty to a criminal fraud charge tied to the fatal 737 Max crashes, the Justice Department said Sunday, months after U.S. prosecutors said the aerospace giant violated a <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2021/01/07/doj-fines-boeing-over-2point5-billion-charges-it-with-fraud-conspiracy-over-737-max-crashes.html">2021 settlement</a> that shielded it from prosecution.</p><p>Under the deal, Boeing agreed to pay a $243.6 million fine. An independent compliance monitor would also be installed to oversee compliance at Boeing for three years during a probationary period. Boeing would also have to invest at least $455 million in compliance and safety programs, according to a U.S. prosecutors' court filing late Sunday. The plea deal requires the approval of a federal judge to take effect.</p><p>Boeing also agreed for the board of directors to meet with crash victims' family members, under the agreement.</p><p>The plea deal offer forced Boeing to decide between a guilty plea and the attached terms, or going to trial, just as the company was seeking to <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/05/23/boeing-cfo-deliveries-cash-flow-max-crisis.html">turn a corner</a> in its <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/05/30/boeing-faa-safety-plan.html">manufacturing and safety crises</a>, <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/03/25/boeing-ceo-board-chair-commercial-head-out-737-max-crisis.html">pick a new CEO</a> and <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/07/01/boeing-to-buy-spirit-aerosystems.html">acquire</a> its fuselage maker, <span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="RegularArticle-QuoteInBody-7"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/SPR/">Spirit AeroSystems</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span>.</p><p>The guilty plea would brand the planemaker a felon and could complicate its ability to sell products to the U.S. government. About 32% of Boeing's nearly $78 billion in revenue last year came from its defense, space and security unit.</p><p>"We can confirm that we have reached an agreement in principle on terms of a resolution with the Justice Department, subject to the memorialization and approval of specific terms," Boeing said in a statement.</p><p>In May, the Justice Department said Boeing had <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/05/14/justice-department-says-boeing-breached-2021-agreement-that-shielded-it-from-criminal-charges-over-737-max-crashes.html">violated the 2021 agreement</a>. Under that deferred prosecution agreement, Boeing agreed to pay $2.5 billion, including an original $243.6 million criminal fine, compensation to airlines and a $500 million fund for victims' family members.</p><p>That 2021 settlement was set to expire two days after a door panel blew out of a nearly new 737 Max 9 operated by <span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="RegularArticle-QuoteInBody-9"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/ALK/">Alaska Airlines</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span> on Jan. 5. While there were no serious injuries, the accident created a fresh safety crisis for Boeing.</p><p>The U.S. accused Boeing of conspiracy to defraud the government by <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2020/01/09/boeing-releases-communications-on-737-max-simulators-it-calls-completely-unacceptable.html">misleading regulators</a> about its inclusion of a flight-control system on the Max that was later implicated in the two Max crashes — a Lion Air flight in October 2018 and an Ethiopian Airlines flight in March 2019. All 346 people on board the flights were killed.</p><p>U.S. prosecutors had told victims' family members on June 30 that they <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/06/30/us-seeks-guilty-plea-from-boeing-over-737-max-crashes.html">planned to seek a guilty plea from Boeing</a>, a plan family attorneys called "a sweetheart deal."</p><p>Paul Cassell, a lawyer for victims' family members, said he plans to ask the federal judge on the case to reject the deal and "simply set the matter for a public trial, so that all the facts surrounding the case will be aired in a fair and open forum before a jury."</p></div><div id="Placeholder-ArticleBody-Video-107396835" data-test="VideoPlaceHolder" role="region" tabindex="0" data-vilynx-id="7000336413" aria-labelledby="Placeholder-ArticleBody-Video-107396835"><p><img src="https://image.cnbcfm.com/api/v1/image/107397085-1712261316858-GettyImages-1241993909.jpeg?v=1715779349&amp;w=750&amp;h=422&amp;vtcrop=y" alt="Why the Boeing 737 Max has been such a mess"><span></span><span></span></p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Do Skis Get Blunt? (222 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://brooker.co.za/misc-blog/2024/01/23/skis.html</link>
            <guid>40902740</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 05:04:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://brooker.co.za/misc-blog/2024/01/23/skis.html">https://brooker.co.za/misc-blog/2024/01/23/skis.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40902740">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    <h2>About Me</h2><p>
    My name is Marc Brooker. I've been writing code, reading code, and living vicariously through computers for as long as I can remember. I like to build things that work. I also dabble in machining, welding, cooking and skiing.</p><p>

    I'm currently an engineer at Amazon Web Services (AWS) in Seattle, where I work on databases, serverless, and serverless databases. Before that, I worked on EC2 and EBS.<br>

    All opinions are my own.

    This is my less-technical blog on non-work topics. For my main blog, visit <a href="https://brooker.co.za/blog/">https://brooker.co.za/blog/</a>.
    </p><h2>Links</h2>
    <p><a href="https://brooker.co.za/blog/publications.html">My Publications and Videos</a><br>
    <a rel="me" href="https://fediscience.org/@marcbrooker">@marcbrooker on Mastodon</a>
    <a href="https://twitter.com/MarcJBrooker">@MarcJBrooker on Twitter</a>
  </p></div><div id="post">


<p>Of course they do.</p>

<p>Last winter, I rode a ski lift alongside a guy who claimed to be a retired Olympic ski tuner. Ski tuning, he said, was all a scam. If you keep your skis dry between days out they’ll stay sharp for their entire lifetime. Don’t get him started on waxing. His specific claim was that skis get blunt from corrosion, and all you have to do is keep them dry.</p>

<p>That didn’t seem right. In fact, it sounded like complete bullshit. Snow and ice are quite abrasive stuff, and even hard steel gets abraded after a while. It’s not unusual for a ski day to include 30km or more of sliding the edges on ice crystals, and so it’s hard to believe that abrasion doesn’t happen.</p>

<p>Turns out it does. Because, luckily, I do keep my skis dry. And I own a very impressive inspection microscope (OK, it’s a $30 one off Amazon, but whatever).</p>

<p>Here’s what one of my ski edges looks like after ~4 days since the last tuning:</p>

<p><img src="https://brooker.co.za/misc-blog/images/edge_blunt.jpg" alt="Picture of a blunt ski edge"></p>

<p>If that doesn’t make any sense to you, I don’t blame you. Here’s what you’re looking at:</p>

<p><img src="https://brooker.co.za/misc-blog/images/edge_diagram.jpg" alt="Picture of a blunt ski edge"></p>

<p>The ideal ski edge is a metal strip with a ~88° angle between the base and the sidewall of the ski. Here, you can see the base edge, and a “corner” on the edge. I’m not a metallurgist, but this sure looks like abrasion damage to me. Corrosion damage is more pitted, more rounded, and a lot more uneven.</p>

<p>Further down the ski, thing get even worse.</p>

<p><img src="https://brooker.co.za/misc-blog/images/edge_damage.jpg" alt="Picture of a blunt ski edge"></p>

<p>Here, the edge isn’t only rounded over, but small chunks of metal have ripped out to create tiny serrations in the edge. I suspect this effect is why blunt skis can feel “grabby” in some snow conditions.</p>

<p>Luckily, fixing this kind of damage isn’t hard. I use a 3D printed jig with a 500 grit diamond stone. A couple of glides down the edge is enough to completely clear this up. This is what the edge looks like after basic tuning:</p>

<p><img src="https://brooker.co.za/misc-blog/images/edge_sharp.jpg" alt="Picture of a blunt ski edge"></p>

<p>Here, the “corner” has completely disappeared, and been replaced with a nice clean sharp angle. The serrations are gone, and the edge is clean. For me, a sharp ski is the difference between fun and terror on an icy day. But maybe I’m in the pocket of Big Ski Tuning.</p>

<p>Knife sharpening nerds will notice that I’ve raised a significant burr here. I believe that race tuners will strop that burr off, but I’ve never noticed a difference (and, let’s be honest, the level of my skiing isn’t exactly “Olympic downhill”).</p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA['It's like I drew a door and disappeared through it' (2021) (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://meduza.io/en/feature/2021/04/01/it-s-like-i-drew-a-door-and-disappeared-through-it</link>
            <guid>40902604</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 04:28:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://meduza.io/en/feature/2021/04/01/it-s-like-i-drew-a-door-and-disappeared-through-it">https://meduza.io/en/feature/2021/04/01/it-s-like-i-drew-a-door-and-disappeared-through-it</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40902604">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><figure><div role="button" tabindex="0" data-testid="image"><picture><source type="image/webp" media="(min-width: 1000px)" srcset="https://meduza.io/impro/G1WMsegJfMFg3iFepLcyfAM-uHGtpLcegWa_8Bx4gAQ/resizing_type:fit/width:1960/height:0/enlarge:1/quality:80/aHR0cHM6Ly9tZWR1/emEuaW8vaW1hZ2Uv/YXR0YWNobWVudHMv/aW1hZ2VzLzAwNi81/OTAvNjc1L29yaWdp/bmFsL3hpYm5fNjVy/b2VON0d3NVlJWDdh/SFEuanBlZw.webp 2x, https://meduza.io/impro/XYq5HjQFnbFfNXiXsPDR3kB0oI5BGTi7lCPh3ba5mEs/resizing_type:fit/width:980/height:0/enlarge:1/quality:80/aHR0cHM6Ly9tZWR1/emEuaW8vaW1hZ2Uv/YXR0YWNobWVudHMv/aW1hZ2VzLzAwNi81/OTAvNjc1L29yaWdp/bmFsL3hpYm5fNjVy/b2VON0d3NVlJWDdh/SFEuanBlZw.webp 1x "><source type="image/png" media="(min-width: 1000px)" srcset="https://meduza.io/impro/tzZ3XneVu_cCVjZ5HLGBHPa6d9w2EmWisRgfaf6nQOs/resizing_type:fit/width:1960/height:0/enlarge:1/quality:80/aHR0cHM6Ly9tZWR1/emEuaW8vaW1hZ2Uv/YXR0YWNobWVudHMv/aW1hZ2VzLzAwNi81/OTAvNjc1L29yaWdp/bmFsL3hpYm5fNjVy/b2VON0d3NVlJWDdh/SFEuanBlZw.jpeg 2x, https://meduza.io/impro/1ofpVCd4so0HBU5JrqhyXRASzIo8g7adNDY9p3U92WA/resizing_type:fit/width:980/height:0/enlarge:1/quality:80/aHR0cHM6Ly9tZWR1/emEuaW8vaW1hZ2Uv/YXR0YWNobWVudHMv/aW1hZ2VzLzAwNi81/OTAvNjc1L29yaWdp/bmFsL3hpYm5fNjVy/b2VON0d3NVlJWDdh/SFEuanBlZw.jpeg 1x "><source type="image/webp" media="(min-width: 650px)" srcset="https://meduza.io/impro/3HU8nV3914vZtLllpSZ8tJKkNcP2Pwon7Ibvk8wcrdM/resizing_type:fit/width:1300/height:0/enlarge:1/quality:80/aHR0cHM6Ly9tZWR1/emEuaW8vaW1hZ2Uv/YXR0YWNobWVudHMv/aW1hZ2VzLzAwNi81/OTAvNjc1L29yaWdp/bmFsL3hpYm5fNjVy/b2VON0d3NVlJWDdh/SFEuanBlZw.webp 2x, https://meduza.io/impro/B4rGNs57Kt3cAOK9CNyLRb5Gm41Pcpq9bfvBwW6IJwA/resizing_type:fit/width:650/height:0/enlarge:1/quality:80/aHR0cHM6Ly9tZWR1/emEuaW8vaW1hZ2Uv/YXR0YWNobWVudHMv/aW1hZ2VzLzAwNi81/OTAvNjc1L29yaWdp/bmFsL3hpYm5fNjVy/b2VON0d3NVlJWDdh/SFEuanBlZw.webp 1x "><source type="image/png" media="(min-width: 650px)" srcset="https://meduza.io/impro/lFBULN-huMnrxaxqecp5yyzU9HEAMXtKaph9gtiI9u8/resizing_type:fit/width:1300/height:0/enlarge:1/quality:80/aHR0cHM6Ly9tZWR1/emEuaW8vaW1hZ2Uv/YXR0YWNobWVudHMv/aW1hZ2VzLzAwNi81/OTAvNjc1L29yaWdp/bmFsL3hpYm5fNjVy/b2VON0d3NVlJWDdh/SFEuanBlZw.jpeg 2x, https://meduza.io/impro/O6J4lRXQtvuF6e4Vj9B5P8mJ1RgqlVHspBYWgABvdAo/resizing_type:fit/width:650/height:0/enlarge:1/quality:80/aHR0cHM6Ly9tZWR1/emEuaW8vaW1hZ2Uv/YXR0YWNobWVudHMv/aW1hZ2VzLzAwNi81/OTAvNjc1L29yaWdp/bmFsL3hpYm5fNjVy/b2VON0d3NVlJWDdh/SFEuanBlZw.jpeg 1x "><source type="image/webp" media="(min-width: 325px)" srcset="https://meduza.io/impro/6AZ7rcolxQeSzWJ6NnbDRnv3eHM9PgxO4TYeE04t8s8/resizing_type:fit/width:1040/height:0/enlarge:1/quality:80/aHR0cHM6Ly9tZWR1/emEuaW8vaW1hZ2Uv/YXR0YWNobWVudHMv/aW1hZ2VzLzAwNi81/OTAvNjc1L29yaWdp/bmFsL3hpYm5fNjVy/b2VON0d3NVlJWDdh/SFEuanBlZw.webp 2x, https://meduza.io/impro/mGx0hHSCENq9v5z3WiIpz6mwhAhBcTeiRl7yUJqFnO8/resizing_type:fit/width:520/height:0/enlarge:1/quality:80/aHR0cHM6Ly9tZWR1/emEuaW8vaW1hZ2Uv/YXR0YWNobWVudHMv/aW1hZ2VzLzAwNi81/OTAvNjc1L29yaWdp/bmFsL3hpYm5fNjVy/b2VON0d3NVlJWDdh/SFEuanBlZw.webp 1x "><source type="image/png" media="(min-width: 325px)" srcset="https://meduza.io/impro/wLsvuGZ-cWWE-Qa7KU1vMZbcU_vXxW7bAt-26FboYro/resizing_type:fit/width:1040/height:0/enlarge:1/quality:80/aHR0cHM6Ly9tZWR1/emEuaW8vaW1hZ2Uv/YXR0YWNobWVudHMv/aW1hZ2VzLzAwNi81/OTAvNjc1L29yaWdp/bmFsL3hpYm5fNjVy/b2VON0d3NVlJWDdh/SFEuanBlZw.jpeg 2x, https://meduza.io/impro/F0lEDngnUjUfod_O1K8JigfFe9fwpe9Iw-LFGBvl-M8/resizing_type:fit/width:520/height:0/enlarge:1/quality:80/aHR0cHM6Ly9tZWR1/emEuaW8vaW1hZ2Uv/YXR0YWNobWVudHMv/aW1hZ2VzLzAwNi81/OTAvNjc1L29yaWdp/bmFsL3hpYm5fNjVy/b2VON0d3NVlJWDdh/SFEuanBlZw.jpeg 1x "><source type="image/webp" media="(min-width: 0)" srcset="https://meduza.io/impro/B4rGNs57Kt3cAOK9CNyLRb5Gm41Pcpq9bfvBwW6IJwA/resizing_type:fit/width:650/height:0/enlarge:1/quality:80/aHR0cHM6Ly9tZWR1/emEuaW8vaW1hZ2Uv/YXR0YWNobWVudHMv/aW1hZ2VzLzAwNi81/OTAvNjc1L29yaWdp/bmFsL3hpYm5fNjVy/b2VON0d3NVlJWDdh/SFEuanBlZw.webp 2x, https://meduza.io/impro/j3lg-wejf6N3Cvpw5bLoDDTUVyhiBlyyaaAc6I7HYV0/resizing_type:fit/width:325/height:0/enlarge:1/quality:80/aHR0cHM6Ly9tZWR1/emEuaW8vaW1hZ2Uv/YXR0YWNobWVudHMv/aW1hZ2VzLzAwNi81/OTAvNjc1L29yaWdp/bmFsL3hpYm5fNjVy/b2VON0d3NVlJWDdh/SFEuanBlZw.webp 1x "><source type="image/png" media="(min-width: 0)" srcset="https://meduza.io/impro/O6J4lRXQtvuF6e4Vj9B5P8mJ1RgqlVHspBYWgABvdAo/resizing_type:fit/width:650/height:0/enlarge:1/quality:80/aHR0cHM6Ly9tZWR1/emEuaW8vaW1hZ2Uv/YXR0YWNobWVudHMv/aW1hZ2VzLzAwNi81/OTAvNjc1L29yaWdp/bmFsL3hpYm5fNjVy/b2VON0d3NVlJWDdh/SFEuanBlZw.jpeg 2x, https://meduza.io/impro/56IW-0B6tZ4yjNrA7i8acn7_FZ2XHvZ0OjFOPu2p8DM/resizing_type:fit/width:325/height:0/enlarge:1/quality:80/aHR0cHM6Ly9tZWR1/emEuaW8vaW1hZ2Uv/YXR0YWNobWVudHMv/aW1hZ2VzLzAwNi81/OTAvNjc1L29yaWdp/bmFsL3hpYm5fNjVy/b2VON0d3NVlJWDdh/SFEuanBlZw.jpeg 1x "><img src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAPAAAPLy8gAAACH5BAAAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAICRAEAOw=="></picture></div></figure><p>Homeless people in Russia have their own terms for things — people who aren’t homeless are “domestic” people, while they themselves are “street” people, or simply “bums.” Meduza’s special correspondent Irina Kravtsova spent several days with homeless people in St. Petersburg, asking them the most obvious questions “domestic” people usually have: Why can’t they just update their documents, get a job, and rent a place to live? According to Igor Antonov, who’s worked with homeless people for years, questions like these underestimate the extent to which life on the street can transform a person. When it comes down to it, returning to a “normal life” is easier said than done.</p><p>Kirill Nikolayevich is a typical retiree — a lonely, trusting old man with kind eyes. For most of his working life, he was a locksmith for a large company. Later, because his pension was so small, he also did some part-time construction work on a church —&nbsp;it didn’t pay well, but they fed him. At the construction site, he got involved with some scammers who talked him into taking out a micro-loan on his apartment —&nbsp;300,000 rubles, nearly $4,000 — so he could buy into a metal trading company.</p><p>His “business partner” then disappeared with the money, the pensioner couldn’t repay the loan, and the court evicted him from his apartment. “Kirill Nikolayevich isn’t able to defend himself in court,” said Igor Antonov, a volunteer from the charity organization <span data-id="1002479" data-title="Nochlezhki" data-body="<p>Nochlezhki is a St. Petersburg-based charity organization that helps homeless people; its “night bus” goes out to remote parts of the city to distribute food and clothing.</p>">“Nochlezhki.”</span> “He ought to be watching a movie while they catch the criminals, walking his dog in the evenings, but instead, they’re dragging him to court. And in court, as he told me, instead of defending himself, he just said, ‘You’re all assholes — not judges, assholes.’ But the judge said everything was by the book. Now, Kirill Nikolayevich lives on the street in St. Petersburg, his hometown, where he has to ask volunteers to boil water so he can make instant noodles.”</p><p>“It’s very difficult to catch someone right at the moment their life is falling apart&nbsp;— when they get sick, they lose their job, they started taking payday loans, and use alcohol to blunt the pain,” Antonov said. “And it’s extremely difficult to help someone who’s already been on the street for a long time. People change dramatically out there — that’s what nobody realizes.”</p><h2 id="7-ffd0873d89b54c4db9b354fc5bc10b4e906820b8bf9cea144b90a77b6dc50729">‘<strong>I don’t have anything at all’</strong></h2><p>49-year-old Anna has a swollen face, red eyelids, and gray hair that’s grown to her shoulders. When she was still a “domestic” person, she would dye her wavy hair a chestnut color before going to her job as an elementary school art teacher.</p><p>When Anna’s daughter was 20 years old, she got married and brought her 28-year-old husband back to Anna’s one-bedroom apartment to live. They didn’t live with the husband’s parents (who had a two-bedroom apartment) because his parents insisted that newlyweds should live separately from their parents to avoid fights. Anna began sleeping on a sofa they had in the kitchen, while Anna’s daughter and her husband took the bedroom. For the first year, the setup worked well.</p><p>One night, when her daughter was at work, Anna’s son-in-law caught her walking out of the shower and raped her for the next several hours, filming her all the while. When he was finished, he told her she was a “bitch,” that he was “fucking sick of cowering around her all the time,” and to “get the fuck out” of the apartment.</p><p>Anna went to stay with a friend. After several weeks, she called her daughter, who hung up on her and then sent a text message asking her not to call them anymore. “I don’t know what he told her,” Anna said.</p><p>Eventually, she bid her friend farewell and “left to wander.” She spent the first nights in the entrance to an apartment building, then relocated to the building’s cellar. Anna struggled to remember the first nights she spent on the street. “I sat in one park, then moved to another, and when it became completely dark, I started to feel uneasy about staying on the street&nbsp;— before that, I was completely afraid of the dark. There were a bunch of drunk guys wandering around. I bought some kind of alcohol, went into an apartment building, and dozed off by the morning.”</p><p>In the fall, when it got cold, Anna started going into a convenience store to warm up. When a security guard asked why she was there, Anna said she and her son-in-law “weren’t getting along.” “Got it,” said the man. The next day, he brought her a warm jacket and a hat, both of which had belonged to his mother before her death. He also gave her the cardboard she now uses to sleep on in the store vestibule, and he started slipping her expired — “but not spoiled” — food, according to Anna.</p><p>It’s difficult for Anna to determine the exact moment she started feeling homeless. When asked about her own feelings, she often answered, “What do you mean how? I just did it,” “Oh no, it wasn’t scary,” or “Well, I just started drinking a lot.” But during our second meeting, Anna became more introspective and tried to determine how exactly she’d felt. Before that “I hadn’t dug so deep,” she said.</p><figure><figcaption></figcaption></figure><p>“Seriously, your questions are all like, ‘How were you feeling? When was the last time you were at peace?’ If that’s the way I thought about things, I would have killed myself already,” said Anna. “I remember how, the first night, I was so sick, there aren’t words to describe it.”</p><p>There was a pause, and we walked in silence for a while. I wasn’t sure whether to keep pressing her for answers; I knew that when I left, she would be all alone with her thoughts. It turned out, though, that she was just searching for the right metaphor. “It’s just like in a cartoon, see: I took a piece of chalk, drew a door, and disappeared through it.”</p><p>“Hey, you want to get ice cream? It’s on me!” Anna offered suddenly, despite the fact that neither of us can feel our legs because it’s so cold outside. She didn’t want to go into a diner, either.</p><p>“You’re asking about my home&nbsp;— how was it, what happened to it. But the tragedy isn’t the fact that I don’t have a home. It’s that I don’t have anything at all. A home — fine, whatever. The issue isn’t that I live on the street. It’s just that my old life is over. I can’t go back to it. That’s the hardest part.”</p><p>During our conversation, Anna would often fall silent, think about something for a bit, stop responding to questions, then return. She recalled how, at first, she didn’t see herself as a homeless person. “I still held onto the feeling that real bums don’t have homes, that they drank them away or realtors came and took them, but I still had a home. My apartment’s right over there, and I’m its owner, and I can go back to it whenever I want. I just don’t go there because I don’t want to —&nbsp;it’s my decision. But I do have a home.”</p><p>She started thinking of herself as a “bum” gradually. There was the time, for example, when she drank the coffee someone had left on a bench, and she caught someone looking at her as they passed by. “I realized he had seen that I was drinking a stranger’s coffee, and that he saw me as a bum. And I basically realized it was true.”</p><p>Anna works part time as a janitor at the convenience store, through someone else’s contract; she gives part of her paycheck to the person who works there officially. She doesn’t have anything but the clothes on her back, and she doesn’t have any plans for the future.</p><p>“I’ll live as long as I live,” she said. “There’s nowhere for me to go. And besides, you can get used to anything. It’s hard on the street, but was it easy at home? Everyone wants you to be kind, be good, be comfortable. And even then, nobody fucking needs you. And it’s not like that on the street, honestly. You’ve already crossed the line, at some level —&nbsp;you’re already bad by definition. It’s freeing.”</p><h2 id="26-2e5f9537d5e7b3584bb1d570ce548214ea78ab25c64a4920167cec011152e08f"><strong>‘Why are you helping a dirty bum like me?’</strong></h2><p>According to Igor Antonov, homeless people are often happy to be diagnosed with tuberculosis —&nbsp;for them, it means a year and a half in safety. “It sounds like dark humor, but even I get happy about it, because treatment is provided for homeless people with tuberculosis. Even if you get an arm and a leg amputated, after two or three days they’ll stick your torso back in the snow and put on the form that you’re ‘discharged and home,’” he said.</p><figure><figcaption></figcaption></figure><p>Antonov mentioned one woman whose feet turned black from frostbite. She tried three times to get treated at the hospital, but they continued to kick her out. “This woman with rotting, bad-smelling feet was finally given shelter by a passerby, and now she lives in the hallway of his building,” said Antonov.</p><p>“We’re trying to help her, but she probably won’t get into the hospital until the foot needs to be cut off. I took some pictures and sent them around to doctors, and they said, ‘Yes, she needs to be hospitalized, but it’s not an emergency —&nbsp;they might take her, they might not,” Antonov said. “But when someone’s already completely unconscious —&nbsp;when they have gangrene and worms —&nbsp;that’s when they’ll take them. When I talk about worms in people’s feet, that’s not just a scary story. It happens to homeless people very often.”</p><p>All homeless people were once “domestic,” and once viewed homeless people as “degraded,” anthropologist Pavel Inozemtsev told me. “Believe me, it’s not only you who feel contempt toward homeless people, it’s the homeless people themselves. One of them asked me, ‘Why are you helping a dirty bum like me?’ In their own eyes, they’re no longer just people who’ve had some bad luck but will soon recover and keep moving; they no longer feel like a part of their former world.”</p><figure><figcaption></figcaption></figure><p>Many people take the word “homeless” literally: a description of a person who doesn’t have a home, Antonov said. “But at the end of the day, it’s not about the house,&nbsp;we all know a lot of people who don’t own a house — they rent apartments and stuff like that. But still, true homelessness is when the absence of one’s own space combines with social exclusion.”</p><h2 id="36-a218373db25b89fa15917114527691638b2614808da796d86b4d36bb819e73d6"><strong>‘I lie down in the snow, shake for 15 minutes, then fall asleep’</strong></h2><p>I met 40-year-old Sasha outside of the Sortirovochnaya train station in St. Petersburg. For the last 11 years, he’s been living here on the street, spending winters on a blanket he lays right on top of a snowdrift in a strip of forest five kilometers (three miles) away.</p><p>Sasha used to have a room in a two-story log cabin in Ulyanovka, a township in the Leningrad region. When he was little, his mother was a heavy drinker and left him with his father, a soldier. After serving in the army, Sasha became a plumber for the emergency services. When he was 24, his father died.</p><p>“I basically buried him, then sat there and thought, ‘I don’t have anybody left.’ I went to work, returned home, boiled pelmeni, watched television. I had no family, nobody close. Not even anyone to talk to,” said Sasha. So he started drinking — and quickly developed a drinking problem, even blacking out a couple times.</p><p>“Then I came to, these gypsies were in my apartment, and I owed them a bunch of money. They started forcing me out of my room. I called the police, and it turned out the officer knew them, so he took their side. Now I can never go back to that room. Although I could!” Sasha said. “I never signed any papers giving them the room.”</p><p>According to Igor Antonov, this kind of thing happens a lot — people drive out their roommates and change the locks. “A lot of people aren’t able to stand up for themselves, to keep living in a place they’re constantly being driven out of. The police usually treat these situations as disputes, but they don’t try to resolve or settle the disputes&nbsp;— they don’t see it as their job.”</p><p>“Then whose job is it?”</p><p>“Nobody’s. Only the person himself. Either a person has the inner strength to fight for his territory, or he doesn’t.”</p><p>Since Sasha was kicked out of his apartment, he’s gone back to his old home a few times. He’s seen the lights on through the window, but he’s never dared to go inside. Since he’s been homeless, he’s run into his mother a few times (she’s now remarried and had more children), but he’s never approached her, and she’s never recognized him.</p><p>Sasha spoke quietly, looking around like he was distracted. While we spoke, he often used the word “home” to refer to the spot where he sleeps. He said he sleeps “under a canopy” and is separated from the frozen ground by “as much as” ten centimeters (four inches).</p><p>Sasha didn’t understand what everyone was afraid of. “The main thing is to warm up in the summer, find a blanket, and then you can live!” He didn’t show me his home right away. We walked around St. Petersburg’s Obukhovsky district, along the beltline on one side and a tall iron fence on the other. “Yes, I do sometimes get sick,” said Sasha. “But it’s like this: when I lived in a house, my teeth would hurt, and I often went to the dentist. And now, all my teeth have rotted, and it doesn’t hurt at all, I don’t even feel it!”</p><p>Eventually, Sasha found his own footprints leading back to his sleeping spot, and we turned to follow them. We climbed over a fence and started crawling through some branches. Sasha wasn’t used to leading guests, so he neglected to hold back the branches, letting them hit me in the face behind him. After walking a few more feet, he suddenly said we’d reached his home. On the snow-covered ground were an orange, a few plastic bottles, and a thin, beige blanket covered in black fabric. Sasha referred to this as a “tent.”</p><p>It was -19 degree Celsius (-2 degrees Fahrenheit) outside, but at 80 percent humidity, it felt more like -35 degrees (-31 degrees Fahrenheit)&nbsp;—&nbsp;you got the feeling that if you went to sleep, you wouldn’t wake up. “At night, I lie down here, shake for 15-20 minutes, then fall asleep,” said Sasha. He doesn’t have a watch or a phone, but he estimates that he usually falls asleep around 11:00 p.m. — recently, though, he’s started going to bed later, around 1:00 a.m.</p><p>Sasha gets up “at nine in the morning” and sets off on his usual route, searching for food in dumpsters. He travels about 13 kilometers (eight miles) a day doing this. In the evening, he goes to the Nochlezhki “night bus,” where volunteers give out hot food. He drinks hot tea and eats soup, not talking with anyone and giving monosyllabic answers to any questions. He knows people come with problems, so he’s tried to keep to himself for a long time.</p><p>He lost his passport six years ago. When asked why he doesn’t get a new one, Sasha answered vaguely, “Well, yeah, I ought to do that, I just can’t seem to get around to it.” I kept asking in disbelief, is it really easier to live this way than to get new documents, get a job, gradually save up to rent a place? However hard that may be, it can’t be worse than living in these awful conditions, can it? Especially since Sasha, according to himself and people who know him, almost never drinks.</p><p>Sasha didn’t open up about this until our second meeting. He said he’d actually tried to get a part-time job before, but homelessness is “a vicious cycle” that he hasn’t been able to get out of. “When an employer knows you’re homeless, that’s the attitude they take towards you,” he said.</p><figure><figcaption></figcaption></figure><p>“Motivation is all about anticipation,” said Igor Antonov. “Let’s say I’m anticipating a sip of hot coffee in a thermos, so I extend my arm and get an electric shock. The second time, I extend my arm to the thermos and get another electric shock. And then you, Irina, say to me, ‘Igor, would you like some coffee?’ I’ll answer, ‘No, you know, you feel free to have some, but coffee hasn’t been working out for me.’”</p><p>That’s why people who have spent a long time living on the street are often unreceptive to the ideas and solutions that volunteers suggest. “I’ll say to a woman, ‘Let’s get you to the hospital —&nbsp;your feet are rotting!’ And she’ll answer, ’No, I’ve already been to the hospital three times’,” Antonov said.</p><p>We live in different worlds, in different realities, Antonov continued. “For me, as a ‘domestic’ person, the hospital means treatment. But they’ll take one look at that woman, and ten minutes later, she’ll be in the snow in a different part of the city, with the same hurt feet. She’ll already know on that door, and she knows how it ends for her. But from the outside, sure, it seems like their problems should be very easy to solve.”</p><p>Sasha’s least favorite part of his current life isn’t the lack of a house —&nbsp;it’s that every day is exactly the same as the rest. “Every day you get up, look for food, struggle, then boom&nbsp;— it’s nighttime, then morning, and it all starts again.”</p><p>Everything Sasha owns is on his body. He doesn’t even store food. “Why do I need so much? Everything I need, I find and eat. If I need more, I’ll find it.”</p><h2 id="60-e663ecb91874c37e660cc4e682a3dab36bed0b1bbb3a49349c87e48a689f8c38"><strong>‘I was free’</strong></h2><p>Denis is 42 years old. He and his wife Larisa live behind the garages, a few hundred meters from the “Europolis” mall in St. Petersburg. The <a href="https://meduza.io/image/attachments/images/006/565/860/original/e0yt1b8TYRKLehz6h2WMCQ.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">space</a> Denis has built looks like a <a href="https://meduza.io/image/attachments/images/006/565/876/original/9QpASuQQQyN3fOrps2xFDA.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">house</a> without a roof or walls: a sagging door frame without a door, a wardrobe with a mirror, a fireplace, and a bedroom consisting of a tiny canvas tent. A nearby tree is decorated with tinsel for the holidays.</p><p>In 2006, when Denis worked at a construction firm, his boss took a large advance for an order and disappeared with the money. It fell to Denis and his colleagues to pay the debt. Denis was forced to sell his apartment and work for three months without pay. After that, he was only able to find work as a mover or a shipping agent —&nbsp;his reputation in the construction industry had been ruined. “As long as he still had savings, we lived, and when they ran out, my wife said, ‘I’m not gonna feed you,’ and kicked me out. I left my stuff, my computer, and everything I’d earned with her, slammed the door, and left. I left in the clothes I was wearing. That’s my nature —&nbsp;an idiot,” said Denis.</p><p>After leaving home, he “wandered around the street for a bit,” then got a job. According to Denis, he sent some money to his wife for a while before finding out that she and her friend were living off of it together. “It went down, down, down from there. And now I’ve hit rock bottom,” he said. He wanted to become a janitor or a mover, but in the mid-2000s, these jobs were all occupied by migrants, who were being paid “a quarter of a quarter,” so practically nobody was hiring Russians. Even still, Denis eventually found a job “through acquaintances” as a janitor and plumber in Petrogradka.</p><p>One day, Denis was introduced to a friend’s sister, Larisa. Soon after, he moved in with her. Larisa is 15 years older, and Denis calls her Lyalya. Some time later, Larisa’s daughter got divorced, returned to her mother, and started using drugs. According to Denis, the daughter eventually kicked them out, but he was close to leaving himself because he could hardly restrain himself from hitting her and “going to jail under [article] 105 [murder], seeing how she “shakes down her mother for money.”</p><p>At first, Denis rented a room for himself and Larisa. At that point, he still made enough money from working as a courier. Eventually, though, the company went under, so they moved in with friends, then “to the dacha” (Denis has a building further out in Moscow Oblast, but it’s unfurnished, and there are no jobs in the area). In the fall of 2007, Denis and Larisa made their hut between the railroad and the garages and began living on the street. Denis started selling scrap metal and jars.</p><p>“There was a really nice clearing,” said Denis. “I set up the tent. Then more people started coming, and eventually we had a little tent city. It lasted about two years before the authorities came and cut down the ‘jungle’ [the trees growing around them].”</p><p>Denis spoke proudly about the tent he had made. “It was so warm in my tent that me and Lyalya would sleep in T-shirts and underwear when it was -25 degrees [Celsius, -13 degrees Fahrenheit] outside,” he said. “First of all, I insulated it, and second of all, there’s an old army method I use. You take two-kilogram metal milk powder cans and make four holes at the bottom. When your fire burns out, you collect the red coals and put them on two bricks in the tent, and in three minutes, no matter how cold it is outside, you can start to undress.”</p><p>“What did it feel like when you first started living on the street?” I asked.</p><p>“No feeling at all. Do you believe that? No regret, nothing. It might have even felt like relief.”</p><p>“Relief?”</p><p>“Relief that I was free.”</p><p>“In what way?”</p><p>“I lived through a war, I got into so much trouble here, in Petrogradka, as a regular, working person. And now I don’t have to get up at nine to go to work. I don’t have to report somewhere every 15 minutes. I just don’t have to, you know? I got up, and I left. If I do something, it’s for me. If I don’t do something, it’s fine. Nobody’s standing over me and blaming me.”</p><p>Sometimes, Denis and Lyalya climb into the tent, huddle together for warmth, and sleep like that for a day or two because they can’t bring themselves to go out into the cold. “But then we can go out for three days. We’ll go for a walk, get something to eat, get a little something else [alcohol], and have a smoke.”</p><p>Getting out of the tent and getting dressed is hardest in winter, especially when their boots have frozen and shrunk. “You should hear how much I curse when I’m pulling the boots on!” said Denis. “And when you’re collecting those cans, the ends of your fingers freeze really badly.” It’s also hard for them when “it’s impossible to run somewhere to warm up or hide from the rain, if you’re far from your tent.”</p><p>Despite the difficulties, however, Denis and Laisa aren’t saving up for a more permanent place. “I think me and Lyalya have become complete street people. It wouldn’t make any sense.”</p><div data-testid="material-note"><p><a href="https://meduza.io/feature/2021/03/22/ya-na-vas-ustroivshihsya-v-etoy-zhizni-smotryu-kak-na-rybok-v-akvariume" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Story</a> by <strong>Irina Kravtsova</strong>, reporting from St. Petersburg, edited by <strong>Valery Igumenov</strong>, with photographs for <em>Meduza </em>by <strong>Liza Zhakova</strong></p><p>Abridged translation by <strong>Sam Breazeale</strong></p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Simulating 20M Particles in JavaScript (479 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://dgerrells.com/blog/how-fast-is-javascript-simulating-20-000-000-particles</link>
            <guid>40902012</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 01:52:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://dgerrells.com/blog/how-fast-is-javascript-simulating-20-000-000-particles">https://dgerrells.com/blog/how-fast-is-javascript-simulating-20-000-000-particles</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40902012">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="__next"><div><div><p><a href="https://dgerrells.com/">Home</a></p></div><div><p>/ </p><!-- --><p><a href="https://dgerrells.com/blog">blog</a></p></div></div><div><p>...loading</p><!-- --></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Mini Monitor for a Pi (165 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://noamzeise.com/2024/07/05/mini-monitor.html</link>
            <guid>40901623</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 00:27:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://noamzeise.com/2024/07/05/mini-monitor.html">https://noamzeise.com/2024/07/05/mini-monitor.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40901623">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://noamzeise.com/2024/07/05/mini-monitor.html: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I'm funding Ladybird because I can't fund Firefox (255 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://jackkelly.name/blog/archives/2024/07/06/im_funding_ladybird_because_i_cant_fund_firefox/</link>
            <guid>40900648</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jul 2024 21:38:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://jackkelly.name/blog/archives/2024/07/06/im_funding_ladybird_because_i_cant_fund_firefox/">http://jackkelly.name/blog/archives/2024/07/06/im_funding_ladybird_because_i_cant_fund_firefox/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40900648">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
  
  <div><p>
  Posted on July  6, 2024
  
    by Jack Kelly
  

  
    </p>
  
</div>

  <p>I’ve been meaning to write this one for a while, but the <a href="https://ladybird.org/announcement.html">announcement of the
Ladybird Browser Initiative</a> makes now a particularly good time.</p>
<p><strong>TL;DR:</strong> Chrome is eating the web. I have wanted to
help fund a serious alternative browser for quite some time, and while
Firefox remains the largest potential alternative, Mozilla has never let
me. Since I can’t fund Firefox, I’m going to show there’s money in
user-funded web browsers by <a href="https://donorbox.org/ladybird">funding Ladybird instead</a>. You
should too.</p>
<!--more-->
<h2 id="why-browser-diversity-matters">Why Browser Diversity
Matters</h2>
<p>An open web requires a healthy ecosystem of several competing
browsers, where each has enough market share that no one vendor has de
facto control over web standards. That’s the world we used to have,
after Firefox cracked the dominance of Microsoft’s Internet Explorer
(IE) in the 1990s. IE’s poor support for internet standards held back
web development all through the late 1990s and early 2000s, and
competition from Firefox allowed developers to build “for the web”
instead of “for IE6”, forcing browser vendors to catch up.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, we are back in a world without healthy browser
competition. <a href="https://gs.statcounter.com/browser-market-share/">statcounter.com</a>
claims that Chrome, Google’s browser, has over 65% market share. Add
Edge (which uses Blink, Chrome’s browser engine, under the hood) and
you’re over 70%. This market dominance allows Google to push through
changes like its “Manifest V3” format for browser extensions, which
coincidentally cripples <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2024/05/google-starts-deprecating-older-more-capable-chrome-extensions-next-week/">ad
blockers</a>.</p>
<details>
<summary>
Sidebar: Ad companies had their chance
</summary>
<p>While a discussion of the economics of ad-supported sites is outside
the scope of this post, someone will ask “don’t you like free things on
the internet?” if I don’t address it first.</p>
<p>Online advertising has become so obnoxious that ad blockers are
all-but-necessary for users to get anything done online. More than that,
I feel obliged to install ad blockers on family computers that I
support: skipping all those megabytes of random advertising JavaScript
significantly extends the lifespan of older computers and stops my
less-technical family members from being tricked into installing fake
malware versions of software. <a href="https://www.tomsguide.com/news/the-fbi-now-recommends-using-an-ad-blocker-heres-why">Even
the FBI recommends ad blockers</a>.</p>
Sorry, the online advertising industry had its chance, and they blew it.
</details>
<p>This is also the case for other user-hostile features like “Encrypted
Media Extensions” (aka “DRM for the web”). A healthy browser ecosystem
would have been able to vigorously push against features that take
control from the users; instead, <a href="https://www.jwz.org/blog/2024/06/mozillas-original-sin/">Mozilla
caved</a> in the hopes of maintaining Firefox market share but didn’t
even get that.</p>
<h2 id="why-wont-mozilla-let-me-fund-firefox">Why won’t Mozilla let me
Fund Firefox?</h2>
<p>According to the Mozilla Foundation’s <a href="https://foundation.mozilla.org/en/donate/help/#frequently-asked-questions">Donation
FAQ</a>, “Firefox is maintained by the Mozilla Corporation, a
wholly-owned subsidiary of the Mozilla Foundation. While Firefox does
produce revenue — chiefly through search partnerships — this earned
income is largely reinvested back into the Corporation”. “Search
partnerships” means “Google”, who made up <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mozilla_Corporation#Google">81% of
Mozilla Corporation’s revenue in 2022</a>. This means Firefox’s primary
revenue source is also their direct competitor, and they seem to have
little ability to change that.</p>
<p>Mozilla has backed themselves into a very poor position. In recent
years, Mozilla Corporation has made several controversial moves in
pursuit of revenue. Off the top of my head, there was the <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2017/12/16/16784628/mozilla-mr-robot-arg-plugin-firefox-looking-glass">Mr.&nbsp;Robot
addon</a>, automatically loaded into people’s browsers to advertise a TV
show; <a href="https://www.makeuseof.com/firefox-stop-address-bar-sponsored-links/">sponsored
links in the address bar</a>; <a href="https://www.ghacks.net/2020/11/22/how-to-disable-sponsored-top-sites-in-the-firefox-web-browser/">sponsored
“top sites” on the “new tab” page</a> a reading list startup called
“Pocket”, <a href="https://venturebeat.com/mobile/mozilla-responds-to-firefox-user-backlash-over-pocket-integration/">integrated
into Firefox without warning</a>; and a Mozilla VPN service, complete
with <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/05/26/mozilla_apologizes_for_intrusive_vpn_ad/">in-browser
pop-up ads</a>. Cal Paterson has <a href="https://calpaterson.com/mozilla.html">another good list</a>.
Meanwhile, Firefox market share falls and the <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/02/09/mozilla_ceo_mitchell_baker_departs/">outgoing
Mozilla Corporation CEO</a> gets paid millions (<a href="https://assets.mozilla.net/annualreport/2022/mozilla-fdn-990-ty22-public-disclosure.pdf">6.9
million USD in 2022</a> — see page 8).</p>
<p>The problem is that many people specifically use Firefox because
they’re sick of advertising and cross-promotion everywhere and want a
browser that’s “just a browser”. On top of that, silently installing
addons like the Mr.&nbsp;Robot extension undermine user trust in one of the
most sensitive software projects people use.</p>
<p>Despite desperately trying to find more revenue sources, Mozilla
Corporation stubbornly refuses to <em>just let users fund Firefox</em>.
Mozilla Foundation even has a specific donation form for Thunderbird
(Mozilla’s mail client), but not Firefox. I’m sure they could have found
some way of making it work with their corporate structure, and it
baffles me that they haven’t.</p>
<h2 id="ladybird">Ladybird</h2>
<p>Ladybird used to be the web browser for <a href="https://serenityos.org/">SerenityOS</a>, a from-scratch hobby
operating system written by Andreas Kling (and community). On 2024-06-03
(about a month ago), he forked Ladybird into a <a href="https://github.com/LadybirdBrowser/ladybird">separate project</a>
and <a href="https://awesomekling.substack.com/p/forking-ladybird-and-stepping-down-serenityos">stepped
away from SerenityOS</a>. Presumably this was prep-work to launch the <a href="https://ladybird.org/">Ladybird Browser Initiative</a>, a
non-profit dedicated to building the rest of the browser.</p>
<p>They are very open that the browser is unfinished — the first alpha
release is planned for 2026. But they have running code, and I can
<em>actually help fund them</em>. Wesley Moore <a href="https://www.wezm.net/v2/posts/2024/how-much-is-a-browser-worth/">runs
some numbers</a> in a similar post to this one, and concludes that 15
USD/month (~22.50 AUD in July 2024) is a good amount for a recurring
donation. I’m in; are you?</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Unit is a general purpose visual programming system (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://unit.software/</link>
            <guid>40900029</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jul 2024 19:58:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://unit.software/">https://unit.software/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40900029">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>