<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 06:30:04 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Jeffrey Goldberg on being added to the group chat by Trump Administration (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theatlantic.com/newsletters/archive/2025/03/jeffrey-goldberg-group-chat-military-houthi-yemen/682160/</link>
            <guid>43466983</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:45:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/newsletters/archive/2025/03/jeffrey-goldberg-group-chat-military-houthi-yemen/682160/">https://www.theatlantic.com/newsletters/archive/2025/03/jeffrey-goldberg-group-chat-military-houthi-yemen/682160/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43466983">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section data-event-module="article body" data-flatplan-body="true"><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><small><i>This is an edition of </i>The Atlantic<i> Daily, a newsletter that guides you through the biggest stories of the day, helps you discover new ideas, and recommends the best in culture. </i><a data-event-element="inline link" data-gtm-vis-first-on-screen31117857_899="351" data-gtm-vis-has-fired31117857_899="1" data-gtm-vis-recent-on-screen31117857_899="351" data-gtm-vis-total-visible-time31117857_899="100" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/newsletters/sign-up/atlantic-daily/"><i>Sign up for it here.</i></a></small></p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The Trump administration has provided many jaw-dropping moments, but few have been as shocking as editor in chief <a data-event-element="inline link" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2025/03/trump-administration-accidentally-texted-me-its-war-plans/682151/">Jeffrey Goldberg’s scoop</a> published today. Goldberg reported on how he was inadvertently added to a discussion of a military strike on Houthi militias in Yemen, conducted over the encrypted messaging app Signal. In essence, a reporter was invited to listen while the nation’s top security officials weighed and debated a military action, and was sent detailed information about the strike.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">Even President Donald Trump seemed unaware of the breach. “You’re saying that they had what?” he replied when asked about the news. Trump added that he is “not a big fan of <i>The Atlantic</i>,” something he’s <a data-event-element="inline link" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2024/10/trump-attacks-atlantics-jeffrey-goldberg-over-hitler/680422/">previously made clear</a>, and which makes the unintentional leak all the more remarkable. A spokesperson for the National Security Council said, “This appears to be an authentic message chain, and we are reviewing how an inadvertent number was added to the chain.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">I called Goldberg this afternoon to learn more about how the story came about and what the disclosure reveals about the Trump administration. This interview has been condensed and edited.</p><hr><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>David A. Graham: </b>Has anything like this ever happened to you before?</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>Jeffrey Goldberg:</b> I think that on one level, this is very relatable. Everyone has sent a text or an email to an unintended recipient, and sometimes they’ve embarrassed themselves by doing that. This is, I would say, at a different level—but it kind of proves a point, which is that there’s a reason people who work on sensitive issues in the government aren’t supposed to use Signal, even though it is end-to-end encrypted. Anyone can use Signal, so if you’re not careful, you might pull into your conversation a Houthi sympathizer or a magazine editor.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">Our colleague <a data-event-element="inline link" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/author/shane-harris/">Shane Harris</a> points out that the phones of top senior defense and national-security and intelligence officials are targets of intelligence operations. Imagine what you can do if you saw everything that the CIA director may be texting, even on a secure phone—especially on a secure phone. I’m mindful of the fact that the Trump team has already dealt with a <a data-event-element="inline link" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2025/01/classified-documents-trump-case/681327/">serious issue</a> in the securing of sensitive documents in Mar-a-Lago. If you’re going to make a big deal about <a data-event-element="inline link" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2017/07/but-his-emails/533274/">Hillary Clinton’s emails</a>, you may want to have excellent communication hygiene.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>David:</b> Tell me how you came to conclude that this group was real.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>Jeffrey: </b>It was actually chilling: 11:44 a.m., Saturday the 15th, eastern time, in my car in a parking lot, just checking my phone, and I see a text from Pete Hegseth, or somebody who’s hoaxing me as Pete Hegseth. It provides information about upcoming military operations with timings attached: <em>T</em><i>his is going to happen. Then this happens, then this happens, and this happens.</i> I’m sitting there in my car and thinking I’m about to find out if this was an elaborate scam or not. So I thought to myself,<i> I’m sitting here for the next two hours with my hands around my phone.</i> I check on X around 1:55, and yes, Sanaa is being bombed, so then I have the realization that this is almost certainly a real channel and not just an elaborate fakery of some sort. And that’s when I began to realize that I had to write about this massive security breach.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>David: </b>You have done a lot of sensitive national-security reporting. Have you ever received any information like this?</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>Jeffrey: </b>No, nothing like this. This was like an intravenous drip of information that no one in the government thinks journalists should have. Until almost the very last minute, I could not believe that this was actually happening, that there could be a Mack-truck-size breach, that somehow, the editor in chief of <i>The Atlantic</i> was invited into a conversation with the intelligence agencies, secretaries, the national security adviser. Like most reporters, I’ve been a recipient of leaks. A leak is a totally different thing. That’s a whistleblower trying to make complaints. This is just reckless.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>David: </b>There’s the horror that something like this would happen on an operational level, but in terms of what we learn from the substance of the conversation, what are the most important things that people should take away?</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>Jeffrey: </b>The actual conversation that they have is fascinating, and in a certain way impressive. It’s nice to see that they’re disagreeing with one another. It’s very useful for the public to know that the vice president has a more hands-off approach than other members of the administration. One of the things that I found interesting was that when a person named “S M” in the chat, who I took to be Stephen Miller, comes in and says, “As I heard it, the president was clear,” this kind of shuts down the conversation. It suggests that Stephen Miller can be in a conversation with, among others, the vice president of the United States and still can get his way. (Miller did not reply to a request for comment or confirm that he is “S M.”)</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>David: </b>In addition to the question of how secure Signal is, this is also notable, because without this report, none of these conversations might be preserved for posterity. You note that National Security Adviser Michael Waltz set some messages to disappear after a week or so.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>Jeffrey: </b>This is an interesting question: Are they using Signal because it’s convenient? Are they using Signal because it disappears? According to the experts Shane interviewed, the administration should not have established a Signal thread for such conversations in the first place, but once it did, what one is supposed to do legally is copy an official government account, and that government account will then send these threads to the National Archives for posterity, for research, for accountability. But if you’re using a disappearing-text app, I don’t know. That’s one of the questions that I’ve asked and have not gotten answered yet.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>David:</b> It is remarkable that this would happen with any reporter. It’s even more remarkable that this would happen with someone like you, and with a publication that has been specifically singled out by the president. Do you have any sense of how this happened?</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>Jeffrey: </b>I literally have no idea. The remarkable thing is that no one in the group asked, <i>Who’s JG?</i>, and when I removed myself from the group, seemingly nobody said, <i>Hey, why did JG leave?</i></p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>David:</b> Are you concerned about retaliation from the Trump administration because of this story?</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><b>Jeffrey: </b>It’s not my role to care about the possibility of threats or retaliation. We just have to come to work and do our jobs to the best of our ability. Unfortunately, in our society today—we see this across corporate journalism and law firms and other industries—there’s too much preemptive obeying for my taste. All we can do is just go do our jobs.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><a data-event-element="inline link" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2025/03/trump-administration-accidentally-texted-me-its-war-plans/682151/"><b>Read the full article he</b></a><b><a data-event-element="inline link" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2025/03/trump-administration-accidentally-texted-me-its-war-plans/682151/">re</a></b><a data-event-element="inline link" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2025/03/trump-administration-accidentally-texted-me-its-war-plans/682151/"><b>.</b></a></p></section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[German parliament votes as a Git contribution graph (200 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://abstimmung.eu/git/2024</link>
            <guid>43466509</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 23:29:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://abstimmung.eu/git/2024">https://abstimmung.eu/git/2024</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43466509">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><h2>17. Januar 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/53"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Jahresbericht 2022 der Wehrbeauftragten (Entschließungsantrag)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Verteidigung</span><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Ukraine</span><span data-slot="badge">Bundeswehr</span><span data-slot="badge">Militär</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Entschließungsantrag der CDU/CSU-Fraktion zum Jahresbericht 2022 der Wehrbeauftragten, der die Bundesregierung auffordert, einsatzbereite TAURUS-Marschflugkörper an die Ukraine zu liefern und diese unverzüglich nachzubeschaffen.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>18. Januar 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/54"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Entlastung der Landwirtschaft</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Landwirtschaft</span><span data-slot="badge">Wirtschaft</span><span data-slot="badge">Steuerpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Agrarpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Innovation</span><span data-slot="badge">Bürokratie</span></p><p>Der Antrag der CDU/CSU-Fraktion betrifft die Unterstützung der Landwirtschaft und zielt darauf ab, die Wettbewerbsfähigkeit der Landwirtschaft zu erhalten und zu verbessern, anstatt sie durch politische Maßnahmen zu schwächen. Der Antrag fordert die Bundesregierung auf, Maßnahmen zu ergreifen, um die Landwirtschaft zu fördern und zu entlasten.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/55"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Friedensinitiative für die Ukraine und Russland (Beschlussempfehlung)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Friedenspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Ukraine</span><span data-slot="badge">Russland</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft einen Antrag der AfD-Fraktion, der eine Friedensinitiative mit Sicherheitsgarantien für die Ukraine und Russland fordert, um Deutschlands Verantwortung für den Frieden in Europa gerecht zu werden.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>19. Januar 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/56"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Modernisierung des Staatsangehörigkeitsrechts (GesEntw BReg)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Staatsangehörigkeit</span><span data-slot="badge">Integration</span><span data-slot="badge">Recht</span><span data-slot="badge">Gesellschaft</span><span data-slot="badge">Migration</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Modernisierung des Staatsangehörigkeitsrechts (StARModG), um den Zugang zur deutschen Staatsangehörigkeit zu erleichtern und die Integration von Ausländern zu fördern.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>01. Februar 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/57"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Änderung des Bundeswahlgesetzes</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Wahlrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Innenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Bevölkerungsentwicklung</span><span data-slot="badge">Kommunalpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Gesetzgebung</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Änderung des Bundeswahlgesetzes, um die Wahlkreiseinteilung an die aktuelle Bevölkerungsentwicklung anzupassen und kommunale Gebietsänderungen zu berücksichtigen. Ziel ist es, sicherzustellen, dass die Wahl zum Deutschen Bundestag auf einer fairen und gleichmäßigen Grundlage stattfindet.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>22. Februar 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/58"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Zehn Jahre russischer Krieg gegen die Ukraine</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Ukraine</span><span data-slot="badge">Russland</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Militär</span><span data-slot="badge">Völkerrecht</span></p><p>Der Antrag betrifft die Unterstützung der Ukraine angesichts des russischen Krieges und zielt darauf ab, die deutsche und europäische Sicherheit zu stärken sowie die Verantwortlichen für Kriegsverbrechen zur Rechenschaft zu ziehen.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/60"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Deutsche Außen- und Sicherheitspolitik (Antrag CDU/CSU)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Verteidigung</span><span data-slot="badge">Internationale Beziehungen</span><span data-slot="badge">Bevölkerungsschutz</span></p><p>Der Antrag der CDU/CSU betrifft eine Neuausrichtung der deutschen Außen- und Sicherheitspolitik, um auf die veränderte Bedrohungslage durch Russland zu reagieren und Deutschlands Rolle in Europa und der Welt zu stärken. Er fordert eine "echte Zeitenwende" mit konkreten Maßnahmen zur Stärkung der Verteidigungsfähigkeit, des Bevölkerungsschutzes und der internationalen Zusammenarbeit.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>23. Februar 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/59"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Wachstumschancengesetz;Kfz-Haftpflichtversicherung (BeschlEmpf Vermittlungsausschuss)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Wirtschaft</span><span data-slot="badge">Steuerrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Investition</span><span data-slot="badge">Innovation</span><span data-slot="badge">Finanzen</span></p><p>Die Beschlussempfehlung des Vermittlungsausschusses betrifft das Gesetz zur Stärkung von Wachstumschancen, Investitionen und Innovation sowie Steuervereinfachung und Steuerfairness (Wachstumschancengesetz). Sie zielt darauf ab, Änderungen an diesem Gesetz vorzunehmen, um Wachstum, Investitionen und Innovation zu fördern sowie das Steuersystem zu vereinfachen und fairer zu gestalten.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/61"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Cannabisgesetz (GesEntwurf BReg)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Gesundheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Drogenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Jugendschutz</span><span data-slot="badge">Justiz</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheit</span></p><p>Das Cannabisgesetz regelt den kontrollierten Umgang mit Cannabis und ändert weitere Vorschriften. Es zielt darauf ab, den Gesundheitsschutz zu verbessern, den illegalen Markt einzudämmen und den Kinder- und Jugendschutz zu stärken.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/62"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Bundeswehreinsatz EUNAVFOR ASPIDES (BeschlEmpf)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Europäische Union</span><span data-slot="badge">Militär</span><span data-slot="badge">Internationaler Handel</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Beteiligung bewaffneter deutscher Streitkräfte an der von der Europäischen Union geführten Operation EUNAVFOR ASPIDES, die zum Schutz der Schifffahrt im Roten Meer und angrenzenden Gebieten beitragen soll. Der Bundestag stimmt über den Antrag der Bundesregierung zur Entsendung von bis zu 700 Soldaten bis maximal zum 28. Februar 2025 ab.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>14. März 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/63"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Ablehnung von Lieferung des Taurus-Marschflugkörpers (Beschlussempfehlung)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Verteidigung</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Ukraine</span><span data-slot="badge">Militär</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Antrag der CDU/CSU, die Bundesregierung aufzufordern, der Ukraine Taurus-Marschflugkörper aus Bundeswehrbeständen zu liefern, die Integration des Waffensystems in ukrainische Flugzeuge zu unterstützen, ukrainische Soldaten auszubilden, Hemmnisse bei der Weitergabe sensibler Informationen zu beseitigen, Ausrüstungslücken bei der Bundeswehr durch Nachbeschaffung zu schließen, die Produktionskapazitäten der Industrie zu erhöhen und weitere Taurus-Marschflugkörper zu beschaffen. Der Antrag wird abgelehnt.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>20. März 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/64"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Steuervergünstigung für Agrardiesel (Antrag AfD)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Landwirtschaft</span><span data-slot="badge">Steuerpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Subventionen</span><span data-slot="badge">Haushaltspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Agrardiesel</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Antrag der AfD-Fraktion, die Steuervergünstigung für Agrardiesel beizubehalten, um die deutsche Landwirtschaft nicht zusätzlich zu belasten und die Lebensmittelpreise nicht künstlich zu verteuern. Der Antrag sieht vor, Kürzungen in anderen Bereichen des Haushalts vorzunehmen, falls Einsparungen notwendig sind, und die Bundesregierung aufzufordern, Beschlüsse der Parlamentsgremien zu respektieren.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>21. März 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/65"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Bundeswehreinsatz SEA GUARDIAN im Mittelmeer (Antrag BReg)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Militär</span><span data-slot="badge">NATO</span><span data-slot="badge">Mittelmeer</span><span data-slot="badge">Terrorismusbekämpfung</span><span data-slot="badge">Internationale Beziehungen</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Fortsetzung der Beteiligung bewaffneter deutscher Streitkräfte an der NATO-geführten maritimen Sicherheitsoperation SEA GUARDIAN (MSO SG) im Mittelmeer, um zur Sicherheit und Stabilität in der Region beizutragen. Der Deutsche Bundestag stimmt über den Antrag der Bundesregierung zur Verlängerung dieses Einsatzes ab.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/66"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Bundeswehreinsatz in der Republik Südsudan (UNMISS)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Verteidigung</span><span data-slot="badge">Humanitäre Hilfe</span><span data-slot="badge">Friedensmission</span><span data-slot="badge">UN</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Fortsetzung der Beteiligung bewaffneter deutscher Streitkräfte an der UN-Friedensmission UNMISS (United Nations Mission in South Sudan) in der Republik Südsudan. Es geht darum, ob der Bundestag der von der Bundesregierung beschlossenen Verlängerung des Einsatzes zustimmt.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>12. April 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/67"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Selbstbestimmung in Bezug auf den Geschlechtseintrag</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Gesellschaftspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Gleichstellung</span><span data-slot="badge">Selbstbestimmung</span><span data-slot="badge">Transgender</span><span data-slot="badge">Recht</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Entwurf eines Gesetzes über die Selbstbestimmung in Bezug auf den Geschlechtseintrag und zur Änderung weiterer Vorschriften. Das Gesetz zielt darauf ab, die Regelungen zur Änderung des Geschlechtseintrags zu vereinfachen und zu vereinheitlichen.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/68"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Änderung des Energiewirtschaftsgesetzes</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Energiewirtschaft</span><span data-slot="badge">Wasserstoff</span><span data-slot="badge">Infrastruktur</span><span data-slot="badge">Netzentwicklung</span><span data-slot="badge">Finanzierung</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft ein Gesetz zur Änderung des Energiewirtschaftsgesetzes (EnWG), um den Aufbau einer nationalen Wasserstoffinfrastruktur zu fördern und die Finanzierung des Wasserstoff-Kernnetzes zu regeln.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>25. April 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/141"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Operation EUNAVFOR MED IRINI (Beschlussempfehlung)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Europäische Union</span><span data-slot="badge">Militär</span><span data-slot="badge">Libyen</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Fortsetzung der Beteiligung bewaffneter deutscher Streitkräfte an der Operation EUNAVFOR MED IRINI der Europäischen Union. Ziel ist es, das Waffenembargo gegen Libyen weiterhin durchzusetzen und zur Stabilisierung des Landes beizutragen.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>26. April 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/69"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Erneuerbare-Energien-Gesetz (Solarpaket)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Erneuerbare Energien</span><span data-slot="badge">Photovoltaik</span><span data-slot="badge">Klimaschutz</span><span data-slot="badge">Energiewende</span><span data-slot="badge">Bürokratieabbau</span><span data-slot="badge">Netzausbau</span></p><p>Das Gesetz zur Änderung des Erneuerbare-Energien-Gesetzes (EEG) zielt darauf ab, den Ausbau der Photovoltaik (PV) in Deutschland zu beschleunigen und zu steigern, um die Klimaziele zu erreichen. Es werden Anreize für Solaranlagen geschaffen und Bürokratie abgebaut.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>16. Mai 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/70"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Ablehnung eines Antrags gegen den WHO-Pandemievertrag</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Gesundheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Internationale Beziehungen</span><span data-slot="badge">Souveränität</span><span data-slot="badge">WHO</span><span data-slot="badge">Pandemie</span><span data-slot="badge">Demokratie</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Antrag der AfD-Fraktion, den WHO-Pandemievertrag und die überarbeiteten Internationalen Gesundheitsvorschriften abzulehnen. Der Antrag zielt darauf ab, die Souveränität Deutschlands in Gesundheitsfragen zu wahren und eine vermeintliche Machtausweitung der WHO zu verhindern.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>05. Juni 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/71"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Ablehnung eines Antrags zur Abschaffung des Solidaritätszuschlags</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Steuerpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Finanzen</span><span data-slot="badge">Wirtschaft</span><span data-slot="badge">Solidaritätszuschlag</span><span data-slot="badge">Abgabenlast</span><span data-slot="badge">Steuerreform</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Antrag der AfD-Fraktion zur Abschaffung des Solidaritätszuschlags als ersten Schritt einer umfassenden Steuerreform zur Entlastung von Mittelstand, Unternehmen und Arbeitnehmern. Der Finanzausschuss empfiehlt die Ablehnung des Antrags.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>06. Juni 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/72"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Ablehnung eines Antrags zur Bekämpfung des politischen Islam</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Inneres und Heimat</span><span data-slot="badge">Politischer Islam</span><span data-slot="badge">Demokratie</span><span data-slot="badge">Recht</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Migration</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Antrag der CDU/CSU-Fraktion, den politischen Islam als Gefahr für die freiheitliche Demokratie wirksam zu bekämpfen. Der Ausschuss für Inneres und Heimat empfiehlt die Ablehnung des Antrags.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/73"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Beschleunigung immissionsschutzrechtlicher Genehmigungsverfahren</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Umwelt</span><span data-slot="badge">Klimaschutz</span><span data-slot="badge">Energie</span><span data-slot="badge">Wirtschaft</span><span data-slot="badge">Genehmigungsverfahren</span><span data-slot="badge">Erneuerbare Energien</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft ein Gesetz zur Verbesserung des Klimaschutzes, zur Beschleunigung von Genehmigungsverfahren im Immissionsschutz und zur Umsetzung von EU-Recht, mit dem Ziel, Verfahren zu vereinfachen und den Ausbau erneuerbarer Energien zu fördern.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>13. Juni 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/74"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Antrag zu Konsequenzen aus dem Terror von Mannheim</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Innere Sicherheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Migration</span><span data-slot="badge">Integration</span><span data-slot="badge">Terrorismusbekämpfung</span><span data-slot="badge">Rechtspolitik</span></p><p>Der Antrag der CDU/CSU-Fraktion betrifft die Forderung nach klaren Konsequenzen aus dem Terroranschlag von Mannheim und zielt darauf ab, die Migrations- und Integrationspolitik zu verschärfen sowie die Sicherheitsmaßnahmen zu erhöhen.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/75"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Ablehnung eines Antrags zum Verbot des Vereins Muslim Interaktiv</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Inneres und Heimat</span><span data-slot="badge">Vereinsrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Extremismus</span><span data-slot="badge">Islamismus</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Antrag der AfD-Fraktion, den Verein Muslim Interaktiv zu verbieten, da dieser als extremistisch und gegen die freiheitliche demokratische Grundordnung gerichtet angesehen wird. Der Bundestag lehnt den Antrag ab.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/76"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Antrag zum Eintritt in die zweite Beratung zur Aufhebung des Lieferkettengesetzes</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Wirtschaft</span><span data-slot="badge">Recht</span><span data-slot="badge">Soziales</span><span data-slot="badge">Europäische Union</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft einen Antrag der CDU/CSU-Fraktion, direkt in die zweite Beratung eines Gesetzentwurfs zur Aufhebung des Lieferkettensorgfaltspflichtengesetzes (LkSG) einzutreten.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>27. Juni 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/77"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Bundeswehreinsatz EUFOR ALTHEA</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Europäische Union</span><span data-slot="badge">Bundeswehr</span><span data-slot="badge">Bosnien und Herzegowina</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Fortsetzung der Beteiligung bewaffneter deutscher Streitkräfte an der EU-geführten Sicherheitsoperation EUFOR ALTHEA in Bosnien und Herzegowina bis zum 30. Juni 2025.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/78"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Bundeswehreinsatz im Kosovo (KFOR)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Verteidigung</span><span data-slot="badge">Kosovo</span><span data-slot="badge">Bundeswehr</span><span data-slot="badge">Internationale Beziehungen</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Fortsetzung der Beteiligung bewaffneter deutscher Streitkräfte an der internationalen Sicherheitspräsenz im Kosovo (KFOR). Es geht darum, das Mandat für den Einsatz der Bundeswehr im Rahmen von KFOR zu verlängern.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/79"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Bundeswehreinsatz im Libanon (UNIFIL)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Bundeswehr</span><span data-slot="badge">Libanon</span><span data-slot="badge">UNIFIL</span><span data-slot="badge">Friedensmission</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Fortsetzung der Beteiligung bewaffneter deutscher Streitkräfte an der "United Nations Interim Force in Lebanon" (UNIFIL), einer Friedensmission der Vereinten Nationen im Libanon. Es geht um die Verlängerung des Mandats und die damit verbundenen Aufgaben und Befugnisse der deutschen Soldaten.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>05. Juli 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/80"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Änderung des Schwangerschaftskonfliktgesetzes</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Soziales</span><span data-slot="badge">Familie</span><span data-slot="badge">Frauenrechte</span><span data-slot="badge">Gesundheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Recht</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Änderung des Schwangerschaftskonfliktgesetzes (SchKG) und zielt darauf ab, einen bundeseinheitlichen und rechtssicheren Umgang mit sogenannten Gehsteigbelästigungen vor Schwangerschaftsberatungsstellen und Einrichtungen zur Vornahme von Schwangerschaftsabbrüchen sicherzustellen.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>17. Oktober 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/81"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Entwurf zur Aufhebung des Lieferkettengesetzes</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Wirtschaft</span><span data-slot="badge">Menschenrechte</span><span data-slot="badge">Umwelt</span><span data-slot="badge">Lieferketten</span><span data-slot="badge">Gesetzgebung</span><span data-slot="badge">Europäische Union</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Gesetzentwurf der CDU/CSU zur Aufhebung des Lieferkettensorgfaltspflichtengesetzes (LkSG), das Unternehmen zur Einhaltung von Menschenrechten in ihren Lieferketten verpflichtet.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/82"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Gesetzentwurf zur Krankenhausreform</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Gesundheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Krankenhaus</span><span data-slot="badge">Versorgung</span><span data-slot="badge">Finanzierung</span><span data-slot="badge">Qualitätssicherung</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Entwurf eines Gesetzes zur Verbesserung der Versorgungsqualität im Krankenhaus und zur Reform der Vergütungsstrukturen (KHVVG), das darauf abzielt, die Krankenhausversorgung zu verbessern und die Finanzierung zu reformieren.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/83"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Bundeswehreinsatz im Irak</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Außenpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheitspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Militär</span><span data-slot="badge">Irak</span><span data-slot="badge">Terrorismusbekämpfung</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Fortsetzung des Einsatzes bewaffneter deutscher Streitkräfte im Irak, um die Stabilisierung des Landes zu sichern, ein Wiedererstarken des IS (Islamischer Staat) zu verhindern und die Versöhnung im Irak zu fördern. Der Bundestag stimmt über den Antrag der Bundesregierung ab, diesen Einsatz bis zum 31. Januar 2026 mit bis zu 500 Soldatinnen und Soldaten zu verlängern.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>18. Oktober 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/84"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Änderungsantrag zur „Verbesserung der inneren Sicherheit“</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Innere Sicherheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Asylrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Migrationspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Grenzschutz</span><span data-slot="badge">Terrorismusbekämpfung</span><span data-slot="badge">Waffenrecht</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft einen Änderungsantrag der CDU/CSU-Fraktion zu einem Gesetzentwurf, der die innere Sicherheit und das Asylsystem verbessern soll, insbesondere durch Änderungen im Asylgesetz und im Ausweisungsrecht.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/85"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Artikel 5 des Entwurfs „Verbesserung der inneren Sicherheit“ (2. Beratung)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Inneres</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Waffenrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Extremismus</span><span data-slot="badge">Terrorismus</span><span data-slot="badge">Öffentliche Sicherheit</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft Artikel 5 eines Gesetzentwurfs, der darauf abzielt, das Waffenrecht zu verschärfen, um Extremisten und Terroristen den Zugang zu Waffen zu erschweren und die öffentliche Sicherheit zu erhöhen.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/86"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Gesetzentwurf „Verbesserung der Terrorismusbekämpfung“</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Innere Sicherheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Terrorismusbekämpfung</span><span data-slot="badge">Extremismusprävention</span><span data-slot="badge">Datenschutz</span><span data-slot="badge">Bürgerrechte</span><span data-slot="badge">Waffenrecht</span></p><p>Der Gesetzentwurf zur Verbesserung der Terrorismusbekämpfung zielt darauf ab, den Sicherheitsbehörden im digitalen Raum zusätzliche Befugnisse zu geben und die Zusammenarbeit zwischen Bund, Ländern und zivilgesellschaftlichen Akteuren zu stärken, um extremistischen und islamistischen Tendenzen entgegenzuwirken.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/87"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Gesetzentwurf „Verbesserung der inneren Sicherheit“</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Innere Sicherheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Asylrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Waffenrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Extremismus</span><span data-slot="badge">Terrorismusbekämpfung</span></p><p>Der Gesetzentwurf zur Verbesserung der inneren Sicherheit und des Asylsystems betrifft die Anpassung von Gesetzen, um die innere Sicherheit Deutschlands zu stärken und das Asylsystem effektiver zu gestalten. Er reagiert auf aktuelle Bedrohungen und soll den Behörden mehr Handlungsspielraum geben.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/88"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Erster Entschließungsantrag zur „Verbesserung der inneren Sicherheit“</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Innere Sicherheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Asylpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Migrationspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Waffenrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Islamismus</span><span data-slot="badge">Extremismusbekämpfung</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Entschließungsantrag der CDU/CSU zum Gesetzentwurf zur Verbesserung der inneren Sicherheit und des Asylsystems, der sich mit der Migrationspolitik, dem Waffenrecht und der Bekämpfung des Islamismus auseinandersetzt.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/89"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Zweiter Entschließungsantrag zur „Verbesserung der inneren Sicherheit“</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Innere Sicherheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Asylpolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Waffenrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Migrationspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Extremismusprävention</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft einen Entschließungsantrag der CDU/CSU zum Gesetzentwurf zur Verbesserung der inneren Sicherheit und des Asylsystems, der sich gegen die Schwerpunkte der Regierungsfraktionen im Bereich Waffenrecht richtet und stattdessen eine andere Migrations- und Sicherheitspolitik fordert.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/90"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Dritter Entschließungsantrag zur „Verbesserung der inneren Sicherheit“</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Innere Sicherheit</span><span data-slot="badge">Asylrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Migration</span><span data-slot="badge">Grenzschutz</span><span data-slot="badge">EU-Recht</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft einen Entschließungsantrag der CDU/CSU-Fraktion zu einem Gesetzentwurf, der die innere Sicherheit und das Asylsystem verbessern soll. Der Antrag zielt darauf ab, die Bundesregierung zu umfassenden Zurückweisungen von Personen ohne Einreiserecht an den deutschen Grenzen aufzufordern.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/91"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Ablehnung eines Antrags zu Messerangriffen</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Inneres</span><span data-slot="badge">Recht</span><span data-slot="badge">Kriminalität</span><span data-slot="badge">Waffenrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Migration</span><span data-slot="badge">Sicherheit</span></p><p>Die Beschlussempfehlung des Ausschusses für Inneres und Heimat betrifft die Ablehnung eines Antrags der AfD-Fraktion, der eine gezielte Sanktionierung von Messerangriffen anstelle von Verschärfungen im Waffenrecht fordert.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/92"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Ablehnung eines Antrags zu Drittstaatenangehörigen</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Asylrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Migrationspolitik</span><span data-slot="badge">Grenzkontrolle</span><span data-slot="badge">Rücknahmeabkommen</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft den Antrag der AfD-Fraktion, die Bundesregierung zu verpflichten, Drittstaatsangehörige an den Außengrenzen Deutschlands zurückzuweisen und bilaterale Rücknahmeabkommen mit Nachbarstaaten anzuwenden.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>16. Dezember 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/93"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Antrag gemäß Artikel 68 des Grundgesetzes (Vertrauensfrage)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Politik</span><span data-slot="badge">Regierung</span><span data-slot="badge">Grundgesetz</span><span data-slot="badge">Vertrauensfrage</span></p><p>Die Abstimmung betrifft die Vertrauensfrage gemäß Artikel 68 des Grundgesetzes, bei der der Bundeskanzler das Vertrauen des Bundestages ausspricht. Der Bundeskanzler beabsichtigt, vor der Abstimmung eine Erklärung abzugeben.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a><p><h2>19. Dezember 2024</h2><hr></p><a href="https://abstimmung.eu/votes/94"><div data-slot="card"><div><h3 lang="de">Gesetzentwurf zur Änderung von Artikel 93 und 94 des Grundgesetzes (Bundesverfassungsgericht)</h3><p><span data-slot="badge">Verfassungsrecht</span><span data-slot="badge">Bundesverfassungsgericht</span><span data-slot="badge">Rechtsstaat</span><span data-slot="badge">Politik</span><span data-slot="badge">Justiz</span></p><p>Der Gesetzentwurf betrifft die Änderung des Grundgesetzes in Bezug auf die Stellung und Struktur des Bundesverfassungsgerichts, indem Artikel 93 und 94 punktuell ergänzt und deren Inhalte systematisch neu geordnet werden. Ziel ist es, die Organqualität des Bundesverfassungsgerichts sowie die unmittelbare Bindung der öffentlichen Gewalt an seine Entscheidungen stärker hervorzuheben.</p></div><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M3 3v16a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h16"></path><path d="M18 17V9"></path><path d="M13 17V5"></path><path d="M8 17v-3"></path></svg><h4>Ergebnisse des Bundestags</h4></p></div></div></a></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Arc-AGI-2 and ARC Prize 2025 (147 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arcprize.org/blog/announcing-arc-agi-2-and-arc-prize-2025</link>
            <guid>43465147</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 20:35:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arcprize.org/blog/announcing-arc-agi-2-and-arc-prize-2025">https://arcprize.org/blog/announcing-arc-agi-2-and-arc-prize-2025</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43465147">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
		

<div>
    <p><a href="https://arcprize.org/arc-agi#arc-agi-2"><img src="https://arcprize.org/media/images/blog/arc-agi-2-years.jpg" alt="ARC-AGI-2 challenges test-time reasoning"></a>
    </p>
    <p><a href="https://arcprize.org/competition"><img src="https://arcprize.org/media/images/blog/arc-prize-2025-card.png" alt="Launching ARC Prize 2025"></a>
    </p>
</div>

<h3 id="level-up-to-reach-agi">Level Up to Reach AGI</h3>

<p>Good AGI benchmarks act as useful progress indicators. Better AGI benchmarks clearly discern capabilities. The best AGI benchmarks do all this and actively inspire research and guide innovation.</p>

<p>At ARC Prize, our mission is to serve as a North Star towards AGI through enduring benchmarks, directing efforts towards systems capable of general intelligence and significantly compressing the timeline for scientific breakthroughs.</p>

<p>ARC-AGI-1 has measured progress towards AGI since 2019 and was the only benchmark to <a href="https://arcprize.org/oai-o3-pub-breakthrough">pinpoint the exact moment in late 2024</a> when AI moved beyond pure memorization. OpenAI used ARC-AGI-1 to demonstrate this progress with their o3 system which combines deep learning-based LLMs with reasoning synthesis engines.</p>

<p>ARC Prize 2024 inspired thousands of independent <a href="https://arcprize.org/blog/2024-university-tour-recap">students</a> and <a href="https://arcprize.org/2024-results">researchers</a> to work alongside frontier labs on new test-time adaption ideas.</p>

<p>But there is more work to do to reach AGI. AGI still needs new ideas.</p>

<p>We can characterize systems like o3 as going from "zero to one" on the fluid intelligence spectrum. But these systems are highly inefficient and currently require significant human supervision during the training process to adapt to new domains.</p>

<h4 id="announcements">Announcements</h4>

<p>Today we’re excited to launch ARC-AGI-2 to challenge the new frontier. ARC-AGI-2 is even harder for AI (in particular, AI reasoning systems), while maintaining the same relative ease for humans. Pure LLMs score 0% on ARC-AGI-2, and public AI reasoning systems achieve only single-digit percentage scores. In contrast, every task in ARC-AGI-2 has been solved by at least 2 humans in under 2 attempts.</p>

<p>Alongside it, today we're announcing <a href="https://arcprize.org/competition">ARC Prize 2025</a> (going live on Kaggle this week), designed to drive open-source progress on highly efficient, general systems capable of beating ARC-AGI-2.</p>

<hr>

<h3 id="easy-for-humans-hard-for-ai">Easy for Humans, Hard for AI</h3>

<p>All other AI benchmarks focus on superhuman capabilities or specialized knowledge by testing "PhD++" skills. ARC-AGI is the only benchmark that takes the opposite design choice – by focusing on tasks that are relatively easy for humans, yet hard, or impossible, for AI, we shine a spotlight on capability gaps that do not spontaneously emerge from "scaling up".</p>

<p>The ARC Prize Foundation adapts this into our definition for measuring AGI: the gap between the set of tasks that are easy for humans and hard for AI. When this gap is zero, when there are no remaining tasks, we can find that challenge AI, we will have achieved AGI.</p>

<p>Addressing these capability gaps requires novel insight and new ideas. Importantly, ARC-AGI does not exist purely to measure AGI progress. It also exists to inspire researchers to work on new ideas.</p>

<p>Intelligence requires the ability to generalize from limited experience and apply knowledge in new, unexpected situations. AI systems are already superhuman in many specific domains (e.g., playing Go and image recognition.) However, these are narrow, specialized capabilities. The "human-ai gap" reveals what's missing for general intelligence - highly efficiently acquiring new skills.</p>

<hr>

<h3 id="introducing-arc-agi-2">Introducing ARC-AGI-2</h3>

<p>The ARC-AGI-2 benchmark launches today. This second edition in the ARC-AGI series raises the bar for difficulty for AI while maintaining the same relative ease for humans.</p>

<p>Every ARC-AGI-2 task was solved by at least 2 humans in 2 attempts or less in a controlled study with hundreds of human participants. This matches the rules we hold for AI, which gets two attempts per task.</p>

<p>ARC-AGI-1, introduced in 2019, was designed to challenge deep learning. Specifically, it was designed to resist the ability to simply "memorize" the training dataset. ARC-AGI comprises a training dataset and several evaluation sets, including a private eval set used for the ARC Prize 2024 contest. The training set is intended to teach the Core Knowledge Priors required to solve tasks in the evaluation sets. To solve the evaluation tasks, AI systems must demonstrate basic fluid intelligence or the ability to adapt to novel, never-before-seen tasks.</p>

<p>As an analogy, think of the training set as a way to learn grade school math symbols, and the evaluation set requires you to solve algebra equations using your knowledge of those symbols. You cannot simply memorize your way to the answer, you must apply existing knowledge to new problems.</p>

<p>Any AI system capable of beating ARC-AGI-1 demonstrates a binary level of fluid intelligence. In contrast, ARC-AGI-2 significantly raises the bar for AI. To beat it, you must demonstrate <em>both</em> a high level of adaptability and high efficiency.</p>

<p>While designing ARC-AGI-2, we studied these properties of frontier AI reasoning systems. Below are example tasks to illustrate some of what we discovered. All of the following tasks are part of ARC-AGI-2 and were (1) solved by at least 2 humans in under 2 attempts and (2) unsolved by any frontier AI reasoning system.</p>

<p><em>Note: special thank you to the ARC Prize community for contributing to this analysis, including <a href="https://substack.com/home/post/p-153619775">Mace</a>, <a href="https://anokas.substack.com/p/llms-struggle-with-perception-not-reasoning-arcagi">Mikel</a>, and many members in the <a href="https://discord.com/channels/1237180803335720961/1319729162466099290">ARC Prize Discord</a>.</em></p>

<hr>

<h3 id="still-hard-for-ai">Still Hard for AI</h3>

<h4 id="symbolic-interpretation">Symbolic Interpretation</h4>

<p>We found that frontier AI reasoning systems struggle with tasks requiring symbols to be interpreted as having meaning beyond their visual patterns. Systems attempted symmetry checking, mirroring, transformations, and even recognized connecting elements, but failed to assign semantic significance to the symbols themselves.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://arcprize.org/media/images/blog/arc-agi-2-unsolved-1.png" alt="ARC-AGI-2 Pubic Eval Task: #e3721c99">
  <figcaption>Example of symbolic interpretation, ARC-AGI-2 Pubic Eval Task #e3721c99. <a href="https://arcprize.org/play?id=e3721c99" target="_blank">Try this task.</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<h4 id="compositional-reasoning">Compositional Reasoning</h4>

<p>We found AI reasoning systems struggle with tasks requiring simultaneous application of rules, or application of multiple rules that interact with each other. In contrast, if a task only has one, or very few, global rules, we found these systems can consistently discover and apply them.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://arcprize.org/media/images/blog/arc-agi-2-unsolved-2.png" alt="ARC-AGI-2 Pubic Eval Task: #cbebaa4b">
  <figcaption>Example of compositional reasoning, ARC-AGI-2 Pubic Eval Task #cbebaa4b. <a href="https://arcprize.org/play?id=cbebaa4b" target="_blank">Try this task.</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<h4 id="contextual-rule-application">Contextual Rule Application</h4>

<p>We found AI reasoning systems struggle with tasks where rules must be applied differently based on context. Systems tend to fixate on superficial patterns rather than understanding the underlying selection principles.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://arcprize.org/media/images/blog/arc-agi-2-unsolved-3.png" alt="ARC-AGI-2 Pubic Eval Task: #b5ca7ac4">
  <figcaption>Example of contextual rule application, ARC-AGI-2 Pubic Eval Task #b5ca7ac4. <a href="https://arcprize.org/play?id=b5ca7ac4" target="_blank">Try this task.</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<hr>

<h3 id="datasets">Datasets</h3>

<p>ARC-AGI-2 is comprised of the following datasets:</p>

<table>
    <tbody><tr>
        <th>Dataset</th>
        <th>Task Quantity</th>
        <th>Calibration</th>
        <th>Visibilty</th>
        <th>Description</th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td><a href="https://github.com/arcprize/ARC-AGI-2/tree/main/data/training">Training</a></td>
        <td>1000</td>
        <td>Uncalibrated</td>
        <td>Public</td>
        <td>A spectrum of difficulty ranging from very easy to very difficult for both humans and AI, designed to expose and teach Core Knowledge Priors; use to train your system.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td><a href="https://github.com/arcprize/ARC-AGI-2/tree/main/data/evaluation">Public Eval</a></td>
        <td>120</td>
        <td>Calibrated</td>
        <td>Public</td>
        <td>All tasks solved pass@2 by at least two humans; use to test your system.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td><a href="https://arcprize.org/guide#semi-private">Semi-Private Eval</a></td>
        <td>120</td>
        <td>Calibrated</td>
        <td>Private</td>
        <td>All tasks solved pass@2 by at least two humans, used for the Kaggle live contest leaderboard and ARC Prize leaderboard. "Semi" means these tasks may have been exposed to limited third-parties (e.g., via API.)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td><a href="https://arcprize.org/guide#private">Private Eval</a></td>
        <td>120</td>
        <td>Calibrated</td>
        <td>Private</td>
        <td>All tasks solved pass@2 by at least two humans, used for Kaggle final contest leaderboard. "Private" means these tasks have not been exposed to third-parties.</td>
    </tr>
</tbody></table>

<p><code>Calibrated</code> means that these tasks are IDD (independent and identically distributed). In principle, non-overfit scores across the public, semi-private, and private eval sets should be directly comparable. To gather these data, we tested with over 400 humans live in a controlled setting. Human solvability data for public tasks will be open-sourced alongside the ARC-AGI-2 paper in the coming weeks.</p>

<p>Like ARC-AGI-1, ARC-AGI-2 uses a <code>pass@2</code> measurement system to account for the fact that certain tasks have explicit ambiguity and require two guesses to disambiguate. As well as to catch any unintentional ambiguity or mistakes in the dataset. Given controlled human testing with ARC-AGI-2, we are more confident in the task quality compared to ARC-AGI-1.</p>

<p>Here's the official <code>changelog</code> for ARC-AGI-2:</p>

<ol>
    <li>All eval sets (public, semi-private, private) now contain 120 tasks (up from 100).</li>
    <li>Removed tasks from eval sets that were susceptible to brute force search (all solved tasks from the original <a href="https://www.kaggle.com/competitions/abstraction-and-reasoning-challenge">2020 Kaggle contest</a>).</li>
    <li>Performed controlled human testing to calibrate eval set difficulty to ensure IDD and verify pass@2 solvability by at least 2 humans (to match AI rules).</li>
    <li>Designed new tasks to challenge AI reasoning systems based on study (symbolic interpretation, compositional reasoning, contextual rules, and more).</li>
</ol>

<p>We've also re-evaluated ARC-AGI-2 against all public AI systems. Here are the starting scores.</p>

<table>
    <tbody><tr>
        <td><b>System</b></td>
        <td><b>ARC-AGI-1</b></td>
        <td><b>ARC-AGI-2</b></td>
        <td><b>Efficiency (cost/task)</b></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>Human panel (at least 2 humans)</td>
        <td>98%</td>
        <td>100%</td>
        <td>$17</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>Human panel (average)</td>
        <td>64.2%</td>
        <td>60%</td>
        <td>$17</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>o3-low (CoT + Search/Synthesis)</td>
        <td>75.7%</td>
        <td>4%*</td>
        <td>$200</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>o1-pro (CoT + Search/Synthesis)</td>
        <td>~50%</td>
        <td>1%*</td>
        <td>$200*</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>ARChitects (Kaggle 2024 Winner)</td>
        <td>53.5%</td>
        <td>3%</td>
        <td>$0.25</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>o3-mini-high (Single CoT)</td>
        <td>35%</td>
        <td>0.0%</td>
        <td>$0.41</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>r1 and r1-zero (Single CoT)</td>
        <td>15.8%</td>
        <td>0.3%</td>
        <td>$0.08</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>gpt-4.5 (Pure LLM)</td>
        <td>10.3%</td>
        <td>0.0%</td>
        <td>$0.29</td>
    </tr>
</tbody></table>

<p><em>Scores labeled with * are in-progress estimates based on partial results we've been able to aggregate so far and o1-pro pricing. Full results will be published once available.</em></p>

<p>All scores reported pass@2 and on the semi-private eval set (except ARC-AGI-1 human panel and ARChitects, which used public and private eval, respectively).</p>

<p>Human panel efficiency is based upon a $115-150 show-up fee, plus a $5/task solve incentive. We optimized costs to produce show-ups (only 70% of registrations actually showed up). Even though we believe the true limit to human intelligence cost efficiency is likely in the $2-5/task range, we report $17/task to reflect the actual data we collected.</p>

<p>We are looking forward to testing the production version of OpenAI o3 low/high once API access is available. Using ARC-AGI-1 tasks that transferred to ARC-AGI-2, we estimate that o3-low would score ~4% and o3-high would potentially score up to 15-20% with very high compute (thousands of dollars per task).</p>

<hr>

<h3 id="intelligence-is-not-just-capability">Intelligence Is Not Just Capability</h3>

<p>Going forward, all ARC-AGI reporting will come along with an efficiency metric. We are starting with cost because it is the most directly comparable between human and AI performance.</p>

<p>Intelligence is not solely defined by the ability to solve problems or achieve high scores. The efficiency with which those capabilities are acquired and deployed is a crucial, defining component. The core question being asked is not just, "Can AI acquire skill to solve a task?" but also, "At what efficiency or cost?"</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://arcprize.org/media/images/arc-agi-2-efficiency.jpg" alt="ARC-AGI-2: Scale is Not Enough">
  <figcaption>Frontier AI system scores on ARC-AGI-1 vs. ARC-AGI-2</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>We know that brute-force search could eventually solve ARC-AGI (given unlimited resources and time to search). This would not represent true intelligence. Intelligence is about finding the solution efficiently, not exhaustively.</p>

<p>This focus on efficiency is a core principle behind the ARC-AGI. We will now explicitly quantify the cost of intelligence, requiring solutions to demonstrate not just capability, but also the efficient use of resources that defines general intelligence.</p>

<p>Our <a href="https://arcprize.org/leaderboard">new leaderboard page</a> reports progress along both a score and cost axis.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://arcprize.org/media/images/leaderboard-20250323.png" alt="ARC-AGI new leaderboard">
  <figcaption>ARC-AGI's new leaderboard showing both score and efficiency as of March 24, 2025</figcaption>
</figure>

<hr>

<h3 id="competition-goes-live-this-week-1000000-in-prizes">Competition Goes Live this Week! $1,000,000 in Prizes</h3>

<p>
<iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/z6cTTkVqAyg?si=ndNcx1LavLvp2sQ8&amp;controls=0" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</p>

<!--Alongside ARC-AGI-2, we're excited to announce the <a href="https://www.kaggle.com/competitions/arc-prize-2025">ARC Prize 2025 Kaggle Competition</a>.-->
<p>Alongside ARC-AGI-2, we're excited to announce <a href="https://arcprize.org/competition">ARC Prize 2025 is back</a>! The contest will be again hosted on Kaggle between March and November. The competition goes live later this week, sign up <a href="#" data-modal-id="signup">here</a> to get notified.</p>

<p>There is $125K in guaranteed progress prizes, with an additional $700K Grand Prize (up $100k from last year!) waiting to be unlocked by a solution that scores greater than 85%, as well as $175K to-be-announced prizes.</p>

<p>Unlike the <a href="https://arcprize.org/leaderboard">public leaderboard</a> on arcprize.org, Kaggle rules restrict you from using internet APIs, and you only get ~$50 worth of compute per submission. In order to be eligible for prizes, contestants must open source and share their solution and work into the public domain at the end of the competition.</p>

<p>Last year's competition saw incredible success — over 1,500 teams participated, generating 40 influential research papers. ARC Prize-winning researchers introduced innovations now adopted across the AI industry.</p>

<p>What progress can you unlock and share with the world this year?</p>

<h4 id="prize-categories">Prize Categories</h4>

<p><strong>Grand Prize ($700K)</strong><br>
Unlocked once first team reaches 85% within Kaggles efficiency limits.</p>

<p><strong>Top Score Prize ($75K)</strong><br>
Awarded to the highest-scoring submissions.</p>

<p><strong>Paper Prize ($50K)</strong><br>
Awarded to the submission demonstrating the most significant conceptual progress toward solving ARC-AGI. Papers must be tied to a scored submission, but innovative ideas matter more than achieving a high score.</p>

<p><strong>To-be-announced Prizes ($175k)</strong><br>
More details on these coming during the 2025 competition.</p>

<p>You can find more details on our <a href="https://arcprize.org/competition">Competition page</a>.</p>

<h4 id="changelog">Changelog</h4>

<p>Here's a quick look at the competition <code>changelog</code> from 2024 to 2025.</p>

<ol>
    <li><strong>ARC-AGI-2:</strong> we've replaced the ARC-AGI-1 dataset going forward.</li>
    <li><strong>New leaderboard reporting:</strong> The Kaggle live contest leaderboard will report scores on semi-private, with final prize results reported one time on the private eval after content closes.</li>
    <li><strong>Stronger open-source provisions:</strong> teams will be required to open source their solutions before receiving official private eval set scores.</li>
    <li><strong>More compute:</strong> 2x compute vs. 2024 (L4x4s), about $50 worth now.</li>
    <li><strong>More overfit prevention:</strong> we've made additional changes to score reporting on Kaggle to reduce data mining and overfiting and to incentivize conceptual progress.</li>
</ol>

<hr>

<h3 id="progress-depends-on-new-ideas--maybe-yours">Progress Depends On New Ideas — Maybe Yours?</h3>

<p>The current state of AI operates in an idea-constrained environment. The next breakthrough might not come from a major AI lab but from a new, creative approach from someone like you.</p>

<p>If you're driven by curiosity, inspired by complexity, and committed to the rigorous pursuit of genuine general intelligence, ARC Prize 2025 is your opportunity.</p>

<p>Join us in the pursuit of open science.</p>

<h4 id="ready-to-get-started">Ready to get started?</h4>

<p>Good luck! We can't wait to see what you build.</p>



	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Internet Archive Europe – Bringing Collections to Life (131 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.internetarchive.eu/</link>
            <guid>43464230</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 18:52:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.internetarchive.eu/">https://www.internetarchive.eu/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43464230">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content">

		
					<main id="main">
				<article class="page" id="post-282" itemtype="https://schema.org/CreativeWork" itemscope="itemscope">
	
				 <!-- .entry-header -->
		
<div data-ast-blocks-layout="true" itemprop="text">

	
	
<div><div><p><span>building</span></p><h2>Collective Intelligence</h2></div><p>Using AI Tools and our Shared Cultural Heritage</p><p><a href="https://www.internetarchive.eu/#contact" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer" onclick="return true;"><span>Get Involved</span><svg xmlns="https://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 512 512"><path d="M504.3 273.6l-112.1 104c-6.992 6.484-17.18 8.218-25.94 4.406c-8.758-3.812-14.42-12.45-14.42-21.1L351.9 288H32C14.33 288 .0002 273.7 .0002 255.1S14.33 224 32 224h319.9l0-72c0-9.547 5.66-18.19 14.42-22c8.754-3.809 18.95-2.075 25.94 4.41l112.1 104C514.6 247.9 514.6 264.1 504.3 273.6z"></path></svg></a></p></div>



<div>
<p>Internet Archive Europe is a project by the Dutch non-profit research library Stichting Internet Archive. It is building collections and tools to bring them to life.</p>



<p>Working with libraries, museums, and archives, we share these tools and collections to further everyone’s services.</p>
</div>



<div id="about">
<div><div><p>Our Journey</p><h2>Our role in Archiving and Preservation</h2></div><p>Internet Archive Europe began preserving European digital materials since its founding in 2004 in the Netherlands.  Then, working with dozens of European libraries and government agencies to build web collections, Internet Archive Europe prioritized collaboration with cultural heritage organizations to safeguard our collective history.<br></p></div>



<div><p><h2>Bringing research collections to life</h2></p><p>More recently, the library is leveraging AI and other tools to bring collections to life and demonstrate new interactions. If you would like to join us on these adventures, please contact us.<br></p></div>
</div>







<div id="team">
<p><h2>Our Team</h2></p>



<div>
<div id="beatrice"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Beatrice-Avatar-300x300.jpg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Beatrice Murch</h3><p><span>Program Manager</span></p><p>Beatrice returns to Non-Profit management after a long hiatus and is thrilled to once again be working to help preserve Universal Access to all Knowledge.</p></div>



<div id="ben"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/ben-cerveny-300x300.jpg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Ben Cerveny</h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>For over 25 years Ben Cerveny has worked as an executive, strategist, and designer in the context of operating systems, media applications, web services, products, the built environment, and digital games.</p></div>



<div id="bernt"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Bernt-Hugenholtz-crop-300x300.jpg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Bernt Hugenholtz</h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>Bernt Hugenholtz specializes in copyright, neighboring rights and information law. He is emeritus professor of Intellectual Property Law at the University of Amsterdam and former director of the Institute for Information Law (IViR).</p></div>



<div id="brewster"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Brewster-Kahle-300x300.jpeg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Brewster Kahle</h3><p><span>Board Member</span></p><p>A passionate advocate for public Internet access and a successful entrepreneur, Brewster Kahle has spent his career intent on a singular focus: providing Universal Access to All Knowledge. </p></div>



<div id="brigitte"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Brigitte_Veniza-150x150.jpeg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Brigitte Vezina </h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>Brigitte has a deep passion for issues raised by new and emerging technologies and loves to navigate uncharted waters to explore how the law, public policy, and evolving social frameworks can respond and anticipate challenges to the sharing of information, technological innovation, and new forms of creativity.</p></div>



<div id="daniel"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Daniel_Erasmus-150x150.jpeg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Daniel Erasmus</h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>Daniel has been and is facilitating scenario processes for diverse clients across three continents.&nbsp;Daniel pioneered the use of scenarios to facilitate deep dialogue about the emerging information society.&nbsp;</p></div>



<div id="edwin"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Edwin-van-Huis-LNKIN-150x150.jpeg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Edwin van Huis</h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>Edwin is the director of Naturalis Biodiversity Centre in Leiden. Previously he worked at the Rijksmuseum Amsterdam and at the Sound and Vision, the national archive for documentary film, television, radio and music, and the Ministry of Culture.</p></div>



<div id="jeff"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/JeffUbois-150x150.jpg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Jeff Ubois</h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>Jeff is a generalist with a background in philanthropy, innovation, media, archives, software, policy, research, venture-backed startups, and voluntary associations.</p></div>



<div id="jill"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Jill-Cousins-300x300.jpeg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Jill Cousins</h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>Jill Cousins continues the&nbsp;work with Digital Libraries&nbsp;and Europeana started in 2004&nbsp;advocating for&nbsp;digital transformation of cultural heritage, emphasizing the importance of open access, collaboration, and partnerships in making cultural heritage accessible to all.</p></div>



<div id="kaitlin"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/KaitlinThaney-300x300.jpg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Kaitlin Thaney</h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>Kaitlin Thaney’s career has been centered around open infrastructure organizations; helping them think strategically about program design, participatory engagement, and sustainability.</p></div>



<div id="marleen"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Marleen-Stikker-300x300.jpg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Marleen Stikker</h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>Marleen Stikker is founder and executive director of Waag Futurelab in Amsterdam. Waag has grown into a leading European research institute for technology and society, and encourages active citizenship by developing open, fair and inclusive technology.</p></div>



<div id="martin"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/martin-senftleben-150x150.jpg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Martin Senftleben</h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>Martin Senftleben is Professor of Intellectual Property Law and Director of the Institute for Information Law (IViR) at the Amsterdam Law School focusing on the reconciliation of private intellectual property rights with competing public interests of a social, cultural or economic nature.&nbsp;</p></div>



<div id="paul"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Paul_by_Stewart_Acker_Holt_CC_BY_b_w-300x300.jpg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Paul Keller</h3><p><span>Board Advisor</span></p><p>Paul is the Director of Policy at Open Future. He has 20+ years of experience as a media activist, open policy advocate and systems architect to improve access to knowledge and culture.&nbsp;</p></div>



<div id="tony"><p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.internetarchive.eu/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/TonyGuepin-300x300.jpeg" alt="" height="100" width="100" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Tony Guepin</h3><p><span>Board Member</span></p><p>A long-time Software Entrepreneur, Tony brings his knowledge and detailed overview to support Universal Access to All Knowledge as a member of the board of the Stichting Internet Archive.</p></div>
</div>
</div>







<div>
<div>
<p><h3>Impact in Numbers</h3></p>
</div>



<div>
<div><p><span data-duration="1.5" data-to-value="500" data-from-value="0" data-delimiter=","></span><span>+</span></p><p>Over 1 million cultural items digitally archived since our inception, making history accessible to everyone.</p></div>



<div><p><span data-duration="1.5" data-to-value="95" data-from-value="0" data-delimiter=","></span><span>%</span></p><p>More than 500 partnerships with libraries, museums, and educational institutions across Europe and beyond.</p></div>
</div>
</div>



<div><div><p>Take Action Today</p><h2>Support Cultural Heritage Preservation Efforts</h2></div><p>Join our community and help us ensure that Europe’s rich cultural history remains accessible to all.</p></div>

	
	
</div><!-- .entry-content .clear -->

	
	
</article><!-- #post-## -->

			</main><!-- #main -->
			
		
	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Qwen2.5-VL-32B: Smarter and Lighter (417 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://qwenlm.github.io/blog/qwen2.5-vl-32b/</link>
            <guid>43464068</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 18:35:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://qwenlm.github.io/blog/qwen2.5-vl-32b/">https://qwenlm.github.io/blog/qwen2.5-vl-32b/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43464068">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div><p><a href="https://chat.qwenlm.ai/" target="_blank">QWEN CHAT</a>
<a href="https://github.com/QwenLM/Qwen2.5-VL" target="_blank">GITHUB</a>
<a href="https://huggingface.co/collections/Qwen/qwen25-vl-6795ffac22b334a837c0f9a5" target="_blank">HUGGING FACE</a>
<a href="https://modelscope.cn/collections/Qwen25-VL-58fbb5d31f1d47" target="_blank">MODELSCOPE</a>
<a href="https://discord.gg/yPEP2vHTu4" target="_blank">DISCORD</a></p><h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2><p>At the end of January this year, we launched the Qwen2.5-VL series of models, which received widespread attention and positive feedback from the community. Building on the Qwen2.5-VL series, we continued to optimize the model using reinforcement learning and open-sourced the new VL model with the beloved 32B parameter scale under the Apache 2.0 license — <strong>Qwen2.5-VL-32B-Instruct</strong>. Compared to the previously released Qwen2.5-VL series models, the features of this 32B VL model are as follows:</p><ul><li><strong>Responses More Aligned with Human Preferences</strong>: Adjusted the output style to provide more detailed, better-formatted answers that align more closely with human preferences.</li><li><strong>Mathematical Reasoning</strong>: Significant improvement in the accuracy of solving complex mathematical problems.</li><li><strong>Fine-grained Image Understanding and Reasoning</strong>: Enhanced accuracy and detailed analysis in tasks such as image parsing, content recognition, and visual logic deduction.</li></ul><h2 id="performance">Performance</h2><p>Extensive benchmarking against state-of-the-art (SoTA) models of comparable scale, <strong>Qwen2.5-VL-32B-Instruct</strong> has demonstrated superiority over baselines, e.g., Mistral-Small-3.1-24B and Gemma-3-27B-IT, even surpassing the larger <strong>Qwen2-VL-72B-Instruct</strong>. Notably, it achieves significant advantages in multimodal tasks such as <strong>MMMU</strong>, <strong>MMMU-Pro</strong>, and <strong>MathVista</strong>, which focus on complex, multi-step reasoning. On <strong>MM-MT-Bench</strong>, a benchmark emphasizing subjective user experience evaluation, <strong>Qwen2.5-VL-32B-Instruct</strong> outperforms its predecessor <strong>Qwen2-VL-72B-Instruct</strong> by a substantial margin.</p><figure><img src="https://qianwen-res.oss-cn-beijing.aliyuncs.com/Qwen2.5-VL-32B/qwen2.5vl-32b-vision.jpg" width="100%"></figure><p>In addition to excelling in visual capabilities, Qwen2.5-VL-32B-Instruct has also achieved top-tier performance in pure text capabilities at the same scale.</p><figure><img src="https://qianwen-res.oss-cn-beijing.aliyuncs.com/Qwen2.5-VL-32B/qwen2.5vl-32b-text.jpg" width="100%"></figure><h2 id="demo-cases">Demo Cases</h2><div><p><span>Fine-grained Image Understanding and Reasoning</span>
<a>Next</a></p><div><p>User</p><p>I am driving a large truck on this road, and it is now 12 o’clock. Can I reach a place 110 kilometers away before 13 o’clock?
<img loading="lazy" src="https://qianwen-res.oss-cn-beijing.aliyuncs.com/Qwen2.5-VL-32B/reasoning.png" alt="image"></p><p>Qwen2.5-VL-32B</p><div><p>To determine whether you can reach a place 110 kilometers away before 13:00, we need to analyze the information provided:</p><ol><li><strong>Current Time</strong>: It is 12:00.</li><li><strong>Distance to Destination</strong>: 110 kilometers.</li><li><strong>Speed Limit for Trucks</strong>: The speed limit sign indicates that the maximum speed for trucks is <strong>100 km/h</strong>.</li></ol><h3 id="step-by-step-analysis">Step-by-Step Analysis:</h3><h4 id="1-calculate-the-required-travel-time">1. <strong>Calculate the Required Travel Time</strong></h4><p>The formula to calculate travel time is:
\[
\text{Time} = \frac{\text{Distance}}{\text{Speed}}
\]
Given:</p><ul><li>Distance = 110 km</li><li>Maximum Speed = 100 km/h</li></ul><p>Substitute the values:
\[
\text{Time} = \frac{110 \text{ km}}{100 \text{ km/h}} = 1.1 \text{ hours}
\]</p><h4 id="2-convert-time-to-hours-and-minutes">2. <strong>Convert Time to Hours and Minutes</strong></h4><p>1.1 hours is equivalent to:
\[
1 \text{ hour} + 0.1 \times 60 \text{ minutes} = 1 \text{ hour} + 6 \text{ minutes} = 1 \text{ hour and } 6 \text{ minutes}
\]</p><h4 id="3-determine-arrival-time">3. <strong>Determine Arrival Time</strong></h4><p>If you start at 12:00 and it takes 1 hour and 6 minutes to travel 110 kilometers, your arrival time will be:
\[
12:00 + 1 \text{ hour and } 6 \text{ minutes} = 13:06
\]</p><h4 id="4-compare-with-target-time">4. <strong>Compare with Target Time</strong></h4><p>You want to arrive before 13:00. However, based on the calculations, you will arrive at 13:06, which is <strong>after</strong> 13:00.</p><h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion:</h3><p>Given the speed limit of 100 km/h for trucks, it is <strong>not possible</strong> to reach a place 110 kilometers away before 13:00.</p><p>Thus, the final answer is:
\[
\boxed{\text{No}}
\]</p></div></div></div><h2 id="next-step">Next Step</h2><p>While <strong>Qwen2.5-VL-32B</strong> has focused on optimizing subjective experience and mathematical reasoning through reinforcement learning—operating within the paradigm of <strong>“fast thinking”</strong>. Our next research direction will prioritize <strong>long and effective reasoning processes</strong> to push the boundaries of visual models in tackling highly complex, multi-step visual reasoning tasks.</p><h2 id="citation">Citation</h2><p>If you find our model helpful, feel free to cite it:</p><pre tabindex="0"><code>@article{Qwen2.5-VL,
  title={Qwen2.5-VL Technical Report},
  author={Bai, Shuai and Chen, Keqin and Liu, Xuejing and Wang, Jialin and Ge, Wenbin and Song, Sibo and Dang, Kai and Wang, Peng and Wang, Shijie and Tang, Jun and Zhong, Humen and Zhu, Yuanzhi and Yang, Mingkun and Li, Zhaohai and Wan, Jianqiang and Wang, Pengfei and Ding, Wei and Fu, Zheren and Xu, Yiheng and Ye, Jiabo and Zhang, Xi and Xie, Tianbao and Cheng, Zesen and Zhang, Hang and Yang, Zhibo and Xu, Haiyang and Lin, Junyang},
  journal={arXiv preprint arXiv:2502.13923},
  year={2025}
}
</code></pre></div></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I won't connect my dishwasher to your cloud (486 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/i-wont-connect-my-dishwasher-your-stupid-cloud</link>
            <guid>43463200</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 17:09:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/i-wont-connect-my-dishwasher-your-stupid-cloud">https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/i-wont-connect-my-dishwasher-your-stupid-cloud</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43463200">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>This weekend I had to buy a new dishwasher because our old GE died.</p>

<p>I bought a Bosch 500 series because that's what Consumer Reports recommended, and more importantly, I could find one in stock.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/bosch-dishwasher-open.jpg" width="700" height="394" data-insert-type="image" data-entity-type="file" data-entity-uuid="insert-image-882e0a2c-ac38-4027-8ed5-62f41af514f4" data-insert-attach="{&quot;id&quot;:&quot;882e0a2c-ac38-4027-8ed5-62f41af514f4&quot;,&quot;attributes&quot;:{&quot;alt&quot;:[&quot;alt&quot;,&quot;description&quot;],&quot;title&quot;:[&quot;title&quot;]}}" alt="Bosch dishwasher open control panel"></p>

<p>After my dad and I got it installed, I went to run a rinse cycle, only to find that <em>that</em>, along with features like delayed start and eco mode, require an app.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/bosch-dishwasher-home-connect.jpg" width="700" height="394" data-insert-type="image" data-entity-type="file" data-entity-uuid="insert-image-75c66f24-bf26-4873-9ca6-695e60ce93df" data-insert-attach="{&quot;id&quot;:&quot;75c66f24-bf26-4873-9ca6-695e60ce93df&quot;,&quot;attributes&quot;:{&quot;alt&quot;:[&quot;alt&quot;,&quot;description&quot;],&quot;title&quot;:[&quot;title&quot;]}}" alt="Bosch dishwasher Home Connect logo"></p>

<p>Not only that, to <em>use</em> the app, you have to connect your dishwasher to WiFi, set up a cloud account in something called Home Connect, and then, and only then, can you start using all the features on the dishwasher.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This blog post is a lightly-edited transcript of my latest YouTube video on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@Level2Jeff">Level 2 Jeff</a>: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5M_hmwBBPnc">I won't connect my dishwasher to your stupid cloud</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So getting back first to that old GE dishwasher, it was, I don't know, I think that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planned_obsolescence">planned obsolescence</a> is something that applies to many consumer products today.</p>

<p>Companies know if they design something to last only 5 or 10 years, that means in 5 or 10 years someone's going to have to buy a whole new one.</p>

<p>And on my GE Amana dishwasher, it started having weird power issues, like the controls would just not light up unless I reset the circuit breaker for a few minutes. That started happening more often, and this past Saturday it just wouldn't come on no matter what, even after I tested and re-wired it all the way from the panel up to the dishwasher's internal power connector.</p>

<p>So it was dead.</p>

<p>Next up, I looked at what it took to get a control board. Well... <a href="https://www.repairclinic.com/PartDetail/Control-Board/WD21X24901C/4980378">$299 for a control board</a> that was 'special order' and might not even fix the problem? That's a non-starter for my $600, 8-year-old dishwasher.</p>

<p>Even if I got it fixed, the front panel was starting to rust out at the hinge points (leaving some metal jaggies that my soon-to-be-crawling 6 month old could slice his fingers on), and other parts of the machine were showing signs of rust/potential future leaks...</p>

<p>It was Saturday night, and for a family of five, a dishwasher is kinda important. We don't have 1.5 hours every night to spend hand-washing dishes (not to mention the water bill!).</p>

<p>So I needed to get a new one, and it's really hard for me to schedule a few hours for my Dad and I to get it done in the middle of the week (plus that's multiple days without a dishwasher!).</p>

<p>So I did some research, and I found Bosch <em>seemed</em> to have the best bet for under $1,000, available locally on a Sunday.</p>

<p>Consumer Reports, random Redditors, etc. seemed to have some praises for Bosch—on Reddit many also praised Miele, but I couldn't find any of those available locally. And Consumer Reports especially praised <em>all</em> the Bosch units, with them topping all their reliability and customer satisfaction charts!</p>

<p>I remembered five or ten years ago, whenever I had bought my old GE, I remembered Bosch topped the charts too, but back then I settled for GE to save a few bucks...</p>

<h2>Installation was (mostly) great!</h2>

<p>So I spent a little more this time, hoping for a better experience. And installation was actually great—it was a lot easier to install the Bosch than it was that the GE.</p>

<p>It has a plastic base that slides better on the floor, and there's easier routing of the drain hose, inlet hose, and power wire that makes it less risky when you're pushing the thing into the blind cutout under the counter.</p>

<p>The one weird thing was that whoever like tightened the feet on the bottom at the factory must've used an impact driver or something because they were all practically embedded, and wouldn't budge.</p>

<p>I was turning the little screw on the front that pushes the rear foot down through a little gearing, but the worm gear slipped out and kinda shoved the long rod that connects the front to the back out of place. I had to buy a 10mm hex socket to wiggle the foot loose enough the gearing would actually work.</p>

<p>But once that was done, the rest of the install was seamless. (Thanks especially to some help from my Dad).</p>

<h2>First use, encountering the Cloud requirement</h2>

<p>So I turned it on, and immediately hated the new touch sensor stuff on it.</p>

<p>The old GE had buttons: you press them in, they click and you know that you pressed a button.</p>

<p>The touch sensor, you kind of touch it and the firmware—like this new dishwasher actually takes time to boot up! I had to reset it like three times and my wife meanwhile was like laughing at me like look at this guy who does tech stuff and he can't even figure out how to change the cycle on it.</p>

<p>That took about five minutes, sadly.</p>

<p>But eventually I pulled out the manual book because I was like... "this is actually confusing."</p>

<p>It should be like: I touch the button and it changes to that mode! But that was not how it was working.</p>

<p>I wanted to run just a rinse cycle to make sure the water would go in, the water would pump out through the sump, and everything worked post-install.</p>

<p>But I couldn't find a way to do a rinse cycle on the control panel.</p>

<p>So I looked in the manual and found this note:</p>

<p><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/bosch-dishwasher-manual-features-home-connect.jpg" width="700" height="394" data-insert-type="image" data-entity-type="file" data-entity-uuid="insert-image-b39c0aae-ac8e-4760-9392-88c7efa29bd6" data-insert-attach="{&quot;id&quot;:&quot;b39c0aae-ac8e-4760-9392-88c7efa29bd6&quot;,&quot;attributes&quot;:{&quot;alt&quot;:[&quot;alt&quot;,&quot;description&quot;],&quot;title&quot;:[&quot;title&quot;]}}" alt="Bosch dishwasher manual mention of Home Connect"></p>

<p>It says options with an asterisk—including Rinse, Machine Care (self-cleaning), HalfLoad, Eco, and Delay start, are "available through Home Connect app only and depending on your model."</p>

<p>The 500 series model I bought isn't premium enough to feature a 7-segment display like the $400-more-expensive <em>800</em> series, so these fancy modes are hidden behind an app and cloud service.</p>

<p>I was like, "Okay, I'll look up this app and see if I can use it over Bluetooth or locally or whatever."</p>

<p>Nope! To use the app, you have to connect your <em>dishwasher</em> to your <em>Wi-Fi</em>, which lets the dishwasher reach out on the internet to this Home Connect service.</p>

<p>You have to set up an account on Home Connect, set up the Home Connect app on your phone, and <em>then</em> you can control your dishwasher <em>through the Internet</em> to run a rinse cycle.</p>

<p>That doesn't make any sense to me.</p>

<p>An app? I mean, I can understand maybe adding some neat convenience features for those <em>who want them</em>. Like on my new fridge—which I chose not to connect to WiFI—it has an app that would allow me to monitor the inside temperature or look up service codes more easily. If I wanted those add-on features, which my old fridge didn't have, I could get them.</p>

<p>But requiring an app to access features that <em>used</em> to be controllable via buttons on the dishwasher itself—or <em>are still</em> if you pay $400 more for the fancy "800" model? That's <em>no bueno</em>.</p>

<h2>What can I do?</h2>

<p>Well, first of all, I could just not use those features. That's kind of annoying because I bought it with the assumption that I could run the cleaning cycle, that I could run the rinse cycle without having to have an app and Wi-Fi.</p>

<p>Another option is I could just connect it to my Wi-Fi, maybe on an IoT VLAN.</p>

<p>But it's not like a video doorbell, where an Internet connection adds on functionality, like being able to see who rang while you're on vacation, or storing security footage clips on the cloud so you have them available even after someone robs your house...</p>

<p>But a dishwasher... I'm not going to remote control my dishwasher and like, run an extra rinse cycle while I'm on a beach somewhere.</p>

<p>I don't need Internet on my dishwasher.</p>

<p>Another <em>third</em> option is somebody has reverse engineered this protocol and built <a href="https://github.com/osresearch/hcpy">HCPY</a>, a Home Connect Python library.</p>

<p>But here's the problem: I already spent like four hours getting this dishwasher installed in my kitchen. I don't want to spend another four hours configuring my own web UI for it—which still requires at least a one-time connection through Home Connect!—and maintaining that as a service on my local network, relying on an unauthorized third party library using reverse-engineering to get at the private dishwasher API!</p>

<h2>What can <em>we</em> do?</h2>

<p>I don't think we should let vendors get away with this stuff.</p>

<p>First, it lets product designers get lazy.</p>

<p>A feature like a little display, a little seven segment display that can show like two letters and a number of minutes remaining or something like that... How much does that cost?</p>

<p>How hard is it to integrate that into every model, even the cheap ones?</p>

<p>A lot of cheap dishwashers actually <em>have</em> those things, but not Bosch!</p>

<p>With Bosch, you have to pay $400 for the privilege of a little display!</p>

<p>Second, this might be a little bit conspiracy theory or whatever, but it feels like it's part of planned obsolescence. Just like with the GE, where a lot of parts are designed to rust out after 5 or 10 years.</p>

<p>If you have a cloud app, that means there's a cloud service that has to be running. That costs money to maintain.</p>

<p>And if there's no subscription fee right now, that means one of two things:</p>

<ol>
<li>They could be selling our data already.</li>
<li>At some point, they'll either close the service because it's a cost center (so the rinse cycle and eco mode on all these dishwashers just goes "POOF!"), <em>or</em> they're going move to a subscription model.</li>
</ol>

<p>All of a sudden, if you want to run the self-cleaning cycle, you better start paying five bucks to Bosch every month. <em>Forever</em>.</p>

<p>That's insane.</p>

<p>Third, it's a security hole in your local network.</p>

<p>Bosch might be a <em>little</em> better than some no-name light bulb company making IoT light bulbs on Amazon, but only a little.</p>

<p>I don't want to have Bosch having full internet access on my local network.</p>

<p>Their API would be able to talk back to my dishwasher, and the dishwasher—unless I put it on a VLAN, which 99% of consumers have no clue how to do that...</p>

<p>That's just something that shouldn't have to happen.</p>

<p>This is a dishwasher!</p>

<p>I don't know.</p>

<h2>What <em>should</em> be done?</h2>

<p>When I posted on social media about this, a lot of people told me to return it.</p>

<p>But I spent four hours installing this thing built into my kitchen.</p>

<p>I hooked it up to the water, it's running through cycles... it <em>is</em> working. I'll give them that. It does the normal stuff, but you know, there are some features that don't work without the app.</p>

<p>At a minimum, I think what Bosch should do is make it so that the dishwasher can be accessed locally with no requirement for a cloud account. (Really, it'd be even better to have all the functions accessible on the control panel!)</p>

<p>Anyone building an IoT device, here is my consumer-first, e-waste-reduction maxim:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>First local, <em>then</em> cloud.</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Cloud should be an add-on.</p>

<p>It should be a convenience for people who don't know how to do things like connect to their dishwasher with an app locally.</p>

<p>And it's not <em>that</em> hard.</p>

<p>A little ESP32, a little $1 chip that you can put in there could do all this stuff locally with no cloud requirement at all.</p>

<p>I think that there might be some quants or people who want to make a lot of money building all these cloud services.</p>

<p>I don't think that it's people who are consumer-first and eco-conscious because if they were, they would give <em>us</em> control first and <em>then</em> add on 'nice' quality of life features through a cloud service.</p>

<p>With my Bosch 500 series dishwasher, I was excited after the easy install (besides those leveling feet), then was let down <em>so hard</em> once I found out I couldn't use all the features it came with.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Project Operation Whitecoat (2010) (101 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://scholarworks.lib.csusb.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1201&amp;context=history-in-the-making</link>
            <guid>43462882</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 16:35:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://scholarworks.lib.csusb.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1201&#x26;context=history-in-the-making">https://scholarworks.lib.csusb.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1201&#x26;context=history-in-the-making</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43462882">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Trump Administration Accidentally Texted Me Its War Plans (890 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2025/03/trump-administration-accidentally-texted-me-its-war-plans/682151/</link>
            <guid>43462783</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 16:23:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2025/03/trump-administration-accidentally-texted-me-its-war-plans/682151/">https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2025/03/trump-administration-accidentally-texted-me-its-war-plans/682151/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43462783">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><header data-event-module="hero"><div><div><p>U.S. national-security leaders included me in a group chat about upcoming military strikes in Yemen. I didn’t think it could be real. Then the bombs started falling.</p></div><div><figure><div data-flatplan-lead_figure_media="true"><picture><img alt="A photo of Mike Waltz, JD Vance, and Pete Hegseth in the Oval Office" sizes="(min-width: 976px) 976px, 100vw" srcset="https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/f7Tr-k9n3n15dk24f6hAtRgLiUM=/0x312:6000x3687/750x422/media/img/mt/2025/03/GettyImages_2204323444-1/original.jpg 750w, https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/Y30kBmuhz6fmh-ITHUv5a-iG2Vs=/0x312:6000x3687/828x466/media/img/mt/2025/03/GettyImages_2204323444-1/original.jpg 828w, https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/D_O_vZvowTDT8nqHx0byy0U6ioE=/0x312:6000x3687/960x540/media/img/mt/2025/03/GettyImages_2204323444-1/original.jpg 960w, https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/-bqDGhPvCn4xGz7sgQaNIfKjziw=/0x312:6000x3687/976x549/media/img/mt/2025/03/GettyImages_2204323444-1/original.jpg 976w, https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/aB28uMeLzYWXTc3bBiWVg55IFdY=/0x312:6000x3687/1952x1098/media/img/mt/2025/03/GettyImages_2204323444-1/original.jpg 1952w" src="https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/D_O_vZvowTDT8nqHx0byy0U6ioE=/0x312:6000x3687/960x540/media/img/mt/2025/03/GettyImages_2204323444-1/original.jpg" id="article-lead-image" width="960" height="540"></picture></div><figcaption data-flatplan-lead_figure_caption="true">Andrew Harnik / Getty</figcaption></figure></div></div><div><p><time datetime="2025-03-24T16:06:10Z" data-flatplan-timestamp="true">March 24, 2025, 12:06 PM ET</time> </p></div><gpt-ad format="injector" sizes-at-0="mobile-wide" targeting-pos="injector-article-start" sizes-at-976="desktop-wide"></gpt-ad></header><section data-event-module="article body" data-flatplan-body="true"><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The world found out shortly before 2 p.m. eastern time on March 15 that the United States was bombing Houthi targets across Yemen.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">I, however, knew two hours before the first bombs exploded that the attack might be coming. The reason I knew this is that Pete Hegseth, the secretary of defense, had texted me the war plan at 11:44 a.m. The plan included precise information about weapons packages, targets, and timing.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">This is going to require some explaining.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The story technically begins shortly after the Hamas invasion of southern Israel, in October 2023. The Houthis—an Iran-backed terrorist organization whose motto is “God is great, death to America, death to Israel, curse on the Jews, victory to Islam”—soon launched attacks on Israel and on international shipping, creating havoc for global trade. Throughout 2024, the Biden administration was ineffective in countering these Houthi attacks; the incoming Trump administration promised a tougher response.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">This is where Pete Hegseth and I come in.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">On Tuesday, March 11, I received a connection request on Signal from a user identified as Michael Waltz. Signal is an open-source encrypted messaging service popular with journalists and others who seek more privacy than other text-messaging services are capable of delivering. I assumed that the Michael Waltz in question was President Donald Trump’s national security adviser. I did not assume, however, that the request was from the actual Michael Waltz. I have met him in the past, and though I didn’t find it particularly strange that he might be reaching out to me, I did think it somewhat unusual, given the Trump administration’s contentious relationship with journalists—and Trump’s periodic fixation on me specifically. It immediately crossed my mind that someone could be masquerading as Waltz in order to somehow entrap me. It is not at all uncommon these days for nefarious actors to try to induce journalists to share information that could be used against them.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">I accepted the connection request, hoping that this was the actual national security adviser, and that he wanted to chat about Ukraine, or Iran, or some other important matter.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">Two days later—Thursday—at 4:28 p.m., I received a notice that I was to be included in a Signal chat group. It was called the “Houthi PC small group.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">A message to the group, from “Michael Waltz,” read as follows: “Team – establishing a principles [<em>sic</em>] group for coordination on Houthis, particularly for over the next 72 hours. My deputy Alex Wong is pulling together a tiger team at deputies/agency Chief of Staff level following up from the meeting in the Sit Room this morning for action items and will be sending that out later this evening.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The message continued, “Pls provide the best staff POC from your team for us to coordinate with over the next couple days and over the weekend. Thx.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The term <em>principals committee</em> generally refers to a group of the senior-most national-security officials, including the secretaries of defense, state, and the treasury, as well as the director of the CIA. It should go without saying—but I’ll say it anyway—that I have never been invited to a White House principals-committee meeting, and that, in my many years of reporting on national-security matters, I had never heard of one being convened over a commercial messaging app.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">One minute later, a person identified only as “MAR”—the secretary of state is Marco Antonio Rubio—wrote, “Mike Needham for State,” apparently designating the current counselor of the State Department as his representative. At that same moment, a Signal user identified as “JD Vance” wrote, “Andy baker for VP.” One minute after that, “TG” (presumably Tulsi Gabbard, the director of national intelligence, or someone masquerading as her) wrote, “Joe Kent for DNI.” Nine minutes later, “Scott B”—apparently Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent, or someone spoofing his identity, wrote, “Dan Katz for Treasury.” At 4:53 p.m., a user called “Pete Hegseth” wrote, “Dan Caldwell for DoD.” And at 6:34 p.m., “Brian” wrote “Brian McCormack for NSC.” One more person responded: “John Ratcliffe” wrote at 5:24 p.m. with the name of a CIA official to be included in the group. I am not publishing that name, because that person is an active intelligence officer.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The principals had apparently assembled. In all, 18 individuals were listed as members of this group, including various National Security Council officials; Steve Witkoff, President Trump’s Middle East and Ukraine negotiator; Susie Wiles, the White House chief of staff; and someone identified only as “S M,” which I took to stand for Stephen Miller. I appeared on my own screen only as “JG.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">That was the end of the Thursday text chain.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">After receiving the Waltz text related to the “Houthi PC small group,” I consulted a number of colleagues. We discussed the possibility that these texts were part of a disinformation campaign, initiated by either a foreign intelligence service or, more likely, a media-gadfly organization, the sort of group that attempts to place journalists in embarrassing positions, and sometimes succeeds. I had very strong doubts that this text group was real, because I could not believe that the national-security leadership of the United States would communicate on Signal about imminent war plans. I also could not believe that the national security adviser to the president would be so reckless as to include the editor in chief of <em>The Atlantic</em> in such discussions with senior U.S. officials, up to and including the vice president.</p><hr><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The next day, things got even stranger.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">At 8:05 a.m. on Friday, March 14, “Michael Waltz” texted the group: “Team, you should have a statement of conclusions with taskings per the Presidents guidance this morning in your high side inboxes.” (<em>High side</em>, in government parlance, refers to classified computer and communications systems.) “State and DOD, we developed suggested notification lists for regional Allies and partners. Joint Staff is sending this am a more specific sequence of events in the coming days and we will work w DOD to ensure COS, OVP and POTUS are briefed.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">At this point, a fascinating policy discussion commenced. The account labeled “JD Vance” responded at 8:16: “Team, I am out for the day doing an economic event in Michigan. But I think we are making a mistake.” (Vance was indeed in Michigan that day.) The Vance account goes on to state, “3 percent of US trade runs through the suez. 40 percent of European trade does. There is a real risk that the public doesn’t understand this or why it’s necessary. The strongest reason to do this is, as POTUS said, to send a message.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The Vance account then goes on to make a noteworthy statement, considering that the vice president has not deviated publicly from Trump’s position on virtually any issue. “I am not sure the president is aware how inconsistent this is with his message on Europe right now. There’s a further risk that we see a moderate to severe spike in oil prices. I am willing to support the consensus of the team and keep these concerns to myself. But there is a strong argument for delaying this a month, doing the messaging work on why this matters, seeing where the economy is, etc.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">A person identified in Signal as “Joe Kent” (Trump’s nominee to run the National Counterterrorism Center is named Joe Kent) wrote at 8:22, “There is nothing time sensitive driving the time line. We’ll have the exact same options in a month.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">Then, at 8:26 a.m., a message landed in my Signal app from the user “John Ratcliffe.” The message contained information that might be interpreted as related to actual and current intelligence operations.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">At 8:27, a message arrived from the “Pete Hegseth” account. “VP: I understand your concerns – and fully support you raising w/ POTUS. Important considerations, most of which are tough to know how they play out (economy, Ukraine peace, Gaza, etc). I think messaging is going to be tough no matter what – nobody knows who the Houthis are – which is why we would need to stay focused on: 1) Biden failed &amp; 2) Iran funded.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The Hegseth message goes on to state, “Waiting a few weeks or a month does not fundamentally change the calculus. 2 immediate risks on waiting: 1) this leaks, and we look indecisive; 2) Israel takes an action first – or Gaza cease fire falls apart – and we don’t get to start this on our own terms. We can manage both. We are prepared to execute, and if I had final go or no go vote, I believe we should. This [is] not about the Houthis. I see it as two things: 1) Restoring Freedom of Navigation, a core national interest; and 2) Reestablish deterrence, which Biden cratered. But, we can easily pause. And if we do, I will do all we can to enforce 100% OPSEC”—operations security. “I welcome other thoughts.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">A few minutes later, the “Michael Waltz” account posted a lengthy note about trade figures, and the limited capabilities of European navies. “Whether it’s now or several weeks from now, it will have to be the United States that reopens these shipping lanes. Per the president’s request we are working with DOD and State to determine how to compile the cost associated and levy them on the Europeans.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The account identified as “JD Vance” addressed a message at 8:45 to @Pete Hegseth: “if you think we should do it let’s go. I just hate bailing Europe out again.” (The administration has argued that America’s European allies benefit economically from the U.S. Navy’s protection of international shipping lanes.)</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The user identified as Hegseth responded three minutes later: “VP: I fully share your loathing of European free-loading. It’s PATHETIC. But Mike is correct, we are the only ones on the planet (on our side of the ledger) who can do this. Nobody else even close. Question is timing. I feel like now is as good a time as any, given POTUS directive to reopen shipping lanes. I think we should go; but POTUS still retains 24 hours of decision space.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">At this point, the previously silent “S M” joined the conversation. “As I heard it, the president was clear: green light, but we soon make clear to Egypt and Europe what we expect in return. We also need to figure out how to enforce such a requirement. EG, if Europe doesn’t remunerate, then what? If the US successfully restores freedom of navigation at great cost there needs to be some further economic gain extracted in return.”</p><div data-flatplan-inline_image="true"><figure><picture><img alt="A screenshot of a group chat" loading="lazy" srcset="https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/rySa44yfmkE7OFEgHayLiak2F78=/665x484/media/img/posts/2025/03/IMG_0328/original.jpg" src="https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/rySa44yfmkE7OFEgHayLiak2F78=/665x484/media/img/posts/2025/03/IMG_0328/original.jpg" width="665" height="484"></picture></figure></div><div data-flatplan-inline_image="true"><figure><picture><img alt="Screenshot of a group chat" loading="lazy" srcset="https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/w6AXYEmE7rQSN42_PflDXUN1HG8=/665x979/media/img/posts/2025/03/IMG_0329/original.jpg" src="https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/w6AXYEmE7rQSN42_PflDXUN1HG8=/665x979/media/img/posts/2025/03/IMG_0329/original.jpg" width="665" height="979"></picture><figcaption>A screenshot from the Signal group shows debate over the president’s views ahead of the attack.</figcaption></figure></div><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">That message from “S M”—presumably President Trump’s confidant Stephen Miller, the deputy White House chief of staff, or someone playing Stephen Miller—effectively shut down the conversation. The last text of the day came from “Pete Hegseth,” who wrote at 9:46 a.m., “Agree.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">After reading this chain, I recognized that this conversation possessed a high degree of verisimilitude. The texts, in their word choice and arguments, sounded as if they were written by the people who purportedly sent them, or by a particularly adept AI text generator. I was still concerned that this could be a disinformation operation, or a simulation of some sort. And I remained mystified that no one in the group seemed to have noticed my presence. But if it was a hoax, the quality of mimicry and the level of foreign-policy insight were impressive.</p><hr><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">It was the next morning, Saturday, March 15, when this story became truly bizarre.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">At 11:44 a.m., the account labeled “Pete Hegseth” posted in Signal a “TEAM UPDATE.” I will not quote from this update, or from certain other subsequent texts. The information contained in them, if they had been read by an adversary of the United States, could conceivably have been used to harm American military and intelligence personnel, particularly in the broader Middle East, Central Command’s area of responsibility. What I will say, in order to illustrate the shocking recklessness of this Signal conversation, is that the Hegseth post contained operational details of forthcoming strikes on Yemen, including information about targets, weapons the U.S. would be deploying, and attack sequencing.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The only person to reply to the update from Hegseth was the person identified as the vice president. “I will say a prayer for victory,” Vance wrote. (Two other users subsequently added prayer emoji.)</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">According to the lengthy Hegseth text, the first detonations in Yemen would be felt two hours hence, at 1:45 p.m. eastern time. So I waited in my car in a supermarket parking lot. If this Signal chat was real, I reasoned, Houthi targets would soon be bombed. At about 1:55, I checked X and searched <em>Yemen</em>. Explosions were then being heard across Sanaa, the capital city.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">I went back to the Signal channel. At 1:48, “Michael Waltz” had provided the group an update. Again, I won’t quote from this text, except to note that he described the operation as an “amazing job.” A few minutes later, “John Ratcliffe” wrote, “A good start.” Not long after, Waltz responded with three emoji: a fist, an American flag, and fire. Others soon joined in, including “MAR,” who wrote, “Good Job Pete and your team!!,” and “Susie Wiles,” who texted, “Kudos to all – most particularly those in theater and CENTCOM! Really great. God bless.” “Steve Witkoff” responded with five emoji: two hands-praying, a flexed bicep, and two American flags. “TG” responded, “Great work and effects!” The after-action discussion included assessments of damage done, including the likely death of a specific individual. The Houthi-run Yemeni health ministry reported that at least 53 people were killed in the strikes, a number that has not been independently verified.</p><div data-flatplan-inline_image="true"><figure><picture><img alt="Screenshot of a group chat" loading="lazy" srcset="https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/eNC-qJzV_jbc18944_z6t1QhGDc=/665x758/media/img/posts/2025/03/IMG_0330/original.jpg" src="https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/eNC-qJzV_jbc18944_z6t1QhGDc=/665x758/media/img/posts/2025/03/IMG_0330/original.jpg" width="665" height="758"></picture><figcaption>A screenshot from the Signal group shows reactions to the strikes.</figcaption></figure></div><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">On Sunday, Waltz appeared on ABC’s <em>This Week</em> and contrasted the strikes with the Biden administration’s more hesitant approach. “These were not kind of pinprick, back-and-forth—what ultimately proved to be feckless attacks,” he said. “This was an overwhelming response that actually targeted multiple Houthi leaders and took them out.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">The Signal chat group, I concluded, was almost certainly real. Having come to this realization, one that seemed nearly impossible only hours before, I removed myself from the Signal group, understanding that this would trigger an automatic notification to the group’s creator, “Michael Waltz,” that I had left. No one in the chat had seemed to notice that I was there. And I received no subsequent questions about why I left—or, more to the point, who I was.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">Earlier today, I emailed Waltz and sent him a message on his Signal account. I also wrote to Pete Hegseth, John Ratcliffe, Tulsi Gabbard, and other officials. In an email, I outlined some of my questions: Is the “Houthi PC small group” a genuine Signal thread? Did they know that I was included in this group? Was I (on the off chance) included on purpose? If not, who did they think I was? Did anyone realize who I was when I was added, or when I removed myself from the group? Do senior Trump-administration officials use Signal regularly for sensitive discussions? Do the officials believe that the use of such a channel could endanger American personnel?</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">Brian Hughes, the spokesman for the National Security Council, responded two hours later, confirming the veracity of the Signal group. “This appears to be an authentic message chain, and we are reviewing how an inadvertent number was added to the chain,” Hughes wrote. “The thread is a demonstration of the deep and thoughtful policy coordination between senior officials. The ongoing success of the Houthi operation demonstrates that there were no threats to troops or national security.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">William Martin, a spokesperson for Vance, said that despite the impression created by the texts, the vice president is fully aligned with the president. “The Vice President’s first priority is always making sure that the President’s advisers are adequately briefing him on the substance of their internal deliberations,” he said. “Vice President Vance unequivocally supports this administration’s foreign policy. The President and the Vice President have had subsequent conversations about this matter and are in complete agreement.”</p><hr><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">I have never seen a breach quite like this. It is not uncommon for national-security officials to communicate on Signal. But the app is used primarily for meeting planning and other logistical matters—not for detailed and highly confidential discussions of a pending military action. And, of course, I’ve never heard of an instance in which a journalist has been invited to such a discussion.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">Conceivably, Waltz, by coordinating a national-security-related action over Signal, may have violated several provisions of the Espionage Act, which governs the handling of “national defense” information, according to several national-security lawyers interviewed by my colleague Shane Harris for this story. Harris asked them to consider a hypothetical scenario in which a senior U.S. official creates a Signal thread for the express purpose of sharing information with Cabinet officials about an active military operation. He did not show them the actual Signal messages or tell them specifically what had occurred.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">All of these lawyers said that a U.S. official should not establish a Signal thread in the first place. Information about an active operation would presumably fit the law’s definition of “national defense” information. The Signal app is not approved by the government for sharing classified information. The government has its own systems for that purpose. If officials want to discuss military activity, they should go into a specially designed space known as a sensitive compartmented information facility, or SCIF—most Cabinet-level national-security officials have one installed in their home—or communicate only on approved government equipment, the lawyers said. Normally, cellphones are not permitted inside a SCIF, which suggests that as these officials were sharing information about an active military operation, they could have been moving around in public. Had they lost their phones, or had they been stolen, the potential risk to national security would have been severe.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">Hegseth, Ratcliffe, and other Cabinet-level officials presumably would have the authority to declassify information, and several of the national-security lawyers noted that the hypothetical officials on the Signal chain might claim that they had declassified the information they shared. But this argument rings hollow, they cautioned, because Signal is not an authorized venue for sharing information of such a sensitive nature, regardless of whether it has been stamped “top secret” or not.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">There was another potential problem: Waltz set some of the messages in the Signal group to disappear after one week, and some after four. That raises questions about whether the officials may have violated federal records law: Text messages about official acts are considered records that should be preserved.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">“Under the records laws applicable to the White House and federal agencies, all government employees are prohibited from using electronic-messaging applications such as Signal for official business, unless those messages are promptly forwarded or copied to an official government account,” Jason R. Baron, a professor at the University of Maryland and the former director of litigation at the National Archives and Records Administration, told Harris.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">“Intentional violations of these requirements are a basis for disciplinary action. Additionally, agencies such as the Department of Defense restrict electronic messaging containing classified information to classified government networks and/or networks with government-approved encrypted features,” Baron said.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">Several former U.S. officials told Harris and me that they had used Signal to share unclassified information and to discuss routine matters, particularly when traveling overseas without access to U.S. government systems. But they knew never to share classified or sensitive information on the app, because their phones could have been hacked by a foreign intelligence service, which would have been able to read the messages on the devices. It is worth noting that Donald Trump, as a candidate for president (and as president), repeatedly and vociferously demanded that Hillary Clinton be imprisoned for using a private email server for official business when she was secretary of state. (It is also worth noting that Trump was indicted in 2023 for mishandling classified documents, but the charges were dropped after his election.)</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">Waltz and the other Cabinet-level officials were already potentially violating government policy and the law simply by texting one another about the operation. But when Waltz added a journalist—presumably by mistake—to his principals committee, he created new security and legal issues. Now the group was transmitting information to someone not authorized to receive it. That is the classic definition of a leak, even if it was unintentional, and even if the recipient of the leak did not actually believe it was a leak until Yemen came under American attack.</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true">All along, members of the Signal group were aware of the need for secrecy and operations security. In his text detailing aspects of the forthcoming attack on Houthi targets, Hegseth wrote to the group—which, at the time, included me—“We are currently clean on OPSEC.”</p><p data-flatplan-paragraph="true"><em>Shane Harris contributed reporting. </em></p></section><div data-event-module="footer"><p><h3>About the Author</h3></p><div><address id="article-writer-0" data-event-element="author" data-event-position="1" data-flatplan-bio="true"><div><div><p><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/author/jeffrey-goldberg/" data-event-element="image"><img alt="" loading="lazy" src="https://cdn.theatlantic.com/thumbor/umxEbDHzu_6lWzJxYOnCZNM4_sg=/0x0:2977x2977/120x120/media/img/authors/2021/06/Jeffrey_Goldberg_Headshot_bw_1/original.png" width="60" height="60"></a></p></div><div><p><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/author/jeffrey-goldberg/" data-label="https://www.theatlantic.com/author/jeffrey-goldberg/" data-action="click author - name">Jeffrey Goldberg</a> is the editor in chief of <em>The Atlantic<strong> </strong></em>and the moderator of <em>Washington Week With The Atlantic</em>.</p></div></div></address></div></div><gpt-ad format="injector" sizes-at-0="mobile-wide,native,house" targeting-pos="injector-most-popular" sizes-at-976="desktop-wide,native,house"></gpt-ad></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mastering Delphi 5 2025 Annotated Edition Is Now Complete (169 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.marcocantu.com/blog/2025-march-mastering-delphi5-annotated-complete.html</link>
            <guid>43462299</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 15:40:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.marcocantu.com/blog/2025-march-mastering-delphi5-annotated-complete.html">https://blog.marcocantu.com/blog/2025-march-mastering-delphi5-annotated-complete.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43462299">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>I've now completed the review of the 2025 Annotated Edition of Mastering Delphi 5.</p><div>
<p xmlns:gxi="http://geode.it/gxi/2.0/">As I <a href="https://blog.marcocantu.com/blog/2025-february-mastering-delphi5-annotated.html">announced on&nbsp;February 14</a>, I've been creating a free to download edition of my classic "Mastering Delphi 5" with footnotes indicating what is different today. The new edition is now <strong>complete</strong>. You can find it for download at&nbsp;<a href="https://www.marcocantu.com/md52025/">www.marcocantu.com/md52025/</a>.</p>
<p xmlns:gxi="http://geode.it/gxi/2.0/">The final annotated edition is <strong>1,139 pages</strong> and it has<strong>&nbsp;475 footnotes</strong>, plus dozen of new screen snapshots comparing the old the the new UI of the IDE, and in some cases of the running applications. Not everything in the original source code compiles, but most of the programs run untouched, which is almost incredible given the 25 years since that edition.</p>
<p xmlns:gxi="http://geode.it/gxi/2.0/">I hope you like it, it's nice a read and you can probably read something on today's Delphi, but even if you know everything it's an interesting way to go down the memory lane, for those who've been using Delphi since that time.</p>
<p xmlns:gxi="http://geode.it/gxi/2.0/">As mentioned, this is my present to the community for Delphi's 30th anniversary, we celebrated recently.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Triforce – a beamformer for Apple Silicon laptops (489 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://crates.io/crates/triforce-lv2</link>
            <guid>43461701</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 14:45:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://crates.io/crates/triforce-lv2">https://crates.io/crates/triforce-lv2</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43461701">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://crates.io/crates/triforce-lv2: Error: Request failed with status code 404]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Goblin.tools: simple, single-task tools to help neurodivergent people with tasks (304 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://goblin.tools/</link>
            <guid>43461375</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 14:15:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://goblin.tools/">https://goblin.tools/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43461375">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="syncHelp"><p>
                            Please provide credentials to synchronize your ToDo list across devices.<br>
                            There are no accounts, your username must simply be unique. <br>
                            We recommend taking a backup with <i></i> before activating sync on new devices.<br>
                            <a data-bs-toggle="collapse" href="#collapseText" role="button" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="collapseText">
                                How does this work?
                            </a></p><p>
                                All devices with the same username and password will synchronise lists.<br>
                                Your list is encrypted on your devices using your username and password. It can not be seen or decrypted by admins or anyone who doesn't have your credentials. <br>
                                Synchronization is not instant, it can take a few seconds for your changes to come through on other devices.
                            </p>
                        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Game Designer Playing Through His Own Psyche (137 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.newyorker.com/culture/persons-of-interest/the-game-designer-playing-through-his-own-psyche</link>
            <guid>43459361</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 10:39:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/culture/persons-of-interest/the-game-designer-playing-through-his-own-psyche">https://www.newyorker.com/culture/persons-of-interest/the-game-designer-playing-through-his-own-psyche</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43459361">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><figure></figure><p>A little more than a decade ago, the video-game designer Davey Wreden experienced a crippling success. In October, 2013, he and a collaborator, William Pugh, released the Stanley Parable HD, a polished and expanded version of a prototype that Wreden had developed in college, and which he had made available, free of charge, two years before. Wreden and Pugh hoped that they might sell fifty thousand or so copies of the new version in the course of its lifetime. They sold that many on the first day. Wreden was twenty-five years old, and he had everything he’d ever wanted: money, success, recognition. He became severely depressed.</p><p>The Stanley Parable is a game about a lonely man. It centers on an office worker, Stanley, who, one day, looks up from his cubicle and discovers that his colleagues have vanished. All that’s left to keep him company is a voice in his head—provided by the British actor Kevan Brighting—which narrates Stanley’s actions. But Stanley doesn’t have to do what the voice says. The game quickly becomes a contest of will between the player and the narrator.</p><p>When I first played the Stanley Parable, I was gobsmacked by <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=182oi1r-IyU">one sequence in particular</a>, which begins when Stanley walks down a dark corridor marked “<em>ESCAPE</em>.” He finds himself whisked toward a hydraulic press—and certain death, if the narrator’s taunts are to be believed. Just before impact, a previously unheard female narrator (voiced by Lesley Staples) describes how the machine kills Stanley, “crushing every bone in his body.” But the machine doesn’t mush him. Instead, he arrives at a brightly lit museum. Therein lies a small-scale model of his office, with signs explaining how each section was fussed over to insure that the player progresses at a good clip. On the far wall are the game’s credits. The new narrator notes that soon it will be re-started, and Stanley will be alive as ever. “When every path you can walk has been created for you long in advance, death becomes meaningless, making life the same,” she says. Then she adds, “Do you see now that Stanley was already dead from the moment he hit Start?”</p><p>I had been playing video games for thirty years, and I had never seen the medium deconstructed so skillfully or with such existential humor. I felt the way that I imagine cinephiles did in 1960, emerging from dark theatres having just seen “Breathless.” The game’s young creators seemed to be free from the trappings of what had come before.</p><p>Wreden has since released a second critically acclaimed title, the Beginner’s Guide, and cemented his reputation as a designer who defies convention. Neither of his games asks much more of the player than an ability to move through a 3-D space; what distinguishes them is their philosophical bent and penchant for narrative tricks. (Gabriel Winslow-Yost, writing in <em>The New York Review of Books,</em> invoked Nabokov, calling the Beginner’s Guide “a kind of interactive ‘Pale Fire.’&nbsp;”) Among gamers, Wreden has acquired cult-celebrity status, and his influence extends beyond his own medium: even the creator of the TV show “<a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2025/01/20/severance-tv-review-apple-tv-plus">Severance</a>”—another office drama that raises questions about free will as it veers between whimsy and dread—has cited the Stanley Parable as an inspiration. (The game also had <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LWUNxcvZCpg">a brief cameo</a> in an episode of “House of Cards.”)</p><p>Wreden, now thirty-six, has a slim build and a sweep of brown hair. When we spoke for the first time, last year, he was dressed in a dark-gray T-shirt. He works from home, in Vancouver, and the wall behind his desk is adorned with drawings of characters from the video-game franchise Persona, images from the manga <em>Chainsaw Man</em>, and pictures of food. In a corner of the room, next to a bookcase, hangs a ramen-shop paper lantern that he acquired on a trip to Osaka. He was winding down production on his third game, Wanderstop, out this month, and in a reflective mood about its predecessors—works he described as having been designed “to break and unwind the tightly coiled, traditional structure of what games like that were supposed to do.”</p><p>As a teen-ager, Wreden loved stories that set traps: “Fight Club” and “The Usual Suspects,” with their late reveals, and works by Roald Dahl and Shirley Jackson. Growing up in Sacramento, California, as the eldest son of a pair of doctors, he gravitated toward brainy but silly humor; he was a big fan of “Weird Al” Yankovic, Flight of the Conchords, and Joseph Heller’s “<a data-offer-url="https://www.amazon.com/Catch-22-50th-Anniversary-Joseph-Heller/dp/1451626657" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Catch-22-50th-Anniversary-Joseph-Heller/dp/1451626657&quot;}" href="https://www.amazon.com/Catch-22-50th-Anniversary-Joseph-Heller/dp/1451626657" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Catch-22</a>.” Wreden was not an especially happy kid, but from an early age he believed that he could imagine his way to something better. His father once told him that it was hard to have a conversation with him in his adolescence, because Wreden usually forgot what other people said. “It wasn’t, like, a memory thing, or an A.D.H.D. thing,” Wreden recalled. “It was literally just, like, anything that didn’t fit into my big grand plan of doing as much as possible, achieving as much as possible, and thinking as big as possible just wasn’t relevant to me.”</p><p>“I’ve had phases of my life where I became not very functional as a person because I couldn’t distinguish myself from the absurdism of the media that I liked,” he said. He responded by creating, in the Stanley Parable, a realm where he could safely explore his own anxieties. “It can’t hurt me because I own it,” he explained. “I thought that if I made a game that spits in the face of an attempt to find meaning in the world, that it would somehow map onto me, as a real person, and I would get over my fear of meaninglessness in the world. And it did not work.”</p><p>Wreden has since become ambivalent about the Stanley Parable, feeling, he said, “like a guy who had gotten rich making jokes about video games, trying to deceive real writers into thinking that I’m a real writer.” There was also the shadow of the period after its release, when he became, as he put it, “addicted to praise.” He responded to every piece of fan mail—and hate mail—he received, convinced that any endorsement, rejection, or misapprehension of the game was really about him as a person. Mood swings and sudden bouts of rage alienated his best friend (and then roommate), Robin Arnott, the sound designer for the Stanley Parable, who finally confronted him and said that he couldn’t be around Wreden in this state any longer. Wreden went to therapy; gradually, his depression lifted. The Beginner’s Guide includes a line first spoken by Arnott during the argument that snapped Wreden out of his funk: “When I’m around you, I feel physically ill.”</p><p>The Beginner’s Guide was partly inspired by William Goldman’s novel “<a data-offer-url="https://www.amazon.com/Princess-Bride-Morgensterns-Classic-Adventure/dp/0156035219" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Princess-Bride-Morgensterns-Classic-Adventure/dp/0156035219&quot;}" href="https://www.amazon.com/Princess-Bride-Morgensterns-Classic-Adventure/dp/0156035219" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">The Princess Bride</a>,” which Wreden had read while working on the Stanley Parable. Just as the book’s narrator purports to offer an abridgment of a story he’d loved as a child (albeit with plenty of his own editorializing), Wreden thought he might design a documentary-style work around an imaginary game; he was confident no one had done that before. But it was also something far more personal: a game infused with his newfound awareness of the fraught relationship between artist and audience that, as he put it, came from “the deepest place that I could go to within myself.”</p><p>In the opening minutes, Wreden—himself a central character—tells the player that he wants to share the work of his friend Coda, an experimental game designer who got his start by tinkering with the same suite of shareware tools that the real-life Wreden had used to create the Stanley Parable. As the Beginner’s Guide progresses, we watch his output grow conceptually richer and more surreal. One of Coda’s games features an outdoor staircase attached to a windowless skyscraper that leads to an inviting wood-panelled room where ideas for new projects float in the air in the form of short sentences. Another level hems the player in with blocks of self-questioning text while the sound of someone gasping for air drones on in the background.</p></div><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>Throughout the game, Wreden offers interpretations of these designs—and also makes small, player-friendly adjustments to the more challenging ones, which he speculates were shaped by Coda’s social isolation and creative frustration. Eventually, it becomes clear that Coda resents these attempts to both alter and evangelize for his œuvre. He upbraids Wreden for seeing in his games a cry for help, and asks the other designer never to contact him again. Wreden confesses that showing Coda’s work to people gave meaning to his life and helped him feel less alone.</p><p>From the start of development on the Stanley Parable, in the summer of 2009, until the release of the Beginner’s Guide, in October, 2015, Wreden essentially worked without taking a break. “That was what it took to make those games,” he said. “Somehow I kept thinking that, like, one day this will make sense to me, and I’ll just be able to live like a normal person.” The Beginner’s Guide, like the Stanley Parable before it, won a bevy of awards; Wreden’s reputation continued to grow. But his search for new forms never yielded a sense of personal uplift or fulfillment. It took him years, he said, to see that he had built a kind of mental prison. After the release of the Beginner’s Guide, in 2015, he found that he could no longer write at all.</p><p>In January, 2016, Wreden began drawing for upward of five hours nearly every day. He harnessed his obsessive tendencies, producing hundreds of pictures in the course of a six-month span, all of them variations on a simple scene: a pastoral clearing with a quaint-looking tea shop surrounded by trees, rocks, and brooks. He’d deliberately immersed himself in a kind of controlled chaos during the making of the Stanley Parable; this time, he was cultivating serenity. “I really hoped that by working on something that was themed as a relaxing, calming place, that I would relax and calm myself,” he told me.</p><p>After founding a new studio, Ivy Road, he realized that the sketches contained the seeds of his next project. Wanderstop belongs to the tradition of so-called cozy games, a burgeoning genre of nonviolent titles devoted to relationships, crafting, exploration, and routine—to building, rather than destroying. (Animal Crossing, a popular franchise that invites players to participate in the day-to-day life of a village, was a particular inspiration; Wreden wanted his game to have a similar vibe, but also “to make space for more complex emotional exploration.”) His approach to its development was, in part, a product of his aversion to writing. At first, he thought that it would be something akin to a toybox, which immersed players in a mysterious and beautiful world without explicit goals or conclusive endings. He wanted to use procedural generation—a technique that employs algorithms to create shifting paths through a game—so that modular chunks of story could be combined in different ways depending on players’ actions. His protagonist, Alta, was silent: a conceit that he described as “my way of procedurally insuring it would be impossible for me to get lost in writing a bunch of dialogue for her.”</p><p>Relying on generative systems to do the narrative heavy lifting proved to be a tall order. Wreden playtests his games extensively, and he’ll make changes based in part on players’ reactions. He wanted Wanderstop to have a strong sense of purpose: “It wasn’t just there for you to poke at for a minute, but it actually was trying to speak—trying to effect a sort of psychological therapy on the player, to grant them the permission to relax and to unwind.” But when he shared an early version, he recalled, “The responses could charitably be called ‘muted.’&nbsp;” Another writer said that the prototype gave the impression that Wreden didn’t want to be working on the game at all.</p><p>Then Pugh, his old collaborator, contacted him about making a version of the Stanley Parable that could be played on consoles such as the Nintendo Switch and PlayStation. Wreden initially planned to add an extra scenario or two, but soon produced what amounted to a full sequel. He’d slipped easily back into the narrator’s voice, because it was essentially his own. When he returned to Wanderstop, he realized that he had to endow it with more of himself, too.</p><p>Karla Zimonja played a pivotal role in this reversal. She, too, is a Vancouver-based game developer who made her name with exploration-driven, introspective titles—most notably Gone Home, the low-key story of a young woman who arrives at her family home after a year away and has to piece together what’s happened in her absence. Zimonja told me that she’s known Wreden for more than a decade, noting, “There aren’t too many truly narrative-forward, high-production-values indie people out there.” She joined Ivy Road about a year and a half into Wanderstop’s development, and became Wreden’s editor, pushing him toward what he called “true specifics.”</p><p>With Zimonja’s input, the game began to ground itself in a story about Alta, a fighter who’s forced to lay down her weapons and reluctantly ends up managing a tea shop. “I decided to make Alta everything about me that I thought needed healing,” Wreden told me. “She was needy and obsessed with perfection and totally unaware of how much she was hurting herself.” After he drafted the character’s backstory on a whiteboard, a colleague pointed to it and said, “This is the first time I’ve actually felt invested in this game.”</p><p>Wanderstop is the most conventional game that Wreden has made. For that reason, it’s also the most difficult project he’s worked on. Both the Stanley Parable and the Beginner’s Guide were relatively simple to build; Wreden spent the bulk of his time writing and tweaking the narration, so that a fairly basic set of actions would feel “like something grand and captivating.” Wanderstop, by contrast, has mechanics—for gardening, resource-gathering, performing little tasks for other characters—that require far more technical know-how to implement.</p><p>At first, when I tried Wanderstop myself, I was caught off guard by its unironic embrace of familiar video-game activities: in order to provide Alta with what she needs to operate the two-story infuser that dominates the inside of the shop, I collected ingredients and cultivated plants whose fruit could be used to endow a given brew with a distinctive flavor, or even with mind-stimulating properties. Once I got over my surprise, it didn’t take long to fall into the enjoyable routine of making tea for people and listening to what they had to say.</p><p>But Wreden has Trojan-horsed a trauma plot into this seemingly soothing environment. With Wanderstop, he twists the cozy formula, just as his previous works have played with other game-design tropes, telling what he’s described as “a really unpleasant and uncomfortable story in a format designed around comfort.” Alta has a dark alter ego—the personification of the goading internal force that won’t let the former fighter rest—and risks encountering this side of herself whenever she strays too far from the tea shop. The possibility that Alta might ultimately revert to her old ways mirrors Wreden’s anxieties about reverting to his own. “I think if I were to imply that going through this set of events permanently fixed her, it would be radically disingenuous to the actual nature of growth.” All too often, Wreden added, “Your body, for whatever reason, just jettisons the lessons out the air lock, and then you have to relearn them over again.”</p></div><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>In a lecture at Aalto University, in Helsinki, in 2015, Wreden declared that a “fearful state of mind” within the mainstream video-game industry had led to “an art form in which by far the most ubiquitous form of expression is that of firing a gun.” We have, he went on, “a culture where violence is understood and implied to be the central means of problem-solving.” Wanderstop is a kind of rebuttal, prizing dialogue and contemplation over heroic acts. Though Alta spends most of the game longing to fix herself—i.e., to become a fighter again—she must confront the possibility that there may not be a satisfying solution to her problem. In this way, Wanderstop explores a situation which, as Wreden noted in his lecture, often falls outside the purview of video games: namely, how one lives with the consequence of not getting what one wants.</p><p>When I asked Wreden about those remarks, he said that he regrets some of the more hard-nosed things he’s said in the past—then allowed that maybe he’d grown soft, complacent. He likes that some creators push boundaries, he said, while others entertain. “I just want FromSoftware to keep making Sekiro,” he told me, name-checking a Japanese video-game company and its popular samurai game.</p><p>Near the close of our last chat, I asked Wreden where he thinks he’ll go next. He noted that, up until now, the arc of his career has been to move from the absurd to the practical. His desire for Wanderstop to have genuine therapeutic potential is a reflection of that shift. “A pet peeve of mine has really become when people say, ‘I just wanna ask questions,’&nbsp;” he added. This, he said, was something you hear “from a lot of big and popular creators”; it was also an impulse that you could find in his work. “It is something that I have plumbed the depths of, and I have come up and found it wanting,” he said. “Questions aren’t good enough for me anymore. I would like to start talking about answers.”&nbsp;♦</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Japanese scientists use stem cell treatment to restore movement in spinal injury (233 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://medicalxpress.com/news/2025-03-japanese-scientists-stem-cell-treatment.html</link>
            <guid>43459264</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 10:25:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://medicalxpress.com/news/2025-03-japanese-scientists-stem-cell-treatment.html">https://medicalxpress.com/news/2025-03-japanese-scientists-stem-cell-treatment.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43459264">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
									    
<div data-thumb="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2020/spinalcord.jpg" data-src="https://scx2.b-cdn.net/gfx/news/hires/2020/spinalcord.jpg" data-sub-html="Credit: Pixabay/CC0 Public Domain">
        <figure>
            <img src="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/800a/2020/spinalcord.jpg" alt="spinal cord" title="Credit: Pixabay/CC0 Public Domain" width="800" height="530">
             <figcaption>
                Credit: Pixabay/CC0 Public Domain
            </figcaption>        </figure>
    </div><p>A stem cell treatment helped improve the motor function of two out of four patients with a spinal cord injury in the first clinical study of its kind, Japanese scientists said.</p>

                                        
                                                                                  
                                         

                                                                                    <p>There is currently no effective <a href="https://medicalxpress.com/tags/treatment/" rel="tag">treatment</a> for paralysis caused by serious spinal cord injuries, which affect more than 150,000 patients in Japan alone, with 5,000 new cases each year.</p>
<p>Researchers at Tokyo's Keio University are conducting their study using <a href="https://medicalxpress.com/tags/induced+pluripotent+stem+cells/" rel="tag">induced pluripotent stem cells</a> (iPS)—created by stimulating mature, already specialized, cells back into a juvenile state.</p>
<p>They can then be prompted to mature into different kinds of cells, with the Keio researchers using iPS-derived cells of the neural stem.</p>
<p>The university said on Friday that the <a href="https://medicalxpress.com/tags/motor+function/" rel="tag">motor function</a> score for two patients improved after an operation to implant more than two million iPS-derived cells into a spinal cord.</p>
<p>No serious adverse event was observed for all four cases after a year of monitoring, the university said.</p>
<p>The research's main goal was to study the safety of injecting the cells.</p>
<p>Public broadcaster NHK reported that one of the two was an elderly man who suffered the <a href="https://medicalxpress.com/tags/injury/" rel="tag">injury</a> in an accident.</p>
<p>He is now able to stand without support and has started practicing walking, NHK said.</p>
<p>"We were able to achieve results in the world's first <a href="https://medicalxpress.com/tags/spinal+cord/" rel="tag">spinal cord</a> treatment with iPS," Hideyuki Okano, a Keio professor who heads the research, said, according to NHK.</p>
<p>Okano said the team hoped to move to a clinical trial that would be a step towards bringing the treatment to patients.</p>
<p>The university received <a href="https://medicalxpress.com/tags/government+approval/" rel="tag">government approval</a> for their initial study in 2019 and they carried out the first operation in 2022.</p>
<p>Details of the patients remain confidential, but the team is focusing on people who were injured 14-28 days before the operation.</p>
<p>The number of cells implanted was determined after safety experiments in animals.</p>

                                                                                
                                        											
										                                                                                    <p>
                                                © 2025 AFP
                                            </p>
                                                                                
                                        <!-- print only -->
                                        <div>
                                            <p><strong>Citation</strong>:
                                                 Japanese scientists use stem cell treatment to restore movement in spinal injury patients (2025, March 22)
                                                 retrieved 24 March 2025
                                                 from https://medicalxpress.com/news/2025-03-japanese-scientists-stem-cell-treatment.html
                                            </p>
                                            <p>
                                            This document is subject to copyright. Apart from any fair dealing for the purpose of private study or research, no
                                            part may be reproduced without the written permission. The content is provided for information purposes only.
                                            </p>
                                        </div>
                                        
									</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HP avoids monetary damages over bricked printers in class-action settlement (108 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/03/hp-avoids-monetary-damages-over-bricked-printers-in-class-action-settlement/</link>
            <guid>43458759</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 09:00:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/03/hp-avoids-monetary-damages-over-bricked-printers-in-class-action-settlement/">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/03/hp-avoids-monetary-damages-over-bricked-printers-in-class-action-settlement/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43458759">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          
          

<p>HP also now provides disclaimers on the product pages for most of the printers that it sells, stating that the device “is intended to work only with cartridges that have a new or reused HP chip” and uses Dynamic Security “to block cartridges using a non-HP chip.”</p>
<p>“Periodic firmware updates will maintain the effectiveness of these measures and block cartridges that previously worked. A reused HP chip enables the use of reused, remanufactured, and refilled cartridges,” the disclaimer says, adding a link to <a href="https://support.hp.com/us-en/document/ish_7470520-7449625-16">a support page</a> about Dynamic Security. The support page notes that “most HP printers can be configured to receive updates either automatically or with a notification that allows you to choose whether to update or not." However, some HP programs, like Instant Ink, require users to enable automatic firmware updates on HP printers.</p>
<p>All this means that, despite the recently approved settlement, Dynamic Security remains a critical part of most HP printers, and HP will continue to feel entitled to <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/03/customers-fume-as-hp-blocks-third-party-ink-from-more-of-its-printers/">use firmware updates</a> to suddenly block printers made after December 1, 2016, from using non-HP ink and toner. Owners of HP printers made after that date that allow automatic updates and still work with third-party accessories shouldn’t be surprised if that ability is suddenly bricked one day.</p>
<h2>Dynamic litigation</h2>
<p>While HP isn't paying a sum to class-action members this time, it has previously agreed to pay millions in relation to bricking printers: In 2022, it agreed to pay <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2022/09/hp-to-pay-eu-printer-customers-1-35-million-for-disabling-third-party-ink/">$1.35 million to European customers</a>, and in 2020, the Italian Antitrust Authority fined HP for 10 million euros. In 2019, HP said it would pay <a href="https://topclassactions.com/lawsuit-settlements/lawsuit-news/hp-ink-cartridge-monopoly-class-action-lawsuit-settles-1-5m/">$1.5 million</a> to settle a similar class-action case in California, and it paid approximately <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2018/05/03/hp_inc_to_compensate_buyers_for_blocking_third_party_ink_cartridges/">AUD$50 </a>each to Australian customers impacted by Dynamic Security in 2018.</p>
<p>There’s also an open case against HP regarding its ink practices, a class-action complaint filed in the US District Court for the Northern District of Illinois in January 2024. The lawsuit centers on <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2024/01/hp-sued-again-for-blocking-third-party-ink-from-printers-accused-of-monopoly/">Dynamic Security firmware updates</a> pushed “in late 2022 and early 2023" and accuses HP of creating a “monopoly in the aftermarket for replacement cartridges” [<a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/HP_Janunary_5_2023.pdf">PDF</a>]. The plaintiffs seek an order declaring that HP broke the law, an injunction against Dynamic Security, and monetary and punitive damages.</p>
<p>Another lawsuit, filed in mid-2022 about some HP all-in-one <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/08/the-printers-that-require-ink-to-scan-and-fax/">printers failing to scan or fax without ink</a>, was dismissed.</p>
<p>HP’s printer arm has other pressing matters to address, though. Earlier this month, a firmware update <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/03/firmware-update-bricks-hp-printers-makes-them-unable-to-use-hp-cartridges/">broke specific HP printer models</a>, preventing them from printing, even when using HP-brand ink. HP told Ars last week that it’s “actively working on a solution.”</p>


          
                  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tesla sales drop 35% in San Diego County (115 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fox5sandiego.com/news/business/tesla-sales-drop-35-in-san-diego-county/</link>
            <guid>43458758</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 09:00:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fox5sandiego.com/news/business/tesla-sales-drop-35-in-san-diego-county/">https://fox5sandiego.com/news/business/tesla-sales-drop-35-in-san-diego-county/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43458758">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://fox5sandiego.com/news/business/tesla-sales-drop-35-in-san-diego-county/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[European Cloud, Global Reach (239 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://upcloud.com/blog/european-cloud-global-reach</link>
            <guid>43458717</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 08:49:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://upcloud.com/blog/european-cloud-global-reach">https://upcloud.com/blog/european-cloud-global-reach</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43458717">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://upcloud.com/blog/european-cloud-global-reach: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Millions are visiting the European Alternatives site. What trends are we seeing? (461 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://plausible.io/blog/european-alternatives-trends-privacy-tech</link>
            <guid>43458509</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 08:03:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://plausible.io/blog/european-alternatives-trends-privacy-tech">https://plausible.io/blog/european-alternatives-trends-privacy-tech</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43458509">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div> <p>☝️That’s a screenshot from the publicly open Plausible Analytics dashboard of the European Alternatives <a href="https://european-alternatives.eu/">website</a>, featuring independent, privacy-friendly digital tools.</p> <p>With almost 2M visitors, 2.3M total visits, and 8.5M pageviews, this library is no longer a niche project—it’s the go-to destination for users looking for independent, privacy-friendly tools. Over 1 million of the ~2 million all-time visitors came in 2025 alone—and we’re only in March.</p> <p>Let’s use the analytics <a href="https://plausible.io/european-alternatives.eu">dashboard</a> to see what trends are emerging and what is the demand looking like for EU-built, privacy-friendly tech.</p> <ol id="markdown-toc"> <li><a href="#1100-surge-in-2025-traffic" id="markdown-toc-1100-surge-in-2025-traffic">1100% surge in 2025 traffic</a></li> <li><a href="#reddit-surpasses-google-while-privacy-friendly-search-engines-gain-traction" id="markdown-toc-reddit-surpasses-google-while-privacy-friendly-search-engines-gain-traction">Reddit surpasses Google, while privacy-friendly search engines gain traction</a></li> <li><a href="#top-5-categories-what-are-people-looking-for" id="markdown-toc-top-5-categories-what-are-people-looking-for">Top 5 categories: What are people looking for?</a></li> <li><a href="#not-just-a-european-trenddemand-goes-beyond-the-eu-borders" id="markdown-toc-not-just-a-european-trenddemand-goes-beyond-the-eu-borders">Not just a European trend—demand goes beyond the EU borders</a></li> <li><a href="#european-countries-leading-and-lagging-in-the-shift-to-privacy-friendly-tools" id="markdown-toc-european-countries-leading-and-lagging-in-the-shift-to-privacy-friendly-tools">European countries leading (and lagging) in the shift to privacy-friendly tools</a></li> <li><a href="#which-european-tools-are-winning" id="markdown-toc-which-european-tools-are-winning">Which European tools are winning?&nbsp;</a></li> <li><a href="#need-a-hand-in-deciding-which-tools-to-go-with" id="markdown-toc-need-a-hand-in-deciding-which-tools-to-go-with">Need a hand in deciding which tools to go with?</a></li> <li><a href="#privacy-friendly-web-analytics-is-on-the-rise" id="markdown-toc-privacy-friendly-web-analytics-is-on-the-rise">Privacy-friendly web analytics is on the rise</a></li> </ol> <h2 id="1100-surge-in-2025-traffic">1100% surge in 2025 traffic</h2> <p>If we filter the dashboard by “Year to date” period, i.e. 2025 so far, we see there have been 1.3 million visitors to the website, with a surge of 1.1K%.&nbsp;</p> <p><img src="https://plausible.io/uploads/2025-stats-for-eu-alternatives.png" alt="1100% surge in 2025 traffic" title="1100% surge in 2025 traffic"></p> <p>Another interesting number is the “time on page,” which is 2m47s spent on average. This goes on to show that people are interested and engaging well with the library.</p> <h2 id="reddit-surpasses-google-while-privacy-friendly-search-engines-gain-traction">Reddit surpasses Google, while privacy-friendly search engines gain traction</h2> <p>Look at the Top Sources report for 2025 so far:</p> <p><img src="https://plausible.io/uploads/top-sources-2025-eu-alternatives.png" alt="top-sources-2025-eu-alternatives" title="top-sources-2025-eu-alternatives"></p> <p>Google is typically the dominant search driver for most websites—but not here. Reddit ranks as the second-largest traffic source, bringing in 311K visitors—significantly more than Google (193K). This isn’t a regular thing we see with sites.</p> <p>This suggests that people aren’t just searching for alternatives but are actively discussing and recommending them in forums, subreddits, and privacy-conscious communities.</p> <p>But here’s another interesting insight: Privacy-friendly search engines are also key traffic sources:</p> <ul> <li>DuckDuckGo: 33.8K visitors</li> <li>Ecosia: 13.5K visitors</li> <li>Qwant: 10.8K visitors</li> </ul> <p>This says something about the increasing preference for privacy-friendly tools, i.e., more people are actively using privacy-friendly search engines to discover other privacy-friendly alternatives.</p> <h2 id="top-5-categories-what-are-people-looking-for">Top 5 categories: What are people looking for?</h2> <p>A quick look at the “Top Pages” report tells us about the most popular top 5 categories:</p> <p>- Email providers</p> <p>- Search Engines</p> <p>- Cloud Computing Platforms</p> <p>- Navigation Apps</p> <p>- Web Analytics Services</p> <p>Upon expanding the report, we can take a deeper look at the most popular categories in terms of unique visitors, while comparing the engagement metrics.</p> <p><img src="https://plausible.io/uploads/top-pages-eu-alternatives.png" alt="top-pages-eu-alternatives" title="top-pages-eu-alternatives"></p> <p><strong>B2B categories win?</strong></p> <p>While categories like email providers, search engines, and navigation apps attract a large B2C audience, B2B categories are more diverse and consistently rank high.&nbsp;</p> <p>Businesses are actively seeking privacy-friendly analytics, hosting, and infrastructure alternatives, driving growth in EU-built tools.</p> <h2 id="not-just-a-european-trenddemand-goes-beyond-the-eu-borders">Not just a European trend—demand goes beyond the EU borders</h2> <p>Looking at the <a href="https://plausible.io/european-alternatives.eu?period=all&amp;keybindHint=A&amp;comparison=off&amp;match_day_of_week=true">all-time Countries report</a>: European countries make up the bulk of visitors (as expected), but the United States ranks fourth, sending over 100K visitors to the site!&nbsp;</p> <p>Even Canada and India make an appearance in the top 25, contributing decent amounts of visitors to the site.</p> <p>If you scroll all the way down, or simply look at the “Map view,” there’s hardly any part of the globe that’s not participating in the shift towards privacy-focused digital tools.</p> <p><img src="https://plausible.io/uploads/map-view.png" alt="map-view" title="map-view"></p> <p>Privacy-conscious users are everywhere.</p>  <p>Germany leads in visitor numbers, with 379K, and contributing 20.5% of the total traffic all-time! This is followed by the Netherlands (141K) and France (135K). These countries show significant engagement with European digital alternatives.</p> <p>On the lower end, Guernsey recorded 130 visitors, while regions like Vatican City State and Saint Martin (French part) had 3 each. The variation in engagement levels may reflect differences in population size, internet adoption rates, etc.</p>  <p>The dashboard has an <a href="https://plausible.io/docs/outbound-link-click-tracking">Outbound link click goal</a> configured, which is useful in understanding which listed tools eventually attract real visitors. Once we filter the dashboard by this goal (see it <a href="https://plausible.io/european-alternatives.eu?f=is,goal,Outbound%20Link:%20Click&amp;period=all&amp;keybindHint=A&amp;comparison=off&amp;match_day_of_week=true">here</a>), we can see which URLs were clicked.</p> <p>From these results, these are the top 10 tools receiving traffic from the EU alternatives website:&nbsp;</p> <ol> <li><a href="https://mailbox.org/en/">Mailbox.org</a> (email provider)</li> <li><a href="https://proton.me/mail">ProtonMail</a> (email provider)</li> <li><a href="https://soverin.com/">Soverin</a> (email provider)</li> <li><a href="https://www.startpage.com/">Startpage</a> (search engine)</li> <li><a href="https://www.qwant.com/">Qwant</a> (search engine)</li> <li><a href="https://posteo.de/en">Posteo</a> (email provider)</li> <li><a href="https://www.ecosia.org/">Ecosia</a> (search engine)</li> <li><a href="https://www.scaleway.com/en/">Scaleway</a> (cloud provider)</li> <li><a href="https://www.startmail.com/">Startmail</a> (email provider)</li> <li><a href="https://good-search.org/en/">Good search</a> (search engine)</li> </ol> <p>And if we look at the all-time data, there’s a whopping 1.2M total outbound clicks from the website to such tools, that’s more than half of the total all-time visits to the library.</p> <p><img src="https://plausible.io/uploads/outbound-clicks-.png" alt="outbound-clicks" title="outbound-clicks"></p> <p>And conversions aren’t just from Europe—the U.S. audience alone has a 16.8% conversion rate (check <a href="https://plausible.io/european-alternatives.eu?f=is,goal,Outbound%20Link:%20Click&amp;f=is,country,US&amp;l=US,United%20States&amp;period=all&amp;keybindHint=A&amp;comparison=off&amp;match_day_of_week=true">here</a>)!</p>  <p>We recently vetted many EU-built B2B tools and picked out a few of our favourites. They’re all:</p> <ul> <li>Built in the EU – Companies headquartered in a European country.</li> <li>Hosted in the EU – Ensuring your data doesn’t leave the European borders and stays compliant with European privacy laws.</li> <li>GDPR-compliant –&nbsp; Tools that align with European data protection laws.</li> <li>High quality – Competitive with mainstream solutions.</li> <li>Privacy-focused – Respecting user data and following GDPR regulations.</li> </ul> <p>Check out our <a href="https://plausible.io/blog/european-privacy-friendly-tools-for-business">handpicked list of 16 privacy-focused European tools</a>.</p> <h2 id="privacy-friendly-web-analytics-is-on-the-rise">Privacy-friendly web analytics is on the rise</h2> <p>We started Plausible Analytics six years ago as a privacy-first, <a href="https://plausible.io/data-policy">GDPR-compliant</a>, <a href="https://plausible.io/blog/google-analytics-cookies">cookieless</a> and muuuch <a href="https://plausible.io/simple-web-analytics">easier-to-use</a> alternative to Google Analytics.</p> <p>So, we took a look at how our category is doing:</p> <ul> <li>5th most popular category in the library</li> <li>9th most visited page overall</li> <li>More than a 2,700% increase in unique visitors in 2025</li> </ul> <p>The demand for privacy-friendly web analytics is booming. If you’re looking for an alternative, check out our <a href="https://plausible.io/privacy-focused-web-analytics">privacy-first approach</a>.</p> <p>👋</p> </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>