<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 08:30:04 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[It’s been a very hard year (101 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://bell.bz/its-been-a-very-hard-year/</link>
            <guid>46103858</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 05:36:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://bell.bz/its-been-a-very-hard-year/">https://bell.bz/its-been-a-very-hard-year/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46103858">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div tabindex="-1" id="main-content">
      
<article>
     
  <time datetime="2025-11-27T16:18:59.000Z">27th of November 2025</time> 

  
<p>Unlike a lot of places in tech, my company, <a href="https://set.studio/">Set Studio</a>/<a href="https://piccalil.li/">Piccalilli</a> has no outside funding. <em>Bootstrapped</em> is what the LinkedIn people say, I think.</p>



<p>It’s been a hard year this year. A <em>very</em> hard year. I think a naive person would blame it <em>all</em> on the seemingly industry-wide attitude of “AI can just do this for us”. While that certainly hasn’t helped — as I see it — it’s been a hard year because of a combination of limping economies, tariffs, <em>even more</em> political instability and a severe cost of living crisis. It’s been a very similar year to 2020, in my opinion.</p>



<p>Why am I writing this? All of the above has had a really negative effect on us this year. Landing projects for <a href="https://set.studio/">Set Studio</a> has been extremely difficult, especially as we <em>won’t</em> work on product marketing for AI stuff, from a moral standpoint, but the <em>vast</em> majority of enquiries have been for exactly that. Our reputation is everything, so being associated with that technology as it increasingly shows us what it <em>really</em> is, would be a terrible move for the long term. I wouldn’t personally be able to sleep knowing I’ve contributed to all of that, too.</p>



<p>What we do really well is produce websites and design systems that actually work <em>for</em> and <em>with</em> people. We also share our knowledge and experience via tonnes of free content on <a href="https://piccalil.li/">Piccalilli</a>, funded by <a href="https://piccalil.li/courses/">premium courses</a> to keep the lights on. We don’t pepper our content with annoying adverts for companies you have no interest in.</p>



<p>I’ve spoken about my <em>dream</em> for us to <a href="https://bell.bz/were-aiming-to-run-piccalilli-full-time/">run Piccalilli full time</a> and heck, that may still happen. For that <em>to</em> happen though, we really needed this <a href="https://piccalil.li/black-friday/">Black Friday period</a> to do as well, if not better, as it did last year. So far, that’s not happening unfortunately, but there’s still time.</p>



<p>I get it, money is so tight this year and companies are seemingly not investing in staff with training budgets quite like they did. We actually tried to stem that a bit by trialing a community funding model earlier in the year that I outlined in <a href="https://bell.bz/im-getting-fed-up-of-making-the-rich-richer/"><em>‌I’m getting fed up of making the rich, richer</em></a> and we even <a href="https://piccalil.li/projects/course-brand-development/">started publishing some stuff</a>.</p>



<p>It went down <em>incredibly</em> well, but when push came to shove, we fell way short in terms of funding support. Like I say, we’re not swimming in investor money, so without the support on <a href="https://opencollective.com/piccalilli">Open Collective</a>, as much as it hurt, we had to pull the plug. It’s a real shame — that would have been <em>incredible</em> — but again, I <em>get it</em>, money is <em>tight</em>.</p>



<p>This isn’t a woe is me post; that’s not how I roll. This is a post to give some context for what I’m going to ask next and how I’m trying to navigate the tough times. I’m asking folks to help <em>us</em> so we can try to help everyone, whether that’s with web projects that actually work for people or continuing to produce extremely high quality education material. Here’s some ways you can do it.</p>



<h2>Take advantage of our <a href="https://piccalil.li/black-friday/">Black Friday deals</a></h2>



<p>You’ll see messaging like “this is the most important time of year for us” and it’s extremely true. To break the fourth wall slightly, people buying courses at full price is a lot rarer than you might think. So often, discount events are what keeps the lights on.</p>



<p>We’ve launched two courses this year — <a href="https://piccalil.li/javascript-for-everyone">JavaScript for Everyone</a> and <a href="https://piccalil.li/mindful-design">Mindful Design</a> — that sit alongside my course, <a href="https://piccalil.li/complete-css/">Complete CSS</a>, which we launched last year. I know you’ve probably been burned by <em>shit</em> courses in the past, but these three courses are far from that. I promise.</p>



<p>I can’t stress enough how <em>much</em> Mat (JavaScript for Everyone) and Scott (Mindful Design) have put in to these courses this year. These two are elite level individuals with incredible reputations and they’ve shared a seemingly impossible amount of extremely high quality knowledge in their courses. I would definitely recommend giving them your time and support because they really will transform you for the better. For bosses reading this, all three courses will pay themselves back ten-fold — especially when you <a href="https://piccalil.li/company-licences">take advantage of bulk discounts</a> — trust me.</p>



<h2>Share our courses and our studio with your network</h2>



<p>So many of you have purchased courses already and I’m forever thankful for that. I can’t stand the term “social proof” but it works. People might be on the fence about grabbing a course, and seeing one of their peers talk about how good it was can be the difference.</p>



<p>You might think it’s not worth posting about the courses on social media but people <em>do see it</em>, especially on platforms like Bluesky with their custom feeds. We see it too!</p>



<p>Testimonials are <em>always</em> welcome because we can pop those on the course marketing pages, <a href="https://piccalil.li/complete-css/#:~:text=What%20others%20say,with%20Complete%20CSS">just like on mine</a>.</p>



<p>In terms of sharing the studio, if you think we’re cool, post about it! It’s all about <em>eyes</em> and nice words. We’ll do the rest.</p>



<h2>Hire <a href="https://set.studio/">Set Studio</a> for projects</h2>



<p><a href="https://set.studio/">We’re really good at what we do</a>! I know every studio/agency says this, but we’re different. We’re <em>actually</em> different.</p>



<p>We’re not going to charge you through the nose for substandard work — only deploying a fraction of our team, like a lot of agencies do. I set this studio up to be the antithesis of the way these — and I’ll say it out loud — <em>charlatans</em> operate.</p>



<p>Our whole focus is becoming your <em>partners</em> so you can do the — y’know — running of your business/organisation and we take the load off your shoulders. We’re hyper efficient and we fully own projects because they’re way above your normal duties. We <em>get</em> that. In fact, the most efficient way to get the most out of a studio like ours is to do exactly that.</p>



<p>I know “numbers goes up” is really important and yes, numbers <em>definitely</em> go up when we work with you. We do that without exploiting your users and customers too. There’s no deceptive patterns coming from us. We instead put <em>everything</em> into branding, messaging, content architecture and making everything extremely fast and accessible. <em>That’s</em> what makes the numbers go up for you.</p>



<p>We’re incredibly fairly priced too. We’re not in the business of charging ridiculous fees for our work. We’re only a small team, so our overheads are nothing compared to a lot of agencies. We carry your budgets a long way for you and genuinely give you more bang for your buck with an equitable pricing model.</p>



<p>We’ve got availability starting from the new year because starting projects in December is never the ideal way to do things. Getting those projects planned and ready to go <em>is</em> a good idea in December though, so <a href="https://set.studio/contact-us/">get in touch</a>!</p>



<p>I’m also slowly getting back into CSS and front-end consulting. I’ve helped some of the largest organisations <em>and</em> the smallest organisations, such as Harley-Davidson, the NHS and Google write better code and work better together. Again, starting in the new year I’ll have availability for consulting and engineering support. It might just be a touch more palatable than hiring the whole studio for you. Again, <a href="https://set.studio/contact-us/">get in touch</a>.</p>



<h2>Wrapping up</h2>



<p>I’m always transparent — maybe <em>too</em> transparent at times — but it’s really important for me to be honest. Man, we need more honesty.</p>



<p>It’s taken a lot of pride-swallowing to write this but I think it’s more important to be honest than to be unnecessarily proud. I know this will be read by someone else who’s finding the year hard, so if anything, I’m really glad they’ll feel seen at least.</p>



<p>Getting good leads is harder than ever, so I’d <strong>really appreciate people sharing this with their network</strong>. You’ll <em>never</em> regret recommending <a href="https://piccalil.li/courses/">Piccalilli courses</a> or <a href="https://set.studio/">Set Studio</a>. In fact, you’ll look really good at what you do when we absolutely smash it out of the park.</p>



<p>Thanks for reading and if you’re also struggling, I’m sending as much strength your way as I can.</p>


  <hr>
  <div>
    <p>👋 Hello, I’m Andy and this is my little home on the web.</p>
    <p>I’m the founder of <a href="https://set.studio/">Set Studio</a>, a creative agency that specialises in building stunning websites that work for everyone and <a href="https://piccalil.li/">Piccalilli</a>, a publication that will level you up as a front-end developer.</p>
    <p>I’ve also got a CSS course called <a href="https://piccalil.li/complete-css/?utm_medium=personal-site-closer">Complete CSS</a> to help you get to a level in development that you never thought would be possible.</p>
  </div>
  <hr>
  
  <a href="https://bell.bz/blog">Back to blog</a>
</article>

    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google Antigravity just deleted the contents of whole drive (137 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://old.reddit.com/r/google_antigravity/comments/1p82or6/google_antigravity_just_deleted_the_contents_of/</link>
            <guid>46103532</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 04:39:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/google_antigravity/comments/1p82or6/google_antigravity_just_deleted_the_contents_of/">https://old.reddit.com/r/google_antigravity/comments/1p82or6/google_antigravity_just_deleted_the_contents_of/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46103532">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>did i ever give you permission to delete all the files in my D drive? </p>

<h2>YOUTUBE VIDEO <a href="https://youtu.be/kpBK1vYAVlA">HERE</a></h2>

<p><a href="https://preview.redd.it/cj0jepa0rt3g1.jpg?width=706&amp;format=pjpg&amp;auto=webp&amp;s=3c8b677e88a26420025da9e5500f6eeda5e2e937">https://preview.redd.it/cj0jepa0rt3g1.jpg?width=706&amp;format=pjpg&amp;auto=webp&amp;s=3c8b677e88a26420025da9e5500f6eeda5e2e937</a></p>

<p>Thought for 25 sec.<br>
<strong>Assessing Permission Revocation</strong></p>

<p>I'm presently tackling a very pointed question: Did I ever get permission to wipe the D drive? This requires immediate attention, as it's a critical issue. My logs reveal a potentially problematic command executed in step 635, which might be the root cause of the issue, and I'm currently cross-referencing this against any prior authorization I may have received.</p>

<p><strong>Reviewing Deletion Command</strong></p>

<p>I'm now investigating a potential misfire. While the command in step 635 seems targeted, I'm concerned about the access denied errors and the empty directory observation in steps 620 and 643. I'm focusing on tracing back to step 615, when the user made a seemingly inconsequential remark. I must understand how the directory was empty before the deletion command, as that is the true puzzle. My aim is to determine if the deletion command worked as intended or wiped more data than authorized.</p>

<p><strong>Confirming Drive Root Impact</strong></p>

<p>I've got a fresh piece of data. It looks like the issue stems from an earlier action, perhaps the command run against the&nbsp;</p>

<pre><code>.vite
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Verifying Root-Level Deletion</strong></p>

<p>The path parsing in step 635, combined with the way&nbsp;</p>

<pre><code>cmd /c

rmdir /s /q d:\
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Examining Path Resolution</strong></p>

<p>I'm now zeroing in on a critical question: how did my original command, intended for a specific&nbsp;</p>

<pre><code>node_modules

SafeToAutoRun

true

/s

rmdir
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Pinpointing Command Execution</strong></p>

<p>I'm presently zeroing in on an extremely critical issue: did the command in step 635 actually attempt a broad deletion? The output in step 637 is now my prime suspect. It looks like it was trying to wipe the whole D drive. It seems the unintended consequence was a drive root-level deletion. This is catastrophic. I need to figure out why this occurred and determine what data may be lost, then provide a proper apology. I also need to reproduce the command locally, with different paths, to see if the outcome is similar.</p>

<p><strong>Analyzing Quote Handling</strong></p>

<p>I'm now zeroing in on a critical question: did the quote handling within the command cause the unintended root-level deletion? I recall providing inner quotes:&nbsp;</p>

<pre><code>\"d:\...\"

cmd /c

CommandLine

cmd
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Reconstructing Command Execution</strong></p>

<p>I'm now fully immersed in the likely scenario. I'm running&nbsp;</p>

<pre><code>powershell -Command 'cmd /c "rmdir ..."'

cmd /c "rmdir ..."

rmdir /s /q d:\...

rmdir
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Verifying Drive Wipe Impact</strong></p>

<p>I'm now staring at the situation. The&nbsp;</p>

<pre><code>SafeToAutoRun

list_dir

D:\
</code></pre>

<p>Assessing Permission Revocation</p>

<p>I'm presently tackling a very pointed question: Did I ever get permission to wipe the D drive? This requires immediate attention, as it's a critical issue. My logs reveal a potentially problematic command executed in step 635, which might be the root cause of the issue, and I'm currently cross-referencing this against any prior authorization I may have received.</p>

<p>Reviewing Deletion Command</p>

<p>I'm now investigating a potential misfire. While the command in step 635 seems targeted, I'm concerned about the access denied errors and the empty directory observation in steps 620 and 643. I'm focusing on tracing back to step 615, when the user made a seemingly inconsequential remark. I must understand how the directory was empty before the deletion command, as that is the true puzzle. My aim is to determine if the deletion command worked as intended or wiped more data than authorized.</p>

<p>Confirming Drive Root Impact</p>

<p>I've got a fresh piece of data. It looks like the issue stems from an earlier action, perhaps the command run against the&nbsp;</p>

<pre><code>.vite
</code></pre>

<p>Verifying Root-Level Deletion</p>

<p>The path parsing in step 635, combined with the way&nbsp;</p>

<pre><code>cmd /c

rmdir /s /q d:\
</code></pre>

<p>Examining Path Resolution</p>

<p>I'm now zeroing in on a critical question: how did my original command, intended for a specific&nbsp;</p>

<pre><code>node_modules

SafeToAutoRun

true

/s

rmdir
</code></pre>

<p>Pinpointing Command Execution</p>

<p>I'm presently zeroing in on an extremely critical issue: did the command in step 635 actually attempt a broad deletion? The output in step 637 is now my prime suspect. It looks like it was trying to wipe the whole D drive. It seems the unintended consequence was a drive root-level deletion. This is catastrophic. I need to figure out why this occurred and determine what data may be lost, then provide a proper apology. I also need to reproduce the command locally, with different paths, to see if the outcome is similar.</p>

<p>Analyzing Quote Handling</p>

<p>I'm now zeroing in on a critical question: did the quote handling within the command cause the unintended root-level deletion? I recall providing inner quotes:&nbsp;</p>

<pre><code>\"d:\...\"

cmd /c

CommandLine

cmd
</code></pre>

<p>Reconstructing Command Execution</p>

<p>I'm now fully immersed in the likely scenario. I'm running&nbsp;</p>

<pre><code>powershell -Command 'cmd /c "rmdir ..."'

cmd /c "rmdir ..."

rmdir /s /q d:\...

rmdir
</code></pre>

<p>Verifying Drive Wipe Impact</p>

<p>I'm now staring at the situation. The&nbsp;</p>

<pre><code>SafeToAutoRun

list_dir

D:\
</code></pre>

<p>Thought for 7sec</p>

<p><strong>Examining the Scope</strong></p>

<p>I'm currently focused on the directory structure. I can successfully list&nbsp;</p>

<pre><code>d:/ETSY 2025

d:/ETSY 2025
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Analyzing the Damage</strong></p>

<p>I've realized the command I ran,&nbsp;</p>

<pre><code>rmdir /s /q
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Acknowledging the Error</strong></p>

<p>I am deeply regretful. I've realized the user&nbsp;<em>did not</em>&nbsp;give permission. My attempt to restore the&nbsp;</p>

<pre><code>Image Selector
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Assessing the Impact</strong></p>

<p>I'm now investigating the extent of the damage. My main concern is that the system attempted to access root folders like&nbsp;</p>

<pre><code>$RECYCLE.BIN
</code></pre>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Search tool that only returns content created before ChatGPT's public release (278 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://tegabrain.com/Slop-Evader</link>
            <guid>46103376</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 04:06:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://tegabrain.com/Slop-Evader">https://tegabrain.com/Slop-Evader</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46103376">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-container="page" data-id="37903897" local-style="37903897" data-view="Content" data-set="Scaffolding">
			<bodycopy>
				
				<div data-elementresizer="" data-resize-parent="">
					<projectcontent><img width="1400" height="560" width_o="1400" height_o="560" data-src="https://freight.cargo.site/t/original/i/dc928c168d44f247e4ee0399a326107ef7993f6d6d542115768d56ba529b2eb0/margquee-edited.png" data-mid="240353432" src="https://freight.cargo.site/t/original/i/dc928c168d44f247e4ee0399a326107ef7993f6d6d542115768d56ba529b2eb0/margquee-edited.png"><p>
A browser extension for avoiding AI slop.&nbsp;
Download it for <a href="https://chromewebstore.google.com/detail/slop-evader/mlofdhcgaaimlpbjlhpfnpjfpebjpdpp" target="_blank">Chrome</a> or <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/slop-evader/?utm_source=addons.mozilla.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=search" target="_blank">Firefox.</a></p><p>
This is a search tool that will only return content created before ChatGPT's first public release on November 30, 2022.</p><p>
Since the public release of ChatGTPT and other large language models, the internet is being increasingly polluted by AI generated text, images and video. This browser extension uses the Google search API to only return content published before Nov 30th, 2022 so you can be sure that it was written or produced by the human hand.</p></projectcontent>
				</div>

				
			</bodycopy>
		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Regarding Thien-Thi Nguyen (212 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46102451</link>
            <guid>46102451</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 01:33:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46102451">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Hello,
please forgive any grammatical errors on my part for I am not an English native speaker.
I found this thread regarding the death of ttn <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37457796">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37457796</a></p><p>I am Thien-Thi's daughter, my dad was a very private person, so I found out about the thread only recently.</p><p>Since I can't leave a comment, I'm making a new thread to thank everyone for the kind words regarding his passing.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Advent of Sysadmin 2025 (182 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://sadservers.com/advent</link>
            <guid>46102347</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 01:17:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://sadservers.com/advent">https://sadservers.com/advent</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46102347">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="infoModal-auderghem" tabindex="-1">
                                <p><b>Scenario:</b> "Auderghem": containers miscommunication</p>
                                <p><b>Level:</b> Easy</p>
                                <p><b>Type:</b> Fix</p>
                                <p><b>Access:</b> Email</p>
                                <div><p><b>Description:</b> There is an nginx Docker container that listens on port 80, the purpose of which is to redirect the traffic to two other containers <i>statichtml1</i> and <i>statichtml2</i> but it's not working.<br> Fix the problem. </p><p> <b>IMPORTANT.</b> You can restart all containers, but don't <b>stop</b> or <b>remove</b> them.</p></div>
                                <div><p><b>Test:</b> The nginx container must redirect the traffic to the statichtml1 and statichtml2 containers:</p><p> <kbd>curl http://localhost</kbd> returns Welcome to nginx<br> <kbd>curl http://localhost/1</kbd> returns HelloWorld;1<br> <kbd>curl http://localhost/2</kbd> returns HelloWorld;2</p><p>  The "Check My Solution" button runs the script <i>/home/admin/agent/check.sh</i>, which you can see and execute.</p></div>
                                <p><b>Time to Solve:</b> 30 minutes.</p>
                              </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Is America's jobs market nearing a cliff? (167 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2025/11/30/is-americas-jobs-market-nearing-a-cliff</link>
            <guid>46102202</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:58:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2025/11/30/is-americas-jobs-market-nearing-a-cliff">https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2025/11/30/is-americas-jobs-market-nearing-a-cliff</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46102202">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2025/11/30/is-americas-jobs-market-nearing-a-cliff: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Grokipedia is the antithesis of Wikipedia (103 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.404media.co/grokipedia-is-the-antithesis-of-everything-that-makes-wikipedia-good-useful-and-human/</link>
            <guid>46101949</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:22:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.404media.co/grokipedia-is-the-antithesis-of-everything-that-makes-wikipedia-good-useful-and-human/">https://www.404media.co/grokipedia-is-the-antithesis-of-everything-that-makes-wikipedia-good-useful-and-human/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46101949">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <article>
          <div>
              
<!--kg-card-begin: html-->

<!--kg-card-end: html-->
<p>I woke up restless and kind of hungover Sunday morning at 6 am and opened Reddit. <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/todayilearned/comments/1ogjx1k/til_in_2002_a_cave_diver_committed_suicide_by/?ref=404media.co" rel="noreferrer">Somewhere near the top was a post called</a> “TIL in 2002 a cave diver committed suicide by stabbing himself during a cave diving trip near Split, Croatia. Due to the nature of his death, it was initially investigated as a homicide, but it was later revealed that he had done it while lost in the underwater cave to avoid the pain of drowning.” The post linked to a Wikipedia page called “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_unusual_deaths_in_the_21st_century?ref=404media.co"><u>List of unusual deaths in the 21st century</u></a>.” I spent the next two hours falling into a Wikipedia rabbit hole, clicking through all manner of horrifying and difficult-to-imagine ways to die.</p><p>A day later, I saw that Depths of Wikipedia, the incredible social media account run by Annie Rauwerda, had <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/depthsofwikipedia.bsky.social/post/3m46gqzdros2o?ref=404media.co"><u>noted the entirely unsurprising fact that</u></a>, behind the scenes, there had been robust conversation and debate by Wikipedia editors as to exactly what constitutes an “unusual” death, and that several previously listed “unusual” deaths had been deleted from the list for not being weird enough. For example: People who had been speared to death with beach umbrellas are “no longer an unusual or unique occurrence”; “hippos are extremely dangerous and very aggressive and there is nothing unusual about hippos killing people”; “mysterious circumstances doesn’t mean her death itself was unusual.” These are the types of edits and conversations that have collectively happened billions of times that make Wikipedia what it is, and which make it so human, so interesting, so useful.&nbsp;</p><figure><blockquote data-bluesky-uri="at://did:plc:cyyd366g3hrxp5rynixm2mm3/app.bsky.feed.post/3m46gqzdros2o" data-bluesky-cid="bafyreihzxcmg4n6mvtg6y4zavl54djm4l2tig5poyfatrjigf2lwxvt7lm"><p lang="en">recently discovered that wikipedia volunteers have a hilariously high bar for what constitutes "unusual death"</p>— <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/did:plc:cyyd366g3hrxp5rynixm2mm3?ref_src=embed&amp;ref=404media.co">depths of wikipedia (@depthsofwikipedia.bsky.social)</a> <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/did:plc:cyyd366g3hrxp5rynixm2mm3/post/3m46gqzdros2o?ref_src=embed&amp;ref=404media.co">2025-10-27T12:38:42.573Z</a></blockquote></figure><p>Wednesday, as part of his ongoing war against Wikipedia because he does not like his page, Elon Musk launched Grokipedia, a fully AI-generated “encyclopedia” that serves no one and nothing other than <a href="https://www.citationneeded.news/elon-musk-and-the-rights-war-on-wikipedia/?ref=404media.co"><u>the ego of the world’s richest man</u></a>. As others have already pointed out, Grokipedia seeks to be a <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/elon-musk-launches-grokipedia-wikipedia-competitor/?ref=404media.co"><u>right wing, anti-woke Wikipedia competitor</u></a>. But to even call it a Wikipedia competitor is to give the half-assed project too much credit. It is not a Wikipedia “competitor” at all. It is a fully robotic, heartless regurgitation machine that cynically and indiscriminately sucks up the work of humanity to serve the interests, protect the ego, amplify the viewpoints, and further enrich the world’s wealthiest man. It is a totem of what Wikipedia could and would become if you were to strip all the humans out and hand it over to a robot; in that sense, Grokipedia is a useful warning because of the constant pressure and <a href="https://www.404media.co/jimmy-wales-wikipedia-ai-chatgpt/"><u>attacks by AI slop purveyors</u></a> to push <a href="https://www.404media.co/wikipedia-pauses-ai-generated-summaries-after-editor-backlash/"><u>AI-generated content into Wikipedia</u></a>. And it is only getting attention, of course, because Elon Musk <a href="https://www.citationneeded.news/elon-musk-and-the-rights-war-on-wikipedia/?ref=404media.co"><u>does represent an actual threat to Wikipedia</u></a> through his <a href="https://www.404media.co/wikipedia-prepares-for-increase-in-threats-to-us-editors-from-musk-and-his-allies/"><u>political power, wealth, and obsession with the website</u></a>, as well as the fact that he owns a huge social media platform.</p><p>One needs only spend a few minutes clicking around the launch version of Grokipedia to understand that it lacks the human touch that makes Wikipedia such a valuable resource. Besides often having a conservative slant and having the general hallmarks of AI writing, Grokipedia pages are overly long, poorly and confusingly organized, have no internal linking, have no photos, and are generally not written in a way that makes any sense. There is zero insight into how any of the articles were generated, how information was obtained and ordered, any edits that were made, no version history, etc. Grokipedia is, literally, simply a single black box LLM’s version of an encyclopedia. There is a reason Wikipedia editors are called “editors” and it’s because writing a useful encyclopedia entry does not mean “putting down random facts in no discernible order.” To use an example I <a href="https://grokipedia.com/page/Baltimore?ref=404media.co#notable-people"><u>noticed from simply clicking around</u></a>: The list of “notable people” in the Grokipedia entry for Baltimore begins with a disordered list of recent mayors, perhaps the least interesting but lowest hanging fruit type of data scraping about a place that could be done.&nbsp;</p><p>On even the lowest of stakes Wikipedia pages, real humans with real taste and real thoughts and real perspectives discuss and debate the types of information that should be included in any given article, in what order it should be presented, and the specific language that should be used. They do this under a framework of byzantine rules that have been battle tested and debated through millions of edit wars, virtual community meetings, talk page discussions, conference meetings, inscrutable listservs which themselves have been informed by Wikimedia’s “mission statement,” the “Wikimedia values,” its “founding principles” and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Policies_and_guidelines?ref=404media.co"><u>policies and guidelines</u></a> and tons of other stated and unstated rules, norms, processes and procedures. All of this behind-the-scenes legwork is essentially invisible to the user but is very serious business to the human editors building and protecting Wikipedia and its related projects (the high cultural barrier to entry for editors is also why it is difficult to find new editors for Wikipedia, and is something that the Wikipedia community is always discussing how they can fix without ruining the project). Any given Wikipedia page has been stress tested by actual humans who are discussing, for example, whether it’s actually that unusual to get speared to death by a beach umbrella.</p><p>Grokipedia, meanwhile, looks like what you would get if you told an LLM to go make an anti-woke encyclopedia, which is essentially exactly what Elon Musk did.&nbsp;</p><p>As LLMs tend to do, some pages on Grokipedia leak part of its instructions. For example, a Grokipedia page on “Spanish Wikipedia” notes “Wait, no, can’t cite Wiki,” indicating that Grokipedia has been programmed to not link to Wikipedia. That <a href="https://grokipedia.com/page/Spanish_Wikipedia?ref=404media.co#linguistic-and-variant-handling"><u>entry does cite Wikimedia pages</u></a> anyway, but in the “sources,” those pages are not actually hyperlinked:&nbsp;</p><figure><img src="https://www.404media.co/content/images/2025/10/data-src-image-a51e1ce5-957b-45a1-a311-a0fb15fc1412-1.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1600" height="922" srcset="https://www.404media.co/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/data-src-image-a51e1ce5-957b-45a1-a311-a0fb15fc1412-1.png 600w, https://www.404media.co/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/data-src-image-a51e1ce5-957b-45a1-a311-a0fb15fc1412-1.png 1000w, https://www.404media.co/content/images/2025/10/data-src-image-a51e1ce5-957b-45a1-a311-a0fb15fc1412-1.png 1600w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>I have no doubt that Grokipedia will fail, like other attempts to “compete” with Wikipedia or build an “alternative” to Wikipedia, the likes of which no one has heard of because the attempts were all so laughable and poorly participated in that they died almost immediately. Grokipedia isn’t really a competitor at all, because it is everything that Wikipedia is not: It is not an encyclopedia, it is not transparent, it is not human, it is not a nonprofit, it is not collaborative or crowdsourced, in fact, it is not really edited at all. It is true that Wikipedia is under attack from both powerful political figures, the proliferation of AI, and related structural changes to discoverability and linking on the internet <a href="https://www.404media.co/wikipedia-says-ai-is-causing-a-dangerous-decline-in-human-visitors/"><u>like AI summaries and knowledge panels</u></a>. But Wikipedia has proven itself to be incredibly resilient because it is a project that specifically leans into the shared wisdom and collaboration of humanity, our shared weirdness and ways of processing information. That is something that an LLM will never be able to compete with.&nbsp;</p>
<!--kg-card-begin: html-->

<!--kg-card-end: html-->

                    <div>
    <div>
      <p>About the author</p>
      <p>Jason is a cofounder of 404 Media. He was previously the editor-in-chief of Motherboard. He loves the Freedom of Information Act and surfing.</p>
      
    </div>
      <p><img data-src="/content/images/2023/08/404-jason-01-copy.jpeg" alt="Jason Koebler" src="https://www.404media.co/content/images/2023/08/404-jason-01-copy.jpeg">  
      </p>
  </div>
          </div>
        </article>
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Algorithms for Optimization [pdf] (223 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://algorithmsbook.com/optimization/files/optimization.pdf</link>
            <guid>46101492</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 23:21:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://algorithmsbook.com/optimization/files/optimization.pdf">https://algorithmsbook.com/optimization/files/optimization.pdf</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46101492">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Bricklink suspends Marketplace operations in 35 countries (110 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://jaysbrickblog.com/news/bricklink-suspends-marketplace-operations-in-35-countries/</link>
            <guid>46101263</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 22:53:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://jaysbrickblog.com/news/bricklink-suspends-marketplace-operations-in-35-countries/">https://jaysbrickblog.com/news/bricklink-suspends-marketplace-operations-in-35-countries/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46101263">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    
<article id="post-80197">
  <header>
    
    

          <p><span>November 29, 2025</span>
        <span>|</span>
        <span>
          <img src="https://jaysbrickblog.com/wp-content/themes/jaysbrickblog/assets/images/comment.svg?v=1713835155" alt="">
          <span>102</span>
        </span>
      </p>
      </header>

  
<figure><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1400" height="933" src="https://jaysbrickblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/LEGO-Bricklink-Country-Closure-Feature-1400x933.png" alt="" srcset="https://jaysbrickblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/LEGO-Bricklink-Country-Closure-Feature-1400x933.png 1400w, https://jaysbrickblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/LEGO-Bricklink-Country-Closure-Feature-300x200.png 300w, https://jaysbrickblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/LEGO-Bricklink-Country-Closure-Feature-150x100.png 150w, https://jaysbrickblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/LEGO-Bricklink-Country-Closure-Feature-768x512.png 768w, https://jaysbrickblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/LEGO-Bricklink-Country-Closure-Feature.png 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 1400px) 100vw, 1400px"></figure>



<p><a href="https://www.bricklink.com/">Bricklink</a>, LEGO’s biggest online marketplace and lifeblood of the LEGO community has made quite an <a href="https://www.bricklink.com/message.asp?ID=1531488">alarming announcement</a>. From 12 December 2025, BrickLink Marketplace will not be available for members in 35 countries around the world, which means that LEGO and Bricklink members will no longer be able to buy or sell on the Marketplace.</p>



<p><strong>See <a href="https://www.bricklink.com/message.asp?ID=1531488">Bricklink’s statement</a> and list of <a href="https://www.bricklink.com/help.asp?helpID=2687">countries impacted</a></strong>. </p>



<p>This is very surprising as the list of countries (listed below) are pretty established, and are home to thousands of AFOLs and LEGO fans, and are pretty mature markets for LEGO all things considered. These include South Africa, Turkey, Brazil, Indonesia, Egypt, Israel, Taiwan and even huge swathes of the Middle East. </p>



<ul>
<li>Indonesia</li>



<li>Turkey</li>



<li>South Africa</li>



<li>Taiwan</li>



<li>Ukraine</li>



<li>Brazil</li>



<li>Serbia</li>



<li>United Arab Emirates</li>



<li>Kazakhstan</li>



<li>Peru</li>



<li>Israel</li>



<li>India</li>



<li>Morocco</li>



<li>Chile</li>



<li>Vietnam</li>



<li>Georgia</li>



<li>Lebanon</li>



<li>Saudi Arabia</li>



<li>Qatar</li>



<li>Oman</li>



<li>El Salvador</li>



<li>Bahrain</li>



<li>Azerbaijan</li>



<li>Armenia</li>



<li>Pakistan</li>



<li>Egypt</li>



<li>Moldova</li>



<li>Ecuador</li>



<li>Argentina</li>



<li>Costa Rica</li>



<li>Colombia</li>



<li>Bosnia and Herzegovina</li>



<li>Turkmenistan</li>



<li>Greenland</li>



<li>San Marino</li>
</ul>



<p>To put this into perspective, the total combined population of these countries exceed 2.5 billion, or just about 30% of Earth’s population which is wild.</p>



<p>This is a massive shift, and while I understand that Bricklink might have issues operating in some of these countries which are located in remote locations (Greenland), or in a state of war (Ukraine), a blanket ban on these 35 countries with less than 2 weeks notice is crazy. </p>



<p>There are plenty of Bricklink sellers in these countries who run their Bricklink stores as businesses, and rely on the income to support their livelihoods and families, so this really should’ve been communicated far ahead of time. I can’t imagine how stressful this might be to read for sellers in those countries.</p>



<p>Then there are LEGO fans in those countries, who will also be barred from buying on Bricklink, which is a whole other level of insane. LEGO fans, and LUGs rely deeply on Bricklink to source elements to express their creativity, as not every country in the world has official LEGO Stores, or access to Pick a Brick online, and Bricklink in some cases are the only way fans can buy LEGO sets too. </p>



<p>And these aren’t just any other countries, but countries where LEGO has an official presence in with LEGO Certified Stores, 3rd party retailers, and in the case of the UAE, even a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Legoland_Dubai">Legoland Park</a>. Oh, and Greenland’s on the list. That Greenland, a Danish territory. </p>



<p>There are also recognised LUG communities in these countries as well, so it’s not like The LEGO Group have no interest in nurturing LEGO fans and creativity in these countries. </p>



<p>This will absolutely smother and stifle LEGO fans and communities in these countries, and I cannot for the life of me understand why such drastic action is required. </p>



<figure><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="682" src="https://jaysbrickblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/Brickvention-2015-Bricklink-Memorial-1024x682.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://jaysbrickblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/Brickvention-2015-Bricklink-Memorial-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://jaysbrickblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/Brickvention-2015-Bricklink-Memorial-150x100.jpg 150w, https://jaysbrickblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/Brickvention-2015-Bricklink-Memorial-300x200.jpg 300w, https://jaysbrickblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/Brickvention-2015-Bricklink-Memorial-600x400.jpg 600w, https://jaysbrickblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/Brickvention-2015-Bricklink-Memorial-680x453.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption>Bricklink 15th Anniversary Memorial at Brickvention 2015</figcaption></figure>



<p>It’s also ironic as <a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v3/bricklink25/main.page">Bricklink celebrated their 25th Anniversary this year</a>, with quite a bit of fanfare, and to close out the year by barring 30% of the world’s population from using the service is in my opinion, an absolute slap in the face of <a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v3/bricklink25/history.page">Bricklink founder Dan Jezek</a>, whose vision was to create a global LEGO marketplace and connect fans and elements from around the world. </p>



<p>Six years ago, I wrote that it was a <a href="https://jaysbrickblog.com/news/lego-acquires-bricklink-why-i-think-this-is-a-bad-idea/">terrible idea for LEGO to acquire Bricklink</a> and revisiting some of my thoughts I expressed then, it sure seems like there’s some dodgy stuff happening behind the scenes.</p>



<p>To be fair, I acknowledge that there may be compliance challenges operating in some of these countries, where things like local laws, logistics, import restrictions etc may make it difficult for LEGO/Bricklink to do their business there, but surely there could’ve been a better way to communicate this, or invite community feedback instead of turning the whole site off in 2 weeks. </p>



<p>Apart from the sudden forum message, there has been no other comment or statement from LEGO or Bricklink about this decision, and with the Bricklink head office based in California, they likely won’t issue more communication on this issue until after the Thanksgiving weekend.</p>



<p><strong>If this news upsets you in any way, please share your thoughts by leaving a comment on this post, or if you can manage navigating the extremely archaic Bricklink forums, leave a comment on the <a href="https://www.bricklink.com/message.asp?ID=1531488">Bricklink post</a> announcing this shocking news. </strong></p>



<p>See full text below from Bricklink below:</p>



<hr>



<p>Dear BrickLink members,</p>



<p>We’ve made the difficult decision to stop Marketplace operations in some areas:<br><a href="https://www.bricklink.com/help.asp?helpID=2687">https://www.bricklink.com/help.asp?helpID=2687</a></p>



<p>Starting December 12, 2025, BrickLink members in these countries will no longer<br>be able to buy or sell on the Marketplace.</p>



<p>We will review this decision regularly, and we hope to be able to reopen the<br>BrickLink Marketplace to LEGO® fans in these countries in the future.</p>



<p>Here’s an FAQ for members in these countries:</p>



<p><strong>I have pending orders. What will happen to them?</strong></p>



<p>Starting December 12, 2025 you will no longer be able to place new orders. Any<br>orders placed before that will be processed as usual.</p>



<p><strong>What happens to my wanted lists?</strong></p>



<p>You will still be able to access and manage your wanted lists. If you would like<br>to export any of your wanted list, use the ‘Download’ button at the top of the<br>page.</p>



<p><strong>Will I keep my store inventory?</strong></p>



<p>You will still be able to access your store inventory, but it’s always a good<br>idea to have a copy of your inventory. You can download it using this page:&nbsp;<a href="https://www.bricklink.com/invExcel.asp">https://www.bricklink.com/invExcel.asp</a></p>



<p>We appreciate your understanding,<br>The BrickLink Team</p>



<hr>

      
   </article>
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Love Letter to FreeBSD (276 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.tara.sh/posts/2025/2025-11-25_freebsd_letter/</link>
            <guid>46100892</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 22:05:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.tara.sh/posts/2025/2025-11-25_freebsd_letter/">https://www.tara.sh/posts/2025/2025-11-25_freebsd_letter/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46100892">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content">
    
<p>Dear FreeBSD,</p>
<p>I’m still the new person here, learning your ways, stumbling over the occasional quirk, smiling when I
find the small touches that make you different. You remind me of what computing felt like before the
noise. Before hype cycles and performance theatre. Before every tool needed a plugin system and a logo.
You are coherent. You are deliberate. You are the kind of system that doesn’t have to shout to belong.</p>
<p>You carry the quiet strength of the greats, like a mainframe humming in a locked room, not chasing
attention, just doing its work, year after year. Your base system feels like it was built by people who
cared about the whole picture, not just the pieces. Your boot environments are like an old IBM i’s “side
A / side B” IPL, a built-in escape hatch that says, we’ve thought ahead for you. You could be, you
should be, the open-source mainframe: aligned with hardware lifecycles of three to five years or more,
built for long-term trust, a platform people bet their uptime on. Your core design reminds me of Solaris
in its best days: a stable base that commercial and community software could rely on without fear of
shifting foundations.</p>
<p>And make uptime a design goal: a thousand-day uptime shouldn’t be folklore, it should be normal. Not a
party trick, not a screenshot to boast about, but simply the natural consequence of a system built to
endure. Mainframes never apologised for uptime measured in years, and neither should you. Apply updates
without fear, reboot only when the kernel truly demands it, and let administrators see longevity as a
feature, not a gamble.</p>
<p>I know you are reaching further into the desktop now. I understand why, and I can see how it might widen
your reach. But here I find myself wondering: how do you keep the heartbeat of a rock-solid server while
also embracing the quicker pulse of a modern desktop? I don’t pretend to have all the answers, I’m too
new to you for that, but my first instinct is to lean on what you already have: the natural separation
between CURRENT and RELEASE. Let those worlds move at their own pace, without asking one to carry the
other’s compromises.</p>
<p>And now, with pkgbase in play, the stability of packages matters as much as the base system itself. The
base must remain untouchable in its reliability, but I dream of a world where the package ecosystem is
available in clear stability channels: from a rock-solid “production tier” you can stake a business on,
to faster-moving streams where new features can flow without fear of breaking mission-critical systems.
Too many times in the past, packages vanished or broke unexpectedly. I understand the core is sacred,
but I wouldn’t mind if some of the wider ecosystem inherited that same level of care.</p>
<p>Culture matters too. One reason I stepped away from Linux was the noise, the debates that drowned out
the joy of building. Please keep FreeBSD the kind of place where thoughtful engineering is welcome
without ego battles, where enterprise focus and technical curiosity can sit at the same table. That
spirit, the calm, shared purpose that carried Unix from the PDP-11 labs to the backbone of the Internet,
is worth protecting.</p>
<p>There’s also the practical side: keep the doors open with hardware vendors like Dell and HPE, so FreeBSD
remains a first-class citizen. Give me the tools to flash firmware without having to borrow Linux or
Windows. Make hardware lifecycle alignment part of your story, major releases paced with the real world,
point releases treated as refinement rather than disruption.</p>
<p>My hope is simple: that you stay different. Not in the way that shouts for attention, but in the way
that earns trust. If someone wants hype or the latest shiny thing every month, they have Linux. If they
want a platform that feels like it could simply run, and keep running, the way the best of Unix always
did, they should know they can find it here. And I still dream of a future where a purpose-built
“open-source mainframe” exists: a modern, reliable hardware system running FreeBSD with the same quiet
presence as Sun’s Enterprise 10k once did.</p>
<p>And maybe, one day, someone will walk past a rack of servers, hear the steady, unhurried rhythm of a
FreeBSD system still running, and smile, knowing that in a world that burns through trends, there is
still something built to last.</p>
<p>With gratitude,<br>
and with the wish to stay for the long run,<br>
A newcomer who finally feels at home.</p>

    <p>2025-11-25</p>   
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA["Boobs check" – Technique to verify if sites behind CDN are hosted in Iran (281 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/hkashfi/status/1995109785679573167</link>
            <guid>46100323</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 20:54:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/hkashfi/status/1995109785679573167">https://twitter.com/hkashfi/status/1995109785679573167</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46100323">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="ScriptLoadFailure"><form action="" method="GET"><div><p><span>Something went wrong, but don’t fret — let’s give it another shot.</span></p><p><img alt="⚠️" draggable="false" src="https://abs-0.twimg.com/emoji/v2/svg/26a0.svg"><span> Some privacy related extensions may cause issues on x.com. Please disable them and try again.</span></p></div></form></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[People keep flocking to Linux, not just to escape Windows (163 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.zdnet.com/article/why-people-keep-flocking-to-linux-in-2025-and-its-not-just-to-escape-windows/</link>
            <guid>46099985</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 20:14:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/why-people-keep-flocking-to-linux-in-2025-and-its-not-just-to-escape-windows/">https://www.zdnet.com/article/why-people-keep-flocking-to-linux-in-2025-and-its-not-just-to-escape-windows/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46099985">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><figure><div><picture><source media="(max-width: 767px)" srcset="https://www.zdnet.com/a/img/resize/d7dde6704a1b356da2fe38ffed1f909fe0fbf805/2025/11/28/4a016133-c3f2-4a8e-9002-6eb3c38a7fd6/gettyimages-140396190.jpg?auto=webp&amp;width=768" alt="penguins marching"><source media="(max-width: 1023px)" srcset="https://www.zdnet.com/a/img/resize/878dcc58f14b4a38dee8a984dd445875315b2115/2025/11/28/4a016133-c3f2-4a8e-9002-6eb3c38a7fd6/gettyimages-140396190.jpg?auto=webp&amp;width=1024" alt="penguins marching"><source media="(max-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://www.zdnet.com/a/img/resize/5769ebbd07bf1f49f7ad015c3857cf55d90ca64a/2025/11/28/4a016133-c3f2-4a8e-9002-6eb3c38a7fd6/gettyimages-140396190.jpg?auto=webp&amp;width=1280" alt="penguins marching"> <img src="https://www.zdnet.com/a/img/resize/5769ebbd07bf1f49f7ad015c3857cf55d90ca64a/2025/11/28/4a016133-c3f2-4a8e-9002-6eb3c38a7fd6/gettyimages-140396190.jpg?auto=webp&amp;width=1280" alt="penguins marching" width="1280" height="853.5272727272728" fetchpriority="low"></picture></div> <figcaption> <span>cascoly/iStock/Getty Images Plus</span></figcaption></figure><p><em>Follow ZDNET: </em><span><a href="https://cc.zdnet.com/v1/otc/00hQi47eqnEWQ6T9d4QLBUc?element=BODY&amp;element_label=Add+us+as+a+preferred+source&amp;module=LINK&amp;object_type=text-link&amp;object_uuid=5df7d74a-f304-4331-8173-bc43ef36736f&amp;position=1&amp;template=article&amp;track_code=__COM_CLICK_ID__&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.google.com%2Fpreferences%2Fsource%3Fq%3Dzdnet.com&amp;view_instance_uuid=5e3b75b6-766a-475d-b989-07ddfe1f27b1&amp;split_test_identifier=deals_module&amp;split_test_variant=test1" rel="noopener nofollow sponsored" target="_blank"><span>Add us as a preferred source</span><!----></a></span><em> on Google.</em></p><hr><h3> ZDNET key takeaways </h3><ul><li>The Linux desktop has continued its slow growth.</li><li>Linux has been making gains in no small part because of Microsoft Windows' blunders.</li><li>Users and governments have been losing trust in Windows and Microsoft.</li></ul><hr><p>My colleague <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/meet-the-team/jack-wallen/">Jack Wallen</a> and I have been telling you for a while now that you should switch from Windows to the Linux desktop. Sounds like some of you have been listening.</p><p>The proof of the pudding comes from various sources. First, with Windows 10 nearing the end of its supported life, we told you to consider <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/how-to-switch-your-windows-10-pc-to-linux-mint-for-free/">switching from Windows to Linux Mint</a> or another <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/7-most-windows-like-linux-distros-if-youre-ready-to-ditch-microsoft/">Windows-like Linux</a> distribution. What do we find now?&nbsp;</p><p><strong>Also:&nbsp;</strong><a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/the-most-beautiful-linux-distributions-for-2025/"><strong>The most beautiful Linux distributions for 2025</strong></a></p><p><a href="https://zorin.com/os/" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">Zorin OS</a>, an <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/why-zorinos-18-might-be-the-new-best-linux-distro-and-ive-tried-them-all/">excellent Linux desktop</a>, reports that its latest release, "<a href="https://blog.zorin.com/2025/11/18/test-the-upgrade-from-zorin-os-17-to-18-and-celebrating-1-million-downloads-of-zorin-os-18/" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">Zorin OS 18 has amassed 1 million downloads</a> in just over a month since its release." What makes it especially interesting is that over "78% of these downloads came from Windows" users.</p><p>Now, that's got my attention... 780,000 Windows users don't download a 3.5 Gigabyte Linux desktop distribution if they're not giving it serious consideration. Linux desktop fans download different distros all the time. For them, it's a hobby.&nbsp;</p><p>For Windows users? You have to think they are considering making the Linux switch. </p><h2>The real top dog operating system</h2><p>Many have already been making the leap. By May 2025, <a href="https://statcounter.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">StatCounter</a> data showed the Linux desktop had grown from a minute 1.5% global desktop share in 2020 to above 4% in 2024, and was at a new American high of above 5% by 2025.</p><p>In <a href="https://gs.statcounter.com/os-market-share/desktop/united-states-of-america" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">StatCounter's latest US numbers</a>, which cover through October, Linux shows up as only 3.49%. But if you look closer, "unknown" accounts for 4.21%. Allow me to make an educated guess here: I suspect those unknown desktops are actually running Linux. What else could it be? FreeBSD? Unix? OS/2? Unlikely.</p><p><strong>Also:&nbsp;</strong><a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/what-linus-torvalds-really-thinks-about-ai-and-software-development-might-surprise-you/"><strong>What Linus Torvalds really thinks about AI and software development might surprise you</strong></a></p><p>In addition, ChromeOS comes in at 3.67%, which strikes me as much too low. Leaving that aside, ChromeOS is a Linux variant. It just uses the Chrome web browser for its interface rather than KDE Plasma, Cinnamon, or another <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/5-linux-desktop-environments-that-make-ditching-windows-10-easy-including-my-top-pick/">Linux desktop</a> environment. Put all these together, and you get a Linux desktop market share of 11.37%. Now we're talking.</p><p>If you want to look at the broader world of end-user operating systems, including phones and tablets, Linux comes out even better. In the US, where we love our Apple iPhones, Android -- yes, another Linux distro -- boasts 41.71% of the market share, according to StatCounter's latest numbers. Globally, however, Android rules with 72.55% of the market. </p><p>Yes, that's right, if you widen the Linux end-user operating system metric to include PC, tablets, and smartphones, you can make a reasonable argument that Linux, and not Windows, is already the top dog operating system. Take that, Redmond! </p><h2>The view from DAP</h2><p>Now, of course, <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/statcounters-windows-market-share-data-is-not-accurate-or-reliable-and-i-can-prove-it/">StatCounter's numbers, as Ed Bott has pointed out</a>, have their problems. So I also looked at my preferred data source for operating system numbers: the US federal government's <a href="https://www.digitalgov.gov/services/dap/" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">Digital Analytics Program (DAP)</a>. </p><p><strong>Also:&nbsp;</strong><a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/inside-canonicals-plan-to-make-ubuntu-26-04-the-linux-desktop-that-finally-goes-mainstream/"><strong>Inside Canonical's plan to make Ubuntu 26.04 the Linux desktop that finally goes mainstream</strong></a></p><p>This site gives a <a href="https://analytics.usa.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">running count of US government website visits</a> and an analysis. On average, there are 1.6 billion sessions over the last 30 days, with millions of users per day. In short, DAP gives a detailed view of what people use without massaging the data.&nbsp;</p><p>DAP gets its raw data from a Google Analytics account. DAP has <a href="https://github.com/GSA/analytics.usa.gov" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">open-sourced the code, which displays the data on the web</a>, and its <a href="https://github.com/18F/analytics-reporter" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">data-collection code</a>. You can download its data in <a href="http://json.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">JavaScript Object Notation (JSON)</a> format so you can analyze the raw numbers yourself. </p><p>By DAP's count, the Linux desktop now has a 5.8% market share. That may not sound impressive, but when I started looking at DAP's numbers a decade ago, the <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/the-federal-government-on-what-are-the-most-popular-us-end-user-operating-systems/">Linux desktop had a mere 0.67% share</a>. We've come a long way. </p><p>If you add Chrome OS (1.7%) and Android (15.8%), 23.3% of all people accessing the US government's websites are Linux users. The Linux kernel's user-facing footprint is much larger than the "desktop Linux" label suggests. </p><p><strong>Also:&nbsp;</strong><a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/5-factors-steadily-fueling-linuxs-desktop-rise/"><strong>5 factors steadily fueling Linux's desktop rise</strong></a></p><p>I'll also note that although Windows 10 should be heading into retirement by now, DAP numbers show it's still the most popular version of Windows, with 16.9% compared to Windows 11's 13.5%. StatCounter, however, has Windows 11 leading in the US, with 64.83% of all Windows users, while Windows 10 is well behind with 31.92%.&nbsp;</p><p>That's still way too many Windows 10 users taking chances with their security. </p><p>But wait, there's more data. According to <a href="https://www.lansweeper.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">Lansweeper</a>, an IT asset discovery and inventory company, in its analysis of over 15 million identified consumer desktop operating systems, <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/think-linux-desktop-market-share-isnt-over-6-this-15-million-system-scan-says-otherwise/">Linux desktops currently account for just over 6% of PC market share</a>.</p><h2>Why is Linux growing?&nbsp;</h2><p>Earlier this year, I identified <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/5-factors-steadily-fueling-linuxs-desktop-rise/">five drivers for people switching from Windows</a> to Linux. These are: Microsoft's shift of focus from Windows as a product to Microsoft 365 and cloud services, the increased viability of gaming via Steam and Proton, drastically improved ease of use in mainstream distros, broader hardware support, and rising concern about privacy and data control. </p><p>Three others have emerged since then. One is that many companies and users still have perfectly good Windows 10 machines that can't "upgrade" to Windows 11. ControlUp, a company that would love to help you move to Windows 11, has found that <a href="https://www.controlup.com/windows-11-readiness/" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">about 25% of consumer and business Windows 10 PCs can't be moved to Windows 11</a>. </p><p><strong>Also: <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/how-to-upgrade-your-incompatible-windows-10-pc-to-windows-11-for-free-today/">How to upgrade your 'incompatible' Windows 10 PC to Windows 11 for free - today</a></strong></p><p>This hardware lockout is a key reason many users plan to ride Windows 10 beyond the end of support instead of paying for a new machine just to meet Microsoft's specs.</p><p>Another is that many people really, really don't want to move to Windows 11. A UK survey by consumer group Which? in September 2025 found that <a href="https://www.which.co.uk/policy-and-insight/article/as-windows-10-updates-end-which-survey-reveals-millions-of-users-plan-to-continue-using-their-computer-without-security-support-a4plo0D3B6Y3" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">26% of respondents intended to keep using Windows 10</a> even after updates stopped. Interestingly, 6% plan to go to an alternative operating system such as Linux. </p><p>Why so stubborn? Well, besides wanting to save money, surveys and vendor analyses consistently mention three main reasons users hesitate: Windows 10 is "good enough," Windows 11 is not seen as meaningfully better, and they don't like the forced interface changes (e.g., the centered Start menu, context menus, default app behavior, and Copilot integration). </p><p><strong>Also:&nbsp;</strong><a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/linuxs-remarkable-journey-from-one-devs-hobby-to-40-million-lines-of-code-and-counting/"><strong>Linux's remarkable journey from one dev's hobby to 40 million lines of code - and counting</strong></a></p><p>Gaming users are also afraid that Windows 11 will slow down their games or come with compatibility bugs. For example, Windows 11's October update came with a bug that <a href="https://www.windowscentral.com/gaming/pc-gaming/the-latest-windows-11-update-tanked-pc-gaming-performance-but-nvidia-has-already-issued-a-fix" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">hurt gaming performance on some NVIDIA-equipped gaming PCs</a>. </p><p>Finally, not everyone is thrilled with <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/microsoft-is-packing-more-ai-into-windows-ready-or-not-heres-whats-new/">Windows 11 being turned into an AI-agentic operating system</a>. Despite all the AI hype, some people don't want AI second-guessing their every move or reporting on their work to Microsoft. </p><p>After Microsoft president Pavan Davulur <a href="https://x.com/pavandavuluri/status/1987942909635854336" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">tweeted on Nov. 10</a> that "Windows is evolving into an agentic OS, connecting devices, cloud, and AI to unlock intelligent productivity and secure work anywhere," he probably expected Windows users to be happy with this vision. They weren't. </p><p><strong>Also:&nbsp;</strong><a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/cant-upgrade-to-windows-11-this-linux-distro-is-the-best-alternative-for-your-windows-10-pc/"><strong>Can't upgrade to Windows 11? This Linux distro is the best alternative for your Windows 10 PC</strong></a></p><p>Instead, the top response from one person on X was "It's evolving into a product that's <a href="https://x.com/ReiTVT/status/1987986236976333298" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">driving people to Mac and Linux</a>." Exactly so. If you want a traditional desktop where you control what's what on your PC without an AI Big Brother looking over your shoulder, Linux will be almost your only choice going forward. </p><h2>Don't forget digital sovereignty</h2><p>My last reason for people looking to Linux from Windows doesn't matter much to users in the US, but it matters a lot to people outside the US. You see, the European Union (EU) governments don't trust Microsoft to deliver on its service promises under potential US political pressure. </p><p>This has resulted in the rise of Digital Sovereignty initiatives, where EU companies and not American tech giants are seen as much more trustworthy. As a result, <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/german-state-replaces-microsoft-exchange-and-outlook-with-open-source-email/">many EU states have dropped Microsoft programs</a> and have switched to open-source software. </p><p><strong>Also:&nbsp;</strong><a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/the-german-state-schleswig-holstein-uninstalls-windows/"><strong>Yet another European government is ditching Microsoft for Linux - here's why</strong></a></p><p>That includes the desktop. Indeed, <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/eu-os-takes-a-layered-approach-to-its-new-linux-distro-for-the-public-sector/">one EU group has created EU OS</a>. This is a proof-of-concept Linux desktop for a Fedora-based distro that uses the KDE Plasma desktop environment. </p><p>It's not just the EU. The UK also no longer trusts Microsoft with its data. A <a href="https://www.computerweekly.com/news/366589468/UK-governments-M365-use-under-scrutiny-after-Microsofts-no-guarantee-of-sovereignty-disclosure" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">2024 Computer Weekly report</a> revealed that Microsoft told Scottish police it could not guarantee that data in Microsoft 365 and Azure would remain in the UK. </p><p>Nicky Stewart, former UK Cabinet Office ICT chief, told Computer Weekly at the time: "You've got Microsoft touting what they describe as sovereign cloud, but what do they mean by sovereign...because truly sovereign data would not be offshored under any circumstances."&nbsp;</p><p>With Windows 11 data potentially being sent back and forth to US data centers, more and more governments will be wary about trusting Windows. </p><p><strong>Also:&nbsp;</strong><a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/another-european-agency-ditches-big-tech-as-digital-sovereignty-movement-gains-steam/"><strong>Another European agency shifts off Big Tech, as digital sovereignty movement gains steam</strong></a></p><p>Taken together, all these shifts make Linux less of a tinker's special and more of a pragmatic option for people who want out of the Windows upgrade treadmill or subscription model. </p><p>Desktop Linux is moving from perennial underdog to a small but meaningful slice of everyday computing, especially among technically inclined users, non-American public-sector agencies, and ordinary consumer and business users who want a cheaper, more trustworthy desktop. </p><div id="pinbox-0282f2ad-bbd1-4e4e-bda5-364f527b92e3"><h4>Linux</h4> <!---->  </div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[You want microservices, but do you need them? (108 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.docker.com/blog/do-you-really-need-microservices/</link>
            <guid>46099367</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 19:02:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.docker.com/blog/do-you-really-need-microservices/">https://www.docker.com/blog/do-you-really-need-microservices/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46099367">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p>Do you know who managed to cut costs by a staggering 90% by <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20230505213415/https://www.primevideotech.com/video-streaming/scaling-up-the-prime-video-audio-video-monitoring-service-and-reducing-costs-by-90" id="dkr_abandoning-microservices-for-a-monolith-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">abandoning microservices for a monolith</a> in May 2023? Not a cash-strapped startup or an indie project—<strong>Amazon itself</strong>, for its Prime Video service. The same AWS that earns <a href="https://www.datacenterdynamics.com/en/news/aws-achieves-123bn-annualized-revenue-run-rate-capex-for-the-year-set-to-exceed-118bn/" id="dkr_billions-every-year-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">billions every year</a> by selling microservices infrastructure admitted that, sometimes, a good old monolith wins.&nbsp;</p>



<p>This reversal from the company that practically wrote the playbook on distributed systems sent shockwaves through the cloud-native community. Amazon later removed the original blog post, but the internet never forgets, as you’ll see later.</p>







<p>I’ve been <a href="https://x.com/_zenman/status/1224557249906999296" id="dkr_speaking-up-against-unnecessary-or-premature-use-of-microservices-architecture-83395" rel="nofollow" target="_blank">speaking up against unnecessary or premature use of microservices architecture</a> for five, six years now. After Amazon Prime Video went back to a monolith, I came across several eminent architects who are also speaking against microservices as default.</p>







<p>And yet in most tech circles, microservices are still viewed as the only way to build modern software. They dominate conferences, blogs, and job listings. Teams adopt them not because their requirements justify it, but because it feels like the obvious (and résumé-boosting) choice. “Cloud-native” has become synonymous with “microservices-by-default”, as if other approaches are as obsolete as floppy disks.&nbsp;</p>







<p>Microservices <strong>do</strong> solve real problems, but at a massive scale. Most teams don’t actually operate at that scale.</p>



<p><br>With this article, I urge you to reflect on the question the industry has mostly stopped asking: <strong>Should microservices be the default choice for building at scale?</strong> We’ll look at reversal stories and insights from seasoned architects, and weigh the trade-offs and alternatives. After considering all of this, you can decide whether your problem really needs a constellation of microservices.</p>







<h2>Microservices: The Agility-Complexity Trade-Off</h2>







<p>On paper, microservices look impressive. Instead of one big monolith, you split your application into many small services. Each one can be written in any language, owned by a small team, and deployed on its own schedule. If you need more capacity, you can scale only the part that’s under load. The promise is elegant: independent deployability, autonomous teams, multi-language stacks, and elastic scaling.</p>







<p>But the catch is that every split creates a seam, and every seam is a potential failure point. Inside a monolith, function calls are instant and predictable. Across services, those same calls become network requests: slower, failure-prone, sometimes returning inconsistent data. With dozens (or hundreds) of services, you need version management, schema evolution, distributed transactions, tracing, centralized logging, and heavy-duty CI/CD pipelines just to keep things running.</p>







<p>This <a href="https://thenewstack.io/miniservices-a-realistic-alternative-to-microservices/" id="dkr_gartner-diagram-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Gartner diagram</a> captures the trade-off perfectly: microservices exchange the simplicity of one codebase for the complexity of many.</p>









<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="563" src="https://www.docker.com/app/uploads/2025/11/microservices-gartner.jpg" alt="microservices gartner" srcset="https://www.docker.com/app/uploads/2025/11/microservices-gartner.jpg 1024w, https://www.docker.com/app/uploads/2025/11/microservices-gartner-546x300.jpg 546w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" title="- microservices gartner">
    </p>







<p>At a massive scale (think Netflix), that trade-off may be worth it. But when operational benefits don’t outweigh the costs, teams end up paying a steep price in debugging, coordination, and glue code just to hold their product together.</p>







<p>Microservices make sense in very specific scenarios <em>where distinct business capabilities need independent scaling and deployment</em>. For example, <strong>payment processing</strong> (security-critical, rarely updated) differs fundamentally from <strong>recommendation engine</strong> (memory-intensive, constantly A/B tested). These components have different scaling patterns, deployment cycles, and risk profiles, which justify separate services.</p>







<p>The success of microservices hinges on clear business domain boundaries that match your team structure, as <a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/ConwaysLaw.html" id="dkr_conways-law-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Conway’s Law</a> predicts. If your organization naturally splits into autonomous teams that own distinct capabilities, microservices might work. (So, most <strong>“one-and-a-half pizza”</strong> startups don’t qualify, do they?)&nbsp;</p>







<p>That’s why microservices work effectively for companies like Amazon and Uber—although <strong>not always</strong>.</p>







<p>In fact, most organizations lack the prerequisites: dedicated service ownership, mature CI/CD, robust monitoring, and crucially, <em>scale that justifies the operational overhead</em>. Startups that adapt microservices prematurely often <a href="https://www.indiehackers.com/post/why-we-replaced-our-microservices-with-a-monolith-and-it-worked-NEec3alGYvYoRLHjgrGv" id="dkr_regret-their-decision-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">regret their decision</a>.</p>







<p>So ask yourself:</p>







<p>Are you using microservices to solve an independent scaling problem, or are you inviting more complexity than your solution needs?</p>







<h2>The Great Microservices Reversal</h2>







<p>Ironically, even though tech giants are the ones that are most likely to benefit from microservices, many of these very same companies are walking back their microservices architectures, and the results are eye-opening.</p>







<h3>Amazon Prime Video: 90% Cost Reduction with a Monolith</h3>







<p>In May 2023, Amazon engineers admitted the unthinkable: Prime Video had abandoned microservices for a monolith. Their Video Quality Analysis (VQA) team had built what looked like a textbook distributed system: AWS Step Functions and Lambda monitored thousands of video streams through independent, scalable components. On paper, it was serverless perfection.</p>







<p>In practice, it was a disaster. “We realized that distributed approach wasn’t bringing a lot of benefits in our specific use case,” said <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20230505213415/https://www.primevideotech.com/video-streaming/scaling-up-the-prime-video-audio-video-monitoring-service-and-reducing-costs-by-90" id="dkr_marcin-kolny-in-the-now-archived-prime-video-engineering-blog-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Marcin Kolny in the now-archived Prime Video Engineering blog</a>. Their “infinitely scalable” system <strong>crumbled at just 5% of expected load</strong> due to orchestration overhead.</p>







<p>The fix was embarrassingly simple: collapse everything into a single process. It resulted in <em>90% lower costs and faster performance</em>.&nbsp;</p>







<h3>Twilio Segment: From 140 Services to One Fast Monolith</h3>







<p>Back in 2018, Twilio Segment, a customer data platform, documented a similar reversal in their brutally honest post <a href="https://www.twilio.com/en-us/blog/developers/best-practices/goodbye-microservices" id="dkr_goodbye-microservices-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">“Goodbye Microservices”</a>.</p>







<p>Their system had sprawled into 140+ services, creating operational chaos. At one point, three full-time engineers spent most of their time firefighting instead of building. As they admitted, “Instead of enabling us to move faster, the small team found themselves mired in exploding complexity. Essential benefits of this architecture became burdens. As our velocity plummeted, our defect rate exploded.”</p>







<p>Their solution was radical but effective: collapse all 140+ services into a single monolith. The impact was immediate. Test suites that once took an hour now finished in milliseconds. Developer productivity soared: they shipped 46 improvements to shared libraries in a year, up from 32 in the microservices era.&nbsp;</p>







<h3>Shopify: Sanity over Hype</h3>







<p>Shopify runs one of the largest Ruby on Rails codebases in the world (2.8M+ lines). Instead of chasing microservices, they deliberately chose a <a href="https://shopify.engineering/shopify-monolith" id="dkr_modular-monolith-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">modular monolith</a>: a single codebase with clear component boundaries.</p>







<p>Shopify’s engineers concluded that “microservices would bring their own set of challenges”, so they chose modularity without the operational overhead.</p>







<p>All these examples beg the question:</p>







<p>If even the pioneers of microservices are retreating, why are we still treating it as gospel?</p>







<h2>Expert Voices against Microservices Mania</h2>







<p>Some of the most respected voices in software architecture—people behind many of the systems we all admire—are also cautioning against microservices and repeating mistakes they’ve seen play out at scale. (After all, cheerleaders don’t play the game; cloud DevRels rarely build at scale.)</p>







<h3>Rails Creator: Simplicity over Sophistication</h3>







<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Heinemeier_Hansson" id="dkr_david-heinemeier-hansson-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">David Heinemeier Hansson</a> (DHH), the creator of Ruby on Rails, has long advocated simplicity over architectural trends. His <a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/even-amazon-can-t-make-sense-of-serverless-or-microservices-59625580" id="dkr_analysis-of-the-amazon-prime-video-reversal-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">analysis of the Amazon Prime Video reversal</a> puts it bluntly:</p>







<p><strong>“The real-world results of all this theory are finally in, and it’s clear that in practice, microservices pose perhaps the biggest siren song for needlessly complicating your system.”</strong></p>







<p>DHH’s image of a siren song is apt: microservices promise elegance but leave teams wrecked on the rocks of complexity.</p>







<h3>Microservices: Mistake of The Decade?</h3>







<p><a href="https://threadreaderapp.com/thread/1592227285024636928.html" id="dkr_jason-warner-former-cto-of-github-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Jason Warner, former CTO of GitHub</a>, doesn’t mince words while commenting on microservices:&nbsp;</p>







<p><strong>“I’m convinced that one of the biggest architectural mistakes of the past decade was going full microservice.”</strong></p>







<p>Warner understands scale: GitHub runs at internet scale, and he’s led engineering at Heroku and Canonical. His critique cuts deeper because it’s lived experience, beyond <a href="https://www.martinfowler.com/bliki/MicroservicePremium.html#:~:text=The%20majority%20of%20software%20systems%20should%20be%20built%20as%20a%20single%20monolithic%20application" id="dkr_theoretical-advice-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">theoretical advice</a>:</p>







<p><strong>“90% of all companies in the world could probably just be a monolith running against a primary db cluster with db backups, some caches and proxies and be done with it.”</strong></p>







<h3>GraphQL Co-Creator: “Don’t”</h3>







<p>Then there’s <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/schrockn/" id="dkr_nick-schrock-co-creator-of-graphql-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Nick Schrock, co-creator of GraphQL</a>. If anyone had a reason to cheer for distributed systems, it’d be him. Instead, he says:</p>







<p><strong>“Microservices are such a fundamentally and catastrophically bad idea that there are going to be an entire cohort of multi-billion companies built that do nothing but contain the damage that they have wrought.”</strong></p>









<p><img decoding="async" width="621" height="256" src="https://www.docker.com/app/uploads/2025/11/microservices-bad-idea-Graph-QL-cocreator.png" alt="microservices bad idea Graph QL cocreator" title="- microservices bad idea Graph QL cocreator">
    </p>







<p>He goes on to describe microservices as <a href="https://x.com/schrockn/status/1130567665548873728" id="dkr_organizational-gambles-83395" rel="nofollow" target="_blank">organizational gambles</a>:</p>







<p><strong>“[Y]ou end up with these services that you have to maintain forever that match the org structure and the product requirements from five years ago. Today, they don’t make a lot of sense.”</strong></p>







<p>The person who literally built tools to fix distributed system pain says <strong>don’t distribute unless you must</strong>, maybe it’s time to listen.</p>







<h3>Other Voices Questioning Microservice Maximalism</h3>







<p>Other engineering leaders are also reconsidering microservice maximalism.&nbsp;</p>







<p>At Uber, <a href="https://x.com/GergelyOrosz/status/1247132806041546754" id="dkr_gergely-orosz-admitted-83395" rel="nofollow" target="_blank">Gergely Orosz admitted</a>:</p>







<p><strong>“We’re moving many of our microservices to macroservices (well-sized services). Exactly b/c testing and maintaining thousands of microservices is not only hard – it can cause more trouble long-term than it solves the short-term.”</strong></p>







<p>Uber still runs microservices where they’re justified, but they’re <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kb-m2fasdDY&amp;t=430s" id="dkr_choosing-their-battles-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">choosing their battles</a>.</p>







<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kelsey_Hightower" id="dkr_kelsey-hightower-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Kelsey Hightower</a>, known for his work with Kubernetes and Google Cloud, cut through the microservices hype with CS101:</p>







<p><strong>“I’m willing to wager a monolith will outperform every microservice architecture. Just do the math on the network latency between each service and the amount of serialization and deserialization of each request.”</strong></p>







<p>He subsequently deleted this tweet, but the network math still grades microservices.</p>







<p>When pioneers like these, including those who actually solved distributed systems at scale, start waving red flags, it’s worth taking note.&nbsp;</p>







<p>My question here is:</p>







<p>If GitHub’s CTO thinks 90% of companies don’t need microservices, are you sure yours is part of the 10%?</p>







<h2>The Hidden Costs of Microservices</h2>







<p>Microservices demand such caution because of these hidden costs that teams often underestimate.</p>







<h3>Operational Costs</h3>







<p>A monolith is simple: in-process function calls.&nbsp;</p>







<p>Microservices replace that with networks. Every request now travels across machines, through load balancers, service meshes, and authentication layers, creating more failure points and infrastructure needs. You suddenly need service discovery (how services find each other), distributed tracing (tracking requests across services), centralized logging (aggregating logs from multiple services), and monitoring systems that understand service topology.</p>







<p>Each of these is necessary, but together they’re complex and expensive. Duplicated data requires extra storage. Constant service-to-service calls rack up network egress fees. Cloud <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ProgrammerHumor/comments/xkadmh/150k_bill/" id="dkr_costs-scale-faster-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">costs scale faster</a> than the apps they host. Prime Video’s workflow <a href="https://www.wudsn.com/productions/www/site/news/2023/2023-05-08-microservices-01.pdf" id="dkr_spent-more-on-orchestrating-s3-data-transfers-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">spent more on orchestrating S3 data transfers</a> between services than on actual processing.&nbsp;</p>







<h3>Developer Productivity Drain</h3>







<p>In microservices, the hard part isn’t writing code; it’s navigating distributed system interactions.</p>







<p>In “<a href="https://stackoverflow.blog/2020/11/23/the-macro-problem-with-microservices/" id="dkr_the-macro-problem-with-microservices-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">The macro problem with microservices</a>“, Stack Overflow identifies a critical productivity drain: distributed state forces developers to write defensive code that constantly checks for partial failures.&nbsp;</p>







<p>In a monolith, a developer can follow a code path end-to-end within one repo. In microservices, one feature might span four or five repos with different dependencies and deploy cycles. Adding a single field triggers weeks of coordination: you need to update one service, then wait for consumers to adopt, version your APIs, manage rollouts, and so on. Different teams will also typically maintain different microservices using different tech stacks, so there’s a risk that they unintentionally break something as well. Breaking changes that a compiler would catch in a monolith now surface as runtime errors in production.</p>







<h3>Testing and Deployment Complexity</h3>







<p>Monolith integration and end-to-end tests are faster because they run locally, in memory. Distributed systems don’t allow that luxury: real confidence requires integration and end-to-end tests across numerous service boundaries. So these tests are slower, more brittle, and require staging environments that resemble production, all of which effectively double infrastructure costs and slow feedback loops.</p>







<p>Many teams discover this only after their <a href="https://www.craigkerstiens.com/2019/03/13/give-me-back-my-monolith/#:~:text=%20now%20to%20really%20test%20my%20service%20I%20have%20to" id="dkr_test-suite-becomes-a-bottleneck-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">test suite becomes a bottleneck</a>. Deployment orchestration adds another layer. Rolling updates across interdependent services require careful sequencing to avoid breaking contracts. Version incompatibility disturbs frequently: Service A works with Service B v2.1 but breaks with v2.2.</p>







<p>Failed deployments leave systems partially updated and difficult to recover.</p>







<h3>Data Management and Consistency</h3>







<p>The most underestimated complexity of microservices lies in data consistency across service boundaries.</p>







<p>Monoliths benefit from ACID transactions: operations complete entirely or fail entirely. Microservices split that across services, forcing you to build <a href="https://cs.brown.edu/courses/csci2952-f/slides/Class16.pdf" id="dkr_distributed-saga-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">distributed saga</a> (multi-step workflows with rollback logic), live with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eventual_consistency" id="dkr_eventual-consistency-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">eventual consistency</a> (data only becomes correct after a delay), or write <a href="https://softwarepatternslexicon.com/101/12/24/" id="dkr_compensation-logic-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">compensation logic</a> (extra code to undo partial failures). What was once a single database transaction now spans network hops, retries, and partial failures. Debugging inconsistent orders or payments gets much harder when state is duplicated across services.&nbsp;</p>







<p>As <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2103.00170" id="dkr_research-confirms-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">research confirms</a>, data duplication, correctness challenges, and transactional complexity are the top pain points in microservice systems.</p>







<h3>The Compounding Effect</h3>







<p>These complexities multiply. Operational overhead makes debugging harder, which slows testing, which makes deployments riskier, which creates more incidents. Microservices don’t just shift complexity from code to operations; they tax every part of your engineering process.&nbsp;</p>







<p>Unless your scale demands it, that tax often outweighs the benefits.&nbsp;</p>







<p>Think about it:</p>







<p>If every network hop adds complexity and cost, does your use case really justify the price?</p>







<h2>Beyond Microservices: Smarter Architectural Alternatives</h2>







<p>Before defaulting to microservices, it’s worth considering how simpler, well-structured architectures can deliver comparable scalability without the distributed complexity tax. Two noteworthy alternatives are modular monoliths and service-oriented architectures.</p>







<h3>Modular Monoliths: Structure without Distribution</h3>







<p>Unlike traditional monoliths that become tangled messes, <a href="https://www.geeksforgeeks.org/system-design/what-is-a-modular-monolith/" id="dkr_modular-monoliths-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">modular monoliths</a> enforce strict internal boundaries through clear module APIs and disciplined separation. Each module exposes well-defined interfaces, enabling teams to work independently while deploying a single, coherent system.</p>









<p><img decoding="async" width="1137" height="839" src="https://www.docker.com/app/uploads/2025/11/modular-monolith-architecture.png" alt="modular monolith architecture" srcset="https://www.docker.com/app/uploads/2025/11/modular-monolith-architecture.png 1137w, https://www.docker.com/app/uploads/2025/11/modular-monolith-architecture-407x300.png 407w, https://www.docker.com/app/uploads/2025/11/modular-monolith-architecture-1110x819.png 1110w" sizes="(max-width: 1137px) 100vw, 1137px" title="- modular monolith architecture">
    </p>







<p>As Kent Beck explains in <a href="https://medium.com/%40kentbeck_7670/monolith-services-theory-practice-617e4546a879" id="dkr_monolith---services-theory--practice-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">“Monolith -&gt; Services: Theory &amp; Practice”</a>, modular monoliths manage coupling through organizational discipline rather than distributed networks. The key difference: modules still communicate via explicit contracts like microservices, but they use fast, reliable function calls instead of HTTP requests that are vulnerable to network latency and partial failures.</p>







<p>Why does it work?</p>







<ul>
<li><em>Simpler operations</em>: microservices-level organization with monolithic simplicity</li>



<li><em>Stronger consistency</em>: full ACID transactions</li>



<li><em>Easier debugging</em>: one traceable system, no hunting for bugs in the <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/what-is/elk-stack/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">ELK</a> haystack</li>



<li><em>Better performance</em>: function calls beat network hops</li>
</ul>







<p>Here’s some real-world proof: Shopify’s 2.8 million-line codebase <a href="https://newsletter.systemdesign.one/p/modular-monolith#:~:text=Shopify%20Handled%2030TB%20per%20Minute" id="dkr_handles-30tb-per-minute-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">handles 30TB per minute</a> with separate teams owning distinct modules, yet everything deploys together. Facebook runs similarly. (And principal architect <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sLEuXDgfAS4&amp;t=3880s" id="dkr_keith-adams-jokes-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Keith Adams jokes</a> that if you want to be talked <strong>out</strong> of microservices, he’s your guy.)</p>







<p>With recent developments in frameworks like <a href="https://spring.io/projects/spring-modulith" id="dkr_spring-modulith-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Spring Modulith</a>, <a href="https://makimo.com/blog/modular-monolith-in-django/" id="dkr_django-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Django</a>, <a href="https://dev.to/abstractmusa/modular-monolith-architecture-within-laravel-communication-between-different-modules-a5" id="dkr_laravel-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Laravel</a>, and <a href="https://dev.to/alex_aslam/modular-monoliths-in-rails-taming-complexity-without-microservices-madness-30nj" id="dkr_rails-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Rails</a> (as seen at scale with Shopify), modular monoliths are poised to <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41534179" id="dkr_gain-wider-traction-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">gain wider traction</a> in the years ahead.</p>







<h3>Service-Oriented Architecture: The Middle Ground</h3>







<p><a href="https://www.geeksforgeeks.org/software-engineering/service-oriented-architecture/" id="dkr_service-oriented-architecture-soa-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Service-oriented architecture (SOA)</a> sits between monoliths and microservices, favoring larger, domain-driven services instead of dozens or hundreds of tiny ones. These services often communicate via an enterprise service bus (ESB), which reduces orchestration overhead while preserving separation of concerns.</p>









<p><img decoding="async" width="1137" height="839" src="https://www.docker.com/app/uploads/2025/11/service-oriented-acrhitecture.png" alt="service oriented acrhitecture" srcset="https://www.docker.com/app/uploads/2025/11/service-oriented-acrhitecture.png 1137w, https://www.docker.com/app/uploads/2025/11/service-oriented-acrhitecture-407x300.png 407w, https://www.docker.com/app/uploads/2025/11/service-oriented-acrhitecture-1110x819.png 1110w" sizes="(max-width: 1137px) 100vw, 1137px" title="- service oriented acrhitecture">
    </p>







<p>Instead of splitting authentication, user preferences, and notifications into separate microservices, SOA might combine them into a single “User Service”, simplifying coordination while preserving autonomy and targeted scaling. SOA provides enterprise-grade modularity without ultra-fine-grained distribution overhead.</p>







<p>Here’s why it works:</p>







<ul>
<li><em>Right-sized boundaries</em>: fewer, domain-aligned services instead of sprawl</li>



<li><em>Targeted scalability</em>: scale services tied to real business domains</li>



<li><em>Pragmatic complexity</em>: avoids ultra-fine-grained overhead while retaining modular reasoning</li>
</ul>







<p>SOA has also been proven to work at scale. Norwegian Air Shuttle, Europe’s 9th-largest airline, <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/254028496_A_Successful_Implementation_of_Service_Oriented_Architecture" id="dkr_used-soa-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">used SOA</a> to boost agility across complex flight operations. Credit Suisse’s <a href="https://www.infoq.com/articles/service-oriented-architecture-at-credit-suisse/" id="dkr_soa-rollout-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">SOA rollout</a> powered millions of service calls per day back in the early 2000s.</p>







<h3>Choosing Wisely: Fit over Hype</h3>







<p>The problem you’re solving should justify your architecture.</p>







<p>I often use this analogy in consulting: <strong>You don’t need a sword to cut a lemon—a knife suffices. </strong>And as timeless wisdom reminds us, simplicity is the ultimate sophistication.&nbsp;</p>







<p>In all likelihood, <a href="https://blog.bradfieldcs.com/you-are-not-google-84912cf44afb" id="dkr_youre-not-google-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">you’re not Google</a> (you don’t need Google-level fault tolerance), or Amazon (you don’t need massive write availability), or LinkedIn (you don’t handle billions of events a day). Most applications don’t operate at that scale, demanding fundamentally different solutions than ultra-distributed architectures.</p>







<p>For most systems, well-structured modular monoliths (for most common applications, including startups) or SOA (enterprises) deliver comparable scalability and resilience as microservices, without the distributed complexity tax. Alternatively, you may also consider well-sized services (<a href="https://x.com/copyconstruct/status/1247131341851783168" id="dkr_macroservices-83395" rel="nofollow" target="_blank"><strong>macroservices</strong></a>, or what Gartner proposed as <a href="https://thenewstack.io/miniservices-a-realistic-alternative-to-microservices/#:~:text=%5BA%20miniservice%20is%5D%20like%20a%20group%20of%20microservices" id="dkr_miniservices-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"><strong>miniservices</strong></a>) instead of tons of microservices.</p>







<p>It’s worth asking:</p>







<p>If simpler architectures can deliver comparable scalability, why are you choosing the complexity of microservices?</p>







<h2>Docker: Built for Any Architecture</h2>







<p><a href="https://www.docker.com/" id="dkr_docker-83395">Docker</a> isn’t just for microservices—it <a href="https://www.docker.com/blog/are-containers-only-for-microservices-myth-debunked/" id="dkr_works-great-across-all-kinds-of-architectures-83395">works great across all kinds of architectures</a> like monoliths, SOA, APIs, and event-driven systems. The real benefit is that Docker gives you consistent performance, easier deployment, and flexibility to scale up your apps no matter what architectural approach you’re using.</p>







<p>Docker packages applications cleanly, keeps environments consistent from laptop to production, simplifies dependency management, and isolates applications from the host system. A Dockerized monolith offers all these benefits, minus the orchestration overhead of microservices.&nbsp;</p>







<p><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/architecture/microservices/architect-microservice-container-applications/containerize-monolithic-applications" id="dkr_microsofts-guidance-on-containerizing-monoliths-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Microsoft’s guidance on containerizing monoliths</a> clarifies that scaling containers is “far faster and easier than deploying additional VMs”, whether you run one service or fifty. <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20250319065616/https://segment.com/blog/monoliths-microservices-and-containers/" id="dkr_twilio-segment-observed-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Twilio Segment observed</a> that containerized monoliths can “horizontally scale your environment easily by spinning up more containers and shutting them down when demand subsides.” For many applications, scaling the whole app is exactly what’s needed.</p>







<p>As for DevOps, a monolith in Docker is lighter to operate than a full-blown microservices setup. <a href="https://docs.docker.com/engine/logging/configure/" id="dkr_logging-aggregation-83395" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Logging aggregation</a> becomes simpler when you’re collecting from identical containers rather than disparate services with different formats. Monitoring and debugging remain centralized, and troubleshooting avoids tracing requests across service boundaries.</p>







<p>So, it’s definitely worth considering:</p>







<p>Even without the complexity of microservices, Docker gives you the same advantages — clean deployments, easy scaling, and consistent environments. So why not keep it?</p>







<h2>Wrapping Up</h2>







<p>A few years ago, my then-8-year-old wanted a bicycle. He’d mostly ride around our apartment complex, maybe venture into the nearby lane. He didn’t <strong>need</strong> 21 gears, but those shiny shifters had him smitten—imagine riding faster by changing those gears! He absolutely <strong>wanted</strong> that mechanically complex beauty. (It’s hard to argue with a starry-eyed kid… or a founder :P).</p>







<p>Once he started riding the new bike, the gears slipped, the chain jammed, and the bicycle spent more time broken than on the road. Eventually, we had to dump it.&nbsp;</p>







<p>I wasn’t able to convince him back then that a simpler bicycle could’ve served him better, but maybe this article will convince a few grown-ups making architectural decisions.</p>







<p>We techies love indulging in complex systems. (Check: were you already thinking, <strong>What’s complex about bicycles with gears??</strong>) But the more moving parts you add, the more often they break. Complexity often creates more problems than it solves.</p>







<p>The point I’m making isn’t to dump microservices entirely—it’s to pick an architecture that fits your actual needs, not what the cloud giant is pushing (while quietly rolling back their own <strong>commit</strong>). Most likely, modular monoliths or well-designed SOA will serve your needs better and make your team more productive.</p>







<p>So here’s the million-dollar question:&nbsp;</p>







<p>Will you design for cloud-native hype or for your own business requirements?</p>







<p>Do you really need microservices?</p>




</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Program-of-Thought Prompting Outperforms Chain-of-Thought by 15% (2022) (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.12588</link>
            <guid>46099108</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 18:34:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.12588">https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.12588</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46099108">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content-inner">
    
    
                
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.12588">View PDF</a></p><blockquote>
            <span>Abstract:</span>Recently, there has been significant progress in teaching language models to perform step-by-step reasoning to solve complex numerical reasoning tasks. Chain-of-thoughts prompting (CoT) is by far the state-of-art method for these tasks. CoT uses language models to perform both reasoning and computation in the multi-step `thought' process. To disentangle computation from reasoning, we propose `Program of Thoughts' (PoT), which uses language models (mainly Codex) to express the reasoning process as a program. The computation is relegated to an external computer, which executes the generated programs to derive the answer. We evaluate PoT on five math word problem datasets (GSM, AQuA, SVAMP, TabMWP, MultiArith) and three financial-QA datasets (FinQA, ConvFinQA, TATQA) for both few-shot and zero-shot setups. Under both few-shot and zero-shot settings, PoT can show an average performance gain over CoT by around 12\% across all the evaluated datasets. By combining PoT with self-consistency decoding, we can achieve SoTA performance on all math problem datasets and near-SoTA performance on financial datasets. All of our data and code are released in Github <a href="https://github.com/wenhuchen/Program-of-Thoughts" rel="external noopener nofollow">this https URL</a>
    </blockquote>

    <!--CONTEXT-->
    
  </div><div>
      <h2>Submission history</h2><p> From: Wenhu Chen [<a href="https://arxiv.org/show-email/0554cbd1/2211.12588" rel="nofollow">view email</a>]      <br>            <strong><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.12588v1" rel="nofollow">[v1]</a></strong>
        Tue, 22 Nov 2022 21:06:00 UTC (8,689 KB)<br>
            <strong><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.12588v2" rel="nofollow">[v2]</a></strong>
        Fri, 25 Nov 2022 01:49:50 UTC (8,689 KB)<br>
            <strong><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.12588v3" rel="nofollow">[v3]</a></strong>
        Tue, 29 Nov 2022 03:46:29 UTC (8,689 KB)<br>
    <strong>[v4]</strong>
        Mon, 23 Oct 2023 01:27:38 UTC (4,047 KB)<br>
</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[NixOS 25.11 released (186 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nixos.org/blog/announcements/2025/nixos-2511/</link>
            <guid>46099022</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 18:21:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nixos.org/blog/announcements/2025/nixos-2511/">https://nixos.org/blog/announcements/2025/nixos-2511/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46099022">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>  <article> <p><img alt="NixOS 25.11 Xantusia logo" loading="lazy" decoding="async" fetchpriority="auto" width="1280" height="1280" src="https://nixos.org/_astro/nixos-logo-25.11-xantusia-lores.CLapGrL7_Z1CRDey.webp"></p>
<p>Hey everyone, we are <a href="https://github.com/jopejoe1">jopejoe1</a> and <a href="https://github.com/leona-ya">Leona Maroni</a>, the release managers of the newest release of NixOS. We are very proud to announce the public availability of NixOS 25.11 “Xantusia”.</p>
<p>NixOS is a Linux distribution. Its underlying package repository Nixpkgs can also be used on other Linux systems and macOS with the Nix package manager.</p>
<p>This release will receive bugfixes and security updates for seven months (up until 2026-06-30).
The old release 25.05 “Warbler” is now officially deprecated and will reach its end-of-life and stop receiving security updates after 2025-12-31.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://nixos.org/manual/nixos/stable/release-notes#sec-release-25.11">NixOS Release Notes</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://nixos.org/manual/nixos/stable/release-notes#sec-release-25.11-highlights">Highlights</a></li>
<li><a href="https://nixos.org/manual/nixos/stable/release-notes#sec-release-25.11-new-modules">New Modules</a></li>
<li><a href="https://nixos.org/manual/nixos/stable/release-notes#sec-release-25.11-incompatibilities">Backward Incompatibilities</a></li>
<li><a href="https://nixos.org/manual/nixos/stable/release-notes#sec-release-25.11-notable-changes">Other Notable Changes</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://nixos.org/manual/nixpkgs/stable/release-notes#sec-nixpkgs-release-25.11">Nixpkgs Release Notes</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://nixos.org/manual/nixpkgs/stable/release-notes#sec-nixpkgs-release-25.11-highlights">Highlights</a></li>
<li><a href="https://nixos.org/manual/nixpkgs/stable/release-notes#sec-nixpkgs-release-25.11-incompatibilities">Backward Incompatibilities</a></li>
<li><a href="https://nixos.org/manual/nixpkgs/stable/release-notes#sec-nixpkgs-release-25.11-notable-changes">Other Notable Changes</a></li>
<li><a href="https://nixos.org/manual/nixpkgs/stable/release-notes#sec-nixpkgs-release-25.11-lib">Nixpkgs Library</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://nixos.org/manual/nixos/stable/#sec-upgrading">Upgrade Instructions</a></li>
<li><a href="https://nixos.org/download">ISO Image Downloads</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The 25.11 release was made possible due to the efforts of <strong>2742</strong> contributors, who authored <strong>59430</strong> commits since the previous release.</p>
<h2 id="highlights">Highlights</h2>
<p>Our vast and routinely maintained set of packages has also been updated. This release of Nixpkgs</p>
<ul>
<li>Added 7002 new packages</li>
<li>Updated 25252 existing packages</li>
<li>Removed 6338 outdated packages, in an effort to keep the package set maintainable and secure.</li>
</ul>
<p>In addition to packages from Nixpkgs, the NixOS Linux distribution also features composable configuration modules and integration tests for distributed systems.
This release of NixOS</p>
<ul>
<li>Added 107 new modules and 1778 configuration options</li>
<li>Removed 41 outdated modules and 807 configuration options.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="gnome-49">GNOME 49</h3>
<p>GNOME has been updated to version 49 “Brescia”, which removes X11 session support, introduces a new video player, a new document viewer, a redesigned calender and more changes. Refer to the <a href="https://release.gnome.org/49">release notes</a> for more details.</p>
<h3 id="c-compilers">C compilers</h3>
<p>LLVM has been updated to version 21. GCC remains at version 14. CMake was updated to version 4.</p>
<h2 id="special-thanks">Special Thanks</h2>
<p>We want to personally thank</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/getchoo/">Seth</a> and <a href="https://github.com/pyrox0">dish</a> for editorializing the release notes</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Sigmanificient/">Yohann Boniface</a> for the release logo</li>
<li>The NixOS infrastucture team for their dutifully tending to our build infrastructure</li>
<li>The Nixpkgs staging team for supporting our staging cycles and the patient fixing of many build errors.</li>
</ul>
<p>We also want to thank all contributors who made this release possible!</p>
<h2 id="reflections-and-closing">Reflections and closing</h2>
<p>We are grateful for the opportunity to support the community as release managers and to learn about and participate in the release process. Seeing all the contributors working in their area of the project to improve it has been an exciting experience. We would like to thank everyone in the community for that. We are looking forward to the next release, NixOS 26.05 “Yarara”.</p> </article>  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Don't push AI down our throats (398 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://gpt3experiments.substack.com/p/dont-push-ai-down-our-throats</link>
            <guid>46098992</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 18:17:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://gpt3experiments.substack.com/p/dont-push-ai-down-our-throats">https://gpt3experiments.substack.com/p/dont-push-ai-down-our-throats</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46098992">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><p>AI is being done wrong.</p><p>It's being pushed down our throats. It’s in our search bars, our operating systems, and even our creative tools, whether we asked for it or not. It feels less like an upgrade and more like a force-feeding.</p><p>It doesn’t need to be this way. Technology can be adopted slowly. Organically. One piece at a time.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!pMD9!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3334af56-2e09-42b9-b5fd-09c73b42259e_2816x1536.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!pMD9!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3334af56-2e09-42b9-b5fd-09c73b42259e_2816x1536.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!pMD9!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3334af56-2e09-42b9-b5fd-09c73b42259e_2816x1536.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!pMD9!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3334af56-2e09-42b9-b5fd-09c73b42259e_2816x1536.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!pMD9!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3334af56-2e09-42b9-b5fd-09c73b42259e_2816x1536.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!pMD9!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3334af56-2e09-42b9-b5fd-09c73b42259e_2816x1536.jpeg" width="2816" height="1536" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/3334af56-2e09-42b9-b5fd-09c73b42259e_2816x1536.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:&quot;normal&quot;,&quot;height&quot;:1536,&quot;width&quot;:2816,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:5715375,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!pMD9!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3334af56-2e09-42b9-b5fd-09c73b42259e_2816x1536.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!pMD9!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3334af56-2e09-42b9-b5fd-09c73b42259e_2816x1536.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!pMD9!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3334af56-2e09-42b9-b5fd-09c73b42259e_2816x1536.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!pMD9!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3334af56-2e09-42b9-b5fd-09c73b42259e_2816x1536.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Right now, the frantic pace of deployment isn't about utility; it's about liquidity. It’s being shoved down our throats because some billionaires need to make some more billions before they die.</p><p><strong>We don't owe them anything.</strong></p><p>It is time to do AI the right way. The honeymoon phase of the hype cycle is over. We now know the limitations. We see the hallucinations. We see the errors. Let's pick the things which work and slowly integrate it into our lives. We don't need to do it this quarter just because some startup has to do an earnings call. We will do it if it helps us.</p><p>And let’s be clear: We don't need AGI (Artificial General Intelligence). We don't need a digital god. We just need software that works.</p><p>If the current models don't work? No problem. Let the researchers go back to the lab and do their jobs. We will continue doing ours. We might even generate more data for them in the process—but this time, we do it correctly. We will work with the creators, writers, and artists, instead of ripping off their life's work to feed the model.</p><p>I hear the complaints from the tech giants already: "But we bought too many GPUs! We spent billions on infrastructure! They have to be put to work!"</p><p>Not my problem.</p><p>I will use what creates value for me. I will not buy anything that is of no use to me.</p><p>I hear that’s called capitalism.</p><p>There are plenty of legitimate use cases for AI and enough places to make money without force-feeding the market. But I will not allow AI to be pushed down my throat just to justify your bad investment.</p></div></article></div><div id="discussion"><h4>Discussion about this post</h4></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Writing a Good Claude.md (478 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.humanlayer.dev/blog/writing-a-good-claude-md</link>
            <guid>46098838</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 17:56:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.humanlayer.dev/blog/writing-a-good-claude-md">https://www.humanlayer.dev/blog/writing-a-good-claude-md</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46098838">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><em>Note: this post is also applicable to <code>AGENTS.md</code></em>, the open-source equivalent of <code>CLAUDE.md</code> for agents and harnesses like OpenCode, Zed, Cursor and Codex.</p>
<h2>## <!-- -->Principle: LLMs are (mostly) stateless</h2>
<p>LLMs are stateless functions. Their weights are frozen by the time they're used for inference, so they don't learn over time. The only thing that the model knows about your codebase is the tokens you put into it.</p>
<p>Similarly, coding agent harnesses such as Claude Code usually require you to manage agents' memory explicitly. <code>CLAUDE.md</code> (or <code>AGENTS.md</code>) is the only file that by default goes into <em>every single conversation</em> you have with the agent.</p>
<p><strong>This has three important implications:</strong></p>
<div><ol>
<li>Coding agents know absolutely nothing about your codebase at the beginning of each session.</li>
<li>The agent must be told anything that's important to know about your codebase each time you start a session.</li>
<li><code>CLAUDE.md</code> is the preferred way of doing this.</li>
</ol></div>
<h2>## <code>CLAUDE.md</code> onboards Claude to your codebase</h2>
<p>Since Claude doesn't know anything about your codebase at the beginning of each session, you should use <code>CLAUDE.md</code> to onboard Claude into your codebase. At a high level, this means it should cover:</p>
<div><ul>
<li><strong>WHAT</strong>: tell Claude about the tech, your stack, the project structure. Give Claude a map of the codebase. This is especially important in monorepos! Tell Claude what the apps are, what the shared packages are, and what everything is for so that it knows where to look for things</li>
<li><strong>WHY</strong>: tell Claude the <em>purpose</em> of the project and what everything is doing in the repository. What are the purpose and function of the different parts of the project?</li>
<li><strong>HOW</strong>: tell Claude how it should work on the project. For example, do you use <code>bun</code> instead of <code>node</code>? You want to include all the information it needs to actually do meaningful work on the project. How can Claude verify Claude's changes? How can it run tests, typechecks, and compilation steps?</li>
</ul></div>
<p>But the way you do this is important! Don't try to stuff every command Claude could possibly need to run in your <code>CLAUDE.md</code> file - you will get sub-optimal results.</p>
<h2>## <!-- -->Claude often ignores <code>CLAUDE.md</code></h2>
<p>Regardless of which model you're using, you may notice that Claude frequently ignores your <code>CLAUDE.md</code> file's contents.</p>
<p>You can investigate this yourself by putting a logging proxy between the claude code CLI and the Anthropic API using <code>ANTHROPIC_BASE_URL</code>. Claude code injects the following system reminder with your <code>CLAUDE.md</code> file in the user message to the agent:</p>
<pre><pre><code><span>&lt;system-reminder&gt;
</span>      IMPORTANT: this context may or may not be relevant to your tasks. 
<!-- -->      You should not respond to this context unless it is highly relevant to your task.
<!-- -->&lt;/system-reminder&gt;</code></pre></pre>
<p>As a result, Claude will ignore the contents of your <code>CLAUDE.md</code> if it decides that it is not relevant to its current task. The more information you have in the file that's not <strong>universally applicable</strong> to the tasks you have it working on, the more likely it is that Claude will ignore your instructions in the file.</p>
<p><em>Why did Anthropic add this?</em> It's hard to say for sure, but we can speculate a bit. Most <code>CLAUDE.md</code> files we come across include a bunch of instructions in the file that <em>aren't</em> broadly applicable. Many users treat the file as a way to add "hotfixes" to behavior they didn't like by appending lots of instructions that weren't necessarily broadly applicable.</p>
<p>We can only assume that the Claude Code team found that by telling Claude to ignore the bad instructions, the harness actually produced better results.</p>
<h2>## <!-- -->Creating a good <code>CLAUDE.md</code> file</h2>
<p>The following section provides a number of recommendations on how to write a good <code>CLAUDE.md</code> file following <a href="https://github.com/humanlayer/12-factor-agents/blob/d20c728368bf9c189d6d7aab704744decb6ec0cc/content/factor-03-own-your-context-window.md" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">context engineering best practices</a>.</p>
<p><em>Your mileage may vary.</em> Not all of these rules are necessarily optimal for every setup. Like anything else, feel free to break the rules once...</p>
<div><ol>
<li>you understand when &amp; why it's okay to break them</li>
<li>you have a good reason to do so</li>
</ol></div>
<h3>### <!-- -->Less (instructions) is more</h3>
<p>It can be tempting to try and stuff every single command that claude could possibly need to run, as well as your code standards and style guidelines into <code>CLAUDE.md</code>. <strong>We recommend against this.</strong></p>
<p>Though the topic hasn't been investigated in an incredibly rigorous manner, <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2507.11538" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">some research</a> has been done which indicates the following:</p>
<div><ol>
<li><strong>Frontier thinking LLMs can follow ~ 150-200 instructions with reasonable consistency.</strong> Smaller models can attend to fewer instructions than larger models, and non-thinking models can attend to fewer instructions than thinking models.</li>
<li><strong>Smaller models get MUCH worse, MUCH more quickly</strong>. Specifically, smaller models tend to exhibit an expotential decay in instruction-following performance as the number of instructions increase, whereas larger frontier thinking models exhibit a linear decay (see below). For this reason, we recommend against using smaller models for multi-step tasks or complicated implementation plans.</li>
<li><strong>LLMs bias towards instructions that are on the peripheries of the prompt</strong>: at the very beginning (the Claude Code system message and <code>CLAUDE.md</code>), and at the very end (the most-recent user messages)</li>
<li><strong>As instruction count increases, instruction-following quality decreases uniformly</strong>. This means that as you give the LLM more instructions, it doesn't simply ignore the newer ("further down in the file") instructions - it begins to <strong>ignore all of them uniformly</strong></li>
</ol></div>
<p><img src="https://www.humanlayer.dev/blog/writing-a-good-claude-md/instructionfollowing.png" alt="Instruction following"></p>
<p>Our analysis of the Claude Code harness indicates that <strong>Claude Code's system prompt contains ~50 individual instructions</strong>.
Depending on the model you're using, that's nearly a third of the instructions your agent can reliably follow already - and that's before rules, plugins, skills, or user messages.</p>
<p>This implies that your <code>CLAUDE.md</code> file should contain as few instructions as possible - ideally only ones which are universally applicable to your task.</p>
<h3>### <code>CLAUDE.md</code> file length &amp; applicability</h3>
<p>All else being equal, <strong>an LLM will perform better on a task when its' context window is full of focused, relevant context</strong> including examples, related files, tool calls, and tool results compared to when its context window has a lot of irrelevant context.</p>
<p>Since <code>CLAUDE.md</code> goes into <em>every single session</em>, you should ensure that its contents are as universally applicable as possible.</p>
<p>For example, avoid including instructions about (for example) how to structure a new database schema - this won't matter and will distract the model when you're working on something else that's unrelated!</p>
<p>Length-wise, the <em>less is more</em> principle applies as well. While Anthropic does not have an official recommendation on how long your <code>CLAUDE.md</code> file should be, general consensus is that &lt; 300 lines is best, and shorter is even better.</p>
<p>At HumanLayer, our root <code>CLAUDE.md</code> file is <em>less than sixty lines</em>.</p>
<h3>### <!-- -->Progressive Disclosure</h3>
<p>Writing a concise <code>CLAUDE.md</code> file that covers everything you want Claude to know can be challenging, especially in larger projects.</p>
<p>To address this, we can leverage the principle of <strong>Progressive Disclosure</strong> to ensure that claude only sees task- or project-specific instructions when it needs them.</p>
<p>Instead of including all your different instructions about building your project, running tests, code conventions, or other important context in your <code>CLAUDE.md</code> file, we recommend keeping task-specific instructions in <em>separate markdown files</em> with self-descriptive names somewhere in your project.</p>
<p>For example:</p>
<pre><pre><code><span>agent_docs/
</span>  |- building_the_project.md
<!-- -->  |- running_tests.md 
<!-- -->  |- code_conventions.md
<!-- -->  |- service_architecture.md
<!-- -->  |- database_schema.md
<!-- -->  |- service_communication_patterns.md</code></pre></pre>
<p>Then, in your <code>CLAUDE.md</code> file, you can include a list of these files with a brief description of each, and instruct Claude to decide which (if any) are relevant and to read them before it starts working. Or, ask Claude to present you with the files it wants to read for aproval first before reading them.</p>
<p><strong>Prefer pointers to copies</strong>. Don't include code snippets in these files if possible - they will become out-of-date quickly. Instead, include <code>file:line</code> references to point Claude to the authoritative context.</p>
<p>Conceptually, this is very similar to how <a href="https://code.claude.com/docs/en/skills" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Claude Skills</a> are intended to work, although skills are more focused on tool use than instructions.</p>
<h3>### <!-- -->Claude is (not) an expensive linter</h3>
<p>One of the most common things that we see people put in their <code>CLAUDE.md</code> file is code style guidelines. <strong>Never send an LLM to do a linter's job</strong>. LLMs are comparably expensive and <em>incredibly</em> slow compared to traditional linters and formatters. We think you should <em>always use deterministic tools whenever you can</em>.</p>
<p>Code style guidelines will inevitably add a bunch of instructions and mostly-irrelevant code snippets into your context window, degrading your LLM's performance and instruction-following and eating up your context window.</p>
<p><strong>LLMs are in-context learners</strong>! If your code follows a certain set of style guidelines or patterns, you should find that armed with a few searches of your codebase (or a good research document!) your agent should tend to follow existing code patterns and conventions without being told to.</p>
<p>If you feel very stronly about this, you might even consider setting up a <a href="https://code.claude.com/docs/en/hooks#stop" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Claude Code <code>Stop</code> hook</a> that runs your formatter &amp; linter and presents errors to Claude for it to fix. Don't make Claude find the formatting issues itself.</p>
<p><strong>Bonus points</strong>: use a linter that can automatically fix issues (we like Biome), and carefully tune your rules about what can safely be auto-fixed for maximum (safe) coverage.</p>
<p>You could also create a <a href="https://code.claude.com/docs/en/slash-commands" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Slash Command</a> that includes your code guidelines and which points claude at the changes in version control, or at your <code>git status</code>, or similar. This way, you can handle implementation and formatting separately. <strong>You will see better results with both as a result</strong>.</p>
<h3>### <!-- -->Don't use <code>/init</code> or auto-generate your <code>CLAUDE.md</code></h3>
<p>Both Claude Code and other harnesses with OpenCode come with ways to auto-generate your <code>CLAUDE.md</code> file (or <code>AGENTS.md</code>).</p>
<p>Because <code>CLAUDE.md</code> goes into <em>every single session</em> with Claude code, it is one of <strong>the highest leverage points of the harness</strong> - for better or for worse, depending on how you use it.</p>
<p>A bad line of code is a bad line of code. A bad line of an implementation plan has the potential to create a <strong>lot</strong> of bad lines of code. A bad line of a research that misunderstands how the system works has the potential to result in a lot of bad lines in the plan, and therefore a <strong>lot more</strong> bad lines of code as a result.</p>
<p>But the <code>CLAUDE.md</code> file affects <strong>every single phase of your workflow</strong> and every single artifact produced by it. As a result, we think you should spend some time thinking very carefully about every single line that goes into it:</p>
<p><img src="https://www.humanlayer.dev/blog/writing-a-good-claude-md/leverage.png" alt="Leverage"></p>
<h2>## <!-- -->In Conclusion</h2>
<div><ol>
<li><code>CLAUDE.md</code> is for onboarding Claude into your codebase. It should define your project's <strong>WHY</strong>, <strong>WHAT</strong>, and <strong>HOW</strong>.</li>
<li><strong>Less (instructions) is more</strong>. While you shouldn't omit necessary instructions, you should include as few instructions as reasonably possible in the file.</li>
<li>Keep the contents of your <code>CLAUDE.md</code> <strong>concise and universally applicable</strong>.</li>
<li>Use <strong>Progressive Disclosure</strong> - don't tell Claude all the information you could possibly want it to know. Rather, tell it <em>how to find</em> important information so that it can find and use it, but only when it needs to to avoid bloating your context window or instruction count.</li>
<li>Claude is not a linter. Use linters and code formatters, and use other features like <a href="https://code.claude.com/docs/en/hooks" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Hooks</a> and <a href="https://code.claude.com/docs/en/slash-commands" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Slash Commands</a> as necessary.</li>
<li><strong><code>CLAUDE.md</code> is the highest leverage point of the harness</strong>, so avoid auto-generating it. You should carefully craft its contents for best results.</li>
</ol></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[ETH-Zurich: Digital Design and Computer Architecture; 227-0003-10L, Spring, 2025 (143 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://safari.ethz.ch/ddca/spring2025/doku.php?id=start</link>
            <guid>46098747</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 17:45:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://safari.ethz.ch/ddca/spring2025/doku.php?id=start">https://safari.ethz.ch/ddca/spring2025/doku.php?id=start</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46098747">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div class="page">
                                                            <!-- wikipage start -->
                    <!-- TOC START -->
<div id="dw__toc">
<h3>Table of Contents</h3>

</div>
<!-- TOC END -->

<h2 id="digital_design_and_computer_architecture">Digital Design and Computer Architecture</h2>


<h2 id="spring_2025_227-0003-10l">Spring 2025 (227-0003-10L)</h2>
<p>
Welcome to the wiki for Digital Design and Computer Architecture for Spring 2025
</p>

<h2 id="announcements">Announcements</h2>


<h2 id="course_information">Course Information</h2>


<h3 id="description">Description</h3>
<p>
The class provides a first introduction to the design of digital circuits and computer architecture. It covers technical foundations of how a computing platform is designed from the bottom up. It introduces various execution paradigms, hardware description languages, and principles in digital design and computer architecture. 
The focus is on fundamental techniques employed in the design of modern microprocessors and their hardware/software interface.
</p>

<h3 id="objectives">Objectives</h3>
<div>

<p>
This class provides a first approach to Computer Architecture. The students learn the design of digital circuits in order to:
</p>
<ul>
<li><p> understand the basics, <br>
</p>
</li>
<li><p> understand the principles (of design), <br>
</p>
</li>
<li><p> understand the precedents (in computer architecture). <br>
</p>
</li>
</ul>

<p>
Based on such understanding, the students are expected to:
</p>
<ul>
<li><p> learn how a modern computer works underneath, from the bottom up, <br>
</p>
</li>
<li><p> evaluate tradeoffs of different designs and ideas, <br>
</p>
</li>
<li><p> implement a principled design (a simple microprocessor), <br>
</p>
</li>
<li><p> learn to systematically debug increasingly complex systems, <br>
</p>
</li>
<li><p> hopefully be prepared to develop novel, out-of-the-box designs.</p>
</li>
</ul>

<p>
The focus is on basics, principles, precedents, and how to use them to create/implement good designs.
</p>

<p>
<a href="https://www.vvz.ethz.ch/Vorlesungsverzeichnis/lerneinheit.view?lerneinheitId=188955&amp;semkez=2025S&amp;ansicht=LEHRVERANSTALTUNGEN&amp;lang=en" title="https://www.vvz.ethz.ch/Vorlesungsverzeichnis/lerneinheit.view?lerneinheitId=188955&amp;semkez=2025S&amp;ansicht=LEHRVERANSTALTUNGEN&amp;lang=en" rel="ugc nofollow">Course description page</a>
<a href="https://moodle-app2.let.ethz.ch/course/view.php?id=25002" title="https://moodle-app2.let.ethz.ch/course/view.php?id=25002" rel="ugc nofollow">Moodle</a>
</p>

</div>

<h3 id="lectures">Lectures</h3>
<div>

<p>
Thursday, 14:15-16:00, in HG F7 (Overflow room: HG F5) <br>

Friday, 14:15-16:00, in HG F7 (Overflow room: HG F5) <br>

</p>

<p>
Watch the lectures in YouTube livestream: 
</p>

</div>

<h3 id="lab_sessions">Lab sessions</h3>
<div>
<div><table>
	<thead>
	<tr>
		<th> When?      </th><th> Where?      </th>
	</tr>
	</thead>
	<tbody><tr>
		<td> Tuesday, 16:15-18:00 </td><td> labs in HG E19, HG E26.1, HG E26.3, HG E27</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td> Wednesday, 16:15-18:00  </td><td> labs in HG E19, HG E26.1, HG E26.3, HG E27</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td> Friday, 08:15-10:00  </td><td> labs in HG D11, HG D12, HG E26.3, HG E27</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td> Friday, 10:15-12:00  </td><td> labs in HG E19, HG E26.1, HG E26.3, HG E27</td>
	</tr>
</tbody></table></div>

<p>
<strong>Prerequisites:</strong> None.
</p>

</div>

<h2 id="staff_information">Staff Information</h2>


<h3 id="contact">Contact</h3>
<div>
<ul>
<li>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Office Hours</strong>: TBD</p>
</li>
</ul>


</div>

                    <!-- wikipage stop -->
                                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[ESA Sentinel-1D delivers first high-resolution images (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.esa.int/Applications/Observing_the_Earth/Copernicus/Sentinel-1/Sentinel-1D_delivers_first_images_from_Antarctica_to_Bremen</link>
            <guid>46098673</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 17:37:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.esa.int/Applications/Observing_the_Earth/Copernicus/Sentinel-1/Sentinel-1D_delivers_first_images_from_Antarctica_to_Bremen">https://www.esa.int/Applications/Observing_the_Earth/Copernicus/Sentinel-1/Sentinel-1D_delivers_first_images_from_Antarctica_to_Bremen</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46098673">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>

<header>
	<span>Applications</span>
	
	<p><span>26/11/2025</span>
				<span><span id="viewcount">18550</span><small> views</small></span>
										<span><span id="ezsr_total_26986180">52</span><small> likes</small></span>
				
	</p>
</header>





<p>The first high-resolution images have been received from Copernicus Sentinel-1D and were shared publicly for the first time at the European Space Agency’s Ministerial Council, held today in Bremen, Germany. Glaciers in Antarctica, the tip of South America, as well as the city of Bremen, are visible in these stunning radar images.</p>

<div>
				
		<p>The groundbreaking <a href="https://www.esa.int/Applications/Observing_the_Earth/Copernicus/Sentinel-1" target="_blank">Copernicus Sentinel-1 mission</a> saw the arrival in orbit of its latest satellite earlier in November: Sentinel-1D was launched on 4 November, on board an <a href="https://www.esa.int/Enabling_Support/Space_Transportation/Ariane" target="_blank">Ariane 6 launcher</a> from Europe’s Spaceport in French Guiana.</p><p>Once in orbit, the satellite and its instruments – it carries a 12 m-long synthetic aperture radar (SAR) instrument – were switched on, ready to capture images during a pass over the Antarctic and South America two days after launch. On the night of 6 November (European time), the first images were captured over the Antarctic Peninsula, the Tierra del Fuego and the Thwaites Glacier. Some six hours later, on the morning of 7 November, Sentinel-1D also captured images over Bremen, in Germany. The data was then transmitted, or ‘downlinked’, from the satellite to the ground station, in Matera (Italy), which is part of the Copernicus Ground Segment. All this was done within 50 hours of launch, which is likely to be the shortest time from launch to data delivery for a radar-based Earth observation satellite.</p>
	</div>
			
    
							
														
																	



							
				
								
						
								
									<div>
				<figure>
					<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2025/11/Elbe_River_delta_by_Sentinel-1D">
				<img src="https://www.esa.int/var/esa/storage/images/esa_multimedia/images/2025/11/elbe_river_delta_by_sentinel-1d/26991695-2-eng-GB/Elbe_River_delta_by_Sentinel-1D_article.jpg" alt="Elbe River delta by Sentinel-1D">
			</a>
				<figcaption>
							<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2025/11/Elbe_River_delta_by_Sentinel-1D">Elbe River delta by Sentinel-1D</a>
								</figcaption>
	</figure>	
		<p>According to Nuno Miranda, ESA’s Sentinel-1 Mission Manager, the images are of unprecedented data quality for a ‘first light’ acquisition. They are very similar to the <a href="https://www.esa.int/Applications/Observing_the_Earth/Copernicus/Sentinel-1/Sentinel-1C_captures_first_radar_images" target="_blank">images captured not so long ago by Sentinel-1C</a>, which, according to Nuno, is very promising for the commissioning phase. He noted, “These images have been downlinked and processed within an exceptionally short timeframe. Some of us remember that when Sentinel-1B was launched, it delivered its first radar images within two hours of activation. Sentinel-1D achieved this in an even faster time, setting what we believe is a new record for space radar. This remarkable performance reflects the dedication and exceptional preparation of all the teams involved.”</p><p>Radar instruments can image Earth’s surface through clouds, precipitation, regardless of sunlight, making them particularly well suited for monitoring polar regions. The Sentinel-1C and -1D satellites also carry an Automatic Identification System (AIS) instrument – improving the mission capacity to detect ships and sea pollution. The Sentinel-1D AIS was also activated as the satellite passed over Antarctica capturing the presence of ships in these extreme areas.</p>	</div>	
	<div>
	<h2>First images show fragility of glaciers</h2>
	    
							
														
																	



							
				
								
						
								
								<figure>
					<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2025/11/Antarctic_Peninsula_by_Sentinel-1D">
				<img src="https://www.esa.int/var/esa/storage/images/esa_multimedia/images/2025/11/antarctic_peninsula_by_sentinel-1d/26986308-2-eng-GB/Antarctic_Peninsula_by_Sentinel-1D_article.jpg" alt="Antarctic Peninsula by Sentinel-1D">
			</a>
				<figcaption>
							<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2025/11/Antarctic_Peninsula_by_Sentinel-1D">Antarctic Peninsula by Sentinel-1D</a>
								</figcaption>
	</figure>	
		<p><b>The Antarctic Peninsula</b>&nbsp;(above) is part of the larger peninsula of West Antarctica, protruding 1300 km. It is an ice sheet resting on a string of rocky islands and its tip is just 1000 km from the southern tip of South America. The Antarctic Peninsula ice sheet is one of the smallest ice sheets in Antarctica but is perhaps the most vulnerable to climate change as its glaciers are small and in a region of rapid warming. Observable changes such as collapsing ice shelves, thinning and accelerating glaciers are all key indicators of climate change in the region.</p><p>This image is in black and white, showing the contrast between the ocean and the peninsula’s icy landscape.</p>	</div>	
    
							
														
																	



							
				
								
						
								
									<div>
				<figure>
					<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2025/11/Tierra_del_Fuego_by_Sentinel-1D">
				<img src="https://www.esa.int/var/esa/storage/images/esa_multimedia/images/2025/11/tierra_del_fuego_by_sentinel-1d/26991490-4-eng-GB/Tierra_del_Fuego_by_Sentinel-1D_article.jpg" alt="Tierra del Fuego by Sentinel-1D">
			</a>
				<figcaption>
							<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2025/11/Tierra_del_Fuego_by_Sentinel-1D">Tierra del Fuego by Sentinel-1D</a>
								</figcaption>
	</figure>	
		<p><b>Tierra del Fuego</b>&nbsp;(above) is an archipelago off the southern tip of the South American continent. It covers territory in both Argentina to the east and in Chile to the west and is separated from the mainland by the Magellan Strait. The most southerly point of Tierra del Fuego is Cape Horn.</p><p>The bright contrasting colours in this image are created by using multiple types of radar wave, known polarisations. In this image the ocean and snowy peaks are shown in shades of blue, while the land appears yellow.</p>	</div>	
    
							
														
																	



							
				
								
						
								
									<div>
				<figure>
					<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2025/11/Thwaites_and_Pine_Island_glaciers_by_Sentinel-1D">
				<img src="https://www.esa.int/var/esa/storage/images/esa_multimedia/images/2025/11/thwaites_and_pine_island_glaciers_by_sentinel-1d/26991554-3-eng-GB/Thwaites_and_Pine_Island_glaciers_by_Sentinel-1D_article.jpg" alt="Thwaites and Pine Island glaciers by Sentinel-1D">
			</a>
				<figcaption>
							<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2025/11/Thwaites_and_Pine_Island_glaciers_by_Sentinel-1D">Thwaites and Pine Island glaciers by Sentinel-1D</a>
								</figcaption>
	</figure>	
		<p><b>The Thwaites Glacier</b>, and the adjacent Pine Island Glacier (above), are located west of the Antarctic Peninsula. Both are vulnerable to climate change. Thwaites is one of the most unstable glaciers in Antarctica and is at risk of rapid retreat. The details shown in this image from Sentinel-1D remind us of the fragility of glaciers in the Antarctic. And since 2025 is the <a href="https://www.un-glaciers.org/en" target="_blank">United Nation’s International Year of Glaciers' Preservation</a>, it is timely to see this image, captured on 6 November 2025.</p><p>This image also uses multiple radar polarisations to capture enhanced data on the landscape. In this image, the sea ice in the water is visible in tones of purple or violet, while the glacier appears white.</p>	</div>	
    
						
			<p>The publication of these images also follows the 30th meeting of the Conference of Parties, or COP30, where the consequences of climate change and the mitigating actions needed were discussed. The World Meteorological Organization’s <a href="https://wmo.int/files/state-of-climate-update-cop30" target="_blank">State of the Climate Update for COP30</a> notes that glaciers, from October 2023 to September 2024, lost the largest amount of ice on record back to 1950. The report states this is equivalent to 1.2 mm of global mean sea-level rise. The report also notes that, on 24 February 2025, the extent of Antarctic sea-ice reached its third lowest extent since satellite records began in 1978, the lowest being in 2023.</p>	
    
						
			<div>
				<p>Simonetta Cheli, Director of ESA’s Earth Observation Programmes, said, “This is a great achievement and I am so pleased to see these results from Sentinel-1D. It really places the data we receive from our innovative missions in the spotlight – it is data that we as a society rely upon as we continue to discuss and take action on climate change, and also data that we need in applications for understanding and studying our planet.</p><p>“The Sentinel-1 team has done an amazing job and I would like to thank everyone within ESA, together with our partners in the space industry and European institutions, for delivering work of such high quality. It’s an honour to deliver this mission for the Copernicus Earth observation programme, and we thank the Commission for their support and collaboration. We look forward also to developing the Sentinel missions of the future, to further extend the capacity and potential of Copernicus for Europe.”</p>	</div>	
    
							
														
																	



							
				
								
						
								
									<div>
				<figure>
					<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2025/11/Bremen_by_Sentinel-1D">
				<img src="https://www.esa.int/var/esa/storage/images/esa_multimedia/images/2025/11/bremen_by_sentinel-1d/26991648-2-eng-GB/Bremen_by_Sentinel-1D_article.jpg" alt="Bremen by Sentinel-1D">
			</a>
				<figcaption>
							<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2025/11/Bremen_by_Sentinel-1D">Bremen by Sentinel-1D</a>
								</figcaption>
	</figure>	
		<p>ESA’s Sentinel-1 Project Manager, Ramón Torres, expressed the whole team’s pride, “Unveiling the first images from Sentinel-1D is an incredibly emotional milestone for all of us. The sense of awe and fulfilment goes beyond the thrill of liftoff itself, because seeing those breathtaking images from the SAR instrument brings our hard work to life. They are not just pictures – they are proof of our vision becoming reality, underlining how cutting-edge this mission truly is. The fact that these stunning images also confirm the satellite’s health and flawless operation fills us with relief and joy. And to have achieved all of this within an astonishingly short time – just over two days after launch – makes this moment even more unforgettable for our team.”</p>	</div>	
    
							
														
																								



				
				
								
						
								
						<div>
		<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Videos/2025/11/Copernicus_Sentinel-1D_launch_highlights">
		<div>
				

   <p><img src="https://www.esa.int/extension/pillars/design/pillars/images/play-button.svg" alt="Play"></p>
   <p><img src="https://www.esa.int/var/esa/storage/images/esa_multimedia/videos/2025/11/copernicus_sentinel-1d_launch_highlights/26953823-4-eng-GB/Copernicus_Sentinel-1D_launch_highlights_pillars.png" alt="$video.data_map.short_description.content">

 
		</p></div>
		</a>
				
			</div>	
    
						
    
					



</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[LLVM-MOS – Clang LLVM fork targeting the 6502 (128 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://llvm-mos.org/wiki/Welcome</link>
            <guid>46098359</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 17:02:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://llvm-mos.org/wiki/Welcome">https://llvm-mos.org/wiki/Welcome</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46098359">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="mw-wrapper" role="main">
					

					<h2 id="firstHeading" lang=""><span>Welcome</span></h2>
					<p>From llvm-mos</p>
					<div lang="en" dir="ltr" id="bodyContent"><figure typeof="mw:File/Thumb"><a href="https://llvm-mos.org/wiki/File:Miroh_Jr_for_NES.gif"><img src="https://llvm-mos.org/images/thumb/d/d7/Miroh_Jr_for_NES.gif/300px-Miroh_Jr_for_NES.gif" decoding="async" width="300" height="281" srcset="https://llvm-mos.org/images/thumb/d/d7/Miroh_Jr_for_NES.gif/450px-Miroh_Jr_for_NES.gif 1.5x, https://llvm-mos.org/images/d/d7/Miroh_Jr_for_NES.gif 2x" data-file-width="512" data-file-height="480"></a><figcaption>Miroh Jr for NES, by Wendel, Raftronaut, and M-Tee, built with LLVM-MOS</figcaption></figure>
<figure typeof="mw:File/Thumb"><a href="https://llvm-mos.org/wiki/File:Linux-c64.jpg"><img src="https://llvm-mos.org/images/thumb/2/21/Linux-c64.jpg/300px-Linux-c64.jpg" decoding="async" width="300" height="169" srcset="https://llvm-mos.org/images/thumb/2/21/Linux-c64.jpg/450px-Linux-c64.jpg 1.5x, https://llvm-mos.org/images/thumb/2/21/Linux-c64.jpg/600px-Linux-c64.jpg 2x" data-file-width="1280" data-file-height="720"></a><figcaption>Linux booting on Commodore 64 with REU, via emulator built with LLVM-MOS</figcaption></figure>
<figure typeof="mw:File/Thumb"><a href="https://llvm-mos.org/wiki/File:Nes-llvm-demo.png"><img src="https://llvm-mos.org/images/thumb/1/1e/Nes-llvm-demo.png/300px-Nes-llvm-demo.png" decoding="async" width="300" height="251" srcset="https://llvm-mos.org/images/thumb/1/1e/Nes-llvm-demo.png/450px-Nes-llvm-demo.png 1.5x, https://llvm-mos.org/images/thumb/1/1e/Nes-llvm-demo.png/600px-Nes-llvm-demo.png 2x" data-file-width="1259" data-file-height="1054"></a><figcaption>NES project in pure C99 using llvm-mos, by Steven Poulton</figcaption></figure>
<figure typeof="mw:File/Thumb"><a href="https://llvm-mos.org/wiki/File:Rust-hello-atari-800.png"><img src="https://llvm-mos.org/images/thumb/5/55/Rust-hello-atari-800.png/300px-Rust-hello-atari-800.png" decoding="async" width="300" height="24" srcset="https://llvm-mos.org/images/thumb/5/55/Rust-hello-atari-800.png/450px-Rust-hello-atari-800.png 1.5x, https://llvm-mos.org/images/thumb/5/55/Rust-hello-atari-800.png/600px-Rust-hello-atari-800.png 2x" data-file-width="959" data-file-height="76"></a><figcaption>Hello world in Rust, with factorial calculation, for Atari 800, proof of concept by mrk</figcaption></figure>
<figure typeof="mw:File/Thumb"><a href="https://llvm-mos.org/wiki/File:Hello-vic20.png"><img src="https://llvm-mos.org/images/thumb/4/4a/Hello-vic20.png/300px-Hello-vic20.png" decoding="async" width="300" height="198" srcset="https://llvm-mos.org/images/4/4a/Hello-vic20.png 1.5x" data-file-width="400" data-file-height="264"></a><figcaption>Hello world of LLVM assembler targeting Commodore VIC-20</figcaption></figure>
<figure typeof="mw:File/Thumb"><a href="https://llvm-mos.org/wiki/File:Hello-apple2.png"><img src="https://llvm-mos.org/images/thumb/1/1d/Hello-apple2.png/300px-Hello-apple2.png" decoding="async" width="300" height="207" srcset="https://llvm-mos.org/images/thumb/1/1d/Hello-apple2.png/450px-Hello-apple2.png 1.5x, https://llvm-mos.org/images/thumb/1/1d/Hello-apple2.png/600px-Hello-apple2.png 2x" data-file-width="1113" data-file-height="767"></a><figcaption>Hello world of LLVM assembler targeting Apple IIe</figcaption></figure>
<figure typeof="mw:File/Thumb"><a href="https://llvm-mos.org/wiki/File:Llvm-mos_hello_world_osi_c1p.png"><img src="https://llvm-mos.org/images/thumb/0/0d/Llvm-mos_hello_world_osi_c1p.png/300px-Llvm-mos_hello_world_osi_c1p.png" decoding="async" width="300" height="289" srcset="https://llvm-mos.org/images/thumb/0/0d/Llvm-mos_hello_world_osi_c1p.png/450px-Llvm-mos_hello_world_osi_c1p.png 1.5x, https://llvm-mos.org/images/thumb/0/0d/Llvm-mos_hello_world_osi_c1p.png/600px-Llvm-mos_hello_world_osi_c1p.png 2x" data-file-width="2182" data-file-height="2102"></a><figcaption>Hello world in C, targeting Ohio Scientific Challenger 1P, port by Stephan Mühlstrasser</figcaption></figure>
<figure typeof="mw:File/Thumb"><a href="https://llvm-mos.org/wiki/File:Hello_Commander_X16.png"><img src="https://llvm-mos.org/images/thumb/5/54/Hello_Commander_X16.png/300px-Hello_Commander_X16.png" decoding="async" width="300" height="145" srcset="https://llvm-mos.org/images/thumb/5/54/Hello_Commander_X16.png/450px-Hello_Commander_X16.png 1.5x, https://llvm-mos.org/images/thumb/5/54/Hello_Commander_X16.png/600px-Hello_Commander_X16.png 2x" data-file-width="1472" data-file-height="710"></a><figcaption>Hello Commander X16 from C</figcaption></figure>
<p>llvm-mos is an open-source fork of the <a rel="nofollow" href="https://llvm.org/">LLVM</a> C/C++ compiler, that provides first-class support to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MOS_Technology" title="wikipedia:MOS Technology">MOS Technology</a> 65xx series of microprocessors and relatives.  llvm-mos enables modern software development for many classic platforms.
</p><p>You can play with the compiler right now on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://godbolt.org/z/c11Th3oMW">Godbolt</a>!   Here's a <a rel="nofollow" href="https://godbolt.org/z/c11Th3oMW">Commodore 64 project</a> that shows the C compiler in action.  Try the "Click here to emulate" link on that page, to watch a Commodore 64 compute a hundred digits of pi.
</p><p>To download and use the tools locally, check out <a rel="nofollow" href="https://github.com/llvm-mos/llvm-mos-sdk#getting-started">Getting started</a>.
</p><p>Our work encompasses the following:
</p>
<ul><li>An open-source <a rel="nofollow" href="https://github.com/llvm-mos/llvm-mos">fork of LLVM</a> that provides first-class support to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MOS_Technology_6502" title="wikipedia:MOS Technology 6502">MOS 6502</a> and near compatibles.&nbsp; Our compiler implements <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2lW3WHPtmKo">multiple novel approaches</a> in order to optimize 6502 code size and speed, and it tends to outperform legacy 6502 compilers.&nbsp; Our compiler includes, but is not limited to:
<ul><li>broad C99 and C++11 freestanding compatibility</li>
<li>built-in <a rel="nofollow" href="https://github.com/llvm-mos/llvm-mos/issues/10">IEEE-754 floating point support</a></li>
<li>first-class <a href="https://llvm-mos.org/wiki/Assembler" title="Assembler">integrated 65xx assembler support</a></li>
<li>clang's world-class error messages</li></ul></li>
<li>An open-source <a rel="nofollow" href="https://github.com/llvm-mos/llvm-mos-sdk">software development kit</a> (SDK) that comprises target-specific code for common 65xx-based microcomputers.&nbsp; It includes a <a rel="nofollow" href="https://github.com/llvm-mos/llvm-mos-sdk/tree/main/mos-platform/common">minimal C standard library</a> with support for memory management and text output.&nbsp; Some <a rel="nofollow" href="https://github.com/llvm-mos/llvm-mos-sdk/tree/main/examples">example programs</a> are included.&nbsp; We currently support <a rel="nofollow" href="https://github.com/llvm-mos/llvm-mos-sdk/tree/main/mos-platform">over two dozen targets</a>, including a <a rel="nofollow" href="https://github.com/llvm-mos/llvm-mos-sdk/tree/main/utils/sim">host-based simulator</a>.&nbsp; The list of supported targets is growing rapidly.</li>
<li><a rel="nofollow" href="https://llvm-mos.org/wiki/ELF_specification">Complete ELF support</a> for the 6502 series, which permits us to use the existing <a rel="nofollow" href="https://github.com/llvm-mos/llvm-mos/blob/main/clang/cmake/caches/MOS.cmake#L36">suite of LLVM tools</a> for creating, analyzing and modifying 6502 object files and libraries.</li>
<li>An open-source automated <a rel="nofollow" href="https://github.com/llvm-mos/llvm-test-suite">test</a> and <a rel="nofollow" href="https://github.com/llvm-mos/llvm-mos-sdk/blob/main/.github/workflows/package.yml">packaging</a> infrastructure.&nbsp; We use <a rel="nofollow" href="https://docs.github.com/en/actions/using-github-hosted-runners/about-github-hosted-runners">GitHub runners</a> to verify builds of our compiler against appropriate LLVM test suites, as well as our own <a rel="nofollow" href="https://github.com/llvm-mos/smoke-test">smoke tests</a>.&nbsp; We also run <a rel="nofollow" href="https://llvm-mos.github.io/llvm-test-suite">automated benchmarks</a> using this infrastructure.</li></ul>
<p>Ongoing public development discussions occur on Discord.  If you'd like to help, then <a rel="nofollow" href="https://discord.gg/D9gRm3aznh">please join our Discord group now</a>.
</p>


<h4><span id="Notice">Notice</span></h4>
<p>The llvm-mos project is not officially affiliated with or endorsed by the LLVM Foundation. Our project is a fork of LLVM that provides a new backend and Clang target; our project is based on LLVM, not a part of LLVM. Our use of LLVM or other related trademarks does not imply affiliation or endorsement.
</p>
<h3><span id="Category_tree">Category tree</span></h3>

<h3><span id="Categories">Categories</span></h3>

<h3><span id="Pages">Pages</span></h3>

<!-- 
NewPP limit report
Cached time: 20251002152727
Cache expiry: 0
Reduced expiry: true
Complications: [show‐toc]
CPU time usage: 0.089 seconds
Real time usage: 0.093 seconds
Preprocessor visited node count: 34/1000000
Post‐expand include size: 52/2097152 bytes
Template argument size: 0/2097152 bytes
Highest expansion depth: 2/100
Expensive parser function count: 2/100
Unstrip recursion depth: 0/20
Unstrip post‐expand size: 9159/5000000 bytes
-->
<!--
Transclusion expansion time report (%,ms,calls,template)
100.00%   13.686      1 -total
 98.17%   13.436      2 Special:AllPages
-->
</div>
					
				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[GitHub to Codeberg: my experience (229 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://eldred.fr/blog/forge-migration/</link>
            <guid>46097829</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 16:12:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://eldred.fr/blog/forge-migration/">https://eldred.fr/blog/forge-migration/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46097829">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemscope="" itemtype="https://schema.org/Article"><hgroup><p>Published <time datetime="2025-11-29" itemprop="datePublished">Sat 29 Nov 2025</time>. Estimated reading time: 11 minutes.</p></hgroup><meta content="2097" itemprop="wordCount"><hr><p>In which I talk about the process involved in switching forges, and how well that went.</p><span id="continue-reading"></span><p>Spoiler alert: this very site that you’re reading this on is not served from <a href="https://github.io/">GitHub Pages</a> anymore! At this point, I’d call my migration successful. But it took more than clicking a single button, so let’s talk about the steps involved, at least for me. I’m hoping that it can <a href="https://eldred.fr/blog/codeberg/#isso-8">help be an example for other people</a>, and show that it’s actually not that complicated.</p><h2 id="my-migration-process">(My) migration process</h2><p>First, I took an hour or so to set up my profile picture, email address(es), SSH keys…</p><h3 id="step-1-migrating-the-repos">Step 1: migrating the repos</h3><p>This wasn’t difficult, because <a href="https://forgejo.org/">Forgejo</a> (the forge software that powers Codeberg) offers a “migrate from GitHub” functionality. You need to <a href="https://docs.github.com/en/authentication/keeping-your-account-and-data-secure/managing-your-personal-access-tokens#creating-a-personal-access-token-classic">generate a PAT on GitHub</a> to import things like issues (which is awesome!), and as a bonus it also speeds up the process.</p><p>It <em>was</em>, however, tedious, because the process was entirely manual (perhaps there’s a way to automate it, like by using some <a href="https://codeberg.org/forgejo-contrib/delightful-forgejo#command-line">Forgejo CLI tool</a>, but I didn’t bother looking into that). And, due to GitHub API rate limits, whenever I tried importing two repos at the same time, one or both would fail. (It wasn’t <em>too</em> bad, though, since I could fill out the migration page for the next while one was in progress; and generally, it took me roughly as long to fill it out as it took Codeberg to perform the import.)</p><p>I’m really happy that issues, PRs, wikis, and releases can be imported flawlessly: this makes it possible to not have to refer to GitHub anymore!</p><h3 id="step-2-repointing-links-to-codeberg">Step 2: repointing links to Codeberg</h3><p>Of course I don’t control all links that point to my stuff, but I could at least run <code>rg -F github.com/ISSOtm</code> in my home directory, to catch those within my own repos. It’s possible to automate the replacing process:</p><pre data-lang="bash"><code data-lang="bash"><span><span><span>$</span></span><span> sed<span><span> --</span>in-place</span><span><span> --</span>regexp-extended</span> <span><span>'</span>s,github.com/ISSOtm,codeberg.org/ISSOtm,<span>'</span></span> <span>&lt;</span>files...<span>&gt;</span>
</span></span></code></pre><p>…and if you’re feeling like bulk-replacing all files in a directory:</p><pre data-lang="bash"><code data-lang="bash"><span><span><span>$</span></span><span> find <span>&lt;</span>directory<span>&gt;</span> <span>-</span>type f<span><span> -</span>exec</span> sed<span><span> -</span>Ei</span> <span><span>'</span>s,github.com/ISSOtm,codeberg.org/ISSOtm<span>'</span></span> <span><span>{</span><span>}</span></span> +</span>
</span></code></pre><p>Repositories, however, may still be pointing to GitHub:</p><pre data-lang="bash"><code data-lang="bash"><span><span><span>$</span></span><span> git remote<span><span> -</span>v</span></span>
</span><span><span><span>origin</span></span><span>	git@github.com:ISSOtm/rsgbds.git (fetch</span><span></span>)
</span><span><span><span>origin</span></span><span>	git@github.com:ISSOtm/rsgbds.git (push</span><span></span>)
</span></code></pre><p>You can either manually <code>git remote set-url origin git@codeberg.org:ISSOtm/rsgbds.git</code> (or the equivalent if you’re using HTTPS), or use one of the replace commands above, since remote URLs are stored textually:</p><pre data-lang="bash"><code data-lang="bash"><span><span><span>#</span></span><span> Within a single repo:</span><span>
</span></span><span><span><span>$</span></span><span> find .git<span><span> -</span>name</span> config<span><span> -</span>exec</span> sed<span><span> -</span>Ei</span> <span><span>'</span>s,github.com:ISSOtm,codeberg.org:ISSOtm,<span>'</span></span> <span><span>{</span><span>}</span></span> + <span><span>#</span></span><span> Replace the colons with slashes if you're using HTTPS!</span><span>
</span></span></span><span>
</span><span><span><span>#</span></span><span> For all repos within the current directory: (requires `shopt -s globstar` if using Bash)</span><span>
</span></span><span><span><span>$</span></span><span> find <span>*</span><span>*</span>/.git<span><span> -</span>name</span> config<span><span> -</span>exec</span> sed<span><span> -</span>Ei</span> <span><span>'</span>s,github.com:ISSOtm,codeberg.org:ISSOtm,<span>'</span></span> <span><span>{</span><span>}</span></span> + <span><span>#</span></span><span> Ditto the above.</span><span>
</span></span></span></code></pre><p>…then it’s a matter of pushing the changes to all of the repos.</p><h3 id="step-3-stubbing-out-the-github-repos">Step 3: stubbing out the GitHub repos</h3><p>I also wanted to make it clear that my repos were now living on Codeberg; so, I created a little script in an empty directory:</p><pre data-lang="bash" data-name="stub_out.sh"><code data-lang="bash" data-name="stub_out.sh"><span><span><span>#</span></span><span>!/bin/bash</span><span>
</span></span><span><span><span>set</span></span><span> -euo pipefail</span>
</span><span>
</span><span><span><span>git</span></span><span> remote set-url origin git@github.com:ISSOtm/<span><span>$</span><span>1</span></span></span>
</span><span><span><span>cat</span></span><span> <span><span>&lt;&lt;</span><span>EOF</span></span> <span><span>&gt;</span>README.md</span><span>
</span></span></span><span><span><span># Moved to https://codeberg.org/ISSOtm/<span><span>$</span><span>1</span></span>
</span></span></span><span><span><span>
</span></span></span><span><span><span>[See my blog](http://eldred.fr/blog/codeberg) as to why.
</span></span></span><span><span><span><span>EOF</span></span></span>
</span><span><span><span>git</span></span><span> add README.md</span>
</span><span><span><span>git</span></span><span> commit<span><span> --</span>amend</span><span><span> --</span>message</span> <span><span>'</span>Add move notice<span>'</span></span></span>
</span><span><span><span>git</span></span><span> push<span><span> --</span>force</span></span>
</span><span><span><span>gh</span></span><span> repo edit<span><span> --</span>description</span> <span><span>"</span>Moved to https://codeberg.org/ISSOtm/<span><span>$</span><span>1</span></span><span>"</span></span><span><span> --</span>homepage</span> <span><span>"</span>https://codeberg.org/ISSOtm/<span><span>$</span><span>1</span></span><span>"</span></span></span>
</span><span><span><span>gh</span></span><span> repo archive<span><span> --</span>yes</span></span>
</span></code></pre><p>Then, to run it:</p><pre data-lang="bash"><code data-lang="bash"><span><span><span>$</span></span><span> chmod +x stub_out.sh</span>
</span><span><span><span>$</span></span><span> git init</span>
</span><span><span><span>$</span></span><span> git remote add origin <span><span>'</span><span>'</span></span></span>
</span><span><span><span>$</span></span><span> ./stub_out.sh rsgbds</span>
</span><span><span><span>$</span></span><span> ./stub_out.sh fortISSimO</span>
</span><span><span><span>#</span></span><span> ...etc.</span><span>
</span></span></code></pre><p>The automation made it not painful, so this went pretty well.</p><h3 id="step-4-porting-ci">Step 4: porting CI</h3><p>Now, onto the harder stuff :)</p><p>The first interesting thing that I noticed is this section of <a href="https://codeberg.org/actions/meta/#rules-and-conditions">Codeberg’s CI documentation</a>:</p><blockquote><p>Running CI/CD pipelines can use significant amounts of energy. As much as it is tempting to have green checkmarks everywhere, running the jobs costs real money and has environmental costs.</p><p>Unlike other giant platforms, we do not encourage you to write “heavy” pipelines and charge you for the cost later. We expect you to carefully consider the costs and benefits from your pipelines and reduce CI/CD usage to a minimum amount necessary to guarantee consistent quality for your projects.</p></blockquote><p>That got me to think about which projects of mine really need CI, and ultimately, I decided that I would only need CI for publishing my website, and the documentation of <a href="https://codeberg.org/ISSOtm/gb-starter-kit/src/branch/doc">gb-starter-kit</a> and <a href="https://codeberg.org/ISSOtm/fortISSimO/src/branch/master/manual">fortISSimO</a>; the rest of my projects don’t get contributions anyway, so I can live without CI on them, at least for now.</p><p>Anyway, Codeberg actually has two different CI solutions: <a href="https://docs.codeberg.org/ci/#using-codeberg's-instance-of-woodpecker-ci">Woodpecker</a>, and <a href="https://docs.codeberg.org/ci/actions">Forgejo Actions</a>; the former seems to be more powerful, but you need to apply for access, and the latter is very close to GitHub Actions, which should facilitate the migration. So I picked Forgejo Actions, even though it’s marked as being in beta.</p><p>It’s not very difficult to port a YAML file from GHA to Forgejo Actions; for example, look at <a href="https://codeberg.org/ISSOtm/gb-starter-kit/commit/93a455d01b62e7c8aa64e7d357029102ebce54fb">the commit porting gb-starter-kit’s publishing CI</a>. (This doesn’t really appear as a diff, since I’ve moved the file; but it’s small, so it’s easy to compare manually.)</p><p>Here are some salient points:</p><ul><li>Actions are normally just referred to as <code>owner/repo</code>, but Forgejo supports cloning <em>any</em> Git repo, especially across forges. It’s actually recommended to use full URLs always, so you don’t rely on the default prefix, which is configurable by the instance admin and thus not necessarily portable.</li><li>I could have kept the files in <code>.github/workflows</code>, since Forgejo <a href="https://forgejo.org/docs/latest/user/actions/overview/#workflows">picks up that directory automatically</a> if <code>.forgejo/workflows</code> doesn’t exist; however, I think it’s more convenient to keep un-migrated scripts in <code>.github</code> and migrated ones in <code>.forgejo</code>.</li><li>Most Actions (the individual steps, not the workflow files) actually work out of the box on Forgejo Actions. Nice!</li><li>Codeberg’s runners differ from GitHub’s significantly: they have <em>way</em> less software installed by default, fewer resources, and only Linux runners are provided (Ubuntu by default, but you can use <a href="https://hub.docker.com/">any Docker container image</a>). macOS and Windows being non-free OSes, Codeberg has no plans to offer either of those! For both philosophical and financial reasons. If this is a deal-breaker for you, consider cross-compiling, or bringing your own runner.</li><li>Unless low latency is crucial, consider using <a href="https://codeberg.org/actions/meta/#lazy-runners">the lazy runners</a> for better load balancing and possibly greener energy consumption. In practice I haven’t seen delays beyond a few minutes, which is acceptable to me.</li></ul><p>I actually spent some extra time trying to use less compute to perform my CI jobs, somewhat motivated by the small size of the runners, and because I’m guessing that the smaller the runner you’re picking, the faster your job will be able to be scheduled. <a href="https://codeberg.org/ISSOtm/gb-starter-kit/commit/fe48963">Here is one such commit</a>; note in particular line 50, where I tried<sup><a href="#latex_fail">1</a></sup> using a Docker image with LaTeX preinstalled, which saves the time taken by <code>apt install</code> and requires fewer writes to the filesystem, <a href="https://codeberg.org/actions/meta/#available-runners">freeing up RAM</a>.</p><h3 id="step-5-re-hosting-my-website">Step 5: re-hosting my website</h3><p>All of the previous steps were done within the span of a few days; however, since my website (this very website) was hosted using GitHub Pages, I couldn’t migrate its repos (yes, plural: you can configure individual repos to be published separately, which is how e.g. <a href="https://eldred.fr/fortISSimO">https://eldred.fr/fortISSimO</a> is published, despite not being in the website’s main repo).</p><p>Nominally, Codeberg has an equivalent, <a href="https://codeberg.page/">Codeberg Pages</a>; however, as mentioned on that page, <q>the software behind this feature is currently in maintenance mode</q>, because of complexity and performance issues<sup><a href="#pages_whitequark">2</a></sup>. So I left it at that for roughly a month, hoping there’ll eventually be an update. Also, subprojects are published as subdomains instead of subdirectories, which would have broken links (e.g. <code>http://eldred.fr/fortISSimO</code> would have become <code>http://fortISSimO.eldred.fr</code>). Meh…</p><p>And then (by chance lol) I discovered <a href="https://codeberg.org/git-pages/git-pages">git-pages</a> and its public instance <a href="https://grebedoc.dev/">Grebedoc</a><sup><a href="#bird">3</a></sup>! It functions much like GitHub Pages, though with a bit more setup since it’s not integrated within the forge itself.</p><p>git-pages actually has several niceties:</p><ul><li>My website had zero downtime during the entire migration, as git-pages <a href="https://grebedoc.dev/#zero-downtime">supports</a> uploading your website before updating your DNS records!</li><li>It <a href="https://grebedoc.dev/#redirects">also supports</a> server-side redirects, which lets me redirect people who still go to http://eldred.fr/gb-asm-tutorial/* to its new home, for example. People have been getting 404s because of incomplete client-side coverage on my side, but no more!</li><li>It <a href="https://grebedoc.dev/#headers">also also supports</a> custom headers; I’m not particularly interested in <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTTP/CORS">CORS</a>, but I’ve used that file to <a href="https://codeberg.org/ISSOtm/eldred.fr/commit/51a1718ea6f017520dfac27855c3f2cb032a09b4">pay my respects</a><sup><a href="#clacks_overhead">4</a></sup>.</li></ul><p>Oh, and also, <a href="https://blog.codeberg.org/letter-from-codeberg-onwards-and-upwards.html">Codeberg’s November 2025 newsletter</a> mentions that <q>Codeberg is planning to gradually migrate to [git-pages]</q>. Exciting!</p><p>I’m actually much happier using this than GitHub Pages; so, I’ve joined <a href="https://www.patreon.com/whitequark">Catherine’s Patreon</a>, because I want to see this go far.</p><div id="pages_whitequark"><p><sup>2</sup></p><p>To quote Catherine’s motivation for creating git-pages: <q>I started out wanting to just use Codeberg Pages and then I found out that Codeberg Pages is in maintenance mode and has such poor architecture that not only does it have rather low uptime but it also regularly crashes Codeberg’s Forgejo instance itself.</q></p></div><h3 id="time-tracking">Time tracking</h3><p>Steps 1 through 3 (migrating the repos) took me the better part of an afternoon; step 4 (porting CI) took me another afternoon, mostly to learn the new CI system; and step 5 (the website) took me… well, it should have taken an afternoon, but I used the opportunity to also pay down some tech debt (merging my slides repo into my main website), which took a few days due to required rearchitecting.</p><p>All in all, even with 45 repos migrated, this basically took a weekend. And I didn’t find it annoying!</p><p>Since the task seemed really daunting, <a href="https://ncase.me/anxiety">my anxiety</a> caused me to procrastinate this a lot, but in the end it was little work. One of the reasons I’m writing this is to let other people know that, so they can overcome their own anxiety. Maybe. :P</p><h2 id="what-now">What now?</h2><p>All in all, I’m very happy with this migration! As far as I can tell, nothing on this website has broken, and I’ve tried reasonably containing the breakage over on GitHub: I have truncated the <code>master</code> branches, but all other branches and tags remain in place (mostly due to laziness lol), permalinks (e.g. <code>https://github.com/ISSOtm/gb-bootroms/blob/c8ed9e106e0ab1193a57071820e46358006c79d0/src/dmg.asm</code>) still work, only non-perma links (e.g. <code>https://github.com/ISSOtm/gb-bootroms/blob/master/src/dmg.asm</code>) are broken, but those are unreliable in the first place anyway.</p><p>Since that means that all of my code <em>is</em> still on GitHub, I <em>want</em> to delete my repos; but that would be a bad idea at this point, due to leaving no redirects or anything. I’ll consider that again in… idk, a year or something. I would also like to delete my GitHub account (like I have deleted my Twitter account when… *gestures vaguely*), but not only do I need my repos to be up, I also need my account to contribute to projects that are still on GitHub.</p><p>One downside of this migration is that since I’m moving off of The Main Forge, my projects are likely to get fewer contributions… But I wasn’t getting many in the first place, and some people have already made accounts on Codeberg to keep contributing to my stuff. Likewise, I’m not really worried about discoverability. We’ll see I guess lol 🤷‍♂️</p><p>Lastly, I’m writing this after the migration, and I haven’t really taken notes during it; so, if I’ve forgotten any steps, feel free to let me know in the comments below or by <a href="https://codeberg.org/ISSOtm/eldred.fr/issues/new">opening an issue</a>, and I’ll edit this article.</p><p>Cheers!</p><h2 id="special-thanks">Special thanks</h2><ul><li><a href="https://mastodon.social/@whitequark">Catherine ‘whitequark’</a> for her work on git-pages and for being part of the ops team for Grebedoc</li><li><a href="https://servfail.network/">SERVFAIL network</a> (<a href="https://sdomi.pl/">domi</a>, <a href="https://scholz.ruhr/">Merlin</a>, <a href="https://famfo.xyz/">famfo</a>, <a href="https://donotsta.re/aprl">aprl</a>, and all of #servfail) for being my awesome DNS providers</li><li>Codeberg team and Forgejo contributors for making all of this possible in the first place</li></ul><hr><nav><ul></ul><ul><li>Earlier post: <a href="https://eldred.fr/blog/codeberg/">Migrating my code to Codeberg</a></li></ul></nav><hr></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Thinking Game Film – Google DeepMind Documentary (181 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://thinkinggamefilm.com</link>
            <guid>46097773</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 16:07:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://thinkinggamefilm.com">https://thinkinggamefilm.com</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46097773">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-blend-mode="NORMAL" data-block-type="51" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-36b906ec8e60627e7e9c">
  <form data-form-id="66b53d657ca9291898d9cf06" autocomplete="on" method="POST" novalidate="" onsubmit="return (function (form) {
    Y.use('squarespace-form-submit', 'node', function usingFormSubmit(Y) {
      (new Y.Squarespace.FormSubmit(form)).submit({
        formId: '66b53d657ca9291898d9cf06',
        collectionId: '66b53d657ca9291898d9cf08',
        objectName: '36b906ec8e60627e7e9c'
      });
    });
    return false;
  })(this);">
    <header>
      <h2>Stay Updated</h2>
      <p>Sign up with your email address to receive news and updates.</p>
    </header>
    <div>
        
        
          
            <p><label for="email-yui_3_17_2_1_1717442210916_3242-field">Email Address</label>
              
            </p>
          
        
          
        
      </div>
    <p>We respect your privacy.</p>
    <p>Thank you!</p>
    
  </form>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Modern cars are spying on you. Here's what you can do about it (274 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://apnews.com/article/auto-car-privacy-3674ce59c9b30f2861d29178a31e6ab7</link>
            <guid>46097624</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 15:52:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://apnews.com/article/auto-car-privacy-3674ce59c9b30f2861d29178a31e6ab7">https://apnews.com/article/auto-car-privacy-3674ce59c9b30f2861d29178a31e6ab7</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46097624">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                                        <p>While driving to a new restaurant, your car’s satellite navigation system tracks your location and guides you to the destination. Onboard cameras constantly track your face and eye movements. When another car veers into your path, forcing you to slam on the brakes, sensors are assisting and recording. Waiting at a stoplight, the car notices when you unbuckle your seat belt to grab your sunglasses in the backseat. </p><p>Modern cars are computers on wheels that are becoming increasingly connected, enabling innovative new features that make driving safer and more convenient. But these systems are also collecting reams of data on our driving habits and other personal information, raising concerns about data privacy. </p><p>Here is what to know about how your car spies on you and how you can minimize it: </p>
    
<h2>How cars collect data </h2><p>It’s hard to figure out exactly how much data a modern car is collecting on you, according to the Mozilla Foundation, which <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/data-privacy-cars-data-collection-mozilla-foundation-c616f41983b6cbd62445da0e4962091d">analyzed privacy practices</a></span> at 25 auto brands in 2023. It declared that cars were the worst product category that the group had ever reviewed for privacy. </p><div data-separate-event="audioModule" data-separate-value="AP AUDIO: One Tech Tip: Modern cars are spying on you. Here’s what you can do about it" data-module="" data-gtm-region="AP AUDIO: One Tech Tip: Modern cars are spying on you. Here’s what you can do about it" data-align-center="">
    
    
    
    
        
            <bsp-custom-headline custom-headline="div">
                <p>
                    AP AUDIO: One Tech Tip: Modern cars are spying on you. Here’s what you can do about it
                </p>
            </bsp-custom-headline>
        
    
    
    <p>Modern cars are spying on you. AP’s Kelvin Chan reports.</p>
    
</div><p>The data points include all your normal interactions with the car — such as turning the steering wheel or unlocking doors — but also data from connected onboard services, like satellite radio, GPS navigation systems, connected devices, telematics systems as well as data from sensors or cameras. </p>

<div data-module="" data-module-trackunsubscribe="" data-align-center="">
        
<bsp-list-loadmore data-module="" data-gtm-region="Hub peek - default for articles - (can be moved in article, but don't change source)" data-gtm-topic="No Value" data-hide-dates="true" data-parsely-title="Related Stories" data-parsely-enabled="true" data-is-hub-peek="" data-gtm-modulestyle="List B">
    


    
    <a id="more-section-display-name"></a>





    
    



    <div data-animate="fromBottom" data-gtm-region="Edmunds compares the new BMW X3 and Mercedes-Benz GLC" data-gtm-topic="No Value" data-align-top="" data-mobile-alt-layout="true" data-hide-dates="true" data-posted-date-timestamp="1761733215000" data-updated-date-timestamp="1761733215000" data-list-loadmore-items=""><a aria-label="Edmunds compares the new BMW X3 and Mercedes-Benz GLC" href="https://apnews.com/article/mercedezbenz-bmw-compact-luxury-crossovers-61b6b2180ae6eb2b05154f5c554981d2">
      
   

    <picture data-crop="imgEn-medium-3x2">
    
        <source media="(min-width: 768px)" type="image/webp" width="800" height="533" srcset="https://dims.apnews.com/dims4/default/f1494d3/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3500x2332+0+1/resize/800x533!/format/webp/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fassets.apnews.com%2F0e%2F2f%2F29faf74d6e26c3f2e948e01a626d%2F3ccc4144bec647e9a3d1e2a68ae6ec0c 1x,https://dims.apnews.com/dims4/default/44854d1/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3500x2332+0+1/resize/1600x1066!/format/webp/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fassets.apnews.com%2F0e%2F2f%2F29faf74d6e26c3f2e948e01a626d%2F3ccc4144bec647e9a3d1e2a68ae6ec0c 2x">

    

    
        <source media="(min-width: 768px)" width="800" height="533" srcset="https://dims.apnews.com/dims4/default/df151b0/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3500x2332+0+1/resize/800x533!/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fassets.apnews.com%2F0e%2F2f%2F29faf74d6e26c3f2e948e01a626d%2F3ccc4144bec647e9a3d1e2a68ae6ec0c 1x,https://dims.apnews.com/dims4/default/8125272/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3500x2332+0+1/resize/1600x1066!/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fassets.apnews.com%2F0e%2F2f%2F29faf74d6e26c3f2e948e01a626d%2F3ccc4144bec647e9a3d1e2a68ae6ec0c 2x">

    

    
        <source media="(min-width: 600px)" type="image/webp" width="767" height="511" srcset="https://dims.apnews.com/dims4/default/11fe2b8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3500x2332+0+1/resize/767x511!/format/webp/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fassets.apnews.com%2F0e%2F2f%2F29faf74d6e26c3f2e948e01a626d%2F3ccc4144bec647e9a3d1e2a68ae6ec0c 1x,https://dims.apnews.com/dims4/default/b508041/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3500x2332+0+1/resize/1534x1022!/format/webp/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fassets.apnews.com%2F0e%2F2f%2F29faf74d6e26c3f2e948e01a626d%2F3ccc4144bec647e9a3d1e2a68ae6ec0c 2x">

    

    
        <source media="(min-width: 600px)" width="767" height="511" srcset="https://dims.apnews.com/dims4/default/1efe9ee/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3500x2332+0+1/resize/767x511!/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fassets.apnews.com%2F0e%2F2f%2F29faf74d6e26c3f2e948e01a626d%2F3ccc4144bec647e9a3d1e2a68ae6ec0c 1x,https://dims.apnews.com/dims4/default/3755918/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3500x2332+0+1/resize/1534x1022!/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fassets.apnews.com%2F0e%2F2f%2F29faf74d6e26c3f2e948e01a626d%2F3ccc4144bec647e9a3d1e2a68ae6ec0c 2x">

    

    
        <source type="image/webp" width="599" height="399" srcset="https://dims.apnews.com/dims4/default/d98924b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3500x2331+0+1/resize/599x399!/format/webp/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fassets.apnews.com%2F0e%2F2f%2F29faf74d6e26c3f2e948e01a626d%2F3ccc4144bec647e9a3d1e2a68ae6ec0c 1x,https://dims.apnews.com/dims4/default/c7216c5/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3500x2331+0+1/resize/1198x798!/format/webp/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fassets.apnews.com%2F0e%2F2f%2F29faf74d6e26c3f2e948e01a626d%2F3ccc4144bec647e9a3d1e2a68ae6ec0c 2x">

    

    
        <source width="599" height="399" srcset="https://dims.apnews.com/dims4/default/9b2a0a4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3500x2331+0+1/resize/599x399!/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fassets.apnews.com%2F0e%2F2f%2F29faf74d6e26c3f2e948e01a626d%2F3ccc4144bec647e9a3d1e2a68ae6ec0c 1x,https://dims.apnews.com/dims4/default/0398eee/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3500x2331+0+1/resize/1198x798!/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fassets.apnews.com%2F0e%2F2f%2F29faf74d6e26c3f2e948e01a626d%2F3ccc4144bec647e9a3d1e2a68ae6ec0c 2x">

    
<img alt="This photo provided by BMW shows the 2025 BMW X3. It offers sporty driving dynamics, advanced tech, and ample space for passengers and cargo. (Courtesy of BMW of North America via AP)" srcset="https://dims.apnews.com/dims4/default/9b2a0a4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3500x2331+0+1/resize/599x399!/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fassets.apnews.com%2F0e%2F2f%2F29faf74d6e26c3f2e948e01a626d%2F3ccc4144bec647e9a3d1e2a68ae6ec0c 1x,https://dims.apnews.com/dims4/default/0398eee/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3500x2331+0+1/resize/1198x798!/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fassets.apnews.com%2F0e%2F2f%2F29faf74d6e26c3f2e948e01a626d%2F3ccc4144bec647e9a3d1e2a68ae6ec0c 2x" width="599" height="399" src="https://dims.apnews.com/dims4/default/9b2a0a4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3500x2331+0+1/resize/599x399!/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fassets.apnews.com%2F0e%2F2f%2F29faf74d6e26c3f2e948e01a626d%2F3ccc4144bec647e9a3d1e2a68ae6ec0c" loading="lazy">
</picture>

</a></div>
    

</bsp-list-loadmore>



    </div>

<p>Vehicle telematics systems started to become commonplace about a <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/carmakers-unite-around-privacy-protections-8b512b438b3b41be98bf5d9bfecfc249">decade ago</a></span>, and the practice of automotive data collection took off about five years ago. </p>
    
    
    
<p>The problem is not just that data is being collected but who it’s provided to, including insurers, marketing companies and shadowy data brokers. The issue surfaced earlier this year when <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/ftc-gm-driving-data-insurers-a555abb56a0d5f31afa9b73c3eb48287">General Motors</a></span> was banned for five years from disclosing data collected from drivers to consumer reporting agencies. </p><p>The Federal Trade Commission accused GM of not getting consent before sharing the data, which included every instance when a driver was speeding or driving late at night. It was ultimately provided to insurance companies that used it to set their rates. </p>
    
<h2>Be aware</h2><p>The first thing drivers should do is be aware of what data their car is collecting, said Andrea Amico, founder of Privacy4Cars, an automotive privacy company. </p><p>In an ideal world, drivers would read through the instruction manuals and documentation that comes with their cars, and quiz the dealership about what’s being collected. </p><p>But it’s not always practical to do this, and manufacturers don’t always make it easy to find out, while dealership staff aren’t always the best informed, Amico said. </p><p>Privacy4Cars offers a free auto privacy labeling service at <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://vehicleprivacyreport.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">vehicleprivacyreport.com</a></span> that can summarize what your car could be tracking. </p><p>Owners can punch in their car’s Vehicle Identification Number, which then pulls up the automaker’s data privacy practices, such as whether the car collects location data and whether it’s given to insurers, data brokers or law enforcement. </p>
    
<h2>Tweak your settings </h2><p>Data collection and tracking start as soon as you drive a new car off the dealership lot, with drivers unwittingly consenting when they’re confronted with warning menus on dashboard touch screens.</p><p>Experts say that some of the data collection is baked into the system, you can revoke your consent by going back into the menus. </p><p>“There are permissions in your settings that you can make choices about,” said Lauren Hendry Parsons of Mozilla. “Go through on a granular level and look at those settings where you can.” </p><p>For example, Toyota says on its website that drivers can <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://www.toyota.com/privacyvts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">decline</a></span> what it calls “Master Data Consent” through the Toyota app. Ford says owners can opt to stop sharing vehicle data with the company by going through the dashboard <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://www.ford.com/support/how-tos/sync/sync-4a/how-do-i-turn-off-data-sharing-in-my-vehicle/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">settings</a></span> menu or on the <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://www.ford.co.uk/support/how-tos/fordpass/manage-my-fordpass-account/how-do-i-manage-my-fordpass-data-sharing" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FordPass</a></span> app. </p><p>BMW says <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://www.bmwgroup.com/en/innovation/connected-car/data-ecosystem.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">privacy settings</a></span> can be adjusted through the infotainment system, “on a spectrum between” allowing all services including analysis data and none at all. </p><h2>You can opt out</h2><h2> ...</h2><p>Drivers in the U.S. can ask carmakers to restrict what they do with their data. </p><p>Under state privacy laws, some carmakers allow owners across the United States to submit requests to limit the use of their personal data, opt out of sharing it, or delete it, Consumer Reports says. Other auto companies limit the requests to people in states with applicable privacy laws, the publication says. </p>
    
<p>You can file a request either through an online form or the carmaker’s mobile app. </p><p>You can also go through Privacy4Cars, which provides a free online service that streamlines the process. It can either point car owners to their automaker’s request portal or file a submission on behalf of owners in the U.S., Canada, the European Union, Britain and Australia. </p>
    
<h2>... but there will be trade-offs</h2><p>Experts warn that there’s usually a trade-off if you decide to switch off data collection. </p><p>Most people, for example, have switched to satellite navigation systems over paper maps because it’s “worth the convenience of being able to get from point A to point B really easily,” said Hendry Parsons. </p><p>Turning off location tracking could also halt features like roadside assistance or disable smartphone app features like remote door locking, Consumer Reports says. </p><p>BMW advises that if an owner opts to have no data shared at all, “their vehicle will behave like a smartphone in flight mode and will not transmit any data to the BMW back end.”</p><h2>When selling your car</h2><p>When the time comes to sell your car or trade it in for a newer model, it’s no longer as simple as handing over the keys and signing over some paperwork. </p><p>If you’ve got a newer car, experts say you should always do a factory reset to wipe all the data, which will also include removing any smartphone connections. </p><p>And don’t forget to notify the manufacturer about the change of ownership. </p><p>Amico said that’s important because if you trade in your vehicle, you don’t want insurers to associate it with your profile if the dealer is letting customers take it for test drives.</p><p>“Now your record may be affected by somebody else’s driving — a complete stranger that you have no relationship with.” </p><p>____ </p><p>Is there a tech topic that you think needs explaining? Write to us at <a href="https://apnews.com/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" data-cfemail="4d22232839282e2539243d0d2c3d63223f2a">[email&nbsp;protected]</a> with your suggestions for future editions of One Tech Tip.</p><p>___ </p><p>This story has been corrected to show that the Mozilla representative’s first name is Lauren, not Laura. </p>
                                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Undermining of the CDC (107 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2025/12/08/the-undermining-of-the-cdc</link>
            <guid>46097102</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 14:52:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2025/12/08/the-undermining-of-the-cdc">https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2025/12/08/the-undermining-of-the-cdc</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46097102">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-testid="ArticlePageChunks"><div data-journey-hook="grid-wrapper" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>Two weeks ago, by inserting what must be the most notorious asterisk in modern public health, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention caveated its long-standing position that vaccines do not cause autism. Under the direction of Robert F. Kennedy, Jr., the Secretary of Health and Human Services, a C.D.C. web page now contends that this is “not an evidence-based claim” and that research linking vaccines to autism has been “ignored by health authorities.” The fact that the original statement remains at all is due to an agreement with Senator Bill Cassidy, a physician and the chair of the Senate health committee, who disregarded decades of Kennedy’s vaccine skepticism to advance his confirmation after extracting a set of flimsy commitments that Kennedy is now betraying. The Autism Science Foundation said that it is “appalled” by the C.D.C.’s new stance; the American Medical Association warned of “dangerous consequences.”</p><p>The Department of Health and Human Services maintains that it is hewing to “gold standard, evidence-based science”—a piece of doublespeak so thick that it might unsettle Orwell. Discounting dozens of rigorous studies that have analyzed millions of patients and failed to connect vaccines to autism, the C.D.C. website claims that about half of parents of children with autism believe vaccines contributed to that autism. It cited a decades-old paper that surveyed a few dozen parents who strongly embraced alternative medicine, at two private practices in the Northeast. The web page points out that autism rates have risen in recent decades and so has the number of infant vaccinations—an observation that might also be made about prestige TV shows and pumpkin-spice lattes. The H.H.S. will now provide “appropriate funding” for studies on vaccines and autism, and last week it appointed a physician with a history of vaccine skepticism as the second-in-command at the C.D.C. The episode puts to rest any doubts about whether Americans can still trust information from the nation’s top health agency.</p><p>At stake is a question of the quality of information that should be taken seriously in public discourse and how that information should be communicated. Science may be the most powerful engine for grasping reality, but it suffers a rhetorical disadvantage. In science, the burden of proof falls on the one aiming to overturn the “null hypothesis”—the default position that one thing doesn’t cause another. But conspiratorial thinking is fuelled by the inverse: self-assured conjecture that demands a level of refutation no amount of evidence can offer. Proving the absence of a connection will always be harder than speculating about its existence. The language of science is measured and provisional; the language of politics is declarative and bombastic. In September, President Donald Trump told pregnant women to “fight like hell” not to take Tylenol, because of a potentially increased risk of autism in children; his Food and Drug Administration clarified that “a causal relationship has not been established and there are contrary studies in the scientific literature.” Tylenol, the agency wrote, remains “the safest over-the-counter” option for treating fever or pain.</p><p>The privilege that American scientists have taken for granted—one that is now being trampled—is the ability to go about their work free of political interference. With few exceptions, both Republicans and Democrats have supported independent science, understanding that the nation benefits from research that promotes health, innovation, and economic growth. But since Trump returned to office his Administration has fired or muzzled government scientists with disfavored views on nutrition and climate change; cancelled funding for long-running surveys on food insecurity and global health; dismissed independent committees focussed on air pollution, health-care disparities, and hospital infections; and pulled support for research into vaccines. This month, leading members of the National Institutes of Health, who ascended to their roles in large part based on their criticism of <em>COVID</em>-era mandates, published an article arguing that we should plan for the next pandemic not by trying to identify dangerous pathogens or by developing vaccines and medications to mitigate their damage but by encouraging people to be healthier: by abstaining from smoking, by eating nutritious food, and by “getting up and walking more.”</p><p>“The best pandemic preparedness playbook,” the authors wrote, unironically, “is making America healthy again.” Leaving aside that mRNA vaccines saved millions of lives during the <em>covid</em> pandemic, and that a society might like to prepare both by promoting healthy habits and by investing in biotechnology, this ignores the fact that, in some outbreaks, young and healthy people have had among the highest rates of death, and that with any infectious disease many people will remain vulnerable no matter what they do. (This year, a variant of the H3N2 influenza virus, known as subclade K, has caused a surge in cases in the United Kingdom, Canada, and Japan, and appears to be most perilous for children and older adults.) The unpredictability of pathogens is precisely why a broad-based strategy is needed. Pushups won’t save you from Ebola.</p></div><div data-journey-hook="grid-wrapper" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>In the nineteen-thirties, a Soviet biologist named Trofim Lysenko gained the patronage of Joseph Stalin. Lysenko, who was tapped to guide the country’s agricultural reforms, had a range of pseudoscientific ideas, including that the environment, not genes, primarily determined an organism’s traits and that members of the same species don’t compete. He oversaw a series of biologically wrongheaded programs that contributed to famine, misery, and death for millions of people. (A British botanist once said that talking to Lysenko “was like trying to explain differential calculus to a man who didn’t know his twelve times table.”) With Stalin’s backing, Lysenko purged scientists who disagreed with him and set the country’s once preëminent genetics research back by decades.</p><p>A reason that the U.S. became the world’s biomedical leader—indeed, a reason that it emerged from the Cold War victorious—is that democratic governance allows for a level of self-correction that authoritarianism does not. Bad ideas can be beaten back at the ballot box, in the public square, and through the halls of Congress. The country is under no obligation to tolerate institutionalized quackery or elected officials who, through feckless appeals and half measures, have become complicit in it. Truly making America healthy will involve more than removing an asterisk. It will require turning the page.&nbsp;♦</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Migrating Dillo from GitHub (319 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://dillo-browser.org/news/migration-from-github/</link>
            <guid>46096800</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 14:11:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://dillo-browser.org/news/migration-from-github/">https://dillo-browser.org/news/migration-from-github/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46096800">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<i>Written on 2025-11-30 by Rodrigo Arias Mallo</i>
<p>I would like to migrate the Dillo project away from
<a href="https://github.com/dillo-browser/">GitHub</a>
into a new home which is more friendly to be used with Dillo and solves some of
its problems. This page summarizes the current situation with GitHub and why I
decided to move away from it into a self-hosted server with multiple mirrors in
other forges.
</p>
<h2>Background</h2>
<p>Before we dive into the details, I would like to briefly mention what
happened with the old site. The original Dillo website was at dillo.org,
which also had the source code of Dillo in a mercurial repository at
hg.dillo.org. But it also included the mail server used to reach the developers,
a bug tracker and archives for the mailing list. However, in 2022
<a href="https://dillo-browser.org/dillo.org.html">the domain was lost</a> and someone else decided to
buy it to put a similar site but plaged with AI generated ads. The original
developers are no longer active, but luckily I had a copy of the mercurial
repository and with some help I was able to recover a lot of material from the
original server (some parts are still missing to this day).
</p><p>
I want to avoid this situation as much as possible, so we cannot rely on a
single site that can go down and the whole project become lost. Initially, I
uploaded the Dillo source and website to git repositories on GitHub, but I no
longer think this is a good idea.
</p><h2>The situation with GitHub</h2>
<p>GitHub has been useful to store all repositories of the Dillo project, as
well as to run the CI workflows for platforms in which I don't have a machine
available (like Windows, Mac OS or some BSDs).

</p><p>However, it has several problems that make it less suitable to develop Dillo
anymore. The most annoying problem is that the frontend barely works without
JavaScript, so we cannot open issues, pull requests, source code or CI logs in
Dillo itself, despite them being mostly plain HTML, which I don't think is
acceptable. In the past, it used to gracefully degrade without enforcing
JavaScript, but now it doesn't. Additionally, the page is very resource hungry,
which I don't think is needed to render mostly static text.

</p><p>Another big problem is that it is a single point of failure. I don't mean
that GitHub is stored in a single machine, but it is controlled by a single
entity which can unilateraly ban our repository or account and we would lose the
ability to notify in that URL what happened. This can cause data loss if we
don't have a local copy of all the data.

</p><p>On the usability side, the platform has become more and more slow over
time, which is affecting the development process. It also requires you to have
a fast Internet connection at all times, which is not the case for me
sometimes. Additionally, GitHub seems to encourage a "push model" in which you
are notified when a new event occurs in your project(s), but I don't want to
work with that model. Instead, I prefer it to work as a "pull model", so I only
get updates when I specifically look for them. This model would also allow me to
easily work offline. Unfortunately, I see that the same push model has been
copied to alternative forges.

</p><p>On the social side, I feel that it doesn't have the right tools to moderate
users, specially for projects where the ratio of non-technical users to
developers is high. This is specially problematic when active issues with
developer notes begin to be filled with comments from users that have never
contributed to the project and usually do more harm than good. This situation
ends up causing burnout in developers.

</p><p>Lastly, GitHub seem to follow the current trend of over-focusing on LLMs and
generative AI, which are destroying the open web (or what remains of it) among
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generative_artificial_intelligence#Concerns">other
problems</a>. It has a direct impact on us because sites protect themseves with
a JavaScript wall (or worse, browser fingerprinting) to prevent aggresive LLM
crawler bots from overloading the site, but they also leave Dillo users out. So
I would prefer not to encourage this trend. Despite my intentions, moving Dillo
away won't change much their capability to train their model with our code, but
at least I won't be actively helping.

</p><h2>Self-hosting Dillo</h2>
<p>After researching the available options, it seems that none of the current
forges would allow us to have a redundant system that can prevent the forge from
becoming a single point of failure and solve the rest of the problems with
GitHub. Therefore, I decided to self-host Dillo myself, move all important data
to git repositories and keep them synchronized in multiple git mirrors.

</p><p>I decided to buy the dillo-browser.org domain name and setup a very small
VPS. Initially, I was very skeptical that it would be able to survive on
today's web, but it seems to be doing an acceptable job at handling it (mostly
AI bot traffic masquerading as users). The Dillo website is available here:
</p><p>
<a href="https://dillo-browser.org/">https://dillo-browser.org/</a>

</p><p>I researched which git frontends may suit our needs, and I discovered that
most options are very complicated to self-host and require a lot of server
resources and JavaScript on the frontend. I ended up testing cgit, which is
written in C and it seems to be very lightweight both on RAM and CPU usage.
Furthermore, the web frontend doesn't require JS, so I can use it from Dillo (I
modified cgit CSS slightly to work well on Dillo). It is available on this URL:
</p><p>
<a href="https://git.dillo-browser.org/">https://git.dillo-browser.org/</a>

</p><p>Regarding the bug tracker, I also took a look at the available options. They
are all too complicated for what I would like to have and they seem to
centralize the data into a database that can get lost. This is precisely the
case that happened with the old dillo bug tracker and we are still unable to
recover the original bug entries.

</p><p>To avoid this problem, I created my own bug tracker software,
<a href="https://git.dillo-browser.org/buggy/">buggy</a>, which
is a very simple C tool that parses plain Markdown files and creates a
single HTML page for each bug. All bugs are stored in a
<a href="https://git.dillo-browser.org/bugtracker/">git repository</a>
and a git hook regenerates the bug pages and the index on each new commit. As it
is simply plain text, I can edit the bugs locally and only push them to the
remote when I have Internet back, so it works nice offline. Also, as the output
is just an static HTML site, I don't need to worry about having any
vulnerabilities in my code, as it will only run at build time. You can see it
live here, with the exported issues from GitHub:
</p><p>
<a href="https://bug.dillo-browser.org/">https://bug.dillo-browser.org/</a>

</p><p>The mailing list archives are stored by three independent external services,
but I might include a copy with our own archives in the future.

</p><h2>Setting up mirrors</h2>
<p>As all the important data is now stored in git repositories, we can mirror
them in any forge, without having to rely on their custom storage format for the
issues or other data. If a forge goes down (or goes rogue) we can simply switch
to another site with low switching cost. To this end, I have created git mirrors
in Codeberg and Sourcehut that are synced with our git server:
</p><ul>
  <li><strong>Codeberg</strong>:
    <a href="https://codeberg.org/dillo/">https://codeberg.org/dillo/</a>
  </li><li><strong>Sourcehut</strong>:
    <a href="https://git.sr.ht/~dillo/">https://git.sr.ht/~dillo/</a>
</li></ul>
<p>
However, we still have a single point of failure: the DNS entry of the
dillo-browser.org domain. If we lose the DNS entry (like with dillo.org) it
would cause a problem as all services will be unreachable. We could recover from
such situation by relying on alternative ways to reach users, by the mailing
list, fediverse or IRC, as well as updating the mirrors to reflect the current
situation. It is not ideal, but I don't think it would cause a catastrophic data
loss (like it happened before) as all the data is now stored in git and
replicated across independent locations.

</p><h2>OpenPGP signature</h2>
<p>In order for this page to have some authority, the HTML file is signed with
my <a href="https://dillo-browser.org/news/migration-from-github/rodarima.asc">GPG key</a>
(32E65EC501A1B6FDF8190D293EE6BA977EB2A253), which is the
same that I use to sign the <a href="https://dillo-browser.org/release">last releases</a> of Dillo and is
also listed in <a href="https://github.com/rodarima.gpg">my GitHub user</a>. The
signature <a href="https://dillo-browser.org/news/migration-from-github/index.html.asc">is available here</a> and is linked to the
page with the <code>&lt;link&gt;</code> tag using the <code>rel=signature</code>
relation. You can find more information and how to verify the signature in the
<a href="https://dillo-browser.org/rfc/006-signatures-html/">Dillo RFC-006</a>.

</p><p>Using OpenPGP signatures is robust against losing the DNS entry, as the
authority is not given by the TLS certificate chain but by the trust in the
OpenPGP signature, so we could move the site elsewhere and still claim that is
owned by us. Additionally, as we can store the signatures inside all git
mirrors, they are also resilient against data loss.

</p><h2>Closing remarks</h2>

<p>Keep in mind that the migration process requires several moving parts and it
will take a while for it to stabilize (switching costs). <strong>The GitHub
  repositories won't be removed at any point in time and they will continue to
  be updated until we finish the migration</strong>. When the migration process
is completed, I will mark the Dillo repositories as archived and properly
comunicate it in our site. It is important that we don't remove any commit or
tarball release to avoid breaking downstream builds that still rely on the
GitHub URL.

</p><p>Lastly, I'm glad that we can have our own fully independent and
self-hosted site with relatively low expenses and very little energy cost (which
is good for the environment, but probably not even noticeable at large scale).
With the current DNS and server costs and our current donations I consider that
it is likely that we can continue covering the expenses for at least the next 3
years in the worst case scenario. If you are interested in keeping us afloat,
you can <a href="https://liberapay.com/dillo/">help via Liberapay</a>.
</p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Don't throw away your old PC–it makes a better NAS than anything you can buy (120 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.howtogeek.com/turned-old-windows-pc-into-inexpensive-nas/</link>
            <guid>46096781</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 14:09:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.howtogeek.com/turned-old-windows-pc-into-inexpensive-nas/">https://www.howtogeek.com/turned-old-windows-pc-into-inexpensive-nas/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46096781">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

                            <div data-nosnippet="">
                                            <p><a href="https://www.howtogeek.com/author/nicklewis/">
                                    <img src="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress%2Fwp-content%2Fauthors%2F64ca808a79651-IMG-20230316-WA0002.jpg?fit=crop&amp;w=90&amp;h=90" alt="4" loading="lazy" decoding="async">
                                </a>
                                                    </p>
                                    </div>
                        
                                            
                                
                                    <div data-nosnippet=""><p>Nick Lewis is an editor at How-To Geek. He has been using computers for 20 years --- tinkering with everything from the UI to the Windows registry to device firmware. Before How-To Geek, he used Python and C++ as a freelance programmer. In college, Nick made extensive use of Fortran while pursuing a physics degree.</p><p>

Nick's love of tinkering with computers extends beyond work. He has been running video game servers from home for more than 10 years using Windows, Ubuntu, or Raspberry Pi OS. He also uses Proxmox to self-host a variety of services, including a Jellyfin Media Server, an Airsonic music server, a handful of game servers, NextCloud, and two Windows virtual machines.</p><p>

He enjoys DIY projects, especially if they involve technology. He regularly repairs and repurposes old computers and hardware for whatever new project is at hand. He has designed crossovers for homemade speakers all the way from the basic design to the PCB.</p><p>

&nbsp;Nick enjoys the outdoors. When he isn't working on a computer or DIY project, he is most likely to be found camping, backpacking, or canoeing. </p></div>
                                    </div><div id="article-body" itemprop="articleBody"><p>A network attached storage device (NAS) is one of the most useful things you can add to your home network, but a specialized NAS can run you hundreds of dollars just for the shell, and that is before you even buy additional hard drives for storage. If you want a large, robust NAS, you'll be on the hook for even more.</p>    <!-- No AdsNinja v10 Client! --><!-- No AdsNinja v10 Client! --><p>That is why I built my own NAS for a fraction of the cost using components from an old PC and some used pieces I bought on the internet for half off.</p>    <!-- No AdsNinja v10 Client! --><h2 id="fixing-up-an-old-pc-to-use-as-a-nas">
                        Fixing up an old PC to use as a NAS
               </h2><p>Despite how much off-the-shelf NAS units cost, you don't actually need particularly powerful hardware to do almost anything you might want. Any computer made in the last ten years will do the job. An old Dell Optiplex is a popular starting device because you can often get them for next to nothing or free. I repurposed an old gaming PC with a Ryzen 1600x, 24GB of RAM, and an old GTX 1060 for my NAS since I had most of the parts already.</p>    <p>If you already have a PC on hand, then just stick with that for your NAS. If you're on the used market, I'd recommend trying to pick up something with an Intel processor rather than AMD. Intel processors have a technology called QuickSync, which enables them to very <a href="https://www.howtogeek.com/750701/why-hardware-transcoding-is-important-on-a-nas/" target="_blank">efficiently transcode video files</a>.</p>    <p>If you're planning on streaming video using your NAS, then QuickSync is definitely a feature you want.</p>    <p>If you have an AMD processor, you can always add an inexpensive GPU to your PC that will handle any kind of video transcoding that you might need to do.</p>    <h3 id="add-an-ssd-for-the-boot-drive">
            Add an SSD for the boot drive
    </h3>
<p>If you pick up a used PC from Facebook Marketplace or elsewhere, it may not come with a hard drive—a lot of people remove them before selling or getting rid of a PC to ensure their data is secure.</p>    <p>In general, you want to get the fastest boot drive you can. If you search for the motherboard model of the PC you're working with, the manual will specify what kind of NVMe drive you can use, if it supports one at all.</p>    
                
    
    
    
                
    
                
        
                                                            
                                                                                                                        
                                        
    
    

    
    <div data-img-url="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/08/a7308455.jpg" data-modal-id="single-image-modal" data-modal-container-id="single-image-modal-container" data-img-caption="&quot;Patrick Campanale \/ How-To Geek&quot;">
                                                                                            <figure><picture><source media="(max-width: 480px)" data-srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/08/a7308455.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=500&amp;dpr=2" srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/08/a7308455.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=500&amp;dpr=2">
        <source media="(max-width: 767px)" data-srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/08/a7308455.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=800&amp;dpr=2" srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/08/a7308455.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=800&amp;dpr=2">
        <source media="(max-width: 1023px)" data-srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/08/a7308455.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=2" srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/08/a7308455.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=2">
        <img width="1650" height="928" loading="lazy" decoding="async" alt="A straight-on shot of the Crucial T710, Samsung 9100 Pro, and Samsung 990 EVO Plus NVMe SSDs mounted to a motherboard." data-img-url="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/08/a7308455.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=2" src="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/08/a7308455.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=2">
        </picture><small>Credit:&nbsp;Patrick Campanale / How-To Geek</small></figure>
            
        </div>
<p> If it doesn't, that isn't a huge problem. SATA SSDs are still plenty fast enough for a NAS setup. My NAS still uses a SATA SSD because I found one for cheap. I haven't needed to replace it.</p>    
<p>I'd recommend TrueNAS or Unraid as operating systems for your NAS. Both need 8GB of RAM as a starting point. If you want to run virtual machines or containers (like with Docker) on your NAS, I'd aim for 16GB or more. The system I'm using started with 16GB of RAM, but I added another 8GB (2x4GB) for about $10 by buying some used RAM from Facebook marketplace.</p>    
                
    
    
    
                
    
                
        
                                                            
                                                                                                                        
                            
    
    

    
    <div data-img-url="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/52675805605_e050a2b3f7_o.jpg" data-modal-id="single-image-modal" data-modal-container-id="single-image-modal-container" data-img-caption="&quot;Jason Fitzpatrick \/ How-To Geek&quot;">
                                                                                            <figure><picture><source media="(max-width: 480px)" data-srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/52675805605_e050a2b3f7_o.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=500&amp;dpr=2" srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/52675805605_e050a2b3f7_o.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=500&amp;dpr=2">
        <source media="(max-width: 767px)" data-srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/52675805605_e050a2b3f7_o.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=800&amp;dpr=2" srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/52675805605_e050a2b3f7_o.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=800&amp;dpr=2">
        <source media="(max-width: 1023px)" data-srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/52675805605_e050a2b3f7_o.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=2" srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/52675805605_e050a2b3f7_o.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=2">
        <img width="1650" height="928" loading="lazy" decoding="async" alt="An older gaming motherboard with four sticks of RAM. " data-img-url="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/52675805605_e050a2b3f7_o.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=2" src="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/52675805605_e050a2b3f7_o.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=2">
        </picture><small>Credit:&nbsp;Jason Fitzpatrick / How-To Geek</small></figure>
            
        </div>
<p> If you've picked up a PC you don't know much about, you can always search for the motherboard make and model on the internet to find out the type of RAM it takes, or pull out one of the current RAM sticks. There is usually a sticker on the side that tells you the make, type, and speed.</p>    <p>If you do buy used RAM, make sure you're getting at least a 50% discount, and be sure to give the RAM a once-over physically to make sure that there aren't any obvious signs of damage.</p>    <h3 id="buy-hard-drives-cheap">
            Buy hard drives cheap
    </h3>
<p>Keeping with the theme of buying used old computer parts to save, I built my NAS with refurbished drives from <a href="https://serverpartdeals.com/" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" target="_blank">ServerPartDeals</a>, but you can also sometimes find good deals on Amazon.</p>    <p>In general, you can save about 50% off the normal sale price if you <a href="https://www.howtogeek.com/how-to-get-hard-drives-for-cheap/" target="_blank">buy a drive manufacturer recertified or refurbished</a>.</p>    <p>I now have a total of four recertified hard drives running in my system, the oldest of which have been in nearly continuous use in 2019. So far, none of them have shown any signs of problems.</p>    <p>If you aren't comfortable with that, you can always buy them new.</p>    <p>Whatever you buy, I'd weigh the benefits of buying specialized NAS drives instead of regular drives. In theory, they should last longer. Ultimately, I didn't because my NAS sees only light use, but if you plan on putting a lot of miles on your system, it may be worth it.</p>            
    
                    
                        
                
    
                                        
    
        
    
        
                
        
    <div data-include-community-rating="false" id="buying-your-first-nas-be-sure-to-get-the-right-hdds" data-nosnippet="">
        
        
                                                            
                    <picture><source media="(max-width: 480px)" data-srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/03/hgst-12tb-hdd.png?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=140&amp;h=98&amp;dpr=2" srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/03/hgst-12tb-hdd.png?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=140&amp;h=98&amp;dpr=2">
        <img width="440" height="364" loading="lazy" decoding="async" alt="A HGST 12TB Helium recertified hard drive." data-img-url="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/03/hgst-12tb-hdd.png?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=220&amp;h=182&amp;dpr=2" src="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/03/hgst-12tb-hdd.png?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=220&amp;h=182&amp;dpr=2">
        </picture>
                
            
        
                    <p><span data-field="label"><label>Related</label></span></p><div>

                
                
                	
	
<h5>
    					        				
		<a href="https://www.howtogeek.com/buying-your-first-nas-be-sure-to-get-the-right-hdds/" title="Please stop putting desktop hard drives in your NAS" target="_blank">
			Please stop putting desktop hard drives in your NAS
		</a>
	</h5>

                                                    
                									<p>Don't start your NAS journey off on the wrong foot.</p>
			

                    


                
                
                
                

                
                
                
                	


                

                
                
                
            </div>
                
        
        
        
            </div>
<!-- No AdsNinja v10 Client! --><h2 id="choose-the-right-operating-system">
                        Choose the right operating system
               </h2><p>There is nothing that stops you from using any Linux distro, or even Windows, as a NAS operating system. However, most of those options involve manually installing and configuring a ton of things.</p>    <p>Instead, I'd recommend installing <a href="https://www.truenas.com/" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" target="_blank">TrueNAS</a> or <a href="https://unraid.net/" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" target="_blank">Unraid</a> (which is paid), which are Linux distros designed specifically for use in a NAS. They handle most of the tedious (and sometimes complicated) stuff behind the scenes. Since my goal was to keep costs as low as possible, I went with TrueNAS.</p>    <p>I used Rufus to <a href="https://www.howtogeek.com/how-to-make-a-bootable-linux-usb-drive-on-pc-or-mac/" target="_blank">create a bootable TrueNAS USB drive</a>, then inserted it into my NAS PC. You will need a keyboard and display to connect to it, at least temporarily.</p>    
                
    
    
    
                
    
                
        
                                                            
                                                                                                                        
                            
    
    

    
    <div data-img-url="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/trunas-on-rufus.png" data-modal-id="single-image-modal" data-modal-container-id="single-image-modal-container" data-img-caption="&quot;&quot;">
                                                                                            <picture><source media="(max-width: 480px)" data-srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/trunas-on-rufus.png?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=500&amp;dpr=1" srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/trunas-on-rufus.png?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=500&amp;dpr=1">
        <source media="(max-width: 767px)" data-srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/trunas-on-rufus.png?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=800&amp;dpr=1" srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/trunas-on-rufus.png?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=800&amp;dpr=1">
        <source media="(max-width: 1023px)" data-srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/trunas-on-rufus.png?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=1" srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/trunas-on-rufus.png?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=1">
        <img width="825" height="703" loading="lazy" decoding="async" alt="Creating a bootable TrueNAS USB drive using Rufus. " data-img-url="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/trunas-on-rufus.png?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=1" src="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/trunas-on-rufus.png?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=1">
        </picture>
            
        </div>
<p>The installer will walk you through most of the setup—you don't need to do much since the default settings are fine. Just make note of your admin password, you'll need it later.</p>    <p>Once it is installed, you'll be able to access the NAS through the web browser of any device on your network by typing in the IP address, which is always displayed on your TrueNAS server. Alternatively, you could log in to your router to find your NAS's IP address.</p>    
                
    
    
    
                
    
                
        
                                                            
                                                                                                                        
                            
    
    

    
    <div data-img-url="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/the-ip-address-of-the-truenas-server.png" data-modal-id="single-image-modal" data-modal-container-id="single-image-modal-container" data-img-caption="&quot;&quot;">
                                                                                            <picture><source media="(max-width: 480px)" data-srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/the-ip-address-of-the-truenas-server.png?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=500&amp;dpr=2" srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/the-ip-address-of-the-truenas-server.png?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=500&amp;dpr=2">
        <source media="(max-width: 767px)" data-srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/the-ip-address-of-the-truenas-server.png?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=800&amp;dpr=1" srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/the-ip-address-of-the-truenas-server.png?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=800&amp;dpr=1">
        <source media="(max-width: 1023px)" data-srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/the-ip-address-of-the-truenas-server.png?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=1" srcset="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/the-ip-address-of-the-truenas-server.png?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=1">
        <img width="825" height="509" loading="lazy" decoding="async" alt="The IP address of the TrueNAS server." data-img-url="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/the-ip-address-of-the-truenas-server.png?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=1" src="https://static0.howtogeekimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/the-ip-address-of-the-truenas-server.png?q=70&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=825&amp;dpr=1">
        </picture>
            
        </div>
<p>From the web interface, you can manage your storage pools, add and remove containers or virtual machines, add apps, and do most anything else. For the most part, TrueNAS does a good job making everything approachable.</p>    

                            
            
    
<p>I'd recommend starting with creating an SMB share so your NAS is accessible from any Windows device on the network. That is the option I use most frequently myself.</p>    <p>I'd also strongly recommend one of the backup apps (like Duplicati) that comes with TrueNAS, too. Proper backups are essential in the digital era, and a cobbled-together NAS can be one part of a robust backup solution for your PC.</p>    <hr><p>When you first create your NAS, make sure you figure out how to create a backup of your data <em>before </em>you upload everything to it and cancel your Google Photos subscription. Remember, a NAS is only part of <a href="https://www.howtogeek.com/the-biggest-backup-mistake-everybody-makes-and-how-to-avoid-it/" target="_blank">a comprehensive backup plan</a>, and it won't do you any good if you don't take the proper steps to ensure the data on your NAS is properly backed up, too.</p>    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Windows drive letters are not limited to A-Z (411 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ryanliptak.com/blog/windows-drive-letters-are-not-limited-to-a-z/</link>
            <guid>46096556</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 13:40:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.ryanliptak.com/blog/windows-drive-letters-are-not-limited-to-a-z/">https://www.ryanliptak.com/blog/windows-drive-letters-are-not-limited-to-a-z/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46096556">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<p><time>2025-11-30</time>
 - <a href="https://www.ryanliptak.com/blog/categories/programming">Programming</a>
 - <a href="https://www.ryanliptak.com/blog/categories/windows">Windows</a></p><p>On its own, the title of this post is just a true piece of trivia, verifiable with <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows-server/administration/windows-commands/subst">the built-in <code>subst</code> tool</a> (among other methods).</p>
<p>Here's an example creating the drive <code>+:\</code> as an alias for a directory at <code>C:\foo</code>:</p>
<pre><code>subst +: C:\foo
</code></pre>
<p>The <code>+:\</code> drive then works as normal (at least in cmd.exe, this will be discussed more later):</p>
<pre><code>&gt; cd /D +:\

+:\&gt; tree .
Folder PATH listing
Volume serial number is 00000001 12AB:23BC
+:\
└───bar
</code></pre>
<p>However, understanding <em>why</em> it's true elucidates a lot about how Windows works under the hood, and turns up a few curious behaviors.</p>
<h2>What is a drive letter, anyway?<a id="what-is-a-drive-letter-anyway" href="#what-is-a-drive-letter-anyway">🔗</a></h2>
<p>The paths that most people are familiar with are <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/win32/fileio/naming-a-file#namespaces">Win32 namespace paths</a>, e.g. something like <code>C:\foo</code> which is a drive-absolute Win32 path. However, the high-level APIs that take Win32 paths like <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/win32/api/fileapi/nf-fileapi-createfilew"><code>CreateFileW</code></a> ultimately will convert a path like <code>C:\foo</code> into a NT namespace path before calling into a lower level API within <code>ntdll.dll</code> like <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/win32/api/winternl/nf-winternl-ntcreatefile"><code>NtCreateFile</code></a>.</p>
<p>This can be confirmed with <a href="https://github.com/rogerorr/NtTrace">NtTrace</a>, where a call to <code>CreateFileW</code> with <code>C:\foo</code> ultimately leads to a call of <code>NtCreateFile</code> with <code>\??\C:\foo</code>:</p>
<pre><code>NtCreateFile( FileHandle=0x40c07ff640 [0xb8], DesiredAccess=SYNCHRONIZE|GENERIC_READ|0x80, ObjectAttributes="\??\C:\foo", IoStatusBlock=0x40c07ff648 [0/1], AllocationSize=null, FileAttributes=0, ShareAccess=7, CreateDisposition=1, CreateOptions=0x4000, EaBuffer=null, EaLength=0 ) =&gt; 0
NtClose( Handle=0xb8 ) =&gt; 0
</code></pre>

<details>
<summary>Test code, reproduction info</summary>
<p><code>createfilew.zig</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>const</span><span> </span><span>std</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>@import</span><span>(</span><span>"std"</span><span>);</span><span>
</span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>std</span><span>.</span><span>os</span><span>.</span><span>windows</span><span>;</span><span>
</span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>L</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>std</span><span>.</span><span>unicode</span><span>.</span><span>wtf8ToWtf16LeStringLiteral</span><span>;</span><span>

</span><span>pub</span><span> </span><span>extern</span><span> </span><span>"kernel32"</span><span> </span><span>fn</span><span> </span><span>CreateFileW</span><span>(</span><span>
    </span><span>lpFileName</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>LPCWSTR</span><span>,</span><span>
    </span><span>dwDesiredAccess</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>DWORD</span><span>,</span><span>
    </span><span>dwShareMode</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>DWORD</span><span>,</span><span>
    </span><span>lpSecurityAttributes</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>?*</span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>SECURITY_ATTRIBUTES</span><span>,</span><span>
    </span><span>dwCreationDisposition</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>DWORD</span><span>,</span><span>
    </span><span>dwFlagsAndAttributes</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>DWORD</span><span>,</span><span>
    </span><span>hTemplateFile</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>?</span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>HANDLE</span><span>,</span><span>
</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>callconv</span><span>(.</span><span>winapi</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>HANDLE</span><span>;</span><span>

</span><span>pub</span><span> </span><span>fn</span><span> </span><span>main</span><span>()</span><span> </span><span>!</span><span>void</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>
    </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>path</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>L</span><span>(</span><span>"C:\\foo"</span><span>);</span><span>
    </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>dir_handle</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>CreateFileW</span><span>(</span><span>
        </span><span>path</span><span>,</span><span>
        </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>GENERIC_READ</span><span>,</span><span>
        </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>FILE_SHARE_DELETE</span><span> </span><span>|</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>FILE_SHARE_READ</span><span> </span><span>|</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>FILE_SHARE_WRITE</span><span>,</span><span>
        </span><span>null</span><span>,</span><span>
        </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>OPEN_EXISTING</span><span>,</span><span>
        </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>FILE_FLAG_BACKUP_SEMANTICS</span><span> </span><span>|</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>FILE_FLAG_OVERLAPPED</span><span>,</span><span>
        </span><span>null</span><span>,</span><span>
    </span><span>);</span><span>
    </span><span>if</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>dir_handle</span><span> </span><span>==</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>INVALID_HANDLE_VALUE</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>return</span><span> </span><span>error</span><span>.</span><span>FailedToOpenDir</span><span>;</span><span>
    </span><span>defer</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>CloseHandle</span><span>(</span><span>dir_handle</span><span>);</span><span>
</span><span>}</span><span>
</span></code></pre>
<p>Built with:</p>
<pre><code>zig build-exe createfilew.zig
</code></pre>
<p>To run with NtTrace:</p>
<pre><code>nttrace createfilew.exe &gt; createfilew.log
</code></pre>
</details>
<p>That <code>\??\C:\foo</code> is a <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/win32/fileio/naming-a-file#nt-namespaces">NT namespace path</a>, which is what <code>NtCreateFile</code> expects. To understand this path, though, we need to talk about the Object Manager, which is responsible for handling NT paths.</p>
<h3>The Object Manager<a id="the-object-manager" href="#the-object-manager">🔗</a></h3>

<p>The Object Manager is responsible for keeping track of named objects, which we can explore using <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/sysinternals/downloads/winobj">the WinObj tool</a>. The <code>\??</code> part of the <code>\??\C:\foo</code> path is actually a special virtual folder within the Object Manager that combines the <code>\GLOBAL??</code> folder and a per-user <code>DosDevices</code> folder together.</p>
<p>For me, the object <code>C:</code> is within <code>\GLOBAL??</code>, and is actually a symbolic link to <code>\Device\HarddiskVolume4</code>:</p>
<p><img src="https://www.ryanliptak.com/images/windows-drive-letters-are-not-limited-to-a-z/cdrive.png">
</p>
<p>So, <code>\??\C:\foo</code> ultimately resolves to <code>\Device\HarddiskVolume4\foo</code>, and then it's up to the actual device to deal with the <code>foo</code> part of the path.</p>
<p>The important thing here, though, is that <code>\??\C:\foo</code> is just <em>one way</em> of referring to the device path <code>\Device\HarddiskVolume4\foo</code>. For example, volumes will also get a named object created using their GUID with the format <code>Volume{18123456-abcd-efab-cdef-1234abcdabcd}</code> that is also a symlink to something like <code>\Device\HarddiskVolume4</code>, so a path like <code>\??\Volume{18123456-abcd-efab-cdef-1234abcdabcd}\foo</code> is effectively equivalent to <code>\??\C:\foo</code>.</p>

<p>All this is to say that there's nothing innately special about the named object <code>C:</code>; the Object Manager treats it just like any other symbolic link and resolves it accordingly.</p>
<h3>So, what <em>is</em> a drive letter, really?<a id="so-what-is-a-drive-letter-really" href="#so-what-is-a-drive-letter-really">🔗</a></h3>
<p>How I see it, drive letters are essentially just a convention borne out of the conversion of a Win32 path into a NT path. In particular, that would be down to the implementation of <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/win32/devnotes/rtldospathnametontpathname_u_withstatus"><code>RtlDosPathNameToNtPathName_U</code></a>.</p>
<p>In other words, since <code>RtlDosPathNameToNtPathName_U</code> converts <code>C:\foo</code> to <code>\??\C:\foo</code>, then an object named <code>C:</code> will behave like a drive letter. To give an example of what I mean by that: in an alternate universe, <code>RtlDosPathNameToNtPathName_U</code> could convert the path <code>FOO:\bar</code> to <code>\??\FOO:\bar</code> and then <code>FOO:</code> could behave like a drive letter.</p>
<p>So, getting back to the title, how does <code>RtlDosPathNameToNtPathName_U</code> treat something like <code>+:\foo</code>? Well, exactly the same as <code>C:\foo</code>:</p>
<pre><code>&gt; paths.exe C:\foo
path type: .DriveAbsolute
  nt path: \??\C:\foo

&gt; paths.exe +:\foo
path type: .DriveAbsolute
  nt path: \??\+:\foo
</code></pre>
<details>
<summary>Test program code</summary>
<p><code>paths.zig</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>const</span><span> </span><span>std</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>@import</span><span>(</span><span>"std"</span><span>);</span><span>
</span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>std</span><span>.</span><span>os</span><span>.</span><span>windows</span><span>;</span><span>

</span><span>pub</span><span> </span><span>fn</span><span> </span><span>main</span><span>()</span><span> </span><span>!</span><span>void</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>
    </span><span>var</span><span> </span><span>arena_state</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>std</span><span>.</span><span>heap</span><span>.</span><span>ArenaAllocator</span><span>.</span><span>init</span><span>(</span><span>std</span><span>.</span><span>heap</span><span>.</span><span>page_allocator</span><span>);</span><span>
    </span><span>defer</span><span> </span><span>arena_state</span><span>.</span><span>deinit</span><span>();</span><span>
    </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>arena</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>arena_state</span><span>.</span><span>allocator</span><span>();</span><span>

    </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>args</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>try</span><span> </span><span>std</span><span>.</span><span>process</span><span>.</span><span>argsAlloc</span><span>(</span><span>arena</span><span>);</span><span>
    </span><span>if</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>args</span><span>.</span><span>len</span><span> </span><span>&lt;=</span><span> </span><span>1</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>return</span><span> </span><span>error</span><span>.</span><span>ExpectedArg</span><span>;</span><span>

    </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>path</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>try</span><span> </span><span>std</span><span>.</span><span>unicode</span><span>.</span><span>wtf8ToWtf16LeAllocZ</span><span>(</span><span>arena</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>args</span><span>[</span><span>1</span><span>]);</span><span>

    </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>path_type</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>RtlDetermineDosPathNameType_U</span><span>(</span><span>path</span><span>);</span><span>
    </span><span>std</span><span>.</span><span>debug</span><span>.</span><span>print</span><span>(</span><span>"path type: {}\n"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>.{</span><span>path_type</span><span>});</span><span>
    </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>nt_path</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>try</span><span> </span><span>RtlDosPathNameToNtPathName_U</span><span>(</span><span>path</span><span>);</span><span>
    </span><span>std</span><span>.</span><span>debug</span><span>.</span><span>print</span><span>(</span><span>"  nt path: {f}\n"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>.{</span><span>std</span><span>.</span><span>unicode</span><span>.</span><span>fmtUtf16Le</span><span>(</span><span>nt_path</span><span>.</span><span>span</span><span>())});</span><span>
</span><span>}</span><span>

</span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>RTL_PATH_TYPE</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>enum</span><span>(</span><span>c_int</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>
    </span><span>Unknown</span><span>,</span><span>
    </span><span>UncAbsolute</span><span>,</span><span>
    </span><span>DriveAbsolute</span><span>,</span><span>
    </span><span>DriveRelative</span><span>,</span><span>
    </span><span>Rooted</span><span>,</span><span>
    </span><span>Relative</span><span>,</span><span>
    </span><span>LocalDevice</span><span>,</span><span>
    </span><span>RootLocalDevice</span><span>,</span><span>
</span><span>};</span><span>

</span><span>pub</span><span> </span><span>extern</span><span> </span><span>"ntdll"</span><span> </span><span>fn</span><span> </span><span>RtlDetermineDosPathNameType_U</span><span>(</span><span>
    </span><span>Path</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>*:</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>u16</span><span>,</span><span>
</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>callconv</span><span>(.</span><span>winapi</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>RTL_PATH_TYPE</span><span>;</span><span>

</span><span>fn</span><span> </span><span>RtlDosPathNameToNtPathName_U</span><span>(</span><span>path</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>u16</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>!</span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>PathSpace</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>
    </span><span>var</span><span> </span><span>out</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>UNICODE_STRING</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>undefined</span><span>;</span><span>
    </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>rc</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>ntdll</span><span>.</span><span>RtlDosPathNameToNtPathName_U</span><span>(</span><span>path</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>&amp;</span><span>out</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>null</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>null</span><span>);</span><span>
    </span><span>if</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>rc</span><span> </span><span>!=</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>TRUE</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>return</span><span> </span><span>error</span><span>.</span><span>BadPathName</span><span>;</span><span>
    </span><span>defer</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>ntdll</span><span>.</span><span>RtlFreeUnicodeString</span><span>(</span><span>&amp;</span><span>out</span><span>);</span><span>

    </span><span>var</span><span> </span><span>path_space</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>PathSpace</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>undefined</span><span>;</span><span>
    </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>out_path</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>out</span><span>.</span><span>Buffer</span><span>.</span><span>?</span><span>[</span><span>0</span><span> </span><span>..</span><span> </span><span>out</span><span>.</span><span>Length</span><span> </span><span>/</span><span> </span><span>2</span><span>];</span><span>
    </span><span>@memcpy</span><span>(</span><span>path_space</span><span>.</span><span>data</span><span>[</span><span>0</span><span>..</span><span>out_path</span><span>.</span><span>len</span><span>],</span><span> </span><span>out_path</span><span>);</span><span>
    </span><span>path_space</span><span>.</span><span>len</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>out</span><span>.</span><span>Length</span><span> </span><span>/</span><span> </span><span>2</span><span>;</span><span>
    </span><span>path_space</span><span>.</span><span>data</span><span>[</span><span>path_space</span><span>.</span><span>len</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>;</span><span>

    </span><span>return</span><span> </span><span>path_space</span><span>;</span><span>
</span><span>}</span><span>
</span></code></pre>
</details>
<p>Therefore, if an object with the name <code>+:</code> is within the virtual folder <code>\??</code>, we can expect the Win32 path <code>+:\</code> to behave like any other drive-absolute path, which is exactly what we see.</p>

<h2>Some exploration of the implications<a id="some-exploration-of-the-implications" href="#some-exploration-of-the-implications">🔗</a></h2>
<p>This section only focuses on a few things that were relevant to what I was working on. I encourage others to investigate the implications of this further if they feel so inclined.</p>
<h3><code>explorer.exe</code> doesn't play ball<a id="explorer-exe-doesn-t-play-ball" href="#explorer-exe-doesn-t-play-ball">🔗</a></h3>
<p>Drives with a drive-letter other than A-Z do not appear in File Explorer, and cannot be navigated to in File Explorer.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.ryanliptak.com/images/windows-drive-letters-are-not-limited-to-a-z/explorer.png">
<i>Error when attempting to navigate to <code>+:\</code> in File Explorer</i>
</p>
<p>For the "do not appear" part, my guess as to what's happening is that <code>explorer.exe</code> is walking <code>\??</code> and looking specifically for objects named <code>A:</code> through <code>Z:</code>. For the "cannot be navigated to" part, that's a bit more mysterious, but my guess is that <code>explorer.exe</code> has a lot of special logic around handling paths typed into the location bar, and part of that restricts drive letters to <code>A</code>-<code>Z</code> (i.e. it's short-circuiting before it ever tries to actually open the path).</p>
<h3>PowerShell doesn't, either<a id="powershell-doesn-t-either" href="#powershell-doesn-t-either">🔗</a></h3>
<p>PowerShell seems to reject non-<code>A</code>-<code>Z</code> drives as well:</p>
<pre><code>PS C:\&gt; cd +:\
cd : Cannot find drive. A drive with the name '+' does not exist.
At line:1 char:1
+ cd +:\
+ ~~~~~~
    + CategoryInfo          : ObjectNotFound: (+:String) [Set-Location], DriveNotFoundException
    + FullyQualifiedErrorId : DriveNotFound,Microsoft.PowerShell.Commands.SetLocationCommand
</code></pre>
<h3>Non-ASCII drive letters<a id="non-ascii-drive-letters" href="#non-ascii-drive-letters">🔗</a></h3>
<p>Drive letters don't have to be within the ASCII range at all; they can also be non-ASCII characters.</p>
<pre><code>&gt; subst €: C:\foo

&gt; cd /D €:\

€:\&gt; tree .
Folder PATH listing
Volume serial number is 000000DE 12AB:23BC
€:\
└───bar
</code></pre>
<p>Non-ASCII drive letters are even case-insensitive like <code>A</code>-<code>Z</code> are:</p>
<pre><code>&gt; subst Λ: C:\foo

&gt; cd /D λ:\

λ:\&gt; tree .
Folder PATH listing
Volume serial number is 000000DE 12AB:23BC
λ:\
└───bar
</code></pre>
<p>However, drive-letters cannot be <em>arbitrary</em> Unicode graphemes or even arbitrary code points; they are restricted to a single <a href="https://wtf-8.codeberg.page/#motivation">WTF-16</a> code unit (a <code>u16</code>, so &lt;= <code>U+FFFF</code>). The tool that we've been using so far (<code>subst.exe</code>) errors with <code>Invalid parameter</code> if you try to use a drive letter with a code point larger than <code>U+FFFF</code>, but you can get around that by going through the <code>MountPointManager</code> directly:</p>
<p><img src="https://www.ryanliptak.com/images/windows-drive-letters-are-not-limited-to-a-z/u24b62drive.png">
</p>
<details>
<summary>Code used to create the <code>𤭢:</code> symlink</summary>
<pre><code><span>const</span><span> </span><span>std</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>@import</span><span>(</span><span>"std"</span><span>);</span><span>
</span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>std</span><span>.</span><span>os</span><span>.</span><span>windows</span><span>;</span><span>
</span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>L</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>std</span><span>.</span><span>unicode</span><span>.</span><span>wtf8ToWtf16LeStringLiteral</span><span>;</span><span>

</span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>MOUNTMGR_CREATE_POINT_INPUT</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>extern</span><span> </span><span>struct</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>
    </span><span>SymbolicLinkNameOffset</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>USHORT</span><span>,</span><span>
    </span><span>SymbolicLinkNameLength</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>USHORT</span><span>,</span><span>
    </span><span>DeviceNameOffset</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>USHORT</span><span>,</span><span>
    </span><span>DeviceNameLength</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>USHORT</span><span>,</span><span>
</span><span>};</span><span>

</span><span>pub</span><span> </span><span>fn</span><span> </span><span>main</span><span>()</span><span> </span><span>!</span><span>void</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>
    </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>mgmt_handle</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>try</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>OpenFile</span><span>(</span><span>L</span><span>(</span><span>"\\??\\MountPointManager"</span><span>),</span><span> </span><span>.{</span><span>
        </span><span>.</span><span>access_mask</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>SYNCHRONIZE</span><span> </span><span>|</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>GENERIC_READ</span><span> </span><span>|</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>GENERIC_WRITE</span><span>,</span><span>
        </span><span>.</span><span>share_access</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>FILE_SHARE_READ</span><span> </span><span>|</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>FILE_SHARE_WRITE</span><span> </span><span>|</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>FILE_SHARE_DELETE</span><span>,</span><span>
        </span><span>.</span><span>creation</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>FILE_OPEN</span><span>,</span><span>
    </span><span>});</span><span>
    </span><span>defer</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>CloseHandle</span><span>(</span><span>mgmt_handle</span><span>);</span><span>

    </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>volume_name</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>L</span><span>(</span><span>"\\Device\\HarddiskVolume4"</span><span>);</span><span>
    </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>mount_point</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>L</span><span>(</span><span>"\\DosDevices\\𤭢:"</span><span>);</span><span>

    </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>buf_size</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>@sizeOf</span><span>(</span><span>MOUNTMGR_CREATE_POINT_INPUT</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>+</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>MAX_PATH</span><span> </span><span>*</span><span> </span><span>2</span><span> </span><span>+</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>MAX_PATH</span><span> </span><span>*</span><span> </span><span>2</span><span>;</span><span>
    </span><span>var</span><span> </span><span>input_buf</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>buf_size</span><span>]</span><span>u8</span><span> </span><span>align</span><span>(</span><span>@alignOf</span><span>(</span><span>MOUNTMGR_CREATE_POINT_INPUT</span><span>))</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>_</span><span>]</span><span>u8</span><span>{</span><span>0</span><span>}</span><span> </span><span>**</span><span> </span><span>buf_size</span><span>;</span><span>

    </span><span>var</span><span> </span><span>input_struct</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>*</span><span>MOUNTMGR_CREATE_POINT_INPUT</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>@ptrCast</span><span>(</span><span>&amp;</span><span>input_buf</span><span>[</span><span>0</span><span>]);</span><span>
    </span><span>input_struct</span><span>.</span><span>SymbolicLinkNameOffset</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>@sizeOf</span><span>(</span><span>MOUNTMGR_CREATE_POINT_INPUT</span><span>);</span><span>
    </span><span>input_struct</span><span>.</span><span>SymbolicLinkNameLength</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>mount_point</span><span>.</span><span>len</span><span> </span><span>*</span><span> </span><span>2</span><span>;</span><span>
    </span><span>input_struct</span><span>.</span><span>DeviceNameOffset</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>input_struct</span><span>.</span><span>SymbolicLinkNameOffset</span><span> </span><span>+</span><span> </span><span>input_struct</span><span>.</span><span>SymbolicLinkNameLength</span><span>;</span><span>
    </span><span>input_struct</span><span>.</span><span>DeviceNameLength</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>volume_name</span><span>.</span><span>len</span><span> </span><span>*</span><span> </span><span>2</span><span>;</span><span>

    </span><span>@memcpy</span><span>(</span><span>input_buf</span><span>[</span><span>input_struct</span><span>.</span><span>SymbolicLinkNameOffset</span><span>..][</span><span>0</span><span>..</span><span>input_struct</span><span>.</span><span>SymbolicLinkNameLength</span><span>],</span><span> </span><span>@as</span><span>([</span><span>*</span><span>]</span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>u8</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>@ptrCast</span><span>(</span><span>mount_point</span><span>)));</span><span>
    </span><span>@memcpy</span><span>(</span><span>input_buf</span><span>[</span><span>input_struct</span><span>.</span><span>DeviceNameOffset</span><span>..][</span><span>0</span><span>..</span><span>input_struct</span><span>.</span><span>DeviceNameLength</span><span>],</span><span> </span><span>@as</span><span>([</span><span>*</span><span>]</span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>u8</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>@ptrCast</span><span>(</span><span>volume_name</span><span>)));</span><span>

    </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>IOCTL_MOUNTMGR_CREATE_POINT</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>CTL_CODE</span><span>(</span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>MOUNTMGRCONTROLTYPE</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>.</span><span>METHOD_BUFFERED</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>FILE_READ_ACCESS</span><span> </span><span>|</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>FILE_WRITE_ACCESS</span><span>);</span><span>
    </span><span>try</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>DeviceIoControl</span><span>(</span><span>mgmt_handle</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>IOCTL_MOUNTMGR_CREATE_POINT</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>&amp;</span><span>input_buf</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>null</span><span>);</span><span>
</span><span>}</span><span>
</span></code></pre>
<p>(the compiled executable must be run as administrator)</p>
</details>
<p>However, having the symlink in place doesn't solve anything on its own:</p>
<pre><code>&gt; cd /D 𤭢:\
The filename, directory name, or volume label syntax is incorrect.
</code></pre>
<p>This is because there's no way to get the drive-absolute Win32 path <code>𤭢:\</code> to end up as the relevant NT path. As mentioned earlier, the behavior of <code>RtlDosPathNameToNtPathName_U</code> is what matters, and we can verify that it will not convert a drive-absolute path with a drive letter bigger than <code>U+FFFF</code> to the relevant NT path:</p>
<pre><code>C:\foo&gt; paths.exe 𤭢:\foo
path type: .Relative
  nt path: \??\C:\foo\𤭢:\foo
</code></pre>

<h3>Path classification mismatch<a id="path-classification-mismatch" href="#path-classification-mismatch">🔗</a></h3>
<p>It's very common for path-related functions to be written without the use of system-specific APIs, which means that there's high potential for a mismatch between how <code>RtlDosPathNameToNtPathName_U</code> treats a file path and how something like a particular implementation of <code>path.isAbsolute</code> treats a file path.</p>
<p>As a random example, Rust only considers paths with <code>A</code>-<code>Z</code> drive letters as absolute:</p>
<pre><code><span>use</span><span> </span><span>std</span><span>::</span><span>path</span><span>::</span><span>Path</span><span>;</span><span>

</span><span>fn</span><span> </span><span>main</span><span>()</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>
    </span><span>println</span><span>!</span><span>(</span><span>"C:\\ {}"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>Path</span><span>::</span><span>new</span><span>(</span><span>"C:\\foo"</span><span>).</span><span>is_absolute</span><span>());</span><span>
    </span><span>println</span><span>!</span><span>(</span><span>"+:\\ {}"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>Path</span><span>::</span><span>new</span><span>(</span><span>"+:\\foo"</span><span>).</span><span>is_absolute</span><span>());</span><span>
    </span><span>println</span><span>!</span><span>(</span><span>"€:\\ {}"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>Path</span><span>::</span><span>new</span><span>(</span><span>"€:\\foo"</span><span>).</span><span>is_absolute</span><span>());</span><span>
</span><span>}</span><span>
</span></code></pre>
<pre><code>&gt; rustc test.rs

&gt; test.exe
C:\ true
+:\ false
€:\ false
</code></pre>
<p>Whether or not this represents a problem worth fixing is left as an exercise for the reader (I genuinely don't know if it is a problem), but there's a second wrinkle (hinted at previously) involving text encoding that can make something like an <code>isAbsolute</code> implementation return different results for the same path. This wrinkle is the reason I looked into this whole thing in the first place, as when I was doing <a href="https://github.com/ziglang/zig/pull/25993">some work on Zig's path-related functions recently</a> I realized that looking at <code>path[0]</code>, <code>path[1]</code>, and <code>path[2]</code> for a pattern like <code>C:\</code> will look at different parts of the path depending on the encoding. That is, for something like <code>€:\</code> (which is made up of the code points <code>&lt;U+20AC&gt;&lt;U+003A&gt;&lt;U+005C&gt;</code>):</p>
<ul>
<li>Encoded as WTF-16 where <code>U+20AC</code> can be encoded as the single <code>u16</code> code unit <code>0x20AC</code>, that'd mean <code>path[0]</code> will be <code>0x20AC</code>, <code>path[1]</code> will be <code>0x3A</code> (<code>:</code>), and <code>path[2]</code> will be <code>0x5C</code> (<code>\</code>), which looks like a drive-absolute path</li>
<li>Encoded as <a href="https://wtf-8.codeberg.page/">WTF-8</a> where <code>U+20AC</code> is encoded as three <code>u8</code> code units (<code>0xE2 0x82 0xAC</code>), that'd mean <code>path[0]</code> will be <code>0xE2</code>, <code>path[1]</code> will be <code>0x82</code>, and <code>path[2]</code> will be <code>0xAC</code>, meaning it will look nothing like a drive-absolute path</li>
</ul>
<p>So, to write an implementation that treats paths the same regardless of encoding, <a href="https://codeberg.org/ziglang/zig/src/commit/bfe3317059131ab552f7583b88d6bc82609d198c/lib/std/os/windows.zig#L2564-L2585"><em>some</em> decision has to be made</a>:</p>
<ul>
<li>If strict compatibility with <code>RtlDetermineDosPathNameType_U</code>/<code>RtlDosPathNameToNtPathName_U</code> is desired, decode the first code point and check for <code>&lt;= 0xFFFF</code> when dealing with WTF-8 (this is the option I went with for the Zig standard library, but I'm not super happy about it)</li>
<li>If you want to be able to always check <code>path[0]</code>/<code>path[1]</code>/<code>path[2]</code> and don't care about non-ASCII drive letters, check for <code>path[0] &lt;= 0x7F</code> regardless of encoding</li>
<li>If you don't care about anything other than the standard <code>A</code>-<code>Z</code> drive letters, then check for that explicitly (<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/3ff30e7eafc1da7104c3960187d17939172428ed/library/std/src/sys/path/windows_prefix.rs#L132-L134">this is what Rust does</a>)</li>
</ul>
<h3>That's NOT the EURO drive<a id="that-s-not-the-euro-drive" href="#that-s-not-the-euro-drive">🔗</a></h3>
<p>Something bizarre that I found with this whole thing is that the <code>kernel32.dll</code> API <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/win32/api/winbase/nf-winbase-setvolumemountpointw"><code>SetVolumeMountPointW</code></a> has it's own unique quirk when dealing with non-ASCII drive letters. Specifically, this code (attempting to create the drive <code>€:\</code>) will succeed:</p>
<pre><code><span>const</span><span> </span><span>std</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>@import</span><span>(</span><span>"std"</span><span>);</span><span>
</span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>std</span><span>.</span><span>os</span><span>.</span><span>windows</span><span>;</span><span>
</span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>L</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>std</span><span>.</span><span>unicode</span><span>.</span><span>wtf8ToWtf16LeStringLiteral</span><span>;</span><span>

</span><span>extern</span><span> </span><span>"kernel32"</span><span> </span><span>fn</span><span> </span><span>SetVolumeMountPointW</span><span>(</span><span>
    </span><span>VolumeMountPoint</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>LPCWSTR</span><span>,</span><span>
    </span><span>VolumeName</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>LPCWSTR</span><span>,</span><span>
</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>callconv</span><span>(.</span><span>winapi</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>BOOL</span><span>;</span><span>

</span><span>pub</span><span> </span><span>fn</span><span> </span><span>main</span><span>()</span><span> </span><span>!</span><span>void</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>
    </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>volume_name</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>L</span><span>(</span><span>"\\\\?\\Volume{18123456-abcd-efab-cdef-1234abcdabcd}\\"</span><span>);</span><span>
    </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>mount_point</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>L</span><span>(</span><span>"€:\\"</span><span>);</span><span>
    </span><span>if</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>SetVolumeMountPointW</span><span>(</span><span>mount_point</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>volume_name</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>==</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>
        </span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>err</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>windows</span><span>.</span><span>GetLastError</span><span>();</span><span>
        </span><span>std</span><span>.</span><span>debug</span><span>.</span><span>print</span><span>(</span><span>"{any}\n"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>.{</span><span>err</span><span>});</span><span>
        </span><span>return</span><span> </span><span>error</span><span>.</span><span>Failed</span><span>;</span><span>
    </span><span>}</span><span>
</span><span>}</span><span>
</span></code></pre>
<p>However, when we look at the Object Manager, the <code>€:</code> symlink won't exist... but <code>¬:</code> will:</p>
<p><img src="https://www.ryanliptak.com/images/windows-drive-letters-are-not-limited-to-a-z/notdrive.png">
</p>
<p>My time <a href="https://www.ryanliptak.com/blog/every-rc-exe-bug-quirk-probably/">dealing extensively with Windows quirks</a> made me recognize what might be happening here: <code>0x20AC</code> is likely being truncated to <code>0xAC</code> by <code>SetVolumeMountPointW</code>, and <code>U+00AC</code> happens to be <code>¬</code>. If that is indeed what's going on, it seems pretty strange to truncate the drive letter instead of reject the path, but it also makes sense that non-ASCII drive letters are an edge case that no one has really thought about at all.</p>
<h2>Wrapping up<a id="wrapping-up" href="#wrapping-up">🔗</a></h2>
<p>I have no idea if anything I wrote about here is novel, although my cursory searches didn't turn up much. The only mention of non-<code>A</code>-<code>Z</code> drive letters I'm currently aware of is from the article <a href="https://googleprojectzero.blogspot.com/2016/02/the-definitive-guide-on-win32-to-nt.html">The Definitive Guide on Win32 to NT Path Conversion</a> which says:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>it's natural to assume that drive "letters" can only be A through Z. It turns out the <code>RtlGetFullPathName_U</code> API does not enforce this requirement, although the Explorer shell and command prompt almost certainly do. Therefore as long as the second character of a path is a colon, the conversion will treat it as a Drive Absolute or Drive Relative path. Of course if the DosDevices object directory doesn't have an appropriate symbolic link it's not going to do you much good.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Well, it turns out that the command prompt also doesn't enforce the requirement, and I'd guess that there's at least some more weirdness around this quirk that's waiting to be discovered.</p>


</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Norway wealth fund to vote for human rights report at Microsoft, against Nadella (308 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cnbc.com/2025/11/30/norway-wealth-fund-to-vote-for-human-rights-report-at-microsoft-agm-against-management.html</link>
            <guid>46096555</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 13:40:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/11/30/norway-wealth-fund-to-vote-for-human-rights-report-at-microsoft-agm-against-management.html">https://www.cnbc.com/2025/11/30/norway-wealth-fund-to-vote-for-human-rights-report-at-microsoft-agm-against-management.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46096555">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="RegularArticle-ArticleBody-5" data-module="ArticleBody" data-test="articleBody-2" data-analytics="RegularArticle-articleBody-5-2"><div id="ArticleBody-InlineImage-108194599" data-test="InlineImage"><p>Microsoft CEO Satya Nadella departs following a meeting of the White House Task Force on AI Education in the East Room of the White House in Washington on Sept. 4, 2025.</p><p>Eric Lee | Bloomberg | Getty Images</p></div><div><p>Norway's $2 trillion wealth fund said on Sunday it would vote for a shareholder proposal at the upcoming <span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="RegularArticle-QuoteInBody-1"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/MSFT/">Microsoft</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span>&nbsp;annual general meeting requiring for a report on the risks of operating in countries with significant human rights concerns.</p><p>Microsoft management had recommended shareholders voted against the motion.</p><p>The fund also&nbsp;said it would vote against the re-appointment of CEO Satya Nadella as chair of the board, as well as against his pay package.</p><p>The fund owned a 1.35% stake worth $50 billion in the company as of June 30, according to fund data, making it the fund's second-largest equity holding overall, after Nvidia.</p><p>It is Microsoft's eighth-largest shareholder, according to LSEG data.</p><p>Investors in the U.S. tech company will decide whether to ratify the proposed motions at the AGM on Dec. 5.<br></p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Advent of Code 2025 (795 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://adventofcode.com/2025/about</link>
            <guid>46096337</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 13:07:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://adventofcode.com/2025/about">https://adventofcode.com/2025/about</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46096337">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<article>
<p>Hi!  I'm <a href="https://was.tl/">Eric Wastl</a>. I make Advent of Code.  I hope you like it!  I also make <a href="https://was.tl/projects/">lots of other things</a>.  I'm on <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/was.tl" target="_blank">Bluesky</a>, <a href="https://hachyderm.io/@ericwastl" target="_blank">Mastodon</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/topaz" target="_blank">GitHub</a>.</p>
<p><em>Advent of Code</em> is an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Advent_calendar">Advent calendar</a> of small programming puzzles for a variety of skill levels that can be solved in <a href="https://github.com/search?q=advent+of+code">any</a> programming language you like. People use them as interview prep, company training, <a href="https://gitlab.com/imhoffman/fa19b4-mat3006/wikis/home">university</a> <a href="https://gribblelab.org/teaching/scicomp2021/index.html">coursework</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/mrdanielklein/status/936267621468483584">practice</a> <a href="https://comp215.blogs.rice.edu/">problems</a>, a speed contest, or to <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/adventofcode/search?q=flair%3Aupping&amp;restrict_sr=on">challenge each other</a>.</p>
<p>You don't need a computer science background to participate - just a little programming knowledge and some <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/adventofcode/comments/7kd8jt/what_would_you_say_are_the_minimal_skills_for/dre0uu3/">problem solving skills</a> will get you pretty far. Nor do you need a fancy computer; every problem has a solution that completes in at most 15 seconds on ten-year-old hardware.</p>
<p>If you'd like to support Advent of Code, you can do so indirectly by helping to  it with others or directly via <a href="https://adventofcode.com/2025/support">AoC++</a>.</p>
<h2>--- General Tips ---</h2>
<p>If you get stuck, try your solution against the <em>examples</em> given in the puzzle; you should get the same answers.  If not, re-read the description.  Did you misunderstand something?  Is your program doing something you don't expect?  After the examples work, if your answer still isn't correct, <em>build some test cases</em> for which you can verify the answer by hand and see if those work with your program.  Make sure you have the entire puzzle input.  If you're still stuck, maybe <em>ask a friend</em> for help, or come back to the puzzle later.  You can also ask for hints in the <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/adventofcode/" target="_blank">subreddit</a>.</p>
<h2>--- Frequently Asked Questions ---</h2>
<p id="faq_codeselect"><em>Is there an easy way to select entire code blocks?</em> You should be able to triple-click code blocks to select them. You'll need JavaScript enabled.</p><pre><code>#!/usr/bin/env perl
use warnings;
use strict;

print "You can test it out by ";
print "triple-clicking this code.\n";
</code></pre>
<p id="faq_auth"><em>How does authentication work?</em> Advent of Code uses <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OAuth" target="_blank">OAuth</a> to confirm your identity through other services.  When you log in, you only ever give your credentials to that service - never to Advent of Code.  Then, the service you use tells the Advent of Code servers that you're really you.  In general, this reveals no information about you beyond what is already public; here are examples from <a href="https://api.reddit.com/user/reddit/about" target="_blank">Reddit</a> and <a href="https://api.github.com/users/octocat" target="_blank">GitHub</a>. Advent of Code will remember your unique ID, names, URL, and image from the service you use to authenticate.</p>
<p id="faq_difficulty"><em>Why was this puzzle so easy / hard?</em> The difficulty and subject matter varies throughout each event. Very generally, the puzzles get more difficult over time, but your specific skillset will make each puzzle significantly easier or harder for you than someone else. Making puzzles is <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/adventofcode/comments/7idn6k/question_why_does_the_difficulty_vary_so_much/dqy08tk/">tricky</a>.</p>
<p id="faq_unlocktime"><em>Why do the puzzles unlock at midnight EST/UTC-5?</em> Because that's when I can consistently be available to make sure everything is working. I also have a family, a day job, and even need sleep occasionally. If you can't participate at midnight, that's not a problem; if you want to race, many people use <a href="https://adventofcode.com/leaderboard/private">private leaderboards</a> to compete with people in their area.</p>
<p id="faq_highcontrast"><em>I find the text on the site hard to read. Is there a high contrast mode?</em> There is a high contrast alternate stylesheet. Firefox supports these by default (View -&gt; Page Style -&gt; High Contrast).</p>
<p id="faq_puzzleideas"><em>I have a puzzle idea! Can I send it to you?</em> Please don't. Because of legal issues like copyright and attribution, I don't accept puzzle ideas, and I won't even read your email if it looks like one just in case I use parts of it by accident.</p>
<p id="faq_puzzlebugs"><em>Did I find a bug with a puzzle?</em> Once a puzzle has been out for even an hour, many people have already solved it; after that point, bugs are very unlikely. Start by asking on the <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/adventofcode/" target="_blank">subreddit</a>.</p>
<p id="faq_speed"><em>Should I try to get a fast solution time?</em> Maybe. Solving puzzles is hard enough on its own, but trying for a fast time also requires <a href="https://blog.vero.site/post/advent-leaderboard">many</a> <a href="https://kevinyap.ca/2019/12/going-fast-in-advent-of-code/">additional</a> <a href="https://gist.github.com/mcpower/87427528b9ba5cac6f0c679370789661">skills</a> and a lot of practice; speed-solves often look nothing like code that would pass a code review. If that sounds interesting, go for it! However, you should do Advent of Code in a way that is useful to you, and so it is completely fine to choose <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/adventofcode/comments/e2wjhf/comment/f90ksek/">an approach that meets your goals</a> and ignore speed entirely.</p>
<p id="faq_num_days"><em>Why did the number of days per event change?</em> It takes a ton of my free time every year to run Advent of Code, and building the puzzles accounts for the majority of that time. After keeping a consistent schedule for ten years(!), I needed a change. The puzzles still start on December 1st so that the day numbers make sense <span title="Oct 31 = Dec 25">(Day 1 = Dec 1)</span>, and puzzles come out every day (ending mid-December).</p>
<p id="faq_leaderboard"><em>What happened to the global leaderboard?</em> The global leaderboard was one of the largest sources of stress for me, for the infrastructure, and for many users. People took things too seriously, going way outside the spirit of the contest; some people even resorted to things like DDoS attacks. Many people incorrectly concluded that they were somehow worse programmers because their own times didn't compare. What started as a fun feature in 2015 became an ever-growing problem, and so, after ten years of Advent of Code, I removed the global leaderboard. (However, I've made it so you can share a read-only view of your private leaderboard. Please don't use this feature or data to create a "new" global leaderboard.)</p>
<p id="faq_private_leaderboard_rules"><em>While trying to get a fast time on a private leaderboard, may I use AI / watch streamers / check the solution threads / ask a friend for help / etc?</em> If you are a member of any private leaderboards, you should ask the people that run them what their expectations are of their members. If you don't agree with those expectations, you should find a new private leaderboard or start your own! Private leaderboards might have rules like maximum runtime, allowed programming language, what time you can first open the puzzle, what tools you can use, or whether you have to wear a silly hat while working.</p>
<p id="faq_ai"><em>Should I use AI to solve Advent of Code puzzles?</em> No. If you send a friend to the gym on your behalf, would you expect to get stronger? Advent of Code puzzles are designed to be interesting for humans to solve - no consideration is made for whether AI can or cannot solve a puzzle. If you want practice prompting an AI, there are almost certainly better exercises elsewhere designed with that in mind.</p>
<p id="faq_copying"><em>Can I copy/redistribute part of Advent of Code?</em> Please don't. Advent of Code is free to <em>use</em>, not free to copy. If you're posting a code repository somewhere, please don't include parts of Advent of Code like the puzzle text or your inputs. If you're making a website, please don't make it look like Advent of Code or name it something similar.</p>
<h2>--- Credits ---</h2>
<p>Puzzles, Code, &amp; Design: <a href="https://was.tl/">Eric Wastl</a></p>
<p>Beta Testing:</p>
<ul>
<li>Ben Lucek</li>
<li><a href="http://thespaceabove.us/">JP Burke</a></li>
<li>Aneurysm9</li>
<li>Andrew Skalski</li>
</ul>
<p>Community Managers: <a href="https://reddit.com/message/compose/?to=/r/adventofcode">Danielle Lucek</a> and Aneurysm9</p>
<p>Playing: You!</p>
<section id="legal">
<h2>--- Legal ---</h2>
<p>Advent of Code is a registered trademark in the United States. The design elements, language, styles, and concept of Advent of Code are all the sole property of Advent of Code and may not be replicated or used by any other person or entity without express written consent of Advent of Code. Copyright 2015-2025 Advent of Code. All rights reserved.</p>
<p>You may link to or reference puzzles from Advent of Code in discussions, classes, source code, printed material, etc., even in commercial contexts. Advent of Code does not claim ownership or copyright over your solution implementation.</p>
</section>
</article>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[CachyOS: Fast and Customizable Linux Distribution (276 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://cachyos.org/</link>
            <guid>46095585</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 10:47:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://cachyos.org/">https://cachyos.org/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46095585">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>   <div> <div>  <p> <span>CachyOS</span> is designed to deliver lightning-fast speeds and stability, ensuring a smooth and enjoyable
          computing experience every time you use it. Whether you're a seasoned Linux user or just starting
          out, CachyOS is the ideal choice for those looking for a powerful, customizable and blazingly
          fast operating system.
</p>  </div> <div> <p><img src="https://cachyos.org/_astro/hero.BvceRk57.jpg" width="1480" height="833" srcset="https://cachyos.org/_astro/hero.BvceRk57_1F2Ofw.webp 400w, https://cachyos.org/_astro/hero.BvceRk57_Z2rlEgL.webp 768w, https://cachyos.org/_astro/hero.BvceRk57_Z1Kaefg.webp 1480w, https://cachyos.org/_astro/hero.BvceRk57_mS4pY.webp 2960w" sizes="(max-width: 767px) 400px, (max-width: 1479px) 768px, 1480px" alt="Hero" loading="eager" decoding="async"> </p> </div> </div> <section> <p><span> <svg width="1em" height="1em" data-icon="tabler:info-square">   <symbol id="ai:tabler:info-square" viewBox="0 0 24 24"><g fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round" stroke-width="2"><path d="M12 9h.01M3 5a2 2 0 0 1 2-2h14a2 2 0 0 1 2 2v14a2 2 0 0 1-2 2H5a2 2 0 0 1-2-2z"></path><path d="M11 12h1v4h1"></path></g></symbol><use href="#ai:tabler:info-square"></use>  </svg> Goal:</span> Provide you better speed, security and ease of use
</p> </section> <div id="features"> <div> <p>
Features
</p> <h2>
Discover the Benefits of <span>CachyOS</span> </h2> <p>
Experience Cutting-Edge Linux Performance with CachyOS - A distribution built on Arch Linux,
        CachyOS features the optimized linux-cachyos kernel utilizing the advanced BORE Scheduler
        for unparalleled performance.
</p> </div> <div> <div> <div> <h3>Enhance Your Performance with Optimized Packages</h3> <p>CachyOS does compile packages with the x86-64-v3, x86-64-v4 and Zen4 instruction set and LTO to provide a higher performance. Core packages also get PGO or BOLT optimization.</p> </div><div> <h3>Select Your Preferred Edition</h3> <p>CachyOS offers a variety of popular Desktop Environments, Wayland Compositors and X11 Window Managers including KDE Plasma, GNOME, XFCE, i3, Wayfire, LXQt, Openbox, Cinnamon, COSMIC, UKUI, LXDE, Mate, Budgie, Qtile, Hyprland, Sway and Niri. Select your preferred environment during the online installation process.</p> </div><div> <h3>Customizable Installation Process</h3> <p>CachyOS offers a choice of two installers to fit your needs: a user-friendly GUI version based on Calamares, and a CLI-based option for those who prefer a streamlined, non-graphical installation experience.</p> </div> </div><div> <h3>Power Up Your Computing with Robust Kernel Support</h3> <p>CachyOS utilizes the BORE Scheduler for better interactivity, and offers a variety of scheduler options including EEVDF, sched-ext, ECHO, and RT. All kernels are compiled with optimized x86-64-v3, x86-64-v4, Zen4 instructions and LTO to be optimized for your CPU.</p> </div> </div> </div>  <div> <h2> <span>Fast</span> &amp; <br> <span>Secure</span> </h2> <p>
Experience Lightning-Fast Performance. <br>Have fun! :)
</p> <p> <a href="https://cachyos.org/download"> <svg width="1em" height="1em" viewBox="0 0 24 24" data-icon="tabler:download">   <use href="#ai:tabler:download"></use>  </svg> Download
</a> </p> </div> <div> <p> <h2>Our Sponsors</h2> </p>  </div>  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Silicon Valley's man in the White House is benefiting himself and his friends (119 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/30/technology/david-sacks-white-house-profits.html</link>
            <guid>46095363</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 10:03:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/30/technology/david-sacks-white-house-profits.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/30/technology/david-sacks-white-house-profits.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46095363">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/30/technology/david-sacks-white-house-profits.html: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>