<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 07:00:04 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Nitter Shutting Down (343 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nitter.d420.de</link>
            <guid>39161194</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 00:13:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nitter.d420.de">https://nitter.d420.de</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39161194">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://nitter.d420.de: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Philadelphia Jury Hits Monsanto with $2.25B Roundup Verdict (126 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.law.com/thelegalintelligencer/2024/01/26/philadelphia-jury-hits-monsanto-with-2-25b-roundup-verdict/</link>
            <guid>39160463</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2024 22:20:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.law.com/thelegalintelligencer/2024/01/26/philadelphia-jury-hits-monsanto-with-2-25b-roundup-verdict/">https://www.law.com/thelegalintelligencer/2024/01/26/philadelphia-jury-hits-monsanto-with-2-25b-roundup-verdict/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39160463">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="legal-compass-res">
                    <div>
                        <h3><a href="#">From Data to Decisions</a></h3>
                        <p><span>Dynamically explore and compare data on law firms, companies, individual lawyers, and industry trends.</span><br>
                    </p></div>
                    <div>
                        <h3><a href="#">Exclusive Depth and Reach.</a></h3>
                        <p><span>Law.com Compass includes access to our exclusive industry reports, combining the unmatched expertise of our analyst team with ALM’s deep bench of proprietary information to provide insights that can’t be found anywhere else.</span><br>
                    </p></div>
                    <div>
                        <h3><a href="#">Big Pictures and Fine Details</a></h3>
                        <p><span>Law.com Compass delivers you the full scope of information, from the rankings of the Am Law 200 and NLJ 500 to intricate details and comparisons of firms’ financials, staffing, clients, news and events.</span><br>
                    </p></div>
                </div><div id="professional-announcements">
                            <div>
                                <h3><a href="#">DuBose Miller, LLC</a></h3>
                                <p><span>
                                    01/23/2024<br>
                                    Daily Report
                                </span></p><p>TO: ALL MEMBERS OF THE BAR  AND ALL CITIZENS OF THE CITY OF ATLANTA  The Atlanta Judicial Commission is now accepting nominations for the position of Municipal Court Judge for the City of Atlanta Municipal  Court. Members of the bar may nominate themselves or others, and the public is invited to submit nominations. Nominations in writing  must be received by February 10, 2024, and should be addressed to:  The Atlanta Judicial Commission  c/o Von A. DuBose, Esq.  75 14th Street, NE, Suite 2110, Atlanta, GA 30309  A nominee must be at least 25 years of age, a resident of the City of Atlanta for one year prior to appointment and shall have been admitted  to practice law in the State of Georgia for at least five years.  The Commission will send an application and letter outlining its schedules and procedures to each nominee. The list of nominees is public  information and is available upon request. The Commission welcomes communications from organizations or persons familiar with the  specific qualifications, experience and ability of any nominee but discourages general endorsement letter-writing campaigns in support of  a nominee. A copy of any communication regarding a nominee should be sent to all members of the Commission.  FOR THE COMMISSION  Von A. DuBose, Esq.  Chair  Members of The Commission  Von A. DuBose, Esq.  75 14th Street NE, Suite 2110 Atlanta, Georgia 30309  <a href="https://www.law.com/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" data-cfemail="4d29382f223e280d29382f223e2820242121283f632e2220">[email&nbsp;protected]</a> (404) 720 -8111   William A. Morrison, Esq. 50 Hurt Plaza, Suite 1110 Atlanta, Georgia 30303  <a href="https://www.law.com/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" data-cfemail="bbd9d2d7d7fbcfd3ded6d4c9c9d2c8d4d5ddd2c9d695d8d4d6">[email&nbsp;protected]</a> (404) 290-4628   Seth David Kirschenbaum, Esq.   918 Ponce De Leon Ave NE Atlanta, Georgia 30306  <a href="https://www.law.com/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" data-cfemail="d1a2b4a5b991b5abbabdffb2bebc">[email&nbsp;protected]</a> (404) 471-3177   David Coleman  <a href="https://www.law.com/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" data-cfemail="9bfff8f2f5effee9f5faeff2f4f5faf7dbf9fef7f7e8f4eeeff3b5f5feef">[email&nbsp;protected]</a>  (404) 626-1726   Cheryl Turner, Esq.  83 Richmond Street  Atlanta, Georgia 30312 <a href="https://www.law.com/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" data-cfemail="a4c7ccc1d6ddc8c2d0d1d6cac1d6e4cccbd0c9c5cdc88ac7cbc9">[email&nbsp;protected]</a>   Jeffery E. Tompkins, Esq.   3355 Main Street  Atlanta, Georgia 30337  <a href="https://www.law.com/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" data-cfemail="89e3a7fde6e4f9e2e0e7fac9fde2fafde5e8fea7eae6e4">[email&nbsp;protected]</a>  (404) 688-4503   Steven K. Weiner, Esq.  730 Peachtree Street, NE, Suite 600 Atlanta, Georgia 30308  <a href="https://www.law.com/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" data-cfemail="d2a1a5b7bbbcb7a092a5b7bbbcb7a0beb3a5b5a0bda7a2fcb1bdbf">[email&nbsp;protected]</a> (404) 525-0992   Jan Bryson  <a href="https://www.law.com/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" data-cfemail="244e46565d574b4a644649494848470a474b49">[email&nbsp;protected]</a>  (404) 944-0034</p>
                                <p><span><a href="https://www.law.com/professional-announcement/?ad=ON-53794-01">View Announcement ›</a></span>
                            </p></div>
                            
                            <div>
                                <h3><a href="#">MCLAUGHLIN &amp; STERN, LLP</a></h3>
                                <p><span>
                                    01/22/2024<br>
                                    New York Law Journal
                                </span></p><p>McLaughlin &amp; Stern, LLP  is pleased to announce that Charles S. Warren formerly Chair of the Kramer Levin Environmental Practice Group has joined the Firm as a Partner    Mr. Warren is recognized as one of the pre-eminent lawyers in his field who counsels and represents clients in a comprehensive range of environmental law matters.   A former regional administrator with the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), Chuck brings 40 years of knowledge and experience in environmental law, both in government and private practice, to his work on behalf of clients.   January 1, 2024 <a href="https://www.law.com/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" data-cfemail="395a4e584b4b5c5779545a55584c5e515550574a4d5c4b57175a5654">[email&nbsp;protected]</a>  www.mclaughlinstern.com</p>
                                <p><span><a href="https://www.law.com/professional-announcement/?ad=ON-53730-03">View Announcement ›</a></span>
                            </p></div>
                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Pong Wars (259 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://pong-wars.koenvangilst.nl/</link>
            <guid>39159418</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2024 20:19:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://pong-wars.koenvangilst.nl/">https://pong-wars.koenvangilst.nl/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39159418">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="container">
      <canvas id="pongCanvas" width="800" height="800"></canvas>
      
      <p id="made">
        made by <a href="https://koenvangilst.nl/">Koen van Gilst</a> | source on
        <a href="https://github.com/vnglst/pong-wars">github</a>
      </p>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Invention of a New Pasta Shape (2021) (144 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://kottke.org/21/03/the-invention-of-a-new-pasta-shape</link>
            <guid>39159263</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2024 20:03:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://kottke.org/21/03/the-invention-of-a-new-pasta-shape">https://kottke.org/21/03/the-invention-of-a-new-pasta-shape</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39159263">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<p>For the past three years, Dan Pashman of <a href="https://www.sporkful.com/">The Sporkful podcast</a> has been on something of a mission: to invent a new pasta shape. All of Pashman's hard work has paid off with the debut of cascatelli pasta, <a href="https://www.sfoglini.com/products/sporkful">available for sale from Sfoglini</a>.</p>

<p><img src="https://kottke.org/plus/misc/images/cascatelli-pasta-01.jpg" width="1000" height="1000" alt="Cascatelli pasta"></p>

<p>Pashman and Sfoglini engineered the new shape to maximize the amount of sauce that sticks to it, make it easier to get your fork on it, and have it feel good when you bite into it.</p>

<p><img src="https://kottke.org/plus/misc/images/cascatelli-pasta-02.jpg" width="1000" height="1000" alt="Cascatelli Pasta 02"></p>

<blockquote><p>Cascatelli is designed to maximize the three qualities by which Dan believes all pasta shapes should be judged:</p>

<p>Sauceability: How readily sauce adheres to the shape<br>
Forkability: How easy it is to get the shape on your fork and keep it there<br>
Toothsinkability: How satisfying it is to sink your teeth into it</p></blockquote>

<p>Pashman documented the invention of cascatelli in a 5-part series on The Sporkful podcast — <a href="https://www.sporkful.com/mission-impastable-1-spaghetti-sucks/">you can listen to the first episode here</a> — and <a href="https://www.instagram.com/s/aGlnaGxpZ2h0OjE3ODYzOTA1ODY2NDgzOTY0?igshid=fvqxwa81z7nc&amp;story_media_id=2517176903157538890">on Instagram</a>. You can <a href="https://www.sfoglini.com/products/sporkful">order some cascatelli</a> to try it out at home, but it looks like they are currently sold out of everything aside from 5-lb bulk bags.</p>

<p>See also <a href="https://kottke.org/18/03/how-to-make-29-different-shapes-of-pasta-by-hand">How to Make 29 Different Shapes of Pasta by Hand</a> and <a href="https://kottke.org/09/10/150-different-pasta-shapes">150 Different Pasta Shapes</a>.</p>


<ul><li><a href="https://kottke.org/tag/Dan%20Pashman"><i></i>Dan Pashman</a></li><li><a href="https://kottke.org/tag/design"><i></i>design</a></li><li><a href="https://kottke.org/tag/food"><i></i>food</a></li>
</ul>





</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Gitlab password reset bug leaves more than 5.3K servers up for grabs (205 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.scmagazine.com/news/gitlab-password-reset-bug-leaves-more-than-5-3k-servers-up-for-grabs</link>
            <guid>39159002</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2024 19:34:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.scmagazine.com/news/gitlab-password-reset-bug-leaves-more-than-5-3k-servers-up-for-grabs">https://www.scmagazine.com/news/gitlab-password-reset-bug-leaves-more-than-5-3k-servers-up-for-grabs</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39159002">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><div><p><a href="https://www.scmagazine.com/news/gitlab-vulnerability-risks-account-takeover-via-simple-password-reset" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Critical GitLab vulnerability CVE-2023-7028</a> was not patched on more than 5,300 servers as of Tuesday, potentially enabling remote takeover of software developers’ accounts.</p><p>The bug, with a maximum CVSS score of 10, <a href="https://about.gitlab.com/releases/2024/01/11/critical-security-release-gitlab-16-7-2-released/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">was first disclosed and patched by GitLab</a> on Jan. 11. The vulnerability in GitLab’s login system would allow an attacker to have a password reset link sent to their own unverified email address without any user interaction by the victim.</p><p>“Account takeover can be achieved by crafting a specially formatted HTTP request that is capable of sending a password reset email to an unverified email address in an unpatched version,” a GitLab spokesperson told SC Media in a Jan. 12 email.</p><p>Security updates were released for GitLab versions 16.5.6, 16.6.4 and 16.7.2 and backported to versions 16.1.6, 16.2.9, 16.3.7 and 16.4.5, as well.</p><p>One researcher who tested the bug on GitLab Community Edition version 16.6.1 and <a href="https://attackerkb.com/topics/VBDvNxhyjr/cve-2023-7028" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">shared their results on AttackerKB</a> said CVE-2023-7028 was, “Very effective and easy to exploit.”</p><p>Nearly two weeks after patches became available, <a href="https://dashboard.shadowserver.org/statistics/combined/map/?map_type=std&amp;day=2024-01-23&amp;source=http_vulnerable&amp;source=http_vulnerable6&amp;tag=cve-2023-7028%2B&amp;geo=all&amp;data_set=count&amp;scale=log" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">5,379 vulnerable instances of GitLab</a> were detected worldwide by the Shadowserver Foundation. The nonprofit organization, which monitors malicious activity online, <a href="https://twitter.com/Shadowserver/status/1750115947430416434" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">posted the data from Jan. 23 on X</a>, noting that the United States and Germany had the most vulnerable instances, with 964 and 730 respectively.</p><p><a href="https://dashboard.shadowserver.org/statistics/combined/time-series/?date_range=7&amp;source=http_vulnerable&amp;source=http_vulnerable6&amp;tag=cve-2023-7028%2B&amp;group_by=geo&amp;style=stacked" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Shadowserver’s dashboard tool</a> showed fewer vulnerable instances (4,652) on Jan. 24. A Shadowserver spokesperson confirmed with SC Media that there was "a drop in detected vulnerable instances, which is a positive development," but that more time would be needed to determine whether this decrease was a trend or a "blip" in Shadowserver's scans.</p><h2>Indicators of compromise for GitLab CVE-2023-7028</h2><p>GitLab customers with self-managed instances of the affected products — GitLab Community Edition and GitLab Enterprise Edition&nbsp;— should review their logs for exploitation of CVE-2023-7028 using the two following methods, as outlined by GitLab:</p><div><ul><li>Check gitlab-rails/production_json.log for HTTP requests to the /users/password path with params.value.email consisting of a JSON array with multiple email addresses</li><li>Check gitlabs-rails/audit_json.log for entries with meta.caller.id of PasswordsController#create and target_Details consisting of a JSON array with multiple email addresses</li></ul></div><p>The company said no exploitation of the bug on GitLab.com or GitLab Dedicated instances has been detected.</p><p>GitLab recommended customers also enable two-factor authentication (2FA), which prevents account takeover via CVE-2023-7028, although users of unpatched instances are still vulnerable to being locked out of their accounts if an attacker exploits the flaw to reset their password.</p></div></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[In major gaffe, hacked Microsoft test account was assigned admin privileges (196 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/security/2024/01/in-major-gaffe-hacked-microsoft-test-account-was-assigned-admin-privileges/</link>
            <guid>39157888</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2024 17:50:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/security/2024/01/in-major-gaffe-hacked-microsoft-test-account-was-assigned-admin-privileges/">https://arstechnica.com/security/2024/01/in-major-gaffe-hacked-microsoft-test-account-was-assigned-admin-privileges/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39157888">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
                                    
<figure>
  <img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/exploit-vulnerability-security-800x450.jpg" alt="In major gaffe, hacked Microsoft test account was assigned admin privileges">
      <figcaption></figcaption>  </figure>

  




<!-- cache hit 427:single/related:f02fd9aac82ad8fcccfd63a9e4f465e4 --><!-- empty -->
<p>The hackers who recently broke into Microsoft’s network and monitored top executives’ email for two months did so by gaining access to an aging test account with administrative privileges, a major gaffe on the company's part, a researcher said.</p>
<p>The new detail was provided in vaguely worded language included in a post Microsoft published on Thursday. It expanded on a disclosure Microsoft <a href="https://arstechnica.com/security/2024/01/microsoft-network-breached-through-password-spraying-by-russian-state-hackers/">published late last Friday</a>. Russia-state hackers, Microsoft said, used a technique known as password spraying to exploit a weak credential for logging into a “legacy non-production test tenant account” that wasn’t protected by multifactor authentication. From there, they somehow acquired the ability to access email accounts that belonged to senior executives and employees working in security and legal teams.
</p><h2>A “pretty big config error”</h2>
<p>In <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2024/01/25/midnight-blizzard-guidance-for-responders-on-nation-state-attack/">Thursday’s post</a> updating customers on findings from its ongoing investigation, Microsoft provided more details on how the hackers achieved this monumental escalation of access. The hackers, part of a group Microsoft tracks as Midnight Blizzard, gained persistent access to the privileged email accounts by abusing the OAuth authorization protcol, which is used industry-wide to allow an array of apps to access resources on a network. After compromising the test tenant, Midnight Blizzard used it to create a malicious app and assign it rights to access every email address on Microsoft’s Office 365 email service.</p>                                            
                                                        
<p>In Thursday’s update, Microsoft officials said as much, although in language that largely obscured the extent of the major blunder. They wrote:</p>
<blockquote><p>Threat actors like Midnight Blizzard compromise user accounts to create, modify, and grant high permissions to OAuth applications that they can misuse to hide malicious activity. The misuse of OAuth also enables threat actors to maintain access to applications, even if they lose access to the initially compromised account. Midnight Blizzard leveraged their initial access to identify and compromise a legacy test OAuth application that had elevated access to the Microsoft corporate environment. The actor created additional malicious OAuth applications. They created a new user account to grant consent in the Microsoft corporate environment to the actor controlled malicious OAuth applications. <b>The threat actor then used the legacy test OAuth application to grant them the Office 365 Exchange Online full_access_as_app role, which allows access to mailboxes.</b> [Emphasis added.]</p></blockquote>
<p>Kevin Beaumont—a researcher and security professional with decades of experience, including a stint working for Microsoft—<a href="https://cyberplace.social/@GossiTheDog/111823778988979816">pointed out on Mastodon</a> that the only way for an account to assign the all-powerful full_access_as_app role to an OAuth app is for the account to have administrator privileges. “Somebody,” he said, “made a pretty big config error in production.”</p>


                                                </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Is it insider trading if I bought Boeing puts while inside the wrecked airplane? (447 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://law.stackexchange.com/questions/98706/is-it-insider-trading-if-i-bought-boeing-puts-while-i-am-inside-the-wrecked-airp</link>
            <guid>39157797</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2024 17:41:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://law.stackexchange.com/questions/98706/is-it-insider-trading-if-i-bought-boeing-puts-while-i-am-inside-the-wrecked-airp">https://law.stackexchange.com/questions/98706/is-it-insider-trading-if-i-bought-boeing-puts-while-i-am-inside-the-wrecked-airp</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39157797">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="text">
<blockquote>
<p>Is it insider trading if I bought Boeing puts while I am inside the
wrecked airplane?</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>No.</strong></p>
<p>Insider information is information obtained from an "insider" such as an executive or director of the company, or perhaps someone subject to a non-disclosure agreement with the company. Engaging in stock trading based upon confidential information from an insider source, before it is publicly disclosed, is illegal in most cases. <em>See, e.g.</em>, <a href="https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1164964/000101968715004168/globalfuture_8k-ex9904.htm" rel="noreferrer">here</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Insider_trading" rel="noreferrer">here</a>. From the first link:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>SEC Rule 10b-5 prohibits corporate officers and directors or other
insider employees from using confidential corporate information to
reap a profit (or avoid a loss) by trading in the Company’s stock.
This rule also prohibits “tipping” of confidential corporate
information to third parties.</p>
<p>· Who is an insider?</p>
<p>An “insider” is an officer, director, 10%
stockholder and anyone who possesses inside information because of his
or her relationship with the Company or with an officer, director or
principal stockholder of the Company. Rule 10b-5’s application goes
considerably beyond just officers, directors and principal
stockholders. This rule also covers any employee who has obtained
material non-public corporate information, as well as any person who
has received a “tip” from an Insider of the Company concerning
information about the Company that is material and nonpublic, and
trades (i.e. purchase or sells) the Company’s stock or other
securities.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>When you are not personally an insider, and you are relying on your own personal knowledge, you are not relying on knowledge from an "insider", so you are not engaged in insider trading.</p>
<p>It is also worth noting that Boeing is an aircraft manufacturer, not an airline. So, no one employed by the airline flying the plane would be an insider with respect to Boeing.</p>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Remote work won, don't let anyone gaslight you to believe otherwise (146 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.hottakes.space/p/remote-work-won-dont-let-anyone-gaslight</link>
            <guid>39156987</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2024 16:38:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.hottakes.space/p/remote-work-won-dont-let-anyone-gaslight">https://www.hottakes.space/p/remote-work-won-dont-let-anyone-gaslight</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39156987">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><p><span>I </span><a href="https://www.hottakes.space/p/the-final-post-on-remote-work" rel="">previously wrote</a><span> what is still going to be my final post on remote work, at least the work part. In it, I went through the reasons why competent teams will be distributed for bits work, today and into the future (for atoms work we still need a human presence — for now). I’ve nothing really to add to that part of the conversation, remote work isn’t even new, people have been doing it since the 90s. </span></p><p>But in the time since I wrote the above post, remote work won and became a normal part of life for a large cohort of the population. This will only continue to grow, and so I wanted to comment a bit more on the topic as some are still strangely in denial. </p><p>Let’s start with this chart a friend shared with me on remote work quietly reaching equilibrium, which happened last year.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F204e26bc-47be-4d6d-b500-16c3e3ac4662_2452x1280.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F204e26bc-47be-4d6d-b500-16c3e3ac4662_2452x1280.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F204e26bc-47be-4d6d-b500-16c3e3ac4662_2452x1280.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F204e26bc-47be-4d6d-b500-16c3e3ac4662_2452x1280.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F204e26bc-47be-4d6d-b500-16c3e3ac4662_2452x1280.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F204e26bc-47be-4d6d-b500-16c3e3ac4662_2452x1280.jpeg" width="1456" height="760" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/204e26bc-47be-4d6d-b500-16c3e3ac4662_2452x1280.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:760,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;Image&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="Image" title="Image" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F204e26bc-47be-4d6d-b500-16c3e3ac4662_2452x1280.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F204e26bc-47be-4d6d-b500-16c3e3ac4662_2452x1280.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F204e26bc-47be-4d6d-b500-16c3e3ac4662_2452x1280.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F204e26bc-47be-4d6d-b500-16c3e3ac4662_2452x1280.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><span>There is plenty other data, samples and trend sources here you can google, but broadly it is all pretty steady that over 1/4 of employees in the US are working remote in a durable fashion since 2020, and probably more interestingly 68% </span><a href="https://www.zippia.com/advice/remote-work-statistics/" rel="">would prefer</a><span> to be fully remote. Note it’s higher % of people working remote in cities because of the type of work done there. </span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F956bb77b-3df5-4e8c-be28-e06b6ccac2a8_732x655.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F956bb77b-3df5-4e8c-be28-e06b6ccac2a8_732x655.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F956bb77b-3df5-4e8c-be28-e06b6ccac2a8_732x655.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F956bb77b-3df5-4e8c-be28-e06b6ccac2a8_732x655.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F956bb77b-3df5-4e8c-be28-e06b6ccac2a8_732x655.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F956bb77b-3df5-4e8c-be28-e06b6ccac2a8_732x655.jpeg" width="510" height="456.3524590163934" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/956bb77b-3df5-4e8c-be28-e06b6ccac2a8_732x655.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:655,&quot;width&quot;:732,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:510,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;share of americans working remotely 2018-2023&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="share of americans working remotely 2018-2023" title="share of americans working remotely 2018-2023" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F956bb77b-3df5-4e8c-be28-e06b6ccac2a8_732x655.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F956bb77b-3df5-4e8c-be28-e06b6ccac2a8_732x655.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F956bb77b-3df5-4e8c-be28-e06b6ccac2a8_732x655.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F956bb77b-3df5-4e8c-be28-e06b6ccac2a8_732x655.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Endless cubicle farms were never the end state of anything, and all this can be repurposed for better use: shopping, socialization, recreation, residential and exciting/novel concepts we’ve not even considered yet. The future here is something to look forward to: going to city centers purely to do something alone you can do anywhere makes no logical sense. This was all inevitable and good, unless you wanted humans to remain enslaved and great real estate locations to be stuck in 1950s-era industrial economy use.</p><p><span>Even the old guard suits at Goldman Sachs believe remote is here to stay [</span><a href="https://www.axios.com/2024/01/16/ceo-return-to-office-wars" rel="">via Axios</a><span>]:</span></p><blockquote><p><em>Remote work appears likely to be the most persistent economic legacy of the pandemic," write Goldman Sachs economists in a recent note.</em></p><p><em>About 20%-25% of workers in the U.S. work from home at least part of the week, according to data Goldman cites. That's below a peak of 47% during the pandemic but well above its prior average of around 3%.</em></p><p><em><strong>"The battle is over,</strong><span>" said Diana Scott, human capital center leader at The Conference Board. "There are so many other issues CEOs are facing.”</span></em></p></blockquote><p><span>Now that remote has been normalized for some time it was cool to also see some </span><a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=4675401" rel="">new research</a><span> on public firms and distributed work just published December, 2023. The full paper is worth reading, but the summary is what you would expect if you’re paying attention and viewing this issue objectively (emphasis mine).</span></p><blockquote><p><em>Using a sample of Standard and Poor’s 500 firms, we examine determinants and consequences of U.S. firms’ return-to-office (RTO) mandates. Results of our determinant analyses are consistent with managers using RTO mandates to reassert control over employees and blame employees as a scapegoat for bad firm performance. </em></p><p><em><span>…our findings do not support the argument that managers impose mandates because they believe RTO increases firm values. Further, </span><strong>our difference in differences tests report significant declines in employees’ job satisfactions mandates but no significant changes in financial performance or firm values after RTO mandates.</strong></em></p></blockquote><p>So basically, TL;DR: you will make your employees hate their lives, make less money and be less efficient by electing to assert authoritarian control over their movements and do the same work in a different arbitrary building every day. And I am not being hyperbolic here, I have heard stories from friends in legacy sectors whose teams have started location-tracking employees during the day. It’s straight out of a dystopian panopticon science fiction novel. I can’t imagine anyone competent staying at such firms very long.</p><p><span>Absolute top companies like like NVIDIA worth well &gt;$1 trillion are running remote operations for their teams, so there’s really no excuse that “this is just for smaller shops.” My team at Google was distributed many years before this was normalized and we worked on software at internet scale. So when execs comment here, they’re simply putting their lack of (modern) management skills on display for the world to see. I Tweeted jokingly about this over the weekend </span><a href="https://twitter.com/AdamSinger/status/1748883781954494921" rel="">here</a><span>. </span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F047ff842-1ead-4549-86c1-0a8a85f619f0_893x1017.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F047ff842-1ead-4549-86c1-0a8a85f619f0_893x1017.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F047ff842-1ead-4549-86c1-0a8a85f619f0_893x1017.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F047ff842-1ead-4549-86c1-0a8a85f619f0_893x1017.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F047ff842-1ead-4549-86c1-0a8a85f619f0_893x1017.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F047ff842-1ead-4549-86c1-0a8a85f619f0_893x1017.png" width="546" height="621.8163493840985" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/047ff842-1ead-4549-86c1-0a8a85f619f0_893x1017.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1017,&quot;width&quot;:893,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:546,&quot;bytes&quot;:586083,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F047ff842-1ead-4549-86c1-0a8a85f619f0_893x1017.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F047ff842-1ead-4549-86c1-0a8a85f619f0_893x1017.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F047ff842-1ead-4549-86c1-0a8a85f619f0_893x1017.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F047ff842-1ead-4549-86c1-0a8a85f619f0_893x1017.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Really the only other dinosaurs howling into the wind about the latest fax machine going extinct due to the internet are CRE bagholders, who are of course upset they (god forbid) have to reinvest or change strategies, and continue to clutch pearls hoping the world would revert to a previous state. They of course don’t believe Earth can change (something it’s literally defined by). We’re a free capitalist society and so everyone has to go through the ringer of disruption, but ultimately we come out the other side better for the vast majority. They’ll evolve, but for some reason this group are extremely sore losers here. </p><p><span>There was </span><a href="https://www.axios.com/local/twin-cities/2023/08/25/target-backlash-remote-work-downtown-minneapolis" rel="">this story</a><span> last year in Minneapolis which was emblematic of so much I’ve seen in local markets, in which a CRE owner says "hey &lt;company&gt;, please put a gun to your employee's heads bc I want to make more money" …quite the take. </span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd699641d-805f-4f0b-9b2b-f406cd074d90_865x177.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd699641d-805f-4f0b-9b2b-f406cd074d90_865x177.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd699641d-805f-4f0b-9b2b-f406cd074d90_865x177.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd699641d-805f-4f0b-9b2b-f406cd074d90_865x177.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd699641d-805f-4f0b-9b2b-f406cd074d90_865x177.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd699641d-805f-4f0b-9b2b-f406cd074d90_865x177.png" width="560" height="114.58959537572254" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/d699641d-805f-4f0b-9b2b-f406cd074d90_865x177.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:177,&quot;width&quot;:865,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:560,&quot;bytes&quot;:43146,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd699641d-805f-4f0b-9b2b-f406cd074d90_865x177.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd699641d-805f-4f0b-9b2b-f406cd074d90_865x177.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd699641d-805f-4f0b-9b2b-f406cd074d90_865x177.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd699641d-805f-4f0b-9b2b-f406cd074d90_865x177.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><span>The irony of this quote is Randolph Street Realty Capital and Jonathan himself</span><em> are based on Chicago</em><span>, not Minneapolis. They aren’t even a local part of the community they claim to care about (they literally just care about their holdings, of course). They also flex aggregate asset value &gt;600M on </span><a href="https://rstrealty.com/" rel="">their website</a><span>. </span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55082018-72e4-40a7-83ad-567064133eef_649x461.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55082018-72e4-40a7-83ad-567064133eef_649x461.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55082018-72e4-40a7-83ad-567064133eef_649x461.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55082018-72e4-40a7-83ad-567064133eef_649x461.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55082018-72e4-40a7-83ad-567064133eef_649x461.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55082018-72e4-40a7-83ad-567064133eef_649x461.png" width="331" height="235.1171032357473" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/55082018-72e4-40a7-83ad-567064133eef_649x461.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:461,&quot;width&quot;:649,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:331,&quot;bytes&quot;:66403,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55082018-72e4-40a7-83ad-567064133eef_649x461.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55082018-72e4-40a7-83ad-567064133eef_649x461.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55082018-72e4-40a7-83ad-567064133eef_649x461.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55082018-72e4-40a7-83ad-567064133eef_649x461.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><span>It’s incredible for a number of reasons, that there are grown adults who basically sound like children, but anyway if your income relies on political pressure for people to be </span><em>forced</em><span> to do something — sounds pretty un-American to me. This happened across America, and because of such public tantrums no one feels bad for them. </span></p><p><strong>Where we go from here…</strong></p><p>Daily commutes into an office are simply not coming back for competent people. Everyone I talk to who loves their craft would rather simply not work than go back to wasting their lives in traffic (and this is how we designed America). They would rather have that time purely for working, which they can now do. The analogy to best understand this which I’ve said before is like believing in Santa Claus as a child, and later discovering Santa isn’t real. You can’t go back. The spell of the office being a requisite for modern work was broken. The genie is impossible to put back in the bottle. Everyone will adapt.</p><p><span>So all we have left are bad bosses, CRE bagholders who want everyone to be miserable in order to prop up their portfolios, and some % of mid-managers who simply hate their lives and want their peers to sit in traffic for 2 hours a day (</span><a href="https://www.hottakes.space/p/ditching-your-commute-worth-40kyear" rel="">literally </a><em><a href="https://www.hottakes.space/p/ditching-your-commute-worth-40kyear" rel="">the</a></em><a href="https://www.hottakes.space/p/ditching-your-commute-worth-40kyear" rel=""> cause of unhappiness</a><span> in modernity). The world is pretty dark already, but I can’t imagine letting any of these groups claw-back an </span><a href="https://www.firstbase.com/blog/7-reasons-why-companies-shouldnt-go-back-to-the-office-after-covid-19" rel="">inevitable future</a><span> the pandemic let us have early (basically the only positive outcome for our suffering here, if we didn’t keep it we’d have made it through all this for nothing). </span></p><p>There will of course be more nonsense: layoffs in the name of “RTO” using it as an excuse (which we know is a lie, and have research on linked above) and property owners who have no idea how the knowledge economy functions believing they get to dictate how corporate America works. Sane people will continue to point out the absurdity and hypocrisy. And for investors, employees or even just customers: remember any company doing “RTO” is a giant red flag they don't know what they're doing, are lying to the market, or hate their own employees. It’s really just layoffs by another name, because they can’t simply be honest.</p><p>In summary: remote work won, don’t let anyone gaslight you to believe otherwise.</p></div></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Implementing a ChatGPT-like LLM from scratch, step by step (507 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/rasbt/LLMs-from-scratch</link>
            <guid>39156778</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2024 16:19:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/rasbt/LLMs-from-scratch">https://github.com/rasbt/LLMs-from-scratch</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39156778">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          <nav aria-label="Global">
            <ul>
                <li>
      
      <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Actions&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Actions;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/actions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Actions</p><p>
        Automate any workflow
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Packages&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Packages;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/packages">
      
      <div>
        <p>Packages</p><p>
        Host and manage packages
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Security&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Security;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/security">
      
      <div>
        <p>Security</p><p>
        Find and fix vulnerabilities
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Codespaces&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Codespaces;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/codespaces">
      
      <div>
        <p>Codespaces</p><p>
        Instant dev environments
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Copilot&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Copilot;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/copilot">
      
      <div>
        <p>Copilot</p><p>
        Write better code with AI
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Code review&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Code review;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/code-review">
      
      <div>
        <p>Code review</p><p>
        Manage code changes
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Issues&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Issues;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/issues">
      
      <div>
        <p>Issues</p><p>
        Plan and track work
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Discussions&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Discussions;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/discussions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Discussions</p><p>
        Collaborate outside of code
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
</li>


                <li>
      
      
</li>


                <li>
      
      <div>
          <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Open Source&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to GitHub Sponsors&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:GitHub Sponsors;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/sponsors">
      
      <div>
        <p>GitHub Sponsors</p><p>
        Fund open source developers
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
          <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Open Source&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to The ReadME Project&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:The ReadME Project;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/readme">
      
      <div>
        <p>The ReadME Project</p><p>
        GitHub community articles
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
          
      </div>
</li>


                <li>
    <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header menu top item (logged out)&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Pricing&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Pricing;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/pricing">Pricing</a>
</li>

            </ul>
          </nav>

        <div>
                


<qbsearch-input data-scope="repo:rasbt/LLMs-from-scratch" data-custom-scopes-path="/search/custom_scopes" data-delete-custom-scopes-csrf="W_SB5lPLrcsNMnd_Q78TqMmfBKd5EMAe3wIHj6QGFQfWwQwFSwsbWdNvk1pPFI0d6kFw18tfTb-C0M9Dr0OBmQ" data-max-custom-scopes="10" data-header-redesign-enabled="false" data-initial-value="" data-blackbird-suggestions-path="/search/suggestions" data-jump-to-suggestions-path="/_graphql/GetSuggestedNavigationDestinations" data-current-repository="rasbt/LLMs-from-scratch" data-current-org="" data-current-owner="rasbt" data-logged-in="false" data-copilot-chat-enabled="false" data-blackbird-indexed-repo-csrf="<esi:include src=&quot;/_esi/rails_csrf_token_form_hidden?r=4g9paXT3BYYOlNVZpI%2FqCaNtGY3fCtLLK2TBaMkglFiEZdhZOcwmd5XNiTQS9VLEqLEoPdjdHCsmtf2FDU4A%2BfqQI5cJbNH4uUD4rsKcYsBZWM%2BAw6a2QK1qKGf2oFw1SCZdAD3H8uJnEbQdzApaQsIZ8hDgOv99kioirfnbTJs4FtQR8q%2Fwd%2Bz2dg6KFcTRgGbNHSqJ%2BhnP%2F4%2BjDPV7RrNcQhNP7dBcfSzAAXoGxBwX%2Fr%2BrydBNLHk69BDHktEQU6HgMjlbw9jZ0djKhPs%2FCn4wm0CPbzWAsw%2FZTX%2BsHNjEROj%2FHcXHBYp8eclvbjdzodbRbZpEgRMbW6cERiU5LEAEpzF7XLFxX1J0J0d6pPYu7RE1YX9REKHqgAIaDcdeeapkkRRyX75bv6YWu3B0nhJwWyIXDDKSIpkAQJjoH7YxmcrDwaoNSA6JyK1rV9tgava6KTM%2BZOPClIy6TKnj4vi7VbUdDSdCuxjVvuf3FzlJxd0DAnBR23f6u0rV0NUtzYZADpJqYxcWwXm10eU%2BZvl%2Bql3f8A%3D%3D--oDF8zXnq1%2Bb9BKy8--YEhmtPR%2BsCbQbAX9hr0AkQ%3D%3D&quot; />">
  <div data-modal-dialog-overlay="" data-action="click:qbsearch-input#searchInputContainerClicked">
  <modal-dialog data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleClose" data-target="qbsearch-input.searchSuggestionsDialog" role="dialog" id="search-suggestions-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="search-suggestions-dialog-header" data-view-component="true">
      <h2 id="search-suggestions-dialog-header">Search code, repositories, users, issues, pull requests...</h2>
    
</modal-dialog></div>
  
  <div>
    
<div data-modal-dialog-overlay="">
  <modal-dialog data-target="qbsearch-input.feedbackDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" role="dialog" id="feedback-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-disabled="true" aria-labelledby="feedback-dialog-title" aria-describedby="feedback-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="feedback-dialog-title">
        Provide feedback
      </h2>
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="feedback-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</modal-dialog></div>

    <custom-scopes data-target="qbsearch-input.customScopesManager">
    
<div data-modal-dialog-overlay="">
  <modal-dialog data-target="custom-scopes.customScopesModalDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" role="dialog" id="custom-scopes-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-disabled="true" aria-labelledby="custom-scopes-dialog-title" aria-describedby="custom-scopes-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        Saved searches
      </h2>
        <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-description">Use saved searches to filter your results more quickly</h2>
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</modal-dialog></div>
    </custom-scopes>
  </div>
</qbsearch-input>

            <p><a href="https://github.com/signup?ref_cta=Sign+up&amp;ref_loc=header+logged+out&amp;ref_page=%2F%3Cuser-name%3E%2F%3Crepo-name%3E&amp;source=header-repo&amp;source_repo=rasbt%2FLLMs-from-scratch" data-hydro-click="{&quot;event_type&quot;:&quot;authentication.click&quot;,&quot;payload&quot;:{&quot;location_in_page&quot;:&quot;site header menu&quot;,&quot;repository_id&quot;:null,&quot;auth_type&quot;:&quot;SIGN_UP&quot;,&quot;originating_url&quot;:&quot;https://github.com/rasbt/LLMs-from-scratch&quot;,&quot;user_id&quot;:null}}" data-hydro-click-hmac="e43903eb0afd93c1fb333a6bb44bedf17b3c6f6fa7f4f0d5f4f7c5ac5ee8b229" data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Sign up&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to sign up for account&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_page:/<user-name>/<repo-name>;ref_cta:Sign up;ref_loc:header logged out&quot;}">
              Sign up
            </a>
        </p></div>
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Scale of methane leaks from fossil fuel production and landfills exposed (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.sky.com/story/vast-scale-of-methane-leaks-from-fossil-fuel-production-and-landfill-sites-exposed-13023354</link>
            <guid>39156738</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2024 16:16:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://news.sky.com/story/vast-scale-of-methane-leaks-from-fossil-fuel-production-and-landfill-sites-exposed-13023354">https://news.sky.com/story/vast-scale-of-methane-leaks-from-fossil-fuel-production-and-landfill-sites-exposed-13023354</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39156738">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-component-name="sdc-article-body" data-highlight-intro="true">
      
      <p>The vast scale of methane leaks from fossil fuel production and landfill sites has been exposed by analysis carried out exclusively for Sky News.</p><p>Around 1,300 "super-emitters" of the potent greenhouse gas have been identified so far in 2023 by the monitoring company Kayrros, which uses satellites to detect plumes of the gas.</p>
<p>It looks for non-natural sources of methane - primarily gas wells, pipelines, coal mines and landfill sites.</p><p>According to the data, the largest oil and gas source was on the Cheleken Peninsula in Turkmenistan, where a leak from one facility is estimated to have peaked at 333 tonnes per hour in August.</p><p>At that rate the hourly release of methane was equivalent to the greenhouse gas emissions from a car driving around 38,000 miles.</p>
<p>Another leak, from a blown-out drilling well in Kazakhstan, released between 21 and 56 tonnes of the methane every hour for 153 days between June and November.</p><p>Coal is also a problem with one facility in Shanxi, China, peaking at around 181 tonnes an hour last February.</p><p>And the methane release from buried waste at a landfill site in Dhaka city in Bangladesh peaked at 822 tonnes an hour in April.</p><p>Antoine Rostand, co-founder of Kayrros, told Sky News being able to observe emissions from space means there is no hiding.</p>        
<p>"Previously we could measure the amount of methane in the atmosphere, but now we really know exactly where it's coming from," he said.</p><p>"Which country, which company, which assets are emitting methane in the atmosphere."</p><p>Kayrros's data shows Turkmenistan had higher methane emissions than any other nation, followed by the United States, India, Russia and Pakistan.</p><p>Methane is the natural gas burned by boilers and other appliances in people's homes.</p><p>But if it is released without being burned, often during maintenance on pipelines, it acts as a heat "bomb" in the atmosphere.</p><p>The gas causes 80 times more global warming as the same amount of carbon dioxide over a 20-year period.</p> <div aria-label="Consent required" data-component-name="sdc-article-custom-markup" data-aspect-ratio="16/9" data-consent="pending" data-vendor-name="spreaker">
        <p><span>Spreaker</span>
            <span data-show-on-fallback="false">
                This content is provided by <span>Spreaker</span>, which may be using cookies and other technologies.
                To show you this content, we need your permission to use cookies.
                You can use the buttons below to amend your preferences to enable <span>Spreaker</span> cookies or to allow those cookies just once.
                You can change your settings at any time via the <a href="#privacy-options">Privacy Options</a>.
            </span>
            <span data-show-on-fallback="true">
                Unfortunately we have been unable to verify if you have consented to <span>Spreaker</span> cookies.
                To view this content you can use the button below to allow <span>Spreaker</span> cookies for this session only.
            </span></p>
    </div><p><strong><a href="https://podfollow.com/skynewsclimatecast" target="_blank">Click to subscribe to ClimateCast with Tom Heap wherever you get your podcasts</a></strong></p><p>But it also represents a huge opportunity for bending the curve on rising temperatures. Because it only persists in the atmosphere for around a decade rather than several centuries, as in the case of carbon dioxide, turning off the tap on emissions would have a rapid impact.</p><p>The United States has announced new rules for fossil fuel companies requiring them to monitor and fix leaks, which should reduce methane emissions by 58 million tonnes between 2024 and 2038.</p><p>Mr Rostand said the rules are overdue.</p><p>"The have the technology, they have the money, they know exactly what to do," he said.</p><p>"They're almost lacking any kind of overall regulation.</p><p>"A lot of players are doing a bit but some are not. And this is where regulation plays, because then it will put every single producer on an equal footing."</p>     <a href="https://news.sky.com/download-app" target="blank" data-tracking-label="ui-app-promo-download-link" data-type="" data-component-name="ui-app-promo">
        
    </a>


<p><strong>Read more:</strong><br><strong><a href="https://news.sky.com/story/previous-decade-hottest-on-record-with-polar-ice-melting-faster-than-in-the-last-century-13023175" target="_blank">Previous decade 'hottest on record'</a></strong><br><strong><a href="https://news.sky.com/story/china-continues-to-back-coal-plants-despite-world-leading-investment-in-renewables-13020377" target="_blank">Why China continues to invest in coal</a></strong></p><p>So far 150 countries have signed up to the Global Methane Pledge, a commitment to reduce emissions by 30% by 2030.</p><p>If it is achieved it could reduce the global average temperature by 0.2C and prevent 255,000 premature deaths from extreme heat, according to the Pledge text.</p><p>The Kayrros data reveals there are no methane leaks in Europe, but Mr Rostand said the UK and other countries should put more pressure on suppliers of imported natural gas to stop releasing it into the atmosphere.</p><p>"It's really a complete waste, because companies can sell it," he said.</p><p>"It has an economic value, it's easy to fix. It's the elephant in the room, the low hanging fruit."</p>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Researchers demonstrate rapid 3D printing with liquid metal (117 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.mit.edu/2024/researchers-demonstrate-rapid-3d-printing-liquid-metal-0125</link>
            <guid>39156463</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2024 15:43:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://news.mit.edu/2024/researchers-demonstrate-rapid-3d-printing-liquid-metal-0125">https://news.mit.edu/2024/researchers-demonstrate-rapid-3d-printing-liquid-metal-0125</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39156463">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          

            <p>MIT researchers have developed an additive manufacturing technique that can print rapidly with liquid metal, producing large-scale parts like table legs and chair frames in a matter of minutes.</p>

<p>Their technique, called liquid metal printing (LMP), involves depositing molten aluminum along a predefined path into a bed of tiny glass beads. The aluminum quickly hardens into a 3D structure.</p>        

      </div><div>
          

            <p>The researchers say LMP is at least 10 times faster than a comparable metal additive manufacturing process, and the procedure to heat and melt the metal is more efficient than some other methods.</p>

<p>The technique does sacrifice resolution for speed and scale. While it can print components that are larger than those typically made with slower additive techniques, and at a lower cost, it cannot achieve high resolutions.</p>

<p>For instance, parts produced with LMP would be suitable for some applications in architecture, construction, and industrial design, where components of larger structures often don’t require extremely fine details. It could also be utilized effectively for rapid prototyping with recycled or scrap metal.</p>

<p>In a recent study, the researchers demonstrated the procedure by printing aluminum frames and parts for tables and chairs which were strong enough to withstand postprint machining. They showed how components made with LMP could be combined with high-resolution processes and additional materials to create functional furniture.</p>

<p>“This is a completely different direction in how we think about metal manufacturing that has some huge advantages. It has downsides, too. But most of our built world — the things around us like tables, chairs, and buildings — doesn’t need extremely high resolution. Speed and scale, and also repeatability and energy consumption, are all important metrics,” says Skylar Tibbits, associate professor in the Department of Architecture and co-director of the Self-Assembly Lab, who is senior author of a <a href="https://selfassemblylab.mit.edu/s/ACADIA-23-Proceedings_LMP.pdf" target="_blank">paper</a> introducing LMP.</p>

<p>Tibbits is joined on the paper by lead author Zain Karsan SM ’23, who is now a PhD student at ETH Zurich; as well as Kimball Kaiser SM ’22 and Jared Laucks, a research scientist and lab co-director. The research was presented at the Association for Computer Aided Design in Architecture Conference and recently published in the association’s proceedings.</p>

<p><strong>Significant speedup</strong></p>

<p>One method for printing with metals that is common in construction and architecture, called wire arc additive manufacturing (WAAM), is able to produce large, low-resolution structures, but these can be susceptible to cracking and warping because some portions must be remelted during the printing process.</p>

<p>LMP, on the other hand, keeps the material molten throughout the process, avoiding some of the structural issues caused by remelting.</p>

<p>Drawing on the group’s previous work on <a href="https://www.rapidliquidprint.co/" target="_blank">rapid liquid printing with rubber</a>, the researchers built a machine that melts aluminum, holds the molten metal, and deposits it through a nozzle at high speeds. Large-scale parts can be printed in just a few seconds, and then the molten aluminum cools in several minutes.</p>

<p>“Our process rate is really high, but it is also very difficult to control. It is more or less like opening a faucet. You have a big volume of material to melt, which takes some time, but once you get that to melt, it is just like opening a tap. That enables us to print these geometries very quickly,” Karsan explains.</p>

<p>The team chose aluminum because it is commonly used in construction and can be recycled cheaply and efficiently.</p>

<p>Bread loaf-sized pieces of aluminum are deposited into an electric furnace, “which is basically like a scaled-up toaster,” Karsan adds. Metal coils inside the furnace heat the metal to 700 degrees Celsius, slightly above aluminum’s 660-degree melting point.</p>

<p>The aluminum is held at a high temperature in a graphite crucible, and then molten material is gravity-fed through a ceramic nozzle into a print bed along a preset path. They found that the larger the amount of aluminum they could melt, the faster the printer can go.</p>

<p>“Molten aluminum will destroy just about everything in its path. We started with stainless steel nozzles and then moved to titanium before we ended up with ceramic. But even ceramic nozzles can clog because the heating is not always entirely uniform in the nozzle tip,” Karsan says.</p>

<p>By injecting the molten material directly into a granular substance, the researchers don’t need to print supports to hold the aluminum structure as it takes shape.&nbsp;</p>

<p><strong>Perfecting the process</strong></p>

<p>They experimented with a number of materials to fill the print bed, including graphite powders and salt, before selecting 100-micron glass beads. The tiny glass beads, which can withstand the extremely high temperature of molten aluminum, act as a neutral suspension so the metal can cool quickly.</p>

<p>“The glass beads are so fine that they feel like silk in your hand. The powder is so small that it doesn’t really change the surface characteristics of the printed object,” Tibbits says.</p>

<p>The amount of molten material held in the crucible, the depth of the print bed, and the size and shape of the nozzle have the biggest impacts on the geometry of the final object.</p>

<p>For instance, parts of the object with larger diameters are printed first, since the amount of aluminum the nozzle dispenses tapers off as the crucible empties. Changing the depth of the nozzle alters the thickness of the metal structure.</p>

<p>To aid in the LMP process, the researchers developed a numerical model to estimate the amount of material that will be deposited into the print bed at a given time.</p>

<p>Because the nozzle pushes into the glass bead powder, the researchers can’t watch the molten aluminum as it is deposited, so they needed a way to simulate what should be going on at certain points in the printing process, Tibbits explains.</p>

<p>They used LMP to rapidly produce aluminum frames with variable thicknesses, which were durable enough to withstand machining processes like milling and boring. They demonstrated a combination of LMP and these post-processing techniques to make chairs and a table composed of lower-resolution, rapidly printed aluminum parts and other components, like wood pieces.</p>

<p>Moving forward, the researchers want to keep iterating on the machine so they can enable consistent heating in the nozzle to prevent material from sticking, and also achieve better control over the flow of molten material. But larger nozzle diameters can lead to irregular prints, so there are still technical challenges to overcome.</p>

<p>“If we could make this machine something that people could actually use to melt down recycled aluminum and print parts, that would be a game-changer in metal manufacturing. Right now, it is not reliable enough to do that, but that’s the goal,” Tibbits says.</p>

<p>“At Emeco, we come from the world of very analog manufacturing, so seeing the liquid metal printing creating nuanced geometries with the potential for fully structural parts was really compelling,” says Jaye Buchbinder, who leads business development for the furniture company Emeco and was not involved with this work. “The liquid metal printing really walks the line in terms of ability to produce metal parts in custom geometries while maintaining quick turnaround that you don’t normally get in other printing or forming technologies. There is definitely potential for the technology to revolutionize the way metal printing and metal forming are currently handled.”</p>

<p>Additional researchers who worked on this project include Kimball Kaiser, Jeremy Bilotti, Bjorn Sparrman, Schendy Kernizan, and Maria Esteban Casanas.</p>

<p>This research was funded, in part, by Aisin Group, Amada Global, and Emeco.</p>        

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Disney Unveils the HoloTile Floor, Inching Us Closer to a Real-Life Holodeck (652 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ign.com/articles/disney-unveils-the-holotile-floor-inching-us-closer-to-a-real-life-holodeck</link>
            <guid>39156444</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2024 15:41:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.ign.com/articles/disney-unveils-the-holotile-floor-inching-us-closer-to-a-real-life-holodeck">https://www.ign.com/articles/disney-unveils-the-holotile-floor-inching-us-closer-to-a-real-life-holodeck</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39156444">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><h2 data-cy="article-sub-headline">This floor is made up of a bunch of tiles that all work to keep people in the center of them.</h2></div><section><p>Alongside announcing that Lanny Smoot will be the first Disney employee besides Walt to be inducted into the National Inventors Hall of Fame, Disney also shared one of his newest projects called the HoloTile floor, which just may be a game changer for VR and could bring us ever closer to experiencing the Holodeck from Star Trek.</p><p>Disney shared the news and <a href="https://youtu.be/68YMEmaF0rs?si=NJuK14JuvqIKzsa0&amp;t=182" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">a video of the HoloTile floor in action</a> in <a href="https://thewaltdisneycompany.com/lanny-smoot-to-be-the-first-disney-imagineer-inducted-into-the-national-inventors-hall-of-fame/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">a blog celebrating Smoot,</a> who holds over 100 patents and secured 74 of those during his 25 years at The Walt Disney Company.</p><p>As for the HoloTile floor itself, it is described by Disney as the "world’s first multi-person, omni-directional, modular, expandable, treadmill floor." You have to think of it like a floor made of many tiles that do all they can to keep people or objects in the center of them. This could allow people to "have a shared virtual reality (VR) experience, walk an unlimited distance in any direction, and never collide or walk off its surface."</p><p>Many of us have experienced the joy that can be a really stellar VR experience, but there are always certain limitations to the immersion that comes with it. While it's great to be able to visit The Black Spire Outpost on the planet of Batuu in Star Wars: Tales from the Galaxy's Edge in VR, you also run the risk of being pulled back to Earth when you bump into your couch and can only move a few feet here and there.</p><p>With the HoloTile floor, Disney appears to be envisioning a future where those limitations are no more and we can explore wide environments and feel that we are actually walking or running through them despite us staying mostly in one place. For those Star Trek fans out there, this sounds a lot like the promise of the Holodeck, a smallish-room that could virtually take our favorite crews wherever they wanted for some fun and relaxation between missions when it wasn't malfunctioning and trying to murder them. </p><p>The HoloTile floor can do more than just let people walk on it, as it can also move objects around. <a href="https://youtu.be/68YMEmaF0rs?si=ntNM2LGdnNktkZQE&amp;t=257" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">In the video,</a> we see an object being moved around the floor and an arm extending at the corner of the screen, as if they were using the Force to move an object. Yes, the possibilities of this are making a Star Wars fan like myself VERY happy. </p><output><figure><a href="https://assets-prd.ignimgs.com/2024/01/23/floor-1706037202625.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img decoding="async" alt="Lanny Smoot on the HoloTile Floor. Image Credit: The Walt Disney Company" src="https://assets-prd.ignimgs.com/2024/01/23/floor-1706037202625.png?width=1280&amp;fit=bounds&amp;height=720&amp;quality=20&amp;dpr=0.05"></a><figcaption>Lanny Smoot on the HoloTile Floor. Image Credit: The Walt Disney Company</figcaption></figure></output><p>The applications of the HoloTile floor also extend beyond virtual reality, as Disney notes "The HoloTile floor can also be an insert in a theatrical stage, allowing performers to move and dance in new ways, or stage props and structures to move around or appear to set themselves up."</p><p>However, it's important not to get too excited yet as Smoot notes "we don't know yet where that will be used." So, while we may have to wait a while to see what this tech could become, its an exciting glimpse into the future that could hopefully one day change how we experience our favorite universes in Disney Parks, our homes, and beyond.</p><p><em>Adam Bankhurst is a news writer for IGN. You can follow him on Twitter </em><a href="https://twitter.com/AdamBankhurst" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>@AdamBankhurst</em></a><em> and on </em><a href="https://www.twitch.tv/AdamBankhurst" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>Twitch.</em></a></p></section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Pentagon ex-UFO chief says conspiracy theorists in government drive spending (121 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/world/2024/jan/27/sean-kirkpatrick-pentagon-ufo-conspiracy-theory-myths</link>
            <guid>39156388</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2024 15:35:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2024/jan/27/sean-kirkpatrick-pentagon-ufo-conspiracy-theory-myths">https://www.theguardian.com/world/2024/jan/27/sean-kirkpatrick-pentagon-ufo-conspiracy-theory-myths</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39156388">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p>Conspiracy theorists working for and within the US government are perpetuating myths about <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/ufos" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">UFOs</a> that millions of taxpayer dollars are then spent looking into, a “self-licking ice cream cone”, according to the Pentagon’s former chief investigator of unidentified anomalous phenomena (UAP).</p><p>Sean Kirkpatrick made the claim in a podcast this week after stepping down last month as the first director of the defense department’s <a href="https://www.aaro.mil/" data-link-name="in body link">all-domain anomaly resolution office</a> (Aaro). It was set up in 2022 to collate military reports of UAP sightings and to be more transparent about what the government knows.</p><figure id="d1ef49b4-37af-4ba5-8312-51bddaeed1c8" data-spacefinder-role="richLink" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.RichLinkBlockElement"><gu-island name="RichLinkComponent" priority="feature" deferuntil="idle" props="{&quot;richLinkIndex&quot;:2,&quot;element&quot;:{&quot;_type&quot;:&quot;model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.RichLinkBlockElement&quot;,&quot;prefix&quot;:&quot;Related: &quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;US Congress passes stripped-down measure to release UFO records&quot;,&quot;elementId&quot;:&quot;d1ef49b4-37af-4ba5-8312-51bddaeed1c8&quot;,&quot;role&quot;:&quot;richLink&quot;,&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2023/dec/15/ufo-records-release-congress&quot;},&quot;ajaxUrl&quot;:&quot;https://api.nextgen.guardianapps.co.uk&quot;,&quot;format&quot;:{&quot;display&quot;:0,&quot;theme&quot;:0,&quot;design&quot;:0}}" config="{&quot;renderingTarget&quot;:&quot;Web&quot;,&quot;darkModeAvailable&quot;:false}"></gu-island></figure><p>Aaro’s first comprehensive historical record report, which has been submitted to Congress and is set for publication later this year, contains no evidence of the existence of alien life, or any government cover-up, Kirkpatrick says.</p><p>But many lawmakers, he insists, are only too happy to embrace unsubstantiated stories circulated by “a core group of people” about secret government UFO research programs. Those include <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2023/jun/06/whistleblower-ufo-alien-tech-spacecraft" data-link-name="in body link">startling claims</a> from the former US intelligence official and whistleblower David Grusch last year about intact alien vehicles and non-human “biologics”, or biological matter, stored at a remote facility.</p><p>“They’re some of the same people that have been working behind the scenes with Congress to write legislation,” Kirkpatrick told the <a href="https://www.peterbergen.com/podcast/#episode38" data-link-name="in body link">In the Room With Peter Bergen</a> podcast.</p><p>“They’re the same people that worked with a US company and the US army to explore a piece of material that they claim was a UAP and really is a piece of missile casing from the 1950s. They’re the same people that have been influencing some of these whistleblowers who have come forward to say: ‘Hey, I don’t have any first-hand evidence, but all these people are telling me this.’”</p><p>Kirkpatrick declined to identify the people by name, but agreed with Bergen’s observation that “the actual conspiracy is being carried out by a group of true believers themselves to get the government involved in the business of investigating aliens”.</p><p>“That is a self-licking ice cream cone, exactly,” Kirkpatrick said. “The best thing that could have happened in this job is I found the aliens, and I could have rolled them out, but there’s none. There is no evidence of extraterrestrials. There is no evidence of aliens, and there’s no evidence of the government conspiracy.”</p><p>Kirkpatrick said in a resignation essay <a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/heres-what-i-learned-as-the-u-s-governments-ufo-hunter/" data-link-name="in body link">published by Scientific American</a> last week that he feared lawmakers had succumbed to “conspiracy-driven decision-making” and sensationalism in their rush to “<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/live/2023/jul/26/ufo-hearing-congress-david-grusch-whistleblower-live-updates?filterKeyEvents=false&amp;page=with:block-64c12aaa8f0890ba7a1f7a9f#block-64c12aaa8f0890ba7a1f7a9f" data-link-name="in body link">uncover the cover-up</a>”.</p><p>“Worrisome is the willingness of some to make judgments and take actions on these stories without having seen or even requested supporting evidence, an omission that is all the more problematic when the claims are so extraordinary,” he wrote.</p><p>“Some members of Congress prefer to <a href="https://www.c-span.org/video/?529468-1/republican-oversight-committee-members-upcoming-unidentified-aerial-phenomena" data-link-name="in body link">opine about aliens to the press</a> rather than get an evidence-based briefing on the matter. Members have a responsibility to exhibit critical-thinking skills instead of seeking the spotlight.”</p><p>His frustration was apparent in his conversation with Bergen. He said his department’s mission to use a “rigorous scientific framework and a data-driven approach” to collate and evaluate UFO reports and sightings going back decades had been hampered by misrepresentations, half-truths and other snippets of misinformation from unreliable sources.</p><p>“You’ve got people that talk to people who come in to tell the story, or tell the media, and other people come in, but it turns out none of them have any first-hand evidence or knowledge,” Kirkpatrick said.</p><figure data-spacefinder-role="inline" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.NewsletterSignupBlockElement"><a data-ignore="global-link-styling" href="#EmailSignup-skip-link-14">skip past newsletter promotion</a><p id="EmailSignup-skip-link-14" tabindex="0" aria-label="after newsletter promotion" role="note">after newsletter promotion</p></figure><p>“They’re all relaying stories that they’ve heard from other people. And if you track where all those people know each other, it all goes back to the same core group of people.”</p><p>What his team was able to deduce, Kirkpatrick said, was that at least 90% of recorded UFO sightings, including some videos of military encounters <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/apr/27/pentagon-releases-three-ufo-videos-taken-by-us-navy-pilots" data-link-name="in body link">declassified by the Pentagon</a> in recent years, have a perfectly logical explanation.</p><p>“When you dig into those kinds of observations, and we had hundreds, you go back and work with the pilot, you work with the sensor, and you reconstruct the entire engagement, nine times out of 10 or more that turns into an optical illusion that we call <a href="https://www.space.com/30417-parallax.html" data-link-name="in body link">parallax</a>,” he said.</p><p>“Most of the times when we can’t give an explanation, it is because there is a lack of data, and by that I mean consistent, solid, recorded data that you can put into a computer and you can do analysis on.”</p><p>Even so, Kirkpatrick said, there are those unlikely to ever accept scientific explanations.</p><p>“There is absolutely nothing that I’m going to do, say or produce evidentially that is going to make the true believers convert,” he said.</p><p>“It is basically a religion, a religious belief that transcends critical thinking and rational thought.”</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Sxmo: Linux tiling window manager for phones (299 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://sxmo.org/</link>
            <guid>39155103</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2024 12:49:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://sxmo.org/">https://sxmo.org/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39155103">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>


<p>
    “minimal<em>.</em> mobile<em>.</em> hackable<em>.</em>”
</p>

<p><a href="https://framatube.org/w/dHBrnMQeEt8Mq82KxV4zKm?start=0s">
    <img src="https://sxmo.org/img/libreplanet.jpeg" alt="Image link to libreplanet video">
</a></p><p>S<em>x</em>mo is a minimalist environment for Linux mobile devices</p>

<p><strong>Note:</strong> Your old Android phone/tablet may work with Sxmo with some minor configuration!
                              For information about device support <a href="https://sxmo.org/deviceprofile">click here</a></p>
<div>
    <div>
        <h3>Simple menu-driven interface</h3>
        <ul>
            <li>Uses <a href="https://suckless.org/">suckless</a> tools (dwm, dmenu, st, etc) or Wayland tools (sway, bemenu, foot, etc.)</li>
            <li>Augmented touch and gesture support</li>
            <li>Menu-driven interface that can also be controlled with hardware buttons</li>
            <li>Community sourced context menu that changes according to the active application (CLI or GUI)</li>
        </ul>
        <blockquote>
            “I really like this; I've been using this for about a week now.
            I appreciate the developers' willingness to design something
            with a slight learning curve that works very well, and in
            part because of this. This demonstrates a level of respect
            for their end users which I value. I am not saying that this
            mobile computing environment is hard to use, I am saying
            that it is highly efficient and effective, and that I have
            learned things by using it because the people who made this
            do not condescend through oversimplification.”
            <p>
            
            — KoryMac
        </p></blockquote>
    </div>
    <p><img src="https://sxmo.org/img/sxmo_dmenu.jpg" alt="Screenshot of dmenu">
    </p>
    <div>
        <h3>SSH as a first class citizen</h3>
        <ul>
            <li>Send texts via ssh using your favorite text editor (vis, emacs, vim, etc.)</li>
            <li>Read notifications, texts, etc.</li>
            <li>Access bluetooth, wifi menus</li>
        </ul>
        <blockquote>
            “Being able to SSH into my phone and treat it just like any
            other Alpine Linux machine adds a tremendous amount of value.
            Leaving it in my pocket and using it from my computer is very
            convenient. I don't have to treat my phone like an alien in my
            otherwise uniform computing setup anymore.”
            <p>
            
            — Drew Devault,	FLOSS pioneer and creator of Sourcehut and Sway
        </p></blockquote>
    </div>
    <p><img src="https://sxmo.org/img/sxmo_ssh_text.jpg" alt="Screenshot of vismenu on ssh">
    </p>
    <div>
        <h3>Everything is Scriptable</h3>
        <ul>
            <li>Launch user defined scripts at phone calls, texts, etc.</li>
            <li>Bind certain scripts to gestures using lisgd</li>
            <li>Bind device's physical buttons (single/double/triple click) to trigger scripts</li>
            <li>Plain text modem logs, contact list, and sms texts</li>
        </ul>
        <blockquote>
            “Phone calls and text messages are routed through shell scripts,
            a feature I didn’t know I needed until I saw it in action.
            Sxmo probably is the killer app for running an actual Linux
            distribution on your phone.”
            <p>
            
            — Ariadne Conill, Alpine Linux Security Team Chair
        </p></blockquote>
    </div>
    <p><img src="https://sxmo.org/img/sxmo_vim_hook.jpg" alt="Screenshot of vim on sxmo">
    </p>
    <div>
        <h3>Use the same <span hint="free open source software">FOSS</span> apps you use on the desktop</h3>
        <ul>
            <li>No locked-down app ecosystem</li>
            <li>Runs on traditional Linux distributions like <a href="https://alpinelinux.org/">Alpine Linux</a> and <a href="https://postmarketos.org/">postmarketOS</a> optimized for mobile devices</li>
            <li>Use terminal-based applications on a smartphone</li>
        </ul>
        <blockquote>
            “Running a tiling WM on your phone sounds like a
            stupid idea... until you discover #Sxmo. The whole thing is
            simple but amazing - it takes one or two days to get used
            to it, but then you know it inside out. Thanks to the
            built-in extensibility and simple codebase, you can change
            everything to your liking. This interface and its skilled
            community have become a great asset in
            the wider #linux smartphone ecosystem!”
            <p>
            
            — Oliver Smith, Creator of postmarketOS
        </p></blockquote>
    </div>
    <p><img src="https://sxmo.org/img/sxmo_reddit_pmos.jpg" alt="Screenshot of firefox on sxmo with reddit">
    </p>
</div>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I am the cheapest bastard in indie games (2019) (107 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://jeff-vogel.blogspot.com/2019/08/i-am-cheapest-bastard-in-indie-games.html</link>
            <guid>39154929</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2024 12:17:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://jeff-vogel.blogspot.com/2019/08/i-am-cheapest-bastard-in-indie-games.html">http://jeff-vogel.blogspot.com/2019/08/i-am-cheapest-bastard-in-indie-games.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39154929">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post-body-6614953500005566247" itemprop="description articleBody">
<table><tbody>
<tr><td><a href="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-9-Gdns-Es3M/XWRRO7E4TWI/AAAAAAAABLs/_cq5tUWb_04Ap4p__J44B4ppFvHMFiHWACLcBGAs/s1600/QW%2BSS.jpg" imageanchor="1"><img data-original-height="900" data-original-width="1600" height="225" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-9-Gdns-Es3M/XWRRO7E4TWI/AAAAAAAABLs/_cq5tUWb_04Ap4p__J44B4ppFvHMFiHWACLcBGAs/s400/QW%2BSS.jpg" width="400"></a></td></tr>
<tr><td>A Queen's Wish screenshot. Note that I use game art that I like to look at. This is necessary because I'll be staring at it for years, and I don't want to go mad.</td></tr>
</tbody></table>
<p>
A week ago, I put up a blog post called <a href="https://jeff-vogel.blogspot.com/2019/08/why-all-of-our-games-look-like-crap.html">"Why All My Games Look Like Crap."</a> It really blew up. A lot of people read it. Some were highly supportive. Others took precious time out of their days to let me know I am a gigantic, gigantic bozo.</p><p>

Thanks to all! When you're trying to get attention for a small indie game, there's no such thing as bad publicity.</p><p>

Basically, my blog post said, "Some people like my art, but I am still super-bad at art. Always have been. Fixing the problem costs time and cash, and I don't have any of either to spare. So that's why our games look bad."</p><p>

I got a lot of questions about this. Good questions. Why can't I afford art direction? How much does art cost? Why don't I do this or that smart thing? So that's why I'm writing this. I want to answer the good questions.</p><p>

So I am going to say some stuff about making and budgeting video games and why I am a bozo and why I am cursed to be a bozo forever. Along the way, I'm going to explain to you the whole indie games biz, from soup to nuts. If you like indie games, I think you might find how I survive interesting.</p><p>

You see, I am the cheapest bastard in indie games.</p><table><tbody>
<tr><td><a href="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-CGlnE7_Nzks/XWRRpRdb0KI/AAAAAAAABL0/rcwD-u_3diM3fLv9SdGiapSEhUC_vKPBwCLcBGAs/s1600/big-cat-clipart-of-a-rich-tiger-holding-a-bag-of-money-by-hit-toon-4.jpg" imageanchor="1"><img data-original-height="620" data-original-width="600" height="400" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-CGlnE7_Nzks/XWRRpRdb0KI/AAAAAAAABL0/rcwD-u_3diM3fLv9SdGiapSEhUC_vKPBwCLcBGAs/s400/big-cat-clipart-of-a-rich-tiger-holding-a-bag-of-money-by-hit-toon-4.jpg" width="386"></a></td></tr>
<tr><td>I don't have this much money. And, please, I beg you, support <a href="http://bigcatclipart.com/">bigcatclipart.com</a> and the good work they do.</td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<p><b>I've Been Doing This For 25 Years</b></p><p>

Some people really get annoyed when I bring this up. It's as if having long experience and a huge body of work gives my words some sort of weight and my advice some value.</p><p>

Well, it does. Do you realize how few people have turned a good profit for that long in this blood sport business? I am rarer than a unicorn made of bigfoots!</p><p>

The indie games business is hard, one of the toughest there is.</p><p>

<b>Why Is It So Hard To Make Money In Indie Games?</b></p><p>

What do you think the going rate for the best indie games ever made is?</p><p>

Did you guess 'Free'? You're right! Go to the Epic Game Store every week and they'll hand you the best indie games, games way better than mine, for free!</p><p>

That not enough? Join the Humble Monthly Bundle. For just $12/month, they'll send you 6-7 games every month, plus you can also download over 60(!) games in their "Humble Trove." They're good games.</p><p>

So the competition is intense, and you can never ever match your superiors on price, ie free. That makes for tough business, friend.</p><table><tbody>
<tr><td><a href="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-IBv08R44oKE/XWRSJefoKxI/AAAAAAAABL8/fL6Cffbmn0s105OdVrAywD69_tqyEkkvACLcBGAs/s1600/celeste.0.jpeg" imageanchor="1"><img data-original-height="800" data-original-width="1200" height="266" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-IBv08R44oKE/XWRSJefoKxI/AAAAAAAABL8/fL6Cffbmn0s105OdVrAywD69_tqyEkkvACLcBGAs/s400/celeste.0.jpeg" width="400"></a></td></tr>
<tr><td>Award-winning. Critical darling. Huge hit. <a href="https://www.gamespot.com/videos/two-fantastic-epic-games-store-freebies-announced-/2300-6450792/">Free.</a>&nbsp;How do you plan to compete?</td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<p><b>So How Can You Survive?</b></p><p>

Simple. You provide something nobody else can ever provide. Something cool and distinctive that people will rather pay money for your game than get someone else's for free.</p><p>

Consider me. I'm an OK programmer. I'm not good at art and visual stuff, and I haven't been since I was a kid.</p><p>

But I can write well. I make good settings and stories, my spelling and grammar are ok, I make addicting game systems, and my systems and stories blend really well. THAT is the product I sell.</p><p>

I'm in the business of selling Jeff Vogel games. And just like Van Gogh couldn't paint a Renoir, or vice versa, nobody else can make a Jeff Vogel game. Larian Studios is a great company with great resources that makes great products. However, no matter how hard they try, they can never make a game one of my fans will mistake for one of mine.</p><p>

Fortunately for me, there are people who really like Jeff Vogel games, and only we sell them. So we have a business.</p><p>

However, that's not all it takes to stay in business. I can get people to buy my games, sure. But I need to turn a profit.</p><p>

That is why I need to be the cheapest bastard in indie games.</p><table><tbody>
<tr><td><a href="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-AfyC5niox6Y/XWRSk0lNyYI/AAAAAAAABME/ig3q6bVWZKEGRxwHgjDPjn6JlmeYdBpvgCLcBGAs/s1600/a754a1bd-50c0-42cb-a237-10b61315bcbd.jpg" imageanchor="1"><img data-original-height="520" data-original-width="780" height="266" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-AfyC5niox6Y/XWRSk0lNyYI/AAAAAAAABME/ig3q6bVWZKEGRxwHgjDPjn6JlmeYdBpvgCLcBGAs/s400/a754a1bd-50c0-42cb-a237-10b61315bcbd.jpg" width="400"></a></td></tr>
<tr><td>You can find a dedicated fan base for any imaginable art style. That's indie games, baby!</td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<p><b>Let's See Some Numbers</b></p><p>

I got into this kerfuffle talking about how my games look ugly, and I'll get back to that. First, though, let's look at budgets.</p><p>

Our next game is Queen's Wish: The Conqueror. We spent about 20 months on it. For it to have a chance to pay for the time we spent creating it, it needs to make, after Steam and GOG.com and Apple and itch.io and Kickstarter take their cuts, about $200000 US.</p><p>

(It will take years for the game to earn this money, but we'll be earning money from back catalog at the same time, so it evens out.)</p><p>

Why that amount? Because that is what long experience has told us we are most likely to get. Low-budget high-text, thinky RPGs don't become giant hits, but we have a loyal audience, so we'll get decent sales.</p><p>

Then we take out, say, $60000 for business expenses and insurance. Then we spend X dollars on art (the key factor we are discussing here). We use what is left to pay our salaries (to get baubles like food, clothing, and shelter).</p><p>

So our earnings for 20 months of hard work is, let's say, $140000 minus art expenses. Keep your eye on the ball.</p><p>

<b>Twenty Months? That's Not Very Long To Write a Game</b></p><p>

No! It's not! Whenever I ship I game, I immediately begin the race against time to write another game before our bank account runs out. Twenty months is actually an unusually long time for us, but Queen's Wish is an all-new games system and engine, so it needs it. I normally need 12-14 months.</p><p>

By the way, for people who asked me why I don't just learn to do better art myself, this is why. To learn to do better art, I'd need to spend at least 6-12 months. (To think it takes less is insulting to artists.) I just don't have the time to not be writing games.</p><table><tbody>
<tr><td><a href="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-D8KHmCKapg0/XWRS1t8ayoI/AAAAAAAABMM/EjzSxjqNfeYGSiAtRbzFkASJ-wUTizEXQCLcBGAs/s1600/shapinghall.jpg" imageanchor="1"><img data-original-height="428" data-original-width="578" height="295" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-D8KHmCKapg0/XWRS1t8ayoI/AAAAAAAABMM/EjzSxjqNfeYGSiAtRbzFkASJ-wUTizEXQCLcBGAs/s400/shapinghall.jpg" width="400"></a></td></tr>
<tr><td>I made the frames and button background for this interface. It was years before someone say, "Um, Jeff, are you sure this isn't a little too green?"</td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<p><b>So Back To Art</b></p><p>

After I wrote the last blog post, a lot of people wanted to make sure that, "Oh yeah, pal. No matter how bad your art is? It's WAY worse than that." The most common complaint I got is that there is no unified style and color palette. My art looks like it was cobbled together from like 20 different artists, blended together imperfectly by my nonexistent Photoshop stills.</p><p>

Well, I've got news for you. Our art WAS literally cobbled together from like 20 different artists, blended together imperfectly by my nonexistent Photoshop stills.</p><p>

Here's the thing. Many people don't notice this. Some notice, but it doesn't bother them. But for skilled artists and people with an eye for this sort of thing, looking at the icons I use makes their faces do this ...</p><table><tbody>
<tr><td><a href="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-ptGM8o1QxDs/XWRTGDjGdBI/AAAAAAAABMU/h1aKDZ7BcQM2lvEa_mk3W6GvuWqXKSINACLcBGAs/s1600/nazi.png" imageanchor="1"><img data-original-height="298" data-original-width="364" height="326" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-ptGM8o1QxDs/XWRTGDjGdBI/AAAAAAAABMU/h1aKDZ7BcQM2lvEa_mk3W6GvuWqXKSINACLcBGAs/s400/nazi.png" width="400"></a></td></tr>
<tr><td>Hello darkness, my old friend.</td></tr>
</tbody></table>
<p>
Sorry about that.</p><p>

<b>How I "Art Direct"</b></p><p>

When I do what might laughably be called "art design", my first step is to cobble together any floor/terrain objects that will function. I pull art from old games, from https://opengameart.org/, from sites that license icons for cheap, from anywhere I can get icons that will function. I use Photoshop trickery to make it blend as much as possible.</p><p>

Eventually, I will reach a point where I need stuff that I can't use online resources for, stuff that needs to be custom-made for how I want the game to look. Then I go to freelancers.</p><p>

I pay for bespoke art for terrain types with different looks that need to fit the engine, like tables and statues. Also, for terrain that I have my own unique formats for, like walls and doors and gates.</p><p>

My artists work very hard to make sure the icons they do blend well with each other and look great. They do awesome work. Then I defile it by mixing it in with all the other weird stuff I find. If anything looks bad in my games, blame me! Seriously!</p><p>

Doing the art this way costs around $40000. That leaves $100000 of earnings. For 20 months of work, that's pretty thin, but I'll live with it. I'll make up for it with the next two games in the series, which will take a lot less time to write. (Plus, eventually, remasters. I will be squeezing pennies out of Queen's Wish for literally decades.) So it's fine.</p><p>

So that is where the weird mix of styles in my games comes from. Suppose I wanted to have unified art, all one style guide, all one look, everything done from scratch to give the game one pure look. I'm not a total idiot. I know it's possible. This is why I don't do it ...</p>

<p><b>Here! Have Some Hard Numbers!</b></p><p>

Queen's Wish is a big game! Five nations and biomes! A surface and underworld! Multiple sets of furniture, all kinds of environments. The game currently has, to make the different regions look distinct and give enough visual variety, well over 1000 terrain icons. (An icon here is defined to be a 48x48 tile. Some terrains require multiple icons. Each wall type, for example, is assembled from 60 icons.)</p><p>

Now suppose I do all this from scratch for the game. I need to hire freelancers. So I have to assemble a team of them that work in the desired style, that all make art that blend well, that are available and reliable, that are willing to commit to a job this big, and aren't too expensive. (If you think this is easy, you have a lot to learn. Assembling this team takes a lot of my non-existent time.)</p><p>

So I hire Fredrika Freelancer (F.F.) for short. F.F. charges $25/hour.</p><p>

(That’s a really fair price. If you’re paying less, someone else is going to hire her away from you. On the other hand, many freelancers charge $50/hour or more, but F.F. likes me and gives me a break. She probably lives in a country where the U.S. dollar goes farther. If you live in Brooklyn, I can't afford you.)</p><p>

I ask F.F. to do, say, a stone pillar, about 20 pixels wide and 70 pixels high.</p><p>

She builds it in her 3-D program. Textures it. Shadows it. Sizes it properly. Renders it. Sends it to me. I request some changes. She makes them. (I'm really easy to work with. I almost never ask for more than one round of changes. Believe it or not, freelancers tend to really like working with me.) I get the art. This probably will take about two hours.</p><p>

So, if I'm lucky, I get this pillar done for $50. Yay! One terrain type down.</p><p>

999 more to go.</p><p>

But for Queen's Wish, I want 4 different pillars, to give distinct looks to four different cultures. Suppose on opengameart, I find a set of public domain pillar icons that basically work. They aren't great, but they function. If I download them, I save $200.</p><p>

$200!!! That's folding money! You know how much money that is? That's enough money to buy 200 donuts! WITH SPRINKLES!</p><p>


<b>But That's Not All!</b></p><p>

So do a little math and tell me how much money I'll need to shell out to get all 1000 terrain icons done, how much money will be chipped out of my $140000. And then remember that's just terrain! Then I need creature art, and an interface, and portraits, and color paintings, and sfx, and item icons, and ability icons, and ...</p><p>

RPGs are art-intensive!</p><p>

Are you seeing why I go cheap whenever I can? Freelancers charge money because they DESERVE it. They are talented people in a hard job. But they are selling the art ala carte, and I'm too much of a doofus to be able to afford too much of it.</p><p>

To art everything being done from scratch with a unified style and a consistent, pleasing color palette and all the other good things artists like, if I'm lucky and get a lot of charity and really scale back what I want, I can easily end up spending $150000. Again, I can't do it myself. I'm a writer, not an artist, and RPGs absolutely need certain sorts of assets.</p><p>

So here is the math: Doing art the cheap bastard way, I spend $40000. Doing it the good way, I spend around $150000. 150000 – 40000 = 110000</p><p>

So to justify the extra art cost, I need to sell $110000 more worth of games just to break even. Remember that number.</p><table><tbody>
<tr><td><a href="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-O4qcf4H_x1k/XWRVHrVMvII/AAAAAAAABMw/ykoiZJt1oXYqxFTxbA4OtRPQQnloG30HwCLcBGAs/s1600/14-185.png" imageanchor="1"><img data-original-height="480" data-original-width="640" height="300" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-O4qcf4H_x1k/XWRVHrVMvII/AAAAAAAABMw/ykoiZJt1oXYqxFTxbA4OtRPQQnloG30HwCLcBGAs/s400/14-185.png" width="400"></a></td></tr>
<tr><td>We should be grateful that indie games have expanded what a game can look like and still break through. It wasn't like this a decade ago.&nbsp;</td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<p><b>Or I Could Hire An Employee</b></p><p>

I don't have to use freelancers, of course. I could hire an artist full-time for 20 months. Suppose I do a big search and find someone whose style I like and who wants to work for me. How much will that count, taking benefits and taxes into account?</p><p>

Many who are unfamiliar with this industry are surprised to find that artists are some of the highest paid people. Good, reliable artists are rare! Check out this site https://www.careerexplorer.com/careers/games-artist/salary/, for salary estimates.</p><p>

If I'm lucky enough to find a good artist who wants the job, with bonuses and benefits and so on, I might be able to get him or her for $150000.</p><p>

If I'm lucky enough to find a good person, with bonuses and benefits and so on, I might be able to get this person for $150000-180000.</p><p>

(LOL! This is probably way too low, especially if I want the person to live in Seattle so I can work with them face to face, which I do. I will be paying under the median at this rate.)</p><p>

I don't want to do this. I'm an introvert, and one of the reasons I got into this business was so that I could work alone. But I'll do it. For the Sake Of Art. You, the customer, deserve it. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dQw4w9WgXcQ">I will never let you down!</a></p><p>

Again, my cheap bastard art is $40000. If I hire a full-time art director/artist, I need to increase sales by $110000-140000.</p><p>

<b>Where Does the Extra Art-Buying Money Come From, By The Way?</b></p><p>

So can I even spend the extra $110000+ to begin with?</p><p>

I don't have that much cash on hand. Nowhere near. To launch this project, I need to take a bank loan or raid my retirement fund. Then, if I don't break even, I'm in big trouble.</p><p>

<b>OK. I Need To Increase Sales By $110000</b></p><p>

I know. This blog post is a long slog. Here's the punchline! Remember, most indie games are sold at deep discount now. After the store's cut, I'll probably average about $8 a sale.</p><p>

To make that $200000 I think I can earn, I'll need to make about 25000 sales. For an indie game, this is a LOT. But give me a few years and let me luck into a Steam daily deal or a Humble Bundle and I can manage it.</p><p>

But to break even on my all-new art project, to earn that extra $110000, my still very low-budget indie turn-based-retro-word-heavy RPG needs to sell about 40000 copies.</p><p>

That increase may not sound like so much more, but it is a LOT. Ask any indie developer. 40000 copies is a HUGELY aggressive number. (So is 25000, but, again, I have an established fan base. Every sale I get requires more work than the sale before it.)</p><p>

That is just to break even. If we don't hit that number? We can easily lose the entire business, poof, all sacrificed for the sake of a nice, unified art style.</p><p>

And that is why I need to be the cheapest bastard in indie games.</p><table><tbody>
<tr><td><a href="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-QwgaJAMMwRY/XWRVvGR0QII/AAAAAAAABNA/P5qQNSuKIqUEtbJQNM8vgEcmFdPABNL2QCLcBGAs/s1600/haters_gonna_hate_3_by_mezkalito4p-d4f3zsw.gif" imageanchor="1"><img data-original-height="260" data-original-width="290" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-QwgaJAMMwRY/XWRVvGR0QII/AAAAAAAABNA/P5qQNSuKIqUEtbJQNM8vgEcmFdPABNL2QCLcBGAs/s1600/haters_gonna_hate_3_by_mezkalito4p-d4f3zsw.gif"></a></td></tr>
<tr><td>All my best art direction is done when my eyes are covered with slices of cucumber.</td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<p><b>But ... But ... I Thought Indie Games Made You Rich!</b></p><p>

Yeah. Sometimes you get a hit. Then you get a pile of money. Then you hire a bunch of employees and make a real company. Then one of two things happen. You write a new, expensive game and it's a mistake and fails and everything explodes. Or you keep writing good games and grow until GiantMegaCorp gives you hundreds of millions of dollars for your company and you fly free and take a big vacation and buy a Tesla and realize you have no idea what to do with your life.</p><p>

However, most indie developers are like most small business owners. We're humble folks scraping by and doing what we can.</p><p>

That is why I am writing these too-many words. If you want to have a small business or make a living as a humble artist, I have kind words for you, because I really want you to succeed.</p><p>

<b>The Inspirational Ending!</b></p><p>

I got yelled at a lot for the previous article. It was basically a massive expression of contempt at me for being such a hack that I was content writing such ugly games.</p><p>

(And if you want to get <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Games/comments/cubkxa/why_all_of_our_games_look_like_crap_spiderweb/?st=jzoq993n&amp;sh=cebf255f">Extremely Mad Online</a> and <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/gamedev/comments/ctvicn/why_all_of_our_games_look_like_crap/?st=jzne67gx&amp;sh=43ebcb48">dunk on me</a> more, it's cool. Whatever is fun. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8UXircX3VdM">Shine on, you crazy diamond.</a>)</p><p>

But here’s the thing! If you want to be a game writer, or creator, or small businessperson, you should find my story to be inspiring!</p><p>

I write games so ugly that I am showered with contempt, and yet I make money! I’ll have a full, lifelong career! If I can have so many flaws and still succeed, you can too!</p><p>

Figure out what you are really good at doing. Sell that. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oNJy0h6gIpI&amp;list=PL6SSUza2wNqihtsiQQOVMfrQAn0M0LGx-&amp;index=32">Make your dream real.</a>&nbsp;Get it out the door, whatever it takes, whatever corners you have to cut. If you’re better than me (and who isn’t, really), you have a chance.</p><p>

Good luck!</p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Ask HN: What happened to startups, why is everything so polished? (110 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39154380</link>
            <guid>39154380</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2024 10:32:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39154380">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <tbody><tr id="39154594"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154594" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154594&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>I see the same in the consulting space - people who've barely ever talked to a prospect let alone had an actual customer (I happen to know from talking to folks like that) have a shiny website with pricing packages talking about "their team" and what not. Feels like pure hustle culture.<p>I started my business a year ago, and there is no "we". There's me and (at this point) enough clients for comfortable living. I went completely scrappy on my website (<a href="https://dahlke.tech/" rel="nofollow">https://dahlke.tech</a>). Felt rebellious in this day and age, but it doesn't seem to hurt.</p><p>I don't think that stuff matters in the beginning, clients see right through it from what I've heard. Some people get off on trying to look and feel like "a real company". I find there's joy in accepting that my company is not that, not yet, and putting all of my energy into getting there.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39154654"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154654" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154654&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Some feedback:<p>If im a prospective customer I dont care about</p><p>“Over time, I aim to use this income to bootstrap a software business based on one of my side projects.”</p><p>Tell me how you can help me make more money or save more money. Your side project ambitions are not relevant to your customers.</p><p>Instead I would recommend personal info on an about page or a separate site for your side project.</p><p>For your background info this should come later, please tell us what skills you have and recent projects you have done straight away so I can understand if you are the right consultant for me, I dont want to first read your life story!</p><p>Note: feedback can be hard to receive and give, please treat feedback as a gift, I am trying to be kind, but also nice and kind are not the same thing, so if my feedback is unwanted or seems blunt that is why!
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39154683"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154683" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154683&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Thanks for the feedback! I was actually pondering about that sentence. I don't think it helps sales in any way, it's just me trying to be transparent, but it's probably too prominent for how irrelevant it is.<p>In an interesting plot twist, at this point, I enjoy my consulting work more than working on my own projects, so I'm not even sure this is still my strategy. There's something about genuinely helping people that I find more rewarding than building things nobody asked for by myself.</p><p>Edit: Ah, you added some more thoughts - thanks for those too! I might revisit the content of that site and maybe even add a sub page one of these days I think.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="39158293"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39158293" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39158293&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Very cool!<p>I thought the same thing when I started my consulting company 10 years ago.  It'd called Nerdian Inc (My name is Ian).  My website and brand name is simply my name: www.iancollmceachern.com
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154753"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154753" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154753&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>&gt; my answer is usually that I refuse to chose just one<p>Refuse to choose. Not sure if spelling mistake or typo, but since everyone is doing feedback, thought I’d point it out.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39154795"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154795" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154795&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Haha, thanks, I didn't even spell check this I guess. I also wrote "advise" as a noun in there...</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="39157692"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39157692" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39157692&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I'm curious: how come there are no German version of the website? Are most of your (desired) clients not German? Or is it that practically everyone speaks English in Germany so it doesn't matter?</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39158890"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39158890" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39158890&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Almost all of them are German in fact - since I find them through my network primarily. I guess the answer to your question is because I'm too lazy :) Plus I primarily work with startups, they tend to be pretty international here.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="39154626"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154626" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154626&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span><pre><code>  For the time being, I, Firstname Surname, am the main product;
</code></pre>
love it<p>all the stock websites with photos of suited 'professionals' (usually just models) are a real turn-off, unless they show the actual team; customers want to know who they're dealing with.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39154690"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154690" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154690&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Thanks :) I got plenty of advice to not write something like that, but it's just how it is.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="39154964"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154964" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154964&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Honestly, I liked your website. It's clean, minimalist, professional &amp; to the point.<p>In future, I will make for myself similar one.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154643"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154643" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154643&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>In a past role, one of the things done was to create an IVR system that had all manner of different menus for sales, support, or technical questions and they were split by whether you were a casual or enterprise user. There was just one person answering, no matter what you selected. The goal was to seem sophisticated and thus more reliable and trustworthy.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39155742"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155742" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155742&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Did it at least ring through to that person differently depending on menu selection or did they want to seem properly enterprisey by immediately asking all those questions again?</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39160307"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39160307" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39160307&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Properly enterprisey. They didn't record the pathways or announce them. It was just all there to make it seem sophisticated rather than a guy on a cell phone.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                              <tr id="39154470"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154470" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154470&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>You're surely joking. It's gone the other way. Maybe your memory is better than mine.<p>All the apps today look all the same, made on electron, single page landing page, same live chat/support, same style of charging, same flat design, same email campaign styles.</p><p>Everything is set up from a SaaS or tool to help deploy it so rapidly the polish and self character is almost non existent. Everything is rushed to the point they all look the same.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39154575"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154575" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154575&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>I’m not sure that you and OP really disagree that much.<p>Everything looks very similar. Whether you find the look polished or uninspiring is almost tangential.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39155895"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155895" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155895&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I think when you know how the nuts and bolts work, you realize that the shiny chrome is just cheap metal.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="39154586"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154586" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154586&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Personally I can't tell all the SaaS startup sites that get mentioned here from each other.<p>Most of the time I can't even figure out what they do. Maybe they're there to display generic team stock photo with fake smiles #2618782?
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39156267"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39156267" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39156267&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Website using webflow, etc. Reality is that even customers are moving on that direction. If you don't look like you're a serious company, they won't look at you.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154514"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="39154520"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154520" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154520&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>That doesn't seem to be true if you look at Apple products. All the high margin/high growth products/services don't follow that generic nature.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39156639"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="39155923"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="39154814"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154814" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154814&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>I agree that in many cases people are puffing their feathers to try to be something they're not (at least not yet). Some believe in the fake it until you make it mentality.<p>With NeuML (<a href="https://neuml.com/" rel="nofollow">https://neuml.com</a>), the website is a simple HTML page. On social media, I'm honest about what NeuML is, that I'm in my 40s with a family and not striving to be the next Steve Jobs. I've been able to build a fairly successful open source project (txtai 6K stars <a href="https://github.com/neuml/txtai">https://github.com/neuml/txtai</a>) and a revenue positive company. For me, authenticity and being genuine is most important. I would say that being genuine has been way more of an asset than liability.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39155783"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="39156498"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="39154490"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154490" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154490&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Because that visual is easy nowadays. Just take something ready made, slap logo, stock photos. Search replace company name and done.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39154545"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154545" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154545&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I agree. Also bothers me that everything looks the same. People are afraid to try something new or go with their own style.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39158696"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39158696" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39158696&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>You’re both right. You can have a pixel-perfect web site with Tailwind in a few minutes.<p>And that’s why OP sees everything as polished. The backend and features are another story…
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154757"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154757" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154757&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>For big tech products the "style" is dictated by at most one to two hundred people, living in the same place whose formal education involved the same dozen or so people. Those decisions then get bundled into one of several design systems which are filtered down to the rest of us. That's one of the big reasons why there's so little diversity in thought.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="39154761"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154761" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154761&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>The key is that it's not polish, it's simply because the baseline level increased.<p>Now it's easy as hell to get something that looks polished, but that's all it is: visually polished.</p><p>If you talk about actual functionality, I don't think I've ever seen so much half-baked shit being sold as a product as in this day and age. Every startup I see is taking the "fake until you make it" a bit too literally. It's basically only the fake part.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39156647"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39156647" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39156647&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>There what "fake it tip you make it" means. But not "make it" is much later, and "fake it" survives longer from investors.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="39155881"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155881" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155881&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Expectations and abilities have changed. Consumers now expect things to look polished, or at the very least, have a defined aesthetic. Businesses also expect that you have other customers and want assurance that you will not disappear.<p>I believe the bigger story here is that individuals are now capable of doing much more than before. I'm a product designer. And over a decade ago I started my career building Wordpress themes. I'm starting to redesign my personal website—and I'm not going to build a theme from scratch like I used to. I'm going to use the Wordpress block editor because it's just easier.</p><p>So expectations are higher and individuals are more capable than ever before.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39155946"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="39156447"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="39160669"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154687"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154687" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154687&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>All the low-hanging fruit has been picked. You can't start with just a crappy app that solves a problem, you have to get all the packaging around it right too.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39154861"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154861" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154861&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I'm not a businessman, but I don't think so.  Case in point: Beeminder.  Their web app has a bit of an "unfinished" feel to it – definitely not a "modern SPA", rather a traditional Rails web app (not that it's something bad, quite the opposite!), but it solves a real problem and has stayed afloat for over 10 years now.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39156019"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39156019" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39156019&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I absolutely love Beeminder - I use it daily - but they’re not a good example of what an average startup is going for. They have a small but dedicated group of users, not a massive user base that they can later monetize. That makes enough revenue to pay for their employees and for the founders to take a salary, but they’re never going to go big and have an exit. That’s fine (a good thing, in my opinion), but it’s the opposite of what most startup founders want.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39155710"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155710" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155710&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I don’t know Beeminder. But if they launched 10 years ago, they are not a case in point. By now, they probably stay afloat despite feeling unfinished, because they have established marketing channels and word of mouth. Would the same service with the same presentation be as successful if they launched today? Hard to tell.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="39155823"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155823" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155823&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>A crappy app that solves a problem would be an upgrade in a lot of cases, rather than a company engineering a problem to justify an app that’s been created.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39156216"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39156216" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39156216&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>It's more likely that a company started off with a solution for a problem, then got told by investors that it wasn't a big enough problem, and so they had to "pivot" into a more crowded space, without really adding much value.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="39154720"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="39154735"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="39154669"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="39155250"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155250" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155250&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I would suggest to fix the orthography to “PS: Nothing is broken about this page. It's just simple on purpose. :)”. Simplicity is nice, but correct punctuation and capitalization is also appreciated as a proxy indicator for professional diligence.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39155326"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="39155725"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155725" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155725&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Kudos for the transparency of your monorepo, and in addition to its simplicity, the lack of tracking on your homepage.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="39155223"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155223" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155223&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>There used to be several star-architect offices that had white background at their website with only black text for contact. While other firms had shiny websites with all project in huge pictures.<p>But these were just like "me shit is out there and you already know it".
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154876"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154694"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="39154905"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="39155774"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155774" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155774&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>No<p>Mainly because:</p><p>&gt; The globalization ecosystem for software companies.
Plug inlang's products together for market expansion and a broader customer reach.</p><p>I have no idea what that means and who it’s for.</p><p>I don’t know if this is exactly what your product does but maybe a heading like:</p><p>“The developer platform that makes data integrations easy”</p><p>That at least tells me <i>who</i> is the buyer and what <i>benefit</i> I will get
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39160369"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="39155277"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155277" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155277&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Well there is section 'popular products' directly on landing page so it is not hard to guess.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39155207"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="39155337"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155337" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155337&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>What is unclear?<p>we know that we haven't nailed communication yet. one team member is working full time on communication/the website
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39155471"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="5"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="200"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155471" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155471&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I have no idea what “globalization ecosystem” is supposed to mean. There is a list of software components (“products”) I’m probably supposed to see a use for, but why would I go to that website to browse them?  There is mention of “inlang projects”, but what is “inlang” and why would I have such a project? There is mention of “plugins for inlang”, but again, what is inlang and why does it need plugins?</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39160381"><td></td></tr>
                                                <tr id="39154491"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154491" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154491&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>And they all have that "Life at x" section in their website. How can all those businesses I never heard about provide life.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39156662"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="39155958"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155958" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155958&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span><i>Why has the baseline for technology companies improved?</i><p>Because the cost and complexity of implementing technology has improved orders of magnitude.</p><p>Also, people starting startups are flush with cash from the longest bill run in modern history, so tend to spend.</p><p><i>Why do people feel the need to launch with a big “feel” when their companies are still small?</i></p><p>Market incentives and startup advice all explains this phenomenon. Look big, be big. Look small, stay small.</p><p><i>Why do they all look the same?</i></p><p>I’ll take a #3 with fries and a milkshake. Can I get extra salt on the fries?</p><p>Truth is, the technology industry has spend the last 10-15 years optimizing the heck out of its technology platforms for delivering small innovations, and not whole new product categories.</p><p>There was a time where every site had to be hand coded and custome built, but now companies are really focused on just the small part of the tech that’s different, which is often a small component of the overall infrastructure.</p><p>The lower value stuff ends up just being more and more off the shelf and less custom, and therefore less custom looking.</p><p>The rise of SaaS in particular really incentivized everything looking the same, because the “same” was the way to get people started with the least amount of ramping.</p><p>The whole “show instant value” means “use familiar interfaces” et al.</p><p>My 2c.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154765"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154765" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154765&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>There's little to gain from innovating on the landing page. A slick Wordpress template gets the job done just as well as a tailor-made landing page. Effort is better spent elsewhere (the product).</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39158913"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39158913" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39158913&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>If it makes you feel better, I’m at a start up right now and we definitely are not polished yet!<p>But as a point of reference to maybe give insight to your question, the last time I joined a start up was 21 years ago. Here are some differences I have noted:</p><p>- Stunningly vast array of high quality, open source tools, platforms, and frameworks. Some of this stuff we had to pay for. A lot of it wasn’t very good or limited. Even more of it we had to invent ourselves.</p><p>- Cloud services. I, all by myself, can write some YAML and have an industry-standard, production-ready stack published to the Internet and ready for traffic in a couple of hours. Of course, I’ll pay out the nose if it hits big, but compare this to the extremely high barrier to entry when I spent weeks or months planning out infrastructure, procuring and deploying hardware, configuring endless firmware/software, tuning, testing, building out failover, backup strategies, and a billion other things, not to mention the actual software I want to deliver.</p><p>- Available talent. Extraordinary engineers and developers have always been hard to find, but good enough ones are fairly plentiful, especially now that you’re no longer limited to hiring or moving people local.</p><p>- Freely available knowledge. You younger folks shit constantly on Stack Overflow and the likes, but y’all don’t know how good you have it now. Blogs, vlogs, online and often open courses, SO/reddit, ChatGPT, etc. enable you to go from zero to hero in minutes, where I often had to spend days or weeks to figure something out for myself or to find some wizard in a dark cave to share their arcane knowledge.</p><p>- Established patterns. People have written voluminous books and blogs about precisely how to build large scale and high quality applications and systems, and as we discussed, a lot of the tools are readily available to you with little or no money involved.</p><p>It’s called commoditization. As for appearing to already have customers ready to go: I think the low barrier to entry allows people to more freely experiment with ideas closer to a potential customer, get it in front of them, and further build out 
from there fairly quickly and organically. That, however, is no guarantee it will be a sustainable business.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39158674"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39158674" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39158674&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>&gt; “Wind back the block to Microsoft and Apple, and those guys were super scrappy, not an ounce of polish at the outset…”<p>Well, the Personal PC did invent desktop publishing. Before that print brochures, what I guess you would take for polish, were expensive to produce and manufacture.</p><p>And the WWW largely replaced the desktop publishing world. Why print something you can’t change?</p><p>And today commerce on websites has clear solutions you can spin-up in turnkey fashion or DIY with Web frameworks.</p><p>You can call it polish, but I call it evolution. With all of these capabilities, why wouldn’t you do all of these things?
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154807"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154807" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154807&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Co-founded a startup about a year ago. Also released a bunch of websites in the past 15 years.<p>The experience is really different now. It has become really easy to get the design and content 80% there with free tools. We’ve used goHugo with a template at first, it was faster than writing our HTML/CSS, but then discovered webflow and it was REALLY faster. Our non-technical co-founder could do really powerful customizations in there too without diverting efforts from the product. (Result here: <a href="https://www.hellodata.ai/" rel="nofollow">https://www.hellodata.ai</a>)</p><p>In essence, I don’t think people necessarily spend more time on their landing page now, but given that you can get 80% there by spending a weekend or two on your website, not doing it would almost feel sub-optimal.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154627"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154627" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154627&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I came to this post literally 2 minutes after rage quitting doing some UI design for a startup idea I have. I was trying to make it look too shiny. Thank you for reminding me to be more authentic.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154679"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154679" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154679&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Yeh. Makes it intimidating to try to make a startup until you realise it’s just generic polish over some cobbled-together SaaS APIs and docker containers. That’s what depresses me. You don’t need good tech, you just need business sass, marketing, and networks.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154579"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="39156205"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39156205" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39156205&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Not just websites, entire "Businesses" have replaced Marketing/Sales with Bullshit/Hustle and nothing is believable anymore.<p>The biggest problem i see is that the presentations are so vague/over-the-top/buzzword-heavy/Outlandish-claims/throwing-in-everything-and-the-kitchen-sink  that i don't even understand what the product/company is supposed to do for me (as a prospective client). If you can't explain what exactly you do in specific terms, you are doomed to failure.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39155819"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155819" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155819&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I worked with a startup late last year and they were prerevenue with a small amount of investment. They hired an agency build everything for them. This is why all startups look a like. Founders fear looking messy. The tradeoff is massive. You trade polish for intimately understanding your product and customers. To get there you need to be willing to sit through the mud and dirt of a unpolished product. It is painful and many do not want to do that. So we end up with vanilla products which still can be successful but yea that's basically it</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39155772"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="39155887"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155887" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155887&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Costly signalling is a decent way to think about it. Having a polished website/UI used to be more work/money so it served as a costly signal - companies would invest in that polish only after having some measure of success.<p>Now its easy to achieve, so it no longer serves as a signal of success. But if you still believe it signals quality as it once did, you will be confused.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39155967"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155967" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155967&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>I'm just now finishing our first marketing site after having like a crappy landing page for the last year.<p>In part it's users having higher expectations.</p><p>But in part it's also that no one takes you seriously unless you have a proper marketing website. And I don't mean customers but even providers or other companies for stuff like integrations. Everyone just ignores you.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154668"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154668" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154668&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>There's some irony and conflicts of interest.<p>People make slick landing pages and try to get interest to decide if enough people sign up for a thing that doesn't exist yet, then "it may be worth building it"</p><p>But also potential customers are fed up of such tactics and want to actually try a product before signing up to another thing which may or may not ever exist.</p><p>So what happens in the end sometimes is that the developers may think "nobody signed up for it so I will pivot".</p><p>Would love to hear opinions and experiences about it though for success and failure.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39156708"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39156708" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39156708&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>To an extent, having a polished established look is to build trust.<p>If the website looks poorly executed, customers will walk. Think about it, if the site has zero reputation and looks really janky, would you put your credit card in?</p><p>Your average consumer will say no.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39155842"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155842" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155842&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>VC money is more readily available than in the 70s, which means startups staff up faster, which means more ability to polish around the edges. I’d say the core functionality is often similarly incomplete, but design, packaging, docs, localization, etc. are more complete aka polished.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39156625"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39156625" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39156625&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>It was always the way. Microsoft and Apple "fronting" like they were big companies before they were, as did everyone before them.<p>It's just easier to do nice web design now.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154836"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154836" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154836&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>You forget the SEO optimizations, the marketing campaigns, and the general fluff that is filling the Web.<p>Blandness is the common denominator, anything that is not fitting this schema doesn't fit to what the Web has become.</p><p>Edit: in part, the gatekeepers of the Web require this standardisation for their algorithms to handle human content.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154511"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154511" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154511&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Reminds me of amie.so calendar lunch the past few days, cool site UI and all, but still having trouble with the servers until now.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39159114"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154614"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154614" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154614&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Today's tech world is very product and market focused. So it does stuff like webpages well.<p>That's not bad of course, it is how you win against competition or when the value you provide is a convenience or non ground breaking in other ways.
The websites of the hard tech people are often less polished. They just come from a different DNA.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154516"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154516" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154516&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Those things are super easy to put together, so now they are a requirement to get investment. So all the startups do it.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39158106"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154474"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154676"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154676" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154676&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Next time you read the testimonial section, copy paste the author's name into Google. You'll find that they're made up.<p>They also share the same stock photo of the smiling woman in red.</p><p>It's borderline fraud.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39156249"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="39155175"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155175" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155175&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Yes, it all looks very hollow, more marketing front than anything of substance, the marketing copy often bordering on cringe (“beautiful”, “awesome”).</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="39156244"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39156244" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39156244&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Don't forget the Pricing page that asks you to schedule a call with their sales team to get pricing for more than 1 seat.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="39155972"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154883"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154883" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154883&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>We noticed this pattern as well and actively decided against a flashy landing page (you know the one: dark background, large text on the left and interact-able glitzy Rubik’s cube/sphere/graph on the right, the one that spins/asjusts on command…)<p>Instead we put the product front and center — and people seem to like it. After some tweaks, our conversion from unique user to “Loop Creation” is now at 40%(!)</p><p>It lacks polish, but we don’t put up a facade: <a href="https://magicloops.dev/">https://magicloops.dev</a>
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39155054"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155054" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155054&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>That's why I'm making www.aiadbuilder.net slowly, doing it my way, releasing it as I want and ignoring the naysayers.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39156287"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39156287" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39156287&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>I think the expectations of potential users have increased and it's an upward spiral.<p>Reasonable design and interactivity have become the norm with no-code tools, templates and frameworks taking a lot of pressure of those who may have struggled with design if starting from scratch.</p><p>This proliferation also increases the standards of users who expect a more polished feel of a product (even if it's simple and barely works with a dumpster fire backend). Notable mention of Craigslist though which is only able to buck the trend due to lock-in. People using your product is the biggest signal that you are on to something but if potential users bounce because of your lacking UI/UX you may be less likely to pursue the development of your product.</p><p>Of course this isn't everyone and some of us are more than happy to put up with a less-polished UI in favor of the product itself (I'm looking at you *nix users). 'Show HN' states 'A Show HN needn't be complicated or look slick. The community is comfortable with work that's at an early stage.' and I feel that may be a portion of the users here but chances are higher that even those of us who are willing to use early stage products would prefer cleaner UIs.</p><p>Personally though - as someone who likes to launch products - it can be quite disheartening. On one hand I don't want to spend too much time on design however I fear that if I don't it will hinder me. My approach is to apply the 80:20 rule. Educate myself a little in design and use pre-made stuff as much as I can.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154712"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154712" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154712&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Our website is just a bunch of "hand made" HTML files . We promise to update it every month but here we are, like 10 years later.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154604"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154604" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154604&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Aesthetics and branding is a much lower bar than being useful. Substance is much more important, but in very short supply.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154620"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154620" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154620&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>It's just a case of sampling bias.<p>You don't see startups that are not like this because they receive less publicity and press.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154619"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154743"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154655"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154655" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154655&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>With the advent of ChatGPT &amp; its brothers, it's easy to generate fake text and visual effects that are eye-catching.<p>And companies look for more experienced/bigger companies rather than startup-level ones, which have less trust, when it comes to cooperation/business.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39155918"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="39155963"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155963" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155963&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>You see the same thing with influencers. Attractive people with polished perfect lives and comfortable wealth. It’s what the market responds to.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39155230"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155230" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155230&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Everyone is "fake it 'til you make it" today.<p>But Microsoft really was, too. There was some story about a shared tie that was worn to talk to the "shirts" at IBM in the early days. No idea about garters, which were also part of the IBM dress code at the time.</p><p>Not sure about Apple's early days, but there are certainly many stories of Jobs' "reality distortion field."
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39154613"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39154613" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39154613&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>A polished website is as simple as a Webflow template (for landing page) and a component library (for app). It would be more work to have something not polished, as it meant you built everything from scratch.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39155668"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_39155668" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=39155668&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D39154380"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>a lot of the twitter startup and indie dev are totally phoney. they share numbers saying they making money but what they really sell is their course or discord channel or whatever scam they can use to milk their base</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="39155915"><td></td></tr>
            </tbody></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Android now lets you transfer eSIMs between your phones (124 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.androidpolice.com/android-esim-transfer-tool/</link>
            <guid>39153330</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2024 07:03:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.androidpolice.com/android-esim-transfer-tool/">https://www.androidpolice.com/android-esim-transfer-tool/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39153330">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                                                       <div>
                    


        

                        <nav>
                <ul>
                    <li><a href="https://www.androidpolice.com/">Home</a></li>
                                                                                            <li><a href="https://www.androidpolice.com/operating-systems/">Operating Systems</a></li>
                                                                                                <li><a href="https://www.androidpolice.com/features-operating-systems/">Features on Operating Systems</a></li>
                                                                                                                                                            </ul>
            </nav>
            
                </div>
                            

    
            
    
        
            
    
    
    
        
    
                            






            
            

    
    
        
    
            
    
            
    
        
            
    
    
    
        
    
                                
    <p>Carrier support is still spotty, but the feature already works with multiple OEMs</p>

            
            

    
    
        
    
            
    
            
    
        
            
    
    
    
        
    
                                
                                    
                                                                                                                        
                                                        <div data-img-url="https://static1.anpoimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2024/01/esim_transfer_hero_image.jpg" data-modal-id="single-image-modal" data-modal-container-id="single-image-modal-container" data-img-caption="&quot;&quot;">

        <figure>
            <picture>
                <!--[if IE 9]>
                <video style="display: none;"><![endif]-->
                                    <source media="(min-width: 1024px)" sizes="1140px" srcset="https://static1.anpoimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2024/01/esim_transfer_hero_image.jpg?q=50&amp;fit=contain&amp;w=1140&amp;h=&amp;dpr=1.5">
                                    <source media="(min-width: 768px)" sizes="943px" srcset="https://static1.anpoimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2024/01/esim_transfer_hero_image.jpg?q=50&amp;fit=contain&amp;w=943&amp;h=&amp;dpr=1.5">
                                    <source media="(min-width: 481px)" sizes="767px" srcset="https://static1.anpoimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2024/01/esim_transfer_hero_image.jpg?q=50&amp;fit=contain&amp;w=767&amp;h=&amp;dpr=1.5">
                                    <source media="(min-width: 0px)" sizes="480px" srcset="https://static1.anpoimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2024/01/esim_transfer_hero_image.jpg?q=50&amp;fit=contain&amp;w=480&amp;h=&amp;dpr=1.5">
                                <!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]-->
                                    <img width="1920" height="1079" alt="eSIM_Transfer_Hero_Image" data-img-url="https://static1.anpoimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2024/01/esim_transfer_hero_image.jpg" src="https://static1.anpoimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2024/01/esim_transfer_hero_image.jpg">
                            </picture>
            <figcaption></figcaption>
        </figure>
    </div>

    
            <!-- No winning ad found for zone: below main pic! -->
    
            
            

    
    
        
    
            
                    </div><div id="article-body" itemprop="articleBody">
<p>Now that they're seeing widespread adoption, <a href="https://www.androidpolice.com/sim-esim-and-isim/" rel="nofollow">eSIMs</a> have started to change the way we shop for cell phone coverage. Since they're built into your device, they eliminate the need to physically remove your SIM card when you want to switch plans. The convenience of using software to download and provision SIM plans is undeniable, but there's a catch – transferring plans between devices isn't as straightforward as it used to be. To move your plan, you often need to go through the whole setup process again, which can range from simply using your carrier's app to visiting a store for a QR code scan. While eSIMs simplify carrier changes or plan trials, they bring new challenges in device transitions.</p>
<!-- No repeatable ad for zone: character count repeatable. --><!-- Repeatable debug data: {"injection":"none","adPosition":0,"startingPoint":1,"skipEvery":null,"nbrPlacementFilledEachSkip":0,"nbrPlacementsScanned":0,"ruleCount":10,"degradationStartingPoint":2,"stopAds":null,"actualCount":727} -->
<!-- Zone: below first paragraph. -->
<!-- No ads allowed! -->
<!-- No winning ad found for zone: mid intro! -->
<p>Google recognized this issue, and at last year's Mobile World Congress, <a href="https://www.androidpolice.com/android-partnerships-connected-devices-mwc-barcelona/" rel="nofollow">announced its solution</a>. The company promised to introduce a new <a href="https://www.androidpolice.com/google-esim-transfer-tool/" rel="nofollow">eSIM transfer tool for Android</a>, designed to let users securely and swiftly move their mobile plans to new devices, bypassing the need for physical SIMs. Although Google was tight-lipped about the specifics and the launch date of this feature, its practical implementation was <a href="https://www.androidpolice.com/googles-esim-transfer-tool-finally-here-pixel-8/" rel="nofollow">first noticed</a> by users setting up their <a href="https://www.androidpolice.com/google-pixel-8/" rel="nofollow">Pixel 8</a>. People were able to transfer their T-Mobile eSIM to their Pixel 8 from their older Pixel device, which led some to believe the feature might be limited to Google's own devices. However, it turns out that’s not the case.</p>
<!-- Repeatable debug data: {"injection":"before","adPosition":0,"startingPoint":1,"skipEvery":null,"nbrPlacementFilledEachSkip":0,"nbrPlacementsScanned":1,"ruleCount":10,"degradationStartingPoint":2,"stopAds":null,"actualCount":694} --><!-- Zone: character count repeatable. --><!-- No ads allowed! --><!-- Repeatable debug data: {"injection":"after","adPosition":1,"startingPoint":1,"skipEvery":null,"nbrPlacementFilledEachSkip":1,"nbrPlacementsScanned":1,"ruleCount":10,"degradationStartingPoint":2,"stopAds":null,"actualCount":0} -->
<p>While setting up their brand-new <a href="https://www.androidpolice.com/samsung-galaxy-s24/" rel="nofollow">Galaxy S24 Ultra</a>, one of our readers decided to use Samsung’s SIM transfer tool. To their surprise, a pop-up appeared on their nearby LG V60 ThinQ that invited them to transfer their SIM to their Galaxy S24 Ultra by scanning a QR code. I was also able to get this pop-up to appear on my Pixel 8 Pro, as shown below. It's important to note, though, that this feature currently seems to work exclusively with T-Mobile eSIM profiles, aligning with Google's earlier mention at MWC 2023 that Deutsche Telekom, T-Mobile's parent company, would be one of the first carriers to support this feature.</p>
<!-- No repeatable ad for zone: character count repeatable. --><!-- Repeatable debug data: {"injection":"none","adPosition":1,"startingPoint":1,"skipEvery":null,"nbrPlacementFilledEachSkip":1,"nbrPlacementsScanned":2,"ruleCount":1000,"degradationStartingPoint":2,"stopAds":null,"actualCount":642} -->

<!-- No repeatable ad for zone: character count repeatable. --><!-- Repeatable debug data: {"injection":"none","adPosition":1,"startingPoint":1,"skipEvery":null,"nbrPlacementFilledEachSkip":1,"nbrPlacementsScanned":2,"ruleCount":1000,"degradationStartingPoint":2,"stopAds":null,"actualCount":882} -->
<p><em>Transferring an eSIM from a Pixel 8 Pro to a Galaxy S24 Ultra</em></p>
<!-- No repeatable ad for zone: character count repeatable. --><!-- Repeatable debug data: {"injection":"none","adPosition":1,"startingPoint":1,"skipEvery":null,"nbrPlacementFilledEachSkip":1,"nbrPlacementsScanned":2,"ruleCount":1000,"degradationStartingPoint":2,"stopAds":null,"actualCount":943} -->
<p>Samsung's role in this development is particularly noteworthy. Their SIM transfer tool, originally <a href="https://www.androidpolice.com/samsung-beat-google-physical-sim-esim-conversions/" rel="nofollow">added in the One UI 5.1 release</a>, previously only supported transferring eSIM profiles between Galaxy devices. A keen-eyed tipster, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/user/fragmentedchicken" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">FragmentedChicken</a> on Reddit, noticed a subtle change in the tool's language in the latest One UI 6.1 update. The tool now indicates compatibility with non-Galaxy devices, hinting at a broader usability.</p>
<!-- Repeatable debug data: {"injection":"before","adPosition":1,"startingPoint":1,"skipEvery":null,"nbrPlacementFilledEachSkip":1,"nbrPlacementsScanned":2,"ruleCount":1000,"degradationStartingPoint":2,"stopAds":null,"actualCount":1383} --><!-- Zone: character count repeatable. --><!-- No ads allowed! --><!-- Repeatable debug data: {"injection":"after","adPosition":2,"startingPoint":1,"skipEvery":null,"nbrPlacementFilledEachSkip":2,"nbrPlacementsScanned":2,"ruleCount":1000,"degradationStartingPoint":2,"stopAds":null,"actualCount":0} -->
<p>As it turns out, this change is more than just cosmetic; it's actually a shift towards utilizing Google’s eSIM transfer mechanism. When my Galaxy S24 Ultra was open on this page, a pop-up provided by the Google Play Services app appeared on my nearby Android devices, such as my Pixel 8 Pro. This pop-up is part of the EsimTransferHalfSheetActivity that was first spotted by <a href="https://twitter.com/AssembleDebug/status/1693469209316188568" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">AssembleDebug</a> last August. The rollout of this feature represents a major step forward in eSIM support on Android, allowing eSIM transfers between any Android phone, albeit subject to carrier support.</p>
<!-- No repeatable ad for zone: character count repeatable. --><!-- Repeatable debug data: {"injection":"none","adPosition":2,"startingPoint":1,"skipEvery":null,"nbrPlacementFilledEachSkip":2,"nbrPlacementsScanned":3,"ruleCount":1000,"degradationStartingPoint":2,"stopAds":null,"actualCount":585} -->

<!-- No repeatable ad for zone: character count repeatable. --><!-- Repeatable debug data: {"injection":"none","adPosition":2,"startingPoint":1,"skipEvery":null,"nbrPlacementFilledEachSkip":2,"nbrPlacementsScanned":3,"ruleCount":1000,"degradationStartingPoint":2,"stopAds":null,"actualCount":825} -->
<p><em>Transferring an eSIM from a Galaxy S24 Ultra to a Pixel 8 Pro</em></p>
<!-- No repeatable ad for zone: character count repeatable. --><!-- Repeatable debug data: {"injection":"none","adPosition":2,"startingPoint":1,"skipEvery":null,"nbrPlacementFilledEachSkip":2,"nbrPlacementsScanned":3,"ruleCount":1000,"degradationStartingPoint":2,"stopAds":null,"actualCount":886} -->
<p>In essence, the eSIM transfer tool that Google announced at MWC 2023 has quietly but effectively been launched. The pop-up has been tested and confirmed to appear both ways, i.e., when attempting to transfer an eSIM from a Galaxy S24 Ultra back to a Pixel 8 Pro. Although carrier support is still limited, this advancement still marks a significant milestone in Android's ability to manage eSIMs, providing users with enhanced flexibility and convenience in managing their mobile plans across different devices.</p>
<!-- Repeatable debug data: {"injection":"before","adPosition":2,"startingPoint":1,"skipEvery":null,"nbrPlacementFilledEachSkip":2,"nbrPlacementsScanned":3,"ruleCount":1000,"degradationStartingPoint":2,"stopAds":null,"actualCount":1401} --><!-- Zone: character count repeatable. --><!-- No ads allowed! --><!-- Repeatable debug data: {"injection":"after","adPosition":3,"startingPoint":1,"skipEvery":null,"nbrPlacementFilledEachSkip":3,"nbrPlacementsScanned":3,"ruleCount":1000,"degradationStartingPoint":2,"stopAds":null,"actualCount":0} -->
 </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>