<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 20:30:04 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[We Abandoned Matrix: The Dark Truth About User Security and Safety (2024) (159 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://forum.hackliberty.org/t/why-we-abandoned-matrix-the-dark-truth-about-user-security-and-safety/224</link>
            <guid>46376201</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 15:06:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://forum.hackliberty.org/t/why-we-abandoned-matrix-the-dark-truth-about-user-security-and-safety/224">https://forum.hackliberty.org/t/why-we-abandoned-matrix-the-dark-truth-about-user-security-and-safety/224</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46376201">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="text">
              <h2><a name="p-1003-we-have-moved-to-simplex-1" href="#p-1003-we-have-moved-to-simplex-1"></a><strong>WE HAVE MOVED TO SIMPLEX</strong></h2>
<p>Anyone that agrees to our <a href="https://git.hackliberty.org/hackliberty.org/hackliberty.org-legal/src/branch/main/code-of-conduct.md">Code of Conduct</a> is welcome to join our Simplex <a href="https://simplex.chat/contact#/?v=2-5&amp;smp=smp%3A%2F%2FPQUV2eL0t7OStZOoAsPEV2QYWt4-xilbakvGUGOItUo%3D%40smp6.simplex.im%2Fm_GjmB7OCRlv9un-75clOjChzWiT3AZX%23%2F%3Fv%3D1-2%26dh%3DMCowBQYDK2VuAyEAHC830iH16xdofGIOxTS46_BGX-lrfHQqhLaEb680Ygs%253D%26srv%3Dbylepyau3ty4czmn77q4fglvperknl4bi2eb2fdy2bh4jxtf32kf73yd.onion&amp;data=%7B%22type%22%3A%22group%22%2C%22groupLinkId%22%3A%22G-5UKmDf5uIs08KTY-Tf8g%3D%3D%22%7D">Hack Liberty Community Room</a> and our <a href="https://simplex.hackliberty.org/">Simplex server</a>, a decentralized, metadata resistant alternative to Matrix! Incognito profiles welcome!</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Hack Liberty SMP Server</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><code>smp://esPsfRFGZd2TRyKijJDorCMo3Ld-QD8Cq8ASx8qrY_Q=@simplex.hackliberty.org,gstc5w42xawazcr4txrcyhitmkhiyu2vkkwy2xhwovbhlapzrccjeyad.onion</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Hack Liberty XFTP Server</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><code>xftp://DfK0yVcc9P5NgfaRR4retNWDDTKFa9g_NqF11maM87Q=@xftp.hackliberty.org,kf25i7slt6skypu47j5kzl4s4nlt3aw3baiocanygf6gprrrbft4dyqd.onion:5233</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Hack Liberty Community Room</strong><br>
<a href="https://simplex.chat/contact#/?v=2-7&amp;smp=smp%3A%2F%2FesPsfRFGZd2TRyKijJDorCMo3Ld-QD8Cq8ASx8qrY_Q%3D%40simplex.hackliberty.org%2F0XZlyIDKbEoLW0WfnPecTJzi_boCwyFq%23%2F%3Fv%3D1-3%26dh%3DMCowBQYDK2VuAyEA8LCHTUdVcA_pLHrNkLE_GEuh0QeuLyZuI-2m01Qe23k%253D%26srv%3Dgstc5w42xawazcr4txrcyhitmkhiyu2vkkwy2xhwovbhlapzrccjeyad.onion&amp;data=%7B%22groupLinkId%22%3A%223Ypi4wDI0VhGvVDx7e6jAQ%3D%3D%22%7D">SimpleX Chat - Contact</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2><a name="p-1003-why-federation-must-die-2" href="#p-1003-why-federation-must-die-2"></a><em><strong>Why Federation Must Die</strong></em></h2>
<p>The appeal of federation lies in its potential to empower individuals, groups, and communities by enabling the use of open-source software and facilitating decentralized interactions across servers. This model offers a degree of censorship resistance, as the messages or images are replicated across multiple servers, making it difficult for any single entity to censor or control the content.</p>
<p>However, after over two years of administrating public federated services (Matrix, Lemmy), I’ve learned first hand the fundamental problems associated with the design of all federated protocols.</p>
<h2><a name="p-1003-problems-with-matrix-protocol-3" href="#p-1003-problems-with-matrix-protocol-3"></a><em><strong>Problems with Matrix (Protocol)</strong></em></h2>
<h2><a name="p-1003-metadata-leakage-4" href="#p-1003-metadata-leakage-4"></a><strong>Metadata Leakage</strong></h2>
<p><em>From <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20210202175947/https://serpentsec.1337.cx/matrix">serpentsec.1337.cx/matrix</a>:</em></p>
<blockquote>
<p>Federated networks are naturally more vulnerable to metadata leaks than P2P or centralized networks. These leaks can be fixed, at the expense of increased complexity of the protocol (thus making it more vulnerable to faulty implementations). Matrix’s failure to prevent these leaks is necessary for proper functioning of the protocol.</p>
<p>Some metadata must be leaked due to features Matrix provides. For example, Matrix’s message verification requires knowing which user and device sent a message (to know which key to verify with). In other cases (such as global profile pictures and nicknames), the information is considered public anyway, and therefore has no need to be encrypted. Matrix’s failure to prevent these leaks is a triviality.</p>
<p>Some metadata leaks are accepted for performance requirements. For example, message reactions and read receipts might not be encrypted because Matrix’s E2EE is slower than normal (non-E2EE) messaging. Encrypting reactions and read receipts could provide a painful user experience (UX). Matrix’s failure to prevent these leaks is a design feature.</p>
<p>Some metadata leaks are simply a matter of the protocol’s failure to consider them. For example, room-specific nicknames, room-specific profile pictures, and message edit events could all be encrypted without breaking the protocol. Matrix’s failure to prevent these leaks is a design flaw.</p>
<p>Matrix’s E2EE does not, however, encrypt everything. The following information is not encrypted:<br>
Message senders</p>
<ul>
<li>Message senders are never encrypted</li>
<li>Due to Matrix’s design, encrypting session/device IDs would break verification</li>
<li>It’s impossible to prevent timestamps from leaking, since the server can simply note when an event is received anyway</li>
<li>Join/leave/invite and other room events are never encrypted</li>
<li>While contents are not leaked, an attacker can know when messages are edited</li>
<li>Reactions are never encrypted</li>
<li>Read receipts are never encrypted</li>
<li>Nicknames are never encrypted</li>
<li>Profile pictures are never encrypted</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To demonstrate some examples of these leaks, I have made some examples available: <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20210202175947/https://snippets.serpentsec.1337.cx/matrix-metadata-leaks">https://snippets.serpentsec.1337.cx/matrix-metadata-leaks</a></p>
</blockquote>
<h2><a name="p-1003-admin-in-the-middle-5" href="#p-1003-admin-in-the-middle-5"></a><strong>Admin in the Middle</strong></h2>
<p><em>From <a href="https://blog.erethon.com/blog/2022/07/13/what-a-malicious-matrix-homeserver-admin-can-do/">What a malicious matrix homeserver admin can do</a></em>:</p>
<blockquote>
<h3><strong>Passive information gathering</strong></h3>
<p>There’s a lot of passive information gathering a malicious admin can do just by querying the Synapse database and this can happen retroactively. Some of the (meta)data include:</p>
<ol>
<li>Chat history of any unencrypted room (duh!)</li>
<li>Information about the users of their homeserver (duh!), like devices, IPs, etc.</li>
<li>Reactions to end-to-end-encrypted (e2ee) messages, because reactions aren’t encrypted.</li>
<li>Room related metadata (even for e2ee rooms), room participants and their avatars/nicks, the room topic, power levels, number of messages people sent and when, etc.</li>
<li>URL previews of shared links (if enabled on a per room setting)</li>
</ol>
<h3><strong>Active attacks</strong></h3>
<p>A malicious admin can perform active attacks against their users and the rooms they participate in if they want. Some of them might be easy to spot from the client’s perspective, others might not.</p>
<h4>Messing with rooms</h4>
<p>Matrix has the notion of <a href="https://matrix.org/docs/guides/implementing-stateres/">state events</a> which are the events that specify what a room looks like. They specify which users are part of the room, which users are banned, the power levels of users, the name and the topic of the room, etc. These events aren’t e2ee and so, a malicious admin can both read them and send their own events by impersonating a user of their homeserver. This can mainly lead to social engineering attacks. I’ll list a few ways to social engineer and exploit people, as there are multiple ways to do so. I’ll be using <span>@victim</span>:example.com as the account the malicious admin is impersonating.</p>
<ul>
<li>React to messages as the user being impersonated. The malicious admin won’t know the content of the message they’re reacting to, but they’ll be able to see others’ reactions to it.</li>
<li>Set the room topic to an attacker controlled URL. Every participant in the room, regardless of homeserver, will see this as being set by <code>@victim:example.com</code>, a user they personally trust. A drive-by attack or a leak of the IP address of third party users is possible this way.</li>
<li>Invite accounts into the room. The newly joined account won’t be able to read past e2ee messages, but any messages sent after they joined will be visible given the default settings of most clients.</li>
<li>Kick and ban people out of the room, which isn’t that bad in itself, but can be disruptive. Similarly, they can increase the power level of other users in the room.</li>
<li>Send <a href="https://spec.matrix.org/v1.1/client-server-api/#mroomtombstone">tombstone events</a>, marking the room as being replaced for most clients and prevent further message sending to it.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Messing with the user’s devices</h4>
<p>The above attacks can be performed simply by impersonating users without adding any new devices to their account. However, a malicious admin can simply add a new device on a user’s account, thus allowing the sending and receiving of e2ee messages.</p>
<p>In most clients, this will show up as an unverified device, resulting in a red shield icon to be added in the room to showcase the presence of the unverified device. My personal experience is that most people, even privacy minded tech savvy ones, simply ignore this for various reasons. I’m guilty of ignoring this as well. There’s however a per session and per room setting to disable your client from sending messages to unverified devices, if one wants to be completely safe.</p>
<p>In most cases, the attacked user will get a popup in their client that a new unverified device was added. There are ways to circumvent this by not reporting this new device to the user, however I don’t know if encryption will continue working properly for the user in this case.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2><a name="p-1003-protocol-weaknesses-6" href="#p-1003-protocol-weaknesses-6"></a><strong>Protocol Weaknesses</strong></h2>
<p><em>AI Summarized From <a href="https://telegra.ph/why-not-matrix-08-07">why not matrix? – Telegraph</a></em></p>
<p>Matrix is a complex communication protocol that serves as the foundation for chat applications, functioning as a distributed partially-replicated graph database. A “room” in Matrix is structured as a directed acyclic graph (DAG) composed of events, which can include messages, user states, and bans. The servers in a room aim for eventual consistency, meaning they should replicate enough state for all participants to see a similar view.</p>
<p>To send an event into a room, a participating server appends it to the graph. Each server must verify incoming events based on defined authentication rules, with events cryptographically signed to confirm their origin. However, there are several significant issues and risks associated with using Matrix:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Append-only Design</strong>: Events cannot be deleted, leading to potentially endless history accumulation, which can compromise user deniability.</li>
<li><strong>Redaction Limitations</strong>: Redaction events are advisory; poorly behaving servers may ignore them, retaining the original content.</li>
<li><strong>Data Leakage</strong>: Servers that ignore redactions can inadvertently share supposedly deleted data with new servers joining the room.</li>
<li><strong>Irreversible Events</strong>: Certain events, like membership changes, cannot be deleted as they become part of the room’s auth chain.</li>
<li><strong>Spam Vulnerability</strong>: Bots can be used to spam rooms, complicating the graph and consuming server resources, necessitating room recreation to eliminate spam.</li>
<li><strong>History Linearization Challenges</strong>: Linearizing history is difficult, leading to different servers potentially seeing messages in varying orders.</li>
<li><strong>Message Forging</strong>: It is possible to insert messages into history by crafting plausible events, which may go unnoticed by users.</li>
<li><strong>Optional Encryption</strong>: End-to-end encryption is not mandatory, risking exposure of unencrypted messages in federated rooms.</li>
<li><strong>Fragile Encryption</strong>: Encryption relies on reliable device list updates; failures can lead to broken encryption.</li>
<li><strong>Device Information Leakage</strong>: Device list updates may inadvertently reveal user device information.</li>
<li><strong>API Interoperability Issues</strong>: The lack of a strict definition for canonical JSON can lead to signature mismatches between different server implementations.</li>
<li><strong>Signature Check Failures</strong>: Different programming languages used for homeservers can cause JSON interoperability issues, leading to failed signature checks.</li>
<li><strong>Arbitrary Signing Key Expiry</strong>: Signing keys can expire arbitrarily, causing new servers to reject events from the original server, leading to split-brained rooms.</li>
<li><strong>Common Split-Brained Rooms</strong>: The consensus algorithm for resolving conflicting states is not foolproof, leading to frequent state resets.</li>
<li><strong>State Reset Chaos</strong>: State resets can occur more often with servers written in different languages, causing significant disruptions.</li>
<li><strong>Loss of Admin Powers</strong>: State resets can strip room admins of their powers, making it difficult to manage rooms effectively.</li>
<li><strong>Room Shutdown Limitations</strong>: A room cannot be universally shut down across the federation, which can lead to abuse.</li>
<li><strong>Moderation Challenges</strong>: Effective moderation is hindered by the event auth system’s reliance on accurate state resolution.</li>
<li><strong>Unauthenticated Media Uploads</strong>: Users can upload media without authentication, potentially leading to misuse of the media repository.</li>
<li><strong>Media Replication Risks</strong>: Homeservers can replicate media from other servers, which could lead to denial-of-service issues.</li>
<li><strong>Unverified Media Uploads</strong>: Media uploads are unverified by default, posing risks if harmful content is uploaded.</li>
<li><strong>Liability for Illegal Media</strong>: Homeservers could unknowingly host illegal media due to eager replication from undesirable rooms.</li>
</ol>
<h2><a name="p-1003-dubious-encryption-protocols-megolm-7" href="#p-1003-dubious-encryption-protocols-megolm-7"></a><strong>Dubious Encryption Protocols (Megolm)</strong></h2>
<p><em>From: <a href="https://nebuchadnezzar-megolm.github.io/">https://nebuchadnezzar-megolm.github.io</a></em></p>
<blockquote>
<p>We report several practically-exploitable cryptographic vulnerabilities in the end-to-end encryption in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matrix_(protocol)">Matrix</a> and describe proof-of-concept attacks exploiting these vulnerabilities. When relying on implementation specific behaviour, these attacks target the Matrix standard as implemented by the <code>matrix-react-sdk</code> and <code>matrix-js-sdk</code> libraries.<a href="https://nebuchadnezzar-megolm.github.io/#fn:1">1</a> These libraries provide the basis for the flagship <a href="https://element.io/">Element</a> client. The vulnerabilities we exploit differ in their nature (insecure by design, protocol confusion, lack of domain separation, implementation bugs) and are distributed broadly across the different subprotocols and libraries that make up the cryptographic core of Matrix.</p>
<p>We target the setting where encrypted messaging and verification are enabled, i.e. in the presence of the strongest protections offered by the protocol. Furthermore, all attacks require cooperation of the homeserver. This is a natural threat model to consider, given that end-to-end encryption aims to provide protections against such untrusted third parties. We report the following vulnerabilities and attacks:</p>
<ul>
<li>Simple confidentiality break</li>
<li>Attack against out-of-band verification</li>
<li>Semi-trusted impersonation</li>
<li>Trusted impersonation</li>
<li>Impersonation to confidentiality break</li>
<li>IND-CCA break</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>The Megolm protocol, while designed for secure group messaging within the Matrix framework, exhibits several critical weaknesses that can compromise user confidentiality and security.</p>
<h2><a name="p-1003-resource-consumption-8" href="#p-1003-resource-consumption-8"></a><strong>Resource Consumption</strong></h2>
<p>Running a public Matrix server is not cheap. Depending on the number of users, there must be multiple worker containers, effectively requiring that you run between 4 and 12 instances of synapse.</p>
<p>Synapse is hard drive hungry, memory hungry, relatively CPU hungry, and also uses a lot of bandwidth.  Don’t expect to run this pile of bloat without throwing money at it.</p>
<h2><a name="p-1003-problems-with-matrixorg-organization-9" href="#p-1003-problems-with-matrixorg-organization-9"></a><em><strong>Problems with <a href="http://matrix.org/">Matrix.org</a> (Organization)</strong></em></h2>
<h2><a name="p-1003-data-collection-10" href="#p-1003-data-collection-10"></a><strong>Data Collection</strong></h2>
<p><em>From: <a href="https://hackea.org/notas/matrix.html">https://hackea.org/notas/matrix.html</a>:</em></p>
<blockquote>
<p>Summary of the <a href="https://gist.github.com/maxidorius/5736fd09c9194b7a6dc03b6b8d7220d0">Notes on privacy and data collection of Matrix.org</a></p>
<p><strong><a href="http://matrix.org/">matrix.org</a></strong> <em>and</em> <strong>vector.im</strong> <em>receive a lot of private, personal and identifiable data on a regular basis, or metadata that can be used to precisely identify and/or track users/server, their social graph, usage pattern and potential location. This is possible both by the default configuration values in synapse/Riot that do not promote privacy, and by specific choices made by their developers to not disclose, inform users or resolve in a timely manner several known behaviors of the software.</em></p>
<p><em>Data sent on a potential regular basis based on a common web/desktop+smartphone usage even with a self-hosted client and Homeserver:</em></p>
<ul>
<li><em>The Matrix ID of users, usually including their username.</em></li>
<li><em>Email addresses, phone numbers of the user and their contacts.</em></li>
<li><em>Associations of Email, phone numbers with Matrix IDs.</em></li>
<li><em>Usage patterns of the user.</em></li>
<li><em>IP address of the user, which can give more or less precise geographical location information.</em></li>
<li><em>The user’s devices and system information.</em></li>
<li><em>The other servers that users talks to.</em></li>
<li><em>Room IDs, potentially identifying the Direct chat ones and the other user/server.</em></li>
</ul>
<p><em>With default settings, they allow unrestricted, non-obfuscated public access to the following potentially personal data/info:</em></p>
<ul>
<li><em>Matrix IDs mapped to Email addresses/phone numbers added to a user’s settings.</em></li>
<li><em>Every file, image, video, audio that is uploaded to the Homeserver.</em></li>
<li><em>Profile name and avatar of users.</em></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This time, with such an <strong>impressive collection of private data being sent to Matrix central servers, even when you use your own instance</strong>, we have to face the facts: Something is seriously wrong.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Read more at: <a href="https://gitlab.com/libremonde-org/papers/research/privacy-matrix.org/-/blob/master/part1/README.md">https://gitlab.com/libremonde-org/papers/research/privacy-matrix.org/-/blob/master/part1/README.md</a></p>
<h2><a name="p-1003-pedophiles-11" href="#p-1003-pedophiles-11"></a><strong>Pedophiles</strong></h2>
<div><a href="https://forum.hackliberty.org/uploads/default/original/2X/b/bbc0640a5899788a643ad6e7efbb2bba49606f39.jpeg" data-download-href="https://forum.hackliberty.org/uploads/default/bbc0640a5899788a643ad6e7efbb2bba49606f39" title="1000042609"><img src="https://forum.hackliberty.org/uploads/default/optimized/2X/b/bbc0640a5899788a643ad6e7efbb2bba49606f39_2_505x500.jpeg" alt="1000042609" data-base62-sha1="qMVtU3BSsGzrQiCjKiW1IvDgOVj" width="505" height="500" srcset="https://forum.hackliberty.org/uploads/default/optimized/2X/b/bbc0640a5899788a643ad6e7efbb2bba49606f39_2_505x500.jpeg, https://forum.hackliberty.org/uploads/default/optimized/2X/b/bbc0640a5899788a643ad6e7efbb2bba49606f39_2_757x750.jpeg 1.5x, https://forum.hackliberty.org/uploads/default/optimized/2X/b/bbc0640a5899788a643ad6e7efbb2bba49606f39_2_1010x1000.jpeg 2x" data-dominant-color="F8F8F9"></a></div><br>
<div><a href="https://forum.hackliberty.org/uploads/default/original/2X/a/afb8bec84ba24ac57e3f743e3bcb5eb10a672691.jpeg" data-download-href="https://forum.hackliberty.org/uploads/default/afb8bec84ba24ac57e3f743e3bcb5eb10a672691" title="1000042610"><img src="https://forum.hackliberty.org/uploads/default/optimized/2X/a/afb8bec84ba24ac57e3f743e3bcb5eb10a672691_2_690x367.jpeg" alt="1000042610" data-base62-sha1="p4vn4GN5h2WCMC0zEjApod4z0PL" width="690" height="367" srcset="https://forum.hackliberty.org/uploads/default/optimized/2X/a/afb8bec84ba24ac57e3f743e3bcb5eb10a672691_2_690x367.jpeg, https://forum.hackliberty.org/uploads/default/optimized/2X/a/afb8bec84ba24ac57e3f743e3bcb5eb10a672691_2_1035x550.jpeg 1.5x, https://forum.hackliberty.org/uploads/default/optimized/2X/a/afb8bec84ba24ac57e3f743e3bcb5eb10a672691_2_1380x734.jpeg 2x" data-dominant-color="FBFBFB"></a></div>
<p>Matrix is not an adversarial resistant protocol that can and is being abused by many different groups.</p>
<p><em>From <a href="https://telegra.ph/why-not-matrix-08-07">why not matrix? – Telegraph</a></em></p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>speaking of shutting down rooms, <strong>you can’t actually force a room to be shut down across the federation</strong>. if there are three servers in a room and one of them wants to shut down the room, there’s no way to stop the other two servers from continuing along just as they were. this is good news if you care about internet freedom, sure. this is bad news if people start to abuse instances with unsavory rooms or content. in certain legislations this could present a serious problem.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>pretty much any user on your homeserver can upload media to your server’s media repository at pretty much any time, and <strong>media downloads are unauthenticated by default</strong>. as a result, you can often just generate a HTTP link to the media. someone might be using your media repository as their personal sharing box at your expense and you may not even realize. <strong>NOTE: THIS WAS RECENTLY CHANGED</strong></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>you can also <strong>ask someone else’s homeserver to replicate media</strong> by asking that homeserver to return a copy of it. based on the content ID and the origin server name in the URL, the homeserver will download the media from the origin and likely cache it locally in the process. that could end up being a fun denial-of-service.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>in addition to that, <strong>media uploads are unverified by default</strong>. if you are running your own matrix instance, there’s a good chance that nothing is scanning that media for unsavory content (like csam or viruses) unless you have also installed a separate content scanner. this is a separate package and is not a core part of the synapse distribution, nor any other homeserver that is available today.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>actually the eager replication of media could end up potentially being quite a massive headache, since all it takes is for one of your users to request media from an undesirable room for your homeserver to also serve up copies of it, at which point <strong>you could become liable for hosting copies of illegal media</strong> like csam or copyrighted material without necessarily knowing it.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>The <a href="http://matrix.org/">Matrix.org</a> abuse team is notoriously unresponsive to abuse reports or even taking any steps to prevent the abuse of their servers. Because of this, the platform has turned into a safe haven for tens of thousands of pedophiles to spread illegal child abuse materials without consequence.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=W8KEuAEYjQ4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
    <img src="https://forum.hackliberty.org/uploads/default/original/2X/7/72305282f824032b66b0703f20f4d4ec0f22e657.jpeg" title="Matrix - A Pit of Abuse with Government Ties" data-dominant-color="3B3B39" width="690" height="388">
  </a>
</p>

<p><strong>Matrix is no place to build a community without being exposed to pedophiles.</strong> Even worse, they will often hop to as many servers as possible to replicate as much illegal content as possible and make it harder for a (decentralized) admin response. Every homeserver in the federation is likely hosting child sexual abuse images and videos.</p>
<p>Disgusting, and the Matrix team is completely apathetic about it. Can you imagine that?</p>
<h2><a name="p-1003-cloudflare-man-in-the-middle-12" href="#p-1003-cloudflare-man-in-the-middle-12"></a><strong>Cloudflare Man-in-the-Middle</strong></h2>
<p><em>From <a href="https://gist.github.com/maxidorius/5736fd09c9194b7a6dc03b6b8d7220d0?permalink_comment_id=2963692#gistcomment-2963692:">Notes on privacy and data collection of Matrix.org · GitHub</a></em></p>
<p>[…]</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In all cases, we can see the headers <code>set-cookie</code>, <code>server</code>, <code>cf-ray</code> and <code>expect-ct</code> with values set by Cloudflare, which would not be possible if TLS termination was done directly on <code>matrix.org</code>/<code>vector.im</code> servers.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2><a name="p-1003-removed-tor-browser-support-13" href="#p-1003-removed-tor-browser-support-13"></a><strong>Removed Tor Browser Support</strong></h2>
<p><em>From <a href="https://github.com/element-hq/element-web/issues/28147#issuecomment-2393223674:">Why is the latest browser version not supported in Tor? · Issue #28147 · element-hq/element-web · GitHub</a></em></p>
<blockquote>
<p>Tor is built on an over a year old Firefox version which lacks many web features around encryption, i18n and the like. Once Tor updates to the latest Firefox ESR it’ll work once again. Due to lack of funding Tor is not considered a supported browser, there’s also no way for us to run tests against Tor as Playwright does not support it.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/t3chguy"><img src="https://forum.hackliberty.org/uploads/default/original/2X/8/8f4703463b60122d048acad0f368c23492e1d09c.jpeg" alt="@t3chguy" data-base62-sha1="kruqbZQWGM1Qh3dCvqIBK6xTMWU" width="20" height="20"></a> <a href="https://github.com/t3chguy">t3chguy</a> closed this as <a href="https://github.com/element-hq/element-web/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aclosed+archived%3Afalse+reason%3A%22not+planned%22">not planned</a> <a href="https://github.com/element-hq/element-web/issues/28147#event-14516065139">Oct 4, 2024</a></p>
</blockquote>
<h2><a name="p-1003-problems-with-lemmy-14" href="#p-1003-problems-with-lemmy-14"></a><strong>Problems with Lemmy</strong></h2>
<h2><a name="p-1003-data-replication-moderation-and-abuse-15" href="#p-1003-data-replication-moderation-and-abuse-15"></a>Data Replication, Moderation, and Abuse</h2>
<p>All the data replication and moderation issues from Matrix also apply to Lemmy. This one of the underlying flaws of all federated services. Lemmy admins can be held liable for hosting illegal content that is being replicated over the federation. It also makes Lemmy servers easy targets to be taken down by malicious adversaries.</p>
<h2><a name="p-1003-defederation-16" href="#p-1003-defederation-16"></a>deFederation</h2>
<p>Despite being “de-centralized”, there is censorship in the form of “de-federation”, which effectively removes “wrong-think” servers from the global audience on Lemmy. Even though there is claimed decentralization, a large majority of users congregate on the same few servers.</p>
<h2><a name="p-1003-censorship-is-hard-let-the-community-do-it-17" href="#p-1003-censorship-is-hard-let-the-community-do-it-17"></a>Censorship is hard, let the community do it!</h2>
<p>Any posts that don’t adhere to the Lemmy hive mind are immediately down voted, which is effectively a shadow ban that anyone can do by clicking the down vote button. Post that have any kind of negative score (two down votes) will be removed from the default post feed filters. (Active, Hot). This “shadowban” works to make it so 90% of the Lemmy population doesn’t  see your post unless they are filtered specifically for “new” posts.</p>
<h2><a name="p-1003-reddit-and-lemmy-are-one-big-psyop-18" href="#p-1003-reddit-and-lemmy-are-one-big-psyop-18"></a>Reddit and Lemmy are one big Psyop</h2>
<p>The entire framework of both Reddit and Lemmy do nothing but help to promote group think and propaganda. Any posts that don’t adhere to group think will be shunned and hidden. Post “scores” are a manipulation tactic used to influence (you) into being biased before you’ve even looked at the post. Manipulating upvotes and downvotes is trivially easy for really anyone, and it’s abused by governments and corporations to create manufactured consensus and trick you into believing that the “herd” thinks a certain way. Of course, having a lot of upvotes appeals to the most pathetic of egos, and the psyop continues with more incentivized group-think posts in a never ending cycle of garbage user generated content.</p>
<h2><a name="p-1003-why-use-simplex-19" href="#p-1003-why-use-simplex-19"></a><strong>Why use SimpleX</strong></h2>
<h2><a name="p-1003-simplex-unique-approach-to-privacy-and-security-20" href="#p-1003-simplex-unique-approach-to-privacy-and-security-20"></a>SimpleX unique approach to privacy and security</h2>
<p>Everyone should care about privacy and security of their communications - even ordinary conversations can put you in danger.</p>
<h3><a name="p-1003-full-privacy-of-your-identity-profile-contacts-and-metadata-21" href="#p-1003-full-privacy-of-your-identity-profile-contacts-and-metadata-21"></a>Full privacy of your identity, profile, contacts and metadata</h3>
<p><strong>Unlike any other existing messaging platform, SimpleX has no identifiers assigned to the users</strong> - it does not use phone numbers (like Signal or WhatsApp), domain-based addresses (like email, XMPP or Matrix), usernames (like Telegram), public keys or even random numbers (like all other messengers) to identify its users - we do not even know how many people use SimpleX.</p>
<p>To deliver the messages instead of user identifiers that all other platforms use, SimpleX uses the addresses of unidirectional (simplex) message queues. Using SimpleX is like having a different email address or a phone number for each contact you have, but without the hassle of managing all these addresses. In the near future SimpleX apps will also change the message queues automatically, moving the conversations from one server to another, to provide even better privacy to the users.</p>
<p>This approach protects the privacy of who are you communicating with, hiding it from SimpleX platform servers and from any observers. You can further improve your privacy by configuring your network access to connect to SimpleX servers via some overlay transport network, e.g. Tor.</p>
<h3><a name="p-1003-the-best-protection-against-spam-and-abuse-22" href="#p-1003-the-best-protection-against-spam-and-abuse-22"></a>The best protection against spam and abuse</h3>
<p>As you have no identifier on SimpleX platform, you cannot be contacted unless you share a one-time invitation link or an optional temporary user address. Even with the optional user addresses, while they can be used to send spam contact requests, you can change or completely delete it without losing any of your connections.</p>
<h3><a name="p-1003-complete-ownership-control-and-security-of-your-data-23" href="#p-1003-complete-ownership-control-and-security-of-your-data-23"></a>Complete ownership, control and security of your data</h3>
<p>SimpleX stores all user data on client devices, the messages are only held temporarily on SimpleX relay servers until they are received.</p>
<p>We use portable database format that can be used on all supported devices - we will soon add the ability to export the chat database from the mobile app so it can be used on another device.</p>
<p>Unlike servers of federated networks (email, XMPP or Matrix), SimpleX servers do not store user accounts, they simply relay messages to the recipients, protecting the privacy of both parties. There are no identifiers or encrypted messages in common between sent and received traffic of the server, thanks to the additional encryption layer for delivered messages. So if anybody is observing server traffic, they cannot easily determine who is communicating with whom (see <a href="https://github.com/simplex-chat/simplexmq/blob/master/protocol/overview-tjr.md">SimpleX whitepaper</a> for the known traffic correlation attacks).</p>
<h3><a name="p-1003-users-own-simplex-network-24" href="#p-1003-users-own-simplex-network-24"></a>Users own SimpleX network</h3>
<p>You can use SimpleX with your own servers and still communicate with people using the servers that are pre-configured in the apps or any other SimpleX servers.</p>
<p>SimpleX platform uses an open protocol and provides SDK to create chat bots, allowing implementation of services that users can interact with via SimpleX Chat apps – we are really looking forward to see what SimpleX services can be built.</p>
<p>If you are considering developing with the SimpleX platform, whether for chat bot services for SimpleX app users or to integrate the SimpleX Chat library into your mobile apps, please get in touch for any advice and support.</p>
<h2><a name="p-1003-comparison-with-other-protocols-25" href="#p-1003-comparison-with-other-protocols-25"></a>Comparison with other protocols</h2>
<div>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th>SimpleX chat</th>
<th>Signal, big platforms</th>
<th>XMPP, Matrix</th>
<th>P2P protocols</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Requires user identifiers</td>
<td>No = private</td>
<td>Yes<sup>1</sup></td>
<td>Yes<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>Yes<sup>3</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Possibility of MITM</td>
<td>No = secure</td>
<td>Yes<sup>4</sup></td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dependence on DNS</td>
<td>No = resilient</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Single operator or network</td>
<td>No = decentralized</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Yes<sup>5</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Central component or other network-wide attack</td>
<td>No = resilient</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Yes<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>Yes<sup>6</sup></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div><ol>
<li>Usually based on a phone number, in some cases on usernames.</li>
<li>DNS based.</li>
<li>Public key or some other globally unique ID.</li>
<li>If operator’s servers are compromised.</li>
<li>While P2P networks and cryptocurrency-based networks are distributed, they are not decentralized - they operate as a single network, with a single namespace of user addresses.</li>
<li>P2P networks either have a central authority or the whole network can be compromised - see the next section.</li>
</ol>
<h2><a name="p-1003-comparison-with-matrix-26" href="#p-1003-comparison-with-matrix-26"></a>Comparison with Matrix</h2>
<div>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th><strong>Feature</strong></th>
<th><strong>SimpleX</strong></th>
<th><strong>Matrix</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>Encryption Protocol</strong></td>
<td>End-to-end encryption with additional encryption layers and post-quantum resistant key exchange</td>
<td>Megolm protocol with known weaknesses</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Message Routing</strong></td>
<td>Private message routing (2-hop onion routing)</td>
<td>Federated architecture with metadata leaks</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Decentralization</strong></td>
<td>No central component, bootstrap nodes, or global shared state</td>
<td>Central components, bootstrap nodes, and global shared state</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Media Uploads and Downloads</strong></td>
<td>Local files encryption and manual messaging queue rotations</td>
<td>Unverified by default, with eager replication of media</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Scalability</strong></td>
<td>Efficient architecture with horizontal scaling</td>
<td>Complex and resource-intensive architecture with limited scalability</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>End-to-End Encryption</strong></td>
<td>Mandatory end-to-end encryption</td>
<td>Optional end-to-end encryption</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Metadata Protection</strong></td>
<td>Private message routing and metadata protection</td>
<td>Metadata leaks through federated architecture</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Key Exchange</strong></td>
<td>Post-quantum resistant key exchange</td>
<td>No post-quantum resistant key exchange</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Tor Support</strong></td>
<td>Tor support with proxy and onion-only routing feature</td>
<td>Removed Tor browser support</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Cloudflare Integration</strong></td>
<td>No Cloudflare</td>
<td>TLS termination through Cloudflare, introducing man-in-the-middle vulnerability</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div><h2><a name="p-1003-comparison-with-p2p9-messaging-protocols-27" href="#p-1003-comparison-with-p2p9-messaging-protocols-27"></a>Comparison with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peer-to-peer">P2P</a> messaging protocols</h2>
<p>There are several P2P chat/messaging protocols and implementations that aim to solve privacy and centralisation problem, but they have their own set of problems that makes them less reliable than the proposed design, more complex to implement and analyse and more vulnerable to attacks.</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peer-to-peer">P2P</a> networks use some variant of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Distributed_hash_table">DHT</a> to route messages/requests through the network. DHT implementations have complex designs that have to balance reliability, delivery guarantee and latency. The proposed design has both better delivery guarantees and lower latency (the message is passed multiple times in parallel, through one node each time, using servers chosen by the recipient, while in P2P networks the message is passed through <code>O(log N)</code> nodes sequentially, using nodes chosen by the algorithm).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The proposed design, unlike most P2P networks, has no global user identifiers of any kind, even temporary.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>P2P itself does not solve <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Man-in-the-middle_attack">MITM attack</a> problem, and most existing solutions do not use out-of-band messages for the initial key exchange. The proposed design uses out-of-band messages or, in some cases, pre-existing secure and trusted connections for the initial key exchange.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>P2P implementations can be blocked by some Internet providers (like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BitTorrent">BitTorrent</a>). The proposed design is transport agnostic - it can work over standard web protocols, and the servers can be deployed on the same domains as the websites.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>All known P2P networks are likely to be vulnerable to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sybil_attack">Sybil attack</a>, because each node is discoverable, and the network operates as a whole. Known measures to reduce the probability of the Sybil attack either require a centralized component or expensive <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proof_of_work">proof of work</a>. The proposed design, on the opposite, has no server discoverability - servers are not connected, not known to each other and to all clients. The SimpleX network is fragmented and operates as multiple isolated connections. It makes network-wide attacks on SimpleX network impossible - even if some servers are compromised, other parts of the network can operate normally, and affected clients can switch to using other servers without losing contacts or messages.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>P2P networks are likely to be <a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/woot15/workshop-program/presentation/p2p-file-sharing-hell-exploiting-bittorrent">vulnerable</a> to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denial-of-service_attack#Reflected_attack">DRDoS attack</a>. In the proposed design clients only relay traffic from known trusted connection and cannot be used to reflect and amplify the traffic in the whole network.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h2><a name="p-1003-simplex-features-28" href="#p-1003-simplex-features-28"></a><strong>Simplex Features</strong></h2>
<ul>
<li>End-to-end encryption using double-ratchet protocol with additional encryption layer</li>
<li>Post-quantum resistant key exchange in double-ratchet protocol</li>
<li>Private message routing (2-hop onion routing) to prevent server operators from discovering who connects to whom via network traffic metadata</li>
<li>Tor support for accessing messaging servers via Tor, providing an additional layer of anonymity and security</li>
<li>SOCKS proxy support for accessing messaging servers via SOCKS proxy, providing an additional layer of anonymity and security</li>
<li>TLS 1.2/1.3 support with limited cryptographic algorithms (CHACHA20POLY1305_SHA256, Ed25519/Ed448, Curve25519/Curve448) to ensure secure client-server connections</li>
<li>tlsunique channel binding as session ID in each client command signed with per-queue ephemeral key to prevent replay attacks</li>
</ul>
<h2><a name="p-1003-decentralization-and-connection-privacy-29" href="#p-1003-decentralization-and-connection-privacy-29"></a>Decentralization and Connection Privacy</h2>
<ul>
<li>Fully decentralized network with no central component, bootstrap nodes, or global shared state</li>
<li>No user profile identity, making it harder for attackers to discover who talks to whom</li>
<li>Private message routing (2-hop onion routing) to prevent server operators from discovering who connects to whom via network traffic metadata</li>
<li>Flux integration for using pre-configured Flux servers to improve metadata privacy and decentralization</li>
</ul>
<h2><a name="p-1003-user-experience-30" href="#p-1003-user-experience-30"></a>User Experience</h2>
<ul>
<li>End-to-end encrypted WebRTC audio and video calls</li>
<li>Private instant notifications for Android and iOS</li>
<li>Chat database encryption with passphrase</li>
<li>Local files encryption</li>
<li>Manual messaging queue rotations to move conversation to another SMP relay</li>
<li>Sending end-to-end encrypted files using XFTP protocol</li>
<li>Video messages</li>
<li>App access passcode</li>
<li>Optional alternative access password</li>
<li>Message reactions</li>
<li>Message editing history</li>
<li>Reduced battery and traffic usage in large groups</li>
<li>Message delivery confirmation (with sender opt-out per contact)</li>
</ul>
<h2><a name="p-1003-additional-features-31" href="#p-1003-additional-features-31"></a>Additional Features</h2>
<ul>
<li>Incognito mode to share a new random name with each contact</li>
<li>Chat groups in mobile apps</li>
<li>Connecting to messaging servers via Tor</li>
<li>Dual server addresses to access messaging servers as v3 hidden services</li>
<li>Chat server and TypeScript client SDK to develop chat interfaces, integrations, and chat bots</li>
<li>Haskell chat bot templates</li>
<li>Terminal (console) client with groups and files support</li>
<li>One-click SimpleX server deployment on Linode</li>
<li>Easy to deploy SimpleX server with in-memory message storage, without any dependencies</li>
</ul>
<h2><a name="p-1003-roadmap-32" href="#p-1003-roadmap-32"></a>Roadmap</h2>
<ul>
<li>Improve stability and reduce battery usage</li>
<li>Improve experience for new users</li>
<li>Large groups, communities, and public channels</li>
<li>Privacy &amp; security slider - a simple way to set all settings at once</li>
<li>SMP queue redundancy and rotation (manual is supported)</li>
<li>Include optional message into connection request sent via contact address</li>
<li>Improved navigation and search in the conversation (expand and scroll to quoted message, scroll to search results, etc.)</li>
<li>Feeds/broadcasts</li>
<li>Ephemeral/disappearing/OTR conversations with existing contacts</li>
<li>Privately share your location</li>
<li>Web widgets for custom interactivity in the chats</li>
<li>Programmable chat automations / rules (automatic replies/forward/deletion/sending, reminders, etc.)</li>
<li>Privacy-preserving identity server for optional DNS-based contact/group addresses to simplify connection and discovery, but not used to deliver messages</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2><a name="p-1003-get-started-with-the-simplex-user-guide-33" href="#p-1003-get-started-with-the-simplex-user-guide-33"></a>Get started with the Simplex User Guide</h2>



            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AMD entered the CPU market with reverse-engineered Intel 8080 clone 50 years ago (126 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.tomshardware.com/pc-components/cpus/amd-first-entered-the-cpu-market-with-reverse-engineered-intel-8080-clone-50-years-ago-the-am9080-cost-50-cents-apiece-to-make-but-sold-for-usd700</link>
            <guid>46375847</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 14:28:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.tomshardware.com/pc-components/cpus/amd-first-entered-the-cpu-market-with-reverse-engineered-intel-8080-clone-50-years-ago-the-am9080-cost-50-cents-apiece-to-make-but-sold-for-usd700">https://www.tomshardware.com/pc-components/cpus/amd-first-entered-the-cpu-market-with-reverse-engineered-intel-8080-clone-50-years-ago-the-am9080-cost-50-cents-apiece-to-make-but-sold-for-usd700</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46375847">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-widget-type="contentparsed" id="content">
<section>

<div id="article-body">

<p id="14bb569e-1241-4042-8030-8e0d9b55e788">The chip which paved the way for AMD’s illustrious future, eventually creating some of <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.tomshardware.com/reviews/best-cpus,3986.html" data-mrf-recirculation="inline-link" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.tomshardware.com/reviews/best-cpus,3986.html">the best CPUs</a> we've ever tested, entered mass production 50 years ago. AMD’s <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://en.wikichip.org/wiki/amd/am9080" data-url="https://en.wikichip.org/wiki/amd/am9080" target="_blank" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none" data-mrf-recirculation="inline-link">Am9080</a> had something of a shady origin, as it was a reverse-engineered and cloned <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.tomshardware.com/news/rosetta-2-secret-extension" data-mrf-recirculation="inline-link" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.tomshardware.com/news/rosetta-2-secret-extension">Intel 8080</a>. However, due to the importance of second-sourcing among organizations that would end up buying boatloads of 8080 microprocessors (e.g., the military), Intel and AMD eventually reached a licensing agreement, and the rest, as they say, is history.</p><h2 id="copycat-origin-3">Copycat origin</h2><p id="297d597b-6632-48f2-bf8d-234389c0928d-1">Armed with approximately 400 detailed images, the trio managed to draft schematic and logic diagrams and then hawked them around Silicon Valley to see if anyone was interested.</p><p>AMD took the bait, as you may have guessed, and thought the processor could be useful to run on the N-channel MOS process it had just developed. Some sources suggest that initial runs of the Am9080 were sold by AMD in 1974 — the same year Intel debuted the processor commercially. However, it would not be until 1975 that AMD marketed and mass-produced the Am9080.</p><h2 id="made-for-50-cents-sold-for-700-3">Made for 50 cents, sold for $700</h2><p id="df1984cb-1594-4b1d-b928-db48f880d5f5">Pondering the information we have about how much AMD could manufacture the Am9080 for and how much they could sell it for, mass-producing these chips was a great foundation and business-building <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.tomshardware.com/tag/enterprise" data-auto-tag-linker="true" data-mrf-recirculation="inline-link" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.tomshardware.com/tag/enterprise">enterprise</a>. Various sources indicate that a single Am9080 processor cost AMD only 50 cents to make (100 per wafer), yet it could sell them to military customers for $700 each.</p><h2 id="agreement-with-intel-3">Agreement with Intel</h2><p id="67876f09-bf86-4a58-8311-5da035efc080">In 1976, AMD was presented with another great opportunity to profit from its clone of Intel's 8080. Sidestepping interminable legal wrangling, AMD grabbed the chance to sign a cross-licensing agreement with Intel, granting them authorization to become a ‘second source.’</p><p>This wasn’t done out of the goodness of Intel’s heart, of course. Some lucrative contracts (e.g., military, again) required key components to have second sources. So AMD and Intel inked a deal, which meant AMD paid Intel $25,000 on signing and $75,000 per year for licensing. The deal also released both parties from liability for past infringements.</p><div data-hydrate="true" id="slice-container-newsletterForm-articleInbodyContent-DdPaDN9adqCQ2FB7teDHVc"><section><p>Get Tom's Hardware's best news and in-depth reviews, straight to your inbox.</p></section></div><p>WikiChip (linked top) notes the agreement would become the foundation for important future accords between the chipmaking rivals, notably the expanded agreement in 1982, which allowed AMD to make its own <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.tomshardware.com/pc-components/cpus/x86-reigns-supreme-as-snapdragon-x-elite-chips-captured-just-0-8-percent-of-the-market-with-720-000-units-sold-in-q3-2024-qualcomm-misses-out-on-rising-ai-pc-sales-with-intel-and-amd-taking-charge" data-mrf-recirculation="inline-link" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.tomshardware.com/pc-components/cpus/x86-reigns-supreme-as-snapdragon-x-elite-chips-captured-just-0-8-percent-of-the-market-with-720-000-units-sold-in-q3-2024-qualcomm-misses-out-on-rising-ai-pc-sales-with-intel-and-amd-taking-charge">x86 PC processors</a>. AMD’s first chip under the expanded agreement would be its Am286 (1982), a licensed version of the Intel 80286.</p><figure data-bordeaux-image-check="" id="26fe21f3-72fa-4436-b77b-542ac79b79f6"><div><p> <picture data-new-v2-image="true">
<source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/B48Sgsmh7mGvWGJTmGg3un-736-80.jpg.webp 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/B48Sgsmh7mGvWGJTmGg3un-736-80.jpg.webp 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/B48Sgsmh7mGvWGJTmGg3un-736-80.jpg.webp 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/B48Sgsmh7mGvWGJTmGg3un-650-80.jpg.webp 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/B48Sgsmh7mGvWGJTmGg3un-480-80.jpg.webp 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/B48Sgsmh7mGvWGJTmGg3un-320-80.jpg.webp 320w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 970px, calc(100vw - 40px)">
<img src="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/B48Sgsmh7mGvWGJTmGg3un.jpg" alt="AM9080 die shot" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/B48Sgsmh7mGvWGJTmGg3un-736-80.jpg 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/B48Sgsmh7mGvWGJTmGg3un-736-80.jpg 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/B48Sgsmh7mGvWGJTmGg3un-736-80.jpg 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/B48Sgsmh7mGvWGJTmGg3un-650-80.jpg 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/B48Sgsmh7mGvWGJTmGg3un-480-80.jpg 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/B48Sgsmh7mGvWGJTmGg3un-320-80.jpg 320w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 970px, calc(100vw - 40px)" loading="lazy" data-new-v2-image="true" data-original-mos="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/B48Sgsmh7mGvWGJTmGg3un.jpg" data-pin-media="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/B48Sgsmh7mGvWGJTmGg3un.jpg">
</picture><a href="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/B48Sgsmh7mGvWGJTmGg3un.jpg" target="_blank" data-url="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/B48Sgsmh7mGvWGJTmGg3un.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none"></a></p></div><figcaption itemprop="caption description"><span itemprop="copyrightHolder">(Image credit: <a href="https://en.wikichip.org/wiki/File:Am9080_die_shot.png" target="_blank" data-url="https://en.wikichip.org/wiki/File:Am9080_die_shot.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none">Via WikiChip</a>)</span></figcaption></figure><h2 id="am9080-variants-ran-at-up-to-4-0-mhz-3">Am9080 variants ran at up to 4.0 MHz</h2><p id="34bae230-723c-46b6-b50b-0263971cfd2e">AMD produced many variants of the Am9080 to propel its chip-making business forward. Of the 28 versions WikiChip lists, clock frequencies range from 2.083 to 4.0 MHz, and min/max operating temperatures range from models with a modest 0-70 degrees Celsius operating range, to the MIL-STD-883 compliant ‘AM9080ADM’ (for example), which was capable of computing in environments as cold as -70 to as hot as 125 degrees Celsius.</p><p>Am9080 chips had a significantly smaller die than the Intel 8080 that they copied. AMD’s more advanced and compact N-channel MOS fabrication process made this possible. Like now, the more advanced semiconductor process also enabled higher clocks. Intel’s 8080 processor SKUs were never produced with clock speeds above 3.125 MHz.</p><a href="https://news.google.com/publications/CAAqLAgKIiZDQklTRmdnTWFoSUtFSFJ2YlhOb1lYSmtkMkZ5WlM1amIyMG9BQVAB" id="71f94fcf-098b-4891-b753-3638f663fc20" data-url="https://news.google.com/publications/CAAqLAgKIiZDQklTRmdnTWFoSUtFSFJ2YlhOb1lYSmtkMkZ5WlM1amIyMG9BQVAB" target="_blank" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none"><figure data-bordeaux-image-check=""><div><p> <picture data-new-v2-image="true">
<source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/7cUTDmN2PHNRiNBVqbKf56-676-80.png.webp 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/7cUTDmN2PHNRiNBVqbKf56-676-80.png.webp 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/7cUTDmN2PHNRiNBVqbKf56-676-80.png.webp 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/7cUTDmN2PHNRiNBVqbKf56-650-80.png.webp 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/7cUTDmN2PHNRiNBVqbKf56-480-80.png.webp 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/7cUTDmN2PHNRiNBVqbKf56-320-80.png.webp 320w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 970px, calc(100vw - 40px)">
<img src="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/7cUTDmN2PHNRiNBVqbKf56.png" alt="Google Preferred Source" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/7cUTDmN2PHNRiNBVqbKf56-676-80.png 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/7cUTDmN2PHNRiNBVqbKf56-676-80.png 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/7cUTDmN2PHNRiNBVqbKf56-676-80.png 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/7cUTDmN2PHNRiNBVqbKf56-650-80.png 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/7cUTDmN2PHNRiNBVqbKf56-480-80.png 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/7cUTDmN2PHNRiNBVqbKf56-320-80.png 320w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 970px, calc(100vw - 40px)" loading="lazy" data-new-v2-image="true" data-original-mos="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/7cUTDmN2PHNRiNBVqbKf56.png" data-pin-media="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/7cUTDmN2PHNRiNBVqbKf56.png">
</picture></p></div></figure></a><p id="1682ecd1-2fd4-418c-9d56-ea79a7f07366"><em>Follow</em><a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://news.google.com/publications/CAAqLAgKIiZDQklTRmdnTWFoSUtFSFJ2YlhOb1lYSmtkMkZ5WlM1amIyMG9BQVAB" target="_blank" data-url="https://news.google.com/publications/CAAqLAgKIiZDQklTRmdnTWFoSUtFSFJ2YlhOb1lYSmtkMkZ5WlM1amIyMG9BQVAB" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none" data-mrf-recirculation="inline-link"><em> Tom's Hardware on Google News</em></a><em>, or</em><a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://google.com/preferences/source?q=" target="_blank" data-url="https://google.com/preferences/source?q=" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none" data-mrf-recirculation="inline-link"><em> add us as a preferred source</em></a><em>, to get our latest news, analysis, &amp; reviews in your feeds.</em></p>
</div>




<!-- Drop in a standard article here maybe? -->



<div id="slice-container-authorBio-DdPaDN9adqCQ2FB7teDHVc"><p>Mark Tyson is a news editor at Tom's Hardware. He enjoys covering the full breadth of PC tech; from business and semiconductor design to products approaching the edge of reason.</p></div>
</section>




</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Games’ affordance of childlike wonder and reduced burnout risk in young adults (109 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://games.jmir.org/2025/1/e84219/</link>
            <guid>46375499</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 13:43:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://games.jmir.org/2025/1/e84219/">https://games.jmir.org/2025/1/e84219/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46375499">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-test="keyword-links"><main id="wrapper"><section><article><h4><span>Original Paper</span></h4><div><div><div><ul><li><a href="https://games.jmir.org/search/searchResult?field%5B%5D=author&amp;criteria%5B%5D=Winze+Tam">Winze Tam<sup><small>1</small></sup>, BBA, MSc</a><a href="https://orcid.org/0009-0005-4422-4211" target="_blank" title="ORCID">&nbsp;</a>;&nbsp;</li><li><a href="https://games.jmir.org/search/searchResult?field%5B%5D=author&amp;criteria%5B%5D=Congcong+Hou">Congcong Hou<sup><small>2</small></sup>, MSc, PhD</a><a href="https://orcid.org/0009-0004-4526-7945" target="_blank" title="ORCID">&nbsp;</a>;&nbsp;</li><li><a href="https://games.jmir.org/search/searchResult?field%5B%5D=author&amp;criteria%5B%5D=Andreas%20Benedikt+Eisingerich">Andreas Benedikt Eisingerich<sup><small>1</small></sup>, BSc, MPhil, PhD</a><a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5531-4662" target="_blank" title="ORCID">&nbsp;</a></li></ul><div><p><sup>1</sup>Imperial College Business School, Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom</p><p><sup>2</sup>Faculty of Commerce, Kyushu Sangyo University, Fukuoka, Japan</p></div></div><div><h3>Corresponding Author:</h3><p>Andreas Benedikt Eisingerich, BSc, MPhil, PhD</p><p>Imperial College Business School</p><p>Imperial College London</p><p>South Kensington Campus</p><p>London, SW7 2AZ</p><p>United Kingdom</p><p>Phone: 44 207589 ext 5111</p><p>Email: <a href="mailto:a.eisingerich@imperial.ac.uk">a.eisingerich@imperial.ac.uk</a></p><br></div></div><section><article><h3 id="Abstract" data-label="Abstract">Abstract</h3><p><span>Background: </span>Unrelenting pressure and an “always-on” culture can leave no time for genuine rest among young adults. While playing video games has been noted to afford cognitive escapism and relaxation, critical questions remain about the influence of popular video games, such as Super Mario Bros., and their potential effects on young adults’ burnout risk.<br></p><p><span>Objective: </span>This study examined the extent to which, if at all, popular video games such as Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi could foster childlike wonder. It also investigated the potential of these games to reduce burnout risk among young adults.<br></p><p><span>Methods: </span>We used a mixed methods approach. First, qualitative data were collected through 41 exploratory, in-depth interviews (women: n=19, 46.3%; men: n=21, 51.2%; prefer not to disclose sex: n=1, 2.4%; mean age 22.51, SD 1.52 years) with university students who had experience playing Super Mario Bros. or Yoshi. Second, quantitative data were collected in a cross-sectional survey (N=336) of players of Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi to examine the games’ affordance of childlike wonder, overall happiness in life, and burnout risk.<br></p><p><span>Results: </span>Insights from in-depth interviews showed that players appreciated the ability of Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi games to instill childlike wonder, enhance happiness in life, and reduce burnout risk. Quantitative analyses showed that the games’ affordance of childlike wonder positively affected young adults’ happiness (b=0.30, SE=0.04, t=6.80, 95% CI 0.21-0.38; <i>P</i>&lt;.001). In turn, overall happiness significantly reduced the risk of burnout (b=–0.48, SE=0.05, t=–9.55, 95% CI –0.572 to –0.377). Results showed that happiness fully mediated the impact of childlike wonder on burnout, as the direct effect of childlike wonder on burnout risk became insignificant (b=–0.08, SE=0.04, t=–1.88, 95% CI –0.16 to 0.01; <i>P</i>=.06), while the indirect effect of childlike wonder on burnout risk was significant (b=–0.14, bootstrapped SE=0.03, 95% CI –0.20 to –0.09).<br></p><p><span>Conclusions: </span>The findings showed the significant positive effect of popular video games such as Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi on fostering players’ childlike wonder, increasing happiness, and reducing burnout risk. This study was among the first to identify childlike wonder as an emotional pathway through which mainstream video games could enhance well-being and reduce burnout. By moving beyond escapism and nostalgia, it offers a new perspective on how well-designed, globally familiar games can function as accessible, resilience-building digital microenvironments. These findings contributed to research bridging gaming and mental health and have practical implications for game designers, educators, and health professionals interested in promoting mental wellness through everyday play.<br></p><strong>JMIR Serious Games 2025;13:e84219</strong><p><span><a href="https://doi.org/10.2196/84219">doi:10.2196/84219</a></span></p><h3 id="Keywords">Keywords</h3></article><br><article><br><h3 id="Introduction" data-label="Introduction">Introduction</h3><h4>Overview of Young Adults and Burnout Risk</h4><p>Young people today face a unique constellation of interconnected pressures that contribute significantly to anxiety, worry, and burnout [-]. Soaring costs for housing, education (leading to significant student loan debt), and basic necessities create significant financial pressure [,]. Achieving traditional markers of adulthood (home ownership and a stable career) feels increasingly out of reach for numerous young people. Witnessing vast wealth disparities and feeling the system is rigged can fuel pessimism and a sense of unfairness about future prospects []. Furthermore, intense pressure to excel academically from a young age, secure prestigious internships or jobs, and build a seemingly perfect resume can create chronic stress []. Success is often narrowly defined and hypercompetitive. Importantly, these cumulative stressors arise during what developmental psychologists describe as emerging adulthood, a period marked by identity exploration and instability [].</p><p>Young adulthood, often referred to as emerging adulthood, is considered a distinct stage of development characterized by identity exploration, instability, self-focus, and shifts in social roles, typically spanning the late teens and 20s []. Epidemiological research indicates that many mental disorders first appear during this life stage, although timing varies across diagnostic categories—for example, anxiety disorders tend to surface earlier, while mood disorders can appear later [,]. These onset patterns often coincide with major life transitions involving education, work, and growing autonomy, which have been linked to higher psychological distress and lower well-being among young adults []. Hence, focusing on this demographic remains critical for understanding today’s mental health challenges and for identifying where digital interventions might best support well-being.</p><p>In addition, the current “always-on” digital culture and social media expose young people to curated highlights of others’ lives, careers, and achievements 24/7, fostering unrealistic comparisons, fear of missing out, and feelings of inadequacy [-]. The digital world also provides new avenues for bullying and harassment, impacting mental health significantly. Moreover, smartphones make it difficult to disconnect from work, studies, or social obligations [,]. The expectation to be constantly available and responsive erodes downtime and contributes to burnout. Moreover, doomscrolling or the constant exposure to negative news cycles and global crises (climate change, political or social conflict and unrest, or pandemics) can be overwhelming and induce feelings of helplessness [-]. Fueled by social media and competitive environments, many young adults internalize unrealistic expectations of perfection in all areas (looks, career, relationships, and hobbies), leading to self-criticism and anxiety about failure [-].</p><p>Moreover, while digitally connected, many young adults report feeling lonelier than ever [,,]. Traditional community structures (extended family, local community groups, and religious institutions) often play a less central role nowadays. Despite online networks, forming and maintaining deep, meaningful in-person relationships can be challenging in what is often perceived as a fast-paced, transient world []. Taken together, these factors can create a state of chronic, unrelenting stress [,-]. Feeling powerless over economic realities, global issues, or demanding work or school environments fuels burnout. Constant pressure and the “always-on” culture leave little time for genuine rest, relaxation, and hobbies that replenish energy. Hence, these factors do not exist in isolation. They feed into each other.</p><p>Social media comparisons fuel anxiety and worry about the future sap motivation, while perceived loneliness makes coping harder. It creates a vicious cycle that can be difficult to break. This study aims to make a step toward addressing the mental health crisis facing many young adults today. More specifically, video games, such as open-world games, have been shown in prior work to afford cognitive escapism, relaxation, and enhanced well-being to young people []. Video games and gamification techniques have been noted to positively affect the well-being of players in different ways [-]. However, critical questions remain about the potential role popular video games can play in young adults’ lives.</p><h4>Background on Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi Games</h4><p>The Super Mario Bros. franchise created by Nintendo Co, Ltd stands as one of the most globally popular and recognizable in entertainment history [,]. Since the groundbreaking original in 1985, Mario games have sold more than 430 million copies worldwide, making it one of the best-selling video game series ever. Its appeal transcends age, culture, and nationality. Super Mario, Luigi, Princess Peach, and the cute dinosaur Yoshi are all cultural icons, instantly recognizable even to nongamers. Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi games can help act as stress buffers and reduce negative affect in several critical ways. For example, engaging with the demanding spatial navigation, timing, and problem-solving tasks in Super Mario Bros. requires focused attention (working memory load). This acts as a distractor, effectively diverting finite cognitive resources away from rumination on real-world worries or negative thoughts, thereby interrupting cycles of pessimism or anxiety. Players become deeply immersed in “being” Mario or Yoshi, navigating the space, temporarily suspending self-referential thoughts and worries about real-life identity or performance.</p><p>Furthermore, the core narrative of Mario and Yoshi persistently overcoming obstacles to achieve goals serves as a powerful symbolic representation of perseverance and eventual triumph. Engaging with this narrative, especially through active participation (the player is Mario or Yoshi), can subtly reinforce schemas related to resilience and positive outcomes. The core objective (“Help Prince Florian” or “Rescue Princess Peach”) is unambiguous and morally positive, offering a clear purpose without complex emotional baggage or ambiguity. This reduces cognitive load associated with real-world problem interpretation. While challenging in their own ways, Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi games generally lack the prolonged high-stress tension of survival horror or competitive multiplayer games. Their rhythm often involves bursts of focused action followed by brief moments of lower tension (eg, traversing cleared sections), allowing for a more sustainable and restorative form of play.</p><p>Thus, Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi games can be a potent tool for temporary stress reduction, mood enhancement, and cognitive restoration, creating a mental “reset” that can foster a more optimistic and resourceful return to daily life. Their specific game design, combining skill demands with low real-world stakes, predictable rules, and positive affect induction, can make these games an effective vehicle for enhanced mental well-being. Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi games, hence, can act as an antidote by creating a virtual space that is the psychological inverse of a burnout-inducing environment.</p><h4>Enhancing Childlike Wonder and Reducing Burnout Risk</h4><p>Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi video games can offer pure, unadulterated joy and playfulness. More specifically, Super Mario Bros. games may help rekindle childlike wonder and help players see magic in the everyday. Jumping, running, breaking blocks, and collecting coins; these actions are inherently joyful and tactile. The satisfying “boing” of a jump, the “ching” of a coin, the smash of a brick; all these can trigger simple, primal pleasure. Mushrooms make players big, flowers shoot fire, stars make players invincible, turtles are cute enemies, clouds and trees have eyes! It presents a world operating on its own delightful, nonsensical logic, bypassing adult cynicism.</p><p>In addition, the vibrant colors, upbeat music, and generally sunny atmosphere (even underground or in castles has a playful menace) create an optimistic baseline. It is hard to stay cynical when that iconic tune is playing. In essence, Super Mario Bros. games act like a playful lens. It reminds players of the joy of pure discovery, the thrill of simple challenges, the magic of transformation, and the power of imagination that they possessed as children.</p><p>Furthermore, the visual and auditory design of Yoshi games is meticulously crafted to feel safe, warm, and inviting. Games such as <i>Yoshi’s Crafted World</i> and <i>Yoshi’s Woolly World</i> use a tangible, diorama-like aesthetic. Everything appears to be made of yarn, cardboard, and craft supplies. This evokes a sense of handmade charm and nostalgia, reminiscent of childhood arts and crafts. The world feels nonthreatening and playful. Yoshi games are bursting with joyful, bright colors, while the music is famously cheerful and melodic. Yoshi’s vocalizations (the flutter jump and the egg spit) and the sounds of collectibles are satisfying and cute. This creates a consistent visual and audio landscape of positivity.</p><p>Burnout is characterized by exhaustion, cynicism (detachment or negativity), and reduced efficacy. Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi video gameplay can help reduce burnout risk in the following ways. First, the attentional demand of Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi gameplay provides a mental break from work or role-related rumination (a core driver of exhaustion). This allows depleted cognitive resources (eg, prefrontal cortex function taxed by decision fatigue) to replenish. Induced flow states and positive affect (dopamine or serotonin release) counter chronic stress responses (eg, lowered cortisol and reduced sympathetic nervous system activation). This provides physiological recovery crucial for combating exhaustion.</p><p>Furthermore, Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi games’ rewarding mechanics and light-hearted aesthetic actively elevate mood, counteracting the persistent negative affect associated with burnout. That is, the game’s core loop reinforces the belief that effort leads to reward. Collecting coins, finding secrets, or beating a level after multiple tries demonstrates a reliable, predictable link between action and positive outcome, rebuilding trust in effort that burnout erodes. Moreover, the games’ narrative (perseverance leading to success) and aesthetics (colorful and playful) provide exposure to positive, noncynical representations, subtly challenging pervasive negative worldviews fostered by burnout.</p><p>Moreover, Yoshi games are also famously accessible. This removes the stress of failure and allows players to simply enjoy being in the world. The challenge comes from discovery and 100% completion, not from mere survival, making it a choice rather than a demand. While burnout is often fueled by anxiety about the future or rumination on the past, Yoshi games anchor players in the now.</p><p>Taken together, Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi games provide psychological restoration. The warm aesthetics, cheerful music, and a lack of intense pressure are not draining. They are replenishing. Playing feels like a break for the brain, similar to the effect of a walk in a pleasant park. The charm and kindness inherent in these games make it hard to be cynical. The games offer joyful sounds and enchanting visual feedback that help rebuild a sense of competence and agency in a low-pressure environment, countering the helplessness that fuels burnout.</p><p>Thus, in this study we aim to investigate if popular video games such as Nintendo’s classic Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi franchise are able to promote players’ childlike wonder—a state of openness, curiosity, and delight in the face of the new or mundane—and whether such experiences enhance overall happiness in life and reduce the risk of burnout among young adults.</p><br><h3 id="Methods" data-label="Methods">Methods</h3><h4>Study 1</h4><h5>Research Design Overview</h5><p>The findings of our qualitative study were reported in accordance with the Standards for Reporting Qualitative Research guidelines []. In addition, we adhered to the Journal Article Reporting Standards-mixed methods article reporting standards and offered information recommended for inclusion in research that reports the collection and integration of qualitative and quantitative data []. We conducted semistructured, cross-sectional interviews with open-ended, predetermined questions to explore and consider different personal opinions and views and help generate novel insights from data gathered in a natural setting [,]. Specifically, we invited study participants to share their thoughts about Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi games, and how, if at all, such a video game affects their day-to-day life. That is, during the interview, study participants were given an opportunity to reflect on and discuss how Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi games made them feel, what benefits (if any) they got from playing the game, and how and why they played the game. In case study participants played more than one Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi game, they were invited to reflect on the game they played the most.</p><h5>Researcher Description</h5><p>To help minimize any potential bias, 4 trained research assistants (RAs) conducted the interviews. RAs were trained and instructed not to guide the interviewees and their responses in any way. The team of RAs was diverse in sex (2 women and 2 men) and ethnicity (from 3 different continents) to help ensure increased comfort with study participants during interviews.</p><h5>Study Participants or Data Sources</h5><h6>Participant Recruitment</h6><p>As part of our qualitative study, we used a convenience sampling method. Potential participants were recruited via posters and by handing out flyers to students on a university campus in July and August 2025.</p><h6>Participant Selection</h6><p>The specific eligibility criteria for taking part in the qualitative study were that participants were full-time students and that they had some personal experience playing a Super Mario Bros. or Yoshi game before.</p><h6>Data Collection</h6><p>Over the course of 3 weeks, exploratory, in-depth interviews were conducted with 41 participants (women: n=19, 46.3%; men: n=21, 51.2%; preferred not to disclose sex: n=1, 2.4%; mean age 22.51, SD 1.52 years). All interviewees were full-time students (confirmed by their student IDs) and had experience playing a Super Mario Bros. or Yoshi game (screening questions by the RAs included the name of the specific Super Mario Bros. or Yoshi games respondents had played and which console they used to play the game, eg, Wii U, Nintendo Switch, or Nintendo Switch 2). Interviews were conducted in a university cafeteria and lasted between 25 and 40 minutes. All interviewees were reassured of the anonymity of their responses and were informed that their participation would help inform academic research. At the end of the interview, each interviewee was given a chance to ask any questions they may have had.</p><h6>Statistical Analysis</h6><p>We examined our qualitative data gathered from the interviews, following recommended and established procedures for qualitative data analyses [-]. RAs had a chance to familiarize themselves with the data collected by transcribing the interviews and carefully reading the transcripts. Furthermore, the coding of interview data was conducted in duplicate by the authors, and any potential discrepancy was discussed and resolved. In doing so, we followed the constant comparison technique in prior published work, collected and analyzed interview data in tandem, and continuously compared the newly collected data against the existing insights. As a first step of our analysis, we grouped conceptually linked data and reduced them to a set of meaningful concepts. That is, we examined and analyzed the data to develop insights and a holistic understanding of interviewees’ responses and key elements of Super Mario Bros. or Yoshi games that were noted to affect their lives.</p><p>In addition, we used descriptive phrases and open coding to develop further insights regarding key drivers and potential process explanations about interviewees’ reflections of Super Mario Bros. or Yoshi games and critical elements of gameplay that may influence their overall happiness in life and burnout risk. Moreover, in joint discussions by the team of RAs and authors, we integrated relevant literature in an iterative process, further explored key elements of Super Mario Bros. or Yoshi games that influenced players’ lives, and finalized the key elements of our conceptual framework.</p><h4>Study 2</h4><h5>Research Design</h5><p>As part of study 2, we conducted a cross-sectional survey using a convenience sampling approach.</p><h5>Inclusion and Exclusion</h5><p>Participants were deemed eligible to take part in the study if they were full-time university students at the time of completing the study and if they had personal experience playing a Super Mario Bros. or Yoshi game. We conducted the study in July and August 2025 and followed the Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) guidelines to report the observational, cross-sectional studies () [].</p><h5>Sampling Procedures</h5><p>Potential study participants were recruited by handing out flyers and using posters on a university campus in July and August 2025. Trained RAs informed potential study participants that the study would take no longer than 15 minutes and that each participant would receive US $5 (approximately £4) as compensation for taking part in the study.</p><h5>Sample Size, Power, and Precision</h5><p>Over the course of 5 weeks, 4 RAs helped with the data collection (student ID check and simple screening questions before the study, ie, which Super Mario Bros. or Yoshi game participants had played before and which console they had used for gameplay, such as Wii U, Nintendo Switch, Nintendo Switch 2, etc) and managed to recruit a total of 350 participants. Because 14 participants did not complete the entire survey, their responses were discarded from the study, and the effective number of responses was 336. In case study participants noted playing more than one Super Mario Bros. or Yoshi game, they were encouraged to consider and think of the game they played the most when answering the study’s survey questions. RAs invited participants to complete a brief paper-and-pencil questionnaire about gaming and their daily life activities.</p><h5>Participant Characteristics</h5><p>The final sample consisted of 336 full-time university students (women: 19/41, 46.3%; men: 21/41, 51.2%; prefer not to disclose sex: 1/41, 2.4%; mean age 22.51, SD 1.52).</p><h5>Measures and Covariates</h5><p>Specifically, participants answered questions about burnout risk that were adapted from validated, previously published scales designed to measure burnout risk [,], and included items such as “I feel emotionally drained by my daily responsibilities (caregiving, work, etc),” “I have become more cynical or detached about activities I used to care about,” and “I doubt whether my efforts actually make a difference”).</p><p>In addition, participants were invited to answer questions to measure their overall happiness in life. Measurement items to capture life happiness were adapted from previously published happiness in life scales [,] and consisted of 3 items (“I feel grateful for the good things in my life,” “I am satisfied with the overall direction of my life and look forward to what lies ahead,” “Overall I would describe myself as a happy person”). Moreover, we captured the extent to which gameplay enhanced participants’ childlike wonder by adapting three items from previously published scale items on noticing novelty and joy in discovery, feeling wonder in response to stimuli [-] (“Playing a Super Mario Bros./Yoshi game helps me feel delighted by small, ordinary things that others overlook (e.g., shapes in clouds, patterns in pavement),” “Super Mario Bros./Yoshi gameplay encourages me stop to admire or explore things that spark my curiosity, even if they seem unimportant (e.g., a hidden path, an unusual insect),” “Playing a Super Mario Bros./Yoshi game encourages me to pause and to appreciate playful or whimsical details in my environment”). All responses were measured on a 7-point Likert scale (1=strongly disagree, 7=strongly agree). As control, participants indicated their sex (1=female, 2=male, 3=prefer not to disclose).</p><p>To ensure the quality of measurement, all scale items were reviewed by the research team for clarity and consistency before survey administration. The questionnaire was distributed in printed form on campus and completed individually by respondents. RAs who facilitated recruitment and survey distribution were not informed of the study’s hypotheses and followed standardized instructions to minimize expectancy or response bias. Psychometric properties of the measures were examined using confirmatory factor analyses and reliability testing. All factor loadings were significant (<i>P</i>&lt;.001). Cronbach α, composite reliability (CR), and average variance extracted (AVE) all exceeded widely accepted thresholds (α ≥.70, CR ≥0.70, and AVE ≥0.50), indicating strong internal consistency and convergent validity [-]. The Fornell-Larcker criterion further supported discriminant validity across constructs [].</p><h5>Statistical Analysis</h5><p>We followed recommended procedures for conducting confirmatory factor analyses and examined the factor structure and reliability scores for the measurement items in our survey study [,]. This was done to examine whether the items significantly loaded on their intended factors and had weak cross-loadings. Furthermore, we examined the AVE and CR scores for the scales used in our study. Moreover, we tested whether the average variance extracted for each construct was greater than the squared correlations between the construct and other variables in our survey []. The hypothesized 3-factor model (childlike wonder, happiness, and burnout risk) was tested using confirmatory factor analysis in IBM SPSS AMOS 29.0 with maximum likelihood estimation.</p><p>In addition, we conducted a mediation analysis with the PROCESS macro [] (model 4; bootstrapped samples=5000; 95% CI) to examine the influence of Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi games’ affordance of childlike wonder (independent variable) on overall happiness in life (mediator) and, consequently, on players’ burnout risk (dependent variable). In order for PROCESS not to treat sex as a continuous variable, sex was coded as a dummy variable (0=female, 1=male). Due to the insufficient sample size (n=1), the “prefer not to disclose” category was excluded from analysis.</p><h4>Ethical Considerations</h4><h5>Study 1</h5><p>Ethics approval for the study was received from Imperial College London’s Analytics, Marketing, and Operations (AMO) Department. At the time of data collection, the AMO Department followed Imperial College London’s ethics protocol for research involving human participants, which includes internal review and written approval by the departmental head of the research group. The procedure ensures compliance with Imperial College Research Ethics Committee guidelines and the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki. Informed consent was obtained from all participants, and participants were informed that they had the right to withdraw from the study at any time point. Study data were anonymized and kept confidential within the research team. More specifically, we ensured that no identification of individual study participants in any images or supplementary material of the manuscript was possible. After the interview was completed, each participant was thanked, debriefed about the study’s purpose, and given £15 (approximately US $20) as compensation for their time.</p><h5>Study 2</h5><p>For study 2, ethics approval was received from Imperial College London at the Departmental level, Analytics, Marketing, and Operations. The AMO Department follows Imperial College London’s ethics protocol for research involving human participants, which includes internal review and written approval by the departmental head of the research group. This procedure ensures compliance with the Imperial College Research Ethics Committee guidelines and the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki. All data collected were anonymized and kept confidential within the research team. Study participants provided informed consent and were informed that they had the right to withdraw from the study at any time and without having to give a particular reason. We ensured that no identification of individual study participants in any supplementary material or in any images of the manuscript was possible. After completing the survey, each participant was thanked, debriefed, received £4 (approximately US $5) as compensation for their time, and was invited to ask any questions they may have had about the study.</p><br><h3 id="Results" data-label="Results">Results</h3><h4>Study 1: Overview</h4><p>The findings of the in-depth interviews demonstrated that Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi games’ affordance of childlike wonder played an important role in their impact on players’ lives. In , we list the representative quotes, which indicate the extent to which players viewed Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi games as fostering childlike wonder and the influence they had on their day-to-day life. In addition, interviewees noted how Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi gameplay affected their overall happiness in life as well as how gameplay helped reduce their risk of burnout (refer to  for representative quotes).</p><p>Participants frequently described the bright colors and optimistic tone of <i>Super Mario Bros. Wonder</i> as evoking feelings of calm and childlike joy.  illustrates this visual atmosphere, depicting the cheerful landscape that several interviewees referred to when recalling moments of wonder and relaxation.</p><p>Interviewees highlighted how the game’s design balances challenge with playfulness, creating a sense of ease that contrasts with daily pressures.  exemplifies this tone, showing even “enemies” portrayed in a gentle, nonthreatening way—an aspect the interviewees associated with relaxation and stress relief.</p><p>Interviewees often described <i>Yoshi’s Crafted World</i> as a warm, inviting environment that felt comforting and safe.  illustrates the handcrafted, diorama-like aesthetic that many associated with nostalgia and emotional restoration.</p><div><figcaption><span><b>Table 1. </b>Representative quotes of interviewees in an in-depth qualitative study about the key effects of Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi games and their influence on their lives.</span></figcaption><table><colgroup><col width="170" span="1"><col width="830" span="1"></colgroup><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Game key effects</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Representative quotes</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childlike wonder</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ul><li>“Playing Yoshi transports me back in time. It’s a bit like time travel. I see myself as this kid again, wondering about the possibilities and beauty of this world. It’s a bit like a fresh new start.” [Respondent 8]<br></li><li>“Super Mario Bros. Wonder is crazy. I love how the clouds are all animated and full of life. I hardly see the sky these days. Living in a big city it’s hard to get a sense of nature. Deep down that certainly must affect people. We did not evolve over thousands of years to run around like rats underground, squashed in hot and cramped, tight spaces like the subway and compete for the tiniest of spaces. Super Mario Bros. Wonder is like a breath of fresh air with trees, clouds, water and fun everywhere. It makes me feel I am part of nature and nature is part of me. I miss that feeling. When I play Super Mario Wonder it is as if I’m a kid again.” [Respondent 13]<br></li><li>“Haha, the moment I switch on and the game starts with the iconic Super Mario tune in my head I sense a moment of relief and I am playing the game as I used to when I was a child. Probably that was the happiest time of my life when I was a child. Super Mario gives me a chance to appreciate the world and everything again with the eyes of a child that is not jaded, not tired but full of energy, full of enthusiasm, interest, and marveling at what surrounds us and what each new day may bring.” [Respondent 16]<br></li><li>“Playing with friends or just by myself lying on the bed, Super Mario Bros. games make me feel warm and fuzzy and comfortable. A bit like being wrapped in a cozy, warm blanket on a cold winter day when it is snowing outside and as a kid you are dreaming about the snowflakes and wondering how much snow may fall today. Most days I feel exhausted and no energy to appreciate things anymore. Playing Super Mario gives me this new sense of being a kid with wide, interested eyes wanting to learn and explore again.” [Respondent 30]<br></li><li>“There is nothing too fancy about Super Mario games. Come to think about it, that’s what probably makes the Super Mario Bros. games so special. They hold your hand and let you find that first super mushroom, make that first jump, all in a way that feels like play. It is not a chore and does not feel like a nuisance but it’s a game! The colors are so vibrant and fun. The music and tunes are cheerful and put a smile on my face every single time. I play and I cannot help but wonder about… small things. There is this fly on my window. But I don’t mind. Maybe the fly will find a way out. I hear the rain outside and I keep looking at the clouds. I think of the clouds in the game and smile. The game makes me feel like a kid in a candy store. You keep looking at all the sweets with amazement, just wondering which one of these incredible candies should be the one to be picked? What a treat!” [Respondent 39]<br></li><li>It is easy to dismiss this but then I feel it is true. Playing Yoshi games makes me feel like… hey, don’t take everything so seriously out there. You see, it is easy to get lost in all sorts of worries and anxieties, stress and negativity. I don’t see the flowers, the sky, the clouds, the sunset or the sunrise. I have become blind to the beauty of well everything really. But Yoshi video games open my eyes again to that way of looking at the world like a kid in a candy store. Running full speed on top of the clouds? … Hahaha, let’s a go!” [Respondent 40]<br></li></ul></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall happiness in life</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ul><li>“Look at your phone and everyone tells you to buy more, to chase the big dream and exotic destinations and you will get happy there. Only to keep chasing, keep buying more, travel to no end to get lost, and all the while happiness may be just around the corner. Super Mario games give me that feeling that happiness is truly in the small things in life. It does not take a trip to the Maldives. What are you chasing? Stop chasing, it’s right there in front of your eyes. You don’t have to spend millions to feel happy. Do you know what’s crazy? Playing my Super Mario on the Nintendo Switch makes me think back of the time when I played Super Mario waiting in the dentist’s waiting room. And you go, hold on a minute, the dentist room?!? That’s the least likely place to feel happiness and you are right. But I still remember, I am sitting there and I completed the game. I completed the game and listened to the credits roll on and that iconic theme… that music… at that moment, I felt happiness. This is the pure magic of playing Super Mario. You can be sitting in a dentist’s waiting room and feel happiness. That’s truly awesome. Super Mario is simple, pure, happiness.” [Respondent 2]<br></li><li>“So I often think about what it means to be happy. There are zillion of books on this and the internet has even more answers. Everyone seems to know what will definitely make you happy. You need a house. You need to run that marathon. You need to look like this and buy that. When was the last time I felt truly happy. I mean truly happy? It’s when I played Super Mario Bros. Wonder and I switched on and was there in the moment. When I jumped, I jumped, and when I ran, I ran. That was happiness.” [Respondent 17]<br></li><li>“The most precious resources we may have are time, health, knowledge and skill, family and the most previous things in life are free like health. Social media tells me I need to dream big and do big things to achieve big things, everything has to be crazy big. Happiness may be in small things, in the quiet moments, in the time when I am allowed to be myself and just be there and appreciate the moment I have. Super Mario is this simple happiness that made me feel so… happy, there is no other word for it, when I was a kid. Happiness as a kid did not have to be complicated. Happiness was completing a level. Happiness was spending the summer holidays doing nothing special or grand but just enjoying the life one had.” [Respondent 25]<br></li></ul><ul><li>“I love level one in my Super Mario Bros. U Deluxe. The grass is green and the clouds and the sky look so cheerful and endearing. It makes me feel I want to walk through the woods, climb trees, balance, and jump off. Or maybe I should lie on the grass and watch the clouds fly by high in the sky waiting for rain to come or a summer thunderstorm or even rolling thunder and snow? Super Mario Bros. U Deluxe reminds me that I am part of nature and it’s here for me. Jumping, climbing, jumping, picking up a leaf, a flower. Nature is not just an amazing backdrop in Super Mario, it’s integral to the game and how it makes me smile again.” [Respondent 26]<br></li></ul><ul><li>“I kept jumping and falling. Jumping and falling all the time. Finally I made the jump and I was over the moon. What a feeling of happiness. I still remember it. That Super Mario theme is pure, catchy video game magic and happiness for the tired soul! Cannot feel not happy when listening to it. It’s not a big, dramatic piece. Super Mario games are like that. Happiness in the simplest and clean form.” [Respondent 33]<br></li></ul><ul><li>“A while ago I did have the strangest of feelings. I was sitting on my sofa and played Super Mario when I looked outside the window and spotted the moon shining. I haven’t seen the moon for ages. I mean ages. And there it was shining and smiling at me. At least I felt it was smiling at me. I even discovered a few stars. Super Mario is a magical treat for the soul. The game does not shout but it gently holds you and lets you explore by yourself. Why would playing a video game make me appreciate my natural surroundings more? It is not obvious to me. Probably on the subconscious level more than anything Super Mario allows me to be part of nature how humans did for centuries, running around, trying to get a lucky break and find a leaf, flower, mushroom that gives them some much needed energy boost, jumping, exploring, avoiding danger, and finally making it back home.” [Respondent 34]<br></li><li>“Keep collecting those coins of joy. Power-up with little moments of happiness and never stop looking for hidden blocks <img alt="" src="https://asset.jmir.pub/assets/7453200d4c8864ccc85e7a812ac577c7.png">. That’s what Super Mario taught me more than anything.” [Respondent 37]<br></li></ul></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Burnout risk reduction</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ul><li>“Yoshi games help me see the world and my life with softness, playfulness and wonder. The fact that it allows me to appreciate the magic in something as simple and joyful as Super Mario is what brings me joy. Never underestimate the power of play. Life can feel meaningless and empty. Whether it’s jumping as Yoshi or noticing the way light hits a glass window, you are actively co-creating a kinder, more magical world just by choosing to see it that way. This may be Yoshi’s biggest super power.” [Respondent 8]<br></li><li>“Sad how cynical life has become. Do you know when it all started? What is the cause of this? Everyone is cynical and tired of life. It’s almost as if humans have given up already. Tragic really when to think about it. When I play my Nintendo Yoshi games I feel less anxious and worry and the crises in my life seem that little bit further away. That moment of inner peace is priceless.” [Respondent 11]<br></li><li>“It is hard to feel excited and energized how I used to. Life just keeps happening to you. It’s everywhere you look though. Yoshi, Princess Peach, Super Mario and the whole gang brighten my days just keep on running and jumping up that flagpole as high as you can. It gives me a bit more energy and less worry, a bit more strength to keep going another day and not keep thinking about all the things.” [Respondent 28]<br></li><li>“Burnout may be the shadow of deep care. If you feel its weight. Breathe. Remember you don’t need to carry the wonder. You are the wonder. Mario is our fellow traveler in this journey. Super Mario games allow me to see the magic in small things. It’s a true gift to feel life has still something in store and not being tired of it all.” [Respondent 33]<br></li><li>“Do you sometimes feel tired of it all? I do. What helps me is to step out and do things that give me space to stop worrying and overthinking things. For example when I play my favorite Yoshi on my Nintendo Switch and get some energy back and motivation back in life. Not everything seems lost anymore when you got Yoshi to cheer you on.” [Respondent 32]<br></li><li>“Weird how pointless life can be or feel that way. The news gives me thousand things happening at the same time. So much violence, war, hate, abuse, disconnection, all the time. I need a break from this. It just makes me feel exhausted and I cannot make a difference anyway. I am not going to stop that war or people from acting selfishly. I feel lost and sad. Super Mario gives me back some happiness and moment of when I can enjoy the time so I do not lose hope entirely or willingness to do anything. It’s a happiness booster that helps me keep going a bit longer and keep hanging in there. It’s nice to feel life still has some happy moments to offer and not just trouble. To level up and keep looking forward to the next adventure.” [Respondent 41]<br></li></ul></td></tr></tbody></table></div><figure><a name="figure1">‎</a><a title="Figure 1. Cheerful landscape in Super Mario Bros. Wonder (reproduced with permission from Nintendo)." href="https://asset.jmir.pub/assets/2436544ca1a6a5eac36c063d479af35e.png" id="figure1"><img src="https://asset.jmir.pub/assets/2436544ca1a6a5eac36c063d479af35e.png"></a><figcaption><span><b>Figure 1. </b> Cheerful landscape in <i>Super Mario Bros. Wonder</i> (reproduced with permission from Nintendo). </span></figcaption></figure><figure><a name="figure2">‎</a><a title="Figure 2. Super Mario facing sleeping enemies in Super Mario Bros. Wonder (reproduced with permission from Nintendo)." href="https://asset.jmir.pub/assets/cbfe54ef5cffc007f923fb559eb1b2c7.png" id="figure2"><img src="https://asset.jmir.pub/assets/cbfe54ef5cffc007f923fb559eb1b2c7.png"></a><figcaption><span><b>Figure 2. </b> Super Mario facing sleeping enemies in <i>Super Mario Bros. Wonder</i> (reproduced with permission from Nintendo). </span></figcaption></figure><figure><a name="figure3">‎</a><a title="Figure 3. The bright and cheerful environment of Yoshi’s Crafted World (reproduced with permission from Nintendo)." href="https://asset.jmir.pub/assets/da5b5140ec0ce3b07f5270df857326bf.png" id="figure3"><img src="https://asset.jmir.pub/assets/da5b5140ec0ce3b07f5270df857326bf.png"></a><figcaption><span><b>Figure 3. </b> The bright and cheerful environment of <i>Yoshi’s Crafted World</i> (reproduced with permission from Nintendo). </span></figcaption></figure><h4>Study 2: Statistical Analysis Results</h4><p>Detailed survey measurement items and reliability scores are listed in . Confirmatory factor analyses showed that all measurement items significantly loaded on their intended factors (&gt;0.79; <i>P</i>&lt;.001) with weak cross-loadings (&lt;0.27). In addition, AVE and CR scores exceeded the recommended thresholds. In addition, the Cronbach α scores were generally high and results showed that the AVE for each construct was greater than the squared correlations between the construct and other variables in our survey in support of discriminant validity (). The model demonstrated good fit to the data (<i>χ</i><sup>2</sup><sub>24</sub>=30.6, Tucker-Lewis index=0.99, comparative fit index=0.99, normed fit index=0.98, and root mean square error of approximation=0.03; 90% CI 0.00-0.06; <i>P</i>=.17). Estimation of standardized residuals showed that no values were particularly large (&gt;2.00), indicating no substantial localized areas of misfit.</p><div><figcaption><span><b>Table 2. </b>Cross-sectional survey measurement items’ factor loadings and reliabilities.</span></figcaption><table><colgroup><col width="30" span="1"><col width="770" span="1"><col width="0" span="1"><col width="200" span="1"></colgroup><thead><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Survey study constructs and measurement items</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Factor loadings</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><b>Burnout risk<sup>a</sup></b></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><br></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I feel emotionally drained by my daily responsibilities (caregiving, work, etc)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">.84</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><br></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I have become more cynical or detached about activities I used to care about</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">.79</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><br></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I doubt whether my efforts actually make a difference</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">.87</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><b>Happiness in life<sup>b</sup></b></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><br></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I feel grateful for the good things in my life</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">.85</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><br></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I am satisfied with the overall direction of my life and look forward to what lies ahead</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">.80</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><br></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall I would describe myself as a happy person</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">.87</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><b>Childlike wonder<sup>c</sup></b></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><br></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><br></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Playing a Super Mario Bros/Yoshi game helps me feel delighted by small, ordinary things that others overlook (eg, shapes in clouds, patterns in pavement)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">.92</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><br></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Playing a Super Mario Bros/Yoshi game encourages me to pause and to appreciate playful or whimsical details in my environment</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">.90</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><br></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Super Mario Bros/Yoshi gameplay encourages me to stop to admire or explore things that spark my curiosity, even if they seem unimportant (eg, a hidden path, an unusual insect)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">.91</td></tr></tbody></table><fn id="table2fn1"><p><sup>a</sup>α=.83; composite reliability (CR)=0.87; average variance extracted (AVE)=0.70.</p></fn><fn id="table2fn2"><p><sup>b</sup>α=.86; CR=0.88; AVE=0.71.</p></fn><fn id="table2fn3"><p><sup>c</sup>α=.92; CR=0.94; AVE=0.83.</p></fn></div><h4>Study 2: Mediation Analysis Results</h4><p>The results of the mediation analysis with PROCESS macro [] (model 4; bootstrapped samples=5000; 95% CI; sample size=336) showed that Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi games’ affordance of childlike wonder (independent variable) had a significant, positive influence on players’ overall happiness in life (b=0.30, SE=0.04, <i>t</i>=6.8, 95% CI 0.21-0.38; <i>P</i>&lt;.001; ). In turn, overall happiness in life significantly reduced players’ burnout risk (b=–0.48, SE=0.05, <i>t</i>=–9.55, 95% CI –0.57 to –0.38; ). Gender had no significant effect on happiness (b=–0.05, SE=0.12, <i>t</i>=–0.42, 95% CI –0.29 to 0.19; <i>P</i>=.68; ) and no significant effect on burnout (b=0.02, SE=0.11, <i>t</i>=0.14, 95% CI –0.20 to 0.23; <i>P</i>=.89; ). Furthermore, the results showed that happiness fully mediated the impact of childlike wonder on burnout, as the direct effect of childlike wonder on burnout risk became insignificant (b=–0.08, SE=0.04, <i>t</i>=–1.88, 95% CI –0.16 to 0.01; ), while the indirect effect of childlike wonder on burnout risk was significant (b=–0.14, BootSE=0.03, 95% CI –0.20 to –0.09).</p><div><figcaption><span><b>Table 3. </b>Cross-sectional survey mediation regression results: effect of childlike wonder on happiness.</span></figcaption><table><colgroup><col width="30" span="1"><col width="220" span="1"><col width="200" span="1"><col width="190" span="1"><col width="0" span="1"><col width="180" span="1"><col width="0" span="1"><col width="180" span="1"></colgroup><thead><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Predictor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">b (95% CI)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">SE</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><i>t</i> test</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><i>P</i> value</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="8" rowspan="1"><b>DV<sup>a</sup>: Happiness<sup>b</sup></b></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><br></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50 (2.07 to 2.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">11.43</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><br></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childlike wonder</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30 (0.21 to 0.38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">6.79</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><br></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–0.05 (–0.29 to 0.19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">–0.42</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"> .68</td></tr></tbody></table><fn id="table3fn1"><p><sup>a</sup>DV: dependent variable.</p></fn><fn id="table3fn2"><p><sup>b</sup><i>R</i>=0.35, <i>R</i>²=0.12, mean squared error=1.43, <i>F</i><sub>2, 333</sub>=23.16; <i>P</i>&lt;.001.</p></fn></div><div><figcaption><span><b>Table 4. </b>Cross-sectional survey mediation regression results: effect of happiness on burnout.</span></figcaption><table><colgroup><col width="30" span="1"><col width="220" span="1"><col width="200" span="1"><col width="190" span="1"><col width="180" span="1"><col width="180" span="1"></colgroup><thead><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Predictor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">b (95% CI)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><i>t</i> test</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><i>P</i> value</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><b>DV<sup>a</sup>: Burnout<sup>b</sup></b></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><br></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.37 (4.91-5.83)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><br></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childlike wonder</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–0.08 (–0.16 to 0.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–1.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><br></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Happiness</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–0.48 (–0.57 to –0.38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–9.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><br></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 (–0.20 to 0.23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.89</td></tr></tbody></table><fn id="table4fn1"><p><sup>a</sup>DV: dependent variable.</p></fn><fn id="table4fn2"><p><sup>b</sup><i>R</i>=0.52, <i>R</i>²=0.27, mean squared error=1.17, <i>F</i><sub>3, 332</sub>=40.80; <i>P</i>&lt;.001.</p></fn></div><br><h3 id="Discussion" data-label="Discussion">Discussion</h3><h4>Principal Findings</h4><p>The findings of this study show that players appreciated Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi games’ affordance of childlike wonder as well as enhanced feelings of happiness. In addition, the findings of the study indicated the extent to which players noted Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi games’ ability to reduce burnout risks. The findings of the quantitative study further showed that Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi games’ affordance of childlike wonder was positively associated with people’s overall happiness in life. Finally, happiness was negatively associated with burnout risk of study respondents, hence indicating the potential for popular video games such as Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi games to help reduce burnout risk. The colorful, low-pressure worlds of Yoshi games were described by interviewees as a “vacation for the mind.”  illustrates this atmosphere, conveying the playful and uplifting tone that helps transform ordinary play into a restorative emotional experience.</p><figure><a name="figure4">‎</a><a title="Figure 4. Joyous scenery in Yoshi’s Crafted World (reproduced with permission from Nintendo)." href="https://asset.jmir.pub/assets/41d80dc12875dea63b20c88c27ba6f34.png" id="figure4"><img src="https://asset.jmir.pub/assets/41d80dc12875dea63b20c88c27ba6f34.png"></a><figcaption><span><b>Figure 4. </b> Joyous scenery in <i>Yoshi’s Crafted World</i> (reproduced with permission from Nintendo). </span></figcaption></figure><h4>Comparison to Prior Work</h4><p>Prior work has noted the role video games can play in people’s lives, including enhanced cognitive escapism and relaxation [-]. Beyond escapism, prior research using Self-Determination Theory indicates that games can support basic psychological needs for autonomy, competence, and relatedness, which are associated with intrinsic motivation and need-contingent, short-term improvements in well-being []. Players have also been noted to engage with games strategically for mood management and coping-based emotion regulation, selecting particular gameplay challenges or mechanics to reduce stress, elevate mood, or regain a sense of control [-]. How popular video games such as Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi may affect young adults’ ability to look at the world and their lives in renewed, childlike wonder and how this may affect their overall happiness and reduce risk of burnout, however, remains unanswered. Moreover, nostalgia has been noted to promote well-being by drawing on cherished past experiences to restore positive affect, meaning, and a sense of connection [], and mainstream, long-running franchises often cue players’ nostalgia, especially when they prompt recall of past play experience with familiar series, settings, or characters []. However, nostalgia alone may not fully explain the uplifting, playful stance reported by players of whimsical franchises such as Super Mario and Yoshi, pointing to a distinct experiential state-childlike wonder-that has not yet been systematically examined.</p><p>While prior research examined how various gamification techniques may enhance people’s feelings of hope or connection with a new digital offering [-], critical questions remained about the role highly popular video games, such as Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi, may play in reducing people’s burnout risk. Although previous studies shed light on designing offerings that make people’s lives easier, put a smile on their face, and possibly inspire them and help form a stronger bond with them [-], work has only recently begun to examine how specific content and structural features of games shape emotional outcomes. For example, game aesthetics such as visual style, world design, music, and pacing have been proposed to elicit both hedonic enjoyment and deeper, reflective emotions [,]. Likewise, soundtrack music in games has been shown to shape players’ emotional responses, for example, by intensifying positive emotions and enhancing horror experiences []. In addition, in-game success has been found to predict mood repair and satisfaction of competence and autonomy to mediate effects on enjoyment []. Notably, these mechanisms have seldom been linked to broader indicators of well-being, such as sustained happiness or resilience to burnout, particularly among young adults.</p><p>Recent reviews suggest that commercial video games show promise for alleviating symptoms of anxiety and depression [,]. While these findings are encouraging, the present study takes a different perspective: rather than positioning entertainment games as treatments, it considers whether everyday play can function as a subtle, restorative micro-environment. Thus, the current study contributes to work examining the influence of gaming on mental well-being and, in doing so, further helps bridge gaming and mental health science [,] by identifying childlike wonder as a unique emotional pathway through which mainstream games may support happiness and reduce burnout risk.</p><h4>Limitations</h4><p>The benefits of video gameplay, including Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi, are likely to be contingent on moderate, voluntary play primarily for enjoyment. Compulsive video gameplay or excessive escapism used solely to avoid real problems can be maladaptive and undermine optimism by neglecting real-world agency. Moreover, playing Super Mario and Yoshi games can help mitigate individual experiences of burnout, but does not address systemic causes (eg, excessive workload, unfair practices). Thus, it may complement, not replace, organizational interventions. Moreover, in this study, we examined self-reported burnout risk. Future research examining the long-term effects of gameplay on actual burnout risk is richly deserving. In addition, we encourage future work to study the potential effects of gameplay on people of varying ages, demographic backgrounds, etc., and examine the influence that such gameplay may have on various aspects of people’s overall well-being. Examining such variations could reveal how developmental context and lived experience shape how popular games relate to well-being.</p><h4>Future Research</h4><p>The specific design elements of Super Mario Bros., as well as Yoshi games and their focus on skill-based mastery, low violence, predictable rules, achievable goals, and positive aesthetics, may be crucial for fostering the beneficial aspects described in this study. Not all video games offer this combination. Future research that further investigates the potential positive and negative effects of video gameplay on human happiness, resilience, and empathy is richly deserving. Current work examines the extent to which internet use may affect people’s anxiety and stress [,]; however, there is also work suggesting offerings to put a smile on users’ faces and make their lives easier [-].</p><p>Because additional interviews continued to offer new and nuanced insights, saturation in our qualitative study may not have been achieved, and we invite future research to explore and further investigate the role of popular games in people’s lives and their potential impact on the resilience, coping ability, physical and emotional health, as well as overall well-being of people across ages and various lifestyles. As previous research indicates an increasing number of people searching for meaning in their lives and feeling detached from nature as well as fellow human beings [-], additional work studying the effects of popular video games on people’s empathy, perceived loneliness, biophilia, as well as gratitude and levels of overconsumption is richly deserving.</p><p>Nintendo’s Super Mario Bros., as well as Yoshi games, can be more than just platformers. They are carefully constructed wonder simulators. They reject the high-stakes, high-stress models of many modern games in favor of an experience that prioritizes safety, curiosity, and joy. For a person whose life may be dominated by deadlines, overwhelming demands, and a perceived loss of control, stepping into Super Mario’s or Yoshi’s crafted world can be a form of digital therapy. It allows the person to practice being curious again, to experience uncomplicated joy, to succeed in small, measurable ways, and to simply exist in a moment of bright, colorful, and kind-hearted joy.</p><p>These games, in essence, are a vacation for the mind, facilitating the very childlike wonder that burnout so effectively extinguishes. Intentional game design can do more than just entertain - it can heal, restore, and inspire. Future research further exploring the various ways gameplay may affect people’s outlook and approach to life is richly deserving.</p><h4>Conclusions</h4><p>Insights from the qualitative study indicated players’ appreciation of Super Mario and Yoshi games’ affordance of childlike wonder, happiness in life, and a reduction in burnout risk. In addition to this, the findings of the quantitative analyses showed how Super Mario and Yoshi games’ affordance of childlike wonder influenced happiness in life and significantly reduced burnout risk. These video games, hence, can be effective vehicles for enhanced mental well-being. More specifically, the current findings show that Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi games act as an effective antidote by creating a virtual space that is the psychological inverse of a burnout-inducing environment.</p><p>In conclusion, the findings for this study demonstrate that popular video games, such as Super Mario Bros. and Yoshi, can enhance childlike wonder, which in turn increases overall happiness and reduces burnout risk. This work is innovative in identifying childlike wonder as a previously underexplored emotional mechanism that links everyday gameplay with improved well-being. It differs from prior studies that have focused mainly on escapism, stress relief, or need satisfaction by showing how mainstream entertainment games can evoke curiosity, playfulness, and joy that counteract cynicism and exhaustion. The study contributes to the growing field connecting gaming and mental health by positioning popular titles as restorative digital spaces rather than merely sources of distraction. Practically, the findings suggest that thoughtfully designed, low-pressure games may serve as simple, real-world tools to rekindle curiosity, uplift mood, and support resilience among young adults facing burnout.</p></article><h4>Acknowledgments</h4><p>The authors thank all the study participants for their time. In addition, the authors would like to thank Nintendo for permitting us to take photos of their Super Mario and Yoshi games for inclusion in the manuscript. The authors used DeepSeek R1 for spelling and grammar checks of the manuscript.</p><h4>Funding</h4><p>No external financial support or grants were received from any public, commercial, or not-for-profit entities for the research, authorship, or publication of this article.</p><h4>Data Availability</h4><p>The data for the study are available from the authors on reasonable request.</p><h4>Authors' Contributions</h4><p>WT was responsible for methodology, data collection, formal analysis, investigation, writing, and reviewing and editing the manuscript. CH was responsible for methodology, data collection, formal analysis, investigation, writing and editing the manuscript, and supervision. ABE was responsible for conceptualization, methodology, data collection, formal analysis, investigation, writing, reviewing, and editing the manuscript, and supervision.</p><h4>Conflicts of Interest</h4><p>None declared.</p><hr><br><hr><a name="Abbreviations">‎</a><h4 id="Abbreviations" data-label="Abbreviations">Abbreviations</h4><table><tbody><tr><td><b>AMOS:</b> Analysis of Moment Structures</td></tr><tr><td><b>BootSE:</b> bootstrapped standard error</td></tr><tr><td><b>MSE:</b> mean squared error</td></tr><tr><td><b>RA:</b> research assistant</td></tr><tr><td><b>SPSS:</b> Statistical Package for the Social Science</td></tr><tr><td><b>STROBE:</b> Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology</td></tr></tbody></table><br><hr><p>Edited by  S Brini; submitted 16.Sep.2025; peer-reviewed by B Duffek,  K Yoshimura; comments to author 11.Oct.2025; accepted 24.Nov.2025; published 19.Dec.2025.</p><a href="https://support.jmir.org/hc/en-us/articles/115002955531" id="Copyright" target="_blank" aria-label="Copyright - what is a Creative Commons License?" data-label="Copyright">Copyright <span></span></a><p>©Winze Tam, Congcong Hou, Andreas Benedikt Eisingerich. Originally published in JMIR Serious Games (https://games.jmir.org), 19.Dec.2025.</p><small><p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work, first published in JMIR Serious Games, is properly cited. The complete bibliographic information, a link to the original publication on https://games.jmir.org, as well as this copyright and license information must be included.</p></small><br></section></div></article></section></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[When Compilers Surprise You (159 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://xania.org/202512/24-cunning-clang</link>
            <guid>46375384</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 13:27:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://xania.org/202512/24-cunning-clang">https://xania.org/202512/24-cunning-clang</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46375384">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        

        <p>Written by me, proof-read by an LLM.
<br>Details at end.</p>
<p>Every now and then a compiler will surprise me with a really smart trick. When I first saw this optimisation I could hardly believe it. I was looking at loop optimisation, and wrote something like this simple function that sums all the numbers up to a given value:</p>


<p>So far so decent: GCC has done some preliminary checks, then fallen into a loop that efficiently sums numbers using <code>lea</code> (we’ve <a href="https://xania.org/202512/02-adding-integers">seen this before</a>). But taking a closer look at the loop we see something unusual:</p>
<div><pre><code><span>.L3:</span>
<span>  </span><span>lea</span><span> </span><span>edx</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>rdx</span><span>+</span><span>1</span><span>+</span><span>rax</span><span>*</span><span>2</span><span>]</span><span>        </span><span>; result = result + 1 + x*2</span>
<span>  </span><span>add</span><span> </span><span>eax</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>2</span><span>                    </span><span>; x += 2</span>
<span>  </span><span>cmp</span><span> </span><span>edi</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>eax</span><span>                  </span><span>; x != value</span>
<span>  </span><span>jne</span><span> </span><span>.L3</span><span>                       </span><span>; keep looping</span>
</code></pre></div>

<p>The compiler has cleverly realised it can do two numbers<sup id="fnref:check"><a href="#fn:check">1</a></sup> at a time using the fact it can see we’re going to add <code>x</code> <em>and</em> <code>x + 1</code>, which is the same as adding <code>x*2 + 1</code>. Very cunning, I think you’ll agree!</p>
<p>If you turn the optimiser up to <code>-O3</code> you’ll see the compiler works even harder to vectorise the loop using parallel adds. All very clever.</p>
<p>This is all for GCC. Let’s see what clang does with our code:</p>


<p>This is where I nearly fell off my chair: <strong>there is no loop</strong>! Clang checks for positive <code>value</code>, and if so it does:</p>
<div><pre><code><span>  </span><span>lea</span><span> </span><span>eax</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>rdi</span><span> </span><span>-</span><span> </span><span>1</span><span>]</span><span>        </span><span>; eax = value - 1</span>
<span>  </span><span>lea</span><span> </span><span>ecx</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>rdi</span><span> </span><span>-</span><span> </span><span>2</span><span>]</span><span>        </span><span>; ecx = value - 2</span>
<span>  </span><span>imul</span><span> </span><span>rcx</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>rax</span><span>             </span><span>; rcx = (value - 1) * (value - 2)</span>
<span>  </span><span>shr</span><span> </span><span>rcx</span><span>                   </span><span>; rcx &gt;&gt;= 1</span>
<span>  </span><span>lea</span><span> </span><span>eax</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>rdi</span><span> </span><span>+</span><span> </span><span>rcx</span><span>]</span><span>      </span><span>; eax = value + rcx</span>
<span>  </span><span>dec</span><span> </span><span>eax</span><span>                   </span><span>; --eax</span>
<span>  </span><span>ret</span>
</code></pre></div>

<p>It was not at all obvious to me what on earth was going on here. By backing out the maths a little, this is equivalent to:</p>
<div><pre><code>v + ((v - 1)(v - 2) / 2) - 1;
</code></pre></div>

<p>Expanding the parentheses:</p>
<div><pre><code>v + (v² - 2v - v + 2) / 2 - 1
</code></pre></div>

<p>Rearranging a bit:</p>
<div><pre><code>(v² - 3v + 2) / 2 + (v - 1)
</code></pre></div>

<p>Multiplying the <code>(v - 1)</code> by 2 / 2:</p>
<div><pre><code>(v² - 3v + 2) / 2 + (2v - 2)/2
</code></pre></div>

<p>Combining those and cancelling:</p>


<p>Simplifying and factoring gives us <code>v(v - 1) / 2</code> which is the closed-form solution to the “sum of integers”! Truly amazing<sup id="fnref:why"><a href="#fn:why">2</a></sup> - we’ve gone from an O(n) algorithm as written, to an O(1) one!</p>
<p>I love that despite working with compilers for more than twenty years, they can still surprise and delight me. The years of experience and work that have been poured into making compilers great is truly humbling, and inspiring.</p>
<p>We’re nearly at the end of this series - there’s so much more to say but that will have to wait for another time. Tomorrow will be a little different: see you then!</p>
<p><em>See <a href="https://youtu.be/V9dy34slaxA">the video</a> that accompanies this post.</em></p>
<hr>
<p><em>This post is day 24 of <a href="https://xania.org/AoCO2025">Advent of Compiler Optimisations 2025</a>,
a 25-day series exploring how compilers transform our code.</em></p>
<p><em>This post was written by a human (<a href="https://xania.org/MattGodbolt">Matt Godbolt</a>) and reviewed and proof-read by LLMs and humans.</em></p>
<p><em>Support Compiler Explorer on <a href="https://patreon.com/c/mattgodbolt">Patreon</a>
or <a href="https://github.com/sponsors/compiler-explorer">GitHub</a>,
or by buying CE products in the <a href="https://shop.compiler-explorer.com/">Compiler Explorer Shop</a></em>.</p>

    </div><div>
                
                
                <p>Posted at 06:00:00 CST on 24<sup>th</sup> December 2025.</p>
            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[US sanctions EU government officials behind the DSA (108 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://mastodon.social/@fj/115773761468906515</link>
            <guid>46374087</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 09:43:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://mastodon.social/@fj/115773761468906515">https://mastodon.social/@fj/115773761468906515</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46374087">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google 2025 recap: Research breakthroughs of the year (149 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.google/technology/ai/2025-research-breakthroughs/</link>
            <guid>46374018</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 09:30:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.google/technology/ai/2025-research-breakthroughs/">https://blog.google/technology/ai/2025-research-breakthroughs/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46374018">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>

    
    





    

    
      








<div data-analytics-module="{
    &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Hero Menu&quot;,
    &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025&quot;
  }">
  
  <div>
      
      
        <p>
          This was a year of AI agents, reasoning and scientific discovery.
        </p>
      
    </div>
  
  <div data-component="uni-ai-generated-summary" data-analytics-module="{
    &quot;event&quot;: &quot;module_impression&quot;,
    &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;ai_summary&quot;,
    &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;CTA&quot;
  }">
      
        <div data-summary-id="ai_summary_1">
          <h2>General summary</h2>
          <p>In 2025, Google made significant AI research breakthroughs with models like Gemini 3 and Gemma 3. These advancements improved AI's reasoning, multimodality, and efficiency, leading to new products and features across Google's portfolio. Expect more AI-driven innovations in science, computing, and tools for global challenges as Google prioritizes responsible AI development and collaboration.</p>
          
          <p><small>
            Summaries were generated by Google AI. Generative AI is experimental.
          </small>
        </p></div>
      
        <div data-summary-id="ai_summary_2">
          <h2>Bullet points</h2>
          <ul>
<li>"Google's year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025" highlights AI advancements and more.</li>
<li>Gemini 3 models showed big leaps in reasoning, multimodality, efficiency, and creative abilities.</li>
<li>AI is transforming Google's products, from Pixel 10 to Search, with agentic capabilities.</li>
<li>AI is boosting science, from genomics and healthcare to math, coding, and quantum computing.</li>
<li>Google is prioritizing AI safety, collaboration, and addressing global challenges like climate change.</li>
</ul>
          
          <p><small>
            Summaries were generated by Google AI. Generative AI is experimental.
          </small>
        </p></div>
      
        <div data-summary-id="ai_summary_3">
          <h2>Basic explainer</h2>
          <p>Google had a super productive year with AI research. They made their AI models way better at thinking and understanding things. Google also made AI more useful in everyday products and helped people be more creative. Plus, they used AI to make big steps in science and to tackle global problems.</p>
          
          <p><small>
            Summaries were generated by Google AI. Generative AI is experimental.
          </small>
        </p></div>
      

      
      <div>
        <h4>
          Explore other styles:
        </h4>
        
      </div>
      

      </div>
</div>

    

    
      










<div>
    <figure>
      <div>
        <p><img alt="The image depicts a visual collage or mosaic of multiple different images, with one image in the center that is black and displays the text &quot;Gemini 3&quot;." data-component="uni-progressive-image" fetchpriority="high" height="150px" src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/end-of-year-blog_header_light_209.width-200.format-webp.webp" width="360px" data-sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw,(min-width: 1024px and max-width: 1259) 80vw, 1046px" data-srcset="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/end-of-year-blog_header_light_209.width-800.format-webp.webp 800w, https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/end-of-year-blog_header_light_20.width-1200.format-webp.webp 1200w, https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/end-of-year-blog_header_light_20.width-1600.format-webp.webp 1600w, https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/end-of-year-blog_header_light_20.width-2200.format-webp.webp 2200w">
        </p>
      </div>
      
    </figure>
  </div>






    

    
    <div>
        
          
            <div data-component="uni-article-jumplinks" data-analytics-module="{
    &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Article Jumplinks&quot;,
    &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025&quot;
  }">
  <nav aria-label="Article Jumplinks">
    <p><span>In this story</span>
    </p>
    
    
    <div>
      <ul id="article-jumplinks__list">
        
        <li>
          <a aria-label="link to AI models" href="#ai-models" id="ai-models-anchor">AI models</a>
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <a aria-label="link to AI in our products" href="#ai-products" id="ai-products-anchor">AI in our products</a>
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <a aria-label="link to AI and creativity" href="#ai-creativity" id="ai-creativity-anchor">AI and creativity</a>
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <a aria-label="link to Science &amp; mathematics" href="#science-mathematics" id="science-mathematics-anchor">Science &amp; mathematics</a>
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <a aria-label="link to Computing" href="#computing" id="computing-anchor">Computing</a>
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <a aria-label="link to Global impact" href="#global-impact" id="global-impact-anchor">Global impact</a>
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <a aria-label="link to Safety &amp; responsibility" href="#safety-responsibility" id="safety-responsibility-anchor">Safety &amp; responsibility</a>
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <a aria-label="link to Collaborations" href="#collaborations" id="collaborations-anchor">Collaborations</a>
        </li>
        
      </ul>
    </div>
    
  </nav>
</div>
          
          
          <div data-reading-time="true" data-component="uni-article-body">

            
  
    



















<div data-component="uni-audio-player-tts" uni-l10n="{
       &quot;stop&quot;: &quot;Click to stop audio&quot;,
       &quot;play&quot;: &quot;Click to play audio&quot;,
       &quot;progress&quot;: &quot;Current audio progress minutes with seconds: [[progress]]&quot;,
       &quot;duration&quot;: &quot;Duration of the audio minutes with seconds: [[duration]]&quot;,
       &quot;settings&quot;: &quot;Click for settings&quot;,
       &quot;timeText&quot;: &quot;[[duration]] minutes&quot;
     }" data-analytics-module="{
      &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Audio TTS&quot;,
      &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025&quot;
     }" data-tts-audios="[
      
        {&quot;voice_name&quot;: &quot;Gacrux&quot;,
        &quot;voice_source&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/media/tts_audio_83015_gacrux_2025_12_23_19_37_44.wav&quot;,
        &quot;mimetype&quot;: &quot;audio/x-wav&quot;},
      
        {&quot;voice_name&quot;: &quot;Umbriel&quot;,
        &quot;voice_source&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/media/tts_audio_83015_umbriel_2025_12_23_19_38_45.wav&quot;,
        &quot;mimetype&quot;: &quot;audio/x-wav&quot;}
      ]">
  <p><audio title="Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025">
      <source src="https://blog.google/technology/ai/2025-research-breakthroughs/self.ttsaudio_set.first.tts_audio.url" type="self.ttsaudio_set.first.tts_audio.file.file.mime_type">
      <p>Your browser does not support the audio element.</p>
  </audio></p><div aria-label="">
        <p><span>
          Listen to article
          <span tabindex="0" role="tooltip" aria-label="This content is generated by Google AI. Generative AI is experimental">
            <p>This content is generated by Google AI. Generative AI is experimental</p>
            <svg>
  <use xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" href="/static/blogv2/images/icons.svg?version=pr20251215-1743#ttf-info"></use>
</svg>

          </span>
        </span></p><p>[[duration]] minutes</p>
      </div>
</div>

  





            
            
<!--article text-->

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025&quot;
         }"><p data-block-key="8cikp">2025 has been a year of extraordinary progress in research. With artificial intelligence, we can see its trajectory shifting from a tool to a utility: from something people use to something they can put to work. If 2024 was about laying the multimodal foundations for this era, 2025 was the year AI began to really think, act and explore the world alongside us. With quantum computing, we made progress towards real-world applications. And across the board, we helped turn research into reality, with more capable and useful products and tools making a positive impact on people's lives today.</p><p data-block-key="2qvrh">Here’s a look back at some of the breakthroughs, products and scientific milestones that defined the work of Google, Google DeepMind and Google Research in a year of relentless progress<b>.</b></p></div>
  

  
    

  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025&quot;
         }"><h2 data-block-key="8cikp">Delivering breakthroughs on world-class models</h2><p data-block-key="67v7e">This year, we significantly advanced our model capabilities with breakthroughs on reasoning, multimodal understanding, model efficiency, and generative capabilities, beginning with the release of Gemini 2.5 in March and culminating in the November launch of Gemini 3 and the December launch of Gemini 3 Flash.</p><p data-block-key="adj22">Built on a foundation of state-of-the-art reasoning, Gemini 3 Pro is our most powerful model to date, designed to help you bring any idea to life. It topped the LMArena Leaderboard and redefined multimodal reasoning with breakthrough scores on benchmarks like Humanity’s Last Exam — a fiendishly hard test for AI models to see if AI can truly think and reason like humans — and GPQA Diamond. It also set a new standard for frontier models in mathematics, achieving a new state-of-the-art of 23.4% on MathArena Apex. We followed shortly with Gemini 3 Flash, which combines Gemini 3's Pro-grade reasoning with Flash-level latency, efficiency and cost, making it the most performant model for its size. Gemini 3 Flash's quality surpasses our previous Gemini 2.5 Pro-scale model's capabilities at a fraction of the price and substantially better latency, continuing our Gemini-era trend of 'the next generation's Flash model is better than the previous generation's Pro model'.</p><p data-block-key="2qsdp">Learn more about our progress on our world-class AI models this year:</p><ul><li data-block-key="4aapd"><a href="https://blog.google/products/gemini/gemini-3-flash/">Gemini 3 Flash: frontier intelligence built for speed</a> (Dec 2025)</li><li data-block-key="8p9pt"><a href="https://blog.google/products/gemini/gemini-3/">A new era of intelligence with Gemini 3</a> (Nov 2025)</li><li data-block-key="2ku9h"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/ai/nano-banana-pro/">Introducing Nano Banana Pro</a> (Nov 2025)</li><li data-block-key="1oibr"><a href="https://developers.googleblog.com/introducing-veo-3-1-and-new-creative-capabilities-in-the-gemini-api/">Introducing Veo 3.1 and new creative capabilities in the Gemini API</a> (Nov 2025)</li><li data-block-key="5o13k"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/google-deepmind/gemini-model-thinking-updates-march-2025/">Gemini 2.5: Our most intelligent AI model</a> (March 2025)</li></ul></div>
  

  
    














<uni-image-full-width alignment="full" alt-text="Gemini benchmarks table" external-image="" or-mp4-video-title="" or-mp4-video-url="" section-header="Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025" external-link="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/original_images/gemini-3-flash_final_benchmark-table_light_25-12-17_final.gif" custom-class="image-full-width--constrained-width uni-component-spacing">
  
    <div slot="caption-slot">
      <p data-block-key="kzwr4">Gemini 3 Flash price &amp; benchmark table.&nbsp;</p>
    </div>
  
  
    <p><img alt="Gemini benchmarks table" src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/original_images/gemini-3-flash_final_benchmark-table_light_25-12-17_final.gif">
    </p>
  
</uni-image-full-width>


  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025&quot;
         }"><p data-block-key="8cikp">We’re committed to making useful AI technology accessible, with state-of-the-art open models. We built our Gemma family of models to be lightweight and open for public use; this year we were able to introduce multimodal capabilities, significantly increase the context window, expand multilingual capabilities, and improve efficiency and performance.</p><p data-block-key="f0l1f">Learn more about this year’s advances in Gemma models:</p><ul><li data-block-key="c7dof"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/developers/gemma-3/">Introducing Gemma 3: The most capable model you can run on a single GPU or TPU</a> (March 2025)</li><li data-block-key="6ln2d"><a href="https://developers.googleblog.com/en/introducing-gemma-3-270m/">Introducing Gemma 3 270M: The compact model for hyper-efficient AI</a> (Aug 2025)</li></ul></div>
  

  
    

  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025&quot;
         }"><h2 data-block-key="al7tr">Innovating and transforming our products with AI</h2><p data-block-key="fcih3">Throughout 2025, we continued to advance the trajectory of AI from tool to utility, transforming our portfolio of products with new, powerful agentic capabilities. We reimagined software development by moving beyond tools that assist coding to introducing powerful, agentic systems that collaborate with developers. Key advances, such as the impressive coding capabilities in Gemini 3 and the launch of <a href="https://antigravity.google/">Google Antigravity</a>, mark a new era in AI-assisted software development.</p><p data-block-key="a0ept">Learn more about this year’s advances building developer tools:</p><ul><li data-block-key="6dvis"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/developers/gemini-3-developers/">Start building with Gemini 3</a> (Nov 2025)</li><li data-block-key="da2ii"><a href="https://antigravity.google/blog/introducing-google-antigravity">Introducing Google Antigravity, a New Era in AI-Assisted Software Development</a> (Nov 2025)</li></ul></div>
  

  
    
  
    




  <uni-youtube-player-article index="8" thumbnail-alt="Google Antigravity coding platform" video-id="6QeVnO709r0" video-type="video">
  </uni-youtube-player-article>











  


  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025&quot;
         }"><p data-block-key="al7tr">This evolution was also clear across our core products, from AI-enabled features on the Pixel 10 and updates to AI Mode in Search, to AI-first innovations like the Gemini app and NotebookLM, which gained advanced features like Deep Research.</p><p data-block-key="40hu0">Learn more about how we’ve transformed our products with AI:</p><ul><li data-block-key="3fp63"><a href="https://blog.google/products/pixel/google-pixel-10-ai-features-updates/">9 ways AI makes Pixel 10 our most helpful phone yet</a> (Aug 2025)</li><li data-block-key="an8rh"><a href="https://blog.google/products/search/ai-mode-search/">Expanding AI Overviews and introducing AI Mode</a> (March 2025)</li><li data-block-key="2nl4f"><a href="https://blog.google/products/gemini/gemini-3-gemini-app/">Gemini 3 brings upgraded smarts and new capabilities to the Gemini app</a> (Nov 2025)</li><li data-block-key="ej9fc"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/google-labs/notebooklm-deep-research-file-types/">NotebookLM adds Deep Research and support for more source types</a> (Nov 2025)</li></ul></div>
  

  
    

  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025&quot;
         }"><h2 data-block-key="al7tr">Empowering creativity and co-creating with AI</h2><p data-block-key="6cf7b">2025 was a transformative year for generative media, giving people new and unprecedented capabilities to realize their creative ambitions. Generative media models and tools for video, images, audio and worlds became more effective and broadly used, with breakouts Nano Banana and Nano Banana Pro offering unprecedented capabilities for native image generation and editing. We worked with people in creative industries to develop tools like Flow and Music AI Sandbox, making them more helpful for creative workflows, and we expanded creative possibilities for people with new, AI-powered experiences in the Google Arts &amp; Culture lab, major upgrades to image editing within the Gemini app, and the introduction of powerful new generative media models like Veo 3.1, Imagen 4 and Flow.</p><p data-block-key="ffoia">Learn more about how we’re building AI to enhance creativity:</p><ul><li data-block-key="3lhhj"><a href="https://blog.google/outreach-initiatives/arts-culture/ai-cultural-learning/">Art, science, travel: 3 new AI-powered experiences this holiday season</a> (Nov 2025)</li><li data-block-key="cc29g"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/ai/veo-updates-flow/">Introducing Veo 3.1 and advanced capabilities in Flow</a> (Oct 2025)</li><li data-block-key="4uebb"><a href="https://blog.google/products/gemini/updated-image-editing-model/">Nano Banana: Image editing in Gemini just got a major upgrade</a> (Aug 2025)</li><li data-block-key="22gdl"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/ai/generative-media-models-io-2025/">Veo 3, Imagen 4, and Flow: Fuel your creativity with new generative media models and tools</a> (May 2025)</li><li data-block-key="b41j3"><a href="https://deepmind.google/blog/music-ai-sandbox-now-with-new-features-and-broader-access/">Music AI Sandbox, now with new features and broader access</a> (April 2025)</li></ul></div>
  

  
    














<uni-image-full-width alignment="full" alt-text="Image Editing Gemini Inline" external-image="" or-mp4-video-title="ImageEditing" or-mp4-video-url="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/original_videos/ImageEditingGemini_Inline_XZuiDzE.mp4" section-header="Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025" custom-class="image-full-width--constrained-width uni-component-spacing">
  
  
</uni-image-full-width>


  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025&quot;
         }"><p data-block-key="al7tr">As research breakthroughs continue to expand AI’s capabilities, Google Labs is where we share AI experiments as we develop them – hearing from users and evolving as we learn. Some of this year’s most engaging experiments from Labs: Pomelli, an AI experiment for on-brand marketing content; Stitch, which introduced a way to turn prompt and image inputs into complex UI designs and frontend code in minutes; Jules, an asynchronous coding agent that acts as a collaborative partner for developers; and Google Beam, a 3D video communications platform that used AI to advance the possibilities of remote presence.</p><p data-block-key="a3c6m">Learn more about how we’re experimenting in Labs:</p><ul><li data-block-key="b58r7"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/google-labs/pomelli/">Create on-brand marketing content for your business with Pomelli</a> (Oct 2025)</li><li data-block-key="ead1d"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/research/project-starline-google-beam-update/">Google Beam: Our AI-first 3D video communication platform</a> (May 2025)</li><li data-block-key="7m7g6"><a href="https://developers.googleblog.com/stitch-a-new-way-to-design-uis/">From idea to app: Introducing Stitch, a new way to design UIs</a> (May 2025)</li><li data-block-key="26gpp"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/google-labs/jules/">Build with Jules, your asynchronous coding agent</a> (May 2025)</li></ul></div>
  

  
    

  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025&quot;
         }"><h2 data-block-key="al7tr">Advancing science and mathematics</h2><p data-block-key="7p9cf">2025 was also a banner year for scientific advances with AI, marked by breakthroughs in life sciences, health, natural sciences, and mathematics.</p><p data-block-key="3rl8s">In the space of a year, we made progress in building AI resources and tools that empower researchers and help them understand, identify, and develop treatments in healthcare. In genomics, where we’ve been applying advanced technology to research for 10 years, we moved beyond sequencing, using AI to interpret the most complex data. We also marked the 5-year anniversary of AlphaFold, the Nobel-winning AI system that solved the 50-year-old protein folding problem. AlphaFold has been used by over 3 million researchers in more than 190 countries, including over 1 million users in low- and middle-income countries.</p><p data-block-key="s0fe">Learn more about how we’re using AI to advance life sciences and health:</p><ul><li data-block-key="8l8v5"><a href="https://deepmind.google/blog/alphafold-five-years-of-impact/">AlphaFold: Five years of impact</a> (Nov 2025)</li><li data-block-key="7e9u1"><a href="https://research.google/blog/using-ai-to-identify-genetic-variants-in-tumors-with-deepsomatic/">Using AI to identify genetic variants in tumors with DeepSomatic</a> (Oct 2025)</li><li data-block-key="da41m"><a href="https://research.google/blog/ai-as-a-research-partner-advancing-theoretical-computer-science-with-alphaevolve/">AI as a research partner: Advancing theoretical computer science with AlphaEvolve</a> (Sept 2025)</li><li data-block-key="aofp2"><a href="https://deepmind.google/blog/alphagenome-ai-for-better-understanding-the-genome/">AlphaGenome: AI for better understanding the genome</a> (June 2025)</li><li data-block-key="5ndao"><a href="https://research.google/blog/accelerating-scientific-breakthroughs-with-an-ai-co-scientist/">Accelerating scientific breakthroughs with an AI co-scientist</a> (Feb 2025)</li></ul></div>
  

  
    














<uni-image-full-width alignment="full" alt-text="AI co-scientist explanation animation" external-image="" or-mp4-video-title="AI Co-Scientist" or-mp4-video-url="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/original_videos/AICoScientist-0-Hero.mp4" section-header="Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025" custom-class="image-full-width--constrained-width uni-component-spacing">
  
  
</uni-image-full-width>


  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025&quot;
         }"><p data-block-key="al7tr">Gemini’s advanced thinking capabilities, including Deep Think, also enabled historic progress in mathematics and coding. Deep Think was able to solve problems that require deep abstract reasoning – achieving gold medal-standard in two international contests.</p><p data-block-key="97fsj">Learn more about how we’re advancing natural sciences and mathematics:</p><ul><li data-block-key="c43an"><a href="https://deepmind.google/blog/gemini-achieves-gold-medal-level-at-the-international-collegiate-programming-contest-world-finals/">Gemini achieves gold-medal level at the International Collegiate Programming Contest World Finals</a> (Sept 2025)</li><li data-block-key="bi9vr"><a href="https://deepmind.google/blog/advanced-version-of-gemini-with-deep-think-officially-achieves-gold-medal-standard-at-the-international-mathematical-olympiad/">Advanced version of Gemini with Deep Think officially achieves gold-medal standard at the International Mathematical Olympiad</a> (July 2025)</li></ul></div>
  

  
    

  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025&quot;
         }"><h2 data-block-key="al7tr">Shaping innovations in computing and the physical world</h2><p data-block-key="2ng3v">We’re also leading major discoveries and shaping the future of science in areas like quantum computing, energy and moonshots. Research in this area drew new levels of public attention, with progress towards real-world applications of quantum computing as demonstrated by Quantum Echoes and, notably, Googler Michel Devoret becoming a 2025 Physics Nobel Laureate along with former Googler John Martinis and UC Berkeley’s John Clarke, for their foundational 1980s quantum research.</p><p data-block-key="5bmlo">Learn more about our work on space infrastructure and quantum computing:</p><ul><li data-block-key="1dkv0"><a href="https://research.google/blog/exploring-a-space-based-scalable-ai-infrastructure-system-design/">Project Suncatcher: Exploring a space-based, scalable AI infrastructure system design</a> (Nov 2025)</li><li data-block-key="4bp8o"><a href="https://blog.google/inside-google/company-announcements/googler-michel-devoret-awarded-the-nobel-prize-in-physics/">Googler Michel Devoret awarded the Nobel Prize in Physics</a> (Oct 2025)</li><li data-block-key="59ngu"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/research/quantum-echoes-willow-verifiable-quantum-advantage/">Our Quantum Echoes algorithm is a big step toward real-world applications for quantum computing</a> (Oct 2025)</li></ul><p data-block-key="dqc41">In 2025, we continued to advance the core infrastructure that powers our AI, focusing on breakthroughs in hardware design and improving energy efficiency. This included the introduction of Ironwood, a new TPU built for the age of inference, which was designed using a method called <a href="https://deepmind.google/blog/how-alphachip-transformed-computer-chip-design/">AlphaChip</a>, alongside a commitment to measuring the environmental impact of our technology.</p><p data-block-key="e5rqu">Learn more about how we’re using AI to develop chips, infrastructure and improve energy efficiency:</p><ul><li data-block-key="fsj47"><a href="https://blog.google/products/google-cloud/ironwood-google-tpu-things-to-know/">3 things to know about Ironwood, our latest TPU</a> (Nov 2025)</li><li data-block-key="dunkb"><a href="https://cloud.google.com/blog/products/infrastructure/measuring-the-environmental-impact-of-ai-inference">How much energy does Google’s AI use? We did the math</a> (Aug 2025)</li><li data-block-key="5fc9o"><a href="https://blog.google/products/google-cloud/ironwood-tpu-age-of-inference/">Ironwood: The first Google TPU for the age of inference</a> (April 2025)</li></ul></div>
  

  
    














<uni-image-full-width alignment="full" alt-text="Ironwood Superpod" external-image="" or-mp4-video-title="" or-mp4-video-url="" section-header="Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025" custom-class="image-full-width--constrained-width uni-component-spacing">
  
  
    <p><img alt="Ironwood Superpod" src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Ironwood_superpod.width-100.format-webp.webp" loading="lazy" data-loading="{
            &quot;mobile&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Ironwood_superpod.width-500.format-webp.webp&quot;,
            &quot;desktop&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Ironwood_superpod.width-1000.format-webp.webp&quot;
          }">
    </p>
  
</uni-image-full-width>


  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025&quot;
         }"><p data-block-key="al7tr">Our work in robotics and visual understanding brought AI agents into both the physical and virtual worlds, with advancements like the foundational Gemini Robotics models, the more sophisticated Gemini Robotics 1.5, and the introduction of Genie 3 as a new frontier for general-purpose world models.</p><p data-block-key="fo2ab">Learn more about our work with world models and robotics:</p><ul><li data-block-key="7nu4"><a href="https://deepmind.google/blog/gemini-robotics-15-brings-ai-agents-into-the-physical-world/">Gemini Robotics 1.5 brings AI agents into the physical world</a> (Sept 2025)</li><li data-block-key="2ikg3"><a href="https://deepmind.google/blog/genie-3-a-new-frontier-for-world-models/">Genie 3: A new frontier for world models</a> (Aug 2025)</li><li data-block-key="e6vuf"><a href="https://deepmind.google/blog/gemini-robotics-brings-ai-into-the-physical-world/">Gemini Robotics brings AI into the physical world</a> (March 2025)</li></ul></div>
  

  
    
  
    




  <uni-youtube-player-article index="22" thumbnail-alt="Genie 3 promotional video" video-id="PDKhUknuQDg" video-type="video">
  </uni-youtube-player-article>











  


  

  
    

  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025&quot;
         }"><h2 data-block-key="al7tr">Tackling global challenges and opportunities at scale</h2><p data-block-key="6ju6p">Our work throughout 2025 demonstrates how AI-enabled scientific progress is being directly applied to address the world's most critical and pervasive challenges. By leveraging state-of-the-art foundational models and agentic reasoning, we are significantly increasing our understanding of the planet and its systems, while also delivering impactful solutions in areas vital to human flourishing, including climate resilience, public health and education.</p><p data-block-key="bpln9">For example, we are using state-of-the-art foundational models and agentic reasoning to help increase our understanding of the planet, helping enable work that is making a difference in people’s lives now from weather predictions to urban planning to public health. For example, our flood forecasting information now covers more than two billion people in 150 countries for severe riverine floods. And our most advanced and efficient forecasting model, <a href="https://blog.google/technology/google-deepmind/weathernext-2/">WeatherNext 2</a> can generate forecasts 8x faster and with resolution up to 1-hour. Using this technology, we’ve supported weather agencies in making decisions based on a range of scenarios through our experimental cyclone predictions.</p><p data-block-key="af618">Learn more about our work in weather, mapping and wildfires:</p><ul><li data-block-key="tqgc"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/google-deepmind/weathernext-2/">WeatherNext 2: Our most advanced weather forecasting model</a> (Nov 2025)</li><li data-block-key="83jgu"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/research/new-updates-and-more-access-to-google-earth-ai/">New updates and more access to Google Earth AI</a> (Oct 2025)</li><li data-block-key="em46a"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/ai/google-earth-ai/">Google Earth AI: Our state-of-the-art geospatial AI models</a> (July 2025)</li><li data-block-key="2cgpq"><a href="https://deepmind.google/blog/alphaearth-foundations-helps-map-our-planet-in-unprecedented-detail/">AlphaEarth Foundations helps map our planet in unprecedented detail</a> (July 2025)</li><li data-block-key="1fb49"><a href="https://deepmind.google/blog/how-were-supporting-better-tropical-cyclone-prediction-with-ai/">How we're supporting better tropical cyclone prediction with AI</a> (June 2025)</li><li data-block-key="944c9"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/ai/inside-firesat-launch-muon-space/">Inside the launch of FireSat, a system to find wildfires earlier</a> (March 2025)</li></ul><p data-block-key="fvikc">We are working with partners to apply AI-enabled scientific progress closer to patients, opening up new avenues for disease management and therapeutic discovery.</p><p data-block-key="vlom">Learn more about our health-related work:</p><ul><li data-block-key="equf2"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/ai/google-gemma-ai-cancer-therapy-discovery/">Cell2Sentence-Scale 27B:</a> <a href="https://blog.google/technology/ai/google-gemma-ai-cancer-therapy-discovery/">How a Gemma model helped discover a new potential cancer therapy pathway</a> (Oct 2025)</li><li data-block-key="bemfn"><a href="https://research.google/blog/from-diagnosis-to-treatment-advancing-amie-for-longitudinal-disease-management/">From diagnosis to treatment: Advancing AMIE for longitudinal disease management</a> (March 2025)</li></ul><p data-block-key="97km5">AI is proving to be a powerful tool in education, enabling new forms of understanding and expanding curiosity through initiatives like LearnLM and Guided Learning in Gemini. We brought Gemini’s most powerful translation capabilities to Google Translate, enabling much smarter, more natural and accurate translations and piloting new speech to speech translation capabilities.</p><p data-block-key="e48gj">Learn more about how we’re using AI to enable learning:</p><ul><li data-block-key="fajsl"><a href="https://blog.google/products/search/gemini-capabilities-translation-upgrades/">Bringing state-of-the-art Gemini translation capabilities to Google Translate</a> (Dec 2025)</li><li data-block-key="2imjk"><a href="https://blog.google/outreach-initiatives/education/guided-learning/">Guided Learning in Gemini: From answers to understanding</a> (Aug 2025)</li><li data-block-key="c6pqu"><a href="https://blog.google/outreach-initiatives/education/google-learnlm-gemini-generative-ai/">How generative AI expands curiosity and understanding with LearnLM</a> (May 2025)</li></ul></div>
  

  
    
  
    




  <uni-youtube-player-article index="25" thumbnail-alt="WeatherNext 2 promotional video" video-id="YQwqoEm_xis" video-type="video">
  </uni-youtube-player-article>











  


  

  
    

  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025&quot;
         }"><h2 data-block-key="al7tr">Prioritizing responsibility and safety</h2><p data-block-key="51tcq">We couple our research breakthroughs with rigorous and forward-looking work on responsibility and safety. As our models grow more capable, we’re continuing to advance and evolve our tools, resources and safety frameworks to anticipate and mitigate risk. Gemini 3 demonstrated this approach in action: it's our most secure model yet, and has undergone the most comprehensive set of safety evaluations of any Google AI model to date. And we’re looking further ahead, exploring a responsible path to AGI, prioritizing readiness, proactive risk assessment, and collaboration with the wider AI community.</p><p data-block-key="4pgfk">Learn more about our responsibility and safety work:</p><ul><li data-block-key="fp3sj"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/ai/verify-google-ai-videos-gemini-app/">You can now verify Google AI-generated videos in the Gemini app</a> (Dec 2025)</li><li data-block-key="33kjv"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/ai/ai-image-verification-gemini-app/">How we’re bringing AI image verification to the Gemini app</a> (Nov 2025)</li><li data-block-key="a0obe"><a href="https://deepmind.google/blog/strengthening-our-frontier-safety-framework/">Strengthening our Frontier Safety Framework</a> (September 2025)</li><li data-block-key="dhkiq"><a href="https://deepmind.google/blog/taking-a-responsible-path-to-agi/">Taking a responsible path to AGI</a> (April 2025)</li><li data-block-key="a6atd"><a href="https://deepmind.google/blog/evaluating-potential-cybersecurity-threats-of-advanced-ai/">Evaluating potential cybersecurity threats of advanced AI</a> (April 2025)</li></ul></div>
  

  
    

  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Google\u0027s year in review: 8 areas with research breakthroughs in 2025&quot;
         }"><h2 data-block-key="al7tr">Leading frontier collaborations with industry, academia and civil society</h2><p data-block-key="6hthm">Advancing the frontier of AI responsibly demands collaboration across all parts of society. In 2025, we worked with leading AI labs to help to form the Agentic AI Foundation and support open standards to ensure a responsible and interoperable future for agentic AI. In education, we’ve partnered with school districts like Miami Dade County and education groups like Raspberry Pi to equip students with AI skills. Our research partnerships with universities like UC Berkeley, Yale, the University of Chicago and many more have been instrumental to some of this year’s most exciting frontier research, and we’re working with the US Department of Energy’s 17 national laboratories to transform how scientific research is conducted. And we’re working with filmmakers and other creative visionaries to put the best AI tools in their hands and explore storytelling in the age of AI.</p><p data-block-key="9e2s4">Learn more about our work on frontier collaboration:</p><ul><li data-block-key="3drvf"><a href="https://deepmind.google/blog/google-deepmind-supports-us-department-of-energy-on-genesis/">Google DeepMind supports U.S. Department of Energy on Genesis: a national mission to accelerate innovation and scientific discovery</a> (Dec 2025)</li><li data-block-key="9hala"><a href="https://www.linuxfoundation.org/press/linux-foundation-announces-the-formation-of-the-agentic-ai-foundation">Formation of the Agentic AI Foundation (AAIF), Anchored by New Project Contributions Including Model Context Protocol (MCP), goose and AGENTS.md</a> (Dec 2025)</li><li data-block-key="4n2md"><a href="https://cloud.google.com/blog/products/ai-machine-learning/announcing-official-mcp-support-for-google-services">Announcing Model Context Protocol (MCP) support for Google services</a> (Dec 2025)</li><li data-block-key="3ri6n"><a href="https://blog.google/outreach-initiatives/education/ai-learning-commitments/">Our latest commitments in AI and learning</a> (Nov 2025)</li><li data-block-key="2orqk"><a href="https://blog.google/outreach-initiatives/education/google-ai-education-workforce-skills/">Partnering to power Miami’s AI-ready future</a> (Oct 2025)</li><li data-block-key="17udc"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/ai/sweetwater-film/">AI on Screen premiere: “Sweetwater” short film explores new AI narratives</a> (Sept 2025)</li><li data-block-key="m5oq"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/google-deepmind/ancestra-behind-the-scenes/">Behind “ANCESTRA”: combining Veo with live-action filmmaking</a> (Jun 2025)</li><li data-block-key="vts6"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/ai/lab-session-shankar-mahadevan/">How Indian music legend Shankar Mahadevan experiments with Music AI Sandbox</a> (April 2025)</li></ul><h2 data-block-key="6k1h2">Looking ahead</h2><p data-block-key="5b7km">As we look towards 2026, we’re looking forward to continuing to advance the frontier, safely and responsibly, for the benefit of humanity.</p></div>
  

  
    







<uni-related-content-tout title="2025 at Google" cta="See more" summary="Learn more about Google’s launches, milestones and more from 2025." hideimage="False" eyebrow="Collection" image-alt-text="" role="none" fullurl="https://blog.google/technology/ai/look-back-2025/" pagetype="collectiondetailpage" isarticlepage="">
  
    <div slot="rct-image-slot">
      
      
        
    <figure>
        <picture>
            


    

    
        <source media="(max-resolution: 1.5dppx)" sizes="300px" srcset="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/EOY_Collection_ss.width-300.format-webp.webp 300w">
    
        <source media="(min-resolution: 1.5dppx)" sizes="600px" srcset="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/EOY_Collection_ss.width-600.format-webp.webp 600w">
    

    <img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/EOY_Collection_ss.width-600.format-webp.webp" alt="EOY Collection_ss" sizes=" 300px,  600px" srcset="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/EOY_Collection_ss.width-300.format-webp.webp 300w, https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/EOY_Collection_ss.width-600.format-webp.webp 600w" data-target="image" loading="lazy">
    


        </picture>
    </figure>


      
    </div>
  
</uni-related-content-tout>

  


            
            

            
              




            
          </div>
        
      </div>
  </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The e-scooter isn't new – London was zooming around on Autopeds a century ago (107 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ianvisits.co.uk/articles/the-e-scooter-isnt-new-london-was-zooming-around-on-autopeds-a-century-ago-86263/</link>
            <guid>46373644</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 08:32:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.ianvisits.co.uk/articles/the-e-scooter-isnt-new-london-was-zooming-around-on-autopeds-a-century-ago-86263/">https://www.ianvisits.co.uk/articles/the-e-scooter-isnt-new-london-was-zooming-around-on-autopeds-a-century-ago-86263/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46373644">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="text">
	<p>The e-scooters that clutter up pavements may seem like a new thing, but a hundred years ago, there were already people zooming around London on powered scooters.</p>
<figure id="attachment_86265" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-86265"><a href="https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01.jpg"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" src="https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01-1024x626.jpg" alt="" width="605" height="370" srcset="https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01-1024x626.jpg 1024w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01-300x183.jpg 300w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01-768x469.jpg 768w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01-900x550.jpg 900w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01.jpg 1800w" sizes="(max-width: 605px) 100vw, 605px" data-old-src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg'%20viewBox='0%200%20605%20370'%3E%3C/svg%3E" data-lazy-srcset="https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01-1024x626.jpg 1024w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01-300x183.jpg 300w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01-768x469.jpg 768w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01-900x550.jpg 900w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01.jpg 1800w" data-lazy-src="https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01-1024x626.jpg"></a><figcaption id="caption-attachment-86265">Lady Florence Norman 1916 (street background expanded)</figcaption></figure>
<p>These were the Autoped, an American import that was once popular enough to regularly appear in the newspapers before vanishing seemingly without a trace.</p>
<p>Invented in the USA in 1915, they first appeared in London in <a href="https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/974930c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1496x1080+0+0/resize/1330x960!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Farchive%2Fautoped-1916-motor-scooter-10.jpg">1917</a>, despite a ban on imports during WWI, and really took off when the import ban was lifted in 1919.</p>
<p>By today’s standards, they look like a bargain, selling for just £36, although that’s actually about £1,600 in today’s money, so they were really aimed at the wealthy buyers.</p>
<figure id="attachment_86264" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-86264"><a href="https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/autoped-01.jpg"><img decoding="async" src="https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/autoped-01-1024x569.jpg" alt="" width="605" height="336" srcset="https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/autoped-01-1024x569.jpg 1024w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/autoped-01-300x167.jpg 300w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/autoped-01-768x427.jpg 768w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/autoped-01-900x500.jpg 900w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/autoped-01.jpg 1800w" sizes="(max-width: 605px) 100vw, 605px" data-eio="l" data-old-src="data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAABAAAAAI5AQAAAAAXw3VxAAAAAnRSTlMAAHaTzTgAAABeSURBVHja7cExAQAAAMKg9U9tDB+gAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAADOBh7IAAEKt2IDAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC" data-src="https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/autoped-01-1024x569.jpg" data-srcset="https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/autoped-01-1024x569.jpg 1024w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/autoped-01-300x167.jpg 300w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/autoped-01-768x427.jpg 768w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/autoped-01-900x500.jpg 900w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/autoped-01.jpg 1800w"></a><figcaption id="caption-attachment-86264">Clarion: Friday 28 November 1919 / Source: British Newspaper Archive</figcaption></figure>
<p>Gamage’s, the people’s emporium, described them as being made for everybody who feels the necessity of making the most of time, of conserving health and energy, and keeping travelling expenses down to the minimum.</p>
<p>It was <a href="https://www-britishnewspaperarchive-co-uk.lonlib.idm.oclc.org/viewer/bl/0005980/19170203/537/0037">said</a> to be able to reach speeds of 10mph, and unlike modern versions, the Autoped was powered by petrol.</p>
<p><em>(There was apparently an electric version by Eveready, but it might have been only in the USA)</em></p>
<p>For comfort over rough roads, they were fitted with 15-inch-diameter pneumatic tyres. The Lady magazine <a href="https://www-britishnewspaperarchive-co-uk.lonlib.idm.oclc.org/viewer/bl/0005980/19161111/431/0042">suggested</a> the Autoped would make for a more suitable alternative to the motorbike.</p>
<p>They even played a key role in a silent movie, <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0335914/">At Sword’s Point</a>, about an annoying man who refuses to say no when rebuffed by a lady and, when trying to escape the relatives, steals an Autoped but collides with his pursuer, also on an Autoped. An “explosion followed, and they both disappeared”.</p>
<p>Wait, what?</p>
<p>His Majesty’s government wasn’t going to be left behind either, and there was a <a href="https://www-britishnewspaperarchive-co-uk.lonlib.idm.oclc.org/viewer/bl/0000098/19170928/029/0003">report</a> in the Pall Mall Gazette of a “distinguished looking autopedist, gracefully erect” sweeping down Whitehall delivering parcels to 10 Downing Street.</p>
<p><iframe width="560" height="315" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="" data-src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qrBqlxWXgVY?si=th2dP0AoUQZQVdsS"></iframe><br>American Miss Shirley Kellogg brings new motor scooter invention to England. </p>
<p>However, by 1922, the adverts aren’t by Gammages, but by owners selling them off cheaply in the classified ads. Several noted that the owners were switching to a car instead.</p>
<p>It seems that the British weather might have killed off the Autoped.</p>
<p>But finally, to that famous image of a lady on an Autoped – it’s of Lady Florence Priscilla Norman, a noted suffragist and was given the Autoped by her husband, the Liberal MP, Henry Norman.</p>
<figure id="attachment_86265" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-86265"><a href="https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01.jpg"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" src="https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01-1024x626.jpg" alt="" width="605" height="370" srcset="https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01-1024x626.jpg 1024w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01-300x183.jpg 300w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01-768x469.jpg 768w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01-900x550.jpg 900w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01.jpg 1800w" sizes="(max-width: 605px) 100vw, 605px" data-old-src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg'%20viewBox='0%200%20605%20370'%3E%3C/svg%3E" data-lazy-srcset="https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01-1024x626.jpg 1024w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01-300x183.jpg 300w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01-768x469.jpg 768w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01-900x550.jpg 900w, https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01.jpg 1800w" data-lazy-src="https://8400e186.delivery.rocketcdn.me/articles/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Lady-Florence-Norman-autoped-backgroundexpandedusingai-01-1024x626.jpg"></a><figcaption id="caption-attachment-86265">Lady Florence Norman 1916 (street background expanded)</figcaption></figure>
<p>Just think, had the Autoped lingered on for a few more years and become more affordable as manufacturing increased, how different the streets of our cities could have been.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Don't Become the Machine (200 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://armeet.bearblog.dev/becoming-the-machine/</link>
            <guid>46372153</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 03:34:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://armeet.bearblog.dev/becoming-the-machine/">https://armeet.bearblog.dev/becoming-the-machine/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46372153">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    

    

    
        

        <p>
            <i>
                <time datetime="2025-12-24T01:54Z">
    24 Dec, 2025
</time>
            </i>
        </p>
    

    <p>I was recently recommended a YouTube video with the following title:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Only a slave quantifies its existence through productivity</p>
</blockquote>
<pre>'''''',,,,,,,,,,,'''''.''''''...........................................................................   .........................................  ...                                                                                                
'''''',,,,,,,,,,'''''''''''''''...........................................................................  .............................................                                                                                                             
''''',;;,,,,,,'''''''''''''''''...................................................................................................................   ......                                                                                                                         
''',,,;;,,,,,,,''''''''''''''...............................................................................................................................                                                                                                                                 
''',,,,,,,,,,,,,'''''''''''....................................................................................................................................  .                                                                                                       
'''''',,,,,,,,,,,,''''''''...................................................................................................................................................                                                                                        
''''''',,,,,,;;,,,'''''''............................................................................................................''.,:cclcllllllooooodxddxxxxkkxdddddddolcc:;,                                                                                        
'''''',,,,,,,,,,,''''''''...................................................................................................'',:::cloooxOXNNXXXKKK0000OOO0K00OOOkOOkkkOOOOOOOO000OOkxdollccc:,                                                                                     
'''',,,',,,,,,,,,''''''''''...................................................................................,:cooolodolllodoolloxkk0KXXXKK00kkkxxdddddxO000OxxxxxxdddxxkkO000KKKKKKKKKKKXXK0Oxoc:                                                                                         
''',,,,'',,,,,,,,,,,''''''...............................................................................,:ldkKXNNX0xoolccccllodk0KKKK0OkOkkxxxdoollccclodoolllllllllcllooddxxkOOO0KKXXXXXXXXXKK000Okxo:;;::,......                                                                                         
'',''''''',,,,,',,,'''''''...........................................................................,cox0XNWWWWWNNNXK0OOkkOO0KXKK0Okxollc::;;;,''..........................'',,,;:codxk0KKKKK00000OOOkxlclkklcllol'.                                                                                       
''',,,,'',,,,,,'',''''''''.......................................................................';lkKXXXXXNWNNNNNNNXNNXXKKK0Oxdol:;'.......'''''......''''.'',:ccc:,'''.''.............',,:ldxO00Okkkkkocldl,;;cxkl,...                                                                                    
''',,,,''',,,,,,,,'''''''''..................................................................':lx0XNNXK0KXXXNNNNNXXNXKKOxdo:;,.......''''''''',,,.......',,'''',;,'''''',;,.''..'..''..........':dkkkxkOocll;,:c::ll;;:;;,..                                                                                
''''',,,'',,,,,'''....'''................................................................';lx0XNXKOdoc;,cOXXNNXXKKKKOoc,.....................'...,'..,;,..'.....,::,,c:,:c;..,''cl,;l;.;c;........:dxxxdc;:;,cxOOkxl,';oxkdl:,..                                                                            
''',,,,''',,,,,''''....'''............................................................,coxOKK0kxxl,....;o0NNX00000Od;....''..............,;'';:;,';:,,;cc,,c;.,:;;cc;,c:';:,.';.,c,';:,':c,'::'';..lxxxl;,,;:lodxOKK0xlclokOOkxo:'....   .                                                                  
,,,,,,,',,,,,,'''''''''''''.......................................................,;:codkOOxol::;'..':d0X0xo:;:xOOx,..':cc,...'..,::'';;,,:c:;:lc;';c;,,::,;:,,;;',c:',,.';;..;'.,,.';;..;,.,;'',,:ooddoooddlloxko:o0NN0xollxOKK0kdc;'..  ..                                                                
,''''''''',,,''''''''''''''.....................................................,lxkOkdddolcc;'..',cxOOdc;,,'.;dO0k:..,;,,;'',;cc:;;;;,;:;,:l:,:c;.':;,'':;'';,''..,;'....''..'..''',;;;:cllloodkOKXXXXNNKkxdxxkKKl'lOkkKX0xolxO0XXXKkdc,....   ..                                                          
'''''''''',,,,'''''''''''.....................................................'lk0KOdooolooddolc:coxo:;;,'...'lkO00x;',,,,;cc;,,:lc'';;',:,.,;'.,,..,;;'.',..'.....',,',,,;,:lloddkOOOO0KKKKXX00KXNWWWWMWxlOOOOlxNx.,d:.;oOXXOxox0XXXXNXKOd:'.....                                                          
,,''''',,,,,,,,,'''''''''...................................................':xKNKd::clodxkkkxddddddoclc,....:xkkkkOxc:::c:,,;c;.,c:'.'......''.....',,'.',;;::cloddddddxxxOKKXXXNNNNWNNNNNNNX000XWMWWWWWKdollookk;.lkc',',:d0XKOxk00OOOO0KK0xl;'...                                                        
'''''',,,,,,,,,'''''''''''.................................................,lxOXNKkooooodxxxkkOkdollolloollc;coodxkxkkdc;,;,..,;,';cccclooollllloodxkkkkOOkkkkO0OOOOkxddxOKXXNWNWWWWMMWWWWWNX0OO00KXXXXK0Oxl:;;:;',lOOc,::;;;:cxKXKko:,',;:lk0KKOdc'..             .                                        
''''',,,,,'',,,'''''''''''...............................................,lolccc:cllllccloodxxxdlcclooooodxkkdlc:lc:lddddooddxO0K0OO0000KKKKKXXXNNWWWNNNNX0OkkkOOkkkOOkOKXNWWWWWWWWWWWWNNXK0OOxdoolc::::'.''....,cxOKk:,;cllllc::lkXXOl,.....,:lxOK0kl;..  ...  ...                                         
''',,,,,,,''',,''''''''..............................................'',:odool;'.''....'',,:cloxxxddooloxxdllol:;coxOKNXXXKOkdddolc:::cccc:cclllodxkO0XNNXK00KKKK00KKKXXNNNWWNNXK0Okkdoll:;,,''''....,l:..,::...';lkKKkolcloloooolccd0XKxc'......,:okKKOd:'...  ....                                        
'',,,,,,,,,,,,,''''''..............................................';;codxxo:'.,::,..,;:::,.....',:clodddodo;;clkK0xdolc:;;,,;:clldddkkOOkkkkxxdoc:,,lkKNKKXXNNNNXKKK00Oxxddoc::;,,''...',;;;;:;,'..,do'.';:;,,.....:dOKKOdoodoldOK0xook0KOo,.......,:okKKOo;.......                                        
',,,,,,,,,,,,'''''.'..............................................';coxO0Oo;.';:;',:llloo;'',''''.....,codol,:dkKKo;;;;;,;:ccdO00OkkkOOOOkxxdddxkOOO0KNNXXK0Okddol:;;,'',......',;,'.';:::::;,,'....cl,.';:;;l;........:xKNKOxoodkKNNXKOxdx00d;.......';ldk00ko:'.. .                                       
,,,,,,,,,,,,'''''..''.............................................,lxOXXk:''';:::lxkkkkxo:'''..''.''',,'',cocckKKOdoollc::ccclooododdxxkkkOOOOOOOkxdlcc::;,'......'...','....';:,'..':loll;.........'....,,'lo........  .,lkKXKkxdx0XNWWWKkodkOd,.......,;:cdOK0kl;.... ..                                  
,,,,,,,,,,''''''...''............................................;ld0XX0o;,;:cokOkkkkxkkdoo:::::;:olclc:;'.,ccd0kl;;:;;oxxxdxkkkkkkxdoollc:;,,'..................,c:;::;'..coodollclx00Oxxx:':,;oddxxc.....,:............  .,lkXNKkxxOKXXNNKo;o0Oc''......',;;cdOK0xl,......                                
,,,,,,,,,''''''''..............................................,lo::ONX0Okxxkxxkxxxkkdokkxxkxxkkkkkkxlc:.....'cko;;;,'.;dkxdolcc;,'......    ...............';clloodOxollc;dOdoldkxkO0Oxdodc;::k0dddkKd'.:l,.........','.......,lkKX0kxxOKXKkc,cO0xc,........',;cdOXKOo;.....                               
',,,,,,,'''''''''.............................................,oddccONNXXKOkkxxdlc::;,'',,;:::clodxkxl,.......':c:cc,...'.............'',,,.....;,.,:ccldc',loddxkxxOkdoo;.';::::;;:codol:,..''d0kxxkKKklloolool:.. ..'',;,'......,lOXX0xdxkOxc'cOX0d;;,.......':llokXX0d:...                               
,,,,,,,,'''''''''..'.........................................;oxxl:dKNNX0Okdl:;,'.........'.......',,.......;:,,ck0k:......,;,.......,:ccc:'...';:okolooO0c':ol:,,;clllc;'',;;coodkOOkkxdxkkdlloxxlc::cloxxdoddOOc... .',,,''','.....,lk0Kkddxdl;;dKX0xc;::......';::lOXKOd;..                              
'',,,,,''''''''''..'.''''...................................;dOOo:oKNKOkdc:,......'cdo;..;ll:..............:oc:odk0d,.,,'',;;lo:..','';cc:;::clddd0Kkocodc...,:clxO000Okddolloddooodooooodxxk0KXXKOxdoooc:loodkOd::l:'..''':lc,';ll:'...'ck00kddol:cxXX0Oxc,;:......,;:o0XKkl,.                             
'',,,,,'',,,,''''''''''''..................................:dOKx:oKWXkdl,'..'cc'..;lxOxollooc:::lc'........,;;oOOOd:'.,cc:;:::dkc'..,;::,;oodooO0dlc:;;;;;coxkOOOkxollc::;;;;;,,,,'',;;::::c::clooxOO0KKKOdoolc;'':c;;;;:;..l0koccloxoc,...;lxOOxdl:;ck0XXKOdc'.......,ccxKXKkc..                           
',,,,''''''',,,,'''''''...................................:xOKOldKNXOl;'....;ldddxkkxxdllloodxOKKOd:'.''....,oOKKk;....'lxocloooo:'.',;;,:xdlodxo;';lddk000kxlc:,;;;clllllooooodoodoooooooddooodxxdolldk0XNXKOl,''..':clcol'.,;:ldoc:codc,....;oxOkdl,,cxKXNNKxc;......':clkXX0o,..                         
''''''''''',,,''''.......................................:k0KOodKN0x:'...cl;:oddlc::ldddxxkxxxxxddkOxl::,..;dO00k:.......:xd::lc:;'...,:c:clccc;';ok00OOxl:,,;clodxxO0OkkOOkxkkxxdddxxkkkkOOOkkO00000Okdddxk0NNKOdl;,:look0xl:;;''lkkdcccll;....',cdkko:;dKXNNN0xl;''.  .;:cxO00x;.                         
''''''''''''''''''......................................,dOKkclKNOo,.....;oxdl:;;:ldOkl;;;lkKKK0xocclol:'.:xO00Oc..''.....'ll;,,,;;;;,'':;'...';lkOkoc;,,;coxxkkO00000KKKK000ko:,,;:lloxk0KKXXXXXXXXXXK0Okxoodk0XNNKOdoollxklclxo..:k0KOxlclc'.',...,lkOO0K0KXNNNXOdc'.  .,:cdkO0k:..                       
''''''',''''''''........................................ck0OccON0o,...,,;oxl;:oddxxkOd;....lKXK0xool:;:;,ckOOO0o...,;cc::;..,;',ll:lcll'....':dkOxc,,:cldkO0000000K00KXXXXXXOl'.';;;;:clccd0XNNNWWWWWNNXK0000Odoox0000000kl::lcc;;,.':lx00kdll;.......';ok0KKKXNNWWNKxc'. .';oddkOk:..                      
'''''''''.'''''........................................;x00o:kNKd,...';lxdllx0K0OkkxkOd:,':kXNNKOdoll,.,lO0OkOd'...'cxOkdl;.':,;dxooodc..';lxkko:,;lxOOO000000000KKKXXXXNNX0c..........''.;kXNNWWWWMMMWWWWNNXK0OkdoodkOO0KOl;'..,;cl:;,,ckXXOdc,.  ..';,..;oOK00XNNNWNKko:'..,loodxxc..                     
'''''''''''''.........................................'oO0k:dXNO:.....:xo:dKXXXNXK0OO00OO0XWWNXKOxool,'lO00xdo,.....:OOxoc,..',cxdc:;,';lxOOxc:coxO00000000KKKKKKKXXXXXNNNXOl'.............oKXNWMMMMMMMMWWWWWWNNX0kolodxxk00x:...ckxodx:'lx0X0o,.....,c;....'cokOKXNNNK0K0ko;.':cccllc,.                    
'''''''''''...........................................cxkklc0WKl.....;xd;o0KKXNNNNNXK0000000KKK0kdxo;,oOK0OOx:.......dOdc,',,:ooc'.';cdO00xl;:lxOO000000K0KXNNNXXXXXXXXNNNNk,..............cOXNWMMMMMMMMMWWWWWNNXK0kxdooddk00Oxl:cdkxdx:.,ldO0Od:,......   .',';cdkO0KKKKKK0Oxl;,;;:::c:..                  
,,,,,'''''...........................................;dxkxlxNWk,..':cxOccO00KXNNNNNNKdodxxxdooxkxdo:,o0XK0OOl........;do;.:lccldc.;odO00kl:cokkkkxxddoodkOKXNWWWWNXXXXNNWWNO;.';ccllool:,.;kXNWWMMMMMMMMMWNX0OxxxxkOOOkdlokOOO00Od:,;;,;:'.':lxOOxo:,....  ..,'..';lxk000KKKKXXOdc;;'',ldc'..               
,,,,'''''''.........................................'lddkdxXNKo'.',:lOx:okxxk0XNNWWXOdkKXXKkc,,coo:,oKXXK0Oo'....... .cl,.cxolloc'ck0KOl;:oxkOko:,;;,...';cd0NWWWWWNNNNNNNNXOc':oxkkkkkxdokKNWWMMMMMMMMWXkl,',:ccccldOOkkdox0OxO0Ol. .;cloo:,,cdkkkOxdllc;,,,,,,,....;okO0KKXXXXK0kdc:clcldc..              
,'''''''''..........................................;doool0NOkl'''..cKkcoo;,,;dKNNNKkO0kdoclol,,oc;dKXXXKOo,........ .:,..,llc:,.;xKKx;,cxkkOd;.'',,..'.....:kNWWWWWWNNNNNNNNXkolooddoox0KXNNWWMMMMMMMWOc'...';okkxo:ck00Odox00kk00l'.'coxkxo,':loxkkxxxxxddooddo'. ...':dOKKKK0xldk0Ol'.';ol'..            
,''''''''...........................................lkdolOWXkd:.....:KO:c;....;ONNWKdooclxkxdc';c:dKXXKKOd;..'''.... ....',,...'lkK0l,:dxkOOd;.......''...',,c0WWWWMWWNNNNXXNNNXK0kxkO0KKXNNWWMMMMMMMW0;....'..,:dO0OolOKOxddkO00KXKkc;dxldxk:..,',;;;::codl:;;;,',:cl:...,cdOKx;,lodK0c,::lkd,.            
,''','''...........................................,xxldKNNXkd:...,coOOcll,'';dKNNWWOc:d00kl;,:::dKXXXKOx:..''......':lxxl,....:OKk:,:dkkkOxc'......'...':okdckNWWWWMMWNNNNNWNNNXXXXXXXXXNNWWWMMMMMMMWd',c:'..''.,oOKOld00xdxdox0NX0kxllodkKO:............,;ccooooool:,... ..,clc:clkN0:.':d0k:.            
,,''''''...........................................:kkkKK0kOOkd,..'cld0xlkOkk0KXXNWNX0xddoolclc:dKXXXK0xl'.','.....;ooddkOc..'lOKk:,cxddkkxdl,,''''''',;lxkOdlkNWWMMMMMWWNNNNNNNNNXNNNNWWWWWWWWMMMMMWNx';ddo;'.....:xxlkX0OkkxoodOXKkxxdl:l0Kxo;.........;clc:;,....',;;::,.....';cdxd;...;k0ko,.           
'''''''...........................................'l0KK0oc;lOOxc.....'o0ooKXKK00KXXXK00OkOOxoccxKXXXK0ko,..;;,;....;ccoloo;.'lOKx:;ldddxxddxko;'';:;,:cloxkxdxKNWWMMMMMMWWNNNXKK00OO0KKXNWWWWWMMMMMMMWKl;lxkko,.....';dXNX00OxddllkXK00XXkcx0xddl;. ............,cdkOOkxdol'.;:,;;''......'::;:;.           
''''''............................................:kKXk:;,.'o00x;....':xOodK0OO0KKK0OOxoccol:lOXNXXK0kd:..''..'....:loxl;'.'lO0o,,cdxkOkxxxkkxl;,;:cclooddddxKNNWWWWWWWNX0kxxxxxxxkkxxxkOO0KNWWMMMMWWMWXkloxOKx,....;xKNNNXK0OkOxllkNNNNWXxlxdoxko.  . ........:x000Okkkddo:,;cllclc...',.....;:.           
'''''............................................;xKXx,.,,',:xKOd;...;dookkxkOOOOO0OOx:....,lOXNNXK0kdc..'........;xkdc'.',lOKx,'codkOkxk0OO0OOOxdxkddddxkOKXNWWNNNX0OkxxkO0KXNNNWWWWWNNXK0OOO0XWWWMMMWWNKOOkkxl:coOXNWNNWWX000OOxddkNWNNN0c,;cc;..  .......';:dO0OOkdooc:,,;:clllo:...;c;..',lx:...        
''''............................................,dKXk;....',,oK0xo:...''.,dOkxdxxxxdol;...'o0KXNNXKOxl...',......:oO0k;.,:cxXO;.;ldkOOkk0000KKKKKKXX0KXXXNNXXNWNNXOdxk0KNNXXNNNNWWWWWWWWWWWWNKkxkXWMMMMWWNNWWNXXNNWWWWWNNNNNK00OkxxdoOXNNNO;. ..';..  ..:llxkkxdlc;,'......'ccloloo'...;lc'.,;o0O:..        
'''............................................'oKNKc....''..:OXkooc'....'lxkOkxxoc:::;',lOKKXXNXKK0x,....'.  .'c:cooxc.'coO0l';loxOOk00000KKKKXXXXXXXXXXXXXXNNXOdx0NNNNNNK0Okxxxkkk0KKXNWWWWWWN0k0NMMWWWWWWMWWWWWWWWWWWWNNWNXXKOkxxxxKNNNKo...;cl;'.  .;:;;,'..........'..:lclood:..';cll;.';lOXk;.        
''............................................'lKNNk;...,,...;kNKkxxd:'...;:',lk0Oxl;;lkKXKOkkOO00Ok:.......  .,dl:;;c,.,lkKx,;ldkO0O0KK00KKKKKKKXXXXXKXXXXXXX0xd0NNNNNXOxdddkOOO0OxxxxxkKNWWWWWWXOOXMWWWWMMMMMWWMMMWWWMMWWWWWNXXK00OdkXWNX0c'coodxk:. ....... .',,'..';,.'loodldd,..;ccll,..,;lkKk,.       
''............................................:OXN0l'..,;'...:OXKOkkxxoc,......lxdxxcoKNKxlccclcoxxc'...........;ol;,...:dKKc;lxkKKKKKKKKKKXKKKKXXXKKKKKXXXXX0dxXWWNXKkddk0XNWWWWX000O00Okk0XNWWWWN0OXWWWWMMMMMMMMMMMWWMMWWWMMWNNXKKKxd0NXK0oc0OoxO0o........ .;lc..'od:..:dxxdoxo...;loodc...';lxKd.       
''...........................................;kNNXk;.',;,,'':xK0klcooooolc,....;;..,dXN0o:lddxxllxl'.....',:;...,,;,...:d0Xk;,ok0KKXK000OO000KXXXXKKKXXXXXXXKxkNMWWXkodk0XWWWWWWWNXKKKKXKK0xox0XNX0K0OXMMMMMMMMMMMMMMMMMMMMMMMWNNXXXXOokNXK0xcx00O0x,........'cl:..:dd;..,dkOkxkk:...,ldxkd,....:lx0l.      
............................................cOXWNNXOxdddxxkOKXKkolc:ccclccc:;......dNNkllk00Okocdd'.';;ccllol'..,,:;...:xKKo':xO0000ko:,,;;;:dOKKXKXXXXXXXNXkxXWWWXkld0KKXNWWWWWNXKKKXXX00KKk:;:ldkkOkkNMMMMMMMMMMMMMWWMMMMMMWWWWNXXXKddKX000xlok0k;,oc.....','..,cc,....ck000OOo,''.,oxO0x:....':lOO;.     
.........................................;coONNNXXXKKXXXXXKKKKOo;,.....'',::;;'...dNNx:lOKXKkoldd;.,dkdll:;,'...,;;,...;xXKc,lxO0Oxc'........,cdOKKXXXXXXNN0k0NWMW0llkO000KKXNNNNXKKKKXK00K00xclc::cdOx0WMMMMMMMMMWWN0kkkOOKXNWWWNNNNXkoOX0KKKx:lOKd,'. .......'','.....:k0KKK0kl','.'lk0KOl'..  .cxKd.     
........................................:xKXNWNXOxlccccllollodoc'...','.....',,.'xNXo;oOKXX0dloxc.'oxdl:'.....:ooodo,..:kXOccdxkOx:',:,......cddxO0KXXNXNNXkOXNWMW0ookkOOkO0KKKOkkkkKNNNNXKO0KxxOkdc;::dXWMMMMMMWNOdc,.....';lkXNNNNNXOdOXKKKKo;dxdkd'. ...','...',;'...o0KXNX0d,.....cOXNKx;... .,o00:.    
.......................................'o0NNXKOxo:,:xkkxdoc:::,.....''........';OWKl;lOXXX0xlldo,'lkd;.......,xdll:c:..l0Nkllodkxc':dd:.....'lddllk0KKKKXXKxONNWWW0ox0000KKKXXxok00xxKNXNXXK0KkdO0OOkl:;cd0NWMMWXd,';:'.....,::o0XNXXKOdONXKXXdcOkooOd.  .''. ..cdc..'':kXNNNXkc......c0NNN0l'.. .'lOXd..   
.......................................,dKNKKOxol;;kNNX0OOOkOOkdoc;,'.........;ON0:;oOXXKKxccol:;oOd'........,oddool'.;xKXOccdxxd,.cdo:.....'cll::x0KKKKXXKxONWNNN0oxKKKXXXXXKddKKOdckNNNNNNXXkoOK00KKx:::,:oOXWk,'ldl'.....:o:;o0NXXKkdONNNWXl'l0Oxx:. .......cxo'.;c:oKNNNNKd;',,;..;ONNNNk;... .;dX0;.   
.......................................,o0XKK0ko:.,kNWXkdoxxdolc::cllc:::;;,.;ONO:,lOXX00kccod:;d0x,....''....,:oxd'.;ok0Xk;:xxkx:.;ll;.....':cccd0KKXXXXNKxkXNXNNKolOKXXXXXXX0xolloxKWWWWNNNKocOKK0KXdlKXOo:,;lc,cxkl.....'oko:l0XKXXOx0WWWWk'..,;,.   ..   .,dd,.',':kXNWWN0l;;:;'..;ONNNN0l.....'oKXo.   
.......................................,lkKXXKk:...c0WNKkxd;..',,.....';:cc;:ON0:,oOKX0kd::od:.c00o,........'c;,cl;.'cdOKXx;:xkkkd;,:c:'.....,:lkKXXXXXXNNXkd0XXNNX0od0KKK0KKKKK000NWWWWWNNXKd;oKXKXN0cxWMMWX0xc,,cxk:.....:00klo0NXX0kdKWMMWd..';;;'        .,l:....'d0NNWWXx;....  .;ONNNNNd'.....c0WO'   
........................................:okXNXk,...,dXNNKkc...:do;'.......'ckNO:'lkkOOxo:;ldc.,kKko,.. .....';,:dxl'.:oxOKk;:xkkkkxo:;;'.....,lOKNNNNNNWWWNXkd0XKXNX0kkOOOkOOO00KXWWWWWWNNN0l;lKNXNWXolKWWMMWWWNx'..'','...xNXkcdKXNX0dxXMWWWO;':cod:.      ...,,.  .c0NWWWWO;..  ....,xXNNWNx'.....cOWK;   
.........................................;d0XX0l...,;dXWNKd'..coc;,'......'dXXl':docccc::coo'.oX0do;....... ..'ldool;,ldkOx:;dkxkOOOOxolclodxOXNWWWNNWWWWWWWXxoOKXXNXK0kkkkkkkkkOKXNNNNNXOo;:dKWWWWXd:xNWWWWWWWWN0l,..',,,lKXkodKXKKK0xkWWNXX0c;dOkkxc.    .'..',.  'xXWWWWNd'.',,;,..'dKNNNXd,.  .'l0WXc.  
..........................................,lOKX0o,.'.'dXNX0d,.','',''',,..;xX0l;;cdxdk0KOdl'.'xKOdl:. ....'...;occocc;:lxOxc;odddkOOOOOO0XNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNWWWMXdoOKXNNNNX0xdddxxxk0KXKOkdl;:d0NWWWN0l;oKNNNNNWWWWNWN0dc,..';cldk0XXKKOxd0WWNXK0lckkodko.  ..... ... .c0NWWWW0:..';;;'..'dKXXX0o;. ..,oKXKc.  
............................................;okKKx:''',oKNNX0Okkkdlccllc''lx0K0kkOdccdxxOk;..'cxkl:c' .'''....,oolcc;'';dxdo::lldxkkkOOO0KKKKK00KKKK00KKXXNWWNKdlx0XNNNNNXKkolc;,;cc:,;:cx0XNNNNKd;ckNWNXXNNNNWWNNXXNXKOko;''cld00OOxldXWWWXKX0clOK0d,..        ...;OXNNWWXd'..';;'.. .o0XXX0xc. ..'lxOOc...
..............................................;lodoc;;;;c0NNXK0OOxlcccc:,.':xKXK0xdxlokolc....'';;,,'. ....,,...;::,....:ddo:;clodxdxkOOOOOOOOkkkOOOOkOO0KKXXK0Oxold0XNNNNNXXKkc'.':oxkO0KKXXK0xccdKWWNNNNXXNNNNNNXKKKXKX0Oxo:.'loloolOWMMWNNNKocdOo',,..   ..   .'dKNNNWW0:.......   'd0KXKkdl'..';:;::..  
...............................................,lc,,'',;,;oxoc:;,,'''''''....;oO0dxX0cco'...... .'..    ..''.....',,.....:ddc:lcloddodxxxkkkkkkkxxxxxxkOOO000OO000kolokKXNNNNXK0x:,,cdkOO00Oxl;cxKNWWWWWWNXNWWNNNXXKKKKX0O0KKkd:,'',,lXMMWWWWKock0d'..,..        .:kKNWWNXx'   .....  ,dkxxOxoo;..',;ldc.   
................................................cl::;;'...... .,,'........ ....';,':o:... .,:;,..............''.',',,....:odl:cccloooodoodxkkxl:,'':llllldkOO00O0000OdlloxO0XNNX0kxl,';oxdl:cokXWMMMMMWXkddxkO0KXXK0000K000KkkOOxdc;''lOXWWW0c:oOX0:. ....       .oxOKNNX0c.   .',,,. 'ldolxdlo:..;oOOKk'   
...............................................':oc''',;'. ....;,'....  ......',.    ....,;;;:cc::,..,;;col;;olcol:coc. ..'...',,:cccloolodxl,.....,ldxdl::okkO000K000OOxdollooolcc:;..,clokXNWWMMWWW0l;;:clcc:;cd0K0000O0K0kkOOOOxlooc:co0KdododxOo..,,,,'......;ddxO0KKx,.    ..,;. 'colcoool:':kK0OKd.   
......................................... ....,odl,....'..   ....',;::,.  ....''.......,;:::::;;:clc:;;,,lol;:c:oollo;. ..:c...'',;;,:odood:.........;clol;;lxkkO0KXXXXNNXK0kdlccllllooo:;:xXNWMMWWXd,,ldddoc;....:k000OO0OkOOOkxdlxNWNKo'.;lxOOOxo,.';;lxxollc,,lodkOO0Oc.    .. .'..'colllll;;d0XX000:    
.......................................... ...cOKxc;,'.'.  ......;dKXXKk:.'ll:lxxl:okxc,...,:;;;;;:loooc;;;;'':;,:::c;.',cO0xdddodx:.,c:;::..,,.........,;;,'lkOKXXNWNNWNX0kxxxxOXXKKK00Oxc,ckXWWWWx';dkkxl;.......cO0O000OkOO0kl:dXWWWNx,...,:oxo,..',cx0XXKKx:loodxxxkd' .......',...:ll:::,,dKXNX0Kx'    
.............................................cONKkocccc,. ..;cc;'.'oOXNX0l,oOlckKOl:xKkxc..;;,;:::okOkxxxxoc,.''..'cxxddkOKXXNNNNXKOkxdxd;...ld:............'lOKNNNNNNXNXK0kkkkkOKNNNNNXKK0d:;:dKWWx'ckxc;.......;;:x0KKOOOkO0OdcdXWWNN0;..,:;...,clc:,,cdk00Ol:olloooxkc. ......,;'. .;:::;:oxOXNN000:.    
...........................................,o0XN0oc::cc,. .,ldlcc;..l0XXKk;.oo,:xdl;,lool',lc,..,:dOO00000KKKOxl;'';loddxkO0KXNWWWNNNWWWXo'..;ddc;'.........:k0XNNXXWWNXK0OxxddddxOKNNNXKKKK0xl,;xXx,','......':ol;:OK00OOkO0OdokXWNNNKd,':ox:..   .;clc,..';,;cccloodkd'..;cc:c:;:,...,;::cxO0KXNKO0o.     
..........................................ckKXX0l,..'''....:oxc';xx''dkxkkc..,.'ccc,.':c:..:c;.. ..,cdk00KXXNWWNX0d:',coddddxk0KNNWWWWWWWKl'..,clll;.......:x0KXNNNNNNKK00kl;,,:::ccdOKKKXXXKKKkl;:l:.......;lxkxllkXKKK0O0OOolxKNXXKOkl:ccox:.       .;c:'. .,:;:llcdx:..,lkKKXXXKkc',;,;lxO0KXNN00k;.     
........................................:xKNN0x;.......  ..:oxl'.cx,.loodd:.....;;;'.';,'..;;....  ...;cox0KNWWWWWWKxl;,,,',;:ccld0XWWWWWWXOd:.';;;;,'..,:oOKKXNWNNNXKKK0x;.,lxkxxdlclodOXXXXXXX0xl,''''..,lxOkdodOKKKK0000xllx0KK00Odc;lOxll,.          ';:;,;,:c::ldc...'cx0XNNNKOl'',:oO0KXXXNKO0o.      
......................................:d0XNKOkc...''...   .;ldl'....'ol:cc,. ..';,.. .,.  ... ...  ......':d0XNWWWWWNN0o:,...,::;;:o0NWWWWWXx,.','';coodxkOO0XNNNNXXKKKKk;..,cllll::;,'.:OXXXKK00K0kl,';:lodddxk0XKKKK00Okl:oOO00Okxl;;lxkl':;.            ..;:;;::;lo'......;lodxdo;.,cxOkoox0XXOkk;.      
................ ...................:x0KK0kddxc............'cdo;....:d:,,..   ..'..  ..        .  .':,......;lk0XXNWNNX0Oxdl;...,:cclONWWWWW0c...,clokOkxxkkO0KKKKKXXXKKd...............'xKK0OO0KKKK0kl;,;d0K0KKKK00K00OdclxOOOOdc'..cdoodc. .    ....';:ccccccc;'..;,. .':' .....''';oO0k:..'dXKkko.       
................     .............,;::cc::ldxkkd,......,;...'lddoccldl,....   ...  ............ ..:kOdl;.......,cdOKXXK00K0dol,..''::lKWWWWNXOo,.,cllodoodxxkkO00KKKKKK0l...............'x000000K000KKKOd;';ok0OOO0K0OxoldkOOOOxc.  .:doll'  ..':ldxdddk0XNWNNXKOkol:... .;,...,;,..cxOOOOxlcdKNOxx,        
.................  ............':c:,.......:dOKX0o,..',;'... .;oxOOl'....     .'. ...,;;,'......'lOOxo;.... .,,'.';clx000Occxl;,:l:',:kWWWWXK0d,..,cccllloddxkOO00KK0KKKx,.';,'''.......cO00000OO0KKKK0KKOl'.;lxk00koldk0KK0000d,........  ..:dOKKKOkxdxk0KK00OOOOkOOkxl,.',..,;,,;loodxk000KXK0Oxc.        
................   .    ......:dkOxl'...''...:kXNNOc''...,......''......    ...,'...,,.........;kKOxo;. ...'clcc::c,.':oxkl,,;l:cOOc,:kWWWWNKx,...',;:c:cooxkxkOkkOO00K0Oo;;coddoll:;;,lOKXKKK00KXXK0KKKK0ko;'.,cllldk0XNWWNXKxllc:lc'....,lk0K0kxkkOO0KNWWNNNXKK0OxxO0KOd;..;:';locclodkkkkOOkdol;.        
................. .... .....;d0KNNKd'..',,,...;kXNXKx:......;,. ............. ....''..........;OXOoc,.  ...,,;clolc:..'',::;;codk0x:cxKWWWNX0o;. ...',;:cldxdxkOOkkk0000OOOdc:cllcc::lx0KKXXKKKKXXXK00000O0Odc'...:xOKKKNN0ddl:ddccdo. .'lddOOxdkKXNXKKXNWMWMMMMMMN0dodOKKOl'.,:ll::coddoolc:::odo'         
..........................'o0XNWWWWXx:;:;;;;'..lKNXX0kl....,:'...''''.  ......................o0Odc,.......'..ckKOOOd;',:cc:;:cooc;cx0XNNNXKkdc.  .,;;;,;cllllddodkOOOOOO0000OxxkxkOO0KKK000000O0000OOkO0Oxlccodl,.;d0kxko' ..,xxdkx:..;xkxxdoOKKKKKKKKKXNWMWWMWWWWWXOlcx0K0d,.,;,,,',,'..',;lkOo,.         
........  ...   .........:kXNNKOOKX0kdolool:,..:OXNNXX0l...'....,:::'. ..','.  ..........  ...:oo:,....,:,...,lkXNNNNKxlcldoc:;,',cdxkO00K0d;..   .;coddlc::;:llcldxxkkkOO000000OkxxkxxxddxxxxxxxdddddoddlcldkOOOxc;,,cl;.  ..ckkxo'..;OK0OddKX0kxdox00KKXNNNNNKXWWWWXd,,ldxkl...... .....cdxOko,.          
........    .   ........c0XOdl;.'cxxoodxOkl,...;ONXKNNX0dc;,,,..:lcl, ..,,,:,. ..,;cdxxxdlc:;..........','.  ..;xXXNWNK0kdlc:;;;;:lolooodxd;.     .;coxkOko;,,,,,,;::codoooookkxxdddddxxxxxkOxxkxdo:;:cooddxkkxxxdxdl,.','.,oxxkOl. .'d000xdKXkl:;,,dKKXXXXXXKdoxk00kdll:;:codc..,;...,,..ckO0o'.           
..........        ....,dK0dc:,...codxO00Od;.''.:ONK0KXXK0xol:;';odol. .,,;cdd:..'codk0KXXNNXKOo;........,:;''...:kKKKKOxoollccllc:cllllc;;:;...  ..',,,;:c:::clllooxkO0OOOkOO00OkxxxxxxkkOKNXOkO00KO:.;odddxkdolcccdO0o'..:kKdcdO:. .ckOOdoOXK0xc,.'xKXNX0O0OdxXXKkxxkOkdc;codd,..'...'..'okkl.             
..   .....      .....cOKxcoo;...:dxkOOkxdo;....lKN0kOXKkoc:;,'.:xxxl..',;:oO0kl..,:clokO00000Odl:,. ..;clc,'.,,.:occlcc:;;;,,',,,,;:c::cccclooodxkkkOOOOOOkkOOOOOOkxxxxdxOOOOOOOOkxxxxxOxldKOxkkO0KKo.,oxxxkxo:;'.':oooo:..;dOOOd'...lxkdcd0KXNXKOdo0NXOdxkxolONNWWNXKK0Od;:dxx:......'';oxd,               
.      .         ..'o0Olcll,..':ooc:;,:llc:...:kX0xdOKkl;'.....oOOOl..',:ok0KXXx;':::clodxdlcllc,...,;:;'....,,',;;::ccloodddxkO0KKKXKKKKK0OOxxkxdddoodoooodxxkOOOOO0KXXNNNWWWWWWWNKK0OOxlxK0kOKK00k:.;ooodxxoc'     .ld'....'col,.',ldxocxKXNNNNNNNNN0okNWN0dlONWNNNNXKKk;;dkx:..';::clooc.                
 ..             ..:xKk:;c:'..,::;'.....':::,.,d0Oxclkd;..,'...:kKXKc..'.;d0XNNXKd;;cloooxkkdc:;;,',:ccloddxkkO0KXNNNNNNXXK0OOkkxdooddxdddddddddol::coxxxkOOO0OOO000KNWNNWWWWWNX0kxdooooodk0K0000kxo;',,'':x0Kk,    ....;cccc'  .;loc:dOOxckXKKXNNNNNXNOoOWWNKdoOXKXNWNXKKx,,x0k;.',,::coo;.                 
...            .'lxOd;.'..';:::,....''..,;;',dOxoc:c:....'',;,lKNNO;..'..;kKNN0kOo,;:ldkO00K0000KKXKKKKKK00OOkxdooollccccccllolodxk0KNNNNNNNNNKo;,;;';:lddddxdooodxkOOkxxkxxxxxxxxkkkkxdlc;''',;;:c;..   .'co:.  ..''.'ooccdl. ...;lodxkxldK00KXXNNXXX0olxkkxdOXOollx0KKKo';OKx'.,lllooo;.                  
.        ... ..,dkkOkol:,',;,,'....'''..',';dxdoc;;'. .':oxxc,oNWNx. ....':kX0xoxxkO0KNNNXNX0kxolccc::::;,'.....,codddxxk0KXNNNNWWWWWWWWWNWWXK0o,;c,..',:cccc:;;;::cclllldxxkkxdoc::::;.       .;cc'  .... .;,.  ..,;.'lc:ldl..,,...,codkdokOk0OxdxO00xdO0OOKNNXx:'..'l0k;;xKKl...cxxxxc.                   
....  ...  ...ckKXNNNNX0Oxxdl;,...'......,;ldlcc:,....;d0K0kc;kWWNd..';;;;,:dxoxKXXXXXXXK00Oo'..''';:ldkkc;oddxkdlloxOOO0KXXNNNXNNNNNNNWNNNNKOOx:,,:oc,......',;:lollll:;;;'....   .;c,.    .... .;. .::;,''...   .,;,:lodl;. .....  .;xOkolooodkOOkdoxKNNNWWNKOl;;;:oxx::xKKx;..;oddxo.                    
..... ......'o0NNXXXXNX0xoloddxoc:,.......,:;;;:;'..'cx0K0ko;c0WWNd..,lxxxxc;xKKK0000OO0OO000x;':cclodxkl,d0dlldKx',ldxxdxkO00KKKXXXXKKK0kxxdol:'';:lc;'.. ..''''''.....     .....  ';...  ..,,.  ...;xkxl::,;.   .,clxkc'.  ...,::'. .:x0kl:lOXXNNNXKXNNWWWX0OOkxxkOkl,:kK0o'.';:ooo:.                     
..... .....,d0XN0dc:lOXXkdll::ccc:,'':lddxko;...'...;looc:,..lXWWNo..,cdOkxlo0XXK00kc:ldx0KKKKx,,cclloxo''dOxoldKx;cc:odoodddxddddoooodxxxxk0Oko;;:;;::,...            .....;:ccc;.  ...... ..;:'. . ,ddc:ll:,.  .ckocld:.  .,ll:cl:'. .,oO0kod0XWWWWNNWWWWWNXKK0K0Oo:;lxxkl....',;;,.                      
..........;dKNNKd'...:OX0xoc;'....;oOXNWWWNKko;'....,,'......dNWNXc....:odl;dXNNNNKoodoolkKKXX0c;llllodd:..;ooooc',coc:;;;;;:::clooddxxkxxolccc;..,;;:cl:,'.          .;lodxkxxdo;. ........  .ldc'...;:oOOo,.   .oxc,;o:. .,codlccc:'.  .:x0Oxodk0XNNNWNNNWNNXKOxl::dO0ko;.   .......                      
.........,lkXNXKk:..'lO0ko:'....;oOKKXNK0Okxddoc:,.....,'...'OWWWK:....;,;,;kWWWWWXddkl;cx0KKK0c,clcclooo;. ....';:cooc;...':c:cc::;,'.....,;c;'...,;;:cc;,.          .:lddxxolc;.    ..';;..  .;c:;:cdxxo:.   ...:dkxdl'.'cdxdxxl:;'...   .ck00xolclodxkkOkxdoc;;:lkOkl;...'. ....,.                       
...... ...cOXNXXX0xxkOkxl,..,,,:kNNNKxoccdkoc;cdol;....:;...;0WWNx..,..coo:'lXWWWWN0kkkkkOkkOKk;;lcllccllc;'....,:clddol;'.......      .'clc;;col'..,clll:'..         .';;,;;;,'.        ..''.     ......   ..;:,...,,...,oxOkdo:,..    ..  ..:lxkkxdlccc;,,;;:lodxdo;..  .''...,'.,'                       
..........'o0KXXXXKKOdo:..'::;,oKNN0ldkl:d0X0c'cdoo;. .',...lXWWXc.,c;.'loc,'oKXKK00KXXK0OOOOkocoodxxxkkxol:,. .':ldxxxdodl'...,.... .,ll:;:lol;..  .,;;;:,....    .;,.....,......... .     ....        .':oxko;''''.   'dkdl;'. ...    .........,coooxOkdlloooolc:;'. .  .....,;..,'                       
............cx0KKOOko:,...'''',l0XXxcON0l:lOXx':k0k:.  ....,kNNN0;.,lc'.;oddc,:odxkkO0K0OOkkO000kxxdool:;'...    .;lxxxxkkxdc'';,'...clc::c:'.    .  .',coo;','.   .:l'..'lo;..;::.   ...     ....  .';lxOKXkccc:cl:.  .,:,...;:clodool;'..,:ll;.  ...',;,,,,;:;;:cll:'...  ..''...:'                       
.............':ooll:'.   ....'.:k0Kk:cOKOl::o:,dKKO:.......cKNXXk'.';;cd0NNKkl,..,:cloddoooodol;'....   ..     .   .cdxxk0000x:,,.  .';::'.    .....  ..';cc'',..  .'lollxKKxcdOko'...,,.       ..';lxO0K00Oc:dl;;dx.    .,lk0XX0OKNWWWNk:'';lc'........,,,;:lodddkxxxo:,.  .... .;c.                       
...................     . .....;dOOOxc:cll;'',cxkxl'..,''.'dKXXXd'..':kKWWWKo,.';c::::::;;;,'.. ...,'..''. ..  ......,lxxOKXXX0o'     '.    .... .;:;;;,',:ll,';.....:kO0KNNNNNNNKOkxdl,.     ...;lodxkOOOOd;;oxoc:'.  .,xKNNXNNK0KXNNX0Oxdl,,... ....'..';clloooolc;,..    ... ..;,.                       
................................,lxxxxkkxdxxkxdol;..';:::';kKKXKo..',:d0Kkl,....,:lldool:,'..  .,:llc::,. .... .;cc,. .;dOKNNXXXk:.'.        .'...:x0KKk:';:lc;;;..  'lk0XNNWWWWWWWWWWXl'..''....,cclodkOOkd:,cxd,.  ..;kKNNXKkooddoodxxxxkOkd:.   ...... .,;;,,..   .. ..     ..,,.                        
..................................;::cdKNNNXOxl;...,:clc:':kO0K0:..,:clc,..':ll::::;;;;,......'ccllccc,........,okkdl,.',lOKXNNNNXxc:;.      ..:oxOKXNNXk,.,;l:,;;.   'ld0NWN0dccclxKWWX0kko,....',:codxxdd:,;oxc.   .'okO0KOllkXWWKd:::cdk0KXk;. ................. ... ...    .',.                         
.............................     ..,:ooolc:,......,;dkdl;:lodxx, .,,.....,coxOOKXXKK0Ooc:,'.,lodoolc,...''....;dOOkkxdl'.,o0KXNWWWKx:.  .....,oOKXXKkddc'.',:oc,;,.  .:oONWKc.  ...,xXNXKKk;....'..,:;;::;;looxo.   .lO0000ol0NN0dclkKd,l0XNNk;....................... ...   ..'.                          
..........  ............           ..;c,.............l00l,,;dxc:.  .. .....',coxkOOO0Oxl;,.':oddoll:.. ........,dOO00OOOc. .:x0NWMMMWk,  ..';cdkKKKkc'......'coo:','.  .cONNx. .;'...c0NXKKK0xdoc,. ...  .;dl::cl'   'xNNWWXodK0o:cONWXx,cKNWNk:.........''................  ..':,.                         
..........    ... ..  .              .;ldoc;,........'xKd;:llll:. ..............,;,;,''...'lxxdooo;......''....,dOKXXKK0l.   .ckXWWMWW0c.  .,coxO00l'.....;,..,:l:,,'.  ,kNNO:..:c:''oKXXNNWWNX0c. ..     'llcc:,.   .oKXXNKxccloxOXNXOc,dXWWXd,.........''.......;::'... .:llldOo.                         
..........       ...                 .,dO0d,..'.......lKKl',;:;,,,;;::'..,,...',,'.......,dO0Oxdl,..'....'......c0XXXXK0d.... ..ckXWWWWNO:..,;cxOOOd,...;lo;..,:loc,,.  .cOK0OdccclokKXXNWWWNNXKxl:,'.    ......      ,k0O00kl;ldxxkko:;o0NWXx'..........,,...'..'ldo;,;. ;k000KKx.                         
..........                            ;k0Kd..,:' .,:..cKNOl;,'.',,,cdkk:..'...:l,... ...cOXNXKxc'..''...,'...:;.;OKXXXXXO:..'.  .'ckXWWWWXx,.;clodkkd:,;::ccoc;;;coc,,.  .'lkOKXXK00KNWWWWWWNNXK00x,..   .';.          ,dxdxkxolc::c:cx0NWW0o'  .........;;...'..,okxl:;' 'x00000d.                         
.............                        .c0K0l. .;,.,dc..dXNOdl,......'lOKOc..'.'ox:. ...'oKXXXXO:.  ....:o:... ...;kKKXXXK0c..,:.  ..,ckKNWN0o;';clodxxkOOOOOKKx;'',cdc'.   .;oookKK0KNWWNNXNXXNXXK0x:....',,'.           .,lllxkkkkkOKXWWNXx,...  ........,:' ....'okxc;;'.,kXK000x'                         
.........                            .dK0x,   .',oo..;ONKxc'.........:kKOc....ld;....;kXNNXXk:.    ..oOo'...    .o000K0OOd' .cc. .c;..;xKKOkd:',cooddkO0KXNXOl,'.';oo;,.. .oxxdllkKXNNXXKKKKXXXXXK0d;;l:;:lc.             ..'lO0OO0KK00kl,..'c:. ...'....,c;.... ,xOl',;..c0XK0OOd.                         
.......                             .;OK0l.    'l:. .dK0ko'......';;..:x0k;...,:,...:kNNNNKd,     .;xkl'....  ...cOO0OOkkd'  .l; .c:'. .;dOOkdl;'',:cxO0KNXdcc:;'.;ldc;'..;oxkO0l:kKXNXKK0KKKKXKKK0l,lxlcll;.            .'....,,,;;,'...;cdOKo.   ..'...'lc.... 'xOc'c;.,xKKKK0Oo.                         
 ...                                ,dOOo.     .'. .:Oxlc...''',cdl;...:xxc....''..cOXXXX0l..   ..,ld;.  .....::.'oxoll;,..   .. ... .....;dOkd:...;:lkOKXd,;::lc,;:,'''..'cxO00d,l0KXKKK0KK00KKKKOo;;lxkl'        ....  .;:..,:;,'.'.,o0XXXXXd......,,. .:o'....;xx::c'.lOKXK0Okc.                         
                                  .,lllllloooddollc:;:;;. ....;ll;......''........c0NNXXk:.  ...,:;,..     .,c;.. .'....     ....',,';:;;'..:c;:lc.,lc:o00l:lccldxc,;cc::'.:OKKKk:cOXX0dlolcdOKKK0ko,,ldd,      ..'',.....;c'.:xkxkkxll0WWNXX0o...  .:;. .cl'.'..:o;;:'.;OXXXKOOx;                          
                                  ,coOXNNNNXK0kxOKXXKOxc'....,,'........,col:,'.'oXWWNXx,    .',,...'.     ....     ..';cloddxxdoolc:::cc::'. .,c:.'c,.;k0lcoooodkxo::::;..o0K00k;c0XO:......:OKK0o;,;clo:.    .',,,'..,,',c;.,dKXNNKxlkNNXXKOo.    .c:. 'ol.....,,,:;..dXNXKOkOx,                          
                                  .,lkKNNNXKd'.:ld0KKKK0xc;,'.........,:odxoc,.;kNNNN0l.   ...........   ....',:lodkO0KKNWMWNKOOkkxxdlllcclc;,,..''.....l0xcoddxxkkOxoc;,:oO0OOkl,oKKo,::. ...l0Kx;:l;,;lo.    .;,,,',,::,,c:.,x0XNKOxclkxdooo:.   .':'..:o:.... .;;'..l0XXXKOkOx,                          
                                   .,:oOXXXKx;';:oO0OOkdddddlc:;'.......,''...;kNWWNO;.   ...    ....,;:lddxOKXNNWNNWWNXXNWWWNK0OOkxoc::;,,.....    .',.,k0l:odkOO0O0K0kxkO00kxc,lO00x:;'. ..'xXKx;;ll:::,.   .';,;,'';cl:;;,..;:;:;,'..... .      .,'..,c;.... .;,..'oKNNXX0Okkd'                          
                                    ..;ckXXXX0kxk00Okxdoolllc:;;;,,;;;;,..,;,cOXXNKo. ......'',;cloxOOO0KXKXNNWNNNNNNXK0Okxolc:;,'............;;.   ....:OKOl:cx0KKK000kxxxk0xccdO00KKOdl:;:d0NXOl'...'.     ..',:;'',codl,....  ':c:lxdoc,..    ..'...';,..,'..'....dXNNNNXKOkko.                          
                                      .':x0XXK0Okxxdl:;,,;,;;'.....',;coc,..:xKK00l. ...',;:odkOO00O000000Okxddolc:;,'....           ..;;;::'.';;,'.',,:x0KK0koloxO000K0kdolccoOO000KXXNWNNNWNKd:,'....      .,';;'';cldxxxo;:c..:O0kKNNNKxc'.  ......,'...',.......;ONWNNNNK0kko'                          
                                        ..',,'....clcloxkO0Okl,..,,;,..',;'.:lokk:. .';;;:ldxxxddocc:;;,''..........    .....    .     .,oxl;;;',:cooolok0KKXNXKkdoddddddlcodxOOkO0KKXXXNWWWNKoccclc;.  .'. .'';:;,;codkkkOk:;d:.;0Kk0NNNX0xl'  ....''.. .'''.. ..,;cONWNNNNX0Oko'                          
                                               ..ckOKNNXXXK0Okdcccccc::c;..'co;,'  .,,''''''....      .''.    .,,''.  .':loc.    ...  ...'dxccc:;;';ododO0KXNWWNXK000xllodxkxxO0O0KKKKXXNNNNXd;loddoo'.';;..',;c:,,:ldkkkkOk:,ll':KNOxXWWNX0k:.  ..'..  .,,'..  .:oox0NWNNNNX0OOd'                          
                                               .cOXWWXk:;:ccoxkOOkkxxdll:'.....    ...               .,:::' ....'..  'lxOkxl.     .''. ...:xl;:::l'.;xkOKKKXNNNXKK0Od,.,::;cdk0K00KKXXKKXX0Ox:,okdl:'.;lc' .;;c:,,:ldkxxkko,.'lo;;OWKx0WWWNKOl'. .......''. ....'lxkk0NNNNNNX0OOo'                          
         ..                                   .l0XNWNk,..''.;ldxdoolc:,'.....    ........      ..'';cc:,,;'. .       ,d0XKKx,      .,;.   .ldcccc;. 'okOKXNNNNXK000d:'';;;,.cO00KKKKXK000xc;,:lo:'. .cdo' .;;:c:,,cdOxdkd:. .'ld;,kWXxkNWWX0ko'. ...','......,..;okxx0XNNXXK0OOOd'                          
                                             .;xKXNNXOl'.'';ldxdl;'..........  .',;'..'.      .,:;;:c,....    ..     'd0XXKOc.      .;:.    ..,'.....';:okKXNNKK00Ol.....  .lkkk0000K0Od:;c:lcol.  .:kd, .,:cll;,cxOxdxo;,',;:lo;.oNNxxXWWX0ko,....''..  ...:c;;:xOdlOXNXKKK0OOOd'                          
                                             .:d0XXXKKK0OO00Oko;.......,cc::,..';:::'..     ...;;,,,'.        ..     .lkO0KOl.       .;,.        .''',,''':kKKKK0OOd:'....,lxxdlclc;:c:,.;doddxc.  'xk;. .;cdx:'cx0kooc:c;;:'':l:.:KWOxKWWNKOx;.......    .;lolcokOooOXXXXK0OOOOd'                          
                                             .;ldk0K0KXKK0Oko:.  ... ...;;','..;:::::. .''. ....'''..  ..  .. .''    .;ooool:.     ...''.  .....  .,loo:,;,,lxxxxxxdoolccldxko:;:cc;......':c:,.  .c0d. .;ldxc':kKOolcll:,.. .:l:.'kWKxOWWNX0xc.... ..   .'colccokklo0XXKKKK00OOd'                          
                                              .....''',;;;,'.....;do,..........;clodd:..,:,...         .'. .',..',.   .,,,,'..    .:,......,;:,.  .,okOxooc;,;:;''col:;::::cc;:ol:ccl,..'    ......o0c..:ldOd',xX0olclo,..,cc,:ll;.oNXxxNWWN0kl'.....    .,col::dOkoxXXXKKKK00OOo.                          
                                                              ...:k0Oo,........:x00K0x, .,,,.    .:;.  .,.  .,c'.,,.    .....     .,. ...,col,.    ..'',,;llcloo;..',:dl:cdxxxxkdcc:c'    .'::....'dx,.;ddkk;'dXKoc;;l,.,oxc..;ooc.:KNOdKWWNK0d,......  .',:ll::x0OokXNNXKKKK0OOo.                          
                                                                 .:x00kc,.. .;;;xXXXXXd. ......',:dc.  ...    ';.  ..,codxkxdol;,.    .;ldo:.      ...   .,lxkOOc.  'xo,;:lO0dlc;;,'.    .lxl'....cxl.,oxkkc,dNNxl:,c;.ckxc,. ,ool''kN0dOWWNXOo,....... .,:coo::xKOdONNNXK0KK0Okl.                          
                                                                  .'oO0dc. .;:,'lKNKKNKc.  .',:cclc.   ..        .'l0NWWWWXkdxdolc,..,lddl;,.    .,c:::,.  .;;;,.   .:doox0kc.......... 'oxc.....cdl,;oxkkc,oXNOdd;,c';kxc:;,,;loo,.cKKdkNNX0xl,...';'. .,:coo:ckKkd0NXNXKK000Ok:.                          
                                                                    .;l;. ..';;':OXXXNNk;. .,,;::ldo:;';l'      .:kXWWWWWX0kxxxxdc::ldo:'..:,...'ckd:clcc'       ..   .',;,.':oo:,.... .oo;.....coc';ldkOd,cKWKdkk''c',oc:;,c:,ldoc.,k0xxXN0Oxo;.....    ,:lol:l0Kxo0NNNXXK0000Oc.                          
                                                                     ,o:'...',,.'dXNNNWKd'..';,;:ldO0Kkl:.     .:dOKXXXKxoccc:clccd0k:.    .':lcdOkxxolol'      .::..     .:llc,.     .:c;.  .'cc;.'ldxkx::ONN0OK0;.c:..',.....cdl;..,;,':doooc,.       .,clol;o0Kxd0NNNXXXK000Oc.                          
                                                                    .dOkdo:.'loc,cOXNNNXOc. .,;:coxkKNNk,     .cxOKK0Od;;;;,;;,;d0Kd,.  .  .co;:do;,'''.       .:c;....  .;:,..      .':;.  .,c:...;oxkxl:kNN0k0XKo.,l,...  .::,,',;clll::lc'..         .;loxo;oK0ddKNNNXXXK000x:.                          
                                                                    ,kkdodc.'lxd:;d0XNNNNO, .'ccclox0NWW0c....,dxOXK0l,:ddc::;l0Xk;.  ..'. .';;::.            ..'..';:'. ........    .,,...,cc,.  ,oxkxc:kNWKdOXXN0:.,:,.   'l;.:x0XNNNX0kkxolc,.      .'codxo:dK0dxKNNNNXXK000x,.                          
                                                                    ,okOxc.,okkkd:dXNNXXNNd. .;'...;kNWWW0llc.,c:lool''k0c::',okl.  ..'....       ....'',''...',,'''...... .''''.   .....,cl;.   ,dk0Ol'lXWXxxXWWWW0;.',.    .;lkKNNX0kkxdoodxOOd;.    .;lodxockX0xxXNWWNXK0000x;..                         
                                                                    'okOd',x00OOkldXKd:;:co,  ..  .,dXWMMXdc,..;,,,,,',xKo;'',.. .',',;'''     ...,;coddxddxxkkxkOkkkkkkxxxxdolc:,... .,coc.    .lkOOx:;OWNxo0WWWWWWk' .... .,lkKKOdccc;',;:lOKK0k;    .:lodkockX0dkXNWWNNXK00Odclo,                        
                                                                   .:0kxx;,xKK0KKxlxd..,' .;. .::;cd0NWWWKc.  .;;,::lxocoxdc,....:l:;:;,,.    ..';;:lodddddkOOKXXXNNNNXXXXXXNX0xdl;..'co:.  .'..cxOOd:,dNW0okNWWWMWW0:..   .;dkKXOc:xKKo:dkc'l0K0Od.   .:ddkOdckX0dkNNWWWNXKOkkocxKk:.                      
                                                                   .lkdll:'cxl:lk0dox;.....c: .oO0XNNNNNN0:    .;:lxk0KOxooolcoxkxlcc:,'.      .',;:clllloxkxk0KKXNNNXXXXXXXXKkc;...,:;.   .,..:xkOx;.cKWKxxKWWWWWWNKl...  .o00NXd:kWWKldNXOc'dKK0O:   .cxxkko:ON0dONWWWWWXKOkkl:x0KO:.                     
                                                                   .':lll,':'. .;OOokOdcclxx,.cOXXXXXXXK0kc..   .:dO00XNNNXXXWWNXOddo:'.        .......',;;:::cloddxkOOOOOOxo;....,:;.    .;. ,xkOkc.,ONXxdKNWWWWWNXXk;... 'd0XWNo;OWNxl0WXKd'l000k:.  .cxxkkl;kXOdONNNNWNXKOkkl;okO0k:.                    
                                                                    .'....,dc...;OX0xxkkOkdc:oOXNNNXKK0Od:,:;.   .,ok0XWWWWWWWWNX0kdc'   ...   ..  ....... .................  .';c:'.     .. .cdxk:.'dKXkd0NWWWWWNNXK0o..'..c0KXXk;;k0coXNKx;,ldxxl'  ..cddkOl;kNOdONNNWNXXKOkxc.,ldOOd,                    
                                                                     ''.,ccoxdodOKXXK0Okxl::cdO0XNNN0Okd:.... ..,...':ok0XWWWWNX0d:..   .',. .,,....;;,. .;::.....   .,..;,  ,lc,....          .''. 'oOxokXNWWWWWNNXKOkc... .cdxkOxl:,'cxxoldkxxdl,.   .lddkkc,kXkdOXNWWWXKK0Ox:.'::c:.                     
                                                                     .:lccoxocdOO0OO00KKd.. .;kOO0KXXKx;';:::llc:,......';cllc:,..      ..   .,,'...':c:..:l:';:'..,.,l,.;:':l:.  .'.                .',ckKNNWWWNNXK0OK0o'    .:oxOK0xdkO0KXNX0x:..  ..'lddkk:,xXkokXNNNNKKK0Ox:..'....                     
                                                                     .:dllxOOl:ooooxxxO0d,...cxdlcoxxo;.:l,.,ooc;,'''.                .':;. .:ol'.   ..'.. .',c;..:o,.;'.'ldl'.   .'   .      ..         ..;cok0KXXKOOKK0l.     .,;lOKXNNXKK0x:.  .....'ldxOk:;kXkdOXWWNNNXKK0x;...  ...                    
                                                                      ..,;lx00xddo;:oddolc::cc;',,'..   ':;',,.. .......',,'''........';;;'..cc. ..'..      ';'. ..:c...,dxc.     ,;.        ,c,.   ....,..   ..';:loxO0k;          .;:ccc:,.... .,cc..'coxkx:;kXkdOXWNNNNXXKOd,.     ....                  
                                                                           .l0d:lOo..,clloddl;,,,;;'      ...  ..';cclodxkOOkkOO00OOkxdoc,. ... .;lol:,. . .... 'c:'...lxd;...   .lc.       ;xl.  .,'.,xOc:c,.      ..,:,...,:c;.       ....'cdd:..;;...:loxd::kKOxOKNNXXXKK0ko'  .';:;,...                 
                                                                            .:;;cl'  .oo;;ldllolc::'   .......';;;cllloxkO0KKKXXXXXXXNNX0o....'',:::coo:;;...    .,. 'x0x:':do'  .dd.     .lOd'  ,c;.,x0xcdOk;.        .':dkOKKO;.'.  .;:ldxdxO0o'..,. .,::cc'.o0Ox0XXXK0kxkxxo. .;odolol:'.                
                                                                                    ..,clld:...''..   .....',,;cclloodddxkkO0KKKKKKXXXX0x:...;::clodOKXKK0Okxdl;.   ,kOd;..'''.  .xx.    .dOd'  'c:.'dKOoxKKkc.     ...;lxOKXXXx,... .';;lxxo;,,.............  .,'',;:cc:;;::c;. 'clodlcldo:.               
                                                                                     ......               ..  .......''',,,;::::cclddllc'.   ..',:lokOOO00KKXXXKx' .xKO:.  .:c;. .xk:c, 'dd:.  .:c,.lK0odXNKkc.    .''';lxO0Oxl,... .,'',',........ ..'''..  .  ....              ,lcldddxkxc.              
                                                                                                                                  .;c;'.        ..........''',,,,. :KXd.   .:cc' .xO:c;,ol'',..;c,.c00ddKNX0d:.  ..  .'';cloodl,,,. 'c:'.  .';lxkxc....',,...,..:dd:'.          ....::cdkOOkxo,.            
                                                                                                                                   .';'   .... .,:,.   ..      .. .oNXc.     ... .oO; .;,. ...,c;.:O0xd0NXKko,. ..   ..,,:lx0KOc,'. 'c:'. .,:;cx0Oo,....''.';'..cdxlcl,.'.      .,..,ccldkOO00Oc.           
                                                                                                                                     .. ....'. .;c:,. .  .,.. .;l'.dNXc  .'...::..:xc. .     ':;.,x0xdOXXKOd;.      ..,;cloxKXkc;;.  ...'...,;,;::cldxc....,''.'okklcooll,      .,...:cllok0XKX0l.          
                                                                                                                                      ..,,..;,. .coo;.  .:c,.  'c;'dNXo. .:l'.,,. ,oc.   ...';;.,d0kokXXX0x:.       .';;:odxO0d',:.   .:xxc..',:lx0KXX0l...,,'.;k0Oooxdxx:.      ,:'.'cllloOXXXXKd'         
                                                                                                                                       .;o:....  .:oo;...lo;....,c':0NO:. ,c' .'. .cc.  .:c;:;.;x0OoxKXXKOl'         .,c:;lllc,..cc.  .cO0Oc.,::lOKXNXXO:..''..:k0OdxkxxOo.      .',..,looooOXXXXKx'        
                                                                                                                                        .,odl,.    .,;;.'okl... .;:'oKKk;  ..,;;. .;:.  ,l::c''d00ddKNXK0x;.      ..  .,,...',''.:o;.  'okko,.;::oOKK0kl,...''.cOKkdk000Od;.  ..   ....'ldddokKXXXKk;       
                                                                                                                                          ..;l:,'...  . .o0d.    .,''oOOl.  .'.... .,'. .,;c;.c0Kxo0XX0OOo' .... ';.       .';;'.'oc.  .';lxxo;;c:coo:'.  ..,;.cOKkdOKK0Od;.  ....  ..'..:odooxKXXXXO;      
                                                                                                                                            ..........  .lOd. ..   . .:dd;.     ....''. .'c;.:kKOdONXKOkx;. .;c';o,          .;;..;o'  .,:dOKKd,'....';:,..';;'l0KxxKNK0Ox;.    ....  ',..'lxdldKXXXXO:.    
                                                                                                                                             .'''....    ;kx,..'....  ..:o:.  .:;.  ... .;c'.oKOdOXNX0kxc.   ...od.           .,'.'oc. .;;ckKK0o;'.,ccokx:'.;:;o0OdkXXKOOx:.      ...  ';,..lkxoo0XXXX0c.   
                                                                                                                                              ..',;,,'''..:l;.     ...  .,ll'  ;o:. .. .,l;.:O0xkXXX0Oxl.      ,l,           ..';,.ld'  .,;lxkdc'...:lloxc',::,oKOd0NX000x;  .      ....'c;..ckxllkKXKXKl.  
                                                                                                                                                ..'',;;:'.'::'.   .,,.....'lc. .cdc.  .,cc,:k0xOXNXKOxc.      .lc.   .      .,:;;;.;dc. .',,'...'....:lcc;,:c;;xKkdKNXKK0x; ':.       ....;:'.;dkdlxKXXXKd' 
                                                                                                                                                 ...';:c:..;:,....,;,....  .,,. .cxc. ':;':k0xxXNNX0kl....    ':.   .,,.     .;;,'.,odc......,okOko'..,;;';:;':OKxxXNNXK0x,.,oc.          .;:,.,dkxod0XXXXx,
                                                                                                                                                   .',;:c;..;,...:c;....  ...,,. .c:..,,.:OKOx0NNX0ko'..''.   ',.    .:l,.    .,;'.,odo'  .',ckKKKKd.';::,;:..oK0xkNWNXK0d'.';;.   ..      .;c,.;xkxllkKXXKk
                                                                                                                                                    .,;;::'..'..;xo'  .  ':,..''  ...;:.,xKOxOXNX0ko, ..';;.  ..      .cdc.    .'..,dxl.  .;::okO0Oo;';:,';:.'xX0x0NNXXK0d' .      ..       .,:'.:dxxoox0KKK
                                                                                                                                                      .'::,.....ok:..   .clc;....  .,l;.o0OxOXNX0Ox;...'.',;.          .cxo'       'ldc.  .,;;;:cloddl;,,';;.'kXOkKWNXKKOo.         ...      .,c,.,okxdod0KK
                                                                                                                                                        .;c;'. ,kd'      ,olc:.... .c:'l0KkOXNX0kdc.  ..,;;,'.          .:kd.      ,od:.  ..',;ldOKKK0d;'',;.,kXOkKNNXXKOl.   ...    ..       .;l;.'okdoodkK
                                                                                                                                                         .'::;.:xl.       ':cl:.. .:c;c0KOOKNX0Okl. .    .,;;;,..        .:xl.     ;oo;   .,coxO0KXXXNKo'.;;';OXkkXNNXXKk:.   .,,. .  ...      .,c;.'lkdodox
                                                                                                                                                           .;:.;dc.  ...   ..,:, .:l;ckKOkKNNK0Oo'.....   ..',::;,..       ;d:.   .:oo,  .;ldxO0KKXXXXKx:',,.c0XkxXNNXXKx;    ..;codl. ...       .::.'okxxxo
                                                                                                                                                            .;',oc....,,,,'.  ...,c::x0kx0NNK0Od,..',;,'.   ...',;:::'.     ;l,   .:do,  .,cdxk0XKKKOxl;..,'.:0XxxXNXXXKx;  ..,:oOXXKd' .'..      .cc,'cxxxd
                                                                                                                                                             .,,c:''.  ..,:;.   .cccxKOoONNX00k:. .';;::;;.  .'...,cxkd;.    ,:'  .cxo;..,;,:dk00kl:'.....,,.:0XdxNNXXX0x,  .,:clxKXXKk,  ...      'oo,.cxxx
                                                                                                                                                             .',;c,',. ......  .clcd00dxXNN0OOl.   .';;;:ol. ':' .',;lO0x:.  .,:. .okd;..;cc;clc,..';ldd:',;':0KxkNNXXX0d.  .';clox0KKKx'  ..   ..  ,oo;';od
                                                                                                                                                              .,;:;''. .;,..  .:lcoO0xxKNXK0Od'   ....;clodc',,. .,:;,;okOxc. .,, .dkl'..',,......;loxxd;'::,l0KkkNNXXX0o.   .;;clodkOx:'      ...  .;odl,.c
                                                                                                                                                               .,,;,.. .::;,..;ollOKOx0NXK0Ox;.   ..'.':loodddl;.  .:l:,,cxOkc..  .oo'.      .::;;,:oxxo;'::,l0KOOXNXXKOl. .. .;;:c;,,..      .'...',.,ldo,'
                                                                                                                                                                ..''.. .;ll:':olcxK0xkXNK0Ok:...   .,;'';cloxkkko'  .;oo:.'oOOd'  ,c,.        ':::;;lll:'';:,l0KOOXNXX0kl.     ...  .,:;.     .'. .....'coc'
                                                                                                                                                                 ...'.  ,ld::doco00kkKXK0Oko.  ..  ..,;,',coddxkkx:.  ':;. .cO0d'.;,.          ':;;:cll:'';;'l0KOkXNXX0xc.         .cOKOo'   ...        .;lo
                                                                                                                                                                   .... .:c:oxllk0kxKNX0Okd,.   ..''..';;,':ldddxkx;.       .;k0o,'..          .';:okkkl',:,.o00OkXNXKOx:.  ...    .cx0K0d'.  .          .;l
                                                                                                                                                                    ...  .,cdl:x0xoONXK0kx;. ... ..''...,::;;cll:,..          ,kOl'.  .       ,cclclxkko;;c;.l00OkKNXK0kc.  .c;.   .:cdOkd:..''.          .;
                                                                                                                                                                         .,l:;d0klxXNK0Okc.  .':;,..    .'coc;''.              ,xOl. .;;.     .:lllclxxl;;c,.o00OOKNXK0kc.  .:c,....';:c:::cdxdc.          .
                                                                                                                                                                     ..  .:c;l0OoxXNK0OOo.  .,'':ll:'.    .,lo:,..              ,xkc..,cl'     .;cllclxl,;c,.o00kOKXK0Ox;.  .',:oo:.....:lox0KK0o.          
                                                                                                                                                                      ...,c::x0kkXXX0Okd,   .,;'.;ool:.     .;lc;.               :xo'  .'::.    .;cl:;;,,;c'.dKOkOKXX0Od;. .,:cd00x:. .;loodk0KK0o.         
                                                                                                                                                                      .lllc:oOOOXXK0Okk:.    .':;'''..   ..   .:lc.              .:c'.    ,lc'    ......'::''xKOkkKXXKOx, ..;lodk0Od,. ,clddxk0KK0d'.       
                                                                                                                                                                      .ldo;:xOOKXX0Okko....    'cl:.     .......':c,         ...  .;,.     .;ll:.     ..;lc',kKOxkKXXK0x, .'';lddxxo;..':clodxxO000k:.      
                                                                                                                                                                     .'cl;'lOOKXX0Okkd' .',.    'col:.  ......,'. ':,.       'c,  .,,.        .:l:'.   .;o:.;O0kxkKXXK0d'  .'';c:,......;ccloxddk00Kkc.     
                                                                                                                                                                     'cl;'lOO0XX0Okxo,    ..     .,lxd:.......'::. .;;.     .cc.  .','.          .,;,. .;c;.:O0OxkKXXKOd'    .....':loc,';::coxxdkO00Oo'.   
                                                                                                                                                                    .ld:.:kOOKKKOkxo,  ....        .:dxd:....',;lo,..',..  .:o,    .,'.             ....,::.;k0OxkKXK0Oo'       ':;cdkOd,.,:ccoxddxO00Od;.  
                                                                                                                                                                   .:dd,'dOOKK00kxd:.  .';;,'.       .:dkd;. .;::od;  ';.  'lo'    .,,.                ':lc.:O0OxkKXK0Oo'       ,l:,cxO0o..'::clddxkkO00x:. 
                                                                                                                                                                   ,dxl':xk0000Oxdc.     .,cll;.       .;dkd,..:l;cl. .,,..;l:.    .,'.                ,co:.cO0OxxKXK0kd;       .;cc:lxOOl...;ccodxxxkO00xc'
                                                                                                                                                                  .d0d:,lkkOkkkxdo,        .:oko.        .o0x, .;;,c:. .,..:l;     .,,.               .:oo:.:kOOxxKXK0Od;.       .:docokOOl..'loooxxxkkO0Oxl
</pre>
<figcaption>Machine Head - Derek Hobbs 1995</figcaption>
<p>I grew up in the San Jose Bay Area. As of writing this, our company just graduated from the YC Fall 2025 batch. I'm not new to hustle-culture. I'm only where I am right now out of grit and the effort I invested into the things I loved in high school and college. Recently however, as a founder, I've become more attuned to Twitter (X) and LinkedIn, keeping up with <em>the vibes</em>.</p>
<p>There's a massive amount of hustle-culture being pushed on my timeline.</p>
<ul>
<li>Performative posts from people showcasing themselves coding in the most absurd situations</li>
<li>If you don't do X you're not going to make it (where X is some out of touch work hour target)</li>
<li>Good morning posts &amp; various rage-bait engagement farming tactics</li>
<li>Ratio's and one-up's</li>
</ul>
<p>Every machine serves a purpose. People need <em>purpose</em>. The temptation to <em>become the machine</em> is higher than ever. The promise of the machine is alluring. If I can just keep chugging forward, I will end up somewhere that is not here. If I can turn myself into a mechanism that takes input and consistently works towards some goal, I will make it.</p>
<p>I believe in hard work, but I think hustle-culture and the <em>vision</em> being pushed on my timeline is a corrupted one. It's engineered for engagement, optimized by millions competing with one another with just one goal: to capture your attention.</p>
<p>You're not working hard enough. You need to wake up at 5am. You need to be the first to arrive and the last to leave.</p>
<p>This messaging works. Look at me. I feel the need to write a post about it. But it is completely wrong.</p>
<p>Hustle-culture optimizes for work input because it's <em>sexy</em>. It's easy to post the inputs. It's hard to face the output.</p>
<p>The truth is you don't have to become the machine in order to succeed. The machine can't adapt. It can't learn the rules of the game. It is deterministic, set in place, chugging along at a linear pace.</p>
<p>Instead, aim to be nimble. Adapt quick. Define your goal but don't let it become your purpose. Your purpose is sacred; only you truly understand it. Do what you need to do in order to achieve your goals. Don't optimize for sweat. Try to find the most rewarding solution. Optimize for what matters: speed, efficiency, or quality—whatever it may be.</p>
<p>You're not a machine. You're a person. Play to your strengths. Be sharp and strategic like a scalpel, not blunt like a mallet. Stop fetishizing the grind. Dream bigger.</p>
<p><strong>You aren't a stupid blunt tool. Stop acting like one.</strong></p>
<p>[<a href="https://armeet.bearblog.dev/blog">More Posts</a>] [<a href="https://armeet.bearblog.dev/web-mri-volume-renderer-in-rust" title="Web MRI Volume Renderer in Rust">Previous</a>] [<a href="https://armeet.bearblog.dev/the-faster-shell" title="The Faster Shell">Next</a>]</p>


    

    
        
            <p>
                
                
                    <a rel="nofollow" href="https://armeet.bearblog.dev/blog/?q=thoughts">#thoughts</a>
                
            </p>
        

        
            


        

        
            
        
    


  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Turn raw HTML into production-ready images for free (128 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://html2png.dev</link>
            <guid>46371743</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 02:18:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://html2png.dev">https://html2png.dev</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46371743">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="__nuxt"><main><!--[--><div><header data-v-50a0ea11=""></header><div data-v-f059a62b=""><div data-v-f059a62b="" id="playground"><h2 data-v-f059a62b=""> Convert HTML to PNG<span data-v-f059a62b="">.</span></h2><p data-v-f059a62b=""> The image generation API your LLM will love to use. Turn raw HTML into production-ready images for free. No sign up required. </p></div><main data-v-f059a62b=""></main></div><div id="api"><div><h2> Vibe-Ready <span>Endpoint.</span></h2><p>Post https://html2png.dev</p></div><div><p> Parameters</p><div><!--[--><div><p><label><code>html<span>*</span></code></label></p><p><span>str</span> Raw HTML string.</p></div><div><p><label><code>format<!----></code></label></p><p><span>str</span> png | jpeg | webp | pdf</p></div><div><p><label><code>deviceScaleFactor<!----></code></label></p><p><span>int</span> Retina scaling (1-4).</p></div><div><p><label><code>delay<!----></code></label></p><p><span>int</span> Wait time in ms.</p></div><div><p><label><code>zoom<!----></code></label></p><p><span>num</span> Viewport zoom (0.1-3.0).</p></div><div><p><label><code>omitBackground<!----></code></label></p><p><span>bool</span> Transparent background.</p></div><!--]--></div></div><div><p> Fields</p><div><div><p><code>url</code></p><p>Public path to your generated asset. Immutable.</p></div><div><p><code>filename</code></p><p>Unique identifier generated for the file.</p></div><div><p><code>success</code></p><p>Boolean status of the render operation.</p></div></div></div></div><div id="agent"><p><span></span><span>Beyond MCP</span></p><h2> Not everything <br><span>needs an MCP.</span></h2><p> Stop waiting for MCP server updates or proxy configurations. Your LLM agents are already capable of making HTTP requests. Give them the instructions, and let them render directly to the edge. </p><div><div><p><span>01</span></p><div><h4>Zero Setup</h4><p>No plugins, no servers, no local tunnels.</p></div></div><div><p><span>02</span></p><div><h4>Agent Native</h4><p>Works with Claude, GPT-5, and any tool-capable AI. </p></div></div></div></div></div><!--]--></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Autonomously navigating the real world: lessons from the PG&E outage (124 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://waymo.com/blog/2025/12/autonomously-navigating-the-real-world</link>
            <guid>46371730</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 02:16:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://waymo.com/blog/2025/12/autonomously-navigating-the-real-world">https://waymo.com/blog/2025/12/autonomously-navigating-the-real-world</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46371730">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article aria-labelledby="P0-0-title"><div data-slot="body"><p>At Waymo, our mission is to be the world’s most trusted driver. We know trust is built through consistent behavior over time—earned through every mile we drive and every interaction we have with the community. This past Saturday, as a widespread PG&amp;E outage cut power to nearly one-third of San Francisco, our service was put to the test. With power now restored, we want to share an account of our operations during the outage and how we are evolving to better serve the city.</p><p>The scale of the outage and the sheer number of disabled traffic lights were the primary contributors to city-wide gridlock. As signals went dark across major corridors, the resulting congestion required law enforcement to manually manage intersections. The situation was severe enough that the San Francisco Department of Emergency Management advised residents to stay home, underscoring the extraordinary nature of the weekend’s disruptions.</p><p>Navigating an event of this magnitude presented a unique challenge for autonomous technology. While the Waymo Driver is designed to handle dark traffic signals as four-way stops, it may occasionally request a confirmation check to ensure it makes the safest choice. While we successfully traversed more than 7,000 dark signals on Saturday, the outage created a concentrated spike in these requests. This created a backlog that, in some cases, led to response delays contributing to congestion on already-overwhelmed streets.</p><p>We established these confirmation protocols out of an abundance of caution during our early deployment, and we are now refining them to match our current scale. While this strategy was effective during smaller outages, we are now implementing fleet-wide updates that provide the Driver with specific power outage context, allowing it to navigate more decisively.</p><p>As the outage persisted and City officials urged residents to stay off the streets to prioritize first responders, we temporarily paused our service in the area. We directed our fleet to pull over and park appropriately so we could return vehicles to our depots in waves. This ensured we did not further add to the congestion or obstruct emergency vehicles during the peak of the recovery effort.</p><h4 id="the-path-forward"><b>The path forward</b></h4><p>We’ve always focused on developing the Waymo Driver for the world as it is, including when infrastructure fails. We are analyzing the event, and are already integrating the lessons from this weekend’s PG&amp;E outage. Here are some of the immediate steps we’re taking:</p><ul><li><p><b>Integrating more information about outages: </b>While our Driver already handles dark traffic signals as four-way stops, we are now rolling out fleet-wide updates that give our vehicles even more context about regional outages, allowing them to navigate these intersections more decisively.</p></li><li><p><b>Updating our emergency preparedness and response: </b>We will improve our emergency response protocols, incorporating lessons from this event. In San Francisco, we’ll continue to coordinate with Mayor Lurie’s team to identify areas of greater collaboration in our existing emergency preparedness plans.</p></li><li><p><b>Expanding our first responder engagement: </b>To date, we’ve trained more than 25,000 first responders in the U.S. and around the world on how to interact with Waymo. As we discover learnings from this and other widespread events, we’ll continue updating our first responder training.</p></li></ul><h4 id="undaunted-in-our-mis"><b>Undaunted in our mission to make our streets safer</b></h4><p>We live and work in San Francisco, and we are grateful to the city’s first responders for their tireless work, and to Mayor Lurie for his leadership.</p><p>Backed by 100M+ miles of fully autonomous driving experience and a <a href="https://waymo.com/safety/impact"><u>record</u></a> of improving road safety, we are undaunted by the opportunity to challenge the status quo of our roads, and we’re proud to continue serving San Franciscan residents and visitors.</p></div></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Nabokov's guide to foreigners learning Russian (201 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/haravayin_hogh/status/2003299405907247502</link>
            <guid>46371423</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 01:20:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/haravayin_hogh/status/2003299405907247502">https://twitter.com/haravayin_hogh/status/2003299405907247502</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46371423">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="ScriptLoadFailure"><form action="" method="GET"><div><p><span>Something went wrong, but don’t fret — let’s give it another shot.</span></p><p><img alt="⚠️" draggable="false" src="https://abs-0.twimg.com/emoji/v2/svg/26a0.svg"><span> Some privacy related extensions may cause issues on x.com. Please disable them and try again.</span></p></div></form></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Unifi Travel Router (424 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.ui.com/article/travel-in-style-unifi-style-unifi-travel-router</link>
            <guid>46371135</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:30:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.ui.com/article/travel-in-style-unifi-style-unifi-travel-router">https://blog.ui.com/article/travel-in-style-unifi-style-unifi-travel-router</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46371135">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><p><a href="https://blog.ui.com/"><svg viewBox="0 0 20 20" fill="currentColor" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="20px" height="20px" baseclassname="Icon-module_hidden__cSK0B" twotonedclassname="Icon-module_hidden__cSK0B" fillclassname="Icon-module_fill__1THcd" fillwithtwotoneclassname="Icon-module_twoTone__jXINr" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="0"><path d="M18 10a.5.5 0 0 1-.5.5H3.472l4.392 4.657a.5.5 0 0 1-.728.686l-4.849-5.142A.994.994 0 0 1 2 10c0-.264.102-.513.287-.701l4.849-5.142a.5.5 0 0 1 .728.686L3.472 9.5H17.5a.5.5 0 0 1 .5.5Z" fill="currentColor"></path><path d="M18 10a.747.747 0 0 1-.22.53.747.747 0 0 1-.53.22H4.296l3.748 3.986a.75.75 0 1 1-1.092 1.028l-4.598-4.89a1.252 1.252 0 0 1 0-1.748l4.598-4.89a.75.75 0 1 1 1.092 1.028L4.297 9.25H17.25A.75.75 0 0 1 18 10Z" fill="currentColor"></path></svg><span>Back</span></a></p><div><p>22 December 2025</p><div><h6>Tom Hildebrand</h6></div></div></div><div><article><p>Slip it into your pocket, power it on, and your UniFi network follows you wherever you land. No reconfiguring, no rethinking, just the same environment you trust, now mobile.</p>
</article></div><div><article><h2>Your Network, Instantly Recreated</h2>
<p>Wherever you arrive, your network identity comes with you. Location aware policies, routing rules, and WiFi broadcasts light up the moment the router connects, giving you continuity instead of compromise.</p>
<ul>
<li>Automatic geo based policy and Teleport activation</li>
<li>Instant routing and VPN enforcement</li>
<li>Bind to a UniFi site to automatically configure WiFi and Teleport.</li>
</ul>
</article></div><div><article><h2>Familiar Devices, Zero Friction</h2>
<p>Bring your UniFi gear and the tools you already rely on. The moment they power up, everything links together as if it never left home.</p>
<ul>
<li>Plug and play pairing with existing UniFi devices</li>
<li>Consistent LAN behavior across locations</li>
<li>No reconfiguration or manual adoption</li>
</ul>
</article></div><div><article><h2>Small Form, Serious Uplinks</h2>
<p>The Travel Router may be compact, but it is engineered for flexibility. Ethernet, WiFi, or 5G connections via USB can all serve as uplinks, while captive portal logins on hotel networks are handled quietly in the background.</p>
<ul>
<li>Multi uplink support including Ethernet, WiFi, and 5G from a tethered smartphone</li>
<li>Automatic handling of captive portal authentication</li>
<li>High performance routing in a pocket sized device</li>
<li>Multiple uplinks, one unified control plane.</li>
</ul>
</article></div><div><article><p>Travel light, stay connected, and keep your UniFi experience no matter where you are.</p>
</article></div><div><h2>Latest Articles</h2></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Texas app store age verification law blocked by federal judge (302 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.macrumors.com/2025/12/23/texas-app-store-law-blocked/</link>
            <guid>46370012</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 22:03:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/12/23/texas-app-store-law-blocked/">https://www.macrumors.com/2025/12/23/texas-app-store-law-blocked/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46370012">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div role="main" id="maincontent"><article expanded="true"><div data-io-article-url="/2025/12/23/texas-app-store-law-blocked/"><p>A Texas federal judge today blocked an <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/guide/app-store/">App Store</a> age verification law that was set to go into effect on January 1, 2026, which means Apple may not have to support the changes after all.</p>
<p><img src="https://images.macrumors.com/t/T5SjvgLdchGm5DEKzIfFVPQgFIQ=/400x0/article-new/2022/01/iOS-App-Store-General-Feature-Desaturated.jpg?lossy" srcset="https://images.macrumors.com/t/T5SjvgLdchGm5DEKzIfFVPQgFIQ=/400x0/article-new/2022/01/iOS-App-Store-General-Feature-Desaturated.jpg?lossy 400w,https://images.macrumors.com/t/I5bNngcUCU5yI3dtNQSAA25c9cc=/800x0/article-new/2022/01/iOS-App-Store-General-Feature-Desaturated.jpg?lossy 800w,https://images.macrumors.com/t/ZzAm2e6i99b7DKjxBK1W_GKqlHk=/1600x0/article-new/2022/01/iOS-App-Store-General-Feature-Desaturated.jpg 1600w,https://images.macrumors.com/t/DRrqn78jMuNaPRaARegn6ILe_N4=/2500x0/filters:no_upscale()/article-new/2022/01/iOS-App-Store-General-Feature-Desaturated.jpg 2500w" sizes="(max-width: 900px) 100vw, 697px" alt="iOS App Store General Feature Desaturated" width="2250" height="1266"><br>The Texas ‌App Store‌ Accountability Act (SB2420) requires Apple and other app marketplaces to confirm user age when a person creates an Apple Account. Apple Accounts for users under 18 would need to join a Family Sharing group, with new controls available for parents and restrictions for minors.</p>
<p>In a preliminary injunction that delays the implementation of the act, Judge Robert Pitman said that it violates the First Amendment and is "more likely than not unconstitutional."<br>
</p>
<blockquote><p>The Act is akin to a law that would require every bookstore to verify the age of every customer at the door and, for minors, require parental consent before the child or teen could enter and again when they try to purchase a book. As set out below, the Court finds a likelihood that, when considered on the merits, SB 2420 violates the First Amendment.</p></blockquote>
<p>The injunction was in response to a motion filed by the Computer and Communications Industry Association (CCIA), a group that includes Apple and Google. Today's decision is a win for Apple, as Apple has been fighting against age assurance requirements in Texas and other states. Apple says that the Texas law impacts user privacy.<br>
</p>
<blockquote><p>While we share the goal of strengthening kids' online safety, we are concerned that SB2420 impacts the privacy of users by requiring the collection of sensitive, personally identifiable information to download any app, even if a user simply wants to check the weather or sports scores.</p></blockquote>
<p>The court will move on to determining whether the law is facially invalid, which would mean that it is unconstitutional and will be entirely thrown out.</p>
<p><small>Note: Due to the political or social nature of the discussion regarding this topic, the discussion thread is located in our <a href="https://forums.macrumors.com/forums/political-news.218/">Political News</a> forum.  All forum members and site visitors are welcome to read and follow the thread, but posting is limited to forum members with at least 100 posts.</small></p>
</div></article><p><h2>Popular Stories</h2></p><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/12/22/where-is-the-new-apple-tv/">Where's the New Apple TV?</a></h3><p>Monday December 22, 2025 11:30 am PST by <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/author/juli-clover/" rel="author">Juli Clover</a></p><p>Apple hasn't updated the Apple TV 4K since 2022, and 2025 was supposed to be the year that we got a refresh. There were rumors suggesting Apple would release the new Apple TV before the end of 2025, but it looks like that's not going to happen now.
Subscribe to the MacRumors YouTube channel for more videos. 
Bloomberg's Mark Gurman said several times across 2024 and 2025 that Apple would...</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/12/20/top-stories-ios-26-3-beta/">Top Stories: iOS 26.3 Beta, Major Apple Leaks, and More</a></h3><p>You'd think things would be slowing down heading into the holidays, but this week saw a whirlwind of Apple leaks and rumors while Apple started its next cycle of betas following last week's release of iOS 26.2 and related updates.
This week also saw the release of a new Apple Music integration with ChatGPT, so read on below for all the details on this week's biggest stories!
Top Stories
i...</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/12/22/ios-26-3-dma-airpods-pairing/">iOS 26.3 Brings AirPods-Like Pairing to Third-Party Devices in EU Under DMA</a></h3><p>Monday December 22, 2025 3:20 pm PST by <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/author/juli-clover/" rel="author">Juli Clover</a></p><p>The European Commission today praised the interoperability changes that Apple is introducing in iOS 26.3, once again crediting the Digital Markets Act (DMA) with bringing "new opportunities" to European users and developers.
The Digital Markets Act requires Apple to provide third-party accessories with the same capabilities and access to device features that Apple's own products get. In iOS...</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/12/22/ios-26-2-adds-8-features-to-your-iphone/">iOS 26.2 Adds These 8 New Features to Your iPhone</a></h3><p>Monday December 22, 2025 8:47 am PST by <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/author/joe-rossignol/" rel="author">Joe Rossignol</a></p><p>Earlier this month, Apple released iOS 26.2, following more than a month of beta testing. It is a big update, with many new features and changes for iPhones. 
iOS 26.2 adds a Liquid Glass slider for the Lock Screen's clock, offline lyrics in Apple Music, and more. Below, we have highlighted a total of eight new features.
Liquid Glass Slider on Lock Screen
A new slider in the Lock...</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/12/23/iphone-18-pro-rumored-features-list/">iPhone 18 Pro Launching Next Year With These 12 New Features</a></h3><p>Tuesday December 23, 2025 8:36 am PST by <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/author/joe-rossignol/" rel="author">Joe Rossignol</a></p><p>While the iPhone 18 Pro and iPhone 18 Pro Max are not expected to launch for another nine months, there are already plenty of rumors about the devices.
Below, we have recapped 12 features rumored for the iPhone 18 Pro models.
The same overall design is expected, with 6.3-inch and 6.9-inch display sizes, and a "plateau" housing three rear cameras
Under-screen Face ID
Front camera in...</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/12/16/iphone-18-pro-features-report/">iPhone 18 Pro Features Leaked in New Report, Including Under-Screen Face ID</a></h3><p>Tuesday December 16, 2025 8:44 am PST by <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/author/joe-rossignol/" rel="author">Joe Rossignol</a></p><p>Next year's iPhone 18 Pro and iPhone 18 Pro Max will be equipped with under-screen Face ID, and the front camera will be moved to the top-left corner of the screen, according to a new report from The Information's Wayne Ma and Qianer Liu.
As a result of these changes, the report said the iPhone 18 Pro models will not have a pill-shaped Dynamic Island cutout at the top of the screen....</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/12/22/apple-clings-to-samsung-as-ram-prices-soar/">Apple Clings to Samsung as RAM Prices Soar</a></h3><p>Apple is significantly increasing its reliance on Samsung for iPhone memory as component prices surge, according to The Korea Economic Daily. 
Apple is said to be expanding the share of iPhone memory it sources from Samsung due to rapidly rising memory prices. The shift is expected to result in Samsung supplying roughly 60% to 70% of the low-power DRAM used in the iPhone 17, compared with a...</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/12/23/foldable-iphone-small-outer-display/">Why Apple's Foldable iPhone May Be Smaller Than Expected</a></h3><p>Tuesday December 23, 2025 5:21 am PST by <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/author/tim-hardwick/" rel="author">Tim Hardwick</a></p><p>Apple's first foldable iPhone, rumored for release next year, may turn out to be smaller than most people imagine, if a recent report is anything to go by. According to The Information, the outer display on the book-style device will measure just 5.3 inches – that's smaller than the 5.4-inch screen on the ‌iPhone‌ mini, a line Apple discontinued in 2022 due to poor sales. The report has led ...</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[X-ray: a Python library for finding bad redactions in PDF documents (636 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/freelawproject/x-ray</link>
            <guid>46369923</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 21:54:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/freelawproject/x-ray">https://github.com/freelawproject/x-ray</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46369923">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/freelawproject/x-ray/main/redacted.png"><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/freelawproject/x-ray/main/redacted.png" alt="Image of REDACTED STAMP"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">x-ray is a Python library for finding bad redactions in PDF documents.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Why?</h2><a id="user-content-why" aria-label="Permalink: Why?" href="#why"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">At Free Law Project, we collect millions of PDFs. An ongoing problem
is that people fail to properly redact things. Instead of doing it the right
way, they just draw a black rectangle or a black highlight on top of black
text and call it a day. Well, when that happens you just select the text under
the rectangle, and you can read it again. Not great.</p>
<p dir="auto">After witnessing this problem for years, we decided it would be good to figure
out how common it is, so, with some help, we built this simple tool. You give
the tool the path to a PDF. It tells you if it has worthless redactions in it.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What next?</h2><a id="user-content-what-next" aria-label="Permalink: What next?" href="#what-next"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Right now, <code>x-ray</code> works pretty well and we are using it to analyze documents
in our collections. It could be better though. Bad redactions take many forms.
See the issues tab for other examples we don't yet support. We'd love your
help solving some of tougher cases.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h2><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">With uv, do:</p>

<p dir="auto">With pip, that'd be:</p>

<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h2><a id="user-content-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Usage" href="#usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><code>uvx</code> lets you run this without even installing it. For example, here's an amicus brief we filed that doesn't have any bad redactions:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="uvx --from x-ray xray https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.ca3.125346/gov.uscourts.ca3.125346.45.0.pdf
{}"><pre><code>uvx --from x-ray xray https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.ca3.125346/gov.uscourts.ca3.125346.45.0.pdf
{}
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Once you <em>do</em> install x-ray, you can easily use it on the command line. Once installed, just:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="% xray path/to/your/file.pdf
{
  &quot;1&quot;: [
    {
      &quot;bbox&quot;: [
        58.550079345703125,
        72.19873046875,
        75.65007781982422,
        739.3987426757812
      ],
      &quot;text&quot;: &quot;The Ring travels by way of Cirith Ungol&quot;
    }
  ]
}"><pre>% xray path/to/your/file.pdf
{
  <span><span>"</span>1<span>"</span></span>: [
    {
      <span><span>"</span>bbox<span>"</span></span>: [
        58.550079345703125,
        72.19873046875,
        75.65007781982422,
        739.3987426757812
      ],
      <span><span>"</span>text<span>"</span></span>: <span><span>"</span>The Ring travels by way of Cirith Ungol<span>"</span></span>
    }
  ]
}</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Or if you have the file on a server somewhere, give it a URL. If it starts with <code>https://</code>, it will be interpreted as a PDF to download. Here's congressional testimony our directory made (it doesn't have any bad redactions):</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="% xray https://free.law/pdf/congressional-testimony-michael-lissner-free-law-project-hearing-on-ethics-and-transparency-2021-10-26.pdf
{}"><pre>% xray https://free.law/pdf/congressional-testimony-michael-lissner-free-law-project-hearing-on-ethics-and-transparency-2021-10-26.pdf
{}</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">A fun trick you can do is to make a file with one URL per line, call it <code>urls.txt</code>. Then you can run this to check each URL:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="xargs -n 1 xray  < urls.txt"><pre>xargs -n 1 xray  <span>&lt;</span> urls.txt</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">However you run <code>xray</code> on the command line, you'll get JSON as output. When you have that, you can use it with tools like <a href="https://stedolan.github.io/jq/" rel="nofollow"><code>jq</code></a>. The format is as follows:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>It's a dict.</li>
<li>The keys are page numbers.</li>
<li>Each page number maps to a list of dicts.</li>
<li>Each of those dicts maps to two keys.</li>
<li>The first key is <code>bbox</code>. This is a four-tuple that indicates the x,y positions of the upper left corner and then lower right corners of the bad redaction.</li>
<li>The second key is <code>text</code>. This is the text under the bad rectangle.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Simple enough.</p>
<p dir="auto">You can also use it as a Python module, if you prefer the long-form:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="% python -m xray some-file.pdf"><pre><code>% python -m xray some-file.pdf
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">But that's not as easy to remember.</p>
<p dir="auto">If you want a bit more, you can, of course, use <code>xray</code> in Python:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="from pprint import pprint
import xray
bad_redactions = xray.inspect(&quot;some/path/to/your/file.pdf&quot;)  # Pathlib works too
pprint(bad_redactions)
{1: [{'bbox': (58.550079345703125,
               72.19873046875,
               75.65007781982422,
               739.3987426757812),
      'text': 'Aragorn is the one true king.'}]}"><pre><span>from</span> <span>pprint</span> <span>import</span> <span>pprint</span>
<span>import</span> <span>xray</span>
<span>bad_redactions</span> <span>=</span> <span>xray</span>.<span>inspect</span>(<span>"some/path/to/your/file.pdf"</span>)  <span># Pathlib works too</span>
<span>pprint</span>(<span>bad_redactions</span>)
{<span>1</span>: [{<span>'bbox'</span>: (<span>58.550079345703125</span>,
               <span>72.19873046875</span>,
               <span>75.65007781982422</span>,
               <span>739.3987426757812</span>),
      <span>'text'</span>: <span>'Aragorn is the one true king.'</span>}]}</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">The output is the same as above, except it's a Python object, not a JSON object.</p>
<p dir="auto">If you already have the file contents as a <code>bytes</code> object, that'll work too:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="some_bytes = requests.get(&quot;https://lotr-secrets.com/some-doc.pdf&quot;).content
bad_redactions = xray.inspect(some_bytes)"><pre><span>some_bytes</span> <span>=</span> <span>requests</span>.<span>get</span>(<span>"https://lotr-secrets.com/some-doc.pdf"</span>).<span>content</span>
<span>bad_redactions</span> <span>=</span> <span>xray</span>.<span>inspect</span>(<span>some_bytes</span>)</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Note that because the <code>inspect</code> method uses the same signature no matter what,
the type of the object you give it is essential:</p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Input</th>
<th><code>xray</code>'s Assumption</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><code>str</code> or Pathlib <code>Path</code></td>
<td>local file</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>str</code> that starts with <code>https://</code></td>
<td>URL to download</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>bytes</code></td>
<td>PDF in memory</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto">This means that if you provide the filename on disk as a bytes object instead
of a <code>str</code>, it's not going to work. This will fail:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="xray.inspect(b&quot;some-file-path.pdf&quot;)"><pre><span>xray</span>.<span>inspect</span>(<span>b"some-file-path.pdf"</span>)</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">That's pretty much it. There are no configuration files or other variables to
learn. You give it a file name. If there is a bad redaction in it, you'll soon
find out.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How it works</h2><a id="user-content-how-it-works" aria-label="Permalink: How it works" href="#how-it-works"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Under the covers, <code>xray</code> uses the high-performant <a href="https://pymupdf.readthedocs.io/" rel="nofollow">PyMuPDF project</a> to parse PDFs. It has been a wonderful project to work with.</p>
<p dir="auto">You can read the source to see how it works, but the general idea is to:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto">Find rectangles in a PDF.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">Find letters in the same location</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">Render the rectangle as an image</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">Inspect the rectangle to see if it's all one color. If it is, then that's a
bad redaction. If not, then we assume you can see a mix of text and
drawings, indicating a redaction that's OK.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto">The PDF format is a big and complicated one, so it's difficult to do all this perfectly. We do our best, but there's always more to do to make it better. <a href="https://free.law/donate/" rel="nofollow">Donations</a> and sponsored work help.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributions</h2><a id="user-content-contributions" aria-label="Permalink: Contributions" href="#contributions"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Please see the issues list on Github for things we need, or start a conversation if you have questions. Before you do your first contribution, we'll need a signed contributor license agreement. See the template in the repo.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Deployment</h2><a id="user-content-deployment" aria-label="Permalink: Deployment" href="#deployment"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Releases happen automatically via Github Actions. To trigger an automated build:</p>
<ol start="0" dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto">Update CHANGES.md</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">Update the version in pyproject.toml</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">Tag the commit with something like "v0.0.0".</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto">If you wish to create a new version manually, the process is:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto">Update version info in <code>pyproject.toml</code></p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">Configure your Pypi credentials <a href="https://python-poetry.org/docs/repositories/#configuring-credentials" rel="nofollow">with Poetry</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">Build and publish the version:</p>
</li>
</ol>

<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This repository is available under the permissive BSD license, making it easy and safe to incorporate in your own libraries.</p>
<p dir="auto">Pull and feature requests welcome. Online editing in GitHub is possible (and easy!).</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I didn't realize my LG TV was spying on me until I turned off Live Plus (239 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.pocket-lint.com/lg-tv-turn-off-live-plus/</link>
            <guid>46369860</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 21:47:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.pocket-lint.com/lg-tv-turn-off-live-plus/">https://www.pocket-lint.com/lg-tv-turn-off-live-plus/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46369860">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

                            <div data-nosnippet="">
                                            <p><a href="https://www.pocket-lint.com/author/craig-donaldson/">
                                    <img src="https://static0.pocketlintimages.com/wordpress%2Fwp-content%2Fauthors%2F672d31c8b2b25-Craig%20Donaldson.jpg?fit=crop&amp;w=90&amp;h=90" alt="4" loading="lazy" decoding="async">
                                </a>
                                                    </p>
                                    </div>
                        
                                            
                                
                                    <p>Craig is a reporter for Pocket-lint based in Toronto. He earned a diploma in journalism from Seneca Polytechnic and holds a Media Foundations certificate from Humber College. Craig previously interned and wrote for <a href="https://mobilesyrup.com/author/craig-donaldson/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">MobileSyrup</a>, a Canadian tech publication. He enjoys reading and writing about consumer technology, especially phones, tablets, and PCs. </p>
                                        
            
        </div><div id="article-body" itemprop="articleBody"><p>When I first set up my     <span data-id="211105"><a href="https://www.pocket-lint.com/lg-smart-tvs-directv-app/" target="_blank">LG TV</a></span>, my main focus was ensuring the picture quality was perfect. To LG's credit, the TV automatically detected all of my devices -- my PC, PS5, Switch 2, and Fire TV Stick 4K Max -- and applied the best settings for each. The image looked immaculate right out of the box, so I didn't spend much time digging through the settings menu and instead jumped straight into movies and gaming.    </p>    <!-- No AdsNinja v10 Client! --><!-- No AdsNinja v10 Client! --><p>However, about a week later, while I was trying to     <span data-id="211175"><a href="https://www.pocket-lint.com/secret-lg-tv-setting/" target="_blank">disable ads on the home screen</a></span>, I stumbled across a setting I didn't even know existed and instantly knew I wanted to be disabled. It's called Live Plus.    </p>    <p>If you've never heard of Live Plus before, it's a feature on LG smart TVs that uses ACR (automatic content recognition) to analyze what's displayed on your screen (via <a href="https://themarkup.org/privacy/2023/12/12/your-smart-tv-knows-what-youre-watching" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">The Markup</a>). LG then uses that data to offer "personalized services," including content recommendations and advertisements.</p>    <p>Naturally, reading what the feature was on my TV was a bit of a shock. I wasn't thrilled to discover a setting enabled by default that essentially spies on my screen just for ads, but at the same time, I felt a wave of relief when I realized how easy it is to turn off. If you don't want your LG TV quietly snooping on what you watch and using it to serve you ads, here's how to turn Live Plus off.</p>    <!-- No AdsNinja v10 Client! --><h2 id="how-to-turn-off-live-plus-on-your-lg-tv">
                        How to turn off Live Plus on your LG TV
               </h2><h3 id="other-tv-brands-have-a-similar-setting">
            Other TV brands have a similar setting
    </h3>

                
    
    
    
                
    
                
        
                                                            
                                                                                                                        
                                        
    
    

    
    <div data-img-url="https://static0.pocketlintimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/12/lg-live-plus.jpg" data-modal-id="single-image-modal" data-modal-container-id="single-image-modal-container" data-img-caption="&quot;&quot;">
                                                                                            <picture><source media="(max-width: 480px)" data-srcset="https://static0.pocketlintimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/12/lg-live-plus.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=480&amp;dpr=2" srcset="https://static0.pocketlintimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/12/lg-live-plus.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=480&amp;dpr=2">
        <source media="(max-width: 767px)" data-srcset="https://static0.pocketlintimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/12/lg-live-plus.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=767&amp;dpr=2" srcset="https://static0.pocketlintimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/12/lg-live-plus.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=767&amp;dpr=2">
        <source media="(max-width: 1023px)" data-srcset="https://static0.pocketlintimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/12/lg-live-plus.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=943&amp;dpr=2" srcset="https://static0.pocketlintimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/12/lg-live-plus.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=943&amp;dpr=2">
        <img width="1500" height="844" loading="lazy" decoding="async" alt="LG TV Live Plus setting." data-img-url="https://static0.pocketlintimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/12/lg-live-plus.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=750&amp;dpr=2" src="https://static0.pocketlintimages.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/wm/2025/12/lg-live-plus.jpg?q=49&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=750&amp;dpr=2">
        </picture>
            
        </div>
<p>Thankfully, LG doesn't make disabling Live Plus too hard, though you do have to click through a few menus. If you want to turn it off, here's how:</p>    <p>1. Press the <strong>Settings</strong> button on your remote (the gear icon).</p>    <p>2. When the side menu pops up, select <strong>Settings</strong>.</p>    <p>3. Chose the <strong>General</strong> option.</p>    <p>4. Scroll down and select <strong>System</strong>.</p>    <p>5, Select <strong>Additional Settings</strong>.</p>    <p>6. <strong>Toggle Live Plus off</strong>.</p>    <p>In the Settings menu on its TVs, LG says, "By turning Live Plus on, you understand that the content displayed on your TV can be recognized, and that the viewing information may be used to provide you with an enhanced viewing experience and personalized services including content recommendations and advertisements."</p>    

                

                    
    
                                                            <p>Fortunately, once you've toggled Live Plus off, you no longer have to worry about your TV screen constantly being read to see what you're watching and to give you targeted ads. </p>    

<div id="custom_block_16" data-nosnippet="">

        
            <p>...to be clear, this isn't just an LG problem -- other smart TV brands do the same thing with similar ACR (automatic content recognition) settings.</p>
    
        
    </div><p>While it's frustrating that a setting like this exists in the first place, I was at least relieved by how easy it was to turn off. And to be clear, this isn't just an LG problem -- other smart TV brands do the same thing with similar ACR (automatic content recognition) settings.</p>    <p>On Samsung smart TVs, for example, you can disable targeted ads by going to Privacy Choices, selecting Terms and Conditions, and toggling off Viewing Information Services and Internet-Based Advertisement Services. On Roku TVs, ACR can be turned off by disabling Use info from TV inputs, which is tucked away in the settings menu under Smart TV Experience.</p>    <p>In other LG-related news, DirecTV recently     <span data-id="211105"><a href="https://www.pocket-lint.com/lg-smart-tvs-directv-app/" target="_blank">launched its live TV app</a></span> on the LG webOS app store, and LG recently made the controversial move to     <span data-id="211185"><a href="https://www.pocket-lint.com/lg-tv-delete-copilot/" target="_blank">automatically install Copilot</a></span> on all LG Smart TVs with its latest webOS update.    </p>    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>