<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 12:30:02 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The profitable startup (141 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://linear.app/now/the-profitable-startup</link>
            <guid>45778984</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 03:18:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://linear.app/now/the-profitable-startup">https://linear.app/now/the-profitable-startup</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45778984">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>For years, startups have been taught to prioritize growth over everything else. Profitability was seen as unambitious or even wrong – something to worry about when you hit scale. Why focus on profits when money and valuations were easy to come by?</p><p>But that thinking was always flawed.</p><p>Profitability isn't unambitious; it's controlling your own destiny. It means you don't have to rely on investors for survival. It means you can focus on your unaltered vision and mission. And it means you as a founder decide the pace of growth. And once you experience it, it's hard to imagine doing things any other way.</p><p><a href="https://paulgraham.com/ramenprofitable.html">Paul Graham famously wrote about "ramen profitability"</a> – the point where a founding team could survive without external funding. He argued this made startups more attractive to investors, showing they could get customers to pay, were serious about building valuable products, and were disciplined with expenses.</p><p>Graham wrote his essay in 2009. I’d argue that we now live in a world where it’s not just easier to get ramen profitable, but traditionally profitable – while also growing fast.</p><p>At Linear we didn't set out to be profitable but kind of stumbled into it. We believed that to win this market we really needed to build a superior tool. The best way we knew how to do that was to keep the team small and focused. And when we launched after a year in private beta, almost all of our 100 beta users converted to paid customers. To our surprise, we realized it wouldn't take that long to become profitable if we kept the costs in check. Twelve months after launch, we hit profitability, and we've stayed profitable ever since.</p><p>I don't know why hiring massive teams ever became the norm. In my own experience, small teams always delivered better quality, and faster. Maybe it's fear of missing out if you don't grow the team fast. Maybe it's investors whispering that your team is "understaffed compared to benchmarks." Being understaffed compared to benchmarks almost always should be a source of pride, not a problem. People should be surprised how small your team is, not how big it is.</p><p>What holds you back is rarely team size – it's the clarity of your focus, skill and ability to execute. Larger teams mean slower progress, more management overhead, more meetings, more opinions, and usually dilution of vision and standards. Yet growing the team has somehow become a symbol of success.</p><p>At Linear, we hired our first employee after six months and roughly doubled the team each year. With each hire, we make sure they truly elevate the team. We don't set out to hire ten engineers – we hire the next <em>great</em> engineer. This intentional approach has allowed us to maintain both quality and culture.</p><p>The most underrated thing about profitability is how much peace of mind it gives you. Once you're profitable, you stop worrying about survival and focus on what really matters: building something great. Building the way you want. Instead of optimizing for the next fundraising round, you optimize for value creation.</p><p>While profitability might not come quickly for every startup, I believe it's achievable sooner than most think. If you're creating a new market, or truly require massive scale like a social network, or significant upfront investment like a hardware company, it might take longer. But if you're in a category where there isn't hard upfront investment, and you get some level of product-market fit with customers willing to pay, you can probably be profitable. You can decide to become profitable. And usually, it's a decision about how much and how fast you hire.</p><p><strong>Measure What Matters</strong></p><p>Revenue per employee is one of the clearest ways to see you’re hiring appropriately. While some of the best public companies benchmark at $1-2M per employee, for startups it's not unreasonable to target the range of $500k-$1M per employee.</p><p><strong>Understand Your Risk Profile</strong></p><p>Are you building something highly speculative where you're not sure if there's a market for it, or are you building something that already has a market but with a different take on it? In the former case profitability takes longer, but in the latter it could happen right away. Most software today, especially in the B2B space, is about building a modern version of something existing.</p><p><strong>Hire Intentionally and Slower</strong></p><p>For most software startups, ten people before product-market fit should be your ceiling, not your target. After PMF, every hire should address a specific, pressing need – not just fill out an org chart. At Linear, our deliberately slow headcount growth forced us to be selective, which meant making better hires. It also protected our culture, since rapid hiring often dilutes the very things that made your startup special in the first place. When you hire less, you naturally hire better.</p><p><strong>Raise on Your Own Terms </strong></p><p>Being profitable doesn't mean you have to be anti-investors. It means you have that choice, and investors are quite interested in profitable companies that also grow fast. You can raise more, less, or nothing. You can wait for the right timing, the right partner, or fund. For most ambitious startups, it can still be a good idea to raise something even if you could get by bootstrapping. Investors can still be helpful, and the additional cash balance can help you to make larger investments, or acquisitions.</p><p>The point is that you can be and are allowed to be profitable as a startup. It's not a bad thing, it's not an oxymoron or as hard as people make it out to be. The secret is that a lot of successful companies actually were quite profitable early on, they just didn't talk about it. When you're profitable, you make decisions based on what's best for your customers and your product, not what's best for impressing investors.</p><p>I didn't set out to build a profitable startup. But once I got there, I realized I wouldn't want to build a company any other way.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Strange Attractors (557 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.shashanktomar.com/posts/strange-attractors</link>
            <guid>45777810</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 23:23:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/posts/strange-attractors">https://blog.shashanktomar.com/posts/strange-attractors</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45777810">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><header></header><section><article> <p>A few months back, while playing around with <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://threejs.org/">Three.js</a>, I came across something that completely derailed my plans. Strange attractors - fancy math that creates beautiful patterns. At first I thought I'd just render one and move on, but then soon I realized that this is too much fun. When complexity emerges from three simple equations, when you see something chaotic emerge into beautiful, it's hard not to waste some time. I've spent countless hours, maybe more than I'd care to admit, watching these patterns form. I realized there's something deeply satisfying about seeing order emerge from randomness. Let me show you what kept me hooked.</p>

<h2>The Basics: Dynamical Systems and Chaos Theory</h2>
<p>Dynamical Systems are a mathematical way to understand how things <strong>change over time</strong>. Imagine you have a system, which
could be anything from the movement of planets to the growth of a population. In this system, there are rules that
determine how it evolves from one moment to the next. These rules tell you what will happen next based on what is
happening now. Some examples are, a pendulum, the weather patterns, a flock of birds, the spread of a virus in a
population (we are all too familiar with this one), and stock market.</p>
<p>There are two primary things to understand about this system:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Phase Space</strong>: This is like a big collection of all the possible states the system can be in. Each state is like a
snapshot of the system at a specific time. This is also called the <strong>state space</strong> or the <strong>world state</strong>.</li>
<li><strong>Dynamics</strong>: These are the rules that takes one state of the system and moves it to the next state. It can be
represented as a function that transforms the system from now to later.</li>
</ul>
<div><p><img alt="Phase Space in Dynamical Systems" type="button" aria-haspopup="dialog" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="radix-_R_26qklubsnmiv3b_" data-state="closed" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 500px, 1000px" srcset="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fphase-space-figure.webp&amp;w=16&amp;q=75 16w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fphase-space-figure.webp&amp;w=32&amp;q=75 32w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fphase-space-figure.webp&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 48w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fphase-space-figure.webp&amp;w=64&amp;q=75 64w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fphase-space-figure.webp&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 96w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fphase-space-figure.webp&amp;w=128&amp;q=75 128w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fphase-space-figure.webp&amp;w=256&amp;q=75 256w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fphase-space-figure.webp&amp;w=384&amp;q=75 384w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fphase-space-figure.webp&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fphase-space-figure.webp&amp;w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fphase-space-figure.webp&amp;w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fphase-space-figure.webp&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fphase-space-figure.webp&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fphase-space-figure.webp&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fphase-space-figure.webp&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fphase-space-figure.webp&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fphase-space-figure.webp&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></p><p>Figure 1 - Phase Space in Dynamical Systems</p></div>
<p>For instance, when studying population growth, a phase-space (world-state) might consist of the current population size
and the rate of growth or decline at a specific time. The dynamics would then be derived from models of population
dynamics, which, considering factors like birth rates, death rates, and carrying capacity of the environment, dictate
the changes in population size over time.</p>
<p>Another way of saying this is that the dynamical systems describe how things change over time, in a space of
possibilities, governed by a set of rules. Numerous fields such as biology, physics, economics, and applied mathematics,
study systems like these, focusing on the specific rules that dictate their evolution. These rules are grounded in
relevant theories, such as Newtonian mechanics, fluid dynamics, and mathematics of economics, among others.</p>
<h3 id="chaos-theory">Chaos Theory</h3>
<p>There are different ways of classifying dynamical systems, and one of the most interesting is the classification into
chaotic and non-chaotic systems. The change over time in non-chaotic systems is more deterministic as compared to
chaotic systems which exhibit randomness and unpredictability.</p>
<p><strong>Chaos Theory</strong> is the sub branch of dynamical systems that studies chaotic systems and challenges the traditional
deterministic views of causality. Most of the natural systems we observe are chaotic in nature, like the weather, a drop
of ink dissolving in water, social and economic behaviours etc. In contrast, systems like the movement of planets,
pendulums, and simple harmonic oscillators are extremely predictable and non-chaotic.</p>
<p>Chaos Theory deals with systems that exhibit irregular and unpredictable behavior over time, even though they follow
deterministic rules. Having a set of rules that govern the system, and yet exhibit randomness and unpredictability,
might seem a bit contradictory, but it is because the rules do not always represent the whole system. In fact, most of
the time, these rules are an approximation of the system and that is what leads to the unpredictability. In complex
systems, we do not have enough information to come up with a perfect set of rules. And by using incomplete information
to make predictions, we introduce uncertainty, which amplifies over time, leading to the chaotic behaviour.</p>
<div><p><img alt="Unpredictability in Chaos Theory" type="button" aria-haspopup="dialog" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="radix-_R_2dqklubsnmiv3b_" data-state="closed" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 500px, 1000px" srcset="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fchaos-theory-figure.webp&amp;w=16&amp;q=75 16w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fchaos-theory-figure.webp&amp;w=32&amp;q=75 32w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fchaos-theory-figure.webp&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 48w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fchaos-theory-figure.webp&amp;w=64&amp;q=75 64w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fchaos-theory-figure.webp&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 96w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fchaos-theory-figure.webp&amp;w=128&amp;q=75 128w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fchaos-theory-figure.webp&amp;w=256&amp;q=75 256w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fchaos-theory-figure.webp&amp;w=384&amp;q=75 384w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fchaos-theory-figure.webp&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fchaos-theory-figure.webp&amp;w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fchaos-theory-figure.webp&amp;w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fchaos-theory-figure.webp&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fchaos-theory-figure.webp&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fchaos-theory-figure.webp&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fchaos-theory-figure.webp&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fchaos-theory-figure.webp&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fchaos-theory-figure.webp&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></p><p>Figure 2 - Unpredictability in Chaos Theory</p></div>
<p>Chaotic systems generally have many non-linear interacting components, which we partially understand (or can partially
observe) and which are very sensitive to small changes. A small change in the initial conditions can lead to a
completely different outcome, a phenomenon known as the <strong>butterfly effect</strong>. In this post, we will try to see the
butterfly effect in action but before that, let's talk about <strong>Strange Attractors</strong>.</p>
<h2>Strange Attractors</h2>
<p>To understand Strange Attractors, let's first understand what an attractor is. As discussed earlier, dynamical systems
are all about <strong>change over time</strong>. During this change, the system moves through different possible states (remember the
phase space jargon?). An attractor is a set of states towards which a system tends to settle over time, or you can say,
towards which it is <strong>attracted</strong>. It's like a magnet that pulls the system towards it.</p>
<p>For example, think of a pendulum. When you release it, it swings back and forth, but eventually, it comes to rest at the
bottom. The bottom is the attractor in this case. It's the state towards which the pendulum is attracted.</p>
<p>This happens due to the system's inherent dynamics, which govern how states in the phase space change. Here are some of
the reasons why different states get attracted towards attractors:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Stability</strong>: Attractors are stable states of the system, meaning that once the system reaches them, it tends to stay
there. This stability arises from the system's dynamics, which push it towards the attractor and keep it there.</li>
<li><strong>Dissipation</strong>: Many dynamical systems have dissipative forces, which cause the system to lose energy over time. This
loss of energy leads the system to settle into a lower-energy state, which often corresponds to an attractor. This is
what happens in the case of the pendulum.</li>
<li><strong>Contraction</strong>: In some regions of the phase space, the system's dynamics cause trajectories to converge. This
contraction effect means that nearby states will tend to come closer together over time, eventually being drawn
towards the attractor.</li>
</ul>
<div><p><img alt="Attractor state in a simple pendulum" type="button" aria-haspopup="dialog" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="radix-_R_2kqklubsnmiv3b_" data-state="closed" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 500px, 1000px" srcset="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fattractors-figure.webp&amp;w=16&amp;q=75 16w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fattractors-figure.webp&amp;w=32&amp;q=75 32w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fattractors-figure.webp&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 48w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fattractors-figure.webp&amp;w=64&amp;q=75 64w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fattractors-figure.webp&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 96w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fattractors-figure.webp&amp;w=128&amp;q=75 128w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fattractors-figure.webp&amp;w=256&amp;q=75 256w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fattractors-figure.webp&amp;w=384&amp;q=75 384w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fattractors-figure.webp&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fattractors-figure.webp&amp;w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fattractors-figure.webp&amp;w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fattractors-figure.webp&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fattractors-figure.webp&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fattractors-figure.webp&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fattractors-figure.webp&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fattractors-figure.webp&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fattractors-figure.webp&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></p><p>Figure 3 - Attractor state in a simple pendulum</p></div>
<p>Some attractors have complex governing equations that can create unpredictable trajectories or behaviours. These
nonlinear interactions can result in multiple stable states or periodic orbits, towards which the system evolves. These
complex attractors are categorised as <strong>strange attractors</strong>. They are called "strange" due to their unique
characteristics.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Fractal Structure</strong>: Strange attractors often have a fractal-like structure, meaning they display intricate
patterns that repeat at different scales. This complexity sets them apart from simpler, regular attractors.</li>
<li><strong>Sensitive Dependence on Initial Conditions</strong>: Systems with strange attractors are highly sensitive to their initial
conditions. Small changes in the starting point can lead to vastly different long-term behaviors, a phenomenon known
as the "butterfly effect".</li>
<li><strong>Unpredictable Trajectories</strong>: The trajectories on a strange attractor never repeat themselves, exhibiting
non-periodic motion. The system's behavior appears random and unpredictable, even though it is governed by
deterministic rules.</li>
<li><strong>Emergent Order from Chaos</strong>: Despite their chaotic nature, strange attractors exhibit a form of underlying order.
Patterns and structures emerge from the seemingly random behavior, revealing the complex dynamics at play.</li>
</ol>
<p>You can observe most of these characteristics in the visualisation. The one which is most fascinating to observe is the
butterfly effect.</p>
<h3 id="the-butterfly-effect">The Butterfly Effect</h3>
<blockquote><p>A butterfly can flutter its wings over a flower in China and cause a hurricane in the Caribbean.</p></blockquote>
<p>One of the defining features of strange attractors is their sensitivity to initial conditions. This means that small
changes in the starting state of the system can lead to vastly different long-term behaviors, a phenomenon known as the
<strong>butterfly effect</strong>. In chaotic systems, tiny variations in the initial conditions can amplify over time, leading to
drastically different outcomes.</p>
<div><p><img alt="A Simplification of The Bufferfly Effect" type="button" aria-haspopup="dialog" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="radix-_R_2rqklubsnmiv3b_" data-state="closed" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 500px, 1000px" srcset="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fbutterfly-effect-figure.webp&amp;w=16&amp;q=75 16w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fbutterfly-effect-figure.webp&amp;w=32&amp;q=75 32w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fbutterfly-effect-figure.webp&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 48w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fbutterfly-effect-figure.webp&amp;w=64&amp;q=75 64w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fbutterfly-effect-figure.webp&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 96w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fbutterfly-effect-figure.webp&amp;w=128&amp;q=75 128w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fbutterfly-effect-figure.webp&amp;w=256&amp;q=75 256w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fbutterfly-effect-figure.webp&amp;w=384&amp;q=75 384w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fbutterfly-effect-figure.webp&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fbutterfly-effect-figure.webp&amp;w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fbutterfly-effect-figure.webp&amp;w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fbutterfly-effect-figure.webp&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fbutterfly-effect-figure.webp&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fbutterfly-effect-figure.webp&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fbutterfly-effect-figure.webp&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fbutterfly-effect-figure.webp&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fbutterfly-effect-figure.webp&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></p><p>Figure 3 - A Simplification of The Bufferfly Effect</p></div>
<p>In our visualisation, let's observe this behavior on Thomas Attractor. It is governed by the following equations:</p>
<div><p><h3>Thomas Attractor Equation</h3></p></div>
<p>A small change in the parameter <code>a</code> can lead to vastly different particle trajectories and the overall shape of the
attractor. Change this value in the control panel and observe the butterfly effect in action.</p>
<div><div><p><img alt="Thomas Attractor at 0.19" type="button" aria-haspopup="dialog" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="radix-_R_ivqklubsnmiv3b_" data-state="closed" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 300px, 500px" srcset="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-dark.png&amp;w=16&amp;q=75 16w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-dark.png&amp;w=32&amp;q=75 32w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-dark.png&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 48w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-dark.png&amp;w=64&amp;q=75 64w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-dark.png&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 96w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-dark.png&amp;w=128&amp;q=75 128w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-dark.png&amp;w=256&amp;q=75 256w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-dark.png&amp;w=384&amp;q=75 384w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-dark.png&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-dark.png&amp;w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-dark.png&amp;w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-dark.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-dark.png&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-dark.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-dark.png&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-dark.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-dark.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"><img alt="Thomas Attractor at 0.19" type="button" aria-haspopup="dialog" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="radix-_R_ivqklubsnmiv3b_" data-state="closed" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 300px, 500px" srcset="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-light.png&amp;w=16&amp;q=75 16w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-light.png&amp;w=32&amp;q=75 32w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-light.png&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 48w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-light.png&amp;w=64&amp;q=75 64w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-light.png&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 96w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-light.png&amp;w=128&amp;q=75 128w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-light.png&amp;w=256&amp;q=75 256w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-light.png&amp;w=384&amp;q=75 384w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-light.png&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-light.png&amp;w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-light.png&amp;w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-light.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-light.png&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-light.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-light.png&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-light.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-19-light.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></p><p>a = 0.19</p></div><div><p><img alt="Thomas Attractor at 0.21" type="button" aria-haspopup="dialog" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="radix-_R_kvqklubsnmiv3b_" data-state="closed" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 300px, 500px" srcset="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-dark.png&amp;w=16&amp;q=75 16w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-dark.png&amp;w=32&amp;q=75 32w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-dark.png&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 48w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-dark.png&amp;w=64&amp;q=75 64w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-dark.png&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 96w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-dark.png&amp;w=128&amp;q=75 128w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-dark.png&amp;w=256&amp;q=75 256w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-dark.png&amp;w=384&amp;q=75 384w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-dark.png&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-dark.png&amp;w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-dark.png&amp;w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-dark.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-dark.png&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-dark.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-dark.png&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-dark.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-dark.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"><img alt="Thomas Attractor at 0.21" type="button" aria-haspopup="dialog" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="radix-_R_kvqklubsnmiv3b_" data-state="closed" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 300px, 500px" srcset="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-light.png&amp;w=16&amp;q=75 16w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-light.png&amp;w=32&amp;q=75 32w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-light.png&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 48w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-light.png&amp;w=64&amp;q=75 64w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-light.png&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 96w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-light.png&amp;w=128&amp;q=75 128w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-light.png&amp;w=256&amp;q=75 256w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-light.png&amp;w=384&amp;q=75 384w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-light.png&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-light.png&amp;w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-light.png&amp;w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-light.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-light.png&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-light.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-light.png&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-light.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-21-light.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></p><p>a = 0.21</p></div><div><p><img alt="Thomas Attractor at 0.13" type="button" aria-haspopup="dialog" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="radix-_R_mvqklubsnmiv3b_" data-state="closed" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 300px, 500px" srcset="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-dark.png&amp;w=16&amp;q=75 16w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-dark.png&amp;w=32&amp;q=75 32w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-dark.png&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 48w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-dark.png&amp;w=64&amp;q=75 64w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-dark.png&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 96w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-dark.png&amp;w=128&amp;q=75 128w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-dark.png&amp;w=256&amp;q=75 256w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-dark.png&amp;w=384&amp;q=75 384w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-dark.png&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-dark.png&amp;w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-dark.png&amp;w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-dark.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-dark.png&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-dark.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-dark.png&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-dark.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-dark.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"><img alt="Thomas Attractor at 0.13" type="button" aria-haspopup="dialog" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="radix-_R_mvqklubsnmiv3b_" data-state="closed" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 300px, 500px" srcset="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-light.png&amp;w=16&amp;q=75 16w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-light.png&amp;w=32&amp;q=75 32w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-light.png&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 48w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-light.png&amp;w=64&amp;q=75 64w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-light.png&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 96w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-light.png&amp;w=128&amp;q=75 128w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-light.png&amp;w=256&amp;q=75 256w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-light.png&amp;w=384&amp;q=75 384w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-light.png&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-light.png&amp;w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-light.png&amp;w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-light.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-light.png&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-light.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-light.png&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-light.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-13-light.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></p><p>a = 0.13</p></div><div><p><img alt="Thomas Attractor at 0.10" type="button" aria-haspopup="dialog" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="radix-_R_ovqklubsnmiv3b_" data-state="closed" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 300px, 500px" srcset="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-dark.png&amp;w=16&amp;q=75 16w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-dark.png&amp;w=32&amp;q=75 32w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-dark.png&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 48w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-dark.png&amp;w=64&amp;q=75 64w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-dark.png&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 96w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-dark.png&amp;w=128&amp;q=75 128w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-dark.png&amp;w=256&amp;q=75 256w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-dark.png&amp;w=384&amp;q=75 384w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-dark.png&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-dark.png&amp;w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-dark.png&amp;w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-dark.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-dark.png&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-dark.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-dark.png&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-dark.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-dark.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"><img alt="Thomas Attractor at 0.10" type="button" aria-haspopup="dialog" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="radix-_R_ovqklubsnmiv3b_" data-state="closed" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 300px, 500px" srcset="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-light.png&amp;w=16&amp;q=75 16w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-light.png&amp;w=32&amp;q=75 32w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-light.png&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 48w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-light.png&amp;w=64&amp;q=75 64w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-light.png&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 96w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-light.png&amp;w=128&amp;q=75 128w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-light.png&amp;w=256&amp;q=75 256w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-light.png&amp;w=384&amp;q=75 384w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-light.png&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-light.png&amp;w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-light.png&amp;w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-light.png&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-light.png&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-light.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-light.png&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-light.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://blog.shashanktomar.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fattractors%2Fthomas-attractor-10-light.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></p><p>a = 0.10</p></div></div>
<p>There is another way of observing the butterfly effect in this visualisation. Change the <code>Initial State</code> from <code>cube</code> to
<code>sphere surface</code> in the control panel and observe how the particles move differently in the two cases. The particles
eventually get attracted to the same states but have different trajectories.</p>

<h2>Implementation Details</h2>
<p>This visualization required rendering a large number of particles using Three.js. To achieve this efficiently, we used a
technique called <strong>ping-pong rendering</strong> <sup><a href="#user-content-fn-2" id="user-content-fnref-2" aria-describedby="footnote-label">2</a></sup>. This method handles iterative updates of particle systems directly on the GPU,
minimizing data transfers between the CPU and GPU. It utilizes two frame buffer objects (FBOs) that alternate roles: One
stores the current state of particles and render them on the screen, while the other calculates the next state.</p>
<h3 id="implementation-workflow">Implementation Workflow</h3>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>Setting Up Frame Buffer Objects (FBOs):</strong> We start by creating two FBOs, <code>ping</code> and <code>pong</code>, to hold the current and
next state of particles. These buffers store data such as particle positions in RGBA channels, making efficient use
of GPU resources.</p>

</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Shader Programs for Particle Dynamics:</strong> The shader programs execute on the GPU and apply attractor dynamics to
each particle. Following is the attractor function which update the particle positions based on the attractor equation.</p>

</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Rendering and Buffer Swapping:</strong> In each frame, the shader computes the new positions based on the attractor's
equations and stores them in the inactive buffer. After updating, the roles of the FBOs are swapped: The previously
inactive buffer becomes active, and vice versa.</p>

</li>
</ol>
<p>This combination of efficient shader calculations and the ping-pong technique allows us to render the particle system.</p>

<p><strong>If you have any comments, please leave them on <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://github.com/shashanktomar/blog-discussion/discussions/1">this GitHub discussions topic</a>. Sooner or later, I will integrate it with the blog.</strong></p>

<section><h4>Footnotes</h4><ol><li id="user-content-fn-1"><p><a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2011/02/22/196987/when-the-butterfly-effect-took-flight/">When the Butterfly Effect Took
Flight</a></p><a href="#user-content-fnref-1"> <!-- -->[↩]</a></li><li id="user-content-fn-2"><p><a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://webglfundamentals.org/webgl/lessons/webgl-image-processing-continued.html">WebGLFundamentals: Ping Pong Rendering</a></p><a href="#user-content-fnref-2"> <!-- -->[↩]</a></li></ol><h4 id="references">References</h4><ul>
<li><a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://r3f.maximeheckel.com/attractor">Inspired by the work of Maxim</a></li>
<li><a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Attractor">Wikipedia: Attractor</a></li>
<li><a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_chaotic_maps">Wikipedia: List Of Chaotic Maps</a></li>
<li><a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="http://math.huji.ac.il/~mhochman/research-expo.html">Dynamical Systems Theory: What in the World is it?</a></li>
</ul><ul>
<li><a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://fusefactory.github.io/openfuse/strange%20attractors/particle%20system/Strange-Attractors-GPU/">https://fusefactory.github.io/openfuse/strange%20attractors/particle%20system/Strange-Attractors-GPU/</a></li>
<li><a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://chaoticatmospheres.com/mathrules-strange-attractors">https://chaoticatmospheres.com/mathrules-strange-attractors</a></li>
<li><a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://www.dynamicmath.xyz/strange-attractors/">https://www.dynamicmath.xyz/strange-attractors/</a></li>
<li><a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/math/comments/z0dmms/visualization_of_3d_strange_attractors">https://www.reddit.com/r/math/comments/z0dmms/visualization_of_3d_strange_attractors</a></li>
<li><a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://www.clicktorelease.com/code/codevember-2016/3">https://www.clicktorelease.com/code/codevember-2016/3</a></li>
<li><a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://discourse.mcneel.com/t/strange-attractors/120053">https://discourse.mcneel.com/t/strange-attractors/120053</a></li>
<li><a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/generative/comments/191fkkv/genuary_day_8_chaotic_system/">https://www.reddit.com/r/generative/comments/191fkkv/genuary_day_8_chaotic_system/</a></li>
</ul></section> </article></section></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[S.A.R.C.A.S.M: Slightly Annoying Rubik's Cube Automatic Solving Machine (181 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/vindar/SARCASM</link>
            <guid>45777682</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 23:03:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/vindar/SARCASM">https://github.com/vindar/SARCASM</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45777682">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">S.A.R.C.A.S.M</h2><a id="user-content-sarcasm" aria-label="Permalink: S.A.R.C.A.S.M" href="#sarcasm"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Slightly Annoying Rubik's Cube Automatic Solving Machine</strong></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/vindar/SARCASM/blob/main/sarcasm.jpg"><img src="https://github.com/vindar/SARCASM/raw/main/sarcasm.jpg" alt="S.A.R.C.A.S.M"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><em>S.A.R.C.A.S.M</em> is a 3D-printed, Teensy-powered robot that scans, solves, and sassily comments on a Rubik’s Cube.</p>
<p dir="auto">This repository contains the code and schematics of the build.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Demo videos</h2><a id="user-content-demo-videos" aria-label="Permalink: Demo videos" href="#demo-videos"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Short clip: <a href="https://youtube.com/shorts/Xer4mPZZH8E" rel="nofollow">https://youtube.com/shorts/Xer4mPZZH8E</a></li>
<li>Full demo: <a href="https://youtu.be/WV52RtuWXk0" rel="nofollow">https://youtu.be/WV52RtuWXk0</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Highlights</h2><a id="user-content-highlights" aria-label="Permalink: Highlights" href="#highlights"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Teensy 4.1 main controller + ESP32-CAM for image capture.</li>
<li>ILI9341 display with custom 2D&amp;3D graphics, animations, and lip-sync.</li>
<li>Stepper + servos for cube handling with position sensors to detect faults.</li>
<li>RGBW lighting synchronized to audio.</li>
<li>On-device TTS (espeak-ng) with a collection of sarcastic lines.</li>
<li>...</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Note</h2><a id="user-content-note" aria-label="Permalink: Note" href="#note"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">A slight modification of Teensy's core is required in order for the whole code to fit in RAM.</p>
<p dir="auto">Edit <code>cores/teensy4/usb_serial.c</code> and <code>cores/teensy4/usb_serial2.c</code> and, in each file, remove the DMAMEM attribute in front of the definition of the <code>txbuffer[]</code> and <code>rx_buffer[]</code> arrays.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Warning</h2><a id="user-content-warning" aria-label="Permalink: Warning" href="#warning"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This is a work in progress. The repo is currently in a very messy and incomplete state (and will most likely stay that way until I find some time to work on it...). Sorry !</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tim Bray on Grokipedia (160 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/202x/2025/10/28/Grokipedia</link>
            <guid>45777015</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 21:41:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/202x/2025/10/28/Grokipedia">https://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/202x/2025/10/28/Grokipedia</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45777015">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="centercontent">
<p itemprop="description">Last night I had a very strange experience: About two thirds of the way through reading a Web page about myself, Tim Bray, I
    succumbed to boredom and killed the tab. Thus my introduction to
    <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grokipedia">Grokipedia</a>. Here are early impressions.</p>

<p id="p-1"><span>On Bray</span> · 
My Grokipedia entry has over seven thousand words, compared to a mere 1,300 in
    <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim_Bray">my Wikipedia article</a>. It’s pretty clear how it was generated; an LLM, trained
    on who-knows-what but definitely including that Wikipedia article and this blog, was told to go nuts.</p>

<p>Speaking as a leading but highly biased expert on the subject of T. Bray, here are the key take-aways:</p>

<p id="p-2"><span>(Overly) complete</span> · 
It covers all the territory; there is no phase of my life’s activity that could possibly be encountered in combing the Web
    that is not exhaustively covered. In theory this should be good but in fact, who cares about the details of what I worked on
    at Sun Microsystems between 2004 and 2010? I suppose I should but, like I said, I couldn’t force myself to plod all the way
    through it.</p>

<p id="p-3"><span>Wrong</span> · 
Every paragraph contains significant errors. Sometimes the text is explicitly self-contradictory on the face of it,
    sometimes the mistakes are subtle enough that only I would spot them.</p>

<p id="p-4"><span>Style</span> · 
The writing has that LLM view-from-nowhere flat-affect semi-academic flavor. I don’t like it but the evidence suggests that
    some people do?</p>

<p id="p-5"><span>References</span> · 
All the references are just URLs and at least some of them entirely fail to support the text. Here’s an example. In
    discussion of my expert-witness work for the FTC in their litigation against Meta concerning its acquisitions of Instagram and
    WhatsApp, Grokipedia says:</p>

<blockquote><p>[Bray] opined that users' perceptions of response times in online services critically influence market
    dynamics.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It cites
    <a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/FTCReplytoMetaResponse-CounterstatementofMaterialFacts.pdf">Federal
    Trade Commission’s Reply to Meta Platforms, Inc.’s Response to Federal Trade Commission’s Counterstatement of Material
    Facts</a> (warning: 2,857-page PDF). Okay, that was one of the things I argued, but the 425 pages of court documents that I
    filed, and the references to my reporting in the monster document, make it clear that it was one tiny subset of the main
    argument.</p>

<p>Anyhow, I (so that you won’t have to) spent a solid fifteen minutes spelunking back and forth through that FTC doc, looking
    for strings like “response time” and “latency” and so on. Maybe somewhere in those pages there’s support for the claim quoted
    above, but I couldn’t find it.</p>

<p id="p-6"><span>Useful?</span> · 
Wikipedia, in my mind, has two main purposes: A quick visit to find out the basics about some city or person or plant or
    whatever, or a deep-dive to find out what we <em>really</em> know about genetic linkages to autism or Bach’s relationship with
    Frederick the Great or whatever.</p>

<p>At the moment, Grokipedia doesn’t really serve either purpose very well. But, after all, this is release 0.1, maybe we
    should give it a chance.</p>

<p>Or, maybe not.</p>

<p id="p-7"><span>Woke/Anti-Woke</span> · 
The whole point, one gathers, is to provide an antidote to Wikipedia’s alleged woke bias. So I dug into that. Let’s consider
    three examples of what I found.  First, from that same paragraph about the FTC opinion quoted above:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>While Bray and aligned progressives contend that such dominance stifles innovation by enabling predatory acquisitions and
      reduced rivalry—evidenced by fewer startup exits in concentrated sectors—counterarguments highlight that Big Tech's scale has
      fueled empirical gains, with these firms investing over $240 billion in U.S. R&amp;D in 2024 (more than a quarter of national
      totals) and driving AI, cloud, and patent surges.[<a href="https://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/202x/2020/06/08/Anti-monopoly">128</a>]
      [<a href="https://www.intereconomics.eu/contents/year/2025/number/2/article/big-tech-and-the-us-digital-military-industrial-complex.html">131</a>] Six tech industries alone accounted for
      over one-third of 
      U.S. GDP growth from 2012–2021, comprising about 9% of the 
      economy and sustaining 9.3 million jobs amid falling consumer prices and rapid technological diffusion.
      [<a href="https://itif.org/publications/2023/05/30/six-tech-industries-accounted-for-more-than-one-third-of-gdp-growth-in-the-last-decade/">132]</a> 
      [<a href="https://jamesmadison.org/the-united-states-is-the-leader-of-the-digital-revolution-pro-tech-policies-are-key/">133</a>]
      Right-leaning economists often defend consumer welfare metrics and market self-correction, warning that forced divestitures
      risk eroding the efficiencies and investment incentives that have propelled sector productivity above 6% annual growth in key
      areas like durable manufacturing tech.
      [<a href="https://itif.org/publications/2025/09/19/five-persistent-myths-about-big-tech/">134</a>]
      [<a href="https://www.nber.org/digest/oct01/technology-and-productivity-growth?page=1&amp;perPage=50">135</a>]</p>

</blockquote>
<p>I’ve linked the numbered citations to the indicated URLs. Maybe visit one or two of them and see what you think? Four are
    to articles arguing, basically, that monopolies must be OK because the companies accused of it are growing really fast and
    driving the economy. They seem mostly to be from right-wing think-tanks but I guess that’s what those think-tanks are for.  One
    of them, #131, <cite>Big Tech and the US Digital-Military-Industrial Complex</cite>, I think isn’t helpful to the argument at
    all. But still, it’s broadly doing what they advertise: Pushing back against “woke” positions, in this case the position that
    monopolization is bad.</p>

<p>I looked at a couple of other examples.  For example, this is from the header of the Greta Thunberg article:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>While credited with elevating youth engagement on environmental issues, Thunberg's promotion of urgent, existential climate
      threats has drawn scrutiny for diverging from nuanced empirical assessments of climate risks and adaptation capacities, as
      well as for extending her activism into broader political arenas such as anti-capitalist and geopolitical protests.[5][6]</p>

</blockquote>
<p>Somehow I feel no urge to click on those citation links.</p>

<p>If Ms Thunberg is out there on the “woke” end of the spectrum, let’s flit over to the other end, namely the entry for
    J.D. Vance, on the subject of his book <cite>Hillbilly Elegy</cite>.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Critics from progressive outlets, including Sarah Smarsh in her 2018 book <cite>Heartland</cite>, faulted the memoir for
      overemphasizing personal and cultural failings at the expense of structural economic policies, arguing it perpetuated
      stereotypes of rural whites as self-sabotaging.[71] These objections, often rooted in institutional analyses from academia and
      media, overlooked data on behavioral patterns like opioid dependency rates—peaking at 21.5 deaths per 100,000 in Appalachia
      around 2016—that aligned with Vance's observations of "deaths of despair" precursors.[72]</p>

</blockquote>
<p>I read and enjoyed <cite>Heartland</cite> but the citation is to a <cite>New Yorker</cite> article that doesn’t mention
    Smarsh. As for the second sentence… my first reaction as I trudged through its many clauses, was “life’s too short”.
    But seriously, opioid-death statistics weaken the hypothesis about structural economic issues? Don’t get it.</p>

<p id="p-8"><span>Take-away</span> · 
Wikipedia is,
    <a href="https://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/202x/2024/06/15/Wikipedia-Pain">to quote myself</a>, the encyclopedia that “anyone who’s willing to
    provide citations can edit”.
    Grokipedia is “the encyclopedia that Elon Musk’s LLM can edit, with sketchy citations and no progressive argument left
    un-attacked.”</p>

<p>So I guess it’s Working As Intended?</p>

<hr>


</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A theoretical way to circumvent Android developer verification (146 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://enaix.github.io/2025/10/30/developer-verification.html</link>
            <guid>45776269</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 20:20:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://enaix.github.io/2025/10/30/developer-verification.html">https://enaix.github.io/2025/10/30/developer-verification.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45776269">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      

<p><img src="https://enaix.github.io/assets/img/android-skull.jpg" alt="android skull"></p>

<p>As you all know, Google has introduced developer verification as a way to prevent users from installing “unregistered” APKs. This measure was taken as a security feature to link every APK in existence to its developer, as in Play Store.</p>

<p><a href="https://developer.android.com/developer-verification">Link to the Android documentation</a>, <a href="https://developer.android.com/developer-verification/guides/faq">link to FAQ</a></p>

<h2 id="why-this-is-bad">Why this is bad</h2>

<p>This has already been discussed by <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/10/google-confirms-android-dev-verification-will-have-free-and-paid-tiers-no-public-list-of-devs/">ArsTechnica</a> and on some threads (some cherry-picked ones): <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/Android/comments/1nwddik/heres_how_androids_new_app_verification_rules/">reddit</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45017028">ycombinator</a>, <a href="https://hackaday.com/2025/08/26/google-will-require-developer-verification-even-for-sideloading/">hackaday</a>.</p>

<p>A quick recap of the main points (as of 30 Oct 2025):</p>

<ul>
  <li>The base tier costs $25, as in Play Market. Requires an ID</li>
  <li>There will be a limited “hobbyist” unpaid license. Google claims that they won’t require an ID</li>
  <li>Legal info is told to be private, unlike with Play Market</li>
  <li>The verification code is supposed to be located in Play Services, <strong>but Google hasn’t published the source code yet</strong></li>
  <li>Google assures that it would be possible to install applications locally using ADB, <strong>but there are no details on this</strong></li>
  <li>Hobbyist license restrictions are unknown</li>
</ul>

<p>A few months prior Google has decided to <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/03/google-makes-android-development-private-will-continue-open-source-releases/">make Android development private</a>, which seems to be a preparation for the upcoming changes (<a href="https://www.androidauthority.com/google-not-killing-aosp-3566882/">another article</a>). Due to this change in AOSP release format, it is no longer possible to track what exactly Google is doing.</p>

<p>My answer to this question is that it would simply prevent small developers from distributing their apps, including myself. If we take the legal route, a hobbyist license is supposed to have some limit on the number of installs by design. If we take, say, 10K installs, this is not enough in my case. Another question is how exactly the process of verification is going to happen, what if Google adopts the same rules as in Play Store? Taking my <a href="https://github.com/enaix/Kirikiroid2-debloated">fork of the old VN engine port</a>, this apk would not pass security checks, as the old codebase relies on legacy external storage permissions, which are banned in Play Store. If we take the adb route, there are <strong>no guarantees that this method is going to work in the future in the form you expect</strong>. For instance, Google mentions that this method is meant for on-device tests during development, and nothing prevents them from reporting the install to their servers and checking if a self-signed apk has been installed on other devices. Another way to put it, this is problematic for an average Android user to perform these steps, and this is going to be the developer’s problem.</p>

<p>The situation links pretty well with Samsung <a href="https://www.sammobile.com/news/say-goodbye-to-your-custom-roms-as-one-ui-8-kills-bootloader-unlock/">removing bootloader unlocking with the One UI 8 update</a>. Great, duh…</p>

<h2 id="the-concept">The concept</h2>

<p><img src="https://enaix.github.io/assets/img/loader1.svg" alt="apk loader"></p>

<p>My vision of the hack is to distribute a verified loader apk, which in turn dynamically loads any apk the user wants. A user obtains the loader apk once and loads apps without installing as much as they want.</p>

<p>The Java virtual machine in Android is the ART/Dalvik runtime (I will refer to it as Dalvik, it seems that Google hates cool names). Did you know that Dalvik natively <a href="https://developer.android.com/reference/dalvik/system/PathClassLoader">allows dynamic code execution using PathClassLoader</a>? So an apk may just load some zip/apk/dex code from external storage and execute it in current context. Essentially, this means that we can natively load the apk into memory and execute any code inside of the target apk, and we are not altering the original code signature of the loader.</p>

<p>In order to actually run the apk, the loader needs to properly initialize the main activity (aka the main screen, or the entrypoint) of the target apk. So, the main activity needs to be initialized and somehow placed inside of the Android’s activity cycle with the loader acting as a wrapper. Then, the loader apk should handle other aspects like local files handling and names conflict resolution. This can be achieved by patching the target apk bytecode: .odex/.dex classes may be dynamically decompiled into .smali, analyzed and compiled back into a modified apk. Furthermore, the loader would have to parse AndroidManifest options of the target (main activity location, screen options).</p>

<h3 id="implementation">Implementation</h3>

<p>Developing such wrapper in a straightforward way has proven to be rather difficult, as Android <a href="https://android.googlesource.com/platform/frameworks/base/+/master/core/java/android/app/Activity.java">activity management logic</a> is extremely complicated and differs from version to version. In short, it was problematic to perform the initialization process the right way. Some people suggested to avoid the initialization step completely, and use Unsafe Dalvik api to register the target’s activity as the loader apk activity stub, which is declared in the loader’s manifest without class. I couldn’t find exact methods in the <a href="https://developer.android.com/reference/sun/misc/Unsafe">Unsafe documentation</a>, but this actually may be a way to go.</p>

<p>Due to this particular issue I couldn’t bring the proof of concept to a working state in a reasonable time, and because of this I was considering to not publish this article at all. The purpose of this post is not to give a somewhat ready solution, but get some feedback on the concept, as I was not ready to devote lots of time on a potentially broken solution.</p>

<h2 id="the-logistics">The logistics</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Information provided in this section is for educational use only, all scenarios discussed below are hypothetical.</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p>In order to install the loader apk on the device, it would require, well, some form of verification. Hobbyist license is the only choice here, as paying $25 for each attempt is not optimal. Since the hobbyist license has a limited number of installs, there should be multiple instances of the apk with separate licences. In this hypothetical scenario there may either be a pool of volunteers who sign the code, or completely random users who are willing to help. In the second case, the loader code would somehow need to be verified or scanned, since such distribution system would be vulnerable to malware.</p>

<p>The final and the most important issue in this process is the verification process itself, as the loader code may (and likely will) be flagged by Google. So, the code would require some form of obfuscation like code flow modification and implementing double functionality (for instance, registering it as a file manager). If Google decides to ban dynamic code loading altogether, the final solution would be to pack the Dalvik runtime into the loader as a native library. This of course would have extremely low performance, but it should be technically possible.</p>

<p>Overall, the hypothetical plan has lots of assumptions, with which I’m not happy with. First of all, it requires lots of manual work by the volunteers or random people, and this work also includes the apk obfuscation, which was not discussed in detail. Then, the verification process itself should be somewhat permissive to allow potentially suspicious apps (I would like to hear how does this happen with current Play Store verification).</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>The project described in this article by no means is a finished solution, and if you have started to think what else could work, it means that the article has reached its original goal. I believe that we would eventually come up with a proper solution in the future. Thank you for reading!</p>

<p>You may find the source code <a href="https://github.com/enaix/apk-loader">here</a>. Feel free to create an issue if you wish to discuss</p>

    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to build silos and decrease collaboration on purpose (135 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.rubick.com/how-to-build-silos-and-decrease-collaboration/</link>
            <guid>45775642</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 19:16:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.rubick.com/how-to-build-silos-and-decrease-collaboration/">https://www.rubick.com/how-to-build-silos-and-decrease-collaboration/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45775642">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><em>“We need to break down silos between departments and get people to collaborate better” — almost every leader everywhere.</em></p>
<div><a href="https://www.rubick.com/static/49e7b817bacc5b4e752102948a7061a0/d8eca/silo.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><p><img src="https://www.rubick.com/static/49e7b817bacc5b4e752102948a7061a0/5fd6b/silo.jpg" srcset="https://www.rubick.com/static/49e7b817bacc5b4e752102948a7061a0/16d62/silo.jpg 200w,
https://www.rubick.com/static/49e7b817bacc5b4e752102948a7061a0/27ec1/silo.jpg 400w,
https://www.rubick.com/static/49e7b817bacc5b4e752102948a7061a0/5fd6b/silo.jpg 800w,
https://www.rubick.com/static/49e7b817bacc5b4e752102948a7061a0/5a523/silo.jpg 1200w,
https://www.rubick.com/static/49e7b817bacc5b4e752102948a7061a0/b46c2/silo.jpg 1600w,
https://www.rubick.com/static/49e7b817bacc5b4e752102948a7061a0/d8eca/silo.jpg 1874w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" alt=""></p></a></div>
<p>Most leaders reflexively think of silos as BAD and collaboration as GOOD. This manifesto defends silos and challenges the value of collaboration.</p>
<h2>Increasing collaboration can do harm</h2>
<p>In general, you should aim to maximize collaboration <em>within</em> teams, and minimize collaboration <em>between</em> teams.</p>
<h3>Why maximize collaboration within teams?</h3>
<p>A collaborative team works together on one or two goals. Why?</p>
<ul>
<li>This maximizes <a href="https://www.rubick.com/communication-is-shared-state/">shared state</a> — everyone has a common understanding of goals, progress, and who is doing what.</li>
<li>This gives team members a better ability to focus and coordinate their work with each other.</li>
<li>Team members have overlapping areas of knowledge, so they can critique each other’s work and help each other grow.</li>
<li>They are more innovative, because the interplay between people as they work on the same goal helps generate more diverse thinking and improve decision-making.</li>
<li>When someone leaves the team, the fact that others have a shared understanding of the work means the team can survive and continue to work effectively.</li>
<li>People can go on vacation or leave without as much disruption.</li>
</ul>
<p>Collaborative teams feel great to be a part of — everyone shares the same victories and accomplishments together. A team that doesn’t collaborate often really isn’t a team at all.</p>
<h3>Why minimize collaboration between teams?</h3>
<p>To the maximum extent possible, teams should have what they need to succeed within the borders of their team. And where that is not true, you need some structure to ensure the team can get what it needs in a way that will scale with the organization’s growth.</p>
<p>As companies grow, communication and dependencies proliferate. Companies start out with many-to-many communication. As they grow, the communication patterns within the company must necessarily switch to being segmented and defined. Otherwise, the communication burden on teams will grow at an exponential rate, and the increasing complexity will degrade the effectiveness of the company.</p>
<p>I observed an example of this at New Relic:</p>
<ol>
<li>As the engineering organization grew, we encouraged a collaborative culture and rewarded people for collaboration between teams (it was even part of our promotion criteria — you can blame that on me!).</li>
<li>After a few years, the increasing number of teams made it more and more difficult to manage dependencies between teams, to the point that it eventually became impossible to accomplish any large project within the organization. I know, because I was one of the “best project managers”, so I got put on many of those large projects — and they were systematically impossible to execute on. We all tried heroically to make it work, but the system was rigged — there wasn’t a way to accomplish these larger projects.</li>
<li>The solution to this was to eventually define the interaction models between teams, reduce dependencies, and add some <a href="https://www.rubick.com/product-council/?utm_source=ck-silos&amp;utm_medium=link&amp;utm_campaign=silos">structure to prioritization</a> and communication.</li>
</ol>
<p>Looking back in retrospect, it was as obvious as math what happened, but I see organizations fall into this trap over and over. We’ll talk more about how to structure these solutions in the second blog post in this series.</p>
<p>Collaboration <em>sounds</em> great, but it’s something you want to actively be combating between teams. A little collaboration is fine, but excessive collaboration between teams is a sign your organization isn’t structured well. If you ever wonder why Bezos took such a hard line on his <a href="https://chrislaing.net/blog/the-memo/#fn:1">API mandate</a> in 2002, this probably factored into it. Bezos structured Amazon so that teams were as independent as possible.</p>
<h2>What are silos?</h2>
<p>Silos are boundaries between groups of people, based on the organizational structure and teams they’re working on.</p>
<h2>Why do silos exist?</h2>
<p>Silos exist because humans have cognitive and communication limits:</p>
<ul>
<li>Humans can only handle a certain number of relationships</li>
<li>Humans have a limit to how much communication they can handle.</li>
<li>Humans are pre-wired to think in terms of teams and tribes. We work better in small groups.</li>
<li>Humans have cognitive limits on the amount they can focus on.</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s important to recognize that these limits are real limits, and not something you can wish away. Every company in the world (above a certain size) operates in teams that specialize. We organize into teams and have org structures generally because that is what human beings need to work in larger groups.</p>
<p>There are ways to flex certain aspects of this. For example, a company that is designed to be fully asynchronous can rely on process and tooling to change some of these constraints. But even then, you’re moving the constraints around, not eliminating them completely. You need to operate in a way that recognizes these limits.</p>
<h2>Why do leaders want to break down silos?</h2>
<p>Leaders start talking about breaking down silos when they see that individual parts of the company aren’t achieving larger business outcomes and are excessively focused on their own area. Alternatively, they talk about breaking down silos when parts of the company aren’t well coordinated with each other. Generally this happens once the organization has become complex enough that the structure is getting in the way.</p>
<p>Here are a couple of examples:</p>
<ul>
<li>Marketing is planning a major announcement of an upcoming launch, but can’t get a timing commitment from the product and engineering teams.</li>
<li>Two teams in engineering are building the same service, but in slightly different ways.</li>
</ul>
<p>Leaders see these things, and start blathering about “breaking down silos” and “increasing collaboration”. What’s wrong with that?</p>
<h2>“Breaking down silos” represents incomplete thinking</h2>
<p><strong>“Breaking down silos” is an exhortation rather than a diagnosis or prescription of how to improve the situation</strong>. “Breaking down silos” blames individuals for not having a big enough vision and working across boundaries, instead of looking with curiosity at the system and asking <em>why</em> they are doing what they’re doing. It’s expecting people to have your level of perspective without figuring out why they don’t.</p>
<p>But the main problem is that it isn’t specific enough.</p>
<h2>Communication != Collaboration != Coordination</h2>
<p>When you hear someone say they want teams to collaborate more or break down silos, encourage them to look at the problem from three perspectives:</p>
<h3>Coordination</h3>
<p>Usually when people talk about collaboration, what they’re really looking for is better coordination.</p>
<p>Coordination is “the harmonious functioning of parts for effective results” (<a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/coordination">Merriam-Webster</a>)</p>
<p>The US military found that the best way to coordinate groups of people quickly and effectively was to <a href="https://www.marines.mil/News/Publications/MCPEL/Electronic-Library-Display/Article/899837/mcdp-1/">centralize coordination and decentralize decision-making and execution</a>. This is still the state of the art for organizational design. You want local groups to be able to act independently and have what they need to be successful. You want centralized functions to set high level objectives and coordinate where necessary to produce the right outcomes.</p>
<p>We’ll talk in the second post in this series about a multitude of ways you can coordinate groups of people working together.</p>
<h3>Communication</h3>
<p>Communication is transferring information from one person or group to another.</p>
<p>When people talk about needing increased collaboration, you can often achieve this more effectively by looking at the flow of information between people, and redesigning it. Typically, you can do something like this:</p>
<ol>
<li>Ask people how they are getting information today.</li>
<li>Find out what information people actually need.</li>
<li>Design the lightest weight version of this you can imagine.</li>
<li>Try it out</li>
<li>Get feedback and act on that feedback.</li>
</ol>
<p>One thing I’ve done over and over in many startups is set up weekly communication on projects in engineering. This helps the marketing organization understand how to coordinate their work with engineering, among other benefits.</p>
<h3>Collaboration</h3>
<p>Collaboration is when people work together to produce an outcome. When teams are collaborating, it means they’re working with other teams to achieve outcomes together. That’s often a sign the team isn’t set up well. Ideally, it should have what it needs to do what it needs without dependencies on other teams.</p>
<p>A team that has to collaborate to achieve its objectives is going to be less reliably successful. In general, teams shouldn’t be collaborating with more than a couple of teams, unless they’re explicitly set up to be that way. For example, in some organizations you might set up the design team as a “service” organization which provides design for a larger organization. For teams that are set up that way, it can be fine, but it usually should be very carefully thought through. What is the interaction model for the team, and how will it deal with the inevitable fact that there will be excess demands on it? We’ll cover some of these patterns and their tradeoffs in the second post in this series.</p>
<p>Of course, the world is messy, and you shouldn’t expect a complete lack of collaboration between teams. But when you see teams collaborate, that’s something to pay attention to.</p>
<h2>Technical analogy</h2>
<p>You might think of silos as “encapsulation”. Leaders want to dig into the internals of the classes holding the logic they need. But it’s a bad solution to just bolt that on — you really need to refactor things so that they are better structured.</p>
<h2>How do you get teams to coordinate better?</h2>
<p>In the next post in this series, I share concrete <a href="https://www.rubick.com/coordination-models/">patterns that help teams and departments work across organizational boundaries</a>.</p>
<h2>What do you think?</h2>
<p>I always appreciate hearing your thoughts and reactions to my posts.</p>
<h2>Thank you</h2>
<p>Thank you to the many people who helped improve this post. <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/rebecca--campbell/">Rebecca Campbell</a> always makes my work better. She helped me tighten up many of my arguments and helped me realize that I needed to make the section on coordination more explicit. <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/foliosus/">Brent Miller</a>, always the purveyer of astute observations, offered structural feedback that made the post much stronger. <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/chaupt/">Chris Haupt</a>, always thoughtful, pointed out a few areas that he didn’t find convincing, and helped me see that I needed to go deeper on information flow. <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/aaronerickson/">Aaron Erickson</a> suggested the metaphor of encapsulation. Thanks to Neville Kuyt for suggesting I define silo. And additional thank you to <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/robert-difalco-a40378/">Robert DiFalco</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/darinswanson/">Darin Swanson</a> for reviewing and commenting on the post. Always appreciate your insight!</p>
<p>Image by <a href="https://pixabay.com/users/1778011-1778011/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=4015505">1778011</a> from <a href="https://pixabay.com/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=4015505">Pixabay</a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Addiction Markets (299 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.thebignewsletter.com/p/addiction-markets-abolish-corporate</link>
            <guid>45774640</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 17:42:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.thebignewsletter.com/p/addiction-markets-abolish-corporate">https://www.thebignewsletter.com/p/addiction-markets-abolish-corporate</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45774640">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><p><span>Earlier this year, Maryland state Senator Joanne C. Benson did something remarkable. She introduced Senate </span><a href="https://mgaleg.maryland.gov/2025RS/bills/sb/sb1033f.pdf" rel="">bill 1033</a><span>, written for the “purpose of repealing online sports wagering” in the state. Now, I wouldn’t normally say a random state legislator introducing a proposal is a big deal. Except in this case, it’s the start of a counter-attack on the proliferation of corporate-run gambling across America, a trend that has largely gone un-rebutted since the 1970s. And Benson is not alone; lawmakers in </span><a href="https://www.covers.com/industry/vermont-lawmakers-introduce-bill-to-repeal-online-sports-betting-feb-15-2025#:~:text=was%20quite%20enough.-,Vermont%20Representatives%20Thomas%20Stevens%20(D)%2C%20Troy%20Headrick%20(I,Government%20Operations%20and%20Military%20Affairs." rel="">Vermont</a><span> and </span><a href="https://nystateofpolitics.com/state-of-politics/new-york/politics/2025/10/29/lawmakers-sports-betting-regulations" rel="">New York</a><span> are seeking to push back, and more state legislatures are likely to follow.</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!67A2!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F933fab7a-ba50-45ae-a78b-7d07f253da54_1210x372.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!67A2!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F933fab7a-ba50-45ae-a78b-7d07f253da54_1210x372.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!67A2!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F933fab7a-ba50-45ae-a78b-7d07f253da54_1210x372.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!67A2!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F933fab7a-ba50-45ae-a78b-7d07f253da54_1210x372.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!67A2!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F933fab7a-ba50-45ae-a78b-7d07f253da54_1210x372.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!67A2!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F933fab7a-ba50-45ae-a78b-7d07f253da54_1210x372.png" width="1210" height="372" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/933fab7a-ba50-45ae-a78b-7d07f253da54_1210x372.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:372,&quot;width&quot;:1210,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:133239,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.thebignewsletter.com/i/177563599?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F933fab7a-ba50-45ae-a78b-7d07f253da54_1210x372.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!67A2!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F933fab7a-ba50-45ae-a78b-7d07f253da54_1210x372.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!67A2!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F933fab7a-ba50-45ae-a78b-7d07f253da54_1210x372.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!67A2!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F933fab7a-ba50-45ae-a78b-7d07f253da54_1210x372.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!67A2!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F933fab7a-ba50-45ae-a78b-7d07f253da54_1210x372.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Gpib!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb3ae2e5e-e6ee-44c6-9faf-805eab47d3b6_881x468.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Gpib!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb3ae2e5e-e6ee-44c6-9faf-805eab47d3b6_881x468.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Gpib!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb3ae2e5e-e6ee-44c6-9faf-805eab47d3b6_881x468.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Gpib!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb3ae2e5e-e6ee-44c6-9faf-805eab47d3b6_881x468.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Gpib!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb3ae2e5e-e6ee-44c6-9faf-805eab47d3b6_881x468.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Gpib!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb3ae2e5e-e6ee-44c6-9faf-805eab47d3b6_881x468.png" width="881" height="468" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/b3ae2e5e-e6ee-44c6-9faf-805eab47d3b6_881x468.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:468,&quot;width&quot;:881,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:109865,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.thebignewsletter.com/i/177563599?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb3ae2e5e-e6ee-44c6-9faf-805eab47d3b6_881x468.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Gpib!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb3ae2e5e-e6ee-44c6-9faf-805eab47d3b6_881x468.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Gpib!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb3ae2e5e-e6ee-44c6-9faf-805eab47d3b6_881x468.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Gpib!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb3ae2e5e-e6ee-44c6-9faf-805eab47d3b6_881x468.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Gpib!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb3ae2e5e-e6ee-44c6-9faf-805eab47d3b6_881x468.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><span>Why the pushback? The answer is that corporate-run gambling is now pervasive in America, and Americans don’t like what they see. Gambling, particularly online sports betting, is now everywhere. About a fifth of Americans </span><a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/short-reads/2025/10/02/americans-increasingly-see-legal-sports-betting-as-a-bad-thing-for-society-and-sports/" rel="">placed</a><span> a bet in the past year, mostly through gambling apps. Since 2018, when online sports gambling got a big boost from a key Supreme Court decision, Americans have </span><a href="https://www.legalsportsreport.com/sports-betting-states/revenue/" rel="">bet</a><span> more than half a trillion dollars on sports. </span></p><p><span>And the attempts to change our culture are extremely visible; I watched the Dolphins-Ravens game last night on Amazon Prime, and I lost count of the number of ads for DraftKings and FanDuel, with various celebrities lending their names to this cultural phenomenon. Every major sports media network, sports league, and podcast are now working with a major gambling company. At this point, gambling is intrinsic to the financing of sports; FanDuel now </span><a href="https://www.theringer.com/2025/10/24/nba/nba-gambling-scandal-chauncey-billups-terry-rozier-adam-silver" rel="">operates</a><span> “15 regional sports networks across the country previously on the brink of bankruptcy.”</span></p><p><span>The broad consequences are also extremely visible. Take athletics. Americans love sports, and that cultural centerpiece is being corrupted in an orgy of greed and speculative ferver. Last week, the government </span><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/10/24/nyregion/nba-sports-betting-gambling-scandal.html" rel="">charged</a><span> six people, including two NBA players, for gambling-related fraud. It’s also contributing to a courser culture, with a lot of unfair pressure on athletes. According to </span><a href="https://www.usnews.com/banking/articles/2025-sports-betting-and-debt-survey" rel="">US News</a><span>, “21% of sports bettors say they’ve verbally abused an athlete, either in person or online, after losing money on a bet.”</span></p><p><span>And that’s not even getting into the costs of fostering a nation of gamblers, lured in by an app-based model that is far more convenient and addictive than traditional in-person betting. Today, four out of five </span><a href="https://www.usnews.com/banking/articles/2025-sports-betting-and-debt-survey" rel="">betters</a><span> are using betting apps or online platforms. A quarter of bettors can’t pay a bill because of their wagers, a third have gambling debts, more than half carry credit card debts, and a quarter of them are afraid they can’t control their gambling. Economists are </span><a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=4903302" rel="">finding</a><span> a “substantial increase in average bankruptcy rates, debt sent to collections, use of debt consolidation loans, and auto loan delinquencies” for consumers in states that legalized online sports betting versus those that restrict it to in-person locations. The estimates I’m told privately by experts in the field is that in the next five years, all gambling - including lotteries, Las Vegas casinos, and online sports betting - will likely see Americans lose a trillion dollars or so. </span></p><p><span>Last year, I did an Organized Money episode with </span><a href="https://www.organizedmoney.fm/p/episode-9-vice-monopolists-fanduel" rel="">Les Bernal and Dr. Kavita Fischer</a><span> on the problem; Fischer is a psychiatrist who downloaded Draft Kings in 2022 to unwind after putting her kids to bed. She ended up losing $600,000, explaining to the Wall Street Journal </span><a href="https://www.wsj.com/business/hospitality/gambling-addiction-sports-betting-apps-4463cde0?gaa_at=eafs&amp;gaa_n=AWEtsqe_LgM0Z396EKHXo_vX_T0lmObkaGlhcn_70DubGAlGLAdOYy3eVA3oEIMTn54%3D&amp;gaa_ts=6903c02c&amp;gaa_sig=4Unk99tCx4UcVWnftJq8NI6YmawFu_0g7uLipAxDCJHhMqxXNTJwZpnNcAEIbnSPCv8Prh1ibH__NiNBzMETJA%3D%3D" rel="">the story</a><span> of how DraftKings used sophisticated techniques to keep her betting, even as she desperately tried to stop. (Most of the loss was not on sports, but on standard casino games.)</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!zWRH!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd268c66b-cf7f-4913-b6e3-d8410002eb3b_1030x461.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!zWRH!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd268c66b-cf7f-4913-b6e3-d8410002eb3b_1030x461.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!zWRH!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd268c66b-cf7f-4913-b6e3-d8410002eb3b_1030x461.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!zWRH!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd268c66b-cf7f-4913-b6e3-d8410002eb3b_1030x461.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!zWRH!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd268c66b-cf7f-4913-b6e3-d8410002eb3b_1030x461.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!zWRH!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd268c66b-cf7f-4913-b6e3-d8410002eb3b_1030x461.png" width="1030" height="461" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/d268c66b-cf7f-4913-b6e3-d8410002eb3b_1030x461.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:461,&quot;width&quot;:1030,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:350710,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.thebignewsletter.com/i/177563599?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd268c66b-cf7f-4913-b6e3-d8410002eb3b_1030x461.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" title="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!zWRH!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd268c66b-cf7f-4913-b6e3-d8410002eb3b_1030x461.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!zWRH!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd268c66b-cf7f-4913-b6e3-d8410002eb3b_1030x461.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!zWRH!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd268c66b-cf7f-4913-b6e3-d8410002eb3b_1030x461.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!zWRH!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd268c66b-cf7f-4913-b6e3-d8410002eb3b_1030x461.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Online sports betting is reaching new more politically empowered groups. Fischer’s story is very common, and it’s occurring among middle and upper middle class people who were never exposed to other forms of gambling, like state lotteries and casinos. It’s also hitting kids, who themselves are often calling in to help lines with addiction. It’s so common that Saturday Night Live did a viral skit for a fictional company called “Rock Bottom Kings,” which allows people to take bets on their degenerate gambling addict friend’s behavior. </p><div id="youtube2-wXZNuwY_5-U" data-attrs="{&quot;videoId&quot;:&quot;wXZNuwY_5-U&quot;,&quot;startTime&quot;:null,&quot;endTime&quot;:null}" data-component-name="Youtube2ToDOM"><p><iframe src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/wXZNuwY_5-U?rel=0&amp;autoplay=0&amp;showinfo=0&amp;enablejsapi=0" frameborder="0" loading="lazy" gesture="media" allow="autoplay; fullscreen" allowautoplay="true" allowfullscreen="true" width="728" height="409"></iframe></p></div><p><span>Increasingly, people are turning against this form of betting. According to Pew,  43% of U.S. adults </span><a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/short-reads/2025/10/02/americans-increasingly-see-legal-sports-betting-as-a-bad-thing-for-society-and-sports/" rel="">say</a><span> “the fact that sports betting is now legal in much of the country is a bad thing for society,” up from 34% just a few years ago. And that’s concentrated among young men, who are most exposed; “47% of men under 30 say legal sports betting is a bad thing for society, up from 22% who said this in 2022.” And opposition is increasing faster among people who bet than people who don’t. It’s not that people oppose betting with friends, what’s problematic is the ability to build a business around being the house.</span></p><p><span>In an important sense, it’s odd that we’re even dealing with pervasive corporate-run gambling. Historically, Americans understood systemic gambling, and associated similar abuses of power like usury, as a moral and social catastrophe in waiting. That has been true since the 19th century, with many states making gambling unconstitutional, through to the fixing of the 1919 World Series, but it was also true well into the 20th century, when corporate gambling was constrained to mobster-run places like Las Vegas and Atlantic City. Even into the 1960s, courts </span><a href="https://scholarship.law.cornell.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?referer=&amp;httpsredir=1&amp;article=2957&amp;context=clr" rel="">prevented</a><span> the patenting of gambling machines on the grounds they conflicted with the “sound morals of society.”</span></p><p><span>And culturally, we understood it as well, with gambling represented as a sinful and harmful enterprise. Take the 1987 smash hit movie </span><em>Back to the Future II. </em><span>In it, the villain, Biff Tannen, uses a time machine to alter the past so that he becomes a wealthy and corrupt casino magnate over a dilapidated town, Hill Valley. The hero, Marty McFly, in turn, must find a way to revert Hill Valley to its previous state. </span><em>Back to the Future II</em><span> was the third highest grossing film of 1989, and I remember as a kid we all saw it, and in school all my friends wondered whether hoverboards were real. Everyone just knew that corporate-run gambling was seedy.</span></p><p><span>With a few exceptions, up until the 1960s this attitude applied to all corporate gambling, from sports betting to lotteries, which were seen as similar to the “numbers racket” of the mob. But in 1963, New Hampshire Governor John King, egged on by the conservative </span><em>Manchester Union Leader, </em><span>signed a bill to create the first state lottery, to the horror of most newspapers nationwide and the Federal government, which arrested out-of-state residents for buying tickets. </span></p><p><span>Why did New Hampshire allow its new “sweepstakes” game? Well, it was </span><a href="https://www.nhmagazine.com/how-nh-defied-the-feds-mob-and-church-to-create-the-first-state-lottery/" rel="">pitched</a><span> as part of the anti-tax revolution that would take over the nation fifteen years later. One of the key supporters was Bill Loeb, the arch-conservative publisher of the </span><em>Manchester Union Leader, </em><span>who “favored the Sweepstakes because he feared without it the Legislature would pass a sales tax — something he abhorred over all else.” </span></p><blockquote><p>Pointing to the state’s reliance on so-called “sin taxes,” Loeb penned the strongest defense of the lottery yet. “No one has to go to the track and bet. No one has to smoke tobacco. No one has to drink. But how do those who oppose the Sweepstakes propose to raise the money? Either a sales tax or a property tax or some other kind of levy that people will have to pay, even though it will hurt them dreadfully to do so.”</p></blockquote><p>The New Hampshire lottery served as the “legitimization” of gambling, turning it from a seedy activity into something sanctioned by a state. And it also set in motion the same dynamic with gambling we see today, which is that residents from outside of New Hampshire would buy lottery tickets from that state, because they couldn’t get them where they live. So their state officials would wonder why they are foregoing revenue, leading to a daisy chain of legalization. Corporate gambling tended to expand in a similar pattern. After people saw that a simple state lottery could bring in more revenue, they allowed more complex gambling games, and then in-person casinos and racetracks, slot machines, and sports betting. And every time someone tried to block the expansion, the response was “well people will just do it across state lines.”</p><p>After New Hampshire, New Jersey and New York created lotteries. Then, in the 1970s, a host of progressive-leaning states across the northeast created lotteries to deal with austerity budgets, and to capture the revenue they were foregoing when their own residents went to other states to buy lottery tickets. These included Connecticut, Massachusetts, Maryland, Maine, Illinois, Ohio, Rhode Island, Vermont, Pennsylvania, and Michigan. Much of the rest of the country legalized lotteries in the 1980s for similar reasons, though a few states - Utah, Alaska, and Hawaii - have not. </p><p><span>In the South, religious conservatives opposed gambling, but Reagan Republicans changed this dynamic. Moral scold Bill Bennett, who wrote “The Book of Virtues” and served as Secretary of Education and Drug Czar under Reagan, </span><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/03/us/relentless-moral-crusader-is-relentless-gambler-too.html" rel="">exempted</a><span> gambling from his list of sins, himself carrying millions in gambling debts. A key actor was eventual RNC Chair Frank Fahrenkopf, who brought casino interests into the national Republican world, welding it together with Wall Street cash and big hotel chains by forming the American Gaming Association. </span></p><p>Corporations got into gambling in a major way. “Before 1989, you couldn’t get mainstream, Wall Street money in this industry,” said one reporter. “Now, not only can you get, they’re throwing it at you.” Fahrenkopf talked about the inflow of big corporate interests, it was now “professionals - people who have gone to business school.” These were “some of the brightest business men and women now involved in running these companies,” with the ability to “sit down with Goldman Sachs, or Bear Sterns or whoever it might be and convince them that number one, it’s a legitimate business.”</p><p><span>Martin Scorcese, in the ending of the iconic movie </span><em>Casino, </em><span>described this shift from the mob control of Vegas to Wall Street control. “Where did the money to rebuild the pyramids come from?” asked Las Vegas Sands casino leader and mobster Sam “Ace” Rothstein after he lost control of the town. “Junk Bonds.”</span></p><div id="youtube2-fBp8lLjZohg" data-attrs="{&quot;videoId&quot;:&quot;fBp8lLjZohg&quot;,&quot;startTime&quot;:&quot;78&quot;,&quot;endTime&quot;:null}" data-component-name="Youtube2ToDOM"><p><iframe src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/fBp8lLjZohg?start=78&amp;rel=0&amp;autoplay=0&amp;showinfo=0&amp;enablejsapi=0" frameborder="0" loading="lazy" gesture="media" allow="autoplay; fullscreen" allowautoplay="true" allowfullscreen="true" width="728" height="409"></iframe></p></div><p>When the internet became mainstream in the 1990s, online gambling wasn’t legal, but online gambling offerings from offshore casinos became a major problem. Tennessee Senator Bill Frist, with a coalition of progressives and religious conservatives, moved a bill called the Unlawful Internet Gambling Enforcement Act in 2006, which banned money transfers to offshore gaming companies. But the UIGEA had an exemption for fantasy sports, which proponents laughably called a game of skill and not chance. Over the course of the next two decades, the firms that took advantage of this law then unleashed a state-by-state lobbying campaign to legalize online sports betting.</p><p><span>The Supreme Court, in 2018, </span><a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/17pdf/16-476_dbfi.pdf" rel="">said</a><span> states could legalize online sports gambling, unleashing a lobbying campaign such that 39 states now allow it. Today, when you pass sports bars on Sunday’s, many of them now have special sections dedicated to gambling. On a moral and political level, many Americans came to accept corporate gambling as just another business, like usury or wild forms of financial speculation. </span></p><p>Democrats often invite gambling as a mechanism to bring in more revenue for the state. And on the right, a former casino magnate, Donald Trump, is now in the White House, and his track record running that sort of business simply didn’t enter the political debate. Trump drew immense support from the anti-gambling religious right, and progressive Democrats mocked Trump for losing money running a casino, but not for engaging in that business in the first place. </p><p>In other words, Biff Tannen’s dastardly scheme to organize a town around gambling interests would today be framed as just good economic development. </p><p>Beyond the substantive harm, there’s an ideological valence to corporate gambling. Corporate-run gambling is an unusual commercial activity, for two reasons. One is that there’s nothing produced, it’s a pure net transfer of wealth from the gambler to the casino. But the second and more important one is that it’s addictive, and thus coercive. </p><p>Gambling releases dopamine, the chemical behind pleasure and anticipation, and over time, it changes the chemistry of one’s brain to create a dependency on continuing the activity. As Fischer put it, “There was just something in my brain that made me keep going.” Thus, a company engaged in corporate gambling is seeking to take advantage of the other party’s very ability to govern their own rational faculties. </p><p>Most people think of legitimate market transactions as involving two parties coming together in a voluntary exchange based on reasonably honest information. You can go back to Aristotle and Thomas Aquinas, all the way through the populists and John Wanamaker, and find the basics of fair pricing - no coercion, no deception. But the coercion is real, and so is deception. Every online sports gambling commercial includes a help line if you have a problem, and all of the firms in the industry say they maintain ethical standards. And yet, as the Wall Street Journal story showed, their ideal customer is one who gambles excessively. </p><p><span>As legal scholar Matthew Lawrence noted, addiction is a </span><a href="https://scholarlycommons.law.emory.edu/faculty-articles/82/" rel="">fundamental threat</a><span> to liberty. Because there is an imbalance in power between the parties in the transaction, corporate gambling requires far stricter rules and regulations, or perhaps even bans, than markets for goods that are not addictive. </span></p><p>Corporate gambling also has significant broader negative consequences. Online sports betting corrupts sports and the public itself. And states often derive revenue from the practice, meaning that legislators, even if they wanted to eliminate the activity, would have to plug a fiscal hole. Like all products that foster addiction, corporate gambling creates a form of social pollution, in the form of ruined lives and public corruption. And that’s why it’s important to impose market rules that significantly limit the activity and the political power of those who profit from it.</p><p>While the religious right and Catholic institutions oppose gambling, progressives have not been particularly concerned until recently, preferring to scold around questions of race and gender than traditional fire and brimstone sins. But that is changing, as the left swings more towards concern over inequality and economics than non-commercial questions. </p><p>So what can be done?</p><p><span>Gambling is legal in other countries, for better or worse. There are a number of regulatory choices that lessen its impact. In the UK, for instance, they have what are called “</span><a href="https://harmreductionjournal.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12954-024-01150-3" rel="">stake limits</a><span>” for certain online games, meaning that gamblers have a limit on the amount they can bet in any one contest. The stake limits </span><a href="https://www.gamblinginsider.com/news/28198/government-debates-gambling-reform-online-slot-stake-limits-and-statutory-levy-introduced" rel="">are lower</a><span> for certain ages. In addition, they regulate VIP programs such as the ones that entrapped Fischer, which has cut problem gambling somewhat.</span></p><p>In the U.S., we are just starting to figure out how to push back. There are possible levers around the use of data to target customers with advertisements, eliminating push notifications and VIP programs, prohibiting discrimination against “sharps,” aka people who are good at sports betting. </p><p><span>But there are significant hurdles, and not just the standard issues involved in dealing with well-capitalized corporate opponents, who engage in multiple forms of lobbying, everything from direct contacts with lawmakers to working with think tanks like </span><a href="https://www.progressivepolicy.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/PPI-Legalized-Sports-Betting.pdf" rel="">the Progressive Policy Institute</a><span>. Unlike most other industries, corporate gambling is also a partnership with the state. To run a casino, race track, or online betting app, you need a license, and must pay the state some portion of your revenues. States themselves run lotteries. And that means gambling revenue is part of state budgets.</span></p><p><span>Take Maryland. Out of $24.86 billion of </span><a href="https://www.marylandcomptroller.gov/content/dam/mdcomp/md/reports/financial/FY2024-Closeout.pdf" rel="">state revenue</a><span> last year, $1.589 billion came from the lottery, the state’s casinos, sportsbooks and daily fantasy sports operators. Most of that was from casinos and lotteries, sports was just $89.9 million. But if you want to outlaw this harmful activity, you have to find a way to replace 6.4% of Maryland’s budget, which is slightly less than the entire amount the state brings in from corporate taxes. The fiscal gains from gambling revenues </span><a href="https://rockinst.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/2016-04-12-Blinken_Report_Three-min.pdf" rel="">are vastly overstated</a><span>. In the short-term, it usually delivers, but quickly peters out. Indeed, Maryland Governor Wes Moore just </span><a href="https://www.legalsportsreport.com/233974/moore-signs-maryland-sports-betting-tax-hike/" rel="">increased taxes</a><span> on sports betting, as a way to plug a budget gap. And the costs are </span><a href="https://www.crainsnewyork.com/op-ed/op-ed-casino-revenues-are-often-short-lived-and-not-sustainable-over-long-run" rel="">likely higher</a><span> than the revenue gains. Gambling, as it turns out, is just as addictive to states as it is to gamblers, with less bang for the buck over time.</span></p><p><span>And it gets worse during economic downturns, as Pat Garofalo </span><a href="https://boondoggle.substack.com/p/the-biggest-lottery-scam-is-the-lottery" rel="">wrote</a><span> in his invaluable newsletter. </span></p><blockquote><p><span>Lottery playing increases </span><a href="https://taxfoundation.org/blog/does-lottery-revenue-rise-or-fall-during-economic-hardship/#:~:text=Of%20the%2042%20states%20with,.%20%2C%20in%202001%2D2." rel="">when joblessness rises</a><span>, and more than 20 state lotteries set sales records during the Great Recession.</span></p><p><span>Because states have tied specific programs to lottery funding, they </span><em>need</em><span> that desperation, or else lottery-tied funding falls during economic downturns, when other revenues are also going south, leaving states with more holes they need to fill.</span></p><p><span>Just look at </span><a href="https://www.governing.com/finance/what-happens-to-public-budgets-when-residents-spend-less-on-the-lottery?utm_campaign=Newsletter%20-%20GOV%20-%20Future%20of%20Finance&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;_hsenc=p2ANqtz-_7WehIfJlb1uP4po4OjBslRQp91fDfrmHzge7Rpdrq7BjHEk9kLWH_Xf9Al028bB-6WJ9cjW_aaApgTQPU7575UtilXw&amp;_hsmi=387104456&amp;utm_content=387104456&amp;utm_source=hs_email" rel="">this recent interview</a><span> with the executive director of the Virginia lottery. Though he pays a lot of lip service to ensuring that Virginians don’t become addicted to lottery games, it’s clear his overriding concern is ensuring that people keep playing even as the state’s economic outlook worsens.</span></p><p>He brings up expanding online games in order to bring in more young players, explains that “offering a mix of gaming experiences and price points helps draw in different kinds of players,” and says he wants to put lottery games into restaurants and bars — because nothing says “we’re taking gambling addiction seriously” quite like giving people easy access to gambling and alcohol together.</p></blockquote><p><span>As Garofalo noted, </span><a href="https://www.governing.com/finance/what-happens-to-public-budgets-when-residents-spend-less-on-the-lottery?utm_campaign=Newsletter%20-%20GOV%20-%20Future%20of%20Finance&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;_hsenc=p2ANqtz-_7WehIfJlb1uP4po4OjBslRQp91fDfrmHzge7Rpdrq7BjHEk9kLWH_Xf9Al028bB-6WJ9cjW_aaApgTQPU7575UtilXw&amp;_hsmi=387104456&amp;utm_content=387104456&amp;utm_source=hs_email" rel="">10 percent</a><span> of Virginia’s public education is tied to gambling money. Even though gambling costs a state more than it brings in, cutting corporate gambling likely means it’ll be necessary to tax the wealthy.</span></p><p><span>Beyond the fiscal hurdles, there are attempts to make it impossible to even regulate gambling at a state level. Kalshi, a company that operates what it calls “prediction markets” to allow people to speculate on things like elections, is now offering sports betting. Kalshi claims that its sports betting is not gambling, but a form of useful financial market-exchange. That’s of course nonsense, but the goal is to have a Federal regulator, the Commodities Futures Trading Commission, override state limits on gambling. If Kalshi wins on its legal argument, then online sports betting will be legal everywhere, without state permission. So far, Kalshi </span><a href="https://www.bhfs.com/insight/third-times-the-charm-for-gambling-regulators-in-kalshi-litigation/" rel="">has won</a><span> in Nevada and New Jersey, but lost in Maryland, which means this decision will eventually have to be addressed on appeal.</span></p><p><span>The politics of this particular administration on gambling are ugly; Trump’s first pick to run the CFTC was a board member of Kalshi; after he withdrew, the </span><a href="https://www.ingame.com/cftc-pick-selig-letter-backing-sports-contracts/" rel="">next pick</a><span> is a lawyer for a firm that invested in Kalshi. Moreover, Donald Trump Jr. is an investor in Kalshi, and President Trump’s company, TruthSocial, is </span><a href="https://www.wired.com/story/trump-truth-social-launches-prediction-market/" rel="">launching</a><span> a predictions market as well (as is DraftKings).</span></p><p>All of these dynamics make the institutions hard to reform. Yet, the most important tool is public opinion, and that has not been brought to bear until recently. </p><p>The underpinning of the anti-corporate gambling movement is the same as the anti-monopoly argument. A free society relies on rules that prevent arbitrary coercion, both in and out of the marketplace. For a long time, we have neglected the role of commerce in a moral order, choosing to ignore gambling, usury, fraud, and deceit, as well as monopolization and a whole variety of games around price. What’s happening, as we are enveloped in a world of unreality, of crypto and fraud, AI bubbles, and sports gambling, is that the corruption of our society, with the rise of scams and flattery, is becoming impossible to ignore.</p><p>Senator Benson’s bill to roll back online sports gambling in Maryland may be one of the first important moves to go on offense against corporate gambling, but it won’t be the last.</p><p><span>Thanks for reading! Your tips make this newsletter what it is, so please send me tips on weird monopolies, stories I’ve missed, or other thoughts. And if you liked this issue of BIG, you can sign up </span><a href="http://email.mg1.substack.com/c/eJxVUMFuwyAM_ZpwjIAmYT34UHXtb0QEnBSNQARmVf5-pN1hkyzberae37PRhEtMOxBmYiVjGp0FZoEradTEXB7nhLhq54FtZfLOaHIxHFtC9LJjDzhxNUs7nKTlnGsthRKDmj-s4dIYO0i2xUyjLtZhMAj4jWmPAZmHB9GWm9OlkfcaqybKFL3H1OYyZdLmqzVxraMn-togcyC5OPNzzT3ve9WKVnS3y5WL4a54d1PdZ9PxdRH_CFiCX946XA4vL7TaGWtdS3C0jxj05NECpYKM3v94Cad9Qwj4zB6JML3Bw74chFCsHrKxcgb4o_8H-RJ1Kg" rel="">here</a><span> for more issues, a newsletter on how to restore fair commerce, innovation, and democracy. Consider becoming a </span><a href="https://email.mg1.substack.com/c/eJxVUMtuwyAQ_JpwtABjEw4ceulvIB6Lg4rBgrUq_31J0kO7Wmk1-xrNeIuw1XZphI7kqB0NXgfoAt89AyI0cnZoJgVNgqaSe-lI6iY2gN2mrMlxupy8xVTLc4uxhQvy0DZKpyjQIL31CqigggOPQYWBIqg3lz1DguJB15Ivc9gUSNYPxKPf5o8b_xy5W8SONWdoUz9dR-u_Jl_3MXpC35IDkjSnnI2Y6cwkZROfhIwuSrXauC7e2_u0rNhtvJaboPvG_v0iTf9SjOH21PXqDmlm1P0sCS8DxboMQWM7geDbsJcHZoMCbRgZjEXN1nmVchaci5W9VQ5bxEzlXVFFBm2o46roP8J-AJJ0hnE" rel="">paying subscriber</a><span> to support this work, or if you are a paying subscriber, giving a </span><a href="https://email.mg1.substack.com/c/eJxVUEtuxSAMPE1YRnwSSBYsKlW9BiJgUlQCETiqcvvy3uuitSxZ9tgezTiLsJd6a4SG5CwNDd4n6AzfLQEiVHI1qCZ6Tbymiju1kdhMqACHjUmT89pSdBZjyY8txmY-kU_tOZOU-bB5urhl9ouc-RomtnoXpOX0xWUvHyE70CWn25w2epL0J-LZBvE28I-eh0VsWFKCOrZra2jd1-jK0aFH62rcYBB9U-4x4CDesV5AouaUsx6CCqYoG_k4qbAFtUob5OycXcZZYrPhnoeJHjv795xU_cvZwf0h9DntWk2vx5Uj3gay3RJ4_STEl4NPU8wOGWp31huLmkkhlRIT55NkL9ndp0lQtax0JZ3Wl36V9R-lPyvjiqk" rel="">gift subscription</a><span> to a friend, colleague, or family member. If you really liked it, read my book, </span><a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/Goliath/Matt-Stoller/9781501183089" rel="">Goliath: The 100-Year War Between Monopoly Power and Democracy</a><span>.</span></p><p>cheers,</p><p>Matt Stoller</p></div></article></div><div id="discussion"><h4>Discussion about this post</h4></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Use DuckDB-WASM to query TB of data in browser (199 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lil.law.harvard.edu/blog/2025/10/24/rethinking-data-discovery-for-libraries-and-digital-humanities/</link>
            <guid>45774571</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 17:37:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lil.law.harvard.edu/blog/2025/10/24/rethinking-data-discovery-for-libraries-and-digital-humanities/">https://lil.law.harvard.edu/blog/2025/10/24/rethinking-data-discovery-for-libraries-and-digital-humanities/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45774571">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
        <figure>
  <img src="https://lil-blog-media.s3.amazonaws.com/macey_vertical_filing_cabinet_1903.jpg" alt="Illustration of a woman using a Macey vertical filing cabinet, from a 1903 catalogue">
  <figcaption>Woman using a Macey vertical filing cabinet (detail, 1903). Source: <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Macey_Vertical_Filing_Cabinet_1903.jpg">Wikimedia Commons</a>.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p><em>As part of our <a href="https://lil.law.harvard.edu/our-work/public-data-project/">Public Data Project</a>, LIL recently launched <a href="https://lil.law.harvard.edu/data-gov-archive/">Data.gov Archive Search</a>. In this post, we look under the hood and reflect on how and why we built this project the way we did.</em></p>

<hr>

<h2 id="rethinking-the-old-trade-off-cost-complexity-and-access">Rethinking the Old Trade-Off: Cost, Complexity, and Access</h2>

<p>Libraries, digital humanities projects, and cultural heritage organizations have long had to perform a balancing act when sharing their collections online, negotiating between access and affordability. Providing robust features for data discovery, such as browsing, filtering, and search, has traditionally required dedicated computing infrastructure such as servers and databases. Ongoing server hosting, regular security and software updates, and consistent operational oversight are expensive and require skilled staff. Over years or decades, budget changes and staff turnover often strand these projects in an unmaintained or nonfunctioning state.</p>

<p>The alternative, static file hosting, requires minimal maintenance and reduces expenses dramatically. For example, storing gigabytes of data on Amazon S3 may cost $1/month or less. However, static hosting often diminishes the capacity for rich data discovery. Without a dynamic computing layer between the user’s web browser and the source files, data access may be restricted to brittle pre-rendered browsing hierarchies or search functionality that is impeded by client memory limits. Under such barriers, the collection’s discoverability suffers.</p>

<p>For years, online collection discovery has been stuck between a rock and a hard place: accept the complexity and expense required for a good user experience, or opt for simplicity and leave users to contend with the blunt limitations of a static discovery layer.</p>

<hr>

<h2 id="why-we-explored-a-new-approach">Why We Explored a New Approach</h2>

<p>When LIL began thinking about how to provide discovery for the <a href="https://source.coop/harvard-lil/gov-data/">Data.gov Archive</a>, we decided that building a lightweight and easily maintained access point from the beginning would be worth our team’s effort. We wanted to provide low-effort discovery with minimal impact on our resources. We also wanted to ensure that whatever path we chose would encourage, rather than impede, long-term access.</p>

<p>This approach builds on our recent experience when the Caselaw Access Project (CAP) hit <a href="https://lil.law.harvard.edu/blog/2024/03/26/transitions-for-the-caselaw-access-project/">a transition moment</a>. At that time, we elected to switch <a href="http://case.law/">case.law</a> to a static site and to partner with others dedicated to open legal data to provide more feature-rich access.</p>

<p>CAP includes some 11 TB of data; the Data.gov Archive represents nearly 18 TB, with the catalog metadata alone accounting for about 1 GB. Manually browsing the archive data in its repository, even for a user who knows what she’s looking for, is laborious and time-consuming. Thus we faced a challenge. Could we enable dynamic, scalable discovery of the Data.gov Archive while enjoying the frugality, simplicity, and maintainability of static hosting?</p>

<hr>

<h2 id="our-experiment-rich-discovery-no-server-required">Our Experiment: Rich Discovery, No Server Required</h2>

<p>Recent advancements in client-side data analysis led us to try something new. Tools like <a href="https://duckdb.org/docs/api/wasm/">DuckDB-Wasm</a>, <a href="https://phiresky.github.io/blog/2021/hosting-sqlite-databases-on-github-pages/">sql.js-httpvfs</a>, and <a href="https://protomaps.com/">Protomaps</a>, powered by standards such as WebAssembly, web workers, and HTTP range requests, allow users to efficiently query large remote datasets in the browser. Rather than downloading a 2 GB data file into memory, these tools can incrementally retrieve only the relevant parts of the file and process query results locally.</p>

<p>We developed Data.gov Archive Search on the same model. Here’s how it works:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Data storage:</strong> We store Data.gov Archive catalog metadata as sorted, compressed Parquet files on Source.coop, taking advantage of performant static file hosting.</li>
  <li><strong>In-browser query engine:</strong> Our client-side web application loads DuckDB-Wasm, a fully functional database engine running inside the user’s browser.</li>
  <li><strong>On-demand data access:</strong> When a user navigates to a resource or submits a search, our DuckDB-Wasm client executes a targeted retrieval of the data needed to fulfill the request. No dedicated server is required; queries run entirely in the browser.</li>
</ul>

<p>This experiment has not been without obstacles. Getting good performance out of this model demands careful data engineering, and the large DuckDB-Wasm binary imposes a considerable latency cost. As of this writing, we’re continuing to explore speedy alternatives like <a href="https://github.com/hyparam/hyparquet">hyparquet</a> and <a href="https://idl.uw.edu/arquero">Arquero</a> to further improve performance.</p>

<p>Still, we’re pleased with the result: an inexpensive, low-maintenance static discovery platform that allows users to browse, search, and filter Data.gov Archive records entirely in the browser.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://lil-blog-media.s3.amazonaws.com/data_gov_archive_search.jpg" alt="Screenshot of Data.gov Archive Search">
  <figcaption>Screenshot of <a href="https://lil.law.harvard.edu/data-gov-archive/">Data.gov Archive Search</a>.</figcaption>
</figure>

<hr>

<h2 id="why-this-matters-for-libraries-digital-humanities-projects-and-beyond">Why This Matters for Libraries, Digital Humanities Projects, and Beyond</h2>

<p>This new pattern offers a compelling model for libraries, academic archives, and DH projects of all sizes:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Lower operating costs:</strong> By shifting from an expensive server to lower cost static storage, projects can sustainably offer their users access to data.</li>
  <li><strong>Reduced technical overhead:</strong> With no dedicated backend server, security risks are reduced, no patching or upgrades are needed, and crashing servers are not a concern.</li>
  <li><strong>Sustained access:</strong> Projects can be set up with care, but without demanding constant attention. Organizations can be more confident that their archive and discovery interfaces remain usable and accessible, even as staffing or funding changes over time.</li>
</ul>

<p>Knowing that we are not the only group interested in approaching access in this way, we’re sharing our generalized learnings. We see a few ways forward for others in the knowledge and information world:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Prototype or pilot:</strong> If your organization has large, relatively static datasets, consider experimenting with a browser-based search tool using static hosting.</li>
  <li><strong>Share and collaborate:</strong> Template applications, workflows, and lessons learned can help this new pattern gain adoption and maturity across the community.</li>
</ul>

<p>This project is still evolving, and we invite others—particularly those in libraries and digital cultural heritage—to explore these possibilities with us. We’re committed to open sharing as we refine our tools, and we welcome collaboration or feedback at <a href="mailto:lil@law.harvard.edu">lil@law.harvard.edu</a>.</p>

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Just Use a Button (268 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://gomakethings.com/just-use-a-button/</link>
            <guid>45774182</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 16:59:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://gomakethings.com/just-use-a-button/">https://gomakethings.com/just-use-a-button/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45774182">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://gomakethings.com/just-use-a-button/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Futurelock: A subtle risk in async Rust (355 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://rfd.shared.oxide.computer/rfd/0609</link>
            <guid>45774086</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 16:49:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://rfd.shared.oxide.computer/rfd/0609">https://rfd.shared.oxide.computer/rfd/0609</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45774086">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://rfd.shared.oxide.computer/rfd/0609: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Another European agency shifts off US Tech as digital sovereignty gains steam (238 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.zdnet.com/article/another-european-agency-ditches-big-tech-as-digital-sovereignty-movement-gains-steam/</link>
            <guid>45773974</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 16:39:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/another-european-agency-ditches-big-tech-as-digital-sovereignty-movement-gains-steam/">https://www.zdnet.com/article/another-european-agency-ditches-big-tech-as-digital-sovereignty-movement-gains-steam/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45773974">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><figure><div><picture><source media="(max-width: 767px)" srcset="https://www.zdnet.com/a/img/resize/1bf426f379fa84c0a19809efd8025dc62de1828b/2025/10/31/9427f086-2451-4b2b-9a9a-ad4296867031/gettyimages-90784932.jpg?auto=webp&amp;width=768" alt="Vienna parliament"><source media="(max-width: 1023px)" srcset="https://www.zdnet.com/a/img/resize/1bbd3ae2650d27d2cd071cff0b475a53172f733d/2025/10/31/9427f086-2451-4b2b-9a9a-ad4296867031/gettyimages-90784932.jpg?auto=webp&amp;width=1024" alt="Vienna parliament"><source media="(max-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://www.zdnet.com/a/img/resize/4d4a458cdb14100b6968ce03f5776a24e952c744/2025/10/31/9427f086-2451-4b2b-9a9a-ad4296867031/gettyimages-90784932.jpg?auto=webp&amp;width=1280" alt="Vienna parliament"> <img src="https://www.zdnet.com/a/img/resize/4d4a458cdb14100b6968ce03f5776a24e952c744/2025/10/31/9427f086-2451-4b2b-9a9a-ad4296867031/gettyimages-90784932.jpg?auto=webp&amp;width=1280" alt="Vienna parliament" width="1280" height="848.6001056524036" fetchpriority="low"></picture></div> <figcaption> <span>traumlichtfabrik/Moment/Getty Images</span></figcaption></figure><p><em>Follow ZDNET:&nbsp;</em><span><a href="https://cc.zdnet.com/v1/otc/00hQi47eqnEWQ6T9d4QLBUc?element=BODY&amp;element_label=Add+us+as+a+preferred+Google+source&amp;module=LINK&amp;object_type=text-link&amp;object_uuid=5e5d2e64-4b30-43e6-8555-26eac7e449f3&amp;position=1&amp;template=article&amp;track_code=__COM_CLICK_ID__&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.google.com%2Fpreferences%2Fsource%3Fq%3Dzdnet.com&amp;view_instance_uuid=379e95d2-6b56-476b-a90b-043a8dd63bd3" rel="noopener nofollow sponsored" target="_blank"><span>Add us as a preferred source</span><!----></a></span><em>&nbsp;on Google.</em></p><hr><h3>ZDNET's key takeaways</h3><ul><li>Austria's Ministry of Economy has migrated to a Nextcloud platform.</li><li>It's the latest move in a European trend to shift away from Big Tech.</li><li>European governments and agencies want to control sensitive data.</li></ul><hr><p>Even before <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/massive-azure-outage-is-over-but-problems-linger-heres-what-happened/">Azure had a global failure this week</a>, Austria's Ministry of Economy had taken a decisive step toward digital sovereignty. The Ministry achieved this status by <a href="https://nextcloud.com/blog/austrias-ministry-of-economy-takes-decisive-steps-toward-digital-sovereignty/" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">migrating 1,200 employees to a Nextcloud-based cloud and collaboration platform</a> hosted on Austrian-based infrastructure.&nbsp;</p><p>This shift away from proprietary, foreign-owned cloud services, such as <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/how-you-can-get-microsoft-365-formerly-office-for-free-3-easy-ways/">Microsoft 365</a>, to an <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/what-is-open-source-and-how-does-it-benefit-you/">open-source</a>, European-based cloud service aligns with a growing trend among European governments and agencies. They want control over sensitive data and to declare their independence from US-based tech providers.&nbsp;</p><p><strong>Also: <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/europes-plan-to-ditch-us-tech-giants-is-built-on-open-source-and-its-gaining-steam/">Europe's plan to ditch US tech giants is built on open source - and it's gaining steam</a></strong></p><p>European companies are encouraging this trend. Many of them have joined forces in the newly created non-profit foundation, the EuroStack Initiative. This foundation's goal is " to organize action, not just talk, around the pillars of the initiative: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/euro-stack_foundation-press-release-activity-7389635091049840641-J3gZ?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop&amp;rcm=ACoAAAAAKH4BBvA-ZwpVFbaZDTqwLgneEpGsrHQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">Buy European, Sell European, Fund European</a>."&nbsp;</p><p>What's the motive behind these moves away from proprietary tech? Well, in Austria's case, Florian Zinnagl, CISO of the Ministry of Economy, Energy, and Tourism (BMWET), explained, "We carry responsibility for a large amount of sensitive data -- from employees, companies, and citizens. As a public institution, we take this responsibility very seriously. That's why we view it critically to rely on cloud solutions from non-European corporations for processing this information."</p><p><a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/europes-plan-to-ditch-us-tech-giants-is-built-on-open-source-and-its-gaining-steam/">Austria's move and motivation echo similar efforts in Germany, Denmark, and other EU states and agencies</a>. The organizations include the German state of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/german-state-replaces-microsoft-exchange-and-outlook-with-open-source-email/">Schleswig-Holstein, which abandoned Exchange and Outlook for open-source programs</a>. Other agencies that have taken the same path away from Microsoft include the <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/this-european-military-just-ditched-microsoft-for-open-source-libreoffice-heres-why/">Austrian military</a>, <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/why-denmark-is-dumping-microsoft-office-and-windows-for-libreoffice-and-linux/">Danish government</a> organizations, and the <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/this-city-is-dumping-microsoft-office-and-windows-for-onlyoffice-and-linux-heres-why/">French city of Lyon</a>.&nbsp;</p><p><strong>Also: <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/inside-canonicals-plan-to-make-ubuntu-26-04-the-linux-desktop-that-finally-goes-mainstream/">Inside Canonical's plan to make Ubuntu 26.04 the Linux desktop that finally goes mainstream</a></strong></p><p>All of these organizations aim to keep data storage and processing within national or European borders to enhance security, comply with privacy laws such as the <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/gdpr-an-executive-guide-to-what-you-need-to-know/">EU's General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR)</a>, and mitigate risks from potential commercial and foreign government surveillance.&nbsp;</p><p>Open-source software is seen as combining the virtues of faster development and better security, while providing companies and governments with more control, as general manager Thierry Carrez of the <a href="https://openinfra.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">OpenInfra Foundation</a> recently suggested: "Open infrastructure allows nations and organizations to maintain control over their applications, their data, and their destiny while benefiting from global collaboration." &nbsp;</p><!----><p>The US government is worried about this trend. <a href="https://pro.politico.eu/news/207200" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">American diplomats have complained to French and German officials</a> ahead of November's <a href="https://dig.watch/event/summit-on-european-digital-sovereignty" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">Summit on European Digital Sovereignty</a>&nbsp;about the European push for digital sovereignty. This high-level event will bring together EU institutions, member states, public and private sector leaders, and other key stakeholders to advance Europe's digital sovereignty agenda.&nbsp;</p><p>While the US may not like it, with NextCloud's help, BMWET completed its migration in just four months. Although BMWET had already begun adopting Microsoft 365 and <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/microsoft-copilot-is-taking-over-teams-heres-how-ai-will-shape-your-daily-workflow/">Teams</a>&nbsp;before the project's start, the shift was still considered a success. That's because instead of reversing its path, the ministry implemented a hybrid architecture: Nextcloud handles internal collaboration and secure data management, while Teams remains available for external meetings.</p><p>The project emphasized integration with existing workflows, including seamless integration with Outlook email and calendar via Sendent's Outlook app. This approach minimized disruption and ensured user acceptance. However, not all migrations progress so well.&nbsp;</p><p>For example, in Austria, the <a href="https://www.derstandard.de/story/3000000293383/prozentzeichen-statt-bundesadler-wie-die-justiz-ihre-it-umstellt" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">Ministry of Justice decided to replace Office with LibreOffice</a>. Yet the transition has run into trouble. It appears that the move of 20,000 desktops, which was prompted by a desire to reduce spending on Microsoft licenses, has been, as one person reported, an "unprofessional, rushed operation." Some offices are still on Office, others on LibreOffice, and they're running into incompatible document format problems and misfires in e-mail systems.&nbsp;</p><p><strong>Also:&nbsp;<a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/10-open-source-windows-apps-i-cant-live-without-and-theyre-all-free/">10 open-source Windows apps I can't live without - and they're all free</a></strong></p><p>The moral of the story is that any switch from one software suite to another requires careful handling by the IT department and helpdesk staff. Otherwise, you end up with unhappy users.</p><p>That said, BMWET's bold shift to Nextcloud appears to have gone well. This initiative demonstrates that adopting sovereign cloud solutions can be practical, user-friendly, and rapid in the public sector. However, as Austria's Justice Ministry experience has shown, simply shifting to an open-source approach without careful planning can get in the way of getting work done.&nbsp;</p><div id="pinbox-575d8711-4f9c-4bea-8980-f0ae20a04381"><h4>Open Source</h4> <!---->  </div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AI scrapers request commented scripts (233 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://cryptography.dog/blog/AI-scrapers-request-commented-scripts/</link>
            <guid>45773347</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 15:44:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://cryptography.dog/blog/AI-scrapers-request-commented-scripts/">https://cryptography.dog/blog/AI-scrapers-request-commented-scripts/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45773347">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://cryptography.dog/blog/AI-scrapers-request-commented-scripts/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ubuntu Introduces Architecture Variants (134 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lwn.net/Articles/1044383/</link>
            <guid>45772579</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 14:49:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/1044383/">https://lwn.net/Articles/1044383/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45772579">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://lwn.net/Articles/1044383/: AggregateError]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Nix Derivation Madness (174 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fzakaria.com/2025/10/29/nix-derivation-madness</link>
            <guid>45772347</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 14:28:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fzakaria.com/2025/10/29/nix-derivation-madness">https://fzakaria.com/2025/10/29/nix-derivation-madness</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45772347">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><p>I’ve written <em>a bit</em> about <a href="https://nixos.org/">Nix</a> and I still face moments where foundational aspects of the package system confounds and surprises me.</p>

<p>Recently I hit an issue that stumped me as it break some basic comprehension I had on how Nix works. I wanted to produce the build and runtime graph for the Ruby interpreter.</p>

<div><pre><code><span>&gt;</span> nix-shell <span>-p</span> ruby

<span>&gt;</span> which ruby
/nix/store/mp4rpz283gw3abvxyb4lbh4vp9pmayp2-ruby-3.3.9/bin/ruby

<span>&gt;</span> nix-store <span>--query</span> <span>--include-outputs</span> <span>--graph</span> <span>\</span>
  <span>$(</span>nix-store <span>--query</span> <span>--deriver</span> <span>$(</span>which ruby<span>))</span>
error: path <span>'/nix/store/24v9wpp393ib1gllip7ic13aycbi704g-ruby-3.3.9.drv'</span> is not valid

<span>&gt;</span> <span>ls</span> /nix/store/24v9wpp393ib1gllip7ic13aycbi704g-ruby-3.3.9.drv
<span>ls</span>: cannot access <span>'/nix/store/24v9wpp393ib1gllip7ic13aycbi704g-ruby-3.3.9.drv'</span>:
No such file or directory
</code></pre></div>

<p>Huh. 🤔</p>

<p>I have Ruby but I don’t seem to have the derivation, <code>24v9wpp393ib1gllip7ic13aycbi704g</code>, file present on my machine.</p>

<p>No worries, I think I can <code>--realize</code> it and download it from the NixOS cache.</p>

<div><pre><code><span>&gt;</span> nix-store <span>--realize</span> /nix/store/24v9wpp393ib1gllip7ic13aycbi704g-ruby-3.3.9.drv
don<span>'t know how to build these paths:
  /nix/store/24v9wpp393ib1gllip7ic13aycbi704g-ruby-3.3.9.drv
error: cannot build missing derivation '</span>/nix/store/24v9wpp393ib1gllip7ic13aycbi704g-ruby-3.3.9.drv<span>'
</span></code></pre></div>

<p>I guess the NixOS cache doesn’t seem to have it. 🤷</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This was actually perplexing me at this moment. In fact there are <a href="https://discourse.nixos.org/t/how-to-get-a-missing-drv-file-for-a-derivation-from-nixpkgs/2300/1">multiple</a> <a href="https://discourse.nixos.org/t/why-isnt-deriver-and-realize-identity-functions-see-example/47490/1">discourse</a> posts about it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>My mental model however of Nix though is that I must have first evaluated the derivation (drv) in order to determine the output path to even substitute. How could the NixOS cache not have it present?</p>

<p>Is this derivation wrong somehow? Nope. This is the derivation Nix believes that produced this Ruby binary from the <code>sqlite</code> database. 🤨</p>

<div><pre><code><span>&gt;</span> sqlite3 <span>"/nix/var/nix/db/db.sqlite"</span> 
    <span>"select deriver from ValidPaths where path = 
    '/nix/store/mp4rpz283gw3abvxyb4lbh4vp9pmayp2-ruby-3.3.9'"</span>
/nix/store/24v9wpp393ib1gllip7ic13aycbi704g-ruby-3.3.9.drv
</code></pre></div>

<p>What does the binary cache itself say? Even the cache itself thinks this particular derivation, <code>24v9wpp393ib1gllip7ic13aycbi704g</code>, produced this particular Ruby output.</p>

<div><pre><code><span>&gt;</span> curl <span>-s</span> https://cache.nixos.org/mp4rpz283gw3abvxyb4lbh4vp9pmayp2.narinfo |<span>\</span>
  <span>grep </span>Deriver
Deriver: 24v9wpp393ib1gllip7ic13aycbi704g-ruby-3.3.9.drv
</code></pre></div>

<p>What if I try a different command?</p>

<div><pre><code><span>&gt;</span> nix derivation show <span>$(</span>which ruby<span>)</span> | jq <span>-r</span> <span>"keys[0]"</span>
/nix/store/kmx8kkggm5i2r17s6l67v022jz9gc4c5-ruby-3.3.9.drv

<span>&gt;</span> <span>ls</span> /nix/store/kmx8kkggm5i2r17s6l67v022jz9gc4c5-ruby-3.3.9.drv
/nix/store/kmx8kkggm5i2r17s6l67v022jz9gc4c5-ruby-3.3.9.drv
</code></pre></div>

<p>So I seem to have a completely different derivation, <code>kmx8kkggm5i2r17s6l67v022jz9gc4c5</code>, that resulted in the same output which <em>is not</em> what the binary cache announces. WTF? 🫠</p>

<p>Thinking back to a previous post, I remember touching on <a href="https://fzakaria.com/2025/03/28/what-s-in-a-nix-store-path">modulo fixed-output derivations</a>. Is that what’s going on? Let’s investigate from first principles. 🤓</p>

<p>Let’s first create <code>fod.nix</code> which is our <em>fixed-output derivation</em>.</p>

<div><pre><code><span>let</span>
  <span>system</span> <span>=</span> <span>builtins</span><span>.</span><span>currentSystem</span><span>;</span>
<span>in</span> <span>derivation</span> <span>{</span>
  <span>name</span> <span>=</span> <span>"hello-world-fixed"</span><span>;</span>
  <span>builder</span> <span>=</span> <span>"/bin/sh"</span><span>;</span>
  <span>system</span> <span>=</span> <span>system</span><span>;</span>
  <span>args</span> <span>=</span> <span>[</span> <span>"-c"</span> <span>''</span><span>
</span><span>    echo -n "hello world" &gt; "$out"</span><span>
</span><span>  ''</span> <span>];</span>
  <span>outputHashMode</span> <span>=</span> <span>"flat"</span><span>;</span>
  <span>outputHashAlgo</span> <span>=</span> <span>"sha256"</span><span>;</span>
  <span>outputHash</span> <span>=</span> <span>"b94d27b9934d3e08a52e52d7da7dabfac484efe37a5380ee9088f7ace2efcde9"</span><span>;</span>
<span>}</span>
</code></pre></div>

<p>☝️ Since this is a <em>fixed-output derivation</em> (FOD) the produced <code>/nix/store</code> path will not be affected to changes to the derivation beyond the contents of <code>$out</code>.</p>

<div><pre><code><span>&gt;</span> nix-instantiate fod.nix
/nix/store/k2wjpwq43685j6vlvaarrfml4gl4196n-hello-world-fixed.drv

<span>&gt;</span> nix-build fod.nix
/nix/store/ajk19jb8h5h3lmz20yz6wj9vif18lhp1-hello-world-fixed
</code></pre></div>

<p>Now we will create a derivation that uses this FOD.</p>

<div><pre><code><span>{</span> <span>fodDrv</span> <span>?</span> <span>import</span> <span>./fod.nix</span> <span>}:</span>

<span>let</span>
  <span>system</span> <span>=</span> <span>builtins</span><span>.</span><span>currentSystem</span><span>;</span>
<span>in</span>
<span>builtins</span><span>.</span><span>derivation</span> <span>{</span>
  <span>name</span> <span>=</span> <span>"uses-fod"</span><span>;</span>
  <span>inherit</span> <span>system</span><span>;</span>
  <span>builder</span> <span>=</span> <span>"/bin/sh"</span><span>;</span>
  <span>args</span> <span>=</span> <span>[</span> <span>"-c"</span> <span>''</span><span>
</span><span>    echo </span><span>${</span><span>fodDrv</span><span>}</span><span> &gt; $out</span><span>
</span><span>    echo "Good bye world" &gt;&gt; $out</span><span>
</span><span>  ''</span> <span>];</span>
<span>}</span>
</code></pre></div>

<p>The <code>/nix/store</code> for the output for this derivation <em>will change</em> on changes to the derivation <strong>except</strong> if the derivation path for the FOD changes. This is in fact what makes it “modulo” the fixed-output derivations.</p>

<div><pre><code><span>&gt;</span> nix-instantiate uses-fod.nix
/nix/store/85d15y7irq7x4fxv4nc7k1cw2rlfp3ag-uses-fod.drv

<span>&gt;</span> nix-build uses-fod.nix
/nix/store/sd12qjak7rlxhdprj10187f9an787lk3-uses-fod
</code></pre></div>

<p>Let’s test this all out by changing our <code>fod.nix</code> derivation.
Let’s do this by just adding some <em>garbage</em> attribute to the derivation.</p>

<div><pre><code><span>@@ -4,6 +4,7 @@</span>
   name = "hello-world-fixed";
   builder = "/bin/sh";
   system = system;
<span>+  garbage = 123;
</span>   args = [ "-c" ''
     echo -n "hello world" &gt; "$out"
   '' ];
</code></pre></div>

<p>What happens now?</p>

<div><pre><code><span>&gt;</span> nix-instantiate fod.nix
/nix/store/yimff0d4zr4krwx6cvdiqlin0y6vkis0-hello-world-fixed.drv

<span>&gt;</span> nix-build fod.nix
/nix/store/ajk19jb8h5h3lmz20yz6wj9vif18lhp1-hello-world-fixed
</code></pre></div>

<p>The path of the derivation itself, <code>.drv</code>, has changed but the output path <code>ajk19jb8h5h3lmz20yz6wj9vif18lhp1</code> remains consistent.</p>

<p>What about the derivation that leverages it?</p>

<div><pre><code><span>&gt;</span> nix-instantiate uses-fod.nix
/nix/store/85wkdaaq6q08f71xn420v4irll4a8g8v-uses-fod.drv

<span>&gt;</span> nix-build uses-fod.nix
/nix/store/sd12qjak7rlxhdprj10187f9an787lk3-uses-fod
</code></pre></div>

<p>It also got a new derivation path but the output path remained unchanged. 😮</p>

<p>That means changes to <em>fixed-output-derivations</em> didn’t cause new outputs in either derivation <em>but</em> it did create a complete new tree of <code>.drv</code> files. 🤯</p>

<p>That means in <a href="https://github.com/NixOS/nixpkgs">nixpkgs</a> changes to <em>fixed-output</em> derivations can cause them to have new store paths for their <code>.drv</code> but result in dependent derivations to have the same output path. If the output path had already been stored in the NixOS cache, then we lose the link between the new <code>.drv</code> and this output path. 💥</p>

<!--

digraph NixDerivationMadness {

    // Global Styling for consistency
    node [shape=box, style="filled"];

    // Subgraph for the original, cached state (V1)
    subgraph cluster_v1 {
        label = "1: Initial Build & Cache Upload";
        bgcolor = "#E6F4EA"; // Light Green Background

        // V1 Nodes
        FOD_V1 [label="FOD drv V1\n(k2wjpwq43685j6vlvaarrfml4gl4196n-hello-world-fixed.drv)", fillcolor="#B3E0C9"];
        USES_FOD_V1 [label="Uses-FOD Drv V1\n(85d15y7irq7x4fxv4nc7k1cw2rlfp3ag-uses-fod.drv)", fillcolor="#80CBC4"];
        OUTPUT [label="Uses-FOD Output\n(sd12qjak7rlxhdprj10187f9an787lk3-uses-fod)", fillcolor="#FFD54F", color=black];
        CACHE [label="Nix Cache", shape=cylinder, fillcolor="#90CAF9"];

        // V1 Edges
        FOD_V1 -> USES_FOD_V1 [label="Input"];
        USES_FOD_V1 -> OUTPUT [label="Produces output path"];
        OUTPUT -> CACHE [label="Output cached", penwidth=1];
    }

    // Subgraph for the changed state (V2)
    subgraph cluster_v2 {
        label = "2: FOD Changed (i.e. garbage added)";
        bgcolor = "#FCE4EC"; // Light Pink/Red Background

        // V2 Nodes
        FOD_V2 [label="FOD drv V2\n(yimff0d4zr4krwx6cvdiqlin0y6vkis0-hello-world-fixed.drv)", fillcolor="#F48FB1"];
        USES_FOD_V2 [label="Uses-FOD Drv V2\n(85wkdaaq6q08f71xn420v4irll4a8g8v-uses-fod.drv)", fillcolor="#E57373"];

        // V2 Edges
        FOD_V2 -> USES_FOD_V2 [label="Input"];
        USES_FOD_V2 -> OUTPUT [label="Produces SAME Output Hash", style=bold, color=darkgreen];
    }
    
    // Connection between subgraphs
    // The link from the new derivation (V2) to the existing cache entry is MISSING.
    USES_FOD_V2 -> CACHE [label="Missing Cache Mapping for V2", color=red, style=dashed, penwidth=2, arrowhead=cross];
}

 -->
<p><img src="https://fzakaria.com/assets/images/derivation_madness.svg" alt="Derivation graphic"></p>

<p>The amount of churn that we are creating in derivations was unbeknownst to me.</p>

<p>It can get even weirder! This example came from <a href="https://github.com/ericson2314">@ericson2314</a>.</p>

<p>We will duplicate the <code>fod.nix</code> to another file <code>fod2.nix</code> whose only difference is the value of the garbage.</p>

<div><pre><code><span>@@ -4,7 +4,7 @@</span>
   name = "hello-world-fixed";
   builder = "/bin/sh";
   system = system;
<span>-  garbage = 123;
</span><span>+  garbage = 124;
</span>   args = [ "-c" ''
     echo -n "hello world" &gt; "$out"
   '' ];
</code></pre></div>

<p>Let’s now use both of these in our derivation.</p>

<div><pre><code><span>{</span> <span>fodDrv</span> <span>?</span> <span>import</span> <span>./fod.nix</span><span>,</span>
  <span>fod2Drv</span> <span>?</span> <span>import</span> <span>./fod2.nix</span>
<span>}:</span>
<span>let</span>
  <span>system</span> <span>=</span> <span>builtins</span><span>.</span><span>currentSystem</span><span>;</span>
<span>in</span>
<span>builtins</span><span>.</span><span>derivation</span> <span>{</span>
  <span>name</span> <span>=</span> <span>"uses-fod"</span><span>;</span>
  <span>inherit</span> <span>system</span><span>;</span>
  <span>builder</span> <span>=</span> <span>"/bin/sh"</span><span>;</span>
  <span>args</span> <span>=</span> <span>[</span> <span>"-c"</span> <span>''</span><span>
</span><span>    echo </span><span>${</span><span>fodDrv</span><span>}</span><span> &gt; $out</span><span>
</span><span>    echo </span><span>${</span><span>fod2Drv</span><span>}</span><span> &gt;&gt; $out</span><span>
</span><span>    echo "Good bye world" &gt;&gt; $out</span><span>
</span><span>  ''</span> <span>];</span>
<span>}</span>
</code></pre></div>

<p>We can now instantiate and build this as normal.</p>

<div><pre><code><span>&gt;</span> nix-instantiate uses-fod.nix
/nix/store/z6nr2k2hy982fiynyjkvq8dliwbxklwf-uses-fod.drv

<span>&gt;</span> nix-build uses-fod.nix
/nix/store/211nlyx2ga7mh5fdk76aggb04y1wsgkj-uses-fod
</code></pre></div>

<p>What is weird about that?</p>

<p>Well, let’s take the JSON representation of the derivation and remove one of the inputs.</p>

<div><pre><code><span>&gt;</span> nix derivation show <span>\</span>
    /nix/store/z6nr2k2hy982fiynyjkvq8dliwbxklwf-uses-fod.drv <span>\</span>
    jq <span>'values[].inputDrvs | keys[]'</span>
<span>"/nix/store/6p93r6x0bwyd8gngf5n4r432n6l380ry-hello-world-fixed.drv"</span>
<span>"/nix/store/yimff0d4zr4krwx6cvdiqlin0y6vkis0-hello-world-fixed.drv"</span>
</code></pre></div>

<p>We can do this because although there are two input derivations, we know they both produce the same output!</p>

<div><pre><code><span>@@ -12,12 +12,6 @@</span>
       "system": "x86_64-linux"
     },
     "inputDrvs": {
<span>-      "/nix/store/6p93r6x0bwyd8gngf5n4r432n6l380ry-hello-world-fixed.drv": {
-        "dynamicOutputs": {},
-        "outputs": [
-          "out"
-        ]
-      },
</span>       "/nix/store/yimff0d4zr4krwx6cvdiqlin0y6vkis0-hello-world-fixed.drv": {
         "dynamicOutputs": {},
         "outputs": [
</code></pre></div>

<p>Let’s load this modified derivation back into our <code>/nix/store</code> and build it again!</p>

<div><pre><code><span>&gt;</span> nix derivation add &lt; derivation.json
/nix/store/s4qrdkq3a85gxmlpiay334vd1ndg8hm1-uses-fod.drv

<span>&gt;</span> nix-build /nix/store/s4qrdkq3a85gxmlpiay334vd1ndg8hm1-uses-fod.drv
/nix/store/211nlyx2ga7mh5fdk76aggb04y1wsgkj-uses-fod
</code></pre></div>

<p>We got the same output <code>211nlyx2ga7mh5fdk76aggb04y1wsgkj</code>. Not only do we have a <code>1:N</code> trait for our output paths to derivations but we can also take certain derivations and completely change them by removing inputs and still get the same output! 😹</p>

<p>The road to Nix enlightenment is no joke and full of dragons.</p>

</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Nim 2.2.6 (155 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nim-lang.org//blog/2025/10/31/nim-226.html</link>
            <guid>45772224</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 14:15:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nim-lang.org//blog/2025/10/31/nim-226.html">https://nim-lang.org//blog/2025/10/31/nim-226.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45772224">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          
          <h3>
            <span>
              
              31 October 2025
            </span>
            
            <span>
              
              The Nim Team
            </span>
            
          </h3>
          <p>The Nim Team is happy to announce version 2.2.6, the third patch release for our stable release, Nim 2.2.</p>

<p>It comes six months after the 2.2.4 release and it contains <a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/compare/v2.2.4...v2.2.6">141 commits</a>, bringing bugfixes and improvements.</p>

<p>If you’re still on Nim 1.6, take a look at the <a href="https://nim-lang.org/blog/2023/08/01/nim-v20-released.html">version 2.0 release article</a> to see all the features you’re missing.
If you’ve been using Nim 2.0, the <a href="https://nim-lang.org/blog/2024/10/02/nim-220-2010.html">version 2.2 release article</a> shows the improvements available in Nim 2.2.</p>

<p>The Nim 2.2.6 changelog is available <a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/blob/v2.2.6/changelog.md">here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="highlights">Highlights</h2>

<p>Exception handling combined with Nim’s <code>async</code> is more stable than ever before
as the underlying closure iterator transformation has been rewritten.</p>

<p>The compiler is now smart enough to produce a move operation for <code>return obj.field</code>.
Previously it performed a copy.
Expect your code to run slightly faster due to this and other minor performance improvements.</p>

<h2 id="installing-nim-226">Installing Nim 2.2.6</h2>

<p>Check out if the package manager of your OS already ships version 2.2.6 or
install it as described <a href="https://nim-lang.org/install.html">here</a>.</p>

<p>If you have installed a previous version of Nim using <code>choosenim</code>,
getting Nim 2.2.6 is as easy as:</p>

<div><pre><code><span>$ </span>choosenim update self
<span>$ </span>choosenim update stable
</code></pre>
</div>

<p><strong>NOTE:</strong> We recommend you to install and use the latest version of <code>choosenim</code>, v.0.8.16, available in <a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/choosenim">our choosenim repo</a>.</p>

<p>Alternatively, you can download Nim 2.2.6 from
<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/nightlies/releases/tag/2025-10-31-version-2-2-ab00c56904e3126ad826bb520d243513a139436a">our nightlies builds</a>.</p>

<h2 id="bugfixes">Bugfixes</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Fixed “<code>=destroy</code> for non-var failed to compile when JS”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/24914">#24914</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “<code><span>{</span><span>.push</span><span> </span><span>raises:</span><span> </span><span>[].</span><span>}</span></code> doesn’t respect lexical scoping”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/23355">#23355</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Pragma block disabling warning has effect beyond block”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/21975">#21975</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “missing <code>&lt;</code> (less than), <code>cmp</code> for <code>cstring</code>”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/24941">#24941</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “[GC] Illegal storage access when collecting cycle”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/4851">#4851</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Globals in proc with static params end up being re-initialized”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/24940">#24940</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Constructor to global variable in converter generates illegal c code”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/4594">#4594</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Compile-time regression from v2.2.4 to <code>version-2-2</code>/<code>devel</code> with <code>global</code> variable with <code>unhandled exception: iterators.nim(254, 11) len(a) == L the length of the seq changed while iterating over it [AssertionDefect]</code>”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/24981">#24981</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “SIGSEGV when raising <code>Defect</code>/doAssert”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/24974">#24974</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Crash on marking destroy hook as .error”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/24996">#24996</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “<code>hasCustomPragma</code> stops working after typedesc is copied”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/23564">#23564</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Asyncnet accept leaks socket on SSL error; Regression in devel”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25023">#25023</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “SIGSEGV in closure iterator with try/except not at top level”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/21235">#21235</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Regression from v2.2.4 to <code>version-2-2</code>/<code>devel</code> with closure iterator”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25038">#25038</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “fixes #24997; {.global.} variable in recursive function”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25016">#25016</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “concept param passed to varargs causes <code>internal error: genTypeInfo(tyUserTypeClassInst)</code> when  JS backend”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25043">#25043</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Bad order of destruction”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/24719">#24719</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Floats are not range checked”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/7179">#7179</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “typo in docs”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25084">#25084</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Regression from Nim v2.2.2 to v2.2.4/<code>version-2-2</code>/devel in <code>nim cpp</code> with compatible types not keeping L-valueness”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25109">#25109</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “<code>FieldDefect</code> compiler crash when comparing pointers at compile time”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25066">#25066</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Slow compilation due to <code>vmgen.sameConstant</code> and memory allocations”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25114">#25114</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “<code>unhandled exception: field 'sym' is not accessible for type 'TNode' using 'kind = nkEmpty' [FieldDefect]</code> with iterator-loop”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25121">#25121</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “<code>strutils.formatSize</code> returns wrong values from large values close to int64.high”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25125">#25125</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Dereferencing result of <code>cast</code> in single expression triggers unnecessary copy”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/24093">#24093</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “<code>internal error: '=destroy' operator not found for type NimNode</code> returning <code>NimNode</code>”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25120">#25120</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “<code>requiresInit</code> not checked for <code>result</code> if it has been used (2.2 regression)”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25117">#25117</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “<code>filterIt</code> wrongly results in rvalue”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25078">#25078</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “<code>@</code> extremely slow for trivial types”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25063">#25063</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “withValue for immut tab wrong chk cond”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25162">#25162</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Invalid C codegen <code>refc</code> with generic types containing gc memory”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/24844">#24844</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “SinglyLinkedList.remove broken / AssertionDefect”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25173">#25173</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “<code>error: ‘T2_’ undeclared</code> and <code>error: incompatible types when assigning to type ‘void *’</code>”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/24361">#24361</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Noncopyable base type ignored”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/24760">#24760</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “<code>lent string</code> generic field isn’t preserving its value”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25127">#25127</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “cannot return <code>lent</code> expression from conditionals like <code>case</code>”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/23949">#23949</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “<code>Error: internal error: proc has no result symbol</code>”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/21476">#21476</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Invalid codegen / dangling pointer for openArray escaping from <code>block</code>”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/24261">#24261</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “lib/system/iterators.nim(250, 14) Error: internal error: genArrayLen()”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25167">#25167</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “<code>Error: unhandled exception: field 'sym' is not accessible for type 'TNode'</code>”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/21138">#21138</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “<code>error: ‘pthread_mutex_t’ has no member named ‘abi’</code> in refc with <code>reset</code>/<code><span>{</span><span>.exportc.</span><span>}</span></code>”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25205">#25205</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Uninitialized variable usage in <code>resize__system_u...</code> in <code>@psystem.nim.c</code> in ORC”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25204">#25204</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “VM error when passing object field ref to <code>proc(var T): var T</code>”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25210">#25210</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Closure environement wrongly marked as cyclic (orc)”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25048">#25048</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Infinite loop with anonymous iterator”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25046">#25046</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “JS: <code>cast[char](i)</code> for <code>i &gt; 255</code> not truncate”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25222">#25222</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “VM issue with globals and assignments”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25208">#25208</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Case object from <code>compileTime</code> proc unable to be passed as <code>static</code> param”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25123">#25123</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “VM <code>repr</code> raises RangeDefect for long string under refc”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25226">#25226</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Broken assignment of union with bool inside variant object”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25236">#25236</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “deques: Deque items behavior is not the same on 2.0.16 and 2.2.0”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25240">#25240</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “<code>nim doc</code> uses doc comment from private field for public field”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25027">#25027</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Compiler internal error <code>compiler/vmgen.nim(1771, 23)</code> with <code>static</code> overload”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25008">#25008</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixed “Wrong exception raised wrapped in finally in closure iterator; Regression in devel/version-2-2”
(<a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/issues/25202">#25202</a>)</li>
</ul>

<p>The complete list of changes is available <a href="https://github.com/nim-lang/Nim/compare/v2.2.4...v2.2.6">here</a>.</p>

        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Immutable releases are now generally available on GitHub (147 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.blog/changelog/2025-10-28-immutable-releases-are-now-generally-available/</link>
            <guid>45772064</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 13:59:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.blog/changelog/2025-10-28-immutable-releases-are-now-generally-available/">https://github.blog/changelog/2025-10-28-immutable-releases-are-now-generally-available/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45772064">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
				
<p>GitHub releases now support immutability, adding a new layer of supply chain security. With immutable releases, assets and tags are protected from tampering after publication, so the software you publish—and your users consume—remains secure and trustworthy.</p>
<h3 id="about-immutable-releases"><a href="#about-immutable-releases">About immutable releases</a></h3>
<p>Immutable releases offer:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Immutable assets</strong>: Once you publish a release as immutable, its assets can’t be added, modified, or deleted. This helps protect distributed artifacts from supply chain attacks.</li>
<li><strong>Tag protection</strong>: Tags for new immutable releases are protected and can’t be deleted or moved.</li>
<li><strong>Release attestations</strong>: Immutable releases receive signed attestations so you can easily verify the authenticity and integrity of assets, both on GitHub and in external environments.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="how-to-enable-immutable-releases"><a href="#how-to-enable-immutable-releases">How to enable immutable releases</a></h3>
<p>You can enable immutable releases at the repository or organization level in your settings. Once enabled:</p>
<ul>
<li>All new releases are immutable (i.e., assets are locked and tags are protected).</li>
<li>Existing releases remain mutable unless you republish them.</li>
</ul>
<p>Disabling immutability doesn’t affect releases created while it was enabled. They remain immutable.</p>
<h3 id="release-attestations-and-verification"><a href="#release-attestations-and-verification">Release attestations and verification</a></h3>
<p>Release attestations let you verify that an artifact is authentic and unchanged, even outside GitHub. Attestations use the <a href="https://docs.sigstore.dev/about/bundle/">Sigstore bundle format</a>, so you can easily verify releases and assets using the GitHub CLI or integrate with any Sigstore-compatible tooling to automate policy enforcement in your CI/CD pipelines. For instructions on how to verify the integrity of a release, see <a href="https://docs.github.com/code-security/supply-chain-security/understanding-your-software-supply-chain/verifying-the-integrity-of-a-release?tool=cli?utm_source=changelog-docs-immutable-releases&amp;utm_medium=changelog&amp;utm_campaign=universe25">our docs on verifying the integrity of a release</a>.</p>
<p>We’d love your feedback. Share your thoughts and questions on the <a href="https://gh.io/immutable-releases-ga?utm_source=changelog-community-immutable-releases&amp;utm_medium=changelog&amp;utm_campaign=universe25">GitHub Community</a>.</p>
<p>For more information, see our <a href="https://docs.github.com/code-security/supply-chain-security/understanding-your-software-supply-chain/immutable-releases?utm_source=changelog-docs-immutable-releases&amp;utm_medium=changelog&amp;utm_campaign=universe25">immutable releases documentation</a>.</p>

			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Ask HN: Who uses open LLMs and coding assistants locally? Share setup and laptop (286 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45771870</link>
            <guid>45771870</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 13:39:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45771870">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45771870: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Sustainable memristors from shiitake mycelium for high-frequency bioelectronics (135 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0328965</link>
            <guid>45771796</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 13:32:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0328965">https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0328965</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45771796">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main-content">

<header>





<ul id="almSignposts">
  <li id="loadingMetrics">
    <p>Loading metrics</p>
  </li>
</ul>







    <div>
  <p id="licenseShort">Open Access</p>
  <p id="peerReviewed">Peer-reviewed</p>

<p id="artType">Research Article</p>


</div>
    <div>



<div>
  

<ul data-js-tooltip="tooltip_container" id="author-list">



<li data-js-tooltip="tooltip_trigger">
       
</li>

<li data-js-tooltip="tooltip_trigger">
   <a data-author-id="1">
Qudsia Tahmina,</a>    
</li>

<li data-js-tooltip="tooltip_trigger">
   <a data-author-id="2">
Ruben Petreaca,</a>    
</li>

<li data-js-tooltip="tooltip_trigger">
   <a data-author-id="3">
John Simonis,</a>    
</li>

<li data-js-tooltip="tooltip_trigger">
   <a data-author-id="4">
Justin Hill</a>    
</li>

</ul>


</div>


<div id="floatTitleTop" data-js-floater="title_author" role="presentation">
    <div>
      <h2><!--?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?-->Sustainable memristors from shiitake mycelium for high-frequency bioelectronics</h2>

<ul id="floatAuthorList" data-js-floater="floated_authors">

  <li data-float-index="1">John LaRocco,&nbsp;

  </li>
  <li data-float-index="2">Qudsia Tahmina,&nbsp;

  </li>
  <li data-float-index="3">Ruben Petreaca,&nbsp;

  </li>
  <li data-float-index="4">John Simonis,&nbsp;

  </li>
  <li data-float-index="5">Justin Hill

  </li>

</ul>



    </div>
    <div id="titleTopCloser">
      <p><img src="https://journals.plos.org/resource/img/logo-plos-full-color.svg" alt="PLOS"></p><p>x</p>
    </div>
  </div>

      <ul>
        <li id="artPubDate">Published: October 10, 2025</li>
        <li id="artDoi">
<a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0328965">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0328965</a>
        </li>
        <li></li>
      </ul>

    </div>
  
</header>
  <div>






<div id="figure-carousel-section">
  <h2>Figures</h2>

  
</div>





        <div id="artText">
          



<div xmlns:plos="http://plos.org"><h2>Abstract</h2><div><p>Neuromorphic computing, inspired by the structure of the brain, offers advantages in parallel processing, memory storage, and energy efficiency. However, current semiconductor-based neuromorphic chips require rare-earth materials and costly fabrication processes, whereas neural organoids need complex bioreactor maintenance. In this study, we explored shiitake (<em><em>Lentinula edodes</em></em>) fungi as a robust, sustainable alternative, exploiting its adaptive electrical signaling, which is akin to neuronal spiking. We demonstrate fungal computing via mycelial networks interfaced with electrodes, showing that fungal memristors can be grown, trained, and preserved through dehydration, retaining functionality at frequencies up to 5.85 kHz, with an accuracy of 90 ± 1%. Notably, shiitake has exhibited radiation resistance, suggesting its viability for aerospace applications. Our findings show that fungal computers can provide scalable, eco-friendly platforms for neuromorphic tasks, bridging bioelectronics and unconventional computing.</p>
</div></div>


<div xmlns:plos="http://plos.org"><p><strong>Citation: </strong>LaRocco J, Tahmina Q, Petreaca R, Simonis J, Hill J (2025) Sustainable memristors from shiitake mycelium for high-frequency bioelectronics. PLoS One 20(10):
           e0328965.
        
        https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0328965</p><p><strong>Editor: </strong>Ye Zhou, Shenzhen University, HONG KONG</p><p><strong>Received: </strong>July 8, 2025; <strong>Accepted: </strong>September 25, 2025; <strong>Published: </strong> October 10, 2025</p><p><strong>Copyright: </strong> © 2025 LaRocco et al. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</a>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</p><p><strong>Data Availability: </strong>The data is available at this repository: <a href="https://github.com/javeharron/abhothData">https://github.com/javeharron/abhothData</a>.</p><p><strong>Funding: </strong>Authors J.S. and J.H. were supported by Honda Research Institute (grant AWD-118684). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p><p><strong>Competing interests: </strong> The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></div>





<div xmlns:plos="http://plos.org" id="section1"><h2>Background</h2>
<div id="section1"><h3>Overview</h3>
<p>The development of neuromorphic hardware relies on memristive devices capable of emulating synaptic behavior, with potential applications in energy-efficient computing and artificial intelligence<sup>1</sup>. Recent work has explored natural, biodegradable substrates as sustainable alternatives to conventional inorganic memristors [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref001">1</a>]. In this study, we investigated the potential of the edible fungus <em><em>Lentinula edodes</em></em> (shiitake mushroom) as a platform for memristor fabrication. By examining the electrical response of mushroom-derived materials under repeated voltage cycling, we explored stable memristive switching behavior, retention, and endurance. Shiitake-based devices not only demonstrate reproducible memory effects, but also highlight the potential for scalable, low-cost, and environmentally friendly neuromorphic components.</p>
</div>

<div id="section2"><h3>Memristors</h3>
<p>Memristor devices offer substantial advantages in robotic, industrial, and transport applications due to their unique electrical properties and ability to mimic neural functions. They can enhance various control systems, facilitate efficient information processing, and ultimately improve the overall performance of autonomous systems.</p>
<p>One of the key strengths of memristors is their capacity for efficient and self-adaptive in situ learning, which is critical for applications in robotics and autonomous vehicles. In memristor-based neural networks, the devices can adjust their resistance based on previous inputs, allowing for a form of analog learning that closely resembles the synaptic behavior in biological systems [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref001">1</a>]. This capability enables robots and autonomous vehicles to learn from their environment and adapt in real time, enhancing their ability to navigate complex situations effectively. It has been found that such systems can achieve low-latency responses, which are essential for high-speed decision-making in dynamic environments [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref002">2</a>].</p>
<p>Memristors also have the advantage of integrating memory and processing capabilities into a single device, enabling a simplified architecture for autonomous control systems [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref003">3</a>]. For instance, in autonomous vehicles, trajectory-tracking and path-following tasks can be performed using memristor-based controllers that allow for rapid calculations and real-time adjustments to control variables [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref004">4</a>]. This integration, especially with parallelization, helps to address the challenges posed by separate memory and processing units, which can lead to delays and increased power consumption in traditional control systems [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref004">4</a>].</p>
<p>Additionally, the resilience of memristor devices against environmental changes, and their ability to operate under varying conditions, make them particularly suitable for autonomous applications, such as spacecraft electronics or vehicles operating in unpredictable road environments [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref004">4</a>]. This is complemented by the precision in control that memristor-based systems can offer, which is significant for maintaining stability and performance while following desired trajectories [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref005">5</a>].</p>
<p>Moreover, the low power consumption of memristors is particularly beneficial in robotics and autonomous vehicles, where energy efficiency is paramount. Hybrid analog–digital memristor systems can minimize power usage during processing without sacrificing responsiveness, which can prolong operational times by reducing the frequency at which recharging or battery replacement is required, enhancing the feasibility of deploying such systems in mobile applications [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref002">2</a>].</p>
<p>Ultimately, the potential of memristors to emulate human-like decision-making and learning processes could be exploited to endow robotic systems and autonomous vehicles with functionalities not found in conventional control systems. The ability of memristors to perform complex computations efficiently, learn adaptively, and integrate both memory and processing into a unified approach make them a cornerstone technology for the future development of intelligent autonomous systems. However, the production of memristors often requires rare-earth minerals and expensive semiconductor foundries.</p>
</div>

<div id="section3"><h3>Fungal electronics</h3>
<p>Fungi possess innate abilities to adapt to various environmental conditions and efficiently process information through their interconnected network of hyphae. These characteristics make fungi an ideal candidate for developing sustainable computing systems from. Our aim was to design and implement a novel fungal memristor-based computing architecture that could significantly reduce energy consumption and minimize electronic waste. We approached this using substantially simpler bioreactors and nutrient cultures than those required for conventional neurons and neural organoids. The unique advantages of fungal memristors stem from the biological properties of fungal materials, which distinguish them from typical inorganic or polymer alternatives [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref006">6</a>,<a href="#pone.0328965.ref007">7</a>].</p>
<p>First, one of the main benefits of fungal memristors is their environmentally sustainable and biodegradable nature. Conventional memristors often contain transition metal oxides or silicon-based structures, the production or disposal of which can pose environmental challenges [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref006">6</a>,<a href="#pone.0328965.ref007">7</a>]. By contrast, fungal materials are derived from organic biomass, making them both sustainable and significantly less harmful to the environment. This aligns with increasing efforts toward developing greener electronic materials, as highlighted in previous work emphasizing the importance of sustainability in technology development [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref008">8</a>].</p>
<p>Second, fungal memristors exhibit remarkable adaptability in their electrical properties. The structural composition of fungal materials often allows for a range of conductive pathways that can form dynamically under the influence of electrical stimuli, similar to the conductive filaments formed in conventional memristors [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref009">9</a>,<a href="#pone.0328965.ref010">10</a>]. This adaptability can lead to enhanced performance in neuromorphic applications through the facilitation of variable resistance states that mimic synaptic behaviors more closely than traditional memristive materials, which often have static crystalline structures that can lead to variability problems or performance limitations at the nanoscale [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref011">11</a>].</p>
<p>Furthermore, fungal memristors may consume less power than traditional materials due to their unique electrochemical properties. It has been claimed that some organic materials, including those derived from fungi, can operate effectively at lower voltages while maintaining stable switching characteristics––a trait that is crucial for developing energy-efficient devices for portable electronics and Internet of Things applications [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref012">12</a>]. This can significantly extend battery life and reduce energy costs in processing and memory applications, which have become focal points in the research into neuromorphic systems [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref013">13</a>].</p>
<p>Finally, the natural composition and multicellularity of fungal materials can lead to more naturalistic models for neural networks. Because these materials are subject to biological processes, they may inherently incorporate characteristics that resemble biological neuronal networks, including plasticity and memory capabilities that could evolve with usage. This biological mimicry could strengthen the development of more advanced artificial neural networks, enabling applications such as adaptive learning systems and intelligent sensor networks [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref014">14</a>].</p>
</div>

<div id="section4"><h3>Fungus types</h3>
<p>The potential use of common food mushrooms, such as shiitake and button mushrooms (<em><em>Agaricus bisporus</em></em>), as organic memristors is an emerging area of research that exploits the unique properties of these fungi [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref006">6</a>,<a href="#pone.0328965.ref007">7</a>,<a href="#pone.0328965.ref013">13</a>]. Memristors, which are non-volatile memory devices that retain information even without power, can benefit from the porous structures and electrical properties of the organic materials derived from mushrooms.</p>
<p>Shiitake mushrooms have been shown to possess a hierarchically porous carbon structure when activated. This porous structure can enhance the electrochemical performance of devices, making them suitable candidates for use in energy storage systems, including supercapacitors and, potentially, memristors [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref015">15</a>]. Highly conductive carbon materials have been created from shiitake, suggesting that these materials could be engineered to exhibit memristive behavior [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref016">16</a>]. Shiitake-derived carbon is a sustainable alternative to traditional materials and can enhance the performance of electronic devices due to its unique structural properties.</p>
<p>Button mushrooms have also shown significant potential in this context. Research has indicated that their porosity can be exploited to create materials with large surface areas, which are essential for the development of efficient electronic components [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref017">17</a>]. The synthesis of carbon composites from button mushrooms has been explored, revealing their ability to function effectively in energy storage applications [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref017">17</a>]. Furthermore, the integration of button mushrooms into electronic systems has been investigated, demonstrating their potential as substrates for electronic devices [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref018">18</a>].</p>
<p>In addition to their structural properties, the unique biological characteristics of fungi, including their ability to interact with various chemical compounds, can be harnessed to develop novel sensing technologies. For instance, electronic noses have been developed that use mushroom extracts to detect volatile compounds. These could be adapted for use in electronic devices that require environmental-sensing capabilities [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref019">19</a>,<a href="#pone.0328965.ref020">20</a>]. This intersection of biology and electronics opens new avenues for creating multifunctional devices that incorporate the sensory capabilities of mushrooms.</p>
</div>

<div id="section5"><h3>Radiation, resistance, and resilience</h3>
<p>The radiation resistance of shiitake mushrooms has been studied primarily in terms of their ability to withstand and possibly derive benefits from exposure to ionizing radiation. This resistance can be attributed to several biochemical and physiological attributes. A possible factor is lentinan, a polysaccharide found in the cell walls of shiitake. Lentinan provides structural integrity and exhibits immunomodulatory effects that may enhance the mushroom’s ability to respond to environmental stresses, including radiation exposure. Although some research has suggested that lentinan possesses properties that may help mitigate oxidative stress [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref021">21</a>], there have been limited studies directly linking lentinan to radiation resistance in shiitake mushrooms.</p>
<p>Shiitake mushrooms have also shown a notable ability to adapt to their environmental conditions, including variable radiation levels. Studies involving fungi in space research have indicated that certain taxa can enhance their survival through morphological changes or increased melanin production in response to radiation [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref022">22</a>]. This radiation resistance implies a suitability of fungal electronics for aerospace applications, where cosmic rays and ambient radiation can interfere with conventional electronics. Fungi’s physical flexibility and low energy requirements would also be advantageous relative to conventional solutions [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref018">18</a>,<a href="#pone.0328965.ref019">19</a>]. These studies have not specifically addressed shiitake, but the general adaptability observed in fungi suggests that this species could respond similarly to such conditions.</p>
<p>Another example of the resilience of shiitake mushrooms is their ability to maintain their nutritional and bioactive qualities after irradiation. For example, they retain essential nutrients and bioactive compounds even after exposure to ultraviolet radiation [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref023">23</a>]. The high content of ergosterol, a precursor to vitamin D, found in shiitake mushrooms, reinforces their potential for beneficial outcomes following exposure to radiation because this compound can be converted into vitamin D<sub>2</sub> when subjected to ultraviolet light [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref024">24</a>].</p>
<p>Lastly, shiitake mushrooms could be considered in the development of dietary supplements or functional foods that could serve a broader purpose in radioprotection. Their multirole efficacy as a food source and electrical component emphasizes a sustainable approach to utilizing biological entities that can withstand environmental stresses, including radiation. This is especially relevant in aerospace and exploration contexts, where promoting health in astronauts could reduce the risks associated with their increased radiation exposure during missions [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref022">22</a>]. Also, shiitake mushrooms can withstand environmental stresses, including radiation, while remaining safe for human consumption.</p>
<p>In summary, the radiation resistance of shiitake mushrooms is linked to the presence of protective compounds, such as lentinan, and their ability to adapt morphologically. These factors have contributed to our understanding of their survival strategies and are suggestive of potential applications in areas where radiation exposure is a significant concern, such as aerospace and radiation sensing. By culturing and evaluating the memristive properties of shiitake mushrooms, we can determine their suitability for use as sustainable, low-cost bioelectronics.</p>
</div>
</div>

<div xmlns:plos="http://plos.org" id="section2"><h2>Methods</h2>
<div id="section1"><h3>Summary</h3>
<p>Testing the memristive behavior of shiitake mycelium involved several steps, the first being culturing the fungi, and then preparing the samples by drying and rehydrating them. Following this, the most successfully cultivated samples were electrically characterized using a test circuit. Additionally, a special circuit was constructed for further evaluating the feasibility of using mycelium for violate memory.</p>
</div>

<div id="section2"><h3>Hyphal cultivation</h3>
<p>Due to the financial and environmental constraints of this project, all four evaluated memristors fabricated for our experiments were composed exclusively of low-cost, organic materials. Based on previous research, we identified materials such as biocompatible composites [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref025">25</a>,<a href="#pone.0328965.ref026">26</a>] as viable candidates for device construction and programming due to their biodegradability and compatibility with fungal growth.</p>
<p>The initial phase of experimentation focused on the cultivation of fungal hyphae in the selected organic growth media. Nine samples were prepared in standard polycarbonate Petri dishes. The growth conditions were carefully maintained to promote optimal fungal development, with a controlled temperature range of 20–22°C, a relative humidity of 70%, and mixed light exposure to replicate natural terrestrial conditions. The nutrient substrate consisted of a mixture of farro seed, wheat germ, and hay, selected for their organic compositions and ability to support robust fungal growth. Each sample was inoculated with spores or mycelial plugs of shiitake.</p>
<p>The samples (e.g., see <a href="#pone-0328965-g001">Fig 1</a>) were observed and documented biweekly to track their growth consistency and morphological development. Observations including hyphal density, surface coverage, and color changes were recorded in a structured laboratory logbook. In addition to these visual inspections, a brief scratch test was performed to track the progress of the mycelium throughout the substrate. The log included timestamps and qualitative notes, enabling consistent comparison across samples and time points.</p>
</div>

<div id="section3"><h3>Drying and rehydration process</h3>
<p>Once full hyphal coverage and structural maturation were achieved (i.e., when the Petri dish was covered), the samples were transitioned to the drying phase. The Petri dishes were left in a well-ventilated area under direct sunlight at room temperature for approximately seven days to ensure uniform dehydration. The samples were rotated periodically to avoid uneven hardening. As previously reported, this process transformed the fungal matrix into a rigid, disk-like structure while retaining its overall shape and connectivity [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref026">26</a>,<a href="#pone.0328965.ref027">27</a>].</p>
<p>Prior to testing, the samples were rehydrated using a fine mist of aerosolized deionized water. The rehydration was conducted using a standard commercial spray bottle, held within a distance of 10 cm from each sample. This brief rehydration step restored the required level of conductivity without introducing bulk moisture that could have altered their mechanical integrity.</p>
</div>

<div id="section4"><h3>Electrical characterization</h3>
<p>Electrical testing protocols were designed based on theoretical memristors [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref006">6</a>,<a href="#pone.0328965.ref007">7</a>]. An alternating current was applied to each sample, and the corresponding current–voltage (I–V) characteristics were measured using a digital oscilloscope. As established in previous works, the test setup used a voltage divider to model multiple memristors in the same circuit [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref006">6</a>,<a href="#pone.0328965.ref007">7</a>].</p>
<p>To extract accurate current values, a known shunt resistor was placed in series with each sample. As shown in <a href="#pone-0328965-g002">Fig 2</a>, voltage readings were captured across both the sample and the resistor, with Channel 1 of the oscilloscope measuring the input voltage and Channel 2 capturing the voltage drop across the shunt resistor. The current values were then calculated using Kirchhoff’s current law, allowing derivation of the I–V characteristics from the voltage differentials. All waveform data were exported in comma-separated values (CSV) format for subsequent digital analysis and visualization.</p>
<p>To thoroughly investigate the memristive behavior of the four samples using mycelium coverage density, voltage sweeps were conducted using both square and sinusoidal waveforms. The square waves were employed to detect sharp threshold-based resistance changes, whereas the sinusoidal inputs provided insights into the more subtle, continuous mem-fractive behaviors. This dual approach enabled the identification of hysteresis loops in the I–V curves––a key signature of memristor functionality.</p>
<p>A square wave was used first, with the peak-to-peak voltage starting at 200 mV<sub>pp</sub> and increasing. If a sinusoidal wave form exhibited more promising results, a broader range of frequencies was explored. The frequencies and voltages used in the initial tests for memristive properties are detailed in <a href="#pone-0328965-t001">Table 1</a>.</p>
<p>Accuracy and error were calculated based on how many reads agreed with the analog threshold, the number of malformed readings, timing jitter, recording instability, and port delays [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref028">28</a>].</p>
<p><a name="pone.0328965.e001" id="pone.0328965.e001"></a><span><img src="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article/file?type=thumbnail&amp;id=10.1371/journal.pone.0328965.e001" loading="lazy"><span>(1)</span></span><a id="article1.body1.sec2.sec4.p6" name="article1.body1.sec2.sec4.p6"></a></p><p>The accuracy was calculated using <a href="#pone.0328965.e001">Equation 1</a>, where accuracy is a percentage converted from product of correct samples <em><em>C</em></em> over the total number of samples <em><em>N</em></em>. The standard error <em>SE</em> was calculated for each case, as shown in <a href="#pone.0328965.e002">Equation 2</a>.</p>
<p><a name="pone.0328965.e002" id="pone.0328965.e002"></a><span><img src="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article/file?type=thumbnail&amp;id=10.1371/journal.pone.0328965.e002" loading="lazy"><span>(2)</span></span><a id="article1.body1.sec2.sec4.p7" name="article1.body1.sec2.sec4.p7"></a></p><p>A simulated ideal memristive curve was compared against each experimental result, where the statistical distance <em><em>d</em></em> was calculated between both curves [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref028">28</a>]. The distance was used to compute memristive accuracy <span><img src="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article/file?type=thumbnail&amp;id=10.1371/journal.pone.0328965.e003" loading="lazy"></span> at a particular frequency, as shown in <a href="#pone.0328965.e004">Equation 3</a>.</p>
<p><a name="pone.0328965.e004" id="pone.0328965.e004"></a><span><img src="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article/file?type=thumbnail&amp;id=10.1371/journal.pone.0328965.e004" loading="lazy"><span>(3)</span></span></p></div>

<div id="section5"><h3>Volatile memory testing</h3>
<p>In the event that the fungal samples exhibited memristive behavior, a specialized electronic circuit was designed and implemented to investigate the volatile memory characteristics of two fungal samples in series. The test circuit was a voltage divider with memory. The test involved setting an arbitrary analog voltage value to represent a high value, and below that threshold was a low value. The frequency range started at 200 Hz and concluded at 5.85 kHz. Similarly to previous work, <a href="#pone-0328965-g003">Fig 3</a> shows the configuration and layout of this testing circuit [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref006">6</a>].</p>
<p>Comparably to previous work in memristive computing, the volatile memory circuit employed an Arduino UNO microcontroller development board and a voltage divider consisting of two memristive elements [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref006">6</a>,<a href="#pone.0328965.ref007">7</a>]. Given the polarized nature of memristors, the circuit was designed to allow a voltage of opposite polarity to that used during read operations to be set. Both voltages used were approximately 5 V. The Arduino UNO cyclically applied a high signal to a relay containing a half-rectified sine wave through one of its digital output pins when reading the memristor bridge, thereby charging the divider. This process induced an asymmetry in resistance, with the memristor closest to the input experiencing a reduction in resistance, while the output-side memristor exhibited an increase. The voltage across the divider was subsequently read using an analog input pin, and another digital pin was used to run 5 V across the divider. The Arduino interpreted the stored state as “on” only when the measured voltage exceeded a predefined threshold, effectively enabling volatile memory detection based on the transient resistance states of the memristors. Ten tests were repeated on each of the four samples. The physical implementation of this circuit is shown in <a href="#pone-0328965-g004">Fig 4</a>.</p>
<p>The memristor voltage divider was tested by applying a 5 V<sub>pp</sub> sinusoidal signal to the memristors for approximately 0.01–0.1 ms. This signal was delivered via a relay triggered by digital pin 6 of the Arduino UNO. Following this brief stimulation period, the sinusoidal input was disabled, and digital pin 5 was activated to initiate the read phase. Analog voltage measurements were then acquired through the A1 analog input pin. To minimize the effects of floating voltages, a 1 MΩ pull-down resistor was connected to this pin. Voltage readings were recorded for approximately 0.1–0.10 ms before the cycle repeated, allowing for rapid and continuous testing of the memristive behavior.</p>
<p>The measurements were transmitted over a serial communication interface at a baud rate of 57,600 and were captured as raw text files for analysis. The data were post-processed and visualized using a custom Python script based on the matplotlib library, enabling clear identification of memory retention patterns and resistance state changes across successive cycles.</p>
</div>

<div id="section6"><h3>Hypothesis</h3>
<p>The general testing setup, based on that used in the literature, is able to indicate memristive behavior in fungal samples. If present, this behavior would manifest as a characteristic pinched hysteresis loop in the I–V curves, typically intersecting at or near the origin––a well-established signature of memristive systems [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref006">6</a>,<a href="#pone.0328965.ref007">7</a>]. We hypothesized that such a response would emerge under specific combinations of voltage amplitude and input frequency. Where memristive behavior was indicated, volatile memory tests were conducted.</p>
</div>
</div>

<div xmlns:plos="http://plos.org" id="section3"><h2>Results</h2>
<div id="section1"><h3>Overview</h3>
<p>The fungal memristors were tested across a range of voltages, waveforms, and frequencies. Below, we first detail the test inputs used to explore the memristive properties and generate I–V curves. Then we present the voltage and frequency (graphical) test results, followed by the volatile memory test results. Each figure represents the averaged, smoothed results across the samples.</p>
</div>

<div id="section2"><h3>Voltage testing</h3>
<p>The first five tests were conducted to determine which voltage amplitude produced the most favorable memristive response. These initial trials revealed that a 1 V<sub>pp</sub> signal yielded the most consistent and measurable results. As outlined in the Methods section, the first four of these tests were performed using a square wave input.</p>
</div>

<div id="section3"><h3>Frequency testing</h3>
<p>After identifying 1 V<sub>pp</sub> as the optimal input voltage during the initial square wave tests (Tests 1–4), the waveform was switched to a sine wave for further analysis (Tests 5–10). The aim of this phase was to identify the frequency at which memristive behavior––specifically a pinched hysteresis loop––became apparent.</p>
<p>In Tests 1–5, the voltage amplitude was optimized using square waves. Between Tests 5 and 6, the waveform was changed from square to sine. From Tests 6–10, frequency sweeps were carried out with sine waves to identify memristive crossing. In Test 11, the voltage range was expanded at 10 Hz (5 V<sub>pp</sub>) to enhance the response. This revealed behavior close to that of an ideal memristor. Notably, Test 1 had already shown consistent linear behavior, indicating resistive characteristics. The results are shown in <a href="#pone-0328965-g005">Figs 5</a>–<a href="#pone-0328965-g013">13</a>. <a href="#pone-0328965-g014">Fig 14</a> details a sample noise profile, and <a href="#pone-0328965-g015">Fig 15</a> summarizes memristive accuracy.</p>
<p><a href="#pone-0328965-g005">Figs 5</a>–<a href="#pone-0328965-g010">10</a> show the output of Tests 2–7. The frequency was gradually reduced until a crossing near the origin was first observed, as shown in <a href="#pone-0328965-g010">Fig 10</a>. To ensure this result was not an outlier caused by overshooting the ideal frequency, the test was repeated at a slightly higher frequency (50 Hz, Test 8, shown in <a href="#pone-0328965-g011">Fig 11</a>). This confirmed that the optimal response occurred below 25 Hz.</p>
<p>As summarized in <a href="#pone-0328965-t002">Table 2</a>, the frequency was decreased to 10 Hz (Test 9, shown in <a href="#pone-0328965-g012">Fig 12</a>), which produced a clear crossing in the I–V curve near the −0.4 V region. To enhance the visibility of this behavior, the voltage was increased to 5 V<sub>pp</sub>, which resulted in a more pronounced memristive signature (Test 10). <a href="#pone-0328965-g013">Fig 13</a> illustrates this result, displaying a nearly ideal pinched hysteresis loop indicative of memristor functionality. The highest accuracy, at 95%, was at a 10 Hz sine wave at 1 V. <a href="#pone-0328965-g014">Fig 14</a> details the noise from an individual sample. <a href="#pone-0328965-g015">Fig 15</a> details the average memristive accuracy of each configuration.</p>
</div>

<div id="section4"><h3>Volatile memory experiment</h3>
<p>For the volatile memory tests 1 and 2, single read and write operations were performed across the memristor voltage divider. For volatile memory test 3, continuous read and write operations were performed across the memristor voltage divider while the frequency was gradually increased. The primary results are summarized in <a href="#pone-0328965-t003">Table 3</a>. The results are displayed in <a href="#pone-0328965-g016">Figs 16</a>–<a href="#pone-0328965-g020">20</a>. Averaged nemristive accuracy is displayed in <a href="#pone-0328965-g021">Fig 21</a>.</p>
</div>
</div>

<div xmlns:plos="http://plos.org" id="section4"><h2>Discussion</h2>
<div id="section1"><h3>Overview</h3>
<p>Using low-cost materials, shiitake mushrooms were cultured into ideal memristors. Ideal and non-ideal memristive properties have been observed previously in fungi, but these required far more complex interfacing methods [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref026">26</a>]. Although several techniques have been proposed to preserve fungal samples, we obtained experimental validation that dehydration can preserve the observed properties in a previously “programmed” sample [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref027">27</a>]. Ideal memristor properties are observed at lower frequencies, but potential latencies can be offset through massive parallelization, as in nature [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref026">26</a>,<a href="#pone.0328965.ref028">28</a>,<a href="#pone.0328965.ref029">29</a>]. As known from previous works on fungal memristors, the mycelial structure contains capacitive, memfractive, and memristive proteins [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref025">25</a>,<a href="#pone.0328965.ref026">26</a>]. In the memristive tests, accuracy decreased as the frequency increased. The observed rapid switching speed of 5,850 Hz, an accuracy of 90% (± 1%) low energy consumption relative to prior conventional systems, light weight, and radiation resistance all make fungal memristors attractive for edge computing, aerospace, and embedded firmware applications [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref025">25</a>–<a href="#pone.0328965.ref027">27</a>]. Unlike expensive conventional memristors, culturing fungal memristors does not require large facilities or rare minerals. The process can be scaled to grow large systems, which can be programmed and preserved for long-term use at low cost.</p>
</div>

<div id="section2"><h3>Limitations</h3>
<p>Our study was limited by the relatively short timescale of less than two months. Other researchers have documented memristive properties in mycelial materials, but their studies also focused on short-term performance [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref026">26</a>]. Another limitation was that only single, relatively bulky samples were prepared. To truly compete with conventional devices at the microscale and below, memristors will need to be far smaller [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref007">7</a>,<a href="#pone.0328965.ref008">8</a>,<a href="#pone.0328965.ref011">11</a>]. Even in the same growth medium, each sample produced a vastly different culture, and the outcomes have yet to be fully characterized by electrical properties. However, the development of these devices is in an early stage, and they could eventually be miniaturized, especially using improved cultivation techniques. Complications associated with the growth media were not explored, although previous research has found that fungi are quite robust to varying conditions [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref026">26</a>].</p>
</div>

<div id="section3"><h3>Future work</h3>
<p>Although fungal memristors can be produced at low cost, certain aspects of the process could be further optimized. First, consistent cultivation techniques could be improved using three-dimensional (3D)-printed templates and structures that shape the shiitake mushroom into the desired geometry. Second, programming could be facilitated by adding electrical contacts into a 3D-printed cultivation structure. Finally, long-term use would necessitate preservation, which could involve a variety of techniques, including dehydration, desiccation, freeze-drying, certain hydrogels, and special coatings [<a href="#pone.0328965.ref027">27</a>]. By testing devices produced to physical stress conditions, a combination of these techniques could enable the development of fast, radiation-resistant, and low-energy memristors grown from low-cost organic materials. The future of computing could be fungal.</p>
</div>
</div>

<div xmlns:plos="http://plos.org" id="section5"><h2>Conclusions</h2><p>Currently, the fabrication of semiconductor memristors requires rare-earth minerals and large facilities, and culturing delicate neural organoids requires a complex chemical environment to be maintained in a bioreactor. Fungal computing may provide a robust and accessible alternative. Fungal systems have lower power requirements, lighter weights, faster switching speeds, and lower industrial overheads than conventional devices. In this study, fungal memristors were fabricated, programmed, and tested using shiitake mushrooms and conventional electronics. Dehydration-based preservation was successfully explored, demonstrating the robustness of our devices. When used as RAM, our mushroom memristor was able to operate at up to 5,850 Hz at an accuracy of 90 ± 1%. In addition, shiitake mushrooms are biodegradable and have demonstrated radiation resistance, suggesting that the potential applications of fungal computing range from sustainable computing devices to aerospace technologies.</p>
</div>





<div xmlns:plos="http://plos.org"><h2>Acknowledgments</h2>
<p>We would like to thank Ryan Lingo and Rajeev Chhajer of the Honda Research Institute.</p>
</div><div xmlns:plos="http://plos.org"><h2>References</h2><ol><li id="ref1"><span>1.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref001" id="pone.0328965.ref001"></a>Li C, Han L, Jiang H, Jang M-H, Lin P, Wu Q, et al. Three-dimensional crossbar arrays of self-rectifying Si/SiO2/Si memristors. Nat Commun. 2017;8:15666.  pmid:28580928 <ul data-doi="10.1038/ncomms15666"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/ncomms15666" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/28580928" target="_new" title="Go to article in PubMed">
                        PubMed/NCBI
                      </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Three-dimensional+crossbar+arrays+of+self-rectifying+Si%2FSiO2%2FSi+memristors+Li+2017" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref2"><span>2.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref002" id="pone.0328965.ref002"></a>Cheng P, Gao S, Zang P, Yang X, Bai Y, Xu H, et al. Hierarchically porous carbon by activation of shiitake mushroom for capacitive energy storage. Carbon. 2015;93:315–24.  <ul data-doi="10.1016/j.carbon.2015.05.056"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.carbon.2015.05.056" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Hierarchically+porous+carbon+by+activation+of+shiitake+mushroom+for+capacitive+energy+storage+Cheng+2015" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref3"><span>3.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref003" id="pone.0328965.ref003"></a>Lin F, Chen Y, Zhao Y, Wang S. Path tracking of autonomous vehicle based on adaptive model predictive control. International Journal of Advanced Robotic Systems. 2019;16(5).  <ul data-doi="10.1177/1729881419880089"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1729881419880089" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Path+tracking+of+autonomous+vehicle+based+on+adaptive+model+predictive+control+Lin+2019" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref4"><span>4.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref004" id="pone.0328965.ref004"></a>Wang Q, Hu Z, Li Z, Liu T, Bian G. Exploring the Application and Prospects of Synthetic Biology in Engineered Living Materials. Adv Mater. 2025;37(31):e2305828.  pmid:37677048 <ul data-doi="10.1002/adma.202305828"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/adma.202305828" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/37677048" target="_new" title="Go to article in PubMed">
                        PubMed/NCBI
                      </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Exploring+the+Application+and+Prospects+of+Synthetic+Biology+in+Engineered+Living+Materials+Wang+2025" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref5"><span>5.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref005" id="pone.0328965.ref005"></a>Li C, Han L, Jiang H, Jang M-H, Lin P, Wu Q, et al. Three-dimensional crossbar arrays of self-rectifying Si/SiO2/Si memristors. Nat Commun. 2017;8:15666.  pmid:28580928 <ul data-doi="10.1038/ncomms15666"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/ncomms15666" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/28580928" target="_new" title="Go to article in PubMed">
                        PubMed/NCBI
                      </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Three-dimensional+crossbar+arrays+of+self-rectifying+Si%2FSiO2%2FSi+memristors+Li+2017" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref6"><span>6.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref006" id="pone.0328965.ref006"></a>Yuan L, Liu S, Chen W, Fan F, Liu G. Organic Memory and Memristors: From Mechanisms, Materials to Devices. Adv Elect Materials. 2021;7(11).  <ul data-doi="10.1002/aelm.202100432"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/aelm.202100432" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Organic+Memory+and+Memristors%3A+From+Mechanisms%2C+Materials+to+Devices+Yuan+2021" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref7"><span>7.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref007" id="pone.0328965.ref007"></a>Femi O. Unveiling the fourth fundamental circuit element and its real-world applications. In: Chang YF, ed. Memristors – The Fourth Fundamental Circuit Element – Theory, Device, and Applications. IntechOpen; 2024:3–12.  <ul data-doi="10.5772/intechopen.1002330"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.5772/intechopen.1002330" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Unveiling+the+fourth+fundamental+circuit+element+and+its+real-world+applications.+Femi+2024" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref8"><span>8.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref008" id="pone.0328965.ref008"></a>Li C, Han L, Jiang H, Jang M-H, Lin P, Wu Q, et al. Three-dimensional crossbar arrays of self-rectifying Si/SiO2/Si memristors. Nat Commun. 2017;8:15666.  pmid:28580928 <ul data-doi="10.1038/ncomms15666"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/ncomms15666" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/28580928" target="_new" title="Go to article in PubMed">
                        PubMed/NCBI
                      </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Three-dimensional+crossbar+arrays+of+self-rectifying+Si%2FSiO2%2FSi+memristors+Li+2017" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref9"><span>9.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref009" id="pone.0328965.ref009"></a>Yang C, Sun B, Zhou G, Guo T, Ke C, Chen Y, et al. Photoelectric Memristor-Based Machine Vision for Artificial Intelligence Applications. ACS Materials Lett. 2023;5(2):504–26.  <ul data-doi="10.1021/acsmaterialslett.2c00911"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acsmaterialslett.2c00911" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Photoelectric+Memristor-Based+Machine+Vision+for+Artificial+Intelligence+Applications+Yang+2023" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref10"><span>10.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref010" id="pone.0328965.ref010"></a>Campbell KA, Drake KT, Barney Smith EH. Pulse Shape and Timing Dependence on the Spike-Timing Dependent Plasticity Response of Ion-Conducting Memristors as Synapses. Front Bioeng Biotechnol. 2016;4:97.  pmid:28083531 <ul data-doi="10.3389/fbioe.2016.00097"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fbioe.2016.00097" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/28083531" target="_new" title="Go to article in PubMed">
                        PubMed/NCBI
                      </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Pulse+Shape+and+Timing+Dependence+on+the+Spike-Timing+Dependent+Plasticity+Response+of+Ion-Conducting+Memristors+as+Synapses+Campbell+2016" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref11"><span>11.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref011" id="pone.0328965.ref011"></a>Ko T-J, Li H, Mofid SA, Yoo C, Okogbue E, Han SS, et al. Two-Dimensional Near-Atom-Thickness Materials for Emerging Neuromorphic Devices and Applications. iScience. 2020;23(11):101676.  pmid:33163934 <ul data-doi="10.1016/j.isci.2020.101676"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.isci.2020.101676" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/33163934" target="_new" title="Go to article in PubMed">
                        PubMed/NCBI
                      </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Two-Dimensional+Near-Atom-Thickness+Materials+for+Emerging+Neuromorphic+Devices+and+Applications+Ko+2020" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref12"><span>12.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref012" id="pone.0328965.ref012"></a>Lu XF, Zhang Y, Wang N, Luo S, Peng K, Wang L, et al. Exploring Low Power and Ultrafast Memristor on p-Type van der Waals SnS. Nano Lett. 2021;21(20):8800–7.  pmid:34644096 <ul data-doi="10.1021/acs.nanolett.1c03169"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.nanolett.1c03169" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/34644096" target="_new" title="Go to article in PubMed">
                        PubMed/NCBI
                      </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Exploring+Low+Power+and+Ultrafast+Memristor+on+p-Type+van+der+Waals+SnS+Lu+2021" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref13"><span>13.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref013" id="pone.0328965.ref013"></a>Liao K, Lei P, Tu M, Luo S, Jiang T, Jie W, et al. Memristor Based on Inorganic and Organic Two-Dimensional Materials: Mechanisms, Performance, and Synaptic Applications. ACS Appl Mater Interfaces. 2021;13(28):32606–23.  pmid:34253011 <ul data-doi="10.1021/acsami.1c07665"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acsami.1c07665" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/34253011" target="_new" title="Go to article in PubMed">
                        PubMed/NCBI
                      </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Memristor+Based+on+Inorganic+and+Organic+Two-Dimensional+Materials%3A+Mechanisms%2C+Performance%2C+and+Synaptic+Applications+Liao+2021" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref14"><span>14.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref014" id="pone.0328965.ref014"></a>Sun J, Yang R, Li Q, Zhu R, Jiang Y, Zang L, et al. Living Synthelectronics: A New Era for Bioelectronics Powered by Synthetic Biology. Adv Mater. 2024;36(25):e2400110.  pmid:38494761 <ul data-doi="10.1002/adma.202400110"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/adma.202400110" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/38494761" target="_new" title="Go to article in PubMed">
                        PubMed/NCBI
                      </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Living+Synthelectronics%3A+A+New+Era+for+Bioelectronics+Powered+by+Synthetic+Biology+Sun+2024" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref15"><span>15.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref015" id="pone.0328965.ref015"></a>Cheng P, Gao S, Zang P, Yang X, Bai Y, Xu H, et al. Hierarchically porous carbon by activation of shiitake mushroom for capacitive energy storage. Carbon. 2015;93:315–24.  <ul data-doi="10.1016/j.carbon.2015.05.056"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.carbon.2015.05.056" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Hierarchically+porous+carbon+by+activation+of+shiitake+mushroom+for+capacitive+energy+storage+Cheng+2015" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref16"><span>16.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref016" id="pone.0328965.ref016"></a>Yadav P, Basu A, Suryawanshi A, Game O, Ogale S. Highly Stable Laser‐Scribed Flexible Planar Microsupercapacitor Using Mushroom Derived Carbon Electrodes. Adv Materials Inter. 2016;3(11).  <ul data-doi="10.1002/admi.201600057"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/admi.201600057" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Highly+Stable+Laser%E2%80%90Scribed+Flexible+Planar+Microsupercapacitor+Using+Mushroom+Derived+Carbon+Electrodes+Yadav+2016" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref17"><span>17.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref017" id="pone.0328965.ref017"></a>Li J, Wu Q, Zan G. Facile synthesis and high electrochemical performance of porous carbon composites for supercapacitors. RSC Adv. 2014;4(66):35186.  <ul data-doi="10.1039/c4ra05196c"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1039/c4ra05196c" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Facile+synthesis+and+high+electrochemical+performance+of+porous+carbon+composites+for+supercapacitors+Li+2014" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref18"><span>18.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref018" id="pone.0328965.ref018"></a>Joshi S, Cook E, Mannoor MS. Bacterial Nanobionics via 3D Printing. Nano Lett. 2018;18(12):7448–56.  pmid:30403141 <ul data-doi="10.1021/acs.nanolett.8b02642"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.nanolett.8b02642" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/30403141" target="_new" title="Go to article in PubMed">
                        PubMed/NCBI
                      </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Bacterial+Nanobionics+via+3D+Printing+Joshi+2018" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref19"><span>19.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref019" id="pone.0328965.ref019"></a>Gómez I, Lavega González R, Tejedor-Calvo E, Pérez Clavijo M, Carrasco J. Odor Profile of Four Cultivated and Freeze-Dried Edible Mushrooms by Using Sensory Panel, Electronic Nose and GC-MS. J Fungi (Basel). 2022;8(9):953.  pmid:36135678 <ul data-doi="10.3390/jof8090953"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/jof8090953" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/36135678" target="_new" title="Go to article in PubMed">
                        PubMed/NCBI
                      </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Odor+Profile+of+Four+Cultivated+and+Freeze-Dried+Edible+Mushrooms+by+Using+Sensory+Panel%2C+Electronic+Nose+and+GC-MS+G%C3%B3mez+2022" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref20"><span>20.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref020" id="pone.0328965.ref020"></a>Fujioka K, Shimizu N, Manome Y, Ikeda K, Yamamoto K, Tomizawa Y. Discrimination method of the volatiles from fresh mushrooms by an electronic nose using a trapping system and statistical standardization to reduce sensor value variation. Sensors (Basel). 2013;13(11):15532–48.  pmid:24233028 <ul data-doi="10.3390/s131115532"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/s131115532" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24233028" target="_new" title="Go to article in PubMed">
                        PubMed/NCBI
                      </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Discrimination+method+of+the+volatiles+from+fresh+mushrooms+by+an+electronic+nose+using+a+trapping+system+and+statistical+standardization+to+reduce+sensor+value+variation+Fujioka+2013" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref21"><span>21.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref021" id="pone.0328965.ref021"></a>Chung I-M, Kim S-Y, Han J-G, Kong W-S, Jung MY, Kim S-H. Fatty Acids and Stable Isotope Ratios in Shiitake Mushrooms (Lentinula edodes) Indicate the Origin of the Cultivation Substrate Used: A Preliminary Case Study in Korea. Foods. 2020;9(9):1210.  pmid:32882944 <ul data-doi="10.3390/foods9091210"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/foods9091210" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/32882944" target="_new" title="Go to article in PubMed">
                        PubMed/NCBI
                      </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Fatty+Acids+and+Stable+Isotope+Ratios+in+Shiitake+Mushrooms+%28Lentinula+edodes%29+Indicate+the+Origin+of+the+Cultivation+Substrate+Used%3A+A+Preliminary+Case+Study+in+Korea+Chung+2020" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref22"><span>22.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref022" id="pone.0328965.ref022"></a>Wu K, de Menezes S, Robinson A. Flagellate Erythema: A Case of Shiitake Dermatitis and Review of Pathogenesis. EMJ Allergy Immunol. 2022.  <ul data-doi="10.33590/emjallergyimmunol/21-00187"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.33590/emjallergyimmunol/21-00187" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Flagellate+Erythema%3A+A+Case+of+Shiitake+Dermatitis+and+Review+of+Pathogenesis+Wu+2022" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref23"><span>23.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref023" id="pone.0328965.ref023"></a>Won DJ, Kim SY, Jang CH, Lee JS, Ko JA, Park HJ. Optimization of UV irradiation conditions for the vitamin D2-fortified shiitake mushroom (Lentinula edodes) using response surface methodology. Food Sci Biotechnol. 2017;27(2):417–24.  pmid:30263765 <ul data-doi="10.1007/s10068-017-0266-0"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10068-017-0266-0" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/30263765" target="_new" title="Go to article in PubMed">
                        PubMed/NCBI
                      </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Optimization+of+UV+irradiation+conditions+for+the+vitamin+D2-fortified+shiitake+mushroom+%28Lentinula+edodes%29+using+response+surface+methodology+Won+2017" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref24"><span>24.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref024" id="pone.0328965.ref024"></a>Loo HV, Oon HH. Flagellate dermatitis following consumption of shiitake mushroom. Dermatol Reports. 2011;3(2):e21.  pmid:25386273 <ul data-doi="10.4081/dr.2011.e21"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.4081/dr.2011.e21" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25386273" target="_new" title="Go to article in PubMed">
                        PubMed/NCBI
                      </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Flagellate+dermatitis+following+consumption+of+shiitake+mushroom+Loo+2011" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref25"><span>25.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref025" id="pone.0328965.ref025"></a>Wang H, Tao J, Wu Z, Weiland K, Wang Z, Masania K, et al. Fabrication of Living Entangled Network Composites Enabled by Mycelium. Adv Sci (Weinh). 2024;11(24):e2309370.  pmid:38477443 <ul data-doi="10.1002/advs.202309370"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/advs.202309370" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/38477443" target="_new" title="Go to article in PubMed">
                        PubMed/NCBI
                      </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Fabrication+of+Living+Entangled+Network+Composites+Enabled+by+Mycelium+Wang+2024" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref26"><span>26.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref026" id="pone.0328965.ref026"></a>Adamatzky A, Ayres P, Beasley AE, Roberts N, Wösten HAB. Logics in Fungal Mycelium Networks. Log Univers. 2022;16(4):655–69.  <ul data-doi="10.1007/s11787-022-00318-4"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11787-022-00318-4" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Logics+in+Fungal+Mycelium+Networks+Adamatzky+2022" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref27"><span>27.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref027" id="pone.0328965.ref027"></a>Al-Bedak OA, Sayed RM, Hassan SHA. A new low-cost method for long-term preservation of filamentous fungi. Biocatalysis and Agricultural Biotechnology. 2019;22:101417.  <ul data-doi="10.1016/j.bcab.2019.101417"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bcab.2019.101417" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=A+new+low-cost+method+for+long-term+preservation+of+filamentous+fungi+Al-Bedak+2019" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref28"><span>28.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref028" id="pone.0328965.ref028"></a>Yin S-F, Sun Q-J, Liu L-F, Liu S-Z, Jiang Y-P, Tang X-G. TiO2/Bi4Ti3O12 heterojunction optoelectronic synaptic devices for simulating associative memory and neuromorphic computation. Applied Surface Science. 2025;711:164049.  <ul data-doi="10.1016/j.apsusc.2025.164049"><li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apsusc.2025.164049" data-author="doi-provided" data-cit="doi-provided" data-title="doi-provided" target="_new" title="Go to article">
                      View Article
                    </a></li><li><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=TiO2%2FBi4Ti3O12+heterojunction+optoelectronic+synaptic+devices+for+simulating+associative+memory+and+neuromorphic+computation+Yin+2025" target="_new" title="Go to article in Google Scholar">
                      Google Scholar
                    </a></li></ul></li><li id="ref29"><span>29.
            </span><a name="pone.0328965.ref029" id="pone.0328965.ref029"></a>Dixon WJ, Massey FJ. Introduction to statistical analysis. 1951. <ul></ul></li></ol></div>



          

        </div>
      </div>
  
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Attention lapses due to sleep deprivation due to flushing fluid from brain (560 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.mit.edu/2025/your-brain-without-sleep-1029</link>
            <guid>45771636</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 13:14:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://news.mit.edu/2025/your-brain-without-sleep-1029">https://news.mit.edu/2025/your-brain-without-sleep-1029</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45771636">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          

            <p>Nearly everyone has experienced it: After a night of poor sleep, you don’t feel as alert as you should. Your brain might seem foggy, and your mind drifts off when you should be paying attention.</p><p>A new study from MIT reveals what happens inside the brain as these momentary failures of attention occur. The scientists found that during these lapses, a wave of cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) flows out of the brain — a process that typically occurs during sleep and helps to wash away waste products that have built up during the day. This flushing is believed to be necessary for maintaining a healthy, normally functioning brain.</p><p>When a person is sleep-deprived, it appears that their body attempts to catch up on this cleansing process by initiating pulses of CSF flow. However, this comes at a cost of dramatically impaired attention.</p><p>“If you don’t sleep, the CSF waves start to intrude into wakefulness where normally you wouldn’t see them. However, they come with an attentional tradeoff, where attention fails during the moments that you have this wave of fluid flow,” says Laura Lewis, the Athinoula A. Martinos Associate Professor of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, a member of MIT’s Institute for Medical Engineering and Science and the Research Laboratory of Electronics, and an associate member of the Picower Institute for Learning and Memory.</p><p>Lewis is the senior author of the study, which <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41593-025-02098-8" target="_blank">appears today</a> in <em>Nature Neuroscience</em>. MIT visiting graduate student Zinong Yang&nbsp;is the lead author of the paper.</p><p><strong>Flushing the brain</strong></p><p>Although sleep is a critical biological process, it’s not known exactly why it is so important. It appears to be essential for maintaining alertness, and it has been well-documented that sleep deprivation leads to impairments of attention and other cognitive functions.</p><p>During sleep, the cerebrospinal fluid that cushions the brain helps to remove waste that has built up during the day. In a 2019&nbsp;<a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.aax5440" target="_blank">study</a>, Lewis and colleagues showed that CSF flow during sleep follows a rhythmic pattern in and out of the brain, and that these flows are linked to changes in brain waves during sleep.</p><p>That finding led Lewis to wonder what might happen to CSF flow after sleep deprivation. To explore that question, she and her colleagues recruited 26 volunteers who were tested twice — once following a night of sleep deprivation in the lab, and once when they were well-rested.</p><p>In the morning, the researchers monitored several different measures of brain and body function as the participants performed a task that is commonly used to evaluate the effects of sleep deprivation.</p><p>During the task, each participant wore an electroencephalogram (EEG) cap that could record brain waves while they were also in a functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) scanner. The researchers used a modified version of fMRI that allowed them to measure not only blood oxygenation in the brain, but also the flow of CSF in and out of the brain. They also measured each subject’s heart rate, breathing rate, and pupil diameter.</p><p>The participants performed two attentional tasks while in the fMRI scanner, one visual and one auditory. For the visual task, they had to look at a screen that had a fixed cross. At random intervals, the cross would turn into a square, and the participants were told to press a button whenever they saw this happen. For the auditory task, they would hear a beep instead of seeing a visual transformation.</p><p>Sleep-deprived participants performed much worse than well-rested participants on these tasks, as expected. Their response times were slower, and for some of the stimuli, the participants never registered the change at all.</p><p>During these momentary lapses of attention, the researchers identified several physiological changes that occurred at the same time. Most significantly, they found a flux of CSF out of the brain just as those lapses occurred. After each lapse, CSF flowed back into the brain.</p><p>“The results are suggesting that at the moment that attention fails, this fluid is actually being expelled outward away from the brain. And when attention recovers, it’s drawn back in,” Lewis says.</p><p>The researchers hypothesize that when the brain is sleep-deprived, it begins to compensate for the loss of the cleansing that normally occurs during sleep, even though these pulses of CSF flow&nbsp;come with the cost of attention loss.</p><p>“One way to think about those events is because your brain is so in need of sleep, it tries its best to enter into a sleep-like state to restore some cognitive functions,” Yang says. “Your brain’s fluid system is trying to restore function by pushing the brain to iterate between high-attention and high-flow states.”</p><p><strong>A unified circuit</strong></p><p>The researchers also found several other physiological events linked to attentional lapses, including decreases in breathing and heart rate, along with constriction of the pupils. They found that pupil constriction began about 12 seconds before CSF flowed out of the brain, and pupils dilated again after the attentional lapse.</p><p>“What’s interesting is it seems like this isn’t just a phenomenon in the brain, it’s also a body-wide event. It suggests that there’s a tight coordination of these systems, where when your attention fails, you might feel it perceptually and psychologically, but it’s also reflecting an event that’s happening throughout the brain and body,” Lewis says.</p><p>This close linkage between disparate events may indicate that there is a single circuit that controls both attention and bodily functions such as fluid flow, heart rate, and arousal, according to the researchers.</p><p>“These results suggest to us that there’s a unified circuit that’s governing both what we think of as very high-level functions of the brain — our attention, our ability to perceive and respond to the world — and then also really basic fundamental physiological processes like fluid dynamics of the brain, brain-wide blood flow, and blood vessel constriction,” Lewis says.</p><p>In this study, the researchers did not explore what circuit might be controlling this switching, but one good candidate, they say, is the noradrenergic system. Recent research has shown that this system, which regulates many cognitive and bodily functions through the neurotransmitter norepinephrine, oscillates during normal sleep.</p><p>The research was funded by the National Institutes of Health, a National Defense Science and Engineering Graduate Research Fellowship, a NAWA Fellowship, a McKnight Scholar Award, a Sloan Fellowship, a Pew Biomedical Scholar Award, a One Mind Rising Star Award, and the Simons Collaboration on Plasticity in the Aging Brain.</p>        

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OpenAI Uses Complex and Circular Deals to Fuel Its Multibillion-Dollar Rise (382 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2025/10/31/technology/openai-fundraising-deals.html</link>
            <guid>45771538</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 13:03:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2025/10/31/technology/openai-fundraising-deals.html">https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2025/10/31/technology/openai-fundraising-deals.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45771538">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="g-bk-Prh5jeFdOVdDfQ" data-preview-slug="bk-Prh5jeFdOVdDfQ" data-birdkit-hydrate="4ecfcbdd0b1559e1">
			
	<!--[--><!--[--><!----><!----><!--[--><!--[--><!----><!----><figure><!--[!--><!--]--> <!--[!--><!--]--> <!----> <!--[!--><!--]--><!----></figure><!----><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><p><!--[--><!---->Sam Altman, the chief executive of OpenAI, says that technological revolutions are driven by more than just technology. They are also driven, he argues, by new ways of paying for them.<!----><!--]--><!----></p><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><p><!--[--><!---->“There is always a lot of focus on technological innovation. What really drives a lot of progress is when people also figure out how to innovate on the financial model,” he recently said at the site of a data center that OpenAI is building in Abilene, Texas.<!----><!--]--><!----></p><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><p><!--[--><!---->Over the last several years, Mr. Altman’s company has found unusual and creative ways of paying for the computing power needed to fuel its ambitions.<!----><!--]--><!----></p><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><p><!--[--><!---->Many of the deals OpenAI has struck — with chipmakers, cloud computing companies and others — are strangely circular. OpenAI receives billions from tech companies before sending those billions back to the same companies to pay for computing power and other services.<!----><!--]--><!----></p><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><p><!--[--><!---->Industry experts and financial analysts have welcomed the start-up’s creativity. But these unorthodox arrangements have also fueled concerns that OpenAI is helping to inflate a potential financial bubble as it builds what is still a highly speculative technology.<!----><!--]--><!----></p><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><p><!--[--><!---->Here are unusual financial agreements helping to drive the ambitions of OpenAI, the poster child of the artificial intelligence revolution.<!----><!--]--><!----></p><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!----><figure><!--[!--><!--]--> <!--[!--><!--]--> <!----> <!--[!--><!--]--><!----></figure><!----><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><p><!--[--><!---->From 2019 through 2023, Microsoft was OpenAI’s primary investor. The tech giant pumped more than <span>$13 billion</span> into the start-up. Then OpenAI funneled most of those billions back into Microsoft, buying <span>cloud computing power</span> needed to fuel the development of new A.I. technologies.<!----><!--]--><!----></p><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><p><!--[--><!---->(The New York Times has <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/12/27/business/media/new-york-times-open-ai-microsoft-lawsuit.html">sued</a> OpenAI and Microsoft, claiming copyright infringement of news content related to A.I. systems. The two companies have denied the suit’s claims.)<!----><!--]--><!----></p><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><!----><!--]--><!----><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!----><figure><!--[!--><!--]--> <!--[!--><!--]--> <!----> <!--[!--><!--]--><!----></figure><!----><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><p><!--[--><!---->By the summer of last year, OpenAI could not get all the computing power it wanted from Microsoft. So it started signing cloud computing contracts with other companies, including Oracle and little-known start-ups with names like CoreWeave.<!----><!--]--><!----></p><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><p><!--[--><!---->Across three different deals signed this year, OpenAI agreed to pay CoreWeave, a company that builds A.I. data centers, more than <span>$22 billion</span> for computing power. As part of these agreements, OpenAI received <span>$350 million</span> in CoreWeave stock, which could ultimately help pay for this computing power.<!----><!--]--><!----></p><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><!----><!--]--><!----><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!----><figure><!--[!--><!--]--> <!--[!--><!--]--> <!----> <!--[!--><!--]--><!----></figure><!----><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><p><!--[--><!---->OpenAI also struggled to get the additional investment dollars it wanted from Microsoft. So, it turned to other investors. Earlier this year, the Japanese conglomerate SoftBank led a <span>$40 billion</span> investment in OpenAI.<!----><!--]--><!----></p><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><p><!--[--><!---->At the same time, OpenAI has been working with various companies to build its own computing data centers, rather than rely on cloud computing deals. This also includes SoftBank, which is known for highly speculative technological bets that don’t always pay off. The company is raising <span>$100 billion</span> to help OpenAI build data centers in Texas and Ohio.<!----><!--]--><!----></p><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><!----><!--]--><!----><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!----><figure><!--[!--><!--]--> <!--[!--><!--]--> <!----> <!--[!--><!--]--><!----></figure><!----><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><p><!--[--><!---->Similarly, Oracle, a software and cloud computing giant, has agreed to spend <span>$300 billion</span> building new data centers for OpenAI in Texas, New Mexico, Michigan and Wisconsin. OpenAI will then pay Oracle roughly the same amount to use these <span>computing facilities</span> over the next several years.<!----><!--]--><!----></p><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><!----><!--]--><!----><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!----><figure><!--[!--><!--]--> <!--[!--><!--]--> <!----> <!--[!--><!--]--><!----></figure><!----><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><p><!--[--><!---->The United Arab Emirates was part of an OpenAI’s fund-raising round in October 2024. Now, G42, a firm with close ties to the Emirati government, is building a roughly <span>$20 billion data center complex</span> for OpenAI in the Emirates.<!----><!--]--><!----></p><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><!----><!--]--><!----><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!----><figure><!--[!--><!--]--> <!--[!--><!--]--> <!----> <!--[!--><!--]--><!----></figure><!----><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><p><!--[--><!---->Last month, Nvidia announced that it intended to invest <span>$100 billion</span> in OpenAI over the next several years. This could help OpenAI pay for its new data centers. As OpenAI buys or leases specialized chips from Nvidia, Nvidia will pump billions back into OpenAI.<!----><!--]--><!----></p><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><!----><!--]--><!----><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!----><figure><!--[!--><!--]--> <!--[!--><!--]--> <!----> <!--[!--><!--]--><!----></figure><!----><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><p><!--[--><!---->Two weeks later, OpenAI signed an agreement with AMD that allows OpenAI to buy up to <span>160 million shares</span> in the chipmaker at a penny per share. That translates to roughly a 10 percent stake in the company. This stock could supply OpenAI with additional capital as it works to build new data centers.<!----><!--]--><!----></p><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><!----><!--]--><!----><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><p><!--[--><!---->OpenAI pulls in billions of dollars in revenue each year from customers who pay for ChatGPT, computer programming tools and other technologies. But it still loses more money than it makes, according to a person familiar with the company’s finances.<!----><!--]--><!----></p><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><p><!--[--><!---->If the company can use its new data centers to significantly improve A.I. technologies and expand its revenue over the next several years, it can become a viable business, as Mr. Altman believes it will. If technology progress stalls, OpenAI – and its many partners – could lose enormous amounts of money. Smaller companies like CoreWeave, which are taking on enormous amounts of debt to build new data centers, could go bankrupt.<!----><!--]--><!----></p><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--[--><!----><!--[--><!--[!--><!----><p><!--[--><!---->In some cases, companies are hedging their bets. Nvidia and AMD, for instance, have the option of reducing the cash and stock they send to OpenAI if the A.I. market does not expand as quickly as expected. But others would be left with enormous debt, which could send ripples across the larger economy.<!----><!--]--><!----></p><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!--]--><!--]--><!----><!----><!----><!--]--> <!--[!--><!--]--><!--]-->
			
			
		

		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>