<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 15:30:17 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Patent troll Sable pays up, dedicates all its patents to the public (196 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.cloudflare.com/patent-troll-sable-pays-up/</link>
            <guid>41730415</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 13:05:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/patent-troll-sable-pays-up/">https://blog.cloudflare.com/patent-troll-sable-pays-up/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41730415">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post"><article><p>2024-10-02</p><section><p>9 min read</p><img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/slt3lc6tev37/50x8xiEb0xDPtv0CmgkGjj/1baada5ffda318ea15ea1125473b9587/BLOG-2579_1.png" alt=""><div><p>Back in February, we celebrated our <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/cloudflare-defeats-patent-troll-sable-at-trial"><u>victory at trial</u></a> in the U.S. District Court for the Western District of Texas against patent trolls Sable IP and Sable Networks. This was the culmination of nearly three years of litigation against Sable, but it wasn’t the end of the story.&nbsp;</p><p>Today we’re pleased to announce that the litigation against Sable has finally concluded on terms that we believe send a strong message to patent trolls everywhere — if you bring meritless patent claims against Cloudflare, we will fight back and we will win.</p><p>We’re also pleased to announce additional prizes in <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/jengo/sable-prior-art-search/"><u>Project Jengo</u></a>, and to make a final call for submissions before we determine the winners of the Final Awards. As a reminder, Project Jengo is Cloudflare’s effort to fight back against patent trolls by flipping the incentive structure that has encouraged the growth of patent trolls who extract settlements out of companies using frivolous lawsuits. We do this by asking the public to help identify prior art that can invalidate any of the patents that a troll holds, not just the ones that are asserted against Cloudflare. We’ve already given out over $125,000 to individuals since the <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/project-jengo/"><u>launch of Project Jengo in 2017</u></a>, and we’re looking forward to celebrating the successful end of the Sable iteration of Project Jengo with our Final Awards!</p><p>To learn more about how things concluded with Sable and next steps in Project Jengo, read on.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><h3>Background</h3><p>For anyone just joining us on this odyssey, here is a little background on how we got here:</p><p>Sable sued Cloudflare back in March 2021. Sable is a patent troll. It doesn’t make, develop, innovate, or sell anything. Sable IP is merely a shell entity formed to monetize (make money from) an ancient patent portfolio acquired by Sable Networks from Caspian Networks in 2006. <a href="https://www.lightreading.com/cable-technology/caspian-closes-its-doors"><u>Caspian Networks was a router company that went out of business nearly 20 years ago</u></a>. Using Caspian’s old patents, Sable sued Cloudflare and many other companies, including Cisco, Fortinet, Check Point, SonicWall, and Juniper Networks, alleging patent infringement. While these other companies resolved their disputes with Sable out of court, Cloudflare fought back.&nbsp;</p><p>Sable initially asserted around 100 claims from four different patents against Cloudflare, accusing multiple Cloudflare products and features of infringement. Sable’s patents — the old Caspian Networks patents — related to hardware-based router technologies common over 20 years ago. Sable’s infringement arguments stretched these patent claims to their limits (and beyond) as Sable tried to apply Caspian’s hardware-based technologies to Cloudflare’s modern software-defined services delivered on the cloud.</p><p>Cloudflare fought back against Sable by launching a <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/jengo/sable-prior-art-search/"><u>new round of Project Jengo</u></a>, Cloudflare’s prior art contest, seeking prior art to invalidate all of Sable’s patents.</p><p>After years of Cloudflare aggressively litigating against Sable’s patents before the U.S. Patent and Trademark Office and the district court, Sable was left with only one claim from one patent to assert against Cloudflare at trial. If you’d like to know more, we described those battles, in which Cloudflare successfully eliminated around 99% of Sable’s claims, in more detail in a <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/cloudflare-defeats-patent-troll-sable-at-trial/"><u>prior blog post</u></a>.</p><p>Sable and Cloudflare came together in a five-day jury trial in Waco, Texas in February 2024. At trial, Sable did its best to try to map its decades-old router technology onto Cloudflare’s modern software-based architecture. But Sable’s case was riddled with technical issues and its efforts backed only by the desire for a payout.</p><h3>The jury agrees: Cloudflare <u>does not infringe</u></h3><p>To defeat Sable’s claim of infringement we needed to explain to the jury — in clear and understandable terms — why what Cloudflare does is different from what was covered by claim 25 of Sable’s remaining patent, U.S. Patent No. <a href="https://patents.google.com/patent/US7012919B1/en?oq=7012919"><u>7,012,919</u></a> (the ’919 patent). To do this, we enlisted the help of one of our talented Cloudflare engineers, Eric Reeves, as well as <a href="https://engineering.washu.edu/faculty/Paul-Min.html"><u>Dr. Paul Min, Senior Professor of Electrical &amp; Systems Engineering at Washington University</u></a>, an expert in the field of computer networking. Eric and Dr. Min helped us explain to the jury the multiple reasons we didn’t infringe.</p>
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/slt3lc6tev37/XWCN4456ulrVi0xmCMfbb/8efb979e5788ee1321c3115eeb526a2d/BLOG-2579_2.png" alt="BLOG-2579 2" width="1077" height="569" loading="lazy">
          </figure><p><sup><i>From slide deck presented by Cloudflare to the jury during the trial</i></sup></p><p>First, we explained that the accused Cloudflare products (<a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/magic-transit/"><u>Magic Transit</u></a> and <a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/argo-smart-routing/argo-for-packets/"><u>Argo for Packets</u></a>) do not route “flows” or “micro-flows” as required by claim 25. Instead, they handle packets individually, on a packet-by-packet basis. Indeed, processing each packet individually is important to the functioning of these products and Cloudflare’s DDoS and security services as a whole.</p><p>Eric also helped to tell our invention story to the jury. He explained how the Cloudflare team saw problems that needed to be solved, and built unique and innovative new products to solve them. He described the work that went into developing Magic Transit and Argo for Packets, and how these products are part of Cloudflare’s modern software-based approach, which is fundamentally different from the hardware-based technology of the ’919 patent. Together, Eric and Dr. Min explained how the benefits of Magic Transit and Argo for Packets enjoyed by Cloudflare’s customers are not attributable to any technology claimed by the ’919 patent.</p>
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/slt3lc6tev37/mYelecmdKiTa0Nm76ziHY/f27109c3dd34dfcea79d2db1b58439eb/BLOG-2579_3.png" alt="BLOG-2579 3" width="1085" height="619" loading="lazy">
          </figure><p><sup><i>From slide deck presented by Cloudflare to the jury during the trial</i></sup></p><p>Second, we explained that Cloudflare doesn’t infringe because claim 25 of the ’919 patent requires certain processes to occur “at” ingress and egress line cards, and Cloudflare’s accused servers do not include line cards.</p>
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/slt3lc6tev37/2BDR7faD5Y8xCnbMn43VLP/3b25b64ab573c964936b478c1c34848e/BLOG-2579_4.png" alt="BLOG-2579 4" width="1074" height="572" loading="lazy">
          </figure><p><sup><i>From slide deck presented by Cloudflare to the jury during the trial</i></sup></p><p>As Dr. Min explained, “line cards” are a specific type of hardware — a physical hardware “card” — that are commonly used in routers. Sable’s witnesses could not deny that the technology of the ’919 patent was tied to old router technology. After all, Caspian Networks Inc. (where the ’919 patent inventors worked) was a router company. Caspian’s core products were routers, and we showed the jury documents describing Caspian’s routers, which used “flow-based” technology on physical hardware line cards.</p>
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/slt3lc6tev37/2So3SbVAhV4bR7Mtcgd1ys/1b3053c8e273b0091267875dd30dd445/Screenshot_2024-10-01_at_11.54.29_AM.png" alt="BLOG-2579 5" width="774" height="574" loading="lazy">
          </figure><p><sup><i>Trial exhibit, image of sample line card</i></sup></p><p>While Sable’s technical expert tried his hardest to convince the jury that various software and hardware components of Cloudflare’s servers constitute “line cards,” his explanations defied credibility. The simple fact is that Cloudflare’s servers do not have line cards.</p><p>Ultimately, the jury understood, returning a verdict that Cloudflare does not infringe claim 25 of the ‘919 patent.</p>
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/slt3lc6tev37/RvaSu6DljUohL3bWZEZAa/e94e72c6c3360bb3efea10b19206cc4c/BLOG-2579_6.png" alt="BLOG-2579 6" width="509" height="321" loading="lazy">
          </figure><p><sup><i>Excerpt from Verdict Form completed by the jury</i></sup></p><h3>The jury agrees: Sable’s patent claim is <u>invalid</u></h3><p>In addition to proving that we do not infringe, we also took on the challenge of proving to the jury that claim 25 of the ’919 patent is invalid and never should have been issued.</p><p>Proving invalidity to a jury is hard. The burden on the defendant is high: Cloudflare needed to prove by clear and convincing evidence that claim 25 is invalid.&nbsp; And, proving it by describing how the claim is obvious in light of the prior art is complicated.</p><p>To do this, we again relied on our technical expert, Dr. Min, to explain how two prior art references, U.S. Patent No. <a href="https://patents.google.com/patent/US6584071B1/en?oq=6584071"><u>6,584,071</u></a> (Kodialam) and U.S. Patent No. <a href="https://patents.google.com/patent/US6680933B1/en?oq=6680933"><u>6,680,933</u></a> (Cheeseman) together render claim 25 of the ’919 patent obvious. Kodialam and Cheeseman are patents from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nortel"><u>Nortel Networks</u></a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucent_Technologies"><u>Lucent</u></a> relating to router technology developed in the late 1990s. Both are prior art to the ’919 patent (i.e., they pre-date the priority date of the ’919 patent), and when considered together by a person skilled in the area of computer engineering and computer networking technology, they rendered obvious the so-called invention of claim 25.</p>
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/slt3lc6tev37/2AwZ3KBpPNQ6Hvfu7I3myv/10d396e88fffb51b02b588e5e95d6cbe/BLOG-2579_7.png" alt="BLOG-2579 7" width="509" height="263" loading="lazy">
          </figure><p><sup><i>Excerpt from Verdict Form completed by the jury</i></sup><sup>&nbsp;</sup></p><h3>Sable does not get its payday …</h3><p>Sable’s real motivation for suing Cloudflare — its desire for a payout — was made clear by Sable’s trial witnesses, who were unified only by their desire to present a wildly inflated view of the alleged “value” of the Sable patent and the damages allegedly owed by Cloudflare.&nbsp;</p><p>Sable’s attorneys tried their best to present their clients as reasonable businessmen, just trying to get what they’re owed for Cloudflare’s purported use of Sable’s patent. But Sable couldn’t hide its true colors from the jury. When Sable presented testimony from Brooks Borchers, the founder of Sable IP, Mr. Borchers was forced to admit that Sable IP is in the “business” of filing lawsuits.</p>
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/slt3lc6tev37/33xEZlojjm1nvnjnV4H7UC/6db1f410d21b919cc744317047f127ef/Screenshot_2024-10-01_at_11.37.17_AM.png" alt="BLOG-2579 8" width="725" height="326" loading="lazy">
          </figure><p><sup><i>Excerpt from Borchers trial testimony</i></sup></p><p>&nbsp;In fact, Mr. Borchers was forced to admit that Sable’s approach is to sue first and ask questions later. Even among patent trolls, this is hardly a noble business practice.</p>
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/slt3lc6tev37/4Dr73QwC1urT9QNZYTzYK7/3882fcdbdeae32f583be2fdea8641729/BLOG-2579_9.png" alt="BLOG-2579 9" width="638" height="796" loading="lazy">
          </figure><p><sup><i>Excerpts from Borchers trial testimony</i></sup></p><p>What's more, Mr. Borchers and his lawyers have teamed up on cases like this before, following the same sue-first-and-ask-questions-later playbook in hopes of a payout. Sable’s true motivations for suing Cloudflare were on full display after this testimony, making Sable’s damages demand all the more galling.</p><p>Sable’s damages expert, Stephen Dell, told the jury that Sable was owed somewhere between <span>$</span>25 million and $94.2 million in damages. But, Mr. Dell was forced to admit to multiple flaws in his damages calculation, and Cloudflare’s damages expert Chris Bakewell explained to the jury how bad inputs and faulty assumptions led Mr. Dell to a wildly inflated damages figure. Indeed, after hearing Sable’s expert’s testimony, Judge Albright said he was “very skeptical” of Mr. Dell’s opinions, explaining that he was “very concerned that there’s not support for his methodology.”</p><p>In the end, Mr. Dell’s outsized damages demand didn’t matter because the jury found that Cloudflare did not infringe and that the asserted patent claim is invalid. But, it was revealing of Sable’s motivation (greed) and the lengths that it would go to try to get a payout.</p><p>When all was said and done, after all the testimony and argument, we were thrilled when the jury returned its verdict — after less than two hours of deliberations — finding across the board for Cloudflare. The jury’s verdict is truly a validation of our strong belief in the importance of standing up to patent trolls like Sable, and we are grateful for the jury’s time, attention and consideration!</p><h3>Sable admits defeat, and agrees to pay Cloudflare!</h3><p>A jury verdict is not the end of the road in a patent case ... there are post-trial motions, appeals, and other procedural hurdles to jump through before a case is truly over. Tired from the fight, and smarting from its loss, Sable decided it wanted to throw in the towel and end the fight once and for all.</p><p>In the end, Sable agreed to pay Cloudflare $225,000, grant Cloudflare a royalty-free license to its entire patent portfolio, and to dedicate its patents to the public, ensuring that Sable can never again assert them against another company.</p><p>Let’s repeat that first part, just to make sure everyone understands:&nbsp;</p><p>Sable, the patent troll that sued Cloudflare back in March 2021 asserting around 100 claims across four patents, in the end wound up paying Cloudflare. While this $225,000 can’t fully compensate us for the time, energy and frustration of having to deal with this litigation for nearly three years, it does help to even the score a bit. And we hope that it sends an important message to patent trolls everywhere to beware before taking on Cloudflare.</p>
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/slt3lc6tev37/N9m8NlHvXQxDqPyeKVkvW/25fd9499ec94efe977f63de6bcfc78b7/BLOG-2579_10.png" alt="BLOG-2579 10" width="749" height="139" loading="lazy">
          </figure><p><sup>&nbsp;</sup><sup><i>Excerpt from the Dedication to the Public and Royalty Free License Agreement between Sable and Cloudflare</i></sup></p><p>And, let’s talk a bit more about that final part:</p><p>Sable has agreed to dedicate its entire patent portfolio to the public. This means that Sable will tell the U.S. Patent and Trademark Office that it gives up all of its legal rights to its patent portfolio. Sable can never again use these patents to sue for infringement; they can never again use these patents to try to make a quick buck.</p>
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/slt3lc6tev37/4rpPZkNJBZYB7t69g1YssH/b7da43e0686c05ac752effa4411227a1/BLOG-2579_11.png" alt="BLOG-2579 11" width="740" height="205" loading="lazy">
          </figure><p><sup><i>Excerpt from the Dedication to the Public and Royalty Free License Agreement between Sable and Cloudflare</i></sup></p><h3>To sum it up …</h3><p>Cloudflare fought back against the patent troll and we won. We not only defeated Sable's claims in court, we forced Sable to pay Cloudflare for the trouble, and we got Sable's patents dedicated to the public, ensuring that it can never assert these patents against any other company ever again. It was admittedly a lot of work for Cloudflare, but totally worth it.</p><h3>Project Jengo for Sable: Conclusion of the Case</h3><p>A crucial part of our efforts to secure this across-the-board win are our Project Jengo participants.</p><p>Since the <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/project-jengo-redux-cloudflares-prior-art-search-bounty-returns/"><u>launch of the Project Jengo for the Sable case</u></a>, we’ve received hundreds of prior art references from dedicated Project Jengo participants. So far we have awarded <span>$</span>70,000 in prizes to the winners of Chapters 1 through 8. And we still have $30,000 in prizes to award in the Final Awards.</p><p>This blog post marks the official “Conclusion of the Case” under the <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/jengo/sable-rules/"><u>Project Jengo Sable Rules</u></a>. We will continue to accept submissions during the 30-day Grace Period, which lasts until November 2, 2024, and then will move on to selecting winners of the Final Awards.</p><h3>We are thrilled to announce the winners of Chapters 7 and 8</h3><p>We publicly celebrated the <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/project-jengo-2-first-three-winners/"><u>Chapter 1</u></a>, <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/former-rd-engineer-wins-round-2-of-project-jengo-and-cloudflare-wins-at-the-patent-office/"><u>Chapter 2</u></a>, <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/arkansas-engineer-wins-round-3-of-project-jengo-and-cloudflare-continues-to-win-at-the-patent-office/"><u>Chapter 3</u></a> and <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/three-new-winners-of-project-jengo-and-more-defeats-for-the-patent-troll/"><u>Chapters 4-6</u></a> winners in previous blog posts. However, as the trial approached in the Sable case, we chose not to make public announcements for the Chapter 7 and 8 winners out of respect for the judicial process. Now that the case is over, we are delighted to give a big public shout out to the winners of Project Jengo Chapters 7 and 8!</p><p>We selected four total winners in Chapters 7 and 8, each receiving prizes of <span>$</span>5,000, for a grand total of $20,000. Our Chapter 7 winners, George W. and Madhu, each provided helpful and detailed charts containing element-by-element comparisons of the prior art to the relevant Sable patents. George W. is an electrical engineer and lawyer, who is active in the intellectual property community. He learned about Project Jengo in an article posted online, and thought it was a clever idea. The Chapter 8 winners, Jatin and Ketan, also provided thoughtful and detailed submissions. Jatin submitted two pieces of prior art that were particularly good references for Sable’s U.S. Patent No. 7,012,919, which contains the one claim that remained asserted against Cloudflare at trial.</p><p>We also want to again thank our prior chapter winners and everyone who participated in Project Jengo! We look forward to selecting the Final Awards winners — it will be fun to take a walk down memory lane re-reviewing the fantastic prior art submitted by our prior winners, and we can’t wait to check out the new submissions, too! Please use the “Submit Prior Art” link on <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/jengo/sable-prior-art-search/"><u>this page</u></a> for your final entries. Once we’ve announced our Final Awards, we will also update the <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/jengo/priorart/"><u>Sable patents prior art listing</u></a> on our website, to share all the prior art submitted by our Project Jengo participants.</p></div></section><div><p>Cloudflare's connectivity cloud protects <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/network-services/" rel="noreferrer">entire corporate networks</a>, helps customers build <a target="_blank" href="https://workers.cloudflare.com/" rel="noreferrer">Internet-scale applications efficiently</a>, accelerates any <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/performance/accelerate-internet-applications/" rel="noreferrer">website or Internet application</a>, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/ddos/" rel="noreferrer">wards off DDoS attacks</a>, keeps <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/application-security/" rel="noreferrer">hackers at bay</a>, and can help you on <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/products/zero-trust/" rel="noreferrer">your journey to Zero Trust</a>.</p><p>Visit <a target="_blank" href="https://one.one.one.one/" rel="noreferrer">1.1.1.1</a> from any device to get started with our free app that makes your Internet faster and safer.</p><p>To learn more about our mission to help build a better Internet, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/what-is-cloudflare/" rel="noreferrer">start here</a>. If you're looking for a new career direction, check out <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/careers" rel="noreferrer">our open positions</a>.</p></div><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/jengo">Jengo</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/patents">Patents</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/legal">Legal</a></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Image Editing with Gaussian Splatting (137 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.unite.ai/image-editing-with-gaussian-splatting/</link>
            <guid>41729891</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 12:05:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.unite.ai/image-editing-with-gaussian-splatting/">https://www.unite.ai/image-editing-with-gaussian-splatting/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41729891">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="mvp-content-main"><p>A new&nbsp; collaboration between researchers in Poland and the UK proposes the prospect of using <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2308.04079" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Gaussian Splatting</a> to edit images, by temporarily interpreting a selected part of the image into 3D space, allowing the user to modify and manipulate the 3D representation of the image, and then applying the transformation.</p><div id="attachment_206991"><p><img decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-206991" src="https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/cat-example.jpg" alt="To change the orientation of the cat's head, the relevant section is moved into 3D space via Gaussian Splatting, and then manipulated by the user. The modification is then applied. The process is analogous to various modal techniques in Adobe software, that lock off the interface until a current complex process is completed. Source: https://github.com/waczjoan/MiraGe/" width="657" height="296" srcset="https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/cat-example.jpg 1200w, https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/cat-example-300x135.jpg 300w, https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/cat-example-250x113.jpg 250w, https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/cat-example-768x346.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 657px) 100vw, 657px"></p><p id="caption-attachment-206991"><span><em>To change the orientation of the cat's head, the relevant section is moved into 3D space via Gaussian Splatting, and then manipulated by the user. The modification is then applied. The process is analogous to various modal techniques in Adobe software, that lock off the interface until a current complex process is completed.</em> Source: https://github.com/waczjoan/MiraGe/</span></p></div><p>Since the Gaussian Splat element is temporarily represented by a mesh of triangles, and momentarily enters a ‘CGI state', a physics engine integrated into the process can interpret natural movement, either to change the static state of an object, or to produce an animation.</p><div id="attachment_206993"><p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-206993" src="https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/blanket.gif" alt="A physics engine incorporated into the new MiraGe system can perform natural interpretations of physical movement, either for animations or static alterations to an image. " width="666" height="666"></p><p id="caption-attachment-206993"><span><em>A physics engine incorporated into the new MiraGe system can perform natural interpretations of physical movement, either for animations or static alterations to an image.</em></span></p></div><p>There is no generative AI involved in the process, meaning that no <a href="https://www.unite.ai/understanding-diffusion-models-a-deep-dive-into-generative-ai/">Latent Diffusion Models</a> (LDMs) are involved, unlike Adobe's <a href="https://www.unite.ai/adobe-express-enhances-user-experience-with-firefly-generative-ai/">Firefly system</a>, which is trained on Adobe Stock (formerly Fotolia).</p><p>The system – called <em><i>MiraGe</i></em> – interprets selections into 3D space and infers geometry by creating a <em><i>mirror image</i></em> of the selection, and approximating 3D coordinates that can be embodied in a Splat, which then interprets the image into a mesh.</p><p><!--[if lt IE 9]><script>document.createElement('video');</script><![endif]--><video id="video-206987-1" width="740" height="382" preload="metadata" controls="controls"><source type="video/mp4" src="https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/branch-and-god-MIRAGE-AE.mp4?_=1"><a href="https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/branch-and-god-MIRAGE-AE.mp4">https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/branch-and-god-MIRAGE-AE.mp4</a></video></p><p><span><strong><em><b><i>Click to play. </i></b></em></strong><em><i>Further examples of elements that have been either altered manually by a user of the MiraGe system, or subject to physics-based deformation.</i></em></span></p><p>The authors compared the MiraGe system to former approaches, and found that it achieves state-of-the-art performance in the target task.</p><p>Users of the zBrush modeling system will be familiar with this process, since zBrush allows the user to essentially <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FD4w8e8mqTg&amp;t=317s" target="_blank" rel="noopener">‘flatten' a 3D model</a> and add 2D detail, while preserving the underlying mesh, and interpreting the new detail into it – a ‘freeze' that is the opposite of the MiraGe method, which operates more like Firefly or other Photoshop-style modal manipulations, such as warping or crude 3D interpretations.</p><div id="attachment_206996"><p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-206996" src="https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/splatting-mod-MiraGe.jpg" alt="Parametrized Gaussian Splats allow MiraGe to create high-quality reconstructions of selected areas of a 2D image, and apply soft-body physics to the temporarily-3D selection." width="794" height="364" srcset="https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/splatting-mod-MiraGe.jpg 1200w, https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/splatting-mod-MiraGe-300x138.jpg 300w, https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/splatting-mod-MiraGe-250x115.jpg 250w, https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/splatting-mod-MiraGe-768x352.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 794px) 100vw, 794px"></p><p id="caption-attachment-206996"><span><em>Parametrized Gaussian Splats allow MiraGe to create high-quality reconstructions of selected areas of a 2D image, and apply soft-body physics to the temporarily-3D selection.</em></span></p></div><p>The paper states:</p><p><em><i>‘[We] introduce a model that encodes 2D images by simulating human interpretation. Specifically, our model perceives a 2D image as a human would view a photograph or a sheet of paper, treating it as a flat object within a 3D space. </i></em></p><p><em><i>‘This approach allows for intuitive and flexible image editing, capturing the nuances of human perception while enabling complex transformations.'</i></em></p><p>The <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01521">new paper</a> is titled <em><i>MiraGe: Editable 2D Images using Gaussian Splatting</i></em>, and comes from four authors across Jagiellonian University at Kraków, and the University of Cambridge. The full code for the system has been <a href="https://github.com/waczjoan/MiraGe/">released at GitHub</a>.</p><p>Let's take a look at how the researchers tackled the challenge.</p><h2><strong>Method</strong></h2><p>The MiraGe approach utilizes <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2402.01459" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Gaussian Mesh Splatting</a> (GaMeS) parametrization, a technique developed by a group that includes two of the authors of the new paper. GaMeS allows Gaussian Splats to be interpreted as traditional CGI meshes, and to become subject to the standard range of warping and modification techniques that the CGI community has developed over the last several decades.</p><p>MiraGe interprets ‘flat' Gaussians, in a 2D space, and uses GaMeS to ‘pull' content into GSplat-enabled 3D space, temporarily.</p><div id="attachment_206997"><p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-206997" src="https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/games-parametrization-MiraGe.jpg" alt="Each flat Gaussian is represented as three points in a cloud of triangles, called 'triangle soup', opening up the inferred image to manipulation. Source: https://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01521" width="889" height="358" srcset="https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/games-parametrization-MiraGe.jpg 1200w, https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/games-parametrization-MiraGe-300x121.jpg 300w, https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/games-parametrization-MiraGe-250x101.jpg 250w, https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/games-parametrization-MiraGe-768x309.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 889px) 100vw, 889px"></p><p id="caption-attachment-206997"><span><em>Each flat Gaussian is represented as three points in a cloud of triangles, called ‘triangle soup', opening up the inferred image to manipulation.</em> Source: https://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01521</span></p></div><p>We can see in the lower-left corner of the image above that MiraGe creates a ‘mirror' image of the section of an image to be interpreted.</p><p>The authors state:</p><p><em><i>‘[We] employ a novel approach utilizing two opposing cameras positioned along the Y axis, symmetrically aligned around the origin and directed towards one another. The first camera is tasked with reconstructing the original image, while the second models the mirror reflection. </i></em></p><p><em><i>‘The photograph is thus conceptualized as a translucent tracing paper sheet, embedded within the 3D spatial context. The reflection can be effectively represented by horizontally flipping the [image]. This mirror-camera setup enhances the fidelity of the generated reflections, providing a robust solution for accurately capturing visual elements.'</i></em></p><p>The paper notes that once this extraction has been achieved, perspective adjustments that would typically be challenging become accessible via direct editing in 3D. In the example below, we see a selection of an image of a woman that encompasses only her arm. In this instance, the user has tilted the hand downward in a plausible manner, which would be a challenging task by just pushing pixels around.</p><div id="attachment_207000"><p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-207000" src="https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/hand-MiraGe2.jpg" alt="An example of the MiraGe editing technique" width="538" height="328" srcset="https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/hand-MiraGe2.jpg 1000w, https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/hand-MiraGe2-300x183.jpg 300w, https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/hand-MiraGe2-246x150.jpg 246w, https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/hand-MiraGe2-768x468.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 538px) 100vw, 538px"></p><p id="caption-attachment-207000"><span><em>An example of the MiraGe editing technique.</em></span></p></div><p>Attempting this using the Firefly generative tools in Photoshop would usually mean that the hand becomes replaced by a synthesized, diffusion-imagined hand, breaking the authenticity of the edit. Even the more capable systems, such as the <a href="https://github.com/lllyasviel/ControlNet" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ControlNet</a> ancillary system for Stable Diffusion and other Latent Diffusion Models, <a href="https://huggingface.co/XLabs-AI/flux-controlnet-collections" target="_blank" rel="noopener">such as Flux</a>, struggle to achieve this kind of edit in an image-to-image pipeline.</p><p>This particular pursuit has been dominated by methods using Implicit Neural Representations (INRs), such as <a href="https://proceedings.neurips.cc/paper_files/paper/2020/file/53c04118df112c13a8c34b38343b9c10-Paper.pdf">SIREN</a> and <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.05187">WIRE</a>. The difference between an implicit and explicit representation method is that the coordinates of the model are not directly addressable in INRs, which use a <a href="https://byjus.com/maths/continuous-function/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">continuous function</a>.</p><p>By contrast, Gaussian Splatting offers explicit and addressable X/Y/Z <a href="https://mathinsight.org/cartesian_coordinates" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Cartesian coordinates</a>, even though it uses Gaussian ellipses rather than <a href="https://archive.is/Tnl4i" target="_blank" rel="noopener">voxels</a> or other methods of depicting content in a 3D space.</p><p>The idea of using GSplat in a 2D space has been most prominently presented, the authors note, in the 2024 Chinese academic collaboration <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2403.08551" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GaussianImage</a>, which offered a 2D version of Gaussian Splatting, enabling inference frame rates of 1000fps. However, this model has no implementation related to image editing.</p><p>After GaMeS parametrization extracts the selected area into a Gaussian/mesh representation, the image is reconstructed using the Material Points Method (MPM) technique first outlined in a <a href="https://yuanming.taichi.graphics/publication/2018-mlsmpm/mls-mpm-cpic.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2018 CSAIL paper</a>.</p><p>In MiraGe, during the process of alteration, the Gaussian Splat exists as a guiding proxy for an equivalent mesh version, much as <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.01815.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">3DMM CGI models</a> are <a href="https://www.unite.ai/rignerf-a-new-deepfakes-method-that-uses-neural-radiance-fields/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">frequently used</a> as orchestration methods for implicit neural rendering techniques such as Neural Radiance Fields (NeRF).</p><p>In the process, two-dimensional objects are modeled in 3D space, and the parts of the image that are not being influenced are not visible to the end user, so that the contextual effect of the manipulations are not apparent until the process is concluded.</p><p>MiraGe can be integrated into the popular open source 3D program <a href="https://www.blender.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Blender</a>, which is now <a href="https://github.com/benrugg/AI-Render" target="_blank" rel="noopener">frequently used</a> in AI-inclusive workflows, primarily for image-to-image purposes.</p><div id="attachment_207001"><p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-207001" src="https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/blender-MiraGe.jpg" alt="A workflow for MiraGe in Blender, involving the movement of the arm of a figure depicted in a 2D image." width="1200" height="416" srcset="https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/blender-MiraGe.jpg 1200w, https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/blender-MiraGe-300x104.jpg 300w, https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/blender-MiraGe-250x87.jpg 250w, https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/blender-MiraGe-768x266.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px"></p><p id="caption-attachment-207001"><span>A workflow for MiraGe in Blender, involving the movement of the arm of a figure depicted in a 2D image.</span></p></div><p>The authors offer two versions of a deformation approach based on Gaussian Splatting – <em><i>Amorphous</i></em> and <em><i>Graphite</i></em>.</p><p>The Amorphous approach directly utilizes the GaMeS method, and allows the extracted 2D selection to move freely in 3D space, whereas the Graphite approach constrains the Gaussians to 2D space during initialization and training.</p><p>The researchers found that though the Amorphous approach might handle complex shapes better than Graphite, ‘tears' or rift artefacts were more evident, where the edge of the deformation aligns with the unaffected portion of the image*.</p><p>Therefore, they developed the aforementioned ‘mirror image' system:</p><p><em><i>‘[We] employ a novel approach utilizing two opposing cameras positioned along the Y axis, symmetrically aligned around the origin and directed towards one another. </i></em></p><p><em><i>‘The first camera is tasked with reconstructing the original image, while the second models the mirror reflection. The photograph is thus conceptualized as a translucent tracing paper sheet, embedded within the 3D spatial context. The reflection can be effectively represented by horizontally flipping the [image]. </i></em></p><p><em><i>‘This mirror-camera setup enhances the fidelity of the generated reflections, providing a robust solution for accurately capturing visual elements.'</i></em></p><p>The paper notes that MiraGe can use external physics engines such as those <a href="https://docs.blender.org/manual/en/latest/physics/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">available in Blender</a>, or in <a href="https://github.com/taichi-dev/taichi_elements" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Taichi_Elements</a>.</p><h2><strong>Data and Tests</strong></h2><p>For image quality assessments in tests carried out for MiraGe, the <a href="https://www.unite.ai/what-is-noise-in-image-processing-a-primer/">Signal-to-Noise Ratio</a> (SNR) and <a href="https://www.cns.nyu.edu/pub/eero/wang03b.pdf">MS-SIM</a> metrics were used.</p><p>Datasets used were the <a href="https://r0k.us/graphics/kodak/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kodak Lossless True Color Image Suite</a>, and the <a href="https://data.vision.ee.ethz.ch/cvl/DIV2K/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">DIV2K </a><a href="https://developers.google.com/machine-learning/crash-course/training-and-test-sets/splitting-data" target="_blank" rel="noopener">validation</a> set. The resolutions of these datasets suited a comparison with the closest prior work, Gaussian Image. The other rival frameworks trialed were SIREN, WIRE, NVIDIA's <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05989" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Instant Neural Graphics Primitives</a> (I-NGP), and <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2309.15426" target="_blank" rel="noopener">NeuRBF</a>.</p><p>The experiments took place on a NVIDIA GEFORCE RTX 4070 laptop and on a NVIDIA RTX 2080.</p><div id="attachment_207002"><p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-207002" src="https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/tab-1.jpg" alt="MiraGe offers state-of-the-art results against the chosen prior frameworks, according to the results featured in the new paper." width="759" height="274" srcset="https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/tab-1.jpg 1200w, https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/tab-1-300x108.jpg 300w, https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/tab-1-250x90.jpg 250w, https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/tab-1-768x277.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 759px) 100vw, 759px"></p><p id="caption-attachment-207002"><span><em>MiraGe offers state-of-the-art results against the chosen prior frameworks, according to the results featured in the new paper.</em></span></p></div><p>Of these results, the authors state:</p><p><em><i>‘We see that our proposition outperforms the previous solutions on both datasets. The quality measured by both metrics shows significant improvement compared to all the previous approaches.'</i></em></p><h2><strong>Conclusion</strong></h2><p>MiraGe's adaptation of 2D Gaussian Splatting is clearly a nascent and tentative foray into what may prove to be a very interesting alternative to the vagaries and whims of using diffusion models to effect modifications to an image (i.e., via Firefly and other API-based diffusion methods, and via open source architectures such as Stable Diffusion and Flux).</p><p>Though there are many diffusion models that can effect minor changes in images, LDMs are limited by their semantic and often ‘over-imaginative' approach to a text-based user request for a modification.</p><p>Therefore the ability to temporarily pull part of an image into 3D space, manipulate it and replace it back into the image, while using only the source image as a reference, seems a task that Gaussian Splatting may be well suited for in the future.</p><p>* <em><i>There is some confusion in the paper, in that it cites ‘Amorphous-Mirage' as the most effective and capable method, in spite of its tendency to produce unwanted Gaussians (artifacts), while arguing that ‘Graphite-Mirage' is more flexible. It appears that Amorphous-Mirage obtains the best detail, and Graphite-Mirage the best flexibility. Since both methods are presented in the paper, with their diverse strengths and weaknesses, the authors' preference, if any, does not appear to be clear at this time.</i></em></p><p><em><i>First published Thursday, October 3, 2024</i></em></p>   <p><a href="https://subscribe.unite.ai/"> <img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/join-the-future-newsletter.png" alt="" width="1099" height="628" srcset="https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/join-the-future-newsletter.png 1099w, https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/join-the-future-newsletter-300x171.png 300w, https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/join-the-future-newsletter-250x143.png 250w, https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/join-the-future-newsletter-768x439.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1099px) 100vw, 1099px"> </a>  <a href="https://subscribe.unite.ai/"> <img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.unite.ai/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/Unite-AI-Mobile-Newsletter-1.png" alt="" width="1099" height="628"> </a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Ask HN: What happens to ".io" TLD after UK gives back the Chagos Islands? (140 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41729526</link>
            <guid>41729526</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 11:18:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41729526">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <tbody><tr id="41730140"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730140" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730140&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Nothing, because .io was operated by some wheeler-dealer without the authority of the UK. Apparently he just dumped money into the bank accounts of the various overseas territories he was selling the domain names for and they were OK with it?</p><p>He's since sold it on and now a hedge fund owns it.</p><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.io" rel="nofollow">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.io</a></p><p>Officially, the British Indian Ocean Territories will cease to exist, therefore so would the ISO 2-letter country code. However, ccTLDs have outlasted countries before, notably ".su" for the no longer existing USSR. I suspect that IANA would prioritise not breaking millions of domain names over trying to police ccTLDs.</p><p>Google's view on the matter is that .io is already effectively a gTLD rather than a ccTLD, like with .nu, .to, .tv, as most of the registrants run websites with a global audience or at least an audience other than the island nations whose ccTLDs they are.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730333"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730333" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730333&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>As far as I can find .su is the <i>exception</i> in surviving, not the rule, and who operated the ccTLD is irrelevant to the question of whether ICANN decides to allow it to live on.</p><p>It does seem <i>likely</i> that ICANN won't kill off all existing registrations, but this is supposition, not an answer. If we look only at what they've done historically to ccTLDs the most likely outcome is that new registrations become locked and ICANN attempts to phase the .io TLD out.</p><p>They may break that trend now given how much they've already polluted the TLD space, but they may not, and I think your comment is a bit too optimistic. People with .io domains should absolutely be paying close attention here.</p><p>Edit: gnfargbl found the actual written policy [0].</p><p>[0] <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41730559">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41730559</a></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730977"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730977" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730977&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>That's not entirely true.  .su is an exceptional reservation but it's not the only one with a tld. For instance ".uk" exists and ".ac" exists.</p><p>It's absolutely possible that someone will asking for an exceptional reservation for IO at ISO and it can be kept alive forever.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41731024"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41731024" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41731024&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; It's absolutely possible that someone will asking for an exceptional reservation for IO at ISO and it can be kept alive forever.</p><p>I agree it's possible, I disagree with OP that it's a foregone conclusion.</p><p>At this point if I were the owner of a .io domain I would treat that as the unlikely best case scenario and start looking at what domain I'd fall back to if ICANN sticks to their rules.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41730919"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41730222"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730222" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730222&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>As someone with an io domain, I really appreciate this post.  I've had general fears that political decisions would be made that would make trouble for me on top of the standard business decisions to take as much as they can from me.</p><p>Now it seems likely I will only have to worry about the hedge funds!</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730621"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730621" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730621&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Won't the hedge fund have to acquiesce to the ICANN if it demands that .Io be shut down? Afaik, ICANN only allows two letter domains for countries.</p><p>Alternatively ICANN might (should imo) transfer the TLD registrar to Mauritius.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41730301"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730332"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730332" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730332&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Oh be quiet. That’s a ludicrously uncharitable interpretation of what they were saying, all in service of you…getting to be…snarky?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41730323"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="41731082"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41730504"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41730320"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730320" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730320&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; I suspect that IANA would prioritise not breaking millions of domain names over trying to police ccTLDs.</p><p>I'm surprised this wouldn't be the default behavior for existing owners? Kinda making me re-think buying an IO domain for my personal stuff. Are gTLDs the safest option?</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730359"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730409"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730409" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730409&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Outages and poor management are one possibility. Other is the fact that you have to trust the country running the ccTLD with DNSSEC keys. This might rule out things like using TLSA/DANE or SSHFP records.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730496"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730496" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730496&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I think more relevantly than DNSSEC, couldn't they issue TLS certificates using DNS-01 validation? You have to trust your DNS registry.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="41730623"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730623" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730623&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>The gTLDs are also subject to the whims of a foreign country (usually the USA). The safest option is probably your own country's ccTLD, since any dispute would go solely through your own country's laws and courts (to which you're already subjected, by virtue of living there).</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41730628"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730650"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41731062"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41731062" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41731062&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>The .io/.sh/.ac TLDs were effectively invented and run by a British guy; he states some of the resulting profits were shared back with the UK government, which controls those territories, to benefit the inhabitants of such territories; the UK government denies this ever happened. The reality is likely that those people were effectively stripped of their rightful "internet property", in a way not dissimilar from old colonial exploitation.</p><p>To be honest, if .io is not handed back to the Chagossian, it would be better to shut it down and turn the page on a pretty shameful page of internet history.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41730837"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730837" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730837&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I don't think it does directly, but I suppose in a macro sense, by paying for a .io domain you're contributing to the system responsible for the exploitation of these people.</p><p>An analogy: a bunch of indigenous people are kicked off their island, and coffee is grown there by the people who evicted them. You buy the coffee, and the people who have the rightful claim to the land don't receive any of the profits.</p><p>To add insult to injury, the coffee is named after the island it's grown on, and that's mostly why it's popular - because it's a really good name for coffee (maybe it's called Java Island).</p><p>That's basically what the .io domain is.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                              <tr id="41730559"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730559" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730559&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>ICANN actually has a relevant written policy at <a href="https://www.iana.org/help/cctld-retirement" rel="nofollow">https://www.iana.org/help/cctld-retirement</a>.</p><p>The short answer is that -- if ICANN follows the policy -- then following the removal of IO from ISO-3166-2, the ccTLD has five years to initiate an orderly shutdown.</p><p>The ccTLD manager may request that this be extended to a maximum of ten years, but to do so they need to have reasons beyond a general desire to retain the existing ccTLD.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730914"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730914" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730914&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>From the policy document:</p><p>"ccTLD eligibility is determined by the associated country or territory being assigned in the ISO 3166-1 standard."</p><p>So how does a country code get removed from the ISO 3166-1 list? A cursory web search wasn't very revealing.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41731079"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41730573"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730609"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730609" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730609&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>You're welcome. I think people here are often surprised that the internet registries actually spend time thinking about this stuff, and developing policy for it. But they do, and the results are easily accessible -- the link I provided was the top search engine hit for "icann cctld retirement policy".</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                            <tr id="41730664"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730720"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730788"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730788" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730788&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>ICANN's position is that their policy is triggered by changes to ISO-3166. The code SU has not been removed from ISO-3166-2; instead it is "exceptionally reserved" (as is the code UK).</p><p>If the standards committee takes the same approach with IO, then it's possible that gives ICANN a route not to apply this policy. However, if IO is deleted completely, then my reading is the policy would apply.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                              <tr id="41730212"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730212" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730212&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>The .su ccTLD survived the collapse of the Soviet Union [0], with Russia maintaining it. It sounds like ICANN has tried to get rid of it but had too much opposition.</p><p>On the other hand, .yu expired after being managed by Serbia for a few years [1].</p><p>If I had to guess I'd say .io will likely follow .su, not .yu, because there's enough lobbying power behind the TLD to at least keep resolving the existing domains. But from what I can see the default course for a ccTLD is to get phased out when its corresponding country disappears.</p><p>Edit: gnfargbl found the actual written policy [3].</p><p>[0] <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/.su" rel="nofollow">https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/.su</a></p><p>[1] <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/.yu" rel="nofollow">https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/.yu</a></p><p>[3] <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41730559">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41730559</a></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730315"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730315" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730315&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>.su hopefully dies in the future. It is often used for cybercrime, neo-nazi websites and the russian controlled puppet government of certain russian controlled Ukrainian territories.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730482"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730482" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730482&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>TIL that the USSR had its own TLD. As a child, I always thought .su domains were specifically for warez uses.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730591"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730591" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730591&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>The GDR (East Germany) also had its own TLD, .dd (for Deutsche Demokratische Republik), but it was never operated in the global DNS and there were only like two registrations.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41730417"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730417" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730417&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>It's actually kinda crazy that it has been kept. I personally think resolvers should not resolve that zone at all.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730477"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730477" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730477&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>The crazy thing is that there's a list of actually agreed-upon root name servers and they maintain a uniform namespace for the internet.</p><p>I suspect the above statement isn't actually a true statement across the world, but at least for today the list of roots isn't generically ideological in the same way a broad set of "obvious truths" is now ideological.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41731007"><td></td></tr>
                              <tr id="41730083"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730083" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730083&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>The .io registry is operated by Identity Digital which is a consolidation of a bunch of different registries from the last decade[1]. Identity Digital own (and sometimes just operate) many different TLDs and ccTLDs: most likely, the registrar will retain the right to operate the ccTLD and start paying license fees for each .io to Mauritius. The .tv ccTLD is the most famous example of this, as something like 15% of Tuvalu's GDP is from licensing of the .tv ccTLD.</p><p>[1] ICB acquired by Afilias, Afilias acquired by Donuts, Donuts rebranded to Identity Digital.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730288"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730288" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730288&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>The ccTLD for Mauritius is .mu. The e British Indian Ocean territories stop existing once the UK releases its claims to the territories so there goes the country code of "io"</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730352"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730352" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730352&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>The country codes used for ccTLDs are arbitrary, I thought: they're <i>roughly</i> consistent with ISO 3166-1 alpha-2 codes but not exactly. Are there precedents to suggest a country can only have one ccTLD?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730430"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730430" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730430&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>No, there's lots of counterexamples that are typically designed around subregions or territories (I understand there are nuances here, but this sets the general spirit of when this happens).  The UK has .uk and .gb, US has .us and had .um , Austrailia has .au, .cx (Christmas Island), .cc (Cocos/Keeling Islands)</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730499"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730499" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730499&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Had to look .gb up!</p><p><i>With the demise of X.400 e-mail and IANA's general aim of one TLD per country, use of .gb declined; the domain remains in existence, but it is not currently open to new domain registrations.</i></p><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.gb" rel="nofollow">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.gb</a></p><p>NB I was curious as to whether .gb would be strict and exclude NI - who get to use .ie if they want...</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                                    <tr id="41731101"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41730470"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730470" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730470&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>The .io TLD will disappear, but given its huge use I expect ICANN to allow an especially long transition period.</p><p>Since it's two letters long, it cannot be retained as a generic TLD, as it's in the country TLD namespace and might be reused as such for a different country in the (very far) future. With only 26*26 = 676 possibilities and currently around 200 countries you just can't keep old codes around without an extremely good reason.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41729640"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41729640" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41729640&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Let’s start my comment new /o\</p><p>My guess is that noting will happen for now. It’s mostly a decision that ICANN working groups have to figure out. But given the current size of the .io zone and that we already have a non existing cctld (.su for Soviet Unite), I’m pretty confident it will exist in the mid-term future.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41729964"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41729964" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41729964&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>.su is administered by the Russian national registry, because Russia is de facto the Soviet Union’s successor state. In this case, though, would .io stay with the UK or come under Mauritian control? It’s not clear.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730416"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730416" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730416&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Like the other remnants of the British Empire, the British Indian Ocean Territory was never a part of the UK. It was just land that we (the UK) expropriated from Mauritius at independence. A just solution would be for Mauritius, as the (now) actual successor state, to control dot-io.</p><p>IMO what will probably happen is that ICANN "promotes" the zone to being yet another top-level non-country code domain like .biz or .horse etc. Which is effectively what it is now.</p><p>Edit to add:</p><p>I don't think the .su precedent is applicable here. The Soviet Union was an internationally recognised state with a population, military, Montevideo Convention duties, seat at the UN, etc. The BIOT was and is nothing like that.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730557"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730557" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730557&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>This isn't quite true for Ascension or the Falkland Islands, they were both uninhabited when discovered and they're not part of any existing country</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730831"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730831" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730831&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I'm not sure of the point you're making.</p><p>Sure, there's a lot of evidence that they were "terra nullius" before being claimed for the British empire. But the Chagos archipelago was inhabited utill its population was compulsorily expelled in the mid twentieth century.</p><p>I was surprised to discover that Ascension even has a ccTLD. I guess I assumed that the population was wholly military.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41731119"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="5"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="200"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41731119" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41731119&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p><i>&gt; I was surprised to discover that Ascension even has a ccTLD</i></p><p>That's because it was created by the same guy who created .io and .sh - British DNS "pioneer" Paul Kane, who clearly had a passion for finding remaining corners of the British Empire that could "claim" a bit of internet land (for his own profit).</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="41730719"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730719" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730719&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Turning dot-io into a gTLD is certainly seems like the best course of action, but I think it's far from likely that ICANN will do that considering that there are no other two-letter gTLDs.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730853"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41731129"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="5"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="200"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41731129" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41731129&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>because there are fewer combinations of two-letter codes. This is also why they are reserved to actual countries.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                              <tr id="41730130"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730130" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730130&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; In this case, though, would .io stay with the UK or come under Mauritian control? It’s not clear.</p><p>Before the retirement of .yu, Slovenia wanted to hold on to it, but it was not the successor state of Yugoslavia so they had to relinquish control and pass it to Serbia.  So going by that logic, it would not stay in the UK (for long).</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730451"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730451" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730451&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>British Indian Ocean Territory isn’t a state, it’s just a territory with a military base on it, so there is no successor state.</p><p>It’s like if Guantanamo Bay had its own ccTLD.</p><p>The land will go to Mauritius, the legal entity of British Indian Ocean Territory will cease to exist (presumably).</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730696"><td></td></tr>
                              <tr id="41730176"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730176" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730176&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>ccTLDs other than .su have been retired when the country they represented ceased to exist or got renamed. .zr, .tp, .cs (twice?) according to [0]</p><p>I agree with you though, there doesn't seem to be a strong rule for this kind of thing and all interested parties would likely prefer for .io to continue to exist, so it will continue to exist, probably under Mauritius's ownership.</p><p>[0] <a href="https://snapshot.internetx.com/en/these-tlds-do-not-exist-anymore/" rel="nofollow">https://snapshot.internetx.com/en/these-tlds-do-not-exist-an...</a></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41731003"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41730393"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730393" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730393&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>The fact that there is an answer other than “every TLD will definitely exist until the death of the internet itself” is wild to me.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730528"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730528" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730528&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>The "internet" has died several times already.</p><p>I doubt I could send email to anyone on bitnet or via a UUCP bang path, for example.</p><p>This iteration of the internet is pretty big; it may not die (where you live) but it will likely continue fragmenting into a loosely coupled set of affiliated networks with semi-realtime gateways between them (see also UUCP / bitnet).</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730744"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730744" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730744&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; This iteration of the internet is pretty big; it may not die (where you live) but it will likely continue fragmenting into a loosely coupled set of affiliated networks [...]</p><p>Isn't the Internet already a "loosely coupled set of affiliated networks", with each AS being a separate network?</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730838"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730838" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730838&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Yes -- to some degree.  And "AS" could mean "BGP AS" or it could mean "country or alliance of countries" -- the internet as seen in the west vs iran are likely very different things.</p><p>Maybe skynet uses one set of roots and thenet uses a different set of roots and freenet has taken the IPs of the roots and sends you to their dns heirarchy and they also mandate that you have their set of CAs.</p><p>But as of right now people don't carry different phones to communicate on different internets (though they do have different chat / voice communication applications / networks).</p><p>UUCP / bitnet were (are?) store-and-forward gateway mechanisms.  "If you want to send email to that google address you have to send it as friend@gmail.com@@freenet_audit and it'll be forwarded if the filters approve."</p><p>My point is that there have been a variety of different internets in the past; this one got the name "the internet" but there's no reason it won't fragment (more) into a morass semi-incompatible fragments.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                              <tr id="41730514"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730514" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730514&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Do people really think ICANN will make a large number of popular startups/websites/apps unusable overnight based on a technicality? That's not how the world works. .io has a globally recognized registrar and they will continue doing business as they do today.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730562"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730562" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730562&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I don't think they'd do it overnight, but I can absolutely see them locking future registrations and setting an expiration date.</p><p>They might get enough complaints that they have to keep extending that date indefinitely. And they might not choose to do it at all in this case. But they've been very clear over the years what ccTLDs are supposed to be for, and their first instinct will be to preserve the integrity of the naming system as designed, not to preserve startups who bet on them ignoring their own rules.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41730767"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730767" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730767&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Crimes against humanity, colonialism, recognition of territorial integrity are not a "technicality".</p><p>The British Indian Ocean Territory was always a walking example of all of the above. It was created by the UK, illegally, to keep a strategic military base instead of liberating it with the rest of the previous colony, Mauritius. It was never OK, and it was never OK to use .io. If I had to make an analogy with the real world, it would be like paying to sleep in a house that you knew was stolen from its actual and rightful owner who is now living under a bridge. You are strictly morally in the wrong.</p><p>BIOT will longer exist, so logically .io shouldn't either. None of that is a "technicality".</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730877"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41731077"><td></td></tr>
                              <tr id="41729531"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41729973"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41729973" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41729973&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; The US-UK base will remain on Diego Garcia – a key factor enabling the deal to go forward at a time of growing geopolitical rivalries in the region between Western countries, India, and China.</p><p>So nothing really changes lol. Just a couple of paperwork remarks</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730597"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730597" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730597&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I think this will depend on the treaty.</p><p>If Diego Garcia remains as UK-sovereign land, then since different laws (etc) apply it's likely ISO would keep the IO code for it.</p><p>If Mauritius keeps the islands they gain with a different status (tax, immigration and so on) compared to the rest of Mauritius, then a code might be needed for that — but Mauritius probably won't be keen on "IO".</p><p>If the whole lot becomes 'ordinary Mauritius' then the code is no longer needed and will be removed.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41731104"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41730193"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730193" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730193&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Per TFA, Mauritius will be able to resettle the other islands, so this isn't just a paperwork change.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41730806"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730806" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730806&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; So nothing really changes lol</p><p>A crime against humanity begins to get fixed. Chagosians will finally be allowed to go back to their homes. Mauritius will get paid a rent for the lease of the Diego Garcia base from the US.</p><p>Also, Mauritius is a signatory of the Treaty on the Prohibition of Nuclear Weapons, and thus no nuclear weapons are allowed within its territory. TBD if there will be a special agreement allowing special sovereignty for the US/UK, which might allow the US to station nuclear weapons there (which it probably currently does).</p><p>So there's definitely change. The UK and US finally accepted their crime, which is extremely rare. Genuinely, are there other examples of them suffering consequences (even if their consequences are a return to the status quo, ish), for other of their violations of international law and/or crimes against humanity? None come to mind.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41730220"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730220" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730220&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Mauritius will get 'financial support' for 'leasing' the military base and resettlement can happen on the other islands</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41730572"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41730234"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730234" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730234&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>In an ideal world, orphan TLDs should be kept alive until a new country with that code is born. New registrations should be closed though.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41730385"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730385" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730385&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Is there anything that can be done to petition ICANN or some other authority to help preserve this?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41729895"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41729986"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41729986" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41729986&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I did, but none of the articles about this news that are currently available mention the .io issue.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41730004"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41731052"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41731046"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41730452"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730452" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730452&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I feel like some of you are going to run for politics in a few decades and owning a .io domain with no residence or operation in that part of the world, while technically not wrong at the time, will be the seen with the same disdain as blackface, cultural appropriation, or wearing a Nazi uniform to a Halloween party.</p><p>It seems in poor taste to use your privileges to perform digital colonization, revise the intention that .IO was never about Indian Ocean territory, and justify it all simply because it was a convenient way at the time for you to get attention and make money.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730495"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730695"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41730949"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="41729918"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41730058"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41730058" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41730058&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41729526"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>That is not possible.  However it's possible that "not much" will happen, but the .io domain would have to move to the control of another country with the current rules in place.  For historic precedent on this you can look at the .yu domain which was forcefully transferred to Serbia (more precisely FR Yugoslavia) when Slovenia did not want to give it up.</p><p>I don't think it's very likely that it will be retired given the state of .su.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  </tbody></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[EU: Definition of "potential terrorists" opens door to broad information-sharing (143 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.statewatch.org/news/2024/october/eu-definition-of-potential-terrorists-opens-door-to-broad-information-sharing/</link>
            <guid>41729278</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 10:36:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.statewatch.org/news/2024/october/eu-definition-of-potential-terrorists-opens-door-to-broad-information-sharing/">https://www.statewatch.org/news/2024/october/eu-definition-of-potential-terrorists-opens-door-to-broad-information-sharing/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41729278">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                    

    <ul>
        
            <li><a href="https://www.statewatch.org/">Home</a> <span>/</span></li>
            <li><a href="https://www.statewatch.org/news/">News</a> <span>/</span></li>
            <li><a href="https://www.statewatch.org/news/2024/">2024</a> <span>/</span></li>
            <li><a href="https://www.statewatch.org/news/2024/october/">October</a> <span>/</span></li>

        
        <li>EU: Definition of “potential terrorists” opens door to broad information-sharing</li>
    </ul>

                    
                            <h6>Topic</h6>
                            <h6>Country/Region</h6>

                    <p>02 October 2024</p>
                    
                    <p><em>EU member states can now collect and share information on “potential terrorists”. This category is based on a new informal definition that was agreed with no democratic scrutiny. While claiming to target those who may engage in political violence, there is potential for far broader application.</em></p>
                    
<p><img src="https://www.statewatch.org/media/4524/eu-potential-terrorists.jpg" alt="" width="100%" data-udi="umb://media/c6e140caf1114300adab6f4e8d8c0cb4"><br><em>Image: <a rel="noopener" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/inaction/4223929686/in/photostream/" target="_blank">Andrew</a>, <a rel="noopener" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/" target="_blank">CC BY-NC-ND 2.0</a></em></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>Increasing efforts against “radicalisation”</strong></p>
<p>The EU and its forerunners have targeted radicalism and “radicalisation” for <a href="https://www.tni.org/en/publication/the-globalisation-of-countering-violent-extremism-policies">decades</a>. This &nbsp;agenda gained a firmer hold <a href="https://www.statewatch.org/news/2013/july/eu-seeks-increased-surveillance-of-travel-and-social-media-to-deal-with-foreign-fighters/">in 2011</a>, when the European Commission established the Radicalisation Awareness Network.</p>
<p>In June this year, the Commission <a href="https://home-affairs.ec.europa.eu/policies/internal-security/counter-terrorism-and-radicalisation/prevention-radicalisation/eu-knowledge-hub-radicalisation-prevention-20_en">launched</a> a new <a rel="noopener" data-udi="umb://media/ac969f084247428a9b253f528940c845" href="https://www.statewatch.org/media/4525/eu-com-brochure-radicalisation-knowledge-hub-6-24.pdf" target="_blank" title="Eu Com Brochure Radicalisation Knowledge Hub 6 24">€60 million</a> (pdf) “Knowledge Hub” to further expand the agenda. The hub aims “to collaborate in a new way at the EU level to address the challenges posed by radicalisation.”</p>
<p>Around the same time, the Belgian Council presidency circulated a document (pdf) which “sums up the Presidency focus areas and initiatives for the past six months in the domain of counter-terrorism (CT)”. It says:</p>
<p><em>“</em><em>Member States should continue their efforts </em><em>to recognise and handle, at an early stage, public security threats stemming from individuals considered by national law enforcement authorities to constitute a violent extremist/terrorist threat.”</em></p>
<p>This would rely on information on these individuals being entered into EU databases, such as the Schengen Information System or Europol’s files. The document says information should be entered “where possible and in line with national and EU legislation.”</p>
<p><strong>Informal definition of “potential terrorist”</strong></p>
<p>These plans build upon a recent “shared understanding” of who EU authorities consider a "potential terrorist or violent extremist threat,” a concept encapsulated in the document by the German term <em>Gefährder</em>. The German authorities introduced the phrase and the topic of “potential terrorists” into EU institutions.</p>
<p>The Council’s internal security committee (COSI) approved this “shared understanding” <a rel="noopener" data-udi="umb://media/ab42a726c66147f8a70989d76791367a" href="https://www.statewatch.org/media/4527/eu-council-cosi-minutes-10752-24.pdf" target="_blank" title="Eu Council Cosi Minutes 10752 24">in May this year</a> (pdf).</p>
<p>By framing it as a “shared understanding”, COSI avoided legal reforms. This would have required lengthy negotiations, as well as an opportunity for democratic scrutiny.</p>
<p>The document that sets out <a rel="noopener" data-udi="umb://media/ab8ea0d926e64d4f9bbf3b2ea8d4aaf4" href="https://www.statewatch.org/media/4526/eu-council-gefahrder-shared-understanding-9988-24.pdf" target="_blank" title="Eu Council Gefahrder Shared Understanding 9988 24">the definition</a> (pdf) notes:</p>
<p><em>“The criteria are strictly <strong>non-binding</strong> and do not affect the existing mechanisms and procedures already established at European and national level. Their goal is to promote entering such individuals into the European databases and information systems by the Member States subject to the legal requirements governing these systems.” (emphasis in original)</em></p>
<p>As <a href="https://www.statewatch.org/news/2024/may/who-s-a-potential-terrorist-or-violent-extremist-threat-plans-to-exchange-information-about-future-criminals/">previously reported by <em>Statewatch</em></a>, the criteria consist of three points.</p>
<ol>
<li>A “minimum materiality threshold”. This requires “objective and verifiable… information suggesting that a criminal offence, or future criminal offence, has a certain degree of seriousness.”</li>
<li>A “basic indicative criterion”. This requires “objective, verifiable information” leading to a belief that the individual in question “will in the future commit, facilitate, support or engage in terrorist or violent extremist offences.”</li>
<li>A series of “indicative auxiliary criteria”. This could be involvement in terrorist offences, sharing terrorist content online, or being the subject of an EU entry ban.</li>
</ol>
<p>This Council initiative comes at the same time as the EU’s rollout of new information systems and an updated Europol mandate. These developments will massively expand the EU’s collection of information on “risky” individuals.</p>
<p>Through this “shared understanding”, the Council of the EU has created space for a new, informal practice. It will likely permit the collection and sharing of data on far more people than those involved in terrorism and violence.</p>
<p><strong>The effects on asylum-seekers and refugees</strong></p>
<p>The Belgian Presidency document outlines categories of people who this new practice may cover. These include asylum seekers and refugees, as well as climate and environmental activists.</p>
<p>The document notes the “limited” number of asylum seekers and refugees involved in terrorism and violence, but the new initiative adds to others that frame them as suspects.</p>
<p>As <a href="https://www.statewatch.org/news/2024/march/eu-intelligence-sharing-plan-extended-from-asylum-seekers-to-any-foreigner-involved-in-a-migratory-procedure/"><em>Statewatch</em> reported in March</a>, this includes an expanded intelligence-sharing plan introduced by the Belgian Presidency. This seeks to “strengthen cooperation and exchange of information between immigration and asylum authorities and between CT [counter-terrorism] authorities,” likely to be policing and intelligence agencies.</p>
<p>They justify this as a response to “terrorist attacks in Europe” that have “triggered a debate on how to better prevent future attacks.”</p>
<p><strong>The effects on climate and environmental activists</strong></p>
<p>The EU’s interest in “radicalisation” also targets climate and environmental activists. The recent Belgian Presidency document states:</p>
<p><em>“Climate activism is on the rise, together with an increased willingness to use violence, marking a shift from environmental activism to <strong>environmental extremism</strong>” (emphasis in original).</em></p>
<p>To back this up, the document refers to a report by the EU Counter-Terrorism Coordinator, which purportedly examined “the role climate change and environmental concerns play in the ideologies and narratives of violent extremists and terrorists in the EU.”</p>
<p>Yet, the report itself said it was largely speculative:</p>
<p><em>“The potential for terrorism and violent extremism linked to the environment and climate change is at this moment limited but might become more significant in the coming years.”</em></p>
<p>The Belgian Presidency document included a similar note on the “limited” number of asylum seekers and refugees involved in terrorism and violence. Yet, both groups remain targets of the EU’s agenda against “radicalisation”.</p>
<p>The UN Special Rapporteur on Environmental Defenders under the Aarhus Convention has <a href="https://www.statewatch.org/media/4190/un-unsr-environmental-protest-civil-disobedience-crackdowns-28-2-24.pdf">issued a warning</a> that:</p>
<p><em>“…the conflation of peaceful climate activism with radicalisation and terrorism may increase polarisation by wrongly labelling activists as radicals and trivialising terrorism.” </em></p>
<p>Harsh sentences are being handed down to peaceful climate protesters by both EU member states and the UK. The latter remains closely tied to the EU’s policing structures through its cooperation with Europol.</p>
<p>For example, at the end of August, <em>Climate Rights International</em> <a href="https://cri.org/reports/on-thin-ice/">reported</a>:</p>
<p><em>“…a German court sentenced 65-year-old Winfried Lorenz to 22 months in prison without parole, for his involvement in a climate protest that blocked a road. It is believed to be the longest sentence ever imposed in Berlin against a climate activist.”</em></p>
<p><strong>Documentation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a rel="noopener" data-udi="umb://media/60160745bee540f3a354d300203f7f40" href="https://www.statewatch.org/media/4528/eu-council-presidency-ct-plans-challenges-10406-24.pdf" target="_blank" title="Eu Council Presidency Ct Plans Challenges 10406 24">Counterterrorism: Current challenges and Presidency initiatives and activities in the area</a> (Council doc. 10406/24, LIMITE, 3 June 2024, pdf)</li>
<li><a rel="noopener" data-udi="umb://media/ab8ea0d926e64d4f9bbf3b2ea8d4aaf4" href="https://www.statewatch.org/media/4526/eu-council-gefahrder-shared-understanding-9988-24.pdf" target="_blank" title="Eu Council Gefahrder Shared Understanding 9988 24">A shared understanding of when a person should be regarded as a potential terrorist or violent extremist threat (“Gefährder”)</a> (Council doc. 9988/24, LIMITE, 22 May 2024, pdf)</li>
<li><a rel="noopener" data-udi="umb://media/ab42a726c66147f8a70989d76791367a" href="https://www.statewatch.org/media/4527/eu-council-cosi-minutes-10752-24.pdf" target="_blank" title="Eu Council Cosi Minutes 10752 24">Outcome of proceedings, Standing Committee on Operational Cooperation on Internal Security (COSI)</a> (Council doc. 10752/24, 27 June 2024, pdf)</li>
</ul>                    <p>
<h2><b>Our work is only possible with your support.<br> <a href="https://www.statewatch.org/donate/" title="Donate">Become a Friend of Statewatch</a> from as little as £1/€1 per month.</b></h2>
</p>

                        <h4><strong>Further reading</strong></h4>
                            
                            <div>
                                <p><span>28 March 2024</span>

                                    <a href="https://www.statewatch.org/news/2024/march/eu-intelligence-sharing-plan-extended-from-asylum-seekers-to-any-foreigner-involved-in-a-migratory-procedure/">
                                        <img src="https://www.statewatch.org/media/4218/eu-asylum-intel.jpg" alt="">
                                    </a></p><h2><a href="https://www.statewatch.org/news/2024/march/eu-intelligence-sharing-plan-extended-from-asylum-seekers-to-any-foreigner-involved-in-a-migratory-procedure/">EU: Intelligence-sharing plan extended from asylum-seekers to "any foreigner involved in a migratory procedure"</a></h2>
                                    <p>In 2022, EU member states began discussing ways to increase the amount of information sent to intelligence agencies on "the timing and state of progress of applications for international protection lodged by individuals posing a terrorist threat". Now the intention is to cover not just asylum-seekers, but "any foreigner involved in a migratory procedure." According to the Belgian Presidency, "security concerns go beyond the mere scope of applicants for international protection, as they also cover other people who apply for the legal right to stay in Europe."</p>
                                

                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <p><span>28 February 2024</span>

                                    <a href="https://www.statewatch.org/analyses/2024/environmental-activism-under-the-eu-counter-terror-microscope/">
                                        <img src="https://www.statewatch.org/media/4187/2024-04-ctc-environmental-protest.jpg" alt="">
                                    </a></p><h2><a href="https://www.statewatch.org/analyses/2024/environmental-activism-under-the-eu-counter-terror-microscope/">Environmental activism under the EU counter-terror microscope</a></h2>
                                    <p>Next week, EU and member state officials will discuss “the role of climate change and environmental concerns in violent extremist and terrorist radicalisation.” A discussion paper for the meeting, obtained by Statewatch, considers the threat posed by “violent left-wing and anarchist extremism” – a heading under which a number of prominent environmental protest groups are mentioned. The inclusion of peaceful but disruptive groups in the paper may legitimate further police surveillance and infiltration, legal harassment and government crackdowns – a problem identified as “a major threat to human rights and democracy” by a UN Special Rapporteur.</p>
                                

                            </div>

                </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[France's oldest treasure hunt has been solved (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://goldenowlhunt.com/</link>
            <guid>41728829</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 09:16:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://goldenowlhunt.com/">https://goldenowlhunt.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41728829">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://goldenowlhunt.com/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What Excessive Screen Time Does to the Adult Brain (234 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://longevity.stanford.edu/lifestyle/2024/05/30/what-excessive-screen-time-does-to-the-adult-brain/</link>
            <guid>41728001</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 07:04:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://longevity.stanford.edu/lifestyle/2024/05/30/what-excessive-screen-time-does-to-the-adult-brain/">https://longevity.stanford.edu/lifestyle/2024/05/30/what-excessive-screen-time-does-to-the-adult-brain/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41728001">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="text"><p><span><span>By </span><span>Mary Grace Descourouez, MS, NBC-HWC</span></span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" width="851" height="315" src="https://longevity.stanford.edu/lifestyle/wp-content/uploads/sites/31/2024/05/Social-Med-POM.png" alt="" srcset="https://longevity.stanford.edu/lifestyle/wp-content/uploads/sites/31/2024/05/Social-Med-POM.png 851w, https://longevity.stanford.edu/lifestyle/wp-content/uploads/sites/31/2024/05/Social-Med-POM-300x111.png 300w, https://longevity.stanford.edu/lifestyle/wp-content/uploads/sites/31/2024/05/Social-Med-POM-768x284.png 768w, https://longevity.stanford.edu/lifestyle/wp-content/uploads/sites/31/2024/05/Social-Med-POM-705x261.png 705w, https://longevity.stanford.edu/lifestyle/wp-content/uploads/sites/31/2024/05/Social-Med-POM-450x167.png 450w, https://longevity.stanford.edu/lifestyle/wp-content/uploads/sites/31/2024/05/Social-Med-POM-500x185.png 500w, https://longevity.stanford.edu/lifestyle/wp-content/uploads/sites/31/2024/05/Social-Med-POM-750x278.png 750w" sizes="(max-width: 851px) 100vw, 851px"></p>
<p>Binge-watching television, watching YouTube videos for hours, or scrolling on your phone every morning may seem harmless, but research shows that too much screen time may be detrimental to your health.</p>
<p>We know children’s brains are affected by spending too much time glued to their cell phones,&nbsp;however&nbsp;research shows that adult brains are also negatively impacted by excessive screen time, defined as&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/educational/wecan/reduce-screen-time/index.htm">more than two hours</a>&nbsp;a day outside of work hours.</p>
<p>Too much screen time can impact our health in a myriad of ways, from eye strain and neck pain to social isolation and mental health, and in some cases, it may cause harm to our brains.</p>
<blockquote><p>“The negative effects of screen time are insidious because you can’t see what’s happening in your brain as you’re staring at the screen,” says Maris Loeffler, MA, Family and Marriage Therapist, member of the Stanford Lifestyle Medicine Cognitive Enhancement pillar. “If you scrolled on your phone in bed for an hour just one morning, the negative impacts would be minimal. But if it becomes a habit, day after day, month after month, this behavior can take a toll.”</p></blockquote>
<p>Since the eyes&nbsp;are directly connected&nbsp;to the brain, Loeffler encourages us to think about our eye health to ensure overall brain health. Rather than looking at our phones upon waking, Loeffler recommends starting each morning looking at the horizon or an object outside and far away.</p>
<p>To prevent eye strain throughout the workday,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.aao.org/">The American Academy of Ophthalmology</a>&nbsp;recommends the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/computer-usage#:~:text=Take%20regular%20breaks%20using%20the,for%20at%20least%2020%20seconds.">20-20-20 rule</a>&nbsp;for adults who work on a computer. This rule suggests that individuals look at something 20 feet away for 20 seconds every 20 minutes of the day.</p>
<h2>What is Happening in the Brain During Screen Time?</h2>
<p>This <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11469-019-00182-2">study</a> found that increased use of screens among adults may harm learning, memory, and mental health, as well as the potential to increase the risk of early neurodegeneration. The study shows that in adults aged 18 – 25, excessive screen time causes thinning of the cerebral cortex, the brain’s outermost layer responsible for processing memory and cognitive functions, such as decision-making and problem-solving.</p>
<p>Another&nbsp;<a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S1525861024002263">study</a> found that adults who watched television for five hours or more per day had an increased risk of developing brain-related disease like dementia, stroke, or Parkinson’s.</p>
<p>This&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9638701/">study</a>&nbsp;found that excessive screen time can hinder sleep, especially when looking at screens late at night. Light from the screen can delay melatonin release from the brain’s pineal gland, impacting the body’s natural circadian rhythm and causing difficulty sleeping.</p>
<p>Additional&nbsp;<a href="https://www.imrpress.com/journal/JIN/21/1/10.31083/j.jin2101028/htm">studies</a>&nbsp;found that adults who engage in excessive screen time or have a diagnosed&nbsp;<a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0306460319313802#b0080">smartphone addiction</a>&nbsp;had lower&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK553239/#:~:text=%5B1%5D%20Grey%20matter%20makes%20up,concentration%20of%20neuronal%20cell%20bodies.">gray matter</a>&nbsp;volume. Gray matter is brain tissue essential for daily human functioning and is responsible for everything from movement to memory to emotions.&nbsp;Gray matter volume naturally decreases as we age, so along with reducing screen time, engaging in activities that maintain our gray matter volume and promote brain health, such as exercise and movement, restorative sleep, social engagement, and stress management, is crucial.</p>
<p>“Passive screen time is like eating sugar but for your brain.&nbsp;It&nbsp;‘tastes’&nbsp;good, and you want it now, but you’re not&nbsp;actually&nbsp;feeding yourself.&nbsp;You’re not giving your brain any nutrition,” says Loeffler. “Instead, replace screen time with an intentional healthy habit that&nbsp;feeds your brain in a healthy way. Lifestyle medicine activities, like exercise, good sleep, social connection, and stress management, function like ‘nutrition’ for your brain and mental health.”</p>
<p>Specifically, Loeffler cautions us not to pick up the phone after the alarm goes off in the morning. She explains that looking at our email or social media on our phones while still in bed jolts the nervous system and can trigger the fight-or-flight response since we aren’t fully awake yet.</p>
<p>Also, if we look at our&nbsp;phones&nbsp;first thing&nbsp;every&nbsp;morning, we create a pattern and can set the flight-or-flight response as our default mode of operation. So, not only does this behavior set an anxiety-filled tone for the day, but&nbsp;we are also training our brains to be more hypervigilant in general.</p>
<p><strong>“One of the biggest issues with picking up the phone right away in the morning is that when you have an object close to your face, it’s registered as a threat,” says Loeffler. “You wouldn’t want to wake up and look a bear in the face every morning. On a physiological level, it’s the same thing.”</strong></p>
<h2>Practice of the Month: No Screen Time for the First Hour of the Day</h2>
<p>Stanford Lifestyle Medicine experts recommend no screen time for the first hour of the day to support cognitive enhancement. Instead, we suggest engaging in a lifestyle medicine activity upon waking to promote whole-body health:</p>
<ul>
<li>Exercise</li>
<li>Call a friend or family member</li>
<li>Prepare a healthy <a href="https://longevity.stanford.edu/lifestyle/2024/04/08/dr-spencers-science-based-smoothie-for-gut-health/">breakfast</a></li>
<li>Meditate and count your&nbsp;<a href="https://longevity.stanford.edu/lifestyle/2023/11/14/optimism-as-a-means-to-a-longer-life/">blessings</a></li>
<li>Listen to music</li>
<li>Create a&nbsp;<a href="https://longevity.stanford.edu/lifestyle/2023/11/14/gratitude-is-good-medicine/">gratitude</a>&nbsp;list</li>
<li>Read a book</li>
<li>Spend time outside and get&nbsp;<a href="https://longevity.stanford.edu/lifestyle/2024/03/11/vitamin-d-benefits-sources-deficiency/">morning light</a></li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p>“How do you want your day’s energy and mood to start?” says Loeffler. “Intentionally implementing a morning routine that reflects lifestyle medicine choices instead of screen time sets a positive tone for the day and supports brain health and cognitive enhancement.”</p></blockquote>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Terminal Colours Are Tricky (222 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://jvns.ca/blog/2024/10/01/terminal-colours/</link>
            <guid>41727971</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 06:58:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://jvns.ca/blog/2024/10/01/terminal-colours/">https://jvns.ca/blog/2024/10/01/terminal-colours/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41727971">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
     

<p>Yesterday I was thinking about how long it took me to get a colorscheme in my
terminal that I was mostly happy with (SO MANY YEARS), and it made me wonder
what about terminal colours made it so hard.</p>

<p>So I <a href="https://social.jvns.ca/@b0rk/113226972156366201">asked people on Mastodon</a> what problems
they’ve run into with colours in the terminal, and I got a ton of interesting
responses! Let’s talk about some of the problems and a few possible ways to fix
them.</p>

<h3 id="problem-1-blue-on-black">problem 1: blue on black</h3>

<p>One of the top complaints was “blue on black is hard to read”. Here’s an
example of that: if I open Terminal.app, set the background to black, and run
<code>ls</code>, the directories are displayed in a blue that isn’t that easy to read:</p>

<p><img src="https://jvns.ca/images/terminal-blue.png"></p>

<p>To understand why we’re seeing this blue, let’s talk about ANSI colours!</p>

<h3 id="the-16-ansi-colours">the 16 ANSI colours</h3>

<p>Your terminal has 16 numbered colours – black, red, green, yellow, blue,
magenta, cyan, white, and “bright” version of each of those.</p>

<p>Programs can use them by printing out an “ANSI escape code” – for example if
you want to see each of the 16 colours in your terminal, you can run this
Python program:</p>

<pre><code>def color(num, text):
    return f"\033[38;5;{num}m{text}\033[0m"

for i in range(16):
    print(color(i, f"number {i:02}"))
</code></pre>

<h3 id="what-are-the-ansi-colours">what are the ANSI colours?</h3>

<p>This made me wonder – if blue is colour number 5, who decides what hex color
that should correspond to?</p>

<p>The answer seems to be “there’s no standard, terminal emulators just choose
colours and it’s not very consistent”. Here’s a <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/ANSI_escape_code#Colors">screenshot of a table from Wikipedia</a>, where you
can see that there’s a lot of variation:</p>

<p><img src="https://jvns.ca/images/wikipedia.png"></p>

<h3 id="problem-1-5-bright-yellow-on-white">problem 1.5: bright yellow on white</h3>

<p>Bright yellow on white is even worse than blue on black, here’s what I get in
a terminal with the default settings:</p>

<p><img src="https://jvns.ca/images/terminal-yellow.png"></p>

<p>That’s almost impossible to read (and some other colours like light green cause
similar issues), so let’s talk about solutions!</p>

<h3 id="two-ways-to-reconfigure-your-colours">two ways to reconfigure your colours</h3>

<p>If you’re annoyed by these colour contrast issues (or maybe you just think the
default ANSI colours are ugly), you might think – well, I’ll just choose a
different “blue” and pick something I like better!</p>

<p>There are two ways you can do this:</p>

<p><strong>Way 1: Configure your terminal emulator</strong>: I think most modern terminal emulators
   have a way to reconfigure the colours, and some of them even come with some
   preinstalled themes that you might like better than the defaults.</p>

<p><strong>Way 2: Run a shell script</strong>: There are ANSI escape codes that you can print
out to tell your terminal emulator to reconfigure its colours. <a href="https://github.com/chriskempson/base16-shell/blob/master/scripts/base16-solarized-light.sh">Here’s a shell script that does that</a>,
from the <a href="https://github.com/chriskempson/base16-shell">base16-shell</a> project.
You can see that it has a few different conventions for changing the colours –
I guess different terminal emulators have different escape codes for changing
their colour palette, and so the script is trying to pick the right style of
escape code based on the <code>TERM</code> environment variable.</p>

<h3 id="what-are-the-pros-and-cons-of-the-2-ways-of-configuring-your-colours">what are the pros and cons of the 2 ways of configuring your colours?</h3>

<p>I prefer to use the “shell script” method, because:</p>

<ul>
<li>if I switch terminal emulators for some reason, I don’t need to a different configuration system, my colours still Just Work</li>
<li>I use <a href="https://github.com/chriskempson/base16-shell">base16-shell</a> with base16-vim to make my vim colours match my terminal colours, which is convenient</li>
</ul>

<p>The main advantage I can think of for configuring colours in your terminal
emulator is that, if you use a popular terminal emulator, there are probably a
lot of nice terminal themes out there that you can choose from. I think there are some more advantages I’m not thinking of though.</p>

<p>This is what my shell has looked like for probably the last 5 years (using the
solarized light base16 theme), and I’m pretty happy with it. Here’s <code>htop</code>:</p>

<p><img src="https://jvns.ca/images/terminal-my-colours.png"></p>

<p>Okay, so let’s say you’ve found a terminal colorscheme that you like. What else
can go wrong?</p>

<h3 id="problem-2-programs-using-256-colours">problem 2: programs using 256 colours</h3>

<p>Here’s what some output of <code>fd</code>, a <code>find</code> alternative, looks like in my
colorscheme:</p>

<p><img src="https://jvns.ca/images/terminal-problem-fd.png"></p>

<p>The contrast is pretty bad here, and I definitely don’t have that lime green in
my normal colorscheme. What’s going on?</p>

<p>We can see what color codes <code>fd</code> is using using the <code>unbuffer</code> program to
capture its output including the color codes:</p>

<pre><code>$ unbuffer fd . &gt; out
$ vim out
[38;5;48mbad-again.sh[0m
[38;5;48mbad.sh[0m
[38;5;48mbetter.sh[0m
out
</code></pre>

<p><code>[38;5;48</code> means “set the foreground color to color <code>48</code>”. Terminals don’t
only have 16 colours – many terminals these days actually have 3 ways of
specifying colours:</p>

<ol>
<li>the 16 ANSI colours we already talked about</li>
<li>an extended set of 256 colours</li>
<li>a further extended set of 24-bit hex colours, like <code>#ffea03</code></li>
</ol>

<p>So <code>fd</code> is using one of the colours from the extended 256-color set. <code>bat</code> (a
<code>cat</code> alternative) does something similar – here’s what it looks like by
default in my terminal.</p>

<p><img src="https://jvns.ca/images/terminal-bat.png"></p>

<p>This looks fine though and it really seems like it’s trying to work well with a
variety of terminal themes.</p>

<h3 id="some-newer-tools-seem-to-have-theme-support">some newer tools seem to have theme support</h3>

<p>I think it’s interesting that some of these newer terminal tools (<code>fd</code>, <code>cat</code>,
<code>delta</code>, and probably more) have support for arbitrary custom themes. I guess
the downside of this approach is that the default theme might clash with your
terminal’s background, but the upside is that it gives you a lot more control
over theming the tool’s output than just choosing 16 ANSI colours.</p>

<p>I don’t really use <code>bat</code>, but if I did I’d probably use <code>bat --theme ansi</code> to
just use the ANSI colours that I have set in my normal terminal colorscheme.</p>

<h3 id="problem-3-the-grays-in-solarized">problem 3: the grays in Solarized</h3>

<p>A bunch of people on Mastodon mentioned a specific issue with grays in the
Solarized theme: when I list a directory, the base16 Solarized Light theme
looks like this:</p>

<p><img src="https://jvns.ca/images/terminal-solarized-base16.png"></p>

<p>but iTerm’s default Solarized Light theme looks like this:</p>

<p><img src="https://jvns.ca/images/terminal-solarized-iterm.png"></p>

<p>This is because in the iTerm theme (which is the <a href="https://ethanschoonover.com/solarized/#the-values">original Solarized design</a>), colors 9-14 (the “bright blue”, “bright
red”, etc) are mapped to a series of grays, and when I run <code>ls</code>, it’s trying to
use those “bright” colours to color my directories and executables.</p>

<p>My best guess for why the original Solarized theme is designed this way is to
make the grays available to the <a href="https://github.com/altercation/vim-colors-solarized/blob/528a59f26d12278698bb946f8fb82a63711eec21/colors/solarized.vim">vim Solarized colorscheme</a>.</p>

<p>I’m pretty sure I prefer the modified base16 version I use where the “bright”
colours are actually colours instead of all being shades of gray though. (I
didn’t actually realize the version I was using wasn’t the “original” Solarized
theme until I wrote this post)</p>

<h3 id="problem-4-a-vim-theme-that-doesn-t-match-the-terminal-background">problem 4: a vim theme that doesn’t match the terminal background</h3>

<p>If I my vim theme has a different background colour than my terminal theme, I
get this ugly border, like this:</p>

<p><img src="https://jvns.ca/images/terminal-vim-black-bg.png"></p>

<p>This one is a pretty minor issue though and I think making your terminal
background match your vim background is pretty straightforward.</p>

<h3 id="problem-5-programs-setting-a-background-color">problem 5: programs setting a background color</h3>

<p>A few people mentioned problems with terminal applications setting an
unwanted background colour, so let’s look at an example of that.</p>

<p>Here <code>ngrok</code> has set the background to color #16 (“black”), but the
<code>base16-shell</code> script I use sets color 16 to be bright orange, so I get this,
which is pretty bad:</p>

<p><img src="https://jvns.ca/images/terminal-ngrok-solarized.png"></p>

<p>I think the intention is for ngrok to look something like this:</p>

<p><img src="https://jvns.ca/images/terminal-ngrok-regular.png"></p>

<p>I think <code>base16-shell</code> sets color #16 to orange (instead of black)
so that it can provide extra colours for use by <a href="https://github.com/chriskempson/base16-vim/blob/3be3cd82cd31acfcab9a41bad853d9c68d30478d/colors/base16-solarized-light.vim">base16-vim</a>.
This feels reasonable to me – I use <code>base16-vim</code> in the terminal, so I guess I’m
using that feature and it’s probably more important to me than <code>ngrok</code> (which I
rarely use) behaving a bit weirdly.</p>

<p>This particular issue is a maybe obscure clash between ngrok and my colorschem,
but I think this kind of clash is pretty common when a program sets an ANSI
background color that the user has remapped for some reason.</p>

<h3 id="a-nice-solution-to-contrast-issues-minimum-contrast">a nice solution to contrast issues: “minimum contrast”</h3>

<p>A bunch of terminals (iTerm2, <a href="https://github.com/Eugeny/tabby">tabby</a>, kitty’s <a href="https://sw.kovidgoyal.net/kitty/conf/#opt-kitty.text_fg_override_threshold">text_fg_override_threshold</a>, and
folks tell me also Ghostty and Windows Terminal) have a “minimum
contrast” feature that will automatically adjust colours to make sure they have enough contrast.</p>

<p>Here’s an example from iTerm. This ngrok accident from before has pretty bad
contrast, I find it pretty difficult to read:</p>

<p><img src="https://jvns.ca/images/terminal-ngrok-solarized.png"></p>

<p>With “minimum contrast” set to 40 in iTerm, it looks like this instead:</p>

<p><img src="https://jvns.ca/images/terminal-ngrok-solarized-contrast.png"></p>

<p>I didn’t have minimum contrast turned on before but I just turned it on today
because it makes such a big difference when something goes wrong with colours
in the terminal.</p>

<h3 id="problem-6-term-being-set-to-the-wrong-thing">problem 6: <code>TERM</code> being set to the wrong thing</h3>

<p>A few people mentioned that they’ll SSH into a system that doesn’t support the
<code>TERM</code> environment variable that they have set locally, and then the colours
won’t work.</p>

<p>I think the way <code>TERM</code> works is that systems have a <code>terminfo</code> database, so if
the value of the <code>TERM</code> environment variable isn’t in the system’s terminfo
database, then it won’t know how to output colours for that terminal. I don’t
know too much about terminfo, but someone linked me to this <a href="https://twoot.site/@bean/113056942625234032">terminfo rant</a> that talks about a few other
issues with terminfo.</p>

<p>I don’t have a system on hand to reproduce this one so I can’t say for sure how
to fix it, but <a href="https://unix.stackexchange.com/questions/67537/prevent-ssh-client-passing-term-environment-variable-to-server">this stackoverflow question</a>
suggests running something like <code>TERM=xterm ssh</code> instead of <code>ssh</code>.</p>

<h3 id="problem-7-picking-good-colours-is-hard">problem 7: picking “good” colours is hard</h3>

<p>A couple of problems people mentioned with designing / finding terminal colorschemes:</p>

<ul>
<li>some folks are colorblind and have trouble finding an appropriate colorscheme</li>
<li>accidentally making the background color too close to the cursor or selection color, so they’re hard to find</li>
<li>generally finding colours that work with every program is a struggle (for example you can see me having a problem with this with ngrok above!)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="problem-8-making-nethack-mc-look-right">problem 8: making nethack/mc look right</h3>

<p>Another problem people mentioned is using a program like nethack or midnight
commander which you might expect to have a specific colourscheme based on the
default ANSI terminal colours.</p>

<p>For example, midnight commander has a really specific classic look:</p>

<p><img src="https://jvns.ca/images/terminal-mc-normal.png"></p>

<p>But in my Solarized theme, midnight commander looks like this:</p>

<p><img src="https://jvns.ca/images/terminal-mc-solarized.png"></p>

<p>The Solarized version feels like it could be disorienting if you’re
very used to the “classic” look.</p>

<p>One solution Simon Tatham mentioned to this is using some palette customization
ANSI codes (like the ones base16 uses that I talked about earlier) to change
the color palette right before starting the program, for example remapping
yellow to a brighter yellow before starting Nethack so that the yellow
characters look better.</p>

<h3 id="problem-9-commands-disabling-colours-when-writing-to-a-pipe">problem 9: commands disabling colours when writing to a pipe</h3>

<p>If I run <code>fd | less</code>, I see something like this, with the colours disabled.</p>

<p><img src="https://jvns.ca/images/terminal-fd-bw.png"></p>

<p>In generan I find this useful – if I pipe a command to <code>grep</code>, I don’t want it
to print out all those color escape codes, I just want the plain text. But what if you want to see the colours?</p>

<p>To see the colours, you can run <code>unbuffer fd | less -r</code>! I just learned about
<code>unbuffer</code> recently and I think it’s really cool, <code>unbuffer</code> opens a tty for the
command to write to so that it thinks it’s writing to a TTY. It also fixes
issues with programs buffering their output when writing to a pipe, which is
why it’s called <code>unbuffer</code>.</p>

<p>Here’s what the output of <code>unbuffer fd | less -r</code> looks like for me:</p>

<p><img src="https://jvns.ca/images/terminal-fd-color.png"></p>

<h3 id="problem-10-unwanted-colour-in-ls-and-other-commands">problem 10: unwanted colour in <code>ls</code> and other commands</h3>

<p>Some people mentioned that they don’t want <code>ls</code> to use colour at all, perhaps
because <code>ls</code> uses blue, it’s hard to read on black, and maybe they don’t feel like
customizing their terminal’s colourscheme to make the blue more readable or
just don’t find the use of colour helpful.</p>

<p>Some possible solutions to this one:</p>

<ul>
<li>you can run <code>ls --color=never</code>, which is probably easiest</li>
<li>you can also set <code>LS_COLORS</code> to customize the colours used by <code>ls</code>. I think some other programs other than <code>ls</code> support the <code>LS_COLORS</code> environment variable too.</li>
<li>also some programs support setting <code>NO_COLOR=true</code> (there’s a <a href="https://no-color.org/">list here</a>)</li>
</ul>

<p>Here’s an example of running <code>LS_COLORS="fi=0:di=0:ln=0:pi=0:so=0:bd=0:cd=0:or=0:ex=0" ls</code>:</p>

<p><img src="https://jvns.ca/images/terminal-ls-colors.png"></p>

<h3 id="problem-11-the-colours-in-vim">problem 11: the colours in vim</h3>

<p>I used to have a lot of problems with configuring my colours in vim – I’d set
up my terminal colours in a way that I thought was okay, and then I’d start vim
and it would just be a disaster.</p>

<p>I think what was going on here is that today, there are two ways to set up a vim colorscheme in the terminal:</p>

<ol>
<li>using your ANSI terminal colours – you tell vim which ANSI colour number to use for the background, for functions, etc.</li>
<li>using 24-bit hex colours – instead of ANSI terminal colours, the vim colorscheme can use hex codes like #faea99 directly</li>
</ol>

<p>20 years ago when I started using vim, terminals with 24-bit hex color support
were a lot less common (or maybe they didn’t exist at all), and vim certainly
didn’t have support for using 24-bit colour in the terminal. From some quick
searching through git, it looks like <a href="https://github.com/vim/vim/commit/8a633e3427b47286869aa4b96f2bfc1fe65b25cd">vim added support for 24-bit colour in 2016</a>
– just 8 years ago!</p>

<p>So to get colours to work properly in vim before 2016, you needed to synchronize
your terminal colorscheme and your vim colorscheme. <a href="https://github.com/chriskempson/base16-vim/blob/3be3cd82cd31acfcab9a41bad853d9c68d30478d/colors/base16-solarized-light.vim#L52-L71">Here’s what that looked like</a>,
the colorscheme needed to map the vim color classes like <code>cterm05</code> to ANSI colour numbers.</p>

<p>But in 2024, the story is really different! Vim (and Neovim, which I use now)
support 24-bit colours, and as of Neovim 0.10 (released in May 2024), the
<code>termguicolors</code> setting (which tells Vim to use 24-bit hex colours for
colorschemes) is <a href="https://neovim.io/doc/user/news-0.10.html">turned on by default</a> in any terminal with 24-bit
color support.</p>

<p>So this “you need to synchronize your terminal colorscheme and your vim
colorscheme” problem is not an issue anymore for me in 2024, since I
don’t plan to use terminals without 24-bit color support in the future.</p>

<p>The biggest consequence for me of this whole thing is that I don’t need base16
to set colors 16-21 to weird stuff anymore to integrate with vim – I can just
use a terminal theme and a vim theme, and as long as the two themes use similar
colours (so it’s not jarring for me to switch between them) there’s no problem.
I think I can just remove those parts from my <code>base16</code> shell script and totally
avoid the problem with ngrok and the weird orange background I talked about
above.</p>

<h3 id="some-more-problems-i-left-out">some more problems I left out</h3>

<p>I think there are a lot of issues around the intersection of multiple programs,
like using some combination tmux/ssh/vim that I couldn’t figure out how to
reproduce well enough to talk about them. Also I’m sure I missed a lot of other
things too.</p>

<h3 id="okay-that-was-a-lot">okay, that was a lot</h3>

<p>We talked about a lot in this post and  while I think learning about all these
details is kind of fun if I’m in the mood to do a deep dive, I find it SO
FRUSTRATING to deal with it when I just want my colours to work! Being
surprised by unreadable text and having to find a workaround is just not my
idea of a good day.</p>

<p>Personally I’m a zero-configuration kind of person and it’s not that appealing
to me to have to put together a lot of custom configuration just to make my
colours in the terminal look acceptable. I’d much rather just have some
reasonable defaults that I don’t have to change.</p>

<h3 id="base16-has-really-worked-for-me">base16 has really worked for me</h3>

<p>I’ve personally had a lot of success with using
<a href="https://github.com/chriskempson/base16-shell">base16-shell</a> with
<a href="https://github.com/chriskempson/base16-vim">base16-vim</a> – I just need to add <a href="https://github.com/chriskempson/base16-shell?tab=readme-ov-file#fish">a couple of lines</a> to my
fish config to set it up (+ a few <code>.vimrc</code> lines) and then I can move on and
accept any remaining problems that that doesn’t solve.</p>

<p>I don’t think base16 is for everyone though, some limitations I’m aware
of with base16 that might make it not work for you:</p>

<ul>
<li>it comes with a limited set of builtin themes and you might not like any of them</li>
<li>the Solarized base16 theme (and maybe all of the themes?) sets the “bright”
ANSI colours to be exactly the same as the normal colours, which might cause
a problem if you’re relying on the “bright” colours to be different from the
regular ones</li>
<li>it sets colours 16-21 in order to give the vim colorschemes from <code>base16-vim</code>
access to more colours, which might not be relevant if you always use a
terminal with 24-bit color support, and can cause problems like the ngrok
issue above</li>
<li>also the way it sets colours 16-21 could be a problem in terminals that don’t have
256-color support</li>
</ul>

<p>Apparently there’s a community fork of base16 called
<a href="https://github.com/tinted-theming/home">tinted-theming</a>, which I haven’t
looked into much yet.</p>

<h3 id="some-other-colorscheme-tools">some other colorscheme tools</h3>

<p>Just one so far but I’ll link more if people tell me about them:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://rootloops.sh/">rootloops.sh</a> for generating colorschemes (and <a href="https://hamvocke.com/blog/lets-create-a-terminal-color-scheme/">“let’s create a terminal color scheme”</a>)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="minimum-contrast-seems-like-an-amazing-feature">minimum contrast seems like an amazing feature</h3>

<p>My one big takeaway from writing this was to turn on “minimum contrast” in my
terminal, I think it’s going to fix most of the occasional accidental
unreadable text issues I run into and I’m pretty excited about it.</p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why my apps will soon be gone from the Google Play Store (176 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://frozenfractal.com/blog/2024/9/6/why-my-apps-will-soon-be-gone-from-google-play/</link>
            <guid>41727933</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 06:50:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://frozenfractal.com/blog/2024/9/6/why-my-apps-will-soon-be-gone-from-google-play/">https://frozenfractal.com/blog/2024/9/6/why-my-apps-will-soon-be-gone-from-google-play/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41727933">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content"><p>Fri, 6 Sep 2024 by Thomas ten Cate · <a href="https://frozenfractal.com/blog/2024/9/6/why-my-apps-will-soon-be-gone-from-google-play/#isso-thread" data-isso-id="/blog/2024/9/6/why-my-apps-will-soon-be-gone-from-google-play/">Comments</a><br><svg><use xlink:href="https://frozenfractal.com/img/icomoon/symbol-defs.min.svg#icon-price-tags"></use></svg>
&nbsp;<a href="https://frozenfractal.com/blog/tags/business/">Business</a>, <a href="https://frozenfractal.com/blog/tags/bigcanvas/">Bigcanvas</a>, <a href="https://frozenfractal.com/blog/tags/patchy/">Patchy</a>, <a href="https://frozenfractal.com/blog/tags/twistago/">Twistago</a>, <a href="https://frozenfractal.com/blog/tags/rocket-mail/">Rocket Mail</a></p><p>The first real money I ever made from game development was on Android. It was in 2013, when Android was still the underdog compared to the iPhone, and was being touted as a great platform for developers. I’d taken two weeks to build <a href="https://frozenfractal.com/games/patchy/">Patchy</a>, a retro arcade game revamped for touch controls, and published it on the Google Play Store without any hassle. Since then, I’ve also published <a href="https://frozenfractal.com/games/twistago/">Twistago</a>, <a href="https://frozenfractal.com/games/rocket-mail/">Rocket Mail</a>, <a href="https://frozenfractal.com/blog/2015/6/14/bigcanvas-released/">Bigcanvas</a>, <a href="https://frozenfractal.com/projects/radio-nul/">Radio Nul</a> and <a href="https://frozenfractal.com/projects/papageno/">Papageno</a>.</p><p>With each next app, the bar for publishing kept getting higher. At some point, Google started publishing developers’ full company address on the store alongside the app. That’s fine for a professional company, but quite problematic for a solo indie developer who works from home, especially if the app <em>or the developer</em> is even remotely controversial. I worked around it at the time by just putting the name of the town instead of the full address, which is only right morally, but not legally.</p><p>The technical requirements also kept going up. To publish an update to an app, it has to target the latest API version, which goes up once or twice a year. Each API update comes with a slew of deprecations, and breaking changes to the already inscrutable build system. And even if you don’t want to update the app, Google will eventually start hiding apps from users if the app doesn’t target some minimum API version. This means you can’t just publish an app and leave it at that; it’s several days of work per app per year to keep up with the latest rug-pulls from Google. Again this is no problem for a company for whom the app is their core business, but bad news for indie and hobbyist developers who just want to make something cool, put it out there, and move on to the next project.</p><p>And then, there’s the latest increase in publishing requirements, the straw that broke the camel’s back, which made me decide to abandon the Google Play Store altogether.</p><h2 id="the-new-rules">The new rules</h2><p>The <a href="https://android-developers.googleblog.com/2023/07/boosting-trust-and-transparency-in-google-play.html">original announcement</a> just mentioned that organizations will need to provide a D-U-N-S number. It was possible to choose your own deadline, so I set it as far in the future as I could. Now that deadline, 5 November, is getting close, and I can start the verification process. The email, however, makes it clear that they want much more than a D-U-N-S number:</p><blockquote><p><strong>What you need to provide to verify</strong></p><ul><li>a D-U-N-S number for your organization<br>If you don’t have a D-U-N-S number, request one at no cost from Dun &amp; Bradstreet now. This process can take up to 30 days, so we recommend requesting a D-U-N-S number immediately. <a href="https://support.google.com/googleplay/android-developer/answer/13628312#duns">Learn more about requesting a D-U-N-S number</a></li><li>a phone number and email address for Google Play users to contact you</li><li>a phone number and email address for Google to contact you</li><li>an official document to verify your identity</li><li>an official document to verify your organization</li></ul></blockquote><p>There is only one of these items that I don’t have a problem with.</p><p>The D-U-N-S number is only needed if your Play Store publisher account is for an organization, not an individual. But I’m registered as a sole proprietor, so the rule applies to me. You can <a href="https://www.dnb.com/duns-number/lookup.html">look up</a> your company’s D-U-N-S number, but the form doesn’t (currently?) allow selecting any country except the US. Dun &amp; Bradstreet’s partner in the Netherlands, <a href="https://www.altares.nl/en/our-data/duns-number/">Altares</a>, does allow me to look up my own company, but charges 15 € for the privilege of seeing my own data, <em>including my own D-U-N-S number</em>, which they’ve apparently already assigned when I registered with the Chamber of Commerce. If I didn’t already have one, I don’t see a way on their website to request one either, even though the FAQ mentions that you can (for a fee, of course).</p><p>While that may be just some paperwork and a small expense, the next requirement is more insidious: “a phone number and email address for Google Play users to contact you”. I’m fine showing an email address, but I <em>absolutely do not want</em> my phone number to be available to anyone on the internet. (Even for phone calls. But remember that a phone number is used for much more than phone calls these days.) And that’s just me, a privileged hetero white cis dude who is unlikely to be the target of harassment or doxxing.</p><p>The requirement “a phone number and email address for Google to contact you” is the only one that sounds benign to me, although I have yet to see Google trying to contact small-fry developers like me by phone, instead of just reaching for the algorithmic ban hammer if I cross any line.</p><p>An “official document to verify your identity” would presumably be a scan or photo of my passport. Now, I have reasonable confidence in the security of Google’s systems, but this is something very sensitive and can easily be abused if it fell into the wrong hands. And why is it necessary? I’ve done business with many other companies, where a lot more money was changing hands than I’m getting from my Play Store apps, but they never asked for my passport. Why does Google?</p><p>Those other companies also never asked for “an official document to verify your organization”. Presumably this is a document I can request from the Chamber of Commerce to the tune of another 9 €, but again I’ve never had another company ask for this when doing business with them.</p><h2 id="in-conclusion">In conclusion</h2><p>I sort of understand why Google is doing all this. It’s partly legal requirements (especially EU), partly an attempt to reduce spam and malicious stuff. Some of it might even be in the best interest of the end user.</p><p>Larger companies have the resources to deal with all this, and for personal accounts the <a href="https://support.google.com/googleplay/android-developer/answer/13628312">rules</a> are much more lenient. Sadly, there has been little consideration for sole proprietorships like mine, which fall somewhere in between: bound by the same rules as big companies, but without the means to play by them.</p><p>And this is why I’m just going to let my Play Store developer account expire. Starting on 5 November, you won’t be able to install any of my apps anymore. Most of them were not actively maintained anymore, <em>but they still worked</em>, because the Android operating system itself is actually pretty good at backwards compatibility.</p><p>Even though there was little remaining interest in my older apps, it makes me sad that people won’t be able to use them anymore. The one I’m most sad about, though, is <a href="https://papageno.app/">Papageno</a>, an unfinished side project about bird sounds that I haven’t worked on for three years, but keeps popping into my mind as something I’d really like to finish some day. Maybe it could be in the form of a web app. We’ll see.</p><p><img src="https://frozenfractal.com/blog/2024/9/6/why-my-apps-will-soon-be-gone-from-google-play/no_more_google_play.png" alt="The official “Get it on Google Play” button, but with the text “You can no longer” scribbled above it, probably flying in the face of official brand guidelines"></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Flyon UI – Tailwind Components Library (158 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://flyonui.com/</link>
            <guid>41727621</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 05:30:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://flyonui.com/">https://flyonui.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41727621">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><h2>The
<span>Easiest</span><br>Tailwind CSS<br>Components Library</h2><p>FlyonUI is an open-source Tailwind CSS Components Library with
<span>semantic classes</span>
and
<span>powerful JS plugins.</span></p></div><div><p><span>Main Features</span></p><h2 x-ref="sectionHeader"><span>All Essentials
</span>
<span>in One Place</span></h2><div><p>Save countless hours by using FlyonUI’s ready-made components, blocks, and templates,</p><p>designed to simplify your workflow and bring your projects to life with ease.</p></div></div><div><p>Unlimited Themes</p><p><img src="https://flyonui.com/images/landing-page/section-gradient.png" alt="Gradient Background"></p></div><div><div><p><span>Unlimited themes</span></p><h2><span>Apply your own design decisions with</span>
<span>Unlimited Themes
</span></h2><p><span>With FlyonUI colour names, you can achieve Dark Mode and<br>access a variety of additional themes, all without the need to add any new class names.</span></p></div><div><div><div><p>CHAT LIST</p><ul><li><img src="https://cdn.flyonui.com/fy-assets/avatar/avatar-1.png" alt="User Image"><div><div><p>Phillip George</p><p><small>Hii samira, thanks...</small></p></div><p><span>9.00AM</span>
<span>1</span></p></div></li><li><img src="https://cdn.flyonui.com/fy-assets/avatar/avatar-2.png" alt="User Image"><div><div><p>Jaylon Donin</p><p><small>I’ll send the texts...</small></p></div><p><span>10.00PM</span>
<span>3</span></p></div></li><li><img src="https://cdn.flyonui.com/fy-assets/avatar/avatar-3.png" alt="User Image"><div><div><p>Tiana Curtis</p><p><small>That’s Great!</small></p></div><p><span>8.30AM</span></p></div></li><li><img src="https://cdn.flyonui.com/fy-assets/avatar/avatar-4.png" alt="User Image"><div><div><p>Zaire Vetrovs</p><p><small>https://www.youtub...</small></p></div><p><span>5.50AM</span>
<span>2</span></p></div></li><li><img src="https://cdn.flyonui.com/fy-assets/avatar/avatar-5.png" alt="User Image"><div><div><p>Kianna Philips</p><p><small>It was awesome.</small></p></div><p><span>6.45PM</span></p></div></li></ul></div><div><p>APPS NOTIFICATION</p><ul><li><p><img src="https://cdn.flyonui.com/fy-assets/components/social-icon/google.png" alt="google logo">
<span>Google</span></p></li><li><p><img src="https://cdn.flyonui.com/fy-assets/components/social-icon/twitter.png" alt="twitter logo">
<span>Twitter</span></p></li><li><p><img src="https://cdn.flyonui.com/fy-assets/components/social-icon/linkedin.png" alt="linkedin logo">
<span>Linkedin</span></p></li><li><p><img src="https://cdn.flyonui.com/fy-assets/components/social-icon/dribbble.png" alt="dribble logo">
<span>Dribbble</span></p></li><li><p><img src="https://cdn.flyonui.com/fy-assets/components/social-icon/behance.png" alt="behance logo">
<span>Behance</span></p></li></ul></div></div><div><p><label><p><span><span>Basic</span>
<span>Free</span></span>
<span><span>Get 1 project with 1 teams members.</span></span></p></label></p></div></div></div><div><p>Components</p><p><img src="https://flyonui.com/images/landing-page/section-gradient.png" alt="Gradient Background"></p></div><div><p><span>Components</span></p><div><p>FlyonUI combines elegant semantic classes with robust JS plugins,</p><p>creating a powerful toolkit for building stunning, responsive, and interactive user interfaces with ease.</p></div></div><div><p><span>Stats</span></p><h2><span>FlyonUI
</span>
<span>Impact</span></h2><p><span>Celebrating the milestones achieved with FlyonUI.</span></p></div><div><p><span>Get FlyonUI Now</span></p><h2><span>Install
</span>
<span>FlyonUI</span></h2><p><span>Follow these simple steps to get started with FlyonUI in your project</span></p></div><div><p>Free &amp; Open Source
     </p><p><img src="https://flyonui.com/images/landing-page/section-gradient.png" alt="Gradient Background"></p></div><div><div><p><span>Free and open-source</span></p><h2><span>Built with</span>
<span>Open-Source
</span>
<span>Built for the Community ❤️</span></h2><p><span>FlyonUI combines Adss the best features of<br>DaisyUI and PrelineJS to provide a robust Tailwind CSS UI kit</span></p></div><div><p>We are grateful for the contributions of the open-source community, particularly
<a href="https://daisyui.com/" target="_blank">DaisyUI</a>
and
<a href="https://preline.co/" target="_blank">PrelineJS</a>
. These projects form the backbone of FlyonUI, allowing us to build a powerful and user-friendly UI kit.</p><div><h3>Special thanks 👍🏼 to:</h3><p><a href="https://daisyui.com/" target="_blank"><img src="https://flyonui.com/logos/daisyui-logo.png" alt="DaisyUI Logo" href="https://daisyui.com/"></a>
<a href="https://preline.co/" target="_blank"><img src="https://flyonui.com/logos/prelineui-logo.png" alt="PrelineUI Logo"></a></p></div></div><div><p>We welcome contributions from developers worldwide. Together, we can make FlyonUI even better.</p><p>Visit our
<a href="https://github.com/themeselection/flyonui" target="_blank">GitHub repository</a>
to get involved and be a part of our growing community.</p></div></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Gamma radiation is produced in large tropical thunderstorms (101 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://phys.org/news/2024-10-amount-variety-gamma-large-tropical.html</link>
            <guid>41726698</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 02:17:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://phys.org/news/2024-10-amount-variety-gamma-large-tropical.html">https://phys.org/news/2024-10-amount-variety-gamma-large-tropical.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41726698">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
										
<div data-thumb="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2019/thunderstorm.jpg" data-src="https://scx2.b-cdn.net/gfx/news/hires/2019/thunderstorm.jpg" data-sub-html="Credit: CC0 Public Domain">
        <figure>
            <img src="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/800a/2019/thunderstorm.jpg" alt="thunderstorm" title="Credit: CC0 Public Domain" width="800" height="524">
             <figcaption>
                Credit: CC0 Public Domain
            </figcaption>        </figure>
    </div><p>In the 1990s, NASA satellites built to spot high-energy particles coming from supernovae and other celestial-sized objects discovered a surprise—high energy gamma radiation bursts coming from right here on Earth.</p>


										      
																																	<p>While it didn't take long for researchers to determine that these high-energy gamma rays were originating from thunderstorms, how commonly the phenomenon happened remained a mystery. Satellites weren't built to find <a href="https://phys.org/tags/gamma+radiation/" rel="tag">gamma radiation</a> coming from Earth, and they had to be in just the right place at just the right time to do so.</p>
<p>After years of making do with platforms not ideal for the task, a group of scientists secured an opportunity to fly a retrofitted U2 <a href="https://phys.org/tags/spy+plane/" rel="tag">spy plane</a> owned by NASA over storms to take a proper look. In two new papers <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-07893-0" target="_blank">published</a> in <i>Nature</i>, the team discovered that gamma radiation produced in thunderstorms is far more common than anyone thought and that the dynamics creating the radiation hold a treasure trove of mysteries yet to be solved.</p>
<p>"There is way more going on in thunderstorms than we ever imagined," said Steve Cummer, the William H. Younger Distinguished Professor of Engineering at Duke University, who was a co-author on both papers. "As it turns out, essentially all big thunderstorms generate gamma rays all day long in many different forms."</p>
<p>The general physics behind how thunderstorms create high-energy flashes of gamma radiation is not a mystery. As thunderstorms develop, swirling drafts drive <a href="https://phys.org/tags/water+droplets/" rel="tag">water droplets</a>, hail and ice into a mixture that creates an <a href="https://phys.org/tags/electric+charge/" rel="tag">electric charge</a> much like rubbing a balloon on your shirt.</p>

																																						
																																			<p>Positively charged particles end up at the top of the storm while negatively charged particles drop to the bottom, creating an enormous electric field that can be as strong as 100 million AA batteries stacked end-to-end.</p>
<p>When other charged particles—such as electrons—find themselves in such a strong field, they accelerate. If they accelerate to high enough speeds and happen to strike an air molecule, they knock off more high-energy electrons. The process cascades until the collisions have enough energy to create <a href="https://phys.org/tags/nuclear+reactions/" rel="tag">nuclear reactions</a>, producing extremely strong and extremely fast flashes of gamma rays, antimatter and other forms of radiation.</p>
<p>But that's not the end of the thunderstorm gamma radiation story. Aircraft flying close to thunderstorms have also seen a faint glow of gamma radiation coming from clouds. These storms seem to have enough energy to produce a low-level simmering of gamma radiation, but something prevents it from creating an explosive burst like a popping corn kernel.</p>
<p>"A few aircraft campaigns tried to figure out if these phenomena were common or not, but there were mixed results, and several campaigns over the United States didn't find any gamma radiation at all," Cummer said. "This project was designed to address these questions once and for all."</p>
<p>The research group secured the use of a NASA ER-2 High-Altitude Airborne Science Aircraft. A retrofitted U2 spy plane left over from the Cold War, it flies over twice as high as <a href="https://phys.org/tags/commercial+aircraft/" rel="tag">commercial aircraft</a> and about three miles above most thunderstorms. It's also extremely fast, giving the team the opportunity to pick the exact thunderstorms they thought were most likely to produce results.</p>

																																			<p>"The ER-2 aircraft would be the ultimate observing platform for <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-07936-6" target="_blank">gamma-rays from thunderclouds</a>," said Nikolai Østgaard, professor of space physics at the University of Bergen in Norway and lead investigator of the project. "Flying at 20 km [12.4 miles], we can fly directly over the cloud top, as close as possible to the gamma-ray source."</p>
<p>Because the ER-2 was the perfect solution and the team was going to fly over the right storms, the researchers figured that if these phenomena were rare, then they'd barely see any at all. But if they were common, then they'd see a lot.</p>
<p>And they saw a lot.</p>
<p>Over the course of a month, the ER-2 flew 10 flights over large storms in the tropics south of Florida, and nine of them yielded observations of this summer of gamma radiation, which was also more dynamic than expected.</p>
<p>"The dynamics of gamma-glowing thunderclouds starkly contradicts the former quasi-stationary picture of glows, and rather resembles that of a huge gamma-glowing boiling pot both in pattern and behavior," said Martino Marisaldi, professor of physics and technology at the University of Bergen.</p>
<p>Given the size of a typical thunderstorm in the tropics, which is much larger than storms at other latitudes, this suggests that more than half of all thunderstorms in the tropics are radioactive. The researchers postulate that this low-level production of gamma radiation acts like steam boiling off a pot of water and limits how much energy can be built up inside.</p>

																																						
																																			<p>The researchers were equally excited to see numerous examples of short duration and intense gamma radiation bursts coming from the same thunderstorms. Some of these were precisely like those that were originally detected by NASA satellites. These almost always occurred in conjunction with an active lightning discharge.</p>
<p>This suggests that the large electric field created by lightning is likely supercharging the already high-energy electrons, enabling them to create high-energy nuclear reactions.</p>
<p>But there were also at least two other types of short gamma radiation bursts that had never been seen before. One type is incredibly short, less than a thousandth of a second, while the other is a sequence of about 10 individual bursts that repeat over the course of about a tenth of a second.</p>
<p>"Those two new forms of gamma radiation are what I find most interesting," Cummer said. "They don't seem to be associated with developing lightning flashes. They emerge spontaneously somehow. There are hints in the data that they may actually be linked to the processes that initiate lightning flashes, which are still a mystery to scientists."</p>
<p>If there is anybody out there worried about getting turned into the Hulk by all of this gamma radiation, Cummer added, they shouldn't be. The amount of radiation being produced would only be dangerous if a person or object were quite close to the origination source.</p>
<p>"The radiation would be the least of your problems if you found yourself there. Airplanes avoid flying in active <a href="https://phys.org/tags/thunderstorm/" rel="tag">thunderstorm</a> cores due to the extreme turbulence and winds," Cummer said. "Even knowing what we now know, I don't worry about flying any more than I used to."</p>

																																																					
																				<div>
																						<p><strong>More information:</strong>
												Nikolai Østgaard, Flickering gamma-ray flashes, the missing link between gamma glows and TGFs, <i>Nature</i> (2024). <a data-doi="1" href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1038/s41586-024-07893-0" target="_blank">DOI: 10.1038/s41586-024-07893-0</a>. <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-07893-0" target="_blank">www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-07893-0</a>
</p><p>Highly dynamic gamma-ray emissions are common in tropical thunderclouds, <i>Nature</i> (2024), <a data-doi="1" href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1038/s41586-024-07936-6" target="_blank">DOI: 10.1038/s41586-024-07936-6</a>. <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-07936-6" target="_blank">www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-07936-6</a></p>

																						
																						<p>
													<strong>Journal information:</strong>
																											<a href="https://phys.org/journals/nature/"><cite>Nature</cite></a>
														<a href="http://www.nature.com/nature/index.html" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">
															<svg>
																<use href="https://phys.b-cdn.net/tmpl/v6/img/svg/sprite.svg#icon_open" x="0" y="0"></use>
															</svg>
														</a> 
																									</p>
																					</div>
                               											
																					
                              										                                        
										<!-- print only -->
										<div>
											 <p><strong>Citation</strong>:
												Surprising amount and variety of gamma radiation is produced in large tropical thunderstorms, observations reveal (2024, October 2)
												retrieved 3 October 2024
												from https://phys.org/news/2024-10-amount-variety-gamma-large-tropical.html
											 </p>
											 <p>
											 This document is subject to copyright. Apart from any fair dealing for the purpose of private study or research, no
											 part may be reproduced without the written permission. The content is provided for information purposes only.
											 </p>
										</div>
                                        
									</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OpenAI and Anthropic Revenue Breakdown (111 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.tanayj.com/p/openai-and-anthropic-revenue-breakdown</link>
            <guid>41726603</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 01:58:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.tanayj.com/p/openai-and-anthropic-revenue-breakdown">https://www.tanayj.com/p/openai-and-anthropic-revenue-breakdown</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41726603">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><p>This is a weekly newsletter about the business of the technology industry. To receive Tanay’s Newsletter in your inbox, subscribe here for free:</p><p>Hi friends,</p><p>With both OpenAI and Anthropic rumored to be raising new financing rounds, some of their financial metrics have been reported by various publications. In this piece, I’ll discuss what we know about their financials and highlight a few observations from that data. </p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1aae2610-a216-4901-9f83-10d09421b82f_1760x990.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1aae2610-a216-4901-9f83-10d09421b82f_1760x990.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1aae2610-a216-4901-9f83-10d09421b82f_1760x990.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1aae2610-a216-4901-9f83-10d09421b82f_1760x990.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1aae2610-a216-4901-9f83-10d09421b82f_1760x990.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1aae2610-a216-4901-9f83-10d09421b82f_1760x990.png" width="1456" height="819" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/1aae2610-a216-4901-9f83-10d09421b82f_1760x990.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:819,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:240574,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1aae2610-a216-4901-9f83-10d09421b82f_1760x990.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1aae2610-a216-4901-9f83-10d09421b82f_1760x990.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1aae2610-a216-4901-9f83-10d09421b82f_1760x990.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1aae2610-a216-4901-9f83-10d09421b82f_1760x990.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><strong>Revenue: </strong><span>OpenAI is at ~$3.6B in annualized run rate revenue as of August 2024, and was roughly at $1.6B in annualized run rate revenue near the tail end of 2023. Based on their projected total revenue of $3.7B for 2024, I estimate OpenAI ending 2024 at ~$5B-5.2B in annualized run rate revenue. This would represent a growth rate of 225% y/y from $1.6B at the end of last year. OpenAI also further projects to get to $11.6B in revenue in 2025, an increase of 213% y/y next year if they are able to achieve it.</span></p><p><strong>Revenue Breakdown: </strong><span>The split of OpenAI’s revenue, per company projections for the end of 2024 is roughly:</span></p><ul><li><p><strong>ChatGPT subscriptions</strong><span>: $2.7B (~73%) representing 285% y/y growth</span></p><ul><li><p>This includes about 10M subscribers on the ChatGPT plus plan and another 1M on higher priced plans</p></li></ul></li><li><p><strong>API</strong><span>: $1B (~27%) representing 200-225% y/y growth</span></p></li></ul><p><strong>Margins: </strong><span>We don’t know much about OpenAI’s margins, but given reports that they are expected to </span><strong>lose about $5B this year</strong><span> on about $3.7B of revenue which is obviously not great. Futuresearch estimates that their API business actually has ~50% gross margins, and that most of the losses come from operating costs (R&amp;D, etc) and their ChatGPT business, which gives basically unlimited usage for ~$20/month.</span></p><p><strong>Revenue: </strong><span>Anthropic is expected to be at $1B annualized run rate revenue at the end of this year, about a 900% increase from the ~$100M or so in annualized run rate revenue they were generating at the end of 2023.</span></p><p><strong>Revenue Breakdown</strong><span>: Anthropic’s revenue breakdown skews much more towards its API, particularly through it’s 3P API which is largely via Amazon. Their breakdown is roughly:</span></p><ul><li><p><strong>Third Party API (via Amazon, etc)</strong><span>: 60-75% </span></p></li><li><p><strong>Direct API</strong><span>: 10-25%</span></p></li><li><p><strong>Claude chatbot subscriptions</strong><span>: 15% </span></p></li><li><p><strong>Professional Services</strong><span>: 2%</span></p></li></ul><p><strong>Margins: </strong><span>We don’t know much about Anthropic’s margins either, but again, they are expected to lose about ~$2B this year, on revenue in the high hundreds of millions. While a lot of this is largely compute and headcount, their business skew more towards they API, which if it does indeed support higher gross margins in the short to medium term, may be beneficial.</span></p><p>If you don’t yet receive Tanay's newsletter in your email inbox, please join the 9,000+ subscribers who do:</p><p>Putting the above together, we can make a few observations when comparing the two. While OpenAI is 5x larger than Anthropic, OpenAI is much more dominant on the consumer side, while the two are much closer on the API side.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc98146dc-0fc5-4cc8-8e53-eb884f021bf8_1696x954.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc98146dc-0fc5-4cc8-8e53-eb884f021bf8_1696x954.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc98146dc-0fc5-4cc8-8e53-eb884f021bf8_1696x954.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc98146dc-0fc5-4cc8-8e53-eb884f021bf8_1696x954.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc98146dc-0fc5-4cc8-8e53-eb884f021bf8_1696x954.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc98146dc-0fc5-4cc8-8e53-eb884f021bf8_1696x954.png" width="1456" height="819" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/c98146dc-0fc5-4cc8-8e53-eb884f021bf8_1696x954.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:819,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:207123,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc98146dc-0fc5-4cc8-8e53-eb884f021bf8_1696x954.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc98146dc-0fc5-4cc8-8e53-eb884f021bf8_1696x954.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc98146dc-0fc5-4cc8-8e53-eb884f021bf8_1696x954.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc98146dc-0fc5-4cc8-8e53-eb884f021bf8_1696x954.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>From a scale perspective, OpenAI is roughly 5x the scale of Anthropic in terms of annualized revenue (~$5B vs ~$1B). Anthropic is growing faster, however. At the start of the year, OpenAI was likely around 15x the scale of Anthropic.</p><p>Despite a lot of buzz around Anthropic’s latest class of models including Sonnet, and around Claude and features such as Artifacts, the vast majority of people who use ChatGPT have likely never even tried or heard of Anthropic’s Claude.</p><p><span>From a revenue perspective, ChatGPT will be bringing in about ~$2.7B at the end of the year for OpenAI, relative to Anthropic’s Claude bringing in about ~$150M. </span><strong>That makes ChatGPT about 18x the size from a revenue perspective</strong><span>. </span></p><p>Anthropic recently launched an enterprise version of Claude to bolster their Claude offering for businesses, but even there is likely far behind, with ChatGPT already boasting over 1M users on higher paid ChatGPT plans (enterprise/teams).</p><p>Anthropic generating ~65% of their revenue from their third party API highlights how important distribution is. According to many benchmarks, at least until OpenAI launched o-1, Anthropic’s sonnet and similar models have been the best for a number of use cases. But having a great product alone is insufficient, and distribution is equally if not even more important.</p><p><span>For Anthropic, that distribution, in the </span><strong>form of their partnership with Amazon</strong><span> to allow their models to be made available on AWS Bedrock seems to be driving the vast majority of their revenue.</span></p><p><span>I’m a bit surprised by how close things seem to be on the API front. It would appear that OpenAI is somewhere around ~$1.2-1.5B in run-rate revenue from its API revenue, while Anthropic is at around ~$800M in run-rate revenue. That would put </span><strong>OpenAI only about 50-100% larger than Anthropic on the API side</strong><span>, which is a much smaller gap than in aggregate.</span></p><p>Again, this seems to be largely driven by Anthropic’s success on the AWS platform. But I’m also surprised that OpenAI isn’t seeing even more uptick than they are from the Azure OpenAI usage and it raises the question around whether there is some difference in how Azure vs AWS API revenue is accounted for between OpenAI and Anthropic respectively.</p><p>Based on the losses that both have and the reported rounds they are raising ($6.5B in the case of OpenAI and likely &gt;1B in the case of Anthropic), it’s clear that foundation models will continue to require large amounts of capital, and that the number of players that can compete is quite small. We’re basically down to OpenAI, Anthropic, Meta, Mistral, Google and X.AI as well as various other attempts by Amazon/Microsoft.</p><p>In addition, as these companies push towards profitability at some point (even if not immediately as capital is still available), they seem to be betting on a few trends:</p><ul><li><p>A large reduction in inference costs over time to improve margins on the subscription products / API</p></li><li><p>Potential price increases in consumer subscription plans as model capabiltiy improves. OpenAI has already hinted at increasing prices to $22/mo this year and up to $44/month over the coming years.</p></li><li><p>A shift from training-time compute to inference-time compute, as highlighted by o1, to somewhat slow the ballooning training costs every 1-2 years.</p></li></ul><p>In closing, here are a few of the publications and reports I used to triangulate various datapoints:</p><ol><li><p><a href="https://fortune.com/2024/09/28/openai-5-billion-loss-2024-revenue-forecasts-fundraising-chapgpt-fee-hikes/" rel="">Fortune piece on ChatGPT fundraise</a></p></li><li><p><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/video/2024/09/24/ai-startup-anthropic-expects-revenue-surge-as-it-ramps-up-competition-with-openai.html" rel="">CNBC piece on Anthropic revenue and breakdown</a></p></li><li><p><a href="https://futuresearch.ai/openai-api-profit" rel="">Futuresearch estimates on Gross Margins</a></p></li></ol></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Filed: WP Engine Inc. v Automattic Inc. and Matthew Charles Mullenweg [pdf] (475 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Complaint-WP-Engine-v-Automattic-et-al-with-Exhibit.pdf</link>
            <guid>41726197</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 00:29:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Complaint-WP-Engine-v-Automattic-et-al-with-Exhibit.pdf">https://wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Complaint-WP-Engine-v-Automattic-et-al-with-Exhibit.pdf</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41726197">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Anatomy of an Internet Argument (144 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://defenderofthebasic.substack.com/p/anatomy-of-an-internet-argument</link>
            <guid>41724881</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 20:53:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://defenderofthebasic.substack.com/p/anatomy-of-an-internet-argument">https://defenderofthebasic.substack.com/p/anatomy-of-an-internet-argument</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41724881">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><p>I’ve spent the last 6 months arguing daily on the internet, and I’ve gotten *really* good at it. This is what the majority of my twitter arguments end up like:  </p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb8420823-b42e-4f23-991d-e9e1722f3150_756x900.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb8420823-b42e-4f23-991d-e9e1722f3150_756x900.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb8420823-b42e-4f23-991d-e9e1722f3150_756x900.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb8420823-b42e-4f23-991d-e9e1722f3150_756x900.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb8420823-b42e-4f23-991d-e9e1722f3150_756x900.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb8420823-b42e-4f23-991d-e9e1722f3150_756x900.jpeg" width="428" height="509.5238095238095" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/b8420823-b42e-4f23-991d-e9e1722f3150_756x900.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:900,&quot;width&quot;:756,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:428,&quot;bytes&quot;:83084,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb8420823-b42e-4f23-991d-e9e1722f3150_756x900.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb8420823-b42e-4f23-991d-e9e1722f3150_756x900.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb8420823-b42e-4f23-991d-e9e1722f3150_756x900.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb8420823-b42e-4f23-991d-e9e1722f3150_756x900.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>They always say something like “wow, a civil interaction, how rare!” but it’s not rare for me. I’ve gotten to a point where I can do this very consistently now, and I think others can learn this too.</p><p><span>There’s a misconception that good faith discussion only happens in close-knit communities like LessWrong or HackerNews. </span><strong>The reality I’m looking at here is that ~everyone on the internet is rational AND is arguing in good faith</strong><span>. If it doesn’t look that way, it’s because you’re speaking different languages.</span></p><p>Let’s look at 2 cases.</p><p><span>Here’s a puzzle: how do you respond to this insult to get them to apologize? </span><br><em>(I’ve blanked out the reply from user “InGoodFaith” for this exercise)</em></p><p>Some incorrect ways to respond:</p><ul><li><p>❌ Insulting them back </p><ul><li><p><em>(that just makes them more angry)</em></p></li></ul></li><li><p>❌ Telling them they’re wrong</p><ul><li><p><em> (they won’t understand what you’re saying because they’re already mad &amp; feeling attacked)</em></p></li><li><p><em>(even if they change their mind, they will not tell you this because it would feel like failure)</em></p></li></ul></li><li><p>❌ Telling them NOT to be rude </p><ul><li><p><em>(no one likes having their tone policied, they feel justified because (1) they are angry (2) your words are the source of their anger. Or at least their intrpretation of your words)</em></p></li></ul></li></ul><p>Here’s the winning move:</p><ul><li><p>✅ Signal that you are genuinely interested in understanding them, not attacking them</p></li></ul><p><span>No one has ever changed their mind while being attacked. People are way more likely to change their mind when they feel understood. </span><strong>It doesn’t matter if you understand them: you have to prove to *them* </strong><span>that you understand them</span><strong>.</strong></p><p>Yes, this is a lot of work. If you’re not willing to do this, then *you’re* not arguing in good faith in my book. You’re just here to beat people over the head with words that they don’t understand. It’s a waste of your time AND their time, and you leave with the (incorrect) belief that people are dumb, or don’t care about the truth etc. </p><p>This was the reply:</p><blockquote><p>sorry, I am too dumb to understand what "fortiori point" means! I think I'm just trying to understand the relationship of left/right towards Norway </p><p>I thought Norway = socialist policies = left-ist people aspire to it, but not republicans? right?</p></blockquote><p>The “too dumb” part I think helps to diffuse the anger, showing him that I’m not interested in fighting, but it’s probably not necessary. I think the important part was articulating what I don’t understand, asking a specific question. I’m also showing vulnerability by stating my beliefs and asking them to correct me. </p><p>This shows a genuine interest in understanding because it cannot be faked. It’s like “proof of work” in blockchain. It’s not enough to say:</p><blockquote><p>I really do want to understand you! Can you please explain your point without the insults?</p></blockquote><p>Because what the other person hears is:</p><blockquote><p><span>You’re not allowed to talk to me this way. Now repeat the point you’ve already said, but in a way that I will understand it. </span><strong>Also, I’m not going to bother telling you what part I didn’t understand</strong><span>, I want *you* to figure that out.</span></p></blockquote><p>I made an open call for anyone who feels like they encountered someone arguing “in bad faith” to send it to me and I will help analyze it/tell you what you could have done differently. </p><p>KJ took me up on it.</p><p>Here is the full interaction between them, and my analysis afterwards:</p><p>(1) 🪓“axial age” posts an anti-government post, in response to an obama quote</p><blockquote><p>Where did all those billions supposed to be spent on EV charging stations go? I patiently await your response.</p><p><em>Obama: "The other side knows it's easier to play on people's fears and cynicism. They will tell you that government is inherently corrupt."</em></p></blockquote><p>(2) 🎵 KJ responds</p><blockquote><p><span>looks like grants have been going out! and round 2 is coming up! </span><em>[link to source]</em></p><p><span>and not sure precisely the percentage that can be attributed to the CFI but there are certainly stations being built! </span><em>[link to source 2]</em></p><p>(i patiently await ur response 😛)</p></blockquote><p>(3) 🪓 axial responds</p><blockquote><p>How many built due to this program and at what cost? Press releases are cheap.</p></blockquote><p>(4) 🎵 KJ</p><blockquote><p>ok so actually, it looks like NONE have been built due to this program yet, bc the first round of funding was only just announced...</p><p>but the plan is to fund 47 projects (~7500 chargers) using 623mil of the total 2.5bil</p><p>(avg 80k per charger)</p></blockquote><p>(5) 🪓 axial </p><blockquote><p>this is why you're getting blocked</p></blockquote><p>From KJ’s prespective, this is bizarre: KJ was polite &amp; sincere, he included links to sources in every reply, he responded to every point axial brought it up. KJ is left with the conclusion that this person must not care at all about truth. </p><p>This is objectively the wrong conclusion. </p><p>Let’s look at this from axial’s side: </p><ol><li><p>He’s making a point about a strawman that Obama is using</p><ol><li><p>Obama says, vote blue, the other side is manipulating you into fearing the gov!</p></li><li><p>axial says, no, it’s not manipulation, it’s a valid criticism! </p></li></ol></li><li><p>Axial’s point is that it’s *not* about fear, it’s about, at best (1) government incompetence wasting tons of money (2) at worst, malicious actors getting rich off of these subsidies without actually providing value for society</p></li><li><p>KJ comes in with “proof” about the funding/plans for this money, and a smug, “patiently awaiting your response 😛”</p></li><li><p>This is totally missing the point. Axial very kindly explains:</p><ol><li><p>Yes, they’re saying they’re using this money for good, but how much good has it *actually* done?</p></li><li><p>And also, even if they did do these things, how much did it cost? Did it really need to cost this much? Could it have been done better &amp; cheaper if it was private? Is it possible that private companies are taking advantage of these gov programs and ripping us off?</p></li></ol></li><li><p>KJ doubles down: </p><ol><li><p>Insists that they’re going to build more, shares more links/press releases</p></li><li><p>Will not concede that there is a maybe a problem here, that maybe *some* government programs are not working, and that the rhetoric of the democratic party can sometimes strawman the other side</p></li></ol></li></ol><p>At this point axial blocks him because KJ comes off as NOT arguing in good faith, NOT interested in the truth. </p><p>KJ’s problem is he came in refuting a point that he didn’t understand. He was in fact arguing the wrong point. This is one of the most common failure modes I see. </p><p>The first step in any online argument is to understand the other side. You must empirically *confirm* this understanding with the other person. I would have said:</p><blockquote><p>“Where *did* those billions go? My understanding is a lot of it is going into building the initial infrastructure, so it’s slow going but we’ll see progress soon. Is that not true?” </p></blockquote><p>See, we don’t even know if axial is against EV and environmental protections, or if he just thinks the gov is doing a bad job executing it. How can you argue against this if you have no idea what he’s even saying? </p><p>So we start by (1) asking a question (2) articulating our understanding of the issue. The first point helps you understand them, the second point signals that you’re genuinely interested in understanding them, you’re laying your cards out. You’re revealing your beliefs and opening yourself up to being corrected.</p><p>It’s not about pretending that you’re willing to change your mind. You’re here because you think the solution is clear, and you don’t understand why people are voting against the things you believe are good. </p><p><span>I used to feel a deep sense of despair about humanity. I used to feel like, we </span><em>*knew*</em><span> how to make the world a better place, and the *only* reason we’re not doing it is because “people suck/are bad/evil/stupid”. </span></p><p><strong>This is a very difficult way to live life, it’s also just flat out false. </strong><span>This is not why the world isn’t getting better. This becomes very clear when talking to people with views &amp; opinions that I find repulsive/evil:</span></p><ol><li><p>I realize I had no idea that there are good reasons to be opposed to solution X</p></li><li><p>Or that a lot of people don’t understand why solution X is good, and they actually change their mind when someone explains it</p></li><li><p>Or that solution X is actually bad/not working. They are on my side, in that they also want to solve the problem, but they are skeptical that X is the way</p></li></ol><p>Everyone always asks me, how do you have so much patience to engage with “these trolls/haters”. I don’t do this for them. I do this for me. I share the earth with these people we call vile. Their opinions &amp; actions affect me greatly. Closing my eyes &amp; ears only hurts me. </p><p>The more I lean into things I hate &amp; that I know nothing about, the more I realize a lot of them are all good, reasonable people. A lot of us are really on the same side in wanting to make the world a better place for ourselves, our family, our community.</p><p>I’ll leave you with this reminder:</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F48c5064b-7a9e-477e-ba16-8a107f5d40b0_555x342.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F48c5064b-7a9e-477e-ba16-8a107f5d40b0_555x342.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F48c5064b-7a9e-477e-ba16-8a107f5d40b0_555x342.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F48c5064b-7a9e-477e-ba16-8a107f5d40b0_555x342.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F48c5064b-7a9e-477e-ba16-8a107f5d40b0_555x342.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F48c5064b-7a9e-477e-ba16-8a107f5d40b0_555x342.png" width="411" height="253.26486486486488" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/48c5064b-7a9e-477e-ba16-8a107f5d40b0_555x342.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:342,&quot;width&quot;:555,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:411,&quot;bytes&quot;:32240,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F48c5064b-7a9e-477e-ba16-8a107f5d40b0_555x342.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F48c5064b-7a9e-477e-ba16-8a107f5d40b0_555x342.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F48c5064b-7a9e-477e-ba16-8a107f5d40b0_555x342.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F48c5064b-7a9e-477e-ba16-8a107f5d40b0_555x342.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><em>Thanks for reading! I’m hoping to make this into a series, would love your feedback! Also, if you think my philosophy here is bullshit and overly naiive, I’d love to hear from you! If you have examples of people that are vile/clearly evil/not in good faith, send it my way.</em></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[In Mexico’s underwater caves, a glimpse of artifacts, fossils and human remains (161 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.smithsonianmag.com/travel/divers-in-mexicos-underwater-caves-get-a-glimpse-of-rarely-seen-artifacts-fossils-and-human-remains-180985159/</link>
            <guid>41724747</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 20:36:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/travel/divers-in-mexicos-underwater-caves-get-a-glimpse-of-rarely-seen-artifacts-fossils-and-human-remains-180985159/">https://www.smithsonianmag.com/travel/divers-in-mexicos-underwater-caves-get-a-glimpse-of-rarely-seen-artifacts-fossils-and-human-remains-180985159/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41724747">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>

    <div data-article-body="">

        

      

      <p>The underwater caves of the Yucatán Peninsula are a window to the distant past. Through two million years and over multiple glaciation cycles, these caves have been transformed. When the sea level was high, the caves flooded, and their reach expanded.</p>

<p>During the ice ages, the caves dried out as the sea level dropped, and the seeping water from the surface decorated the caverns with deposits such as stalagmites and stalactites, collectively known as <a href="https://www.ncei.noaa.gov/products/paleoclimatology/speleothem">speleothems</a>. Then, with the next cycle came higher sea levels again, flooding the caves and preserving in time the speleothems and everything else with them.</p>

<p>I have been diving the unique submerged landscapes of Mexican cenotes, or sinkholes, for almost ten years, exploring their dark, flooded tunnels and capturing their secrets. The last time the shallow caves on the Yucatán Peninsula flooded was around 8,000 years ago, which means that every diver in these caves travels back in time to a prehistoric age. The paleontological and archaeological remains preserved within them would disintegrate at the surface, which makes these caves a perfect time capsule.</p>

<h2>How Mexico’s cenotes came to be</h2>

<figure>
  
    <img src="https://th-thumbnailer.cdn-si-edu.com/M-8eBGgfzUpenD5cGXaAmlIDsPs=/fit-in/1072x0/filters:focal(500x779:501x780)/https://tf-cmsv2-smithsonianmag-media.s3.amazonaws.com/filer_public/8f/39/8f399fc2-5560-45d8-900f-00b07c99e2c2/martin_broen_page36.jpg" alt="Divers in Mexico's Underwater Caves Get a Glimpse of Rarely Seen Artifacts, Fossils and Human Remains" loading="lazy">
  

  <figcaption>
    
      The lagoon-like entrance of an unnamed cenote stretches out near the Caribbean Sea.
    
    
      <span>Martin Broen</span>
    
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>This underworld is formed by a massive underground aquifer in the northern Yucatán Peninsula of Mexico. It is accessible by cenotes that connect the surface of the Earth to the longest underground river systems in the world. Here, water doesn’t accumulate on the surface as rivers, but instead gets absorbed through the porous limestone to flow within underground tunnels. Much as our blood vessels send life-sustaining fluid throughout our bodies, these tunnels convey the precious water that sustains all life in this region. It is no wonder that cenotes were considered sacred by the Maya.</p>

<p>The Maya established their civilization on the Yucatán Peninsula about 4,000 years ago. In order to thrive, they needed to settle close to a freshwater source. All of their largest settlements on the northern part of the peninsula—including the famed Chichén Itzá—were built beside cenotes. During the region’s dry season, cenotes were the only source of water; therefore, the sinkholes were not only a fundamental part of Maya life but also a place for worship and rituals related to rain, life, death and rebirth.</p>

<figure>
  
    <img src="https://th-thumbnailer.cdn-si-edu.com/_40F8FoUKD7itn62hRgM92UwUS4=/fit-in/1072x0/filters:focal(1000x724:1001x725)/https://tf-cmsv2-smithsonianmag-media.s3.amazonaws.com/filer_public/90/79/90790f3b-89bf-400f-bb9d-1ec7163b56a7/martin_broen_page64.jpg" alt="Divers in Mexico's Underwater Caves Get a Glimpse of Rarely Seen Artifacts, Fossils and Human Remains" loading="lazy">
  

  <figcaption>
    
      Looking up from the depths of the Blue Abyss highlights this in-cave sinkhole's distinctive shape and azure tones.
    
    
      <span>Martin Broen</span>
    
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Each Maya <em>d’zonot </em>(the Maya word from which the word cenote comes from) was an entrance to the mystical underworld called Xibalba, where various deities and supernatural beings resided. It is a mysterious and powerful realm associated with death, a portal to a domain where ritualistic offerings honored both the gods and the deceased and sought protection and guidance for the living. Living within, and the protector of this underworld, was Chaac, the god of rain, fertility and agriculture. He was an important deity in Maya mythology, as rain was vital for the success of crops and the well-being of the community.</p>

<p>Beneath the cenotes, deeper in their caves, artifacts and human remains from the Maya civilization have lain undisturbed for centuries and can be seen by explorers. But these are not the only indicators of human presence. While the Maya settled the region only a few thousand years ago, evidence found in the cenotes points to human settlements in the area dating back more than 13,000 years. These finds challenge the accepted notion of when our ancestors first crossed into America via the Bering Land Bridge between Siberia and Alaska during the last ice age.</p>
<div>
    <p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/084783090X?tag=smithsonianco-20&amp;linkCode=ogi&amp;th=1&amp;psc=1" target="_blank">
        <img src="https://th-thumbnailer.cdn-si-edu.com/I2jVLjzb201khSa5BminO6sygrY=/fit-in/300x0/https://tf-cmsv2-smithsonianmag-media.s3.amazonaws.com/amazon/amazon_image_a9e46f4491b50afa6ef6849b608a35b55ecb35f3.jpg" title="Light in the Underworld: Diving the Mexican Cenotes" alt="Preview thumbnail for 'Light in the Underworld: Diving the Mexican Cenotes">
      </a>
    </p>
    
  </div>
<p>These ancient hunter-gatherers also depended on the cenotes as a water source, and probably for shelter as well. Back then, the cenotes were much drier, with the water level some 300 feet below current-day levels. The ancient inhabitants had to venture deep into the caves to access the water, crossing paths with huge prehistoric animals from the late Pleistocene—now long extinct—that also sought fresh water.</p>

<h2>Finding Maya artifacts and human remains</h2>

<figure>
  
    <img src="https://th-thumbnailer.cdn-si-edu.com/kzNrFLtGJkdGTpQKQMeRKQgLya4=/fit-in/1072x0/filters:focal(500x560:501x561)/https://tf-cmsv2-smithsonianmag-media.s3.amazonaws.com/filer_public/51/53/51530ab9-54e0-431f-a9b7-ee6e1c23d66a/martin_broen_page142.jpg" alt="Divers in Mexico's Underwater Caves Get a Glimpse of Rarely Seen Artifacts, Fossils and Human Remains" loading="lazy">
  

  <figcaption>
    
      A skull of a high-ranking Maya features an intentionally deformed forehead bone and front teeth carved to hold decorations.
    
    
      <span>Martin Broen</span>
    
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>It’s challenging to put into words the raw and profound sensation that accompanies encountering a human skull in the darkness of the flooded caves. Long before I recognize a skull as mere remains, I can feel its gaze upon me from the shadows, a haunting presence that defies description. Particularly in the area of the Ring of Cenotes, many sacrificial cenotes hold skulls of the higher-ranking Maya families. Along with modified front teeth to host ornaments, these skulls were artificially deformed to create a physical distinction. The higher-ranking Maya used different techniques to shape their children’s skulls, creating an oblique deformation, which made their heads look longer than the average Maya’s. Said to resemble a jaguar’s head, this shape was a symbol of power. Also rare sightings for cave explorers are sophisticated Maya paintings on cave walls close to the entrances of cenotes. Depicting wars, animals, gods and stories, these treasures can be forever lost once submerged, washed away over time.</p>

<p>Long before the Maya settled in the area, the first Homo sapiens crossed into America over the Bering Land Bridge at least 25,000 years ago. They made their way down to South America and arrived on the Yucatán Peninsula at the end of the last ice age around 13,000 years ago. There they used the caves to extract water and minerals, to find shelter, and to bury their dead. While it is typically hard to find remains of these hunter-gatherers on the surface of the Earth, evidence of early human presence was preserved in these caves from before the last time the caves flooded. That evidence gives us clues to understanding early humans’ biology and even their social interactions.</p>

<p>Within the flooded caves it is common to see purposely broken formations that create passages through the tunnels, and even cairns—made of piles of rocks or broken speleothems—placed at the junctions of tunnels to navigate the intricate cave labyrinths. Early humans also excavated rocks and mined red ocher using only Stone Age tools and their mastery of fire. They used the ocher to decorate objects for personal ornamentation and burials. They also decorated the caves with multiple art forms, from paintings on the walls to sculptures. A well-known example is the figure of a woman at the entrance of Cenote Dos Ojos; while it was not sculpted as such, it is a carefully selected speleothem that resembles the silhouette of a woman and was intentionally exhibited on a pedestal to decorate the cave entrance, evidence of paleoart from more than 8,000 years ago that anyone can visit.</p>

<figure>
  
    <img src="https://th-thumbnailer.cdn-si-edu.com/ZMqt5EBWJ3jPMbWQW9-VVu-zrc4=/fit-in/1072x0/filters:focal(1000x981:1001x982)/https://tf-cmsv2-smithsonianmag-media.s3.amazonaws.com/filer_public/7e/c4/7ec494ec-ea5e-4be9-9064-a5a39e210a8d/martin_broen_page13.jpg" alt="Divers in Mexico's Underwater Caves Get a Glimpse of Rarely Seen Artifacts, Fossils and Human Remains" loading="lazy">
  

  <figcaption>
    
      Maya remains preserved within flooded caves are a haunting reminder of this ancient civilization.
    
    
      <span>Martin Broen</span>
    
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<h2>Diving for fossil evidence of extinct megafauna</h2>

<p>As if they were corridors of a museum, the submerged passageways of these time capsules also offer divers the opportunity to uncover exquisitely preserved fossils of diverse creatures—most of which are now extinct—that once inhabited the Yucatán during the late Pleistocene.</p>

<p>Following the cataclysmic impact of the Chicxulub asteroid 66 million years ago, which marked the end of the dinosaur age, mammals began to dominate the lands once ruled by dinosaurs. Over time, North and South America underwent distinct evolutionary trajectories. However, around 2.7 million years ago, the formation of the Panamanian land bridge facilitated a pivotal event: the Great American Biotic Interchange.</p>

<p>During this exchange, North American fauna migrated southward, including large mammals called megafauna, like saber-toothed cats, lions, gomphotheres (related to modern elephants), horses and camels. Meanwhile, South American megafauna moved northward, including giant ground sloths and glyptodonts (enormous armadillos). This monumental event significantly influenced and sculpted the ecosystems and biodiversity of both continents, affecting the composition of species and ecosystems we see today.</p>

<figure>
  
    <img src="https://th-thumbnailer.cdn-si-edu.com/U2pfEYCo-sa7ygDafegrOjcr5AQ=/fit-in/1072x0/filters:focal(1000x671:1001x672)/https://tf-cmsv2-smithsonianmag-media.s3.amazonaws.com/filer_public/7c/26/7c267208-c0f6-4589-9e6f-1ca9c6c34347/martin_broen_page110.jpg" alt="Divers in Mexico's Underwater Caves Get a Glimpse of Rarely Seen Artifacts, Fossils and Human Remains" loading="lazy">
  

  <figcaption>
    
      A fossilized shell of a loggerhead sea turtle (<em>Caretta caretta</em>) may mark where it perished in the cave 200,000 years ago.
    
    
      <span>Martin Broen</span>
    
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The thrill of exploring the underwater caves of the Yucatán is heightened upon uncovering the fossilized remains of these long-extinct megafauna. Visualizing these colossal creatures coming to life right where you are diving, in what was once a prehistoric cave that had been frozen in time by these waters, is like being teleported back to their era, immersed in a thrilling journey through time. How their fossils came to be submerged underwater can be easily imagined. With the water level during the last ice age up to 300 feet lower than it is today, these animals had to venture down dark, dry cave passages to reach drinking water, sometimes surprisingly far away from an entrance. Trapped in sinkholes or lost within labyrinthine passages, these animals died, and their remains became fossilized and preserved by rising water levels.</p>

<p>Among the many extinct species that lived in this region are members of the family Megalonychidae (including the genus <em>Megalonyx</em>, Greek for “large claw”). Fossils of these giant ground sloths are commonly found in the caves, as they probably took refuge within them, such as members of the genus <em>Xibalbaonyx</em> (“great claw of Xibalba”), a polar bear-sized ground sloth with big claws that measured up to 12 feet in height and weighed nearly a ton. They are joined by members of related families, including the genus <em>Nothrotheriops</em>, a grizzly bear-sized mammal that reached five feet tall and weighed 1,000 pounds.</p>

<p>Representing archaeological and paleontological marvels, the fossils concealed within the caves constitute genuine treasures, allowing for teams of specialized scientists to explore these wonders, aiming to unravel scientific enigmas, construct hypotheses and shed light on the mysteries that shroud our planet’s history.</p>

<figure>
  
    <img src="https://th-thumbnailer.cdn-si-edu.com/m_vsP2V37uUoOS_WUiy0SusBCgI=/fit-in/1072x0/filters:focal(1000x629:1001x630)/https://tf-cmsv2-smithsonianmag-media.s3.amazonaws.com/filer_public/59/00/59008b60-1dd4-463c-9919-470052ade97d/martin_broen_page4.jpg" alt="Divers in Mexico's Underwater Caves Get a Glimpse of Rarely Seen Artifacts, Fossils and Human Remains" loading="lazy">
  

  <figcaption>
    
      Green from concentrated tannic acid in the water gives an otherworldly hue to tunnels close to Cenote Hatzutz Aktun.
    
    
      <span>Martin Broen</span>
    
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<h2>Many more mysteries to be solved</h2>

<p>There’s a symbiotic relationship between the passionate and technical cave explorers who investigate every hole in a cave in their free time (and just for fun) and those in the scientific community who want to study these prehistoric materials but cannot reach where they’re hidden in the underwater darkness. This relationship of discovery and research has already provided evidence of many newly discovered extinct species, as well as ancient humans who had vanished for millennia, a relationship that could be fostered even more by leveraging the world-class level of the dive explorers in the area. After all, the majority of these secrets remain yet to be discovered!</p>

<p>The caves also hold evidence that could solve a prehistoric murder mystery. After the Great American Biotic Interchange, these megafauna species coexisted in this region for hundreds of thousands of years and through multiple ice age cycles, until their abrupt extinction more than 10,000 years ago when a new species arrived on the Yucatán Peninsula: Homo sapiens.</p>

<p>After humans arrived in the region, many genera of large mammals became extinct. There are different ways to explain this mass extinction event. One leading hypothesis states that the already reduced populations of those animals, stressed due to the changing climate after the latest ice age, were hunted to extinction by the humans. These big mammals, which needed a long time to become sexually mature and had slow reproduction rates (up to 22 months), were particularly vulnerable to this new threat.</p>

<figure>
  
    <img src="https://th-thumbnailer.cdn-si-edu.com/XM69tCsgGM10dUxUszWcN4J7oD0=/fit-in/1072x0/filters:focal(1000x671:1001x672)/https://tf-cmsv2-smithsonianmag-media.s3.amazonaws.com/filer_public/27/75/27752fce-4a20-463b-85b6-eadaca0d3fdb/martin_broen_page37.jpg" alt="Divers in Mexico's Underwater Caves Get a Glimpse of Rarely Seen Artifacts, Fossils and Human Remains" loading="lazy">
  

  <figcaption>
    
      The narrow entrance of Cenote Corral focuses the pulsing light beams.
    
    
      <span>Martin Broen</span>
    
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Among the fossils preserved within the flooded caves, I have witnessed many examples indicating that these extinct species had been hunted and eaten by our predecessors, such as preserved megafauna bones exhibiting cut marks from human-made stone tools, the repetitive marks showing the methodical action taken to remove flesh from the bone. Also noted are perforations on fossilized bones inflicted by projectiles, extinct animal remains beside cooking pits with bones in them, organized piles of bones, and burn marks on animal fossils inside the cave. Indications such as these have been found at cave depths that correspond to the time horizon when humans and the now-extinct animals coexisted and within areas that also exhibit indications of the kind of sophisticated social organization required for early humans to hunt these big creatures, like the mining of red ocher.</p>

<p>The hypothesis of the Paleo-Americans overhunting these species to extinction still needs to be validated, but it is undeniable that these caves protect invaluable material for scientists to study, information that will help us understand our past—and hopefully inform our future.</p>

<p><em>Adaptation from </em><a href="https://amzn.to/3BvmODq">Light in the Underworld: Diving the Mexican Cenotes</a><em> by Martin Broen (Rizzoli New York).</em></p>

      
        
  
  <div>
      <p>Get the latest <strong>Travel &amp; Culture</strong> stories in your inbox.</p>
      
    </div>


      

      
      
        <p><strong>A Note to our Readers</strong><br>
          Smithsonian magazine participates in affiliate link advertising programs. If you purchase an item through these links, we receive a commission.</p>
      

      
        


  
    
      
    
  

  


      

      
      

      
        
          <section>
            <nav>Filed Under:
              
                
                  <a href="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/tag/archaeology/">Archaeology</a>, 
                
              
                
                  <a href="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/tag/artifacts/">Artifacts</a>, 
                
              
                
                  <a href="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/tag/books/">Books</a>, 
                
              
                
                  <a href="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/tag/caves/">Caves</a>, 
                
              
                
                  <a href="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/tag/extinction/">Extinction</a>, 
                
              
                
                  <a href="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/tag/fossils/">Fossils</a>, 
                
              
                
                  <a href="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/tag/geology/">Geology</a>, 
                
              
                
                  <a href="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/tag/mayas/">Mayas</a>, 
                
              
                
                  <a href="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/tag/mexico/">Mexico</a>, 
                
              
                
                  <a href="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/tag/paleontology/">Paleontology</a>
                
              
            </nav>
          </section>
        
      

    </div>

    

  </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[WALDO: Whereabouts Ascertainment for Low-Lying Detectable Objects (101 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/stephansturges/WALDO</link>
            <guid>41723311</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 17:56:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/stephansturges/WALDO">https://github.com/stephansturges/WALDO</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41723311">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">W.A.L.D.O.
Whereabouts Ascertainment for Low-lying Detectable Objects</h2><a id="user-content-waldowhereabouts-ascertainment-for-low-lying-detectable-objects" aria-label="Permalink: W.A.L.D.O.
Whereabouts Ascertainment for Low-lying Detectable Objects" href="#waldowhereabouts-ascertainment-for-low-lying-detectable-objects"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1caA0ZVPqhA" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/0874c110d856f31f4fb03ec230c65fabb3a26a773bd28fcf7d155256abe36369/68747470733a2f2f692e696d6775722e636f6d2f36597a6d5a35502e706e67" alt="WALDO 2.4 preview vid" data-canonical-src="https://i.imgur.com/6YzmZ5P.png"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Welcome to the WALDO v2.5 FINAL release! 🥳🥳🥳🥳</h2><a id="user-content-welcome-to-the-waldo-v25-final-release-" aria-label="Permalink: Welcome to the WALDO v2.5 FINAL release! 🥳🥳🥳🥳" href="#welcome-to-the-waldo-v25-final-release-"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Thanks to all participants in the beta! I had over 3000 sign-ups for the
beta release and iterated really fast... I hope you'll like the result!</p>
<p dir="auto">I am assuming you have  some experience with deployment of AI systems,
but if you have any trouble using this release you can contact me at
stephan.sturges at gmail</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto">WHAT IS WALDO?</p>
<p dir="auto">WALDO is a detection AI model, based on a large YOLO-v7 backbone and my own
synthetic data pipeline. The basic model shared here, which is the only
one published as FOSS at the moment, is capable of detecting these classes
of items in overhead images ranging in altitude from about 30 feet to
satellite imagery with a resolution of 50cm per pixel or better.</p>
<p dir="auto">Well trained classes:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>'car'  --&gt; all kinds of civilan cars, including pickup trucks</li>
<li>'van' --&gt; all kinds of civilian vans, gets confused with "car" a lot. You might want to fuse them! 🚗</li>
<li>'truck' --&gt; all kinds of box-trucks, flatbeds or articulated trucks, NOT small pickup trucks 🚚</li>
<li>'building' --&gt; buildings of all kinds 🏣</li>
<li>'human' --&gt; people! 🧍</li>
<li>'gastank'--&gt; cylindrical tanks such as butane tanks and gas expansion tanks, or grain silos 🫙</li>
<li>'digger' --&gt; all kinds of construction vehicles, including tractors and construction gear 🚜</li>
<li>'container' --&gt; shipping containers, including on the back of an articulated truck</li>
<li>'bus' --&gt; a bus 🚌</li>
<li>'u_pole' --&gt; utility poles, power poles, anything thin and sticking up that you should avoid with a plane 🎏</li>
<li>'boat' --&gt; boats 🚢</li>
<li>'bike' --&gt; bikes, mopeds, motorbikes, all things with 2 wheels 🚲</li>
<li>'smoke' --&gt; smoke and fire 🔥🔥🔥</li>
<li>'solarpanels' --&gt; solar panels</li>
<li>'arm/mil' --&gt; this class detects certain types of armored vehicles (very unreliable for now, don't use it yet)</li>
<li>'plane' --&gt; planes (very unreliable for now, probably not worth using yet)</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<p dir="auto">WHERE IS WALDO?</p>
<p dir="auto">Due to the size of the model files and the constraints of github LFS the files
are no longer stored directly on Github, please download the latest package
using the link below:</p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://bit.ly/3P7UdZ6" rel="nofollow">https://bit.ly/3P7UdZ6</a></p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto">FOR AI NERDS !</p>
<p dir="auto">It's a big set of YOLOv7 model, trained on my own datasets of synthetic and "augmented" / semi-synthetic data.
I'm not going to release the dataset for the time being.</p>
<p dir="auto">The ONNX models are exported for onnx-runtime with a batch-size of 1 and a max input size corresponding to the
the network dimensions. They are also set up to export only the top 200 highest-confidence objects in most cases.</p>
<p dir="auto">I'm planning to set up a way for people to get the .pt files and the ONNX models with unlimited outputs
for people who support further development of the project on Ko-Fi (<a href="https://ko-fi.com/stephansturges" rel="nofollow">https://ko-fi.com/stephansturges</a>), the goal
being to offset some of the cost of training these networks (over 60K USD spent on AWS to date! 😅)</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto">HOW CAN I START WITH WALDO?</p>
<p dir="auto">Setup the environment with python3:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>(optional) create a virtual python env for the project</li>
<li>install dependencies using the <code>setup.py</code> file: <code>python3 setup.py install</code></li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto">You may need to install a couple of other bits and pieces depending on your python3 env...
If you find anything really blocking send me an email and I'll update this readme.</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto">RUN THE MODELS USING THE BOILERPLATE CODE IN /playground:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>To run on video:
put one or multiple .mp4 files in the ./input_vids subfolder, and then run:</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto">python3 run_local_onnx_on_videos.py</p>
<p dir="auto">This will run the detection network in default settings and save an annotated video to
the ./output_vids/ subfolder.</p>
<p dir="auto">You can also use the following command-line arguments:</p>
<p dir="auto">python3 run_local_onnx_on_videos.py --frame_limit 3000 --frame_skip 8</p>
<p dir="auto">"frame limit" defines where to stop processing the video, if you only want to test it
on the first 1000 frame then use --frame_limit 1000 for example</p>
<p dir="auto">"frame skip" allows you to skip frames to keep processing quicker for testing, so
if your video is 30 fps and you only one 1 frame per second to be AI-annotated
then you can use --frame_skip 30 for instance</p>
<ol start="2" dir="auto">
<li>To run on a single image of any size:</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto">Put some images in ./images_in/ and run:</p>
<p dir="auto">python3 run_local_onnx_on_images.py</p>
<p dir="auto">This will run detection on all images in the input folder and save the annotated
output images in the output folder, along with the txt files of the detections
in YOLO format.</p>
<p dir="auto">If the image is LARGER than 960x960px format it will be tiled into squares of 960px with
a litte overlap for analysis and then merged back together, so you can process
huge satellite images for example without needing to split them first.</p>
<p dir="auto">If you want to run the network on a single image that should be processed at native resolution
you can use the "--resize" flag like this:</p>
<p dir="auto">python3 run_local_onnx_on_images.py --resize</p>
<p dir="auto">The output can be found in ./images_out/, you'll get images with pretty overlays and .txt files
with the actual detections</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto">WHAT IS INCLUDED?</p>
<p dir="auto">In the FOSS package there are a bunch of networks in ONNX format prepared for ONNXruntime, as
well as a few examples of networks in other export formats. Only the "V7-base/square/416px"
network is included in all formats as part of this release, meaning you get a selection of
ONNX exported models including some quantized and prepared for Nvidia TensorRT, and you
also have the raw .pt files for the training run so that you can export your own.
I also added the base .pt files for the 512px V7 model.
These files also exist for each other network (or can be exported), but I'm thinking about
how to make those available for people who support the future development of WALDO in order
to support the cost of AI model training (which is over 50K $ already up to this point).
Reach out to me via email if you want a model / export that isn't in here!</p>
<p dir="auto">/!\ Some tips for use:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>In real-world use cases you may want to merge classes 1 &amp; 2 since there this still
a lot of confusion between those classes</li>
<li>The models are exported with non-maximum-suppression, so if you are using the
AI system in cases where objects are occluded by one another you will only get
the "most valid" object in most cases.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Some of the network that is in this repo is very large, and is meant to be run on
an inference server, and some are made for embedding on tiny edge devices... take
a look around and find one that works for you!</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto">GOING DEEPER</p>
<p dir="auto">Of course if you know your way around deploying AI models there is a lot more you do
with this release, inclusing:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>There are certain models already released in CoreML format for iOS, give those a try</li>
<li>There are some models that are exported for TensorRT, including some cool quantization!</li>
<li>For a couple of models the .pt files are included in this release, play with making
your own exports or running thos directly using YOLOv7 from <a href="https://github.com/WongKinYiu/yolov7">https://github.com/WongKinYiu/yolov7</a></li>
<li>Get yourself a cool, cheap, little AI camera from Luxonis and run one of the OpenVino blobs
that are currently exported for the V7-base/416px network and the V7-tiny/512px network. These
are super cool and do excellent AI detections directly on 15g hardware that costs &lt;200$... crazy stuff.</li>
<li>Build your own commercial application!</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto">Enjoy!</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto">PREVIOUS VERSIONS</p>
<p dir="auto">You can find the repo with WALDO v1.0 here:
<a href="https://github.com/stephansturges/WALDO">https://github.com/stephansturges/WALDO</a></p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto">CAN YOU HELP ME WITH X?</p>
<p dir="auto">Sure, email me at <a href="mailto:stephan.sturges@gmail.com">stephan.sturges@gmail.com</a></p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto">DETECTION OF X ISN'T WORKING AS EXPECTED:</p>
<p dir="auto">I'd love to see example images, videos, sample data, etc at:
<a href="mailto:stephan.sturges@gmail.com">stephan.sturges@gmail.com</a></p>
<p dir="auto">HOW DOES AIRCORTEX MAKE MONEY?</p>
<p dir="auto">Aircortex' mission statement is to make the SOTA in ground-risk AI and sensing,
and to make the basic models free and easy to use for both hobbyists and
professionals in the UAV / AAM industry, to acclerate safe access to the skies
in the 21st century.</p>
<p dir="auto">Aircortex is an "open-core" AI company: the basic model is completely
free and open-source for anyone to use including in commercial products.</p>
<p dir="auto">I make money by charging for:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>help with training additional detection classes,</li>
<li>retraining for your specific hardware,</li>
<li>building the software stack to support specific deployment cases,</li>
<li>helping companies set up the right hardware architecture for AI integration,</li>
<li>custom hardware setups for specific environments</li>
<li>more "feature-complete" versions of my FOSS products such as integrating 3D perception
etc...</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto">Contact me at <a href="mailto:stephan.sturges@gmail.com">stephan.sturges@gmail.com</a> to find out more.</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto">SUPPORT WALDO!</p>
<p dir="auto">Training this base model took about 3 months of work and ~20K$ in cloud compute.
If you find value in it, please support development of the next version on:
<a href="https://ko-fi.com/stephansturges" rel="nofollow">https://ko-fi.com/stephansturges</a></p>
<p dir="auto">You can also sign-up there to be a sponsor of WALDO for 500$ / month and get
early access to future models.</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto">/_<em><strong>//_</strong></em>//_<em><strong>//_</strong></em>//_<em><strong>//_</strong></em>//_<em><strong>//_</strong></em>//_<em><strong>//_</strong>
/</em><em><strong>//</strong></em><em>//</em><em><strong>//</strong></em><em>//</em><em><strong>//</strong></em><em>//</em><em><strong>//</strong></em><em>//</em><em><strong>//</strong></em></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">LICENSE</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: LICENSE" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Unless otherwise specified all code in this release is published with the
licence conditions below.</h2><a id="user-content-unless-otherwise-specified-all-code-in-this-release-is-published-with-thelicence-conditions-below" aria-label="Permalink: Unless otherwise specified all code in this release is published with the
licence conditions below." href="#unless-otherwise-specified-all-code-in-this-release-is-published-with-thelicence-conditions-below"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">MIT License</p>
<p dir="auto">Copyright (c) 2023 Stephan Sturges / Aircortex.com</p>
<p dir="auto">Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy
of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"), to deal
in the Software without restriction, including without limitation the rights
to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell
copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is
furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:</p>
<p dir="auto">The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in all
copies or substantial portions of the Software.</p>
<p dir="auto">THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM,
OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE
SOFTWARE.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OpenAI completes deal that values company at $157B (224 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/2024/10/02/technology/openai-valuation-150-billion.html</link>
            <guid>41722742</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 17:04:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/10/02/technology/openai-valuation-150-billion.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2024/10/02/technology/openai-valuation-150-billion.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41722742">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nytimes.com/2024/10/02/technology/openai-valuation-150-billion.html: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[An adult fruit fly brain has been mapped (497 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.economist.com/science-and-technology/2024/10/02/an-adult-fruit-fly-brain-has-been-mapped-human-brains-could-follow</link>
            <guid>41722159</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 16:16:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.economist.com/science-and-technology/2024/10/02/an-adult-fruit-fly-brain-has-been-mapped-human-brains-could-follow">https://www.economist.com/science-and-technology/2024/10/02/an-adult-fruit-fly-brain-has-been-mapped-human-brains-could-follow</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41722159">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><section><div><p><span><a href="https://www.economist.com/science-and-technology" data-analytics="sidebar:section"><span>Science &amp; technology</span></a></span><span> | <!-- -->On the fly</span></p></div><h2>For now, it is the most sophisticated connectome ever made</h2></section><section><figure><img alt="50 largest neurons of the fly brain connectome." fetchpriority="high" width="1280" height="720" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" sizes="(min-width: 960px) 700px, 95vw" srcset="https://www.economist.com/cdn-cgi/image/width=360,quality=80,format=auto/content-assets/images/20241005_STP001.jpg 360w, https://www.economist.com/cdn-cgi/image/width=384,quality=80,format=auto/content-assets/images/20241005_STP001.jpg 384w, https://www.economist.com/cdn-cgi/image/width=480,quality=80,format=auto/content-assets/images/20241005_STP001.jpg 480w, https://www.economist.com/cdn-cgi/image/width=600,quality=80,format=auto/content-assets/images/20241005_STP001.jpg 600w, https://www.economist.com/cdn-cgi/image/width=834,quality=80,format=auto/content-assets/images/20241005_STP001.jpg 834w, https://www.economist.com/cdn-cgi/image/width=960,quality=80,format=auto/content-assets/images/20241005_STP001.jpg 960w, https://www.economist.com/cdn-cgi/image/width=1096,quality=80,format=auto/content-assets/images/20241005_STP001.jpg 1096w, https://www.economist.com/cdn-cgi/image/width=1280,quality=80,format=auto/content-assets/images/20241005_STP001.jpg 1280w, https://www.economist.com/cdn-cgi/image/width=1424,quality=80,format=auto/content-assets/images/20241005_STP001.jpg 1424w" src="https://www.economist.com/cdn-cgi/image/width=1424,quality=80,format=auto/content-assets/images/20241005_STP001.jpg"><figcaption><span>Photograph: Tyler Sloan &amp; Amy Sterling/ FlyW</span></figcaption></figure></section><div><div><p><time datetime="2024-10-02T15:02:44.481Z"> <!-- -->Oct 2nd 2024</time></p></div><section data-body-id="cp2"><p data-component="paragraph"><span data-caps="initial">F</span><small>RUIT FLIES</small> are smart. For a start—the clue is in the name—they can fly. They can also flirt; fight; form complex, long-term memories of their surroundings; and even warn one another about the presence of unseen dangers, such as parasitic wasps. </p></section><div><p><a href="https://s100.copyright.com/AppDispatchServlet?publisherName=economist&amp;publication=economist&amp;title=An%20adult%20fruit%20fly%20brain%20has%20been%20mapped%E2%80%94human%20brains%20could%20follow&amp;publicationDate=2024-10-02&amp;contentID=%2Fcontent%2Fc2v47l1ps9nddstit39seocd2ecb2k1m&amp;type=A&amp;orderBeanReset=TRUE" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer" data-analytics="end_of_article:reuse_this_content"><span>Reuse this content</span></a></p></div></div><div data-test-id="right-hand-rail-ads"></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Fastest Mutexes (819 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://justine.lol/mutex/</link>
            <guid>41721668</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 15:31:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://justine.lol/mutex/">https://justine.lol/mutex/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41721668">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">

<p>
Oct 2<sup>nd</sup>, 2024 @ <a href="https://justine.lol/index.html">justine's web page</a>
</p>

<p><img src="https://justine.lol/mutex/honeybadger.png" alt="[cosmpolitan honeybadger logo]" width="334" height="200"><br>
Cosmopolitan Honeybadger
</p>

<p>
<a href="https://justine.lol/cosmo3/">Cosmopolitan Libc</a> is well-known for
its <a href="https://justine.lol/ape.html">polyglot fat binary</a> hack
that lets your executables run on six OSes for AMD64 / ARM64. What may
surprise you is that it could also be the best C library for your
production workloads too. To demonstrate this point, let's compare
Cosmo's mutex library with other platforms.

</p><p>
We'll do this by writing a simple test that spawns <strong>30
threads</strong> which increment the same integer <strong>100,000
times</strong>. This tests how well a mutex implementation performs in
the heavily contended use case. In essence, that means the following
(see the segment at the bottom of the page for the full source code).

</p><pre><span>int</span> g_chores;
<span>pthread_mutex_t</span> g_locker = PTHREAD_MUTEX_INITIALIZER;

<span>void</span> *<span>worker</span>(<span>void</span> *arg) {
  <span>for</span> (<span>int</span> i = 0; i &lt; ITERATIONS; ++i) {
    pthread_mutex_lock(&amp;g_locker);
    ++g_chores;
    pthread_mutex_unlock(&amp;g_locker);
  }
  <span>return</span> 0;
}
</pre>

<p>
Now let's start with the exciting part, which are my benchmark results.

</p><h3>Benchmarks</h3>

<p>
Times will be measured in microseconds. Wall time is how long the test
program takes to run. That includes the overhead of spawning and joining
threads. User time is how much CPU time was spent in userspace, and
system time is how much CPU time was spent in the kernel. System and
user time can exceed the actual wall time because multiple threads are
running in parallel.

</p><p>
The first results I'll show are for Windows because Mark Waterman did an
excellent <a href="https://github.com/markwaterman/MutexShootout">mutex
shootout</a> three months ago, where he said, "in the highly contended
scenario, Windows wins the day with its SRWLOCK". Contention is where
mutex implementations show their inequality. Mark was so impressed by
Microsoft's SRWLOCK that he went on to recommend Linux and FreeBSD users
consider targeting Windows if mutex contention is an issue.

</p><div>
<table>
<tbody><tr>
  <th colspan="4"><p>
      Windows Mutex Implementations<br>
      24-core Threadripper 29070WX

</p></th></tr><tr>
  <th>wall<br>time (µs)
  </th><th>user<br>time (µs)
  </th><th>system<br>time (µs)
  </th><th>implementation

</th></tr><tr>
  <td>148,940
  </td><td>328,125
  </td><td>62,500
  </td><td>Cosmopolitan pthread_mutex_t

</td></tr><tr>
  <td>410,416
  </td><td>5,515,625
  </td><td>1,640,625
  </td><td>Microsoft SRWLOCK

</td></tr><tr>
  <td>949,187
  </td><td>7,937,500
  </td><td>5,078,125
  </td><td>Microsoft CRITICAL_SECTION

</td></tr><tr>
  <td>991,750
  </td><td>12,156,250
  </td><td>4,031,250
  </td><td>MSVC 2022 std::mutex

</td></tr><tr>
  <td>1,165,435
  </td><td>24,515,000
  </td><td>15,000
  </td><td>spin lock

</td></tr><tr>
  <td>9,780,803
  </td><td>1,937,000
  </td><td>6,156,000
  </td><td>Cygwin pthread_mutex_t

</td></tr></tbody></table>
</div>

<p>
As we can see, Cosmopolitan Libc mutexes go 2.75x faster than
Microsoft's SRWLOCK (which was previously believed to be the best of the
best) while consuming 18x fewer CPU resources. Cosmopolitan mutexes were
also 65x faster than Cygwin, which like Cosmopolitan provides a POSIX
implementation on Windows. Cygwin's mutexes are so bad that they would
have been better off for this use case just using a spin lock.

</p><p>
Now onto Linux, the lord of all operating systems.

</p><div>
<table>
<tbody><tr>
  <th colspan="4"><p>
      Linux Mutex Implementations<br>
      96-core Threadripper Pro 7995WX

</p></th></tr><tr>
  <th>wall<br>time (µs)
  </th><th>user<br>time (µs)
  </th><th>system<br>time (µs)
  </th><th>implementation

</th></tr><tr>
  <td>36,905
  </td><td>44,511
  </td><td>23,492
  </td><td>Cosmopolitan pthread_mutex_t

</td></tr><tr>
  <td>101,353
  </td><td>150,706
  </td><td>2,724,851
  </td><td>glibc pthread_mutex_t

</td></tr><tr>
  <td>202,423
  </td><td>4,694,749
  </td><td>2,000
  </td><td>spin lock

</td></tr><tr>
  <td>411,013
  </td><td>2,167,898
  </td><td>9,926,850
  </td><td>Musl libc pthread_mutex_t

</td></tr></tbody></table>
</div>

<p>
  Here we see Cosmopolitan mutexes are:

</p><ul>
<li>3x faster than glibc
</li><li>11x faster than glibc
</li><li>42x less CPU time than glibc
</li><li>178x less CPU time than Musl Libc
</li></ul>

<p>
Here's how things actually work in practice. Imagine you have a workload
where all your threads need to do a serialized operation. With Cosmo, if
you're looking at htop, then it's going to appear like only one core is
active, whereas glibc and musl libc will fill up your entire CPU meter.
That's bad news if you're running a lot of jobs on the same server. If
just one of your servers has a mutex bloodbath, then all your resources
are gone, unless you're using cosmo. It's still a new C library and it's
a little rough around the edges. But it's getting so good, so fast, that
I'm starting to view <em>not</em> using it in production as an
abandonment of professional responsibility. The C library is so deeply
embedded in the software supply chain, and so depended upon, that you
really don't want it to be a planet killer. If essential unquestioned
tools are this wasteful then it's no wonder Amazon Cloud makes such a
fortune.

</p><p>
Last but not least, we have MacOS.

</p><div>
<table>
<tbody><tr>
  <th colspan="4"><p>
      MacOS Mutex Implementations<br>
      M2 Ultra

</p></th></tr><tr>
  <th>wall<br>time (µs)
  </th><th>user<br>time (µs)
  </th><th>system<br>time (µs)
  </th><th>implementation

</th></tr><tr>
  <td>52,263
  </td><td>43,202
  </td><td>911,009
  </td><td>Apple Libc

</td></tr><tr>
  <td>54,700
  </td><td>63,055
  </td><td>1,003,674
  </td><td>Cosmopolitan pthread_mutex_t

</td></tr></tbody></table>
</div>

<p>
On MacOS with an M2 ARM64 microprocessor, Apple's Libc slightly
outperforms Cosmopolitan's mutexes. For reasons I do not yet fully
understand, Cosmopolitan's normal mutex implementation doesn't work well
on this platform. It's possibly because the M2 and XNU are in league. So
on MacOS ARM, Cosmopolitan uses a simpler algorithm based on Ulrich
Drepper's
"<a href="https://dept-info.labri.fr/~denis/Enseignement/2008-IR/Articles/01-futex.pdf">Futexes
Are Tricky</a>" paper that basically just farms out all the heavy
lifting to XNU's ulock system calls. That's why performance is nearly
identical to what Apple does.

</p><p>
So in summary, these benchmark results indicate that Cosmopolitan
mutexes, in the best case, will be overwhelmingly better than
alternatives at the contended + tiny critical section use case, and in
the worst case, Cosmopolitan will be roughly as good.

</p><h3>How I Did It</h3>

<p>
The reason why Cosmopolitan Mutexes are so good is because I used a
library called <a href="https://github.com/google/nsync">nsync</a>. It
only has 371 stars on GitHub, but it was written by a distinguished
engineer at Google named Mike Burrows. If you don't know who he is, he's
the guy who coded Google's fiercest competitor, which was Altavista. If
you're not old enough to remember Altavista, it was the first search
engine that was good, and it ran on a single computer.

</p><p>
I've had a lot of fun integrating nsync into Cosmopolitan. I've even
had the opportunity to make upstream contributions. For example, I found
and fixed a bug in his mutex unlock function that had gone undiscovered
for years. I also managed to make contended nsync mutexes go 30% faster
than nsync upstream on AARCH64, by porting it to use C11 atomics. I
wrote new system integration for things like futexes that enable it do
portability at runtime. Lastly I made it work seamlessly with POSIX
thread cancelations.

</p><p>
So how does nsync do it? What are the tricks that it uses? Here's some
of my takes and analysis:

</p><ul>

<li>
nsync uses an optimistic CAS (compare and swap) immediately, so that
locking happens quickly when there's no contention.

</li><li>
When a lock can't be acquired, nsync adds the calling thread to a
doubly linked list of waiters. Each waiter gets its own semaphore on a
separate independent cacheline. This serves an important purpose. Once a
thread enters the wait state, it's no longer touching the main lock. To
understand why that's important, read Ulrich Drepper's paper
"<a href="https://people.freebsd.org/~lstewart/articles/cpumemory.pdf">What
Every Programmer Should Know About Memory</a>". He goes into great depth
on the coherency protocols used by modern microprocessors, where cores
basically talk to each other under the hood about which cachelines
they're using. When multiple cores touch the same ones, that creates a
lot of communication overhead within the processor.

</li><li>
nsync enlists the help of the operating system by using futexes. This is
a great abstraction invented by Linux some years ago, that quickly found
its way into other OSes. On MacOS, futexes are called ulock. On Windows,
futexes are called <code>WaitOnAddress()</code>. The only OS Cosmo
supports that doesn't have futexes is NetBSD, which implements POSIX
semaphores in kernelspace, and each semaphore sadly requires creating a
new file descriptor. But the important thing about futexes and
semaphores is they allow the OS to put a thread to sleep. That's what
lets nsync avoid consuming CPU time when there's nothing to do.

</li><li>
nsync avoids starvation with this concept of a "long wait". If a waiter
gets woken 30 times and fails to acquire the lock internally every time,
then nsync adds a bit to the lock that prevents threads that haven't
waited yet from acquiring. This means that initial CAS at the beginning
will fail for everyone else until the queue has had some time to clear.

</li><li>
nsync makes the use case we benchmarked go fast (contended lock with a
small critical section) using this concept of a "designated waker". This
bit on the main lock is set when a thread is awake and trying to acquire
the lock. In nsync, the unlock function is what's responsible for waking
the next thread in line waiting for the lock. Having this bit allows the
unlocking thread to know it needn't bother waking a second locker since
one is already awake.

</li></ul>

<p>
To learn more of nsync's secrets, you can read the source code here:
<a href="https://github.com/jart/cosmopolitan/tree/master/third_party/nsync/mu.c"><code>cosmopolitan/third_party/nsync/mu.c</code></a>.
See also
<a href="https://github.com/jart/cosmopolitan/tree/master/libc/intrin/pthread_mutex_lock.c"><code>cosmopolitan/libc/intrin/pthread_mutex_lock.c</code></a>.

</p><h3>Online Proof</h3>

<p>
If you want to see a live demo of a piece of software built with Cosmo
mutexes, then do your worst DDOS to the
<a href="http://ipv4.games/">http://ipv4.games/</a> web server. Now this
is truly a game for hackers, competing to dominate the Internet. You're
already playing this game because your IP was just claimed for jart. The
service runs on a GCE VM with 2 cores and so far it's managed to survive
being DDOS'd by botnets as large as 49,131,669 IPs. A lot of that is
thanks to nsync which allowed me to move SQL queries to background
threads which send messages to each other. There are still improvements
to be made, but overall it's held up well. You can even monitor
its <a href="http://ipv4.games/statusz">/statusz</a> health metrics.

</p><h3>Source Code</h3>

<pre><span>#define ITERATIONS 100000
#define THREADS    30</span>

<span>int</span> g_chores;
<span>pthread_mutex_t</span> g_locker = PTHREAD_MUTEX_INITIALIZER;

<span>void</span> *<span>worker</span>(<span>void</span> *arg) {
  <span>for</span> (<span>int</span> i = 0; i &lt; ITERATIONS; ++i) {
    pthread_mutex_lock(&amp;g_locker);
    ++g_chores;
    pthread_mutex_unlock(&amp;g_locker);
  }
  <span>return</span> 0;
}

<span>struct</span> <span>timeval</span> <span>tub</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>timeval</span> a, <span>struct</span> <span>timeval</span> b) {
  a.tv_sec -= b.tv_sec;
  <span>if</span> (a.tv_usec &lt; b.tv_usec) {
    a.tv_usec += 1000000;
    a.tv_sec--;
  }
  a.tv_usec -= b.tv_usec;
  <span>return</span> a;
}

<span>long</span> <span>tomicros</span>(<span>struct</span> <span>timeval</span> x) {
  <span>return</span> x.tv_sec * 1000000ul + x.tv_usec;
}

<span>int</span> <span>main</span>() {
  <span>struct</span> <span>timeval</span> start;
  gettimeofday(&amp;start, 0);

  <span>pthread_t</span> th[THREADS];
  for (int i = 0; i &lt; THREADS; ++i)
    pthread_create(&amp;th[i], 0, worker, 0);
  for (int i = 0; i &lt; THREADS; ++i)
    pthread_join(th[i], 0);
  assert(g_chores == THREADS * ITERATIONS);

  <span>struct</span> <span>rusage</span> ru;
  <span>struct</span> <span>timeval</span> end;
  gettimeofday(&amp;end, 0);
  getrusage(RUSAGE_SELF, &amp;ru);
  printf(<span>"%16ld us real\n"</span>
         <span>"%16ld us user\n"</span>
         <span>"%16ld us sys\n"</span>,
         tomicros(tub(end, start)),
         tomicros(ru.ru_utime),
         tomicros(ru.ru_stime));
}

</pre>

<p>
The reason we care about the contended case, because that's where mutex
implementations show their inequality. Uncontended mutexes usually
perform the same across implementations, and even then you might be
better off with a spin lock, which only takes a few lines:

</p><pre><span>void</span> <span>spin_lock</span>(<span>atomic_int</span> *lock) {
  if (atomic_exchange_explicit(lock, 1, memory_order_acquire)) {
    <span>for</span> (;;) {
      <span>for</span> (;;)
        <span>if</span> (!atomic_load_explicit(lock, memory_order_relaxed))
          <span>break</span>;
      <span>if</span> (!atomic_exchange_explicit(lock, 1, memory_order_acquire))
        <span>break</span>;
    }
  }
}

<span>void</span> <span>spin_unlock</span>(<span>atomic_int</span> *lock) {
  atomic_store_explicit(lock, 0, memory_order_release);
}
</pre>

<p>
Please note that spin locks should really only be used when you have no
other choice. They're useful in kernels, where extreme low level
constraints disallow anything fancy. Spin locks are also a useful
implementation detail in nsync locks. But overall they're bad. I imagine
many developers believe they're good. If so, it's probably because
they've only benchmarked wall time. With locks, it's important to take
CPU time into consideration too. That's why we use
<code>getrusage()</code>.

</p><h2 class="page" id="funding"><a href="#funding">Funding</a></h2>

<p>
  <a href="https://justine.lol/lemuria.png">
    <picture>
      <source srcset="https://worker.jart.workers.dev/sectorlisp2/lemuria.webp" type="image/webp">
      <img src="https://worker.jart.workers.dev/sectorlisp2/lemuria.png" width="850" height="360" alt="[United States of Lemuria - two dollar bill - all debts public and primate]">
    </picture>
  </a>

</p><p>
Funding for The Fastest Mutex was crowdsourced from Justine
Tunney's <a href="https://github.com/sponsors/jart">GitHub sponsors</a>
and <a href="https://www.patreon.com/jart">Patreon subscribers</a>, the
backing of
<a href="https://future.mozilla.org/mieco/">Mozilla's MIECO program</a>,
and the generous contributions of our
<a href="https://discord.gg/FwAVVu7eJ4">developer community</a> on
Discord. Your support is what makes projects like Cosmopolitan possible.
Thank you!

</p>
<img src="https://ipv4.games/claim?name=jart">
</div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>