<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 09:30:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Calendar (302 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://neatnik.net/calendar/?year=2026</link>
            <guid>46408613</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 05:02:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://neatnik.net/calendar/?year=2026">https://neatnik.net/calendar/?year=2026</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46408613">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="info">
<p>👋 <strong>Hello!</strong> If you print this page, you’ll get a nifty calendar that displays all of the year’s dates on a single page. It will automatically fit on a single sheet of paper of any size. For best results, adjust your print settings to landscape orientation and disable the header and footer.</p>
<p>Take in the year all at once. Fold it up and carry it with you. Jot down your notes on it. Plan things out and observe the passage of time. Above all else, be kind to others.</p>
<p>Looking for 2026? <a href="https://neatnik.net/calendar/?year=2026">Here you go!</a></p>
<p>Made by <a href="https://neatnik.net/">Neatnik</a> · <a href="https://source.tube/neatnik/calendar">Source</a></p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Fathers’ choices may be packaged and passed down in sperm RNA (173 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.quantamagazine.org/how-dads-fitness-may-be-packaged-and-passed-down-in-sperm-rna-20251222/</link>
            <guid>46407502</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 01:33:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/how-dads-fitness-may-be-packaged-and-passed-down-in-sperm-rna-20251222/">https://www.quantamagazine.org/how-dads-fitness-may-be-packaged-and-passed-down-in-sperm-rna-20251222/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46407502">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <p>
            Research into how a father’s choices — such as diet, exercise, stress, nicotine use — may transfer traits to his children has become impossible to ignore.        </p>
        
    </div><div>
            <h2>Introduction</h2>
            <div data-role="selectable">
    <p>The standard sperm-meets-egg story posits that sperm cells are hardly more than bundles of shrink-wrapped DNA with tails. Their mission is simple: Deliver a father’s genes into a mother’s egg for sexual reproduction. Just about all other aspects of a developing embryo, including its cellular and environmental components, have nothing to do with dad. Those all come from mom.</p>
<p>But nearly two decades of studies from multiple independent labs threaten to rewrite that story. They suggest that dad’s gametes shuttle more than DNA: Within a sperm’s minuscule head are stowaway molecules, which enter the egg and convey information about the father’s fitness, such as diet, exercise habits and stress levels, to his offspring. These non-DNA transfers may influence genomic activity that boots up during and after fertilization, exerting some control over the embryo’s development and influencing the adult they will become.</p>
<p>The findings, so far largely described in mouse models, could end up changing the way we think about heredity. They suggest “that what we do in this life affects the next generation,” said <a href="http://qichen-lab.info/">Qi Chen</a>, a reproductive and developmental biologist at the University of Utah Medical School who is among the pioneers of this research. In other words: What a father eats, drinks, inhales, is stressed by or otherwise experiences in the weeks and months before he conceives a child might be encoded in molecules, packaged into his sperm cells and transmitted to his future kid. The researchers have largely zeroed in on RNA molecules, those short-lived copies of DNA that reflect genetic activity at a given time.</p>
<p>It’s a tantalizing notion. But the mechanistic details — how experience is encoded, how it’s transferred from sperm to egg, and whether and how it affects a developing embryo — are not easy to unpack, especially given the challenges of conducting research in human subjects. For this reason, and because of the potentially textbook-rewriting implications of the findings, researchers, including those spearheading the work, are cautious about overselling their results.</p>

<p>“It’s still very hand-wavy,” said the epigeneticist <a href="https://www.coninelab.com/">Colin Conine</a> of the University of Pennsylvania Perelman School of Medicine and Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia, who has been trying to uncover the mechanics of how sperm RNA can contribute nongenetic information to progeny. Some elements of the story are clear, he said: Researchers have significant evidence that the environment can regulate sperm RNAs, that these molecules transmit traits to offspring and that they can regulate embryonic development after fertilization. “We just don’t have really any understanding of how RNAs can do this, and that’s the hand-wavy part,” Conine said.</p>
<p>But evidence keeps piling up. Most recently, in November 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2025.09.003">a comprehensive paper</a> published in <em>Cell Metabolism</em> traced the downstream molecular effects of a father mouse’s exercise regimen on sperm microRNAs that target genes “critical for mitochondrial function and metabolic control” in a developing embryo. The researchers found many of those same RNAs overexpressed in the sperm of well-exercised human men.</p>
<p>“This study shows that paternal exercise can confer benefits — enhanced endurance and metabolic health — to offspring,” said Chen, who was not involved in the study. “It’s a powerful reminder that many sperm-mediated epigenetic effects are deeply adaptive in nature.”</p>
<p>The possibility that a previously undocumented avenue of inheritance is at play is too important to ignore. That’s why the researchers are now hunkering down in their labs to trace out the molecular processes that would have to operate for a father’s here-and-now experience to be transferred as developmental instructions to his partner’s egg.</p>
<h2><strong>Epigenetic Avenues</strong></h2>
<p>In most animals, a sperm cell is tiny compared to an egg cell. In humans, an egg contains 10 million times the volume of a sperm and contributes most cellular components — nutrition, cytoplasm, mitochondria and other organelles, the molecular machinery to make proteins, and more — to a zygote (a newly fertilized egg that hasn’t started dividing). Plus, a mother provides the environment within which an embryo and then fetus develops and grows. As a result, the effect of a mother’s health on her children has <a href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.f4539">long been scrutinized</a>, including <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41420-019-0153-y">at the molecular level</a>. But over the past 15 years or so, the evidence for some kind of non-DNA inheritance of paternal experience has also been strengthening.</p>
<p>“There are many different labs that have done diet and stress studies, and typically the readouts of those in the next generation are either metabolism or behavioral changes,” Conine said. Feed a male mouse a <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-024-07472-3">high-fat</a> or <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2020.02.028">low-protein</a> diet, or <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nn.3695">take him away from his mom</a> when he is young, and his offspring will inherit traits, such as changes in mitochondrial function, related to those environmental conditions. These traits aren’t necessarily detrimental. For instance, mouse fathers &nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.24771">exposed to nicotine</a> sire male pups with livers that are good at disarming not just nicotine but cocaine and other toxins as well.</p>
<p>There is a survival logic here, said <a href="https://www.umassmed.edu/randolab/">Oliver Rando</a>, an epigeneticist at the University of Massachusetts Chan Medical School who led the nicotine study. It’s reasonable to expect that offspring will experience an environmental context similar to that of their parents. Biologically priming them for those conditions could therefore help them survive.</p>
</div>
    </div><div data-role="selectable">
    <p>“You might think of this as a way to tell your kids something useful for them so that they can be better at dealing with the world they inherit,” said Rando, a father of two boys.</p>
<p>But logic does not make the story true. That’s why Chen, Rando, Conine and other researchers have been working to uncover the mechanistic components of dad-based epigenetic heredity to add to what is already known about these processes in mothers. “Epigenetics” refers to heredity processes that do not change the DNA sequences of genes, but rather involve when and to what degree genes are expressed and made into functional proteins. Epigeneticists focus on the molecular biology that unfolds around genomic and chromosomal frameworks that can switch genes on and off in response to internal and external cues.</p>

<p>This kind of differential gene expression is central to some of biology’s greatest wonders — for example, the fact that all cells in the human body have the same DNA, and yet brain cells differ dramatically from liver, skin and blood cells. Some cues that trigger changes in gene expression are programmed into DNA, while others come from the environment — for example, a dearth of <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/how-metabolism-can-shape-cells-destinies-20250321/">calories or nutrients</a> due to food deprivation, or rising cortisol levels due to stressors such as the absence of parental care. These conditions affect the kinds of metabolites and other molecules circulating in our bodies, which influences what kinds of reactions and genomic processes cells can carry out.</p>
<p>Some molecules involved in epigenetic processes, such as methyl or acetyl groups, interface directly with DNA or bind to proteins attached to DNA. These actions loosen up or batten down portions of the genome and are akin to opening or closing doors to specific genes.</p>
<p>RNA molecules — flexible, ephemeral versions of DNA sequences — can also intervene in gene expression. But because they are relatively short-lived, sometimes surviving mere minutes or hours before degrading, they have been overlooked as epigenetic regulators. Since the 1990s, their roles have been clarified, as has their longevity: Certain RNAs can survive for weeks or longer. Some RNAs (such as long noncoding RNAs, or lncRNAs) regulate gene expression by modifying DNA or its proteins. Others, known as microRNAs, alter or repress other RNAs, including those that would otherwise be translated into proteins; this discovery was awarded the <a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/medicine/2024/press-release/">2024 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine</a>.</p>
</div><div data-role="selectable">
    <p>Could sperm carry RNA or other molecules that then participate in epigenetic processes in the embryo? It seemed plausible to some researchers, but it would take a whole lot of experimental work to put the pieces together.</p>
<h2><strong>A Package of RNA</strong></h2>
<p>There are three core questions that biologists need to resolve to confirm that sperm cells transmit epigenetic inheritance. The first is how a father’s body physically encodes lived experience, such as stress, diet, exercise or nicotine use, in the form of molecules — for example, as RNAs <a href="https://doi.org/10.1155/2017/7404912">circulating in blood</a> that reflect gene expression in tissues. The next centers on how molecularly encoded experience could make its way into sperm cells. The third traces how those signals in sperm could become epigenetic vectors during and after fertilization to specify observable traits, known as phenotypes, in offspring.</p>
<p>In a series of studies beginning in 2012, Qi Chen started answering all three questions. In what he describes as one of the most serendipitous discoveries of his career, his team at the Chinese Academy of Sciences in Beijing used sequencing techniques to inventory the short RNA molecules present in mice sperm cells.</p>

<p>They were shocked to see a subset of the RNAs drastically increasing in concentration <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/cr.2012.141">as sperm cells matured</a>, and then crowding into the sperm heads with DNA. This same class of RNAs was abundant <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/jmcb/mjt052">in the blood serum</a> of various vertebrates, ranging from fish to humans, they found. All of this pointed to the possibility that information-carrying molecules were being transferred into the reproductive cells.</p>
<p>It got even more interesting when Chen, who moved to the U.S. academic circuit in 2015, and his team collected sperm RNAs from male mice fed different diets. The RNA assemblages in mice reared on high-fat foods differed dramatically from those in mice that were fed normal diets. And when the researchers injected the RNAs from the sperm of the fat-eating mice into a zygote, some of the male offspring <a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aad7977">showed metabolic issues</a> associated with a high-fat diet.</p>
<p>The experiments hinted at a seemingly heretical possibility, Chen said: that “certain acquired traits during paternal exposure can be ‘memorized’ in the sperm and inherited by the offspring.” After <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41556-018-0087-2">characterizing a pathway</a> that regulates sperm RNAs, in 2019 Chen dubbed this channel of heredity the “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41574-019-0226-2">sperm RNA code</a>,” which he suggested “programs the metabolic health of offspring.”</p>
<p>He wasn’t the only one to become fixated on this idea. Around the same time, in an article published in <em>Developmental Cell</em> in 2018, Rando’s team reported the use of biochemical techniques to characterize where and when <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.devcel.2018.06.023">RNAs are packaged into sperm cells</a> and how those RNAs might change during this process. They were trying to answer the question: “What tissue could be responsible for choosing what to tell sperm to tell kids?” he said. One logical place to start looking was the epididymis. Within this tubular organ attached to the back of the testicle, sperm cells undergo a maturation process, taking about one to two weeks in most mammalian species, before they become ready for fertilization.</p>
</div><div data-role="selectable">
    <p>Rando’s data showed that sperm cells gain almost all their small RNAs when they are in the epididymis. Using techniques for tracking specific RNA molecules, the scientists observed RNAs getting packaged into virus-size capsules, called epididymosomes, which shuttled the molecules into sperm.</p>
<p>“This shows how small RNAs can get trafficked between the body’s nonreproductive cells, like those in the epididymis, and germline cells,” such as sperm, Rando said. “The epididymis has been emerging as a key location for paternal effects. Certainly the epididymis has to be taken seriously as a potential sensor of the world.”</p>
<h2><strong>A Molecular Snapshot</strong></h2>
<p>By “sensor of the world,” Rando is referring to the first stage of a presumed paternal-effects mechanism — when a male’s body translates a lived condition, such as a high-fat diet, rigorous exercise or toxin exposure, into molecular signals. The epididymis then provides a route for the second step, packaging those signals for the next generation.</p>
<p>This is also where investigations by <a href="https://www.mansuylab.ch/">Isabelle Mansuy</a> come in. At the University of Zurich and the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology Zurich, she studies the molecular and cellular mechanisms of epigenetic inheritance in mammals.</p>
</div><div data-role="selectable">
    <p>In one line of her research, she focuses on processes that transmit the molecular effects of traumatic stress to subsequent generations by focusing on extracellular vesicles (EVs) that circulate in blood. Shed by almost every type of cell in the body, including in the epididymis (the epididymosomes are EVs), they carry a diversity of molecular cargo, such as RNAs, proteins, lipids and metabolites. Because EVs circulate in blood just about anywhere in the body and can cross cell membranes, they provide a potential means to transfer molecules and the biological cues they carry between bodily tissues and reproductive cells. Notably, RNAs tend to survive longer when packaged in EVs.</p>
<p>Mansuy creates trauma in mice by subjecting the animals to conditions such as restraint or maternal separation when they are young. Then she searches for molecular changes in reproductive cells that could cause similar consequences of trauma to manifest in the children or even grandchildren of the animals who directly endure it.</p>
<p>She’s shown that traumatic stress <a href="https://doi.org/10.15252/embj.2020104579">alters metabolic pathways</a>, especially those that involve lipids, in exposed male mice and their offspring. She has also found a similar metabolic profile in humans who experienced high stress in childhood. In mice, some of the metabolic changes remained discernible <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/eep/dvac024">through five generations</a> — a rare data-backed finding for epigenetic inheritance cascading through generations.</p>
</div><div data-role="selectable">
    <p>In March 2025, in <a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2025.03.21.644551">a preprint uploaded to biorxiv.org</a>, Mansuy and colleagues reported that EVs in mice can transport certain RNAs, metabolites and lipids linked to early-life stress from circulating blood to sperm, with consequences for offspring. The offspring produced by these sperm cells had stress-related metabolic dysfunction as adults and bore the stress signatures in their own sperm RNA. “These changes imply a mechanistic link between sperm RNA modifications and phenotypic features in the offspring,” Mansuy’s team concluded in their paper, which has not yet been peer-reviewed.</p>
<h2><strong>Phenotypic Translation</strong></h2>
<p>Perhaps the trickiest step to understand is how sperm-borne molecules could influence an adult’s observable traits. In one form of experiment, researchers extract all the sperm RNA from mice that have been raised under stressful or health-altering conditions. Those isolated RNAs are then injected into a zygote. Pups that emerge usually “get the dad’s phenotypes,” Conine said, suggesting that the RNAs alone confer traits from dad to offspring.</p>
<p>But how? During early development, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.stem.2023.09.010">epigenetic processes reign</a>. As one fertilized cell divides into two, and those cells divide again, and so on, one set of DNA instructions is dynamically and repeatedly reprogrammed. The growing body specializes into different cell types and is sculpted into a sequence of increasingly complex forms. It’s possible, then, that early epigenetic alterations to the genome could have significant downstream effects on an adult.</p>

<p>Research out of Conine’s lab, published in 2024, showed that sperm microRNAs <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2024.114698">alter gene expression</a> in mouse embryos. Experiments like these, he said, support the idea that offspring can inherit paternal traits via the transfer of non-DNA molecular stowaways in sperm.</p>
<p>The recent <em>Cell Metabolism</em> paper took this idea a step further by <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2025.09.003">tracing a mechanism</a> by which this can happen. A team of more than two dozen Chinese researchers focused on the epigenetic transmission of exercise benefits, homing in on a set of microRNAs that reprogram gene expression in the early embryo. These changes ultimately result in skeletal muscle adaptations in adult offspring that enhance exercise endurance. The researchers found that well-exercised mice had more of these microRNAs in their sperm than sedentary mice did. When these microRNAs were transferred into zygotes, the adults they grew into were more physically fit, with more mitochondria in skeletal muscle and higher endurance.</p>
<p>But how did the molecules generate the exercise-positive phenotype? In experiments, the researchers found that the microRNAs suppressed a particular protein, which had the effect of boosting genes related to mitochondrial activity and metabolism.</p>
<p>Intriguingly, the sperm of physically trained male humans also hosted higher levels of many of the same microRNAs than those of untrained cohorts. “This cross-species conservation suggests a potential role for these sperm mi[cro]RNAs in intergenerational exercise adaptations in humans,” the researchers wrote.</p>
<h2><strong>The First Draft </strong></h2>
<p>The notion that a father’s lived experience can become recorded by his body, transmitted to his gametes and relayed to his offspring is no longer as outlandish as it once seemed. Many researchers in the field are willing to float speculative visions of what could be going on, even as they acknowledge that gaps remain.</p>
<p>“Our hypothesis is that the epididymis ‘sees’ the world and alters the small RNAs it produces in response,” Rando said. “These RNAs are then delivered to the zygote upon fertilization and control early gene regulation and development to shape offspring health and disease.”</p>
<p>Conine speculates that once certain RNAs make their way into the egg, they trigger “a cascade of changes in developmental gene expression that then leads to these phenotypes” of the father showing up in the next generation. Remarkably, this unfolds even though the sheer volume of the sperm’s contents is so much less than an egg’s contents, including the relative amounts of RNA.</p>
<p>The full picture of how paternal experience and behavior might epigenetically influence offspring is not nearly in hand. Researchers are currently piecing the story together, one experiment at a time, rather than proving out every step sequentially in the same set of organisms. One of the gaps is in the characterization of what RNA and perhaps other epigenetic factors do in the zygote to modify genomic activity as it unfolds during development, Mansuy said.</p>
<p>“We are still blind men describing for the first time different parts of the same elephant,” Chen said. “The underlying mechanism is almost certainly an orchestra of a sperm RNA code and factors beyond that.”</p>
        
        
<p>Confirming the findings in humans would take enormous effort, but it would be key to turning these findings in mice into “informed medical advice,” Chen said. This would require well-controlled experiments following multiple generations, tracking diet, exercise, aging and environmental exposures, while also <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41556-021-00652-7">using advanced tools</a> to decode sperm-packaged molecules — and then looking for strong correlations between the molecular and phenotypic data.</p>
<p>Even amid the uncertainties, researchers are cautiously moving forward as they learn to believe the results of their own experiments. If they’re right, they will have discovered a new fact of life, Rando said. When he thinks about his two boys, he wonders what he might have done differently when he was younger, before they were born, that might have tweaked his RNA profile in ways that would affect them today.</p>
<p>“We don’t know enough yet to develop guidance like that,” Rando said. “Maybe we will get there.”</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Replacing JavaScript with Just HTML (344 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.htmhell.dev/adventcalendar/2025/27/</link>
            <guid>46407337</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 01:07:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.htmhell.dev/adventcalendar/2025/27/">https://www.htmhell.dev/adventcalendar/2025/27/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46407337">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><main id="content"><div><p>by <a href="https://aarontgrogg.com/">Aaron T. Grogg</a> published on <time datetime="2025-12-27">Dec 27, 2025</time></p><p>For many years now, JavaScript has been the workhorse of the web. If you wanted to do something that couldn't be done with just HTML and CSS, you could usually find a way to do it with JS.<br>And that is great! JS has helped push user experiences forward, and honestly helped push HTML and CSS forward!</p><p>But as time marches on, and the HTML and CSS methods <a href="https://webstatus.dev/?q=%28group%3Ahtml+OR+css%29&amp;sort=name_asc">gain traction</a>, we need to start replacing the old JS methods that feel so comfy with new methods that require less JS.</p><p><em><strong>Nothing against JS</strong></em>, but it has better things to do than setup and manage your accordions or offscreen navigation menus... Plus, JS needs to be downloaded, decompressed, evaluated, processed, and then often consumes memory to monitor and maintain features. If we can <em>hand-off</em> any JS functionality to native HTML or CSS, then users can download less stuff, and the remaining JS can pay attention to more important tasks that HTML and CSS can't handle (yet).</p><p>Below are a few examples; any you care to add?</p><h2 id="table-of-contents">Table of Contents:</h2><ul><li><a href="#accordions-expanding-content-panels">Accordions / Expanding Content Panels</a></li><li><a href="#input-with-autofilter-suggestions-dropdown">Input with Autofilter Suggestions Dropdown</a></li><li><a href="#modals-popovers">Modals / Popovers</a></li><li><a href="#offscreen-nav-content">Offscreen Nav / Content</a></li></ul><h2 id="accordions-/-expanding-content-panels">Accordions / Expanding Content Panels</h2><h3 id="description">Description:</h3><p>The <code>details</code> and <code>summary</code> HTML elements provide an HTML-only replacement to the typical JS accordion:<br><img src="https://www.htmhell.dev/adventcalendar/2025/27/accordion-expanding-content.gif" alt="Examples of HTML  element expanding and contracting"><br>CopePen: <a href="https://codepen.io/aarontgrogg/pen/GgoOqVX">Accordion / Expanding Content</a></p><h3 id="use-cases">Use cases:</h3><ul><li>Hiding/showing content</li><li>Expanding content sections</li></ul><h3 id="basic-implementation">Basic implementation:</h3><pre><code><span><span><span><span>&lt;</span>details</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>summary</span><span>&gt;</span></span>Initially closed, click to open<span><span><span>&lt;/</span>summary</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  Content is initially hidden, but can be revealed by clicking the summary.</span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>details</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span></code></pre><p>Add an <code>open</code> attribute to set the default appearance as "open":</p><pre><code><span><span><span><span>&lt;</span>details</span> <span>open</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>summary</span><span>&gt;</span></span>Initially open, click to close<span><span><span>&lt;/</span>summary</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  Content is initially visible, but can be hidden by clicking the summary.</span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>details</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span></code></pre><p>Use the same <code>name</code> attribute on all related <code>details</code> (like radio buttons) to restrict only one open panel at a time:</p><pre><code><span><span><span><span>&lt;</span>details</span> <span>name</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>foo<span>"</span></span> <span>open</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>summary</span><span>&gt;</span></span>Initially open, clicking others will close this<span><span><span>&lt;/</span>summary</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  Content is initially visible, but can be hidden by clicking the summary; only one panel can be open at a time.</span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>details</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;</span>details</span> <span>name</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>foo<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>summary</span><span>&gt;</span></span>Initially closed, clicking will open this, and close others<span><span><span>&lt;/</span>summary</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  Content is initially hidden, but can be revealed by clicking the summary; only one panel can be open at a time.</span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>details</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;</span>details</span> <span>name</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>foo<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>summary</span><span>&gt;</span></span>Initially closed, clicking will open this, and close others<span><span><span>&lt;/</span>summary</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  Content is initially hidden, but can be revealed by clicking the summary; only one panel can be open at a time.</span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>details</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span></code></pre><p>You can also customize the appearance with CSS and trigger the open/close via JS.</p><p>Learn more about the <code>details</code> element in the previously-published “<a href="https://www.htmhell.dev/adventcalendar/2025/23">For the Love of &lt;details&gt;</a>".</p><h3 id="resources">Resources:</h3><ul><li><a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Element/details">MDN <code>details</code> page</a></li><li><a href="https://www.codewithshripal.com/playground/html/details-element">&lt;details&gt; element</a></li></ul><h3 id="browser-compatibility">Browser compatibility:</h3><ul><li><a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Element/details#browser_compatibility">MDN <code>details</code> Browser Compatibility</a></li></ul><h2 id="input-with-autofilter-suggestions-dropdown">Input with Autofilter Suggestions Dropdown</h2><h3 id="description-2">Description:</h3><p>Combining the HTML <code>input</code> and <code>datalist</code> elements can create a dropdown of options that autofilters as you type:<br><img src="https://www.htmhell.dev/adventcalendar/2025/27/input-with-datalist.gif" alt="Examples of HTML  and  providing autofilter dropdown"><br>CodePen: <a href="https://codepen.io/aarontgrogg/pen/yyePPor">Input with Autofilter Suggestions Dropdown</a></p><h3 id="use-cases-2">Use cases:</h3><ul><li>Site search</li><li>Product search or filter</li><li>Filter any list of data</li></ul><h3 id="basic-implementation-2">Basic implementation:</h3><pre><code><span><span><span><span>&lt;</span>label</span> <span>for</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>browser<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span>Browser<span><span><span>&lt;/</span>label</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span><span><span>&lt;</span>input</span> <span>type</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>text<span>"</span></span><br><span>       <span>list</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>browsers<span>"</span></span></span><br><span>       <span>id</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>browser<span>"</span></span> <span>name</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>browser<span>"</span></span></span><br><span>       <span>size</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>50<span>"</span></span></span><br>       <span>autocomplete</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>off<span>"</span></span> <span>/&gt;</span></span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;</span>datalist</span> <span>id</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>browsers<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>option</span> <span>value</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>Arc<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>option</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>option</span> <span>value</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>Brave<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>option</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>option</span> <span>value</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>Chrome<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>option</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>option</span> <span>value</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>DuckDuckGo<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>option</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>option</span> <span>value</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>Firefox<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>option</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>option</span> <span>value</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>Microsoft Edge<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>option</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>option</span> <span>value</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>Opera<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>option</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>option</span> <span>value</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>Safari<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>option</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>option</span> <span>value</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>Tor<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>option</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>option</span> <span>value</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>Vivaldi<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>option</span><span>&gt;</span></span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>option</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>datalist</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span></code></pre><p>You can also use other input types:</p><pre><code><span><span><span><span>&lt;</span>label</span> <span>for</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>quantity<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span>Quantity<span><span><span>&lt;/</span>label</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span><span><span>&lt;</span>input</span> <span>type</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>number<span>"</span></span> <br><span>       <span>list</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>quantity-options<span>"</span></span></span><br>       <span>id</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>quantity<span>"</span></span> <span>name</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>quantity<span>"</span></span> <span>/&gt;</span></span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;</span>datalist</span> <span>id</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>quantity-options<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>option</span> <span>value</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>1<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>option</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>option</span> <span>value</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>2<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>option</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>option</span> <span>value</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>5<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>option</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>option</span> <span>value</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>10<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>option</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>option</span> <span>value</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>20<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>option</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>option</span> <span>value</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>50<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>option</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>datalist</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span></span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;</span>label</span> <span>for</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>appointment<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span>Appointment<span><span><span>&lt;/</span>label</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span><span><span>&lt;</span>input</span> <span>type</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>time<span>"</span></span> <br><span>       <span>list</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>appointments<span>"</span></span></span><br>       <span>id</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>appointment<span>"</span></span> <span>name</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>appointment<span>"</span></span> <span>/&gt;</span></span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;</span>datalist</span> <span>id</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>appointments<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>option</span> <span>value</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>12:00<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>option</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>option</span> <span>value</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>13:00<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>option</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>  <span><span><span>&lt;</span>option</span> <span>value</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>14:00<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>option</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>datalist</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span></code></pre><p>Note that, at the time of this writing, Firefox was limited to only textual-based input types, so no <code>date</code>, <code>time</code>, <code>range</code> or <code>color</code> for now... :-(</p><p>Also note that, at the time of this writing, <a href="https://htmhell.dev/adventcalendar/2025/5/#the-list-attribute-on-lessinputgreater-elements">there are limitations on mobile, and accessibility concerns</a>.</p><h3 id="resources-2">Resources:</h3><ul><li><a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Element/datalist">MDN <code>datalist</code> page</a></li><li><a href="https://www.sitepoint.com/html5-datalist-autocomplete/">HTML5 datalist autocomplete</a></li></ul><h3 id="browser-compatibility-2">Browser compatibility:</h3><ul><li><a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Element/datalist#browser_compatibility">MDN <code>datalist</code> Browser Compatibility</a></li></ul><h2 id="modals-/-popovers">Modals / Popovers</h2><h3 id="description-3">Description:</h3><p>The <code>popover</code> and <code>popovertarget</code> attributes can replace the traditional JS-driven modal/popover/overlay:<br><img src="https://www.htmhell.dev/adventcalendar/2025/27/modal-popover.gif" alt="Examples of HTML  elements opening and closing"><br>CodePen: <a href="https://codepen.io/aarontgrogg/pen/QwyOKNW">Modal / Popover</a></p><h3 id="use-cases-3">Use cases:</h3><ul><li>Hiding/showing side panels / additional information</li></ul><h3 id="basic-implementation-3">Basic implementation</h3><p>An <code>auto</code> popover (default) can be "light dismissed" (clicking outside of it or hitting the <code>esc</code> key). Opening an <code>auto</code> automatically closes any other <code>auto</code> popovers that were open. Clicking the <code>button</code> a second time will close the one it opened.</p><pre><code><span><span><span><span>&lt;</span>button</span> <span>popovertarget</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>pop-auto<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>   Toggle Popover</span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>button</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;</span>dialog</span> <span>popover</span> <span>id</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>pop-auto<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>   I'm an "auto" Popover!</span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>dialog</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span></code></pre><p>A <code>hint</code> popover can also be "light dismissed". It does <em>not</em> close other <code>hint</code> popovers when opened. Clicking the <code>button</code> a second time will close the one it opened.</p><pre><code><span><span><span><span>&lt;</span>button</span> <span>popovertarget</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>pop-hint<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>   Toggle Popover</span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>button</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;</span>dialog</span> <span>popover</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>hint<span>"</span></span> <span>id</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>pop-hint<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>   I'm a "hint" Popover!</span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>dialog</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span></code></pre><p>Note that, at the time of this writing, Firefox and all iOS varieties do not support <code>hint</code> popovers.</p><p>A <code>manual</code> popover can <em>not</em> be "light dismissed". It does <em>not</em> close other <code>manual</code> popovers when opened. Clicking the <code>button</code> a second time will close the one it opened.</p><pre><code><span><span><span><span>&lt;</span>button</span> <span>popovertarget</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>pop-manual<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>   Toggle Popover</span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>button</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;</span>dialog</span> <span>popover</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>manual<span>"</span></span> <span>id</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>pop-manual<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>   I'm a "manual" Popover!</span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>dialog</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span></code></pre><p>Learn more about the opening and closing dialogs and popovers in the previously-published “<a href="https://www.htmhell.dev/adventcalendar/2025/7">Controlling dialogs and popovers with the Invoker Commands API</a>".</p><h3 id="resources-3">Resources:</h3><ul><li><a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Global_attributes/popover">MDN <code>popover</code> page</a></li><li><a href="https://mdn.github.io/dom-examples/popover-api/">Popover API examples</a></li><li><a href="https://developer.chrome.com/blog/introducing-popover-api/">Introducing the popover API</a></li><li><a href="https://codepen.io/jh3y/pen/XWPBmmo">Popover API!</a></li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KX8YQW7stzs">HTMHell #5 - An introduction to the popover attribute</a></li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RVxl5nZY790">The accessibility of the popover attribute</a></li></ul><h3 id="browser-compatibility-3">Browser compatibility:</h3><ul><li><a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Reference/Global_attributes/popover#browser_compatibility">MDN <code>popover</code> Browser Compatibility</a></li></ul><h2 id="offscreen-nav-/-content">Offscreen Nav / Content</h2><h3 id="description-4">Description:</h3><p>The above Modal / Popover functionality can also be used to create an offscreen navigation that requires no JS:<br><img src="https://www.htmhell.dev/adventcalendar/2025/27/offscreen-nav.gif" alt="Example of HTML Popover used as an offscreen navigation menu"></p><p>CodePen: <a href="https://codepen.io/aarontgrogg/pen/wBMPMVG">Offscreen Content</a></p><h3 id="use-cases-4">Use cases:</h3><ul><li>Hiding/showing navigation menus</li></ul><h3 id="basic-implementation-4">Basic implementation:</h3><pre><code><span><span><span><span>&lt;</span>button</span> <span>popovertarget</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>menu<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>   Toggle Menu</span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>button</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;</span>nav</span> <span>popover</span> <span>id</span><span><span>=</span><span>"</span>menu<span>"</span></span><span>&gt;</span></span></span><br><span>   Nav Content</span><br><span><span><span><span>&lt;/</span>nav</span><span>&gt;</span></span></span></code></pre><pre><code><span><span>#menu</span> <span>{</span></span><br><span>  <span>margin</span><span>:</span> 0<span>;</span></span><br><span>  <span>height</span><span>:</span> 100vh<span>;</span></span><br><span>  <span>translate</span><span>:</span> -100vw<span>;</span></span><br><span><span>}</span></span><br><span><span>#menu:popover-open</span> <span>{</span></span><br><span>  <span>translate</span><span>:</span> 0<span>;</span></span><br><span><span>}</span></span></code></pre><p>I use a <code>nav</code> element to give it semantic value, but you can use any HTML element (<code>div</code>, <code>section</code>, <code>aside</code>, etc.).</p><p>A <code>popover</code> defaults to <code>position: fixed</code> per the User Agent Stylesheet, and is simply pushed off screen when closed, and pulled back onscreen when it is open. Note that <code>margin: 0</code> is required if you want to override the User Agent center-alignment.</p><p>Clicking outside of the above menu closes it. You can force the panel to stay open, requiring a manual/explicit close, by using <code>popover="manual"</code>.</p><p>You can also add a <code>backdrop</code> pseudo element and style it as you wish:</p><pre><code><span><span>#menu::backdrop</span> <span>{</span></span><br><span>  <span>background</span><span>:</span> <span>rgb</span><span>(</span>190 190 190 / 75%<span>)</span><span>;</span></span><br><span><span>}</span></span></code></pre><h3 id="resources-4">Resources:</h3><ul><li><a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Global_attributes/popover">MDN <code>popover</code> page</a></li><li><a href="https://mdn.github.io/dom-examples/popover-api/">MDN Popover API examples</a></li><li><a href="https://developer.chrome.com/blog/introducing-popover-api/">Introducing the popover API</a></li><li><a href="https://codepen.io/jh3y/pen/XWPBmmo">Popover API!</a></li></ul><h3 id="browser-compatibility-4">Browser compatibility:</h3><ul><li><a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Reference/Global_attributes/popover#browser_compatibility">MDN <code>popover</code> Browser Compatibility</a></li></ul><h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2><p>While we all love the power and flexibility JS provides, we should also respect it, and our users, by limiting its use to what it <em>needs</em> to do.</p><p>There is <strong>so</strong> much more that has changed in recent years, including a ton of options that CSS now covers. If you are now hungry for more, have a look at [my longer article that covers those as well](<a href="https://aarontgrogg.com/blog/2023/05/31/replace-js-with-no-js-or-lo-js-options/">https://aarontgrogg.com/blog/2023/05/31/replace-js-with-no-js-or-lo-js-options/</a>.</p><p>Happy reducing!<br>Atg</p><h2 id="about-aaron-t-grogg">About Aaron T. Grogg</h2><p>Web Developer / Performance Optimization Specialist</p><p>Blog: <a href="https://aarontgrogg.com/">aarontgrogg.com</a><br>BlueSky: <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/aarontgrogg.bsky.social">aarontgrogg.bsky.social</a><br>Mastodon: <a href="https://mastodon.social/@aarontgrogg">mastodon.social/@aarontgrogg</a><br>LinkedIn: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/aarontgrogg/">linkedin.com/in/aarontgrogg</a></p></div></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Say No to Palantir in the NHS (264 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://notopalantir.goodlawproject.org/email-to-target/stop-palantir-in-the-nhs/</link>
            <guid>46405309</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 21:15:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://notopalantir.goodlawproject.org/email-to-target/stop-palantir-in-the-nhs/">https://notopalantir.goodlawproject.org/email-to-target/stop-palantir-in-the-nhs/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46405309">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div class="page" id="main">
          
<div>
    <p>NHS England is rolling out software to run our health records from Palantir – a US spy-tech firm that has supported mass deportation in the US and enabled genocide in Gaza.</p>
<p>One of Palantir’s founders is also openly against the NHS. Peter Thiel claimed it “makes people sick” and said that the British people love the NHS because we’re suffering from Stockholm syndrome.</p>
<p>We can’t let a company like this take control of our healthcare system.</p>
<p>But we can fight back right now. We’ve set up a simple tool so you can find out if your local NHS trust has started using the software, and then send an email demanding they say no to Palantir.</p>
<p>With the government putting NHS trusts under pressure to adopt the software, we need to act right now. <span>If you want to keep Palantir out of our NHS, send an email to your local trust and Wes Streeting, secretary of state for health.</span><b><br>
</b></p>
      </div>

      <p>Please provide your full name and email address.</p>
            <p>Sorry, your session has expired. Please try again. If it continues to not work please <a target="_blank" href="https://notopalantir.goodlawproject.org/contact">Get in touch</a></p>
      


        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Richard Stallman at the First Hackers Conference in 1984 [video] (132 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Hf2pfzzWPYE</link>
            <guid>46405306</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 21:15:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Hf2pfzzWPYE">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Hf2pfzzWPYE</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46405306">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[White House pushes to dismantle leading climate and weather research center (259 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.pbs.org/newshour/show/white-house-pushes-to-dismantle-leading-climate-and-weather-research-center</link>
            <guid>46405183</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 21:01:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/show/white-house-pushes-to-dismantle-leading-climate-and-weather-research-center">https://www.pbs.org/newshour/show/white-house-pushes-to-dismantle-leading-climate-and-weather-research-center</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46405183">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>The Trump administration says it plans to dismantle the National Center for Atmospheric Research in Colorado, which is the nation’s premier atmospheric science center. The center was founded in 1960 and has facilitated generations of breakthroughs in climate and weather science. William Brangham discussed the move with climate scientist Kim Cobb and meteorologist Matthew Cappucci.</p><p><i>Notice: Transcripts are machine and human generated and lightly edited for accuracy. They may contain errors.</i></p><div>
                        <p><strong>William Brangham:</strong></p>
            <p>The Trump administration says it plans to dismantle the National Center for Atmospheric Research in Colorado, which is the nation's premier atmospheric science center.</p><p>In announcing the closing, Budget Director Russell Vought called the center -- quote -- "one of the largest sources of climate alarmism in the country."</p><p>NCAR, as the center is known, was founded in 1960 and has facilitated generations of breakthroughs in climate and weather science. The announcement has drawn outcry from meteorologists and climate scientists across the country.</p><p>Earlier this week, I spoke with two of them who are very familiar with the center's work. Brown University's Kim Cobb is a climate scientist and director of the Institute at Brown for Environment and Society, and Matthew Cappucci is senior meteorologist at MyRadar.</p><p>Thank you both so much for being here.</p><p>Kim Cobb, to you first. What is NCAR and why, as a climate scientist, is it so important and seemingly precious to this community?</p>
                                <p><strong>Kim Cobb, Brown University:</strong></p>
            <p>Thanks for having me, William.</p><p>NCAR is a really historic institution in our field. It, of course, dates back decades now. And, over that time, it has really woven itself into the fabric of both weather and climate science across the country and around the world.</p><p>We're talking about unique, one-of-a-kind facilities like supercomputers, ticked-out airplanes, and most importantly, a staff of over 800 people who are at the top of their game in innovating in weather and climate science for public good, putting out data that is on every single climate scientist's computer around the country, if not around the world, and a nexus of collaboration as well that is important training grounds for the next generation of leaders.</p>
                                <p><strong>William Brangham:</strong></p>
            <p>And, Matthew Cappucci, as a meteorologist, how important is NCAR to your profession?</p>
                                <p><strong>Matthew Cappucci, Senior Meteorologist, MyRadar:</strong></p>
            <p>I mean, NCAR is really the birthplace of all the tools we use, both technologically.</p><p>And, really, the discoveries that are made at NCAR are crucial to our understanding of how the atmosphere works. That's where we first learned about the MJO, the Madden-Julian Oscillation, one of the biggest overturning circulations in the atmosphere that governs how so many things, for example, hurricanes behave.</p><p>It's where we first created a special product used by airplanes when they're landing to avoid wind shear, disruptive changing winds with height that could cause plane crashes. They invented a system there to prevent that. That's where dropsondes were invented, those little probes that are dropped out of the belly of airplanes in the middle of hurricanes to figure out how strong the hurricanes are.</p><p>So, so many different tools and discoveries have come from NCAR. In addition, the modeling is incredibly important. And if we're sort of putting the brakes on that, I worry about the implications for weather forecasting.</p>
                                <p><strong>William Brangham:</strong></p>
            <p>Kim Cobb, well, what more on that? Well, let's say NCAR is broken up. What are the impacts, both for the scientific community and for Americans who benefit from its research?</p>
                                <p><strong>Kim Cobb:</strong></p>
            <p>I think what's really important to remember is that NCAR focuses on the entire continuum from weather that ranges over hours and days that's designed to aid the forecasts that keep people safe and protect infrastructure and our economy.</p><p>But they also go all the way out to looking decades into the future and really understanding that most important intersection right now, how weather is responding to ongoing climate change. It's these kinds of questions at the very forefront of our field that they're focused on right now.</p><p>And these are innovations that are going to reap absolutely untold dividends through time. So, by breaking this -- these up and its component parts, if you will, first of all, the administration has made clear that it's the climate portion of the portfolio which they are taking squarely in aim.</p><p>And, of course, that is the portion that is right now so important to invest in as we seek to understand more about the coming threats and impacts of ongoing climate change, 2025, of course, wrapping up to be tied for the second warmest year ever.</p>
                                <p><strong>William Brangham:</strong></p>
            <p>And, Matthew, the White House has argued that NCAR and its undertakings and its work is somehow contaminated with woke ideology or climate alarmism.</p><p>Is there research or data that is coming out of NCAR that is politicized or ideological in any way?</p>
                                <p><strong>Matthew Cappucci:</strong></p>
            <p>Truth be told, no. The atmosphere does not possess a voter registration card. I think it's important to remember that scientists do science. And, really, the only people doing the politicization are, for the most part, politicians and the general public and the media.</p><p>It worries me, though, that this fits into an overall pattern of the demonization of both science and academia. The idea that we're trying to shut down science that produces results we don't like, it's a very worrisome trend. And we have seen this other times in history, and it never really ended well.</p><p>And I'm just very concerned about the tone that's being taken that simply because one political party or even one political person doesn't like the fact that we're learning about the atmosphere.</p>
                                <p><strong>William Brangham:</strong></p>
            <p>I mean, Kim, as Matthew is saying, we know that President Trump has called climate change a hoax. He believes it's nothing that we need to focus on. He has directed so much of the administration to move away from climate research, from renewable energy, doubling down on fossil fuels.</p><p>I'm just curious as to what -- are you worried similarly about the future of climate research if we continue to chip away at these foundational projects?</p>
                                <p><strong>Kim Cobb:</strong></p>
            <p>Well, obviously, as Matthew said, we turn our backs on science to great risk and peril.</p><p>And I think most Americans get it right now. In the headlines every year are these horrific climate-fueled disasters that have taken such a toll on communities and our national economy, to the tune of billions of dollars per year. So this is not a controversial subject in that regard. People do want the best available science information to protect themselves.</p><p>And that's exactly what NCAR and its scientists are focused on. And I think the Trump administration is just not understanding how long an investment has been made to get us to this point and the many dividends that we have already reached and that, once you break something like this, it's really going to be hard to put it back together again. That's my concern.</p>
                                <p><strong>William Brangham:</strong></p>
            <p>Matthew, the OMB director in his announcement said they will do a systematic review of the work that NCAR does, and critical weather information and research will just get sent somewhere else or done in another location.</p><p>How confident are you that a breakup of NCAR could still keep some of the critical elements intact?</p>
                                <p><strong>Matthew Cappucci:</strong></p>
            <p>I think so many times this administration has historically put the cart before the horse. And what I mean by that is, it seems like just a year ago, they were cutting a huge chunk of National Weather Service forecasters.</p><p>And then, after they were laid off, the government realized, oh, wait, we kind of need them, and brought them back. This seems like another really shortsighted decision made by the administration without realizing or fully researching the potential implications of what could happen.</p><p>And I also just sort of think this strikes the wrong tone for just about everybody. Weather and climate affect everybody. And, realistically, you're much more likely to be hit by a tornado or hurricane in a red state. And so I'm surprised by sort of Trump and his administration doing something that could potentially have negative impacts on his own core audience and following.</p>
                                <p><strong>William Brangham:</strong></p>
            <p>All right, that is Matthew Cappucci and Kim Cobb.</p><p>Thank you both so much for being here. We really appreciate it.</p>
            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How we lost communication to entertainment (412 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ploum.net/2025-12-15-communication-entertainment.html</link>
            <guid>46404848</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 20:15:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ploum.net/2025-12-15-communication-entertainment.html">https://ploum.net/2025-12-15-communication-entertainment.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46404848">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>


<p>by <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ploum">Ploum</a> on 2025-12-15</p>
<blockquote> All our communication channels are morphed into content distribution networks. We are more and more entertained but less and less connected.<br></blockquote>
<p>A few days ago, I did a controversial blog post about Pixelfed hurting the Fediverse. I defended the theory that, in a communication network, you hurt the trust in the whole network if you create clients that arbitrarily drop messages, something that Pixelfed is doing deliberately. It gathered a lot of reactions. </p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://ploum.net/2025-12-04-pixelfed-against-fediverse.html">Is Pixelfed sawing off the branch that the Fediverse is sitting on? (ploum.net)</a></li>
</ul>
<p>When I originally wrote this post, nearly one year ago, I thought that either I was missing something or Dansup, Pixelfed’s creator, was missing it. We could not both be right. But as the reactions piled in on the Fediverse, I realised that such irreconcilable opinions do not arise only from ignorance or oversight. It usually means that both parties have vastly different assumptions about the world. They don’t live in the same world.</p>
<h2 id="soustitre-1">Two incompatible universes</h2>
<p>I started to see a pattern in the two kinds of reactions to my blog post.</p>
<p>There were people like me, often above 40, who like sending emails and browsing old-fashioned websites. We think of ActivityPub as a "communication protocol" between humans. As such, anything that implies losing messages without feedback is the worst thing that could happen. Not losing messages is the top priority of a communication protocol.</p>
<p>And then there are people like Dansup, who believe that ActivityPub is a content consumption protocol. It’s there for entertainment. You create as many accounts as the kinds of media you want to consume. Dansup himself is communicating through a Mastodon account, not a Pixelfed one. Many Pixelfed users also have a Mastodon account, and they never questioned that. They actually want multiple accounts for different use cases. </p>
<p>On the Fediverse threads, nearly all the people defending the Pixelfed philosophy posted from Mastodon accounts. They usually boasted about having both a Mastodon and a Pixelfed account.</p>
<h2 id="soustitre-2">A multiplicity of accounts</h2>
<p>To me, the very goal of interoperability is not to force you into creating multiple accounts. Big Monopolies have managed to convince people that they need one account on each platform. This was done, on purpose, for purely unethical reasons in order to keep users captive.</p>
<p>That brainwash/marketing is so deeply entrenched that most people cannot see an alternative anymore. It looks like a natural law: you need an account on a platform to communicate with someone on that platform. That also explains why most politicians want to "regulate" Facebook or X. They think it is impossible not to be on those platforms. They believe those platforms are "public spaces" while they truly are "private spaces trying to destroy all other public spaces in order to get a monopoly."</p>
<p>People flock to the Fediverse with this philosophy of "one platform, one account", which makes no sense if you truly want to create a federated communication protocol like email or XMPP.</p>
<p>But Manuel Moreale cracked it for me: the Fediverse is not a communication network. ActivityPub is not a communication protocol. The spec says it: ActivityPub is a protocol to build a "social platform" whose goal is "to deliver content."</p>
<blockquote> The ActivityPub protocol is a decentralised social networking protocol based upon the ActivityStreams 2.0 data format. It provides a client to server API for creating, updating and deleting content, as well as a federated server-to-server API for delivering notifications and content. (official W3C definition of ActivityPub) <br></blockquote>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://manuelmoreale.com/thoughts/on-open-protocols">On open protocols (manuelmoreale.com)</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="soustitre-3">No more communication</h2>
<p>But aren’t social networks also communication networks? That’s what I thought. That’s how they historically were marketed. That’s what we all believed during the "Arab Spring."</p>
<p>But that was a lie. Communication networks are not profitable. Social networks are entertainment platforms, media consumption protocols. Historically, they disguised themselves as communication platforms to attract users and keep them captive. </p>
<p>The point was never to avoid missing a message sent from a fellow human being. The point was always to fill your time with "content."</p>
<p>We dreamed of decentralised social networks as "email 2.0." They truly are "television 2.0."</p>
<p>They are entertainment platforms that delegate media creation to the users themselves the same way Uber replaced taxis by having people drive others in their own car.</p>
<p>But what was created as "ride-sharing" was in fact a way to 1) destroy competition and 2) make a shittier service while people producing the work were paid less and lost labour rights. It was never about the social!</p>
<h2 id="soustitre-4">The lost messages</h2>
<p>My own interpretation is that social media users don’t mind losing messages because they were raised on algorithmic platforms that did that all the time. They don’t see the point in trusting a platform because they never experienced a trusted means of communication. </p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://ploum.net/facebook-ma-rendu-injoignable/index.html">Facebook m’a rendu injoignable (ploum.net)</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Now that I write it, it may also explain why instant messaging became the dominant communication medium: because if you don’t receive an immediate answer, you don’t even trust the recipient to have received your messages. In fact, even if the message was received, you don’t even trust the recipient's attention span to remember the message.</p>
<p>Multiple studies have confirmed that we don’t remember the vast majority of what we see while doomscrolling. While the "view" was registered to increase statistics, we don’t have the slightest memory of most of that content, even after only a few seconds. It thus makes sense not to consider social media as a means of communication at all.</p>
<p>There’s no need for a reliable communication protocol if we assume that human brains are not reliable enough to handle asynchronous messages.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://ploum.net/2024-03-18-lost-focus.html">A Society That Lost Focus (ploum.net)</a></li>
</ul>
<p>It’s not Dansup who is missing something. It is me who is unadapted to the current society. I understand now that Pixelfed was only following some design decisions and protocol abuses fathered by Mastodon. Pixelfed was my own "gotcha" moment because I never understood Instagram in the first place, and, in my eyes, Pixelfed was no better. But if you take that route, Mastodon is no better than Twitter. </p>
<p>Many reactions pointed, justly, that other Fediverse tools such as PeerTube, WriteFreely, or Mobilizon were just not displaying messages at all.</p>
<p>I didn’t consider it a big problem because they never pretended to do it in the first place. Nobody uses those tools to follow others. There’s no expectation. Those platforms are "publish only." But this is still a big flaw in the Fediverse! Someone could, using autocompletion, send a message pinging your PeerTube address and you will never see it. Try autocomplete "@ploum" from your Mastodon account and guess which suggestion is the only one that will send me a valid notification!</p>
<p>On a more positive note, I should give credit to Dansup for announcing that Pixelfed will soon allow people to optionally "not drop" text messages.</p>
<h2 id="soustitre-5">How we lost email</h2>
<p>I cling to asynchronous reliable communications, but those are disappearing. I use email a lot because I see it as a true means of communication: reliable, asynchronous, decentralised, standardised, manageable offline with my own tools. But many people, even barely younger than me, tell me that email is "too formal" or "for old people" or "even worse than social network feeds."</p>
<p>And they are probably right. I like it because I’ve learned to use it. I apply a strong inbox 0 methodology. If I don’t reply or act on your email, it is because I decided not to. I’m actively keeping my inbox clean by sharing only disposable email addresses that I disable once they start to be spammed. </p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://ploum.net/why-you-are-not-at-inbox-0/index.html">Why you are probably not at inbox 0 (but should be) (ploum.net)</a></li>
</ul>
<p>But for most people, their email inbox is simply one more feed full of bad advertising. They have 4 or 5 digit unread count. They scroll through their inbox like they do through their social media feeds.</p>
<h2 id="soustitre-6">Boringness of communications</h2>
<p>The main problem with reliable communication protocols? It is a mostly solved problem. Build simple websites, read RSS feeds, write emails. Use IRC and XMPP if you truly want real-time communication. Those are working and working great.</p>
<p>And because of that, they are boring.</p>
<p>Communications protocols are boring. They don’t give you that well-studied random hit of dopamine. They don’t make you addicted.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="gemini://gem.sdf.org/beej/blog/2025-01-10-socialmedia.gmi">On Social Media (gem.sdf.org)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/9ZodFr54FtpLThHZh/experiential-pica">Experiential Pica (www.lesswrong.com)</a></li>
</ul>
<p>They don’t make you addicted which means they are not hugely profitable and thus are not advertised. They are not new. They are not as shiny as a new app or a new random chatbot. </p>
<p>The problem with communication protocols was never the protocol part. It’s the communication part. A few sad humans never wanted to communicate in the first place and managed to become billionaires by convincing the rest of mankind that being entertained is better than communicating with other humans.</p>
<h2 id="soustitre-7">As long as I’m not alone</h2>
<p>We believe that a communication network must reach a critical mass to be really useful. People stay on Facebook to "stay in touch with the majority." I don’t believe that lie anymore. I’m falling back to good old mailing lists. I’m reading the Web and Gemini while offline through Offpunk. I also handle my emails asynchronously while offline.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://offpunk.net/">Offpunk, an offline-first command-line browser (offpunk.net)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://ploum.net/2022-10-05-there-is-no-content-on-gemini.html">There Is No Content on Gemini (ploum.net)</a></li>
</ul>
<p>I may be part of an endangered species.</p>
<p>It doesn’t matter. I made peace with the fact that I will never get in touch with everyone. As long as there are people posting on their gemlogs or blogs with RSS feeds, as long as there are people willing to read my emails without automatically summarising them, there will be a place for those who want to simply communicate. A protected reserve.</p>
<p>You are welcome to join!</p>
<figure>
<a href="https://ploum.net/files/framagroupes.jpg"><img alt="/files/framagroupes.jpg" src="https://ploum.net/files/framagroupes.jpg" width="450"></a>
</figure>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.peppercarrot.com/en/viewer/framasoft__2023-05-20_Framalistes_by-David-Revoy.html">Illustration of a message board piled with messages by David Revoy (CC By 4.0)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.peppercarrot.com/en/viewer/framasoft__2023-05-20_Framagroupes_by-David-Revoy.html">Illustration of animal meeting at an intersection with messages by David Revoy (CC By 4.0)</a></li>
</ul>

<div><p>I’m <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ploum">Ploum</a>, a writer and an engineer. I like to explore how technology impacts society. You can subscribe <a href="https://listes.ploum.net/mailman3/lists/en.listes.ploum.net/">by email</a> or <a href="https://ploum.net/atom_en.xml">by rss</a>. I value privacy and never share your adress.</p>
<p>I write <a href="https://pvh-editions.com/ploum">science-fiction novels in French</a>. For <a href="https://bikepunk.fr/">Bikepunk</a>, my new post-apocalyptic-cyclist book, my publisher is looking for contacts in other countries to distribute it in languages other than French. If you can help, <a href="https://ploum.net/about.html">contact me</a>!</p> 

</div>
</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Rainbow Six Siege hacked as players get billions of credits and random bans (173 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.shanethegamer.com/esports-news/rainbow-six-siege-hacked-global-server-outage/</link>
            <guid>46404597</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 19:45:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.shanethegamer.com/esports-news/rainbow-six-siege-hacked-global-server-outage/">https://www.shanethegamer.com/esports-news/rainbow-six-siege-hacked-global-server-outage/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46404597">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="post-79841"><div id="cb-featured-image"><p><img width="759" height="500" src="https://www.shanethegamer.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/STG-Cover-7-1-759x500.webp?x67281" data-src="https://www.shanethegamer.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/STG-Cover-7-1-759x500.webp?x67281" alt="Rainbow Six Siege hacked" decoding="async" data-srcset="https://www.shanethegamer.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/STG-Cover-7-1-759x500.webp 759w, https://www.shanethegamer.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/STG-Cover-7-1-300x197.webp 300w, https://www.shanethegamer.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/STG-Cover-7-1-100x65.webp 100w, https://www.shanethegamer.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/STG-Cover-7-1-260x170.webp 260w" data-sizes="(max-width: 759px) 100vw, 759px" srcset="https://www.shanethegamer.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/STG-Cover-7-1-759x500.webp 759w, https://www.shanethegamer.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/STG-Cover-7-1-300x197.webp 300w, https://www.shanethegamer.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/STG-Cover-7-1-100x65.webp 100w, https://www.shanethegamer.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/STG-Cover-7-1-260x170.webp 260w"></p><p>Image Credit: Ubisoft Entertainment</p></div><section itemprop="articleBody"> <span itemprop="reviewBody"><p data-start="143" data-end="469"><strong data-start="143" data-end="164">Rainbow Six Siege</strong> is currently facing a major crisis, with mounting evidence pointing to a large scale hack or exploit, even as Ubisoft continues to describe the situation as a server incident. The disruption has now escalated into full service outages across all platforms, <a href="https://www.ubisoft.com/en-us/game/rainbow-six/siege/status">according to Ubisoft’s own service status page.</a></p><p data-start="471" data-end="693">Players across PC and console are being urged by the community to stay offline, as reports continue to surface of accounts receiving billions of in game credits, rare and developer only skins, and experiencing random bans.</p><blockquote data-theme="dark"><p dir="ltr" lang="en">BREAKING: Ubisoft Rainbow Six Siege servers have been breached.</p><p>Players are reporting massive amounts of R6 Credits, Renown, Alpha Packs, and exclusive items unexpectedly.</p><p>Numerous accounts even Ubisoft, including streamers’ and possibly official ones, have received random or… <a href="https://t.co/9hGNbBCMAm">pic.twitter.com/9hGNbBCMAm</a></p><p>— Pirat_Nation 🔴 (@Pirat_Nation) <a href="https://twitter.com/Pirat_Nation/status/2004901721336590703?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December 27, 2025</a></p></blockquote><h2 data-start="695" data-end="754">Ubisoft Confirms Widespread Outages Across All Platforms</h2><p data-start="756" data-end="889">The official service status page for <strong data-start="793" data-end="834"><span><span>Rainbow Six Siege</span></span></strong> now shows critical issues across every major platform.</p><div id="attachment_79842"><p><img decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-79842" src="https://www.shanethegamer.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/image-21-1.webp?x67281" data-src="https://www.shanethegamer.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/image-21-1.webp?x67281" alt="Rainbow Six Siege hacked" width="981" height="866" data-srcset="https://www.shanethegamer.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/image-21-1.webp 981w, https://www.shanethegamer.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/image-21-1-300x265.webp 300w, https://www.shanethegamer.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/image-21-1-768x678.webp 768w" data-sizes="(max-width: 981px) 100vw, 981px" srcset="https://www.shanethegamer.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/image-21-1.webp 981w, https://www.shanethegamer.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/image-21-1-300x265.webp 300w, https://www.shanethegamer.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/image-21-1-768x678.webp 768w"></p><p id="caption-attachment-79842">Image via ubisoft.com</p></div><p data-start="891" data-end="1198">On PC, PS4, PS5, Xbox One, and Xbox Series X|S, core services including authentication, in game store access, and matchmaking are all listed as being in outage, while overall connectivity is marked as degraded. Ubisoft states that issues are being investigated, but has not provided a timeline for recovery.</p><p data-start="1200" data-end="1314">The scale of the outages has further fuelled claims that this is far more serious than routine server instability.</p><h2 data-start="1316" data-end="1360">Ubisoft’s Statement Draws Heavy Criticism</h2><p data-start="1362" data-end="1573">Earlier, the official Rainbow Six account acknowledged that it was aware of an incident affecting the game and said teams were working on a resolution. No mention was made of a security breach, hack, or exploit.</p><blockquote data-theme="dark"><p dir="ltr" lang="en">We’re aware of an incident currently affecting Rainbow Six Siege. Our teams are working on a resolution.</p><p>We will share further updates once available.</p><p>— Rainbow Six Siege X (@Rainbow6Game) <a href="https://twitter.com/Rainbow6Game/status/2004917731829948808?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December 27, 2025</a></p></blockquote><p data-start="1575" data-end="1835">That wording has been met with heavy backlash from players, many of whom believe Ubisoft is attempting to downplay the severity of the situation. Community responses have accused the publisher of calling it a server issue while core systems appear compromised.</p><p data-start="1837" data-end="1952">Some players also questioned why the game remained online for hours while accounts were being altered in real time.</p><h2 data-start="1954" data-end="2017">Players Report Billions of Credits, Dev Skins, and Ban Chaos</h2><p data-start="2019" data-end="2241">As the incident unfolded, players reported logging in to find their accounts flooded with billions of R6 Credits and Renown, thousands of Alpha Packs, and access to exclusive cosmetics such as developer skins and Glaciers.</p><blockquote data-theme="dark"><p dir="ltr" lang="en">Why is nobody talking about what is happening on Siege right now? Everyone that logs in gets 2 Billion R6 credits, Renown, Developer Skins and Glaciers 😭 <a href="https://t.co/9SBiLdrirm">pic.twitter.com/9SBiLdrirm</a></p><p>— Terd (@Terdsta) <a href="https://twitter.com/Terdsta/status/2004887399890129325?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December 27, 2025</a></p></blockquote><p data-start="2243" data-end="2488">There were also widespread claims that the in game ban feed had been taken over, displaying arbitrary messages. Thousands of accounts were reportedly banned and unbanned at random, including those belonging to streamers and high profile players.</p><blockquote data-theme="dark"><p dir="ltr" lang="en">Rainbow Six is fucked <a href="https://t.co/OZpDXzttOZ">pic.twitter.com/OZpDXzttOZ</a></p><p>— Pirat_Nation 🔴 (@Pirat_Nation) <a href="https://twitter.com/Pirat_Nation/status/2004921104721477963?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December 27, 2025</a></p></blockquote><p data-start="2490" data-end="2752">Prominent Siege creator <strong data-start="2514" data-end="2555"><span><span>KingGeorge</span></span></strong> described the situation as completely broken, warning players not to log in and strongly advising against spending any currency, as it could lead to bans or rollbacks once Ubisoft regains control.</p><blockquote data-theme="dark"><p dir="ltr" lang="en">Btw as a side note I would not login right now, definitely don’t spend any credits or renown could lead to a ban.</p><p>— KingGeorge (@KingGeorge) <a href="https://twitter.com/KingGeorge/status/2004906746071191796?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December 27, 2025</a></p></blockquote><h2 data-start="2754" data-end="2802">Community Expects Rollbacks, Fears Punishment</h2><p data-start="2804" data-end="3087">With authentication and account systems affected, many players now expect Ubisoft to roll accounts back to a previous state. However, fears remain that innocent players could still face penalties, especially those who unknowingly spent credits thinking the issue was a visual glitch.</p><p data-start="3089" data-end="3253">Others argue that banning a significant portion of the active player base would be disastrous, adding further pressure on Ubisoft to handle the aftermath carefully.</p><p data-start="3255" data-end="3386">The lack of clear communication has only intensified frustration, with players demanding transparency about what actually happened.</p><h2 data-start="3388" data-end="3423">What Players Should Do Right Now</h2><p data-start="3425" data-end="3625">Until Ubisoft confirms the issue is fully resolved and explains the cause, players are strongly advised to stay offline, avoid logging in, and do not spend any credits or Renown if access is restored.</p><p data-start="3627" data-end="3891">With Rainbow Six Siege’s core services offline worldwide and player accounts potentially compromised, this incident could have lasting implications for the game if not handled properly. Ubisoft is expected to provide further updates as its investigation continues.</p> </span></section></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Toll roads are spreading in America (174 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.economist.com/united-states/2025/12/18/toll-roads-are-spreading-in-america</link>
            <guid>46403992</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 18:31:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2025/12/18/toll-roads-are-spreading-in-america">https://www.economist.com/united-states/2025/12/18/toll-roads-are-spreading-in-america</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46403992">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.economist.com/united-states/2025/12/18/toll-roads-are-spreading-in-america: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Scientists edited genes in a living person and saved his life (113 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.popularmechanics.com/science/health/a64815804/crispr-therapy/</link>
            <guid>46403955</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 18:26:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.popularmechanics.com/science/health/a64815804/crispr-therapy/">https://www.popularmechanics.com/science/health/a64815804/crispr-therapy/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46403955">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-journey-body="standard-article"><p data-journey-content="true" data-node-id="0">Here’s what you’ll learn in this story.</p><ul data-node-id="1"><li data-node-id="1.0">The world’s first bespoke gene therapy saved the life of a newborn with a rare genetic disorder that cause the build-up of life-threatening ammonia in the body. </li><li data-node-id="1.1">In a race against time, scientists and doctors across the U.S. developed the first in vivo gene therapy, thanks to decades of medical research. </li><li data-node-id="1.2">After three doses, the newborn patient showed drastic improvement, and this new era of in vivo gene therapies could save the lives of millions more in the future.</li></ul><hr data-node-id="2"><p data-journey-content="true" data-node-id="3">Life’s ability to successfully copy three billion distinct letters in the <a href="https://www.popularmechanics.com/science/health/a39610385/entire-human-genome-officially-published/" target="_blank" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="https://www.popularmechanics.com/science/health/a39610385/entire-human-genome-officially-published/" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="human genome" data-node-id="3.1">human genome</a> is an absolute biological wonder—but sometimes, mistakes are made. Whether inherited or formed in utero, genetic disorders and other birth defects are common, and occur in one in every 33 babies in the U.S., according to the <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/birth-defects/index.html" target="_blank" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="https://www.cdc.gov/birth-defects/index.html" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="Centers of Disease Control and Prevention" data-node-id="3.3"><u data-node-id="3.3.0">Centers of Disease Control and Prevention</u></a> (CDC). For all of human history, a person born with such a disorder likely had to live with the condition, and depending on the defect, those lives could be brutally short. </p><p data-journey-content="true" data-node-id="4">But in 2025, human history changed forever. </p><p data-journey-content="true" data-node-id="6">In a groundbreaking announcement, detailed in a study published in the <a href="https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMoa2504747" target="_blank" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMoa2504747" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="New England Journal of Medicine" data-node-id="6.1"><u data-node-id="6.1.0"><em data-node-id="6.1.0.0">New England Journal of Medicine</em></u></a>, scientists, doctors, and specialists from institutions around the U.S.—including the Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia, University of California-Berkeley, and Penn Medicine—successfully saved the life of a newborn patient named KJ, who had been born with a rare genetic disorder. To pull off this incredible medical feat, doctors employed the world’s first custom in vivo (i.e. inside a living organism, rather than in a petri dish) <a href="https://www.popularmechanics.com/science/health/a28539000/crispr-testing-will-challenge-inherited-blindess/" target="_blank" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="https://www.popularmechanics.com/science/health/a28539000/crispr-testing-will-challenge-inherited-blindess/" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="CRISPR gene therapy" data-node-id="6.3">CRISPR gene therapy</a>. This technique, developed over decades thanks to U.S.-funded medical research, could help alleviate painful lives for millions of people born every year with now-fixable genetic disorders. </p><p data-journey-content="true" data-node-id="8">“Years and years of progress in <a href="https://www.popularmechanics.com/science/health/a21461/crispr-human-trials/" target="_blank" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="https://www.popularmechanics.com/science/health/a21461/crispr-human-trials/" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="gene editing" data-node-id="8.1">gene editing</a> and collaboration between researchers and clinicians made this moment possible, and while KJ is just one patient, we hope he is the first of many to benefit from a methodology that can be scaled to fit an individual patient’s needs,” Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia’s Rebecca Ahrens-Nicklas, a co-author of the study, <a href="https://www.pennmedicine.org/news/news-releases/2025/may/worlds-first-patient-treated-with-personalized-crispr-therapy" target="_blank" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="https://www.pennmedicine.org/news/news-releases/2025/may/worlds-first-patient-treated-with-personalized-crispr-therapy" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="said in a press statement" data-node-id="8.3">said in a press statement</a>.</p><p data-journey-content="true" data-node-id="9">The details of this incredible medical intervention play out like a made-for-tv medical drama, but the stakes were incredibly real and deadly serious. A week after his birth, doctors noticed something wasn’t quite right with KJ. After ruling out a few possibilities, they stumbled across the unfortunate answer—a rare genetic disorder called severe carbamoyl phosphate synthetase 1 (CPS1) deficiency that affects only one in every 1.3 million babies. This disorder inhibits the body’s ability to get rid of <a href="https://www.popularmechanics.com/science/a31036312/green-ammonia-renewable-energy-risks/" target="_blank" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="https://www.popularmechanics.com/science/a31036312/green-ammonia-renewable-energy-risks/" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="ammonia" data-node-id="9.1">ammonia</a>, a product of protein metabolism. This can have deadly consequences, impact brain development, and wreak havoc on the liver. Usually, the treatment for a disorder like this is a liver transplant, but that was not an option for the infant boy, who was still too young to be considered for the surgery.</p><p data-journey-content="true" data-node-id="10">So, once arriving at a diagnosis, Ahrens-Nicklas contacted a gene-editing specialist at the University of Pennsylvania named Kiran Musunuru and “the clock start[ed]in my mind,” he later told <em data-node-id="10.1"><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/05/15/health/gene-editing-personalized-rare-disorders.html" target="_blank" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/05/15/health/gene-editing-personalized-rare-disorders.html" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="The New York Times" data-vars-ga-product-id="169050d8-6b17-45fe-a1da-c392d92c105c" rel="nofollow" data-node-id="10.1.0">The New York Times</a></em>. Working with a team of specialists across the country for six months, Ahrens-Nicklas and Musunuru developed a targeted gene therapy to fix KJ’s specific variant of CPS1. Meanwhile, KJ was kept under medical surveillance at the hospital and subsisted on a diet completely devoid of <a href="https://www.popularmechanics.com/space/solar-system/a31192959/protein-meteorite/" target="_blank" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="https://www.popularmechanics.com/space/solar-system/a31192959/protein-meteorite/" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="protein" data-node-id="10.3">protein</a> to avoid making his condition worse. By the time the CRISPR treatment was ready, KJ was in the 7<sup data-node-id="10.5">th</sup> percentile for his weight. </p><p data-journey-content="true" data-node-id="11">On February 25, the team began administering the <a href="https://www.popularmechanics.com/science/health/a64593150/gold-nanoparticles-vision/" target="_blank" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="https://www.popularmechanics.com/science/health/a64593150/gold-nanoparticles-vision/" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="treatment" data-node-id="11.1">treatment</a>, with Ahrens-Nicklas and Musunuru describing the process as both exciting and terrifying. </p><p data-journey-content="true" data-node-id="13">“One of the most terrifying moments was when I walked into the room and said, ‘I don’t know if it will work but I promise I will do everything I can to make sure it is safe,’” Ahrens-Nicklas told <em data-node-id="13.1">The New York Times</em>. </p><p data-journey-content="true" data-node-id="14">The first infusion took two hours, and within two weeks, KJ began eating protein like a healthy baby. A second dose arrived 22 days later, and about two weeks ago, KJ received a third. Although it’s unknown if he will eventually still need a liver <a href="https://www.popularmechanics.com/science/health/a64514733/heart-transplant-beating/" target="_blank" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="https://www.popularmechanics.com/science/health/a64514733/heart-transplant-beating/" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="transplant" data-node-id="14.1">transplant</a>, doctors can now safely say that a human life has been saved thanks to the world’s first bespoke in vivo gene therapy—a huge testament to decades of a research and experimentation. KJ is now at home with his family.</p><p data-journey-content="true" data-node-id="15">“We want each and every patient to have the potential to experience the same results we saw in this first patient, and we hope that other academic investigators will replicate this method for many rare <a href="https://www.popularmechanics.com/science/a32837605/mosquito-borne-illness-spreading/" target="_blank" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="https://www.popularmechanics.com/science/a32837605/mosquito-borne-illness-spreading/" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="diseases" data-node-id="15.1">diseases</a> and give many patients a fair shot at living a healthy life,” Musunuru said in a press statement. “The promise of gene therapy that we’ve heard about for decades is coming to fruition, and it’s going to utterly transform the way we approach medicine.”<br data-node-id="15.3"></p><div data-journey-blur="partial" data-ad-exclude="true"><p><span><img src="https://hips.hearstapps.com/rover/profile_photos/e9b7a87b-359a-4fff-859b-ab9cf5e31c5b_1565789938.file?fill=1:1&amp;resize=120:*" alt="Headshot of Darren Orf" title="Headshot of Darren Orf" width="100%" height="100%" decoding="async" loading="lazy"></span></p><div><p>Darren lives in Portland, has a cat, and writes/edits about sci-fi and how our world works. You can find his previous stuff at Gizmodo and Paste if you look hard enough.&nbsp;</p></div></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Windows 2 for the Apricot PC/Xi (122 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/</link>
            <guid>46403915</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 18:22:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/">https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46403915">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<p>(and Word, and Excel, and so much more) by Nina Kalinina, December 27th, 2025 (rev. 1.02 2025-12-27)</p>
<p>I bought my first Apricot PC about three years ago, when I realised I wanted an 8086-based computer. At the time, I knew nothing about it and simply bought it because it looked rad and the price was low. I had no idea that it was not IBM PC-compatible, and that there were very few programs available for it.</p>
<p>I have been on a quest to get a modern-ish word processor and spreadsheet program for it ever since. Which eventually made me "port" Windows 2 on it. In this post, I will tell you the story of this port.</p>
<p>As a side-quest, I also wrote an <a href="https://ninakalinina.com/notes/win2/">article explaining why Windows 2 is kind of awesome</a>. Make sure to check it out, too, if you need more Windows 2 screenshots in your life.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0000.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0000.jpg" alt="0000.jpg"></a></p>
<p>A photograph of a dark grey computer with a CRT monitor - an Apricot PC - running Windows 2</p>
<p>Please note that most of the images in this post were taken from a real green CRT, and thus their quality might vary. You can click the image to load it in full size.</p>
<div><p>If you have comments or feedback, please leave them in <a href="https://tech.lgbt/@nina_kali_nina/115792788459542758">the Mastodon thread</a>.
</p><p>If you own an Apricot PC, or want to try the port in an emulator, check out <a href="https://git.sr.ht/~nkali/win2-apricot">the project on sr.ht</a>. You need an Apricot PC, PC/Xi or Xen with at least 512 kB of RAM.</p>
</div>

<p>If you find technical details boring the heck out of you, please don't hesitate to <b>scroll down to the screenshot section</b>.</p>
<hr><hr><hr>
<div>
<h2>A few words about the Apricot PC/Xi</h2>
<p>If you want a personal computer today, your general choice is between a "PC" and a "Mac". Back in the 1980s, you would have to choose between dozens or even hundreds of computer architectures, and "PC" was not necessarily the most popular choice for a computer. One of the most promising market contenders, Victor 9000, also known as Sirius 1, was released in 1981. It gained popularity in Europe, creating a niche market for "Sirius-compatible" computers. Two years later, the British company ACT released its Sirius-compatible Apricot PC.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0001.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0001.jpg" alt="0001.jpg"></a></p>
<p>A photograph of the main board of Apricot PC/Xi, in the process of being washed.</p>
<p>Apricot PC is a delightful computer with a great design. Its heart is Intel 8086, the older sibling of the 8088 used in the IBM PC. It uses lovely 3.5" floppy disks; and it is the first Western computer to have a 3.5" drive - before Apple Macintosh. The screen is 9 inches, 800x400 pixels, with great image fidelity. The PC/Xi model comes with a 10 megabyte Winchester hard drive, British-made Rodime RO352, the first-ever 3.5" hard drive.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0001a.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0001a.jpg" alt="0001a.jpg"></a></p>
<p>A photograph of the computer's display showing multiple images at once: photographs of computer chips, schematics, and oscilloscope charts.</p>
<p>The computer is simple enough to be understood by one person in its entirety (over the course of many months of studying). There are schematics, technical manuals, BIOS reference manuals, and example code available for it, too. Its CPU is supported by Microsoft C, Turbo Pascal, and Open Watcom. It even runs MS-DOS (2.0 to 3.20), though, of course, it cannot run any IBM PC programs.</p>
<p>The lack of IBM PC-compatibility proved to be fatal for the Apricot. The entirety of its software catalogue is less than 300 megabytes. There is only one <a href="https://74ls373.itch.io/where-is-owl">graphical game with a soundtrack</a> for it, and it was made in 2025.</p>
<p>There were, of course, productivity applications for the Apricot, including Microsoft Word for DOS. But among those, only two word processors had a graphical interface: GEM Write and Microsoft Write for Windows 1. Neither were popular; <a href="https://www.seasip.info/Gem/drivers3.html">GEM drivers were lost and re-created by John Elliot in 2012 or so</a>. Windows 1 was thought to be lost.</p>
<p>Hypothetically, it should be possible to port a 16-bit Windows to this computer. It would require creating <code>SYSTEM.DRV</code>, <code>DISPLAY.DRV</code>, <code>KEYBOARD.DRV</code>, <code>MOUSE.DRV</code>, and ideally <code>COMM.DRV</code> drivers. But that would be a lot of work.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0001b.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0001b.jpg" alt="0001b.jpg"></a></p>
<p>A screenshot of Windows 1 Notepad. I didn't have a Windows 1 Write screenshot at hand, but trust me, it looks almost the same.</p>
<p>This is where things get interesting. A port of Windows 1 for the Apricot PC (released by ACT in 1987, a year before Windows 2) was miraculously preserved and surfaced online not that long ago. By itself, Windows 1 is unremarkable, as it does not have much useful software. But its driver architecture is not too different from Windows 2, so I thought it might be just about possible to make Windows 2 for the Apricot. And if I could somehow boot Windows 2, I'd be able to run Word, Excel, and Adobe Illustrator on my Apricot.</p>
<p>Well, it only took two and a half years to pull it off!</p>
</div>
<div>
<h2>Porting Windows 2 on the Apricot</h2>
<h3>Booting, fast and slow</h3>
<p>Even today, software historians are still arguing whether Windows 2.0 deserves to be called a major Windows update. It added dozens of new kernel features, but it barely changed the driver architecture of the system. The mouse and the keyboard drivers for Windows 2 would work fine on Windows 1, and vice versa. The CGA and EGA video drivers from Windows 1 would allow Windows 2 to boot, but could not render the fonts correctly.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0002a.png"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0002a.png" alt="0002a.png"></a></p>
<p>A screenshot of Windows 2 for IBM PC with a broken video driver; all text on the screen is garbled.</p>
<p>A natural thing to try would be installing Windows 2 with the Apricot drivers for Windows 1. Except that there are no <em>driver files</em>.</p>
<p>When you install Windows 1 or 2 on your computer, the SETUP utility combines (links) the driver files with the kernel. It is called "fast boot" and is supposed to improve the boot times of the system. The result of the SETUP is two files, WIN100.BIN and WIN100.OVL. The BIN file is an EXE file in disguise, consisting of the Windows kernel and the system drivers. The OVL file has resources and code that the system uses only from time to time.</p>
<p>The Windows 1 port of Apricot was only ever distributed with the "fast boot". The individual driver files were not distributed, so we cannot use them.</p>
<h3>The stub drivers</h3>
<p>If there are no drivers, we can make some! Microsoft has a Driver Development Kit for Windows, also known as Windows DDK. The DDK comes with the drivers for the IBM PC, meant to be used as a reference for other platforms. With the help of the DDK, I implemented a <a href="https://git.sr.ht/~nkali/win2-apricot/commit/51fcc80c4c26867ef7f153618ee4c0970dd735f0#win2stub_dd">stub video driver</a>, and somehow got a stub mouse and system drivers. This was enough to confirm that Windows 2, indeed, can start on the Apricot PC without any patches to the kernel. I had my doubts about that, because Windows 2 comes with EMS memory support, and it might have been using something IBM PC-specific to test for it. Thankfully not.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0002.png"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0002.png" alt="0002.png"></a></p>
<p>A screenshot of Windows 2 booting in the text mode. The file manager application simply dumps the list of files on the screen, without drawing any windows.</p>
<h3>Trying to write a video driver</h3>
<p>Now I could expand the drivers to support the Apricot PC. Keyboard, mouse, and even system drivers are small and simple. The real beast of a driver is DISPLAY.DRV, as it has to implement a large subset of the Windows graphical subsystem. With the reference display drivers, this should not be a problem, as long as the video card supports a graphical mode.</p>
<p>But the Apricot PC doesn't have a real graphical mode. It has a 50x25 "graphics screen" with a fake 16x16 font. This is a big problem.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0003a.png"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0003a.png" alt="0003a.png"></a></p>
<p>A page of the Apricot technical reference explaining the organisation of the Video RAM.</p>
<p>The reference video driver from Microsoft makes many bold assumptions about the way video RAM is organised. With the display initialisation routines corrected, the image produced by the reference driver is still undecipherable.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0003.png"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0003.png" alt="0003.png"></a></p>
<p>A screenshot of the MAME emulator, running Windows 2 on the Apricot. There are no windows, only stripes of black.</p>
<p>Writing a driver for such a video card is significantly more painful than designing a VGA-compatible video card for the Apricot. Maybe I return to <a href="https://git.sr.ht/~nkali/win2-apricot/tree/main/item/Apricot">the Apricot display driver project</a> one day (for the Windows 3.0 port), but for now, I have given up on it.</p>
<h3>Lose the battle, win the war: re-linking</h3>
<p>Originally, I entertained the idea of unlinking the drivers from the WIN100.BIN/OVL files and reusing them, but rejected it. Not only is it difficult to do, but it is also useless, because the Windows 1 video driver would not display the fonts on the screen under Windows 2.</p>
<p>But when I hit the roadblock with writing the driver from scratch, I got an idea: what if I use a driver from Windows 1 <em>with fonts from Windows 1</em>? Apparently, this trick works!  And so, I decided to abandon the video driver writing if I could somehow extract a video driver from the WIN100.BIN/OVL, because I would not need to reverse-engineer it to patch in the font support; it could work out of the box. But how?</p>
<p>The driver files in WIN100 are not "simply concatenated together": some parts from DISPLAY.DRV ends up in WIN100.BIN, and some in WIN100.OVL. Looking closely at those parts, I realised that the part in WIN100.OVL is identical to the Hercules driver. This gave me an idea: I could get a Hercules video driver; then I could extract CODE and DATA segments along with the Entry Table from the WIN100.BIN, and patch them into the Hercules driver. Unfortunately, not a single NE file format tool supported this use-case. I ended up writing <a href="https://git.sr.ht/~nkali/nexus-relink">my own tool NExus-relink</a> to assist in this process; the tool is still incomplete, but it gave me enough leverage to finish the job manually.</p>
<p>For the video driver, I used a "combine" tool I made for NExus, and then manually patched in the offsets and lengths in the NE header (one for the entry table, two for the segments). Incredibly, this was enough to make Windows 2 happy about the display:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0004.png"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0004.png" alt="0004.png"></a></p>
<p>A screenshot of Windows 2 running in the MAME emulator.</p>
<p>The same trick worked for the keyboard driver, but the mouse driver gave me a headache. I knew that when the mouse is not found, Windows doesn't display it on the screen, so I kept iterating on the driver, going deeper and deeper. The mouse driver has a relocation table of the OS Fixup type, and there are very few things written about it, so I wasn't sure if the driver was loading correctly.</p>
<p>I confirmed that the interrupt handler of the driver works, and was about to check the kernel source of the corresponding event handler when I discovered that, in fact, the mouse was working fine. It's just that the cursor wasn't displayed on the screen.</p>
<p>In Windows 1/2, the cursor is handled by the video driver to allow hardware acceleration and "hide cursor before taking a screenshot or drawing a bitmap". So, why is the video driver not drawing the cursor?</p>
<p>Windows DDK documentation has an answer: the mouse cursor drawing routines in the video driver are called by a timer routine, from the SYSTEM.DRV. I told about this to my fiancée, Atsuko, and she said: "Oh, you didn't notice the cursor wasn't blinking?"</p>
<p>Turns out, the timer routines in the SYSTEM.DRV were broken. The SYSTEM.DRV from Windows 1.0 cannot be used with Windows 2, so I implemented <a href="https://git.sr.ht/~nkali/win2-apricot/tree/main/item/System/SOURCE">the Apricot PC <code>SYSTEM.DRV</code></a> using Windows DDK as a reference.</p>
<p>With this driver complete, I had Windows 2 working on my Apricot PC/Xi.</p>
</div>
<div>
<h2>Windows 2 for the Apricot PC: a tour</h2>
<p>Welcome, welcome, let me show you around!</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0010.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0010.jpg" alt="0010.jpg"></a></p>
<p>I am greeted with the AUG logo when I power up my Apricot. I use the AUG BIOS because it supports the upgraded CPU, NEC V30, much better than the original one. Note that my machine has 896 kB of RAM.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0020.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0020.jpg" alt="0020.jpg"></a></p>
<p>The PC/Xi comes with a single 720 kB floppy drive and a 10 MB hard drive. I have MS-DOS 3.20 installed on the hard drive.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0030.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0030.jpg" alt="0030.jpg"></a></p>
<p>I have created a file called `win.bat` that simply starts the kernel.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0110.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0110.jpg" alt="0110.jpg"></a></p>
<p>Welcome to Windows 2. I have GW Basic, Turbo Pascal, Windows 1, Windows 2, Word and Excel installed on the hard drive, and I still have almost 2 megabytes free.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0201.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0201.jpg" alt="0201.jpg"></a></p>
<p>PC Paintbrush is one of the few programs that work on both Windows 1 and Windows 2. But it is more stable when running on top of Windows 2. Note that this is not Microsoft Paint **yet**: Microsoft would license this product only for its Windows 3.0 release.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0202.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0202.jpg" alt="0202.jpg"></a></p>
<p>I have to remind you that the screen is <em>monochrome</em>. Pixel dithering works really well on a 100 PPI 800x400 display, creating shades of grey from pixel patterns.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0210.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0210.jpg" alt="0210.jpg"></a></p>
<p>The screen is 4:3, so the pixels are not square. I have to pre-process raster images so they would look right on the Apricot's screen. Vector images are fine, though.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0310.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0310.jpg" alt="0310.jpg"></a></p>
<p>The default shell for Windows 2 is a bit too minimalistic to my taste. WANG's ClearView for Windows 2 brings a familiar to Windows 3 users PROGMAN-like experience to the Apricot.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0320.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0320.jpg" alt="0320.jpg"></a></p>
<p>Windows 1 came with tiling windows; Windows 2 uses overlapping windows that quickly become a disorganised mess. ClearView's window manager can arrange the windows for you.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0330.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0330.jpg" alt="0330.jpg"></a></p>
<p>Windows 2 control panel looks a bit funny in monochrome, but it is a powerful reminder that Windows supports 24-bit colour, which is important for printing and publishing.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0410.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0410.jpg" alt="0410.jpg"></a></p>
<p>A side note: Apricot's keyboard had an LED in the logo before ThinkPad did.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0420.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0420.jpg" alt="0420.jpg"></a></p>
<p>The MicroScreen and re-programmable keys are fully supported by the Windows keyboard driver. There is no ALT key, so "Close" is as close as we can get to pressing ALT+f4. Note that there is a hotkey for starting the XENTEL telephone accessory. The XENTEL button is somewhat similar to a Copilot button, except it can actually be useful in some situations.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0510.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0510.jpg" alt="0510.jpg"></a></p>
<p>Microsoft Word for Windows. Word for DOS, a completely different program, was first released back in 1983. Word for Windows had its first release in late 1989 due to a non-competition agreement with Apple. The success of Word for Windows made Microsoft abandon Word for DOS and Word for Mac; all the new versions of Word were based on <em>this</em> Word.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0520.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0520.jpg" alt="0520.jpg"></a></p>
<p>Word for Windows is surprisingly powerful for a brand-new product. There is a spellchecker, a page layout editor, and even support for macros. I have deleted the macros to save space on the hard drive, so the README file shows "Error!" where the macros were. The files created by Word for Windows 1.0 can be opened by modern office suites if you save as RTF.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0610.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0610.jpg" alt="0610.jpg"></a></p>
<p>Microsoft Excel is a real must-have. There is no other spreadsheet as powerful as Excel on the Apricot.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0620.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0620.jpg" alt="0620.jpg"></a></p>
<p>Excel for Windows from 1988 looks almost exactly like Excel for Windows from 2018.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0630.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0630.jpg" alt="0630.jpg"></a></p>
<p>My previous trip to Japan was planned between Google Docs and Excel for Windows 2 (I had to convert the file back and forth). I needed a few GB of RAM for Google Docs, and only a few hundred kilobytes for Excel.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0640.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0640.jpg" alt="0640.jpg"></a></p>
<p>Excel Help is a hidden gem. It is a hypertext application that feels a lot like a web browser.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0650.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0650.jpg" alt="0650.jpg"></a></p>
<p>I used the Help application to see how to create a stonks chart.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0670.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0670.jpg" alt="0670.jpg"></a></p>
<p>Creating a stonks chart is surprisingly easy. There are 44 chart types, more than many modern programs offer.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0710.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0710.jpg" alt="0710.jpg"></a></p>
<p>Until yesterday, Apricot PC had five graphical games: Chess, Where Is The Owl, Windows 1 Reversi, Windows 1 Minesweeper, and Windows 1 Risk. Now there are many more, including a solitaire and a Taipei mahjongg.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0810.jpg"><img src="https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/0810.jpg" alt="0810.jpg"></a></p>
<p>That's it! There are many Windows 2 programs I have yet to try on the Apricot, but my quest for running modern-ish Word and Excel for Windows is finally over.</p>
</div>
<hr><hr><hr>
<div>
<h2>Acknowledgments</h2>
<ul>
<li>Thank you for reading! If you have any questions or comments, please let me know. You can leave a comment in the <a href="https://tech.lgbt/@nina_kali_nina/115792788459542758">Mastodon thread about this article</a>.</li>
<li>My fiancée not only helped with beta-testing, she even designed a RAM expansion board for the Apricot PC/Xi that was necessary to run Windows on it. Love~</li>
<li>This project could not exist without advice from Michal Necasek of <a href="https://www.os2museum.com/wp/author/michaln/">os2museum</a> and David Simunič of <a href="https://win1.krnl386.com/about.php">krnl386</a> regarding drivers for ancient Windows version.</li>
</ul>
</div>
<hr><hr><hr>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Nvidia's $20B Antitrust Loophole (Not an Acquisition) (445 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ossa-ma.github.io/blog/groq</link>
            <guid>46403559</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 17:42:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ossa-ma.github.io/blog/groq">https://ossa-ma.github.io/blog/groq</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46403559">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section><p><span>AI</span><span>Research</span><span>Opinion/Mild Hating</span><span>Geopolitical Circlejerk</span><span>Venture Capital</span></p><article><p>"You're taking on a giant. What gives you the audacity?"</p>
<p>On November 5th, 2025, Groq CEO Jonathan Ross was asked why he was even bothering to challenge Nvidia. He didn't blink:</p>
<p>"I think that was a polite way to ask why in the world are we competing with Nvidia, so we're not. Competition is a waste of money; competition fundamentally means you are taking something someone else is doing and trying to copy it. You're wasting R&amp;D dollars trying to do the exact same thing they've done instead of using them to differentiate."</p>
<p>49 days later, Nvidia paid $20 billion for Groq's assets and hired Ross along with his entire executive team.</p>
<p>Except this wasn't actually an acquisition, at least not in the traditional sense. Nvidia paid $20 billion for Groq's IP and people, but explicitly did NOT buy the company.
Jensen Huang's statement was surgical: "While we are adding talented employees to our ranks and licensing Groq's IP, we are not acquiring Groq as a company."</p>
<p>That phrasing is the entire story. Because what Nvidia carved out of the deal tells you everything about why this happened.</p>
<p>Forget the AI doomer takes about a bubble forming, lets look into the actual reasons.</p>
<h2>What Nvidia Actually Bought (And What It Didn't)</h2>
<p>Nvidia acquired:</p>
<ul>
<li>All of Groq's intellectual property and patents</li>
<li>Non-exclusive licensing rights to Groq's inference technology</li>
<li>Jonathan Ross (CEO), Sunny Madra (President), and the entire senior leadership team</li>
</ul>
<p>Nvidia explicitly did NOT buy:</p>
<ul>
<li>GroqCloud (the cloud infrastructure business)</li>
</ul>
<p>GroqCloud continues as an independent company under CFO Simon Edwards.
This is Nvidia's largest acquisition ever (previous record was Mellanox at $7B in 2019), and they structured it to leave the actual operating business behind. That doesn't happen by accident.</p>
<h2>LPU vs TPU vs CPU: Why SRAM Matters</h2>
<p>To understand why Nvidia paid anything for Groq, you need to understand the architectural bet Ross made when he left Google.</p>
<p><strong>CPUs and GPUs</strong> are built around external DRAM/HBM (High Bandwidth Memory). Every compute operation requires shuttling data between the processor and off-chip memory. This works fine for general-purpose computing, but for inference workloads, that constant round-trip creates latency and energy overhead. GPUs evolved from graphics rendering, so they're optimized for parallel training workloads, not sequential inference.</p>
<p><strong>TPUs (Google's Tensor Processing Units)</strong> reduce some of this overhead with larger on-chip buffers and a systolic array architecture, but they still rely on HBM for model weights and activations. They're deterministic in execution but non-deterministic in memory access patterns.</p>
<p><strong>LPUs (Groq's Language Processing Units)</strong> take a different approach: massive on-chip SRAM instead of external DRAM/HBM. The entire model (for models that fit) lives in SRAM with 80 TB/s of bandwidth and 230 MB capacity per chip. No off-chip memory bottleneck. No dynamic scheduling. The architecture is entirely deterministic from compilation to execution. You know exactly what happens at each cycle on each chip at each moment.</p>
<p>This creates massive advantages for inference:</p>
<ul>
<li>Llama 2 7B: 750 tokens/sec (2048 token context)</li>
<li>Llama 2 70B: 300 tokens/sec (4096 token context)</li>
<li>Mixtral 8x7B: 480 tokens/sec (4096 token context)</li>
</ul>
<p>And 10x better energy efficiency because you're not constantly moving data across a memory bus.</p>
<p><img src="https://ossa-ma.github.io/images/sota_tps_chart.png" alt="SOTA model tokens/sec throughput on GPU inference">
<em>Compare this to SOTA model tokens/sec throughput on GPU inference</em></p>
<p>Serious trade off though, only 14GB of SRAM per rack means you can't run Llama 3.1 405B. And LPUs can't train models at all. This is an inference-only architecture with limited model size support.</p>
<p>But here's what makes this interesting: if DRAM/HBM prices continue climbing (DRAM has tripled in a year I should've gone all in DRAM in Jan I'm done with indexes), and if inference becomes the dominant AI workload (which it is), SRAM-based architectures become economically compelling despite the size limitations. Most production AI applications aren't running 405B models. They're running 7B-70B models that need low latency and high throughput.</p>
<h2>The $13.1B Premium and the Non-Traditional Structure</h2>
<p>Groq raised $750 million in September 2025 at a post-money valuation of $6.9 billion. Three months later on Xmas Eve, Nvidia paid $20 billion through a "non-exclusive licensing agreement" that acquired all IP and talent while explicitly NOT buying the company.</p>
<p>That's a $13.1 billion premium (3x the September valuation) for a company valued at 40x target revenue (double Anthropic's recent 20x multiple) with slashed projections (The Information reported Groq cut over $1B from 2025 revenue forecasts).</p>
<p>The structure is the story. Traditional M&amp;A would trigger:</p>
<ul>
<li>CFIUS review (given Saudi contracts)</li>
<li>Antitrust scrutiny (Nvidia's dominant position)</li>
<li>Shareholder votes and disclosure requirements</li>
<li>Multi-year regulatory review</li>
</ul>
<p>Non-exclusive licensing bypasses all of it. No acquisition means no CFIUS review. "Non-exclusive" means no monopoly concerns (anyone can license Groq's tech). No shareholder votes, minimal disclosure.</p>
<p>But in practice: Nvidia gets the IP (can integrate before anyone else), the talent (Ross + team can't work for competitors now), and the elimination of GroqCloud (will likely die without IP or leadership). The "non-exclusive" label is legal fiction. When you acquire all the IP and hire everyone who knows how to use it, exclusivity doesn't matter.</p>
<p>The question isn't just why Nvidia paid $13.1B more than market rate for technology they could build themselves (they have the PDK, volume, talent, infrastructure, and cash). The question is why they structured it this way.</p>
<p><strong>The $13.1B premium bought five things a traditional acquisition couldn't:</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>Regulatory arbitrage</strong>: Non-exclusive licensing avoids years of antitrust review. Structure the deal as IP licensing + talent acquisition, and regulators have no grounds to block it. This alone is worth billions in time and certainty.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Neutralizing Meta/Llama</strong>: The April 2025 partnership gave Groq distribution to millions of developers. If Llama + Groq became the default open-source inference stack, Nvidia's ecosystem gets commoditized. Kill the partnership before it scales.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Eliminating GroqCloud without inheriting Saudi contracts</strong>: Nvidia has invested in other cloud providers. GroqCloud was a competitor. Traditional acquisition would mean inheriting $1.5B worth of contracts to build AI infrastructure for Saudi Arabia, triggering CFIUS scrutiny. The carve-out kills GroqCloud while avoiding geopolitical entanglement.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Political access</strong>: Chamath makes ~$2B (Social Capital's ~10% stake). Sacks looks good (major AI deal under his watch as AI Czar). Nvidia gets favorable regulatory treatment from the Trump administration. Timing it for Christmas Eve ensures minimal media scrutiny of these connections.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Preempting other acquirers</strong>: Ross invented Google's TPU. If Google had acquired Groq and brought Ross back, they'd have the original TPU creator plus LPU IP. Amazon and Microsoft were also exploring alternatives to Nvidia GPUs. Better to pay $20B now than compete with Ross at Google/Amazon/Microsoft later.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Two speculative reasons worth considering:</strong></p>
<ol start="6">
<li>
<p><strong>Blocking Google/Amazon/Microsoft from partnering with Groq</strong>: Both are developing custom AI chips (Trainium, Maia). If either had hired Ross + team or licensed Groq's tech, Nvidia's inference dominance faces a real challenger. If Google had acquired Groq and brought Ross back, they'd have the original TPU inventor plus LPU IP.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Chiplet integration for future products</strong>: Nvidia might integrate LPU as a chiplet alongside GPUs in Blackwell or future architectures. Having Ross's team makes that possible. You can't integrate IP you don't own, and you can't build it without the people who invented it.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>That's how business works when regulation hasn't caught up to structural innovation. Nvidia paid $6.9B for technology and $13.1B to solve everything else using a deal structure that traditional antitrust can't touch.</p>
<h2>The Saudi Arabia Problem</h2>
<p>In February 2025, Saudi Arabia committed $1.5 billion to expand Groq's Dammam data center. The publicly stated goal was supporting SDAIA's ALLaM, Saudi Arabia's Arabic large language model. The actual goal was Vision 2030: positioning the Kingdom as an AI superpower.</p>
<p>Groq built the region's largest inference cluster in eight days in December 2024. From that Dammam facility, GroqCloud serves "nearly four billion people regionally adjacent to the KSA." This isn't API access. This is critical AI infrastructure for a nation-state, funded by the Public Investment Fund, processing inference workloads at national scale.</p>
<p>According to Ross in the Series E announcement, Groq powers Humain's services including the Humain chat product and supported OpenAI's GPT-OSS model release in Saudi Arabia. Groq operates 13 facilities across the US, Canada, Europe, and the Middle East. Ross noted that capacity expanded more than 10% in the month before the funding announcement and all of that capacity was already in use. Customers were asking for more capacity than Groq could satisfy.</p>
<p>That creates a CFIUS (Committee on Foreign Investment in the United States) problem. A U.S. chip company, venture-backed by American investors, building sovereign AI capability for Saudi Arabia. If Nvidia had acquired GroqCloud outright, they would inherit those contracts and the regulatory scrutiny that comes with them. Foreign investment reviews, export control questions, congressional inquiries about why an American company is providing cutting-edge AI to a Middle Eastern monarchy.</p>
<p>By carving out GroqCloud, Nvidia gets the technology and the talent without the geopolitical mess. The Saudi contracts stay with Edwards and the independent GroqCloud entity. Clean separation. No CFIUS entanglement.</p>
<h2>Who Actually Gets Paid (And Who Gets Left Behind)</h2>
<p>The Financial Times reported that "despite the loss of much of its leadership team, Groq said it will continue to operate as an independent company." That's corporate speak for: executives and VCs are cashing out while regular employees watch the company they built get hollowed out.</p>
<p>Here's how the $20B probably breaks down (we'll never know the exact numbers since Groq is private and this isn't a traditional acquisition):</p>
<p><strong>Who definitely wins:</strong></p>
<p><strong>VCs (Chamath, BlackRock, Neuberger Berman, Deutsche Telekom, etc.)</strong>: They own equity in Groq Inc. Depending on how the deal is structured, they get paid based on their ownership percentage. Social Capital's ~10% stake (after dilution) is worth $1.6-2.4B. BlackRock, Neuberger Berman, and other Series E investors get their cut. They're protected regardless of structure.</p>
<p><strong>Executives joining Nvidia (Ross, Madra, senior leadership)</strong>: They get:</p>
<ul>
<li>Retention packages from Nvidia (likely massive given the $20B deal size)</li>
<li>Sign-on bonuses</li>
<li>Accelerated vesting of any unvested Groq equity</li>
<li>New Nvidia equity compensation packages</li>
<li>Their existing Groq equity gets paid out at the $20B valuation</li>
</ul>
<p>Jensen Huang's email to Nvidia staff (obtained by the FT) said they're "adding talented employees to our ranks." When you're talent important enough to be mentioned in a $20B deal, you're getting paid.</p>
<p><strong>Who might get paid (depending on deal structure):</strong></p>
<p><strong>Regular Groq employees with vested equity</strong>: This is where it gets murky. There are three possible scenarios:</p>
<p><strong>Scenario 1: The IP licensing fee goes to Groq Inc.</strong>
If the $20B (or a significant portion) is structured as a licensing fee paid to Groq Inc. for the IP rights, that money gets distributed to all shareholders based on ownership percentage. Employees with vested stock options or RSUs get their pro-rata share. This is the best case for employees.</p>
<p>Example: Engineer with 0.01% fully vested equity gets $2M ($20B × 0.01%). Not bad for an engineer who's been there since 2018-2020.</p>
<p><strong>Scenario 2: Most of the $20B goes to retention packages</strong>
If the deal is structured so that the bulk of the money goes to retention/hiring packages for Ross, Madra, and the senior team joining Nvidia, with a smaller licensing fee to Groq Inc., employees get less. Maybe the split is $15B retention, $5B licensing fee. Now that same engineer with 0.01% gets $500K instead of $2M.</p>
<p><strong>Scenario 3: The IP licensing is separate from talent acquisition</strong>
Nvidia pays Groq Inc. for the IP (say $5-7B, roughly the Sept 2024 valuation), and separately pays Ross + team retention packages directly. Regular employees get their share of the IP licensing fee only. That same engineer might get $500-700K.</p>
<p><strong>The critical question</strong>: Is the $20B figure the total cost to Nvidia (including retention packages), or is it just the IP licensing fee? If it's total cost and most goes to retention, regular employees get scammed.</p>
<p><strong>Who definitely gets done over:</strong></p>
<p><strong>Employees staying at GroqCloud</strong>: These are the people who:</p>
<ul>
<li>Weren't important enough to be hired by Nvidia</li>
<li>Have equity tied to GroqCloud's future value</li>
<li>Just watched their CEO, President, and entire engineering leadership leave</li>
<li>Are now working for a company with no IP rights, no technical leadership, and no future</li>
</ul>
<p>Their equity is worthless. GroqCloud will wind down over 12-18 months. They'll either get laid off or jump ship to wherever they can land. They built the LPU architecture, contributed to the compiler stack, supported the infrastructure, and got nothing while Chamath made $2B.</p>
<h2>The All-In Connection</h2>
<p>This gets messier when you look at who was involved. Chamath Palihapitiya, through Social Capital, led Groq's initial $10 million investment in 2017 at a $25 million pre-money valuation. Social Capital secured 28.57% of the company and a board seat for Chamath.</p>
<p>David Sacks, Chamath's co-host on the All-In podcast, became Trump's AI and Crypto Czar in late 2024. In July 2025, Sacks co-authored "America's AI Action Plan," a White House strategy document positioning AI as a matter of national security. The plan called for exporting "the full AI technology stack to all countries willing to join America's AI alliance" while preventing adversarial nations from building independent AI capabilities.</p>
<p>Two months later at the All-In Summit in September 2025, Tareq Amin (CEO of HUMAIN, Saudi Arabia's state-backed AI company) presented Groq as "the American AI stack in action." This was seven months after the $1.5B Saudi deal.</p>
<p>Sunny Madra, Groq's President and COO, was actively promoting the All-In narrative during this period. He appeared on the All-In podcast in March 2024 to provide a "Groq update" and joined Sacks on "This Week in Startups" in November 2023. When Anthropic raised AI safety regulation concerns in October 2025, Madra publicly sided with Sacks, suggesting "one company is causing chaos for the entire industry" and echoing Sacks's accusation that Anthropic was engaged in "regulatory capture."</p>
<p>So you have Sacks pushing an "America First" AI policy from the White House while Chamath's portfolio company (where Madra is President) is building AI infrastructure for Saudi Arabia. Then Groq gets presented at the All-In Summit as an example of American AI leadership. Three months later, announced on Christmas Eve when media coverage is minimal, Nvidia pays $20 billion to clean up the geopolitical contradiction.</p>
<p>Chamath walks away with $1.6B to $2.4B. Sacks gets a major AI deal under his watch. Nvidia gets favorable regulatory treatment and eliminates multiple problems. The timing ensures minimal scrutiny of these connections.</p>
<h2>Chamath's $2 Billion Win vs. His SPAC Graveyard</h2>
<p>After dilution from raising $1.7 billion across Series C, D, and E rounds, Social Capital's stake in Groq was probably 8-12% by the time of the Nvidia deal. At a $20 billion exit, that's $1.6 billion to $2.4 billion.</p>
<p><img src="https://ossa-ma.github.io/images/victorian_chamath.jpg" alt="Chamath after using you as exit liquidity and bankrolling it into a 200x win for himself">
<em>Chamath after using you as exit liquidity and bankrolling it into a 200x win for himself</em></p>
<p>Why do I hate Chamath?</p>
<p>Let's look at the sh he dumped on retail with his abysmal SPAC track record:</p>
<ul>
<li>IPOA (Virgin Galactic): -98.5% since inception</li>
<li>IPOB (Opendoor): -62.9% (was -95% before a brief spike)</li>
<li>IPOC (Clover Health): -74.4%</li>
<li>IPOE (SoFi): +46% (still underperformed S&amp;P 500's +86%)</li>
</ul>
<p>Chamath personally dumped $213 million of Virgin Galactic stock before it crashed, using PIPE structures that let him exit while retail investors stayed locked up. In October 2025, when launching a new SPAC, he posted a warning telling retail investors not to buy it: "these vehicles are not ideal for most retail investors."</p>
<p>The Groq bet was classic venture capital: concentrated bet on an exceptional founder (Jonathan Ross, the engineer who invented Google's TPU) building non-obvious technology. Social Capital's 2017 internal memo projected a "High" exit scenario of $3.2 billion. They landed within range despite dilution.</p>
<p>But retail investors never got access to deals like Groq. They got Virgin Galactic. LOL.</p>
<h2>To Conclude</h2>
<p>Nvidia paid $20 billion for a company valued at $6.9 billion three months earlier, structured the deal to avoid traditional M&amp;A oversight, killed the cloud business without inheriting Saudi contracts, and enriched the exact people (Chamath, Sacks) who spent the last year promoting "American AI leadership" while cutting deals with foreign governments. The employees who built the technology either got hired by Nvidia or have been utterly shafted.</p>
<p>This was fun to look into. If you have any questions or comments, <a href="mailto:ossamachaib.cs@gmail.com">shout me</a>.</p>
<hr>
<h2>Sources</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/12/24/nvidia-buying-ai-chip-startup-groq-for-about-20-billion-biggest-deal.html">Nvidia Acquiring Groq for $20B</a></li>
<li><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/12/24/nvidia-acquires-ai-chip-challenger-groq-for-20b-report-says/">Nvidia-Groq Deal Structure</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2024-09-03/ai-chip-startup-groq-raises-750-million-at-6-9-billion-value">Groq Series E: $750M at $6.9B Valuation</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.techpowerup.com/319286/groq-lpu-ai-inference-chip-is-rivaling-major-players-like-nvidia-amd-and-intel">Groq LPU Architecture</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.webpronews.com/the-deterministic-bet-how-groqs-lpu-is-rewriting-the-rules-of-ai-inference-speed/">Groq Deterministic Inference</a></li>
<li><a href="https://groq.com/blog/saudi-arabia-announces-1-5-billion-expansion-to-fuel-ai-powered-economy-with-groq">Saudi Arabia $1.5B Groq Investment</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.datacenterdynamics.com/en/news/groq-secures-15bn-from-saudi-arabia-to-expand-ai-inference-infrastructure-in-the-region/">Groq Dammam Data Center</a></li>
<li><a href="https://fortune.com/2025/07/23/all-in-podcast-trump-ai-action-plan-david-sacks-jd-vance-jensen-huang/">America's AI Action Plan</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/articles/2025/07/white-house-unveils-americas-ai-action-plan/">White House AI Action Plan</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.benzinga.com/markets/ipos/25/08/47213886/chamath-palihapitiya-returns-to-spacs-past-18-deals-investments-average-loss-of-14">Chamath SPAC Performance</a></li>
<li><a href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/chamath-palihapitiya-crumbling-spac-empire-100748788.html">Chamath Virgin Galactic Stock Dump</a></li>
<li><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/10/01/chamath-warns-retail-investors-to-avoid-his-new-spac/">Chamath SPAC Warning</a></li>
<li><a href="https://groq.com/newsroom/meta-and-groq-collaborate-to-deliver-fast-inference-for-the-official-llama-api">Meta-Groq Partnership</a></li>
<li><a href="https://groq.com/newsroom/groq-powers-humain-one--real-time-ai-operating-system-for-enterprise">HUMAIN Groq Partnership</a></li>
<li><a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/e169-elon-sues-openai-apples-decline-tiktok-ban-bitcoin/id1502871393?i=1000648540648">Sunny Madra All-In Appearance</a></li>
<li><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/10/21/anthropic-ceo-claps-back-after-trump-officials-accuse-firm-of-ai-fear-mongering/">David Sacks Anthropic Criticism</a></li>
</ul></article></section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Janet Jackson had the power to crash laptop computers (2022) (267 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://devblogs.microsoft.com/oldnewthing/20220816-00/?p=106994</link>
            <guid>46403291</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 17:16:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/oldnewthing/20220816-00/?p=106994">https://devblogs.microsoft.com/oldnewthing/20220816-00/?p=106994</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46403291">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="single-wrapper">
    
    <article data-clarity-region="article" id="post-106994">
        <div data-bi-area="body_article" data-bi-id="post_page_body_article">
            <p>A colleague of mine shared a story from Windows XP product support. A major computer manufacturer discovered that playing the music video for Janet Jackson’s “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhythm_Nation">Rhythm Nation</a>” would crash certain models of laptops. I would not have wanted to be in the laboratory that they must have set up to investigate this problem. Not an artistic judgement.</p>
<p>One discovery during the investigation is that playing the music video also crashed some of their competitors’ laptops.</p>
<p>And then they discovered something extremely weird: Playing the music video on one laptop caused a laptop sitting nearby to crash, even though that other laptop wasn’t playing the video!</p>
<p>What’s going on?</p>
<p>It turns out that the song contained one of the natural resonant frequencies for the model of 5400 rpm laptop hard drives that they and other manufacturers used.</p>
<p>The manufacturer worked around the problem by adding a custom filter in the audio pipeline that detected and removed the offending frequencies during audio playback.</p>
<p>And I’m sure they put a digital version of a “Do not remove” sticker on that audio filter. (Though I’m worried that in the many years since the workaround was added, nobody remembers why it’s there. Hopefully, their laptops are not still carrying this audio filter to protect against damage to a model of hard drive they are no longer using.)</p>
<p>And of course, no story about natural resonant frequencies can pass without a reference to <a href="https://www.history.com/this-day-in-history/tacoma-narrows-bridge-collapses"> the collapse of the Tacoma Narrows Bridge in 1940</a>.¹</p>
<p><b>Related</b>: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tDacjrSCeq4"> Shouting in the Datacenter</a>.</p>
<p><b>Bonus chatter</b>: <a href="https://twitter.com/WindowsDocs/status/1558114944738103297"> Video version of this story</a> and a <a href="https://twitter.com/WindowsDocs/status/1558115433449852929"> Twitter poll</a>.</p>
<p>Also, <a href="https://twitter.com/osterman">Larry Osterman</a> had a similar experience with <a href="https://twitter.com/osterman/status/1558676353196494850"> a specific game that crashed a prototype PC</a>.</p>
<p><b>Follow-up</b>: <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/oldnewthing/20220920-00/?p=107201"> Janet Jackson had the power to crash laptop computers, follow-up</a>.</p>
<p>¹ <b>Follow-up 2</b>: Yes, I know that the Tacoma Narrows Bridge collapse was not the result of resonance, but I felt I had to drop the reference to forestall the “You forgot to mention the Tacoma Narrows Bridge!” comments.</p>
        </div><!-- .entry-content -->

        <!-- AI Disclaimer -->
            </article>
    
</div><div><!-- Author section -->
            <h2>Author</h2>
            <div><div><p><img src="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/oldnewthing/wp-content/uploads/sites/38/2019/02/RaymondChen_5in-150x150.jpg" alt="Raymond Chen"></p></div><p>Raymond has been involved in the evolution of Windows for more than 30 years. In 2003, he began a Web site known as The Old New Thing which has grown in popularity far beyond his wildest imagination, a development which still gives him the heebie-jeebies. The Web site spawned a book, coincidentally also titled The Old New Thing (Addison Wesley 2007). He occasionally appears on the Windows Dev Docs Twitter account to tell stories which convey no useful information.</p></div>        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[USD share as global reserve currency drops to lowest since 1994 (214 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://wolfstreet.com/2025/12/26/status-of-the-us-dollar-as-global-reserve-currency-usd-share-drops-to-lowest-since-1994/</link>
            <guid>46403276</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 17:14:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://wolfstreet.com/2025/12/26/status-of-the-us-dollar-as-global-reserve-currency-usd-share-drops-to-lowest-since-1994/">https://wolfstreet.com/2025/12/26/status-of-the-us-dollar-as-global-reserve-currency-usd-share-drops-to-lowest-since-1994/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46403276">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
		    <h2><strong><span>Central Banks diversify their holdings into dozens of smaller “non-traditional reserve currencies.”</span></strong></h2>
<h4>By&nbsp;<a href="https://wolfstreet.com/author/wolf-richter/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wolf Richter</a>&nbsp;for&nbsp;<a href="https://wolfstreet.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">WOLF STREET</a>.</h4>
<p>The share of USD-denominated assets held by other central banks dropped to 56.9% of total foreign exchange reserves in Q3, the lowest since 1994, from 57.1% in Q2 and 58.5% in Q1, according to the IMF’s new data on Currency Composition of Official Foreign Exchange Reserves.</p>
<p>USD-denominated foreign exchange reserves include US Treasury securities, US mortgage-backed securities (MBS), US agency securities, US corporate bonds, and other USD-denominated assets held by central banks other than the Fed.</p>
<p>Excluded are any central bank’s assets denominated in its own currency, such as the Fed’s Treasury securities or the ECB’s euro-denominated securities.</p>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" src="https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-USD-share-quarterly.png" alt="" width="952" height="769" srcset="https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-USD-share-quarterly.png 952w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-USD-share-quarterly-560x452.png 560w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-USD-share-quarterly-768x620.png 768w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-USD-share-quarterly-260x210.png 260w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-USD-share-quarterly-160x129.png 160w" sizes="(max-width: 952px) 100vw, 952px"></p>
<p>It’s not that foreign central banks dumped US-dollar-denominated assets, such as Treasury securities. They did not. They added a little to their holdings. But they added more assets denominated in other currencies, particularly a gaggle of smaller currencies whose combined share has surged, while central banks’ holdings of USD-denominated assets haven’t changed much for a decade, and so the percentage share of those USD assets continued to decline.</p>
<p>As the dollar’s share declines toward the 50% line, the dollar would still be by far the largest reserve currency, as all other currencies&nbsp;<em>combined</em>&nbsp;would weigh as much as the dollar. But it does have consequences.</p>
<h3><strong>Why is having the top reserve currency important for the US?</strong></h3>
<p>Foreign central banks buying USD-denominated assets, such as Treasury securities, helps push up prices and push down yields of those assets. Being the dominant reserve currency had the effect of helping the US borrow more cheaply to fund its huge twin deficits – the trade deficit and the budget deficit – and thereby has enabled the US to run those huge twin deficits for decades. At some point, this continued decline as a reserve currency, as it reduces demand for USD debt, would make the trade deficit and the budget deficit more difficult to sustain.</p>
<p>The dollar’s share had already been below 50% before, in 1990 and 1991, after a long plunge from the peak in 1977 (share of 85.5%). This plunge accompanied a deep crisis in the US with sky-high inflation and interest rates, and four recessions over those years, including the nasty double-dip recession. Central banks lost confidence in the Fed’s willingness or ability to do what it takes to get this inflation under control that had washed over the US in three ever larger waves.</p>
<p>The dotted line in the chart below indicates the 50%-share. The dollar’s share bottomed out at 46% in 1991, by which time the Fed had brought inflation under control, and soon, central banks began loading up on dollar-assets.</p>
<p>Then came the euro, which turned into the next set-back for the dollar, but not nearly as much as European politicians had promised when pushing the euro through the system; they were talking about parity with the dollar. That talk ended with the Euro Debt Crisis that began in 2009.</p>
<p>Then, over the past 10 years, came dozens of smaller “non-traditional reserve currencies,” as the IMF calls them.</p>
<p>The chart shows the dollar’s share at the end of each year, except 2025 where it shows the share in Q3:</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-USD-share-long.png" alt="" width="1049" height="813" srcset="https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-USD-share-long.png 1049w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-USD-share-long-560x434.png 560w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-USD-share-long-1024x794.png 1024w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-USD-share-long-768x595.png 768w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-USD-share-long-260x202.png 260w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-USD-share-long-160x124.png 160w" sizes="(max-width: 1049px) 100vw, 1049px"></p>
<h3><strong>But they didn’t actually dump USD-denominated securities.</strong></h3>
<p>Foreign central banks increased their holdings of USD-denominated assets by a hair in Q3 to $7.4 trillion, the third increase in a row.</p>
<p>Since mid-2014, despite some sharp ups and downs, their holdings of USD-assets have remained essentially flat.</p>
<p>So, what has caused the percentage share of USD assets to decline over the years is the growth of foreign exchange reserves denominated in other currencies, particularly many smaller currencies, as central banks have been diversifying their growing pile of foreign exchange assets.</p>
<p>The chart below shows foreign central banks’ holdings of USD-denominated assets – US Treasury securities, US MBS, US agency securities, US corporate bonds, etc. – in trillions of dollars:</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-USD-level.png" alt="" width="955" height="771" srcset="https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-USD-level.png 955w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-USD-level-560x452.png 560w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-USD-level-768x620.png 768w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-USD-level-260x210.png 260w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-USD-level-160x129.png 160w" sizes="(max-width: 955px) 100vw, 955px"></p>
<h3><strong>The top foreign exchange reserves by currency.</strong></h3>
<p>Central banks’ holdings of foreign exchange reserves in all currencies, and expressed in USD, rose to $13.0 trillion in Q3.</p>

<p>Top holdings, expressed in USD:</p>
<ol>
<li>USD assets: $7.41 trillion</li>
<li>Euro assets (EUR): $2.65 trillion</li>
<li>Yen assets (YEN): $0.76 trillion</li>
<li>British pound assets (GBP): $0.58 trillion</li>
<li>Canadian dollar assets (CAD): $0.35 trillion</li>
<li>Australian dollar assets (AUD): $0.27 trillion</li>
<li>Chinese renminbi (RMB) assets: $0.25 trillion</li>
</ol>
<p>The euro’s share, #2,&nbsp;has been around 20% since 2015. Before the Euro Debt Crisis, it was on an upward trajectory and had already risen to nearly 25%.</p>
<p>The rest of the reserve currencies are the colorful spaghetti at the bottom of the chart (more in a moment). Combined, they have gained share over the years, at the expense of the dollar, while the euro’s share has remained roughly stable since 2015.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-all.png" alt="" width="980" height="787" srcset="https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-all.png 980w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-all-560x450.png 560w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-all-768x617.png 768w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-all-260x209.png 260w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-all-160x128.png 160w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 980px) 100vw, 980px"></p>
<h3><strong>The rise of the “non-traditional” reserve currencies</strong>.</h3>
<p>The chart below takes a magnifying glass to the colorful spaghetti at the bottom of the chart above.</p>
<p>The soaring red line shows the combined surge of assets denominated in dozens of smaller “nontraditional reserve currencies,” as the IMF calls them. Combined, they reached a share of 5.6%, just below the yen-denominated assets (5.8%).</p>
<p>But the share of the RMB (yellow) has been declining since Q1 2022, and its share is now back where it had been in 2019, amid ongoing capital controls, convertibility issues, and a slew of other issues.</p>
<p>In other words, the USD and the RMB both have given up share to the “non-traditional reserve currencies” as other central banks have been diversifying away from assets denominated in USD and RMB.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-other_detail.png" alt="" width="1031" height="827" srcset="https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-other_detail.png 1031w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-other_detail-560x449.png 560w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-other_detail-1024x821.png 1024w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-other_detail-768x616.png 768w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-other_detail-260x209.png 260w, https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Global-Reserve-Currencies-12-25-2025-other_detail-160x128.png 160w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1031px) 100vw, 1031px"></p>
<p>In case you missed my update on a slightly less ugly situation: <a href="https://wolfstreet.com/2025/12/24/us-government-interest-payments-to-tax-receipts-average-interest-rate-on-the-debt-and-debt-to-gdp-ratio-in-q3-2025/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">US Government Interest Payments to Tax Receipts, Average Interest Rate on the Debt, and Debt-to-GDP Ratio in Q3 2025</a></p>
<p><i><strong>Enjoy reading WOLF STREET and want to support it? You can donate. I appreciate it immensely. Click on the mug to find out how:</strong></i></p>
<p>
<a href="https://wolfstreet.com/how-to-donate-to-wolf-street/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/BeerMug2.jpg" alt="" width="100" height="115"></a>
</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://wolfstreet.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/placeholder2.png" alt="" width="26" height="65"></p>
<h3><strong>WOLF STREET FEATURE: Daily Market Insights by Chris Vermeulen, Chief Investment Officer, <a href="https://thetechnicaltraders.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">TheTechnicalTraders.com</a>.</strong></h3>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" title="New Trade Signal Issued - Stock Indices &amp; Precious Metals in Holiday Rally Mode" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Av5ZQvNB100?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>

	    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Gpg.fail (349 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://gpg.fail</link>
            <guid>46403200</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 17:05:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://gpg.fail">https://gpg.fail</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46403200">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><!----> <p><span>"in the hurry of leaving i forgot the sites src at home, sorry, had to rewrite the whole thing. expect a nicer site by tomorrow. im patching as we speak."</span> <br> <span>-  crackticker (&lt;- to blame)</span></p> <ol><!--[--><li><a href="https://gpg.fail/detached">Multiple Plaintext Attack on Detached PGP Signatures in GnuPG</a></li><li><a href="https://gpg.fail/filename">GnuPG Accepts Path Separators and Path Traversals in Literal Data "Filename" Field</a></li><li><a href="https://gpg.fail/formfeed">Cleartext Signature Plaintext Truncated for Hash Calculation</a></li><li><a href="https://gpg.fail/malleability">Encrypted message malleability checks are incorrectly enforced causing plaintext recovery attacks</a></li><li><a href="https://gpg.fail/memcpy">Memory Corruption in ASCII-Armor Parsing</a></li><li><a href="https://gpg.fail/minisign">Trusted comment injection (minisign)</a></li><li><a href="https://gpg.fail/notdash">Cleartext Signature Forgery in the NotDashEscaped header implementation in GnuPG</a></li><li><a href="https://gpg.fail/notsoclear">OpenPGP Cleartext Signature Framework Susceptible to Format Confusion</a></li><li><a href="https://gpg.fail/noverify">GnuPG Output Fails To Distinguish Signature Verification Success From Message Content</a></li><li><a href="https://gpg.fail/nullbyte">Cleartext Signature Forgery in GnuPG</a></li><li><a href="https://gpg.fail/polyglot">Radix64 Line-Truncation Enabling Polyglot Attacks</a></li><li><a href="https://gpg.fail/sha1">GnuPG may downgrade digest algorithm to SHA1 during key signature checking</a></li><li><a href="https://gpg.fail/trust">GnuPG Trust Packet Parsing Enables Adding Arbitrary Subkeys</a></li><li><a href="https://gpg.fail/trustcomment">Trusted comment Injection (minisign)</a></li><!--]--></ol> <h2>VOD:</h2> <!----><!----></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Employee commits suicide after MongoDB fired her during mental health leave (169 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.linkedin.com/posts/gsurman_our-beloved-irreplaceable-daughter-annie-activity-7407842359826120704-kFaq</link>
            <guid>46403128</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 16:57:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/gsurman_our-beloved-irreplaceable-daughter-annie-activity-7407842359826120704-kFaq">https://www.linkedin.com/posts/gsurman_our-beloved-irreplaceable-daughter-annie-activity-7407842359826120704-kFaq</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46403128">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main-content" role="main">
      <section>
                <h2>
Greg Surman’s Post</h2>
<!---->
                
    

    
      

    <article data-activity-urn="urn:li:activity:7407842359826120704" data-featured-activity-urn="urn:li:activity:7407842359826120704" data-attributed-urn="urn:li:share:7407842358471536640">
<!---->
      
<!---->        

      

      
            
            
  <p dir="ltr" data-test-id="main-feed-activity-card__commentary">Our beloved, irreplaceable daughter Annie should’ve been celebrating her 30th birthday this week. Instead, we’re left marking that milestone without her -- remembering all that she was and grieving all that should have been.

Annie died by suicide last year, after being fired by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/mongodbinc?trk=public_post-text" target="_self" data-tracking-control-name="public_post-text" data-tracking-will-navigate="">MongoDB</a> while she was on disability leave. 
 
Yesterday, we filed a legal complaint against <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/mongodbinc?trk=public_post-text" target="_self" data-tracking-control-name="public_post-text" data-tracking-will-navigate="">MongoDB</a>, seeking accountability for Annie’s wrongful termination and wrongful death. The complaint alleges as follows:

Annie was on leave receiving intensive mental health treatment when MongoDB demanded her immediate return to work. She asked for an extension to complete her treatment, or at the least a short period to consult with her medical providers about whether and how she might be able to return to work before the treatment was completed. Instead, MongoDB terminated her health insurance and then fired her in violation of the Americans with Disabilities Act and the New York State and City Human Rights Laws. Shortly afterward, Annie took her own life.

An extension of Annie’s leave would have cost MongoDB nothing. We made it clear that they did not need to pay her or hold her job open for her. We just asked them not to fire her while she was in such a vulnerable state, as we feared that would result in tragedy. We just wanted a little more time to get her stabilized.

We understand MongoDB may have told some of Annie’s colleagues that she quit. That is not true. MongoDB fired her.

We’re pursuing this case to set the record straight and to help ensure that powerful companies like MongoDB do not continue to violate the rights of their employees.</p>



        

        
            
      
    
    
    

      <ul data-test-id="feed-images-content">
              <li data-test-id="feed-images-content__list-item" data-position="0">
                  
<!----><!---->              </li>
      </ul>
<!---->  
  
                  

      
          
        

      
          
        

      
            
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    

    
    

      
  
  
        

      
                
    
    
    

    
  
                      

      
              
            

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    
    
    

      
  
  
            

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    
    
    

      
  
  
            

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    
    
    

      
  
  
            

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    
    
    

      
  
  
            

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    
    
    

      
  
  
            

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    
    
    

      
  
  
            

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    
    
    

      
  
  
            

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    
    
    

      
  
  
            

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    
    
    

      
  
  
              <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/signup/cold-join?session_redirect=https%3A%2F%2Fwww%2Elinkedin%2Ecom%2Fposts%2Fgsurman_our-beloved-irreplaceable-daughter-annie-activity-7407842359826120704-kFaq&amp;trk=public_post_see-more-comments" data-test-id="main-feed-activity-card-with-comments__see-more-comments" data-tracking-control-name="public_post_see-more-comments" data-tracking-will-navigate="">
                See more comments
              </a>
      
        

      
              

    
    
    
    
    
    

    
  
        
    </article>
  
      
  
  
            </section>
      <section>

            <h2>
              Explore content categories
            </h2>

<!---->
        
      </section>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Nvidia just paid $20B for a company that missed its revenue target by 75% (207 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.drjoshcsimmons.com/p/nvidia-just-paid-20-billion-for-a</link>
            <guid>46403041</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 16:47:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.drjoshcsimmons.com/p/nvidia-just-paid-20-billion-for-a">https://blog.drjoshcsimmons.com/p/nvidia-just-paid-20-billion-for-a</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46403041">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><p>If you’ve heard “Grok” thrown around lately, you’re probably thinking of Elon’s chatbot from xAI. We’re not talking about that one. That model isn’t particularly good, but its whole value prop is being politically incorrect so you can get it to say edgy things.</p><p>The company Nvidia bought is Groq (with a Q). Totally different beast.</p><p><span>If you’ve used any high quality LLM, you’ve noticed it takes </span><em>a while to generate a response.</em><span> Especially for something rapid fire like a conversation, you want high quality AND speed. But speed is often what gets sacrificed. There’s always that “thinking... gathering my notes... taking some time to form the best response” delay.</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!7ppM!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9a099433-4de1-45a1-9804-cfcede6b28da_5064x2704.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!7ppM!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9a099433-4de1-45a1-9804-cfcede6b28da_5064x2704.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!7ppM!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9a099433-4de1-45a1-9804-cfcede6b28da_5064x2704.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!7ppM!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9a099433-4de1-45a1-9804-cfcede6b28da_5064x2704.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!7ppM!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9a099433-4de1-45a1-9804-cfcede6b28da_5064x2704.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!7ppM!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9a099433-4de1-45a1-9804-cfcede6b28da_5064x2704.png" width="1456" height="777" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/9a099433-4de1-45a1-9804-cfcede6b28da_5064x2704.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:777,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:3954485,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://blog.drjoshcsimmons.com/i/182706966?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9a099433-4de1-45a1-9804-cfcede6b28da_5064x2704.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!7ppM!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9a099433-4de1-45a1-9804-cfcede6b28da_5064x2704.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!7ppM!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9a099433-4de1-45a1-9804-cfcede6b28da_5064x2704.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!7ppM!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9a099433-4de1-45a1-9804-cfcede6b28da_5064x2704.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!7ppM!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9a099433-4de1-45a1-9804-cfcede6b28da_5064x2704.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a><figcaption>My default Zellij layout so I can parallelize Claude Code tasks.</figcaption></figure></div><p><span>Groq specialized in hardware and software that makes this way faster. They created a new type of chip called an LPU (Language Processing Unit). It’s based on an ASIC, an application specific integrated circuit. If that’s confusing, don’t worry about it. It’s just </span><strong>a processor that does a specific type of task really well.</strong></p><p>So imagine you’re talking to Gemini and it takes a couple seconds to respond. Now imagine it responded instantly, like 10 or 100 times faster. That’s the problem Groq was solving.</p><p>To go one level deeper on LPUs versus GPUs (the processors most LLMs run on, typically Nvidia cards): those GPU calculations have to access a lot of things in memory. Nvidia’s chips depend on HBM, high bandwidth memory. But LPUs use something called SRAM that’s much faster to reference.</p><p>Think about it like this. Your wife has a grocery list for you. You go to the store but forget the list. Every time you’re in an aisle, you have to call her on the phone: “Hey, do I need anything from the bread aisle?” Get the bread. Put the phone down. Go to the next aisle. “Hey, do I need anything from canned goods?” And so on through produce, meat, pick up the beer, check out, get home. Very inefficient.</p><p>Groq’s approach is like you just took the list to the store. Get to a new aisle, look at the list. Next aisle, look at the list. Much faster than a phone call.</p><p>That’s the key difference. Nvidia GPUs are phoning out every time they hit a new aisle. Groq’s LPUs mean the shopper has the list in their pocket.</p><p>Groq’s main offering is GroqCloud. An engineer like me isn’t going to go out and buy an LPU (I don’t even know if they’re commercially available). What I’m going to do is, if I need lightning fast response in an application I’m building, I’ll use GroqCloud. That inference happens at an extremely fast rate, running on LPUs in a data center somewhere.</p><p>Their value prop is: fast, cheap, low energy.</p><p>Where they’ve been falling short is they mostly use open source models. Llama, Mistral, GPT-OSS (OpenAI’s open source offering). These are decent models, but nowhere near the quality of something like Anthropic’s Opus 4.5 or Gemini 3 Pro.</p><p>Groq positioned themselves for hardcore use cases where milliseconds matter. One of their big industry fits is real time data analysis for Formula 1. When your driver’s out there on the track, you don’t have time to send a query to Gemini and wait 20 to 30 seconds to figure out if you should pit this guy for new tires this lap. You want something like Groq which does pretty good analysis, really really really fast.</p><p>This is insider baseball you’re going to miss from mainstream news headlines. The media is paying attention to Grok (Elon’s chatbot), not Groq (the chip company). This isn’t a conspiracy, it’s just that the only people aware of Groq are software developers and tech nuts like me.</p><p>This is a canary in the coal mine for worse things to come in 2026.</p><p>About a year ago, Groq announced a $1.5 billion infrastructure investment deal with Saudi Arabia. They also secured a $750 million Series D funding round. These are crazy multiples even for a software company that’s somewhat leveraged in hardware. Bubble level projections.</p><p>To visualize $1.5 billion: if you cashed that check out in $100 bills and stacked them one on top of another, it would reach a five story building. For ordinary plebeians like us, at the average US salary of around $75K, you’d need to work 20,000 years to earn that.</p><p>At that time, the company was valued at $2 billion. Hello bubble.</p><p><span>Then in maybe one of the best rug pulls of all time, in July they quietly changed their revenue projections to $500 million.</span><span data-state="closed"><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-1-182706966" href="https://blog.drjoshcsimmons.com/p/nvidia-just-paid-20-billion-for-a#footnote-1-182706966" target="_self" rel="">1</a></span><span> A 75% cut in four months. I’ve never seen anything like that since the 2008 financial crisis.</span></p><p data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2po-s2yOCcg&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Prefer to Watch the Video&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:null,&quot;class&quot;:null}" data-component-name="ButtonCreateButton"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2po-s2yOCcg" rel=""><span>Prefer to Watch the Video</span></a></p><p>This was a company valued at $2 billion, enough that the government of Saudi Arabia was investing at that valuation. Then they took a 75% haircut four months later without anything major happening.</p><p>If it can happen to Groq, who else can it happen to? Nvidia? Intel?</p><p>The rumors started flying on Christmas Eve. Confirmed the 26th: Nvidia will be buying Groq, their key product line, and key personnel including the CEO, for $20 billion.</p><p><strong>Let’s walk through that again:</strong></p><ul><li><p><strong>February: $2 billion valuation</strong></p></li><li><p><strong>July: Down to $500 million</strong></p></li><li><p><strong>December: Nvidia buys them for $20 billion after they took a 75% haircut</strong></p></li></ul><p>What is going on? This is a bubble.</p><p>The only explanation is this is a fear purchase. Groq was promising faster, cheaper, more efficient, less electricity use for their chips. But they couldn’t scale fast enough to compete with the vendor lock in and buddy system Nvidia has going.</p><p>Nvidia’s buying them with their insanely inflated war chest. They don’t want a chunk taken out of their market share. They can’t afford to take that chance. So it’s like they’re just saying: “Shut up, take the $20 billion, walk away from this project.”</p><p>This is a sign that in order to succeed, Nvidia needs a monopoly on the market. Otherwise they would not pay ten times the company’s valuation that was then decreased by 75%. This is a desperate move to consolidate the market into “you have to go with us.”</p><p>Saudi Arabia didn’t keep that $1.5 billion sitting around. They redirected it to Nvidia and AMD instead. Nvidia still gets paid ofc.</p><p><span>Smaller competitors like Cerebras and Inflection, doing things in Groq’s space or exploring different architectures for AI inference, are canceling IPOs, dropping like flies, seeking emergency funding. The chatter I’m hearing from VCs and friends in that world? </span><strong>Ain’t nobody buying it right now.</strong></p><p>Google made their own chip. Microsoft and Amazon are racing to make competition chips that run on less electricity, are more efficient, faster. But no matter what anybody does, the market is consolidating around the Nvidia monopoly for AI hardware. Engineers like me and architects at large enterprises are trying to escape this. Once they consolidate enough of the market, they can set their price for chips and usage. If you don’t own them, you go through Oracle or some cloud computing service, and they can charge whatever they want because there will be no competitors. Even a competitor having a rough time but getting some traction? They just buy them out for $20 billion because with this monopoly going, that’s pocket change.</p><p>$20 billion is a rounding error to Nvidia.</p><p><strong>The AI infrastructure boom ran on one large errant assumption: that power is cheap and plentiful. </strong><span>That assumption was very, very wrong.</span></p><p><span>We’ve seen parts of the power grid fail, go unmaintained. </span><a href="https://www.palladiummag.com/2023/06/01/complex-systems-wont-survive-the-competence-crisis/" rel="">There’s a great article on Palladium called “The Competency Crisis” that explains some of what’s going on in the US right now.</a><span> Electricity is now the bottleneck. It’s the constraint. Too expensive or you can’t get enough of it. Who’s paying these costs? The tech companies aren’t. Trump is meeting with Jensen Huang, with Sam Altman. He hasn’t been over my place lately. He hasn’t invited you to the White House to talk about how you can’t afford groceries and eggs cost three times what they did a few years ago.</span></p><p>No.</p><p><strong>You and I are going to pay to subsidize the electricity constraints.</strong></p><p>US data centers are using about 4% of all electricity right now. If growth continues at the same rate, in ten years they’ll use 9%. Almost one tenth of all electricity generated in the US.</p><p>I’m not much of an environmentalist. But even someone like me, pretty jaded to some amount of waste because of industrialization, something like this actually makes my stomach turn. In places with lots of data centers, AI heavy regions, they’re experiencing about a 250% increase in energy costs compared to just five years ago. That’s huge. Even compared to grocery costs, which are out of control. At least with food you have alternatives. Red meat too expensive? Buy chicken. Chicken too expensive? Buy eggs. But electricity? You have to run electricity. It’s a public utility. You can’t just “use a lot less” when your bill goes up 2.5x.</p><p>Let me walk you through what happens. Some business development guy from Oracle wants to build a new data center in Rural America. A year before it’s even built, they meet with city officials, maybe the governor. They grease the right people. Get legislation passed with the utility companies that says they’ll pay a preferential rate for electricity because they’re going to use a shit ton.</p><p>They’re Oracle or Nvidia, they’re good for it. They pay five years upfront. Then the utility decides what to do with the rest of the electricity. The grid is strained. They want everyone else to use less. They can’t just tell them to use less, so they keep raising the price until naturally you just can’t afford to use more.</p><p>You turn the lights off. Turn the TV off. Get those LED bulbs that disrupt your sleep. Do everything to keep electricity costs down. But you and I are left holding the bag. The data center folks aren’t paying for that, they paid upfront at a preferential rate.</p><p>Senate Democrats are allegedly investigating this. I’ll believe it when I see it. These tech companies have their hooks so far into influential politicians. It’s a vote grab. I’d be happy to be wrong about that, but I know I’m not going to be.</p><p>I talked about this in my last piece on the AI bubble. This computer communism that’s going on, pricing you out of personal computing, keeping it all in the family of these tech companies. But with the Groq deal confirmed, it’s gone one step further. Nvidia is not just selling chips anymore. They are lending money to customers who buy the chips. They are artificially inflating demand.</p><p>It’s like if I run a small grocery store and I need to show good signal to investors that I’m bringing cash in the door. So I go downtown during farmer’s market and give everybody a $20 voucher to use at my store. I take a wholesale hit when they come in and buy stuff. But what I can show is: “Hey, people are coming in and spending money. Look at the revenue. Give me more venture capital money.”</p><p>This can’t work infinitely, for the same reason any perpetual motion machine can’t work.</p><p><span>Back in September, Nvidia announced a $100 billion investment in OpenAI. Coming through in $10 billion tranches over time. And it’s not equity, it’s lease agreements for Nvidia’s chips. Literally paying them to pay themselves.There’s probably some tax shenanigans going on there since they’re typically offering $xxx in </span><em>leases of their chips</em><span> to the company they’re “lending” to. Assuming they do this in part because the depreciation on the physical asset (the chips) can be written off on their taxes somehow. They’re essentially incentivizing another person to use them with money. Even OpenAI’s CFO has admitted, quote: “Most of the money will go back to Nvidia.”</span></p><p>They’re playing both sides. In the OpenAI case, they’re financing software that uses their chips. But they’re also getting their hooks into data centers.</p><p>CoreWeave: they have something like 7% share in the company. Worth $3 billion. That’s funded by GPU revenue from CoreWeave.</p><p>Lambda: another data center operator. That’s a $1.3 billion spending deal. Renting Nvidia’s own chips back from them.</p><p>They’ve pledged to invest £2 billion across British startups, which of course are going to go back to Nvidia chips one way or another.</p><p>In 2024, they invested about $1 billion across startups and saw a $24 billion return in chip spend. They 24x’d their billion dollar investment in one year. Nvidia has more power than the Fed right now. More power than the president over the economy. They have their hand on the knob of the economy. They can choose how fast or slow they want it to go. If the Nvidia cash machine stops printing, if they stop funding startups, data centers, hardware companies, software companies, that whole part of the economy slows way down and maybe crashes if investors get spooked.</p><p>I’m waiting for somebody to blow the whistle on this. I’m not a finance guy, so it’s strange I’m even talking about it. But their entire success story for the next couple years hinges on their $100 billion investment in OpenAI, which they’re expecting to bring back about $300 billion in chip purchases.</p><p><span>It’s vendor financing. It’s sweetening the pot on your own deals. </span><strong>I cannot believe more people are not talking about this.</strong></p><p>OpenAI, the leader of this space, the company whose CEO Sam Altman is invited to the White House numerous times, probably has a direct line to Trump, a lot of the economy hinges on this guy’s strategy, opinions, and public statements.</p><p><strong>And he runs a company that is not profitable. </strong><span>Actually insane if you think about it. All he’s done with that company, from an economics point of view, is rack up debt. Spent more than he’s earned.</span></p><p>By that metric, I’m richer than Sam Altman. Not in net worth. But if I consider myself a business and the fact that I bring in any salary at all, even a dollar a year, that would make me earn more than Sam Altman, who has only lost money. In the next few years, they’re expected to burn something like $75 billion a year. Just set that money on fire. I have a credit card with no preset spending limit, but I assume if I run up a $75 billion charge it’s going to get denied. By their projections, they think they’ll become profitable around 2029/2030, and they need $200 billion in annual revenue to offset their debts and losses.</p><p>To visualize $200 billion: if you cashed that out in $100 bills and stacked them, it would reach halfway to the International Space Station. That’s how much they’d have to make every single year to just be profitable. Not be a massively successful company. Just to not spend more than they earn.</p><ul><li><p>2024: Spent $5 billion, earned $3.7 billion. Spending $1.35 for every dollar earned.</p></li><li><p>2025: Set $8 billion on fire (after profits).</p></li><li><p>2028 (projected): Will lose $74 billion that year. Just lose it.</p></li><li><p>Cumulative losses through 2029: $143 billion.</p></li></ul><p>They’d need to make $200 billion in a year to offset that. Are they including interest? I have no idea how these things work, but in simple terms: they’re spending a lot more money than they make.</p><p>Groq was kind of a one off because Nvidia panic bought the competition. But they also need to figure out how to get prices down or they can’t keep this money machine moving.</p><p>Groq is probably one of the last companies that caught a good lifeboat off a sinking ship.</p><p>What we’re going to see this year: it’ll start small, but get major. A company first, then multiple larger ones, that had a 2025 valuation, will go to raise. They’ll do a 409A evaluation. A bunch of smart analysts will say what it’s worth to investors. And you’re going to see the valuation drop. They won’t be able to raise money.</p><p>Then the shit is really going to start to hit the fan.</p><p>The dominoes will start falling. That’s probably what kicks off the actual pop, and it’s imminent. Any day now.</p><p>Part of the big gamble they’ve sold investors is: we’ve got to replace you. The worker. That’s why we need to spend so much money, go into debt. It’ll all be worth it because then we won’t have to pay people to do these jobs anymore.</p><p>We’re going to continue to see massive labor displacement. To a degree this is a shell game, an investor illusion. What these larger enterprise companies are hoping to do: cut a lot of folks, have big layoffs, say it’s because AI is replacing the jobs.</p><p>In some cases they’re right. Data entry, for example. I don’t mean to be mean if you do data entry for a living, but there are models very good at that now. You need someone to manage the work, spot check it. But it’s kind of a job AI can do.</p><p>Like how grocery stores have automatic checkout lines now with one person monitoring six or eight of them. So some of that’s real. A lot of it isn’t though.</p><p>They cut a bunch of American workers under the guise that AI’s replacing workers. A lot of these megacorp execs are actually convinced of it. Americans are expensive, especially tech workers.</p><p>Then they see: damn, maybe we could have cut some, but not as many. We got greedy. Now our services are failing in production. AWS in Northern Virginia is flaky, going down again. That just happened, by the way, direct result of these layoffs.</p><p>So instead they think, “We’ll look globally! Spin up a campus in Hyderabad!” Pay them way less. The cost of living is less there, they expect less. Bring them over on H-1B when needed. I’ve written about the H-1B program. This is nothing against the individuals on that program. I’ve worked with very talented H-1Bs, and some very inferior ones, just like American citizens.</p><p>But the corporate sleight of hand is something like this, we can get those H-1B visas, and they’re not going to ask for pesky stuff like Sunday off for church. We can put them on call 24/7 and they can’t say no because if they do, we kick them back to their country. Same thing that’s happened with migrant labor in farming over the past century. Even if it doesn’t look like it on the surface, corporations know that they can pay H-1B employees less than American citizens. If a US citizen and H-1B recipient both make $120k but the H-1B works double the hours because they have no room to push back and are under threat of being sent home, they are making 50% less than the American per-hour.</p><p>Amazon/AWS: 14,000 laid off.</p><p>Microsoft: 15,000 total just in 2025.</p><p>Salesforce: My favorite one. 4,000 customer support roles cut. And the CEO is gloating about it in interviews. So great that he can replace workers!</p><p><a href="https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/technology/tech-news/after-laying-off-4000-employees-and-automating-with-ai-agents-salesforce-executives-admit-we-were-more-confident-about-/articleshow/126121875.cms" rel="">Now Salesforce is admitting that they fucked up. They cut too many people. </a></p><p><span>I’ve been on the other side of this when I was an engineering director at a Fortune 500 company. They were </span><em>neurotic</em><span> about tracking AI use. Spending an exorbitant amount of money on shitty AI tools. Like tools from a year ago. GPT-4o in the GPT-5 era, in the Anthropic dominance era. More or less useless.</span></p><p>Not only would they monitor all usage across employees, specifically who’s using it how much, they could see every single message being sent to the AI. So theoretically you could check somebody’s queries and do a performance evaluation based on where you perceive them to be.</p><p>Pretty creepy.</p><p>They’re using yesterday’s tools because of regulation and compliance, blowing an absurd amount of money. The CEO just sees a lot going out the door: “I thought these were supposed to save money, what’s going on here?” So his lieutenants have to get a grip on it, monitor everything. Even at Amazon this is being included in performance reviews, how much they’re using AI.</p><p>That’s why if you’re a software developer wondering why your boss is on you about using AI tools. They’re probably getting pressure from their bosses. I want my engineers to be as productive as possible. I think AI is probably part of that tool belt for everyone at this point. But is tracking it really the best way? I’m going to gauge performance on metrics, how you interacted with the team, what you shipped. It puts the cart before the horse to say you’re paid by how much you use these AI tools. If I’m a developer, I’m just spinning up a script to send lorem ipsum text 24 hours a day, get maximum ratings because I used GPT-3.5 the most.</p><p>MIT did a study in summer 2025. They’re saying 95% of companies report zero measurable ROI on AI products.</p><p>Actually not that crazy if you consider that a lot of them did layoffs and subbed in AI. That’s just going according to plan in my estimation.</p><p>They estimate about $30 to $40 billion has been spent on enterprise AI. That’s the money your JPMorgan Chase is spending for their engineers to use Claude Code or whatever dated tool they have access to.</p><p>The market heard that signal. When that study came out:</p><ul><li><p>Nvidia crashed 3.5%</p></li><li><p>Palantir down 10%</p></li><li><p>Nasdaq in general down 1.2%</p></li></ul><p>That last one isn’t encouraging for an AI bubble pop because it indicates this is a big part of the economy.</p><p>January through February: Maybe down valuations, just a very flat market without much growth.</p><p>Q1 to Q2: We’ll start to see a couple businesses, or maybe one major one at first like a domino starting to fall, not able to raise capital at their 2025 valuation. We’ll see valuations go down. VCs will be like: “Not touching it, not giving them more money, cutting our losses.”</p><p>Then timing a little more indeterminate but these things will happen quickly in succession:</p><ul><li><p>Credit markets start to tighten</p></li><li><p>Debt refinancing pressure builds up in the system</p></li><li><p>Nvidia revises its revenue guidance to something at least vaguely linked to reality</p></li></ul><p>And that’s when the big reckoning begins.</p><p>I want to be clear. AI is not going anywhere. It’s going to continue being a mainstream part of the world. I like a lot of these tools, I think they’re very helpful.</p><p>But the talking heads have really promised us the world. It’s clear the technology cannot deliver above and beyond what it’s doing now.</p><p>We’ve seen progress of these models slow at an exponential rate of slowing over the past few releases. Each release is better, but the gap between the current release and the last release is much smaller than it used to be.</p><p>Because of that, a lot of these AI companies are going to survive, but their valuations are going to get giga slashed.</p><p>Valuations of $500 billion for OpenAI, $42 billion for Anthropic are unsustainable. We’re going to actually see them become unsustainable in 2026 as they’re eventually cut. Smaller companies will face those slashes first. But it’s coming for the major AI labs as well.</p><p>This is good news, honestly. This AI hype has really turned tech into something different these days, different than it used to be. While I don’t feel AI is going anywhere, I do feel we’ll get a little more back to normal once this bubble pops and resolves.</p><p><em>What do you think? Drop a comment below. Subscribe if you found this interesting.</em></p></div></article></div><div><div id="discussion"><h4>Discussion about this post</h4></div><div><h3>Ready for more?</h3></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Floor796 (720 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://floor796.com/</link>
            <guid>46401612</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 13:13:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://floor796.com/">https://floor796.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46401612">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Apple releases open-source model that instantly turns 2D photos into 3D views (374 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/apple/ml-sharp</link>
            <guid>46401539</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 12:58:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/apple/ml-sharp">https://github.com/apple/ml-sharp</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46401539">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Sharp Monocular View Synthesis in Less Than a Second</h2><a id="user-content-sharp-monocular-view-synthesis-in-less-than-a-second" aria-label="Permalink: Sharp Monocular View Synthesis in Less Than a Second" href="#sharp-monocular-view-synthesis-in-less-than-a-second"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://apple.github.io/ml-sharp/" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/cafdcb5612b1ab28528d47af9245604f8f7b0792562c7c5151fff90340a3d6cc/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f50726f6a6563742d506167652d677265656e" alt="Project Page" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/Project-Page-green"></a>
<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10685" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/dba21084a03f7471ad5ab1cbe4b2eeb9c6c4333dde6dae06cd437bc9b9163cf7/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f61725869762d323531322e31303638352d6233316231622e737667" alt="arXiv" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/arXiv-2512.10685-b31b1b.svg"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This software project accompanies the research paper: <em>Sharp Monocular View Synthesis in Less Than a Second</em>
by <em>Lars Mescheder, Wei Dong, Shiwei Li, Xuyang Bai, Marcel Santos, Peiyun Hu, Bruno Lecouat, Mingmin Zhen, Amaël Delaunoy,
Tian Fang, Yanghai Tsin, Stephan Richter and Vladlen Koltun</em>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/apple/ml-sharp/blob/main/data/teaser.jpg"><img src="https://github.com/apple/ml-sharp/raw/main/data/teaser.jpg" alt=""></a></p>
<p dir="auto">We present SHARP, an approach to photorealistic view synthesis from a single image. Given a single photograph, SHARP regresses the parameters of a 3D Gaussian representation of the depicted scene. This is done in less than a second on a standard GPU via a single feedforward pass through a neural network. The 3D Gaussian representation produced by SHARP can then be rendered in real time, yielding high-resolution photorealistic images for nearby views. The representation is metric, with absolute scale, supporting metric camera movements. Experimental results demonstrate that SHARP delivers robust zero-shot generalization across datasets. It sets a new state of the art on multiple datasets, reducing LPIPS by 25–34% and DISTS by 21–43% versus the best prior model, while lowering the synthesis time by three orders of magnitude.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Getting started</h2><a id="user-content-getting-started" aria-label="Permalink: Getting started" href="#getting-started"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">We recommend to first create a python environment:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="conda create -n sharp python=3.13"><pre><code>conda create -n sharp python=3.13
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Afterwards, you can install the project using</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="pip install -r requirements.txt"><pre><code>pip install -r requirements.txt
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">To test the installation, run</p>

<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Using the CLI</h2><a id="user-content-using-the-cli" aria-label="Permalink: Using the CLI" href="#using-the-cli"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To run prediction:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="sharp predict -i /path/to/input/images -o /path/to/output/gaussians"><pre><code>sharp predict -i /path/to/input/images -o /path/to/output/gaussians
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">The model checkpoint will be downloaded automatically on first run and cached locally at <code>~/.cache/torch/hub/checkpoints/</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Alternatively, you can download the model directly:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="wget https://ml-site.cdn-apple.com/models/sharp/sharp_2572gikvuh.pt"><pre><code>wget https://ml-site.cdn-apple.com/models/sharp/sharp_2572gikvuh.pt
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">To use a manually downloaded checkpoint, specify it with the <code>-c</code> flag:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="sharp predict -i /path/to/input/images -o /path/to/output/gaussians -c sharp_2572gikvuh.pt"><pre><code>sharp predict -i /path/to/input/images -o /path/to/output/gaussians -c sharp_2572gikvuh.pt
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">The results will be 3D gaussian splats (3DGS) in the output folder. The 3DGS <code>.ply</code> files are compatible to various public 3DGS renderers. We follow the OpenCV coordinate convention (x right, y down, z forward). The 3DGS scene center is roughly at (0, 0, +z). When dealing with 3rdparty renderers, please scale and rotate to re-center the scene accordingly.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Rendering trajectories (CUDA GPU only)</h3><a id="user-content-rendering-trajectories-cuda-gpu-only" aria-label="Permalink: Rendering trajectories (CUDA GPU only)" href="#rendering-trajectories-cuda-gpu-only"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Additionally you can render videos with a camera trajectory. While the gaussians prediction works for all CPU, CUDA, and MPS, rendering videos via the <code>--render</code> option currently requires a CUDA GPU. The gsplat renderer takes a while to initialize at the first launch.</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="sharp predict -i /path/to/input/images -o /path/to/output/gaussians --render

# Or from the intermediate gaussians:
sharp render -i /path/to/output/gaussians -o /path/to/output/renderings"><pre><code>sharp predict -i /path/to/input/images -o /path/to/output/gaussians --render

# Or from the intermediate gaussians:
sharp render -i /path/to/output/gaussians -o /path/to/output/renderings
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Evaluation</h2><a id="user-content-evaluation" aria-label="Permalink: Evaluation" href="#evaluation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Please refer to the paper for both quantitative and qualitative evaluations.
Additionally, please check out this <a href="https://apple.github.io/ml-sharp/" rel="nofollow">qualitative examples page</a> containing several video comparisons against related work.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Citation</h2><a id="user-content-citation" aria-label="Permalink: Citation" href="#citation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If you find our work useful, please cite the following paper:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="@inproceedings{Sharp2025:arxiv,
  title      = {Sharp Monocular View Synthesis in Less Than a Second},
  author     = {Lars Mescheder and Wei Dong and Shiwei Li and Xuyang Bai and Marcel Santos and Peiyun Hu and Bruno Lecouat and Mingmin Zhen and Ama\&quot;{e}l Delaunoy and Tian Fang and Yanghai Tsin and Stephan R. Richter and Vladlen Koltun},
  journal    = {arXiv preprint arXiv:2512.10685},
  year       = {2025},
  url        = {https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10685},
}"><pre><span>@inproceedings</span>{<span>Sharp2025:arxiv</span>,
  <span>title</span>      = <span><span>{</span>Sharp Monocular View Synthesis in Less Than a Second<span>}</span></span>,
  <span>author</span>     = <span><span>{</span>Lars Mescheder and Wei Dong and Shiwei Li and Xuyang Bai and Marcel Santos and Peiyun Hu and Bruno Lecouat and Mingmin Zhen and Ama\"{e}l Delaunoy and Tian Fang and Yanghai Tsin and Stephan R. Richter and Vladlen Koltun<span>}</span></span>,
  <span>journal</span>    = <span><span>{</span>arXiv preprint arXiv:2512.10685<span>}</span></span>,
  <span>year</span>       = <span><span>{</span>2025<span>}</span></span>,
  <span>url</span>        = <span><span>{</span>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10685<span>}</span></span>,
}</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Acknowledgements</h2><a id="user-content-acknowledgements" aria-label="Permalink: Acknowledgements" href="#acknowledgements"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Our codebase is built using multiple opensource contributions, please see <a href="https://github.com/apple/ml-sharp/blob/main/ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</a> for more details.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Please check out the repository <a href="https://github.com/apple/ml-sharp/blob/main/LICENSE">LICENSE</a> before using the provided code and
<a href="https://github.com/apple/ml-sharp/blob/main/LICENSE_MODEL">LICENSE_MODEL</a> for the released models.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OrangePi 6 Plus Review (167 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/</link>
            <guid>46401499</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 12:51:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/">https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46401499">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section>
    <p>So after our previous reviews (that started <a href="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-rv2-new-risc-v-board-review/">mainly around RISC-V</a> since we are really interested in this new architecture) of SBC, we continue to review what’s available these days in the world of small, versatile computers. Today this is going to be about the <em>OrangePi 6 Plus</em>, following our previous review of the <a href="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-5-ultra-review/">OrangePi 5 ultra board</a>.</p>
<p>This is NOT a super small, credit card format SBC. We are talking about something that’s definitely larger, and that comes directly with an integrated heatsink.</p>
<p><img src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/orangepi6plus_board.avif" alt="OrangePi 6 Plus seen in real"></p>
<p>At the bottom there’s a wealth of ports, and it’s where you will install the necessary wireless module if you want Wifi and Bluetooth.</p>
<p><img src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/orangepi6plus_board_wifi.avif" alt="OrangePi 6 Plus bottom view with wifi"></p>
<p>Now let’s dive into what you can do with this.</p>
<h2 id="sec:ports">Ports</h2>
<p>Here is what you can get from the top of the device. Note that most of it will be hidden from view as the board comes pre-installed with the heatsink that covers the SOC and the memory chips.</p>
<p><img src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/orangepi6plus_top_ports.avif" alt=""></p>
<p>And the bottom view.</p>
<p><img src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/orangepi6plus_bottom_ports.avif" alt=""></p>
<p>You can tell just from the format that you should have higher expectations from the hardware.</p>
<h2 id="sec:specs-of-the-orangepi-6-plus">Specs of the OrangePi 6 Plus</h2>
<p>In a table format:</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Component</th>
<th>Specification</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>SoC</strong></td>
<td>CIX CD8180 / CD8160 (12-core 64-bit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>CPU Architecture</strong></td>
<td>4× Cortex-A720 (High-perf) + 4× Cortex-A720 (Main) + 4× Cortex-A520 (Efficiency)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>GPU</strong></td>
<td>Arm Immortalis-G720 MC10 (Ray Tracing &amp; 8K Decoding support)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>NPU (AI)</strong></td>
<td>Up to 45 TOPS (System-wide); ~30 TOPS Dedicated NPU</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>RAM</strong></td>
<td>16GB / 32GB / 64GB LPDDR5 (128-bit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Storage</strong></td>
<td>2× M.2 2280 slots (PCIe 4.0 x4 NVMe), 1× MicroSD (TF) slot</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Networking</strong></td>
<td>Dual 5GbE (5000Mbps) Ethernet ports</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Wireless</strong></td>
<td>M.2 Key-E (2230) slot for Wi-Fi 6E/7 &amp; Bluetooth 5.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Video Output</strong></td>
<td>1× HDMI 2.1 (8K@60Hz), 1× DP 1.4, 2× USB-C (DP Alt Mode), 1× eDP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>USB Ports</strong></td>
<td>2× USB 3.0 Type-A, 2× USB 2.0 Type-A, 2× Full-function USB Type-C</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Camera (MIPI)</strong></td>
<td>2× 4-lane MIPI CSI interfaces</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Expansion</strong></td>
<td>40-pin GPIO header (UART, I2C, SPI, PWM, etc.)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Audio</strong></td>
<td>3.5mm Headphone/Mic jack, 2× Speaker headers, 1× Analog MIC header</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Power Supply</strong></td>
<td>100W Dual USB Type-C PD (20V/5A)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Dimensions</strong></td>
<td>115mm × 100mm</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>As you can see from the specs, this is no joke. 16GB RAM by default, 12-cores processor, with a powerful GPU (Immortalis G720), and a NPU that has a claimed performance up to 30 TOPS. Not just that, but there’s numerous ports on this SBC, with 2 full sized M2 2280 slots! You can tell that the IO is not going to be a joke here.</p>
<p>If you are wondering about the SOC itself, we have more info about what to expect from CIX.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Feature</th>
<th>Specification</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>SoC Model</strong></td>
<td>CIX CD8180 / CD8160 (Codename: CIX P1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Architecture</strong></td>
<td>Armv9.2-A (64-bit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Total CPU Cores</strong></td>
<td>12 Cores (Tri-cluster configuration)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Big Cores</strong></td>
<td>4× Cortex-A720 @ Up to 2.8 GHz (Performance)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Medium Cores</strong></td>
<td>4× Cortex-A720 @ Up to 2.4 GHz (Mainstream)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Little Cores</strong></td>
<td>4× Cortex-A520 @ 1.8 GHz (Efficiency)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>L3 Cache</strong></td>
<td>12MB Shared L3 Cache</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>GPU</strong></td>
<td>Arm Immortalis-G720 MC10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Graphics Features</strong></td>
<td>Hardware Ray Tracing, Vulkan 1.3, OpenGL ES 3.2, OpenCL 3.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>NPU (AI Engine)</strong></td>
<td>Arm-China Zhouyi: 30 TOPS (Dedicated); ~45 TOPS (Total System AI)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>AI Precision</strong></td>
<td>INT4, INT8, INT16, FP16, TF32</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>VPU (Video)</strong></td>
<td>Linlon V8: 8K@60fps Decode (AV1/H.265/VP9), 8K@30fps Encode (H.265)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Memory Interface</strong></td>
<td>128-bit LPDDR5 / LPDDR5X (Up to 5500 MT/s)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Memory Bandwidth</strong></td>
<td>Up to 96 GB/s (Theoretical peak)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>PCIe Support</strong></td>
<td>PCIe Gen4 (Supports x8, x4, and x2 configurations)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>System Security</strong></td>
<td>Integrated Security Engine (Standard Arm SystemReady / ACPI support)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>2.8Ghz ARM Big Cores processors! That’s no joke, this is way beyond the typical frequency we see for small boards where things are usually below 2 Ghz. The memory interface also has a huge bandwidth, and we get full PCI4 with 8 lanes! This means that this board could probably be attached to an external GPU (eGPU) and be able to drive it (provided adequate software support).</p>
<p>About the NPU, the usual problem on Linux is that there is poor software support, and it’s certainly not in the mainline either. To leverage the 30 TOPS of dedicated AI power, you cannot simply use standard versions of PyTorch or TensorFlow out of the box. You must use the NeuralONE AI SDK. This also means that the NPU cannot use regular weights, and need to compile them into a different format to make them work. On paper, the NPU is highly versatile and supports the following data types: INT4, INT8, INT16, FP16, BF16, and TF32. The board has extensive documentation on a bunch of embedded models for vision detection, automation, such as YOLOv8 (Vision), ResNet50, OpenPose, and DeepLabv3.</p>
<p>Now let’s jump into the actual user experience.</p>
<h2 id="sec:software-support">Software Support</h2>
<h3 id="sec:desktop-experience">Desktop Experience</h3>
<h4 id="sec:debian-bookworm">Debian Bookworm</h4>
<p>There is a <em>Debian Bookworm</em> (12) image available at the time of writing. I was actually waiting for a 24.04 Ubuntu image to be made available, and that was the plan at some point according to my <em>OrangePi</em> contact, but they had to shift priorities apparently and now there is no ETA for the Ubuntu image. So instead of waiting, I decided to go ahead and review what’s possible with this Debian image. As you know, <em>Debian Bookworm</em> is not that new anymore (the base is from Mid-2023), and is now superseded by <em>Debian Trixie</em> (released in 2025). This Debian image comes with two kernels available, 6.1 and 6.6. The 6.6 kernel is also from 2023, and it’s not surprising you don’t get a more recent kernel, since the Linux support for various parts of the boards, not being upstreamed and mainlined, is very likely to be stuck on an older version. This is usually what causes headaches down the road: maybe some general functionality can be upstreamed, but will the NPU have working drivers for a more recent kernel? Your guess is as good as mine.</p>
<p><img src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/fastfetch.avif" alt="Fastfetch for the OrangePi 6 Plus Bookworm"></p>
<p>You can burn the image directly on the NVME drive - no need to boot on a MicroSD card this time around. Note that at the beginning, my OrangePi did not boot, but I could see from the BIOS (yes, this board comes with a BIOS-like interface!) that everything was supposed to be seen by the SBC. Turns out that the firmware required an update to be able to boot on this Linux kernel, and after imaging the latest firmware on a USB stick and booting on it, a few minutes later, things worked as expected.</p>
<p>In any case, we get a GNOME desktop after boot. And everything works pretty much as you’d expect. Once thing that is immediately apparent when you start with the desktop is how snappy everything is. SBC boards like the Raspberry Pi 4 provide a good desktop experience but have some general sluggishness to them. On this board, this is pretty much like having a X86_64 experience. It recognized immediately my Ultra Wide Display and supported the 3440 x 1440 resolution without a hitch. Everything from navigating the desktop and settings is very fast. You get Chromium by default (and Firefox ESR in the repos) and the browser experience is very clean and fast, too. This board has absolutely no problem to play Youtube streams, even at 4k. This thing is FAST!</p>
<video autoplay="" loop="" muted="" playsinline="">
  <source src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/browsing2_optimized.webm" type="video/webm">
  <source src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/browsing2_optimized.mp4" type="video/mp4">
</video>
<p>A quick look at vulkaninfo shows that we have working Vulkan drivers on this board! This is something that was initially very exciting, but it turns out that there are some limitations. More on that later.</p>
<p><img src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/glxgears.avif" alt="Glx gears running on the OrangePi 6 Plus"></p>
<p>Turns out the Vulkan driver is limited to some early 1.3 version. You have options to upgrade Mesa, by using Debian backports - it gets you to a 25.07 Mesa version, where you don’t rely anymore on the proprietary driver - no, this time you get Panfrost, which means a more robust driver potentially… except that you are stuck on the 6.6 Linux Kernel, and Panfrost requires a more recent kernel to work properly (6.10+ apparently). So the solution would be to move to a more recent kernel, right? Do the Debian backports have it? Yes. Problem is, moving away from 6.6 will break a lot of patches that are necessary for the hardware of this board to work. Such as HDMI out at resolutions higher than 1080p, and NPU support! So, it’s a major trade-off.</p>
<h4 id="sec:getting-bluetooth-to-work">Getting Bluetooth to work</h4>
<p>Even though bluetooth shows in the GNOME desktop controls, and that it could see some of my peripherals, it could not connect to any of my external audio devices. But I don’t give up so fast. Turns out there’s an issue with a missing pipewire dependency to allow for bluetooth audio to work. Here’s how you can get it done:</p>
<pre><code>sudo apt install libspa-0.2-bluetooth pipewire-audio-client-libraries
</code></pre>
<p>Afterwards you can launch <em>bluetoothctl</em> from the command line, and you can execute the following commands one by one</p>
<pre><code>power on
agent on
default-agent
scan on
</code></pre>
<p>After the scan is activated you should see bluetooth device popping up in the terminal. Note the ID of the bluetooth device you want to connect, and then:</p>
<pre><code>pair &lt;device id&gt;
trust &lt;device id&gt;
connect &lt;devic_id&gt;
</code></pre>
<p>Once this is fixed, things work as expected. And now I get audio!</p>
<h4 id="sec:compiling-obs">Compiling OBS</h4>
<p>OBS is not available as flatpak for arm64, and not in the repos either. This means, that you are in for a compilation from sources. This is not the thing that scares me. But in our situation, it’s a little more convoluted that I expected. First, turns out that OBS did not like the fact that the Cmake was relatively old. So I had to get one of the recent Cmake binaries. Thanksfully they have <a href="https://cmake.org/download/">arm64 binaries already available on their website</a>, so that was easy.</p>
<p><img src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/cmake_aarch64_linux.avif" alt="Cmake binaries"></p>
<p>Next, OBS would complain of a too old FFmpeg version. Not too surprising for something that depends so heavily on it. So I had to go for a full FFmpeg compilation. Here’s what I did to save you time:</p>
<pre><code>git clone https://github.com/FFmpeg/FFmpeg.git
cd ffmpeg
git checkout release/7.1 # in order to have a stable release, not the master branch in itself

./configure --prefix=/usr/local --enable-shared --disable-static --enable-gpl --enable-libx264 --enable-libx265
make -j$(nproc)

sudo make install
</code></pre>
<p>Finally, compiling OBS is a game of cat and mouse, you need to basically give up one extension after the other as new errors arise. Most of the things you need to remove are not critical (NVENC, not relevant on non-nvidia hardware, browser support, not really our thing either) and at the end you get a fairly long series of command.</p>
<pre><code>git clone https://github.com/obsproject/obs-studio.git
cd obs-studio

# remove the obs-browser plugin from the obs folder root directlroy
mv plugins/obs-browser plugins/obs-browser.bak

# from the obs root folder
git submodule update --init --recursive

# a couple of exports to avoid the compilation to fail because of FFmpeg warnings
export CFLAGS="-Wno-error=deprecated-declarations"
export CXXFLAGS="-Wno-error=deprecated-declarations"

# since the flags can be ignored, we also edit the following file from the root directory
echo 'target_compile_options(obs-ffmpeg PRIVATE "-Wno-error=deprecated-declarations")' &gt;&gt; plugins/obs-ffmpeg/CMakeLists.txt

# use the path to the cmake version you just downloaded
&lt;path_to_newer_cmake_binary&gt;/cmake -DCMAKE_PREFIX_PATH=/usr/local -DFFMPEG_INCLUDE_DIR=/usr/local/include  -DPKG_CONFIG_PATH=/usr/local/lib/pkgconfig -DENABLE_AJA=OFF -DUNIX_STRUCTURE=1 -DENABLE_GIO=OFF -DENABLE_VPL=OFF  -DENABLE_QSV11=OFF -DENABLE_BROWSER=OFF  -DENABLE_WEBRTC=OFF -DENABLE_NATIVE_NVENC=OFF -DCMAKE_COMPILE_WARNING_AS_ERROR=OFF ..

make -j$(nproc)

sudo make install

</code></pre>
<p>It took a little while, but it worked!</p>
<video autoplay="" loop="" muted="" playsinline="">
  <source src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/obs-working_optimized.webm" type="video/webm">
  <source src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/obs-working_optimized.mp4" type="video/mp4">
</video>
<p>I must admit, I did not expect that it would go so well in the end.
Now, thanks to this, you will get a lot of videos from the board in action that no other site reviewing that board has been able to offer.</p>
<h4 id="sec:noise-and-temperature">Noise and Temperature</h4>
<p>The board is very quiet by default. Even when the fan is activated, you barely hear it, at least under fairly typical conditions. Things change when you push the board to its full power, for example a long compilation time. In such conditions, the fan becomes louder with a <em>woosh</em> kind of sound. You will definitely hear it when doing benchmarks, and in my case, when running LLMs, for example.</p>
<p><img src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/temperature_control.avif" alt="Pretty good temperature control for the OrangePi 6 Plus"></p>
<p>In terms of temperature, the control is very good. At 100% usage even for long durations, while the fan becomes clearly noticeable, it maintains the temperature under 60 C (this is winter right now, and the temperature remained at 58 C). Kudos for the good engineering there. It’s as good as the <a href="https://boilingsteam.com/upgrading-fans-with-a-custom-shroud-on-a-rtx3090-goodbye-fan-noise/">custom cooling solution for my RTX3090</a>.</p>
<h4 id="sec:power-draw">Power Draw</h4>
<p>I don’t have a way to measure the power draw currently, but based on reports from other publications it looks like we are looking at:</p>
<ul>
<li>15W at idle, which is fairly high</li>
<li>30+W during usage - this is why they recommend to use the provided PSU with USB-C. Note that any charger that can provide 45W should do the trick as well.</li>
</ul>
<p>So, if you are looking for something that has almost no footprint at idle, this is not it. At idle the <em>OrangePi 5 Ultra</em> consumes more than 3 times less, so that sound more like something you’d use for a server.</p>
<h4 id="sec:benchmarks">Benchmarks</h4>
<p>A quick run at Geekbench 6 shows a very strong single core score, and an exceptional multi-core score.</p>
<p><img src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/overall-bench-orangepi6plus-vs-raspberrypi5.svg" alt="Geekbench 6 results for the orangepi 6 plus vs Raspbnerry Pi 5"></p>
<p>Now the details in single score:</p>
<p><img src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/single-core-bench-orangepi6-plus-vs-raspberrypi5.svg" alt="Geekbench 6 results for the orangepi 6 plus vs Raspbnerry Pi 5 single core"></p>
<p>And in multi-core where we can see that the OrangePi 6 absolutely crushes what you can find on a <em>Raspberry Pi 5</em>.</p>
<p><img src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/multi-core-bench-orangepi6-plus-vs-raspberrypi5.svg" alt="Geekbench 6 results for the orangepi 6 plus vs Raspbnerry Pi 5 single core"></p>
<p>Of course, this is a relatively cheap system that is not going to win the benchmark charts. But look at the results. On single core, we get a score equivalent to a <em>i5-10500</em> running at a similar frequency (2.3 Ghz).</p>
<p><img src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/geekbench_context_single_core_1290.avif" alt="Geekbench 6 results context for the orangepi 6 plus single core"></p>
<p>On multicore this is much more impressive, thanks to its twelve cores. And it gets very close, according to the bench, to what an <em>AMD Ryzen 7 4800H</em> (8 cores) can deliver.</p>
<p><img src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/geekbench_context_multi_core_6032.avif" alt="Geekbench 6 results context for the orangepi 6 plus multi core"></p>
<p>This is clearly a powerhouse, CPU-wise. For a starting price at 199 USD for the 16GB version, this is a fantastic value proposition. We reviewed the <em>OrangePi 5 Ultra</em> a few months back and the price point is very close (around 160 USD), and unless you need something very small and fanless, the <em>OrangePi 6 Plus</em> is (very clearly) a better deal.</p>
<h4 id="sec:gaming">Gaming</h4>
<p>Since we have both a fairly powerful SOC, and a working <em>Vulkan</em> driver, this means that we can expect <a href="https://boilingsteam.com/new-box86-and-box64-releases-for-may-2024/">Box64</a> to do some magic for us there. I compiled Box64 to make it possible to launch Steam, and for some reason there is some Vulkan related error that prevents <em>Steam</em> from launching. Too bad. I still have a GOG account with a few games that have Linux clients. I tried the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Beholder 2</li>
<li>Shadow Warrior 2013</li>
<li>Oxenfree</li>
<li>Day of the Tentacle Remastered</li>
<li>Torchlight 2</li>
</ul>
<p>And with some degree of success! <em>Beholder 2</em> worked just fine, and are definitely playable on this board, while the framerate remains between the 20s and 30s FPS (here a little slower on this video because of software OBS capture).</p>
<video autoplay="" loop="" muted="" playsinline="">
  <source src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/beholder2_optimized.webm" type="video/webm">
  <source src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/beholder2_optimized.mp4" type="video/mp4">
</video>
<p>Here’s <em>Oxenfree’s</em> Linux x86_64 client running in Full HD on the OrangePi 6 Plus, using Box64:</p>
<video autoplay="" loop="" muted="" playsinline="">
  <source src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/oxenfree_optimized.webm" type="video/webm">
  <source src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/oxenfree_optimized.mp4" type="video/mp4">
</video>
<p><em>Torchlight 2</em> runs nicely too, at something like 20 to 30 FPS in Full HD.</p>
<video autoplay="" loop="" muted="" playsinline="">
  <source src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/torchlight2_optimized.webm" type="video/webm">
  <source src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/torchlight2_optimized.mp4" type="video/mp4">
</video>
<p><em>Shadow Warrior</em> refused to launch, complaining about the graphics drivers not being recent enough (turns out that Zink provides OpenGL support, and there is some issue to detect that the OpenGL version is properly supported… my guess). <em>Day of the Tentacle</em> crashes at start too, not sure why. When games work, the performance is not staggering but convincing for a somewhat small SoC at the end of the day. AMD and Intel are certainly ahead in terms of graphics performance on integrated chips, but they have much larger processors and much more expensive ones, too.</p>
<p>I also tried FOSS games or engines:</p>
<ul>
<li>GZDoom (compiled from source, the flatpak version sucks in performance!)</li>
<li>Luanti (ex-Minetest)</li>
<li>IOQuake3 (compiled from source)</li>
<li>OAD (from Debian repos)</li>
</ul>
<p><em>GZDoom</em> works exceptionally well with the OpenGLES renderer at Full HD. It’s fast, responsive. Stable at 60 FPS on Full HD. And <em>Doom</em> is still as fun as it was in the days, or more so if you run <strong>Brutal Doom</strong>.</p>
<video autoplay="" loop="" muted="" playsinline="">
  <source src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/gzdoom_optimized.webm" type="video/webm">
  <source src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/gzdoom_optimized.mp4" type="video/mp4">
</video>
<p>While I don’t have a sample video here, <em>Quake 3 Arena</em> with the <em>IOQuake3</em> engine works perfectly, and runs at 60 fps on Full HD without a sweat.</p>
<p><em>Luanti</em> (ex Minetest) works extremely well - I turned most of the details to the max at 1080p and it kept at a solid 60 FPS. Sure, that’s no AAA game, but it’s a good alternative to <em>Minecraft</em>.</p>
<video autoplay="" loop="" muted="" playsinline="">
  <source src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/luanti_optimized.webm" type="video/webm">
  <source src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/luanti_optimized.mp4" type="video/mp4">
</video>
<p><em>0Ad</em> works extremely well, even in full screen at my Ultra Wide screen resolution. I took a video at FUll HD, and while OBS does slow the framerate a little, you can still see it’s very smooth.</p>
<video autoplay="" loop="" muted="" playsinline="">
  <source src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/0ad_optimized.webm" type="video/webm">
  <source src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/0ad_optimized.mp4" type="video/mp4">
</video>
<p><em>0ad</em> has come a long way, I really need to revisit a recent version of the game to see how much it has changed!</p>
<h3 id="sec:server-use">Server use</h3>
<p>This is a very capable board that would make a very powerful server. The <em>Debian</em> image comes with <em>Docker</em>, and as we have seen before during the <a href="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-5-ultra-review/">OrangePi 5 Ultra review</a>, the landscape of ready-to-use Docker Hub images is huge and can get you started with numerous server-side applications in no time. Since we have at least 16Gb of memory, very fast I/O (PCIe4!), and a very fast CPU, this SBC will be able to wonders with a wide variety of applications. The only problem is the power draw. It looks like we are stuck with 15W as an idle baseline, and that seems a bit too much for some light server use.</p>
<h3 id="sec:ai-applications">AI applications</h3>
<p>This board comes with a very large repository (60 GB!) that you can install and sync automatically, with tons of applications and demos you can try out. There is a large part of their documentation dedicated to that part <a href="https://orangepi.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/OrangePi_6_Plus_Cix_Linux-System_User-Manual_v0.4.pdf">in their manual</a>. And for what I could try, it seems to work as long as you follow their instructions.</p>
<p>In my case I like to work with LLMs for a range of applications, so I was interested to see how fast this board could run some small-ish models. One of the major limitations is that we don’t have working NPU support for <a href="https://github.com/ggml-org/llama.cpp">llama.cpp</a> (oh no!). I was thinking, <em>“no worries, we have a vulkan driver so let’s use Vulkan instead”</em>. I like to be optimistic sometimes. Turns out that the <em>Vulkan</em> driver is below the minimum Vulkan drivers specs required by <em>llama.cpp</em> recently, and I would need to go back to a end 2024 build to be able to compile for Vulkan support. Going back one year on <em>llama.cpp</em>… not an option, sorry (too many models would not be supported going back so far in time). So, we are left with using the raw power of the CPU. Which means it won’t be quiet - expect some good old noise fan in such use cases.</p>
<p>Anyway, I went for <a href="https://huggingface.co/Qwen/Qwen3-1.7B">Qwen3 1.7b</a> - downloaded the safetensors weights, then converted them to <a href="https://github.com/ggml-org/ggml/blob/master/docs/gguf.md">gguf</a>, followed by a quantization step to make them IQ4_S. Running the model at this kind of quantization gives us about 14 tokens per second when doing inference. Definitely usable, very usable even, while this is a small model.</p>
<video autoplay="" loop="" muted="" playsinline="">
  <source src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/llm_inference_optimized.webm" type="video/webm">
  <source src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/llm_inference_optimized.mp4" type="video/mp4">
</video>
<p>Ideally, you’d want to have a board that can run a 7b model with proper hardware acceleration and no fan usage. Not sure if having actual NPU support in the future would help for that or not. In other words, we are not there yet.</p>
<h2 id="sec:existing-alternatives">Existing Alternatives</h2>
<p>As usual there is not a single vendor who can provide you with a CIX experience. This time the main competitor is Radxa, and they have two boards called Orion 6 that feature the same chip - one that is much bigger in footprint (mini-ITX size), and another one that is more similar to the OrangePi 6 Plus size (the Orion 6N). While I don’t have access to the Radxa ones, I can’t comment on how good their support is, but they are very likely to suffer from the same limitations, software wise.</p>
<p><img src="https://boilingsteam.com/orange-pi-6-plus-review/orangepi6plus_alternatives.avif" alt="OrangePi 6 Plus versus the Radxa competition"></p>
<p>As expected, they also only provide a <a href="https://docs.radxa.com/en/orion/download#radxa-os">Debian Bookworm image under the Radxa OS nickname</a> so this is no different from what you can get on the <em>OrangePi 6 Plus</em>. Price-wise, they are both available at around similar price points, so you could make you decision based on the best deal you can get.</p>
<h2 id="sec:verdict">Verdict</h2>
<p>This is a <strong>very impressive SBC</strong>, with an exceptional value proposition. Its performance profile puts if far away from the <em>toy</em> category from what we have seen before in the SBC category, and puts it right into the desktop performance realm. It’s still relatively small so you could easily attach it behind a monitor and power a personal computer this way. As a Linux user, things are so fast that you’d be very surprised this is an ARM board running under the hood. For server use, you’d probably want to avoid this one, because of the fairly heavily baseline power consumption.</p>
<p>As usual, the pitfalls are always going to be the same. This time around you get an <em>older Debian image</em> (bookworm), with an <em>older kernel</em> (6.6), and some proprietary drivers that you have to live with. Ultimately if you want to upgrade the software running on your SBC that will mean breaking things, and there’s often a fairly long time (if ever) for some hardware components to be supported in newer distros. It’s not necessarily a deal breaker these days. This board is fast enough to compile software fairly quickly if needed. You have Flatpak as well providing some good coverage for a lot of application (even if performance may be sub-par). There are ongoing efforts to mainline the GPU found in the chip, so it could be that a year from now we are in a better place when it comes to proper hardware support beyond kernel 6.6.</p>
<p>In any case, this is a surprising new entry in terms of performance / price point. This puts the bar very high for future SBCs ARM64 SBCs. On a personal note, I’d like to see some serious hardware dedicated to running AI models (instead of large desktops chaining multiple GPUs), and maybe highly customized ARM64 SBCs are going to become one option at some point.</p>
<p>If you are interested in getting one, there are many resellers, but one of the most direct ones are on Aliexpress:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://ja.aliexpress.com/item/1005010153505031.html">Link1</a> : 16GB at about 223 USD</li>
<li><a href="https://ja.aliexpress.com/item/1005010153177606.html">Link2</a> : 32GB at about 258 USD</li>
<li><a href="https://ja.aliexpress.com/item/1005010159135486.html">Link3</a> : 32GB at about 258 USD</li>
</ul>
<p>Since the difference of price between 16 GB and 32GB is so small currently, it would make total sense to go for the 32GB.</p>
<p>Note: we were provided with a review unit from <em>OrangePi</em> (more specifically the OrangePi 6 Plus 16GB version).</p>
    
    </section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>