<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 22:30:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How the "Kim" dump exposed North Korea's credential theft playbook (120 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://dti.domaintools.com/inside-the-kimsuky-leak-how-the-kim-dump-exposed-north-koreas-credential-theft-playbook/</link>
            <guid>45152066</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 19:14:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://dti.domaintools.com/inside-the-kimsuky-leak-how-the-kim-dump-exposed-north-koreas-credential-theft-playbook/">https://dti.domaintools.com/inside-the-kimsuky-leak-how-the-kim-dump-exposed-north-koreas-credential-theft-playbook/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45152066">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                                
<p>Contents:<br>Part I: Technical Analysis<br>Part II: Goals Analysis<br>Part III: Threat Intelligence Report</p>



<h2><strong>Executive Summary</strong></h2>



<p>A rare and revealing <a href="https://ddosecrets.com/article/apt-down-the-north-korea-files">breach</a> attributed to a North Korean-affiliated actor, known only as “Kim” as named by the hackers who dumped the data, has delivered a new insight into Kimsuky (APT43) tactics, techniques, and infrastructure. This actor’s operational profile showcases credential-focused intrusions targeting South Korean and Taiwanese networks, with a blending of Chinese-language tooling, infrastructure, and possible logistical support. The “Kim” dump, which includes bash histories, phishing domains, OCR workflows, compiled stagers, and rootkit evidence, reflects a hybrid operation situated between DPRK attribution and Chinese resource utilization.</p>



<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;68bcb3c94b616&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1546" height="965" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-41.png" alt=""><figcaption>Screen shot of the adversary’s desktop VM</figcaption></figure>



<p>This report is broken down into three parts:&nbsp;</p>



<ul>
<li>Technical Analysis of the dump materials</li>



<li>Motivation and Goals of the APT actor (group)</li>



<li>A CTI report compartment for analysts</li>
</ul>



<p>While this leak only gives a partial idea of what the Kimusky/PRC activities have been, the material provides insight into the expansion of activities, nature of the actor(s), and goals they have in their penetration of the South Korean governmental systems that would benefit not only DPRK, but also PRC.</p>



<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;68bcb3c94c51c&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image"><img decoding="async" width="1418" height="1152" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-40.png" alt=""><figcaption>Phrack article</figcaption></figure>



<p>Without a doubt, there will be more coming out from this dump in the future, particularly if the burned assets have not been taken offline and access is still available, or if others have cloned those assets for further analysis. We may revisit this in the future if additional novel information comes to light.</p>



<h2><strong>Part I: Technical Analysis</strong></h2>



<h2><strong>The Leak at a Glance</strong></h2>



<p>The leaked dataset attributed to the “Kim” operator offers a uniquely operational perspective into North Korean-aligned cyber operations. Among the contents were terminal history files revealing active malware development efforts using NASM (Netwide Assembler), a choice consistent with low-level shellcode engineering typically reserved for custom loaders and injection tools. These logs were not static forensic artifacts but active command-line histories showing iterative compilation and cleanup processes, suggesting a hands-on attacker directly involved in tool assembly.</p>



<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;68bcb3c94cb8c&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image"><img decoding="async" width="220" height="329" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-39.png" alt=""><figcaption>File list of dump</figcaption></figure>



<p>In parallel, the operator ran OCR (Optical Character Recognition) commands against sensitive Korean PDF documents related to public key infrastructure (PKI) standards and VPN deployments. These actions likely aimed to extract structured language or configurations for use in spoofing, credential forgery, or internal tool emulation.</p>



<p>Privileged Access Management (PAM) logs also surfaced in the dump, detailing a timeline of password changes and administrative account use. Many were tagged with the Korean string 변경완료 (“change complete”), and the logs included repeated references to elevated accounts such as oracle, svradmin, and app_adm01, indicating sustained access to critical systems.</p>



<p>The phishing infrastructure was extensive. Domain telemetry pointed to a network of malicious sites designed to mimic legitimate Korean government portals. Sites like nid-security[.]com were crafted to fool users into handing over credentials via advanced AiTM (Adversary-in-the-Middle) techniques.</p>



<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;68bcb3c94d0a7&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1600" height="630" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-38.png" alt=""><figcaption>nid-security[.]com phishing domain (anon reg 2024)</figcaption></figure>



<p>Finally, network artifacts within the dump showed targeted reconnaissance of Taiwanese government and academic institutions. Specific IP addresses and .tw domain access, along with attempts to crawl .git repositories, reveal a deliberate focus on high-value administrative and developer targets.</p>



<p>Perhaps most concerning was the inclusion of a Linux rootkit using syscall hooking (<a href="https://sandflysecurity.com/blog/leaked-north-korean-linux-stealth-rootkit-analysis">khook</a>) and stealth persistence via directories like /usr/lib64/tracker-fs. This highlights a capability for deep system compromise and covert command-and-control operations, far beyond phishing and data theft.</p>



<p>Artifacts recovered from the dump include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Terminal history files demonstrating malware compilation using NASM<br></li>



<li>OCR commands parsing Korean PDF documents related to PKI and VPN infrastructure<br></li>



<li>PAM logs reflecting password changes and credential lifecycle events<br></li>



<li>Phishing infrastructure mimicking Korean government sites<br></li>



<li>IP addresses indicating reconnaissance of Taiwanese government and research institutions<br></li>



<li>Linux rootkit code using syscall hooking and covert channel deployment<br></li>
</ul>



<h2><strong>Credential Theft Focus</strong></h2>



<p>The dump strongly emphasizes credential harvesting as a central operational goal. Key files such as 136백운규001_env.key <em>(The presence of 136백운규001_env.key is a smoking gun indicator of stolen South Korean Government PKI material, as its structure (numeric ID + Korean name + .key) aligns uniquely with SK GPKI issuance practices and provides clear evidence of compromised, identity-tied state cryptographic keys.)</em> This was discovered alongside plaintext passwords, that indicate clear evidence of active compromise of South Korea’s GPKI (Government Public Key Infrastructure). Possession of such certificates would allow for highly effective identity spoofing across government systems.</p>



<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;68bcb3c94d537&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1600" height="80" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-37.png" alt=""></figure>



<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;68bcb3c94daaa&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1417" height="427" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-36.png" alt=""></figure>



<p>PAM logs further confirmed this focus, showing a pattern of administrative account rotation and password resets, all timestamped and labeled with success indicators (변경완료: Change Complete). The accounts affected were not low-privilege; instead, usernames like oracle, svradmin, and app_adm01, often used by IT staff and infrastructure services, suggested access to core backend environments.</p>



<p>These findings point to a strategy centered on capturing and maintaining access to privileged credentials and digital certificates, effectively allowing the attacker to act as an insider within trusted systems.</p>



<ul>
<li>Leaked .key files (e.g., 136백운규001_env.key) with plaintext passwords confirm access to GPKI systems<br></li>



<li>PAM logs show administrative password rotations tagged with 변경완료 (change complete)<br></li>



<li>Admin-level accounts such as oracle, svradmin, and app_adm01 repeatedly appear in compromised logs<br></li>
</ul>



<h2><strong>Phishing Infrastructure</strong></h2>



<p>The operator’s phishing infrastructure was both expansive and regionally tailored. Domains such as nid-security[.]com and webcloud-notice[.]com mimicked Korean identity and document delivery services, likely designed to intercept user logins or deploy malicious payloads. More sophisticated spoofing was seen in sites that emulated official government agencies like dcc.mil[.]kr, spo.go[.]kr, and mofa.go[.]kr.</p>



<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;68bcb3c94df9d&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1600" height="813" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-35.png" alt=""><figcaption>Whoisof domains created by dysoni91@tutamail[.]com</figcaption></figure>



<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;68bcb3c94e530&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1600" height="1592" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-34.png" alt=""><figcaption>Historical Whois of webcloud-notice[.]com</figcaption></figure>



<p>Burner email usage added another layer of operational tradecraft. The address jeder97271[@]wuzak[.]com is likely linked to phishing kits that operated through TLS proxies, capturing credentials in real time as victims interacted with spoofed login forms.</p>



<p>These tactics align with previously known Kimsuky behaviors but also demonstrate an evolution in technical implementation, particularly the use of AiTM interception rather than relying solely on credential-harvesting documents.</p>



<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;68bcb3c94e7cb&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1130" height="548" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-33.png" alt=""><figcaption>Domain connections map</figcaption></figure>



<ul>
<li>Domains include: nid-security[.]com, html-load[.]com, webcloud-notice[.]com, koala-app[.]com, and wuzak[.]com<br></li>



<li>Mimicked portals: dcc.mil[.]kr, spo.go[.]kr, mofa.go[.]kr<br></li>



<li>Burner email evidence: jeder97271[@]wuzak[.]com<br></li>



<li>Phishing kits leveraged TLS proxies for AiTM credential capture<br></li>
</ul>



<h2><strong>Malware Development Activity</strong></h2>



<p>Kim’s malware development environment showcased a highly manual, tailored approach. Shellcode was compiled using NASM, specifically with flags like -f win32, revealing a focus on targeting Windows environments. Commands such as make and rm were used to automate and sanitize builds, while hashed API call resolution (VirtualAlloc, HttpSendRequestA, etc.) was implemented to evade antivirus heuristics.</p>



<p>The dump also revealed reliance on GitHub repositories known for offensive tooling. TitanLdr, minbeacon, Blacklotus, and CobaltStrike-Auto-Keystore were all cloned or referenced in command logs. This hybrid use of public frameworks for private malware assembly is consistent with modern APT workflows.</p>



<p>A notable technical indicator was the use of the proxyres library to extract Windows proxy settings, particularly via functions like proxy_config_win_get_auto_config_url. This suggests an interest in hijacking or bypassing network-level security controls within enterprise environments.</p>



<ul>
<li>Manual shellcode compilation via nasm -f win32 source/asm/x86/start.asm<br></li>



<li>Use of make, rm, and hash obfuscation of Win32 API calls (e.g., VirtualAlloc, HttpSendRequestA)<br></li>



<li>GitHub tools in use: TitanLdr, minbeacon, Blacklotus, CobaltStrike-Auto-Keystore<br></li>



<li>Proxy configuration probing through proxyres library (proxy_config_win_get_auto_config_url)</li>
</ul>



<h2><strong>Rootkit Toolkit and Implant Structure</strong></h2>



<p>The Kim dump offers deep insight into a stealthy and modular Linux rootkit attributed to the operator’s post-compromise persistence tactics. The core implant, identified as vmmisc.ko (alternatively VMmisc.ko in some shells), was designed for kernel-mode deployment across multiple x86_64 Linux distributions and utilizes classic syscall hooking and covert channeling to maintain long-term undetected access.</p>



<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;68bcb3c94ed9a&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="791" height="1123" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-32.png" alt=""></figure>



<h3>Google Translation of Koh doc: Rootkit Endpoint Reuse Authentication Tool</h3>



<p><em>“This tool uses kernel-level rootkit hiding technology, providing a high degree of stealth and penetration connection capability. It can hide while running on common Linux systems, and at the kernel layer supports connection forwarding, allowing reuse of external ports to connect to controlled hosts. Its communication behavior is hidden within normal traffic.</em></p>



<p><em>The tool uses </em><strong><em>binary merging technology</em></strong><em>: at compile time, the application layer program is encrypted and fused into a </em><strong><em>.ko driver file</em></strong><em>. When installed, only the </em><em>.ko</em><em> file exists. When the </em><em>.ko</em><em> driver starts, it will automatically decompress and release the hidden application-layer program.</em></p>



<p><em>Tools like </em><strong><em>chkrootkit</em></strong><em>, </em><strong><em>rkhunter</em></strong><em>, and management utilities (such as </em><em>ps</em><em>, </em><em>netstat</em><em>, etc.) are bypassed through technical evasion and hiding, making them unable to detect hidden </em><strong><em>networks, ports, processes, or file information</em></strong><em>.</em></p>



<p><em>To ensure software stability, all functions have also passed stress testing.</em></p>



<p><strong><em>Supported systems:</em></strong><em> Linux Kernel 2.6.x / 3.x / 4.x, both x32 and x64 systems”.</em></p>



<p><strong>Implant Features and Behavior</strong></p>



<p>This rootkit exhibits several advanced features:</p>



<ul>
<li>Syscall Hooking: Hooks critical kernel functions (e.g., getdents, read, write) to hide files, directories, and processes by name or PID.</li>



<li>SOCKS5 Proxy: Integrated remote networking capability using dynamic port forwarding and chained routing.</li>



<li>PTY Backdoor Shell: Spawns pseudoterminals that operate as interactive reverse shells with password protection.</li>



<li>Encrypted Sessions: Session commands must match a pre-set passphrase (e.g., testtest) to activate rootkit control mode.</li>
</ul>



<p>Once installed (typically using insmod vmmisc.ko), the rootkit listens silently and allows manipulation via an associated client binary found in the dump. The client supports an extensive set of interactive commands, including:</p>



<p>+p&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; # list hidden processes</p>



<p>+f&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; # list hidden files</p>



<p>callrk&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; # load client ↔ kernel handshake</p>



<p>exitrk&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; # gracefully unload implant</p>



<p>shell &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; # spawn reverse shell</p>



<p>socks5&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; # initiate proxy channel</p>



<p>upload / download # file transfer interface</p>



<p>These capabilities align closely with known DPRK malware behaviors, particularly from the Kimsuky and Lazarus groups, who have historically leveraged rootkits for lateral movement, stealth, persistence, and exfiltration staging.</p>



<h2><strong>Observed Deployment</strong></h2>



<p>Terminal history (.bash_history) shows the implant was staged and tested from the following paths:</p>



<pre><code>.cache/vmware/drag_and_drop/VMmisc.ko

/usr/lib64/tracker-fs/vmmisc.ko

Execution logs show the use of commands such as:

insmod /usr/lib64/tracker-fs/vmmisc.ko

./client 192.168.0[.]39 testtest</code></pre>



<p>These paths were not random—they mimic legitimate system service locations to avoid detection by file integrity monitoring (FIM) tools.</p>



<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;68bcb3c94f4b1&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1600" height="287" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-31.png" alt=""><figcaption>Deployment map</figcaption></figure>



<p>This structure highlights the modular, command-activated nature of the implant and its ability to serve multiple post-exploitation roles while maintaining stealth through kernel-layer masking.</p>



<h2><strong>Strategic Implications</strong></h2>



<p>The presence of such an advanced toolkit in the “Kim” dump strongly suggests the actor had persistent access to Linux server environments, likely via credential compromise. The use of kernel-mode implants also indicates long-term intent and trust-based privilege escalation. The implant’s pathing, language patterns, and tactics (e.g., use of /tracker-fs/, use of test passwords) match TTPs previously observed in operations attributed to Kimsuky, enhancing confidence in North Korean origin.</p>



<h2><strong>OCR-Based Recon</strong></h2>



<p>A defining component of Kim’s tradecraft was the use of OCR to analyze Korean-language security documentation. The attacker issued commands such as ocrmypdf -l kor+eng “file.pdf” to parse documents like 별지2)행정전자서명_기술요건_141125.pdf (“Appendix 2: Administrative Electronic Signature_Technical Requirements_141125.pdf”) and SecuwaySSL U_카달로그.pdf (“SecuwaySSL U_Catalog.pdf”). These files contain technical language around digital signatures, SSL implementations, and identity verification standards used in South Korea’s PKI infrastructure.</p>



<p>This OCR-based collection approach indicates more than passive intelligence gathering – it reflects a deliberate effort to model and potentially clone government-grade authentication systems. The use of bilingual OCR (Korean + English) further confirms the operator’s intention to extract usable configuration data across documentation types.</p>



<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;68bcb3c94faf6&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="841" height="766" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-30.png" alt=""><figcaption>OCR run on Korean PDFs</figcaption></figure>



<ul>
<li>OCR commands used to extract Korean PKI policy language from PDFs such as (별지2)행정전자서명_기술요건_141125.pdf and SecuwaySSL U_카달로그.pdf
<ul>
<li><em>별지2)행정전자서명_기술요건_141125.pdf → (Appendix 2: Administrative Electronic Signature_Technical Requirements_141125.pdf</em></li>



<li><em>SecuwaySSL U_카달로그.pdf → SecuwaySSL U_Catalog.pdf</em><br></li>
</ul>
</li>



<li>Command examples: ocrmypdf -l kor+eng “file.pdf”<br></li>
</ul>



<h2><strong>SSH and Log-Based Evidence</strong></h2>



<p>The forensic evidence contained within the logs, specifically SSH authentication records and PAM outputs, provides clear technical confirmation of the operator’s tactics and target focus.</p>



<p>Several IP addresses stood out as sources of brute-force login attempts. These include 23.95.213[.]210 (a known VPS provider used in past credential-stuffing campaigns), 218.92.0[.]210 (allocated to a Chinese ISP), and 122.114.233[.]77 (Henan Mobile, China). These IPs were recorded during multiple failed login events, strongly suggesting automated password attacks against exposed SSH services. Their geographic distribution and known history in malicious infrastructure usage point to an external staging environment, possibly used for pivoting into Korean and Taiwanese systems.</p>



<p>Beyond brute force, the logs also contain evidence of authentication infrastructure reconnaissance. Multiple PAM and OCSP (Online Certificate Status Protocol) errors referenced South Korea’s national PKI authority, including domains like gva.gpki.go[.]kr and ivs.gpki.go[.]kr. These errors appear during scripted or automated access attempts, indicating a potential strategy of credential replay or certificate misuse against GPKI endpoints, an approach that aligns with Kim’s broader PKI-targeting operations.</p>



<p>Perhaps the most revealing detail was the presence of successful superuser logins labeled with the Korean term 최고 관리자 (“Super Administrator”). This suggests the actor was not just harvesting credentials but successfully leveraging them for privileged access, possibly through cracked accounts, reused credentials, or insider-sourced passwords. The presence of such accounts in conjunction with password rotation entries marked as 변경완료 (“change complete”) further implies active control over PAM-protected systems during the operational window captured in the dump.</p>



<p>Together, these logs demonstrate a methodical campaign combining external brute-force access, PKI service probing, and administrative credential takeover, a sequence tailored for persistent infiltration and lateral movement within sensitive government and enterprise networks.</p>



<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;68bcb3c950073&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1600" height="402" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-29.png" alt=""><figcaption>Brute force mapping</figcaption></figure>



<ul>
<li>Brute-force IPs: 23.95.213[.]210, 218.92.0[.]210, 122.114.233[.]77</li>
</ul>



<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><strong>IP Address</strong></td><td><strong>Origin</strong></td><td><strong>Role / Threat Context</strong></td></tr><tr><td>218.92.0[.]210</td><td>China Telecom (Jiangsu)</td><td>Part of Chinanet backbone, likely proxy or scanning node</td></tr><tr><td>23.95.213[.]210</td><td>Colocrossing (US)</td><td>Frequently used in brute-force and anonymized hosting for malware ops</td></tr><tr><td>122.114.233[.]77</td><td>Presumed PRC local ISP</td><td>Possibly mobile/ISP-based proxy used to obfuscate lateral movement</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<ul>
<li>PAM/OCSP errors targeting gva.gpki.go[.]kr, ivs.gpki.go[.]kr<br></li>



<li>Superuser login events under 최고 관리자 (Super Administrator)</li>
</ul>



<h2><strong>Part II: Goals Analysis</strong></h2>



<h2><strong>Targeting South Korea: Identity, Infrastructure, and Credential Theft</strong></h2>



<p>The “Kim” operator’s campaign against South Korea was deliberate and strategic, aiming to infiltrate the nation’s digital trust infrastructure at multiple levels. A central focus was the Government Public Key Infrastructure (GPKI), where the attacker exfiltrated certificate files, including .key and .crt formats, some with plaintext passwords, and attempted repeated authentication against domains like gva.gpki.go[.]kr and ivs.gpki.go[.]kr. OCR tools were used to parse Korean technical documents detailing PKI and VPN architectures, demonstrating a sophisticated effort to understand and potentially subvert national identity frameworks. These efforts were not limited to reconnaissance; administrative password changes were logged, and phishing kits targeted military and diplomatic webmail, including clones of mofa.go[.]kr and credential harvesting through adversary-in-the-middle (AiTM) proxy setups.</p>



<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;68bcb3c9506b0&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1600" height="961" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-28.png" alt=""><figcaption>Attempts at user account authentication</figcaption></figure>



<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;68bcb3c950b1b&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1504" height="54" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-27.png" alt=""><figcaption>Servlet requests for KR domains</figcaption></figure>



<p>Beyond authentication systems, Kim targeted privileged accounts (oracle, unwadm, svradmin) and rotated credentials to maintain persistent administrative access, as evidenced by PAM and SSH logs showing elevated user activity under the title 최고 관리자 (“Super Administrator”). The actor also showed interest in bypassing VPN controls, parsing SecuwaySSL configurations for exploitation potential, and deployed custom Linux rootkits using syscall hooking to establish covert persistence on compromised machines. Taken together, the dump reveals a threat actor deeply invested in credential dominance, policy reconnaissance, and system-level infiltration, placing South Korea’s public sector identity systems, administrative infrastructure, and secure communications at the core of its long-term espionage objectives.</p>



<h2><strong>Taiwan Reconnaissance</strong></h2>



<p>Among the most notable aspects of the “Kim” leak is the operator’s deliberate focus on Taiwanese infrastructure. The attacker accessed a number of domains with clear affiliations to the island’s public and private sectors, including tw.systexcloud[.]com (linked to enterprise cloud solutions), mlogin.mdfapps[.]com (a mobile authentication or enterprise login portal), and the .git/ directory of caa.org[.]tw, which belongs to the Chinese Institute of Aeronautics, a government-adjacent research entity.</p>



<p>This last domain is especially telling. Accessing .git/ paths directly implies an attempt to enumerate internal source code repositories, a tactic often used to discover hardcoded secrets, API keys, deployment scripts, or developer credentials inadvertently exposed via misconfigured web servers. This behavior points to&nbsp; more technical depth than simple phishing; it indicates supply chain reconnaissance and long-term infiltration planning.</p>



<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;68bcb3c950f25&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1600" height="546" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-26.png" alt=""><figcaption>Taiwanese target map</figcaption></figure>



<p>The associated IP addresses further reinforce this conclusion. All three, 163.29.3[.]119, 118.163.30[.]45, and 59.125.159[.]81, are registered to academic, government, or research backbone providers in Taiwan. These are not random scans; they reflect targeted probing of strategic digital assets.</p>



<h2>Summary of Whois &amp; Ownership Insights</h2>



<ul>
<li>118.163.30[.]45
<ul>
<li>Appears as part of the IP range used for the domain dtc-tpe.com[.]tw, linked to Taiwan’s HINET provider (118.163.30[.]46 )<a href="https://dtc-tpe.com.tw.siteindices.com/?utm">Site Indices page of HINET provider</a>.</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li>163.29.3[.]119
<ul>
<li>Falls within the 163.29.3[.]0/24 subnet identified with Taiwanese government or institutional use, notably in Taipei. This corresponds to B‑class subnets assigned to public/government entities<a href="https://zh-hant.ipshu.com/ip_d_list/163.29.3?utm_source=chatgpt.com"> IP地址 (繁體中文)</a>.</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li>59.125.159[.]81<br>
<ul>
<li>Belongs to the broader 59.125.159[.]0–59.125.159[.]254 block, commonly used by Taiwanese ISP operators such as Chunghwa Telecom in Taipei</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<p>Taken together, this Taiwan-focused activity reveals an expanded operational mandate. Whether the attacker is purely DPRK-aligned or operating within a <em>DPRK–PRC fusion cell</em>, the intent is clear: compromise administrative and developer infrastructure in Taiwan, likely in preparation for broader credential theft, espionage, or disruption campaigns.</p>



<ul>
<li>Targeted domains: tw.systexcloud[.]com, caa.org[.]tw/.git/, mlogin.mdfapps[.]com<br></li>



<li>IPs linked to Taiwanese academic/government assets: 163.29.3[.]119, 118.163.30[.]45, 59.125.159[.]81<br></li>



<li>Git crawling suggests interest in developer secrets or exposed tokens<br></li>
</ul>



<h2><strong>Hybrid Attribution Model</strong></h2>



<p>The “Kim” operator embodies the growing complexity of modern nation-state attribution, where cyber activities often blur traditional boundaries and merge capabilities across geopolitical spheres. This case reveals strong indicators of both North Korean origin and Chinese operational entanglement, presenting a textbook example of a hybrid APT model.</p>



<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;68bcb3c951456&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1600" height="175" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-25.png" alt=""></figure>



<p>On one hand, the technical and linguistic evidence strongly supports a DPRK-native operator. Terminal environments, OCR parsing routines, and system artifacts consistently leverage Korean language and character sets. The operator’s activities reflect a deep understanding of Korean PKI systems, with targeted extraction of GPKI .key files and automation to parse sensitive Korean government PDF documentation. These are hallmarks of Kimsuky/APT43 operations, known for credential-focused espionage against South Korean institutions and diplomatic targets. The intent to infiltrate identity infrastructure is consistent with North Korea’s historical targeting priorities. <a href="https://data.ddosecrets.com/APT%20Down%20-%20The%20North%20Korea%20Files/phrack-apt-down-the-north-korea-files.pdf">Notably, the system time zone</a> on Kim’s host machine was set to UTC+9 (Pyongyang Standard Time), reinforcing the theory that the actor maintains direct ties to the DPRK’s internal environment, even if operating remotely.</p>



<p>However, this actor’s digital footprint extends well into Chinese infrastructure. Browser and download logs reveal frequent interaction with platforms like gitee[.]com, baidu[.]com, and zhihu[.]com, highly popular within the PRC but unusual for DPRK operators who typically minimize exposure to foreign services. Moreover, session logs include simplified Chinese content and PRC browsing behaviors, suggesting that the actor may be physically operating within China or through Chinese-language systems. This aligns with longstanding intelligence on North Korean cyber operators stationed in Chinese border cities such as Shenyang and Dandong, where DPRK nationals often conduct cyber operations with tacit approval or logistical consent from Chinese authorities. These locations provide higher-speed internet, relaxed oversight, and convenient geopolitical proximity.</p>



<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;68bcb3c9518d7&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1600" height="322" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-24.png" alt=""><figcaption>Browser History viewing Taiwanese and Chinese sites</figcaption></figure>



<p>The targeting of Taiwanese infrastructure further complicates attribution. Kimsuky has not historically prioritized Taiwan, yet in this case, the actor demonstrated direct reconnaissance of Taiwanese government and developer networks. While this overlaps with Chinese APT priorities, recent evidence from the “Kim” dump, including analysis of phishing kits and credential theft workflows, suggests this activity was likely performed by a DPRK actor exploring broader regional interests, possibly in alignment with Chinese strategic goals. Researchers have noted that Kimsuky operators have recently asked questions in phishing lures related to potential Chinese-Taiwanese conflicts, implying interest beyond the Korean peninsula.</p>



<p>Some tooling overlaps with PRC-linked APTs, particularly GitHub-based stagers and proxy-resolving modules, but these are not uncommon in the open-source malware ecosystem and may reflect opportunistic reuse rather than deliberate mimicry.</p>



<h2><strong>IMINT Analysis: Visual Tradecraft and Cultural Camouflage</strong></h2>



<p>A review of image artifacts linked to the “Kim” actor reveals a deliberate and calculated use of Chinese social and technological visual content as part of their operational persona. These images, extracted from browser history and uploads attributed to the actor, demonstrate both strategic alignment with DPRK priorities and active cultural camouflage within the PRC digital ecosystem.</p>



<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;68bcb3c951cce&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1600" height="886" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-23.png" alt=""><figcaption>Uploads of images by Kim found in browser history</figcaption></figure>



<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;68bcb3c95208f&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1600" height="1287" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-22.png" alt=""><figcaption>Images downloaded from aixfan[.]com</figcaption></figure>



<p>The visual set includes promotional graphics for Honor smartphones, SoC chipset evolution charts, Weibo posts featuring vehicle registration certificates, meme-based sarcasm, and lifestyle imagery typical of Chinese internet users. Notably, the content is exclusively rendered in simplified Chinese, reinforcing prior assessments that the operator either resides within mainland China or maintains a working digital identity embedded in Chinese platforms. Devices and services referenced, such as Xiaomi phones, Zhihu, Weibo, and Baidu, suggest intimate familiarity with PRC user environments.</p>



<p>Operationally, this behavior achieves two goals. First, it enables the actor to blend in seamlessly with native PRC user activity, which complicates attribution and helps bypass platform moderation or behavioral anomaly detection. Second, the content itself may serve as bait or credibility scaffolding (e.g. A framework to give the illusion of trust to allow for easier compromise ) in phishing and social engineering campaigns, especially those targeting developers or technical users on Chinese-language platforms.</p>



<p>Some images, such as the detailed chipset timelines and VPN or device certification posts, suggest a continued interest in supply chain reconnaissance and endpoint profiling—both tradecraft hallmarks of Kimsuky and similar APT units. Simultaneously, meme humor, sarcastic overlays, and visual metaphors (e.g., the “Kaiju’s tail is showing” idiom) indicate the actor’s fluency in PRC netizen culture and possible mockery of operational security breaches—whether their own or others’.</p>



<p>Taken together, this IMINT corpus supports the broader attribution model: a DPRK-origin operator embedded, physically or virtually, within the PRC, leveraging local infrastructure and social platforms to facilitate long-term campaigns against South Korea, Taiwan, and other regional targets while maintaining cultural and technical deniability.</p>



<h2><strong>Attribution Scenarios:</strong></h2>



<ul>
<li><strong>Option A: DPRK Operator Embedded in PRC</strong><br>
<ul>
<li>Use of Korean language, OCR targeting of Korean documents, and focus on GPKI systems strongly suggest North Korean origin.<br></li>



<li>Use of PRC infrastructure (e.g., Baidu, Gitee) and simplified Chinese content implies the operator is physically located in China or benefits from access to Chinese internet infrastructure.<br></li>
</ul>
</li>



<li><strong>Option B: PRC Operator Emulating DPRK</strong><br>
<ul>
<li>Taiwan-focused reconnaissance aligns with PRC cyber priorities.<br></li>



<li>Use of open-source tooling and phishing methods shared with PRC APTs could indicate tactical emulation.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<p>The preponderance of evidence supports the hypothesis that “Kim” is a North Korean cyber operator embedded in China or collaborating with PRC infrastructure providers. This operational model allows the DPRK to amplify its reach, mask attribution, and adopt regional targeting strategies beyond South Korea, particularly toward Taiwan. As this hybrid model matures, it reflects the strategic adaptation of DPRK-aligned threat actors who exploit the permissive digital environment of Chinese networks to evade detection and expand their operational playbook.</p>



<h2><strong>Targeting Profiles</strong></h2>



<p>The “Kim” leak provides one of the clearest windows to date into the role-specific targeting preferences of the operator, revealing a deliberate focus on system administrators, credential issuers, and backend developers, particularly in South Korea and Taiwan.</p>



<p>In South Korea, the operator’s interest centers around PKI administrators and infrastructure engineers. The recovered OCR commands were used to extract technical details from PDF documents outlining Korea’s digital signature protocols, such as identity verification, certificate validation, and encrypted communications, components that form the backbone of Korea’s secure authentication systems. The goal appears to be not only credential theft but full understanding and potential replication of government-trusted PKI procedures. This level of targeting suggests a strategic intent to penetrate deeply trusted systems, potentially for use in later spoofing or identity masquerading operations.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1058" height="1264" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-21.png" alt=""><figcaption>PKI attack targets</figcaption></figure>



<p>In Taiwan, the operator shifted focus to developer infrastructure and cloud access portals. Specific domains accessed, like caa.org[.]tw/.git/, indicate attempts to enumerate internal repositories, most likely to discover hardcoded secrets, authentication tokens, or deployment keys. This is a classic supply chain targeting method, aiming to access downstream systems via compromised developer credentials or misconfigured services.</p>



<p>Additional activity pointed to interaction with cloud service login panels such as tw.systexcloud[.]com and mlogin.mdfapps[.]com. These suggest an attempt to breach centralized authentication systems or identity providers, granting the actor broader access into enterprise or government networks with a single credential set.</p>



<p>Taken together, these targeting profiles reflect a clear emphasis on identity providers, backend engineers, and those with access to system-level secrets. This reinforces the broader theme of the dump: persistent, credential-first intrusion strategies, augmented by reconnaissance of authentication standards, key management policies, and endpoint development infrastructure.</p>



<p><strong>South Korean</strong>:</p>



<ul>
<li>PKI admins, infrastructure engineers<br></li>



<li>OCR focus on Korean identity standards<br></li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Taiwanese</strong>:</p>



<ul>
<li>Developer endpoints and internal .git/ repos<br></li>



<li>Access to cloud panels and login gateways<br></li>
</ul>



<h2><strong>Final Assessment</strong></h2>



<p>The “Kim” leak represents one of the most comprehensive and technically intimate disclosures ever associated with Kimsuky (APT43) or its adjacent operators. It not only reaffirms known tactics, credential theft, phishing, and PKI compromise, but exposes the inner workings of the operator’s environment, tradecraft, and operational intent in ways rarely observed outside of active forensic investigations.</p>



<p>At the core of the leak is a technically competent actor, well-versed in low-level shellcode development, Linux-based persistence mechanisms, and certificate infrastructure abuse. Their use of NASM, API hashing, and rootkit deployment points to custom malware authorship. Furthermore, the presence of parsed government-issued Korean PDFs, combined with OCR automation, shows not just opportunistic data collection but a concerted effort to model, mimic, or break state-level identity systems, particularly South Korea’s GPKI.</p>



<p>The operator’s cultural and linguistic fluency in Korean, and their targeting of administrative and privileged systems across South Korean institutions, support a high-confidence attribution to a DPRK-native threat actor. However, the extensive use of Chinese platforms like gitee[.]com, Baidu, and Zhihu, and Chinese infrastructure for both malware hosting and browsing activity reveals a geographical pivot or collaboration: a hybrid APT footprint rooted in DPRK tradecraft but operating from or with Chinese support.</p>



<p>Most notably, this leak uncovers a geographical expansion of operational interest; the actor is no longer solely focused on the Korean peninsula. The targeting of Taiwanese developer portals, government research IPs, and .git/ repositories shows a broadened agenda that likely maps to both espionage and supply chain infiltration priorities. This places Taiwan, like South Korea, at the forefront of North Korean cyber interest, whether for intelligence gathering, credential hijacking, or as staging points for more complex campaigns.</p>



<p>The threat uncovered here is not merely malware or phishing; it is an infrastructure-centric, credential-first APT campaign that blends highly manual operations (e.g., hand-compiled shellcode, direct OCR of sensitive PDFs) with modern deception tactics such as AiTM phishing and TLS proxy abuse.</p>



<p>Organizations in Taiwan and South Korea, particularly those managing identity, certificate, and cloud access infrastructure, should consider themselves under persistent, credential-focused surveillance. Defensive strategies must prioritize detection of behavioral anomalies (e.g., use of OCR tools, GPKI access attempts), outbound communications with spoofed Korean domains, and the appearance of low-level toolchains like NASM or proxyres-based scanning utilities within developer or admin environments.</p>



<p>In short: the “Kim” actor embodies the evolution of nation-state cyber threats—a fusion of old-school persistence, credential abuse, and modern multi-jurisdictional staging. The threat is long-term, embedded, and adaptive.</p>



<h2><strong>Part III: Threat Intelligence Report</strong></h2>



<h2><strong>TLP WHITE:</strong></h2>



<h3><strong>Targeting Summary</strong></h3>



<p>The analysis of the “Kim” operator dump reveals a highly focused credential-theft and infrastructure-access campaign targeting high-value assets in both South Korea and Taiwan. Victims were selected based on their proximity to trusted authentication systems, administrative control panels, and development environments.</p>



<figure><table><tbody><tr><td>Category</td><td>Details</td></tr><tr><td>Regions</td><td>South Korea, Taiwan</td></tr><tr><td>Targets</td><td>Government, Telecom, Enterprise IT</td></tr><tr><td>Accounts</td><td>svradmin, oracle, app_adm01, unwadm, shkim88, jaejung91</td></tr><tr><td>Domains</td><td>tw.systexcloud[.]com, nid-security[.]com, spo.go[.]kr, caa.org[.]tw/.git/</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h3><strong>Indicators of Compromise (IOCs)</strong></h3>



<h4><strong>Domains</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Phishing: nid-security[.]com, html-load[.]com, wuzak[.]com, koala-app[.]com, webcloud-notice[.]com</li>



<li>Spoofed portals: dcc.mil[.]kr, spo.go[.]kr, mofa.go[.]kr</li>



<li>Pastebin raw links: Used for payload staging and malware delivery</li>
</ul>



<p>IP Addresses</p>



<ul>
<li>External Targets (Taiwan):
<ul>
<li>163.29.3[.]119 &nbsp; &nbsp; National Center for High-performance Computing</li>



<li>118.163.30[.]45 &nbsp; Taiwanese government subnet</li>



<li>59.125.159[.]81 &nbsp; Chunghwa Telecom</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li>Brute Forcing / Infrastructure Origins:
<ul>
<li>23.95.213[.]210 &nbsp; VPS provider with malicious history</li>



<li>218.92.0[.]210 &nbsp; &nbsp; China Unicom</li>



<li>122.114.233[.]77&nbsp; Henan Mobile, PRC</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<p>Internal Host IPs (Operator Environment)</p>



<ul>
<li>192.168.130[.]117</li>



<li>192.168.150[.]117</li>



<li>192.168.0[.]39</li>
</ul>



<h3><strong>Operator Environment: Internal Host IP Narrative</strong></h3>



<p>The presence of internal IP addresses such as 192.168.130[.]117, 192.168.150[.]117, and 192.168.0[.]39 within the dump offers valuable insight into the attacker’s local infrastructure, an often-overlooked element in threat intelligence analysis. These addresses fall within private, non-routable RFC1918 address space, commonly assigned by consumer off-the-shelf (COTS) routers and small office/home office (SOHO) network gear.</p>



<p>The use of the 192.168.0[.]0/16 subnet, particularly 192.168.0.x and 192.168.150.x, strongly suggests that the actor was operating from a residential or low-profile environment, not a formal nation-state facility or hardened infrastructure. This supports existing assessments that North Korean operators, particularly those affiliated with Kimsuky, often work remotely from locations in third countries such as China or Southeast Asia, where they can maintain inconspicuous, low-cost setups while accessing global infrastructure.</p>



<p>Moreover, the distinction between multiple internal subnets (130.x, 150.x, and 0.x) may indicate segmentation of test environments or multiple virtual machines running within a single NATed network. This aligns with the forensic evidence of iterative development and testing workflows seen in the .bash_history files, where malware stagers, rootkits, and API obfuscation utilities were compiled, cleaned, and rerun repeatedly.</p>



<p>Together, these IPs reveal an operator likely working from a clandestine, residential base of operations, with modest hardware and commercial-grade routers. This operational setup is consistent with known DPRK remote IT workers and cyber operators who avoid attribution by blending into civilian infrastructure. It also suggests the attacker may be physically located outside of North Korea, possibly embedded in a friendly or complicit environment, strengthening the case for China-based activity by DPRK nationals.</p>



<h3><strong>MITRE ATT&amp;CK Mapping</strong></h3>



<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><strong>Phase</strong></td><td><strong>Technique(s)</strong></td></tr><tr><td>Initial Access</td><td>T1566.002 ,&nbsp; Adversary-in-the-Middle (AiTM) Phishing</td></tr><tr><td>Execution</td><td>T1059.005 ,&nbsp; Native API ShellcodeT1059.003 ,&nbsp; Bash/Shell Scripts</td></tr><tr><td>Credential Access</td><td>T1555 ,&nbsp; Credential Store DumpingT1557.003 ,&nbsp; Session Hijacking</td></tr><tr><td>Persistence</td><td>T1176 ,&nbsp; Rootkit (via khook syscall manipulation)</td></tr><tr><td>Defense Evasion</td><td>T1562.001 ,&nbsp; Disable Security ToolsT1552 ,&nbsp; Unsecured Credential Files</td></tr><tr><td>Discovery</td><td>T1592 ,&nbsp; Technical Information DiscoveryT1590 ,&nbsp; Network Information</td></tr><tr><td>Exfiltration</td><td>T1041 ,&nbsp; Exfiltration over C2 ChannelT1567.002 ,&nbsp; Exfil via Cloud Services</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h3><strong>Tooling and Capabilities</strong></h3>



<p>The actor’s toolkit spans multiple disciplines, blending malware development, system reconnaissance, phishing, and proxy evasion:</p>



<ul>
<li>NASM-based shellcode loaders: Compiled manually for Windows execution.</li>



<li>Win32 API hashing: Obfuscated imports via hashstring.py to evade detection.</li>



<li>GitHub/Gitee abuse: Tooling hosted or cloned from public developer platforms.</li>



<li>OCR exploitation: Used ocrmypdf to parse Korean PDF specs related to digital certificates and VPN appliances.</li>



<li>Rootkit deployment: Hidden persistence paths including /usr/lib64/tracker-fs and /proc/acpi/pcicard.</li>



<li>Proxy config extraction: Investigated PAC URLs using proxyres-based recon.</li>
</ul>



<h3><strong>Attribution Confidence Assessment</strong></h3>



<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><strong>Attribution Candidate</strong></td><td><strong>Confidence Level</strong></td></tr><tr><td>DPRK-aligned (Kimsuky)</td><td>High, Native Korean targeting, GPKI focus, OCR behavior</td></tr><tr><td>China-blended infrastructure</td><td>Moderate, PRC hosting, Gitee usage, Taiwan focus</td></tr><tr><td>Solely PRC Actor</td><td>Low-to-Moderate, Tooling overlap but weak linguistic match</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<p>Assessment: The actor appears to be a DPRK-based APT operator working from within or in partnership with Chinese infrastructure, representing a hybrid attribution model.</p>



<h3><strong>Defensive Recommendations</strong></h3>



<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><strong>Area</strong></td><td><strong>Recommendation</strong></td></tr><tr><td>PKI Security</td><td>Monitor usage of .key, .sig, .crt artifacts; enforce HSM or 2FA for key use</td></tr><tr><td>Phishing Defense</td><td>Block domains identified in IoCs; validate TLS fingerprints and referrer headers</td></tr><tr><td>Endpoint Hardening</td><td>Detect use of nasm, make, and OCR tools; monitor /usr/lib*/tracker-* paths</td></tr><tr><td>Network Telemetry</td><td>Alert on .git/ directory access from external IPs; monitor outbound to Pastebin/GitHub</td></tr><tr><td>Taiwan Focus</td><td>Establish watchlists for .tw domains targeted by PRC-originating IPs</td></tr><tr><td>Admin Accounts</td><td>Review usage logs for svradmin, oracle, app_adm01, and ensure rotation policies</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h2><strong>APPENDIX A</strong></h2>



<h2><strong>Overlap or Confusion with Chinese Threat Actors</strong></h2>



<p>There is notable evidence of <strong>operational blur between Kimsuky and Chinese APTs</strong> in the context of Taiwan. The 2025 “Kim” data breach revealed an attacker targeting Taiwan whose tools and phishing kits matched Kimsuky’s, yet whose personal indicators (language, browsing habits) suggested a Chinese national. Researchers concluded this actor was likely a Chinese hacker either <a href="https://www.darkreading.com/threat-intelligence/data-dump-apt-actor-attacker-capabilities#:~:text=,Yarochkin%20says"><strong>mimicking Kimsuky tactics or collaborating</strong></a> with them.. In fact, the leaked files on<a href="https://data.ddosecrets.com/APT%20Down%20-%20The%20North%20Korea%20Files/article.txt#:~:text=instrumentality%2C%20or%20a%20controlled%20entity,You%20have%20seen%20their%20scans"> DDoS Secrets</a> hint that Kimsuky has <em>“openly cooperated with other Chinese APTs and shared their tools and techniques”</em>. This overlap can cause attribution confusion – a Taiwan-focused operation might initially be blamed on China but could involve Kimsuky elements, or vice versa. So far, consensus is that <strong>North Korean and Chinese cyber operations remain separate</strong>, but cases like “Kim” show how a DPRK-aligned actor can operate against Taiwan using TTPs common to Chinese groups, muddying the waters of attribution.</p>



<h2><strong>File List from dump:</strong></h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="281" height="284" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-18.png" alt=""></figure>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="193" height="199" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-19.png" alt=""></figure>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="190" height="167" src="https://dti.domaintools.com/wp-content/uploads/image-20.png" alt=""></figure>



<h2><strong>Master Evidence Inventory:</strong></h2>



<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><strong>File Name</strong></td><td><strong>Language</strong></td><td><strong>Content Summary</strong></td><td><strong>Category</strong></td><td><strong>Relevance</strong></td></tr><tr><td>.bash_history</td><td>Mixed (EN/KR)</td><td>Operator shell history commands</td><td>System/Log</td><td>Shows rootkit compilation, file ops, network tests</td></tr><tr><td>user-bash_history</td><td>Mixed (EN/KR)</td><td>User-level shell commands</td><td>System/Log</td><td>Development and test activity</td></tr><tr><td>root-bash_history</td><td>Mixed (EN/KR)</td><td>Root-level shell commands</td><td>System/Log</td><td>Privilege-level activity, implant deployment</td></tr><tr><td>auth.log.2</td><td>EN/KR</td><td>Authentication logs (PAM/SSH)</td><td>System/Log</td><td>Credential changes marked 변경완료, brute force IPs</td></tr><tr><td>20190315.log</td><td>EN</td><td>System log file</td><td>System/Log</td><td>Auth and system access events</td></tr><tr><td>chrome-timeline.txt</td><td>EN</td><td>Browser activity timeline</td><td>Browser</td><td>Visited domains extraction</td></tr><tr><td>chromehistory.txt</td><td>EN</td><td>Browser history export</td><td>Browser</td><td>URLs visited</td></tr><tr><td>history.sqlite</td><td>EN</td><td>Empty DB file</td><td>Browser</td><td>No useful data</td></tr><tr><td>Media History</td><td>EN</td><td>Empty SQLite DB</td><td>Browser</td><td>No playback activity</td></tr><tr><td>History</td><td>EN</td><td>Empty Brave/Chromium DB</td><td>Browser</td><td>No visited URLs</td></tr><tr><td>Web Data</td><td>EN</td><td>Autofill/search DB</td><td>Browser</td><td>Search engines used (Google, DuckDuckGo, Qwant, Startpage, Ecosia)</td></tr><tr><td>Visited Links</td><td>Binary</td><td>LevelDB/binary structure</td><td>Browser</td><td>Could not extract URLs</td></tr><tr><td>Cookies</td><td>EN</td><td>SQLite DB with cookies</td><td>Browser</td><td>Google cookies found</td></tr><tr><td>request_log.txt.20250220</td><td>EN</td><td>Captured phishing session</td><td>Phishing</td><td>Spoofed spo.go.kr, base64 credential logging</td></tr><tr><td>技术说明书 – 22.docx</td><td>ZH</td><td>Chinese rootkit stealth manual</td><td>Rootkit</td><td>Kernel hiding, binary embedding</td></tr><tr><td>1.ko 图文编译 .doc</td><td>ZH</td><td>Chinese compilation guide</td><td>Rootkit</td><td>Rootkit build process</td></tr><tr><td>1. build ko .txt</td><td>ZH</td><td>Build notes</td><td>Rootkit</td><td>Implant compilation instructions</td></tr><tr><td>0. 使用.txt</td><td>ZH</td><td>Usage notes</td><td>Rootkit</td><td>Implant usage and commands</td></tr><tr><td>re 正向工具修改建议 1.0.txt</td><td>ZH</td><td>Modification notes</td><td>Rootkit</td><td>Reverse tool modification suggestions</td></tr><tr><td>1111.txt</td><td>ZH</td><td>Rootkit/tool snippet</td><td>Rootkit</td><td>Part of implant notes</td></tr><tr><td>client</td><td>Binary</td><td>Rootkit client binary</td><td>Rootkit</td><td>Controller for implant communication</td></tr><tr><td>SSA_AO_AD_WT_002_웹보안 프로토콜설계서_Ver1.0_.doc</td><td>KR</td><td>GPKI protocol design doc</td><td>PKI</td><td>Korean web PKI standards</td></tr><tr><td>행자부 웹보안API 인수인계.doc</td><td>KR</td><td>GPKI API deployment manual</td><td>PKI</td><td>Deployment and cert API internals</td></tr><tr><td>HIRA-IR-T02_의약품처방조제_ComLibrary_통신전문.doc</td><td>KR</td><td>Medical ComLibrary XML spec</td><td>Healthcare</td><td>Prescription system communication</td></tr><tr><td>(별지2)행정전자서명_기술요건_141125.pdf</td><td>KR</td><td>PKI requirements PDF</td><td>PKI</td><td>OCR target</td></tr><tr><td>SecuwaySSL U_카달로그.pdf</td><td>KR</td><td>VPN catalog</td><td>PKI/VPN</td><td>OCR target</td></tr><tr><td>phrack-apt-down-the-north-korea-files.pdf</td><td>EN</td><td>Phrack article</td><td>Reference</td><td>Background on Kimsuky dump</td></tr><tr><td>Muddled Libra Threat Assessment.pdf</td><td>EN</td><td>Threat intel report</td><td>Reference</td><td>Comparative threat actor study</td></tr><tr><td>Leaked North Korean Linux Stealth Rootkit Analysis.pdf</td><td>EN</td><td>Rootkit analysis</td><td>Reference</td><td>Detailed implant study</td></tr><tr><td>Inside the Kimsuky Leak.docx (various)</td><td>EN</td><td>Threat report drafts</td><td>Report</td><td>Working versions</td></tr><tr><td>account (2).txt</td><td>EN</td><td>DB export (DBsafer, TrustedOrange)</td><td>Infra</td><td>Accounts and DB changes</td></tr><tr><td>result.txt</td><td>KR</td><td>Cert-related parsed data</td><td>Infra</td><td>Included GPKI .key/.sig</td></tr><tr><td>english_wikipedia.txt</td><td>EN</td><td>Wikipedia dump</td><td>Reference</td><td>Unrelated baseline</td></tr><tr><td>bookmarks-2021-01-04.jsonlz4</td><td>EN</td><td>Firefox bookmarks (compressed)</td><td>Browser</td><td>Needs decompression</td></tr><tr><td>Screenshot translations</td><td>ZH</td><td>Chinese text (rootkit marketing blurb)</td><td>Rootkit</td><td>Kernel hiding tool description</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>




                            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Zuckerberg Caught in Revealing Hot Mic Moment During White House Dinner (128 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.pcmag.com/news/zuckerberg-caught-in-revealing-hot-mic-moment-during-white-house-dinner</link>
            <guid>45150759</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 16:38:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.pcmag.com/news/zuckerberg-caught-in-revealing-hot-mic-moment-during-white-house-dinner">https://www.pcmag.com/news/zuckerberg-caught-in-revealing-hot-mic-moment-during-white-house-dinner</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45150759">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.pcmag.com/news/zuckerberg-caught-in-revealing-hot-mic-moment-during-white-house-dinner: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Oldest recorded transaction (130 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://avi.im/blag/2025/oldest-txn/</link>
            <guid>45149626</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 14:34:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://avi.im/blag/2025/oldest-txn/">https://avi.im/blag/2025/oldest-txn/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45149626">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><p>The other day I posted a <a href="https://x.com/iavins/status/1963597448321855793">tweet</a> with this image which I thought was funny:</p><img src="https://avi.im/blag/images/2025/oldest-txn.png" alt="tablet from Sumer"><p><em>This is the oldest transaction database from 3100 BC - recording accounts of malt and barley groats. Considering this thing survived 5000 years (holy shit!) with zero downtime and has stronger durability guarantees than most databases today.</em></p><p><em>I call it rock solid durability.</em></p><p>This got me thinking, can I insert this date in today’s database? What is the oldest timestamp a database can support?</p><p>So I checked the top three databases: <a href="https://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/8.4/en/datetime.html">MySQL</a>, <a href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/17/datatype-datetime.html">Postgres</a>, and <a href="https://sqlite.org/lang_datefunc.html">SQLite</a>:</p><table><thead><tr><th></th><th></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>MySQL</td><td>1000 AD</td></tr><tr><td>Postgres</td><td>4713 BC</td></tr><tr><td>SQLite</td><td>4713 BC</td></tr></tbody></table><p><br>Too bad you cannot use MySQL for this. Postgres and SQLite support the Julian calendar and the lowest date is Jan 01, 4713 BC:</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="sql"><span><span>sales<span>=#</span> <span>INSERT</span> <span>INTO</span> orders <span>VALUES</span> (<span>'4713-01-01 BC'</span>::date);
</span></span><span><span><span>INSERT</span> <span>0</span> <span>1</span>
</span></span><span><span>sales<span>=#</span> <span>SELECT</span> <span>*</span> <span>FROM</span> orders;
</span></span><span><span>   <span>timestamp</span>
</span></span><span><span><span>---------------
</span></span></span><span><span><span></span> <span>4713</span><span>-</span><span>01</span><span>-</span><span>01</span> BC
</span></span><span><span>(<span>1</span> <span>row</span>)
</span></span><span><span>sales<span>=#</span> <span>INSERT</span> <span>INTO</span> orders <span>VALUES</span> (<span>'4714-01-01 BC'</span>::date);
</span></span><span><span>ERROR:  date <span>out</span> <span>of</span> range: <span>"4714-01-01 BC"</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>I wonder how people store dates older than this. Maybe if I’m a British Museum manager, and I want to keep <del>theft</del> inventory details. How do I do it? As an epoch? Store it as text? Use some custom system? How do I get it to support all the custom operations that a typical <code>TIMESTAMP</code> supports?</p><p><small><i>Thanks to aku, happy_shady, Mr. Bhat, and General Bruh for reading an early draft of this post.</i></small></p><hr><p><small>1. Source of the image: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sumer#Language_and_writing">Sumer civilization</a></small><br><small>2. I found this from the talk <em>1000x: The Power of an Interface for Performance</em> by
Joran Dirk Greef, CEO of TigerBeetle, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yKgfk8lTQuE&amp;t=2290s">timestamped @ 38:10</a>.</small><br><small>3. The talk has other bangers too, <a href="https://x.com/iavins/status/1962568729671414266">like this</a> or <a href="https://x.com/iavins/status/1962568011728199836">this</a>.</small></p></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[DuckDuckGo founder: AI surveillance should be banned (430 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://gabrielweinberg.com/p/ai-surveillance-should-be-banned</link>
            <guid>45149281</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 13:52:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://gabrielweinberg.com/p/ai-surveillance-should-be-banned">https://gabrielweinberg.com/p/ai-surveillance-should-be-banned</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45149281">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://gabrielweinberg.com/p/ai-surveillance-should-be-banned: Error: getaddrinfo ENOTFOUND gabrielweinberg.com]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[996 (878 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lucumr.pocoo.org/2025/9/4/996/</link>
            <guid>45149049</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 13:20:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lucumr.pocoo.org/2025/9/4/996/">https://lucumr.pocoo.org/2025/9/4/996/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45149049">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        
  

  
  <p data-date="2025-09-04T00:00:00">written on September 04, 2025</p>
  

  <blockquote>
<p>“Amazing salary, hackerhouse in SF, crazy equity.
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/996_working_hour_system">996</a>. Our mission is
OSS.” — <a href="https://x.com/gregpr07/status/1963605449791639745">Gregor Zunic</a></p>
<p>“The current vibe is no drinking, no drugs, 9-9-6, […].” — <a href="https://www.ndtv.com/world-news/daksh-gupta-23-year-old-indian-origin-ceo-backs-72-hour-workweek-no-remote-work-no-drugs-9200900">Daksh
Gupta</a></p>
<p>“The truth is, China’s really doing ‘007’ now—midnight to midnight, seven
days a week […] if you want to build a $10 billion company, you have to work
seven days a week.” — <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/silicon-valley-china-996-work-schedule/">Harry Stebbings</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I love work.  I love working late nights, hacking on things.  This week I
didn’t go to sleep before midnight once.  And yet…</p>
<p>I also love my wife and kids. I love long walks, contemplating life over good
coffee, and deep, meaningful conversations.  None of this would be possible if
my life was defined by 12 hour days, six days a week.  More importantly, a
successful company is not a sprint, it’s a marathon.</p>
<p>And this is when this is your own company!  When you devote 72 hours a week to
someone else’s startup, you need to really think about that arrangement a few
times.  I find it highly irresponsible for a founder to promote that model.  As
a founder, you are not an employee, and your risks and leverage are
fundamentally different.</p>
<p>I will always advocate <a href="https://lucumr.pocoo.org/2024/12/26/reflecting-on-life/">for putting the time
in</a> because it is what brought me happiness.
Intensity, and giving a shit about what I’m doing, will always matter to me.
But you don’t measure that by the energy you put in, or the hours you’re
sitting in the office, but the output you produce.  Burning out on twelve-hour
days, six days a week, has no prize at the end.  It’s unsustainable, it
shouldn’t be the standard and it sure as hell should not be seen as a positive
sign of a company.</p>
<p>I’ve pulled many all-nighters, and I’ve enjoyed them.  I still do.  But they’re
enjoyable in the right context, for the right reasons, and when that is a
completely personal choice, not the basis of company culture.</p>
<p>And that all-nighter?  It comes with a fucked up and unproductive morning the
day after.</p>
<p>When someone promotes a 996 work culture, we should push back.</p>


  
  <p>This entry was tagged
    
      <a href="https://lucumr.pocoo.org/tags/thoughts/">thoughts</a>
  

  </p><p>
    <a href="https://lucumr.pocoo.org/2025/9/4/996.md" id="copy-markdown">copy as</a> / <a href="https://lucumr.pocoo.org/2025/9/4/996.md" id="view-markdown">view</a> markdown
  </p>
  
  

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[We Hacked Burger King: How Auth Bypass Led to Drive-Thru Audio Surveillance (253 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://bobdahacker.com/blog/rbi-hacked-drive-thrus/</link>
            <guid>45148944</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 13:04:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://bobdahacker.com/blog/rbi-hacked-drive-thrus/">https://bobdahacker.com/blog/rbi-hacked-drive-thrus/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45148944">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
            <div>
                <h2>The Setup</h2>
<p>Picture this: Restaurant Brands International (RBI) – the corporate overlords behind <strong>Burger King</strong>, <strong>Tim Hortons</strong>, and <strong>Popeyes</strong> – control over <strong>30,000 locations worldwide</strong>. That's a lot of chicken sandwiches, maple syrup, and flame-broiled beef.</p>
<p>What they also control is something called the "assistant" platform – the digital brain behind every drive-thru screen, bathroom tablet review, and the slightly-too-cheerful burger king employee asking if you want to make it a combo.</p>
<p>Spoiler alert: Their security was about as solid as a paper Whopper wrapper in the rain.</p>
<p>We stumbled upon vulnerabilities so catastrophic that we could access <strong>every single store</strong> in their global empire. From a Burger King in Times Square to that lonely Tim Hortons where Bugs Bunny shoulda taken a left turn at Albuquerque. Oh, and did we mention we could listen to your actual drive-thru conversations? Yeah, that happened too.</p>
<p>The platforms were spread across three domains, each with the same delicious vulnerabilities:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>https://assistant.bk.com</code></li>
<li><code>https://assistant.popeyes.com</code>  </li>
<li><code>https://assistant.timhortons.com</code></li>
</ul>
<p>Buckle up, this is going to be a wild ride. 🍔</p>
<h2>The Vulnerabilities</h2>
<h3>The "Anyone Can Join This Party" Signup API</h3>
<p>Our journey began innocently enough. We tried logging in with fake credentials and discovered they were using AWS Cognito. The good news? The system worked exactly as designed. The bad news? They forgot to disable user signups. Oops.</p>
<p>After a quick email verification dance with AWS's <code>ConfirmSignup</code> method, we were in. But wait, there's more!</p>
<p>Using GraphQL introspection (because who doesn't love a good schema leak), we found an even easier signup endpoint that completely bypassed email verification. It was like finding a secret menu item, except this one came with user privileges.</p>
<pre><code>mutation SignUp {
  signUp(input: { email: "<a href="https://bobdahacker.com/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" data-cfemail="0f6b6a696661667b6a63762261607b226e22676e6c646a7d4f6a776e627f636a216c6062">[email&nbsp;protected]</a>", password: "password123" })
}
</code></pre>
<p>The cherry on top? <strong>They emailed us the password in plain text.</strong> In 2025. We're not even mad, just impressed by the commitment to terrible security practices.</p>
<p><img src="https://bobdahacker.com/static/images/blogs/rbi/Passwordemail.png" alt="Password sent in email"><br><em>When your password security is more outdated than the ice cream machine</em></p>
<hr>
<h3>"Gotta Catch 'Em All" - The Global Store Directory</h3>
<p>Once authenticated, we hit the jackpot: a single GraphQL endpoint that returned <strong>a store in their global empire</strong>. (the store ids were incrementing) Not just the store name, but the good stuff – store employees personal information, internal IDs, configuration details.</p>
<p><img src="https://bobdahacker.com/static/images/blogs/rbi/Allthestores.png" alt="All the stores.png"><br><img src="https://bobdahacker.com/static/images/blogs/rbi/getStore2.png" alt="All the stores.png"></p>
<p>But wait, there's more! We also found a GraphQL query to search users who have access to assistant by name, revealing personal info faster than you can say "would you like fries with that data breach?"</p>
<hr>
<h3>The "No Authentication, No Problem" Token Generator</h3>
<p>Here's where things got spicy. We discovered a GraphQL mutation called <code>createToken</code> that was about as secure as leaving your house key under a welcome mat labeled "HOUSE KEY HERE."</p>
<p>This beautiful piece of mutation accepted a <code>storeId</code> parameter and required <strong>absolutely zero authentication</strong>. None. Nada. Zilch.</p>
<pre><code>mutation CreateToken {
  createToken(input: { storeId: "1" })
}
</code></pre>
<p><img src="https://bobdahacker.com/static/images/blogs/rbi/CreateToken2.png" alt="CreateToken"><br><em>Authentication is optional, apparently</em></p>
<p>This token wasn't just a key to one store – it was the master key to the entire kingdom. With it, we could promote ourselves to admin status across the entire platform:</p>
<pre><code>mutation BecomeTheKing {
  updateUser(input: { id: "definitely-us", roles: "admin" }) {
    roles  # Spoiler: it's "admin" now
  }
}
</code></pre>
<p><img src="https://bobdahacker.com/static/images/blogs/rbi/WeAreAdmin.png" alt="We Are Admin"><br><em>Look at us. We're the captain now.</em></p>
<h3>The Drive-Thru Equipment Store (A Detour Into Absurdity)</h3>
<p>While exploring, we stumbled upon RBI's equipment ordering website. The password protection? <strong>Client-side only.</strong> The password? <strong>Hardcoded in da HTML.</strong> </p>
<p><img src="https://bobdahacker.com/static/images/blogs/rbi/hardCodedPassword.png" alt="Hard Coded Password"><br><em>Security through obscurity, but the obscurity is in plain sight</em></p>
<p>Here you could order drive-thru essentials like "Single Lane Kits" (tablets included!) or just grab a tablet for those bathroom feedback screens because apparently everything needs to be digital now.</p>
<p><img src="https://bobdahacker.com/static/images/blogs/rbi/singleLaneKit.png" alt="Single Lane Kit"><br><em>Your complete drive-thru starter pack, no security included</em></p>
<hr>
<h3>Welcome to the Drive-Thru Control Room</h3>
<p>The tokens unlocked access to the actual tablet interfaces used in stores. The tablet is primarly composed of what seems to be a web app.</p>
<p><strong>Main Screen</strong> (<code>https://assistant.bk.com/screens/main?authToken=yourNewBestFriend</code>)</p>
<ul>
<li>Lists previous conversations (spoiler: you can listen to them)</li>
<li>Shows the "tone" employees should focus on</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://bobdahacker.com/static/images/blogs/rbi/Screensystem.png" alt="Screen System"></p>
<p><strong>Diagnostic Screen</strong> (<code>https://assistant.bk.com/screens/diagnostic?authToken=stillYourBestFriend</code>)<br>This one had an additional password protection. The password? <strong>"admin"</strong>. Client-side, of course.</p>
<p><img src="https://bobdahacker.com/static/images/blogs/rbi/DiagnosticScreenPasswordProtected.png" alt="Diagnostic Screen Password Protected"><br><em>Advanced password security, circa 1995</em></p>
<p><img src="https://bobdahacker.com/static/images/blogs/rbi/AdvancedPasswordSecurity.png" alt="Advanced Password Security"><br><em>When your password security is more predictable than McDonald's ice cream machines being broken</em></p>
<p>Once inside, we found APIs to control drive-thru audio levels. Want to blast customers' eardrums or make them whisper their order? We got you covered:</p>
<p><img src="https://bobdahacker.com/static/images/blogs/rbi/EarBlast.png" alt="Ear Gain"></p>
<p>Any store token could also list any store's drive-thru config, because apparently access control is just a suggestion.</p>
<p><img src="https://bobdahacker.com/static/images/blogs/rbi/GPIOStrings.png" alt="GPIOStrings.png"></p>
<p>Notice something? Well it returns a JWT that can be used to call an API to return a signed AWS upload url, for any store's path, which is bad. Very bad. </p>
<p>First it was kind enough to reveal the missing values:</p>
<p><img src="https://bobdahacker.com/static/images/blogs/rbi/FileUploadApi.png" alt="FileUploadApi.png"></p>
<p>Then it returned with the signed upload URL for "amongus.mp4":</p>
<p><img src="https://bobdahacker.com/static/images/blogs/rbi/sus.png" alt="sus.png"></p>
<hr>
<h3>The Drive-Thru Surveillance State</h3>
<p>Now for the truly mind-blowing part: <strong>We could access actual voice recordings</strong> of customer orders. Which god knows how long they store those for.</p>
<p>Not just transcripts. Not just metadata. <strong>Raw audio files</strong> of real people ordering food, complete with background conversations, car radios, and sometimes personally identifiable information.</p>
<p><img src="https://bobdahacker.com/static/images/blogs/rbi/DriveTroughHistory2.png" alt="Drive Through History"></p>
<p><em>Big Brother is watching, and he wants to know if you'd like to supersize that</em></p>
<p>This audio goldmine was being fed into AI systems to analyze:</p>
<ul>
<li>Customer sentiment </li>
<li>Employee friendliness levels</li>
<li>Upsell success rates</li>
<li>Order processing times</li>
<li>How many times employees said "You rule" (because that's definitely a crucial business metric)</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://bobdahacker.com/static/images/blogs/rbi/HowFriendly.png" alt="How Friendly"><br><em>AI-powered friendliness monitoring: dystopian but thorough</em></p>
<p><img src="https://bobdahacker.com/static/images/blogs/rbi/MoreStats.png" alt="More Stats"><br><em>Your drive-thru performance review, brought to you by artificial intelligence</em></p>
<h3>The Bathroom Chronicles</h3>
<p>We found the code for the bathroom rating screen for the tablet was in the assistant panel as well, For example, the bathroom rating screen is located at:</p>
<p><code>https://assistant.bk.com/feedback/storeid/</code></p>
<p>Which we assume the tablet loads in a webapp with its storeId</p>
<p><img src="https://bobdahacker.com/static/images/blogs/rbi/Toiletrating.png" alt="Toiletrating.png"><br><em>Rating bathroom experiences: because everything needs a digital feedback loop</em></p>
<p>The cherry on this porcelain throne? The API that gets called for the feedback sends <strong>zero authentication</strong>. That's right – you could spam bathroom reviews for every Burger King location without even proving you've ever been within a mile of their restrooms.</p>
<p>Want to give a 5-star review to a bathroom in Tokyo while sitting in your pajamas in Ohio? The system says "why not!" 🚽</p>
<hr>
<h2>The Full Damage Report'</h2>
<p>With our newfound admin powers, we could:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Add/remove/manage stores</strong> (Want to open a Burger King on the Moon? Now you can!)  </li>
<li><strong>View/edit employee accounts</strong> (Everyone gets a promotion!)  </li>
<li><strong>Send notifications to any store ids tablet</strong></li>
<li><strong>Access store analytics and sales data</strong> (Numbers, so many numbers)  </li>
<li><strong>Upload files to any store's systems</strong> (Via convenient JWT-signed AWS URLs)  </li>
<li><strong>AND More</strong></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2>Privacy Violations of Epic Proportions</h2>
<ul>
<li>Access to <strong>thousands, possibly hundreds of thousands of voice recordings</strong> containing PII, if you visited a burger king and went thru the drive thru, your voice is probably in the aws bucket, and analyzed by AI.</li>
<li>GDPR lawyers worldwide suddenly perking up</li>
<li>We now know about your embarrassing order of 47 chicken nuggets at 2 AM</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2>Timeline: The Speed Run</h2>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>When</th>
<th>What Happened</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody><tr>
<td><strong>Day 1</strong></td>
<td>"Hey, let's see how this drive-thru system works"</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Day 1, 2 hours later</strong></td>
<td>"Oh no... OH NO... <strong>OH NO</strong>"</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Day 1, 3 hours later</strong></td>
<td>"We can hear people ordering food. This is not good."</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Day 1, same day</strong></td>
<td>RBI fixes everything faster than you can say "code red"</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p>Credit where it's due – RBI's response time was impressive. However they never commented on the vulnerabilities or answered us. (I guess our report was too hot to handle.)</p>
<hr>
<h2>The Fine Print</h2>
<p><em>No customer data was retained during this research. No drive-thru orders were harmed in the making of this blog post. Responsible disclosure protocols were followed throughout. We still think the Whopper is pretty good, but Wendys is better</em></p>
<p><strong>So Long, and Thanks for All the Fish</strong></p>
<section>
  
  <p><img src="https://bobdahacker.com/static/images/bobdahackerReal.png" alt="Bobdahacker Avatar">
    <span>🤝</span>
    <img src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/22559547?v=4" alt="BobTheShoplifter Avatar">
  </p>
  
  <h2>Official Hacker Collab</h2>
  
  <p>
    This blog is a proud and official <strong>@BobDaHacker</strong> &amp; <strong>@BobTheShoplifter</strong> collab.
  </p>
  
  <p>Check out the other Bob here:</p>
  
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/BobTheShoplifter">
    
  </a>
    <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://x.com/BobTShoplifter">
    
  </a>
</section>


            </div>
        </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Qwen3 30B A3B Hits 13 token/s on 4xRaspberry Pi 5 (263 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/b4rtaz/distributed-llama/discussions/255</link>
            <guid>45148237</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 10:59:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/b4rtaz/distributed-llama/discussions/255">https://github.com/b4rtaz/distributed-llama/discussions/255</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45148237">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div role="presentation" data-paste-markdown-skip="">
    <tbody data-target-translation-id="8845881" data-target-translation-type="discussion">
        <tr>
    <td>
        <details open="">
  <summary>
    
    <span aria-label="Video description qwen3_30b.mov">qwen3_30b.mov</span>
    <span></span>
  </summary>

  <video src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/12797776/486206597-f220246c-9e74-4134-9b12-7787948233c7.mov?jwt=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3NTcxNzI5MDIsIm5iZiI6MTc1NzE3MjYwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii8xMjc5Nzc3Ni80ODYyMDY1OTctZjIyMDI0NmMtOWU3NC00MTM0LTliMTItNzc4Nzk0ODIzM2M3Lm1vdj9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNTA5MDYlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjUwOTA2VDE1MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTAzOTUzMWRjYzJlNWE1ZDk1YzAyNDdhMTUzOWRhYjQ4NmNkNjExYmVmMTliM2QyYmQzMmI1M2E2YjY5MTUxMGUmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0In0.AgtMqxqyz3GqbKL1mYoV2p6TgjqTs3uJ3Af0uEB58TM" data-canonical-src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/12797776/486206597-f220246c-9e74-4134-9b12-7787948233c7.mov?jwt=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3NTcxNzI5MDIsIm5iZiI6MTc1NzE3MjYwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii8xMjc5Nzc3Ni80ODYyMDY1OTctZjIyMDI0NmMtOWU3NC00MTM0LTliMTItNzc4Nzk0ODIzM2M3Lm1vdj9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNTA5MDYlMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjUwOTA2VDE1MzAwMlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTAzOTUzMWRjYzJlNWE1ZDk1YzAyNDdhMTUzOWRhYjQ4NmNkNjExYmVmMTliM2QyYmQzMmI1M2E2YjY5MTUxMGUmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0In0.AgtMqxqyz3GqbKL1mYoV2p6TgjqTs3uJ3Af0uEB58TM" controls="controls" muted="muted">

  </video>
</details>

<h3 dir="auto">Setup</h3>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="[🔀 TP-Link LS1008G Switch]
      | | | |
      | | | |_______ 🔸 raspberrypi2 (ROOT)     10.0.0.2
      | | |_________ 🔹 raspberrypi1 (WORKER 1) 10.0.0.1
      | |___________ 🔹 raspberrypi3 (WORKER 2) 10.0.0.3
      |_____________ 🔹 raspberrypi4 (WORKER 3) 10.0.0.4"><pre><code>[🔀 TP-Link LS1008G Switch]
      | | | |
      | | | |_______ 🔸 raspberrypi2 (ROOT)     10.0.0.2
      | | |_________ 🔹 raspberrypi1 (WORKER 1) 10.0.0.1
      | |___________ 🔹 raspberrypi3 (WORKER 2) 10.0.0.3
      |_____________ 🔹 raspberrypi4 (WORKER 3) 10.0.0.4
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Device: <code>4 x Raspberry Pi 5 8GB</code><br>
Distributed Llama version: <code>0.16.0</code><br>
Model: <code>qwen3_30b_a3b_q40</code></p>
<h3 dir="auto">Benchmark</h3>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table role="table">
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th>Evaluation</th>
<th>Prediction</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>4 x Raspberry Pi 5 8GB</td>
<td>14.33 tok/s</td>
<td>13.04 tok/s</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="b4rtaz@raspberrypi2:~/distributed-llama $ ./dllama inference --prompt &quot;<|im_start|>user
Please explain me where is Poland as I have 1 year<|im_end|>
<|im_start|>assistant
&quot; --steps 128 --model models/qwen3_30b_a3b_q40/dllama_model_qwen3_30b_a3b_q40.m --tokenizer models/qwen3_30b_a3b_q40/dllama_tokenizer_qwen3_30b_a3b_q40.t --buffer-float-type q80 --nthreads 4 --max-seq-len 4096 --workers 10.0.0.1:9999 10.0.0.3:9999 10.0.0.4:9999
📄 AddBos: 0
📄 BosId: 151643 (<|endoftext|>)
📄 EosId: 151645 (<|im_end|>) 
📄 RegularVocabSize: 151643
📄 SpecialVocabSize: 26
Tokenizer vocab size (151669) does not match the model vocab size (151936)
💡 Arch: Qwen3 MoE
💡 HiddenAct: Silu
💡 Dim: 2048
💡 HeadDim: 128
💡 QDim: 4096
💡 KvDim: 512
💡 HiddenDim: 6144
💡 VocabSize: 151936
💡 nLayers: 48
💡 nHeads: 32
💡 nKvHeads: 4
💡 OrigSeqLen: 262144
💡 nExperts: 128
💡 nActiveExperts: 8
💡 MoeHiddenDim: 768
💡 SeqLen: 4096
💡 NormEpsilon: 0.000001
💡 RopeType: Falcon
💡 RopeTheta: 10000000
📀 RequiredMemory: 5513 MB
⭕ Socket[0]: connecting to 10.0.0.1:9999 worker
⭕ Socket[0]: connected
⭕ Socket[1]: connecting to 10.0.0.3:9999 worker
⭕ Socket[1]: connected
⭕ Socket[2]: connecting to 10.0.0.4:9999 worker
⭕ Socket[2]: connected
⭕ Network is initialized
🧠 CPU: neon dotprod fp16
💿 Loading weights...
💿 Weights loaded
🚁 Network is in non-blocking mode
<|im_start|>user
Please explain me where is Poland as I have 1 year<|im_end|>
<|im_start|>assistant

🔷️ Eval  996 ms Sync  330 ms | Sent 12084 kB Recv 20085 kB | (19 tokens)
🔶 Pred   49 ms Sync   37 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB | Of
🔶 Pred   50 ms Sync   94 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  course
🔶 Pred   60 ms Sync   37 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB | !
🔶 Pred   60 ms Sync   18 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  Let
🔶 Pred   59 ms Sync   18 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  me
🔶 Pred   49 ms Sync   27 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  explain
🔶 Pred   49 ms Sync   18 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  where
🔶 Pred   49 ms Sync   18 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  Poland
🔶 Pred   49 ms Sync   18 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  is
🔶 Pred   49 ms Sync   18 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB | ,
🔶 Pred   53 ms Sync   18 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  in
...
🔶 Pred   70 ms Sync   15 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB | zech
🔶 Pred   53 ms Sync   24 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  Republic
🔶 Pred   69 ms Sync   14 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB | **
🔶 Pred   59 ms Sync   16 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  –
🔶 Pred   55 ms Sync   20 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  to
🔶 Pred   64 ms Sync   16 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  the
🔶 Pred   53 ms Sync   36 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  south
🔶 Pred   62 ms Sync   18 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |   

🔶 Pred   61 ms Sync   16 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB | 3

Evaluation
   nBatches: 32
    nTokens: 19
   tokens/s: 14.33 (69.80 ms/tok)
Prediction
    nTokens: 109
   tokens/s: 13.04 (76.69 ms/tok)
⭕ Network is closed"><pre><code>b4rtaz@raspberrypi2:~/distributed-llama $ ./dllama inference --prompt "&lt;|im_start|&gt;user
Please explain me where is Poland as I have 1 year&lt;|im_end|&gt;
&lt;|im_start|&gt;assistant
" --steps 128 --model models/qwen3_30b_a3b_q40/dllama_model_qwen3_30b_a3b_q40.m --tokenizer models/qwen3_30b_a3b_q40/dllama_tokenizer_qwen3_30b_a3b_q40.t --buffer-float-type q80 --nthreads 4 --max-seq-len 4096 --workers 10.0.0.1:9999 10.0.0.3:9999 10.0.0.4:9999
📄 AddBos: 0
📄 BosId: 151643 (&lt;|endoftext|&gt;)
📄 EosId: 151645 (&lt;|im_end|&gt;) 
📄 RegularVocabSize: 151643
📄 SpecialVocabSize: 26
Tokenizer vocab size (151669) does not match the model vocab size (151936)
💡 Arch: Qwen3 MoE
💡 HiddenAct: Silu
💡 Dim: 2048
💡 HeadDim: 128
💡 QDim: 4096
💡 KvDim: 512
💡 HiddenDim: 6144
💡 VocabSize: 151936
💡 nLayers: 48
💡 nHeads: 32
💡 nKvHeads: 4
💡 OrigSeqLen: 262144
💡 nExperts: 128
💡 nActiveExperts: 8
💡 MoeHiddenDim: 768
💡 SeqLen: 4096
💡 NormEpsilon: 0.000001
💡 RopeType: Falcon
💡 RopeTheta: 10000000
📀 RequiredMemory: 5513 MB
⭕ Socket[0]: connecting to 10.0.0.1:9999 worker
⭕ Socket[0]: connected
⭕ Socket[1]: connecting to 10.0.0.3:9999 worker
⭕ Socket[1]: connected
⭕ Socket[2]: connecting to 10.0.0.4:9999 worker
⭕ Socket[2]: connected
⭕ Network is initialized
🧠 CPU: neon dotprod fp16
💿 Loading weights...
💿 Weights loaded
🚁 Network is in non-blocking mode
&lt;|im_start|&gt;user
Please explain me where is Poland as I have 1 year&lt;|im_end|&gt;
&lt;|im_start|&gt;assistant

🔷️ Eval  996 ms Sync  330 ms | Sent 12084 kB Recv 20085 kB | (19 tokens)
🔶 Pred   49 ms Sync   37 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB | Of
🔶 Pred   50 ms Sync   94 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  course
🔶 Pred   60 ms Sync   37 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB | !
🔶 Pred   60 ms Sync   18 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  Let
🔶 Pred   59 ms Sync   18 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  me
🔶 Pred   49 ms Sync   27 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  explain
🔶 Pred   49 ms Sync   18 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  where
🔶 Pred   49 ms Sync   18 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  Poland
🔶 Pred   49 ms Sync   18 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  is
🔶 Pred   49 ms Sync   18 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB | ,
🔶 Pred   53 ms Sync   18 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  in
...
🔶 Pred   70 ms Sync   15 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB | zech
🔶 Pred   53 ms Sync   24 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  Republic
🔶 Pred   69 ms Sync   14 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB | **
🔶 Pred   59 ms Sync   16 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  –
🔶 Pred   55 ms Sync   20 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  to
🔶 Pred   64 ms Sync   16 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  the
🔶 Pred   53 ms Sync   36 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |  south
🔶 Pred   62 ms Sync   18 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB |   

🔶 Pred   61 ms Sync   16 ms | Sent   636 kB Recv  1057 kB | 3

Evaluation
   nBatches: 32
    nTokens: 19
   tokens/s: 14.33 (69.80 ms/tok)
Prediction
    nTokens: 109
   tokens/s: 13.04 (76.69 ms/tok)
⭕ Network is closed
</code></pre></div>
    </td>
  </tr>

    </tbody>
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Let us git rid of it, angry GitHub users say of forced Copilot features (386 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theregister.com/2025/09/05/github_copilot_complaints/</link>
            <guid>45148167</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 10:44:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/09/05/github_copilot_complaints/">https://www.theregister.com/2025/09/05/github_copilot_complaints/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45148167">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="body">
<p>Among the software developers who use Microsoft's GitHub, the most popular community discussion in the past 12 months has been a request for a way to block Copilot, the company's AI service, from generating issues and pull requests in code repositories.</p>
<p>The second most popular discussion – where popularity is <a href="https://github.com/orgs/community/discussions?discussions_q=is%3Aopen+sort%3Atop+created%3A%3E%3D2024-09-04" rel="nofollow">measured in upvotes</a> – is a bug report that seeks a fix for the inability of users to disable Copilot code reviews.</p>
<p>Both of these questions, <a href="https://github.com/orgs/community/discussions/159749" rel="nofollow">the first</a> opened in May and <a href="https://github.com/orgs/community/discussions/169148" rel="nofollow">the second</a> opened a month ago, remain unanswered, despite an abundance of comments critical of generative AI and Copilot.&nbsp;</p>

    

<p>The author of the first, developer Andi McClure, published <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/vscode/issues/237819" rel="nofollow">a similar request</a> to Microsoft's Visual Studio Code repository in January, objecting to the reappearance of a Copilot icon in VS Code after she had uninstalled the Copilot extension.</p>

        


        

<p>Microsoft and GitHub, not to mention rivals like Google, have gone all-in on a technology that a sizable or at least vocal portion of their customers simply don't want. And with <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/07/30/microsoft_hails_cloud_and_ai/">billions in capital expenditures</a> to recoup, they're making it difficult to avoid.</p>
<p>During Microsoft's July 30, 2025 earnings call, CEO Satya Nadella <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://view.officeapps.live.com/op/view.aspx?src=https://cdn-dynmedia-1.microsoft.com/is/content/microsoftcorp/TranscriptFY25q4">said</a> GitHub Copilot continued to exhibit strong momentum and had reached 20 million users.</p>

        

<p>"GitHub Copilot Enterprise customers increased 75 percent quarter over quarter as companies tailor Copilot to their own codebases," said Nadella, noting that AI adoption has increased usage of GitHub over the past year.</p>
<blockquote>

<p>I deeply resent that on top of Copilot seemingly training itself on my GitHub-posted code in violation of my licenses, GitHub wants me to look at (effectively) ads for this project I will never touch</p>
</blockquote>
<p>"I've been for a while now filing issues in the GitHub Community feedback area when Copilot intrudes on my GitHub usage," McClure told <em>The Register</em> in an email. "I deeply resent that on top of Copilot seemingly training itself on my GitHub-posted code in violation of my licenses, GitHub wants me to look at (effectively) ads for this project I will never touch. If something's bothering me, I don't see a reason to stay quiet about it. I think part of how we get pushed into things we collectively don't want is because we stay quiet about it."</p>
<p>It's not just the burden of responding to AI slop, an <a href="https://daniel.haxx.se/blog/2025/07/14/death-by-a-thousand-slops/" rel="nofollow">ongoing issue</a> for Curl maintainer Daniel Stenberg. It's the permissionless copying and <a href="https://mastodon.social/@sonicrocketman/115149008178747518" rel="nofollow">regurgitation of speculation as fact</a>, mitigated only by small print disclaimers that generative AI may produce inaccurate results. It's also GitHub's <a href="https://github.com/orgs/community/discussions/148571" rel="nofollow">disavowal of liability</a> if Copilot code suggestions happen to have reproduced source code that requires attribution.</p>
<p>It's what the Servo project characterizes in its <a href="https://book.servo.org/contributing.html#ai-contributions" rel="nofollow">ban on AI code contributions</a> as the lack of code correctness guarantees, copyright issues, and ethical concerns. Similar objections have been used to justify AI code bans in GNOME's <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/loupe/-/blob/main/CONTRIBUTING.md?ref_type=heads#use-of-generative-ai" rel="nofollow">Loupe</a> project, <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/09/03/freebsd_project_update_no_ai/">FreeBSD</a>, <a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Council/AI_policy" rel="nofollow">Gentoo</a>, <a href="https://www.netbsd.org/developers/commit-guidelines.html" rel="nofollow">NetBSD</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/qemu/qemu/commit/3d40db0efc22520fa6c399cf73960dced423b048" rel="nofollow">QEMU</a>.</p>
<p>McClure said she has been filing requests to opt out of Copilot for a few years now, but in the last six months, her posts have been attracting more community support.&nbsp;</p>

        

<p>Two issues, about the abovementioned Copilot menu in VS Code and the inability to block Copilot-generated issues and pull requests, she said, have continued to attract comments.</p>
<p>"People keep finding these issues somehow and tacking on to them," McClure said. "Although Microsoft's been forcing the Copilot 'asks' into more and more places in the interface for a while, sometime this year they hit an inflection point where mass numbers of people don't feel like ignoring it anymore, where before they could shrug and ignore it or find the off switch."</p>
<p>In the past month, she said, there's been a second change in the way people see GitHub – GitHub's <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/08/11/github_head_ankles_as_microsoft/">demotion from distinct subsidiary to part of Microsoft's CoreAI group</a>.</p>
<ul>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/09/05/us_army_enlists_ai_startup/">Bot shots: US Army enlists AI startup to provide target-tracking</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/09/05/openai_jobs_board/">OpenAI eats jobs, then offers to help you find a new one at Walmart</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/09/04/boffins_build_automated_android_bug_hunting/">Boffins build automated Android bug hunting system</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/09/04/atlassian_browser_company/">Atlassian acquisition drives dream of AI-powered ChromeOS challenger</a></li>
</ul>
<p>"Despite being a symbolic change, it seems to have galvanized the open source community from just complaining about Copilot to now actively moving away from GitHub," said McClure. "Many of my contacts in the open source community have been talking about plans to move from GitHub to Codeberg or a self-hosted Forgejo (Forgejo is the software used by Codeberg) over the last month, and the comments in those two always-busy GitHub threads have increasingly been people describing how Copilot is inspiring them to move to Codeberg as well."</p>
<p>Calls to shun Microsoft and GitHub go back a long way in the open source community, but moved beyond simmering dissatisfaction in 2022 when the Software Freedom Conservancy (SFC) <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2022/06/30/software_freedom_conservancy_quits_github/">urged free software supporters</a> to <a href="https://sfconservancy.org/GiveUpGitHub/" rel="nofollow">give up GitHub</a>, a position SFC policy fellow Bradley M. Kuhn <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/08/15/codeberg_beset_by_ai_bots/">recently reiterated</a>.</p>
<p>Some of the developers participating in the issues raised by McClure and by others have said they intend to move away from GitHub over its stance on AI.</p>
<p>"Today I rejected two Copilot-generated code suggestions on my PR," <a href="https://github.com/orgs/community/discussions/159749#discussioncomment-13329811" rel="nofollow">wrote</a> a developer who posted to McClure's thread under the name Constantine. "This was very disturbing, so I started googling and found this discussion. I refuse using AI in the same way I don't take drugs or steal things - for me it's a matter of principle. So if this continues and Microsoft does not provide a way to opt out of AI for my repositories soon, I will move my code to a self-hosted solution and won't ever return to GitHub."</p>
<p>McClure said she has been slowly shifting toward Codeberg over the past few months. "I haven't been proactively moving repos but whenever I make a change to a repo I clone it to Codeberg, post the change there, and replace my main branch on the GitHub repo with a relocation notice," she said.</p>
<p>"Microsoft as a company has a running problem where they won't take no for an answer, whether with 'AI' or with any other product they want to ship," said McClure. "A favorite tactic of theirs recently is they will enable a thing by default and put an off switch, wait six months, and then slightly change or rename the feature you turned off, and create a new off switch you have to separately turn off. They did this with Bing in Windows 10 and now they're doing it with Copilot in their developer tools (and presumably Windows 11, I don't know, I don't use Windows 11)."</p>
<p>McClure said that when Microsoft began adding Copilot to everything, starting with Android keyboard SwiftKey, she concluded that the situation would reprise the handling of Bing/Cortana in Windows 10 and turning it off would not be enough.</p>
<blockquote>

<p>If you really find Copilot unacceptable – and I do, Copilot is so much more noxious than Microsoft's previous forced bundlings – the only option is to stop using any Microsoft product that Copilot shows up in</p>
</blockquote>
<p>"If you really find Copilot unacceptable – and I do, Copilot is so much more noxious than Microsoft's previous forced bundlings – the only option is to stop using any Microsoft product that Copilot shows up in," she said. "I stopped using SwiftKey; I started migrating from desktop Windows to Linux when it became clear mandatory AI surveillance would be a core part of Win11. GitHub and, more sporadically, Visual Studio Code I have had to keep using because they're monopolies in a way even Windows isn't. The network effects (projects whose sole method of communication is GitHub, software whose only IDE integration is a VSCode plugin) are too strong."</p>
<p>Things have progressed as expected, McClure said, with Copilot buttons appearing in VS Code even when Copilot has been uninstalled and poorly labeled buttons that redirect to Copilot searches. She suggests people are starting to tire of the situation and that if it continues, it will weaken the network effects that keep developers tied to GitHub, accelerating further migration.</p>
<p>"When this happens I have no idea if Microsoft will notice or care," said McClure. "The Copilot push at Microsoft appears to be completely top-down and the people at the top seem to have completely forgotten about conventional goals like customer retention. They want to pump up those 'AI' numbers, for whatever reason, and they view their customer base as just a resource to burn to get those metrics up."</p>
<p>GitHub did not respond to a request for comment. ®</p>                                
                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why language models hallucinate (120 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://openai.com/index/why-language-models-hallucinate/</link>
            <guid>45147385</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 07:41:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://openai.com/index/why-language-models-hallucinate/">https://openai.com/index/why-language-models-hallucinate/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45147385">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://openai.com/index/why-language-models-hallucinate/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Rug pulls, forks, and open-source feudalism (236 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lwn.net/SubscriberLink/1036465/e80ebbc4cee39bfb/</link>
            <guid>45146967</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 05:59:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lwn.net/SubscriberLink/1036465/e80ebbc4cee39bfb/">https://lwn.net/SubscriberLink/1036465/e80ebbc4cee39bfb/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45146967">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<blockquote>
<div>
<h3>Welcome to LWN.net</h3>
<p>
The following subscription-only content has been made available to you 
by an LWN subscriber.  Thousands of subscribers depend on LWN for the 
best news from the Linux and free software communities.  If you enjoy this 
article, please consider <a href="https://lwn.net/subscribe/">subscribing to LWN</a>.  Thank you
for visiting LWN.net!
</p></div>
</blockquote>
<p>
Like almost all human endeavors, open-source software development involves
a range of power dynamics.  Companies, developers, and users are all
concerned with the power to influence the direction of the software — and,
often, to profit from it.  At the 2025 <a href="https://events.linuxfoundation.org/open-source-summit-europe/">Open
Source Summit Europe</a>, Dawn Foster talked about how those dynamics can
play out, with an eye toward a couple of tactics — rug pulls and forks — that
are available to try to shift power in one direction or another.
</p><h4>Power dynamics</h4>
<p>
Since the beginning of history, Foster began, those in power have tended to
use it against those who were weaker.  In the days of feudalism, control of
the land led to exploitation at several levels.  In the open-source world,
the large cloud providers often seem to have the most power, which they use
against smaller companies.  Contributors and maintainers often have less
power than even the smaller companies, and users have less power yet.  
</p><p>
<a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/1036470/"><img src="https://static.lwn.net/images/conf/2025/osseu/DawnFoster-sm.png" alt="[Dawn Foster]" title="Dawn Foster"></a>

We have built a world where it is often easiest to just use whatever a
cloud provider offers, even with open-source software.  Those providers may
not contribute back to the projects they turn into services, though,
upsetting the smaller companies that are, likely as not, doing the bulk of
the work to provide the software in question in the first place.  Those
companies can have a power of their own, however: the power to relicense
the software.  Pulling the rug out from under users of the software in this
way can change the balance of power with regard to cloud providers, but it
leaves contributors and users in a worse position than before.  But
there is a power at this level too: the power to fork the software,
flipping the power balance yet again.
</p><p>
Companies that control a software project have the power to carry out this
sort of rug pull, and they are often not shy about exercising it.
Single-company projects, clearly, are at a much higher risk of rug pulls;
the company has all the power in this case, and others have little
recourse.  So one should look at a company's reputation before adopting a
software project, but that is only so helpful.  Companies can change
direction without notice, be acquired, or go out of business, making
previous assessments of their reputation irrelevant.
</p><p>
The problem often comes down to the simple fact that companies have to
answer to their investors, and that often leads to pressure to relicense
the software they have created in order to increase revenue.  This is
especially true in cases where cloud providers are competing for the same
customers as the company that owns the project.  The result can be a switch
to a more restrictive license aimed at making it harder for other companies
to profit from the project.
</p><p>
A rug pull of this nature can lead to a fork of the project — a rebellious,
collective action aimed at regaining some power over the code.  But a fork
is not a simple matter; it is a lot of work, and will fail without people
and resources behind it.  The natural source for that is a large company;
cloud providers, too, can try to shift power via a fork, and they have the
ability to back their fork up with the resources it needs to succeed.
</p><p>
<!-- middle-ad -->

A relicensing event does not always lead to a popular fork; that did not
happen with MongoDB or Sentry, for example.  Foster said she had not looked
into why that was the case.  Sometimes rug pulls take other forms, such as
when Perforce, after acquiring Puppet in 2022, moved it development and
releases behind closed doors, with a reduced frequency of releases back to
the public repository.  That action kicked off the <a href="https://voxpupuli.org/openvox/">OpenVox</a> fork.
</p><h4>Looking at the numbers</h4>
<p>
Foster has spent some time analyzing rug pulls, forks, and what happens
thereafter; a lot of the results are <a href="https://github.com/chaoss/wg-data-science/tree/main/dataset/license-changes/fork-case-study/notebooks">available
for download as Jupyter notebooks</a>.  For each rug-pull event, she looked
at the contributor makeup of the project before and after the ensuing fork
in an attempt to see what effects are felt by the projects involved.
</p><p>
In 2021, Elastic <a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/844016/">relicensed Elasticsearch</a>
under the non-free Server Side Public License (SSPL).  Amazon Web Services
then forked the project as <a href="https://opensearch.org/">OpenSearch</a>.  Before the fork, most of
the Elasticsearch contributors were Elastic employees; that,
unsurprisingly, did not change afterward.  OpenSearch started with no
strong contributor base, so had to build its community from scratch.  As a
result, the project has been dominated by Amazon contributors ever since;
the balance has shifted slowly over time, but there was not a big uptick in
outside contributors even after OpenSearch became a Linux Foundation
project in 2024.  While starting a project under a neutral foundation can
help attract contributors, she said, moving a project under a foundation's
umbrella later on does not seem to provide the same benefit.
</p><p>
<a href="https://developer.hashicorp.com/terraform">Terraform</a> was
developed mostly by Hashicorp, which <a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/942346/">relicensed
the software</a> under the non-free Business Source License in 2023.  One
month later, the <a href="https://opentofu.org/">OpenTofu</a> fork was
started under the Linux Foundation.  While the contributor base for
Terraform, which was almost entirely Hashicorp employees, changed little
after the fork, OpenTofu quickly acquired a number of contributors from
several companies, none of whom had been Terraform contributors before.  In
this case, users drove the fork and placed it under a neutral foundation,
resulting in a more active developer community.
</p><p>
In 2024, <a href="https://redis.io/">Redis</a> was relicensed under the
SSPL; the <a href="https://valkey.io/">Valkey</a> fork was <a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/966631/">quickly organized</a>, under the Linux Foundation,
by Redis contributors.  The Redis project differed from the others
mentioned here in that, before the fork, it had nearly twice as many
contributors from outside the company as from within; after the fork, the
number of external Redis contributors dropped to zero.  All of the external
contributors fled to Valkey, with the result that Valkey started with a
strong community representing a dozen or so companies.
</p><p>
Looking at how the <i>usage</i> of these projects changes is harder, she
said, but there appears to be a correlation between the usage of a project
and the number of GitHub forks (cloned repository copies) it has.  There is
typically a spike in these clones after a relicensing event, suggesting
that people are considering creating a hard fork of the project.  In all
cases, the forks that emerged appeared to have less usage than the original
by the "GitHub forks" metric; both branches of the fork continue to go
forward.  But, she said, projects that are relicensed do tend to show
reduced usage, especially when competing forks are created under foundations.
</p><h4>What to do</h4>
<p>
This kind of power game creates problems for both contributors and users,
she said; we contribute our time to these projects, and need them to not be
pulled out from under us.  There is no way to know when a rug pull might
happen, but there are some warning signs to look out for.  At the top of
her list was the use of a contributor license agreement (CLA); these
agreements create a power imbalance, giving the company involved the power
to relicense the software.  Projects with CLAs more commonly are subject to
rug pulls; projects using a developers certificate of origin do not have the
same power imbalance and are less likely to be rug pulled.
</p><p>
One should also look at the governance of a project; while being housed
under a foundation reduces the chance of a rug pull, that can still happen,
especially in cases where the contributors are mostly from a single
company.  She mentioned the <a href="https://www.cncf.io/projects/cortex/">Cortex</a> project, housed under
the Cloud Native Computing Foundation, which was controlled by Grafana; that
company eventually forked its own project to create <a href="https://grafana.com/oss/mimir/">Mimir</a>.  To avoid this kind of
surprise, one should look for projects with neutral governance, with
leaders from multiple organizations.
</p><p>
Projects should also be evaluated on their contributor base; are there
enough contributors to keep things going?  Companies can help, of course,
by having their employees contribute to the projects they depend on,
increasing influence and making those projects more sustainable.  She
mentioned the <a href="https://chaoss.community/">CHAOSS project</a>, which
generates metrics to help in the judgment of the viability of development
projects.  CHAOSS has put together <a href="https://chaoss.community/practitioner-guide-introduction/">a set of
"practitioner guides"</a> intended to help contributors and maintainers
make improvements within a project.
</p><p>
With the sustained rise of the big cloud providers, she concluded, the
power dynamics around open-source software are looking increasingly feudal.
Companies can use relicensing to shift power away from those providers, but
they also take power from contributors when the pull the rug in this way.
Those contributors, though, are in a better position than the serfs of old,
since they have the ability to fork a project they care about, shifting
power back in their direction.

</p><p>
Hazel Weakly asked if there are other protections that contributors and
users might develop to address this problem.  Foster answered that at least
one company changed its mind about a planned relicensing action after
seeing the success of the Valkey and OpenTofu forks.  The ability to fork
has the effect of making companies think harder, knowing that there may be
consequences that follow a rug pull.  Beyond that, she reiterated that
projects should be pushed toward neutral governance.

Dirk Hohndel added that the best thing to do is to bring more outside
contributors into a project; the more of them there are, the higher the
risk associated with a rug pull.  Anybody who just sits back within a
project, he said, is just a passenger; it is better to be driving.
</p><p>
<a href="https://static.sched.com/hosted_files/osseu2025/ee/Power%20Dynamics%20Rug%20Pulls%20Other%20Impact%20on%20Sustainability%20OSSEU%202025.pdf">Foster's
slides</a> are available for interested readers.
</p><p>
[Thanks to the Linux Foundation, LWN's travel sponsor, for supporting my
travel to this event.]<br clear="all"></p><table>
           <tbody><tr><th colspan="2">Index entries for this article</th></tr>
           <tr><td><a href="https://lwn.net/Archives/ConferenceIndex/">Conference</a></td><td><a href="https://lwn.net/Archives/ConferenceIndex/#Open_Source_Summit_Europe-2025">Open Source Summit Europe/2025</a></td></tr>
            </tbody></table><br clear="all">

               <br clear="all">
               <hr>
            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[GOP Cries Censorship Over Spam Filters That Work (118 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://krebsonsecurity.com/2025/09/gop-cries-censorship-over-spam-filters-that-work/</link>
            <guid>45146375</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 03:32:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2025/09/gop-cries-censorship-over-spam-filters-that-work/">https://krebsonsecurity.com/2025/09/gop-cries-censorship-over-spam-filters-that-work/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45146375">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
												<p>The chairman of the <strong>Federal Trade Commission</strong> (FTC) last week sent a letter to Google’s CEO demanding to know why Gmail was blocking messages from Republican senders while allegedly failing to block similar missives supporting Democrats. The letter followed media reports accusing Gmail of disproportionately flagging messages from the GOP fundraising platform <strong>WinRed</strong> and sending them to the spam folder. But according to experts who track daily spam volumes worldwide, WinRed’s messages are getting blocked more because its methods of blasting email are increasingly way more spammy than that of <strong>ActBlue</strong>, the fundraising platform for Democrats.</p>
<div id="attachment_72095"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-72095" decoding="async" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/nyp-google-spam.png" alt="" width="749" height="255" srcset="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/nyp-google-spam.png 865w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/nyp-google-spam-768x262.png 768w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/nyp-google-spam-782x267.png 782w" sizes="(max-width: 749px) 100vw, 749px"></p><p id="caption-attachment-72095">Image: nypost.com</p></div>
<p>On Aug. 13, <strong>The New York Post</strong> ran an “exclusive” <a href="https://nypost.com/2025/08/13/business/google-caught-flagging-gop-fundraiser-emails-as-suspicious-sending-them-directly-to-spam-memo/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">story</a> titled, “Google caught flagging GOP fundraiser emails as ‘suspicious’ — sending them directly to spam.” The story cited a memo from Targeted Victory – whose clients include the National Republican Senatorial Committee (NRSC), Rep. Steve Scalise and Sen. Marsha Blackburn – which said it observed that the “serious and troubling” trend was still going on as recently as June and July of this year.</p>
<p>“If Gmail is allowed to quietly suppress WinRed links while giving ActBlue a free pass, it will continue to tilt the playing field in ways that voters never see, but campaigns will feel every single day,” the memo reportedly said.</p>
<p>In an August 28 letter to Google CEO <strong>Sundar Pichai</strong>, FTC Chairman <strong>Andrew Ferguson</strong> cited the New York Post story and warned that Gmail’s parent <strong>Alphabet</strong> may be engaging in unfair or deceptive practices.</p>
<p>“Alphabet’s alleged partisan treatment of comparable messages or messengers in Gmail to achieve political objectives may violate both of these prohibitions under the FTC Act,” Ferguson wrote. “And the partisan treatment may cause harm to consumers.”</p>
<p>However, the situation looks very different when you ask spam experts what’s going on with WinRed’s recent messaging campaigns. <strong>Atro Tossavainen</strong> and <strong>Pekka Jalonen</strong> are co-founders at <a href="https://www.koliloks.eu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Koli-Lõks OÜ</a>, an email intelligence company in Estonia. Koli-Lõks taps into real-time intelligence about daily spam volumes by monitoring large numbers of “spamtraps” — email addresses that are intentionally set up to catch unsolicited emails.</p>
<p>Spamtraps are generally not used for communication or account creation, but instead are created to identify senders exhibiting spammy behavior, such as scraping the Internet for email addresses or buying unmanaged distribution lists. As an email sender, blasting these spamtraps over and over with unsolicited email is the fastest way to ruin your domain’s reputation online. Such activity also virtually ensures that more of your messages are going to start getting listed on spam blocklists that are broadly shared within the global anti-abuse community.</p>
<p>Tossavainen told KrebsOnSecurity that WinRed’s emails hit its spamtraps in the .com, .net, and .org space far more frequently than do fundraising emails sent by ActBlue. Koli-Lõks published a graph of the stark disparity in spamtrap activity for WinRed versus ActBlue, showing a nearly fourfold increase in spamtrap hits from WinRed emails in the final week of July 2025.</p>
<div id="attachment_72094"><p><a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/koli-loks-red-v-blue.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-72094" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/koli-loks-red-v-blue.png" alt="" width="749" height="399" srcset="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/koli-loks-red-v-blue.png 974w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/koli-loks-red-v-blue-768x409.png 768w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/koli-loks-red-v-blue-782x417.png 782w" sizes="(max-width: 749px) 100vw, 749px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-72094">Image: Koliloks.eu</p></div>
<p>“Many of our spamtraps are in repurposed legacy-TLD domains (.com, .org, .net) and therefore could be understood to have been involved with a U.S. entity in their pre-zombie life,” Tossavainen explained in the LinkedIn post.<span id="more-72091"></span></p>
<p><strong>Raymond Dijkxhoorn</strong> is the CEO and a founding member of <a href="https://www.surbl.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">SURBL</a>, a widely-used blocklist that flags domains and IP addresses known to be used in unsolicited messages, phishing and malware distribution. Dijkxhoorn said their spamtrap data mirrors that of Koli-Lõks, and shows that WinRed has consistently been far more aggressive in sending email than ActBlue.</p>
<p>Dijkxhoorn said the fact that WinRed’s emails so often end up dinging the organization’s sender reputation is not a content issue but rather a technical one.</p>
<p>“On our end we don’t really care if the content is political or trying to sell viagra or penis enlargements,” Dijkhoorn said. “It’s the mechanics, they should not end up in spamtraps. And that’s the reason the domain reputation is tempered. Not ‘because domain reputation firms have a political agenda.’ We really don’t care about the political situation anywhere. The same as we don’t mind people buying penis enlargements. But when either of those land in spamtraps it will impact sending experience.”</p>
<p>The FTC letter to Google’s CEO also referenced a <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/2022/04/11/despite-what-fox-news-tells-you-a-new-study-did-not-prove-that-gmail-is-biased-against-conservatives/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">debunked</a> <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.16743.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2022 study</a> (PDF) by political consultants who found Google caught more Republican emails in spam filters. <strong>Techdirt</strong> editor <strong>Mike Masnick</strong> notes that while the 2022 study also found that other email providers caught more Democratic emails as spam, “Republicans laser-focused on Gmail because it fit their victimization narrative better.”</p>
<p>Masnick said GOP lawmakers then filed both lawsuits and complaints with the <strong>Federal Election Commission</strong> (both of which failed easily), claiming this was somehow an “in-kind contribution” to Democrats.</p>
<p>“This is political posturing designed to keep the White House happy by appearing to ‘do something’ about conservative claims of ‘censorship,'” Masnick <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/2025/09/04/ftc-chair-fergusons-ridiculous-crusade-threatening-google-over-spam-filters-that-actually-work/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">wrote</a> of the FTC letter. “The FTC has never policed ‘political bias’ in private companies’ editorial decisions, and for good reason—the First Amendment prohibits exactly this kind of government interference.”</p>
<p>WinRed did not respond to a request for comment.</p>
<p>The WinRed website says it is an online fundraising platform supported by a united front of the Trump campaign, the <strong>Republican National Committee</strong> (RNC), the NRSC,&nbsp;and the <strong>National Republican Congressional Committee</strong> (NRCC).</p>
<p>WinRed has recently come under fire for aggressive fundraising via text message as well. In June, <strong>404 Media</strong> reported on <a href="https://www.404media.co/winred-texts-class-action-lawsuit-rnc-donations/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a lawsuit</a> filed by a family in Utah against the RNC for allegedly bombarding their mobile phones with text messages seeking donations after they’d tried to unsubscribe from the missives dozens of times.</p>
<p>One of the family members said they received 27 such messages from 25 numbers, even after sending 20 stop requests. The plaintiffs in that case allege the texts from WinRed and the RNC “knowingly disregard stop requests and purposefully use different phone numbers to make it impossible to block new messages.”</p>
<p>Dijkhoorn said WinRed did inquire recently about why some of its assets had been marked as a risk by SURBL, but he said they appeared to have zero interest in investigating the likely causes he offered in reply.</p>
<p>“They only replied with, ‘You are interfering with U.S. elections,'” Dijkhoorn said, noting that many of SURBL’s spamtrap domains are only publicly listed in the registration records for random domain names.</p>
<p>“They’re at best harvested by themselves but more likely [they] just went and bought lists,” he said. “It’s not like ‘Oh Google is filtering this and not the other,’ the reason isn’t the provider. The reason is the fundraising spammers and the lists they send to.”</p>
											</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Developing a Space Flight Simulator in Clojure (209 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wedesoft.de/software/2025/09/05/clojure-game/</link>
            <guid>45145794</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 01:39:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wedesoft.de/software/2025/09/05/clojure-game/">https://www.wedesoft.de/software/2025/09/05/clojure-game/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45145794">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
  
  <p><span>05 Sep 2025</span></p><p>    <iframe title="YouTube video player" width="640" height="390" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/38FGT7SWVh0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>

<p>In 2017 I discovered the free of charge <a href="http://orbit.medphys.ucl.ac.uk/">Orbiter 2016</a> space flight simulator which was proprietary at the time and it inspired me to develop a space flight simulator myself.
I prototyped some rigid body physics in C and later in <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/guile/">GNU Guile</a> and also prototyped loading and rendering of Wavefront OBJ files.
I used GNU Guile (a Scheme implementation) because it has a good native interface and of course it has hygienic macros.
Eventually I got interested in Clojure because unlike GNU Guile it has multi-methods as well as fast hash maps and vectors.
I finally decided to develop the game for real in Clojure.
I have been developing a space flight simulator in Clojure for almost 5 years now.
While using Clojure I have come to appreciate the immutable values and safe parallelism using atoms, agents, and refs.</p>

<p>In the beginning I decided to work on the hard parts first, which for me were 3D rendering of a planet, an atmosphere, shadows, and volumetric clouds.
I read the <a href="https://www.informit.com/store/opengl-superbible-comprehensive-tutorial-and-reference-9780672337475">OpenGL Superbible</a> to get an understanding on what functionality OpenGL provides.
When Orbiter was eventually open sourced and released unter MIT license <a href="https://github.com/orbitersim/orbiter">here</a>, I inspected the source code and discovered that about 90% of the code is graphics-related.
So starting with the graphics problems was not a bad decision.</p>

<h2 id="software-dependencies">Software dependencies</h2>

<p>The following software is used for development.
The software libraries run on both GNU/Linux and Microsoft Windows.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://clojure.org/">Clojure</a> the programming language</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.lwjgl.org/">LWJGL</a> provides Java wrappers for various libraries
    <ul>
      <li>lwjgl-opengl for 3D graphics</li>
      <li>lwjgl-glfw for windowing and input devices</li>
      <li>lwjgl-nuklear for graphical user interfaces</li>
      <li>lwjgl-stb for image I/O and using truetype fonts</li>
      <li>lwjgl-assimp to load glTF 3D models with animation data</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/jrouwe/JoltPhysics">Jolt Physics</a> to simulate wheeled vehicles and collisions with meshes</li>
  <li><a href="https://generateme.github.io/fastmath/">Fastmath</a> for fast matrix and vector math as well as spline interpolation</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/weavejester/comb">Comb</a> for templating shader code</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/Engelberg/instaparse">Instaparse</a> to parse NASA Planetary Constant Kernel (PCK) files</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/clj-commons/gloss">Gloss</a> to parse NASA Double Precision Array Files (DAF)</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/IGJoshua/coffi">Coffi</a> as a foreign function interface</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/clojure/core.memoize">core.memoize</a> for least recently used caching of function results</li>
  <li><a href="https://commons.apache.org/proper/commons-compress/">Apache Commons Compress</a> to read map tiles from tar files</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/metosin/malli">Malli</a> to add schemas to functions</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/levand/immuconf">Immuconf</a> to load the configuration file</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/weavejester/progrock">Progrock</a> a progress bar for long running builds</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/clj-commons/claypoole">Claypoole</a> to implement parallel for loops</li>
  <li><a href="https://clojure.org/guides/tools_build">tools.build</a> to build the project</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/clojure-goes-fast/clj-async-profiler">clj-async-profiler</a> Clojure profiler creating flame graphs</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/fzakaria/slf4j-timbre">slf4j-timbre</a> Java logging implementation for Clojure</li>
</ul>

<p>The <em>deps.edn</em> file contains operating system dependent LWJGL bindings.
For example on GNU/Linux the <em>deps.edn</em> file contains the following:</p>

<figure><pre><code data-lang="clojure"><span>{</span><span>:deps</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>; ...</span><span>
        </span><span>org.lwjgl/lwjgl</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>:mvn/version</span><span> </span><span>"3.3.6"</span><span>}</span><span>
        </span><span>org.lwjgl/lwjgl$natives-linux</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>:mvn/version</span><span> </span><span>"3.3.6"</span><span>}</span><span>
        </span><span>org.lwjgl/lwjgl-opengl</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>:mvn/version</span><span> </span><span>"3.3.6"</span><span>}</span><span>
        </span><span>org.lwjgl/lwjgl-opengl$natives-linux</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>:mvn/version</span><span> </span><span>"3.3.6"</span><span>}</span><span>
        </span><span>org.lwjgl/lwjgl-glfw</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>:mvn/version</span><span> </span><span>"3.3.6"</span><span>}</span><span>
        </span><span>org.lwjgl/lwjgl-glfw$natives-linux</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>:mvn/version</span><span> </span><span>"3.3.6"</span><span>}</span><span>
        </span><span>org.lwjgl/lwjgl-nuklear</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>:mvn/version</span><span> </span><span>"3.3.6"</span><span>}</span><span>
        </span><span>org.lwjgl/lwjgl-nuklear$natives-linux</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>:mvn/version</span><span> </span><span>"3.3.6"</span><span>}</span><span>
        </span><span>org.lwjgl/lwjgl-stb</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>:mvn/version</span><span> </span><span>"3.3.6"</span><span>}</span><span>
        </span><span>org.lwjgl/lwjgl-stb$natives-linux</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>:mvn/version</span><span> </span><span>"3.3.6"</span><span>}</span><span>
        </span><span>org.lwjgl/lwjgl-assimp</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>:mvn/version</span><span> </span><span>"3.3.6"</span><span>}</span><span>
        </span><span>org.lwjgl/lwjgl-assimp$natives-linux</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>:mvn/version</span><span> </span><span>"3.3.6"</span><span>}}</span><span>
        </span><span>; ...</span><span>
        </span><span>}</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>In order to manage the different dependencies for Microsoft Windows, a separate Git branch is maintained.</p>

<h2 id="atmosphere-rendering">Atmosphere rendering</h2>


<p>    <iframe title="YouTube video player" width="640" height="390" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/q9aWd_14qhA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>

<p>For the atmosphere, <a href="https://ebruneton.github.io/precomputed_atmospheric_scattering/">Bruneton’s precomputed atmospheric scattering</a> was used.
The implementation uses a 2D transmittance table, a 2D surface scattering table, a 4D Rayleigh scattering, and a 4D Mie scattering table.
The tables are computed using several iterations of numerical integration.
Higher order functions for integration over a sphere and over a line segment were implemented in Clojure.
Integration over a ray in 3D space (using fastmath vectors) was implemented as follows for example:</p>

<figure><pre><code data-lang="clojure"><span>(</span><span>defn</span><span> </span><span>integral-ray</span><span>
  </span><span>"Integrate given function over a ray in 3D space"</span><span>
  </span><span>{</span><span>:malli/schema</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:=&gt;</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:cat</span><span> </span><span>ray</span><span> </span><span>N</span><span> </span><span>:double</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:=&gt;</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:cat</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:vector</span><span> </span><span>:double</span><span>]]</span><span> </span><span>:some</span><span>]]</span><span> </span><span>:some</span><span>]}</span><span>
  </span><span>[{</span><span>::keys</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>origin</span><span> </span><span>direction</span><span>]}</span><span> </span><span>steps</span><span> </span><span>distance</span><span> </span><span>fun</span><span>]</span><span>
  </span><span>(</span><span>let</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>stepsize</span><span>      </span><span>(</span><span>/</span><span> </span><span>distance</span><span> </span><span>steps</span><span>)</span><span>
        </span><span>samples</span><span>       </span><span>(</span><span>mapv</span><span> </span><span>#</span><span>(</span><span>*</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>+</span><span> </span><span>0.5</span><span> </span><span>%</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>stepsize</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>range</span><span> </span><span>steps</span><span>))</span><span>
        </span><span>interpolate</span><span>   </span><span>(</span><span>fn</span><span> </span><span>interpolate</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>s</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>add</span><span> </span><span>origin</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>mult</span><span> </span><span>direction</span><span> </span><span>s</span><span>)))</span><span>
        </span><span>direction-len</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>mag</span><span> </span><span>direction</span><span>)]</span><span>
    </span><span>(</span><span>reduce</span><span> </span><span>add</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>mapv</span><span> </span><span>#</span><span>(</span><span>-&gt;</span><span> </span><span>%</span><span> </span><span>interpolate</span><span> </span><span>fun</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>mult</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>*</span><span> </span><span>stepsize</span><span> </span><span>direction-len</span><span>)))</span><span> </span><span>samples</span><span>))))</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>Precomputing the atmospheric tables takes several hours even though <a href="https://clojuredocs.org/clojure.core/pmap">pmap</a> was used.
When sampling the multi-dimensional functions, <em>pmap</em> was used as a top-level loop and <em>map</em> was used for interior loops.
Using <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/nio/ByteBuffer.html">java.nio.ByteBuffer</a> the floating point values were converted to a byte array and then written to disk using a <a href="https://clojuredocs.org/clojure.java.io/output-stream">clojure.java.io/output-stream</a>:</p>

<figure><pre><code data-lang="clojure"><span>(</span><span>defn</span><span> </span><span>floats-&gt;bytes</span><span>
  </span><span>"Convert float array to byte buffer"</span><span>
  </span><span>[</span><span>^</span><span>floats</span><span> </span><span>float-data</span><span>]</span><span>
  </span><span>(</span><span>let</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>n</span><span>           </span><span>(</span><span>count</span><span> </span><span>float-data</span><span>)</span><span>
        </span><span>byte-buffer</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>.order</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>ByteBuffer/allocate</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>*</span><span> </span><span>n</span><span> </span><span>4</span><span>))</span><span> </span><span>ByteOrder/LITTLE_ENDIAN</span><span>)]</span><span>
    </span><span>(</span><span>.put</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>.asFloatBuffer</span><span> </span><span>byte-buffer</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>float-data</span><span>)</span><span>
    </span><span>(</span><span>.array</span><span> </span><span>byte-buffer</span><span>)))</span><span>

</span><span>(</span><span>defn</span><span> </span><span>spit-bytes</span><span>
  </span><span>"Write bytes to a file"</span><span>
  </span><span>{</span><span>:malli/schema</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:=&gt;</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:cat</span><span> </span><span>non-empty-string</span><span> </span><span>bytes?</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>:nil</span><span>]}</span><span>
  </span><span>[</span><span>^</span><span>String</span><span> </span><span>file-name</span><span> </span><span>^</span><span>bytes</span><span> </span><span>byte-data</span><span>]</span><span>
  </span><span>(</span><span>with-open</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>out</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>io/output-stream</span><span> </span><span>file-name</span><span>)]</span><span>
    </span><span>(</span><span>.write</span><span> </span><span>out</span><span> </span><span>byte-data</span><span>)))</span><span>

</span><span>(</span><span>defn</span><span> </span><span>spit-floats</span><span>
  </span><span>"Write floating point numbers to a file"</span><span>
  </span><span>{</span><span>:malli/schema</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:=&gt;</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:cat</span><span> </span><span>non-empty-string</span><span> </span><span>seqable?</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>:nil</span><span>]}</span><span>
  </span><span>[</span><span>^</span><span>String</span><span> </span><span>file-name</span><span> </span><span>^</span><span>floats</span><span> </span><span>float-data</span><span>]</span><span>
  </span><span>(</span><span>spit-bytes</span><span> </span><span>file-name</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>floats-&gt;bytes</span><span> </span><span>float-data</span><span>)))</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>When launching the game, the lookup tables get loaded and copied into OpenGL textures.
Shader functions are used to lookup and interpolate values from the tables.
When rendering the planet surface or the space craft, the atmosphere essentially gets superimposed using ray tracing.
After rendering the planet, a background quad is rendered to display the remaining part of the atmosphere above the horizon.</p>

<h2 id="templating-opengl-shaders">Templating OpenGL shaders</h2>

<p>It is possible to make programming with OpenGL shaders more flexible by using a templating library such as <em>Comb</em>.
The following shader defines multiple octaves of noise on a base noise function:</p>

<figure><pre><code data-lang="glsl"><span>#version 410 core
</span>
<span>float</span> <span>&lt;%=</span> <span>base</span><span>-</span><span>function</span> <span>%&gt;</span><span>(</span><span>vec3</span> <span>idx</span><span>);</span>

<span>float</span> <span>&lt;%=</span> <span>method</span><span>-</span><span>name</span> <span>%&gt;</span><span>(</span><span>vec3</span> <span>idx</span><span>)</span>
<span>{</span>
  <span>float</span> <span>result</span> <span>=</span> <span>0</span><span>.</span><span>0</span><span>;</span>
<span>&lt;%</span> <span>(</span><span>doseq</span> <span>[</span><span>multiplier</span> <span>octaves</span><span>]</span> <span>%&gt;</span>
  <span>result</span> <span>+=</span> <span>&lt;%=</span> <span>multiplier</span> <span>%&gt;</span> <span>*</span> <span>&lt;%=</span> <span>base</span><span>-</span><span>function</span> <span>%&gt;</span><span>(</span><span>idx</span><span>);</span>
  <span>idx</span> <span>*=</span> <span>2</span><span>;</span>
<span>&lt;%</span> <span>)</span> <span>%&gt;</span>
  <span>return</span> <span>result</span><span>;</span>
<span>}</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>One can then for example define the function <em>fbm_noise</em> using octaves of the base function <em>noise</em> as follows:</p>

<figure><pre><code data-lang="clojure"><span>(</span><span>def</span><span> </span><span>noise-octaves</span><span>
  </span><span>"Shader function to sum octaves of noise"</span><span>
  </span><span>(</span><span>template/fn</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>method-name</span><span> </span><span>base-function</span><span> </span><span>octaves</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>slurp</span><span> </span><span>"resources/shaders/core/noise-octaves.glsl"</span><span>)))</span><span>

</span><span>; ...</span><span>

</span><span>(</span><span>def</span><span> </span><span>fbm-noise-shader</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>noise-octaves</span><span> </span><span>"fbm_noise"</span><span> </span><span>"noise"</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>0.57</span><span> </span><span>0.28</span><span> </span><span>0.15</span><span>]))</span></code></pre></figure>

<h2 id="planet-rendering">Planet rendering</h2>


<p>    <iframe title="YouTube video player" width="640" height="390" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/Ce3oWQflYOY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>

<p>To render the planet, <a href="https://visibleearth.nasa.gov/collection/1484/blue-marble">NASA Bluemarble</a> data, <a href="https://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/features/NightLights/page3.php">NASA Blackmarble</a> data, and <a href="https://www.ngdc.noaa.gov/mgg/topo/gltiles.html">NASA Elevation</a> data was used.
The images were converted to a multi resolution pyramid of map tiles.
The following functions were implemented for color map tiles and for elevation tiles:</p>

<ul>
  <li>a function to load and cache map tiles of given 2D tile index and level of detail</li>
  <li>a function to extract a pixel from a map tile</li>
  <li>a function to extract the pixel for a specific longitude and latitude</li>
</ul>

<p>The functions for extracting a pixel for given longitude and latitude then were used to generate a cube map with a quad tree of tiles for each face.
For each tile, the following files were generated:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A daytime texture</li>
  <li>A night time texture</li>
  <li>An image of 3D vectors defining a surface mesh</li>
  <li>A water mask</li>
  <li>A normal map</li>
</ul>

<p>Altogether 655350 files were generated.
Because the Steam ContentBuilder does not support a large number of files, each row of tile data was aggregated into a tar file.
The <em>Apache Commons Compress</em> library allows you to open a tar file to get a list of entries and then perform random access on the contents of the tar file.
A Clojure LRU cache was used to maintain a cache of open tar files for improved performance.</p>

<p>At run time, a future is created, which returns an updated tile tree, a list of tiles to drop, and a path list of the tiles to load into OpenGL.
When the future is realized, the main thread deletes the OpenGL textures from the drop list, and then uses the path list to get the new loaded images from the tile tree, load them into OpenGL textures, and create an updated tile tree with the new OpenGL textures added.
The following functions to manipulate quad trees were implemented to realize this:</p>

<figure><pre><code data-lang="clojure"><span>(</span><span>defn</span><span> </span><span>quadtree-add</span><span>
  </span><span>"Add tiles to quad tree"</span><span>
  </span><span>{</span><span>:malli/schema</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:=&gt;</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:cat</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:maybe</span><span> </span><span>:map</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:sequential</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:vector</span><span> </span><span>:keyword</span><span>]]</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:sequential</span><span> </span><span>:map</span><span>]]</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:maybe</span><span> </span><span>:map</span><span>]]}</span><span>
  </span><span>[</span><span>tree</span><span> </span><span>paths</span><span> </span><span>tiles</span><span>]</span><span>
  </span><span>(</span><span>reduce</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>fn</span><span> </span><span>add-title-to-quadtree</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>tree</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>path</span><span> </span><span>tile</span><span>]]</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>assoc-in</span><span> </span><span>tree</span><span> </span><span>path</span><span> </span><span>tile</span><span>))</span><span> </span><span>tree</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>mapv</span><span> </span><span>vector</span><span> </span><span>paths</span><span> </span><span>tiles</span><span>)))</span><span>

</span><span>(</span><span>defn</span><span> </span><span>quadtree-extract</span><span>
  </span><span>"Extract a list of tiles from quad tree"</span><span>
  </span><span>{</span><span>:malli/schema</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:=&gt;</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:cat</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:maybe</span><span> </span><span>:map</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:sequential</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:vector</span><span> </span><span>:keyword</span><span>]]]</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:vector</span><span> </span><span>:map</span><span>]]}</span><span>
  </span><span>[</span><span>tree</span><span> </span><span>paths</span><span>]</span><span>
  </span><span>(</span><span>mapv</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>partial</span><span> </span><span>get-in</span><span> </span><span>tree</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>paths</span><span>))</span><span>

</span><span>(</span><span>defn</span><span> </span><span>quadtree-drop</span><span>
  </span><span>"Drop tiles specified by path list from quad tree"</span><span>
  </span><span>{</span><span>:malli/schema</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:=&gt;</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:cat</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:maybe</span><span> </span><span>:map</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:sequential</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:vector</span><span> </span><span>:keyword</span><span>]]]</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:maybe</span><span> </span><span>:map</span><span>]]}</span><span>
  </span><span>[</span><span>tree</span><span> </span><span>paths</span><span>]</span><span>
  </span><span>(</span><span>reduce</span><span> </span><span>dissoc-in</span><span> </span><span>tree</span><span> </span><span>paths</span><span>))</span><span>

</span><span>(</span><span>defn</span><span> </span><span>quadtree-update</span><span>
  </span><span>"Update tiles with specified paths using a function with optional arguments from lists"</span><span>
  </span><span>{</span><span>:malli/schema</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:=&gt;</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:cat</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:maybe</span><span> </span><span>:map</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:sequential</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:vector</span><span> </span><span>:keyword</span><span>]]</span><span> </span><span>fn?</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:*</span><span> </span><span>:any</span><span>]]</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>:maybe</span><span> </span><span>:map</span><span>]]}</span><span>
  </span><span>[</span><span>tree</span><span> </span><span>paths</span><span> </span><span>fun</span><span> </span><span>&amp;</span><span> </span><span>arglists</span><span>]</span><span>
  </span><span>(</span><span>reduce</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>fn</span><span> </span><span>update-tile-in-quadtree</span><span>
            </span><span>[</span><span>tree</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>path</span><span> </span><span>&amp;</span><span> </span><span>args</span><span>]]</span><span>
            </span><span>(</span><span>apply</span><span> </span><span>update-in</span><span> </span><span>tree</span><span> </span><span>path</span><span> </span><span>fun</span><span> </span><span>args</span><span>))</span><span> </span><span>tree</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>apply</span><span> </span><span>map</span><span> </span><span>list</span><span> </span><span>paths</span><span> </span><span>arglists</span><span>)))</span></code></pre></figure>

<h2 id="other-topics">Other topics</h2>

<h3 id="solar-system">Solar system</h3>

<p>The astronomy code for getting the position and orientation of planets was implemented according to the <a href="https://rhodesmill.org/skyfield/">Skyfield</a> Python library.
The Python library in turn is based on the <a href="https://naif.jpl.nasa.gov/naif/index.html">SPICE</a> toolkit of the NASA JPL.
The JPL basically provides sequences of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chebyshev_polynomials">Chebyshev polynomials</a> to interpolate positions of Moon and planets as well as the orientation of the Moon as binary files.
Reference coordinate systems and orientations of other bodies are provided in text files which consist of human and machine readable sections.
The binary files were parsed using <em>Gloss</em> (see <a href="https://github.com/clj-commons/gloss/wiki/Introduction">Wiki</a> for some examples) and the text files using <em>Instaparse</em>.</p>

<h3 id="jolt-bindings">Jolt bindings</h3>

<p>The required Jolt functions for wheeled vehicle dynamics and collisions with meshes were wrapped in C functions and compiled into a shared library.
The <em>Coffi</em> Clojure library (which is a wrapper for Java’s new Foreign Function &amp; Memory API) was used to make the C functions and data types usable in Clojure.</p>

<p>For example the following code implements a call to the C function <em>add_force</em>:</p>

<figure><pre><code data-lang="clojure"><span>(</span><span>defcfn</span><span> </span><span>add-force</span><span>
  </span><span>"Apply a force in the next physics update"</span><span>
  </span><span>add_force</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>::mem/int</span><span> </span><span>::vec3</span><span>]</span><span> </span><span>::mem/void</span><span>)</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>Here <em>::vec3</em> refers to a custom composite type defined using basic types.
The memory layout, serialisation, and deserialisation for <em>::vec3</em> are defined as follows:</p>

<figure><pre><code data-lang="clojure"><span>(</span><span>def</span><span> </span><span>vec3-struct</span><span>
  </span><span>[</span><span>::mem/struct</span><span>
   </span><span>[[</span><span>:x</span><span> </span><span>::mem/double</span><span>]</span><span>
    </span><span>[</span><span>:y</span><span> </span><span>::mem/double</span><span>]</span><span>
    </span><span>[</span><span>:z</span><span> </span><span>::mem/double</span><span>]]])</span><span>


</span><span>(</span><span>defmethod</span><span> </span><span>mem/c-layout</span><span> </span><span>::vec3</span><span>
  </span><span>[</span><span>_vec3</span><span>]</span><span>
  </span><span>(</span><span>mem/c-layout</span><span> </span><span>vec3-struct</span><span>))</span><span>


</span><span>(</span><span>defmethod</span><span> </span><span>mem/serialize-into</span><span> </span><span>::vec3</span><span>
  </span><span>[</span><span>obj</span><span> </span><span>_vec3</span><span> </span><span>segment</span><span> </span><span>arena</span><span>]</span><span>
  </span><span>(</span><span>mem/serialize-into</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>:x</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>obj</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>:y</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>obj</span><span> </span><span>1</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>:z</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>obj</span><span> </span><span>2</span><span>)}</span><span> </span><span>vec3-struct</span><span> </span><span>segment</span><span> </span><span>arena</span><span>))</span><span>


</span><span>(</span><span>defmethod</span><span> </span><span>mem/deserialize-from</span><span> </span><span>::vec3</span><span>
  </span><span>[</span><span>segment</span><span> </span><span>_vec3</span><span>]</span><span>
  </span><span>(</span><span>let</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>result</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>mem/deserialize-from</span><span> </span><span>segment</span><span> </span><span>vec3-struct</span><span>)]</span><span>
    </span><span>(</span><span>vec3</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>:x</span><span> </span><span>result</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>:y</span><span> </span><span>result</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>:z</span><span> </span><span>result</span><span>))))</span></code></pre></figure>

<h3 id="performance">Performance</h3>

<p>The <em>clj-async-profiler</em> was used to create flame graphs visualising the performance of the game.
In order to get reflection warnings for Java calls without sufficient type declarations, <em>*unchecked-math*</em> was set to <em>:warn-on-boxed</em>.</p>

<figure><pre><code data-lang="clojure"><span>(</span><span>set!</span><span> </span><span>*unchecked-math*</span><span> </span><span>:warn-on-boxed</span><span>)</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>Furthermore to discover missing declarations of numerical types, <em>*warn-on-reflection*</em> was set to <em>true</em>.</p>

<figure><pre><code data-lang="clojure"><span>(</span><span>set!</span><span> </span><span>*warn-on-reflection*</span><span> </span><span>true</span><span>)</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>To reduce garbage collector pauses, the ZGC low-latency garbage collector for the JVM was used.
The following section in <em>deps.edn</em> ensures that the ZGC garbage collector is used when running the project with <em>clj -M:run</em>:</p>

<figure><pre><code data-lang="clojure"><span>{</span><span>:deps</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>; ...</span><span>
        </span><span>}</span><span>
 </span><span>:aliases</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>:run</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>:jvm-opts</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>"-Xms2g"</span><span> </span><span>"-Xmx4g"</span><span> </span><span>"--enable-native-access=ALL-UNNAMED"</span><span> </span><span>"-XX:+UseZGC"</span><span>
                            </span><span>"--sun-misc-unsafe-memory-access=allow"</span><span>]</span><span>
                 </span><span>:main-opts</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>"-m"</span><span> </span><span>"sfsim.core"</span><span>]}}}</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>The option to use ZGC is also specified in the Packr JSON file used to deploy the application.</p>

<h3 id="building-the-project">Building the project</h3>

<p>In order to build the map tiles, atmospheric lookup tables, and other data files using <em>tools.build</em>, the project source code was made available in the <em>build.clj</em> file using a <em>:local/root</em> dependency:</p>

<figure><pre><code data-lang="clojure"><span>{</span><span>:deps</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>; ...</span><span>
        </span><span>}</span><span>
 </span><span>:aliases</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>; ...</span><span>
           </span><span>:build</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>:deps</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>io.github.clojure/tools.build</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>:mvn/version</span><span> </span><span>"0.10.10"</span><span>}</span><span>
                          </span><span>sfsim/sfsim</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>:local/root</span><span> </span><span>"."</span><span>}}</span><span>
                   </span><span>:ns-default</span><span> </span><span>build</span><span>
                   </span><span>:exec-fn</span><span> </span><span>all</span><span>
                   </span><span>:jvm-opts</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>"-Xms2g"</span><span> </span><span>"-Xmx4g"</span><span> </span><span>"--sun-misc-unsafe-memory-access=allow"</span><span>]}}}</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>Various targets were defined to build the different components of the project.
For example the atmospheric lookup tables can be build by specifying <em>clj -T:build atmosphere-lut</em> on the command line.</p>

<p>The following section in the <em>build.clj</em> file was added to allow creating an “Uberjar” JAR file with all dependencies by specifying <em>clj -T:build uber</em> on the command-line.</p>

<figure><pre><code data-lang="clojure"><span>(</span><span>defn</span><span> </span><span>uber</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>_</span><span>]</span><span>
  </span><span>(</span><span>b/copy-dir</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>:src-dirs</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>"src/clj"</span><span>]</span><span>
               </span><span>:target-dir</span><span> </span><span>class-dir</span><span>})</span><span>
  </span><span>(</span><span>b/compile-clj</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>:basis</span><span> </span><span>basis</span><span>
                  </span><span>:src-dirs</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>"src/clj"</span><span>]</span><span>
                  </span><span>:class-dir</span><span> </span><span>class-dir</span><span>})</span><span>
  </span><span>(</span><span>b/uber</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>:class-dir</span><span> </span><span>class-dir</span><span>
           </span><span>:uber-file</span><span> </span><span>"target/sfsim.jar"</span><span>
           </span><span>:basis</span><span> </span><span>basis</span><span>
           </span><span>:main</span><span> </span><span>'sfsim.core</span><span>}))</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>To create a Linux executable with Packr, one can then run <em>java -jar packr-all-4.0.0.jar scripts/packr-config-linux.json</em> where the JSON file has the following content:</p>

<figure><pre><code data-lang="json"><span>{</span><span>
  </span><span>"platform"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"linux64"</span><span>,</span><span>
  </span><span>"jdk"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"/usr/lib/jvm/jdk-24.0.2-oracle-x64"</span><span>,</span><span>
  </span><span>"executable"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"sfsim"</span><span>,</span><span>
  </span><span>"classpath"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>"target/sfsim.jar"</span><span>],</span><span>
  </span><span>"mainclass"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"sfsim.core"</span><span>,</span><span>
  </span><span>"resources"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>"LICENSE"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>"libjolt.so"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>"venturestar.glb"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>"resources"</span><span>],</span><span>
  </span><span>"vmargs"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>"Xms2g"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>"Xmx4g"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>"XX:+UseZGC"</span><span>],</span><span>
  </span><span>"output"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"out-linux"</span><span>
</span><span>}</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>In order to distribute the game on Steam, three depots were created:</p>

<ul>
  <li>a data depot with the operating system independent data files</li>
  <li>a Linux depot with the Linux executable and Uberjar including LWJGL’s Linux native bindings</li>
  <li>and a Windows depot with the Windows executable and an Uberjar including LWJGL’s Windows native bindings</li>
</ul>

<p>When updating a depot, the Steam ContentBuilder command line tool creates and uploads a patch in order to preserve storage space and bandwidth.</p>

<h2 id="future-work">Future work</h2>

<p>Although the hard parts are mostly done, there are still several things to do:</p>

<ul>
  <li>control surfaces and thruster graphics</li>
  <li>launchpad and runway graphics</li>
  <li>sound effects</li>
  <li>a 3D cockpit</li>
  <li>the Moon</li>
  <li>a space station</li>
</ul>

<p>It would also be interesting to make the game modable in a safe way (maybe evaluating Clojure files in a sandboxed environment?).</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>


<p>    <iframe title="YouTube video player" width="640" height="390" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/1PqmVLUt5_g" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>

<p>You can find the <a href="https://github.com/wedesoft/sfsim">source code on Github</a>.
Currently there is only a playtest build, but if you want to get notified, when the game gets released, you can <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/3687560/sfsim/">wishlist it here</a>.</p>

<p>Anyway, let me know any comments and suggestions.</p>

<p>Enjoy!</p>



<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.wedesoft.de/simulation/2025/06/06/flight-model-physics-venturestar/">Flight dynamics model for simulating Venturestar style spacecraft</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.wedesoft.de/software/2022/07/01/tdd-with-opengl/">Test Driven Development with OpenGL</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.wedesoft.de/software/2024/05/11/clojure-nuklear/">Implementing GUIs using Clojure and LWJGL Nuklear bindings</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.wedesoft.de/software/2023/05/03/volumetric-clouds/">Procedural Volumetric Clouds</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.wedesoft.de/software/2023/03/20/procedural-global-cloud-cover/">Procedural generation of global cloud cover</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.wedesoft.de/software/2021/09/20/reversed-z-rendering/">Reversed-Z Rendering in OpenGL</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.wedesoft.de/software/2023/12/25/clojure-function-schemas-with-malli/">Specifying Clojure function schemas with Malli</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.wedesoft.de/software/2024/07/05/clojure-instaparse/">Implement an Interpreter using Clojure Instaparse</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.wedesoft.de/simulation/2025/08/09/orbits-with-jolt-physics/">Orbits with Jolt Physics</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.wedesoft.de/simulation/2024/09/26/jolt-physics-engine/">Getting started with the Jolt Physics Engine</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.wedesoft.de/graphics/2023/09/29/blender-animate-bones-assimp/">Create Blender bones and animate and import with Assimp</a></li>
</ul>


</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A sunscreen scandal shocking Australia (116 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c4gzl41rpdqo</link>
            <guid>45145624</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 01:10:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c4gzl41rpdqo">https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c4gzl41rpdqo</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45145624">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><div data-testid="byline-new" data-component="byline-block"><p><span data-testid="byline-new-contributors"><p><span>Tabby Wilson and Tiffanie Turnbull</span><span data-testid="undefined-role-location">BBC News, Sydney</span></p></span></p></div><figure><div data-component="image-block"><p><img src="https://static.files.bbci.co.uk/bbcdotcom/web/20250828-055926-c20c0c03f5-2.28.1-2/grey-placeholder.png" aria-label="image unavailable"><img sizes="(min-width: 1280px) 50vw, (min-width: 1008px) 66vw, 96vw" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/3042/live/3de63510-8a4c-11f0-84c8-99de564f0440.jpg.webp 240w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/3042/live/3de63510-8a4c-11f0-84c8-99de564f0440.jpg.webp 320w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/3042/live/3de63510-8a4c-11f0-84c8-99de564f0440.jpg.webp 480w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/3042/live/3de63510-8a4c-11f0-84c8-99de564f0440.jpg.webp 640w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/3042/live/3de63510-8a4c-11f0-84c8-99de564f0440.jpg.webp 800w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1024/cpsprodpb/3042/live/3de63510-8a4c-11f0-84c8-99de564f0440.jpg.webp 1024w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1536/cpsprodpb/3042/live/3de63510-8a4c-11f0-84c8-99de564f0440.jpg.webp 1536w" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/3042/live/3de63510-8a4c-11f0-84c8-99de564f0440.jpg.webp" loading="eager" alt="Marianna Massey/Getty Images Two women wipe sunscreen on the backs of two men on a beach. The men are wearing swimming shorts while the women are in shorts ad in one case a bikini top and the other a sleeveless white top"><span>Marianna Massey/Getty Images</span></p></div><p data-component="caption-block"><figcaption>Sunscreens are at the heart of a national scandal in Australia </figcaption></p></figure><div data-component="text-block"><p>Like many Australians, Rach grew up "terrified of the sun" in the country with the highest rates of skin cancer in the world.</p><p>Her childhood was characterised by the infamous "no hat, no play" rule that is commonplace in Australian schools, 90s advertisements that warned the sun would give you cancer, and sunscreen tubes that stood guard at every door in her home.</p><p>It made the now 34-year-old the kind of person who religiously applies sunscreen multiple times a day and rarely leaves the house without a hat.</p><p>So she was shocked when doctors found a skin cancer on her nose during a check last November, something they said was abnormal given her age and ray-dodging regime.</p><p>Though technically classified as a "low grade" skin cancer – a basal cell carcinoma – it had to be surgically removed, leaving the Newcastle mum with a scar just below her eye.</p><p>"I was just confused, and I was a little bit angry because I was like, 'Are you kidding me?'" Rach – who asked that her surname not be used – told the BBC. "I thought I'd done all the right stuff and it still happened to me."</p><p>That rage grew when she learned the sunscreen she had been using for years was unreliable and, according to some tests, offered next to no sun protection at all.</p></div><figure><div data-component="image-block"><p><img src="https://static.files.bbci.co.uk/bbcdotcom/web/20250828-055926-c20c0c03f5-2.28.1-2/grey-placeholder.png" aria-label="image unavailable"><img sizes="(min-width: 1280px) 50vw, (min-width: 1008px) 66vw, 96vw" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/5822/live/d6ebadf0-8964-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.png.webp 240w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/5822/live/d6ebadf0-8964-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.png.webp 320w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/5822/live/d6ebadf0-8964-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.png.webp 480w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/5822/live/d6ebadf0-8964-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.png.webp 640w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/5822/live/d6ebadf0-8964-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.png.webp 800w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1024/cpsprodpb/5822/live/d6ebadf0-8964-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.png.webp 1024w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1536/cpsprodpb/5822/live/d6ebadf0-8964-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.png.webp 1536w" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/5822/live/d6ebadf0-8964-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.png.webp" loading="lazy" alt="ABC News/Billy Cooper A purple and blue tube of sunscreen stands on a counter, with a range of other sunscreens blurred in the background"><span>ABC News/Billy Cooper</span></p></div><p data-component="caption-block"><figcaption>This Ultra Violette product is at the centre of the sunscreen controversy </figcaption></p></figure><div data-component="text-block"><p>Independent analysis by a trusted consumer advocacy group has found that several of Australia's most popular, and expensive, sunscreens are not providing the protection they claim to, kicking off a national scandal.</p><p>There has been a massive backlash from customers, a probe launched by the country's medical watchdog, multiple products pulled from shelves, and questions raised about the regulation of sunscreen around the globe.</p><p>"It's definitely not an issue isolated to Australia," cosmetic chemist Michelle Wong told the BBC.</p></div><p data-component="subheadline-block"><h2>The reckoning</h2></p><div data-component="text-block"><p>Australians have a complicated relationship with the sun: they love it, but they also fear it. </p><p>Effective public health messaging – which has drilled "Slip, Slop, Slap" into their heads – competes with a beauty culture which often idolises bronzed skin.</p><p>The country has the highest incidence of skin cancers in the world and it is estimated that two out of three Australians will have at least one cut out in their lifetime.</p><p>So when Choice Australia released its damning report in June, it immediately made waves. The group had tested 20 sunscreens in an independent accredited Australian lab, finding 16 did not meet the SPF, or skin protection factor, rating listed on the packet.</p><p>Ultra Violette's Lean Screen SPF 50+ Mattifying Zinc Skinscreen, a facial product that Rach says she used exclusively, was the "most significant failure" identified. It returned a result of SPF 4, something that shocked Choice so much it commissioned a second test that produced a similar reading.</p><p>Other products that did not meet their SPF claims included those from Neutrogena, Banana Boat, Bondi Sands and the Cancer Council - but they all rejected Choice's findings and said their own independent testing showed their sunscreens worked as advertised.</p></div><figure><div data-component="image-block"><p><img src="https://static.files.bbci.co.uk/bbcdotcom/web/20250828-055926-c20c0c03f5-2.28.1-2/grey-placeholder.png" aria-label="image unavailable"><img sizes="(min-width: 1280px) 50vw, (min-width: 1008px) 66vw, 96vw" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/afd9/live/4d52f570-8965-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.jpg.webp 240w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/afd9/live/4d52f570-8965-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.jpg.webp 320w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/afd9/live/4d52f570-8965-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.jpg.webp 480w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/afd9/live/4d52f570-8965-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.jpg.webp 640w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/afd9/live/4d52f570-8965-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.jpg.webp 800w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1024/cpsprodpb/afd9/live/4d52f570-8965-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.jpg.webp 1024w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1536/cpsprodpb/afd9/live/4d52f570-8965-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.jpg.webp 1536w" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/afd9/live/4d52f570-8965-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.jpg.webp" loading="lazy" alt="Getty Images A young cricket player, her red hair braided over her shoulder, rubbing in sunscreen"><span>Getty Images</span></p></div><p data-component="caption-block"><figcaption>For decades Australians have been urged to slip on a shirt, slop on sunscreen and slap on a hat</figcaption></p></figure><div data-component="text-block"><p>The uproar was immediate for the brands named in the report, and also prompted a swift response from the Therapeutic Goods Association (TGA), which said it would investigate the findings and "take regulatory action as required".</p><p>Ultra Violette bit back, saying they were "confident that Lean Screen is safe and effective" and detailing extensive testing of the product - which has been sold in almost 30 countries, including the UK, and retails for upwards of A$50 (£24, $33).</p><p>But less than two months later, it announced that Lean Screen would be recalled after it returned inconsistent results across eight different sets of lab testing.</p><p>"We are deeply sorry that one of our products has fallen short of the standards we pride ourselves on and that you have come to expect of us," read a statement published to the brand's Instagram account.</p><p>It added that it has "since ended the relationship with the initial testing lab".</p><p>In the past fortnight, other brands have "paused" the sale of at least four more products, none of which were included in the Choice report.</p><p>Rach knows there is no way to prove that there is a link between her diagnosis and the brand of sunscreen she relied on. She says she is not alleging there is such a connection. </p><p>But she said Ultra Violette's response to the scandal was like "a kick in the guts". </p><p>She felt that they took no real accountability for the pitfalls of their product, and was let down by their decision to continue selling it for two months despite doubts over its efficacy.</p><p>"I just had like the five stages of grief, you know?" she said. "I was angry, I was upset, I was almost in denial."</p><p>Like Rach, a horde of annoyed customers say the saga has shaken their faith in the industry.</p><p>"A refund isn't really going to reverse years of sun damage, is it?" one wrote in response to Ultra Violette's recall statement.</p><p>A spokesperson told the BBC Ultra Violette had retested all its other products and confirmed their SPF ratings.</p><p>"We were the first, and currently the only of the 16 products that failed Choice's test to not just pause sales but withdraw the product all together, prioritising safety, and giving customers access to refunds and a product voucher," they said in a statement.</p></div><figure><div data-component="image-block"><p><img src="https://static.files.bbci.co.uk/bbcdotcom/web/20250828-055926-c20c0c03f5-2.28.1-2/grey-placeholder.png" aria-label="image unavailable"><img sizes="(min-width: 1280px) 50vw, (min-width: 1008px) 66vw, 96vw" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/e2d7/live/626633e0-8966-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.jpg.webp 240w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/e2d7/live/626633e0-8966-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.jpg.webp 320w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/e2d7/live/626633e0-8966-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.jpg.webp 480w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/e2d7/live/626633e0-8966-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.jpg.webp 640w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/e2d7/live/626633e0-8966-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.jpg.webp 800w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1024/cpsprodpb/e2d7/live/626633e0-8966-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.jpg.webp 1024w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1536/cpsprodpb/e2d7/live/626633e0-8966-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.jpg.webp 1536w" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/e2d7/live/626633e0-8966-11f0-9df7-33c9b75a833d.jpg.webp" loading="lazy" alt="Getty Images Ava Chandler-Matthews and Rebecca Jefferd of Ultra Violette"><span>Getty Images</span></p></div><p data-component="caption-block"><figcaption>Ava Chandler-Matthews and Rebecca Jefferd founded Ultra Violette in 2019</figcaption></p></figure><div data-component="text-block"><p>The Ultra Violette spokesperson added that the brand was working with the TGA and others to make sure this moment of reckoning isn't wasted.</p><p>"We are committed to doing our part in driving this category forward."</p><p>Choice has urged the TGA to conduct further investigations into the sunscreen market, and also urged any brands who had reason to question the SPF protection listed on their products to remove them from sale immediately.</p><p>"It is clear there is a serious issue in the Australian sunscreen industry that urgently needs to be addressed," said Rosie Thomas, the director of campaigns, in a statement to the BBC.</p></div><p data-component="subheadline-block"><h2>How did this happen?</h2></p><div data-component="text-block"><p>While in Europe sunscreen is classed as a cosmetic, Australia regulates it as a therapeutic good – essentially a medicine – which means it is subject to some of the most robust sunscreen regulations in the world. </p><p>And that's something many of the brands caught up in this saga trade on. So, how did this happen?</p><p>An investigation by the Australian Broadcasting Corporation found that <a target="_blank" href="https://www.abc.net.au/news/2025-07-04/questions-over-lab-that-tested-sunscreen-spf-claims/105458458">a single US-based laboratory had certified at least half of the products</a> that had failed Choice's testing, and that this facility routinely recorded high test results.</p><p>It also found that <a target="_blank" href="https://www.abc.net.au/news/2025-08-30/sunscreen-spf-consumer-protection-base-formula/105711012">several of the sunscreens pulled from shelves shared a similar base formula</a> and linked them to a manufacturer in Western Australia.</p><p>The TGA says it does not usually speak about ongoing investigations because it does not want to compromise them, but that it is also looking into "reviewing existing SPF testing requirements" which can be "highly subjective".</p><p>"The TGA is also aware that it is common practice for different sunscreen products to share the same or similar base formulations," a spokesperson said in a statement to the BBC.</p><p>"Ultimately it is the sponsor's [seller's] responsibility to ensure that their medicine remains compliant with all applicable legislative requirements."</p><p>Consistent and comfortable sunscreens which offer high protection are very technical and difficult to make, says Dr Wong, founder of Lab Muffin Beauty Science. </p><p>Everyone's skin responds differently to the product, she adds, and it's one that is almost always being stress-tested - by sweat, water, or makeup.</p><p>It is very difficult to rate effectively for the same reasons. Historically, it has been done by spreading the sunscreen on 10 people at the same thickness, then timing how long it takes for their skin to start burning both with and without the product applied.</p></div><figure><div data-component="image-block"><p><img src="https://static.files.bbci.co.uk/bbcdotcom/web/20250828-055926-c20c0c03f5-2.28.1-2/grey-placeholder.png" aria-label="image unavailable"><img sizes="(min-width: 1280px) 50vw, (min-width: 1008px) 66vw, 96vw" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/d151/live/d59b3b40-8a37-11f0-a26a-51aa2f3dec3f.jpg.webp 240w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/d151/live/d59b3b40-8a37-11f0-a26a-51aa2f3dec3f.jpg.webp 320w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/d151/live/d59b3b40-8a37-11f0-a26a-51aa2f3dec3f.jpg.webp 480w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/d151/live/d59b3b40-8a37-11f0-a26a-51aa2f3dec3f.jpg.webp 640w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/d151/live/d59b3b40-8a37-11f0-a26a-51aa2f3dec3f.jpg.webp 800w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1024/cpsprodpb/d151/live/d59b3b40-8a37-11f0-a26a-51aa2f3dec3f.jpg.webp 1024w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1536/cpsprodpb/d151/live/d59b3b40-8a37-11f0-a26a-51aa2f3dec3f.jpg.webp 1536w" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/d151/live/d59b3b40-8a37-11f0-a26a-51aa2f3dec3f.jpg.webp" loading="lazy" alt="Getty Images A spectator uses an umbrella to shield herself from the sun as another applies sunscreen during the men's singles third round match between Luxembourg's Gilles Muller and Spain's Pablo Carreno Busta on day five of the Australian Open tennis tournament in Melbourne on January 19, 2018."><span>Getty Images</span></p></div><p data-component="caption-block"><figcaption>Effective and popular sunscreens are hard to get right, experts say</figcaption></p></figure><div data-component="text-block"><p>While there are clear guidelines as to what you are looking for, Dr Wong says there is still a lot of variability. That is down to skin texture or tone, or even the colour of the walls, and "different labs get different results".</p><p>But she says results are also quite easy to fake, pointing to a 2019 probe by US authorities into a sunscreen testing laboratory <a target="_blank" href="https://www.justice.gov/usao-sdny/pr/owner-consumer-products-testing-company-sentenced-60-months-prison-fraud-scheme">which resulted in the owner being jailed for fraud</a>.</p><p>Many sunscreen brands from all over the world use the same manufacturers and testing labs - and so this issue is unlikely to be isolated to Australia, she adds.</p><p>"Until someone goes out and tests a whole bunch of sunscreens in other countries, we just don't know the extent of it."</p><p>She says the scandal is a reminder that regulations are only as good as they are enforced.</p><p>But while it has touched a nerve for many people who are at high risk for skin cancer simply by virtue of being Australian, Dr Wong said she felt the panic triggered by the investigation was blown out of proportion.</p><p>She points to the world's largest clinical trial of sunscreen, done in the 90s, which found that the daily use of an SPF 16 sunscreen dramatically dropped skin cancer rates.</p><p>"95% of the sunscreens tested [by Choice] have high enough SPF to more than halve the incidence of skin cancer," Dr Wong said.</p><p>"Some of the SPF testing, I feel, has become a bit more of a marketing exercise than a real reflection of efficacy."</p><p>The most important thing you can do when choosing a sunscreen, she says, is actually wear enough of it – a full teaspoon at least for each part of your body, face included. </p><p>And ideally you should apply it about every two hours, especially if you have been sweating a lot or swimming.  </p><p>Experts also advise that you combine the sunscreen with other safety methods, such as wearing protective clothing and seeking out shade.</p></div><div data-component="links-block"><p><span data-testid="links-title">Read more Australia stories </span></p></div></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[GLM 4.5 with Claude Code (182 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://docs.z.ai/guides/llm/glm-4.5</link>
            <guid>45145457</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 00:45:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://docs.z.ai/guides/llm/glm-4.5">https://docs.z.ai/guides/llm/glm-4.5</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45145457">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-page-title="GLM-4.5" data-page-href="/guides/llm/glm-4.5"><h2 id="overview"><span><svg style="-webkit-mask-image:url(https://d3gk2c5xim1je2.cloudfront.net/v6.6.0/solid/rectangle-list.svg);-webkit-mask-repeat:no-repeat;-webkit-mask-position:center;mask-image:url(https://d3gk2c5xim1je2.cloudfront.net/v6.6.0/solid/rectangle-list.svg);mask-repeat:no-repeat;mask-position:center;background-color:#ffffff;width:36px;height:36px;display:inline-block;vertical-align:middle"></svg>   Overview</span></h2>

<p><span data-as="p">GLM-4.5 and GLM-4.5-Air are our latest flagship models, purpose-built as foundational models for agent-oriented applications. Both leverage a Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) architecture. GLM-4.5 has a total parameter count of 355B with 32B active parameters per forward pass, while GLM-4.5-Air adopts a more streamlined design with 106B total parameters and 12B active parameters.</span>
<span data-as="p">Both models share a similar training pipeline: an initial pretraining phase on 15 trillion tokens of general-domain data, followed by targeted fine-tuning on datasets covering code, reasoning, and agent-specific tasks. The context length has been extended to 128k tokens, and reinforcement learning was applied to further enhance reasoning, coding, and agent performance.</span>
<span data-as="p">GLM-4.5 and GLM-4.5-Air are optimized for tool invocation, web browsing, software engineering, and front-end development. They can be integrated into code-centric agents such as Claude Code and Roo Code, and also support arbitrary agent applications through tool invocation APIs.</span>
<span data-as="p">Both models support hybrid reasoning modes, offering two execution modes: Thinking Mode for complex reasoning and tool usage, and Non-Thinking Mode for instant responses. These modes can be toggled via the <code>thinking.type</code>parameter (with <code>enabled</code> and <code>disabled</code> settings), and dynamic thinking is enabled by default.</span></p>
<h2 id="glm-4-5-serials"><span><svg style="-webkit-mask-image:url(https://d3gk2c5xim1je2.cloudfront.net/v6.6.0/solid/list-ol.svg);-webkit-mask-repeat:no-repeat;-webkit-mask-position:center;mask-image:url(https://d3gk2c5xim1je2.cloudfront.net/v6.6.0/solid/list-ol.svg);mask-repeat:no-repeat;mask-position:center;background-color:#ffffff;width:36px;height:36px;display:inline-block;vertical-align:middle"></svg>   GLM-4.5 Serials</span></h2>

<h2 id="capability"><span><svg style="-webkit-mask-image:url(https://d3gk2c5xim1je2.cloudfront.net/v6.6.0/solid/table-cells.svg);-webkit-mask-repeat:no-repeat;-webkit-mask-position:center;mask-image:url(https://d3gk2c5xim1je2.cloudfront.net/v6.6.0/solid/table-cells.svg);mask-repeat:no-repeat;mask-position:center;background-color:#ffffff;width:36px;height:36px;display:inline-block;vertical-align:middle"></svg>   Capability</span></h2>

<h2 id="introducting-glm-4-5"><span><svg style="-webkit-mask-image:url(https://d3gk2c5xim1je2.cloudfront.net/v6.6.0/solid/arrow-down-from-line.svg);-webkit-mask-repeat:no-repeat;-webkit-mask-position:center;mask-image:url(https://d3gk2c5xim1je2.cloudfront.net/v6.6.0/solid/arrow-down-from-line.svg);mask-repeat:no-repeat;mask-position:center;background-color:#ffffff;width:36px;height:36px;display:inline-block;vertical-align:middle"></svg>   Introducting GLM-4.5</span></h2>
<h3 id="overview-2"><span>Overview</span></h3>
<p><span data-as="p">The first-principle measure of AGI lies in integrating more general intelligence capabilities without compromising existing functions. GLM-4.5 represents our first complete realization of this concept. It combines advanced reasoning, coding, and agent capabilities within a single model, achieving a significant technological breakthrough by natively fusing reasoning, coding, and agent abilities to meet the complex demands of agent-based applications.</span>
<span data-as="p">To comprehensively evaluate the model’s general intelligence, we selected 12 of the most representative benchmark suites, including MMLU Pro, AIME24, MATH 500, SciCode, GPQA, HLE, LiveCodeBench, SWE-Bench, Terminal-bench, TAU-Bench, BFCL v3, and BrowseComp. Based on the aggregated average scores, GLM-4.5 ranks second globally among all models, first among domestic models, and first among open-source models.</span>
<span aria-owns="rmiz-modal-" data-rmiz=""><span data-rmiz-content="not-found"><picture><img data-path="resource/benchmark-0.png" src="https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark-0.png?fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=d565bc82527cd77841a018a7e9fe2df0" alt="Description" width="1280" height="519" decoding="async" sizes="(max-width: 840px) 100vw, (max-width: 1100px) 50vw, 33vw" srcset="https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark-0.png?w=280&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=7365968bdde0823d47d300cc47513784 280w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark-0.png?w=560&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=148a0bf8b7521d83038120f905dd6405 560w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark-0.png?w=840&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=cdd09f501f000d35951a58d40bd4df64 840w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark-0.png?w=1100&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=13c5518e6b936b26576417406e13b126 1100w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark-0.png?w=1650&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=e0fac97416d648104e20863f6df4e7b3 1650w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark-0.png?w=2500&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=fbf4e15b30ce23327b31afadddfb3efa 2500w" data-optimize="true"></picture></span></span>
<span aria-owns="rmiz-modal-" data-rmiz=""><span data-rmiz-content="not-found"><picture><img data-path="resource/benchmark-1.png" src="https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark-1.png?fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=a296f62a9517735d7af5b0580094065b" alt="Description" width="1280" height="338" decoding="async" sizes="(max-width: 840px) 100vw, (max-width: 1100px) 50vw, 33vw" srcset="https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark-1.png?w=280&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=7081c526e679395aa8dee0e9913da019 280w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark-1.png?w=560&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=6cbaf319c9f8da2ed44676b778b2f5ed 560w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark-1.png?w=840&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=cae5d25fb5c262fd222636e46da12130 840w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark-1.png?w=1100&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=272ffdfd95d6f3c2c12f0bd146c7a3a9 1100w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark-1.png?w=1650&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=ed785a2a6b7c309d9ec2554144d92201 1650w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark-1.png?w=2500&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=c20fdadadb52a4a60fa0fe9e6fbcdfaf 2500w" data-optimize="true"></picture></span></span></p><h3 id="higher-parameter-efficiency"><span><strong>Higher Parameter Efficiency</strong></span></h3>
<p><span data-as="p">GLM-4.5 has half the number of parameters of DeepSeek-R1 and one-third that of Kimi-K2, yet it outperforms them on multiple standard benchmark tests. This is attributed to the higher parameter efficiency of GLM architecture. Notably, GLM-4.5-Air, with 106 billion total parameters and 12 billion active parameters, achieves a significant breakthrough—surpassing models such as Gemini 2.5 Flash, Qwen3-235B, and Claude 4 Opus on reasoning benchmarks like Artificial Analysis, ranking among the top three domestic models in performance.</span>
<span data-as="p">On charts such as SWE-Bench Verified, the GLM-4.5 series lies on the Pareto frontier for performance-to-parameter ratio, demonstrating that at the same scale, the GLM-4.5 series delivers optimal performance.</span>
<span aria-owns="rmiz-modal-" data-rmiz=""><span data-rmiz-content="not-found"><picture><img data-path="resource/benchmark-2.png" src="https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark-2.png?fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=0ab97aeb6f7d4cef4e2b33fcb76231b4" alt="Description" width="1280" height="777" decoding="async" sizes="(max-width: 840px) 100vw, (max-width: 1100px) 50vw, 33vw" srcset="https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark-2.png?w=280&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=e5462bd8ceb960fc00833ad31277cc71 280w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark-2.png?w=560&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=affcf850f56f6592379fb9577bd59d00 560w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark-2.png?w=840&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=ba573ed2e9c7995afda5ff2b4fa114f3 840w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark-2.png?w=1100&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=2cb08db672a6d9695d1cbf94f63cb5aa 1100w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark-2.png?w=1650&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=a0b96f5aa3489394465c341141076bcc 1650w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark-2.png?w=2500&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=e2114df239206110bf9cb0a6d4270023 2500w" data-optimize="true"></picture></span></span></p><h3 id="low-cost%2C-high-speed"><span><strong>Low Cost, High Speed</strong></span></h3>
<p><span data-as="p">Beyond performance optimization, the GLM-4.5 series also achieves breakthroughs in cost and efficiency, resulting in pricing far lower than mainstream models: API call costs are as low as $0.2 per million input tokens and $1.1 per million output tokens.</span>
<span data-as="p">At the same time, the high-speed version demonstrates a generation speed exceeding 100 tokens per second in real-world tests, supporting low-latency and high-concurrency deployment scenarios—balancing cost-effectiveness with user interaction experience.</span>
<span aria-owns="rmiz-modal-" data-rmiz=""><span data-rmiz-content="not-found"><picture><img data-path="resource/benchmark2.png" src="https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark2.png?fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=d39c7575956dbe42a1c437e3cf14279f" alt="Description" width="990" height="305" decoding="async" sizes="(max-width: 840px) 100vw, (max-width: 1100px) 50vw, 33vw" srcset="https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark2.png?w=280&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=36ded49da55eee897a3c75da1cf8a462 280w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark2.png?w=560&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=a66679e1487639408b67b6e09c3c3567 560w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark2.png?w=840&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=1bcb41a8f67aad17e947d332bc4fb851 840w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark2.png?w=1100&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=91584a7f2d33cadd159b991cf0bec447 1100w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark2.png?w=1650&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=aabc285869f2becb3cb49e474fc72837 1650w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/benchmark2.png?w=2500&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=92553133a8200bd6a6adf57ce447e250 2500w" data-optimize="true"></picture></span></span></p><h3 id="real-world-evaluation"><span><strong>Real-World Evaluation</strong></span></h3>
<p><span data-as="p">Real-world performance matters more than leaderboard rankings. To evaluate GLM-4.5’s effectiveness in practical Agent Coding scenarios, we integrated it into Claude Code and benchmarked it against Claude 4 Sonnet, Kimi-K2, and Qwen3-Coder.</span>
<span data-as="p">The evaluation consisted of 52 programming and development tasks spanning six major domains, executed in isolated container environments with multi-turn interaction tests.</span>
<span data-as="p">As shown in the results (below), GLM-4.5 demonstrates a strong competitive advantage over other open-source models, particularly in tool invocation reliability and task completion rate. While there remains room for improvement compared to Claude 4 Sonnet, GLM-4.5 delivers a largely comparable experience in most scenarios.</span>
<span data-as="p">To ensure transparency, we have released all <a href="https://huggingface.co/datasets/zai-org/CC-Bench-trajectories" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">52 test problems along with full agent trajectories</a> for industry validation and reproducibility.</span>
<span aria-owns="rmiz-modal-" data-rmiz=""><span data-rmiz-content="not-found"><picture><img data-path="resource/expr1.jpeg" src="https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/expr1.jpeg?fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=f8b051792b065926cf99bed4648197e0" alt="Description" width="1280" height="564" decoding="async" sizes="(max-width: 840px) 100vw, (max-width: 1100px) 50vw, 33vw" srcset="https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/expr1.jpeg?w=280&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=26e0bf74011f877a3b7fa71a75236a13 280w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/expr1.jpeg?w=560&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=793e94d145f933d9684b39a145ca814f 560w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/expr1.jpeg?w=840&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=451457ec301347d9f1a6dc48dbf51032 840w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/expr1.jpeg?w=1100&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=b27b4502c1a38d9745d07c3052dbeb6c 1100w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/expr1.jpeg?w=1650&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=776abd81fff1c5f0bf70ad16f540eb34 1650w, https://mintcdn.com/zhipu-32152247/fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i/resource/expr1.jpeg?w=2500&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format&amp;n=fQm1SxNtD2jBDQ3i&amp;q=85&amp;s=32403d412a1c80d552ce0fe2dbd96fad 2500w" data-optimize="true"></picture></span></span></p><h2 id="usage"><span><svg style="-webkit-mask-image:url(https://d3gk2c5xim1je2.cloudfront.net/v6.6.0/solid/list.svg);-webkit-mask-repeat:no-repeat;-webkit-mask-position:center;mask-image:url(https://d3gk2c5xim1je2.cloudfront.net/v6.6.0/solid/list.svg);mask-repeat:no-repeat;mask-position:center;background-color:#ffffff;width:36px;height:36px;display:inline-block;vertical-align:middle"></svg>   Usage</span></h2>
<div id="web-development"><ul data-component-part="tabs-list"><li id="web-development"></li><li id="ai-assistant"></li><li id="smart-office"></li><li id="intelligent-question-answering"></li><li id="complex-text-translation"></li><li id="content-creation"></li><li id="virtual-characters"></li></ul><div data-component-part="tab-content"><p><span data-as="p"><strong>Core Capability:</strong> <u>Coding Skills</u> → Intelligent code generation | Real-time code completion | Automated bug fixing</span></p><ul>
<li>Supports major languages including Python, JavaScript, and Java.</li>
<li>Generates well-structured, scalable, high-quality code based on natural language instructions.</li>
<li>Focuses on real-world development needs, avoiding templated or generic outputs.</li>
</ul><p><span data-as="p"><strong>Use Case:</strong> Complete refactoring-level tasks within 1 hour; generate full product prototypes in 5 minutes.</span></p><video src="https://cdn.bigmodel.cn/agent-demos/lark/113123.mov" controls=""></video></div></div>
<h2 id="resources"><span><svg style="-webkit-mask-image:url(https://d3gk2c5xim1je2.cloudfront.net/v6.6.0/solid/bars-sort.svg);-webkit-mask-repeat:no-repeat;-webkit-mask-position:center;mask-image:url(https://d3gk2c5xim1je2.cloudfront.net/v6.6.0/solid/bars-sort.svg);mask-repeat:no-repeat;mask-position:center;background-color:#ffffff;width:36px;height:36px;display:inline-block;vertical-align:middle"></svg>   Resources</span></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://docs.z.ai/api-reference/llm/chat-completion">API Documentation</a>: Learn how to call the API.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="quick-start"><span><svg style="-webkit-mask-image:url(https://d3gk2c5xim1je2.cloudfront.net/v6.6.0/solid/rectangle-code.svg);-webkit-mask-repeat:no-repeat;-webkit-mask-position:center;mask-image:url(https://d3gk2c5xim1je2.cloudfront.net/v6.6.0/solid/rectangle-code.svg);mask-repeat:no-repeat;mask-position:center;background-color:#ffffff;width:36px;height:36px;display:inline-block;vertical-align:middle"></svg>    Quick Start</span></h2>
<h3 id="thinking-mode"><span>Thinking Mode</span></h3>
<p><span data-as="p">GLM-4.5 offers a “Deep Thinking Mode” that users can enable or disable by setting the <code>thinking.type</code> parameter. This parameter supports two values: <code>enabled</code> (enabled) and <code>disabled</code> (disabled). By default, dynamic thinking is enabled.</span></p><ul>
<li><strong>Simple Tasks (No Thinking Required):</strong> For straightforward requests that do not require complex reasoning (e.g., fact retrieval or classification), thinking is unnecessary. Examples include:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li>When was Z.AI founded?</li>
<li>Translate the sentence “I love you” into Chinese.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Moderate Tasks (Default/Some Thinking Required):</strong> Many common requests require stepwise processing or deeper understanding. The GLM-4.5 series can flexibly apply thinking capabilities to handle tasks such as:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li>Why does Jupiter have more moons than Saturn, despite Saturn being larger?</li>
<li>Compare the advantages and disadvantages of flying versus taking the high-speed train from Beijing to Shanghai.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><span data-as="p"><strong>Difficult Tasks (Maximum Thinking Capacity):</strong> For truly complex challenges—such as solving advanced math problems, network-related questions, or coding issues—these tasks require the model to fully engage its reasoning and planning abilities, often involving many internal steps before arriving at an answer. Examples include:</span></p><ul>
<li>Explain in detail how different experts in a Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) model collaborate.</li>
<li>Based on the recent week’s fluctuations of the Shanghai Composite Index and current political information, should I invest in a stock index ETF? Why?</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="samples-code"><span>Samples Code</span></h3>
<div id="curl"><ul data-component-part="tabs-list"><li id="curl"></li><li id="official-python-sdk"></li><li id="official-java-sdk"></li><li id="openai-python-sdk"></li></ul><div data-component-part="tab-content"><p><span data-as="p"><strong>Basic Call</strong></span></p><div data-component-part="code-block-root" numberoflines="25" language="shellscript"><pre language="shellscript"><code language="shellscript" numberoflines="25"><span><span>curl</span><span> -X</span><span> POST</span><span> "https://api.z.ai/api/paas/v4/chat/completions"</span><span> \</span></span>
<span><span>  -H</span><span> "Content-Type: application/json"</span><span> \</span></span>
<span><span>  -H</span><span> "Authorization: Bearer your-api-key"</span><span> \</span></span>
<span><span>  -d</span><span> '{</span></span>
<span><span>    "model": "glm-4.5",</span></span>
<span><span>    "messages": [</span></span>
<span><span>      {</span></span>
<span><span>        "role": "user",</span></span>
<span><span>        "content": "As a marketing expert, please create an attractive slogan for my product."</span></span>
<span><span>      },</span></span>
<span><span>      {</span></span>
<span><span>        "role": "assistant",</span></span>
<span><span>        "content": "Sure, to craft a compelling slogan, please tell me more about your product."</span></span>
<span><span>      },</span></span>
<span><span>      {</span></span>
<span><span>        "role": "user",</span></span>
<span><span>        "content": "Z.AI Open Platform"</span></span>
<span><span>      }</span></span>
<span><span>    ],</span></span>
<span><span>    "thinking": {</span></span>
<span><span>      "type": "enabled"</span></span>
<span><span>    },</span></span>
<span><span>    "max_tokens": 4096,</span></span>
<span><span>    "temperature": 0.6</span></span>
<span><span>  }'</span></span>
</code></pre></div><p><span data-as="p"><strong>Streaming Call</strong></span></p><div data-component-part="code-block-root" numberoflines="26" language="shellscript"><pre language="shellscript"><code language="shellscript" numberoflines="26"><span><span>curl</span><span> -X</span><span> POST</span><span> "https://api.z.ai/api/paas/v4/chat/completions"</span><span> \</span></span>
<span><span>  -H</span><span> "Content-Type: application/json"</span><span> \</span></span>
<span><span>  -H</span><span> "Authorization: Bearer your-api-key"</span><span> \</span></span>
<span><span>  -d</span><span> '{</span></span>
<span><span>    "model": "glm-4.5",</span></span>
<span><span>    "messages": [</span></span>
<span><span>      {</span></span>
<span><span>        "role": "user",</span></span>
<span><span>        "content": "As a marketing expert, please create an attractive slogan for my product."</span></span>
<span><span>      },</span></span>
<span><span>      {</span></span>
<span><span>        "role": "assistant",</span></span>
<span><span>        "content": "Sure, to craft a compelling slogan, please tell me more about your product."</span></span>
<span><span>      },</span></span>
<span><span>      {</span></span>
<span><span>        "role": "user",</span></span>
<span><span>        "content": "Z.AI Open Platform"</span></span>
<span><span>      }</span></span>
<span><span>    ],</span></span>
<span><span>    "thinking": {</span></span>
<span><span>      "type": "enabled"</span></span>
<span><span>    },</span></span>
<span><span>    "stream": true,</span></span>
<span><span>    "max_tokens": 4096,</span></span>
<span><span>    "temperature": 0.6</span></span>
<span><span>  }'</span></span>
</code></pre></div></div></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tesla changes meaning of 'Full Self-Driving', gives up on promise of autonomy (420 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://electrek.co/2025/09/05/tesla-changes-meaning-full-self-driving-give-up-promise-autonomy/</link>
            <guid>45144900</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 23:23:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://electrek.co/2025/09/05/tesla-changes-meaning-full-self-driving-give-up-promise-autonomy/">https://electrek.co/2025/09/05/tesla-changes-meaning-full-self-driving-give-up-promise-autonomy/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45144900">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
					
<figure>
	<img width="1600" height="875" src="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Tesla-Self-Driving-FSD-Hero.png?w=1600" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Tesla-Self-Driving-FSD-Hero.png?w=320&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 320w, https://i0.wp.com/electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Tesla-Self-Driving-FSD-Hero.png?w=640&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 640w, https://i0.wp.com/electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Tesla-Self-Driving-FSD-Hero.png?w=1024&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Tesla-Self-Driving-FSD-Hero.png?w=1500&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 1500w" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high"></figure>

<p>Tesla has changed the meaning of “Full Self-Driving”, also known as “FSD”, to give up on its original promise of delivering unsupervised autonomy.</p>



<p>Since 2016, Tesla has claimed that all its vehicles in production would be capable of achieving unsupervised self-driving capability.</p>



<p>CEO Elon Musk has claimed that it would happen by the end of every year since 2018.</p>



<p>Tesla has even sold a software package, known as “Full Self-Driving Capability” (FSD), for up to $15,000 to customers, promising that the advanced driver-assist system would become fully autonomous through over-the-air software updates.</p>	
	



<p>Almost a decade later, the promise has yet to be fulfilled, and Tesla has already confirmed that all vehicles produced between 2016 and 2023 don’t have the proper hardware to deliver unsupervised self-driving as promised.</p>



<p>Musk has been discussing the upgrade of the computers in these vehicles to appease owners, but there’s no concrete plan to implement it.</p>



<p>While there’s no doubt that Tesla has promised unsupervised self-driving capabilities to FSD buyers between 2016 and 2023, the automaker has since updated its language and now only sells “Full Self-Driving (Supervised)” to customers:</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" width="630" height="694" src="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-05-at-2.07.54-PM.png" alt="" srcset="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-05-at-2.07.54-PM.png 630w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-05-at-2.07.54-PM.png?resize=136,150 136w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-05-at-2.07.54-PM.png?resize=272,300 272w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-05-at-2.07.54-PM.png?resize=318,350 318w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-05-at-2.07.54-PM.png?resize=140,154 140w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-05-at-2.07.54-PM.png?resize=150,165 150w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px"></figure>



<p>The fine print mentions that it doesn’t make the vehicle “autonomous” and doesn’t promise it as a feature. </p>



<p>In other words, people buying FSD today are not really buying the capability of unsupervised self-driving as prior buyers did.</p>



<p>Furthermore, Tesla’s board has just submitted <a href="https://electrek.co/2025/09/05/tesla-tsla-board-fully-loses-its-mind-and-offers-elon-musk-a-pay-package-worth-up-to-1-trillion/">a new</a><span><a href="https://electrek.co/2025/09/05/tesla-tsla-board-fully-loses-its-mind-and-offers-elon-musk-a-pay-package-worth-up-to-1-trillion/" target="_blank">, unprecedented CEO compensation package for shareholders’ approval, which could give Musk up to $1 trillion</a>&nbsp;in stock options pending</span> the achievement of certain milestones.</p>



<p>One of these milestones is Tesla having “10 Million Active FSD Subscriptions.”</p>



<p>At first glance, this would be hopeful for FSD buyers since part of Musk’s compensation would be dependent on delivering on the FSD promises.</p>



<p>However, Tesla has changed the definition of FSD in the compensation package with an extremely vague one”</p>



<blockquote>
<p>“FSD” means an advanced driving system, regardless of the marketing name used, that is capable of performing transportation tasks that provide autonomous or similar functionality under specified driving conditions.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Tesla now considers FSD only an “advanced driving system” that should be “capable of performing transportation tasks that prove autonomous or similar functionality”.</p>



<p>The current version of FSD, which requires constant supervising by the driver, could easily fit that description.</p>



<p>Therefore, FSD now doesn’t come with the inital promise of Tesla owners being able to go to sleep in their vehicles and wake up at their destination – a promise that Musk has used to sell Tesla vehicles for years.</p>



<h2 id="h-electrek-s-take">Electrek’s Take</h2>



<p>The way Tesla discusses autonomy with customers and investors versus how it presents it in its court filings and legally binding documents is strikingly different.</p>



<p>It should be worrying to anyone with an interest in this.</p>



<p>With this very vague description in the new CEO compensation package, Tesla could literally lower the price of FSD and even remove base Autopilot to push customers toward FSD and give Musk hundreds of billions of dollars in shares in the process.</p>




	<p>There’s precedent for Tesla decreasing pricing on FSD. Initially, Musk said that Tesla would gradually increase the price of the FSD package as the features improved and approached unsupervised autonomy.</p>



<p>That was true for a while, but then Tesla started slashing FSD prices, which are now down $7,000 from their high in 2023:</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" height="577" width="1024" src="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-05-at-2.33.55-PM.png?w=1024" alt="" srcset="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-05-at-2.33.55-PM.png 1818w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-05-at-2.33.55-PM.png?resize=150,84 150w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-05-at-2.33.55-PM.png?resize=300,169 300w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-05-at-2.33.55-PM.png?resize=768,433 768w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-05-at-2.33.55-PM.png?resize=1024,577 1024w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-05-at-2.33.55-PM.png?resize=1536,865 1536w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-05-at-2.33.55-PM.png?resize=350,197 350w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-05-at-2.33.55-PM.png?resize=140,79 140w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-05-at-2.33.55-PM.png?resize=1600,901 1600w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>The trend is quite apparent and coincidentally began when Tesla’s sales started to decline.</p>



<p>FSD is now a simple ADAS system without any promise of unsupervised self-driving. This might quite honestly be one of the biggest cases of false advertising or bait-and-switch ever.</p>
	<p>
				<a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://news.google.com/publications/CAAqBwgKMKqD-Qow6c_gAg?hl=en-US&amp;gl=US&amp;ceid=US:en">
			<em>Add Electrek to your Google News feed.</em>&nbsp;
					</a>
			</p>
	<p><em>FTC: We use income earning auto affiliate links.</em> <a href="https://electrek.co/about/#affiliate">More.</a></p>				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>