<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 11:30:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Roblox is the biggest game in the world, but is unprofitable (227 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.matthewball.co/all/roblox2024</link>
            <guid>41287099</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 01:45:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.matthewball.co/all/roblox2024">https://www.matthewball.co/all/roblox2024</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41287099">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="page" role="main">
        
          
<article id="sections" data-page-sections="5d8e94500fa50d2aaaa7c406">
  
  
    
    


  


<div data-content-field="main-content" data-item-id="" data-test="page-section" data-section-theme="" data-section-id="5d8e94500fa50d2aaaa7c408" data-controller="SectionWrapperController" data-current-styles="{
&quot;imageOverlayOpacity&quot;: 0.15,
&quot;backgroundWidth&quot;: &quot;background-width--full-bleed&quot;,
&quot;sectionHeight&quot;: &quot;section-height--medium&quot;,
&quot;customSectionHeight&quot;: 10,
&quot;horizontalAlignment&quot;: &quot;horizontal-alignment--center&quot;,
&quot;verticalAlignment&quot;: &quot;vertical-alignment--middle&quot;,
&quot;contentWidth&quot;: &quot;content-width--wide&quot;,
&quot;customContentWidth&quot;: 50,
&quot;sectionTheme&quot;: &quot;&quot;,
&quot;sectionAnimation&quot;: &quot;none&quot;,
&quot;backgroundMode&quot;: &quot;image&quot;
}" data-current-context="{
&quot;video&quot;: {
&quot;playbackSpeed&quot;: 0.5,
&quot;filter&quot;: 1,
&quot;filterStrength&quot;: 0,
&quot;zoom&quot;: 0,
&quot;videoSourceProvider&quot;: &quot;none&quot;
},
&quot;backgroundImageId&quot;: null,
&quot;backgroundMediaEffect&quot;: null,
&quot;divider&quot;: null,
&quot;typeName&quot;: &quot;blog-basic-grid&quot;
}" data-animation="none">
  <article id="article-">
  
    
    
    
    <div data-layout-label="Post Body" data-type="item" id="item-66c0f500ff2a1801ff10faf9"><div data-test="image-block-inline-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1723984145602_27340">

      

      
        <figure>
          
        
        

        
          
            
          <div data-animation-role="image">
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/77d86f55-4f38-4af0-8f3e-87b3598bf2c4/Screenshot+2024-08-18+091153.png" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/77d86f55-4f38-4af0-8f3e-87b3598bf2c4/Screenshot+2024-08-18+091153.png" data-image-dimensions="3255x1862" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/77d86f55-4f38-4af0-8f3e-87b3598bf2c4/Screenshot+2024-08-18+091153.png" width="3255" height="1862" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/77d86f55-4f38-4af0-8f3e-87b3598bf2c4/Screenshot+2024-08-18+091153.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/77d86f55-4f38-4af0-8f3e-87b3598bf2c4/Screenshot+2024-08-18+091153.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/77d86f55-4f38-4af0-8f3e-87b3598bf2c4/Screenshot+2024-08-18+091153.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/77d86f55-4f38-4af0-8f3e-87b3598bf2c4/Screenshot+2024-08-18+091153.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/77d86f55-4f38-4af0-8f3e-87b3598bf2c4/Screenshot+2024-08-18+091153.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/77d86f55-4f38-4af0-8f3e-87b3598bf2c4/Screenshot+2024-08-18+091153.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/77d86f55-4f38-4af0-8f3e-87b3598bf2c4/Screenshot+2024-08-18+091153.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            </p>
          </div>
        
          
        

        
      
        </figure>
      

    </div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1723921664409_2256">
  <p>Everyone knows Roblox is huge. But as COVID receded into memory, Roblox shifted from “new” to “familiar,” and gaming experienced its <a href="https://www.matthewball.co/all/gaming2024" target="_blank">largest contraction in nearly a quarter century</a>, the platform continued to grow. And grow. And grow. As a result, there is now a significant disparity between the perceived size of Roblox and its actual, unprecedented scale.</p><p>During the average day, more than 80MM people log onto Roblox. As a historical point of contrast, this means that more people log onto Roblox every 10 or so minutes than used <em>Second Life</em> in a month at its peak. On a monthly basis, Roblox now counts more than 380MM users according to RTrack – 2x as many as PC gaming leader Steam, 3x that of Sony’s PlayStations, 3x the number of unique <em>annual </em>users of the Nintendo Switch in a <em>year</em>, and 5x as many as have bought an Xbox console in the last decade. After accounting for duplication across these platforms, as well as the gap between monthly and annual Switch users, it’s likely Roblox has more monthly users than the entire AAA gaming ecosystem combined. What’s more, NPD/Circana reports that Roblox is <a href="https://x.com/MatPiscatella/status/1823016887443509700/photo/1" target="_blank">typically</a> one of the 3–7 most played games on PlayStation and Xbox (Roblox is not available on Switch or Steam), and SensorTower <a href="https://sensortower.com/state-of-mobile-2024" target="_blank">says that in 2023</a>, Roblox averaged more iOS/Android monthly active users than any other game (including <em>Candy Crush</em>!).</p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1723939387829_17010">
  <p>Compared to its most similar competitors—the social virtual world platforms, <em>Minecraft </em>and <em>Fortnite</em> — Roblox has about 5x and 2.25x as many monthly players. For non-gamers, Roblox has about two thirds as many monthly users as Spotify and half as many as Snap (though it probably has a lower share of daily-to-monthly active users) and is roughly as popular as Instagram circa Q4 2015, and Facebook in Q3 2009. </p><p>Each month, players spend close to six billion hours using Roblox. This time excludes the viewing of Roblox content on Twitch or YouTube, the largest video platform on earth and which counts non-live gaming content as its second most popular genre, with Roblox one of its five most watched games. Most estimates suggest the average Disney+ account watches no more than 20 hours per month, which would mean about 3.1 billion hours in total monthly watch time—barely half of Roblox’s total.</p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1723921664409_28206">

<p>Not only is Roblox enormously popular, but its growth has been shockingly linear (there is some quarter-to-quarter seasonality, which is common to all media products and particularly significant for Roblox given its over-indexing to children and thus the school calendar). Even at its present scale, it’s difficult to argue that growth won’t continue and that the platform should pass a half billion MAUs and 100 million DAUs. This growth is also resilient. And in contrast to other supposed pandemic darlings such as Zoom, Shopify, and Peloton, Roblox never contracted after the pandemic. Instead, it maintained its overall “pull forward” as well as its accelerated rate of growth. </p>




















  
  



</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1724025845767_19518">

<p>The composition of Roblox’s growth has also been healthy. The share of Roblox’s total monthly users who use the platform on the average day has grown from 16%–19% pre-pandemic to 22% today. The hours played per DAU and per MAU has also grown, showing that new users are not less engaged users. The share of players over 13 has grown from 40% to 58% (in total there are now 2.5x as many users over 13 as there were users of any age pre-pandemic). Though U.S. and Canadian players are up 250% since the pandemic, their share of the total user base has fallen from 35% to 22% because APAC and ROW users surged 650% and 750%, respectively, taking their share from ~16% and ~21% to 24% and 27%. The global share of players also maps nearly exactly to the global share of playtime, demonstrating that Roblox, like all major social platforms, is a global phenomenon.</p>




















  
  



</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1723921664409_30295">
  <p>Although Roblox has diversified its playerbase away from high-income markets and toward more developing ones, revenues per MAU and DAU are up compared to pre-pandemic levels (spending has come down a bit since the peak of the pandemic, though spending was inflated due to a surge in new users that spent heavily to fill their otherwise empty virtual closets). More impressively, spend per hour is also up since before the pandemic—even though users currently play more per month than at any point during Roblox’s existence, with the sole exception of the peak of the pandemic. In other words, Roblox continues to scale its appeal, usage, and monetization.</p><p>Annual spending on Roblox is over $3.8 billion and will pass $4 billion by the end of the year, a quarter of which goes to developers. Given these figures, it is no surprise that Roblox users are hyper-productive. In 2022, Roblox’s users designed 170,000 virtual clothing/accessory items and 15,000 virtual worlds each day (current figures are not known, though average daily users have grown 40% and the ease of creation has improved, as has the quality of the output). Over a hundred user-created worlds have been played over a billion times (and one has over 50 billion plays). </p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1723921664409_32397">
  <p>So yes, Roblox is unquestionably “working.” Yet Roblox is also unprofitable. <em>Very</em> unprofitable. What’s more, Roblox’s losses continue to swell because its impressive rate of revenue growth has been outpaced by that of its costs. Over the last four quarters, Roblox’s income from operations was ($1.2B) on revenues of $3.2B, representing a -38% profit margin. During the company’s four pre-pandemic quarters, income was ($66MM) on $508MM, for a -13% profit margin. Put another way, revenues are now 6.2x greater, but losses are 18x greater. This is not the typical path of a company, least of all a tech company that is a <em>platform</em> and at Roblox’s scale. So what gives and what’s the significance of the answer?</p><p><strong>Growth, But Not Profits</strong></p><p>Obviously, Roblox has a cost<em>s</em> problem. Over the last twelve months it has averaged $138 in costs for every $100 in revenue. </p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1723922947689_8732">

<p>Unfortunately, many of these costs are outside of Roblox’s control. To start, an average of 23% of revenues are consumed by various App Store/platform fees (this sum is less than 30% because roughly 20% of sales are direct via browser or PC, where Roblox pays credit card processing fees but not 30% store commissions). Another 26% of revenues are paid out to Roblox’s UGC developers. Though the company could theoretically reduce these payments, doing so would harm both brand and developer investment, both of which drive topline. If anything, Roblox wants to grow revenue share, as it would enable developers to invest even more into the platform (many developers are also understandably annoyed they <em>only</em> get a quarter of the revenue they generate, too). In total, Roblox loses 49% of revenue before it even gets to its own costs (let alone the potential of profits).</p>




















  
  



</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1723922947689_10383">
  <p>Infrastructure and Trust &amp; Safety devours another 28% of revenues on average, down from a peak of 37% but only a point below its six-year average. Unlike App Store fee and developer revenue shares, these costs are not strictly marginal ones. There is a fixed cost per hour for Roblox to operate, and it’s not particularly low, but it does not increase if users increase their spending. As such, this category can see declines on a percentage revenue basis. However, this will not be easy. For example, the clearest way to increase spending is usually to increase playtime, which results in incremental services costs (Roblox has three times the users of PlayStation, but Roblox has only 50% more playtime because its players play half as much per month).</p><p>In order to attract more players—especially older players with money to spend and the discretion to spend it—more playtime per player, and more spend per player and play hour, Roblox is also investing in experiences that, on average, are more expensive to operate, as is the case with Generative AI. Roblox is increasingly focused on using GenAI to provide real-time player communications (e.g., transcription and translation), as well as power asset and world creation, and operate AI agents and NPCs – none of which is cheap to create or operate. The company is also investing deeply in more AI tools and human moderators in order to combat harassment, predation, and more. In August 2024, Turkey banned Roblox outright for the “protection of our children”; a month earlier, <em>Bloomberg</em> published <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/features/2024-roblox-pedophile-problem/">a brutal report</a> on the platform’s “pedophile problem.”</p><p>So after just three of Roblox’s six cost categories, 77% of revenues are eaten. Combined, the next three are about as costly today—though they have comparatively greater room for improvements and are more under Roblox’s control. Both General &amp; Administrative (13%) and Sales &amp; Marketing (5%) costs are down a few points compared to a few years ago and should continue to decline. Yet even if Roblox cuts these categories down by a third each, that’s only six points of the thirty-eight needed just to break even.</p><p>The biggest and most interesting category is R&amp;D. As a platform, R&amp;D is not just the foundation of Roblox’s present-day scale, it’s essential to all future growth - and to that end, the company reinvests much of its current revenues in order to grow future ones (and the company’s history of doing so is precisely why they are so large today). Specifically, improvements in Roblox’s tools and capabilities help attract developers and enable them to produce “better” and “more” experiences, which helps attract more users, retain users as they age up, and encourage more user spend—all of which increases Roblox’s revenue, which in turn funds more R&amp;D and provides more money to developers, who can then invest more in their experiences. As already mentioned, much of Roblox’s R&amp;D investments are in Generative AI. Roblox Founder and CEO David Baszucki <a href="https://www.theverge.com/23775268/roblox-ceo-david-baszucki-gaming-metaverse-robux-virtual-reality">has said</a> he believes generative AI will enable users to type or speak entire worlds into existence by 2028, and earlier this year, the company <a href="https://corp.roblox.com/newsroom/2024/06/robloxs-road-to-4d-generative-ai">began to demo</a> these tools, too, inclusive of detailed object components and attributes (e.g., when a car is created, it is made up of many parts, rather than just being a “car,” and the car not only moves but has the properties of reflection, the ability to inflict and sustain damage, etc.). Roblox has also said they are working to integrate LLMs into their NPCs and to power real-time translation. By dropping the cost, time, and difficulty involved in creating Roblox experiences while also bolstering their levels of immersion and facilitating more/easier social play, Roblox should be able to increase the platform’s popularity, usage, and revenue.</p><p>At the same time, Roblox’s R&amp;D investments are <em>enormous</em>. R&amp;D now takes up 44% of revenues on average, equivalent to $1.5B on a run-rate basis. In comparison, Sony’s PlayStation <a href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/sony-boost-gaming-unit-with-217-bln-rd-war-chest-2024-nikkei-2023-07-12/" target="_blank">anticipates spending</a> $2.2B in 2024, with these investments spanning R&amp;D at its twenty-one largely independent studios, virtual reality devices, accessories (including the cloud-based PlayStation Portal), the PlayStation 6 (and, it is rumored, handheld), its network technologies, and so on. In 2024, Unity Technologies will spend “only” $1.1B on R&amp;D, and even the most fantastical (and doubtless egregious) forecasts for <em>Grand Theft Auto VI,</em> anticipated to drop in October 2025, suggest it will cost a billion to develop in total after close to a decade. It is difficult to imagine R&amp;D will continue to grow with sales—let alone in excess of sales, as has been the case over the last few years. For most large technology companies, R&amp;D stabilizes at 6%–12%. Yet even if R&amp;D dropped to 10% (about as much as Spotify and Uber spend), Roblox would still be unprofitable.</p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1724025845767_22710">
  <p><strong>Profit Light but Cash Heavy?</strong></p><p>Though Roblox isn’t profitable, there are some significant caveats to the situation. Over the last twelve months, operating cash flow—a far more important measure than accounting-defined profits—were $650MM, about 20% of revenue. Roblox has been cash-positive for at least twenty-four quarters. Hard to say that’s not a business that’s “working!”</p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1723922947689_12138">
  <p>Part of the cause for this discrepancy is Roblox’s approach to revenue recognition. When a user buys $30 in Robux, the platform’s virtual currency, Roblox recognizes $30 in bookings. An average of $3 of that $30 is spent on a “consumable” (i.e., a single-user or otherwise perishable good), and so Roblox recognizes that $3 as revenue right away. The remaining $27 is spent on “durable” goods such as an avatar. As an avatar can and often will be used over time, Roblox recognizes this revenue over the average lifetime of a Roblox user. This lifetime is currently 27 months, and so the remaining $27 is allocated as $1 for each of the next $27 months, which means that Month One has a total of $4 recognized ($3+$1) and $26 deferred.</p><p>Roblox’s accounting practices are generally viewed as conservative. To point, Roblox notes that on average, a user uses all of their newly purchased Robux within only three days. Users do not, as Roblox’s revenue recognition policies seem to suggest, take more than two years to spend their Robux account balance on a miscellany of avatars, outfits, and other items. Roblox also does not allow refunds of Robux or virtual goods, and so the company does not hold a liability to the user (the spend is due to the App Store and developers). Most evidence suggests that the usage of virtual goods, like most cosmetics, is front-loaded. As such, a straightline allocation is probably a misfit versus, say, a double or triple declining balance. Furthermore, Roblox is effectively P&amp;L penalized when it increases the lifetime of a customer—which should be a good thing!—because it extends the revenue recognition period. If Roblox users go from an average of 27 months to 30, for example, then the Month One “loss” above increases from $4.50 to $4.60. Indeed, this has happened since the company went public. In Q1 2021, Roblox users averaged 23 months on the platform, and now they last 27.</p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1723922947689_13529">
  <p>Roblox’s accounting methodology does mean that some costs (i.e., App Store fees and developer payments) are also deferred, which partly offsets the consequence of delayed revenue recognition. But all operating costs (i.e., Infrastructure, Trust &amp; Safety) and personnel costs (R&amp;D, S&amp;M, G&amp;A) are incurred right away, and so the net effect of Roblox’s revenue recognition policy is that it shrinks accounting profits as long as total user spend is growing (and the degree of this compression increases as the rate of user spending increases). On average, Roblox’s bookings per quarter (i.e., the money users are spending on Roblox that quarter) exceed the revenues recognized by Roblox by about 23%. This isn’t enough to overcome Roblox’s 138% in costs per dollar, but as a percentage of bookings, costs shrink down to 114%.</p><p>So how does Roblox generate so much cash? Over the last twelve months, Roblox’s total compensation to its employees was $1.8B. However, 53% of this compensation was in the form of stock, a non-cash expense. As such, Roblox is able to “shield” its operating cash flow by a sum equivalent to about 31% of revenues (between 2-4x that of most tech companies).</p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1723922947689_14836">
  <p>It would be misleading to ignore the cost of stock-based compensation – especially since companies tend to shift total compensation toward cash and away from stock as they mature, which would decrease profits at the very time a company is supposed to be steadily earning them. If stock-based compensation is normalized to around 10%, then another 21% of revenue would be consumed by cash expenses. This would increase Roblox’s costs from 114% of bookings to 135%—just short of the 138% provided by Roblox’s GAAP methodology.</p><p><strong>How Does Roblox Get Profitable? </strong></p><p>A detailed picture of Roblox’s P&amp;L paints both a better picture (Roblox is generating lots of operating cash flow, R&amp;D should eventually fall by a quarter of revenue or more) and a worse one (30% of costs are paid in stock, at least half of revenue must be paid out). So how does Roblox become a “great” business? </p><p>First, one additional profit caveat is necessary. For users in the United States and Canada, Roblox’s Average Billings per Daily Active User (“ABPDAU,” a Roblox measure) is $37 per quarter, more than four times as high as European ABPDAU, over six times as high as the Asia-Pacific market, and nearly nine times that of all other markets (Rest of Word). This gap is so large that UCAN net ABPDAU (i.e. after 23% App Store fees and 26% developer revenue share) is still a multiple of gross ABPDAU elsewhere.</p><p>On a globally blended basis, ABPDAU is $13, and we know that Roblox loses roughly 35% on that spend, meaning costs are about $18. In UCAN, Roblox more than doubles that cost basis.</p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1723921664409_25710">

<p>The more than 50% net income margins on UCAN users is important because not only is Roblox “working” for developers and consumers, it is working as a business . . . for at least 25% of players. Sure, that’s a bit cheap: “Roblox does make money, just not all the time and not enough for the times they don’t!” But Roblox is also unique as a social platform.</p>




















  
  



</div><div data-test="image-block-inline-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1723922947689_16109">

      

      
        <figure>
          
        
        

        
          
            
          <div data-animation-role="image">
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/5b66bd3b-6ac0-4a28-bf51-295f1e814d12/Roblox+2024_Page_12.png" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/5b66bd3b-6ac0-4a28-bf51-295f1e814d12/Roblox+2024_Page_12.png" data-image-dimensions="8000x4500" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/5b66bd3b-6ac0-4a28-bf51-295f1e814d12/Roblox+2024_Page_12.png" width="8000" height="4500" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/5b66bd3b-6ac0-4a28-bf51-295f1e814d12/Roblox+2024_Page_12.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/5b66bd3b-6ac0-4a28-bf51-295f1e814d12/Roblox+2024_Page_12.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/5b66bd3b-6ac0-4a28-bf51-295f1e814d12/Roblox+2024_Page_12.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/5b66bd3b-6ac0-4a28-bf51-295f1e814d12/Roblox+2024_Page_12.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/5b66bd3b-6ac0-4a28-bf51-295f1e814d12/Roblox+2024_Page_12.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/5b66bd3b-6ac0-4a28-bf51-295f1e814d12/Roblox+2024_Page_12.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/5b66bd3b-6ac0-4a28-bf51-295f1e814d12/Roblox+2024_Page_12.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            </p>
          </div>
        
          
        

        
      
        </figure>
      

    </div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1723922947689_16426">
  <p>Because of Roblox’s high cost to serve per hour, users in lower-income or lower-propensity-to-spend markets typically reduce profitability, rather than just harm overall margins. For Facebook, Twitter, Snap, etc., low monetizing users are still accretive because however little revenue they generate, the marginal costs incurred are near zero. This issue is exacerbated on the revenue side, too. Unlike other social platforms, Roblox’s revenue is nearly all via user spending rather than advertising. As such, Roblox pays 25% of its revenue to Apple and Google (30% of transactions on those platforms) whereas Facebook, Snap, et al pay effectively 0. Note that Facebook, which has structurally lower costs to service users than Roblox and is far more mature, has an operating margin of roughly 40% — if the company had to pay out 25-30% first, it would never have “tech company” profit margins, let alone profit dollars.</p><p>So to achieve overall profitability, Roblox needs to either increase its average bookings per DAU from $13 to at least $18 or achieve a level of revenue scale such that all fees other than developer payouts (currently $3.38 per $13) are effectively halved. In practice, both pushes will likely be needed; fortunately, there are a few mechanisms for each.</p><p>First is <strong>App Store</strong> <strong>fees</strong>. In various markets around the world, Apple’s iOS platform and Google’s Android are being forced to open up their app distribution and monetization models, at least in part. The specifics vary by market, by platform, and sometimes type of transaction. There’s not yet reliable data to suggest the degree to which Roblox might save on commissions (at a minimum, they will substitute a 30% fee with a 4% credit card processing expense, but additional iOS/Android fees might also apply), and the more complicated purchasing flow may require discounts and/or lead to fewer transactions, which would harm revenue. Accordingly, the net opportunity may be a reduction from 25% to 20% in the medium term, with a longer-term possibility of something closer to 10%.</p><p>Another option is to <strong>increase</strong> <strong>ABPDAU</strong> so that profitable users are more directly profitable and unprofitable users are less directly unprofitable. This would mean more revenue, which reduces the mostly-fixed costs of R&amp;D, G&amp;A, and S&amp;M. In the average month, fewer than 6% of users and 17% of average DAUs purchase Robux. There are many natural reasons to skip buying Robux in a given month—some MAUs are just trying Roblox for the first time, others don’t use the platform enough to routine spenders, a large portion of users are likely too young and thus purchasing depends on parental permissions, there are financial discounts for bulk purchasing (which naturally results in a delay to the next purchase), and so on. But there is clearly upside here. As a point of example, PlayStation, which has 120MM MAUs to Roblox’s 375MM and 50MM DAUs to Roblox’s 80MM, generated over $31 billion in revenue over the last twelve months compared to Roblox’s $3.8 billion in bookings.</p><p>These increases can come from further aging up Roblox’s userbase (older users can typically spend more—mainly because they’re no longer reliant on their parents for money), higher-end experiences (PlayStation is evidence of the premium users will pay for “premium” games), growing cultural cachet (which should enable higher prices for Roblox’s virtual goods), as well as more playtime per user (PlayStation has about twice the hours per user per month).</p><p><strong>Advertising</strong> solves a few goals for Roblox. First, it turns all users into revenue-generating users (no matter how miniscule) while also increasing the revenue for high-spending customers (which helps cover all other costs and/or subsidize the money-losing users). Second, it means that marginal consumption will continuously result in marginal revenues rather than just marginal cost (primarily via Infrastructure and Trust &amp; Safety expenses). Third, neither the Apple App Store nor Google’s Google Play collect a portion of ad revenues. Accordingly, all advertising would necessarily decrease app store fees as a percentage of revenue. For instance, if Roblox currently earns $10 per month from each paying user, they pay $2.40 to app stores, which is 24% of their revenue. However, if they generate an additional $3 from advertising on top of that $10, the $2.40 payment to stores would now represent just 18% of their total revenue. Moreover, as already stated, that additional revenue from non-paying users would go directly to Roblox (i.e. 0% would go to app stores). There are marginal IT&amp;S costs to support advertising on a per-hour basis, as well as R&amp;D to continuously improve Roblox’s ad platform, plus incremental G&amp;A for ad sales, ad ops, and ad service, etc. However, IT&amp;S should be relatively modest (and far cheaper than the other way to increase ABPDAU—more playtime), and the latter cost categories should be mostly fixed costs and thus offer greater operating leverage.</p><p>Advertisers have been investing in Roblox for years through the production of their own branded worlds. As with all of Roblox’s worlds, Roblox doesn’t charge for their creation (though certainly, some brands do pay agencies to construct them). Instead, Roblox is “compensated” through the engagement and purchases that world might inspire (to this end, Roblox might even be <em>paying</em> the advertiser through its developer royalty payments). At the same time, Roblox did have ways to generate <em>advertising</em> revenue from these world-builders, as well as from those whose <em>primary</em> business was the creation and operation of Roblox worlds. Specifically, Roblox would sell banner ads inside its launcher/application (think the Netflix homescreen), as well as sponsored search results. However, these ads were limited to the promotion of virtual worlds or items (e.g., Starbucks could promote Starbucks World or virtual Starbucks aprons, but not real-world Starbucks drinks or coupons, etc.). These restrictions, though “good” for users, had pretty severe constraints on advertising revenue as it meant that advertiser’s who lacked Roblox worlds or integrations couldn’t buy any ads (lots of Facebook ad spend is for local businesses, but your local hair stylist can’t build a Roblox world, nor can a local doctor’s office, etc., and even if they could, they probably shouldn’t). And those companies or organizations that <em>did</em> have a world or various items had the business cases from platform advertising effectively limited constrained to the efficacy of those worlds or various items (yes, in theory Starbucks advertising a sellable apron also aided Starbuck’s overall brand awareness, but that’s a pretty inefficient way to advertise online).</p><p>Since late 2022, Roblox has begun to prioritize new ad units and technologies to support its burgeoning ad business. In 2024, for example, Roblox launched in-world billboards that, unlike other ad units, could advertise whatever (e.g. an upcoming music, real world sneakers, etc.), and could be programmatically bid upon by advertisers and served across any worlds that chose to support billboard ads. This sort of advertising has existed “unofficially” for years (a developer would just build a billboard and either sell the ad slot directly or, more commonly, hook into an outside ad network to have the unit filled). In 2023, however, Roblox began to block developers from pinging a third-party server for ad units. Developers are still permitted to sell custom ads inside their world, but programmatic insertion, dynamic pricing, and/or targeting all require the use of Roblox’s ad network. </p>
</div><div data-test="image-block-inline-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1723922947689_25018">

      

      
        <figure>
          
        
        

        
          
            
          <div data-animation-role="image">
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/2e078f90-6187-4bcb-9443-ac393b0c64da/Screenshot+2024-08-17+195037.png" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/2e078f90-6187-4bcb-9443-ac393b0c64da/Screenshot+2024-08-17+195037.png" data-image-dimensions="2537x1420" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/2e078f90-6187-4bcb-9443-ac393b0c64da/Screenshot+2024-08-17+195037.png" width="2537" height="1420" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/2e078f90-6187-4bcb-9443-ac393b0c64da/Screenshot+2024-08-17+195037.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/2e078f90-6187-4bcb-9443-ac393b0c64da/Screenshot+2024-08-17+195037.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/2e078f90-6187-4bcb-9443-ac393b0c64da/Screenshot+2024-08-17+195037.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/2e078f90-6187-4bcb-9443-ac393b0c64da/Screenshot+2024-08-17+195037.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/2e078f90-6187-4bcb-9443-ac393b0c64da/Screenshot+2024-08-17+195037.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/2e078f90-6187-4bcb-9443-ac393b0c64da/Screenshot+2024-08-17+195037.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/2e078f90-6187-4bcb-9443-ac393b0c64da/Screenshot+2024-08-17+195037.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            </p>
          </div>
        
          
        

        
      
        </figure>
      

    </div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1723922947689_27086">

<p>Another new unit are “Immersive Ads,” which are portals that enable a user to travel directly from one Roblox experience into another. In this case, Pepsi or Nike might (programmatically) purchase a “portal” inside hit sports-themed worlds (e.g. a Golden State Warriors world, a FIFA world, etc.) that make it easier to directly acquire these world’s users compared to just throwing up a digital billboard. This format, too, was originally “hacked” by independent Roblox developers whom would cut their own deals with other world developers, but Roblox has since built it natively into their platforms and requires developers to use their system. Developers can still try to bypass Roblox through custom deals, but only Roblox's platform provides advanced analytics, such as tracking how many users entered the portal, how long they stayed in the destination, and what activities they engaged in, and advertisers can only programmatically purchase immersive ads through Roblox.</p>




















  
  



</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1723922947689_24140">
  <p>The last new ad unit lets advertisers sponsor items that users can claim for free. For example, Nike might do a deal through Roblox whereby any users who visit Developer World A on a given weekend would receive a free virtual pair of Air Jordan Sneakers. Again, this could be achieved through a direct deal between Nike and Developer A, but Roblox’s own platform offers programmatic placement, better analytics, a greater number of partnering worlds, related tools, etc. </p><p>It’s not clear how big Roblox’s advertising business might become. In November 2023, Baszucki <a href="https://stratechery.com/2023/an-interview-with-roblox-ceo-david-baszucki-about-advertising-and-ai/">told Ben Thomspon</a> “Yeah, I don’t think we’ve ever said advertising is going to be the meat of our business” – but he also argued “the size of the potential immersive advertising experience is uncharted right now. It’s immersive, there’s so much time spent there, the memories are really profound when I go with a friend to do that. So I do think it’s uncharted and very big.” Baszucki also mentioned “someday on Roblox, when we go to Nike World, we will not just be trying on virtual Nike shoes. We may be buying the physical versions as well from that place because it’s been such a connection for us with that brand.” Regardless of any physical tie-ins, it’s obvious that with over 350 million young, and otherwise hard-to-reach players, Roblox has the potential to generate meaningful revenue even if <em>most</em> of its business is based on user subscription.</p><p><strong>Master Builder(man)</strong></p><p>Smaller App Store payments, more ARPU, and a bigger ad platform are the <em>linear </em>opportunities for Roblox.</p>
</div><div data-test="image-block-inline-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1723986767310_18534">

      

      
        <figure>
          
        
        

        
          
            
          <div data-animation-role="image">
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/140ecd36-fd0e-458f-8e88-9499ccf0f2e4/Screenshot+2024-08-17+195752.png" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/140ecd36-fd0e-458f-8e88-9499ccf0f2e4/Screenshot+2024-08-17+195752.png" data-image-dimensions="2895x1407" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/140ecd36-fd0e-458f-8e88-9499ccf0f2e4/Screenshot+2024-08-17+195752.png" width="2895" height="1407" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/140ecd36-fd0e-458f-8e88-9499ccf0f2e4/Screenshot+2024-08-17+195752.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/140ecd36-fd0e-458f-8e88-9499ccf0f2e4/Screenshot+2024-08-17+195752.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/140ecd36-fd0e-458f-8e88-9499ccf0f2e4/Screenshot+2024-08-17+195752.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/140ecd36-fd0e-458f-8e88-9499ccf0f2e4/Screenshot+2024-08-17+195752.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/140ecd36-fd0e-458f-8e88-9499ccf0f2e4/Screenshot+2024-08-17+195752.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/140ecd36-fd0e-458f-8e88-9499ccf0f2e4/Screenshot+2024-08-17+195752.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/140ecd36-fd0e-458f-8e88-9499ccf0f2e4/Screenshot+2024-08-17+195752.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            </p>
          </div>
        
          
        

        
          
          <figcaption>
            <p><em>Roblox Founder/CEO&nbsp;Baszucki's 5-year predictions from 2018 (as scored in 2023)</em></p>
          </figcaption>
        
      
        </figure>
      

    </div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1723922947689_35221">

<p>At 380MM monthly users and nearly 6B hours of monthly usage, Roblox is already one of the biggest media properties globally – not just the most played video game. Very few products ever get to Roblox’s size, let alone continue growing. And at this present size, altogether “new” opportunities start to emerge.</p>




















  
  



</div><div data-test="image-block-inline-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1723986767310_21402">

      

      
        <figure>
          
        
        

        
          
            
          <div data-animation-role="image">
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/0041673f-1c84-434e-929a-586469f3bdbc/2023.png" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/0041673f-1c84-434e-929a-586469f3bdbc/2023.png" data-image-dimensions="2552x1835" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/0041673f-1c84-434e-929a-586469f3bdbc/2023.png" width="2552" height="1835" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/0041673f-1c84-434e-929a-586469f3bdbc/2023.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/0041673f-1c84-434e-929a-586469f3bdbc/2023.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/0041673f-1c84-434e-929a-586469f3bdbc/2023.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/0041673f-1c84-434e-929a-586469f3bdbc/2023.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/0041673f-1c84-434e-929a-586469f3bdbc/2023.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/0041673f-1c84-434e-929a-586469f3bdbc/2023.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5d8e9007bc3d0e18a4c49673/0041673f-1c84-434e-929a-586469f3bdbc/2023.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            </p>
          </div>
        
          
        

        
          
          <figcaption>
            <p><em>Roblox Founder/CEO&nbsp;Baszucki's 5-year predictions from 2023</em></p>
          </figcaption>
        
      
        </figure>
      

    </div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1723986767310_21719">
  <p>In 2023, for example, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/09/08/roblox-connect-avatar-calling/" target="_blank">Roblox launched new features</a> that enabled “basic” communications capabilities between connected players that were <em>not</em> actively using a Roblox word, including messaging and voice calling, as well as avatar-to-avatar "video calling” that uses a phone or tablet’s front-facing camera to power real-time motion capture. This functionality puts Roblox in more direct competition with social networks and platforms such as Snap and WhatsApp, which boast 800MM and 2.8B users each, but underindex to younger Gen Zs and especially Gen Alphas. Moreover, such functionality is not just “bigger” than immersive socializing, it’s also cheaper to operate and easier to advertise through. Roblox Founder/CEO David Baszucki seems to believe instant messaging is just one of many 2D use cases that the company will soon be able to conquer. At the Roblox Developer Conference in 2023, he teased a forthcoming dating product for verified users over the age of 17, corporate recruiting integrations, and educational programs, among others.</p><p><strong><em>Matthew Ball (</em></strong><a href="https://twitter.com/ballmatthew"><strong><em>@ballmatthew</em></strong></a><strong><em>)</em></strong></p>
</div></div>
  
</article>

</div>

  
</article>


          

          
            
              

            
          
        
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Eric Schmidt deleted Stanford interview (161 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3f6XM6_7pUE</link>
            <guid>41287014</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 01:27:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3f6XM6_7pUE">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3f6XM6_7pUE</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41287014">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Markov chains are funnier than LLMs (305 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://emnudge.dev/blog/markov-chains-are-funny/</link>
            <guid>41286203</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 22:52:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://emnudge.dev/blog/markov-chains-are-funny/">https://emnudge.dev/blog/markov-chains-are-funny/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41286203">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article data-astro-cid-w6n32adp=""> <details><summary>Table Of Contents</summary><ol><li><a href="#what-is-a-markov-chain">What is a Markov chain</a></li><li><a href="#what-is-funny">What is funny</a></li><li><a href="#the-predictability-of-llms">The predictability of LLMs</a></li><li><a href="#why-this-is-interesting">Why this is interesting</a></li></ol></details><p>Before explaining any of these terms, let’s try to establish this anecdotally.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>12:2 And I will make all my goodness pass before thee, and our sins be upon us, because of our use of not and lisp-value.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In the beginning was the lambda expression, and the lambda expression was with Scheme, and the lambda expression was Scheme.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>One of these is the result of a Markov chain trained on the dataset of the King James Bible and a Computer Science textbook. The other is ChatGPT 3.5 given instructions to form a similar output.</p>
<p>These 2 examples are somewhat cherry-picked, but each was given a fair fight. I tried to choose the best candidate from both sides. Can you tell which one was which?</p>
<p>You have a good chance of guessing correctly. The sentence with funky semantics is the Markov chain. It almost makes sense, but makes a right turn into gibberish before you reach the end of the sentence.</p>
<p>The second sentence is Chat GPT.</p>
<p>My goal in this article is to convince you that humor is measurable and that Markov chains are funny. To do this, I will need to define both Markov chains and humor itself. Let’s start with the easier one.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-a-markov-chain">What is a Markov chain</h2>
<p>When LLMs first came on the scene, people would describe them as a very smart Markov chain. These days, people are more familiar with LLMs than Markov chains, so I’ll describe a Markov chain as a very dumb LLM.</p>
<p>If it wasn’t clear earlier, ChatGPT is a kind of LLM - a Large Language Model. We have LLMs that are very large (greater than 300GB) and ones that are much smaller (less than 10GB), but you wouldn’t call them a “small language model” - they’re just a small LLM.</p>
<p>You could call Markov chains a very very small, very simple, very naive LLM.</p>
<p>Like an LLM, it predicts the next word based off the current context. However, it doesn’t take into account semantics, dimensionality, and a whole bunch of other specialized vector math. It’s a really primitive statistical model.</p>
<p>Have you ever used those “next word suggestions” on the top of your phone’s keyboard? That’s generally built using a Markov chain. It’s cheap to run and can be easily updated with suggestions more common to your own texting style.</p>
<p>I could go into depth talking about how both LLMs and Markov chains work, but I only need you to know this - Markov chains are worse at doing the work that LLMs are used for. If you ask it to generate a sentence with a certain goal in mind, an LLM will often outperform the Markov chain.</p>
<p>But accuracy is not what makes something funny.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-funny">What is funny</h2>
<p>This is a weird obsession of mine. I’ve wrote at length about it several times, so just to summarize - humor is about unserious surprise.</p>
<p>The best jokes involve a pleasant and significant “snap”. I use “snap” instead of “punchline” to avoid the semantic baggage. A snap is the whiplash received from the surprise. The less surprise, the less funny.</p>
<p>This is why jokes you’ve heard many times become less funny. It’s why “random” humor feels humorless - although the exact words are unpredictable, the expectation of unpredictability is predictable. If you truly expect the unexpected, you probably won’t laugh.</p>
<p>You can strengthen the snap by reusing common patterns with predictable endings and violating the user’s expectation. As an example, the word coupling “banana, apple, orange, vehicular manslaughter” sets up a pattern of single-word fruit and violates the expectation with a crime.</p>
<p>Joke writing is mostly about violating a pattern.</p>
<p>The snap is also made stronger via the “realization of scene”. If you use more original or descriptive language, you can make the scene appear more real. Instead of “he was shot”, you might say “he was pierced by a 35mm”. Instead of “he fell”, perhaps “his face met the ground”.</p>
<p>You also might want to try starting from the middle of a scene. Imagining what happened before will also help with realization. For example “a urinal cake? I’m not falling for that one again” implies a scene we have to imagine, increasing its realization.</p>
<p>You’ll notice many parallels between good <em>joke</em> writing and good writing in general. Both sorts of authors have similar goals. Using cliche is just wasting words because you leave your scenes <em>unrealized</em>.</p>
<p>We call humor subjective because what qualifies as “unserious surprise” is not universal. Crass humor might not be funny because it is not unserious; it’s blasphemy! Or, it might not be funny because it’s not a surprise; it’s expected.</p>
<p>Anti-jokes are only funny if the joke structure itself is predictable. Absurdism has to be bought into. You can violate cultural norms, but the violation must be well understood unserious.</p>
<p>As a monolingual American, I still managed to make (successful) jokes in a very non-english environment by using the word “no” in ways that were culturally unexpected. I refused certain gifts in an unserious way.</p>
<p>Jokes are varied and humor is subject. Yet, at the end of the day, it is unserious surprise.</p>
<h2 id="the-predictability-of-llms">The predictability of LLMs</h2>
<p>To predict a sentence successfully, you need a lot of context. Large language models have a lot of context. They do tons of fancy math and find the most probable next token. A “better” LLM will necessarily be more predictable if its corpus is sensible speech.</p>
<p>This makes LLMs a really poor choice for creative writing. Without a ton of “prompt engineering”, it’s actually quite easy to spot if some paragraph was LLM generated. It sounds soulless. It’s the most average thing you could have possibly produced given the context.</p>
<p>Asking an LLM for an “original thought” is almost oxymoronic, if not just moronic. It was built with the express purpose of not doing that.</p>
<p>To generate a joke, an LLM would have to be surprising. It would need to take a common turn of phrase and shift its meaning in an unusual way. Good LLMs don’t do this.</p>
<p>I’ve heard people claim that comedy cannot be generated by an algorithm. If it wasn’t obvious, I disagree with this. I think comedy can be analyzed and measured. I think, given a large enough grant, we could probably generate comedy on demand. I think it’s doable - not that we should do it.</p>
<p>The LLMs we have today are just the wrong tool for this task.</p>
<p>LLMs were funniest at their earliest stages. Image generation was funniest here as well. Remember those “trail cam” images we got from <em>Dall-e mini</em>? As our systems got better, the humor was lost.</p>
<p>A really good predictability machine is not very helpful in artistic expression. There is still much use, sure, but it’s not the perfect tool for the job. An LLM will often miss interesting concepts that a child can readily offer.</p>
<p>I’m open to the idea that, given this framework, we can probably build a kind of language model which takes this task into account. It would just need to be categorically different than the kinds of LLMs we have today. It would be different enough that we probably wouldn’t call it an LLM.</p>
<h2 id="why-this-is-interesting">Why this is interesting</h2>
<p>This is a weird thing to get passionate about. It’s manifestly true, but I think it speaks to something deeper.</p>
<p>Again, I am not making the spiritual man versus machine argument. It’s simply a flaw you’ll see come up time and time again when interacting with these models, no matter how advanced they seem to be getting. It’s a leaky abstraction, baring its inner architecture when it meant to masquerade as an anthropomorphism.</p>
<p>This is why every message from ChatGPT reads like a high school essay. It has taken the most average kind of output and reproduced it. It has been stripped of personality and toughened with scholastic rigor. It is bland, corporate speak.</p>
<p>It’s easy to spot fake Amazon reviews these days by thinking “would I ever write something like this?“. Would you add an intro and conclusion to your experiences with Oxiclean dish wipes? Would you thank the manufacturers and acknowledge their dedication to customer service?</p>
<p>Our LLM detection models, like an on-screen captcha, must soon start screening for personality.</p> </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google took three months to remove scam app that stole over $5M (333 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theblock.co/post/311707/google-took-three-months-to-remove-scam-app-that-stole-over-5-million-in-crypto-lawsuit</link>
            <guid>41286045</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 22:25:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theblock.co/post/311707/google-took-three-months-to-remove-scam-app-that-stole-over-5-million-in-crypto-lawsuit">https://www.theblock.co/post/311707/google-took-three-months-to-remove-scam-app-that-stole-over-5-million-in-crypto-lawsuit</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41286045">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.theblock.co/post/311707/google-took-three-months-to-remove-scam-app-that-stole-over-5-million-in-crypto-lawsuit: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mike Magee, founder of the Register, has died (272 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fudzilla.com/news/59503-mike-mageek-is-dead</link>
            <guid>41285851</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 21:56:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fudzilla.com/news/59503-mike-mageek-is-dead">https://fudzilla.com/news/59503-mike-mageek-is-dead</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41285851">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
	  	<p><br><strong>Industry gadfly and mate died yesterday</strong></p>
<p>One of the legends of the IT industry, tantric guru, and the inventor of the cynical red-top tech tabloid, Mike Magee, has died at the age of 74.</p>
	  </div><div>
	  	
<p>Magee started his career as a printer before working for VNU Business Publications on PC Dealer and then at their IT news venture, VNU Newswire. This was where I met him; his effective method proved a handful for his editors.</p>
<p>His technique was simple: He would disappear for most of the day and somehow write the lead story. If needed, he could be found in one of Soho’s nearby waterholes. If you were a good editor you learnt not to interfere.</p>
<p>He left the Newswire and co-founded The Register, the UK's first Internet-based IT tabloid, with John Lettice in 1994. Magee focused on computer chip reporting in the newsletter, and Lettice covered software.</p>
<p>"We realised the chip industry was worth about $200bn a year then, and we were down the pub one day and said, ‘Why don't we do a newsletter because we can and this is a big, big market, and nobody else seems to be doing much about&nbsp;<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090710051814/http:/www.pressgazette.co.uk/story.asp?sectioncode=1&amp;storycode=34330">it</a>," Magee said.</p>
<p>The Rodgister used the slogan "Biting the Hand That Feeds IT" to reflect its iconoclastic attitude, attracting a following among IT professionals and investors.</p>
<p>In December 2000, Magee suffered a heart attack and died on the operating table only to revive and being told that he would have to do the same operation in ten years (he didn’t). When he returned to work, he stated publicly that he disagreed with the editorial direction of The Register.</p>
<p>He left to found The Inquirer, which reflected the original editorial philosophy. Unlike The Register, which received a lot of investment, The Inquirer received little financing but managed to make a profit. Magee was the only full-time employee. The entire magazine was based on freelance submissions, and staff and advertising were outsourced. Many technology journalists who got their start at the INQ owe something to Mike.</p>
<p>In 2006, Magee met with VNU leaders over their alleged use of a web layout similar to that of The Inquirer. Later that year, Magee sold The Inquirer to VNU. He remained as editor of The Inquirer until February 2008, when he left to pursue other publishing ventures, including TechEye and ChannelEye. He joined Fudzilla as Editor-at-Large in July 2016.</p>
<p>In 2009 the Daily Telegraph placed Magee 35 in its list of Top 50 most influential Britons in technology.</p>
<p>Mike was a poster child for ignoring the doctor’s advice. Despite some severe illness in later life, he continued his life as always.</p>
<p>While most people know about his fame as a tech industry gadfly, fewer are aware of his interest in the esoteric and the occult. This began with his work with Alistair Crowley’s secretary, Kenneth Grant.</p>
<p>In 1971, he started an occult fanzine called Azoth, and in 1973, in conjunction with David Hall and his then girlfriend Janet Bailey, he started a more ambitious six-monthly magazine called SOTHiS.</p>
<p>This brought him into contact with Led Zeppelin guitarist Jimmy Page. Despite his fame, his accountant did not allow Page to have much money, so he approached Magee for a loan to buy an esoteric bookstore. The loan was never repaid. &nbsp;</p>
<p>In 1973, while on holiday, he had a lucid dream about the Indian goddess Kali, which left him keen to learn more about Indian traditions. After various mystical experiences, he became interested in the tantric tradition.</p>
<p>In 1977, he went to India and met with an English tantrik guru called HH Shri Gurudev Mahendranath (1911-1992) who was a guru (some say the last guru) of the Uttarakaula Tantric Order of northern India. Mahendranath gave him the title of a guru and a charter to form a group of students.</p>
<p>Later, this was to become a nucleus for the "Arcane Magical Order of the Knights of Shambhala" (AMOOKOS). This group was highly influential, particularly in bringing Tantrik teachings to the&nbsp;West.&nbsp;In the UK, it had about 500 members.</p>
<p>In 1980, Mahendranath claimed, despite some evidence, that he had never given Magee the right to form AMOOKOS and the group fragmented. Magee went on to do his own thing, concentrating more on&nbsp;<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090710051814/http:/www.shivashakti.com/PersonalStatement.htm">Tantra.</a>&nbsp;He has also provided translations for Tantra website&nbsp;<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090710051814/http:/www.religiousworlds.com/mandalam/index.html%20">Shiva Shakti Mandalam</a>.</p>
<p>He formed his own publishing company producing translations of Indian tantric texts.</p>
<p>He married Jan Bailey in a civil ceremony at Edgware Registry Office in 1978. Two witnesses were present, one of whom was pulled in from the Street. They had a son, Tamlin, who was an occasion Techeye writer.</p>
<p>Writing a mate’s obit is an arse. Whatever you want to write about, cannot do justice to a bloke who lived life to the full and made a difference to many. &nbsp;You want to write something like “I am sure he is in the heavenly Star and Garter with Dave Evans and others he worked with.” &nbsp;But that would dumb down someone who was incredibly complex and multifaceted. How can you be sad that someone who literally walked through Indian cemeteries to find a death goddess finally found what he was searching for?</p>
<p>Still it is an arse for the rest of the planet.</p>	  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Parents outraged at Snoo after smart bassinet company charges fee to rock crib (105 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/snoo-bassinet-baby-sleeping-subscription-b2597869.html</link>
            <guid>41285484</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 21:02:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/snoo-bassinet-baby-sleeping-subscription-b2597869.html">https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/snoo-bassinet-baby-sleeping-subscription-b2597869.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41285484">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main"><div data-newsletter-key="receiveEveningHeadlinesUSNews"><p><img src="https://static.independent.co.uk/static-assets/images/newsletter/evening-headlines/evening-headlines.png" loading="lazy" alt="Evening Headlines"></p><div><p><h3 data-nosnippet="">The latest headlines from our reporters across the US sent straight to your inbox each weekday</h3><h3 data-nosnippet="">Your briefing on the latest headlines from across the US</h3></p></div></div><p>Some <a href="https://www.independent.co.uk/topic/parents">parents</a> are complaining that a <a href="https://www.independent.co.uk/extras/indybest/kids/baby-tech-essentials/snoo-smart-sleeper-baby-cot-bassinet-review-pod-test-uk-a9470376.html">high-tech bassinet</a> company is nickel and dime-ing them through a monthly subscription program. </p><p>The new parents are upset because some of the <a href="https://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/health-and-families/robotic-cot-baby-sleep-parents-debate-viral-video-snoo-a8323836.html">basic functions</a> of the <a href="https://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/mila-kunis-ashton-kutcher-robotic-crib-snoo-smart-sleeper-lazy-a8230411.html">$1,700 Snoo</a> bassinets are locked behind subscription paywalls, the <a rel="nofollow" data-affiliate="true" target="_blank" href="https://clicks.trx-hub.com/xid/esimedia_t58ukgmjkf95_theindependent?q=http%3A%2F%2Fgo.redirectingat.com%2F%3Fid%3D44681X1458326%26url%3Dhttps%253A%252F%252Fwww.nytimes.com%252F2024%252F08%252F16%252Fstyle%252Fsnoo-bassinet-smart-sleeper.html%26sref%3Dhttps%3A%2F%2Fwww.independent.co.uk%2Fnews%2Fworld%2Famericas%2Fsnoo-bassinet-baby-sleeping-subscription-b2597869.html&amp;p=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.independent.co.uk%2Fnews%2Fworld%2Famericas%2Fsnoo-bassinet-baby-sleeping-subscription-b2597869.html&amp;article_id=2597869&amp;author=Graig+Graziosi&amp;tag=New+York+Times%2Cparents&amp;section=World&amp;category=Americas&amp;sub_category=&amp;updated_time=2024-08-17T18%3A09%3A06.000Z&amp;utm_campaign=news-body&amp;utm_term=B-3&amp;utm_content=&amp;utm_medium=&amp;ref=&amp;utm_source=direct&amp;fbclid=&amp;gclid="></a><a href="https://www.independent.co.uk/topic/new-york-times"><em>New York Times</em></a> reports.</p><p>One might ask: "what — beyond being being soft and portable — other functions could a bassinet have?" </p><p>The Snoo, made by the "Happiest Baby" company, is equipped with sensors that detect when the baby is crying and simulates the sounds of the womb to help keep babies — and their parents — sleeping with fewer interruptions. The bassinet also includes a self-rocking and sleep tracking feature, among others. </p><p>Those features all used to be free with the substantial $1,700 purchase, but now some of them are locked behind a $20 per month paywall. If parents use the bassinet for five months, that's an extra $100 fee on top of the hefty purchase price. </p><div><figure><p><img src="https://static.independent.co.uk/2024/08/17/18/newFile-1.jpg" srcset="https://static.independent.co.uk/2024/08/17/18/newFile-1.jpg?quality=75&amp;width=320&amp;auto=webp 320w, https://static.independent.co.uk/2024/08/17/18/newFile-1.jpg?quality=75&amp;width=640&amp;auto=webp 640w" loading="lazy" alt="A child sleeping in a Snoo bassinet. The Snoo bassinet is equipped with sensors to track a baby’s sleep, a self-rocking feature, and requires the infant to be strapped in to help prevent SIDS. Happiest Baby, which makes the Snoo, recently changed its pricing structure, locking some of its basic features behind a $20 per month subscription" on="tap:auto-image-gallery,inline-image-carousel.goToSlide(index=0)" tabindex="0" role="button" data-gallery-length="3"></p><figcaption>A child sleeping in a Snoo bassinet. The Snoo bassinet is equipped with sensors to track a baby’s sleep, a self-rocking feature, and requires the infant to be strapped in to help prevent SIDS. Happiest Baby, which makes the Snoo, recently changed its pricing structure, locking some of its basic features behind a $20 per month subscription<span> <!-- -->(<!-- -->Snoo/Happiest Baby<!-- -->)</span></figcaption></figure></div><p>Since babies grow quickly, a bassinet is only useful to parents for approximately four to five months. At that point, many parents either hand down their newborn gear to friends or relatives with newborns, or post them for sale on online hand-me-down markets. </p><p>With the new pricing scheme in place, the Snoo will be able to continue collecting cash from parents even after its been handed down several times. </p><p>Parents angry with the change has prompted some backlash, with calls for review bombs and instructions for how to complain to the company being shared on social media. </p><p>Happy Baby customers received an email in June alerting them to the change in pricing. Buyers who picked up a Snoo before July 15 were grandfathered into the previous structure, while anyone who bought after that was locked into the subscription model. </p><p>Andrew Gwin, a father who bought the Snoo, told the <em>Times</em> he likened the new pay structure to having to shell out extra to use an iPhone's camera or a car's radio. </p><p>He said he had a great experience using the Snoo with his first child. The family has a second on the way, but said they won't be paying for the subscription. He has gone so far as to file a complaint with the Federal Trade Commission over the app's price. </p><div><figure><p><img src="https://static.independent.co.uk/2024/08/08/09/db2c7451e790996846edf93c7063cb52Y29udGVudHNlYXJjaGFwaSwxNzIzMTg5OTQ2-2.73233002.jpg" srcset="https://static.independent.co.uk/2024/08/08/09/db2c7451e790996846edf93c7063cb52Y29udGVudHNlYXJjaGFwaSwxNzIzMTg5OTQ2-2.73233002.jpg?quality=75&amp;width=320&amp;auto=webp 320w, https://static.independent.co.uk/2024/08/08/09/db2c7451e790996846edf93c7063cb52Y29udGVudHNlYXJjaGFwaSwxNzIzMTg5OTQ2-2.73233002.jpg?quality=75&amp;width=640&amp;auto=webp 640w" loading="lazy" alt="A baby who is wide awake and not sleeping in its Snoo" on="tap:auto-image-gallery,inline-image-carousel.goToSlide(index=2)" tabindex="0" role="button" data-gallery-length="3"></p><figcaption>A baby who is wide awake and not sleeping in its Snoo<span> <!-- -->(<!-- -->PA Archive<!-- -->)</span></figcaption></figure></div><p>“It’s clearly a way to punish those who go to the secondhand market and just add a tax on top of the expenses the parents already face,” he told the <em>Times</em>. </p><p>The company's founder, Harvey Karp, said the pricing change was necessary to "bring in revenue," noting that the company was not underwritten by a university or the government, and must survive on its sales alone. </p><p>He said his ultimate goal would be to see the Snoo paid for by the government or by insurance companies, but it's unclear if there has been any substantive movement toward achieving that end. </p><p>Karp is a former pediatrician, and said he developed the Snoo in order to help prevent SIDS — sudden infant death syndrome. Babies placed in the Snoo have to be strapped in, preventing them from rolling around. That nighttime movement can lead to SIDS, according to the<a rel="nofollow" target="_blank" href="https://www.cdc.gov/sids/data.htm"> US Centers for Disease Control</a>. </p><p>Approximately 3,400 babies die from SIDS every year, the CDC reports. </p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[NASA acknowledges it cannot quantify risk of Starliner propulsion issues (109 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/space/2024/08/nasa-acknowledges-it-cannot-quantify-risk-of-starliner-propulsion-issues/</link>
            <guid>41285046</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 20:09:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/space/2024/08/nasa-acknowledges-it-cannot-quantify-risk-of-starliner-propulsion-issues/">https://arstechnica.com/space/2024/08/nasa-acknowledges-it-cannot-quantify-risk-of-starliner-propulsion-issues/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41285046">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
                                    
<figure>
  <img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/starliner_omacs-800x515.jpg" alt="Artist's illustration of Boeing's Starliner spacecraft firing four of its orbital maneuvering engines, as it will during the deorbit burn at the end of the mission.">
      <figcaption><p><a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/starliner_omacs.jpg" data-height="773" data-width="1200">Enlarge</a> <span>/</span> Artist's illustration of Boeing's Starliner spacecraft firing four of its orbital maneuvering engines, as it will during the deorbit burn at the end of the mission.</p></figcaption>  </figure>

  




<!-- cache hit 197:single/related:cb6717049347381af568dc8b87d1b29f --><!-- empty -->
<p>With no consensus on the safety of the Starliner crew capsule, NASA officials said Wednesday they need another week or two before deciding whether to bring two astronauts back to Earth on Boeing's spacecraft or extend their stay on the International Space Station until next year.</p>
<p>Boeing's Starliner spacecraft, stricken by suspect thrusters and helium leaks, is taking up a valuable parking spot at the space station. It needs to depart the orbiting research complex, with or without its two-person crew, before the launch of SpaceX's next Dragon crew mission to the station, scheduled for September 24.</p>
<p>"We can juggle things and make things work if we need to extend, but it’s getting a lot harder," said Ken Bowersox, associate administrator of NASA's spaceflight operations directorate. "With the consumables we’re using, with the need for the use of the ports for cargo missions, those types of things, we’re reaching a point where that last week in August, we really should be making a call, if not sooner.”</p>
<p>Last week, NASA officials said they expected to make a decision in mid-August—presumably this week—but Bowersox said Wednesday NASA probably won't make the final call on what to do with the Starliner spacecraft until the end of next week, or the beginning of the week of August 26.</p>
<p>“We’ve got time available before we bring Starliner home and we want to use that time wisely," Bowersox said.</p>
<p>NASA astronauts Butch Wilmore and Suni Williams launched inside Boeing's Starliner spacecraft on June 5. Their mission is the first crew test flight on Boeing's capsule before NASA clears Starliner for regular crew rotation flights to the space station. But after software setbacks, parachute concerns, and previous problems with its propulsion system, Boeing's Starliner program is running more than four years behind SpaceX's Dragon crew spacecraft, which flew astronauts to the station for the first time in 2020.</p>                                                                        
                                                                                
<p>And now, there's a significant chance the Starliner crew won't come home in the spacecraft they launched in. Bowersox, a former astronaut, said NASA brought in propulsion experts from other programs to take a fresh look at the thruster issue.</p>
<p>Engineers are still investigating the root cause of why five of Starliner's 28 reaction control system thrusters, supplied by Aerojet Rocketdyne, failed during approach to the space station the day after launch. The thrusters overheated as they pulsed over and over again to fine-tune the ship's rendezvous with the station. Tests of a similar control jet on the ground suggested a Teflon seal in an internal valve could swell at higher temperatures, restricting the flow of propellant to the thruster.</p>
<p>Four of the five thrusters that failed before Starliner docked at the station have recovered and generated near-normal thrust levels during test-firings last month. But many engineers at NASA aren't convinced the thrusters will work normally on Starliner's journey from the space station back to Earth. These control jets are needed to keep the spacecraft pointed in the right direction when four larger rocket engines fire for the deorbit burn to steer the capsule on a trajectory back into the atmosphere for landing.</p>
<p>Rapid pulses of the thrusters, coupled with a long firing of the four larger engines, could raise temperatures inside four doghouse-shaped propulsion pods around the perimeter of Starliner's service module. Once the deorbit burn is complete, Starliner will jettison the service module to burn up in the atmosphere, and its crew module will use a different set of thrusters to guide its reentry. Then, it will deploy parachutes to slow for landing, likely at White Sands, New Mexico.</p>

                                                </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The brain simulates actions and their consequences during REM sleep (147 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2024.08.13.607810v1</link>
            <guid>41284873</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 19:48:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2024.08.13.607810v1">https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2024.08.13.607810v1</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41284873">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div class="page" id="page"><div data-node-nid="4023992" id="node-4023992--2138276754" data-pisa="biorxiv;2024.08.13.607810v1" data-pisa-master="biorxiv;2024.08.13.607810" data-apath="/biorxiv/early/2024/08/16/2024.08.13.607810.atom" data-hw-author-tooltip-instance="highwire_author_tooltip">

      <p><span>
        New Results    </span></p>  
      
  
      <p><span><span>doi:</span> https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.08.13.607810 </span></p>
  
  
  </div>

<div data-panels-ajax-tab-preloaded="biorxiv_tab_art" id="panels-ajax-tab-container-highwire_article_tabs"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" data-highwire-cite-ref-tooltip-instance="highwire_reflinks_tooltip" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div id="abstract-1"><h2>Abstract</h2><p id="p-2">Vivid dreams mostly occur during a phase of sleep called REM. During REM sleep, the brain's internal representation of direction keeps shifting like that of an awake animal moving through its environment. What causes these shifts, given the immobility of the sleeping animal?  Here we show that the superior colliculus of the mouse, a motor command center involved in orienting movements, issues motor commands during REM sleep, e.g. turn left, that are similar to those issued in the awake behaving animal. Strikingly, these motor commands, despite not being executed, shift the internal representation of direction as if the animal had turned. Thus, during REM sleep, the brain simulates actions by issuing motor commands that, while not executed, have consequences as if they had been. This study suggests that the sleeping brain, while disengaged from the external world, uses its internal model of the world to simulate interactions with it.</p></div><h3>Competing Interest Statement</h3><p id="p-3">The authors have declared no competing interest.</p></div>
<div><p>Copyright&nbsp;</p><div><p>The copyright holder for this preprint is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity.<span> All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission.</span></p></div></div>
</div>


</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: PgQueuer – Transform PostgreSQL into a Job Queue (278 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/janbjorge/PgQueuer</link>
            <guid>41284703</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 19:22:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/janbjorge/PgQueuer">https://github.com/janbjorge/PgQueuer</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41284703">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Readme</h3><a id="user-content-readme" aria-label="Permalink: Readme" href="#readme"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🚀 PgQueuer - Building Smoother Workflows One Queue at a Time 🚀</h2><a id="user-content--pgqueuer---building-smoother-workflows-one-queue-at-a-time-" aria-label="Permalink: 🚀 PgQueuer - Building Smoother Workflows One Queue at a Time 🚀" href="#-pgqueuer---building-smoother-workflows-one-queue-at-a-time-"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/janbjorge/PgQueuer/actions/workflows/ci.yml?query=branch%3Amain"><img src="https://github.com/janbjorge/PgQueuer/actions/workflows/ci.yml/badge.svg" alt="CI"></a>
<a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/PgQueuer" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/3ed5f661e8b8f69d87ecdc757dc90611c3cb2e779c24471a9cde62d2e72aa0d8/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f707970692f762f50675175657565722e737667" alt="pypi" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/pypi/v/PgQueuer.svg"></a>
<a href="https://pepy.tech/project/PgQueuer" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/00e23d45c630c4f1265ffd374d12f511e427973e5614801b1f2362e1a492b89e/68747470733a2f2f7374617469632e706570792e746563682f62616467652f50675175657565722f6d6f6e7468" alt="downloads" data-canonical-src="https://static.pepy.tech/badge/PgQueuer/month"></a>
<a href="https://github.com/janbjorge/PgQueuer"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/b02d89cd2cbefb23891326d63a1e72e3a7a643ccdd083eff83d0f4d701f42ae3/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f707970692f707976657273696f6e732f50675175657565722e737667" alt="versions" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/pypi/pyversions/PgQueuer.svg"></a></p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto">📚 <strong>Documentation</strong>: <a href="https://pgqueuer.readthedocs.io/en/latest/" rel="nofollow">Explore the Docs 📖</a></p>
<p dir="auto">🔍 <strong>Source Code</strong>: <a href="https://github.com/janbjorge/PgQueuer/">View on GitHub 💾</a></p>
<p dir="auto">💬 <strong>Join the Discussion</strong>: <a href="https://discord.gg/C7YMBzcRMQ" rel="nofollow">Discord Community</a></p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">PgQueuer</h2><a id="user-content-pgqueuer" aria-label="Permalink: PgQueuer" href="#pgqueuer"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">PgQueuer is a minimalist, high-performance job queue library for Python, leveraging the robustness of PostgreSQL. Designed for simplicity and efficiency, PgQueuer uses PostgreSQL's LISTEN/NOTIFY to manage job queues effortlessly.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Features</h3><a id="user-content-features" aria-label="Permalink: Features" href="#features"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>Simple Integration</strong>: Easy to integrate with existing Python applications using PostgreSQL.</li>
<li><strong>Efficient Concurrency Handling</strong>: Utilizes PostgreSQL's <code>FOR UPDATE SKIP LOCKED</code> for reliable and concurrent job processing.</li>
<li><strong>Real-time Notifications</strong>: Leverages <code>LISTEN</code> and <code>NOTIFY</code> for real-time updates on job status changes.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h3><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To install PgQueuer, simply install with pip the following command:</p>

<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Example Usage</h3><a id="user-content-example-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Example Usage" href="#example-usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Here's how you can use PgQueuer in a typical scenario processing incoming data messages:</p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Write and run a consumer</h4><a id="user-content-write-and-run-a-consumer" aria-label="Permalink: Write and run a consumer" href="#write-and-run-a-consumer"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Start a long-lived consumer that will begin processing jobs as soon as they are enqueued by another process. In this case we want to be a bit more carefull as we want gracefull shutdowns, <code>PgQueuer run</code> will setup signals to
ensure this.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="from __future__ import annotations

import asyncpg
from PgQueuer.db import AsyncpgDriver, dsn
from PgQueuer.models import Job
from PgQueuer.qm import QueueManager


async def main() -> QueueManager:
    connection = await asyncpg.connect(dsn())
    driver = AsyncpgDriver(connection)
    qm = QueueManager(driver)

    # Setup the 'fetch' entrypoint
    @qm.entrypoint(&quot;fetch&quot;)
    async def process_message(job: Job) -> None:
        print(f&quot;Processed message: {job}&quot;)

    return qm"><pre><span>from</span> __future__ <span>import</span> <span>annotations</span>

<span>import</span> <span>asyncpg</span>
<span>from</span> <span>PgQueuer</span>.<span>db</span> <span>import</span> <span>AsyncpgDriver</span>, <span>dsn</span>
<span>from</span> <span>PgQueuer</span>.<span>models</span> <span>import</span> <span>Job</span>
<span>from</span> <span>PgQueuer</span>.<span>qm</span> <span>import</span> <span>QueueManager</span>


<span>async</span> <span>def</span> <span>main</span>() <span>-&gt;</span> <span>QueueManager</span>:
    <span>connection</span> <span>=</span> <span>await</span> <span>asyncpg</span>.<span>connect</span>(<span>dsn</span>())
    <span>driver</span> <span>=</span> <span>AsyncpgDriver</span>(<span>connection</span>)
    <span>qm</span> <span>=</span> <span>QueueManager</span>(<span>driver</span>)

    <span># Setup the 'fetch' entrypoint</span>
    <span>@<span>qm</span>.<span>entrypoint</span>(<span>"fetch"</span>)</span>
    <span>async</span> <span>def</span> <span>process_message</span>(<span>job</span>: <span>Job</span>) <span>-&gt;</span> <span>None</span>:
        <span>print</span>(<span>f"Processed message: <span><span>{</span><span>job</span><span>}</span></span>"</span>)

    <span>return</span> <span>qm</span></pre></div>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="python3 -m PgQueuer run tools.consumer.main"><pre>python3 -m PgQueuer run tools.consumer.main</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Write and run a producer</h4><a id="user-content-write-and-run-a-producer" aria-label="Permalink: Write and run a producer" href="#write-and-run-a-producer"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Start a short-lived producer that will enqueue 10,000 jobs.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="from __future__ import annotations

import asyncio
import sys

import asyncpg
from PgQueuer.db import AsyncpgDriver
from PgQueuer.queries import Queries


async def main(N: int) -> None:
    connection = await asyncpg.connect()
    driver = AsyncpgDriver(connection)
    queries = Queries(driver)
    await queries.enqueue(
        [&quot;fetch&quot;] * N,
        [f&quot;this is from me: {n}&quot;.encode() for n in range(1, N+1)],
        [0] * N,
    )


if __name__ == &quot;__main__&quot;:
    print(sys.argv)
    N = 1_000 if len(sys.argv) == 1 else int(sys.argv[1])
    asyncio.run(main(N))"><pre><span>from</span> __future__ <span>import</span> <span>annotations</span>

<span>import</span> <span>asyncio</span>
<span>import</span> <span>sys</span>

<span>import</span> <span>asyncpg</span>
<span>from</span> <span>PgQueuer</span>.<span>db</span> <span>import</span> <span>AsyncpgDriver</span>
<span>from</span> <span>PgQueuer</span>.<span>queries</span> <span>import</span> <span>Queries</span>


<span>async</span> <span>def</span> <span>main</span>(<span>N</span>: <span>int</span>) <span>-&gt;</span> <span>None</span>:
    <span>connection</span> <span>=</span> <span>await</span> <span>asyncpg</span>.<span>connect</span>()
    <span>driver</span> <span>=</span> <span>AsyncpgDriver</span>(<span>connection</span>)
    <span>queries</span> <span>=</span> <span>Queries</span>(<span>driver</span>)
    <span>await</span> <span>queries</span>.<span>enqueue</span>(
        [<span>"fetch"</span>] <span>*</span> <span>N</span>,
        [<span>f"this is from me: <span><span>{</span><span>n</span><span>}</span></span>"</span>.<span>encode</span>() <span>for</span> <span>n</span> <span>in</span> <span>range</span>(<span>1</span>, <span>N</span><span>+</span><span>1</span>)],
        [<span>0</span>] <span>*</span> <span>N</span>,
    )


<span>if</span> <span>__name__</span> <span>==</span> <span>"__main__"</span>:
    <span>print</span>(<span>sys</span>.<span>argv</span>)
    <span>N</span> <span>=</span> <span>1_000</span> <span>if</span> <span>len</span>(<span>sys</span>.<span>argv</span>) <span>==</span> <span>1</span> <span>else</span> <span>int</span>(<span>sys</span>.<span>argv</span>[<span>1</span>])
    <span>asyncio</span>.<span>run</span>(<span>main</span>(<span>N</span>))</pre></div>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="python3 tools/producer.py 10000"><pre>python3 tools/producer.py 10000</pre></div>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Prompt Caching (156 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://docs.anthropic.com/en/docs/build-with-claude/prompt-caching</link>
            <guid>41284639</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 19:14:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://docs.anthropic.com/en/docs/build-with-claude/prompt-caching">https://docs.anthropic.com/en/docs/build-with-claude/prompt-caching</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41284639">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Prompt Caching is a powerful feature that optimizes your API usage by allowing resuming from specific prefixes in your prompts. This approach significantly reduces processing time and costs for repetitive tasks or prompts with consistent elements.</p>
<p>Here’s an example of how to implement Prompt Caching with the Messages API using a <code>cache_control</code> block:</p>

<p>In this example, the entire text of “Pride and Prejudice” is cached using the <code>cache_control</code> parameter. This enables reuse of this large text across multiple API calls without reprocessing it each time. Changing only the user message allows you to ask various questions about the book while utilizing the cached content, leading to faster responses and improved efficiency.</p>

<hr>
<h2 id="how-prompt-caching-works"><span>How Prompt Caching works</span></h2>
<p>When you send a request with Prompt Caching enabled:</p>
<ol>
<li>The system checks if the prompt prefix is already cached from a recent query.</li>
<li>If found, it uses the cached version, reducing processing time and costs.</li>
<li>Otherwise, it processes the full prompt and caches the prefix for future use.</li>
</ol>
<p>This is especially useful for:</p>
<ul>
<li>Prompts with many examples</li>
<li>Large amounts of context or background information</li>
<li>Repetitive tasks with consistent instructions</li>
<li>Long multi-turn conversations</li>
</ul>
<p>The cache has a 5-minute lifetime, refreshed each time the cached content is used.</p>

<hr>
<h2 id="pricing"><span>Pricing</span></h2>
<p>Prompt Caching introduces a new pricing structure. The table below shows the price per token for each supported model:</p>
<table><thead><tr><th>Model</th><th>Base Input Tokens</th><th>Cache Writes</th><th>Cache Hits</th><th>Output Tokens</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Claude 3.5 Sonnet</td><td>$3 / MTok</td><td>$3.75 / MTok</td><td>$0.30 / MTok</td><td>$15 / MTok</td></tr><tr><td>Claude 3.0 Haiku</td><td>$0.25 / MTok</td><td>$0.30 / MTok</td><td>$0.03 / MTok</td><td>$1.25 / MTok</td></tr><tr><td>Claude 3.0 Opus (coming soon)</td><td>$15 / MTok</td><td>$18.75 / MTok</td><td>$1.50 / MTok</td><td>$75 / MTok</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>Note:</p>
<ul>
<li>Cache write tokens are 25% more expensive than base input tokens</li>
<li>Cache read tokens are 90% cheaper than base input tokens</li>
<li>Regular input and output tokens are priced at standard rates</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 id="how-to-implement-prompt-caching"><span>How to implement Prompt Caching</span></h2>
<h3 id="supported-models"><span>Supported models</span></h3>
<p>Prompt Caching is currently supported on:</p>
<ul>
<li>Claude 3.5 Sonnet</li>
<li>Claude 3.0 Haiku</li>
</ul>
<p>Claude 3.0 Opus support is coming soon.</p>
<h3 id="structuring-your-prompt"><span>Structuring your prompt</span></h3>
<p>Place static content (system instructions, context, tool definitions) at the beginning of your prompt. Mark the end of the reusable content for caching using the <code>cache_control</code> parameter.</p>
<p>Cache prefixes are created in the following order: <code>tools</code>, <code>system</code>, then <code>messages</code>.</p>
<p>Using the <code>cache_control</code> parameter, you can define up to 4 cache breakpoints, allowing you to cache different reusable sections separately.</p>
<p>The minimum cacheable prompt length is:</p>
<ul>
<li>1024 tokens for Claude 3.5 Sonnet and Claude 3 Opus</li>
<li>2048 tokens for Claude 3.0 Haiku</li>
</ul>
<p>Shorter prompts cannot be cached, even if marked with <code>cache_control</code>. Any requests to cache fewer than this number of tokens will be processed without caching. To see if a prompt was cached, see the response usage <a href="https://docs.anthropic.com/en/docs/build-with-claude/prompt-caching#tracking-cache-performance" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">fields</a>.</p>
<h3 id="best-practices-for-effective-caching"><span>Best practices for effective caching</span></h3>
<p>To optimize Prompt Caching performance:</p>
<ul>
<li>Cache stable, reusable content like system instructions, background information, large contexts, or frequent tool definitions.</li>
<li>Place cached content at the prompt’s beginning for best performance.</li>
<li>Use cache breakpoints strategically to separate different cacheable prefix sections.</li>
<li>Regularly analyze cache hit rates and adjust your strategy as needed.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="tracking-cache-performance"><span>Tracking cache performance</span></h3>
<p>Monitor cache performance using these API response fields, within <code>usage</code>:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>cache_creation_input_tokens</code>: Tokens written to the cache when creating a new entry.</li>
<li><code>cache_read_input_tokens</code>: Tokens retrieved from the cache for this request.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="optimizing-for-different-use-cases"><span>Optimizing for different use cases</span></h3>
<p>Tailor your prefix caching strategy to your scenario:</p>
<ul>
<li>Conversational agents: Reduce cost and latency for extended conversations, especially those with long instructions or uploaded documents.</li>
<li>Coding assistants: Improve autocomplete and codebase Q&amp;A by keeping relevant sections or a summarized version of the codebase in the prompt.</li>
<li>Large document processing: Incorporate complete long-form material including images in your prompt without increasing response latency.</li>
<li>Detailed instruction sets: Share extensive lists of instructions, procedures, and examples to fine-tune Claude’s responses.  Developers often include an example or two in the prompt, but with prompt caching you can get even better performance by including 20+ diverse examples of high quality answers.</li>
<li>Agentic tool use: Enhance performance for scenarios involving multiple tool calls and iterative code changes, where each step typically requires a new API call.</li>
<li>Talk to books, papers, documentation, podcast transcripts, and other longform content:  Bring any knowledge base alive by embedding the entire document(s) into the prompt, and letting users ask it questions.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="troubleshooting-common-issues"><span>Troubleshooting common issues</span></h3>
<p>If experiencing unexpected behavior:</p>
<ul>
<li>Ensure cached sections are identical across calls</li>
<li>Check that calls are made within the 5-minute cache lifetime</li>
<li>Verify that <code>tool_choice.type</code> and image usage remain consistent between calls</li>
</ul>
<p>Note that changes to <code>tool_choice.type</code> or the presence/absence of images anywhere in the prompt will invalidate the cache, requiring a new cache entry to be created.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="prompt-caching-examples"><span>Prompt Caching examples</span></h2>
<p>To help you get started with Prompt Caching, we’ve prepared a <a href="https://github.com/anthropics/anthropic-cookbook/blob/main/misc/prompt_caching.ipynb" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">prompt caching cookbook</a> with detailed examples and best practices.</p>
<p>Below, we’ve included several code snippets that showcase various Prompt Caching patterns. These examples demonstrate how to implement caching in different scenarios, helping you understand the practical applications of this feature:</p>

<hr>
<h2 id="faq"><span>FAQ</span></h2>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Apple might be implementing a VPN censorship order in Brazil (108 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://status.proton.me/incidents/0frlp8crn7kx</link>
            <guid>41284549</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 19:04:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://status.proton.me/incidents/0frlp8crn7kx">https://status.proton.me/incidents/0frlp8crn7kx</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41284549">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <p><span>PT <p>Recebemos vários relatos hoje de usuários no Brasil com dificuldades para instalar o aplicativo Proton VPN em dispositivos iOS via a Apple App Store. Podemos confirmar que o problema não está do nosso lado, mas provavelmente na própria App Store, que é controlada pela Apple. O que torna essa coincidência extremamente estranha é que também está impactando vários outros VPNs na loja de aplicativos brasileira.</p><p>Muito provavelmente, algo aconteceu do lado da Apple, e não sabemos se é acidental ou se a Apple está implementando secretamente uma ordem de censura. Mas, devido ao monopólio da Apple na distribuição de aplicativos iOS, não há outra maneira de obter o aplicativo em dispositivos iOS.</p><p>Como solução alternativa para usuários de iOS, sugerimos tentar a versão beta do iOS via Testflight (<a target="_blank" href="https://protonvpn.com/blog/vpn-ios-beta/">https://protonvpn.com/blog/vpn-ios-beta/</a>), ou alternativamente, uma configuração manual do WireGuard pode ser usada (<a target="_blank" href="https://protonvpn.com/support/wireguard-manual-ios">https://protonvpn.com/support/wireguard-manual-ios</a>) para acessar nossos servidores VPN.</p><p>Observe que os aplicativos Proton VPN ainda estão disponíveis em todas as outras plataformas no Brasil (<a target="_blank" href="https://protonvpn.com/download">https://protonvpn.com/download</a>) e outros aplicativos Proton, como Proton Mail, Proton Drive e Proton Pass, permanecem inalterados neste momento.</p><p>EN </p><p>We have received multiple reports today from users in Brazil having difficulties installing the Proton VPN app on iOS devices via the Apple App Store. We can confirm that the issue is not on our side, but likely with the App Store itself, which is controlled by Apple. What makes this an extremely strange coincidence is that it is also impacting multiple other VPNs in the Brazilian app store.</p><p>Most likely, something has happened on the Apple side, and we do not know if it is accidental, or if Apple is secretly implementing a censorship order. But because of Apple's monopoly on iOS app distribution, there is no other way to get the app on iOS devices.</p><p>As a workaround for iOS users, we suggest trying the iOS beta version via Testflight ( <a target="_blank" href="https://protonvpn.com/blog/vpn-ios-beta/">https://protonvpn.com/blog/vpn-ios-beta/</a> ), or alternatively, a manual WireGuard setup can be used ( <a target="_blank" href="https://protonvpn.com/support/wireguard-manual-ios">https://protonvpn.com/support/wireguard-manual-ios</a> ) to access our VPN servers.</p><p>Note that Proton VPN apps are still available through all other platforms in Brazil (<a target="_blank" href="https://protonvpn.com/download">https://protonvpn.com/download</a>) and other Proton Apps such as Proton Mail, Proton Drive and Proton Pass remain unaffected at this time.</p></span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1723988758000"></span>Aug <var data-var="date">18</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">15:45</var> CEST
            </p>
          </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Algorithms we develop software by (214 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://grantslatton.com/software-pathfinding</link>
            <guid>41284409</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 18:47:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://grantslatton.com/software-pathfinding">https://grantslatton.com/software-pathfinding</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41284409">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><header>
        <nav>
            <a href="https://grantslatton.com/">Home</a>
        </nav>
    </header>
    
        
<p>I recently had a conversation with a distinguished tech CEO and engineer. I loved hearing his description of a software development methodology he's occasionally used, and it got me thinking about other heuristics and generalizations.</p>
<h2 id="his-method"><a href="#his-method">His method</a></h2>
<p>Start working on the feature at the beginning of the day. If you don't finish by the end of the day, delete it all and start over the next day. You're allowed to keep unit tests you wrote.</p>
<p>If, after a few days, you can't actually implement the feature, think of what groundwork, infrastructure, or refactoring would need to be done to enable it. Use this method to implement <em>that</em>, then come back to the feature.</p>
<p>He said he didn't invent this, but it was something adjacent to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extreme_programming">Extreme Programming</a> movement of the late 90s and early 00s.</p>
<h2 id="some-thoughts-on-the-method"><a href="#some-thoughts-on-the-method">Some thoughts on the method</a></h2>
<h3 id="write-everything-twice"><a href="#write-everything-twice">"Write everything twice"</a></h3>
<p>A piece of advice I've given junior engineers is to write everything twice. Solve the problem. Stash your code onto a branch. Then write all the code again.</p>
<p>I discovered this method by accident after the laptop containing a few days of work died. Rewriting the solution only took 25% the time as the initial implementation, and the result was <em>much better</em>.</p>
<p>So you get maybe 2x higher quality code for 1.25x the time — this trade is usually a good one to make on projects you'll have to maintain for a long time.</p>
<p>N.B. Obviously, don't write <em>literally everything</em> twice. It's a heuristic. Apply intelligently.</p>
<p>The "start over each day" method is an even more extreme version of this. Every time you rewrite, you carve a smoother path to the solution. The final solution can be really, really clean.</p>
<h3 id="quantity-has-a-quality-all-of-its-own"><a href="#quantity-has-a-quality-all-of-its-own">"Quantity has a quality all of its own"</a></h3>
<p>Almost certainly apocryphal Stalin quote is applicable to becoming a good software engineer. As a junior engineer, there's simply no substitute for getting the first 100K lines of code under your belt. The "start over each day" method will help get you to those 100K lines faster.</p>
<p>You might think covering the same ground multiple times isn't as valuable as getting 100K diverse lines of code. I disagree. Solving the same problem repeatedly is actually really beneficial for <em>retaining</em> knowledge of patterns you figure out.</p>
<p>You only need 5K perfect lines to see all the major patterns once. The other 95K lines are repetition to rewire your neurons.</p>
<h3 id="comparison-to-the-gun-to-the-head-heuristic"><a href="#comparison-to-the-gun-to-the-head-heuristic">Comparison to the "gun to the head" heuristic</a></h3>
<p>Another heuristic I've used is to ask someone to come up with a solution to a problem. Maybe they say it'll take 4 weeks to implement. Then I say "gun to your head, you have to finish in 24 hours, what do you do?"</p>
<p>The purpose here is to break their frame and their anchoring bias. If you've just said something will take a month, doing it in a day must require a radically different solution.</p>
<p>The surprising thing about this technique is <em>how often it works</em>. How often someone — minutes after presenting their month-long plan — can be induced to figure out a plan that could potentially be done in a day.</p>
<p>In practice, none of the day-long plans are actually a day. The gun isn't actually to your head. You can go home and sleep. But the new solution can often actually be done in just a few days. A ten-minute thought experiment becomes a 10x time saving.</p>
<p>The purpose of the thought experiment isn't to generate the <em>real</em> solution. It's meant to put a lower bound on the solution. Then you think of a <em>real</em> solution with that lower bound in eyesight, and you'll find it's often better than your original solution.</p>
<h2 id="pathfinding"><a href="#pathfinding">Pathfinding</a></h2>
<p>The core of the matter here is pathfinding in problem space. Each path is a solution, and it's the engineer's job to find the best one.</p>
<p>There are a lot of kind of sketchy analogies to be drawn between these heuristics and different pathfinding algorithms. There's some relation to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iterative_deepening_A%2A">iterative deepening</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A*_search_algorithm#Bounded_relaxation">bounded relaxation A*</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beam_search">beam search</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simulated_annealing">simulated annealing</a>, and others.</p>
<p>I don't think there's <em>too</em> much to be learned by trying to concretize that analogy, but it's valuable to think about it conceptually. All the different search algorithms have different pros and cons, depending on your constraints and knowledge of the domain.</p>
<p>So to with the engineering heuristics. Becoming a better engineer is becoming a better pathfinder in problem space.</p>
<p>There's probably a compelling general theory to be concocted in this space, but that's beyond the scope of this post. Spin up a background thread in your brain and think about it. Maybe you'll find a good path to an answer.</p>

    
</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Micro-libraries should never be used (140 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://bvisness.me/microlibraries/</link>
            <guid>41284335</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 18:38:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://bvisness.me/microlibraries/">https://bvisness.me/microlibraries/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41284335">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        

        
    <article>
      <header>
        
        
        <p><time datetime="2024-08-18T12:00:00+0000" itemprop="datePublished">August 18, 2024</time>
        </p>
    
      </header>
      
  <p>
    It is the year 2024. It has been eight years since <code>left-pad</code> first made people realize that, hey, maybe it’s not a great idea to outsource trivial functionality to random people on the internet.
  </p>
  <p>
    But in the year 2024, I still see some people arguing that actually, micro-libraries are good, and we should do more of them. We should make packages smaller and use even more dependencies. The problem with npm is really that we just haven’t made the packages small enough yet.
  </p>
  <p>
    This is so unbelievably wrong that it should not even be up for debate. But because there is a debate regardless, someone needs to exhaustively and painfully explain why bad practices are bad.
  </p>
  <p>
    Here is my thesis: <strong>Micro-libraries should never be used. They should either be copy-pasted into your codebase, or not used at all.</strong>
  </p>
  <p>
    However, my actual goal with this article is to break down the way I think about the costs and benefits of dependencies. I won’t be <em>quantifying</em> these costs and benefits, but I hope that by explaining the way I think about dependencies, it will be clear why I think micro-libraries are all downside and no upside.
  </p>

  <h2 id="costs-and-benefits">Costs and benefits</h2>
  <p>
    Everyone knows that programming is all about <a href="https://bvisness.me/tradeoffs/">tradeoffs</a>. You gotta use the right tool for the job, you know?
  </p>
  <p>
    Well, you can’t make a reasonable tradeoff unless you can actually articulate the costs and benefits. So let’s examine the pros and cons of libraries in general, starting with the benefits:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <strong>It saves development time.</strong> This is the most obvious benefit of a library, especially if the problem it solves is complicated.
    </li>
    <li>
      <strong>The code is (hopefully) more robust.</strong> Library authors have presumably thought a lot about the problem, and if their implementation is mature, it might handle more edge cases and subtle pitfalls. Their implementation may also be more “future-proof”, anticipating future use cases. This property is strongest when the library has lots of users—it may not be <em>good</em>, but it is less likely to be <em>wrong</em>.
    </li>
    <li>
      <strong>You can upgrade to get features, bug fixes, or security updates.</strong> This extends the first point: not only do other people write the code for you, but other people <em>maintain</em> it for you. In the best case, an upgrade can simply make your life better without breaking compatibility.
    </li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    That’s about it for benefits. Unfortunately, there are also many costs associated with dependencies—more than most people account for:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <p>
        <strong>The library may be a bad fit for your problem.</strong> This often cancels out the primary benefit of libraries. No, you don’t have to write the code, but you <em>do</em> have to adapt your problem to fit the library, and adapt the library’s results to fit your app again. This cost can be very extreme!
      </p>
      <p>
        For example, at my last job, we tried using Amazon’s Simple Notification Service to send push notifications to both iOS and Android devices. In theory, we could have saved time by targeting just one API instead of two. But after juggling AWS auth and device registration and SQS queues and SNS topics and API incompatibilities, it turned out to be much easier to just target the Apple and Google push APIs directly.
      </p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <strong>The library may be poorly written.</strong> Programmers typically assume that library code is higher-quality than their code. This is often just not true. Any random person can publish an npm package, and many npm packages are just bad. This is even true of very popular packages; the correlation between popularity and quality is extremely weak.
      </p>
      <p>
        Using libraries also often results in performance penalties, even when “well-written”. Libraries are for everyone, therefore they are optimized for no one.
      </p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <strong>Third-party code is inherently risky.</strong> The library may have critical bugs, or the author may be overtly malicious. It is very hard to properly audit everything, and the more complex the library, the more opportunities there are for mistakes or attacks. On the other hand, if you write the code yourself, you know there’s nothing malicious about it, and you have an opportunity to vet it for bugs.
    </li>
    <li>
      <strong>Every dependency is a supply chain attack vector.</strong> Any package, from the biggest framework to the tiniest utility, could be compromised, and would have equal access to sensitive resources. The more packages you have, and the more maintainers there are, the more opportunities there are to get pwned.
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <strong>The library may have a large footprint.</strong> Libraries are often just way bigger than you need. This bloat can come from multiple sources: features you never use, metadata in <code>node_modules</code>, duplicate versions of the same package, and of course piles and piles of transitive dependencies. Furthermore, this footprint is highly variable—a routine update can invisibly quadruple the footprint of a package.
      </p>
      <p>
        This footprint negatively affects all stages of the process: increased install times, increased build times, larger bundle sizes for users. This problem is so prevalent in the JavaScript ecosystem that many common packages have a total footprint in the hundreds of megabytes, a truly shocking amount of waste. The issue has gotten so bad that there is now an initiative called <a href="https://e18e.dev/">e18e</a> that is attempting to clean things up.
      </p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <strong>Updates are not free.</strong> In theory, updating a package should be fine as long as the version is compatible. But in practice, updating causes all kinds of problems: breaking changes, deprecated functions (and associated rewrites), performance regressions, bundle size bloat, new bugs. This cost is unpredictable; you never really know what might have changed upstream.
    </li>
    <li>
      <strong>Libraries may have lots of transitive dependencies.</strong> Transitive dependencies are also dependencies. Everything in your <code>package_lock.json</code> is a real dependency with real costs that you cannot ignore. Transitive dependencies increase the risk of bad code, increase the risk of security issues, and of course increase the footprint of your application.
    </li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    This is how I look at dependencies—and clearly, in my view, there are many more costs than benefits. The benefits can be very strong, but you cannot make a wise decision without considering the costs as well. Beginners in particular tend to ignore the costs—but their libraries will betray them eventually.
  </p>

  <h2 id="is-number-a-case-study"><code>is-number</code>: a case study</h2>
  <p>
    Let’s examine a popular micro-library, <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/is-number"><code>is-number</code></a>. This is an npm package with just a single function, <code>isNumber</code>. It takes a value and tells you if it’s a finite number, or a finite non-empty numeric string. This spectacularly useful function exemplifies all the problems with micro-libraries in the JS ecosystem.
  </p>
  <p>
    Let’s examine the benefits of this package:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      You can write <code>isNumber(foo)</code> instead of <code>typeof foo === "number"</code>.
    </li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    That’s quite a list.
  </p>
  <p>
    But seriously, test it against our possible benefits from earlier:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <strong>Does it save development time? Barely.</strong> Assuming you do, for some reason, need to check if a value is a finite number or a finite non-empty numeric string, this library may save you a few minutes. But in practice this function is almost entirely useless, as we’ll see below.
    </li>
    <li>
      <strong>Is it more robust than what you could write? No.</strong> The code is extremely straightforward and easy to verify.
    </li>
    <li>
      <strong>Would future updates be useful? No.</strong> The library is so simple that any change to the logic would be breaking, and it is already clear that there are no bugs.
    </li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    And now we get to the costs:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <strong>Is it a good fit for your problem? Almost certainly not.</strong> 99% of the time, all you need is <code>typeof foo === "number"</code>. 0.9% of the time, all you need is <code>foo == Number(foo)</code> (which will include numeric strings and exclude <code>NaN</code>). At most 0.1% of the time do you <em>also</em> need to exclude empty strings and <code>Infinity</code>. These are trivial to write and should be familiar to any JavaScript programmer. Therefore, <code>is-number</code> is almost always just bloat, performing unnecessary checks out of paranoia and likely breaking some optimizations that the JS engine could otherwise make.
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <strong>Are updates breaking? Yes.</strong> Incredibly, <code>is-number</code> is already on major version 7.0.0. This is an amazing number of breaking changes for such a simple function.
      </p>
      <p>
        Why all these new versions? Many reasons, none of them good. Sometimes the author arbitrarily changes his mind about what’s a “number”—for example, <code>NaN</code> used to be considered a number; now it’s not. One breaking change simply upgraded the minimum supported Node version from 0.10.0 to 0.12.0 and changed <em>nothing else</em>. And sometimes he just calls it a breaking change because he feels like it.
      </p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <strong>Is it bloated? Kinda.</strong> Although the actual code is a mere 245 bytes, the size when installed is 9.62 kB. That is, the footprint on your computer is 39x larger than necessary, due to metadata like the README, LICENSE, and package.json. Thankfully this shouldn’t affect build times or bundle sizes, but this amazing level of waste adds up across the thousands of packages installed in people’s <code>node_modules</code>. Furthermore, because the author releases so many major versions, it’s common to find multiple copies of the library in your <code>node_modules</code> for no good reason.
    </li>
    <li>
      <strong>Is it risky? Yes.</strong> It’s a supply chain attack opportunity like any other, and because it updates fairly frequently, updates are less likely to trigger scrutiny.
    </li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    So, by my count, we have <strong>zero upsides</strong> and <strong>several downsides</strong>. So much for that tradeoff.
  </p>

  <h2 id="copy-paste-a-case-study">Copy-paste: a case study</h2>
  <p>
    Suppose that, for whatever incomprehensible reason, we actually did need to check if a JS value was either a finite number or a finite non-empty numeric string. Instead of installing an npm package, we could just copy-paste the entirety of <code>is-number</code> into our program:
  </p>
  <pre><code><span><span><span>function</span> <span>isNumber</span><span>(</span><span>num</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
</span></span><span><span>  <span>if</span> <span>(</span><span>typeof</span> <span>num</span> <span>===</span> <span>'number'</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
</span></span><span><span>    <span>return</span> <span>num</span> <span>-</span> <span>num</span> <span>===</span> <span>0</span><span>;</span>
</span></span><span><span>  <span>}</span>
</span></span><span><span>
</span></span><span><span>  <span>if</span> <span>(</span><span>typeof</span> <span>num</span> <span>===</span> <span>'string'</span> <span>&amp;&amp;</span> <span>num</span><span>.</span><span>trim</span><span>()</span> <span>!==</span> <span>''</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
</span></span><span><span>    <span>return</span> <span>Number</span><span>.</span><span>isFinite</span> <span>?</span> <span>Number</span><span>.</span><span>isFinite</span><span>(</span><span>+</span><span>num</span><span>)</span> <span>:</span> <span>isFinite</span><span>(</span><span>+</span><span>num</span><span>);</span>
</span></span><span><span>  <span>}</span>
</span></span><span><span>
</span></span><span><span>  <span>return</span> <span>false</span><span>;</span>
</span></span><span><span><span>}</span></span></span></code></pre>
  <p>
    This mitigates all the remaining downsides. We still <strong>save development time</strong> by copy-pasting. It <strong>cannot cause breakage</strong> in the future, since it will never change. It has a <strong>smaller footprint</strong>, since it doesn’t include unnecessary metadata, and it will never mysteriously duplicate itself. It is <strong>not risky</strong>, since its functionality is obvious and it cannot be attacked via the supply chain.
  </p>
  <p>
    And of course, we probably could have just written <code>typeof foo === "number"</code>.
  </p>

  <h2 id="what-about-duplication-">What about duplication?</h2>
  <p>
    One of the purported benefits of tiny libraries is reduced duplication across your whole app. Say your app has a utility like <code>isNumber</code>, and several libraries have utilities like <code>isNumber</code>—wouldn’t it be better to reduce all the duplication and let them all share one version of the utility?
  </p>
  <p>
    In practice this is obviously not what happens. Look at the dependency graphs for popular projects and you will see amazing amounts of duplication. Often there are multiple packages performing similar functions, but also there often multiple major versions of the <em>same package</em>.
  </p>
  <p>
    It should be obvious why this happens: not all users have the exact same requirements. Wherever the requirements differ, there will be a different implementation. We wouldn’t expect every copy-pasted utility to be exactly the same, so why would we expect the duplication to disappear when using a package manager instead?
  </p>
  <p>
    But really, it’s worse than that, because when multiple major versions of <code>is-number</code> are installed in your <code>node_modules</code>, something else is clearly wrong. Semantic versioning simply isn’t the sharp tool people think it is. If you’re on Node 20, it is <em>not a breaking change</em> for the library to raise the minimum Node version from 0.10.0 to 0.12.0. There would be no need for a duplicate version, but your tools do not know this. Likewise if the package author releases a major version because of an edge case. Technically breaking for <em>some</em> users, but not for you.
  </p>
  <p>
    And finally—many use cases of tiny libraries can literally be replaced with one-liners. In this case you don’t have to worry about duplication at all anyway. Your code will still be small. It will be a tiny amount of source code and just a handful of bytecode ops. You don’t need a package manager to solve this problem for you.
  </p>

  <h2 id="stop-already">Stop already!</h2>
  <p>
    I could have written the same analysis about <code>left-pad</code> eight years ago, or <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/shebang-regex">many</a> <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/is-regexp">other</a> <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/run-applescript">packages</a> today. <strong>Tiny utilities simply should not be libraries.</strong>
  </p>
  <p>
    There is absolutely nothing wrong with copy-pasting code into your project. Sometimes it really is useful to grab a snippet of code from Stack Overflow, but there is literally zero benefit to installing these things through a package manager. You are exposing yourself to a whole world of pain, which you can trivially avoid by just copy-pasting.
  </p>
  <p>
    I have talked a lot about the costs of libraries, and I do hope people are more cautious about them. But there’s one factor I left out from my previous discussion. I think there’s one more reason why people use libraries: <strong>fear</strong>.
  </p>
  <p>
    Programmers are afraid of causing bugs. Afraid of making mistakes. Afraid of missing edge cases. Afraid that they won’t be able to understand how things work. In their fear they fall back on libraries. “Thank goodness someone else has solved the problem; surely I <em>never</em> would have been able to.”
  </p>
  <p>
    But they should not be afraid! Libraries are not magic. They are just code someone else wrote. After all, I pasted the entirety of <code>is-number</code> above, and nothing in there is too mysterious. And beyond libraries—languages are not magic, operating systems are not magic, nothing is magic. Dig into the source code and you will find code you can read and understand. This attitude is fundamental to the <a href="https://handmade.network/manifesto">Handmade ethos</a> and I endorse it fully.
  </p>
  <p>
    If you are a proponent of tiny libraries, I encourage you to overcome your fear and try writing the code yourself. You are more capable than you think.
  </p>

    </article>
  
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Leaving Neovim for Zed (289 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://stevedylan.dev/posts/leaving-neovim-for-zed/</link>
            <guid>41284322</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 18:37:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://stevedylan.dev/posts/leaving-neovim-for-zed/">https://stevedylan.dev/posts/leaving-neovim-for-zed/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41284322">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
				
	<p><img src="https://dweb.mypinata.cloud/ipfs/Qmc6r5uT5GiAonoo98YLTzxysvjV8x6cVaT1cQnToLsva6?img-quality=60" alt="cover-image"></p><p>I think every developer has their own text editor journey and how they landed on the tool they use today. Perhaps I’m a geek but I love those stories. I have a great appreciation for developer tools and the work that goes into them. This post is for the other geeks out there that also care, and I hope my journey and perspective can prompt others to experiment and try developer tools outside their comfort zones. You never know what you might land on and how much you might enjoy it!</p>
<p>My text editor journey starts with a faint memory of Atom. I was learning the true fundamentals of HTML CSS and Javascript, and I honestly can’t tell you how I landed on Atom as a text editor. I do remember using it for a few weeks, and I kept seeing other people use or mention VSCode, so of course I gave it a shot and used it for a while. However this didn’t last long. At the time my wife needed my laptop for her photo editing job, so I used my brother’s old Macbook that was holding on for dear life. VSCode’s Electron build started taking a noticeable toll on performance, and by chance I also discovered Vim around the same time.</p>
<p>Immediately I was mesmerized by the speed and powers demonstrated by The Primeagen’s early videos. I was already a keyboard maximalist from <a href="https://stevedylan.dev/posts/leaving-neovim-for-zed/posts/why-i-learned-vim">previous jobs</a> where I learned speed = productivity, so it was a no brainer that I had to learn it. Started with the basic motions and Vim tutor, and I had the advantage that I was just learning programming on the side instead of doing it full time. Within a few weeks I was in Vim consistently, writing and learning to code. The tweaking of my Vim RC eventually led to discovering Neovim thanks to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@chrisatmachine">chris@machine</a> and his early videos.</p>
<p>For the next several years I stuck with Neovim and I loved it, and I owe a mass amount of my productivity to it. There were countless hours spent configuring it like many of us do. I eventually got to a point where I didn’t adjust my config much, but that soon didn’t matter.</p>
<h2 id="what-changed">What Changed</h2>
<p>Every now and then I would update a plugin in Neovim and everything would break, and I would have to spend time fixing it instead of getting work done. This resulted in slimming down my config more and more, but there was still so much that went into making all the basics work. I stuck with it because it was still better than using VSCode, which I did try for a two week sprint to see if it could be any better. It was also key to a <a href="https://stevedylan.dev/posts/a-terminal-based-workflow">terminal based workflow</a> that other editors couldn’t really match.</p>
<p>The sentiment started to shift again not too long ago as I started working in some really large code bases, and boy Neovim was struggling. I would have random hang ups, frozen screens, stuff that just drove me nuts when productivity was king. I tried switching to other terminal emulators too such as Alacritty and Wezterm but it didn’t help much.</p>
<p>This is when Zed came back into my sights. I heard about it months before and even gave it a shot back then, but didn’t stick with it because it wasn’t a terminal workflow. However it boasted as being fast, and I decided it was worth another shot. Two months later and I’ve been daily driving it since. I wasn’t sure if it would really hold up, but I can say now it has been an amazing experience and I don’t see myself going back.</p>
<h2 id="my-experience-with-zed">My Experience with Zed</h2>
<p>In order to understand why I eventually settled on Zed we’ll look at my general experience with it so far and how I made it work for me.</p>
<h3 id="it-just-works">It Just Works</h3>
<p>One of the biggest things that has stood out to me using Zed so far is how “everything just works.” There are so many features of an IDE or text editor that people take for granted until they have to set it up themselves in something lower level like Neovim. LSP (language server protocol) is certainly one of them. If you’re not familiar it’s the hints or errors that show up while you’re writing up your code, giving you deep insights to your repo on a language level. When you setup LSP in Neovim it’s a lot of work, and sometimes it can be a bit harder to figure out why it might be bugging out. However it does give you way more control and the option to do a lot of customization. With Zed LSP just works. There are configurations you can make to edit some things, but as a whole it just zips out of the box. There are already keybindings for things like “show definition”, “go to definition”, or even code actions. The only downside is outside of an extension you can’t use your own LSP that’s installed on your machine, but there’s always a pretty large language support that I haven’t had this issue yet.</p>
<p><img src="https://dweb.mypinata.cloud/ipfs/QmNkysZ5Roy723sphUST8abmHakKR86K2YHXeeVTU22ASH" alt="image of LSP"></p><p>Another piece that’s related to LSP is completions. This is when you’re typing some code and get  suggestions for auto completions that quickly fill the rest of the code out. LSPs usually have great auto-completion because they’re aware of the patterns used in that language. Just to be clear we’re not talking about Copilot yet, this is just completions for snippets and LSP. Once again with Zed it just works out of the box, unlike Neovim which ends up requiring several plugins to make it work right.</p>
<video autoplay="" muted="true" loop="" playsinline="" src="https://dweb.mypinata.cloud/ipfs/QmVEqwPxAoWgDwCLM3PrVxseLtLjCDK8LMxxz6DyD5fjxz"></video>
<p>Finally there’s Git integrations. What normally required multiple plugins in Neovim is again ready out of the box with Zed, including feature like toggling Git Blame, viewing diffs, and gutter symbols showing the status of edited lines.</p>
<video autoplay="" muted="true" loop="" playsinline="" src="https://dweb.mypinata.cloud/ipfs/Qmcqv6kXnHHVbX8RxWpK6coPZHyNcPU7bxPfZ2Zwbsm6bz"></video>
<p>If I had to make a crude comparison, it’s similar to Linux and Apple. Linux will give you far more control over every piece of your software and hardware at the cost of spending time to configure it. Apple will give you less control but it will likely run smoother.</p>
<h3 id="speed">Speed</h3>
<p>Of course one of the biggest reasons I gave Zed a shot was speed, and boy it was worth it. It is noticeably snappy, handles larger codebases like a champ, and I haven’t experienced any lag so far. Normally I wouldn’t recommend building most things in Rust, but this app kinda makes me reconsider. There are so many developer tools written in Rust and perhaps that’s one of its biggest boasts. The team at Zed have really outdone themselves as this app; its truly a work of art.</p>
<p>Could I possibly make neovim faster by adjusting my config? Perhaps, but in the end it’s more time down the drain that I could have used writing code and being productive. For productivity nerds like me I believe there is a delicate scale: how much time I spend automating a task vs how much time the task would have taken without automation. In this case the benefits aren’t worth the cost when there’s a tool like Zed that will do just fine.</p>
<h3 id="vim-mode">Vim Mode</h3>
<p>While in the middle of my time with Neovim I came across other frustrated Neovim users that found themselves spending too much time fixing issues in Neovim to the point they switched to VSCode. Of course I had a few moments like this myself and I wondered if I had missed something. At this point I had a much faster computer, so I figured I would give it another shot. Of course I downloaded the Vim plugin as the Vim keybindings are worth learning no matter what text editor you use, and it was incredibly disappointing. Nothing had every felt so buggy and jagged, and it remained one of the big reasons I couldn’t stick with VSCode. I was back in Neovim within a week or two.</p>
<p>When I was considering Zed again I read <a href="https://registerspill.thorstenball.com/p/from-vim-to-zed">a blog post</a> about the custom Vim mode built into Zed. This was not a third party plugin; this was a labor of love from the developers building Zed. They’ve made it clear that they don’t plan to port absolutely everything to Zed, but they have done a fantastic job supporting the important stuff that makes the editor an S-tier experience.</p>
<p>I’ll likely get into this further into the post, but the way you can structure keybindings for Vim mode in Zed is fantastic. The structure allows for your typical VScode style config, but with the ability to scope a keybinding to a Vim mode is such a huge win for Neovim users. For instance, I can cheat my way into using a leader key when in normal mode and get things like <code>space d</code> to see diagnostics, or <code>space t</code> to open a full window terminal. It’s a pattern many Vim users will appreciate and I wish there was more docs for it as I’ve had to figure some of it out myself.</p>
<p>Beyond keybindings all the other stuff you would expect in Vim motions are here, with of course a few obscure ones slowly being added release by release. Some of them take a unique approach by using some of Zed’s built in features as a replacement for what Vim would normally use, like search and replace for example. Generally you would have to do a Vim command to search for a word and replace it, and those commands still do what you expect, but it brings up Zed’s Multibuffer view when doing a project wide search. You get Vim mode but it’s still Zed and it’s unique feature set.</p>
<h3 id="ai-stuff">AI Stuff</h3>
<p>When it comes to AI features I think Zed provides some great built in tools. I will disclose that I’m not a big user of AI within the text editor (a topic for another blog post), so there might be things you’re looking for compared to Cursor that I can’t speak to. With that said it does have Copilot built in which is probably what most people want to know.</p>
<p>Zed also features an assistant panel where you can access several AI models via API, including OpenAI, Ollama, and Anthropic. Just requires a few lines of config to get started.</p>
<video autoplay="" muted="true" loop="" playsinline="" src="https://dweb.mypinata.cloud/ipfs/QmPo8nXP8w9hJfxnhCpggrGKP89VbtiV1Rf3mFRHj9fUqA"></video>
<p>One feature that I think is particularly nice is the inline assistant, where you can select some lines of code and use <code>ctrl-enter</code> to trigger a request to be made to your code via the AI assistance configuration mentioned previously. If you like the results then you can confirm and keep coding.</p>
<video autoplay="" muted="true" loop="" playsinline="" src="https://dweb.mypinata.cloud/ipfs/QmTTGznMRr64oqJG7hXFiCrqrTqXiY3kaPuQnhWbCCSAaL"></video>
<h3 id="zed--neovim">Zed ≠ Neovim</h3>
<p>You can probably gather so far that I’m a huge Zed fan, however I will say it’s not a 1/1 replacement to Neovim. What makes Neovim so special is that it’s native to the terminal. Whenever I need to edit a configuration file for an app or just edit something really quickly while I’m already navigating in a terminal, nothing beats the convenience of whipping out Neovim. Opening Zed for every single file like that would get exhausting, but for longer term sessions or projects it’s perfect. If you compare to motorcycles, Neovim is my dirt bike and Zed is my cruiser.</p>
<h2 id="making-zed-work-for-a-neovim-user">Making Zed Work for A Neovim User</h2>
<p>While Zed can’t truly be a drop in replacement of Neovim, there are a lot of small configurations that really help improve the experience and make it familiar to a Neovim/Vim user.</p>
<h3 id="vim-mode--keybindings">Vim Mode &amp; Keybindings</h3>
<p>First one is obvious, turn on Vim mode. Zed has a great <a href="https://zed.dev/docs/vim">docs page</a> with loads of extra info, some default Vim bindings, and some extra configs available to make it work for you. By far my favorite piece that I mentioned earlier is the ability to do key bindings based on Vim modes. Here’s some examples:</p>
<pre><code><span><span>[</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>		</span><span>"</span><span>context</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Editor &amp;&amp; VimControl &amp;&amp; !VimWaiting &amp;&amp; !menu</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>		</span><span>"</span><span>bindings</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>"</span><span>space b</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>editor::ToggleGitBlame</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>"</span><span>shift-k</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>editor::Hover</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>"</span><span>space l f</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>editor::Format</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>"</span><span>space d</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>diagnostics::Deploy</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>"</span><span>space f f</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>file_finder::Toggle</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>"</span><span>space o</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>tab_switcher::Toggle</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>"</span><span>space e</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>workspace::ToggleLeftDock</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>"</span><span>space /</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>workspace::NewSearch</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>"</span><span>n</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>search::SelectNextMatch</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>"</span><span>shift-n</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>search::SelectPrevMatch</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>"</span><span>space t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>workspace::NewCenterTerminal</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>"</span><span>g b</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>editor::ToggleComments</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>"</span><span>+ +</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>workspace::Save</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>"</span><span>space c</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>pane::CloseActiveItem</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>		</span><span>}</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>		</span><span>"</span><span>context</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Editor &amp;&amp; vim_mode == visual &amp;&amp; !VimWaiting &amp;&amp; !VimObject</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>		</span><span>"</span><span>bindings</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>"</span><span>shift-j</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>editor::MoveLineDown</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>"</span><span>shift-k</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>editor::MoveLineUp</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>		</span><span>}</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>]</span></span></code></pre>
<p>Most of these are pretty self explanatory, but the key is that the first set is in “Normal” mode, while the next set is “Visual.” There’s also small improvements or shortcuts they provide in the docs like this set of key bindings that allows you to switch panes similar to how most people have Neovim setup.</p>
<pre><code><span><span>[</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>		</span><span>"</span><span>context</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Dock || Terminal || Editor</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>		</span><span>"</span><span>bindings</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>"</span><span>ctrl-h</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>"</span><span>workspace::ActivatePaneInDirection</span><span>"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Left</span><span>"</span><span>],</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>"</span><span>ctrl-l</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>"</span><span>workspace::ActivatePaneInDirection</span><span>"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Right</span><span>"</span><span>],</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>"</span><span>ctrl-k</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>"</span><span>workspace::ActivatePaneInDirection</span><span>"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Up</span><span>"</span><span>],</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>"</span><span>ctrl-j</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>"</span><span>workspace::ActivatePaneInDirection</span><span>"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Down</span><span>"</span><span>]</span></span>
<span><span>		</span><span>}</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>]</span></span></code></pre>
<p>Something else I would recommend to anyone who is trying to migrate from Vim/Neovim to Zed is checking out the <a href="https://github.com/zed-industries/zed/blob/340a1d145ed15e39a4a27afc5a189851308fb91d/assets/keymaps/vim.json#L4">default Vim keymap</a>. There’s so much there that acts as a helpful reference of what’s supported and what you may want to adjust!</p>
<h3 id="reduced-ui">Reduced UI</h3>
<p>Zed already has a pretty nice minimal UI, but I prefer something closer to my Neovim setup. Thankfully Zed offers these options, such as disabling the tab bar, scroll bar, reduced toolbar, and relative line numbers</p>
<pre><code><span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>"</span><span>cursor_blink</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>false</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>"</span><span>relative_line_numbers</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>true</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>"</span><span>scrollbar</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>		</span><span>"</span><span>show</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>never</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>"</span><span>vertical_scroll_margin</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>"</span><span>tab_bar</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>		</span><span>"</span><span>show</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>false</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>"</span><span>toolbar</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>	    </span><span>"</span><span>breadcrumbs</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>true</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>	    </span><span>"</span><span>quick_actions</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>false</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>}</span></span></code></pre>
<p><img src="https://dweb.mypinata.cloud/ipfs/QmVtqSNc6Ff9Zy8vBxr92AcVdh9eAGYkU8zWGLoyTnoeDL?img-quality=60" alt="reduced UI"></p><h3 id="plugin-replacements">Plugin Replacements</h3>
<p>Since I don’t use the tab bar I wanted something similar to Telescope to navigate between buffers or files, and thankfully there is an option for that! This key binding will show currently open all buffers, which is separate from the file finder.</p>
<pre><code><span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>"</span><span>context</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Editor &amp;&amp; VimControl &amp;&amp; !VimWaiting &amp;&amp; !menu</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>"</span><span>bindings</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>		</span><span>"</span><span>space o</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>tab_switcher::Toggle</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>}</span></span>
<span><span>}</span></span></code></pre>
<video autoplay="" muted="true" loop="" playsinline="" src="https://dweb.mypinata.cloud/ipfs/QmQntcJQkJKoh2bmreRYun4BfDuLb8rXry6ZFmiVYPaeRx"></video>
<p>Speaking of Telescope, one big replacement is project wide search. While Zed doesn’t have a fuzzy find feature, the project wide search is excellent. It will show all results in a multibuffer view which is pretty slick, and allows you to jump between that view and the buffer itself pretty easily.</p>
<video autoplay="" muted="true" loop="" playsinline="" src="https://dweb.mypinata.cloud/ipfs/QmY2Cs7zBk7bEa7skNLBcA5dFnSmTS7CotFjftcMA2r3m1"></video>
<p>The terminal toggle is pretty similar to something like VSCode but there are some other hidden ways to get a better terminal experience. One of them is a shortcut to toggle the bottom terminal to be full screen, but even better is opening a terminal as a buffer in the main editing view.</p>
<pre><code><span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>"</span><span>context</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Editor &amp;&amp; VimControl &amp;&amp; !VimWaiting &amp;&amp; !menu</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>"</span><span>bindings</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>		</span><span>"</span><span>space t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>workspace::NewCenterTerminal</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>}</span></span>
<span><span>}</span></span></code></pre>
<video autoplay="" muted="true" loop="" playsinline="" src="https://dweb.mypinata.cloud/ipfs/QmYGcEqane6cpVPJj9H7qjgYmV75GPhmy7hkKob6YPVscY"></video>
<p>One of the big things I had to leave behind was Tmux and switching projects. While it isn’t a perfect replacement, Zed has a “switch projects” feature which works really well and makes it pretty easy to switch contexts. You just won’t get the exact same control and layout setup that you can get with Tmux</p>
<pre><code><span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>"</span><span>context</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Workspace</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>"</span><span>bindings</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>		</span><span>"</span><span>cmd-k</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>[</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>"</span><span>projects::OpenRecent</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>				</span><span>"</span><span>create_new_window</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>false</span></span>
<span><span>			</span><span>}</span></span>
<span><span>		</span><span>]</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>}</span></span>
<span><span>}</span></span></code></pre>
<video autoplay="" muted="true" loop="" playsinline="" src="https://dweb.mypinata.cloud/ipfs/QmXh5mDRJyQRSCfmHNeZ5DDwnzPr3uo5mqCMQN1mLzGh6T"></video>
<h2 id="should-you-use-zed">Should You Use Zed?</h2>
<p>If you’re still on the fence of trying Zed I would say it’s at least worth giving it a shot for a few days. In my experience so far it’s a unique and capable text editor, but ultimately I vouch for anything that makes you more productive. That might end up being VS Code or Jetbrains or hell maybe even EMacs. Do what’s best for you, but don’t be too stubborn to try something new.</p>
<p>Edit: Thank you for all the love on this post! If you want to see my full settings and keymaps I have them linked below for your convenience.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.snippets.so/snip/bafkreia4sliyaggmemdbvfl2cv4iakkz343pn4bjbdxcig6mmekjvy2o5a">settings.json</a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.snippets.so/snip/bafkreifwoopkah2ouf7iuuvnx5n4b7slcoqyo6c3uwifenw4ikp3rzauuq">keymap.json</a></p>

			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Debugging operating systems with time-traveling virtual machines (2005) [pdf] (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.usenix.org/legacy/events/usenix05/tech/general/king/king.pdf</link>
            <guid>41284235</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 18:28:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.usenix.org/legacy/events/usenix05/tech/general/king/king.pdf">https://www.usenix.org/legacy/events/usenix05/tech/general/king/king.pdf</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41284235">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Detailed Map of Cancer-Causing Industrial Air Pollution in the U.S. (156 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://projects.propublica.org/toxmap/</link>
            <guid>41283675</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 17:18:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://projects.propublica.org/toxmap/">https://projects.propublica.org/toxmap/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41283675">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><a href="https://projects.propublica.org/"><svg role="image" width="574" height="75"><use xlink:href="#propublica-logo"></use><text>ProPublica</text></svg></a><p>© Copyright <span id="year"></span> Pro Publica Inc.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Greenwich schools to ban most cellphones, Apple Watches, Fitbits and more (124 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.greenwichtime.com/news/education/article/greenwich-schools-cellphones-ban-fitbit-19660245.php</link>
            <guid>41283479</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 16:53:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.greenwichtime.com/news/education/article/greenwich-schools-cellphones-ban-fitbit-19660245.php">https://www.greenwichtime.com/news/education/article/greenwich-schools-cellphones-ban-fitbit-19660245.php</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41283479">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.greenwichtime.com/news/education/article/greenwich-schools-cellphones-ban-fitbit-19660245.php: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Police Cannot Seize Property Indefinitely After an Arrest, Federal Court Rules (632 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://reason.com/2024/08/16/police-cannot-seize-property-indefinitely-after-an-arrest-federal-court-rules/</link>
            <guid>41283310</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 16:28:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://reason.com/2024/08/16/police-cannot-seize-property-indefinitely-after-an-arrest-federal-court-rules/">https://reason.com/2024/08/16/police-cannot-seize-property-indefinitely-after-an-arrest-federal-court-rules/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41283310">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
							<p><span>The Fourth Amendment's protection against unreasonable searches and seizures extends to the <em>length</em> of a seizure, a federal court ruled last week, significantly restricting how long law enforcement can retain private property after an arrest.</span></p> <p><span>"When the government seizes property incident to a lawful arrest, the Fourth Amendment requires that any continued possession of the property must be reasonable," </span><a href="https://www.cadc.uscourts.gov/internet/opinions.nsf/543BA8AD10156CE685258B7400533CE0/$file/22-7129-2069152.pdf"><span>wrote</span></a><span> Judge Gregory Katsas of the U.S. Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia in a unanimous ruling.</span></p> <p><span>Most courts of appeal to pass judgment on the issue—namely, the </span><a href="https://www.cadc.uscourts.gov/internet/opinions.nsf/543BA8AD10156CE685258B7400533CE0/$file/22-7129-2069152.pdf"><span>1st, 2nd, 6th, 7th, and 11th circuits</span></a><span>—have held that, once an item is seized, law enforcement can retain the item indefinitely without violating the <a href="https://www.reaganlibrary.gov/constitutional-amendments-amendment-4-right-privacy#:~:text=%E2%80%9CThe%20right%20of,to%20be%20seized.%E2%80%9D">Fourth Amendment</a>. These precedents have allowed police to retain personal property without clear legal grounds, effectively stripping people of their property rights merely because they were arrested. The D.C. Court of Appeals' ruling complicates this general consensus.</span></p> <p><span>Though law enforcement does not have to return property "instantaneously," Katsas wrote, the Fourth Amendment requires that any "continuing retention of seized property" be reasonable. So while police can use seized items for "legitimate law-enforcement purposes," such as for evidence at trial, and are permitted some delay for "matching a person with his effects," prolonged seizures serving no important function can implicate the Fourth Amendment, the court ruled.</span></p> <p><span>Given that the D.C. court finds itself in the minority on the question, some say that the case may be primed for the Supreme Court if the District chooses to appeal. "This case has potential to make national precedent," Paul Belonick, a professor at the University of California, San Francisco law school, tells </span><i><span>Reason</span></i><span>. "The influential D.C. Circuit deliberately intensified a circuit split and put itself in the minority of circuits on the question, teeing it up cleanly for certiorari."</span></p> <p><span>The plaintiffs each had their property seized by D.C.'s Metropolitan Police Department (MPD). Five of the plaintiffs were arrested during a Black Lives Matter protest in the Adams Morgan neighborhood of D.C. on August 13, 2020.</span></p> <p><span>As they were arrested, MPD officers seized their phones and other items. Though the protesters did not face any charges and were, in Katsas' words, "quickly released," MPD retained their phones for around a year. Some of the plaintiffs had to wait over 14 months to get their property back.</span></p> <p><span>In the meantime, the plaintiffs say that they were forced to replace their phones and lost access to the important information on the originals, including personal files, contacts, and passwords. </span><span>"The plaintiffs have alleged that the seizures at issue, though lawful at their inception, later came to unreasonably interfere with their protected possessory interests in their own property," Katsas explained.</span></p> <p><span>"MPD is aware of the ruling and will continue to work with our partners at the United States Attorney's Office to ensure that our members are trained appropriately to ensure compliance with recent rulings," a spokesperson for MPD&nbsp;tells </span><i><span>Reason</span></i><span>.</span></p> <p><span>"Practically, this case is important because police have been exploiting a gap in the Fourth Amendment," Andrew Ferguson, a professor at American University's Washington College of Law, tells </span><i><span>Reason</span></i><span>. "In situations where there is a lawful arrest, but no prosecution, there are no clear rules on retaining personal property. In these cases, police have been confiscating phones to punish protestors."</span></p> <p><span>Michael Perloff, the lead attorney for the plaintiffs, agreed that the D.C. Circuit's decision could set an important precedent going forward. "Nationally, we've seen litigants attempt to challenge similar practices only to fail because the court concluded that the Fourth Amendment does not limit the duration of a seizure," he tells </span><i><span>Reason</span></i><span>. "Moving forward, we are hopeful that the D.C. Circuit's opinion will lead courts to reconsider those rulings and, instead, enforce the Fourth Amendment as fully as the framers intended."</span></p>						</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tell HN: X stopped requiring authentication, nitter works again (116 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nitter.lucabased.xyz/x</link>
            <guid>41283209</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 16:11:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nitter.lucabased.xyz/x">https://nitter.lucabased.xyz/x</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41283209">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://nitter.lucabased.xyz/x: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Surveillance Watch – the hidden connections within the surveillance industry (143 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.surveillancewatch.io</link>
            <guid>41283149</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 16:02:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.surveillancewatch.io">https://www.surveillancewatch.io</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41283149">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><h2><p><span><span>They know who you are.</span><span></span></span></p><p><span><span>It's time to uncover</span><span></span></span><span><span>who they are.</span><span></span></span></p></h2><p>Surveillance Watch is an interactive map revealing the intricate connections between surveillance companies, their funding sources and affiliations.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[CSS adds vertical centering in 2024 (129 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://build-your-own.org/blog/20240813_css_vertical_center/</link>
            <guid>41282889</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 15:21:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://build-your-own.org/blog/20240813_css_vertical_center/">https://build-your-own.org/blog/20240813_css_vertical_center/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41282889">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<p><code>align-content</code> works in the default layout in 2024,
allowing vertical centering with <strong>1 CSS property</strong>.</p>
<div><pre><code>&lt;div style="<strong>align-content: center;</strong> height: 100px;"&gt;
  &lt;code&gt;align-content&lt;/code&gt; just works!
&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre></div>


<p><code>align-content</code> just works!
</p>


<p><a href="https://caniuse.com/mdn-css_properties_align-content_block_context">Supported
since</a>: <br>
<img width="16" height="16" src="data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABAAAAAQCAYAAAAf8/9hAAACaklEQVR42nWTA6xsVxhG17/3mXm2bds2w96oRlgzqo34IqxtG1GNsDbmPtvG+b/OHtRdx1jfduAflGaOXfrrrHHNpTkTSq1zJ2rD/Em+YcGUzzctmvrQlrlTh/IPrPTnu66etbkZ7MoQAsFM6WQhYGaVI6SD2HwknLwV2Atgn1cDunYMxXeDhSkWLFGXFGLSUOU5BQcD48sj8mUpJAB0DIVU8lSBUcEQUEmo3lBNxAQGYWrHLCs7yXqqYeglb2wuLf1uX7XaZlYYMIBeN93Ftp6jiJ06MSB/C//5anS0JENIMsMl1/IswM3Pze/FrF8P0PG4rNB/AN7yHGe/KT799RhwjEHd5vLc+R/S75fFpqOtYE6FQEPwnKnbOxV4Y1p3Ej2uuppTHz9Zlo9TZ8OenKueN+K4uzGLYBkQMcIpAWmqy/XalK5s71xg9+RlbCwL/yQFbjwxHiXRgkRmsjA0uDtyt4NF4/4FPeQHD/B/dOnYDUJERCNUaxIkb1XCnc+GtbdthfXMG1Hkn0zon9Hp8DsYGVZrAha/SH3wslwmCbm47v1GbmuIFaFGObBA85kF8l9vRRYQAbOIEb+wifetXZrDuxIgIaB/h95cN/9CZvedx4a9BzjoJT79/EYu6/oVIKQcQ8Tch9mY+9YANMl1BQJJhoRLAiHHBhRP8tiobQwsngAc5JjUDFwVAI4dPHarXF/Wm+IuSPd59fm83ocY1FbCIiKi1PY83gpgQ5uWUqNrzOItolYThMoMLLq9N2UXIMCR5y3ZiRO31BdToEbtxZV+0oe59IhcX0jisgFHwGKrCC0ylqV/6nLid9CxMOX4sHSyAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC">
Chrome: 123 |
<img width="16" height="16" src="data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABAAAAAQCAYAAAAf8/9hAAAAZ0lEQVR42q2SAQbAMBRD/2VztF1p18lsiCJ7Nhqiqt7ztZ2aw659izVeQWuqwOc8Z1UAMEoiWEpwkRQBiALf61eYJQj3BraKgECeoIuyxwmg++/ACmwLXgJh0T/gdgFLGAYJwpw/4AWWCw/0v3nNDwAAAABJRU5ErkJggg==">
Firefox: 125 |
<img width="16" height="16" src="data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABAAAAAQBAMAAADt3eJSAAAAJ1BMVEUAAAAQfd0fhvkSrvH/UVAGwudtnampc33RpKe23ubx8fGQyt1mq9Ygasa0AAAAAXRSTlMAQObYZgAAAGdJREFUeNpjYGBgFBQUYADRQkpKiiCWoBIQCIIFjI2VHAUYGJWMQ0NTlAQYhJRMQ8PclBQZhJRDQ0tSjcCMCPdQCGNWK4QRvTIUzFA6tTU0VEkRqH1NaGgwUDujlBJIQABmBcJSuDMAytIVRxPqOxAAAAAASUVORK5CYII=">
Safari: 17.4</p>
<h2 id="whats-new">What’s new?</h2>
<p>The status quo for CSS alignment is to switch to <em>flexbox</em> or
<em>grid</em> because <code>align-content</code> doesn’t work in the
default layout (<em>flow</em>). In 2024, browsers have <a href="https://web.dev/blog/align-content-block">implemented</a>
<code>align-content</code> for <em>flow layout</em>. This has some
advantages:</p>
<ul>
<li>You do not need flexbox or grid, just 1 CSS property for
alignment.</li>
<li>Therefore, the content doesn’t need to be wrapped in a div.</li>
</ul>
<div><pre><code>&lt;!-- Works --&gt;
&lt;div style="<strong>display: grid; align-content: center;</strong>"&gt;
  Content.
&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<div><pre><code>&lt;!-- <span>FAIL!</span> --&gt;
&lt;div style="<strong>display: grid; align-content: center;</strong>"&gt;
  Content with <strong>&lt;em&gt;multiple&lt;/em&gt;</strong> nodes.
&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<div><pre><code>&lt;!-- Works with the content wrapper --&gt;
&lt;div style="<strong>display: grid; align-content: center;</strong>"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;  &lt;!-- The extra wrapper --&gt;
    Content with <strong>&lt;em&gt;multiple&lt;/em&gt;</strong> nodes.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<div><pre><code>&lt;!-- Works without the content wrapper --&gt;
&lt;div style="<strong>align-content: center;</strong>"&gt;
  Content with <strong>&lt;em&gt;multiple&lt;/em&gt;</strong> nodes.
&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<p>It’s amazing that CSS finally has a <strong>single property</strong>
to control vertical align after decades of progress!</p>
<h2 id="vertical-centering-a-history">Vertical centering — a
history</h2>
<p>Browsers are funny, basic needs like aligning stuff do not have
simple answers for a very long time. Here is how to center stuff in
libreoffice:</p>
<p><img src="https://build-your-own.org/blog/20240813_css_vertical_center/libreoffice_center.png"></p>
<p>Here is how to center <em>vertically</em> in a browser
(<em>horizontal</em> centering is another topic):</p>
<h3 id="method-1-table-cell">Method 1: table cell</h3>
<p>Sanity: ★★★☆☆</p>
<p>There are 4 major layouts: flow (default), table, flexbox, grid. How
to align stuff depends on the layout of the container. Flexbox and grid
were added rather late, so table was the first option.</p>
<div><pre><code>&lt;div style="<strong>display: table;</strong>"&gt;
  &lt;div style="<strong>display: table-cell; vertical-align: middle;</strong>"&gt;
    Content.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<p>A table can be summoned purely from CSS, but it’s a shame that such
an indirection was needed.</p>
<h3 id="method-2-absolute-positioning">Method 2: absolute
positioning</h3>
<p>Sanity: ☆☆☆☆☆</p>
<p>For reasons I don’t understand. People kept inventing more indirect
ways to do things.</p>
<div><pre><code>&lt;div style="<strong>position: relative;</strong>"&gt;
  &lt;div style="<strong>position: absolute; top: 50%; transform: translateY(-50%);</strong>"&gt;
    Content.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<p>This one uses absolute positioning to bypass the layout, since the
flow layout doesn’t help us:</p>
<ol start="0" type="1">
<li>Mark the reference container with
<code>position: relative</code>.</li>
<li>Place the edge of the content at the center with
<code>position: absolute; top: 50%</code>.</li>
<li>Offset the content center to the edge with
<code>transform: translateY(-50%)</code>.</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="method-3-inline-content">Method 3: inline content</h3>
<p>Sanity: ☆☆☆☆☆</p>
<p>While the flow layout doesn’t help with content alignment. It allows
vertical alignment <em>within</em> a line. So why not make a line as
tall as the container?</p>
<div><pre><code>&lt;div class="<strong>container</strong>"&gt;
  <strong>::before</strong>
  &lt;div class="<strong>content</strong>"&gt;Content.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<div><pre><code>.container::before {
  content: '';
  height: 100%;
  display: inline-block;
  vertical-align: middle;
}
.content {
  display: inline-block;
  vertical-align: middle;
}
</code></pre></div>
<p>This has some flaws: besides sacrificing a pseudo-element, there’s a
zero-width <a href="https://christopheraue.net/design/vertical-align#:~:text=strut">“strut”
character</a> at the beginning that can mess stuff up.</p>
<h3 id="method-4-single-line-flexbox">Method 4: single-line flexbox</h3>
<p>Sanity: ★★★☆☆</p>
<p>Flexbox became widely available 2 decades after the Web has taken
off. It has 2 modes: single-line and multi-line. In single-line mode
(default), the line fills the vertical space, and
<code>align-items</code> aligns stuff inside the line.</p>
<div><pre><code>&lt;div style="<strong>display: flex; align-items: center;</strong>"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Content.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<p>Alternatively, make the line columnar and align items with
<code>justify-content</code>.</p>
<div><pre><code>&lt;div style="<strong>display: flex; flex-flow: column; justify-content: center;</strong>"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Content.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<h3 id="method-5-multi-line-flexbox">Method 5: multi-line flexbox</h3>
<p>Sanity: ★★★☆☆</p>
<p>In a multi-line flexbox, the line no longer fills the vertical space,
so the line (with just 1 item in it) can be aligned with
<code>align-content</code>.</p>
<div><pre><code>&lt;div style="<strong>display: flex; flex-flow: row wrap; align-content: center;</strong>"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Content.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<h3 id="method-6-grid-content">Method 6: grid content</h3>
<p>Sanity: ★★★★☆</p>
<p>Grid was even later. Alignment became simpler.</p>
<div><pre><code>&lt;div style="<strong>display: grid; align-content: center;</strong>"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Content.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<h3 id="method-7-grid-cell">Method 7: grid cell</h3>
<p>Sanity: ★★★★☆</p>
<p>Note the subtle difference from the previous one:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>align-content</code> centers the <em>cell</em> to the
<em>container</em>.</li>
<li><code>align-items</code> centers the <em>content</em> to the
<em>cell</em> while the <em>cell</em> stretches to fit the
<em>container</em>.</li>
</ul>
<div><pre><code>&lt;div style="<strong>display: grid; align-items: center;</strong>"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Content.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<p>There seems to be many ways to do the same thing.</p>
<h3 id="method-8-auto-margin">Method 8: auto-margin</h3>
<p>Sanity: ★★★☆☆</p>
<p>In flow layout, <code>margin:auto</code> centers horizontally, but
not vertically. Flexbox and grid do not share this absurdity.</p>
<div><pre><code>&lt;div style="<strong>display: grid;</strong>"&gt;
  &lt;div style="<strong>margin-block: auto;</strong>"&gt;
    Content.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<p>Still, it puzzled me why margin was designed to also control
alignment.</p>
<h3 id="method-9-this-post-in-2024">Method 9: this post in 2024</h3>
<p>Sanity: ★★★★★</p>
<p>Why didn’t browsers add this in the first place?</p>
<div><pre><code>&lt;div style="<strong>align-content: center;</strong>"&gt;
  &lt;code&gt;align-content&lt;/code&gt; just works!
&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<p>The table cell from the <a href="#method-1-table-cell">Method 1</a>,
like this method, also doesn’t require a content wrapper (it requires a
table wrapper, though). We’re back to square one!</p>
<h3 id="summary">Summary</h3>
<p>All vertical centering methods in this <a href="https://codepen.io/byo-books/pen/Porpmab?editors=1000">codepen</a>.
Know other methods? Feel free to <a href="https://build-your-own.org/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection#3b51487b594e52575f1642544e4916544c551554495c">tell me</a>.</p>
<h2 id="going-2-dimensional">Going 2-dimensional</h2>
<p>Is there a <strong>single property</strong> for <em>horizontal</em>
align? What’s the counterpart of <code>align-content</code>? Let’s take
a look at various alignment properties:</p>
<table>
<caption>Table: alignment properties in different layouts</caption>
<colgroup>
<col>
<col>
<col>
<col>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th>flow</th>
<th>flexbox</th>
<th>grid</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><code>&nbsp;&nbsp;align-content</code></td>
<td>block axis</td>
<td>cross axis (line)</td>
<td>block axis (grid)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>justify-content</code></td>
<td>no effect</td>
<td>main axis</td>
<td>inline axis (grid)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>&nbsp;&nbsp;align-items</code></td>
<td>no effect</td>
<td>cross axis (item)</td>
<td>block axis (cell)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>justify-items</code></td>
<td>no effect</td>
<td>no effect</td>
<td>inline axis (cell)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h3 id="background-css-axis-terminology">Background: CSS axis
terminology</h3>
<p>The <em>block axis</em> is usually <em>vertical</em>, and the
<em>inline axis</em> is <em>horizontal</em>. These terms are needed
because <a href="https://build-your-own.org/visual_css/2p40_box_model.html#:~:text=Logical%20properties">vertical
<code>writing-mode</code></a> is a thing, so <strong>block axis and
inline axis are relative to the text direction</strong>. This is similar
to how <em>main axis</em> and <em>cross axis</em> are relative to the
flexbox item direction.</p>

<svg version="1.1" id="svg1" viewBox="0 0 385.51181 143.62206" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
  <defs id="defs1">
    <clipPath clipPathUnits="userSpaceOnUse" id="clipPath3">
      <path d="M 0,0.028 H 289.105 V 107.716 L 0,107.716 Z" clip-rule="evenodd" id="path3"></path>
    </clipPath>
  </defs>
  <g id="g1">
    <g id="g2">
      <path id="path2" d="M 0,107.716 H 289.106 V 0.028 L 0,0.028 Z" style="fill:#ffffff;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:none" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)" clip-path="url(#clipPath3)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g3">
      <path id="path4" d="M 41.102,19.842 H 19.843 v 42.52 h 42.519 v -42.52 z" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g4">
      <path id="path5" d="M 19.843,70.866 H 68.4" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
      <path id="path6" d="m 68.031,73.7 5.67,-2.834 -5.67,-2.835 z" style="fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:none" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g6">
      <text id="text6" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,1.3333333,26.457333,39.346047)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" y="0" id="tspan6">inline axis</tspan></text>
    </g>
    <g id="g7">
      <path id="path7" d="M 70.866,62.362 V 13.804" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
      <path id="path8" d="m 73.701,14.173 -2.835,-5.67 -2.835,5.67 z" style="fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:none" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g8">
      <text id="text8" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,104.27733,60.472714)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan8">b</tspan></text>
      <text id="text9" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,104.27733,67.200714)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan9">l</tspan></text>
      <text id="text10" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,104.27733,73.928714)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan10">o</tspan></text>
      <text id="text11" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,104.27733,80.618047)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan11">c</tspan></text>
      <text id="text12" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,104.27733,87.346047)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan12">k</tspan></text>
      <text id="text13" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,104.27733,100.80071)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan13">a</tspan></text>
      <text id="text14" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,104.27733,107.52871)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan14">x</tspan></text>
      <text id="text15" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,104.27733,114.21805)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan15">i</tspan></text>
      <text id="text16" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,104.27733,120.94605)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan16">s</tspan></text>
    </g>
    <g id="g16">
      <path id="path16" d="M 25.512,53.858 H 56.693" style="fill:none;stroke:#666666;stroke-width:2.8346;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g17">
      <path id="path17" d="M 25.512,45.354 H 56.693" style="fill:none;stroke:#666666;stroke-width:2.8346;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g18">
      <path id="path18" d="M 25.512,36.85 H 43.228" style="fill:none;stroke:#666666;stroke-width:2.8346;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
      <path id="path19" d="M 42.661,41.102 48.189,36.85 42.661,32.598 Z" style="fill:#666666;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:none" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g19">
      <path id="path20" d="M 120.472,19.842 H 99.213 v 42.52 h 42.519 v -42.52 z" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g20">
      <path id="path21" d="m 101.679,70.866 h 48.557" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
      <path id="path22" d="m 102.047,68.031 -5.669,2.835 5.669,2.834 z" style="fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:none" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g22">
      <text id="text22" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,1.3333333,132.284,39.346047)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" y="0" id="tspan22">block axis</tspan></text>
    </g>
    <g id="g23">
      <path id="path23" d="M 150.236,62.362 V 13.804" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
      <path id="path24" d="m 153.071,14.173 -2.835,-5.67 -2.834,5.67 z" style="fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:none" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g24">
      <text id="text24" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,210.104,60.472714)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan24">i</tspan></text>
      <text id="text25" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,210.104,67.200714)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan25">n</tspan></text>
      <text id="text26" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,210.104,73.928714)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan26">l</tspan></text>
      <text id="text27" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,210.104,80.618047)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan27">i</tspan></text>
      <text id="text28" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,210.104,87.346047)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan28">n</tspan></text>
      <text id="text29" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,210.104,94.072714)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan29">e</tspan></text>
      <text id="text30" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,210.104,107.52871)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan30">a</tspan></text>
      <text id="text31" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,210.104,114.21805)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan31">x</tspan></text>
      <text id="text32" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,210.104,120.94605)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan32">i</tspan></text>
      <text id="text33" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,210.104,127.67271)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan33">s</tspan></text>
    </g>
    <g id="g33">
      <path id="path33" d="M 133.228,25.511 V 56.692" style="fill:none;stroke:#666666;stroke-width:2.8346;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g34">
      <path id="path34" d="M 124.724,56.692 V 25.511" style="fill:none;stroke:#666666;stroke-width:2.8346;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g35">
      <path id="path35" d="M 116.22,56.692 V 41.81" style="fill:none;stroke:#666666;stroke-width:2.8346;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
      <path id="path36" d="m 120.472,42.377 -4.252,-5.527 -4.251,5.527 z" style="fill:#666666;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:none" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g36">
      <path id="path37" d="m 188.957,59.499 h 0.029 c -0.34,0 -0.68,-0.085 -0.964,-0.255 -0.283,-0.171 -0.51,-0.397 -0.68,-0.681 -0.17,-0.283 -0.255,-0.623 -0.255,-0.964 v -10.403 0 c 0,-0.34 0.085,-0.68 0.255,-0.963 0.17,-0.284 0.397,-0.511 0.68,-0.681 0.284,-0.17 0.624,-0.255 0.964,-0.255 h 7.54 v 0 c 0.34,0 0.68,0.085 0.964,0.255 0.283,0.17 0.51,0.397 0.68,0.681 0.17,0.283 0.255,0.623 0.255,0.963 v 10.432 -0.029 0 c 0,0.341 -0.085,0.681 -0.255,0.964 -0.17,0.284 -0.397,0.51 -0.68,0.681 -0.284,0.17 -0.624,0.255 -0.964,0.255 z" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g37">
      <text id="text37" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,1.3333333,253.60667,78.123381)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan37">1</tspan></text>
    </g>
    <g id="g38">
      <path id="path38" d="m 226.29,59.527 h 0.028 c -0.425,0 -0.85,-0.113 -1.19,-0.312 -0.369,-0.227 -0.652,-0.51 -0.879,-0.879 -0.199,-0.34 -0.312,-0.765 -0.312,-1.19 v -9.439 -0.029 c 0,-0.397 0.113,-0.822 0.312,-1.162 0.227,-0.369 0.51,-0.652 0.879,-0.879 0.34,-0.198 0.765,-0.312 1.19,-0.312 h 9.439 0.029 c 0.397,0 0.822,0.114 1.162,0.312 0.369,0.227 0.652,0.51 0.879,0.879 0.198,0.34 0.312,0.765 0.312,1.162 v 9.496 -0.028 0 c 0,0.425 -0.114,0.85 -0.312,1.19 -0.227,0.369 -0.51,0.652 -0.879,0.879 -0.34,0.199 -0.765,0.312 -1.162,0.312 z" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g39">
      <text id="text39" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,1.3333333,304.62933,78.086047)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan39">3</tspan></text>
    </g>
    <g id="g40">
      <path id="path40" d="m 203.613,59.527 h 0.028 c -0.425,0 -0.85,-0.113 -1.191,-0.312 -0.368,-0.227 -0.652,-0.51 -0.878,-0.879 -0.199,-0.34 -0.312,-0.765 -0.312,-1.19 v -9.439 -0.029 c 0,-0.397 0.113,-0.822 0.312,-1.162 0.226,-0.369 0.51,-0.652 0.878,-0.879 0.341,-0.198 0.766,-0.312 1.191,-0.312 h 15.08 0.029 c 0.396,0 0.822,0.114 1.162,0.312 0.368,0.227 0.652,0.51 0.879,0.879 0.198,0.34 0.311,0.765 0.311,1.162 l -0.028,9.496 0.028,-0.028 v 0 c 0,0.425 -0.113,0.85 -0.311,1.19 -0.227,0.369 -0.511,0.652 -0.879,0.879 -0.34,0.199 -0.766,0.312 -1.162,0.312 z" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g41">
      <text id="text41" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,1.3333333,278.17333,78.086047)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan41">2</tspan></text>
    </g>
    <g id="g42">
      <path id="path42" d="m 184.252,70.866 h 65.565" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
      <path id="path43" d="m 249.449,73.7 5.669,-2.834 -5.669,-2.835 z" style="fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:none" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g43">
      <text id="text43" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,1.3333333,245.66933,39.346047)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" y="0" id="tspan43">main axis</tspan></text>
    </g>
    <g id="g44">
      <path id="path44" d="m 189.439,42.519 h 0.029 c -0.425,0 -0.851,-0.113 -1.191,-0.312 -0.368,-0.226 -0.652,-0.51 -0.879,-0.878 -0.198,-0.341 -0.311,-0.766 -0.311,-1.191 V 30.699 30.67 c 0,-0.397 0.113,-0.822 0.311,-1.162 0.227,-0.368 0.511,-0.652 0.879,-0.879 0.34,-0.198 0.766,-0.311 1.191,-0.311 h 12.274 0.028 c 0.397,0 0.822,0.113 1.162,0.311 0.369,0.227 0.652,0.511 0.879,0.879 0.198,0.34 0.312,0.765 0.312,1.162 v 9.496 -0.028 0 c 0,0.425 -0.114,0.85 -0.312,1.191 -0.227,0.368 -0.51,0.652 -0.879,0.878 -0.34,0.199 -0.765,0.312 -1.162,0.312 z" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g45">
      <text id="text45" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,1.3333333,257.38533,100.76338)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan45">4</tspan></text>
    </g>
    <g id="g46">
      <path id="path46" d="m 215.433,19.842 h -31.181 v 42.52 h 62.362 v -42.52 z" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:3.40152, 2.55114;stroke-dashoffset:0;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g47">
      <path id="path47" d="M 255.118,62.362 V 13.804" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
      <path id="path48" d="m 257.953,14.173 -2.835,-5.67 -2.835,5.67 z" style="fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:none" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g48">
      <text id="text48" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,349.94667,60.472714)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan48">c</tspan></text>
      <text id="text49" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,349.94667,67.200714)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan49">r</tspan></text>
      <text id="text50" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,349.94667,73.928714)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan50">o</tspan></text>
      <text id="text51" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,349.94667,80.618047)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan51">s</tspan></text>
      <text id="text52" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,349.94667,87.346047)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan52">s</tspan></text>
      <text id="text53" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,349.94667,100.80071)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan53">a</tspan></text>
      <text id="text54" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,349.94667,107.52871)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan54">x</tspan></text>
      <text id="text55" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,349.94667,114.21805)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan55">i</tspan></text>
      <text id="text56" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(0,1.3333333,-1.3333333,0,349.94667,120.94605)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan56">s</tspan></text>
    </g>
    <g id="g56">
      <text id="text57" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,1.3333333,26.457333,14.816714)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" y="0" id="tspan57">text direction (writing-mode)</tspan></text>
    </g>
    <g id="g57">
      <text id="text58" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,1.3333333,245.66933,14.816714)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" y="0" id="tspan58">flexbox direction</tspan></text>
    </g>
    <g id="g58">
      <path id="path58" d="M 14.173,90.708 H 274.961" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g59">
      <path id="path59" d="M 172.913,104.881 V 5.669" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,143.62205)"></path>
    </g>
  </g>
</svg>
<h3 id="on-naming-things">On naming things</h3>
<p>From the names of properties we can infer how CSS is designed:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>align-*</code> is mostly vertical, while
<code>justify-*</code> is mostly horizontal.</li>
<li><code>*-content</code> and <code>*-items</code> control different
levels of objects?</li>
</ul>
<p><code>justify-content</code> is the counterpart of
<code>align-content</code>, which is handy in grid layout but has no
effect in flow layout. The <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/place-content"><code>place-content</code>
shorthand</a> sets both.</p>
<h3 id="align-vs.-justify">“Align” vs.&nbsp;“justify”</h3>

<p>Why do “align” and “justify” refer to axes in CSS? Is
<code>justify-*</code> inspired by text justification? It’s chaotic,
considering there’s also
<code>text-<span>align</span>: <span>justify</span></code>.</p>
<p>Usually when people say “align”, they mean the <em>placement</em> of
a single object, while “justify” means the <em>distribution</em> of
multiple objects.</p>
<p>While in CSS, both <code>justify-*</code> and <code>align-*</code>
are like text justification, because they accept values like
<code>space-between</code>; they just mean different axes!</p>
<p><strong>How to memorize</strong>: Text justification is horizontal,
so is <code>justify-*</code>.</p>
<h3 id="content-vs.-items">“Content” vs.&nbsp;“items”</h3>
<p>In flexbox, “content” and “items” are confusing:</p>
<ul>
<li>Main axis: <code>justify-content</code> controls items, while
<code>justify-items</code> has no effect.</li>
<li>Cross axis: differences between single-line and multi-line
modes.</li>
</ul>
<svg version="1.1" id="svg1" viewBox="0 0 385.51181 128.50394" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
  <defs id="defs1">
    <clipPath clipPathUnits="userSpaceOnUse" id="clipPath3">
      <path d="M 0,0.028 H 289.105 V 96.377 L 0,96.377 Z" clip-rule="evenodd" id="path3"></path>
    </clipPath>
  </defs>
  <g id="g1">
    <g id="g2">
      <path id="path2" d="M 0,96.377 H 289.106 V 0.027 H 0 Z" style="fill:#ffffff;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:none" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)" clip-path="url(#clipPath3)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g3">
      <path id="path4" d="M 187.087,96.377 V -0.001" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g4">
      <path id="path5" d="m 214.016,45.353 h -21.26 V 73.7 h 42.52 V 45.353 Z" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:3.40152, 2.55114;stroke-dashoffset:0;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g5">
      <path id="path6" d="m 209.764,48.188 h -14.173 v 22.677 h 28.346 V 48.188 Z" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g6">
      <path id="path7" d="M 201.26,70.865 V 48.188" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g7">
      <path id="path8" d="M 209.764,70.865 V 48.188" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g8">
      <path id="path9" d="m 195.591,59.527 h 28.346" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g9">
      <path id="path10" d="m 262.205,45.353 h -21.26 V 73.7 h 42.52 V 45.353 Z" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:3.40152, 2.55114;stroke-dashoffset:0;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g10">
      <path id="path11" d="M 266.457,48.188 H 252.283 V 70.865 H 280.63 V 48.188 Z" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g11">
      <path id="path12" d="M 257.953,70.865 V 48.188" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g12">
      <path id="path13" d="M 266.457,70.865 V 48.188" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g13">
      <path id="path14" d="M 252.283,59.527 H 280.63" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g14">
      <path id="path15" d="m 214.016,5.668 h -21.26 v 28.347 h 42.52 V 5.668 Z" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:3.40152, 2.55114;stroke-dashoffset:0;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g15">
      <path id="path16" d="M 214.016,8.503 H 195.591 V 31.18 h 36.85 V 8.503 Z" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g16">
      <path id="path17" d="M 215.433,31.18 V 8.503" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g17">
      <path id="path18" d="m 195.591,19.842 h 36.85" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g18">
      <path id="path19" d="m 262.205,5.668 h -21.26 v 28.347 h 42.52 V 5.668 Z" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:3.40152, 2.55114;stroke-dashoffset:0;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g19">
      <path id="path20" d="M 262.205,8.503 H 243.78 V 31.18 h 36.85 V 8.503 Z" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g20">
      <path id="path21" d="M 263.622,31.18 V 8.503" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g21">
      <path id="path22" d="m 243.78,19.842 h 36.85" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g22">
      <path id="path23" d="m 199.361,28.346 h 0.028 c -0.17,0 -0.34,-0.057 -0.482,-0.114 -0.142,-0.085 -0.283,-0.227 -0.368,-0.368 -0.057,-0.142 -0.114,-0.312 -0.114,-0.482 v -3.77 -0.029 c 0,-0.141 0.057,-0.312 0.114,-0.453 0.085,-0.142 0.226,-0.284 0.368,-0.369 0.142,-0.056 0.312,-0.113 0.482,-0.113 l 9.439,0.028 0.029,-0.028 c 0.141,0 0.312,0.057 0.453,0.113 0.142,0.085 0.284,0.227 0.369,0.369 0.056,0.141 0.113,0.312 0.113,0.453 v 3.827 -0.028 0 c 0,0.17 -0.057,0.34 -0.113,0.482 -0.085,0.141 -0.227,0.283 -0.369,0.368 -0.141,0.057 -0.312,0.114 -0.453,0.114 z" style="fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g23">
      <path id="path24" d="m 199.361,17.007 h 0.028 c -0.17,0 -0.34,-0.057 -0.482,-0.113 -0.142,-0.086 -0.283,-0.227 -0.368,-0.369 -0.057,-0.142 -0.114,-0.312 -0.114,-0.482 v -3.77 -0.028 c 0,-0.142 0.057,-0.312 0.114,-0.454 0.085,-0.142 0.226,-0.283 0.368,-0.368 0.142,-0.057 0.312,-0.114 0.482,-0.114 l 6.605,0.029 0.028,-0.029 c 0.142,0 0.312,0.057 0.454,0.114 0.141,0.085 0.283,0.226 0.368,0.368 0.057,0.142 0.113,0.312 0.113,0.454 v 3.826 -0.028 0 c 0,0.17 -0.056,0.34 -0.113,0.482 -0.085,0.142 -0.227,0.283 -0.368,0.369 -0.142,0.056 -0.312,0.113 -0.454,0.113 z" style="fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g24">
      <path id="path25" d="m 218.721,28.346 h 0.029 c -0.085,0 -0.17,-0.029 -0.256,-0.057 -0.056,-0.057 -0.113,-0.114 -0.17,-0.17 -0.028,-0.085 -0.056,-0.17 -0.056,-0.255 v -4.734 0 c 0,-0.085 0.028,-0.17 0.056,-0.255 0.057,-0.057 0.114,-0.114 0.17,-0.17 0.086,-0.029 0.171,-0.057 0.256,-0.057 h 1.899 v 0 c 0.085,0 0.17,0.028 0.255,0.057 0.057,0.056 0.113,0.113 0.17,0.17 0.028,0.085 0.057,0.17 0.057,0.255 v 4.762 -0.028 0 c 0,0.085 -0.029,0.17 -0.057,0.255 -0.057,0.056 -0.113,0.113 -0.17,0.17 -0.085,0.028 -0.17,0.057 -0.255,0.057 z" style="fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g25">
      <path id="path26" d="m 219.203,17.007 h 0.028 c -0.17,0 -0.34,-0.057 -0.481,-0.113 -0.142,-0.086 -0.284,-0.227 -0.369,-0.369 -0.057,-0.142 -0.113,-0.312 -0.113,-0.482 v -3.77 -0.028 c 0,-0.142 0.056,-0.312 0.113,-0.454 0.085,-0.142 0.227,-0.283 0.369,-0.368 0.141,-0.057 0.311,-0.114 0.481,-0.114 l 6.605,0.029 0.029,-0.029 c 0.141,0 0.311,0.057 0.453,0.114 0.142,0.085 0.284,0.226 0.369,0.368 0.056,0.142 0.113,0.312 0.113,0.454 v 3.826 -0.028 0 c 0,0.17 -0.057,0.34 -0.113,0.482 -0.085,0.142 -0.227,0.283 -0.369,0.369 -0.142,0.056 -0.312,0.113 -0.453,0.113 z" style="fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g26">
      <path id="path27" d="m 250.384,28.346 v 0 c -0.141,0 -0.312,-0.057 -0.453,-0.114 -0.142,-0.085 -0.284,-0.227 -0.369,-0.368 -0.056,-0.142 -0.113,-0.312 -0.113,-0.482 v -3.77 -0.029 c 0,-0.141 0.057,-0.312 0.113,-0.453 0.085,-0.142 0.227,-0.284 0.369,-0.369 0.141,-0.056 0.312,-0.113 0.453,-0.113 l 9.468,0.028 0.028,-0.028 c 0.142,0 0.312,0.057 0.454,0.113 0.142,0.085 0.283,0.227 0.368,0.369 0.057,0.141 0.114,0.312 0.114,0.453 v 3.827 -0.028 0 c 0,0.17 -0.057,0.34 -0.114,0.482 -0.085,0.141 -0.226,0.283 -0.368,0.368 -0.142,0.057 -0.312,0.114 -0.454,0.114 z" style="fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g27">
      <path id="path28" d="m 275.414,28.346 h 0.029 c -0.086,0 -0.171,-0.029 -0.256,-0.057 -0.056,-0.057 -0.113,-0.114 -0.17,-0.17 -0.028,-0.085 -0.056,-0.17 -0.056,-0.255 v -4.734 0 c 0,-0.085 0.028,-0.17 0.056,-0.255 0.057,-0.057 0.114,-0.114 0.17,-0.17 0.085,-0.029 0.17,-0.057 0.256,-0.057 h 1.899 v 0 c 0.085,0 0.17,0.028 0.255,0.057 0.057,0.056 0.113,0.113 0.17,0.17 0.028,0.085 0.057,0.17 0.057,0.255 v 4.762 -0.028 0 c 0,0.085 -0.029,0.17 -0.057,0.255 -0.057,0.056 -0.113,0.113 -0.17,0.17 -0.085,0.028 -0.17,0.057 -0.255,0.057 z" style="fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g28">
      <path id="path29" d="m 270.227,17.007 h 0.028 c -0.17,0 -0.34,-0.057 -0.482,-0.113 -0.142,-0.086 -0.283,-0.227 -0.368,-0.369 -0.057,-0.142 -0.114,-0.312 -0.114,-0.482 v -3.77 -0.028 c 0,-0.142 0.057,-0.312 0.114,-0.454 0.085,-0.142 0.226,-0.283 0.368,-0.368 0.142,-0.057 0.312,-0.114 0.482,-0.114 l 6.605,0.029 0.028,-0.029 c 0.142,0 0.312,0.057 0.454,0.114 0.141,0.085 0.283,0.226 0.368,0.368 0.057,0.142 0.114,0.312 0.114,0.454 v 3.826 -0.028 0 c 0,0.17 -0.057,0.34 -0.114,0.482 -0.085,0.142 -0.227,0.283 -0.368,0.369 -0.142,0.056 -0.312,0.113 -0.454,0.113 z" style="fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g29">
      <path id="path30" d="m 253.219,17.007 h 0.028 c -0.17,0 -0.34,-0.057 -0.482,-0.113 -0.141,-0.086 -0.283,-0.227 -0.368,-0.369 -0.057,-0.142 -0.114,-0.312 -0.114,-0.482 v -3.77 -0.028 c 0,-0.142 0.057,-0.312 0.114,-0.454 0.085,-0.142 0.227,-0.283 0.368,-0.368 0.142,-0.057 0.312,-0.114 0.482,-0.114 l 6.605,0.029 0.028,-0.029 c 0.142,0 0.312,0.057 0.454,0.114 0.142,0.085 0.283,0.226 0.368,0.368 0.057,0.142 0.114,0.312 0.114,0.454 v 3.826 -0.028 0 c 0,0.17 -0.057,0.34 -0.114,0.482 -0.085,0.142 -0.226,0.283 -0.368,0.369 -0.142,0.056 -0.312,0.113 -0.454,0.113 z" style="fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g30">
      <path id="path31" d="M 111.969,45.353 H 90.709 V 73.7 h 42.519 V 45.353 Z" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:3.40152, 2.55114;stroke-dashoffset:0;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g31">
      <path id="path32" d="m 94.961,70.865 v 0 c -0.255,0 -0.482,-0.057 -0.709,-0.198 -0.227,-0.114 -0.397,-0.284 -0.51,-0.51 C 93.6,69.93 93.543,69.703 93.543,69.448 V 63.779 63.75 c 0,-0.255 0.057,-0.482 0.199,-0.708 0.113,-0.227 0.283,-0.397 0.51,-0.511 0.227,-0.141 0.454,-0.198 0.709,-0.198 h 5.669 0.028 c 0.255,0 0.482,0.057 0.709,0.198 0.227,0.114 0.397,0.284 0.51,0.511 0.142,0.226 0.199,0.453 0.199,0.708 v 5.698 0 0 c 0,0.255 -0.057,0.482 -0.199,0.709 -0.113,0.226 -0.283,0.396 -0.51,0.51 -0.227,0.141 -0.454,0.198 -0.709,0.198 z" style="fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g32">
      <path id="path33" d="m 106.299,70.865 v 0 c -0.255,0 -0.482,-0.057 -0.708,-0.198 -0.227,-0.114 -0.397,-0.284 -0.511,-0.51 -0.141,-0.227 -0.198,-0.454 -0.198,-0.709 V 63.779 63.75 c 0,-0.255 0.057,-0.482 0.198,-0.708 0.114,-0.227 0.284,-0.397 0.511,-0.511 0.226,-0.141 0.453,-0.198 0.708,-0.198 h 14.173 0.029 c 0.255,0 0.482,0.057 0.708,0.198 0.227,0.114 0.397,0.284 0.511,0.511 0.141,0.226 0.198,0.453 0.198,0.708 v 5.698 0 0 c 0,0.255 -0.057,0.482 -0.198,0.709 -0.114,0.226 -0.284,0.396 -0.511,0.51 -0.226,0.141 -0.453,0.198 -0.708,0.198 z" style="fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g33">
      <path id="path34" d="m 95.414,59.527 h 0.029 c -0.341,0 -0.652,-0.085 -0.964,-0.256 -0.284,-0.17 -0.51,-0.396 -0.681,-0.68 -0.17,-0.312 -0.255,-0.623 -0.255,-0.964 v -7.568 0 c 0,-0.34 0.085,-0.652 0.255,-0.964 0.171,-0.283 0.397,-0.51 0.681,-0.68 0.312,-0.17 0.623,-0.255 0.964,-0.255 h 18.907 v 0 c 0.34,0 0.652,0.085 0.963,0.255 0.284,0.17 0.511,0.397 0.681,0.68 0.17,0.312 0.255,0.624 0.255,0.964 v 7.597 -0.029 0 c 0,0.341 -0.085,0.652 -0.255,0.964 -0.17,0.284 -0.397,0.51 -0.681,0.68 -0.311,0.171 -0.623,0.256 -0.963,0.256 z" style="fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g34">
      <path id="path35" d="M 160.157,45.353 H 138.898 V 73.7 h 42.519 V 45.353 Z" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:3.40152, 2.55114;stroke-dashoffset:0;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g35">
      <path id="path36" d="m 151.654,70.865 v 0 c -0.256,0 -0.482,-0.057 -0.709,-0.198 -0.227,-0.114 -0.397,-0.284 -0.51,-0.51 -0.142,-0.227 -0.199,-0.454 -0.199,-0.709 V 63.779 63.75 c 0,-0.255 0.057,-0.482 0.199,-0.708 0.113,-0.227 0.283,-0.397 0.51,-0.511 0.227,-0.141 0.453,-0.198 0.709,-0.198 h 5.669 0.028 c 0.255,0 0.482,0.057 0.709,0.198 0.227,0.114 0.397,0.284 0.51,0.511 0.142,0.226 0.199,0.453 0.199,0.708 v 5.698 0 0 c 0,0.255 -0.057,0.482 -0.199,0.709 -0.113,0.226 -0.283,0.396 -0.51,0.51 -0.227,0.141 -0.454,0.198 -0.709,0.198 z" style="fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g36">
      <path id="path37" d="m 162.992,70.865 v 0 c -0.255,0 -0.482,-0.057 -0.709,-0.198 -0.226,-0.114 -0.396,-0.284 -0.51,-0.51 -0.142,-0.227 -0.198,-0.454 -0.198,-0.709 V 63.779 63.75 c 0,-0.255 0.056,-0.482 0.198,-0.708 0.114,-0.227 0.284,-0.397 0.51,-0.511 0.227,-0.141 0.454,-0.198 0.709,-0.198 h 14.173 0.029 c 0.255,0 0.482,0.057 0.708,0.198 0.227,0.114 0.397,0.284 0.511,0.511 0.141,0.226 0.198,0.453 0.198,0.708 v 5.698 0 0 c 0,0.255 -0.057,0.482 -0.198,0.709 -0.114,0.226 -0.284,0.396 -0.511,0.51 -0.226,0.141 -0.453,0.198 -0.708,0.198 z" style="fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g37">
      <path id="path38" d="m 157.776,59.527 h 0.029 c -0.34,0 -0.652,-0.085 -0.964,-0.256 -0.284,-0.17 -0.51,-0.396 -0.68,-0.68 -0.17,-0.312 -0.255,-0.623 -0.255,-0.964 v -7.568 0 c 0,-0.34 0.085,-0.652 0.255,-0.964 0.17,-0.283 0.396,-0.51 0.68,-0.68 0.312,-0.17 0.624,-0.255 0.964,-0.255 h 18.907 v 0 c 0.34,0 0.652,0.085 0.964,0.255 0.283,0.17 0.51,0.397 0.68,0.68 0.17,0.312 0.255,0.624 0.255,0.964 v 7.597 -0.029 0 c 0,0.341 -0.085,0.652 -0.255,0.964 -0.17,0.284 -0.397,0.51 -0.68,0.68 -0.312,0.171 -0.624,0.256 -0.964,0.256 z" style="fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:evenodd;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g38">
      <path id="path39" d="M 85.039,96.377 V -0.001" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g39">
      <path id="path40" d="M 0,79.369 H 289.134" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g40">
      <path id="path41" d="M 0,39.684 H 289.134" style="fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:0.85038;stroke-linecap:butt;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;stroke-dasharray:none;stroke-opacity:1" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,-1.3333333,0,128.50394)"></path>
    </g>
    <g id="g41">
      <text id="text41" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,1.3333333,120.94533,14.81727)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" y="0" id="tspan41">flexbox</tspan></text>
    </g>
    <g id="g42">
      <text id="text42" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,1.3333333,4.9893333,53.519937)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" y="0" id="tspan42">justify-content</tspan></text>
    </g>
    <g id="g43">
      <text id="text43" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,1.3333333,4.9893333,106.43327)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" y="0" id="tspan43">justify-items</tspan></text>
    </g>
    <g id="g44">
      <text id="text44" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,1.3333333,257.008,14.81727)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:10.006px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" y="0" id="tspan44">grid</tspan></text>
    </g>
    <g id="g45">
      <text id="text45" xml:space="preserve" transform="matrix(1.3333333,0,0,1.3333333,172.68667,113.4626)"><tspan style="font-variant:normal;font-weight:normal;font-size:25.994px;font-family:'Ubuntu Mono';writing-mode:lr-tb;fill:#000000;fill-opacity:1;fill-rule:nonzero;stroke:none" x="0" y="0" id="tspan45">?</tspan></text>
    </g>
  </g>
</svg>
<p><strong>Conclusion</strong>: “items” is for stuff that can be aligned
<em>individually</em>. On the main axis, flex items cannot be aligned
individually, so it’s “content”.</p>
<h2 id="why-is-css-so-confusing">Why is CSS so confusing?</h2>
<p>Even if we ignore historical artifacts, CSS is still too confusing
for most of us. It has hundreds of poorly named properties, each can
influence the outcome in unintuitive ways.</p>
<h3 id="software-projects-gone-haywire">Software projects gone
haywire</h3>
<p>This is a case study in software design paradigms:</p>
<ul>
<li>Unix: <strong>orthogonal, composable primitives</strong> that can be
reasoned about independently.</li>
<li>CSS (<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40130549"><strong>C</strong>entral
<strong>S</strong>oftware <strong>S</strong>ystem</a>): just amend the
software with <strong>more and more knobs</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p>The early WWW was just linked documents. CSS was created to
<em>style</em> documents without regard to <em>layout</em>. Over time,
CSS gained some random layout features without a coherent vision.</p>
<p>Often you have many ways to do something in CSS, but not the right
feature to do it sanely. This entire post is about a new feature for
saner vertical align, and the horizontal axis is still different.</p>
<!-- In CSS, there are no alignment primitives;
vertical and horizontal axes may require different solutions depending on the container layout. -->
<p>In contrast, libreoffice follows the paradigm of orthogonal,
composable primitives:</p>
<ul>
<li>Alignment is unified. No point that vertical is different from
horizontal.</li>
<li>Unified alignment is possible because “align” and “justify” are
orthogonal, not mixed up.
<ul>
<li>“Align” is a property of the <em>container</em>.</li>
<li>“Justify” is a property of the <em>paragraph</em>.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>“Align” and “justify” can be combined in any way.</li>
</ul>


<h3 id="css-mastery-takes-effort">CSS mastery takes effort!</h3>
<p>Still, <strong>rules can be learned</strong>, even for something as
incomprehensible as CSS. You just need to pay extra attention instead of
relying on trial-and-error and copy-pasting. I’m creating a <a href="https://build-your-own.org/visual_css/">visual guide</a> to the hard parts of CSS. Check it
out!</p>
<p><a href="https://build-your-own.org/visual_css/">
  <img width="200" src="https://build-your-own.org/visual_css/img/book_css_cover_1800.png" alt="A Visual Guide To CSS">
</a>
</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Expert Mind [pdf] (2006) (125 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://personal.utdallas.edu/~otoole/CGS2301_S09/15_expert.pdf</link>
            <guid>41282574</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 14:24:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://personal.utdallas.edu/~otoole/CGS2301_S09/15_expert.pdf">https://personal.utdallas.edu/~otoole/CGS2301_S09/15_expert.pdf</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41282574">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[TomWright/dasel: Select, put and delete data from JSON, TOML, YAML, XML and CSV (323 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/TomWright/dasel</link>
            <guid>41282495</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 14:11:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/TomWright/dasel">https://github.com/TomWright/dasel</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41282495">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">dasel</h2><a id="user-content-dasel" aria-label="Permalink: dasel" href="#dasel"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/74935debba0eb2c6ce3d5b318677865ccc6bd21ee9b365ab8be3e92a5a057045/68747470733a2f2f6261646765732e616c65656e34322e636f6d2f7372632f676974626f6f6b5f312e737667" alt="Gitbook" data-canonical-src="https://badges.aleen42.com/src/gitbook_1.svg"></a>
<a href="https://goreportcard.com/report/github.com/TomWright/dasel/v2" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/053c608060f6014a174ceffdf5aeda709744ca50f48fe6eddb11f608ada5ef01/68747470733a2f2f676f7265706f7274636172642e636f6d2f62616467652f6769746875622e636f6d2f546f6d5772696768742f646173656c2f7632" alt="Go Report Card" data-canonical-src="https://goreportcard.com/badge/github.com/TomWright/dasel/v2"></a>
<a href="https://pkg.go.dev/github.com/tomwright/dasel/v2" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/ff0d25709999ad838c57871cb33da8de2a2d8bc9c6ec31d61409993f4a5e51f8/68747470733a2f2f706b672e676f2e6465762f62616467652f6769746875622e636f6d2f746f6d7772696768742f646173656c" alt="PkgGoDev" data-canonical-src="https://pkg.go.dev/badge/github.com/tomwright/dasel"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/TomWright/dasel/workflows/Test/badge.svg"><img src="https://github.com/TomWright/dasel/workflows/Test/badge.svg" alt="Test"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/TomWright/dasel/workflows/Build/badge.svg"><img src="https://github.com/TomWright/dasel/workflows/Build/badge.svg" alt="Build"></a>
<a href="https://codecov.io/gh/TomWright/dasel" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/00d7b33a9066c396c007a281e508f104666a032ddce2a91dbe0fa60d1900b393/68747470733a2f2f636f6465636f762e696f2f67682f546f6d5772696768742f646173656c2f6272616e63682f6d61737465722f67726170682f62616467652e737667" alt="codecov" data-canonical-src="https://codecov.io/gh/TomWright/dasel/branch/master/graph/badge.svg"></a>
<a href="https://github.com/avelino/awesome-go"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/522920003893b259cdbe58547f34408775b7b65bd699e11092999f8019b3cc07/68747470733a2f2f617765736f6d652e72652f6d656e74696f6e65642d62616467652e737667" alt="Mentioned in Awesome Go" data-canonical-src="https://awesome.re/mentioned-badge.svg"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/8cd5a8d2dfb97526959ac5aeb704dfdd82c00914774dceca021d8c5e4b47a477/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f646f776e6c6f6164732f546f6d5772696768742f646173656c2f746f74616c"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/8cd5a8d2dfb97526959ac5aeb704dfdd82c00914774dceca021d8c5e4b47a477/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f646f776e6c6f6164732f546f6d5772696768742f646173656c2f746f74616c" alt="GitHub All Releases Downloads" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/github/downloads/TomWright/dasel/total"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/849994f935fae4543ec782cae31aebd55f084b1395a187eef419898cd8874bce/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f6c6963656e73652f546f6d5772696768742f646173656c"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/849994f935fae4543ec782cae31aebd55f084b1395a187eef419898cd8874bce/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f6c6963656e73652f546f6d5772696768742f646173656c" alt="GitHub License" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/github/license/TomWright/dasel"></a>
<a href="https://github.com/TomWright/dasel/releases/latest"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/bf9f5ced9856fbb06746de1efacfe57f3690bd8da2a0457fc7600a669a76f85b/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f762f7461672f546f6d5772696768742f646173656c3f6c6162656c3d6c617465737425323072656c65617365" alt="GitHub tag (latest by date)" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/github/v/tag/TomWright/dasel?label=latest%20release"></a>
<a href="https://formulae.brew.sh/formula/dasel" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/89b197585198a89659cba53f60b93ba12aa04eb402c8b318af1d5af87aa8e13f/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f686f6d65627265772f762f646173656c" alt="Homebrew tag (latest by date)" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/homebrew/v/dasel"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Dasel (short for data-selector) allows you to query and modify data structures using selector strings.</p>
<p dir="auto">Comparable to <a href="https://github.com/stedolan/jq">jq</a> / <a href="https://github.com/kislyuk/yq">yq</a>, but supports JSON, YAML, TOML, XML and CSV with zero runtime dependencies.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">One tool to rule them all</h2><a id="user-content-one-tool-to-rule-them-all" aria-label="Permalink: One tool to rule them all" href="#one-tool-to-rule-them-all"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Say good bye to learning new tools just to work with a different data format.</p>
<p dir="auto">Dasel uses a standard selector syntax no matter the data format. This means that once you learn how to use dasel you immediately have the ability to query/modify any of the supported data types without any additional tools or effort.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/TomWright/dasel/blob/master/update_kubernetes.gif"><img src="https://github.com/TomWright/dasel/raw/master/update_kubernetes.gif" alt="Update Kubernetes Manifest" data-animated-image=""></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Table of contents</h2><a id="user-content-table-of-contents" aria-label="Permalink: Table of contents" href="#table-of-contents"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="#dasel">Dasel</a></li>
<li><a href="#one-tool-to-rule-them-all">One tool to rule them all</a></li>
<li><a href="#quickstart">Quickstart</a></li>
<li><a href="#completion">Completion</a></li>
<li><a href="#issue-vs-discussion">Issue vs discussion</a></li>
<li><a href="#features">Features</a></li>
<li><a href="#table-of-contents">Table of contents</a></li>
<li><a href="#documentation">Documentation</a></li>
<li><a href="#playground">Playground</a></li>
<li><a href="#benchmarks">Benchmarks</a></li>
<li><a href="#pre-commit">Pre-Commit</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Quickstart</h2><a id="user-content-quickstart" aria-label="Permalink: Quickstart" href="#quickstart"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Dasel is available on <a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/installation#homebrew" rel="nofollow">homebrew</a>, <a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/installation#asdf" rel="nofollow">ASDF</a>, <a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/installation#scoop" rel="nofollow">scoop</a>, <a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/installation#docker" rel="nofollow">docker</a>, <a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/installation#nix" rel="nofollow">Nix</a> or as <a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/installation#manual" rel="nofollow">compiled binaries</a> from the <a href="https://github.com/TomWright/dasel/releases/latest">latest release</a>.</p>

<p dir="auto">You can also install a <a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/installation#development-version" rel="nofollow">development version</a> with:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="go install github.com/tomwright/dasel/v2/cmd/dasel@master"><pre>go install github.com/tomwright/dasel/v2/cmd/dasel@master</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">For more information see the <a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/installation" rel="nofollow">installation documentation</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Select</h3><a id="user-content-select" aria-label="Permalink: Select" href="#select"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="echo '{&quot;name&quot;: &quot;Tom&quot;}' | dasel -r json 'name'
&quot;Tom&quot;"><pre><span>echo</span> <span><span>'</span>{"name": "Tom"}<span>'</span></span> <span>|</span> dasel -r json <span><span>'</span>name<span>'</span></span>
<span><span>"</span>Tom<span>"</span></span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">See <a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/commands/select" rel="nofollow">select documentation</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Convert json to yaml</h3><a id="user-content-convert-json-to-yaml" aria-label="Permalink: Convert json to yaml" href="#convert-json-to-yaml"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="echo '{&quot;name&quot;: &quot;Tom&quot;}' | dasel -r json -w yaml
name: Tom"><pre><span>echo</span> <span><span>'</span>{"name": "Tom"}<span>'</span></span> <span>|</span> dasel -r json -w yaml
name: Tom</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">See <a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/commands/select" rel="nofollow">select documentation</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Put</h3><a id="user-content-put" aria-label="Permalink: Put" href="#put"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="echo '{&quot;name&quot;: &quot;Tom&quot;}' | dasel put -r json -t string -v 'contact@tomwright.me' 'email'
{
  &quot;email&quot;: &quot;contact@tomwright.me&quot;,
  &quot;name&quot;: &quot;Tom&quot;
}"><pre><span>echo</span> <span><span>'</span>{"name": "Tom"}<span>'</span></span> <span>|</span> dasel put -r json -t string -v <span><span>'</span>contact@tomwright.me<span>'</span></span> <span><span>'</span>email<span>'</span></span>
{
  <span><span>"</span>email<span>"</span></span>: <span><span>"</span>contact@tomwright.me<span>"</span></span>,
  <span><span>"</span>name<span>"</span></span>: <span><span>"</span>Tom<span>"</span></span>
}</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">See <a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/commands/put" rel="nofollow">put documentation</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Delete</h3><a id="user-content-delete" aria-label="Permalink: Delete" href="#delete"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="echo '{
  &quot;email&quot;: &quot;contact@tomwright.me&quot;,
  &quot;name&quot;: &quot;Tom&quot;
}' | dasel delete -r json '.email'
{
  &quot;name&quot;: &quot;Tom&quot;
}"><pre><span>echo</span> <span><span>'</span>{</span>
<span>  "email": "contact@tomwright.me",</span>
<span>  "name": "Tom"</span>
<span>}<span>'</span></span> <span>|</span> dasel delete -r json <span><span>'</span>.email<span>'</span></span>
{
  <span><span>"</span>name<span>"</span></span>: <span><span>"</span>Tom<span>"</span></span>
}</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">See <a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/commands/delete" rel="nofollow">delete documentation</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Completion</h2><a id="user-content-completion" aria-label="Permalink: Completion" href="#completion"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If you want to use completion from the terminal you can do the following (using zsh in this example):</p>
<p dir="auto">Add the following to <code>~/.zshrc</code> and reload your terminal.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="export fpath=(~/zsh/site-functions $fpath)
mkdir -p ~/zsh/site-functions
dasel completion zsh > ~/zsh/site-functions/_dasel
compinit"><pre><span>export</span> fpath=(~/zsh/site-functions <span>$fpath</span>)
mkdir -p <span>~</span>/zsh/site-functions
dasel completion zsh <span>&gt;</span> <span>~</span>/zsh/site-functions/_dasel
compinit</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Pre-Commit</h2><a id="user-content-pre-commit" aria-label="Permalink: Pre-Commit" href="#pre-commit"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Add <code>dasel</code> hooks to <code>.pre-commit-config.yaml</code> file</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="- repo: https://github.com/TomWright/dasel
  rev: v1.25.1
  hooks:
    - id: dasel-validate"><pre>- <span>repo</span>: <span>https://github.com/TomWright/dasel</span>
  <span>rev</span>: <span>v1.25.1</span>
  <span>hooks</span>:
    - <span>id</span>: <span>dasel-validate</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">for a native execution of dasel, or use:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>dasel-validate-docker</code> pre-commit hook for executing dasel using the official <a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/installation#docker" rel="nofollow">Docker images</a></li>
<li><code>dasel-validate-bin</code> pre-commit hook for executing dasel using the official <a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/installation" rel="nofollow">binary</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Issue vs Discussion</h2><a id="user-content-issue-vs-discussion" aria-label="Permalink: Issue vs Discussion" href="#issue-vs-discussion"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">I have enabled <a href="https://github.com/TomWright/dasel/discussions">discussions</a> on this repository.</p>
<p dir="auto">I am aware there may be some confusion when deciding where you should communicate when reporting issues, asking questions or raising feature requests so this section aims to help us align on that.</p>
<p dir="auto">Please <a href="https://github.com/TomWright/dasel/issues">raise an issue</a> if:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>You find a bug.</li>
<li>You have a feature request and can clearly describe your request.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Please <a href="https://github.com/TomWright/dasel/discussions">open a discussion</a> if:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>You have a question.</li>
<li>You're not sure how to achieve something with dasel.</li>
<li>You have an idea but don't quite know how you would like it to work.</li>
<li>You have achieved something cool with dasel and want to show it off.</li>
<li>Anything else!</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Features</h2><a id="user-content-features" aria-label="Permalink: Features" href="#features"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/commands/select" rel="nofollow">Query/select data from structured data files</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/commands/put" rel="nofollow">Update data in structured data files</a>.</li>
<li>Create data files.</li>
<li><a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/supported-file-formats" rel="nofollow">Supports multiple data formats/types</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/examples/change-file-format" rel="nofollow">Convert between data formats/types</a>.</li>
<li>Uses a <a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/functions/selector-overview" rel="nofollow">standard query/selector syntax</a> across all data formats.</li>
<li>Zero runtime dependencies.</li>
<li><a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/installation" rel="nofollow">Available on Linux, Mac and Windows</a>.</li>
<li>Available to <a href="https://pkg.go.dev/github.com/tomwright/dasel/v2" rel="nofollow">import and use in your own projects</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/installation#docker" rel="nofollow">Run via Docker</a>.</li>
<li><a href="#benchmarks">Faster than jq/yq</a>.</li>
<li><a href="#pre-commit">Pre-commit hooks</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Documentation</h2><a id="user-content-documentation" aria-label="Permalink: Documentation" href="#documentation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The official dasel docs can be found at <a href="https://daseldocs.tomwright.me/" rel="nofollow">daseldocs.tomwright.me</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Playground</h2><a id="user-content-playground" aria-label="Permalink: Playground" href="#playground"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">You can test out dasel commands using the <a href="https://dasel.tomwright.me/" rel="nofollow">playground</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Source code for the playground can be found at <a href="https://github.com/TomWright/daselplayground">github.com/TomWright/daselplayground</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Benchmarks</h2><a id="user-content-benchmarks" aria-label="Permalink: Benchmarks" href="#benchmarks"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">In my tests dasel has been up to 3x faster than jq and 15x faster than yq.</p>
<p dir="auto">See the <a href="https://github.com/TomWright/dasel/blob/master/benchmark/README.md">benchmark directory</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Stargazers over time</h2><a id="user-content-stargazers-over-time" aria-label="Permalink: Stargazers over time" href="#stargazers-over-time"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://starchart.cc/TomWright/dasel" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/241ecdaf4591881c33b0b52437e8d9305552820a91043ceac4a1dfa271c2d23f/68747470733a2f2f7374617263686172742e63632f546f6d5772696768742f646173656c2e737667" alt="Stargazers over time" data-canonical-src="https://starchart.cc/TomWright/dasel.svg"></a></p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>