<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 22:00:07 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[FCC: Telcos must now tell you when your personal info is stolen (126 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theregister.com/2024/02/12/fcc_gets_tough_on_telcos/</link>
            <guid>39349389</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 19:44:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/02/12/fcc_gets_tough_on_telcos/">https://www.theregister.com/2024/02/12/fcc_gets_tough_on_telcos/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39349389">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="body">
<p>The FCC's updated reporting requirements mean telcos in America will have just seven days to officially disclose that a criminal has broken into their systems.</p>
<p>After releasing a <a href="https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2024/02/12/2024-01667/data-breach-reporting-requirements" rel="nofollow">proposed</a> rule in early January and giving the industry 30 days to respond, the FCC's <a href="https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2024/02/12/2024-01667/data-breach-reporting-requirements" rel="nofollow">final rule</a> was published today. It solidifies what the agency proposed a little more than a month ago, and what was teased in early 2022 when FCC chairwoman Jessica Rosenworcel <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2022/01/13/fcc_data_rules/">drafted initial changes</a> to the commission's 16-year old security "breach" reporting duties.</p>
<p>Along with requiring that attacks are reported to the FCC within seven days of a telco discovering them, the same deadline now exists to report any data leaks to the FBI and US Secret Service as well. As the FCC planned, the new rule also eliminates the mandatory seven-day waiting period for reporting break-ins to consumers.</p>

    

<p>The FCC now "requires carriers to notify customers of breaches of covered data without unreasonable delay … and in no case more than 30 days following reasonable determination of a breach."&nbsp;</p>

        


        

<p>"Reasonable determination" of a data blurt is further defined as "when the carrier has information indicating that it is more likely than not that there was a breach" and "does not mean reaching a conclusion regarding every fact surrounding a data security incident that may constitute a breach."</p>
<p>In other words, if customers are affected then they had better be notified post-haste.</p>

        

<p>The FCC has additionally extended the scope of data exposure types that telecom customers must be notified of. Prior to the passage of the new rule customers only had to be told if Customer proprietary network information (CPNI) was exposed to the world.&nbsp;</p>
<p>CPNI, for those unfamiliar, is all the data a cellular carrier retains about phone calls and service agreements - i.e., the data that appears on a bill. Personal identifiable information (PII) wasn't included in previous reporting requirements, meaning carriers whose customer records were exposed, didn't have to tell customers if CPNI wasn't accessed.&nbsp;</p>
<p>"Without an FCC rule requiring breach notifications for the above categories of PII, there would be no requirement in Federal law that telecommunications carriers report non-CPNI breaches to their customers," the FCC said of the new rule.&nbsp;</p>

        

<p>Starting now, names, government ID numbers, data used for authentication purposes, email addresses/passwords and biometric data is all included in the FCC's reporting requirements. Dissociated data, if linkable to an individual using other data criminals accessed during a break-in, has to be reported as well.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The new rules add an exception for customer notifications as well. If a carrier can "determine that no harm to customers is reasonably likely to occur," then it doesn't have to inform subscribers of the incident.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Along with increased reporting rules for the content of data leaks, the new rule also expands the FCC's definition of "breach" to include "inadvertent access, use or disclosure of customer information."&nbsp;</p>
<p>Inadvertent, much like the exposure of 63k employee records <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/02/06/verizon_internal_privacy_breach/">Verizon reported</a> last week.</p>
<p>Luckily for Verizon it won't have to worry about falling foul of the new rules, which don't go into effect until March 13.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Telecom relay service providers, which provide assistance for hearing-impaired phone users, will be covered under the new rule as well.&nbsp;</p>
<h3>Here a breach, there a breach, everywhere a breach report</h3>
<p>The FCC's updated directive is the latest in a string of federal agency breach reporting requirements, with rules passed by the <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/10/31/ftc_30_day_breach_disclosure/">FTC</a> and <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/07/26/sec_reporting_security/">SEC</a> set to go into effect later this year, and federal contractors getting their own set of <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/02/08/us_tech_industry_changes/">newly-proposed IT security breach reporting rules</a> too.&nbsp;</p>
<p>As has been the case with those other rules, the FCC's requirements, when formally proposed last month, ran up against opposition.&nbsp;</p>
<ul>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/01/18/cyber_safety_review_board_rethink/">Future of America's Cyber Safety Review Board hangs in balance amid calls for rethink</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/02/02/ftc_blackbaud_settlement/">Blackbaud settles with FTC after that IT breach exposed millions of people's info</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/02/12/infosec_news_roundup/">Mon Dieu! Nearly half the French population have data nabbed in massive breach</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/04/11/in_brief_security/">40% of IT security pros say they've been told not to report a data leak</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Per the FCC, the Cellular Telecommunications Industry Association raised an objection on several grounds, including that the FCC rule would create a system of dual jurisdiction between the FCC and FTC once the latter's rule goes into effect.&nbsp;</p>
<p>As has been the case with objections raised to the wide and varying data leak reporting requirements now enacted by the US federal government, the FCC said it finds industry objections "unpersuasive."&nbsp;</p>
<p>Congress has even raised objections to some of the new reporting rules, with bills <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/02/01/senate_resolution_to_undo_sec/">introduced</a> in the House and Senate to overturn the SEC's four-day reporting deadline for data break-ins that could have a "material" effect on a company's finances and, by extension, its investors.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The feds were generally dismissive of the complaints, with the Biden administration saying it would veto any attempts to undo the SEC's reporting rules.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Industry figures, and congressional representatives, have pointed to the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency's <a href="https://www.cisa.gov/topics/cyber-threats-and-advisories/information-sharing/cyber-incident-reporting-critical-infrastructure-act-2022-circia" rel="nofollow">forthcoming</a> rules for security breach requirements as a potential inter-agency standard. It's not clear whether CISA's rules, a draft of which is expected to be published next month, will harmonize standards or otherwise eliminate the need for companies covered under multiple rules to make multiple reports.&nbsp;®</p>                                
                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[US rail safety legislation stalled one year after East Palestine Ohio disaster (154 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wlbt.com/2024/02/02/rail-safety-legislation-still-stalled-one-year-after-east-palestine-disaster/</link>
            <guid>39349366</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 19:43:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wlbt.com/2024/02/02/rail-safety-legislation-still-stalled-one-year-after-east-palestine-disaster/">https://www.wlbt.com/2024/02/02/rail-safety-legislation-still-stalled-one-year-after-east-palestine-disaster/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39349366">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><p>(InvestigateTV) — It’s been one year since <a href="https://www.cleveland19.com/2024/02/01/east-palestine-1-year-later-part-1-crisis-starts-with-spark/">a train derailment in Ohio</a> thrust the issue of rail safety back into the national spotlight. Congressional lawmakers immediately introduced legislation designed to protect Americans and hold rail companies accountable. But the longest-serving woman in Congressional history says little has changed since the disaster.</p><p><a href="https://kaptur.house.gov/">U.S. Representative Marcy Kaptur</a>, D-Ohio, talked with InvestigateTV on Capitol Hill in advance of the February 3rd anniversary of the <a href="https://www.cleveland19.com/news/derailed-east-palestine/">crisis in East Palestine</a>, saying of the rail industry, “It’s like they’re a power unto themselves. And they’re very, very - in my opinion - destructive to the country in the way they’re behaving.”</p><p>Kaptur, who’s held Congressional office since 1983, pulled no punches as she talked about the ripple effects of the massive incident that forced the evacuation of more than 1,000 people last February. The evacuation came after a Norfolk Southern train carrying hazardous materials derailed in eastern Ohio near the Pennsylvania border, with toxic chemicals contaminating the air, water, and soil all around the area.</p><figure><p><img alt="A photo from the NTSB investigative file shows the aftermath of a massive 2023 train..." loading="lazy" src="https://gray-wlbt-prod.cdn.arcpublishing.com/resizer/v2/LSZAOIG64FGQNNTF6HFUERCXEQ.jpg?auth=9481a340eb1edd3339d29b73f7b1bfead78386d8e5c9c57e6815b30d0df8bb0b&amp;width=980&amp;height=551&amp;smart=true" width="980" height="551" srcset="https://gray-wlbt-prod.cdn.arcpublishing.com/resizer/v2/LSZAOIG64FGQNNTF6HFUERCXEQ.jpg?auth=9481a340eb1edd3339d29b73f7b1bfead78386d8e5c9c57e6815b30d0df8bb0b&amp;width=540&amp;height=303&amp;smart=true 540w, https://gray-wlbt-prod.cdn.arcpublishing.com/resizer/v2/LSZAOIG64FGQNNTF6HFUERCXEQ.jpg?auth=9481a340eb1edd3339d29b73f7b1bfead78386d8e5c9c57e6815b30d0df8bb0b&amp;width=720&amp;height=404&amp;smart=true 720w, https://gray-wlbt-prod.cdn.arcpublishing.com/resizer/v2/LSZAOIG64FGQNNTF6HFUERCXEQ.jpg?auth=9481a340eb1edd3339d29b73f7b1bfead78386d8e5c9c57e6815b30d0df8bb0b&amp;width=980&amp;height=551&amp;smart=true 980w, https://gray-wlbt-prod.cdn.arcpublishing.com/resizer/v2/LSZAOIG64FGQNNTF6HFUERCXEQ.jpg?auth=9481a340eb1edd3339d29b73f7b1bfead78386d8e5c9c57e6815b30d0df8bb0b&amp;width=1300&amp;height=730&amp;smart=true 1300w"></p><figcaption><span>A photo from the NTSB investigative file shows the aftermath of a massive 2023 train derailment in East Palestine, Ohio</span><span>(NTSB)</span></figcaption></figure><p>Within weeks congressional lawmakers proposed bipartisan <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/118th-congress/senate-bill/576/all-info">bills in the Senate</a> and <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/118th-congress/house-bill/1674">House</a> designed to improve rail safety. Those bills included language mandating two-person crews for certain freight trains, updating inspection regulations and bumping up fines for companies that break safety laws.</p><p>The Senate version of the legislation initially made progress, moving through committee with provisions added. But one year after East Palestine, both bills are at a standstill, with no changes made since May.</p><p>Asked why the proposed legislation hasn’t moved forward, Kaptur blamed the rail industry.</p><p>“I think because they have a whole lot of power,” Kaptur said. “They have a lot of political power. And in the committees that are responsible, they do enough to block it.”</p><figure><p><img alt="Congresswoman Marcy Kaptur, D-Ohio, talks about rail safety in her office on Capitol Hill" loading="lazy" src="https://gray-wlbt-prod.cdn.arcpublishing.com/resizer/v2/3KO4ZFMGZBDXNHCMS5E3Q3SYVU.jpg?auth=81b19b7262110de2c1e9634d98cb587be93146e6ea728b941f1bf2ee16f16fcb&amp;width=980&amp;height=735&amp;smart=true" width="980" height="735" srcset="https://gray-wlbt-prod.cdn.arcpublishing.com/resizer/v2/3KO4ZFMGZBDXNHCMS5E3Q3SYVU.jpg?auth=81b19b7262110de2c1e9634d98cb587be93146e6ea728b941f1bf2ee16f16fcb&amp;width=540&amp;height=405&amp;smart=true 540w, https://gray-wlbt-prod.cdn.arcpublishing.com/resizer/v2/3KO4ZFMGZBDXNHCMS5E3Q3SYVU.jpg?auth=81b19b7262110de2c1e9634d98cb587be93146e6ea728b941f1bf2ee16f16fcb&amp;width=720&amp;height=540&amp;smart=true 720w, https://gray-wlbt-prod.cdn.arcpublishing.com/resizer/v2/3KO4ZFMGZBDXNHCMS5E3Q3SYVU.jpg?auth=81b19b7262110de2c1e9634d98cb587be93146e6ea728b941f1bf2ee16f16fcb&amp;width=980&amp;height=735&amp;smart=true 980w, https://gray-wlbt-prod.cdn.arcpublishing.com/resizer/v2/3KO4ZFMGZBDXNHCMS5E3Q3SYVU.jpg?auth=81b19b7262110de2c1e9634d98cb587be93146e6ea728b941f1bf2ee16f16fcb&amp;width=1300&amp;height=975&amp;smart=true 1300w"></p><figcaption><span>Congresswoman Marcy Kaptur, D-Ohio, talks about rail safety in her office on Capitol Hill</span><span>(Scotty Smith, InvestigateTV)</span></figcaption></figure><p>That sentiment, was echoed by <a href="https://www.brown.senate.gov/">U.S. Senator Sherrod Brown</a>, D-Ohio, who sponsored the Rail Safety Act in the Senate and held a virtual press conference this week to talk about the stalled legislation. Both Brown and Kaptur said lobbying groups and major rail companies continue to oppose the legislation, with the industry putting profits over public safety.</p><p>The <a href="https://www.aar.org/">Association of American Railroads</a>, the lobbying group representing the nation’s major rail companies, told InvestigateTV in a written statement, “Railroads and policymakers share the same goal of making the rail network even safer. The industry is dedicated to advancing safety through our own initiatives and in collaboration with policymakers. Despite some allegations, railroads have never been opposed to the Railway Safety Act (RSA) and have had open, productive conversations with policymakers including Rep. Kaptur’s staff.”</p><p>Although the railroad lobby has repeatedly been unavailable for on-camera interviews with InvestigateTV, the organization has been clear in <a href="https://www.aar.org/news/aar-statement-on-senate-commerce-rail-safety-act-vote/">materials on its website</a> that it sees challenges in the legislation, specifically with the proposed crew staffing mandates and inspection requirements.</p><p>“They don’t think that they need anybody but themselves,” Kaptur said. “And look at the country. They’re not meeting the mark.”</p><h3>Other major rail issues also remain unsolved despite national attention</h3><p>Congresswoman Kaptur said the industry is also failing when it comes to fixing another major rail problem brought into sharp focus last year: blocked crossings.</p><p>The issue, highlighted in an <a href="https://www.investigatetv.com/2023/04/26/rail-profits-soar-blocked-crossings-force-kids-crawl-under-trains-get-school/">InvestigateTV/ProPublica series</a>, found stopped trains delaying first responders, cutting off communities and forcing children in Hammond, Indiana to do the unthinkable: crawl over and under trains just to get to school.</p><figure data-video-asset="60c4a43e-4ef0-4813-8531-766a410a7875"><figcaption><span>An InvestigateTV/ProPublica investigation into blocked crossings affects changes. Video captured in Hammond, Indiana sheds light on a larger issue in the U.S.</span></figcaption></figure><p>Last May the congresswoman officially logged the series <a href="https://www.congress.gov/118/crec/2023/05/11/169/80/CREC-2023-05-11.pdf">into the Congressional Record</a>, saying “Railroads of America, wake up.”</p><p>“I was trying to get it out to other Americans so that they can speak up from their parts of the country,” Kaptur said. “All of these places have had accidents. Frankly, I’ve had deaths in my district and the behavior of the companies is that you may as well make them kings.”</p><p>During the interview, and in Kaptur’s time on the House floor, the congresswoman urged <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefing-room/statements-releases/2024/01/31/fact-sheet-one-year-after-train-derailment-biden-harris-administration-continues-to-support-people-in-east-palestine-ohio-and-nearby-communities-and-hold-norfolk-southern-accountable/#:~:text=In%20February%2C%20President%20Biden%20will,and%20hold%20Norfolk%20Southern%20accountable.">President Biden</a> and <a href="https://www.transportation.gov/meet-secretary/secretary-pete-buttigieg">Transportation Secretary Pete Buttigieg</a> to get rail stakeholders together to work to fix systematic rail problems that exist from coast to coast, saying the billions allocated in infrastructure funding provide a pivotal moment for action.</p><p>“We need visionary planning. They don’t give it to us. I would like those CEOs - I’ll invite them, I’ll buy pizza, we’ll spend the whole weekend - let them roll up their sleeves. I want to see how good they are. They shouldn’t feel so good about the legacy they’re leaving to their children and grandchildren because it’s non-functional. It’s not going to be able to meet the needs of the country going forward. Shame on them,” she said.</p><p>The Association of American Railroads said in a press release it has and will continue to “engage in conversations about how legislation can improve safety, encourage innovation and keep the supply chain moving”. The organization also pointed to a <a href="https://www.railwayage.com/freight/class-i/promises-made-promises-kept/?RAchannel=home">number of steps</a> it says the rail industry has independently taken to improve safety in the wake of the East Palestine disaster, including training thousands of first responders in communities across the country and doubling the number of people who can access a specialized system that gives real-time information about what rail cars are carrying.</p><p><i>Copyright 2024 Gray Media Group, Inc. All rights reserved.</i></p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I applied for a software role at FedEx and was asked to take a personality test (196 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://old.reddit.com/r/mildlyinfuriating/comments/1ap1345/i_applied_for_a_software_role_at_fedex_and_was/</link>
            <guid>39346870</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 16:34:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/mildlyinfuriating/comments/1ap1345/i_applied_for_a_software_role_at_fedex_and_was/">https://old.reddit.com/r/mildlyinfuriating/comments/1ap1345/i_applied_for_a_software_role_at_fedex_and_was/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39346870">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>I was instructed to pick whether the character in the image represented "me" or "not me". The images were bizarre and kind of funny to look through. But the infuriating part is how blatantly prejudicial this type of thing is as a candidate pre-screen (or as any step before or aftering hiring someone).</p>

<p>It wasn't disclosed as a personality test prior to getting the results at the end. I received a score across the "big 5" personality traits at the end.</p>

<p>Needless to say, the results are completely inaccurate and don't represent me at all. But fear not, it did give me some completely made up areas where I apparently have "room to grow":
* Can be taken for granted because you complete tasks without objections
* Can tolerate mediocre work from others
* May have trouble avoiding social distractions
* Prioritize meeting deadlines over work quality
* Prone to feeling stressed</p>

<p>I withdrew my application 🤷</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Developers revolt over Apple's new app store rules (115 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wired.com/story/developers-revolt-apple-dma/</link>
            <guid>39346527</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 16:11:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/developers-revolt-apple-dma/">https://www.wired.com/story/developers-revolt-apple-dma/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39346527">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-testid="ArticlePageChunks"><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>A battle for control is taking place inside iPhones across Europe. While Apple <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/apple-app-store-sideloading-europe-dma/">introduced new rules</a> that ostensibly loosen its control over the App Store, local developers are seething at the new system, which they say entrenches the power Apple already wields over their businesses. They’re now breaking into a rare open revolt, mounting pressure on lawmakers to step in.</p><p>So far, they have accused Apple’s new business terms of being “<a data-offer-url="https://proton.me/blog/apple-dma-compliance-plan-trap" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://proton.me/blog/apple-dma-compliance-plan-trap&quot;}" href="https://proton.me/blog/apple-dma-compliance-plan-trap" rel="noopener" target="_blank">abusive</a>,” “<a data-offer-url="https://newsroom.spotify.com/2024-01-26/apples-proposed-changes-reject-the-goals-of-the-dma/" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://newsroom.spotify.com/2024-01-26/apples-proposed-changes-reject-the-goals-of-the-dma/&quot;}" href="https://newsroom.spotify.com/2024-01-26/apples-proposed-changes-reject-the-goals-of-the-dma/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">extortion</a>,” and “<a data-offer-url="https://twitter.com/dhh/status/1750669170411495710" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://twitter.com/dhh/status/1750669170411495710&quot;}" href="https://twitter.com/dhh/status/1750669170411495710" rel="noopener" target="_blank">ludicrously punitive</a>.”</p><p>“Apple holds app providers ransom like the Mafia,” claims Matthias Pfau, CEO and cofounder of Tuta, an encrypted email provider. The tech giant treats iPhones as its territory, Pfau complains, tightly controlling developers’ access before taking a chunk of their profits. “Anyone wanting to provide an iOS app must pay a ransom to Apple; there’s no way around it.”</p><p>For years, Apple has rejected Tuta app updates if they include links to the company’s website, he says. Like all iOS apps, Tuta has also been unable to take in-app payments directly from its customers. Apple acts as an intermediary and charges a fee. Pfau was hoping the App Store reforms mandated by the <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/whatsapp-interoperability-messaging/">EU’s Digital Markets Act</a> (DMA) would make companies like his less tightly bound to Apple. Instead, he is left disappointed by the new terms on offer. “What they came up with is the best proof that they are massively abusing their market dominance,” he says. “Apple is basically behaving like a dictator.”</p><p>Apple was designated a “gatekeeper” under the DMA after the EU decided that the App Store acts as an important gateway between businesses and consumers. The company, along with other tech giants, has until March 7 to make a raft of changes. To avoid fines that can reach up to 20 percent of global revenue, the smartphone maker announced its new rules in late January.</p><p>The rules technically make it possible for users of its hardware to download apps from alternative app stores and also for developers to use their own payment systems—bypassing Apple’s commission.</p><p>But in order to access these new features, developers have to sign up to new business terms. Those terms include restrictions that disincentivize any developers moving away from the status quo, according to Pfau. If his company Tuta were to take advantage of the new system, iPhones would issue warnings—known by critics as “scare screens”—informing users about security risks linked to using payment systems that are not managed by Apple. From Tuta’s testing of how popups affect in-app upgrades, he estimates these warnings would dissuade 50 percent of users from proceeding with their purchase.</p><p>Additionally, although the new terms allow Pfau to make Tuta available in an alternative app store, they would also expose the company to a “core technology fee” every time it was downloaded or updated more than 1 million times in a one-year period. Pfau accepts that Tuta, which he claims has over 100,000 paying subscribers, might not have to pay this fee in the first year. “But we are growing,” he insists. “So we would definitely have to pay it within the next couple of years.”</p></div><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>For Sweden’s Spotify, the download fee is more of an immediate problem if the company were to accept Apple’s new business terms. “With our EU Apple install base in the 100 million range, this new tax on downloads and updates could skyrocket our customer acquisition costs, potentially increasing them tenfold,” Spotify CEO Daniel Ek said on X soon after Apple released its proposal. “While Apple has behaved badly for years, what they did yesterday represents a new low, even for them.”</p><p>For that reason, Spotify, like other apps, believes it has no choice but to stick with its current agreement, Ek elaborated in a call with investors last week. That means still paying commission to Apple and listing their iOS app exclusively on Apple’s App Store. “No sane developer wants to pick any of the new terms,” Ek said. Sticking with the current system doesn’t make the situation worse for companies like Spotify, he added, but it does mean they are missing out on revenues from users buying products such as audiobooks, a <a data-offer-url="https://newsroom.spotify.com/2022-09-20/with-audiobooks-launching-in-the-u-s-today-spotify-is-the-home-for-all-the-audio-you-love/" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://newsroom.spotify.com/2022-09-20/with-audiobooks-launching-in-the-u-s-today-spotify-is-the-home-for-all-the-audio-you-love/&quot;}" href="https://newsroom.spotify.com/2022-09-20/with-audiobooks-launching-in-the-u-s-today-spotify-is-the-home-for-all-the-audio-you-love/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">new</a> focus for the platform, through the company’s app. (Spotify does not sell audiobooks in their iOS app in order to avoid Apple’s commission fee.) “So some of these more innovative things that we would like to do, we’re currently restricted in doing on the iOS ecosystem.”</p><p>Apple maintains its changes are compliant with the DMA while also being necessary to protect its EU users’ devices from the security risks that, it says, are introduced by the new law. “Apple’s approach to the Digital Markets Act was guided by two simple goals: complying with the law and reducing the inevitable, increased risks the DMA creates for our EU users,” says Apple spokesperson Julien Trosdorf. “That meant creating safeguards to protect EU users to the greatest extent possible and to respond to new threats, including new vectors for malware and viruses, opportunities for scams and fraud, and challenges to ensuring apps are functional on Apple’s platforms.”</p><p>App developers don’t have much power on their own to make Apple change course. But they hope their criticism will force the European Commission, a branch of the EU’s government, to take action. After the March 7 deadline, officials are expected to assess both Apple’s proposals&nbsp;and the market’s reaction. “Now [the European Commission] must reject Apple’s proposal and even consider imposing a fine if no further improvements are made,” says Sebastiano Toffaletti, secretary general of the European DIGITAL SME Alliance, an industry group.</p><p>Andy Yen, CEO of Swiss email and cloud service Proton, is less diplomatic. “If I was the European Commission, I would probably look at this as an insult,” he says of Apple’s proposed business terms. “It’s a slap in the face.”</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Ultraviolet Myth (161 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://www.arxiv.org/abs/2402.03405</link>
            <guid>39345618</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 15:11:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://www.arxiv.org/abs/2402.03405">http://www.arxiv.org/abs/2402.03405</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39345618">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content-inner">
    
    
                
    <p><a href="http://www.arxiv.org/pdf/2402.03405.pdf">Download PDF</a>
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/html/2402.03405v1">HTML (experimental)</a></p><blockquote>
            <span>Abstract:</span>It is very common to introduce quantum physics in an historical context. Though there are advantages to this, it is a problem that many of the stories that have become central to the physics lore are mere pseudo-histories far detached from the real events. It is about time that we stop uncritically copying these stories and instead make an effort to present the development of quantum physics as it actually was. This paper deals with one of the most common myths in quantum history, the one about the ultraviolet catastrophe and how it motivated Planck's introduction of quantum physics. On closer inspection it turns out this story has the time-line completely turned on its head. The ultraviolet catastrophe was first discussed several years after Planck published his radiation law so it played no role in his motivation. Instead Planck was concerned with finding a theoretical derivation of the law for blackbody radiation. This law was first thought to be Wien's radiation law, but when new data disagreed, Planck came up with his own law that fitted the data. Planck's radiation law first came about as an elaborate fit to data and to derive it he found no other way than to use statistical mechanics and divide the energy that was to be distributed on the atomic oscillators into packages $hf$ so that he could count the number of ways to distribute this energy. Planck did not consider this a quantization, but merely a mathematical trick to be able to calculate the entropy of the oscillators.
    </blockquote>

    <!--CONTEXT-->
    
  </div><div>
      <h2>Submission history</h2><p> From: Nils-Erik Bomark [<a href="http://www.arxiv.org/show-email/d42e21c6/2402.03405">view email</a>]      <br>    <strong>[v1]</strong>
        Mon, 5 Feb 2024 14:21:07 UTC (32 KB)<br>
</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cloudflare defeats patent troll Sable at trial (777 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.cloudflare.com/cloudflare-defeats-patent-troll-sable-at-trial</link>
            <guid>39344956</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 14:14:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/cloudflare-defeats-patent-troll-sable-at-trial">https://blog.cloudflare.com/cloudflare-defeats-patent-troll-sable-at-trial</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39344956">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post"><article><p>02/12/2024</p><section><p>8 min read</p><div><figure><img src="https://blog.cloudflare.com/content/images/2024/02/image2-34-1.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1201" height="677"></figure><p>For almost seven years, <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/standing-up-to-a-dangerous-new-breed-of-patent-troll">Cloudflare has been fighting against patent trolls</a>. We’ve been doing this successfully through the efforts of our own legal team, external counsel, and the extraordinary efforts of people on the Internet looking for prior art (and getting rewarded for it) through our <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/project-jengo/">Project Jengo</a>.</p><p>While we refuse to pay trolls for their meritless claims, we’ve been happy to <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/project-jengo-2-first-three-winners/">award</a> <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/arkansas-engineer-wins-round-3-of-project-jengo-and-cloudflare-continues-to-win-at-the-patent-office/">prizes</a> to Project Jengo <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/former-rd-engineer-wins-round-2-of-project-jengo-and-cloudflare-wins-at-the-patent-office/">participants</a> who help stop the trolls through prior art that invalidates their patents or claims. Project Jengo participants helped us in the past roundly beat the patent troll <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/winning-the-blackbird-battle/">Blackbird</a> (who subsequently went out of business).</p><p>Today, we’re back to talk about yet another win thanks to a lot of work by us, our external counsel, and Project Jengo participants.</p><h3 id="sable">Sable<br></h3><p>Last Thursday, on a clear, sunny morning in Waco, Texas, a jury returned a verdict after less than two hours of deliberation. The jury found that Cloudflare did not infringe the patent asserted against Cloudflare by patent trolls Sable IP and Sable Networks. </p><p>And while that would have been enough to decide the case by itself, the jury went further and found that Sable’s old and broadly-written patent claim was invalid and never should have been granted in the first place–meaning they can no longer assert the claim against anyone else. Since Sable first sued us, we’ve invalidated significant parts of three Sable patents, hamstringing their ability to bring lawsuits against other companies. </p><p>It’s worth noting that very few lawsuits ever reach a jury. Most non-lawyers are shocked to learn that only about 1% of civil cases make it to trial, because trials are generally what they see on TV or in film. But professional litigators know that almost all cases are resolved much earlier through procedures that are much less entertaining to watch on screen: written motions, delay, or settlement. A big reason for this is that taking a case to trial–even on simple matters–is extremely costly. In patent cases, that means millions of dollars.</p><p>As we described in our first <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/project-jengo">Project Jengo blog post</a>, these costs are the threat that patent trolls rely on to extract sizable settlements out of innovative technology companies. It’s often easier for technology companies to pay a settlement rather than pay millions more in litigation costs that likely can’t be recovered even if the technology company wins. Patent trolls usually don’t want to incur the costs of going to trial either, but they typically wait for the other side to blink first and pay up–especially because the company accused of infringement is the one that faces the risk of a bad verdict and damages award. </p><p>But every once in a while the target doesn’t blink. Cloudflare’s hard fought victory, the culmination of three years of litigation, is a strong warning to all patent trolls–we will not be intimidated into playing your game. &nbsp;</p><h3 id="background">Background<br></h3><p>Let’s recap how we got here. This case began in March 2021 when Sable Networks and Sable IP filed a complaint against Cloudflare in federal court. Sable asserted around <strong>100 claims</strong> spanning <strong>four patents</strong> against multiple Cloudflare products and features. The patents relied on by Sable were filed around the turn of the century, and they addressed the hardware-based router technology of the day. More specifically, they addressed a particular type of hardware focused on “flows'' composed of multiple linked packets. This approach is not used by modern-day software-defined services delivered on the cloud, particularly not services like Cloudflare that handle traffic on a packet-by-packet basis. But that didn’t stop Sable from arguing its broadly-worded patents covered essentially all router operations, including Cloudflare’s cutting edge technology–well beyond what the asserted patent claims were ever intended to cover. </p><p>As with many patent trolls, Sable IP has never made or sold products and doesn’t employ a single person to create or design actual technology. Sable IP was created as a shell entity in 2020 to monetize the patent portfolio of Sable Networks, which itself was formed in 2006 and allegedly acquired the assets–including the patents–of Caspian Networks, a router company that had shuttered its operations. Sable IP is one of many such shell entities formed to “monetize” patents through lawyer-driven litigation campaigns. &nbsp;</p><p>Cloudflare wasn’t Sable’s only target. Sable sued a number of other companies, including Cisco, Fortinet, Check Point, SonicWall, Juniper Networks, and others, each of which eventually resolved the lawsuit against them out of court. Cloudflare took a different approach.</p><p>To kick off our fight against Sable, we launched another round of Project Jengo, crowdsourcing submissions of prior art for all of Sable’s active patents–including patents not asserted against Cloudflare–and committing a $100,000 award to be split among winners that submitted strong prior art. Dedicated readers will remember Cloudflare’s <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/the-project-jengo-saga-how-cloudflare-stood-up-to-a-patent-troll-and-won">first round of Project Jengo</a>, which helped put the notorious patent troll Blackbird out of business. We’ve received dozens of submissions since we launched this Sable-focused round of Project Jengo, and have awarded \$70,000 since 2021. We will distribute the remaining \$30,000 to winners of the Final Awards which we will announce after the official conclusion of the case per the <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/jengo/sable-rules/">Project Jengo Rules</a>. </p><p>Relying on prior art, we filed petitions for <em>inter partes </em>review to the U.S. Patent and Trademark Office (“USPTO”) seeking to invalidate Sable’s patents. The <em>inter partes</em> process is an administrative proceeding that involves filing briefs for administrative patent judges at the USPTO to determine if a patent should have been issued in the first place. In many cases it's a helpful process available to try and limit the threat of patent trolls. In May 2022, to avoid responding to one of those petitions–and to avoid the risk that its patent would be canceled altogether–Sable voluntarily canceled all of the claims asserted against Cloudflare under one of its patents. And in January 2023, we were successful in invalidating the portions of a second Sable patent that had been asserted against us. &nbsp; </p><p>Two patents down, Sable refused to give up. By December 2023, through its petitions to the USPTO and related motions before the court, Cloudflare had successfully narrowed the number of patents and claims at issue from approximately 100 claims across four, to just five claims from two patents. Then, at the pretrial conference on December 13, 2023, the court issued summary judgment in our favor on a third Sable patent. Summary judgment is a process where the court determines that an argument is so clear that no reasonable jury could rule otherwise. This further narrowed the case to a single asserted claim on a single patent–claim 25 of U.S. Patent No. 7,012,919. </p><p>Through years of hard work, we’d successfully whittled down Sable’s case from about 100 claims across four patents to <strong>just one claim of one patent</strong>. But despite all that success, the fact remained…we were heading to trial, and it can be difficult to know what a jury will decide–and what damages they may award–on heavily technical issues.</p><h3 id="trials-and-tribulations-for-sable-ip-and-sable-networks">Trials and tribulations for Sable IP and Sable Networks<br></h3><p>We weren’t just heading to trial, we were heading to the Western District of Texas. Waco, Texas, to be precise, where Sable chose to file its lawsuit. The Western District of Texas has in recent years become <a href="https://www2.law.temple.edu/10q/how-the-west-became-the-east-the-patent-litigation-explosion-in-the-western-district-of-texas/">a popular venue for patent plaintiffs,</a> as it has a reputation for being a friendly jurisdiction for patent holders. </p><p>Sable’s trial story was not compelling. On the technical merits, Sable had the unenviable task of trying to map decades-old flow-based hardware router technology onto Cloudflare’s modern, software-defined packet-by-packet architecture. They attempted to do so through a series of hand waving exercises, equating the “line cards” required by the patent to various different software and hardware used by Cloudflare, and suggesting that any flow of packets across Cloudflare’s network could be construed as the specific “micro-flows” at the center of its patent. </p><p>Beyond the technical issues, Sable’s story was simple, though not very attractive–Sable wanted money. Having acquired rights to the patents of a failed hardware company, they were seeking to “monetize” those patents to the greatest extent possible. If that meant leveraging a patent related to decades-old router hardware to sue a cloud-based service provider, so be it. And if it required leaps of logic and untethered claims that might make a toddler blush, oh well. &nbsp; </p><p>When it was our turn, we told the jury <em>our </em>story. How Cloudflare was founded to help build a better Internet by moving past old, hardware-based solutions to new, cloud-based solutions delivered through our global network. We explained the hard work put into building our network, and all the services that sit on top of it. One of our outstanding engineers described what it’s like to create a new product, working with teams of engineers, product managers, and others to bring something exciting to the market for the first time. </p><p>We drilled down into Sable’s twenty-year old patent, explaining the many reasons why the patent does not describe anything that Cloudflare actually does. Among other things, the patent requires various steps to be performed at a “line card,” and Cloudflare’s accused edge servers don’t include a single such line card. And while the patent focused on flow-based routing, Cloudflare designed its system to perform packet-by-packet inspection to protect against malicious traffic. We also explained that the patent claim asserted against Cloudflare is invalid–and never should have been issued–because it was obvious in view of the prior art and lacked the required written description. In fact, Sable’s patent covered, at best, only technology that had already been described by inventors at Nortel Networks and Lucent Technologies–leading routing technology companies at the time. &nbsp;</p><p>During closing arguments, Cloudflare’s trial lawyer made one thing clear–this case was about more than Sable or Cloudflare. The patent system was designed to foster innovation and promote the progress of science, but what Sable was doing was exactly the opposite: bringing meritless cases in an effort to turn a buck, and stifling progress in the process. That distortion and abuse of the patent system has to stop and, ultimately, only the jury had the power to end it.</p><p>To our great satisfaction, the jury answered that call. The jury’s decision did not take long. Less than two hours after leaving the courtroom to deliberate, the jury returned with a verdict that sends a message far beyond the courthouse. No infringement by Cloudflare, <em>and<strong> </strong></em>Sable’s patent is invalid.</p><figure><img src="https://blog.cloudflare.com/content/images/2024/02/E6A69D49-2943-4997-B0CA-98F98FB95A26_1_201_a.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy" width="2930" height="2198"><figcaption>The combined Cloudflare and external counsel team</figcaption></figure><h3 id="what%E2%80%99s-next">What’s next<br></h3><p>We’ll enjoy this verdict for a long time, but the hard work doesn’t stop here. Cloudflare is dedicated to rebalancing a system that is being distorted by trolls like Sable. As part of our efforts, we look forward to announcing the final awards for Project Jengo on this blog following the conclusion of the case. We’ll also plan to share additional thoughts and insights we’ve gleaned from facing down a troll at trial.</p><p>For now, we want to express our sincere gratitude to the judge and jury for the hard work they put in at trial, including the jury weighing the evidence and understanding the complex technology at issue in the case. Cloudflare is deeply grateful for the jury’s time and efforts over the past week, its careful consideration of all the facts, and for its verdict. We also again want to thank our amazing trial lawyers from Charhon Callahan Robson &amp; Garza PLLC, and The Dacus Firm. If you end up with a patent troll problem, we recommend them highly.</p></div></section><div><p>We protect<!-- --> <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/network-services/" rel="noreferrer">entire corporate networks</a>, help customers build<!-- --> <a target="_blank" href="https://workers.cloudflare.com/" rel="noreferrer">Internet-scale applications efficiently</a>, accelerate any<!-- --> <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/performance/accelerate-internet-applications/" rel="noreferrer">website or Internet application</a>,<!-- --> <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/ddos/" rel="noreferrer">ward off DDoS attacks</a>, keep<!-- --> <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/application-security/" rel="noreferrer">hackers at bay</a>, and can help you on<!-- --> <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/products/zero-trust/" rel="noreferrer">your journey to Zero Trust</a>.</p><p>Visit<!-- --> <a target="_blank" href="https://one.one.one.one/" rel="noreferrer">1.1.1.1</a> <!-- -->from any device to get started with our free app that makes your Internet faster and safer.</p><p>To learn more about our mission to help build a better Internet,<!-- --> <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/what-is-cloudflare/" rel="noreferrer">start here</a>. If you're looking for a new career direction, check out<!-- --> <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/careers" rel="noreferrer">our open positions</a>.</p></div><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/jengo">Jengo</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/sable">Sable</a></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AMD Funded a Drop-In CUDA Implementation Built on ROCm: It's Now Open-Source (777 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.phoronix.com/review/radeon-cuda-zluda</link>
            <guid>39344815</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 14:00:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/review/radeon-cuda-zluda">https://www.phoronix.com/review/radeon-cuda-zluda</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39344815">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content-bg">
						
						<!-- google_ad_section_start -->
<article>




<div>

<p>While there have been efforts by AMD over the years to make it easier to port codebases targeting NVIDIA's CUDA API to run atop HIP/ROCm, it still requires work on the part of developers. The tooling has improved such as with HIPIFY to help in auto-generating but it isn't any simple, instant, and guaranteed solution -- especially if striving for optimal performance. Over the past two years AMD has quietly been funding an effort though to bring binary compatibility so that many NVIDIA CUDA applications could run atop the AMD ROCm stack at the library level -- a drop-in replacement without the need to adapt source code. In practice for many real-world workloads, it's a solution for end-users to run CUDA-enabled software without any developer intervention. Here is more information on this "skunkworks" project that is now available as open-source along with some of my own testing and performance benchmarks of this CUDA implementation built for Radeon GPUs.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=radeon-cuda-zluda&amp;image=radeon_cuda_1_lrg" target="_blank"><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=radeon-cuda-zluda&amp;image=radeon_cuda_1_med" alt="Radeon GPU running CUDA Blender"></a></p>
<p>From several years ago you may recall <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/search/ZLUDA">ZLUDA</a> that was for <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/news/Intel-ZLUDA-CUDA-For-GPUs">enabling CUDA support on Intel graphics</a>. That open-source project aimed to provide <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/news/ZLUDA-v2-Released">a drop-in CUDA implementation on Intel graphics</a> built atop Intel oneAPI Level Zero. ZLUDA was discontinued due to private reasons but it turns out that the developer behind that (and who was also employed by Intel at the time), Andrzej Janik, was contracted by AMD in 2022 to effectively adapt ZLUDA for use on AMD GPUs with HIP/ROCm. Prior to being contracted by AMD, Intel was considering ZLUDA development. However, they ultimately turned down the idea and did not provide funding for the project.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=radeon-cuda-zluda&amp;image=radeon_cuda_2_lrg" target="_blank"><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=radeon-cuda-zluda&amp;image=radeon_cuda_2_med" alt="Radeon GPU with CUDA-Z on Linux"></a></p>
<p>Andrzej Janik spent the past two years bringing ZLUDA to Radeon GPUs and it works: many CUDA software can run on HIP/ROCm without any modifications -- or other processes... Just run the binaries as you normally would while ensuring that the ZLUDA library replacements to CUDA are loaded. For reasons unknown to me, AMD decided this year to discontinue funding the effort and not release it as any software product. But the good news was that there was a clause in case of this eventuality: Janik could open-source the work if/when the contract ended.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=radeon-cuda-zluda&amp;image=radeon_cuda_8" alt="Radeon ZLUDA Git commit"></p>
<p>Andrzej Janik reached out and provided access to the new ZLUDA implementation for AMD ROCm to allow me to test it out and benchmark it in advance of today's planned public announcement. I've been testing it out for a few days and it's been a positive experience: CUDA-enabled software indeed running atop ROCm and without any changes. Even proprietary renderers and the like working with this "CUDA on Radeon" implementation.</p>
<p>The ZLUDA implementation though isn't 100% fail-safe as NVIDIA OptiX support not being fully supported and some features such as software not using PTX assembly code isn't currently handled. But for the most part this implementation is surprisingly capable for being a single developer effort.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=radeon-cuda-zluda&amp;image=radeon_cuda_5_lrg" target="_blank"><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=radeon-cuda-zluda&amp;image=radeon_cuda_5_med" alt="Radeon ZLUDA libraries"></a></p>
<p>For those wondering about the open-source code, it's dual-licensed under either Apache 2.0 or MIT. Rust fans will be excited to know the Rust programming language is leveraged for this Radeon implementation.</p>
<p>NOTE: In my screenshots and for the past two years of development the exposed device name for Radeon GPUs via CUDA has just been "Graphics Device" rather than the actual AMD Radeon graphics adapter with ROCm. The reason for this has been due to CUDA benchmarks auto-reporting results and other software that may have automated telemetry, to avoid leaking the fact of Radeon GPU use under CUDA, it's been set to the generic "Graphics Device" string. I'm told as part of today's open-sourcing of this ZLUDA on Radeon code that the change will be in place to expose the actual Radeon graphics card string rather than the generic "Graphics Device" concealer.</p>
</div>

							


					
						</article>
						
<!-- google_ad_section_end -->
					</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Zigbee and Z-Wave are the best part of my smart home (117 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2024/02/i-was-wrong-to-ignore-zigbee-and-z-wave-theyre-the-best-part-of-my-smart-home/</link>
            <guid>39344786</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 13:58:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2024/02/i-was-wrong-to-ignore-zigbee-and-z-wave-theyre-the-best-part-of-my-smart-home/">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2024/02/i-was-wrong-to-ignore-zigbee-and-z-wave-theyre-the-best-part-of-my-smart-home/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39344786">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <header>
            <h4>
      Waggle dance for the win    —
</h4>
            
            <h2 itemprop="description">There's plenty of room for this early-aughts tech in a modern connected space.</h2>
                    </header>
        <section>
            <div itemprop="articleBody">
                                    
<figure>
  <img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/GettyImages-1214098172-800x533.jpg" alt="Hue hub in stark relief against wood desk">
      <figcaption><p><a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/GettyImages-1214098172-scaled.jpg" data-height="1707" data-width="2560">Enlarge</a> <span>/</span> Where it all started for the author, even if he didn't know it at the time.</p><p>Getty Images</p></figcaption>  </figure>

  




<!-- cache hit 322:single/related:24d60304d8a7390e2e6943022ecf83e6 --><!-- empty -->
<p>I've set up dozens of smart home gadgets across two homes and two apartments over the last five years. I have a mental list of brands I revere and brands from which nothing shall ever be purchased again. In my current abode, you can stand in one place and be subject to six different signal types bouncing around, keeping up the chatter between devices.</p>
<p>What can I say? I'm a sucker for a certain kind of preparedness and creativity. The kind that's completely irrelevant if the power goes out.</p>
<p>When I started at Ars in the summer of 2022, the next generation of smart home standards was <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2022/10/matter-and-thread-could-fix-smart-home-compatibility-but-dont-get-excited-yet/">on the way</a>. Matter, an interoperable device setup and management system, and Thread, a radio network that would provide secure, far-reaching connectivity optimized for tiny batteries. Together, they would offer a home that, while well-connected, could also work entirely inside a home network and switch between controlling ecosystems with ease. I knew this tech wouldn't show up immediately, but I thought it was a good time to start looking to the future, to leave behind the old standards and coalesce into something new.</p>
<p>Instead, <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/12/matter-was-more-of-a-nice-smart-home-concept-than-useful-reality-in-2023/">Matter and Thread are a big mess</a>, and I am now writing to tell you that I was wrong, or at least ignorant, to have ignored the good things that already existed: Zigbee and Z-Wave. I've put in my time with Wi-Fi, Bluetooth, and various brittle combinations of the two. They're useful for data-rich devices and for things that can stay plugged in. Zigbee and Z-Wave have been around, but they always seemed fidgety, obscure, and vaguely European at a glance. But here, in the year 2024, I am now an admirer of both, and I think they still have a place in our homes.</p>                                            
                                                        
<figure><img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/GettyImages-877868442-scaled.jpg" width="2560" height="1707"><figcaption><p>Getty Images</p></figcaption></figure>
<h2>Hue bulbs did a Trojan horse on me, and I am thankful</h2>
<p>Two brands have done a savvy job of incorporating <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zigbee">Zigbee</a> into their tech without making a big deal of it: Philips Hue and Ikea. Hue bulbs were, for me and many others, a first step into home automation. Back then—2018, looking at the receipts—I knew that Hue bulbs ran on their own kind of ad-hoc network, but I didn't know exactly how. All I knew was that, as time went on, the Hue bulbs proved to be the most reliable devices anywhere I set them up.</p>
<p>If the Hue bridge had power and Ethernet, and the bulbs were in anything resembling house distance of one another, they worked. They did not, like a Nest camera above a former garage, lose signal midway through an update and require a 6-foot ladder and multiple support phone calls for a reset. They did not, like a couple Tuya devices I acquired, require registering as a Canadian IoT developer to get local control (long story). I have never tried to turn on a Hue bulb, had it fail, and then start wondering if it was my router, an Amazon Web Services outage, or just a cruddy little antenna inside the thing.</p>
<p>Yes, Hue stuff is not cheap, and the Hue app would occasionally ping me about new features and holiday sales, but I could turn off notifications. There was never an important notification because nothing ever went wrong. And while I didn't know it back then, there was always the option to reset the bulbs and have them run on straight Zigbee, even if you lose some niceties, like fading and multi-bulb schemes.</p>
<p>When I got the chance to review the <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/12/homey-pro-review-a-very-particular-set-of-local-home-automation-skills/">Homey Pro</a>, I had to research and work more directly with Zigbee and its even more obscure (at least in the US) cousin, Z-Wave. The Homey team had sent me a few devices to test out with their hub, including a motion sensor and a magnetic open/close door or window sensor. I procrastinated a bit on setting them up, vaguely stressed by everything I'd read about hubs, routing, and "self-healing" networks.</p>

                                                </div>

            
            
                            <nav>Page: <span>1 <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2024/02/i-was-wrong-to-ignore-zigbee-and-z-wave-theyre-the-best-part-of-my-smart-home/2/">2</a> <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2024/02/i-was-wrong-to-ignore-zigbee-and-z-wave-theyre-the-best-part-of-my-smart-home/2/"><span>Next <span>→</span></span></a></span></nav>
            
        </section>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA['I have not seen one cent': billions stolen in wage theft from US workers (350 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2023/jun/15/wage-theft-us-workers-employees</link>
            <guid>39344770</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 13:57:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2023/jun/15/wage-theft-us-workers-employees">https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2023/jun/15/wage-theft-us-workers-employees</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39344770">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p>Jose Martinez worked for a construction contractor in New York City for six months in 2019 when he and his co-workers suddenly stopped getting paid.</p><p>Martinez said the contractor, Star Builders, initially blamed the owners of the building for not dispersing money for the project.</p><p>Martinez said he and his colleagues were eventually paid late, but the delays kept happening. The contractor came up with more excuses for the lack of payment. Eventually Martinez and several of his co-workers left after not getting paid for four weeks of work.</p><figure id="6efd3dc3-521c-45f4-8397-a905b62cf33a" data-spacefinder-role="richLink" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.RichLinkBlockElement"><gu-island name="RichLinkComponent" priority="feature" deferuntil="idle" props="{&quot;richLinkIndex&quot;:3,&quot;element&quot;:{&quot;_type&quot;:&quot;model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.RichLinkBlockElement&quot;,&quot;prefix&quot;:&quot;Related: &quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Dirty planes and high prices: US workers and passengers expect further misery as air travel rebounds&quot;,&quot;elementId&quot;:&quot;6efd3dc3-521c-45f4-8397-a905b62cf33a&quot;,&quot;role&quot;:&quot;richLink&quot;,&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2023/jun/12/us-air-travel-workers-passengers&quot;},&quot;ajaxUrl&quot;:&quot;https://api.nextgen.guardianapps.co.uk&quot;,&quot;format&quot;:{&quot;display&quot;:0,&quot;theme&quot;:0,&quot;design&quot;:10}}" config="{&quot;renderingTarget&quot;:&quot;Web&quot;,&quot;darkModeAvailable&quot;:false}"></gu-island></figure><p>“I have not seen one cent from that money that is owed yet,” added Martinez, who filed a wage theft claim with the New York state labor department in 2019 with assistance from the non-profit Make the Road New York.</p><p>“It affected me a lot because at the time, I had to start finding other work, I had to pay bills and pay rent and I didn’t have money, so I had to get loans that I eventually had to pay back once I got another job.”</p><p>The contractor, Star Builders, did not respond to multiple requests for comment.</p><p>Martinez is far from alone.</p><p>Workers in the US have an estimated $50bn-plus stolen from them every year, <a href="https://www.epi.org/publication/epidemic-wage-theft-costing-workers-hundreds/" data-link-name="in body link">according </a>to the Economic Policy Institute, surpassing all robberies, burglaries and motor vehicle thefts combined. The majority of these stolen wages are never recovered by workers.</p><p>Between 2017 to 2020, <a href="https://www.epi.org/publication/wage-theft-2021/" data-link-name="in body link">$3.24bn</a> in stolen wages were recovered by the US Department of Labor, state labor departments and attorney generals, and through class- and collective-action litigation.</p><p>Wage theft disproportionately affects lower-wage workers, women, people of color and immigrant workers, and negatively affects local economies and tax revenues.</p><p>There are numerous forms of <a href="https://www.epi.org/publication/wage-theft-2021/" data-link-name="in body link">wage theft</a>, from employers not compensating workers for time worked, violating minimum wage and overtime laws, misclassifying employees as independent contractors, not providing legally required meal breaks, confiscating worker tips, or illegally taking deductions from worker wages.</p><p>Wage-theft violators include some of the largest employers in the US; Amazon <a href="https://www.wweek.com/news/business/2022/11/17/amazon-settles-oregon-wage-theft-lawsuit/" data-link-name="in body link">paid $18m</a> in November 2022 to settle a wage-theft class-action lawsuit in Oregon, the largest in the state’s history, and <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2021/02/02/amazon-to-pay-61point7-million-in-ftc-driver-tipping-settlement-.html#:~:text=Contractors%20working%20for%20the%20Amazon,to%20customers%20in%20San%20Francisco.&amp;text=Amazon%20will%20pay%20%2461.7%20million%20to%20settle%20allegations%20by%20the,of%20tips%20received%20from%20customers." data-link-name="in body link">paid</a> a $61.7m fine in 2021 over allegations of stealing tips from Amazon Flex drivers.</p><p>According to a 2018 <a href="https://www.goodjobsfirst.org/wp-content/uploads/docs/pdfs/wagetheft_report_revised.pdf" data-link-name="in body link">report </a>by Good Jobs, between January 2000 to 2018, Walmart paid over $1.4bn in fines and settlements over wage theft violations, FedEx paid over $500m during the same period, and Bank of America paid over $380m.</p><p>Construction contractors have a <a href="https://www.constructiondive.com/news/gcs-often-excluded-from-wage-theft-liability-law-may-change/640418/" data-link-name="in body link">notorious reputation</a> for wage-theft violations, often affecting immigrant workers, and exploiting loopholes to avoid paying wage-theft claims, such as shutting down businesses and reopening under a different business filing.</p><p>Martinez wants to warn others in the sector.</p><p>“People need to be very careful with contractors, because they always say, ‘We have a lot of work for you to do’ to keep you there. They would say, ‘It’s just a matter of time, we just have to wait for the payment, it’s going to be OK,’ and so they’re always talking that way to keep people working there,” said Martinez.</p><p>“Workers shouldn’t let more than one week go by without getting their payment because they’re always going to come up with some excuse.”</p><p>Despite the state of New York’s worker protections and laws aimed at curtailing wage theft, the Center for Popular Democracy <a href="https://maketheroadny.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Coming-Up-Short_-The-State-of-Wage-Theft-Enforcement-in-NY-4_8_19.pdf" data-link-name="in body link">estimated</a> in 2019 that wage theft may affect 2.1 million workers in New York every year, exceeding $3bn annually.</p><p>Goma Yonjan Gurung has worked as a nail technician in the New York City area for 25 years, an <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2022/mar/15/new-york-nail-salon-industry-council-workers" data-link-name="in body link">industry</a> where wage theft is rampant and scantily enforced. A February 2020 <a href="http://workersunitednynj.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/Race-to-the-Bottom-FINAL.pdf" data-link-name="in body link">report</a> by the New York Nail Salon Workers Association noted 82% of workers reported experiencing wage theft at an average amount of $181 per week.</p><p>“Even though the government says the minimum wage is $15 an hour, what I know is it’s not happening for many nail technicians, including myself. In some places they pay as low as $10 an hour,” she said. “The government in the past has passed bills mandating minimum wage or time off, but what happens is it is not implemented or being practiced by employers.”</p><p>Worker advocates have criticized the state’s labor department for lack of enforcement of wage-theft violations and not recovering stolen wages from employers.</p><p>Other states, such as <a href="https://www.orlandoweekly.com/news/floridas-lack-of-a-labor-department-leaves-workers-with-limited-options-34229517?fbclid=IwAR2w8gfp_4ULwa4y43kna6_qqrp4w-NSBTIadmFVztw99ZeMVcxR-tV00IE" data-link-name="in body link">Florida</a>, do not have a state labor department to oversee the <a href="https://businessfacilities.com/florida-the-sunshine-state-is-bright-for-business/#:~:text=With%20the%20third%20largest%20workforce,which%20business%20can%20draw%20from.&amp;text=Florida%20has%20been%20ranked%20as,attractive%20place%20to%20do%20business." data-link-name="in body link">third largest workforce </a>in the US, leaving workers with fewer options to try to recover stolen wages.</p><p>A bartender in Orlando, Florida who requested to remain anonymous because they still work in the industry, said they started a new bartending job in May and pushed back when they found out their hourly wage was just a daily rate of $30, despite working eight-hour shifts.</p><p>“I reminded my manager that paying less than minimum wage was illegal, and added a link to a law firm’s page about it. He fired me,” the worker said. “Getting fired for not wanting to be paid below the already insanely low minimum wage after working in the industry for over 20 years was pretty rough.”</p><p>The worker attempted to file a complaint with the US Department of Labor and the Florida attorney general’s office but was told they only prioritize higher wage violations and never heard back after being told someone would follow up.</p><p>Rodrigo Camarena, director of the Justicia Lab, an advocacy group, said: “The process for filing a wage-theft complaint form is very onerous and cumbersome, so there’s an immediate obstacle in the process itself. But once that form is filed, it takes months if not years for the department of labor to even investigate it.” The Justicia Lab recently launched a digital tool, <a href="https://nextcity.org/features/a-new-digital-legal-tool-helps-immigrant-workers-reclaim-their-stolen-wages" data-link-name="in body link">¡Reclamo!</a>, for workers to file wage-theft claims.</p><p>Camarena said: “In the meantime, that person is going without that income that they earned potentially, and the employer isn’t being penalized in any way, so there’s a delay in enforcement and then the enforcement process also isn’t as thorough as it could be.”</p><p>New York legislators and worker groups have been pushing to pass the <a href="https://nclej.org/news/nys-failed-to-pass-sweat-bill" data-link-name="in body link">Securing Wages Earned Against Theft (Sweat) Act</a> to enforce New York’s wage-theft laws and make it more difficult for employers to avoid accountability for wage-theft violations.</p><p>“There needs to be more work at the state level, that not just holds individual employers accountable but to really hold industries accountable that are problematic and root out the ways employers get out of paying wages owed,” added Camarena.</p><p>“We need to ensure that worker rights are protected in all cases, because ultimately this issue is about the dignity of everyone.”</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Piezoelectrics enable displays to provide both audio and touch feedback (142 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://spectrum.ieee.org/piezoelectric-speakers</link>
            <guid>39343945</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 12:10:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/piezoelectric-speakers">https://spectrum.ieee.org/piezoelectric-speakers</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39343945">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-headline="Smartphone Screens Are About to Become Speakers" data-elid="2667208046" data-post-url="https://spectrum.ieee.org/piezoelectric-speakers" data-authors="Vineet Ganju" data-page-title="Smartphone Screens Are About to Become Speakers - IEEE Spectrum"><p><strong>Today’</strong><strong>s mobile-device speakers</strong> and haptic generators have several problems.
</p><p>
	The first is with the components themselves. The speakers in your smartphone and the system that gives your finger feedback when you touch a virtual button may be relatively small, but they are still big enough to limit how thin our mobile devices can get. These little components are also delicate, as you may have learned if you have dropped your phone. And they require openings in the enclosure that can admit moisture or debris.
</p><p>
	Then there is a problem with the way we perceive the sound they emit. Speakers usually sit on the sides or back of our devices. The sound is supposed to be coming from the image that our eyes see on the screen, but our ears know it’s coming from somewhere else. This perceptual dissonance limits our ability to immerse ourselves in the experience.
</p><p>
	We could solve all these problems at once if we could use the display panel itself as the source of sound and haptic feedback. The technology to do this is now available—it’s a thin piezoelectric transducer. And it’s going to be moving into mobile phones, laptops, and wearables by the end of this year.
</p><h2>Speakers today</h2><p>
	Traditional speakers function by running a current through a coil, creating a magnetic field that moves a magnet attached to the speaker cone, which in turn displaces air to create a sound wave. The speaker can be no smaller than is allowed by the size of the coil and the cone, which must be wide enough and long enough to displace a reasonable volume of air. Its mechanical durability is limited by the precision with which its small moving parts must be assembled.
</p><p>
	Haptic generators in handsets typically are linear resonant actuators, which are electrically and mechanically like speakers but are optimized to create low-frequency vibrations in a solid rather than sound waves in the air.
</p><p><img id="75945" data-rm-shortcode-id="4f2fb2bfe90b8c12442ee596165ba6b3" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" lazy-loadable="true" src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/an-illustration-of-two-devices-one-labeled-traditional-laptop-speaker-module-and-the-other-is-piezoelectric-speaker.png?id=51433420&amp;width=980" data-runner-src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/an-illustration-of-two-devices-one-labeled-traditional-laptop-speaker-module-and-the-other-is-piezoelectric-speaker.png?id=51433420&amp;width=980" width="2700" height="1800" alt="An illustration of two devices. One labeled &quot;Traditional laptop speaker module&quot; and the other is &quot;Piezoelectric speaker.&quot;"><small placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">Replacing traditional speakers with piezoelectric transducers will allow devices to be much thinner.</small><small placeholder="Add Photo Credit...">James Provost</small></p><p>
	It turns out that both sound and haptic generation can be wrung from the display of a mobile device. The display is a uniform, flat, semiflexible surface–If you tap on it with a fingernail, you can hear it vibrate. The technology to turn flat, semiflexible surfaces into loudspeakers dates to the early years of high fidelity.
</p><p>
	 In the 1950s, you could buy just the part of the speaker that converted electricity into motion—the coil and piston—and attach the piston to a wall or the panel of a cabinet. The wall or panel then vibrated—like a speaker cone—creating the air-pressure waves we perceive as sound. That idea remained a novelty, mainly because it was a do-it-yourself project with unpredictable results. Finding the right surface, mounting the driver in the right place, and powering it properly turned out to be about as easy as building a really good violin.
</p><p>
	More recently, some flat-screen TV developers have turned the screens of large-format TVs into speakers using a similar principle. They use powerful transducers to vibrate the whole display panel at audio frequencies. This delivers the goods: thin displays, no speakers. According to reviewers, the fidelity is great at midrange and high frequencies (if you want low frequencies, you’ll want a supplementary subwoofer). And the sound really does seem to be coming from the images on the screen. But these systems are expensive and require high-voltage amplifiers that consume considerable power, so they need to be shrunk before they can fit into a mobile device.
</p><h2>Enter Piezoelectrics</h2><p>
	To do the job in smaller devices you need piezoelectric transducers. These are made up of tiny single crystals, such as quartz or some ceramics, with two electrodes attached. When you apply a voltage across the electrodes, the material physically bends.
</p><p>
	That bending is called the converse piezoelectric effect. In 1880, physicists Pierre and Jacques Curie observed that when certain crystals were subjected to mechanical force, a voltage would appear between the faces of the crystal; they called this the piezoelectric effect (<em>piezo</em> is Greek for “to press”). This effect is due to the interaction between natural electric dipoles in the crystals and mechanical stresses in the crystals’ molecules. Roughly speaking, bending the crystal causes the dipoles to align, creating a bulk electric field.
</p><p>
	A year later the Curies demonstrated that the converse was true: If a voltage was applied between the faces of these crystals, the dipoles would bend the crystal as they try to align with the field. Work on piezoelectric materials subsequently expanded to include ceramics.
</p><p><img id="accfa" data-rm-shortcode-id="749833884fd6e14cb56819779faaf252" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" lazy-loadable="true" src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/an-illustration-of-a-laptop-showing-traditional-speakers-and-piezoelectric-speakers.png?id=51430421&amp;width=980" data-runner-src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/an-illustration-of-a-laptop-showing-traditional-speakers-and-piezoelectric-speakers.png?id=51430421&amp;width=980" width="2700" height="1890" alt="An illustration of a laptop showing traditional speakers and piezoelectric speakers."><small placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">When piezoelectric transducers vibrate the display itself to create sound waves, the sound seems to come directly from the image on the screen, a much more realistic effect.</small><small placeholder="Add Photo Credit...">James Provost</small></p><p>
	So by applying an alternating voltage, you can make the transducer vibrate with rather considerable force. These vibrations can be slow—the kind needed for haptic feedback—or very fast, to the highest audio frequencies and beyond. While creating the effect with ceramic material requires relatively high voltages—in the range of 40 volts or more—it requires very little current and, hence, little power—far less than the power used by mobile device speakers today.
</p><p>
	Using piezoelectric transducers to generate sound isn’t a new idea. In fact, they’ve been used for decades to produce the unbearable shriek of a smoke alarm.
</p><p>
	Of course, using piezoelectrics to produce a full range of high-quality audio is a long way from making a smoke alarm screech. There are a number of challenges to making it work in a handheld device. There is the need for an amplifier able to step up the voltage that batteries can provide, with high efficiency to conserve energy, and with minimum noise, to preserve audio quality. And the audio signal needs some preprocessing before you send it to the transducer, to correct for the characteristics of the transducer and the display panel that the transducer will shake.
</p><h2>Driving the Transducers</h2><p>
	But we at <a href="https://www.synaptics.com/" target="_blank">Synaptics</a> think that we’ve met those challenges. We’ve developed a chip that incorporates a low-noise, high-voltage boost amplifier and a digital signal processor that sits on a device’s main board and drives a ceramic piezoelectric transducer attached to the back of the display. This does take up space, but then again, it eliminates the moving coil speaker. The exact placement and number of these amplifier-transducer sets depends on the mechanical design of the device and the desired audio modes—one set is enough to replace the handheld receiver functionality in a smartphone, but a second set will be needed to also replace the speakerphone function. That configuration will be the more typical one.
</p><p>
	We expect to see our chip in smartphones, wearables, and laptop computers by the end of 2024.
</p><p><img id="1c6a3" data-rm-shortcode-id="e1400dec68b9298026a9d1f360f40e45" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" lazy-loadable="true" src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/an-illustration-of-the-inside-of-the-laptop-and-dispaly-showing-where-the-speakers-are-placed.png?id=51430438&amp;width=980" data-runner-src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/an-illustration-of-the-inside-of-the-laptop-and-dispaly-showing-where-the-speakers-are-placed.png?id=51430438&amp;width=980" width="2700" height="2753" alt="An illustration of the inside of the laptop and dispaly showing where the speakers are placed.  "><small placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">Traditional speaker modules sit among the other components of a computer or mobile device, taking up valuable real estate. When, instead, thin piezoelectric transducers vibrate the display to generate sound waves and haptic effects, that space is freed for other uses.</small><small placeholder="Add Photo Credit...">James Provost</small></p><p>
	The immediate benefits of moving away from traditional magnetic coil speakers are many. The piezoelectric transducer material requires only one millimeter of enclosure thickness, compared to several millimeters for dynamic speakers or linear resonant actuators, enabling a new generation of thinner handheld devices. Yet such transducers can produce the sound quality and the loudness of the best miniature dynamic speakers. They are being made by a few companies, including <a href="https://www.tdk.com/en/index.html" target="_blank">TDK</a>; others have yet to be announced publicly.
</p><p>
	Since the transducers are bonded to the display panel inside the enclosure, they require no openings that could allow moisture or dirt inside.
</p><p>
	Most importantly, the transducers produce sound waves from the front of the display. This means the sound is directed at the user, not away from the user or off to the side. As the success of sound-generating displays in large-screen TVs has demonstrated, this does in fact provide a more immersive experience. When you see the T-Rex throw back its head and roar, your brain locates the source of the sound at the image of the beast, not somewhere off to the side.
</p><p>
	Many of today’s handheld devices do attempt to correct for this problem by what is called <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/3d-audio" target="_self">psychoacoustic processing</a>, using an algorithm to change the amplitude and phase of the sound waves coming from the speakers, mimicking some of the very complex things that your ears do as sound waves enter them from different directions. The success of these algorithms depends on the surroundings, and extra processor cycles take noticeable energy from the device’s battery. Having the sound physically originate on the display is a far simpler solution.
</p><p>
	As for <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/haptx-inc-reveals-new-haptic-glove-for-virtual-reality" target="_self">haptic feedback</a>, using the same piezoelectric transducers that generate sound to generate haptic feedback eliminates the need for separate driver electronics and a motor to shake the display.
</p><h2>A Two-Way Street</h2><p>
	Also, recall that the piezoelectric effect works both ways. So when you touch the display panel, not only can a conventional touch sensor determine where you are touching, but the piezoelectric transducer can tell how hard you are pressing. This opens a whole new realm of feedback for interactive user interfaces and immersive touchscreen games.
</p><p>
	It also raises an interesting possibility that, frankly, has not been thoroughly explored yet. When a touch, or even reasonably loud ambient noise, flexes the display panel, it will also flex the transducer, generating a voltage. This electrical signal could be harvested to charge the device’s battery, providing a level of <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7503403" target="_blank">energy harvesting</a> that might prolong the time between charges.
</p><p>
	So if your next phone is thinner, has a longer battery life, and more immersive sound, thank piezoelectrics for eliminating the traditional speakers and motor-based haptic generators from your device, and moving the sound up front, where it belongs <span></span></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Native macOS fix for applications hiding under the MacBook Pro notch (217 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://flaky.build/native-fix-for-applications-hiding-under-the-macbook-pro-notch</link>
            <guid>39343919</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 12:05:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://flaky.build/native-fix-for-applications-hiding-under-the-macbook-pro-notch">https://flaky.build/native-fix-for-applications-hiding-under-the-macbook-pro-notch</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39343919">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><div><p><span role="img" aria-label="💡">💡</span></p><p><b>TL;DR:</b> You can adjust MacOS whitespace settings from the command line to display more application icons in the top right section of the menu bar.</p></div><h2 data-id="9201f6a8496f49bb8014a4c808d2fb78"><span><a href="#9201f6a8496f49bb8014a4c808d2fb78" title="Hidden Apps Beneath the 14” and 16” MacBook Pro Notch"><svg viewBox="0 0 16 16" width="16" height="16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7.775 3.275a.75.75 0 001.06 1.06l1.25-1.25a2 2 0 112.83 2.83l-2.5 2.5a2 2 0 01-2.83 0 .75.75 0 00-1.06 1.06 3.5 3.5 0 004.95 0l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 00-4.95-4.95l-1.25 1.25zm-4.69 9.64a2 2 0 010-2.83l2.5-2.5a2 2 0 012.83 0 .75.75 0 001.06-1.06 3.5 3.5 0 00-4.95 0l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 004.95 4.95l1.25-1.25a.75.75 0 00-1.06-1.06l-1.25 1.25a2 2 0 01-2.83 0z"></path></svg></a><span>Hidden Apps Beneath the 14” and 16” MacBook Pro Notch</span></span></h2><p>A frustrating aspect of the new MacBook Pro models is the notch. The notch itself isn't the problem; rather, it's that Apple hasn't automatically adjusted the menu bar icons so they don't hide behind the notch when many apps are running.</p><p>My colleagues often suggest purchasing <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://www.macbartender.com/">Bartender</a> for about 20€ to solve this issue. While it offers many features, I've refused to pay for a 3rd party solution to Apple's poor design decision. I have nothing against Bartender but I just wish I wouldn’t need to install yet another app into my machine to solve such a simple problem.</p><p>Recently, I discovered a free, native macOS solution that doesn't require installing Bartender or any other additional apps. See the results in the images below:</p><div><div><figure><div><p><span><span></span><img alt="With the default settings, the MacBook top menu bar can only accommodate 13 different apps." srcset="https://flaky.build/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.notion.so%2Fimage%2Fhttps%253A%252F%252Fprod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com%252F12b2d7ac-8864-406a-a5ab-b39c864fbaa0%252F1538309c-d706-4709-9e3e-fd5ced4f4975%252FIMG_5938.jpg%3Ftable%3Dblock%26id%3D1ae11007-718c-4f44-a93b-5b39dabd747a%26cache%3Dv2&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 1x, https://flaky.build/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.notion.so%2Fimage%2Fhttps%253A%252F%252Fprod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com%252F12b2d7ac-8864-406a-a5ab-b39c864fbaa0%252F1538309c-d706-4709-9e3e-fd5ced4f4975%252FIMG_5938.jpg%3Ftable%3Dblock%26id%3D1ae11007-718c-4f44-a93b-5b39dabd747a%26cache%3Dv2&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://flaky.build/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.notion.so%2Fimage%2Fhttps%253A%252F%252Fprod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com%252F12b2d7ac-8864-406a-a5ab-b39c864fbaa0%252F1538309c-d706-4709-9e3e-fd5ced4f4975%252FIMG_5938.jpg%3Ftable%3Dblock%26id%3D1ae11007-718c-4f44-a93b-5b39dabd747a%26cache%3Dv2&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75" decoding="async" data-nimg="intrinsic" loading="lazy" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAIAAAAAAAP///yH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAIBRAA7"></span></p><figcaption>With the default settings, the MacBook top menu bar can only accommodate 13 different apps.</figcaption></div></figure></div><div><figure><div><p><span><span></span><img alt="After adjusting the whitespace settings, it can fit several more." srcset="https://flaky.build/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.notion.so%2Fimage%2Fhttps%253A%252F%252Fprod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com%252F12b2d7ac-8864-406a-a5ab-b39c864fbaa0%252Faa624440-fad2-4422-8213-47507e8f06d5%252FIMG_5939.jpg%3Ftable%3Dblock%26id%3D4f2fdde9-697b-4068-9151-0a112409a8d4%26cache%3Dv2&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 1x, https://flaky.build/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.notion.so%2Fimage%2Fhttps%253A%252F%252Fprod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com%252F12b2d7ac-8864-406a-a5ab-b39c864fbaa0%252Faa624440-fad2-4422-8213-47507e8f06d5%252FIMG_5939.jpg%3Ftable%3Dblock%26id%3D4f2fdde9-697b-4068-9151-0a112409a8d4%26cache%3Dv2&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://flaky.build/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.notion.so%2Fimage%2Fhttps%253A%252F%252Fprod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com%252F12b2d7ac-8864-406a-a5ab-b39c864fbaa0%252Faa624440-fad2-4422-8213-47507e8f06d5%252FIMG_5939.jpg%3Ftable%3Dblock%26id%3D4f2fdde9-697b-4068-9151-0a112409a8d4%26cache%3Dv2&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75" decoding="async" data-nimg="intrinsic" loading="lazy" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAIAAAAAAAP///yH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAIBRAA7"></span></p><figcaption>After adjusting the whitespace settings, it can fit several more.</figcaption></div></figure></div></div><h3 data-id="3afaf2253a914c3dbc4395b9fd025424"><span><a href="#3afaf2253a914c3dbc4395b9fd025424" title="Adjusting the Menu Bar Whitespace Settings from the Command Line"><svg viewBox="0 0 16 16" width="16" height="16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7.775 3.275a.75.75 0 001.06 1.06l1.25-1.25a2 2 0 112.83 2.83l-2.5 2.5a2 2 0 01-2.83 0 .75.75 0 00-1.06 1.06 3.5 3.5 0 004.95 0l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 00-4.95-4.95l-1.25 1.25zm-4.69 9.64a2 2 0 010-2.83l2.5-2.5a2 2 0 012.83 0 .75.75 0 001.06-1.06 3.5 3.5 0 00-4.95 0l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 004.95 4.95l1.25-1.25a.75.75 0 00-1.06-1.06l-1.25 1.25a2 2 0 01-2.83 0z"></path></svg></a><span>Adjusting the Menu Bar Whitespace Settings from the Command Line</span></span></h3><p>You can modify the default padding and spacing in the Menu bar by opening <b>Terminal.app</b> and executing the following commands:</p><pre><code># Change the whitespace settings value
defaults -currentHost write -globalDomain NSStatusItemSelectionPadding -int 6
defaults -currentHost write -globalDomain NSStatusItemSpacing -int 6

# After running these commands, you need to log out and log back in</code></pre><p>You can adjust the values from <code>0</code> to <code>6</code> to accommodate even more icons. Personally, I found <code>6</code> to be a good fit.</p><h3 data-id="05824a59e9ff4b0ab39d13c5b4265a09"><span><a href="#05824a59e9ff4b0ab39d13c5b4265a09" title="Reverting to the Original Values"><svg viewBox="0 0 16 16" width="16" height="16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7.775 3.275a.75.75 0 001.06 1.06l1.25-1.25a2 2 0 112.83 2.83l-2.5 2.5a2 2 0 01-2.83 0 .75.75 0 00-1.06 1.06 3.5 3.5 0 004.95 0l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 00-4.95-4.95l-1.25 1.25zm-4.69 9.64a2 2 0 010-2.83l2.5-2.5a2 2 0 012.83 0 .75.75 0 001.06-1.06 3.5 3.5 0 00-4.95 0l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 004.95 4.95l1.25-1.25a.75.75 0 00-1.06-1.06l-1.25 1.25a2 2 0 01-2.83 0z"></path></svg></a><span>Reverting to the Original Values</span></span></h3><p>If you're unhappy with the results, you can delete the settings by executing the following commands:</p><pre><code># Revert to the original values
defaults -currentHost delete -globalDomain NSStatusItemSelectionPadding
defaults -currentHost delete -globalDomain NSStatusItemSpacing

# After running these commands, you need to log out and log back in</code></pre><h3 data-id="6a24bcfa08cd4c6a81f8c1b7edcb62ca"><span><a href="#6a24bcfa08cd4c6a81f8c1b7edcb62ca" title="Sources"><svg viewBox="0 0 16 16" width="16" height="16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7.775 3.275a.75.75 0 001.06 1.06l1.25-1.25a2 2 0 112.83 2.83l-2.5 2.5a2 2 0 01-2.83 0 .75.75 0 00-1.06 1.06 3.5 3.5 0 004.95 0l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 00-4.95-4.95l-1.25 1.25zm-4.69 9.64a2 2 0 010-2.83l2.5-2.5a2 2 0 012.83 0 .75.75 0 001.06-1.06 3.5 3.5 0 00-4.95 0l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 004.95 4.95l1.25-1.25a.75.75 0 00-1.06-1.06l-1.25 1.25a2 2 0 01-2.83 0z"></path></svg></a><span>Sources</span></span></h3><p>I first learned about these settings in this answer on the Apple-themed Stack Exchange, Ask Different:</p><h3 data-id="65ef7b4c6f5240a08be0c81f68850766"><span><a href="#65ef7b4c6f5240a08be0c81f68850766" title="Changelog"><svg viewBox="0 0 16 16" width="16" height="16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7.775 3.275a.75.75 0 001.06 1.06l1.25-1.25a2 2 0 112.83 2.83l-2.5 2.5a2 2 0 01-2.83 0 .75.75 0 00-1.06 1.06 3.5 3.5 0 004.95 0l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 00-4.95-4.95l-1.25 1.25zm-4.69 9.64a2 2 0 010-2.83l2.5-2.5a2 2 0 012.83 0 .75.75 0 001.06-1.06 3.5 3.5 0 00-4.95 0l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 004.95 4.95l1.25-1.25a.75.75 0 00-1.06-1.06l-1.25 1.25a2 2 0 01-2.83 0z"></path></svg></a><span>Changelog</span></span></h3><ul><li><b>12-02-2024 3:17 PM</b>: I clarified that I have nothing against <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://www.macbartender.com/">Bartender</a> after <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39343919#39344587">Eric_WVGG shared great comment in HN</a>. I haven’t been writing a lot before and it seems I still have work to do to be more considerate towards others 🙇</li></ul></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[My Visit to Deep Springs College (2009) (104 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.harrisonbarnes.com/do-not-trust-appearances-my-visit-to-deep-springs-college/</link>
            <guid>39343895</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 12:00:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.harrisonbarnes.com/do-not-trust-appearances-my-visit-to-deep-springs-college/">https://www.harrisonbarnes.com/do-not-trust-appearances-my-visit-to-deep-springs-college/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39343895">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p><span>
								<!-- code for related video starts here -->
				
				
				
							
			
			
			<!-- code for tooltip start -->
				<div id="balloon1">
					<p><span>Summary</span><br>
						You should neither trust outward appearances, nor let them intimidate you. There is always a discord between the appearance that a person or organization projects, and their actual nature. For this reason, always be careful about the people and organizations in whom you place your trust. 					</p>
					</div>
			<!-- code for tooltip END -->
				
			</span></p><div>
									
				<p>The first time I visited Las Vegas was in 1988. The city was far different back then, with an old Western vibe–not at all like the modern strip with all of the new casinos and so forth. Las Vegas, in the late 1980s, was more tired and run down; it was by no means the exciting city it is today.</p>
<p>I am officially changing my license today and becoming a Las Vegas resident. Last night I found a condominium here. There is a massive amount of activity in Las Vegas, which makes it a very exciting place. There are high rises all over the city; there is a great workforce; there are great shows, and there are just so many interesting things to do. I am very impressed by everything going on in the city and think that a lot of work is going to be generated out of Las Vegas in the future. In fact, I think that with all the shows, people, and activity here, the place is likely to rival major cities like New York at some point in the not too distant future.</p>
<p>In the next few days I am planning on moving to Las Vegas and spending at least half my time here starting up a few companies. In these last few days in Las Vegas I have realized exactly how much progress has been made here in the past 20+ years. The city is a completely different place and has become more of a modern metropolis than ever before. The Las Vegas I remember was a place where people went to gamble out West, which had <em>some</em> fun elements to it–but it was much different than the current Las Vegas.</p>
<p>Back in the late 1980s, I had come here to visit Deep Springs College. This college was really a commune of sorts, which was in the middle of the desert, a few hours outside of Las Vegas. At that time, the school boasted the highest SAT scores of any college in the United States and it was very small. In fact, if I recall correctly, there were only about 25 students in the entire school, which was itself supported by an endowment. Tuition was free. In order to attend the school, the students were required to take on various jobs on a farm that the school had established in the middle of the desert. There, the school was supposed to teach its students important<em> real world</em> skills such as self-reliance and resourcefulness, among other abilities. According to the school’s website:</p>
<blockquote><p>Deep Springs is an all-male liberal arts college located on a cattle-ranch and alfalfa farm in California’s High Desert. Electrical pioneer L.L. Nunn founded the school in 1917 on the three pillars of academics, labor, and self-governance in order to help young men prepare themselves for lives of service to humanity. The school’s 26 students, along with its staff and faculty, form a close community engaged in this intense project.</p>
<p>Deep Springs operates on the belief that manual labor and political deliberation are integral parts of a comprehensive <a title="liberal arts education" href="http://www.educationcrossing.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">liberal arts education</a>.</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Each student attends for two years and receives a full scholarship valued at over $50,000 per year. Afterwards, most complete their degrees at the world’s most prestigious four year institutions.</p></blockquote>
<p>The experience I had with visiting Deep Springs College was very entertaining in many respects, and it is something I will never forget. Everything about the school was so unusual, so different from any other place I had ever been.</p>
<p>Since the school was a <em>two year college,</em> students were required to transfer to other schools at the end of the two year period. The list of the schools that people went to after those two years was incredible: Caltech, Yale, Stanford, Harvard, and so forth. From my perspective, this made the prospect of attending the school extremely attractive. To hang out on a farm for two years and then transfer to a really good college, sounded like a great long-term experience. In addition, the sheer experience sounded incredible, if not magical.<span> To top it all off</span>, not having to worry about getting into real schools for the next couple of years sounded even more appealing.</p>
<p>In order to get to the school, I needed to travel to Las Vegas from Detroit, and then take a bus to a place called Lida Junction, where I was told I would be getting picked up by a student and then driven for another hour out into the desert. Prior to visiting the school, I had filled out a very long application that required me to write something like 50+ pages of essays. The essay I spent the most time on was pretty bizarre. It had something to do with examining how to reform criminals in society, and I hypothesized in a long essay that a very effective treatment would be to lock them in a room and play subliminal music with all sorts of hypnotic suggestions, which would change their minds and force them to think like good people instead of criminals. I estimated that several years of this sort of treatment would be enough to permanently alter the criminals and make them fit to reenter society.</p>
<p>Strangely enough, the people who read this essay at the school thought my idea was <em>groundbreaking</em>, and when I arrived at the school, they were eager to discuss this theory with me.<span> As it turned out, t</span>hey had actually spent a few days prior to my arrival, researching hypnosis, subliminal suggestions and so forth, and they all seemed to think I was some kind of an expert on these subjects. At least once or twice I walked into areas where a couple of guys were hanging out, and they had been discussing the theory I had come up with as a small group.</p>
<p>As a high school student in my last year of high school, taking a trip to Las Vegas and then a series of bus rides had offered an exciting prospect. I could not believe my good fortune. My father had bought me an airline ticket and gave me $500 for hotels, buses, and other expenses. Plus, since I was taking the trip during a school vacation, I did not even have to worry about all the school I was missing.</p>
<p>When I got to Las Vegas in the afternoon, I had taken a taxi to the bus station, and I also needed to purchase a ticket to Lida Junction—which was about a five or six hour ride. Las Vegas was so different back then. The bus station was a place where vagrants, workers from Mexico, cowboys, and others gathered. The town had a real Western flair to it and felt much different from how it is today, in all respects. I sat next to a cowboy when I finally got on the bus, after a few hours of waiting.</p>
<p>The bus ride was a lot of fun.<span> We</span> meandered through the desert in areas where there were literally no other cars. Every hour or so, the bus would pull over at a small restaurant or store on the side of the road for everyone to use the bathroom. Many of the restaurants had small casinos inside them and were run down with tired looking dealers. There was a lot of smoke everywhere. Cowboys sat at a table with some beers and a few other people, leisurely placing their bets. You could tell that most of the people were local and just passing some time at the casino.</p>
<p>Since I was relatively young at the time and I was traveling alone, several people spoke to me on the bus and they were all very friendly. When we got to one stop, I was standing out by the bus with a cowboy while he was chewing his tobacco. He had asked me where the heck I was going. I was wearing a blue blazer and khaki pants, trying to look as respectable as possible for the people I was going to visit at the college. I really stuck out and I knew it.</p>
<p>“I know exactly where you are going. It’s a rodeo college,” he told me matter of factly. I never even knew there was such a thing as a “rodeo college,” but he apparently seemed to think that was where I was going.</p>
<p>At around 2:00 in the morning the bus finally stopped at Lida Junction. To my astonishment the only thing there was at Lida Junction was a brothel, the Cottontail Ranch. The brothel consisted of a series of mobile homes that were all connected with various passageways going between them. It was quite a sight. As the bus pulled up I noticed a Suburban with its lights on. It was the only vehicle in the entire parking lot. As I walked up to the car, the driver smiled and let me in. <span> Hi</span>s name was Steve.</p>
<p><a href="https://d18pp9dg727fce.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/cottontailranchfinal1"><img title="cottontailranchfinal1" alt="" src="https://d18pp9dg727fce.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/cottontailranchfinal1" width="500" height="331" srcset="https://d18pp9dg727fce.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/cottontailranchfinal1 1600w, https://d18pp9dg727fce.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/cottontailranchfinal1-300x198.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"></a></p>
<p>He was about a year older than me and he was drinking a hot coffee. Since there did not appear to be anything else around for miles, I assumed that he had gotten the drink in the brothel. His hair looked a little messed up as well, and he looked a little nervous.</p>
<p>The drive to Deep Springs College was over an hour long. We took a two lane highway through the desert and Steve was going over 110 miles an hour most of the way.<span> As a passenger, I found t</span>he speed to be terrifying; however, the more I thought about it, the more I realized that there was nothing around that we could possibly hit. We were surrounded on all sides by stark desert. We finally arrived at the college at about 3:30 in the morning.<span> The campus w</span>as very dark, and it consisted of nothing but a set of small buildings in the middle of the desert. I was led to a room with a bunch of bunk beds and sleeping students, where I quickly fell asleep.</p>
<p>At about 7:00 a.m. a kid with a giant beard came up to me and woke me up. He told me it was “time to work” and pointed me towards the showers. He then told me to put on jeans and a tee shirt.<span> Once</span> I was dressed he led me to a mess hall where a bunch of other kids were sitting around, eating. The group of kids looked like they were all followers of the Grateful Dead. Most of them had beards and they had all let their hair grow extremely long.<span> Everyone</span> seemed a little pissed off at each other and at the world–but I could not really tell for sure; I was not introduced to anyone. I found myself a seat at what looked like a picnic table, where I ate my lunch. None of the kids I was sitting near seemed all that friendly, but after a few minutes everyone started to loosen up. They all had to go to class, do work, and various chores and so forth that day. I was just there to play and have fun and see the school. Or at least that was what I thought.</p>
<p>After breakfast, the guy who had woken me up walked me to a little Toyota pickup truck and started driving me towards what he called the “work site.” We drove for several minutes. During the drive he told me how much he had enjoyed my essay about the subliminal criminal training. He seemed very enthralled by it. Finally, he stopped the truck in the middle of the road and told me that I needed to spend the day digging along the side of the road to create an area where water could go during rainstorms. He told me to dig as much as I could and as far as I could. Then he told me that this was a test to see what a hard worker I was. He seemed to be inferring that a large part of my admission to the school would be determined by how well I dug a ditch. He left me several jugs of plastic milk containers that were filled with water.</p>
<p>I imagine it was around 8:00 a.m. when I started digging. I was already exhausted because I had not gotten any meaningful sleep the previous night. I worked as hard as I could, digging a ditch about two feet deep along the roadside as quickly as I could. The work was completely fatiguing and I had no clue where I was. Several hours into the project, it was really hot and my hands were starting to blister. The guy who had dropped me off came to check on me.</p>
<p>“Looks ok, not bad. C’mon, it’s time for lunch.”</p>
<p>When I got to the cafeteria, there appeared to be an argument underway. A guy wanted to leave the school for three or four days to go visit his girlfriend and the students were debating whether or not he should be allowed to go. If he were to go visit his girlfriend, he would be missing out on various work chores he was responsible for, and many of the other students were not confident that they should allow him to leave. In addition, this student had apparently left a few months previously to visit his girlfriend, so the students were not sure whether allowing him to leave again would be fair to the other students.</p>
<p>As I watched this argument, it occurred to me that I probably would not enjoy this incredible amount of oversight in my life. These guys were being very closely micromanaged by other students, and they did not appear to have much say at all in terms of what they did with their own time.</p>
<p>After lunch I was taken to the road and forced to shovel dirt and dig the culvert some more. However, after an hour or so I was picked up, told to take a shower and invited to a class. It was a literature class, but I do not remember much about it.</p>
<p>I spent the next few days at the school not doing much of anything. I was not asked to do any more work and I spent my days wandering around the campus and climbing the surrounding hills. Most of the students were so engrossed in various work pursuits and classes, that they did not appear to have much time for anything. Most of the kids I had met seemed very quiet and for the most part, pretty withdrawn. Nevertheless, they were interesting kids. Most of their activities outside of studying and work seemed to involve self-governed activities relating to the farm and the campus. The evenings appeared to involve long, drawn out meetings about one thing or another related to the school and work that needed to be done around the campus. These meetings often dragged on for hours and I found them extremely boring and uninteresting. Moreover, many of the students seemed to take their various arguments quite personally.</p>
<p>On my last full day at the college, I was told that I would be interviewed by the admissions committee at 2:00 p.m. and that I should report to a classroom at the school at that time. In the morning, someone came and told me that I should spend “every spare second” reviewing each of my essays prior to my interviews with the admissions committee later that day. At the request of the school, I had brought my essays with me.</p>
<p>When I went into the classroom at the appointed hour, the 25 students were all there ready to interview me. They were all gathered around the classroom and each of them had portions of my various essays in front of them. They proceeded to dissect the essays, everyone going over one part of the essays or another with me. The questions that they asked me were very difficult and I really did not do very well in the interviews. One of the most embarrassing moments came when they asked me a question about Carl Jung, whom I had quoted in one of my essays. I had included a few lines about how Carl Jung believed this or that.</p>
<p>“Have you ever actually read any books by Carl Jung?” one of the students asked me.</p>
<p>“No, I’ve never read a single thing by him,” I answered truthfully.</p>
<p>“Then how can you possibly have a large quote from him in your essay, base an essay around his teachings and also lead us to believe that you know what you are talking about?”</p>
<p>It was a really good question and he had a point. The rest of the experience and all of the questions went basically like this: I would say one thing and they would contradict me and accuse me of not really understanding what I was talking about.</p>
<p>Several years later, I remember I was interviewing for a Rhodes Scholarship in front of a large committee and this entire procedure was much easier than the interviews with the Deep Springs kids. I simply did not fit in with this crowd; they were different sorts of kids from what I had ever encountered. For example, none of them were athletic, they were not clean cut and they all had a whole lot of intellectual arrogance. It seemed as if the kids going to the school had grown up in environments and attended schools where this behavior was accepted. In the high school I attended, this sort of arrogance would not have been tolerated, and it would have probably been beaten out of the kids.</p>
<p>When I left my interview, after around 4 hours of questioning, one of the students said something I’ll never forget: “I have one final question for you: Did you like the food?”</p>
<p>The way he asked the question was layered with subtext. What he meant was: “Hey, we fed you for four days and do not like you. You were here on vacation and we hoped you enjoyed the food.” The guy was a complete dick and I did not understand his need to say something so obnoxious. I did not realize at first that he was being rude; however, after he delivered the line I saw a lot of the students looking at each other and snickering, as if they were sharing an inside joke.</p>
<p>My final thoughts about this place as I prepared to leave were that because I did not have perfect SAT scores, because I was not extremely intellectual, and because I was more of an athletic type than an academic type, I did not fit in. I had felt uncomfortable the whole time I was there. I did not understand how some guy could tolerate a 3 hour debate about whether or not he should be allowed to go visit his girlfriend. This just seemed intolerable. It really made the place seem like a prison. Another strange thing about the school was that it was several hours away from the nearest hospital. For this reason, they had to keep an airplane on the property at all times, in order to fly people out in the case of an emergency; the school was literally in the middle of nowhere.</p>
<p>The bus that took me back to Las Vegas was passing through Lida Junction and was scheduled to pick me up from the front of the brothel at 4:00 a.m. There was only one bus that passed through each day. Steve woke me up at around 2:00 a.m. that morning and told me it was time to go. I had packed all of my bags and was ready to go. Five minutes later I was sitting in the Suburban.</p>
<p>Steve seemed a little bit too excited to be hitting the road. He had just taken a shower, I could tell, and he smelled like too much cologne. Since these kids seemed so moral in many respects, the last thing I expected was that this guy might be interested in going to the brothel, but it was in the back of my mind.</p>
<p>While Steve drove, I started asking him a lot of questions about himself. There was nothing that would be more interesting to me at the moment than getting him to talk about himself, and to find out his various likes and dislikes. I was also curious about his background. Steve was from a suburb outside of Palm Springs, California, from what I remember, and he had come to the school in a roundabout way. He had graduated from high school where he had not done all that well and then attended a community college for a year. He knew someone, or had a relative, who had some involvement with the college and they had urged him to apply when he was in high first year at the community college. Steve said he felt very grateful to be there and that, had he not been invited, he might have been an auto mechanic or something along those lines. I figured that he must have gotten really good SAT scores since the school seemed to emphasize the test so much.</p>
<p>“Oh, I did horribly on that test!” he said. “I do not think I even got in the 50th percentile.</p>
<p>As we zoomed through the desert at over 100 miles an hour, I asked Steve what he thought about the fact that the closest sign of civilization to the school was a brothel. He proceeded to launch into a long tirade about how prostitution was evil and how it exploited women. He seemed to feel strongly about this and he started reciting all sorts of statistics and random facts about the damage that prostitution does to people.</p>
<p>We pulled up in front of the Cottontail ranch a little before 3:00 a.m. and it appeared to be completely open for business. It was pretty unusual that we were there so early. I was also pretty thirsty and after around 20 minutes or so I said, “Let’s go in and get some coffee.” We saw a guy in a semi truck go by and stop the truck for around a minute and walk out with a coffee, which looked pretty good. Steve argued with me for a few minutes about how buying coffee from the establishment was akin to supporting prostitution; however, after a few minutes he agreed to go in with me.</p>
<p>When we got inside, we came upon this bar. An older woman was standing there, looking pretty tired. She looked like she might be in her 60s and she was wearing a sweat suit. When we asked for coffee, she told us to hold on and then disappeared in the back.</p>
<p>We could see a kitchen area from where we were, and as we were standing there, a girl who did not look more than 25 walked by and checked us out. She stopped and looked directly at Steve:</p>
<p>“Bulldog!” she exclaimed, running over to Steve with a hug. “You look so cute. You got a haircut and I love it!” she said.</p>
<p>I could not believe what I was witnessing. “Bulldog” apparently knew this girl very well. He looked incredibly embarrassed, but started talking with her, eventually taking a seat at the bar. The two of them began talking and acting as if I were not even there.</p>
<p>A few minutes later the woman walked out with our coffees.</p>
<p>“You kids must be from Deep Springs College,” she said. “I got a letter from the headmaster there a few days ago and he was very upset. The letter contains a lot of untruths. I am thinking about calling my lawyer.”</p>
<p>For the next several minutes, the woman explained that the headmaster had sent a letter to the brothel about a serious outbreak of a sexually transmitted disease, which a substantial part of the student body had gotten from frequenting the brothel. The headmaster had threatened to report the brothel to the Department of Health in the letter or something along those lines and had also requested that the brothel not service the students anymore.</p>
<p>“These kids come here all the time,” she said. “But they did not get their sex infections here. One of them must have gotten it somewhere else and infected the rest of the boys there. God knows what must go on there. My girls are clean. They are inspected by a doctor. You go back there and tell him my girls are clean!”</p>
<p>The woman was holding a letter on Deep Springs stationary and I sat there speechless. We went back to our car and sat there in silence for a few minutes. Steve then said some intellectual crap about how he was morally justified in having sex with prostitutes instead of having sex with men at Deep Springs; after all, he was at his sexual prime. It was complete bullshit and I knew it.</p>
<p>“Yeah, at least 12 or 13 guys who went to the brothel got a bad infection,” he said. “The doctor has come out a few times and given them shots and stuff but it is not going away. There’s a lot of pus involved and its pretty painful from what I understand. I think there was some talk about disciplining them, but how can you discipline half the school?”</p>
<p>I sat there in silence not really understanding or comprehending the whole situation.</p>
<p>For the past several years I have read one mention or another about Deep Springs College in major magazines and newspapers. Every article I read talks about how great the school is and how special its students are. A September 2006 article in the New Yorker relates:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>ABSTRACT: ANNALS OF THE WEST about Deep Springs College. L. L. Nunn was a short man with a stiff-collared Victorian habit of dress. A lifelong bachelor, he started investing in Western mines in the late 19th century, and grew rich from hydroelectric power. With his brother, P. N., he built the power station at Niagara Falls. Though Nunn, who died in 1925, never graduated from college, he devoted the last 20 years of his life to a novel form of education, a mix of Christian mysticism, imperialist elitism, Boy Scout-like abstinence, and Progressive era learning-by-doing, with an emphasis on leadership training and the formation of strong character. In 1917, he created a small men’s college called Deep Springs College, on a working ranch in Deep Springs Valley, California. He limited enrollment to 25 men and restricted contact with the residents of Bishop, a town 40 miles away. Deep Springs is 5 hours north of L.A. The property, hemmed in by mountains, is 50 square miles. There are two basic rules: observe isolation, and abstain from alcohol and drugs while school is in session. The school is year-round and free, and it requires students to do several hours of manual labor a day. [Mentions the cattle operation] As a two-year institution, Deep Springs is technically a junior college, but its success in placing students at prestigious universities puts it in a category of its own. In recent years, about a fourth of each graduating class has transferred into Harvard, a fourth into the University of Chicago, and a few students have gone on to Oxford, Yale, and Brown. At the college, a committee of students, along with faculty members and the dean, hires teachers, based on their proposed syllabi. Uncanonical subjects, such as the Lusophone language, the writings of Ivan Illich, and auto mechanics, are offered alongside Shakespeare, Proust, and Marx. [Describes a small class on Emily Dickinson, taught by Katie Peterson] The Deep Springs boy is deliberate, thoughtful, studied. [Mentions dairy boys.] Most of the students are white, suburban, and upper-middle-class, and it’s been a struggle for the school to diversify. The typical look-full beard, bandanna, half-unstrapped dungarees, dirty nails, etc. – is an emblem of retreat from mainstream society. The outré is accepted without hesitation and students generally detach themselves from knowledge of the outside world. Most of the ranch work is done without modern machinery and an exaltation of the past can create conditions for absurdity. [Describes Nunn’s “homosexual problem”] His probable attraction to young men has been a source of some anxiety at the college. In 1911, he created the Telluride Association. The reactionary strain in Nunn is the one most evident at the school today. “Every major change at Deep Springs has been opposed by the students,” said Christopher Breiseth, former college president. Deep Springs’s all-male self-enclosure allows its students to feel wildly, hedonically free. The shock of returning to the world of social norms can be profound. In 1994, the college voted against coeducation, but the controversial subject has created a fissure in the school’s relationship with the Telluride Association, where women have been members for 45 years. The Association lent the college $1.8 million in 1988 to renovate its main building with the catch that if it hasn’t changed its all-male policy by 2019 it will have to start repaying the loan. [sic] Some fear that adding women to the mix might upset the college’s already delicate balance. [Mentions Gareth Fisher and Dan Bockrath, student cowboys at the college] Bockrath said that being at Deep Springs was about “the last ages of youth, playing in the woods a little longer, being a cowboy.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>With much relief I finally got on the bus to head back home. As I rode away I looked out the window and saw Steve pull forward; then I saw his brake lights turn on, the Suburban coming to a complete stop. The last I saw was Steve getting out of the truck and walking back toward the brothel. This was about my last and final contact with the school.</p>
<p>The school never sent me either an acceptance letter, or a rejection letter. I imagine that Bulldog went back and related to the other students what had happened, and that they were all simply hoping I would forget about the whole experience and never tell anyone. However, visiting the school was one of the most interesting experiences of my life. When I did go to college, I worked hard and did well. My experience of being humiliated in a four hour interview really showed me how little I knew and it taught me to always be ready to back up my facts and everything I said. I don’t really consider myself an intellectual sort; however, I went into college at the University of Chicago with a tremendous amount of confidence because I knew and <em>accepted</em> that there were people out there who might try to shoot down any idea I had. I had the same understanding when I got to law school.</p>
<p>The most important thing the school taught me, however, was that when you scratch beneath the surface of even the most prestigious people and institutions, you will find reasons not to be intimidated. I had no business going to interview at a school where the students had all perfect SAT scores (or at least said they did) because I was simply not in that league academically. But I did it anyway. When I got beneath the surface of the school, I found an environment where kids could not make decisions for themselves, where men let themselves go, where half the student body had caught a sexually transmitted disease, and where people portrayed themselves as being better than the rest of society. But in the end they all screwed around with hookers.</p>
<p>Over the years as I have read about one sex scandal after another. Whether it has been former President Clinton, Eliot Spitzer, or others, I have come to realize that the models we have in society, who supposedly stand for something great–often when you scratch beneath the surface, they do not really stand for what they say. I watch intellectuals complain about the environment, complain about capitalism and so forth, and then, when I sit down with them and ask questions, I realize that they are mostly pretending to stand for one thing–while in reality they do not. My visit to Deep Springs College taught me, in no uncertain terms, to be extremely careful about trusting anyone. Whether it is trusting a leader, trusting the numbers an institution claims, or trusting someone who is making an argument to you about this or that. A substantial majority of the people, institutions, and others we encounter in our day-to-day lives are completely full of shit. Everything is a facade and you really do not know what is real and what is not. Everything is sort of like Las Vegas out there.</p>
<p>Major financial institutions have crashed recently due to financial numbers not being what they once were. People have lost billions of dollars to people who they thought they could trust, such as Bernard Madoff. People have put faith in real estate and all sorts of other investments that turned out to be completely illusionary. People have gone to work for companies they thought would support them forever but did not, and they are out of work.</p>
<p>When I graduated from <a title="law school" href="http://www.lawfirmstaff.com/">law school</a> at the University of Virginia, the commencement speaker was Jesse Jackson. His commencement speech was titled “Can You Be Trusted?” For an hour or so Jackson gave one example after another about how various people in society including politicians and others simply could not be trusted. He stated that the measurement of trust came down to whether our families could trust us and whether our coworkers could trust us, and he defined trustworthiness as the most important virtue. He must have said the phrase “Can you be trusted” 100+ times during his speech. It was one of the most powerful speeches I have ever heard.</p>
<p>5 years later I picked up the paper and saw there was a giant story about how Jesse Jackson had had a long-term extramarital affair. When I read the story I thought back on the Reverend’s speech and realized that <em>even he</em> could not be trusted (at least not by his wife). These sorts of contradictions are everywhere.</p>
<p>I have met <a title="People in Business" href="http://www.businessdevelopmentcrossing.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">people in business</a> before, who appeared to be extremely powerful, and who acted as if they were better than me; they ended up going to prison for various reasons. I have seen one example after another of the inherent conflict between what something appears to be or <em>wants to be</em> and <em>what it really is.</em></p>
<p>In the end, what Deep Springs College taught me as a visitor in those few days was actually far more valuable than what I might have learned by actually attending the school as a student: Do not be intimidated by, or trust appearances. No one is better than you. Everyone has secrets. Go forward in your life like you belong anywhere you want to be. You can do and be whoever you want to be. <em> It is your life.</em></p>

<p><em> </em><strong>THE LESSON</strong></p>
<p>You should neither trust outward appearances, nor let them intimidate you. There is always a discord between the appearance that a person or organization projects, and their actual nature. For this reason, always be careful about the people and organizations in whom you place your trust.</p>

<p><strong>About Harrison Barnes</strong></p>
<p>
Harrison Barnes is the Founder of BCG Attorney Search and a successful legal recruiter himself.  Harrison is extremely committed to and passionate about the profession of legal placement.  <a href="https://www.bcgsearch.com/testimonials.php" target="_blank">His firm BCG Attorney Search has placed thousands of attorneys.</a>  BCG Attorney Search works with attorneys to dramatically improve their careers by leaving no stone unturned in a search and bringing out the very best in them.  <a href="https://www.bcgsearch.com/pdf/bcgplacements.pdf" target="_blank">Harrison has placed the leaders of the nation’s top law firms</a>, and countless associates who have gone on to lead the nation’s top law firms. There are very few firms Harrison has not made placements with.  <a href="https://www.bcgsearch.com/article/group/12/Harrison_s-Perspectives/" target="_blank">Harrison’s writings about attorney careers and placements attract millions of reads each year.</a>  He coaches and consults with law firms about how to dramatically improve their recruiting and retention efforts.  His company LawCrossing has been ranked on the Inc. 500 twice.  For more information, please visit <a href="https://www.bcgsearch.com/Legal-Recruiter/13/Harrison-Barnes/" target="_blank">Harrison Barnes’ bio.</a> </p>
<p>
<strong>About BCG Attorney Search</strong></p>
<p>
BCG Attorney Search matches attorneys and law firms with unparalleled expertise and drive that gets results. Known globally for its success in locating and placing attorneys in law firms of all sizes, BCG Attorney Search has placed thousands of attorneys in law firms in thousands of different law firms around the country.  Unlike other legal placement firms, BCG Attorney Search brings massive resources of over 150 employees to its placement efforts locating positions and opportunities that its competitors simply cannot.  Every legal recruiter at BCG Attorney Search is a former successful attorney who attended a top law school, worked in top law firms and brought massive drive and commitment to their work.  BCG Attorney Search legal recruiters take your legal career seriously and understand attorneys.  For more information, please visit <a href="https://www.bcgsearch.com/" target="_blank">www.BCGSearch.com.</a>
</p>
				
								
				<!--cat id =1113 for Job Market-->
								
									
					<p>Filed Under : <a href="https://www.harrisonbarnes.com/category/featured/" rel="category tag">Featured</a>, <a href="https://www.harrisonbarnes.com/category/gettingahead/lifelessons/" rel="category tag">Life Lessons</a></p>
					<p>Tagged: <a href="https://www.harrisonbarnes.com/tag/apply-for-a-job/" rel="tag">apply for a job</a>, <a href="https://www.harrisonbarnes.com/tag/attorney-search/" rel="tag">attorney search</a>, <a href="https://www.harrisonbarnes.com/tag/bernard-madoff/" rel="tag">bernard madoff</a>, <a href="https://www.harrisonbarnes.com/tag/career-advice/" rel="tag">career advice</a>, <a href="https://www.harrisonbarnes.com/tag/deep-springs-college/" rel="tag">deep springs college</a>, <a href="https://www.harrisonbarnes.com/tag/inherent-conflict/" rel="tag">inherent conflict</a>, <a href="https://www.harrisonbarnes.com/tag/job-search/" rel="tag">job search</a>, <a href="https://www.harrisonbarnes.com/tag/job-search-guru-a-harrison-barnes/" rel="tag">job search guru | a harrison barnes</a>, <a href="https://www.harrisonbarnes.com/tag/job-search-industry/" rel="tag">job search industry</a>, <a href="https://www.harrisonbarnes.com/tag/legal-jobs/" rel="tag">legal jobs</a>, <a href="https://www.harrisonbarnes.com/tag/legal-profession/" rel="tag">legal profession</a>, <a href="https://www.harrisonbarnes.com/tag/matter-of-facts/" rel="tag">matter-of-facts</a>, <a href="https://www.harrisonbarnes.com/tag/mobile-homes/" rel="tag">mobile homes</a>, <a href="https://www.harrisonbarnes.com/tag/sat-scores/" rel="tag">sat scores</a>, <a href="https://www.harrisonbarnes.com/tag/trust-appearances/" rel="tag">trust appearances</a>											</p>
			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Kalman Filter Explained Simply (254 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://thekalmanfilter.com/kalman-filter-explained-simply/</link>
            <guid>39343746</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 11:33:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://thekalmanfilter.com/kalman-filter-explained-simply/">https://thekalmanfilter.com/kalman-filter-explained-simply/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39343746">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="post-1">

	<!-- .entry-header -->

	<div>
		
<div>
<p>Most tutorials for the Kalman Filter are difficult to understand because they require advanced math skills to understand how the Kalman Filter is derived. If you have tried to read Rudolf E Kalman’s <a href="http://www.cs.unc.edu/~welch/kalman/kalmanPaper.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">1960 Kalman Filter paper</a>, you know how confusing this concept can be. But do you need to understand how to derive the Kalman Filter in order to use it? </p>



<p>No. If you want to design and implement a Kalman Filter, you do not need to know how to derive it, you just need to understand how it works.</p>
</div>



<p>The truth is, anybody can understand the Kalman Filter if it is explained in small digestible chunks. This post simply explains the Kalman Filter and how it works to estimate the state of a system.</p>



<h2>The big picture of the Kalman Filter</h2>



<p>Lets look at the Kalman Filter as a black box. The Kalman Filter has inputs and outputs. The inputs are noisy and sometimes inaccurate measurements. The outputs are less noisy and sometimes more accurate estimates. The estimates can be system state parameters that were not measured or observed. This last sentence describes the super power of the Kalman Filter. Again, the Kalman Filter estimates system parameters that are not observed or measured.</p>



<p>In short, you can think of the Kalman Filter as an algorithm that can estimate observable and unobservable parameters with great accuracy in real-time. Estimates with high accuracy are used to make precise predictions and decisions. For these reasons, Kalman Filters are used in robotics and real-time systems that need reliable information.</p>



<h2>What is the Kalman Filter?</h2>



<p>Simply put, the Kalman Filter is a generic algorithm that is used to estimate system parameters. It can use inaccurate or noisy measurements to estimate the state of that variable or another unobservable variable with greater accuracy. For example, Kalman Filtering is used to do the following:</p>



<ul>
<li>Object Tracking – Use the measured position of an object to more accurately estimate the position and velocity of that object.</li>



<li>Body Weight Estimate on Digital Scale – Use the measured pressure on a surface to estimate the weight of object on that surface.</li>



<li>Guidance, Navigation, and Control – Use Inertial Measurement Unit (IMU) sensors to estimate an objects location, velocity, and acceleration; and use those estimates to control the objects next moves.</li>
</ul>



<p>The real power of the Kalman Filter is not smoothing measurements. It is the ability to estimate system parameters that can not be measured or observed with accuracy. Estimates with improved accuracy in systems that operate in real time, allow systems greater control and thus more capabilities.</p>



<h2>Kalman Filter Algorithm Overview</h2>



<figure><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="700" src="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/kalman_filter_overview-1024x700.png" alt="Kalman Filter algorithm process diagram" srcset="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/kalman_filter_overview-1024x700.png 1024w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/kalman_filter_overview-300x205.png 300w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/kalman_filter_overview-768x525.png 768w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/kalman_filter_overview.png 1234w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>The process diagram above shows the Kalman Filter algorithm step by step. I know those equations are intimidating but I assure you this will all make sense by the time you finish reading this article. Let’s look at this process one step at a time. For your reference, here is a table of definitions that will be referred to throughout.</p>



<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><strong>x</strong></td><td>state variable</td><td>n x 1 column vector</td><td>Output</td></tr><tr><td>P</td><td>state covariance matrix</td><td>n x n matrix</td><td>Output</td></tr><tr><td><strong>z</strong></td><td>measurement</td><td>m x 1 column vector</td><td>Input</td></tr><tr><td>A</td><td>state transition matrix</td><td>n x n matrix</td><td>System Model</td></tr><tr><td>H</td><td>state-to-measurement matrix</td><td>m x n matrix</td><td>System Model</td></tr><tr><td>R</td><td>measurement covariance matrix</td><td>m x m matrix</td><td>Input</td></tr><tr><td>Q</td><td>process noise covariance matrix</td><td>n x n matrix</td><td>System Model</td></tr><tr><td>K</td><td>Kalman Gain</td><td>n x m</td><td>Internal</td></tr></tbody></table><figcaption>Kalman Filter Algorithm Reference Terms</figcaption></figure>



<p>The table above identifies the variables used in the algorithm. Each variable listed has a structure type and category. As this article continues, use the table as a reference.</p>



<hr>



<p><strong>If you are enjoying this post, check out my <a href="https://thekalmanfilter.com/kalman-filter-made-easy-ebook">book</a> Kalman Filter Made Easy. </strong>You will learn: the first principles behind the Kalman Filter, how to create simulations and perform analysis on Kalman Filters, and more. </p>



<hr>



<h2>Kalman Filter Radar Tracking Tutorial</h2>



<p>This tutorial will go through the step by step process of a Kalman Filter being used to track airplanes and objects near airports. The output track states are used to display to the air traffic control operators monitoring the air space.</p>



<h2>Kalman Filter Tutorial Notation</h2>



<p>Radars are not built equally. Each one has different capabilities and therefore provides different types of information to its supporting systems. For this example, the radar will output its measurements in 2D cartesian coordinates, x and y. These measurements will be represented as a 2-by-1 column vector, <strong>z</strong>. The associated <a href="https://thekalmanfilter.com/covariance-matrix-explained/">variance-covariance matrix</a> for these measurements, <strong>R</strong>, will also be provided by the radar along with the time tag for when the measurement occurred, <strong>t</strong>. The subscript<strong> m</strong> denotes the measurement parameters. And the <strong>k</strong> subscript denotes the order of the measurement. </p>



<figure><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="178" src="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/radar_measurement_structures-1024x178.png" alt="radar measurement equations  - Kalman Filter" srcset="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/radar_measurement_structures-1024x178.png 1024w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/radar_measurement_structures-300x52.png 300w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/radar_measurement_structures-768x133.png 768w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/radar_measurement_structures.png 1220w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>The Kalman Filter estimates the objects position and velocity based on the radar measurements. The estimate is represented by a 4-by-1 column vector, <strong>x</strong>. It’s associated <a href="https://thekalmanfilter.com/covariance-matrix-explained/">variance-covariance matrix</a> for the estimate is represented by a 4-by-4 matrix, <strong>P</strong>. Additionally, the state estimate has a time tag denoted as <strong>T</strong>.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="301" src="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/kalman_filter_state_structures-1024x301.png" alt="Kalman Filter object state equations" srcset="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/kalman_filter_state_structures-1024x301.png 1024w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/kalman_filter_state_structures-300x88.png 300w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/kalman_filter_state_structures-768x226.png 768w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/kalman_filter_state_structures.png 1178w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<h2>Step 1: Initialize System State</h2>



<p>Initializing the system state of a Kalman Filter varies across applications. In this tutorial, the Kalman Filter initializes the system state with the first measurement.</p>



<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><strong>x<sub>k</sub></strong></td><td data-align="right">Eqn. 1-1</td></tr><tr><td><strong>P<sub>k</sub></strong></td><td data-align="right">Eqn. 1-2</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<p>In this radar tracking example, the input measurements contain position only information. The output system state will contain the position and velocity of the object.</p>



<p>When the first measurement comes, the only information known about the object is the position at that point in time. The system state estimate will be set to the input position after the first estimate. The system state error covariance will be set to the first measurement’s position accuracy.</p>



<h2>Initialize System State in Equations</h2>



<p>These equations show the input and output values for this Kalman Filter after receiving the first measurement.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="173" src="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_1_equations-1024x173.png" alt="radar measurement 1 equations  - Kalman Filter" srcset="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_1_equations-1024x173.png 1024w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_1_equations-300x51.png 300w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_1_equations-768x130.png 768w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_1_equations.png 1170w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="261" src="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_1_state_vector_and_time_tag-1024x261.png" alt="initialize state and time tag equations  - Kalman Filter" srcset="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_1_state_vector_and_time_tag-1024x261.png 1024w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_1_state_vector_and_time_tag-300x77.png 300w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_1_state_vector_and_time_tag-768x196.png 768w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_1_state_vector_and_time_tag.png 1066w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="268" src="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_1_state_covariance-1024x268.png" alt="initialize state covariance equations  - Kalman Filter" srcset="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_1_state_covariance-1024x268.png 1024w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_1_state_covariance-300x78.png 300w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_1_state_covariance-768x201.png 768w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_1_state_covariance.png 1362w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<h2>Step 2: Reinitialize System State</h2>



<p>The system state estimate is reinitialized because a velocity estimate needs a second position measurement for computation.</p>



<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><strong>x<sub>k</sub></strong></td><td data-align="right">Eqn. 2-1</td></tr><tr><td><strong>P<sub>k</sub></strong></td><td data-align="right">Eqn. 2-2</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<p>Velocity is estimated with a linear approximation. As you most likely recall from high school physics, velocity is equal to the distance traveled divided by the time it took to travel that distance.</p>



<p>The updated system state estimate will be the second measurement’s position and the computed velocity. The updated system state error covariance will be the second measurement’s position accuracy and an approximated velocity accuracy. Note that this velocity accuracy approximation is something that can be tuned and adjusted after running data through your filter. There are different ways of approximating these values so if this doesn’t match your approximation, that’s okay!</p>



<h2>Reinitialize System State in Equations for the Kalman Filter</h2>



<p>These equations show the input and output values for this Kalman Filter after receiving the second measurement. Note the velocity variance terms in the state <a href="https://thekalmanfilter.com/covariance-matrix-explained/">covariance matrix</a>. These values are being set to 10<sup>4</sup>. In other words, this value indicates a large uncertainty for the velocity state values. In this example, the velocity units are meters per second.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="154" src="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_2_equations-1024x154.png" alt="measurement 2 equations  " srcset="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_2_equations-1024x154.png 1024w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_2_equations-300x45.png 300w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_2_equations-768x116.png 768w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_2_equations.png 1234w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="289" src="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_2_state_vector_time_tag_and_delta-1024x289.png" alt="reinitialize state vector and time tag equations  " srcset="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_2_state_vector_time_tag_and_delta-1024x289.png 1024w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_2_state_vector_time_tag_and_delta-300x85.png 300w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_2_state_vector_time_tag_and_delta-768x217.png 768w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_2_state_vector_time_tag_and_delta.png 1238w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="258" src="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_2_state_covariance-1024x258.png" alt="reinitialize state covariance matrix equation  " srcset="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_2_state_covariance-1024x258.png 1024w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_2_state_covariance-300x76.png 300w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_2_state_covariance-768x194.png 768w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_2_state_covariance.png 1444w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<h2>Quick Note on Initialization</h2>



<p>Steps 1 and 2 used the first couple measurements to initialize and re-initialize the system estimate. Each application of the Kalman Filter may do this differently but the goal is to have a system state estimate that can be updated for future measurement with the Kalman Filter equations.</p>



<p>Steps 3 through 6 demonstrate how measurements are filtered in and the state estimate is updated.</p>



<h2>Step 3: Predict System State Estimate </h2>



<p>When the third measurement is received, the system state estimate is propagated forward to time align it with the measurement. This alignment is done so that the measurement and state estimate can be combined.</p>



<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><strong>x<sub>p</sub> = Ax<sub>k-1</sub></strong></td><td data-align="right">Eqn. 3-1</td></tr><tr><td><strong>P<sub>p</sub> = AP<sub>k-1</sub>A<sup>T</sup> + Q</strong></td><td data-align="right">Eqn. 3-2</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<p>The system model is used to perform this prediction. In this example, a constant velocity linear motion model is used to approximate the objects position change over a time interval. Note that a constant velocity model does assume zero acceleration. Remember this because it will resurface later.</p>



<p>The constant velocity linear motion model is something you may also remember from your high school physics class. The equation states that the position of an object is equal to its initial position plus its displacement over a specified time period assuming a constant velocity.</p>



<p>A state transition matrix represents these equations. This matrix is used to propagate the state estimate and state error covariance matrix appropriately. You may be wondering why the state error covariance matrix is propagated. The reason for this is because when a state estimate is propagated in time, the uncertainty about its state at this future time step is inherently uncertain, so the error covariance grows.</p>



<h2>On the Q Matrix</h2>



<p>The Q matrix represents process noise for the system model. The system model is an approximation. Throughout the life of a system state, that system model fluctuates in its accuracy. Therefore, the Q matrix is used to represent this uncertainty and adds to the existing noise on the state. For this example, the systems actual accelerations and decelerations contribute to this error. </p>



<h2>On the H Matrix</h2>



<p>The Kalman Filter uses the state-to-measurement matrix, H, to convert the system state estimate from the state space to the measurement space. For some applications, this is a matrix of zeros and ones. For other applications that use the Extended Kalman Filter, the H matrix is populated with differential equations. To learn more about Extended Kalman Filters, check out my article on them <a href="https://thekalmanfilter.com/extended-kalman-filter-python-example/">here</a>.</p>



<p>In this tutorial, the H matrix is a simple matrix that is set up to reduce the state estimate and error covariance to position only values rather than position and velocity.</p>



<h2>Predict System State in Equations</h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="154" src="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_3_equations-1024x154.png" alt="measurement 3 equations " srcset="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_3_equations-1024x154.png 1024w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_3_equations-300x45.png 300w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_3_equations-768x115.png 768w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_3_equations.png 1238w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="828" height="116" src="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_3_time_tag_and_delta.png" alt="measurement 3 state time tag and delta equations  " srcset="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_3_time_tag_and_delta.png 828w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_3_time_tag_and_delta-300x42.png 300w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_3_time_tag_and_delta-768x108.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 828px) 100vw, 828px"></figure>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="193" src="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_3_state_transistion_and_process_noise-1024x193.png" alt="Kalman Filter state transition and process noise equations" srcset="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_3_state_transistion_and_process_noise-1024x193.png 1024w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_3_state_transistion_and_process_noise-300x56.png 300w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_3_state_transistion_and_process_noise-768x145.png 768w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_3_state_transistion_and_process_noise.png 1360w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="243" src="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_3_state_vector_prediction-1024x243.png" alt="Kalman Filter state vector prediction equation" srcset="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_3_state_vector_prediction-1024x243.png 1024w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_3_state_vector_prediction-300x71.png 300w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_3_state_vector_prediction-768x182.png 768w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/measurement_3_state_vector_prediction.png 1274w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="155" src="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/measurement_2_state_covariance_prediction_2-1024x155.png" alt="Predicted Covariance Equations - Kalman Filter" srcset="https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/measurement_2_state_covariance_prediction_2-1024x155.png 1024w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/measurement_2_state_covariance_prediction_2-300x45.png 300w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/measurement_2_state_covariance_prediction_2-768x116.png 768w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/measurement_2_state_covariance_prediction_2-1536x232.png 1536w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/measurement_2_state_covariance_prediction_2-1568x237.png 1568w, https://thekalmanfilter.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/measurement_2_state_covariance_prediction_2.png 2014w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<h2>Step 4: Compute the Kalman Gain</h2>



<div><p>The Kalman Filter computes a Kalman Gain for each new measurement that determines how much the input measurement will influence the system state estimate. In other words, when a really noisy measurement comes in to update the system state, the Kalman Gain will trust its current state estimate more than this new inaccurate information.</p></div>



<p>This concept is the root of the Kalman Filter algorithm and why it works. It can recognize how to properly weight its current estimate and the new measurement information to form an optimal estimate.</p>



<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><em><strong>K = P<sub>P</sub>H<sup>T</sup> (HP<sub>P</sub>H<sup>T</sup> + R</strong></em>)<sup>-1</sup></td><td data-align="right">Eqn. 4-1</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h2>Step 5: Estimate System State and System State Error Covariance Matrix</h2>



<p>The Kalman Filter uses the Kalman Gain to estimate the system state and error covariance matrix for the time of the input measurement. After the Kalman Gain is computed, it is used to weight the measurement appropriately in two computations.</p>



<p>The first computation is the new system state estimate. The second computation is the system state error covariance.</p>



<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><strong><em>x<sub>k</sub> = x<sub>p</sub> + K(z<sub>k</sub> – Hx<sub>p</sub>)</em></strong></td><td data-align="right">Eqn. 5-1</td></tr><tr><td><strong><em>P<sub>k</sub> = P<sub>P</sub> – KHP<sub>P</sub></em></strong></td><td data-align="right">Eqn. 5-2</td></tr></tbody></table><figcaption>Kalman Filter Estimation Equations</figcaption></figure>



<p>The state estimate computed above is the only state history the Kalman Filter retains. As a result, Kalman Filters can be implemented on machines with low memory restrictions.</p>



<hr>



<p><strong>If you enjoyed reading this post, check out my <a href="https://thekalmanfilter.com/kalman-filter-made-easy-ebook/">eBook</a> Kalman Filter Made Easy and my <a href="https://thekalmanfilter.com/unscented-kalman-filter-made-easy/">Unscented Kalman Filter book</a>. </strong>You will learn: the first principles behind the Kalman Filter, how to create simulations and perform analysis on Kalman Filters, how the Extended Kalman Filter and Unscented Kalman Filter work, and more!</p>



<hr>



<h2>Next Steps</h2>



<p>I hope this post allowed you to see how amazing the Kalman Filter is. And when it is broken up into parts, it is not that intimidating.</p>



<p>In conclusion, the Kalman Filter is a generic process for optimal state estimation. It is used in a variety of applications that require accurate estimation. So now that you know what it is and how it works, go out and use it in your projects!</p>



<p>If you enjoyed reading this post, please share it with your friends on your favorite social network! Thanks for reading!</p>
	</div><!-- .entry-content -->

	<!-- .entry-footer -->

				
</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Understanding Complexity Like an Engineer – The Case of the Ladybird Browser (138 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://t-shaped.nl/understanding-complexity-like-an-engineer-the-case-of-the-ladybird-browser</link>
            <guid>39342887</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 08:58:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://t-shaped.nl/understanding-complexity-like-an-engineer-the-case-of-the-ladybird-browser">https://t-shaped.nl/understanding-complexity-like-an-engineer-the-case-of-the-ladybird-browser</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39342887">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><div>
<p>In order to understand complexity, a good strategy is always to take something apart and try to rebuild it. This is exactly what a few volunteers, lead by a former Safari developer, set out to do. They are building <a href="https://serenityos.org/">SerenityOS</a>, a full-fledged operating system, and <a href="https://ladybird.dev/">Ladybird</a>, a web browser, from the ground up (so: no borrowing an existing module for e.g. reading a JPEG file). Like true engineers, they are doing this <em>for fun</em>. That’s all well and good, but you can’t really build a serious web browser with all its complex features this way, right? Right? This is a story about how engineers approach complexity.</p>



<h2>The complexity called ‘browser engines’</h2>



<p>While twenty years ago you would hand-write the HTML for your website or <em>maybe</em> generate it with PHP, today’s websites are much, much more complicated. As an example, <a href="https://dialogic.nl/2024/02/02/dialogic-is-26-en-lanceert-nieuwe-website/">the recently launched website for Dialogic</a> requires about 700 JavaScript-modules, and has about 19.000 lines of code of its own. There is however a <em>staggering</em> amount of complexity hiding beneath: just this website alone depends on (potentially) another 1.3 million (!) lines of code in modules it uses. This is excluding the browser engine and operating system underneath – that is, the software that is <em>actually</em> doing all the heavy lifting of making a website work. Just consider what these engines need to do: read HTML and CSS, decide what parts go where, decode a dozen image and video formats, parse and execute JavaScript code, deal with secure connections and much, much more. Modern browsers took decades and massive effort to develop, driven by companies like Google (Chrome) and Apple (Safari). </p>



<p>Being curious, I tried the Ladybird browser myself to see if it was any good. Surely these hobbyists have no chance of even reaching 1% of what the big guys can do, right? Setting it up takes a bit of fiddling as they don’t offer any downloads for Ladybird – the project is aimed at nerds to have fun, remember – so you need to download the source code and <a href="https://github.com/SerenityOS/serenity/blob/master/Documentation/BuildInstructions.md">build it yourself</a>. This looks more complicated than it is and a short while later, this Dutch news website showed up on my screen just fine:</p>



<figure><a href="https://t-shaped.nl/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/ladybird-nos.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1000" height="754" src="https://wp.t-shaped.nl/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/ladybird-nos.png" alt="" srcset="https://wp.t-shaped.nl/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/ladybird-nos.png 1000w, https://wp.t-shaped.nl/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/ladybird-nos-300x226.png 300w, https://wp.t-shaped.nl/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/ladybird-nos-768x579.png 768w, https://wp.t-shaped.nl/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/ladybird-nos-265x200.png 265w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px"></a></figure>



<p>If you know what to look for, you will immediately notice this is far from a hobby project anymore and actually quite a bit closer to being an actual browser than the makers are suggesting:</p>



<ul>
<li>The site loads over HTTPS without issue. This means there is a substantial amount of cryptography and networking code is involved.</li>



<li>This site looks and works pretty much the way it should. This means that a fair bit of CSS is actually implemented, and probably a bunch of JavaScript. Just this front page downloads 103 files on load and the browser appears to deal with all of them!</li>



<li>The fonts are all looking as they should. This means that this browser can actually read fonts (WOFF format) and render them correctly. The fact that there is text at all also means this browser deals with Unicode.</li>



<li>There are JPEG images, so they got that sorted out (this is more involved than it seems: decoding the image, resizing it to fit, and a lot more tasks to do before anything can show up on screen)</li>



<li>The browser itself looks a bit like Safari – with tabs and an inspector no less – and a native macOS app. This means that not only did these people build a browser for their own hobby operating system, they actually also built a whole macOS app and the required compatibility layer (they call ‘Lagom’) to run this browser on other operating systems than their own.</li>
</ul>



<p>So wait a minute, why are you not testing that super shiny new Dialogic website you were talking about earlier, you ask? Well…</p>



<figure><a href="https://t-shaped.nl/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/ladybird-crash.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1000" height="480" src="https://wp.t-shaped.nl/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/ladybird-crash.png" alt="" srcset="https://wp.t-shaped.nl/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/ladybird-crash.png 1000w, https://wp.t-shaped.nl/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/ladybird-crash-300x144.png 300w, https://wp.t-shaped.nl/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/ladybird-crash-768x369.png 768w, https://wp.t-shaped.nl/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/ladybird-crash-382x183.png 382w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px"></a></figure>



<p>It crashes, so: time to complain to the developer! Or, not so fast, this project was supposed to be <em>fun</em> remember, so these guys probably want to work on much more interesting things than this little issue. Instead, let’s see how deep the rabbit hole goes and attempt to fix it myself. The first step is to try and cause the same issue with the minimal amount of code possible. The error message hints it has something to do with the <em>grid layout</em> used on the site, which I happen to know is a bit complicated. My first guess was that the engine did not support dynamic CSS calculation (using <em>calc(…)</em>) but it turns out it can do that just fine. After adding some print statements to the code to see which grid the engine was actually trying to process right before the crash, I eventually figured out it was some other grid on the site causing the issue. This grid had the following CSS associated with it:</p>



<pre><code>.four {
        display: grid;
        grid-template-columns: repeat(4, 1fr);
        grid-template-rows: repeat(auto-fit, auto);
}</code></pre>



<p>With this I could reproduce the issue, at which point I decided to <a href="https://github.com/SerenityOS/serenity/issues/23154">raise an issue with the developers</a>, asking them to point me to where I should look to fix the issue (in open source they generally like it when you provide a clear description with a reproducible test case, but they love it when you help actually fix the  issue!). Within a few minutes they pointed me at the CSS spec, and I figured out that my CSS was actually non-compliant – the ‘<em>auto</em>‘ is not allowed in ‘<em>repeat(auto-fit, auto)</em>‘.  Had I looked at this in the Safari inspector, I would have noticed that it too had ignored that specific line. To fix the issue in Ladybird, all that would be needed would be to let it too ignore the invalid CSS rule. <a href="https://github.com/SerenityOS/serenity/pull/23155">So, this is what I did</a> and, let the result speak for itself:</p>



<figure><a href="https://t-shaped.nl/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/ladybird-dialogic.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1000" height="597" src="https://wp.t-shaped.nl/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/ladybird-dialogic.png" alt="" srcset="https://wp.t-shaped.nl/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/ladybird-dialogic.png 1000w, https://wp.t-shaped.nl/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/ladybird-dialogic-300x179.png 300w, https://wp.t-shaped.nl/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/ladybird-dialogic-768x458.png 768w, https://wp.t-shaped.nl/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/ladybird-dialogic-335x200.png 335w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px"></a></figure>



<p>While the layout is still not what it should be (some SVG icons are not showing up, the page is too wide, and there are these annoying dashes breaking words), the browser does not crash and the website is actually usable. I am very curious how far this fun project will be in a year from now.</p>



<p>For me personally, the takeaway from this story is this. Huge complexity does not mean that it cannot be understood nor that the ‘take it apart and rebuild it’ approach is futile – if you are motivated and skilled, you can single-handedly get very far as evidenced by this project. Truth be told, we are not all the 10x programmers these people are – I certainly am not anyway – but the story shows that it is still possible to meaningfully contribute. If tearing it apart and rebuilding from scratch is out of reach, try and contribute a tiny little piece to someone else’s effort – it is very satisfying and indeed, <em>fun</em>.</p>
</div></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Should toggle button show its current state or the state to which it'll change? (2010) (321 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ux.stackexchange.com/questions/1318/should-a-toggle-button-show-its-current-state-or-the-state-to-which-it-will-chan</link>
            <guid>39342649</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 08:13:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ux.stackexchange.com/questions/1318/should-a-toggle-button-show-its-current-state-or-the-state-to-which-it-will-chan">https://ux.stackexchange.com/questions/1318/should-a-toggle-button-show-its-current-state-or-the-state-to-which-it-will-chan</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39342649">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="text">
<div><p><strong>Short Answer</strong>: </p><p>
Quite a late answer, but I'm surprised no one here pointed this out before -- it is possible for a toggle switch to show its current state <em>and</em> the state to which it will change simply <strong>by having text <em>outside</em> the button, instead of on it.</strong></p></div>

<p><img src="https://i.stack.imgur.com/VqPxk.png" alt="Real Life Switches"></p>

<div><p><strong>Long Answer</strong>: </p><p>
As dotancohen points out:</p></div>

<blockquote>
  <p>The problem is that in English "on" and "off" are both adverbs and adjectives.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Buttons that have text outside of their body use this very fact to their advantage! Read on...</p>

<hr><p>
Take the iOS switch design: </p>

<p><img src="https://i.stack.imgur.com/LVcH6.png" alt="iOS On-Off Switch"></p>

<p>Let's focus on the state that's blue and says <strong>ON</strong> for example. </p>

<p><img src="https://i.stack.imgur.com/l3ozk.png" alt="iOS ON"></p>

<p>Can you tell if the switch is ON currently, or if it will go on if you move/click/tap the slider? Is the text obvious? Is "ON" here a state(adjective) or action(verb)? Unclear. Is the color of any use to help you decide this? Probably, but not certainly -- iOS users may be habituated to the states of this design, but there's no telling how non-iOS users would interpret this. To see what I mean, take this real life trip-switch, which has the same design as the iOS switch -- can you tell for sure if the trip switch is currently ON?</p>

<p><img src="https://i.stack.imgur.com/eokjt.png" alt="Ambiguous Trip Switch"></p>

<p>The switch below is along the lines of the iOS design, but far worse...</p>

<p><img src="https://i.stack.imgur.com/zlH4X.png" alt="Ambiguous On-Off Switch"></p>

<p>...it's not even clear which half the slide/click handle is!</p>

<hr><p>
On the other hand, the OS X switch design leaves no room for ambiguity:</p>

<p><img src="https://i.stack.imgur.com/sVmHL.png" alt="Unambiguous On-Off Switch"></p>

<p>The question from jensgram's quote...</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>If the button says ON when the state is off, it is unclear what the setting is. If it is OFF when the state is off, however, where is the ON button?</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>...never arises here since the button neither says ON nor OFF -- it just stands by itself. Also, there's no confusion about the context of the words ON and OFF -- they are very clearly states (adjectives) since clicking on them (in the normal design) would do nothing!</p>

<p>It may be interesting to note that a modification to this design would allow for the text on the far side of the button to be made click-able/tap-able. If so, the word closer to the switch-handle is the state, while other one is the action, and the roles are reversed when the switch is toggled. </p>

<p><img src="https://i.stack.imgur.com/OHRbi.png" alt="Modded On-Off Switch"></p>

<p>Even so, the user's perspective of the switch isn't altered -- at no point is the user confused about the current state of the switch. In fact, the design could be further enhanced for user friendliness by highlighting the current state:</p>

<p><img src="https://i.stack.imgur.com/mp518.png" alt="Highlighted On-Off Switch"></p>

<hr><p>
The Windows Metro UI design for the switch goes a step further, and removes the "action" text from the button, and retains just the "state" text:</p>

<p><img src="https://i.stack.imgur.com/Bh83l.gif" alt="Win8 On-Off Switch"></p>

<p>The color of the button indicates the current state (lit up = ON, as in real life), and the words On/Off underneath the option text reassure the user of the current state.</p>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[28-ton, 1.2-megawatt tidal kite is now exporting power to the grid (251 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://newatlas.com/energy/minesto-tidal-kite/</link>
            <guid>39342532</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 07:50:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://newatlas.com/energy/minesto-tidal-kite/">https://newatlas.com/energy/minesto-tidal-kite/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39342532">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Minesto's fully operational Dragon 12 looks like some sort of futuristic military drone – but it behaves remarkably like a kite underwater. It uses lift generated by tidal flows to fly patterns faster than the currents, harvesting renewable energy.</p><p>Solar energy is the bedrock of most renewable energy grid plans – but lunar energy is even more predictable, and a number of different companies are working to commercialize energy generated from the regular inflows and outflows of the tides.</p><p>One we've completely missed is Minesto, which is taking a very different and remarkably dynamic approach compared to most. Where devices like <a href="https://newatlas.com/energy/orbital-o2-floating-marine-turbine-grid-connection/" data-cms-ai="0">Orbital's O2 tidal turbine</a> more or less just sit there in the water harvesting energy from tidal currents, Minesto's Dragon series are anchored to the sea bed, and fly around like kites, treating the currents like wind. </p><div data-video-disable-history="" data-align-center="">
    
        <p><ps-youtubeplayer data-video-player="" data-player-id="fa70a6e21aa314140a746eac4d3061e0d" data-video-id="dkXinDn67Kw" data-video-title="Minesto's Deep Green technology – Unlocking renewable baseload power">

    <iframe id="YouTubeVideoPlayer-fa70a6e21aa314140a746eac4d3061e0d" role="application" title="YouTube embedded video player" allowfullscreen="" loading="lazy" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/dkXinDn67Kw?enablejsapi=1"></iframe>
</ps-youtubeplayer>
</p>
    
    
        <p>Minesto's Deep Green technology – Unlocking renewable baseload power</p>
    
</div><p>Just as <a href="https://newatlas.com/fraunhofer-nts-kite-wind-power/24843/" data-cms-ai="0">land-based wind energy kites</a> fly in figure 8 patterns to accelerate themselves faster than the wind, so does the Dragon underwater. This, says Minesto, lets the Dragon pull more energy from a given tidal current than other designs – and it also changes the economic equations for relevant sites, making slower tidal flows worth exploiting. </p><p>These are by no means small kites – the Dragon 12 needs to be disassembled to fit in a shipping container. It rocks a monster 12-meter (39-ft) wingspan, and weighs no less than 28 tons. But compared to other offshore power options like wind turbines, it's an absolute minnow, and extremely easy to install using a single smallish boat and a sea bed tether. </p><p>As with any renewable energy project, the key figure here is LCoE (levelized cost of energy) – so what's it gonna cost? Well, back in 2017, <a href="https://minesto.com/news/minestos-technology-transforms-ocean-energy-into-one-of-the-most-cost-effective-energy-resources-new-cost-of-energy-analysis-states/" target="_blank" data-cms-ai="0">Minesto projected</a> about US$108/MWh once its first hundred megawatts of capacity are installed – with costs falling thereafter as low as $54/MWh.</p><div data-align-center="">
                
                    <figure>
    
    
    
    


<p><img alt="The Minesto team poses with the 1.2 megawatt Dragon 12" width="1268" height="960" data-image-size="articleImage" loading="lazy" data-srcset="https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/5edfc48/2147483647/strip/true/crop/7402x5604+0+0/resize/440x333!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F8f%2F3d%2F339b4c3e41d58f891d99c372af53%2Fminesto-gothenburg-team.jpg 440w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/0ce9fd2/2147483647/strip/true/crop/7402x5604+0+0/resize/800x606!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F8f%2F3d%2F339b4c3e41d58f891d99c372af53%2Fminesto-gothenburg-team.jpg 800w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/3874789/2147483647/strip/true/crop/7402x5604+0+0/resize/1200x909!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F8f%2F3d%2F339b4c3e41d58f891d99c372af53%2Fminesto-gothenburg-team.jpg 1200w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/27f2fb6/2147483647/strip/true/crop/7402x5604+0+0/resize/1920x1454!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F8f%2F3d%2F339b4c3e41d58f891d99c372af53%2Fminesto-gothenburg-team.jpg 1920w" data-src="https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/8826b38/2147483647/strip/true/crop/7402x5604+0+0/resize/1268x960!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F8f%2F3d%2F339b4c3e41d58f891d99c372af53%2Fminesto-gothenburg-team.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 1240px) 800px, (min-width: 1024px) 95vw, 100vw" srcset="https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/5edfc48/2147483647/strip/true/crop/7402x5604+0+0/resize/440x333!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F8f%2F3d%2F339b4c3e41d58f891d99c372af53%2Fminesto-gothenburg-team.jpg 440w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/0ce9fd2/2147483647/strip/true/crop/7402x5604+0+0/resize/800x606!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F8f%2F3d%2F339b4c3e41d58f891d99c372af53%2Fminesto-gothenburg-team.jpg 800w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/3874789/2147483647/strip/true/crop/7402x5604+0+0/resize/1200x909!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F8f%2F3d%2F339b4c3e41d58f891d99c372af53%2Fminesto-gothenburg-team.jpg 1200w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/27f2fb6/2147483647/strip/true/crop/7402x5604+0+0/resize/1920x1454!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F8f%2F3d%2F339b4c3e41d58f891d99c372af53%2Fminesto-gothenburg-team.jpg 1920w" src="https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/8826b38/2147483647/strip/true/crop/7402x5604+0+0/resize/1268x960!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F8f%2F3d%2F339b4c3e41d58f891d99c372af53%2Fminesto-gothenburg-team.jpg">
</p>



    
    

    
        <div><figcaption itemprop="caption">The Minesto team poses with the 1.2 megawatt Dragon 12</figcaption><p>Minesto</p></div>
    
</figure>

                
            </div><p>For an unfair comparison, <a href="https://www.orbitalmarine.com/demystifying-the-cost-of-tidal-energy/" target="_blank" data-cms-ai="0">Orbital has claimed</a> it's hoping for an LCoE less than $253/MWh for its very first O2 tidal turbine, a figure that'll drop with scale, and fixed-bottom offshore wind projects in 2022 had an estimated average LCoE around $89/MWh in 2022, <a href="https://www.energy.gov/sites/default/files/2023-08/offshore-wind-market-report-2023-edition-summary.pdf" target="_blank" data-cms-ai="0">according to the US DoE</a>.</p><p>The Dragon 12, like other tidal devices, will be more effective in some places than others – and Denmark's Faroe Islands, an archipelago in the chilly North Atlantic between Scotland and Iceland, offer ideal conditions. Home to about 55,000 people and more than a million puffins, the Faroe Islands funnel tidal currents through a number of slim channels. This accelerates the water significantly, and thus increases the energy that devices like the Dragon 12 can harvest. </p><div data-align-center="">
                
                    <figure>
    
    
    
    


<p><img alt="The narrow channels between the Faroe Islands accelerate tidal flows, creating an ideal location for tidal energy projects" width="1440" height="810" data-image-size="articleImage" loading="lazy" data-srcset="https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/59ebf21/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3840x2160+0+0/resize/440x248!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F39%2Fe291ef3c4e27b40132414f5fd61e%2Fdragon-4-towing-1.jpg 440w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/1357fc0/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3840x2160+0+0/resize/800x450!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F39%2Fe291ef3c4e27b40132414f5fd61e%2Fdragon-4-towing-1.jpg 800w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/869abf1/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3840x2160+0+0/resize/1200x675!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F39%2Fe291ef3c4e27b40132414f5fd61e%2Fdragon-4-towing-1.jpg 1200w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/8eb5956/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3840x2160+0+0/resize/1920x1080!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F39%2Fe291ef3c4e27b40132414f5fd61e%2Fdragon-4-towing-1.jpg 1920w" data-src="https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/9d94ca5/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3840x2160+0+0/resize/1440x810!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F39%2Fe291ef3c4e27b40132414f5fd61e%2Fdragon-4-towing-1.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 1240px) 800px, (min-width: 1024px) 95vw, 100vw" srcset="https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/59ebf21/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3840x2160+0+0/resize/440x248!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F39%2Fe291ef3c4e27b40132414f5fd61e%2Fdragon-4-towing-1.jpg 440w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/1357fc0/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3840x2160+0+0/resize/800x450!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F39%2Fe291ef3c4e27b40132414f5fd61e%2Fdragon-4-towing-1.jpg 800w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/869abf1/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3840x2160+0+0/resize/1200x675!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F39%2Fe291ef3c4e27b40132414f5fd61e%2Fdragon-4-towing-1.jpg 1200w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/8eb5956/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3840x2160+0+0/resize/1920x1080!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F39%2Fe291ef3c4e27b40132414f5fd61e%2Fdragon-4-towing-1.jpg 1920w" src="https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/9d94ca5/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3840x2160+0+0/resize/1440x810!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F39%2Fe291ef3c4e27b40132414f5fd61e%2Fdragon-4-towing-1.jpg">
</p>



    
    

    
        <div><figcaption itemprop="caption">The narrow channels between the Faroe Islands accelerate tidal flows, creating an ideal location for tidal energy projects</figcaption><p>Minesto</p></div>
    
</figure>

                
            </div><p>That's where the first Dragon has been deployed, and on Friday, it was connected to the local power grid to begin delivering energy. </p><p>"This is a big day for Minesto," said Dr Martin Edlund, CEO of Minesto, in a press release. "We have reached the most significant milestone in the history of the company by producing electricity to the grid with our mega-watt scale powerplant. We are both proud and happy and more than ever look forward to the journey ahead ... The competitiveness of the Dragon 12 is straight to the point; it's powerful, cost-effective and feeds predictable electricity to the grid."</p><p>Check out a video below.</p><div data-video-disable-history="" data-align-center="">
    
        <p><ps-youtubeplayer data-video-player="" data-player-id="f239d7734c38c49b799423b48da69bec3" data-video-id="A9aYMGYO_ZA" data-video-title="Minesto reaches historic milestone – first electricity to grid with tidal powerplant Dragon 12">

    <iframe id="YouTubeVideoPlayer-f239d7734c38c49b799423b48da69bec3" role="application" title="YouTube embedded video player" allowfullscreen="" loading="lazy" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/A9aYMGYO_ZA?enablejsapi=1"></iframe>
</ps-youtubeplayer>
</p>
    
    
        <p>Minesto reaches historic milestone – first electricity to grid with tidal powerplant Dragon 12</p>
    
</div><p>Source: <a href="https://minesto.com/" target="_blank" data-cms-ai="0">Minesto</a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[It Can Be Done (2003) (315 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://multicians.org/andre.html</link>
            <guid>39342143</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 06:38:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://multicians.org/andre.html">https://multicians.org/andre.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39342143">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>


 

<p><img src="https://multicians.org/mulimg/andre-small.jpg" width="162" height="272" alt="Andre with coffee cup" title="click for a larger view" srcset="https://multicians.org/mulimg/andre-small.jpg 1x, https://multicians.org/mulimg/andre-small-2x.jpg 2x" onclick="showLightBox2('mulimg/andre-big.jpg','486','811','Andre with coffee cup','click for a larger view','André Bensoussan, CISL, 1975 [THVV]','mulimg/andre-big-2x.jpg')"></p>

<p>
  The late <a href="https://multicians.org/multicians.html#Bensoussan" title="Multician: Designer (GE/CISL): File manager, Initialization, AIM, NSS.">André Bensoussan</a> worked with me on the Multics operating system at Honeywell in Cambridge. 
  We were working on a <a href="https://multicians.org/mgn.html#NSS" title="glossary: New Storage System. MR 4.0 included a rewritten storage...">major change</a> to the file system, 
  which required a subsystem, the <a href="https://multicians.org/mgv.html#VTOC" title="glossary: Volume Table of Contents. Region of a physical volume...">VTOC</a> manager, 
  to manage file description information. 
  It had to transport the file information between disk and memory,
  manage a shared memory buffer pool, 
  and manage space on disk for the information. 
  In other words, it was a small virtual memory manager.
</p>

<p>
  André took on the job of design, implementation, and test of the VTOC manager.
  He started by sitting at his desk and drawing a lot of diagrams. 
  I was the project coordinator, 
  so I used to drop in on him and ask how things were going. 
  "Still designing," he'd say. 
  He wanted the diagrams to look beautiful and symmetrical as well as capturing all the state information.
  I was getting nervous about the schedule, 
  so I was glad when he finally began writing code.
  He wrote in pencil, at his desk, instead of using a terminal.
  He declined offers of typing help, and just kept writing away in pencil.
  He rewrote parts, copied things over, erased and rewrote.
</p>

<p>
  Finally André took his neat final pencil copy to a terminal and typed the whole program in.
  His first compilation attempt failed; he corrected three typos, tried again, and the code compiled. 
  We bound it into the system and tried it out, and it worked the first time.
</p>

<p>
  In fact, <a href="https://multicians.org/vtoc_man.html" title="PL/I source of the Multics storage system VTOC manager.">the VTOC manager</a> worked perfectly from then on.
  Only one bug was ever found in it, and that was my fault: 
  André had asked me the calling sequence for an error procedure, 
  and I'd guessed instead of looking it up, so it crashed the first time it hit an error. 
  Beyond that the program was perfect.
</p>

<p>
  How did André do this, with no tool but a pencil?
</p>

<p>
  <cite>IEEE Computer, April 1994</cite> (Updated November 2003)
</p>
         <!-- tail -->
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[FOSDEM 2024: my experience, some notes and tech tips (218 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/</link>
            <guid>39342109</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 06:32:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/">https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39342109">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      
      <p>I finally went to <a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/">FOSDEM</a>. I’m sleep-deprived, completely exhausted, but incredibly excited
about the whole experience.</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/cover.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/cover_hu7849b20ce9ad2599a2189d7278ab15e2_485705_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="450" alt="FOSDEM in one picture.">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      FOSDEM in one picture.
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>I’ve split this post into three separate sections.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><a href="#the-conference">overall notes on the conference and the city</a></p>
<ul>
<li>less technical, but sheds light on the FOSDEM experience</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="#the-stands-the-hallway-track">the hallway track and stands</a></p>
<ul>
<li>the thing you probably came to FOSDEM for</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="#the-talks">my notes on the sessions I attended</a></p>
<ul>
<li>plus sessions that I plan to watch in the future</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="the-conference">The conference</h2>
<p><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/">FOSDEM (Free and Open source Software Developers’ European Meeting)</a> is a huge non-profit,
volunteer-organized conference that’s free of charge to attend thanks to sponsors and donations. It took place in
Brussels, Belgium at the ULB campus.</p>
<p>I heard about this conference from a friend who went there years ago, and after hearing about the experience and the
content there I knew I had to be there at least once in my life. But then a pandemic happened, so it was sort of in the
backlog for a while.</p>
<p><a href="https://concise.ee/">My current employer</a> provides a perk that allows developers to attend technical conferences. After
the FOSDEM 2024 schedule was available I put together an
initial set of talks to attend, presented it to my employer, and got a green light to attend (and
travelling/accommodation paid for).</p>
<h2 id="the-city">The city</h2>
<p>To make sure that I’m well-rested, I arrived the night before FOSDEM with my friend. After dropping my stuff off at the
hotel, we went to get something to eat and continued at the Delirium Beer Garden to sample some of the finest Belgian
beers. It was very crowded, but after the first beers and some walking around the many floors we found a place to chill.</p>
<p>We ended up with sampling a meter of beer which was a selection of ten small beers, laid out on a plank. It was a nice
way to try different tastes and honestly all of them were either good or great. Cherry, raspberry and the green cactus
option were the sweetest, like some good lemonade that has the potential to cause hangovers.</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/meter-of-beer.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/meter-of-beer_hu021252dd404acda00330095955c35982_2615732_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="Meter of beer. It didn't come pre-sampled by someone else, don't worry.">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      Meter of beer. It didn't come pre-sampled by someone else, don't worry.
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>








  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/cactus.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/cactus_hu44aaccd4a744f8c031de06dc81d7364a_2318858_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="1067" alt="This one was called &quot;Cactus&quot;. Didn't taste like one, but certainly looked the part and was absolutely delicious.">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      This one was called "Cactus". Didn't taste like one, but certainly looked the part and was absolutely delicious.
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p><strong>Free tech tip:</strong> don’t underestimate the strength of Belgian beer. You won’t taste it, but that 8-9% alcohol per
volume really hits in the morning.</p>
<p>Brussels is allegedly very nice, however I’m not a big fan of the way trash is handled, there are bags everywhere and
some of them are broken, leaving small pieces of trash everywhere. You could also smell the lack of public restrooms
when walking down the streets in the city center.</p>
<p>There are some glimpses of good bicycle infrastructure, but they often don’t connect well or are simply lines on the
ground which doesn’t protect that well from cars. Based on the honks and the number of times they did not stop at
crosswalks, I can only assume that drivers in Brussels are both very aggressive and very incompetent at driving. In a
way it felt like home, especially since my hometown of Tallinn also uses red paint on some bicycle paths.</p>
<h2 id="the-dos-and-donts-of-fosdem">The dos and don’ts of FOSDEM</h2>
<p>I went to the ULB campus using a tram. If you’re not sure which one to take, then take the one with the most developers
headed towards it. Knowing when to get off is also easy as you can simply follow the crowd.</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/tofosdem.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/tofosdem_hu7ab5f124a1bf888a54004238401d1e4a_4500232_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="1067" alt="To FOSDEM!">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      To FOSDEM!
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>I arrived roughly 15 minutes before the keynote session. At that time there was plenty of room in the auditorium. By the
time the keynote started there were no seats available, so you might want to do the same and arrive a bit early.</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/keynote.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/keynote_hu4dbaa62b6fbae368049d0bf32da4dce5_3202165_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="15 minutes before the keynote. The place was packed at the start of the keynote, with more people still coming in.">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      15 minutes before the keynote. The place was packed at the start of the keynote, with more people still coming in.
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>There were <em>a lot</em> of people attending FOSDEM. Keep a map handy, because your next session might take place in a room
that might be tricky to find, especially as a
first-timer. <a href="https://f-droid.org/en/packages/be.digitalia.fosdem/">The FOSDEM Companion app</a> is great for that, click
on the session you’re interested in and the room name, and you’ll have a good idea on where it’s taking place.</p>
<p>This FOSDEM was the 24th FOSDEM to take place, which is important because the 25th one is happening next year. If you’ve
been to any previous ones and are attending next year, then bring the oldest FOSDEM shirt with you, there will be a
special photoshoot taking place.</p>
<p>If you’re going to attend FOSDEM in-person, then definitely
read <a href="https://petersouter.xyz/fosdem-survival-guide/">the FOSDEM survival guide.</a> All the points there are still
relevant and helped me out tremendously during my trip.</p>
<p>In short:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>take an earlier bus/tram to get to FOSDEM to avoid crowds and get there on time</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>if you want to guarantee getting a seat in a session, consider joining an earlier session in the same room</p>
<ul>
<li>you might also learn something about an area you had no clue about, which is a great bonus!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>don’t underestimate the strength of Belgian beer</p>
<ul>
<li>trust me on that one</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>food lines can get very long, bring some light snacks and plenty of water with you</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>some places had water bottle refilling stations, such as the U building, but I had a hard time finding one in
others</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>there was plenty of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Club-Mate">Club-Mate for sale</a> and based on the number of empty
bottles it was a crowd favourite</p>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>There were 879 events taking place at FOSDEM 2024. That is a lot of talks to go through. My recommendation is to take an
evening at least a week from the event and go through the list of talks starting with main tracks and lightning talks,
and following it up with devrooms that align with your interests.</p>
<p>If you do it in the <a href="https://f-droid.org/packages/be.digitalia.fosdem/">FOSDEM Companion</a> app, then you can bookmark
them and view your initial schedule. The app will show you where there are overlapping sessions by coloring the
start/end times red. The app can also show you if a room is too full to attend. Don’t forget that switching rooms might
take about 15 minutes in some cases due to the size of the campus, so leave some room for walking in your schedule.</p>
<p>In my experience, the most enjoyable FOSDEM experience is one where you attend at most 2-3 tracks during the day and
leave plenty of time for eating, resting and visiting all the stands. It’s going to be exhausting either way, so you
might as well make the most of the FOSDEM live experience. Talks are recorded and will be published soon after the event
so you’re not going to miss much if you take things easy (unless there are issues capturing the session).</p>
<p>Here are a few simple guidelines that I recommend following so that listening to talks in FOSDEM live is a great
experience for both you and those around you:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>try to get to your next talk about 15 minutes before it starts, that allows you to queue up early and not miss your
session</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>don’t talk or whisper during the talk and the Q&amp;A session with the speakers</p>
<ul>
<li>there were so many cases where the speaker could not even hear the question being asked, which is disrespectful
to the speaker and the audience</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>if you really need to leave early, then be as quiet as possible</p>
<ul>
<li>the old desks at the seats make a lot of noise if you carelessly put them back up-right</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>if you really didn’t have time for a snack, then don’t bring something that makes a lot of noise or smells strongly to
the auditorium</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>If you want to get a FOSDEM t-shirt or hoodie in your favourite size, then the first half of the first day is the ideal
opportunity for that. At FOSDEM 2024 the t-shirts cost 25 EUR, hoodies cost 50 EUR.</p>
<p>Most payments you’ll make will likely be with contactless payments via your card or phone, but definitely bring some
cash with you in smaller denominations as there were a few cases at the start of the conference where the payment
systems were not working properly, likely due to network issues. Somewhere between 100-200 EUR will likely cover
anything you’d need at the conference itself.</p>
<p>With the food trucks I made an observation: the lines were longer for the more expensive and higher quality food
options. The cheaper ones are okay and are generally quite fast to get. The more “premium” trucks were not much slower
though so waiting in line might pay off.</p>
<p>During the keynote it was emphasized that some of the attendees will get sick as a result of this conference. They call
it <em>the FOSDEM flu</em>. I guess it’s a thing that happens at many big conferences, but in any case if you do visit FOSDEM
then please don’t do it while sick. If you fall sick at the event, then rest at the hotel and watch it on a livestream
instead. There’s always next year!</p>
<p>One pattern I noticed is that quite a few talks were used as a great marketing tool for highlighting issues that the
speaker would like some help with solving. What better way to improve FOSS than to involve people who might not even be
aware of the issues but have the technical know-how to help?</p>
<h2 id="the-stands-the-hallway-track">The stands (the hallway track)</h2>
<p>One of the highlights of the FOSDEM experience are the various stands in different buildings in the campus. You’ll find
all sorts of different projects being represented, ranging from big, established ones (Fedora, Debian, Nextcloud,
PostgreSQL etc.) all the way down to small projects and organizations (postmarketOS, Ubuntu Touch, CalyxOS and many
more).</p>
<p>Most stands offer free merch, such as stickers. A lot of stands sell merch, most accept card payments, some accept
payments via online credit card payments, and a few take cash only.</p>
<p>I visited most booths at the event and spoke briefly with many of the people present there. If you’re just curious about
what’s on display and have no background knowledge, then don’t be afraid to ask questions, no matter how simple you
think they are!</p>
<p>Here are my notes on the stands that I found the most interesting</p>
<h2 id="gnu-radiohttpswwwgnuradioorg"><a href="https://www.gnuradio.org/">GNU Radio</a></h2>
<p>This stand had a simple and effective demo of a device monitoring the 2.4 GHz spectrum, which is also where older Wi-Fi
standards operate in. The person hosting the booth was happy to explain what was going on, even bringing out details
such as signals bouncing around the room and how they show up on the spectrum visualizer.</p>
<p>Turns out that you can achieve this by putting together two blocks in a visual editor in GNU Radio, and this is why it’s
on my todo list now.</p>
<p><a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/gnuradio.mp4">There’s also a video clip of the visualization running.</a></p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/gnuradio.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/gnuradio_hu7849b20ce9ad2599a2189d7278ab15e2_787043_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="450" alt="GNU Radio showcasing its visualization prowess.">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      GNU Radio showcasing its visualization prowess.
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<h2 id="minetesthttpswwwminetestnet"><a href="https://www.minetest.net/">Minetest</a></h2>
<p>Minetest is an open source game engine and had a booth present at the event. They had the game running on a laptop. A
Steam Deck with the official dock was also present. I’ve previously heard about this project many years ago, at that
time it was a simple Minecraft-like game but a bit too basic in my opinion. The demo at the booth reminded me of
something more polished and yet familiar enough to remind me of Minecraft 1.8 Beta days.</p>
<p>Turns out that over the years the game engine has seen a lot of development and there are many creators who have mades
games based on this engine. I was also delighted and surprised to hear that Minetest has been used in educational
projects.</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/minetest.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/minetest_hu832b077c1ba8878c10568e18ff8343cb_3779162_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="Minetest running on a laptop, with a booklet showcasing some games made on it in front.">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      Minetest running on a laptop, with a booklet showcasing some games made on it in front.
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>This was a nice and colorful corner of the event, and now I’m interested in giving Minetest a try again.</p>
<h2 id="ubuntu-touchhttpsubuntu-touchio"><a href="https://ubuntu-touch.io/">Ubuntu Touch</a></h2>
<p>Ah, Ubuntu Touch. I believe the first time I heard about Ubuntu Touch was when they introduced the convergence idea.
Your phone is the only computer you have, use it as a phone when out and about, and connect it to a dock when at home to
get a desktop experience.</p>
<p>The booth had a wide variety of devices present, including Fairphone 4 and 5 (this isn’t the first time you’ll see these
models mentioned). At the booth were people who actually daily drive Ubuntu Touch, and one person I talked to expressed
their interest in porting Ubuntu Touch to a Samsung foldable phone.</p>
<p>Ubuntu Touch isn’t probably something I’d run full-time, but perhaps it’s time to give it a go again. My Nexus 5 still
has the boot logo that Ubuntu Touch installer creates, so that will serve as a reminder for me to check it out.</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/ubuntu-touch.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/ubuntu-touch_hud9380aa0b48bafdbd03b71b74b34e828_3111448_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="1067" alt="Ubuntu Touch mascot looking over the phones.">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      Ubuntu Touch mascot looking over the phones.
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<h2 id="sailfishoshttpssailfishosorg"><a href="https://sailfishos.org/">SailfishOS</a></h2>
<p>I knew of SailfishOS, but had never tried a device out with that OS. At FOSDEM I finally had the chance to do it, and
out of all the custom OS options that aren’t Android-based, this one was the one with the smoothest and most polished
experience. When speaking to the person hosting the booth, I also learned that it is possible to even run Android apps
on it, although after doing some research on their website it seems like it’s a feature that you need to pay for.</p>
<p>The phones laid out on the booth were various Sony Xperia devices. I’ve not used or seen those devices, but they felt
really great in hand and were super small compared to modern phones. Seems like these models are also the ones that have
got the most polish and support, based on the materials on the website and my two minutes of fiddling with them.</p>
<p>Out of all the non-Android alternative operating systems, this one has the most potential to be a daily driver. The
person at the booth uses theirs as a daily driver so there must be potential on it. The corporate backing is likely what
allows the OS to feel usable and hopefully that will be enough to keep this project alive.</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/sailfishos.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/sailfishos_hu596441043472fcd255d36606932f4049_2955724_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="Various Sony Xperia phones running SailfishOS.">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      Various Sony Xperia phones running SailfishOS.
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<h2 id="droidianhttpsdroidianorg-and-postmarketoshttpspostmarketosorg"><a href="https://droidian.org/">Droidian</a> and <a href="https://postmarketos.org/">postmarketOS</a></h2>
<p>There were multiple booths where you could try out various versions of Linux-based phones that aren’t Android.</p>
<p>The phones were all sorts of older and newer devices that originally shipped with Android. The experience and support
was a combination of the hardware and the state of the mobile Linux distribution and UI. Some were quite okay, some were
rough, and some were just slow due to the age of the phone itself.</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/droidian.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/droidian_hu72649ef447c4fb8bdf51ecaa90480738_3184444_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="Plain old Linux? On my phone? It's more likely than you think!">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      Plain old Linux? On my phone? It's more likely than you think!
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>I really appreciate these types of efforts to give new life to old devices. Most Android devices lose software support
after a few years, but with projects that basically put Linux on a phone you can still find ways to make use of the
devices. They might not be stable enough yet to be considered a reliable daily driver as a smartphone, but you can do
all sorts of cool things with them, like running web servers or hosting encrypted remote backups of critical data.</p>
<p>One of the booths also had a Pinephone in a keyboard dock, which was neat as I’ve never seen a Pinephone in real life,
nor had the opportunity to try one with a keyboard. It wasn’t ergonomic trying to do it with two hands, but maybe I was
holding it wrong.</p>
<p>It was interesting to see GNOME or KDE-based user interfaces on phones. The gestures and navigating the UI was a bit
rough since there were slight differences on each OS. Still cool though!</p>
<p>Oh, and there was a visitor who had some cool gear with them. Other than a GPD portable computer, they also had a
mechanical keyboard with a wide display attached to it.
They tried connecting it to a phone that was on display at the booth, and it recognized it as a second display on the
first try. The model of the keyboard is <em>Ficihp K2</em> in case you’re interested in similar gear.</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/dockeddroidian.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/dockeddroidian_hu0b57ff4f22c115e2d3388ccba4f4e676_2650852_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="How to take notes in the coolest way possible.">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      How to take notes in the coolest way possible.
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<h2 id="calyxoshttpscalyxosorg"><a href="https://calyxos.org/">CalyxOS</a></h2>
<p>I had never heard of this Android-based OS before, but there they were, showcasing it on a freaking Fairphone 5 (and
also some other phones)!</p>
<p>The people at the booth were very friendly and helpful, answering any of the questions I had about app compatibility and
the OS itself.</p>
<p>The project seems to be backed by an US-based non-profit, <a href="https://calyxinstitute.org/">the Calyx Institute.</a></p>
<p>I’m a bit wary about using this on my daily driver Fairphone 5 running Android 13 as I just got it, but if I had a spare
one for testing
I’d definitely check out how well it fares as a privacy-focused OS. The potential is there and hopefully CalyxOS will
have a chance to prove itself as a long-term and stable project.</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/calyxos.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/calyxos_hu39a404366cc5c1dca967c674d4df7e88_1302941_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="560" alt="Totally forgot to take a photo of phones running CalyxOS as I was too busy giving the OS a try, but here's a hat!">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      Totally forgot to take a photo of phones running CalyxOS as I was too busy giving the OS a try, but here's a hat!
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>Side note: I’m planning on covering my Fairphone 5 experience as a separate post in the future, but one
takeaway from FOSDEM is that I’ve accidentally picked a tinkerer’s dream phone.</p>
<h2 id="automotive-grade-linuxhttpswwwautomotivelinuxorg"><a href="https://www.automotivelinux.org/">Automotive Grade Linux</a></h2>
<p>Like with many projects, I had never heard about this one before FOSDEM.</p>
<p>This booth was displaying various interfaces designed for cars. There was a demo vehicle dashboard which was simulating
a moving car. Next to it were two bigger displays that had infotainment and control panel functionality with all sorts
of buttons on it.</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/automotivelinux.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/automotivelinux_hu56a1e5ea21504e18807957d0c877fdf5_4340882_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="Yup, that's RISC-V!">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      Yup, that's RISC-V!
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>Between these two setups was a small control board with 9 keys and two dials. Some of the buttons popped up warning
lights on the digital dashboard, such as passenger airbag failure. Other buttons had various stickers on them: HTML5, Qt
and Flutter. Turns out that the intotainment display demo was built on top of containers and pressing a key would stop
the running one and start up a different one based on whichever button you clicked.</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/automotivelinuxdash.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/automotivelinuxdash_hu9e86079445646908bb2b5f47c7a5ae8e_3232342_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="Unlike with my actual car, with this one you could turn the warning lights off without having to spend a lot of money!">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      Unlike with my actual car, with this one you could turn the warning lights off without having to spend a lot of money!
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>One of the infotainment displays was running off of a Raspberry Pi, which was cool. The rest of the displays were
running off of a stack of various bits of hardware.</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/automotivelinuxinfotainment.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/automotivelinuxinfotainment_hu267ac6fe5af642731ee88c1cf172ae8a_3811961_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="Dashboard and infotainment setup, with the container switching buttons between them.">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      Dashboard and infotainment setup, with the container switching buttons between them.
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>Based on the marketing materials at the booth it seems like automotive grade Linux is also collaborating with some big
names in the auto industry, which is neat!</p>
<h2 id="pine64httpspine64org"><a href="https://pine64.org/">Pine64</a></h2>
<p>I’ve occasionally checked out Pine64 progress and devices online, and at FOSDEM I finally got around to play around with
some of them.</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/pine64.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/pine64_huf85406092acd00edde211bd515142fb7_3735501_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="So much tech to play with!">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      So much tech to play with!
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>I first checked out the smartwatch named <a href="https://wiki.pine64.org/wiki/PineTime">PineTime</a>. It comes in multiple
versions, one for daily use (the sealed model),
and one which is bulkier but easier to open and flash in case you mess up your firmware. I’m currently using a <a href="https://www.casio.com/us/watches/casio/product.F-105W-1A/">Casio
F105W</a> and haven’t been a big fan of smartwatches, but the
hardware on the sealed model felt premium and something I’d
pay good money for. The functionality was basic, but it had everything you’d want from a basic watch, plus a heart rate
monitor and even a Pong-like game. I’m seriously considering getting one now.</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/pinetime.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/pinetime_hu3ad8e2527eaacd40f83b199c7d6f5a51_2908193_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="1067" alt="Do you know what time it is?">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      Do you know what time it is?
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p><a href="https://wiki.pine64.org/wiki/PineTab-V">The PineTab-V</a>, a RISC-V based tablet, was also present and running KDE Plasma.
The experience was unstable at the time
as I had the settings app crash on me once, but that’s likely down to driver support not being quite there yet. That’s
OK, since they advertise the device as an experimental device right now.</p>
<p>Something I wasn’t even aware of was the <a href="https://wiki.pine64.org/wiki/PineNote">PineNote</a>, a Linux tablet with an e-ink
display. It was running an actual GNOME desktop on it so the interface was instantly familiar to me. As a test case I
opened up my blog on it and it worked just fine. Scrolling the
page to read the blog was a bit clunky due to the low refresh rate that an e-ink display has, that’s just a limitation
of the technology. <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/pinenote-scrolling.mp4">Here’s a clip demonstrating it.</a></p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/pinenote.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/pinenote_hu76e2f6912f9f137ac4aa788316aca27d_3768173_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="1067" alt="Shameless plug, I know.">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      Shameless plug, I know.
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>While I was checking out the hardware, there was also a demonstration going on of the capabilities of
the <a href="https://wiki.pine64.org/wiki/Pinecil">Pinecil</a>, a
small soldering iron that’s really cool and gets quite hot. I’m a bit surprised that it didn’t trigger the smoke alarm
that was a few meters away from the booth.</p>
<h2 id="bytenight-2024--hackerspace-brussels-hsbxl">Bytenight 2024 @ Hackerspace Brussels (HSBXL)</h2>
<p>One of the many FOSDEM fringe events was a party hosted at <a href="https://hsbxl.be/">Hackerspace Brussels</a>, a hackerspace
located in an old industrial building. The event had DJ-s playing music, a t-shirt making booth, a fancy projector
setup, a room with SuperTuxKart on a big screen and a small Raspberry Pi-based mini arcade box, and the room where I
assume work gets done since it had all the electronics equipment and workspaces.</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/hsbxl-workshop.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/hsbxl-workshop_hub30cbfdc236012c2f99017f057794851_3742932_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="Probably where the work happens.">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      Probably where the work happens.
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>The projector setup used in the party area was simple but elegant. It was positioned in a way that allowed various
surfaces to reflect the video at different levels, making it all feel
three-dimensional. <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/hsbxl-visuals.mp4">Here’s a video demonstrating it!</a></p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/hsbxl-vibe.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/hsbxl-vibe_hu7849b20ce9ad2599a2189d7278ab15e2_493439_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="450" alt="Pretty cool vibe, not gonna lie.">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      Pretty cool vibe, not gonna lie.
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>I loved how one of the hackerspace members was excited to show off the insides of the mini arcade cabinet and explain
the build process of it, including the design of the physical components. It’s cool seeing people get enthusiastic about
something they’ve built with their own hands. <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/hsbxl-arcade-doom.mp4">Here they are, playing DOOM (SNES version)!</a></p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/hsbxl-arcade.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/hsbxl-arcade_hu06939393fe7885b844627a8d949b30f4_2866492_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="1067" alt="DOOM? Check. Belgian beer? Check. What else could you ever want from life?">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      DOOM? Check. Belgian beer? Check. What else could you ever want from life?
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>








  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/hsbxl-arcade-insides.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/hsbxl-arcade-insides_hu7d83b68c577d5879a0648593ea1e156a_2637671_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="1067" alt="FOSDEM inside <3">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      FOSDEM inside &lt;3
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>At one point me and my friend ended up speaking to a group of people, one of whom was showcasing their Tamagochi and
offering it to others to interact with. I learned from them that there exists a self-hostable Snapchat-like app
called <a href="https://piqchat.net/">Piqchat.</a> My friend gave it a go on their instance and after fiddling with the sign-up
process (we were at least two beers in at this point) he got it working.</p>
<p>We arrived around 20:45ish at the location, and at that point the dancefloor was a bit empty, but after 23:00ish it
looked like a proper party. I wasn’t in the mood to party much because there was a whole second day of FOSDEM left and I
was already exhausted.</p>
<p>Interesting location, interesting vibe and probably a great place for raves.</p>
<h2 id="and-the-rest">And the rest…</h2>
<p>Here are some quick notes on other booths that I need to throw out there so that I don’t end up forgetting them.</p>
<p><strong>KDE</strong>: other than stickers or merch, they had small handmade plushies of the project mascot Konqi. I’m still a bit sad
that I didn’t get one at the first opportunity because they were all sold out during the first day.</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/kde-gnome.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/kde-gnome_huf96253bf760ae4811522fe30f5ca4d08_3082137_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="Loved the fact that they were next to the GNOME booth. :)">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      Loved the fact that they were next to the GNOME booth. :)
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p><strong>PostgreSQL</strong>: I got to play in a game of Kahoot and while I crashed and burned in the final standings, I learned a lot
about the PostgreSQL project details in the process. They also had cute hand-made (in Germany of all places!) elephant
plushes in PostgreSQL-blue so of course I bought one. Fun fact: the ones sold there were version 2 of the plush which
has the nice feature of not falling over on a flat surface. See, making PostgreSQL stable isn’t that hard!</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/postgresql.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/postgresql_hu61d486b4e62f4789eba813aba70ccc1c_1862913_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="It's clear that I don't know how to take selfies, and the poor low-light performance of the Fairphone 5 camera certainly
didn't help.">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      It's clear that I don't know how to take selfies, and the poor low-light performance of the Fairphone 5 camera certainly
didn't help.
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p><strong>Firefox cookies:</strong> Mozilla handed out free cookies from a pink food truck. No cookie banner included, but I guess it’s
a nice way to remind everyone that Mozilla Firefox still exists. It blocks ads on desktop PC-s and Android, use it or
lose it!</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/cookies.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/cookies_hu177e66cf379866146927a27bc0a7d114_4489449_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="First-party cookies!">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      First-party cookies!
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p><strong>ISRG and LetsEncrypt:</strong> <em>I went to FOSDEM and all I got was this free cert.</em> The person at the booth was
also handing them out in large quantities, just like Let’s Encrypt servers.</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/letsencrypt.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/letsencrypt_hu3a05d6d01e5c0ca30e177faaef86793a_4328313_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="1067" alt="Brilliant!">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      Brilliant!
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p><strong><a href="https://f-droid.org/en/packages/com.enjoyingfoss.feeel/">Feeel</a>
and <a href="https://f-droid.org/en/packages/de.wger.flutter/">wger</a>:</strong> I know that it doesn’t look like it (yet) but I do go to
the gym regularly and my current workflow
involves keeping notes in a Google Sheets file. I never knew that a FOSS solution exists for tracking my workouts. I
need to try it.</p>
<p><strong>FOSSASIA</strong>: these lovely people were selling LED badges that you can program easily with
an <a href="https://f-droid.org/en/packages/org.fossasia.badgemagic/">Android app called Badge Magic.</a> This was 100% nerd bait
and ranked high on the “I don’t need it but it’s so cool that I need to get one”. Simple. Elegant. Awesome!
Oh, and due to the transfers being Bluetooth Low-Energy powered, I think someone accidentally sent their badge contents
to my
device. Whoops. <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/badgemagic.mp4">Here’s mine in action!</a></p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/fossasia.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/fossasia_hu5b589479569ec88c214176e7b0528b0b_4576726_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="1067" alt="A lot of people wore these over the campus, including myself.">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      A lot of people wore these over the campus, including myself.
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p><strong>Jenkins:</strong> they had <em>Roundernetes</em>, a Kubernetes cluster made of lots of Raspberry Pi-s, in a round frame. I’d love to
build something similar one day, just because it’s neat!</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/roundernetes.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/roundernetes_hufe4ee523c444409cfdc8dbf2f9caf02f_4487903_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="They certainly know how to nerd-snipe someone!">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      They certainly know how to nerd-snipe someone!
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p><strong><a href="https://checkmk.com/">Checkmk</a></strong>: it was the first time I heard about this monitoring solution, but after hearing
about their background and
their approach to building Checkmk that involved a lot of cooperation with customers, I’ll need to give this a proper
look. Oh, and they had an air quality sensor hooked up to the booth, the results were OK when I visited the booth.</p>
<h2 id="the-talks">The talks</h2>
<p>You’re probably coming to FOSDEM for the vibe, the people and all the fun stands, but there are also hundreds of talks
that you can choose to attend.</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/curl.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/curl_hu10759f8c9c0ea1b45afdcee82cb619be_3182389_800x0_resize_q80_box.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="Hey, it's that guy from curl!">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      Hey, it's that guy from curl!
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>There were many talks covering interesting topics, but I could only attend a relatively small number of those live.
There’s simply too much interesting content out there.</p>
<p>Here are my notes on the ones I attended live.</p>
<h2 id="where-the--are-the-packets-goinghttpsfosdemorg2024scheduleeventfosdem-2024-2929--where-the-are-the-packets-going-"><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2929--where-the-are-the-packets-going-/">“Where the !?*! are the packets going?”</a></h2>
<p>This was one of those sessions I decided to sit in on to catch one I really wanted to attend and it was a good decision
as the room was packed.</p>
<p>This talk gave a quick overview of a modified version of <code>traceroute</code> by Catchpoint and the enhancements they made to
it, involving QUIC support, functionality that bypasses firewalls and some shenanigans in Linux setups on Azure (the
Microsoft cloud services platform).</p>
<p><strong><em>techtipsy rating:</em> 6/10</strong>, it was alright.</p>
<h2 id="broom-not-included-curling-the-modern-wayhttpsfosdemorg2024scheduleeventfosdem-2024-1909-broom-not-included-curling-the-modern-way"><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1909-broom-not-included-curling-the-modern-way/">Broom not included: curling the modern way</a></h2>
<p>This talk was originally meant for a 40 minute session but due to limitations of the FOSDEM schedule, 20 minutes was all
he got.</p>
<p>This session was a rapid-fire presentation of curl development and all sorts of things that you could do with it. I’ve
used <code>curl</code> so far for simple requests, but after this session I know that you can do all sorts of shenanigans,
including parallel transfers and a lot of JSON mangling. <em>JSON, JSON, JSON!</em></p>
<p>I also learned about <a href="https://curl.se/trurl/">trurl</a> which is handy for working with URL-s. Parse them, modify them, do
whatever you desire without re-implementing all that complexity yourself. Neat!</p>
<p><strong><em>techtipsy rating:</em> 10/10</strong>, short, amusing and yet useful listen about curl, looking forward to a longer version in
the
future!</p>
<h2 id="improving-ipv6-only-experience-on-linuxhttpsfosdemorg2024scheduleeventfosdem-2024-1798-improving-ipv6-only-experience-on-linux"><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1798-improving-ipv6-only-experience-on-linux/">Improving IPv6-only experience on Linux</a></h2>
<p>I initially didn’t plan on sitting in for this one, but since one of the WiFi networks hosted by FOSDEM itself was IPv6
only and I’m plagued by my ISP only working over IPv4 (<em>old-man-yells-at-Elisa.jpg</em>), I decided to listen to this one.</p>
<p>The speaker gave an overview of the situation with IPv6, which operating systems handle it well and which do not, and
how you can improve the IPv6 compatibility on your own machine.</p>
<p>In short: Android works, Linux/Windows mostly work, but all the Internet of Things garbage (smart <em>everything</em>) is
something you should simply avoid at all costs since those hastily thrown together pieces of crap only work over IPv4.</p>
<p>The rest of the session covered possible solutions for making sure that IPv4 and IPv6 both work nicely on your machine.
Turns out that there really isn’t one perfect solution for this problem, especially since you can’t just ignore that
part of the Internet that doesn’t support IPv6, yet.</p>
<p>This talk was also a way to ask for help from the FOSS community to help come up with a solution. If you’re into this
topic, then go ahead and reach out!</p>
<p><strong><em>techtipsy rating</em>: 8/10</strong>, learned a lot about IPv6 support and what’s going on in this area.</p>
<h2 id="an-engineers-guide-to-linux-kernel-upgradeshttpsfosdemorg2024scheduleeventfosdem-2024-3370-an-engineer-s-guide-to-linux-kernel-upgrades"><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3370-an-engineer-s-guide-to-linux-kernel-upgrades/">An engineer’s guide to Linux Kernel upgrades</a></h2>
<p>Great presentation that included useful recommendations for rolling out Linux kernel upgrades and why you don’t want to
wait a long time to upgrade, backed up with data and nice visualisations, and memes.</p>
<p>Although this talk was about Linux kernel upgrades, the main idea is very much applicable in software development as
well. If you don’t release software as often as possible but keep making changes at the same pace, then your change
delta (or
the number of pending changes) increases, and so does the risk of something going wrong, either by releasing a buggy
change that’s now harder to troubleshoot due to the large number of changes deployed, or not releasing new versions of
software with security patches.</p>
<p>This talk also explained the Linux kernel development workflow, the meaning behind version numbers (it’s not
semantic versioning!), and how security patches get merged into “long-term support” versions.</p>
<p>In short: update often, deploy often, measure things.</p>
<p><strong><em>techtipsy rating</em>: 9/10</strong>, great listening for software developers and Linux newbies alike.</p>
<h2 id="soft-reboot-keep-your-containers-running-while-your-image-based-linux-host-gets-updatedhttpsfosdemorg2024scheduleeventfosdem-2024-3282-soft-reboot-keep-your-containers-running-while-your-image-based-linux-host-gets-updated"><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3282-soft-reboot-keep-your-containers-running-while-your-image-based-linux-host-gets-updated/">Soft Reboot: keep your containers running while your image-based Linux host gets updated</a></h2>
<p>My day job uses Kubernetes for running our services. Have some pods (containers) running on a host that you need to
update? No problem, Kubernetes starts new pods on another host, directs traffic to those and you can now update that
host.</p>
<p>This talk shows another way of updating your host operating system and apparently this functionality is already present
on most modern Linux systems that run <code>systemd</code>.</p>
<p>In short, if your containers meet certain criteria, then you can utilize this soft reboot functionality to update
and reboot your base system without any noticeable interruptions to your containers. Your
kernel will still be the same version, so keep that in mind. And yes, the irony of this solution is not lost to me after
listening
to <a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3370-an-engineer-s-guide-to-linux-kernel-upgrades/">the talk that emphasized the importance of updating your kernel as often as possible.</a></p>
<p>Although the customizations behind it are quite simple if you follow the guidelines, this talk still felt like magic to
me. I guess that only means that I should look into it further.</p>
<p><strong><em>techtipsy rating:</em> 9/10</strong>, interesting concept that has real world usages at big tech companies and yet felt like
something I could understand with my small brain.</p>
<h2 id="juggling-with-uids-and-gids-rootless-container-deployment-with-ansiblehttpsfosdemorg2024scheduleeventfosdem-2024-3412-juggling-with-uids-and-gids-rootless-container-deployment-with-ansible"><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3412-juggling-with-uids-and-gids-rootless-container-deployment-with-ansible/">Juggling with UIDs and GIDs: rootless container deployment with Ansible</a></h2>
<p>Short but sweet talk about how the speaker manages their home server, including a neat workaround that most people who
have worked with containers have faced: permission issues between containers and the host.</p>
<p>I’m actually struggling with a similar issue right now in my home server setup and I’ll definitely have to reference
this talk once I get around to trying to fix it.</p>
<p>It was kind of odd how relatable this talk was to me: it’s related to self-hosting, the speaker has a home server
running, they mentioned <a href="https://www.linuxserver.io/">linuxserver.io</a> images, and they care about running containers
rootless. Even my friend made a
note about the similarities.</p>
<p><strong><em>techtipsy rating:</em> 10/10</strong>, incredibly relatable and useful to me, a self-hosting enthusiast.</p>
<h2 id="orchestrating-ebpf-applications-in-kubernetes-and-fedorahttpsfosdemorg2024scheduleeventfosdem-2024-1745-orchestrating-ebpf-applications-in-kubernetes-and-fedora"><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1745-orchestrating-ebpf-applications-in-kubernetes-and-fedora/">Orchestrating eBPF Applications in Kubernetes and Fedora</a></h2>
<p>This was another session that I decided to attend because hey, I’ve already got a good seat and the session after that
is in the same room.</p>
<p>I had little knowledge about <a href="https://ebpf.io/">eBPF</a> before or what it does, but after listening to this one I have a
rough idea about it. In short: small programs in the kernel that are used for networking, security and
monitoring purposes.</p>
<p>This talk shed some light on deploying eBPF applications with <code>bpfman</code> and nuances around it.</p>
<p><strong><em>techtipsy rating:</em> 6/10</strong>, flew a bit over my head due to my knowledge gaps in eBPF, but it did raise my awareness
about this area.</p>
<h2 id="lift-and-shift-modernising-a-legacy-lamp-application-with-systemd-nspawnhttpsfosdemorg2024scheduleeventfosdem-2024-3008-lift-and-shift-modernising-a-legacy-lamp-application-with-systemd-nspawn"><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3008-lift-and-shift-modernising-a-legacy-lamp-application-with-systemd-nspawn/">Lift and shift: Modernising a legacy LAMP application with systemd-nspawn</a></h2>
<p>During my self-hosting adventure I’ve used various setups, including running containers with <code>systemd-nspawn</code>. If you
don’t know what that involves, then it’s pretty much a container that acts more like a virtual machine when you interact
with it. I have also worked with out of date software projects so this one felt like it could be relevant to my
interests.</p>
<p>This talk was a quick overview of the troubles that the speaker faced with a horrifically out of date software stack
that was still actively used at a school.</p>
<p>The steps taken involved securing the system against basic attacks, then working out how to containerize it and run it,
including
ripping apart old Debian Docker images and having to work around such limitations as “there’s no systemd”.</p>
<p>Great reference for anyone facing similar situations. Wish the speaker had more time to go into the whole other category
of issues related to the software stack itself, including the MySQL related issues they faced during this migration.</p>
<p><strong><em>techtipsy rating:</em> 8/10</strong>, great topic and useful tips, would have loved more horror stories and pictures.</p>
<h2 id="beyond-joins-and-indexeshttpsfosdemorg2024scheduleeventfosdem-2024-3598-beyond-joins-and-indexes"><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3598-beyond-joins-and-indexes/">Beyond Joins and Indexes</a></h2>
<p>This session was a sequel to a previous talk that the presenter gave so I was worried a bit about having knowledge gaps,
but luckily that wasn’t that big of a problem.</p>
<p>This talk covered some common PostgreSQL queries and various operations that go on behind the scenes, supported by
illustrations on how exactly PostgreSQL performs those operations.</p>
<p>There were a lot of examples shown and it was genuinely interesting. At one point it became more difficult
to follow along, but I’ll mark that down to this being the first session of the second day of FOSDEM. I think my brain
quit on <em>parallel hash join</em> part. In a way I felt like I was back in school.</p>
<p>Given the background of the speaker, it’s no surprise that
they<a href="https://momjian.us/main/presentations/performance.html"> have lots of presentations</a> and resources on PostgreSQL.
Will definitely have to check those out.</p>
<p><strong><em>techtipsy rating:</em> 9/10</strong>, made my head hurt but I’m now aware of what to Google when dealing with PostgreSQL, and I
know which materials to reference to refresh my memory on this topic.</p>
<h2 id="isolation-levels-and-mvcc-in-sql-databases-a-technical-comparative-studyhttpsfosdemorg2024scheduleeventfosdem-2024-3600-isolation-levels-and-mvcc-in-sql-databases-a-technical-comparative-study"><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3600-isolation-levels-and-mvcc-in-sql-databases-a-technical-comparative-study/">Isolation Levels and MVCC in SQL Databases: A Technical Comparative Study</a></h2>
<p>This talk started out well: forget what you know about SQL standards because those are apparently not correct in modern
SQL databases. Way ahead of you there, Mr. Pachot!</p>
<p>Turns out that life before MVCC (multi-version concurrency control) was rough and reading data involved locking it.
Unintentionally
locking tables is something that’s a common problem at my day job with <em>writes</em>, so I can’t imagine what type of hell
life would
be if that was still the reality.</p>
<p>This talk shed some light on how databases handle transactions, reads and writes. Good resource to refer back to.</p>
<p>Made me awfully paranoid about databases and data consistency now. Can I even <em>trust</em> databases any more? Or my
knowledge on this topic?</p>
<p>Sidenote on <a href="https://www.yugabyte.com/">YugabyteDB</a>: as someone who has been surprised
by <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/rds/aurora/">Amazon Aurora</a> quirks at my day job (broken indices after a
minor version upgrade, anyone?), I find it interesting that there are other companies that provide a similar service
involving a PostgreSQL-compatible database with a custom data storage solution below it.</p>
<p><a href="https://dev.to/franckpachot">Author also has a blog on all things SQL, might be worth checking out.</a></p>
<p><strong><em>techtipsy rating:</em> 8/10</strong>, made me feel even more insecure about my database knowledge, but at least I know how to
fix that.</p>
<h2 id="linux-load-average-and-other-silly-metricshttpsfosdemorg2024scheduleeventfosdem-2024-1921-linux-load-average-and-other-silly-metrics"><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1921-linux-load-average-and-other-silly-metrics/">Linux load average and other silly metrics</a></h2>
<p>Quick overview of why Linux load average is not an useful metric to follow, and can be incredibly misleading in some
scenarios, especially if you compare sync vs async I/O. I’ve been guilty of tracking that metric religiously myself,
so… <em>whoops.</em></p>
<p>Even the Linux kernel source code calls it a silly metric!</p>
<p>Look at Pressure Stall Information instead to understand where your system is bottlenecking.</p>
<p><strong><em>techtipsy rating:</em> 7/10</strong>, good topic but the live demo part could have used some polish.</p>
<h2 id="private-clouds-do-not-need-to-be-legacyhttpsfosdemorg2024scheduleeventfosdem-2024-1779-private-clouds-do-not-need-to-be-legacy-"><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1779-private-clouds-do-not-need-to-be-legacy-/">Private clouds do not need to be legacy!</a></h2>
<p>This one was a run through various high-level tech tips to take into account when faced with the task of moving to a
on-premise cloud setup.</p>
<p>During my own professional career that officially begun in 2016, there has always been a push to move workloads into the
cloud, for all sorts of reasons, legitimate or misguided. Turns out that on-prem isn’t dead and some organizations are
moving back in that direction due to legal or technical requirements.</p>
<p>Here are my takeaways:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>avoid third party software because that’s usually a source of lock-in</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>if faced with <em>buy vs build</em> decisions, prefer build</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>keep things super simple</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>if faced with build-time or run-time complexity, prefer the former, otherwise more technical layers in run-time result
in more difficult troubleshooting due to added complexity</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>consider using Kubernetes (and an open source distribution of it)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>version control your infrastructure</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>if you automate something, automate it 100% end-to-end, don’t half-ass it or include manual middle steps</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>A lot of ideas mentioned here are also applicable to those working with cloud platforms in any large company. If you
have competent engineers, then you’ll probably have no major problems if you move to a private cloud setup as a lot of
the tooling and knowledge should transfer over.</p>
<p><strong><em>techtipsy rating:</em> 7/10</strong>, would have loved to see case studies of public -&gt; private cloud migrations to illustrate
the process and highlight the pain points.</p>
<h2 id="firefox-power-profiling-a-powerful-visualization-of-web-sustainabilityhttpsfosdemorg2024scheduleeventfosdem-2024-2716-firefox-power-profiling-a-powerful-visualization-of-web-sustainability"><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2716-firefox-power-profiling-a-powerful-visualization-of-web-sustainability/">Firefox power profiling: a powerful visualization of web sustainability</a></h2>
<p>This was a fun one for me because I care about how much power my tech consumes, and the speaker put a new twist on it.
Ever wondered how much energy is spent loading your website? Now you can find that out!</p>
<p>This talk ties in with Mozilla’s vision for a better internet and their stated sustainability goals. Building new
computing hardware is very resource and energy intensive, and shoddy websites motivate people to upgrade sooner than
necessary.</p>
<p>The steps to take to measure the performance and power consumption of your webpage are quite simple. The power
measurement support is hardware and platform dependent, but even without that you can get a pretty good idea of how well
your website performs. The whole process was easy enough to do that I could follow it along on my laptop during the
talk.</p>
<p>The talk was simple to follow and yet covered a lot of details and nuance around power profiling on various platforms.
This should be mandatory for anyone working in web development, especially those that add animated full-page backgrounds
on websites or load in megabytes of JavaScript.</p>
<p>Give this talk a listen and start measuring website performance, I highly encourage it!</p>
<p><strong><em>techtipsy rating:</em> 10/10</strong>, I hate poorly performing websites and love my machines running as efficiently as
possible, and this talk brings those two topics together in a very nice way.</p>
<h2 id="postgres-vs-linux-filesystemshttpsfosdemorg2024scheduleeventfosdem-2024-3605-postgres-vs-linux-filesystems"><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3605-postgres-vs-linux-filesystems/">Postgres vs. Linux filesystems</a></h2>
<p>My experience with hosting PostgreSQL has mainly been limited to one instance that is used by Nextcloud, and during my
professional career I’ve only observed migrations away from ZFS-based self-hosted PostgreSQL instances, so I was really
interested in seeing how different filesystems affect PostgreSQL performance.</p>
<p>This talk laid out some general guidelines for anyone running PostgreSQL, such as keeping your kernel up to date to get
the best performance and avoid old kernel bugs, and presented lots of graphs detailing the behaviour of different
filesystems under heavy workloads simulated using <code>pgbench</code>.</p>
<p>I recommend that you view the results, they might surprise you. As a <code>btrfs</code> user, they certainly made me think about
choosing it if I were to ever build a dedicated database server on raw hardware.</p>
<p>Benchmarking is very difficult to get right so I suspect that there might be other nuances at play here with the
results. Interesting presentation regardless.</p>
<p>Sidenote: the presenter was running <a href="https://www.qubes-os.org/">QubesOS</a>, which I’ve briefly played around with in the
past. I never expected to see anyone <em>actually</em> using it as their daily driver. Very impressive!</p>
<p><strong><em>techtipsy rating:</em> 9/10</strong>, I now have an urge to do my own benchmarks to verify these results (but my TODO list is
long enough already).</p>
<h2 id="are-project-tests-enough-for-automated-dependency-updates-a-case-study-of-262-java-projects-on-githubhttpsfosdemorg2024scheduleeventfosdem-2024-3029-are-project-tests-enough-for-automated-dependency-updates-a-case-study-of-262-java-projects-on-github"><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3029-are-project-tests-enough-for-automated-dependency-updates-a-case-study-of-262-java-projects-on-github/">Are Project Tests Enough for Automated Dependency Updates? A Case Study of 262 Java Projects on Github</a></h2>
<p>I picked this one mainly due to being annoyed with Dependabot spam and the state of tests at my day job.</p>
<p>This talk covered the promise of automated dependency upgrades and ways you can avoid seemingly innocent upgrades
breaking things in production, covering tools like <a href="https://pitest.org/">PIT</a>
and <a href="https://github.com/jhejderup/uppdatera">Uppdatera</a>. If your tests suck, then adding mutation testing and/or static
analysis to your project might help catch problems before they make it to prod, find unused dependencies and tests that
do not properly verify that the service works.</p>
<p>The speaker also briefly mentions the age-old problem of balancing code reuse vs increasing operational costs. Maybe
don’t bring in thousands of dependencies so that you can avoid writing a few lines of code?</p>
<p>There’s a whole research paper on this topic as well (check presentation for more details).</p>
<p><strong><em>techtipsy rating:</em> 8/10</strong>, maybe a project where tests are in shambles can be improved after all…</p>
<h2 id="the-talks-i-didnt-make-it-to">The talks I didn’t make it to</h2>
<p>Due to scheduling conflicts, room capacity limitations and the fact that I can’t teleport, I could not attend everything
all at once.</p>
<p>Here are talks that I plan to watch from a recording (once the processing is done). If I do end up watching them, I’ll
try to add my notes below each one later on.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2161-diy-private-container-registry/">FOSDEM 2024 - DIY Private Container Registry</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2352-stopping-all-the-attacks-before-they-start-building-a-security-first-api/">FOSDEM 2024 - Stopping all the attacks before they start: Building a security-first API</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3740-observations-on-a-dnssec-incident-the-russian-tld/">FOSDEM 2024 - Observations on a DNSSEC incident: the russian TLD</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2723-power-profiling-my-entire-house-with-the-firefox-profiler/">FOSDEM 2024 - Power profiling my entire house with the Firefox Profiler</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1899-where-did-all-the-fun-go-and-how-to-bring-it-back-with-foss-/">FOSDEM 2024 - Where Did All the Fun Go? And How to Bring it Back with FOSS!</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2964-streamlining-developer-experience-the-power-of-ci-cd-standardization-and-interoperability/">FOSDEM 2024 - Streamlining Developer Experience: The Power of CI/CD Standardization and Interoperability</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2415-how-to-build-an-open-source-school-cloud-for-5-million-users/">FOSDEM 2024 - How to Build an Open Source School Cloud for 5 Million Users</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2332-magic-and-software/">FOSDEM 2024 - Magic and Software</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1953-using-code-generated-by-ai-issues-misconceptions-and-solutions/">FOSDEM 2024 - Using code generated by AI: issues, misconceptions and solutions</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3025-fosdem-infrastructure-review/">FOSDEM 2024 - FOSDEM infrastructure review</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2029-open-source-in-2024-boundaries-burnout-business/">FOSDEM 2024 - Open Source in 2024: boundaries, burnout, business</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3362-open-source-for-sustainable-and-long-lasting-phones/">FOSDEM 2024 - Open Source for Sustainable and Long lasting Phones</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1931-you-too-could-have-made-curl-/">FOSDEM 2024 - You too could have made curl!</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>If you think there are must-see FOSDEM 2024 talks missing from this list, then do reach out to me and I’ll give them a
look!</p>
<h2 id="closing-thoughts">Closing thoughts</h2>
<p>I <em><strong>loved</strong></em> FOSDEM 2024.</p>
<p>My expectations were high based on what I heard before, and it still exceeded them!
The occasional technical issues weren’t a dealbreaker, there was generally plenty of room in the sessions
(at least those I went to), and both the content and the people were great.</p>
<p>I felt at home, surrounded by people with whom I have similar interests. It’s not an environment I find myself in
often, even at work, which is why FOSDEM felt so special.</p>
<p>Next time I’ll try to take part in more community events if possible, talk to people and leave some time for sightseeing
in Brussels.</p>
<p>I’d like to thank my employer <a href="https://concise.ee/">Concise Systems</a> for paying for travel and accommodation.</p>
<p>Special thanks go to <a href="https://zirk.me/">my friend Arti</a> who introduced me to FOSDEM in the first place and helped make
my
first FOSDEM a memorable one.</p>







  




<figure>
    
    <a href="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/fosdemgang.jpg">
        <img src="https://ounapuu.ee/posts/2024/02/12/fosdem-2024/media/fosdemgang_hu39a404366cc5c1dca967c674d4df7e88_2512065_800x0_resize_q90_box.jpg" width="800" height="652" alt="FOSDEM gang.">
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      FOSDEM gang.
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>


<p>If you’re not a spammer,
<a href="mailto:ihavesomethoughtsonyourblog@ounapuu.ee">just send me an e-mail!</a></p>
<p>Places where you can discuss this post:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39342109">Hacker News</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/%F0%9F%94%A5-herman-%C3%B5unapuu-600516152_fosdem-2024-my-experience-some-notes-and-activity-7162695584452132867-0Ppy">LinkedIn</a></p>
</li>
</ul>

    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Brennan self-balancing monorail [video] (133 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kUYzuAJeg3M</link>
            <guid>39340599</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 01:51:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kUYzuAJeg3M">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kUYzuAJeg3M</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39340599">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cousins are disappearing. Is this reshaping the experience of childhood? (344 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/cousins-decline-canada-1.7103338</link>
            <guid>39340501</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 01:24:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/cousins-decline-canada-1.7103338">https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/cousins-decline-canada-1.7103338</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39340501">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p dir="ltr">Noelene Lancastle&nbsp;grew up&nbsp;surrounded by 27 cousins and 10 second cousins. They were a range of ages and had what seemed like a world of experiences, always ready to teach her to skateboard or swim, help carry heavy boxes, play with her on camping trips&nbsp;or have her back in school in North Delta, B.C.</p><p dir="ltr">"There were always lots of kids around. You know how your parents dragged you around to houses?&nbsp;There were&nbsp;always some kids for us to play with that were somehow related to us,"&nbsp;Lancastle, 46, said from Vancouver.</p><p dir="ltr">It's something her own children won't&nbsp;experience.</p><p dir="ltr">Lancastle's&nbsp;older brother and sister don't have children&nbsp;and her husband is an only child. So Nicholas, 9, and Charlie, 7, don't have any cousins at all — a growing trend as the decreasing fertility rate causes extended families to narrow over time, sociologists and demographers say.</p><p dir="ltr">Worldwide, families are shrinking,&nbsp;according to a kinship study published in December in the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.2315722120">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences USA</a>. That study, using international demographic data for every country in the world, projected a 38 per cent global&nbsp;decline in living relatives for individuals&nbsp;aged 65 by the year 2095, compared to 1950.</p><p dir="ltr">The composition of family networks is also expected to change, with grandparents and great-grandparents&nbsp;living longer, but the number of cousins, nieces&nbsp;and nephews declining, the authors noted.</p><div dir="ltr"><figure><p><img loading="lazy" alt="A dated photograph from the 1990s of a girl and a boy looking over a baby in a cradle in a  grassy field." srcset="https://i.cbc.ca/1.7106198.1707499664!/fileImage/httpImage/image.jpg_gen/derivatives/original_300/noelene-lancastle-cousins.jpg 300w,https://i.cbc.ca/1.7106198.1707499664!/fileImage/httpImage/image.jpg_gen/derivatives/original_460/noelene-lancastle-cousins.jpg 460w,https://i.cbc.ca/1.7106198.1707499664!/fileImage/httpImage/image.jpg_gen/derivatives/original_620/noelene-lancastle-cousins.jpg 620w,https://i.cbc.ca/1.7106198.1707499664!/fileImage/httpImage/image.jpg_gen/derivatives/original_780/noelene-lancastle-cousins.jpg 780w,https://i.cbc.ca/1.7106198.1707499664!/fileImage/httpImage/image.jpg_gen/derivatives/original_1180/noelene-lancastle-cousins.jpg 1180w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 300px,(max-width: 460px) 460px,(max-width: 620px) 620px,(max-width: 780px) 780px,(max-width: 1180px) 1180px" src="https://i.cbc.ca/1.7106198.1707499664!/fileImage/httpImage/image.jpg_gen/derivatives/original_780/noelene-lancastle-cousins.jpg"></p><figcaption>Lancastle, middle, plays with some of her cousins at a family reunion in Saskatchewan in the 1990s.<!-- --> <!-- -->(Submitted by Noelene Lancastle)</figcaption></figure></div><p dir="ltr">"Canadian children nowadays have fewer cousins than previous generations," said&nbsp;Rania Tfaily, an associate professor in&nbsp;sociology at Carleton University in Ottawa who studies&nbsp;social demography&nbsp;and contemporary changes in marriage and family formation.</p><p dir="ltr">This isn't a recent phenomena as fertility rates have been decreasing for some time, added Tfaily, who was not involved in the kinship study.</p><p dir="ltr">"However, what is striking nowadays is not just that the number of cousins is declining but also that an increasing number of children are growing up&nbsp;with no or very few cousins." &nbsp;</p><p dir="ltr">And it's part of the reason&nbsp;Lancastle decided to have two children, despite having them&nbsp;later in life.</p><p dir="ltr">"I could have been a one&nbsp;and done person,"&nbsp;she said. "But they would have no relatives that would be their age. So I wanted them to have each other, at least."</p><div dir="ltr"><figure><p><img loading="lazy" alt="A family of four poses around a tree, with the children sitting on the branches. They are in summer clothes." srcset="https://i.cbc.ca/1.7106185.1707499683!/fileImage/httpImage/image.jpg_gen/derivatives/original_300/noelene-lancastle-family.jpg 300w,https://i.cbc.ca/1.7106185.1707499683!/fileImage/httpImage/image.jpg_gen/derivatives/original_460/noelene-lancastle-family.jpg 460w,https://i.cbc.ca/1.7106185.1707499683!/fileImage/httpImage/image.jpg_gen/derivatives/original_620/noelene-lancastle-family.jpg 620w,https://i.cbc.ca/1.7106185.1707499683!/fileImage/httpImage/image.jpg_gen/derivatives/original_780/noelene-lancastle-family.jpg 780w,https://i.cbc.ca/1.7106185.1707499683!/fileImage/httpImage/image.jpg_gen/derivatives/original_1180/noelene-lancastle-family.jpg 1180w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 300px,(max-width: 460px) 460px,(max-width: 620px) 620px,(max-width: 780px) 780px,(max-width: 1180px) 1180px" src="https://i.cbc.ca/1.7106185.1707499683!/fileImage/httpImage/image.jpg_gen/derivatives/original_780/noelene-lancastle-family.jpg"></p><figcaption>Lancastle, back left, and her children Charlie, 7, and Nicholas, 9, and her husband, Paul Lancastle. Charlie and Nicholas have no cousins.<!-- --> <!-- -->(Submitted by Noelene Lancastle)</figcaption></figure></div><h2 dir="ltr">Families are shrinking</h2><p dir="ltr">Canadian data&nbsp;obtained by&nbsp;CBC News from the researchers of the <a href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.2315722120">kinship study</a>&nbsp;projects that the average Canadian 15-year-old girl will&nbsp;have just 3.6 living cousins in the year 2095, compared to 15.3 in 1950 — a 76 per cent decrease in living cousins.</p><p dir="ltr">Using demographic data, the researchers computed kinship structures for every country in the world from 1950 to present, and then calculated&nbsp;projections to the year 2100. The model is based on a hypothetical person from the population, in this case, a woman of a specified age.</p><p dir="ltr">A Canadian woman aged 35 would have had&nbsp;about 20 living cousins in&nbsp;1950, while a woman the same age would have&nbsp;half that — 10 living cousins — in 2020. By 2095, a Canadian woman aged 35 is projected to have just five living cousins, according to the data.</p><p dir="ltr">This narrowing of extended families tends not to get as much attention as research on the nuclear family,&nbsp;the new kinship study's lead author, Diego Alburez-Gutierrez,&nbsp;told CBC News.&nbsp;</p><p dir="ltr">This may be&nbsp;because much of that research&nbsp;is conducted in and on Western populations, where there's an assumption that extended kin "don't matter as much," said Alburez-Gutierrez, who leads the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.demogr.mpg.de/en/research_6120/kinship_inequalities_10703">Research Group on Kinship Inequalities</a>&nbsp;at the Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research in Rostock, Germany.</p><p dir="ltr">But research has shown that extended family plays an important role in individuals' lives in many cultures around the world,&nbsp;he added in an email interview.</p><p dir="ltr">"Disregarding cousins means that we ignore a 'weak' but important tie that individuals rely on for support and company at different stages of their lives."</p><p><em><strong>LISTEN | Why more Canadians are choosing not to have kids:</strong></em>&nbsp;<span><span><div role="button" tabindex="0" title="Why more Canadians are deciding not to have children"><p><img src="https://thumbnails.cbc.ca/maven_legacy/thumbnails/416/803/640x360_thecurrent_nohost.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"></p><p><span>The Current</span><span>18:28</span><span>Why more Canadians are deciding not to have children</span></p></div><span>A growing number of Canadians are delaying parenthood or choosing not to have children at a time when Canada's fertility rate is at an all-time low. The Current’s producer Kate Cornick looked into these decisions and the long-term implications.</span></span></span></p><p dir="ltr">Statistics Canada doesn't specifically collect data on cousins, a spokesperson confirmed with CBC News.</p><p dir="ltr">But we do know the <a href="https://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/statistics-canada-total-fertility-rate-2022-1.7100404"><u>fertility rate is decreasing</u></a> — currently the lowest on record, with a rate of 1.33 children per woman, according to Statistics Canada&nbsp;—&nbsp;and more people are choosing to have only one child.</p><p dir="ltr">According to the <a href="https://www150.statcan.gc.ca/t1/tbl1/en/tv.action?pid=9810012401&amp;"><u>2021 census</u></a>, one-child families are the most common type in Canada, comprising 45 per cent of families with children that year (two child-families made up 38 per cent&nbsp;and three or more made up 16 per cent). The totals include one-parent families, common-law&nbsp;families and step-families.</p><p dir="ltr">This is a key factor in the cousin decline, said Prof. Yue Qian, an associate professor of sociology at the University of British Columbia whose research&nbsp;focuses on social demography.</p><p dir="ltr">"If this trend continues and more parents have only one child and stop at one child, their only child's kid [or kids]&nbsp;won't have cousins in the future," Qian said.</p><div dir="ltr"><ul><li><a href="https://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/statistics-canada-total-fertility-rate-2022-1.7100404" text="Canada's 2022 fertility rate lowest on record, StatsCan reports" flag="" data-contentid=""><span>Canada's 2022 fertility rate lowest on record, StatsCan reports</span></a></li></ul><ul><li><a href="https://www.cbc.ca/radio/thecurrent/affordability-crisis-delaying-parenthood-1.7036820" text="Cost-of-living crisis means more Canadians are putting parenthood on pause" flag="" data-contentid=""><span>Cost-of-living crisis means more Canadians are putting parenthood on pause</span></a></li></ul></div><p dir="ltr">Further, more people aren't having children at all.</p><p dir="ltr">According to Statistics Canada, the proportion of women aged 50 and over who have no biological children is <a href="https://www150.statcan.gc.ca/n1/pub/11-627-m/11-627-m2023006-eng.htm"><u>on the rise</u></a>, at 17.4 per cent in 2022 compared to 14.1 per cent in 2001. In 2022, more than one-third of all people aged 15 to 49 said they intended to have no children.</p><p dir="ltr">"With fewer children and&nbsp;fewer siblings, there's just quite naturally fewer cousins in the mix," said&nbsp;Margo Hilbrecht, executive director of the Vanier Institute of the Family, a national, independent research institute dedicated to understanding families and family life in Canada.</p><h2 dir="ltr">Why cousins&nbsp;matter</h2><p dir="ltr">Cousins&nbsp;take up an interesting space in many family dynamics — not quite&nbsp;siblings, not quite friends. Some people may&nbsp;grow up alongside their cousins and have a deep bond and others may rarely see them or speak to them&nbsp;at&nbsp;all. Yet experts agree the role can be an&nbsp;important one.</p><p dir="ltr">"It's one of the first places that&nbsp;we might encounter people of our own generation who hold different values or have a different way of doing things, and you wouldn't necessarily choose to be friends with all of them,"&nbsp;Hilbrecht said.</p><p><em><strong>WATCH | Why chosen family means the world to these kids:&nbsp;</strong></em><span><span><div title="'Chosen family' means everything to adopted sisterhood from China" role="button" tabindex="0"><div><p><img srcset="
                        https://thumbnails.cbc.ca/maven_legacy/thumbnails/173/215/WEB_PEI_AdoptiveSisters_7000kbps_1280x720_2066073155883.jpg?crop=1.777xh:h;*,*&amp;downsize=1130px:* 1130w,
                        https://thumbnails.cbc.ca/maven_legacy/thumbnails/173/215/WEB_PEI_AdoptiveSisters_7000kbps_1280x720_2066073155883.jpg?crop=1.777xh:h;*,*&amp;downsize=880px:* 880w,
                        https://thumbnails.cbc.ca/maven_legacy/thumbnails/173/215/WEB_PEI_AdoptiveSisters_7000kbps_1280x720_2066073155883.jpg?crop=1.777xh:h;*,*&amp;downsize=630px:* 630w,
                        https://thumbnails.cbc.ca/maven_legacy/thumbnails/173/215/WEB_PEI_AdoptiveSisters_7000kbps_1280x720_2066073155883.jpg?crop=1.777xh:h;*,*&amp;downsize=510px:* 510w,
                        https://thumbnails.cbc.ca/maven_legacy/thumbnails/173/215/WEB_PEI_AdoptiveSisters_7000kbps_1280x720_2066073155883.jpg?crop=1.777xh:h;*,*&amp;downsize=260px:* 260w" sizes="(max-width: 260px) 4vw, (max-width: 510px) 50vw, (max-width: 630px) 66vw, (max-width: 880px) 88vw" src="https://thumbnails.cbc.ca/maven_legacy/thumbnails/173/215/WEB_PEI_AdoptiveSisters_7000kbps_1280x720_2066073155883.jpg?crop=1.777xh:h;*,*&amp;downsize=510px:*510w" alt="" loading="lazy"></p></div><div><h3>'Chosen family' means everything to adopted sisterhood from China</h3></div></div><span>'We've just made so many memories when we were younger, I just can't see us losing that bond,' says Olivia McKenzie.</span></span></span></p><p dir="ltr">Extended family ties can be especially important for disadvantaged&nbsp;minority&nbsp;families, noted&nbsp;Qian. For example, she said, research shows that Black single mothers often&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5300078/">rely on their extended kin</a> for various types of support; gender and sexual minority adults face much higher levels of <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/fare.12638">parental rejection</a>.</p><p dir="ltr">"Extended kin, like cousins, could be a valuable source of social support" for people in these circumstances, she said.</p><p dir="ltr">Similar-age cousins, especially, can often enrich one's childhood in addition to having some shared experiences, said Tfaily. She said it's important to note&nbsp;the cousin decline is happening alongside other family-related&nbsp;changes, such as the decline in the number of aunts&nbsp;and&nbsp;uncles and the decline in the number of siblings.</p><p dir="ltr">"This is reshaping the experience of childhood compared to previous generations and affecting family dynamics and ties."&nbsp;</p><div dir="ltr"><figure><p><img loading="lazy" alt="A faded photograph shows four children playing on a rocky beach" srcset="https://i.cbc.ca/1.7106180.1707500322!/fileImage/httpImage/image.jpg_gen/derivatives/original_300/cousins-noelene-lancastle.jpg 300w,https://i.cbc.ca/1.7106180.1707500322!/fileImage/httpImage/image.jpg_gen/derivatives/original_460/cousins-noelene-lancastle.jpg 460w,https://i.cbc.ca/1.7106180.1707500322!/fileImage/httpImage/image.jpg_gen/derivatives/original_620/cousins-noelene-lancastle.jpg 620w,https://i.cbc.ca/1.7106180.1707500322!/fileImage/httpImage/image.jpg_gen/derivatives/original_780/cousins-noelene-lancastle.jpg 780w,https://i.cbc.ca/1.7106180.1707500322!/fileImage/httpImage/image.jpg_gen/derivatives/original_1180/cousins-noelene-lancastle.jpg 1180w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 300px,(max-width: 460px) 460px,(max-width: 620px) 620px,(max-width: 780px) 780px,(max-width: 1180px) 1180px" src="https://i.cbc.ca/1.7106180.1707500322!/fileImage/httpImage/image.jpg_gen/derivatives/original_780/cousins-noelene-lancastle.jpg"></p><figcaption>Lancastle, centre right, has happy memories of camping with her cousins. She worries her kids are missing out on the same 'big family' experience, but has focused on cultivating friendships.<!-- --> <!-- -->(Submitted by Noelene Lancastle)</figcaption></figure></div><p dir="ltr">It's something that weighs on Lancastle when she compares how she grew up surrounded by extended family compared&nbsp;with the experience of her own children. Lancastle's father was one of 10&nbsp;children; her mother was one of two.</p><p dir="ltr">"They're missing out on that&nbsp;big family experience, but I think I compensate by having good friends with kids the same&nbsp;age," she said of Nicholas and Charlie.</p><p dir="ltr">"But I knowingly did that&nbsp;because I want them to be&nbsp;surrounded by people."</p><p dir="ltr">This building of extended family by choice shouldn't be diminished, said&nbsp;Qian of UBC, noting that "voluntary kin" is common&nbsp;in many 2SLGBTQ+ communities, and we don't have to define family based on blood ties.</p><p dir="ltr">&nbsp;"If our society and culture celebrate and value developing close friendships and communities and building family we choose&nbsp;to a greater extent, we may not need to worry about a cousin decline&nbsp;so much."</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Orbit: C/C++ Performance Profiler (189 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/google/orbit</link>
            <guid>39339461</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 22:35:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/google/orbit">https://github.com/google/orbit</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39339461">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">ORBIT</h2>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/google/orbit/actions/workflows/build-and-test.yml/badge.svg?branch=main"><img src="https://github.com/google/orbit/actions/workflows/build-and-test.yml/badge.svg?branch=main" alt="builds and tests"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/google/orbit/actions/workflows/release.yml/badge.svg?branch=main"><img src="https://github.com/google/orbit/actions/workflows/release.yml/badge.svg?branch=main" alt="Debian package"></a>
<a href="https://api.securityscorecards.dev/projects/github.com/google/orbit" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/fed985407f21fe04085cfadcb29b72b252061cb80e3871ca1c1c21a7783a3679/68747470733a2f2f6170692e736563757269747973636f726563617264732e6465762f70726f6a656374732f6769746875622e636f6d2f676f6f676c652f6f726269742f6261646765" alt="OpenSSF Scorecard" data-canonical-src="https://api.securityscorecards.dev/projects/github.com/google/orbit/badge"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/google/orbit/blob/main/contrib/logos/orbit_logo_simple.png"><img alt="ORBIT Logo" src="https://github.com/google/orbit/raw/main/contrib/logos/orbit_logo_simple.png" width="520"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Orbit, the <strong>O</strong>pen <strong>R</strong>untime <strong>B</strong>inary <strong>I</strong>nstrumentation <strong>T</strong>ool is a
standalone <strong>native</strong> application profiler for Windows and Linux. It supports
native applications written in languages such as C, C++, Rust, or Go. Its main
purpose is to help developers identify the performance bottlenecks of a complex
application. Orbit can be also used to visualize the execution flow of such
applications.</p>
<p dir="auto">The key differentiator with many existing tools is that no alteration to the
target process is necessary. Orbit does not require you to change a single line
of code. It doesn't require you to recompile or even relaunch the application
you want to profile. Everything is done seamlessly, right when you need it. It
requires zero integration time and zero iteration time.</p>
<p dir="auto">Orbit combines sampling and dynamic instrumentation to optimize the profiling
workflow. Sampling can quickly identify interesting functions to instrument.
Dynamic instrumentation results in exact function entry and exit information
which is presented in the form of per-thread hierarchical call graphs.
Manual instrumentation markers can be added to the source code and further
allows for value-tracking. Scheduling events are also shown to visualize when a
thread was running and on what core. Furthermore, Orbit visualizes thread
dependencies, showing which thread got blocked or unblocked by which other
thread. For AMD GPUs, the submission, scheduling and hardware execution timings
of a job is visualized. Additional GPU data, such as Vulkan debug markers can be
retrieved using Orbit's Vulkan layer. Memory consumption and page-fault
information is visualized as well.</p>
<p dir="auto">An introduction to Orbit's key features can be found in the following YouTube
video:
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8V-EPBPGZPs" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://github.com/google/orbit/raw/main/contrib/logos/orbit_presentation_youtube.png" alt="Orbit Presentation"></a></p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Features</h2>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Dynamic Instrumentation (no code change required)</li>
<li>Callstack Sampling</li>
<li>Wine/Proton Mixed-Callstack Profiling</li>
<li>Thread Scheduling and Dependency Tracing</li>
<li>Memory Tracing</li>
<li>GPU Driver Tracepoints (AMD only)</li>
<li>Vulkan Debug Label and Command Buffer Tracing (AMD only)</li>
<li>Manual Instrumentation</li>
<li>Source Code and Disassembly View</li>
<li>Remote Profiling</li>
<li>Debug Symbol Parsing (ELF, DWARF, PE and PDB)</li>
<li>Full Serialization of Captured Data</li>
</ul>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Note</h3>
<p dir="auto">Orbit's focus has shifted to the Linux version. Windows local profiling is
currently only supported partially and major features, such as dynamic
instrumentation, are not yet implemented. It is possible however to profile
Linux executables from a Windows UI instance. For Windows local profiling,
you can still use the released
<a href="https://github.com/google/orbit/releases">binaries</a>, but please note that
they are deprecated and mostly undocumented.</p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Build</h2>
<p dir="auto">Please have a look at the first three sections of our
<a href="https://github.com/google/orbit/blob/main/DEVELOPMENT.md">development documentation</a>. It describes how to build Orbit and
which compilers, platforms, and tools are supported and needed.</p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Workflow</h2>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Note</strong> An extensive documentation of the usage of Orbit can be found in our
<a href="https://github.com/google/orbit/blob/main/documentation/DOCUMENTATION.md">usage documentation</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto">The following describes the basic workflow of Orbit:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Select a process in the list of currently running processes in the connection
setup dialog, and click <strong>Start Session</strong>.</li>
<li>The list of loaded modules will appear at the top of the <strong>Symbols</strong> tab.</li>
<li>Orbit tries to automatically retrieve debug information of the modules.
See <a href="https://github.com/google/orbit/blob/main/documentation/DOCUMENTATION.md#load-symbols">here</a> on how to load
symbols for modules Orbit failed to load. For successfully loaded module
symbols, the <strong>Functions</strong> tab will get populated.</li>
<li>Select functions you wish to dynamically instrument in the <strong>Functions</strong> tab
by <kbd>Right-Click</kbd> and choosing <strong>Hook</strong>.</li>
<li>Start profiling by pressing <kbd>F5</kbd>. To stop profiling, press
<kbd>F5</kbd> again. You can either zoom time using <kbd>W</kbd> and
<kbd>S</kbd> or <kbd>Ctrl</kbd> + the scroll wheel. You can also
<kbd>Ctrl</kbd>+<kbd>Right-Click</kbd> and drag to zoom to a specific time
range. To scale the UI, press <kbd>Ctrl</kbd> + <kbd>+</kbd>/<kbd>-</kbd>.
Press <kbd>SPACE</kbd> to see the last 2 seconds of capture.</li>
<li>You can select sections of the per-thread sampling event track to get a
sampling report of your selection.</li>
</ol>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Presets</h2>
<p dir="auto">Once you have loaded the debug information for your modules and have chosen
functions of interest to dynamically instrument, you can save your profiling
preset so that you won't have to do this manually again. To save a preset, go to
<strong>File</strong> &gt; <strong>Save Preset</strong></p>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Feedback</h3>
<p dir="auto">Questions and comments are more than welcome: please open an
<a href="https://github.com/google/orbit/issues/new">issue</a>.</p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">About</h2>
<p dir="auto">Orbit was created by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/pgimmig/" rel="nofollow">Pierric Gimmig</a>, but
is now developed and maintained by a team of engineers at Google. The current
maintainers are:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/akopich">@akopich</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/antonrohr">@antonrohr</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/beckerhe">@beckerhe</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/danielfenner">@danielfenner</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dimitry-">@dimitry-</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dpallotti">@dpallotti</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/florian-kuebler">@florian-kuebler</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/karupayun">@karupayun</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/pierricgimmig">@pierricgimmig</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/reichlfl">@reichlfl</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ronaldfw">@ronaldfw</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/vickyliu-go4it">@vickyliu-go4it</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/vwbaker">@vwbaker</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/google/orbit/blob/main/LICENSE">License (BSD 2-clause)</a></p>
<a href="http://opensource.org/licenses/BSD-2-Clause" rel="nofollow">
<img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/f631c49e59bfff81df78853f2a0d2ea6a203e1cbf69fe11913e1fcf8e547c771/687474703a2f2f6f70656e736f757263652e6f72672f74726164656d61726b732f6f70656e736f757263652f4f53492d417070726f7665642d4c6963656e73652d313030783133372e706e67" alt="OSI Approved License" data-canonical-src="http://opensource.org/trademarks/opensource/OSI-Approved-License-100x137.png">
</a>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="Copyright (c) 2020 The Orbit Authors. All rights reserved.

BSD 2-Clause License

Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are met:

* Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright notice, this
  list of conditions and the following disclaimer.

* Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright notice,
  this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the documentation
  and/or other materials provided with the distribution.

THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS &quot;AS IS&quot;
AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE
IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE
DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE
FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL
DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR
SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER
CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY,
OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE
OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE."><pre lang="text"><code>Copyright (c) 2020 The Orbit Authors. All rights reserved.

BSD 2-Clause License

Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are met:

* Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright notice, this
  list of conditions and the following disclaimer.

* Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright notice,
  this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the documentation
  and/or other materials provided with the distribution.

THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS "AS IS"
AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE
IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE
DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE
FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL
DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR
SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER
CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY,
OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE
OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
</code></pre></div>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ｂｉｔｗｉｓｅ Ｌｉｍｉｎａｌ – A Short Film in 256 Bytes of Code (418 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://killedbyapixel.github.io/TinyCode/256B/BitwiseLiminal/</link>
            <guid>39339249</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 22:09:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://killedbyapixel.github.io/TinyCode/256B/BitwiseLiminal/">https://killedbyapixel.github.io/TinyCode/256B/BitwiseLiminal/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39339249">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><canvas id="c"><svg onload="setInterval(&quot;for(t+=.1,R=T=C=Math.cos,c.width=w=128,i=9986,V=t/9&amp;3;Y=i--/w;c.getContext`2d`.fillRect(X,Y,(C(t/6)*T^V*i/1e4*T+t)%20?(R=T++,1):(T=9,19/R),5/Z))for(Z=5,X=i%w+4/R;0<(V*95+C(t/3)+Z*X/64-Z^Z|(60-Y)*Z/58)%13;Z+=.2);&quot;,t=9)">

</svg></canvas><title>Bitwise 📼 Liminal</title><pre>
Ｂｉｔｗｉｓｅ 📼 Ｌｉｍｉｎａｌ
A Short Film in 256 Bytes of Code

Programmed by KilledByAPixel
Presented at Lovebyte Party 2024

...

I found an old VHS tape at a yard sale.
It was labeled "Bitwise Liminal" in sharpie.
But when I watched the video it was only static.

Then I started having vivid and... unsettling dreams.
Also I couldn't stop thinking about that weird VHS tape.
After researching I learned it was a digital backup.
Using some special software I recovered the data.
To my shock, it was a 256 byte program...

With trembling hands I opened it in a web browser.
Strange. This reminds me of the dreams I've been having.
Now I don't need to sleep anymore.
I just keep watching.

...

l ɐ u ᴉ ɯ ᴉ ⅂ 📼 ǝ s ᴉ ʍ ʇ ᴉ ᗺ</pre></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>