<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 00:30:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[iPhone 17 chip becomes the fastest single-core CPU in the world on PassMark (117 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.tomshardware.com/pc-components/cpus/apples-a19-becomes-the-fastest-single-core-cpu-in-the-world-on-passmark-beating-pc-chips-and-apples-own-m3-ultra-passively-cooled-iphone-17-chip-catapults-past-power-hungry-competitors</link>
            <guid>45398802</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 19:48:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.tomshardware.com/pc-components/cpus/apples-a19-becomes-the-fastest-single-core-cpu-in-the-world-on-passmark-beating-pc-chips-and-apples-own-m3-ultra-passively-cooled-iphone-17-chip-catapults-past-power-hungry-competitors">https://www.tomshardware.com/pc-components/cpus/apples-a19-becomes-the-fastest-single-core-cpu-in-the-world-on-passmark-beating-pc-chips-and-apples-own-m3-ultra-passively-cooled-iphone-17-chip-catapults-past-power-hungry-competitors</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45398802">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-widget-type="contentparsed" id="content">
<section>
<div>
<div>
<picture data-new-v2-image="true">
<source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ycugCVL9Mycynwx4LPGKeH-1451-80.jpg.webp 1920w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ycugCVL9Mycynwx4LPGKeH-1200-80.jpg.webp 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ycugCVL9Mycynwx4LPGKeH-1024-80.jpg.webp 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ycugCVL9Mycynwx4LPGKeH-970-80.jpg.webp 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ycugCVL9Mycynwx4LPGKeH-650-80.jpg.webp 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ycugCVL9Mycynwx4LPGKeH-480-80.jpg.webp 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ycugCVL9Mycynwx4LPGKeH-320-80.jpg.webp 320w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 600px, calc(100vw - 40px)">
<img src="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ycugCVL9Mycynwx4LPGKeH.jpg" alt="Apple A19" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ycugCVL9Mycynwx4LPGKeH-1451-80.jpg 1920w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ycugCVL9Mycynwx4LPGKeH-1200-80.jpg 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ycugCVL9Mycynwx4LPGKeH-1024-80.jpg 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ycugCVL9Mycynwx4LPGKeH-970-80.jpg 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ycugCVL9Mycynwx4LPGKeH-650-80.jpg 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ycugCVL9Mycynwx4LPGKeH-480-80.jpg 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ycugCVL9Mycynwx4LPGKeH-320-80.jpg 320w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 600px, calc(100vw - 40px)" data-new-v2-image="true" data-original-mos="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ycugCVL9Mycynwx4LPGKeH.jpg" data-pin-media="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ycugCVL9Mycynwx4LPGKeH.jpg" data-pin-nopin="true" fetchpriority="high">
</picture>
</div>
<figcaption>
<span>(Image credit: Apple)</span>
</figcaption>
</div>

<div id="article-body">
<p id="9598606f-6e07-4467-9c5e-8574022330ed">Apple's latest generation of iPhones is equipped with its A19 chips — the standard A19 on iPhone 17 and the A19 Pro on iPhone 17 Air and Pros — which represent the best the company has to offer, <em>literally</em>. In PassMark's single-threaded benchmark, the A19 produced <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://x.com/PassMarkInc/status/1971365505710817321" data-url="https://x.com/PassMarkInc/status/1971365505710817321" target="_blank" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none">the best numbers of any chip</a> available, including fully-fledged desktop SKUs. It did that while consuming significantly less power and being passively cooled. At least in this hyper-specific case, Apple's A19 has become the fastest CPU available.</p><p>Both the A19 and A19 Pro benchmarked within the margin of error of each other; however, officially, it was the regular A19 that posted 5,149 points to claim the single-thread performance crown. The A19 Pro scored 5,088 points, which makes sense considering both chips share the same cores, just differing amounts of them. The A19 beats heavy hitters like Apple's own desktop-class <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.tomshardware.com/desktops/apple-debuts-m3-ultra-in-refreshed-mac-studio-with-up-to-512gb-memory" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.tomshardware.com/desktops/apple-debuts-m3-ultra-in-refreshed-mac-studio-with-up-to-512gb-memory">M3 Ultra</a> (both 28- and 32-core variants), <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.tomshardware.com/pc-components/cpus/amd-ryzen-9-9950x-vs-intel-core-ultra-9-285k-faceoff-it-isnt-even-close" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.tomshardware.com/pc-components/cpus/amd-ryzen-9-9950x-vs-intel-core-ultra-9-285k-faceoff-it-isnt-even-close">Intel's Core Ultra 9 285K</a>, and even the <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.tomshardware.com/pc-components/cpus/new-zen-5-128-core-epyc-cpu-weilds-512mb-of-l3-cache" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.tomshardware.com/pc-components/cpus/new-zen-5-128-core-epyc-cpu-weilds-512mb-of-l3-cache">EPYC 4585PX</a> from AMD — all of which would be actively cooled.</p><div id="1971365505710817321"><blockquote data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">This is a pretty incredible single threaded benchmark result from Apple with the A19. Plus it is claimed to use only 12watts. For comparison the Ultra 9 is 125W+ and EPYC 4585PX is 170W+https://t.co/ysO73jpaVv pic.twitter.com/e9niPV5I3y<a href="https://twitter.com/cantworkitout/status/1971365505710817321" data-url="https://twitter.com/cantworkitout/status/1971365505710817321" target="_blank" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none">September 26, 2025</a></p></blockquote></div><p id="727fbaf0-c5aa-42b1-b355-91c2dc1f4bca-0">The tweet caption lists nominal TDPs of these chips for comparison, but that's not what a single-core load would actually use. Since it's incredibly difficult to pinpoint that, PassMark itself estimated the single-threaded power consumption <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://x.com/PassMarkInc/status/1971730057862566329" data-url="https://x.com/PassMarkInc/status/1971730057862566329" target="_blank" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none">in a reply</a>, saying the A19 is likely using 4W, the 285K is using 44W, and the EPYC is using 56W. Even if those 1/3 assumptions are wrong, the delta is so high between the three that it doesn't really matter. The A19 is miles ahead in terms of efficiency.</p><p>Where it falters, of course, is multi-threaded performance. It doesn't scale upward when you take more/all cores into account, but that's to be expected with a mobile-only chip, given that it simply has fewer cores than every other CPU on the list. Moreover, keep in mind that the A19 is inside the iPhone 17, which doesn't have a vapor chamber, so it's even more impressive for it to pull these kinds of numbers. Then again, this isn't precisely an uber-scientific test, so don't take these results at face value.</p><p><em>Follow </em><a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://news.google.com/publications/CAAqLAgKIiZDQklTRmdnTWFoSUtFSFJ2YlhOb1lYSmtkMkZ5WlM1amIyMG9BQVAB" target="_blank" data-url="https://news.google.com/publications/CAAqLAgKIiZDQklTRmdnTWFoSUtFSFJ2YlhOb1lYSmtkMkZ5WlM1amIyMG9BQVAB" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none"><em>Tom's Hardware on Google News</em></a><em>, or </em><a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://google.com/preferences/source?q=" target="_blank" data-url="https://google.com/preferences/source?q=" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none"><em>add us as a preferred source</em></a><em>, to get our up-to-date news, analysis, and reviews in your feeds. Make sure to click the Follow button!</em></p><div data-hydrate="true" id="slice-container-newsletterForm-articleInbodyContent-oES5rGgX64e8ph3uKSdwEg"><section><p>Get Tom's Hardware's best news and in-depth reviews, straight to your inbox.</p></section></div>
</div>



<!-- Drop in a standard article here maybe? -->




<div id="slice-container-authorBio-oES5rGgX64e8ph3uKSdwEg"><p>Hassam Nasir is a die-hard hardware enthusiast with years of experience as a tech editor and writer, focusing on detailed CPU comparisons and general hardware news. When he’s not working, you’ll find him bending tubes for his ever-evolving custom water-loop gaming rig or benchmarking the latest CPUs and GPUs just for fun.  </p></div>
</section>




</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The death of east London's most radical bookshop (123 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.the-londoner.co.uk/scarlett-letters-closure-left-wing-bookshop/</link>
            <guid>45398153</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 18:15:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.the-londoner.co.uk/scarlett-letters-closure-left-wing-bookshop/">https://www.the-londoner.co.uk/scarlett-letters-closure-left-wing-bookshop/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45398153">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      
<div data-layout="minimal">
                
                    <p><a href="#/portal/signup/free"><img src="https://www.the-londoner.co.uk/content/images/2025/07/The-Londoner-icons-3.png" alt="CTA Image" data-image-dimensions="170x170"></a>
                    </p>
                
                
                    <div>
                    
                        <p><span>This article was published by </span><b><strong>The Londoner</strong></b><span>: a new newsletter covering the capital. Join our free mailing list below to get great writing and big scoops in your inbox.</span></p>
                    
                    
                        <p><a href="#/portal/signup/free">
                            Join The Londoner for free
                        </a>
                        
                    </p></div>
                
            </div>
<p>It was 4am on the 1st of July as Jack Parker bolted upright in the basement below the Scarlett Letters bookshop. From above, Parker could hear drilling. Then a “thunderstorm” of footsteps. Startled and bleary-eyed, they hurriedly dressed, then crept up the stairs into the main bookshop. What they saw “horrified” them.</p><p>Dozens of people hurriedly packing books into boxes and unscrewing bookshelves. Amongst the torrent of people, maybe the strangest thing they noticed was the face of Blaise Agüera y Arcas: author, AI researcher and the vice president of Google’s research arm. Peculiar though it was to see one of the most senior staff at one of the world’s biggest tech giants busting into a bookshop occupation in Bethnal Green, maybe what was more peculiar was how it all came about in the first place. The setting for this bizarre scene was the Scarlett Letters, named for its owner Marin Scarlett, a radical east London bookshop that was greeted with widespread fanfare by many of the capital's left-wing activists.</p><p>And here Scarlett was, with a team of people, bursting into the bookshop in the middle of the night in an attempt to disrupt an occupation by a radical cohort of the shop’s staff. To Parker's mind, for a project started with the aim of platforming sex workers and being a “hub for resistance, community, stories and imagination” to have reached such a point was mortifying. How had things gotten so bad? Well, at least in Parker's telling, it started with a clogged toilet.</p><p>Sporting a black T-shirt, cropped hair and anticapitalist and LGBT-rights tattoos on each arm, the former bookseller meets me in the bare, debris-littered unit that used to house the bookshop. We’re here to talk about the whole sorry saga of Scarlett Letters — the rise, the fall, the union disputes, the rows, the occupations and the drilled locks under nightfall. But first, we need to talk toilets.</p><figure><img src="https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXcdHMQ65c8ly6f0-tKauKHUlkYWoNO1vN9oHlxsjcsdddccqY3Q0aRCaf48hPa9EbBd9sEcNZ8XIOsvqbobkEj9zY-K983KkJoGpD4HFHO_11kUDBnjV8dGsGU8u455bj9XdtGj?key=kMtj8Yn4kpj1VvRQ2cmVqw" alt="" loading="lazy" width="602" height="339"><figcaption><span>The leftover debris in the bookshop now. Image by Andrew Kersley&nbsp;</span></figcaption></figure><p>On a fateful day in early April, less than six months after the shop opened, a plumber had to be called in to fix the disabled toilet, which was inexplicably installed in the non-wheelchair-accessible basement of the bookshop. After the plumber was done, staff opened the work WhatsApp chat to see a message from Marin Scarlett updating the shop’s toilet policy: “We have had an issue over the last few weeks of people just letting themselves downstairs to use the toilet. Our toilet is there for people to use on request, but it is a problem if someone feels they can just let themselves down there without asking.”</p><p>Keen to thwart any further opportunistic toilet-users, Scarlett had a new policy. Staff were to personally escort anyone who asked to use the toilet to ensure they didn’t steal any stock or snoop around the staff area. She then told her staff she wanted to “role play” some scenarios in which they could practice saying “no”. Seemingly, the crux of the toilet problem was that they were simply too kind, too feminine, too British: “You are all extremely nice, assigned female at birth, in customer service, mostly British etc., and all of this sometimes doesn't lend itself to ‘no,’” the WhatsApp message explained. She suggested staff had been failing to tell customers “no” when they asked to borrow scissors or mugs from the shop, to come behind the counter or when they wanted to serenade them without prompting.</p><p>Like a toilet with a burst pipe, “toilet-gate” then erupted. Almost immediately, a dispute broke out in the work WhatsApp over the message; there was anger not just about that final message, which Parker saw as “bizarre and sexist”, but over the political ramifications of making members of the community ask to use the toilet in the bookshop.</p><p>While there had been rumblings of unease from staff for months at the store over the lack of shifts, sick pay and secure contracts, something changed in that moment. “We hadn't broadly discussed unionising with everyone,” explains Parker. “But I saw this, it was like we were in complete solidarity. We needed to unionise immediately.”</p><div data-lexical-signup-form="">
                    <h2><span>Join for free </span></h2>
                    <p><span>This article was published by </span><b><strong>The Londoner</strong></b><span>, a new quality newspaper delivered via email. Four days a week, we send you a carefully chosen story, plus our best recommendations. We prioritise </span><b><strong>quality over quantity</strong></b><span> and everything we send is in your inbox - you don't need to click on any links. To give us a try, join our </span><b><strong>free mailing list </strong></b><span>below. </span></p>
                    
        
        
                    <p><span>Click subscribe and then check your email now to complete your signup.</span></p>
                </div><p>Unionisation at a place like Scarlett Letters might sound a bit strange. It was, after all, billed as a radical left-wing bookshop, not generally the sort of place that should need unions. Even the union was a bit confused. “I was a bit surprised when they contacted us,” explains Matt Collins, an organiser for the United Voices of the World trade union.</p><p>But within a week of “toilet-gate”, every single member of staff at the shop had joined the UVW. They drafted a list of demands, which included being granted sick pay, an end to the use of zero hours contracts<strong><em> </em></strong>and running the shop on co-operative principles (in other words, allowing staff to have a say in management). It was sent to Scarlett at the end of April. An initial meeting between Scarlett and the UVW yielded some agreements, though Scarlett told the meeting she was working six or seven days most weeks, and was earning less per hour than the booksellers, so needed to hire a manager, a move that would mean several of the booksellers would need to be let go.</p><figure><img src="https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXe4qzupbRocoxtysLm4mwLcA-k65W2VRjrrykHl5L7A76ILaC0x3ZhvwO1LBY0UpXq4jF1JV-vJIxLa0Z51CgFkXfz-ShSwCrlsDRW18VDwPjq4vehbC0NlrpDqWYkhlX0DfvR-?key=kMtj8Yn4kpj1VvRQ2cmVqw" alt="" loading="lazy" width="602" height="339"><figcaption><span>The now abandoned front of the bookshop. Image by Andrew Kersley</span></figcaption></figure><p>Then there was the tricky business of the bookseller’s call for a co-operative management model. Since opening, the Scarlett Letters hadn’t made a month-by-month profit, but had been kept afloat by savings and a monthly donation of £10,000 from an anonymous “angel investor”. Only Scarlett knew the identity of the investor and she shared a response from the investor that they were considering cutting or even pulling their donation if the shop became a co-operative.</p><p>With the dispute at something of a stalemate, the booksellers reached for the most obvious lever available to them, unleashing a broadside of Instagram posts in Scarlett’s direction. A newly launched account said they were in “open dispute” with their employer over the threats to fire staff and the failure to meet all its demands. “The workers are queer, trans, racialised, disabled, sex workers and students,” it argued. “Their identities have been used to advertise and fundraise for the bookshop as a radical space whilst their voices are not listened to.” As might be expected, there was an outraged response online. Responses on Instagram accused the bookshop of being a “marketing campaign” as well as “colonial”.</p><p>Eight days later, Scarlett fired back on the shop’s Instagram, claiming they had attempted to, or were in the process of meeting, almost all the union’s demands. “Trying to create a space like this in advanced capitalism is extremely difficult,” it read. “The management targeted by this dispute is not a faceless collective of executives in boardrooms. It is one person, who is multiply marginalised, a known member of the community and for the past year has been working for six or seven days a week for the fraction of the salary offered to the booksellers.” It ended with a shocking revelation: the bookshop would now be closing. A meeting with an external HR firm was scheduled for the end of June to discuss the closure and the staff’s redundancies. Scarlett herself said she was surprised at how things escalated and insists she “sent requests to meet again four separate times,” but that “these were ignored or refused”.</p><figure><img src="https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXcQaeJGZxNUAHmRaV3XG9UANYazwR3_aRFAF2nCWe7LfGGcPhZ9WdMddWiz2tvi-UCzUNiZMFzcQbg9_vDSmu1g9efuZU3CA7saZ61zjXZ1KL_5Lrvhocq3Mrp4vjOg5AfI1ngirA?key=kMtj8Yn4kpj1VvRQ2cmVqw" alt="" loading="lazy" width="602" height="401"><figcaption><span>The bookstore back when it was still open. Image courtesy of Marin Scarlett</span></figcaption></figure><p>And that might have been that. A sad, if fairly run-of-the-mill tale of how an unfortunate toilet clogging thwarted Bethnal Green’s heady dream of a radical bookshop. But that’s not how our story ends, because the soon-to-be jobless booksellers weren’t giving up that easily. In response to Scarlett’s decision, they hatched a plan: they were going to occupy the bookshop.</p><p>Parker is keen to state that they weren’t aiming to make Scarlett hand over the directorship of the shop, rather they wanted her to donate them the stock. Estimating it to be worth £70,000 (Scarlett puts this figure at closer to £10,000) they felt they could use it to start a new bookshop more closely aligned with their political values.&nbsp;</p><p>On the Sunday ahead of the meeting, the staff moved themselves into the crammed two floor bookshop. Parker came with a suitcase, planning to spend four days there. “I didn't have enough money to keep getting the train back and forth from Wimbledon,” they explain. “So I figured that I'll just put myself on the rota for four nights. I was getting a small payment from a porn site that wasn’t a significant amount of money, but enough for the train home.”</p><p>On Monday, they joined the video call on one computer, sitting as a group with the shelves of the store as their backdrop. The meeting would last just a few minutes. They made their demand for the stock to be transferred to them. The official from the HR firm explained, on behalf of Scarlett, that the<strong><em> </em></strong>bookshop’s legal obligations meant the books were “asset-locked” and that there was no legal mechanism to transfer stock to employees for free. As the shop’s director, Scarlett could even be liable and struck off starting a company if she did so. </p><p>But the booksellers didn’t waver. They announced they would be occupying the shop until their demands were met, and abruptly left the call. Next, they hurriedly unfurled a banner announcing the occupation across the storefront. They had the only set of keys, Parker told me, so thought that as long as no-one allowed management to access the building they could stay indefinitely, protected by squatter’s rights.</p><p>By 10pm that night, the three occupiers who volunteered to stay overnight went down to the basement and bedded down, steeling themselves for the weeks of resistance to come. In the end, it would be much shorter than expected.&nbsp;</p><div data-lexical-signup-form="">
                    <h2><span>Join for free </span></h2>
                    <p><span>This article was published by </span><b><strong>The Londoner</strong></b><span>, a new quality newspaper delivered via email. Four days a week, we send you a carefully chosen story, plus our best recommendations. We prioritise </span><b><strong>quality over quantity</strong></b><span> and everything we send is in your inbox - you don't need to click on any links. To give us a try, join our </span><b><strong>free mailing list </strong></b><span>below. </span></p>
                    
        
        
                    <p><span>Click subscribe and then check your email now to complete your signup.</span></p>
                </div><p>What the group hadn’t accounted for, was the foresight of Marin Scarlett. As it happened, on the first day of the occupation she had arranged a locksmith, as well as a team to help her recover the stock. She’d covered every base: even hiring carpenters to remove the bookshelves and bringing along three legal observers to impartially oversee things. At around 4am, they arrived at Scarlett Letters and started drilling.&nbsp;</p><p>Over the next three hours, books were slid into boxes and shelves were unscrewed from walls. At some point in the night, Parker emerged up the stairwell and saw the whole sorry scene play out. “There were people I knew personally, and that just horrified me,” Parker says. </p><figure><img src="https://www.the-londoner.co.uk/content/images/2025/07/AD_4nXfEOTKGm3VN166-4MxvS1ujhRKvzYwdygLYyc1V-dMIRP5192r-NFS1QKTq82oM6DK-OrMqPo_A4BEo9Vwqb7GPdLOWyE9PoLJ_pbUFLNyWIvRhpoVM_yrneF3syb9inxMuJaQY.jpeg" alt="" loading="lazy" width="900" height="982" srcset="https://www.the-londoner.co.uk/content/images/size/w600/2025/07/AD_4nXfEOTKGm3VN166-4MxvS1ujhRKvzYwdygLYyc1V-dMIRP5192r-NFS1QKTq82oM6DK-OrMqPo_A4BEo9Vwqb7GPdLOWyE9PoLJ_pbUFLNyWIvRhpoVM_yrneF3syb9inxMuJaQY.jpeg 600w, https://www.the-londoner.co.uk/content/images/2025/07/AD_4nXfEOTKGm3VN166-4MxvS1ujhRKvzYwdygLYyc1V-dMIRP5192r-NFS1QKTq82oM6DK-OrMqPo_A4BEo9Vwqb7GPdLOWyE9PoLJ_pbUFLNyWIvRhpoVM_yrneF3syb9inxMuJaQY.jpeg 900w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption><span>A sign on the wall of the now empty bookstore announcing its planned reopening. Image by Andrew Kersley</span></figcaption></figure><p>Now, the bookshop is a husk, almost entirely empty apart from the posters announcing future plans to reopen as “The People’s Letters” — a co-operative run by the booksellers that they believe will adhere to more leftist principles than its predecessor. </p><p>Unsurprisingly, Scarlett sees the whole debacle quite differently to the booksellers. She says she “had hoped to work with the union” and that “an improved sick pay was immediately implemented after our first meeting with UVW”. When the talks with the union broke down and things were taken to social media, sales tanked and it became clear that the store couldn’t stay open. The “shop would have stayed open until late July had the booksellers not tried to steal the stock, but their actions forced us to close several weeks early”. When she and a group of friends entered the shop to reclaim the books, they “did not know that anyone was in the property when we entered”.</p><p>Collins has spent 14 years in the trade union movement, but is equally baffled by how things managed to end where they did. “I've never experienced a dispute like it before,” he tells me. “I imagine I never will again.” Here ends the tale of Scarlett Letters, the radical bookshop the capital could have had, only for those dreams to be flushed away.</p>
<div data-layout="immersive">
                    
                        <div>
                            <p><span>Welcome to The Londoner. We’re the capital’s new magazine, delivered entirely by email. Sign up to our </span><a href="https://www.the-londoner.co.uk/young-successful-and-far-right/#/portal/signup/free" rel="noreferrer"><span>mailing list</span></a><span> and get two </span><b><strong>totally free</strong></b><span> editions of The Londoner every week: a Monday briefing, full of everything you need to know about that’s going on in the city; and an in-depth weekend piece like the one you're currently reading.</span></p><p><span>No ads, no gimmicks: just click the button below and get our unique brand of local journalism straight to your inbox. </span></p>
                        </div>
                    
                    
                        <p><a href="#/portal/signup/free">
                            Sign up for free
                        </a>
                        
                    </p></div>



    </div><p>
  <strong>How to comment:</strong><br>
  If you are <i>already a member, </i>
  <a href="#/portal/signin" onmouseover="this.style.textDecoration='underline'" onmouseout="this.style.textDecoration='none'">
     click here to sign in 
  </a> and leave a comment. <br>
  If you aren't a member, 
  <a href="#/portal/signup" onmouseover="this.style.textDecoration='underline'" onmouseout="this.style.textDecoration='none'">
    sign up here 
  </a> to be able to leave a comment. <br>

To add your photo, <a href="https://gravatar.com/" target="_blank" onmouseover="this.style.textDecoration='underline'" onmouseout="this.style.textDecoration='none'">click here to create a profile on Gravatar.</a><br>



  </p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I made a public living room and the internet keeps putting weirder stuff in it (136 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theroom.lol</link>
            <guid>45398005</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 17:59:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theroom.lol">https://www.theroom.lol</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45398005">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="app">
    
    <p>0</p>
    <p>IMAGE RESET ON NEXT PROMPT</p>
    <div id="overlay">
        
        <div id="uploadPane">
          <div id="uploadSection">
            <p id="uploadMessage">Upload a base image to start editing this room.</p>
            
            
          </div>
          <div id="intervalGroup">
            <p><label for="resetInterval">Reset after this many prompts:</label></p>
            
          </div>
        </div>
        <form id="form">
          
          
          
        </form>
        
        <div id="indicatorRow">
          <p>0 here</p>
          <div id="indicatorRight">
            <div id="roomSwitch" aria-label="Room selector"><p><a href="https://www.theroom.lol/">Room 1</a><span>/</span><a href="https://www.theroom.lol/overflow">Room 2</a></p></div>
            <p>--</p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Greenland Is a Beautiful Nightmare (410 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://matduggan.com/greenland-is-a-beautiful-nightmare/</link>
            <guid>45396754</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 15:46:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://matduggan.com/greenland-is-a-beautiful-nightmare/">https://matduggan.com/greenland-is-a-beautiful-nightmare/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45396754">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        
        <main id="main-content" role="main">
            
<article>
    

    <figure>
        <img srcset="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1573995975633-faee0123f31f?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wxMTc3M3wwfDF8c2VhcmNofDN8fGdyZWVubGFuZHxlbnwwfHx8fDE3NTg5NjI3MzN8MA&amp;ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=80&amp;w=2000 300w,
                    https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1573995975633-faee0123f31f?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wxMTc3M3wwfDF8c2VhcmNofDN8fGdyZWVubGFuZHxlbnwwfHx8fDE3NTg5NjI3MzN8MA&amp;ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=80&amp;w=2000 600w,
                    https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1573995975633-faee0123f31f?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wxMTc3M3wwfDF8c2VhcmNofDN8fGdyZWVubGFuZHxlbnwwfHx8fDE3NTg5NjI3MzN8MA&amp;ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=80&amp;w=2000 1000w,
                    https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1573995975633-faee0123f31f?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wxMTc3M3wwfDF8c2VhcmNofDN8fGdyZWVubGFuZHxlbnwwfHx8fDE3NTg5NjI3MzN8MA&amp;ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=80&amp;w=2000 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 400px, 700px" src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1573995975633-faee0123f31f?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wxMTc3M3wwfDF8c2VhcmNofDN8fGdyZWVubGFuZHxlbnwwfHx8fDE3NTg5NjI3MzN8MA&amp;ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=80&amp;w=2000" alt="Greenland is a beautiful nightmare" loading="lazy" decoding="async">
            <figcaption><span>Photo by </span><a href="https://unsplash.com/@visitgreenland?utm_source=ghost&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=api-credit"><span>Visit Greenland</span></a><span> / </span><a href="https://unsplash.com/?utm_source=ghost&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=api-credit"><span>Unsplash</span></a></figcaption>
    </figure>
    
    <div>
            <p>Greenland is a complicated topic here in Denmark. The former colony that is still treated a bit like a colony is something that inspires a lot of emotions. Greenland has been subjected to a lot of unethical experiments by Denmark, from taking their kids to wild experiments in criminal justice. But there is also a genuine pride a lot of people have here for the place and you run into Danes who grew up there more often than I would have guessed. </p><p>When the idea of going to Greenland was introduced to me, I was curious. Having lived in Denmark for awhile, you hear a lot about the former colony and its 55,000 residents. We were invited by a family that my wife was close with growing up and is Danish. They wanted to take their father back to see the place he had spend some time in during his 20s and had left quite an impression. A few drinks in, I said "absolutely let's do it", not realizing we had already committed to going and I had missed the text message chain. </p><p>A few weeks before I went, I realized "I don't know anything about Greenland" and started to watch some YouTube videos. It was about this time when I started to get a pit in my stomach, the "oh god I think I've made a huge mistake" feeling I'm painfully familiar with after a career in tech.  Greenland appeared to have roughly 9 people living there and maybe 5 things to look at. Even professional travel personalities seemed to be scraping the bottom of the barrel. "There's the grocery store again!" they would point out as they slipped down the snowy roads. I couldn't  tell any difference between different towns in the country.</p><p>It reminded me a lot of driving through Indiana. For those not in the US, Indiana is a state in the US famous for being a state one must drive through in order to get somewhere better. If you live in Michigan, a good state and want to go to Illinois, another good state, one must pass through Indiana, a blank state. Because of this little strip here, you often found yourself passing through this place. </p><figure><img src="https://matduggan.com/content/images/2025/09/image-1.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="470" height="299"></figure><p>Driving through Indiana isn't bad, it's just an empty void. It's like a time machine back to the 90s when people still smoke in restaurants but also there's nothing that sticks out about it. There is nothing distinct about Indiana, it's just a place full of people who got too tired on their way to somewhere better and decided "this is good enough". The difference is that Greenland is very hard to get to, as I was about to learn. </p><p>Finally the day arrived. Me, my wife, daughter, 4 other children and 6 other adults all came to the Copenhagen Airport and held up a gate agent for what felt like an hour to slowly process all of our documents. Meanwhile, I nursed a creeping paranoia that I'd be treated as some sort of American spy, given my government's recent hobby of threatening to purchase entire countries like they're vintage motorcycles on Craigslist.</p><p>The 5 hour flight is uneventful, the children are beautifully behaved and I begin to think "well this seems ok!" like the idiot I am. As I can look down and see the airport, the pilot comes on and informs us that there is too much fog to land safely. <em>Surely fog cannot stop a modern aircraft full of all these dials and screens</em> I think, foolishly. We are informed there is enough fuel to circle the airport for 5 hours to wait for the fog to lift. </p><p>What followed was three hours of flying in lazy circles, like a very expensive, very slow merry-go-round. After the allotted time, we are informed that we must fly to Iceland to refuel and then <em>we will be returning to Denmark</em>. After a total of 15 hours in the air we will be going back to exactly where we started, to do the entire thing again. We were obviously upset at this turn of events, but I noticed the native Greenlandic folks seemed not surprised at this turn of events. As I later learned, this happens <em>all the time</em>. </p><p>The native Greenlanders on board seemed utterly unsurprised by this development, displaying the kind of resigned familiarity that suggested this was Tuesday for them. I began wondering if I could just pretend Iceland was Greenland—surely my family wouldn't notice the difference? But the pilot, apparently reading my mind, announced that no one would be disembarking in Iceland. It felt oddly authoritarian, like being grounded by an airline, as if they knew we'd all just wander off into Reykjavik and call it close enough.</p><p>We crash out in a airport hotel 20 minutes from our apartment after 15 hours in the air and tons of CO2 emissions only to wake up the next day to start again. This time, I notice that all of the people are asking for (and receiving) free beer from the crew that they are stashing in their bags. It turns out soda and beer, really anything that needs to be imported, is pretty expensive in Greenland. The complimentary drinks are there to be kept for later. </p><p>Finally we land. The first thing you notice when you land in Greenland is there are no trees or grass. There is snow and then there is exposed rock. The exterior of the airport is metal but the inside is wood, which is strange because again there are no trees. This would end up being a theme, where buildings representing Denmark were made out of lots of wood, almost to ensure that you understood they weren't from here. We ended up piling all of our stuff into a bus and heading for the hotel in Nuuk. </p><h3 id="nuuk">Nuuk</h3><p>Nuuk is the capital of Greenland and your introduction to the incredible calm of the Greenlandic people. I have never met a less stressed out group of humans in my life. Nobody is really rushing anywhere, it's all pretty quiet and calm. The air is cold and crisp with lots of kids playing outside and just generally enjoying life. </p><figure><img src="https://matduggan.com/content/images/2025/09/image-2.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1280" height="840" srcset="https://matduggan.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/09/image-2.png 600w, https://matduggan.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/09/image-2.png 1000w, https://matduggan.com/content/images/2025/09/image-2.png 1280w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>The city itself sits in a landscape so dramatically inhospitable it makes the surface of Mars look cozy. Walking through the local mall, half the shops sell gear designed to help you survive what appears to be the apocalypse. Yet somehow, there's traffic. Actual traffic jams in a place where you can walk from one end to the other in twenty minutes. It's like being stuck behind a school bus in your own driveway.</p><figure><img src="https://matduggan.com/content/images/2025/09/image-3.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1302" height="1208" srcset="https://matduggan.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/09/image-3.png 600w, https://matduggan.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/09/image-3.png 1000w, https://matduggan.com/content/images/2025/09/image-3.png 1302w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>To put this map into some perspective, it is only six kilometers from the sorta furthest tip to the airport. </p><figure><img src="https://matduggan.com/content/images/2025/09/image-4.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1368" height="1114" srcset="https://matduggan.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/09/image-4.png 600w, https://matduggan.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/09/image-4.png 1000w, https://matduggan.com/content/images/2025/09/image-4.png 1368w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>But riding the bus around Nuuk was a peaceful experience that lets you see pretty much the entire city without needing to book a tour or spend a lot of money. We went to Katuaq, a cultural center with a cafe and a movie theater that was absolutely delicious food. </p><p>But again even riding the bus around it is impossible to escape the feeling that this is a fundamentally hostile to human life place. The sun is bright and during the summer its pretty hot, with my skin feeling like it was starting the burn pretty much the second it was exposed to the light. It's hard to even dress for, with layers of sunscreen, bug spray and then something warm on top if you suddenly got cold. </p><p>The sun, meanwhile, has apparently forgotten how to set, turning our hotel rooms into solar ovens. You wake up in a pool of your own sweat, crack a window for relief, and immediately get hit with air so cold it feels personal. It's like being trapped in a meteorological mood swing.</p><p>So after a night here, we went back to the airport again and flew to our final destination, Ilulissat.</p><h3 id="ilulissat">Ilulissat </h3><figure><img src="https://matduggan.com/content/images/2025/09/FE5AF77D-8082-4A05-B6F4-03B54D9008DE_1_105_c.jpeg" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="768" srcset="https://matduggan.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/09/FE5AF77D-8082-4A05-B6F4-03B54D9008DE_1_105_c.jpeg 600w, https://matduggan.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/09/FE5AF77D-8082-4A05-B6F4-03B54D9008DE_1_105_c.jpeg 1000w, https://matduggan.com/content/images/2025/09/FE5AF77D-8082-4A05-B6F4-03B54D9008DE_1_105_c.jpeg 1024w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption><span>My new favorite airport</span></figcaption></figure><p>The flight to our final destination revealed Greenland's true nature: endless, empty hills stretching toward infinity, punctuated by ice formations that look like nature's sculpture garden.</p><figure><img src="https://matduggan.com/content/images/2025/09/F321BAFB-F30A-4D36-A2C6-E85FB3CA3BEB_1_105_c.jpeg" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="768" srcset="https://matduggan.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/09/F321BAFB-F30A-4D36-A2C6-E85FB3CA3BEB_1_105_c.jpeg 600w, https://matduggan.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/09/F321BAFB-F30A-4D36-A2C6-E85FB3CA3BEB_1_105_c.jpeg 1000w, https://matduggan.com/content/images/2025/09/F321BAFB-F30A-4D36-A2C6-E85FB3CA3BEB_1_105_c.jpeg 1024w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Landing in Ilulissat felt like victory—we'd made it to the actual destination, not just another waypoint in our Arctic odyssey. Walking through the tiny airport, past Danish military recruitment posters (apparently someone, somewhere, thought this place needed defending), I felt genuinely optimistic for the first time in days.</p><p>Well you can sleep easy Danish military, because Ilulissat is completely protected from invasion. The second I stepped outside I was set upon by a flood of mosquitos like I have never experienced before. I have been to the jungles of Vietnam, the swamps of Florida and the Canadian countryside. This was beyond anything I've ever experienced. </p><p>There are bugs in my mouth, ears, eyes and nose almost immediately. The photo below is not me being dramatic, it is actually what is required to keep them off of me. </p><figure><img src="https://matduggan.com/content/images/2025/09/46C37475-5A8C-4702-BC2E-B6B89A12F9D7_4_5005_c.jpeg" alt="" loading="lazy" width="360" height="480"></figure><p>In fact what you need to purchase in order to walk around this area at all are basically bug nets for your face. They're effectively plastic mesh bags that you put on. </p><figure><img src="https://matduggan.com/content/images/2025/09/F3FD1061-F86E-4545-937B-87F8B7FA85E3_1_105_c.jpeg" alt="" loading="lazy" width="768" height="1024" srcset="https://matduggan.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/09/F3FD1061-F86E-4545-937B-87F8B7FA85E3_1_105_c.jpeg 600w, https://matduggan.com/content/images/2025/09/F3FD1061-F86E-4545-937B-87F8B7FA85E3_1_105_c.jpeg 768w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><h3 id="the-dogs">The Dogs</h3><p>Our hotel, charming in that "remote Arctic outpost" way, sat adjacent to what I can only describe as a canine correctional facility. Dozens of sled dogs were chained to rocks like some sort of prehistoric parking lot, each with a tiny house they could retreat to when the existential weight of their circumstances became too much.</p><p>Now, I'd always imagined sled dogs living their best life—running through snow, tongues lolling, living the Disney version of Arctic life. I'd never really considered their downtime, assuming they frolicked in meadows or something equally wholesome. The reality was more "minimum security prison with a view."</p><p>The dogs are visited roughly twice a day by the person who owns and feeds them, which was quite the party for the dogs that lost their minds whenever the car pulled up. Soon the kids really looked forward to dog feeding time. The fish scrapes the dogs lived on came out of a chest freezer that was left exposed up on the rock face without electricity and you could smell it from 50 yards away when it opened. </p><p>During one such performance, a fellow parent leaned over and whispered with the casual tone of someone commenting on the weather, "I think that one is dead." Before I could process this information, the frozen canine was unceremoniously launched over a small cliff like a furry discus. A second doggy popsicle followed shortly after, right in front of our assembled children, who watched with the kind of wide-eyed fascination usually reserved for magic shows.</p><figure><img src="https://matduggan.com/content/images/2025/09/IMG_0069-2.jpeg" alt="" loading="lazy" width="2000" height="2667" srcset="https://matduggan.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/09/IMG_0069-2.jpeg 600w, https://matduggan.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/09/IMG_0069-2.jpeg 1000w, https://matduggan.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/09/IMG_0069-2.jpeg 1600w, https://matduggan.com/content/images/size/w2400/2025/09/IMG_0069-2.jpeg 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>We stopped making dog feeding time a group activity after that and had to distract the kids from ravens flying away with tufts of dog fur. </p><h3 id="whales-taste-like-seaweed">Whales taste like seaweed </h3><p>Obviously a big part of Greenland is the nature, specifically the icebergs. Icebergs are incredible and during the week we spend up there, I enjoyed watching them every morning. It's like watching a mountain slowly moving while you sit still. The visual contrast of the ice and the exposed stone is beautiful and peaceful. </p><figure><img src="https://matduggan.com/content/images/2025/09/IMG_1096-copy.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy" width="2000" height="1500" srcset="https://matduggan.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/09/IMG_1096-copy.jpg 600w, https://matduggan.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/09/IMG_1096-copy.jpg 1000w, https://matduggan.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/09/IMG_1096-copy.jpg 1600w, https://matduggan.com/content/images/size/w2400/2025/09/IMG_1096-copy.jpg 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Finding our tour operator proved to be an exercise in small-town efficiency. The man who gave me directions was the same person who picked us up from the airport, who was also our tour guide, who probably doubled as the mayor and local meteorologist. It was like a one-man civic operation disguised as multiple businesses—the ultimate small-town gig economy.</p><p>The sea around Greenland is calmer than anything I've ever been on before, perfectly calm and serene. All around us whales emerged, thrilling my daughter. However the biggest hit of the entire tour, maybe the entire trip, was a member of the crew who handed each of the kids a giant rock of glacier ice to eat. I had to pull my daughter away to observe the natural beauty as she ate glacier ice like it was ice cream. "LOOK AT MY ICE" she was yelling as they slipped and slid around the deck of this boat. </p><p>So if you've ever wonder "what is a glacier", let me tell you. Greenland has a lot of ice and it pushes out from the land that is covers into the sea. When that happens, a lot of it breaks off. This sounds more exciting than it is. On TV in 4K it looks incredible, giant mountains of ice falling into the ocean. Honestly you can go read the same thing I did <a href="https://science.howstuffworks.com/environmental/earth/geophysics/glacier.htm" rel="noreferrer">here</a>.</p><p>However that doesn't happen very often. So in order for us tourists to be able to see anything, we had to go to a very productive glacier. This means there are constantly small chunks breaking off and falling into the sea. Practically though, it kinda looks like you are a boat in a slushee. It's beautiful and something to see, but also depressing to see along the rock face how much more ice there used to be. </p><p>Back in town, we hopped on the "bus". Now the bus here is clearly a retrofitted party van, complete with blue LED lights. The payment system is zip tied to a desk chair that is, itself, wedged in the front. However the bus works well and does get you around. The confusing part is that you will, once again, sometimes encounter a lot of traffic. People are driving pretty quickly and really seem to have somewhere to go. You also see a lot of fancy cars parked outside of houses here. </p><p>Which begs a pretty basic question. If there was almost nowhere to drive to in Nuuk, where in the <em>hell are these people driving</em>. The distance between the end of the road and the beginning of the road is less than 6 km. Also the process to make a road here is beyond anything you've ever seen. Everything requires a giant pile of explosives. </p><figure><img src="https://matduggan.com/content/images/2025/09/image-5.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="575" height="561"></figure><p>Where did these vehicles even come from? Why does one ship a BMW to a place accessible only by plane and boat? More importantly, where was everyone going with such determination? It was like watching a very expensive version of bumper cars, except everyone was committed to the illusion that they had somewhere important to be. Everyone had dings and scrapes like crashes were common. </p><h3 id="grocery-store-from-the-sea">Grocery Store from the Sea</h3><p>Anyway, as I dodged speeding cars filled with people heading nowhere, I decided to hop off the bus and head to the grocery store. Inside was less a store and more the idea of a store. There was a lot of alcohol, chips, candy and shelf-stable foods, which all makes sense to me. What was strange was there wasn't a lot else, including meat. Locals couldn't be eating at the local restaurants, where the prices were as high as Berlin or Copenhagen for food. So what were they eating?</p><p>When I asked one of my bus drivers, he told me that it was pretty unusual to buy meat. They purchased a lot of whale and seal meat. I had sorta heard this before, but when we stopped the bus he pointed out a group of men hauling guns out into a small boat to go shoot seals. The guns were held together with a surprising amount of duct tape, which is not something I associate with the wild. </p><p>I had assumed, based on my casual reading of the news, that we were <em>mostly</em> done killing whales. As it turns out, I was wrong. They eat a lot of whale and it is, in fact, not hard to find. If you are curious, whale does not taste fishy. It tastes a little bit like if you cooked reindeer in a pot of seaweed. I wouldn't go out of your way for it, but it's not terrible. </p><p>The argument I've always heard for why people still kill whales is because it's part of their culture and also because it's an important source of protein. When you hear the phrase "part of their culture" I always imagined like traditional boats going out with spears. What I didn't imagine was industrial fishing boats and an industrial crane that lifts the dead whale out of the water for "processing". Some of the illusion is broken when your boat tour guide points out the metal warehouse with the word "whale" on the side. "Yeah the water here was red with blood for a week" the guide said, counting the cigarettes left in a pack he had. </p><h3 id="should-you-go-to-greenland">Should you go to Greenland?</h3><p>It's a wild place unlike anywhere I've ever been. It is the closest I have ever felt to living a sci-fi type experience. The people of Greenland are amazing, tough, calm and kind. I have nothing but positive experiences to recount from the many people I met there, Danish and Greenlandic, who patiently sat through my millions of questions. </p><p>However it is, by far, the least hospitable to human life place I've ever been to. The folks who live there have adapted to the situation in, frankly, genius ways. If that's your idea of a good time, Greenland is perfect for you. Maybe don't get emotionally attached to the sled dogs though. Or the whales. </p>
        </div>



</article>

        </main>
        
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AI model trapped in a Raspberry Pi (112 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.adafruit.com/2025/09/26/ai-model-trapped-in-raspberry-pi-piday-raspberrypi/</link>
            <guid>45396624</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 15:34:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.adafruit.com/2025/09/26/ai-model-trapped-in-raspberry-pi-piday-raspberrypi/">https://blog.adafruit.com/2025/09/26/ai-model-trapped-in-raspberry-pi-piday-raspberrypi/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45396624">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://blog.adafruit.com/2025/09/26/ai-model-trapped-in-raspberry-pi-piday-raspberrypi/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A WebGL game where you deliver messages on a tiny planet (775 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://messenger.abeto.co/</link>
            <guid>45396441</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 15:17:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://messenger.abeto.co/">https://messenger.abeto.co/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45396441">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Scientists say X has lost its professional edge and Bluesky is taking its place (216 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.psypost.org/scientists-say-x-formerly-twitter-has-lost-its-professional-edge-and-bluesky-is-taking-its-place/</link>
            <guid>45396377</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 15:10:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.psypost.org/scientists-say-x-formerly-twitter-has-lost-its-professional-edge-and-bluesky-is-taking-its-place/">https://www.psypost.org/scientists-say-x-formerly-twitter-has-lost-its-professional-edge-and-bluesky-is-taking-its-place/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45396377">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>A new study published in <em><a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/icb/icaf127" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Integrative and Comparative Biology</a></em> suggests that scientists are leaving X (formerly known as Twitter) in significant numbers due to its declining professional value. The survey of over 800 researchers and science communicators indicates that many now find Bluesky to be a more effective platform for networking, outreach, and staying updated on research. The findings suggest a significant shift in how scientists interact online, with Bluesky emerging as a preferred space for professional engagement.</p><p>Twitter, once considered the central gathering place for scientists on social media, has changed dramatically in recent years. The platform, now officially called “X,” was purchased by Elon Musk in late 2022. Since then, changes to how the platform is moderated and how content appears in users’ feeds have raised concerns among many users, especially academics.</p><p>Reports have pointed to a rise in misinformation, conspiracy theories, and harassment, particularly directed at minority groups. These shifts appear to have made the platform less welcoming and less useful for professional tasks. As Twitter’s character evolved, so too did the willingness of researchers to remain active on the platform.</p><p>In its place, Bluesky has gained attention as a new space for academic interaction. Although other platforms like Threads and Mastodon have also positioned themselves as alternatives, Bluesky appears to be the primary destination for scientists migrating from X. Against this backdrop, researchers set out to document whether scientists were truly abandoning X and whether Bluesky was filling the gap.</p><p>“I am a scholar of public understanding (and misunderstanding) of science and the environment, and have long been fascinated by where people learn things about nature. Social media has become one of the leading sources of information about the world, but the social media landscape is changing, and I wanted to see how my professional colleagues were adapting,” said study author David Shiffman, a marine biologist and public science engagement specialist based in Washington, D.C, and author of <em><a href="https://www.press.jhu.edu/books/title/12267/why-sharks-matter" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Why Sharks Matter</a></em>.</p><p>To investigate these questions, researchers distributed a survey to professional scientists, science communicators, and educators who had used both X and Bluesky for work-related purposes. In total, 813 individuals participated. The survey asked when participants joined each platform, how they used them, and how their experiences had changed over time.</p><p>The responses showed that X had once served a wide range of professional purposes. Nearly all respondents had used it to learn about developments in their fields, and most had relied on it for networking and public outreach. Many also used it for job postings, research promotion, and casual professional conversation.</p><p>However, those same users reported a sharp decline in the usefulness of X. Roughly three-quarters said the platform was now “much less useful” for networking and science communication. Two-thirds said it was less helpful for keeping up with developments in their field.</p><p>The vast majority described their experience on Twitter as increasingly unpleasant, citing irrelevant content, ads, spam, extremist posts, and a loss of meaningful engagement. Some described ethical discomfort with continuing to use a platform that appeared to tolerate, or even amplify, harassment and misinformation.</p><p>In terms of actual usage patterns, only 11 percent of respondents said they still actively use X. Nearly 40 percent had deleted their accounts entirely. Almost half said they still had accounts but rarely used them.</p><p>In contrast, users reported that Bluesky was meeting many of their professional needs. Like Twitter in its earlier days, Bluesky offered a space for learning, networking, and public engagement. Over 94 percent said they used Bluesky to stay informed about research in their field, and nearly 88 percent used it for professional networking. A majority said the new platform was more useful than X for these purposes.</p><p>The researchers also explored why people chose to try Bluesky. Nearly half said they were invited by a colleague or saw others in the science community making the shift. Many viewed Bluesky’s features — such as stronger moderation tools, less algorithmic interference, and more control over what appears in their feed — as more aligned with their professional goals.</p><p>Others said they were simply trying to avoid X’s drawbacks. More than a quarter said they moved to Bluesky because of what they perceived as a rise in extremism on X, and many explicitly named Elon Musk as a reason for their departure.</p><p>“The degree to which the scientific community’s experiences mirrored my own was surprising,” Shiffman told PsyPost. “I knew that for me, Twitter had become unusable, but the extent to which hundreds of surveyed experts strongly agreed with me on almost every point was surprising. You rarely see that kind of strong agreement in surveys.”</p><p>These results provide new evidence to support what other studies and media reports have been suggesting for some time: that X’s role as a hub for academic communication is fading. A previous study <a href="https://www.psypost.org/elon-musks-twitter-takeover-triggered-academic-exodus-study-suggests/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">documented a noticeable drop in academic activity on X</a> after Musk’s acquisition. That research tracked over 15,000 academic accounts and found a significant reduction in tweets, especially original posts and quote tweets, starting in November 2022. Verified users — typically more established academics — were especially likely to reduce their engagement.</p><p>Both studies indicate that changes to how X is managed and moderated have had measurable effects on academic use of the platform. The new survey adds further weight to this idea by showing that scientists are not just using X less — they are actively replacing it with another platform.</p><p>What makes the current study distinctive is its focus on Bluesky as the replacement. While earlier data showed general declines in X use, this survey points to a specific alternative that scientists are embracing. And unlike the earlier study, which focused on activity levels, the new survey captures users’ motivations and perceptions, offering a more detailed view of what is driving this migration.</p><p>“For many years, Twitter was the leading platform used by academics for a wide variety of purposes, including public education about science,” Shiffman explained. “I was a Twitter power-user and evangelist for a decade, and I trained thousands of scientists how to use the platform. Changes to the platform made by Elon Musk, including changing the algorithm to promote extremist views and changes to harassment policy, have made Twitter almost unusable for professional purposes, and academics are abandoning Twitter in droves. Fortunately, alternatives exist, and I, along with many other academics, prefer Bluesky of the available alternatives.”</p><p>The authors note that the survey was limited to users who had already made the switch from X to Bluesky, or were using both platforms. This means it does not account for those who may have stopped using social media altogether or migrated to other platforms. Because the survey was shared primarily through one author’s network, it may reflect the perspectives of those within particular academic communities more than others.</p><p>Another open question concerns whether Bluesky can support the same level of diversity that once defined the science community on X. Movements like Black Birders Week and Queer in STEM gained traction through Twitter’s large, visible networks. It remains unclear whether Bluesky can foster similar grassroots engagement. The authors suggest this should be the focus of future research, particularly if scientists want to ensure that new digital spaces remain inclusive.</p><p>There is also the issue of platform longevity. Whether Bluesky can maintain momentum over time — or whether users will need to shift again — is uncertain. But for now, it appears to offer what many researchers were missing from X: a sense of community, professional utility, and control over their online interactions.</p><p>The study, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/icb/icaf127" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Scientists no Longer Find Twitter Professionally Useful, and have Switched to Bluesky</a>,” was authored by David S. Shiffman and Julia Wester.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Role of Amazon fires in the record atmospheric CO₂ growth in 2024 (147 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://essopenarchive.org/doi/full/10.22541/essoar.175874118.83695562/v1</link>
            <guid>45396284</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 15:02:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://essopenarchive.org/doi/full/10.22541/essoar.175874118.83695562/v1">https://essopenarchive.org/doi/full/10.22541/essoar.175874118.83695562/v1</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45396284">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://essopenarchive.org/doi/full/10.22541/essoar.175874118.83695562/v1: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[SSH3: Faster and rich secure shell using HTTP/3 (314 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/francoismichel/ssh3</link>
            <guid>45395991</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 14:27:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/francoismichel/ssh3">https://github.com/francoismichel/ssh3</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45395991">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/francoismichel/ssh3/blob/main/resources/figures/ssh3.png"><img src="https://github.com/francoismichel/ssh3/raw/main/resources/figures/ssh3.png"></a>
</p>
<div dir="auto"><p dir="auto">Note</p><p dir="auto">SSH3 is probably going to change its name. It is still the SSH Connection Protocol (RFC4254) running on top of HTTP/3 Extended connect, but the required changes are heavy and
too distant from the philosophy of popular SSH implementations to be considered for integration. The <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-michel-remote-terminal-http3/" rel="nofollow">specification draft</a> has already been renamed ("Remote Terminals over HTTP/3"),
but we need some time to come up with a nice permanent name.</p>
</div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">SSH3: faster and rich secure shell using HTTP/3</h2><a id="user-content-ssh3-faster-and-rich-secure-shell-using-http3" aria-label="Permalink: SSH3: faster and rich secure shell using HTTP/3" href="#ssh3-faster-and-rich-secure-shell-using-http3"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">SSH3 is a complete revisit of the SSH
protocol, mapping its semantics on top of the HTTP mechanisms. It comes from our research work and we (researchers) recently proposed it as an <a href="https://www.ietf.org/how/ids/" rel="nofollow">Internet-Draft</a> (<a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-michel-remote-terminal-http3/" rel="nofollow">draft-michel-remote-terminal-http3-00</a>).</p>
<p dir="auto">In a nutshell, SSH3 uses <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc9000" rel="nofollow">QUIC</a>+<a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc8446" rel="nofollow">TLS1.3</a> for
secure channel establishment and the <a href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc9110.html#name-authorization" rel="nofollow">HTTP Authorization</a> mechanisms for user authentication.
Among others, SSH3 allows the following improvements:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Significantly faster session establishment</li>
<li>New HTTP authentication methods such as <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc6749" rel="nofollow">OAuth 2.0</a> and <a href="https://openid.net/specs/openid-connect-core-1_0.html" rel="nofollow">OpenID Connect</a> in addition to classical SSH authentication</li>
<li>Robustness to port scanning attacks: your SSH3 server can be made <strong>invisible</strong> to other Internet users</li>
<li>UDP port forwarding in addition to classical TCP port forwarding</li>
<li>All the features allowed by the modern QUIC protocol: including connection migration (soon) and multipath connections</li>
</ul>
<div dir="auto"><p dir="auto">Tip</p><p dir="auto">Quickly want to get started ? Checkout how to <a href="#installing-ssh3">install SSH3</a>. You will learn to <a href="#deploying-an-ssh3-server">setup an SSH3 server</a> and <a href="#using-the-ssh3-client">use the SSH3 client</a>.</p>
</div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">⚡ SSH3 is faster</h2><a id="user-content--ssh3-is-faster" aria-label="Permalink: ⚡ SSH3 is faster" href="#-ssh3-is-faster"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Faster for session establishment, not throughput ! SSH3 offers a significantly faster session establishment than SSHv2. Establishing a new session with SSHv2 can take 5 to 7 network round-trip times, which can easily be noticed by the user. SSH3 only needs 3 round-trip times. The keystroke latency in a running session is unchanged.</p>
<p dir="auto">
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/francoismichel/ssh3/blob/main/resources/figures/ssh3_100ms_rtt.gif"><img src="https://github.com/francoismichel/ssh3/raw/main/resources/figures/ssh3_100ms_rtt.gif" data-animated-image=""></a>
<i>SSH3 (top) VS SSHv2 (bottom) session establishement with a 100ms ping towards the server.</i>
</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🔒 SSH3 security</h2><a id="user-content--ssh3-security" aria-label="Permalink: 🔒 SSH3 security" href="#-ssh3-security"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">While SSHv2 defines its own protocols for user authentication and secure channel establishment, SSH3 relies on the robust and time-tested mechanisms of TLS 1.3, QUIC and HTTP. These protocols are already extensively used to secure security-critical applications on the Internet such as e-commerce and Internet banking.</p>
<p dir="auto">SSH3 already implements the common password-based and public-key (RSA and EdDSA/ed25519) authentication methods. It also supports new authentication methods such as OAuth 2.0 and allows logging in to your servers using your Google/Microsoft/Github accounts.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🧪 SSH3 is still experimental</h3><a id="user-content--ssh3-is-still-experimental" aria-label="Permalink: 🧪 SSH3 is still experimental" href="#-ssh3-is-still-experimental"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">While SSH3 shows promise for faster session establishment, it is still at an early proof-of-concept stage. As with any new complex protocol, <strong>expert cryptographic review over an extended timeframe is required before reasonable security conclusions can be made</strong>.</p>
<p dir="auto">We are developing SSH3 as an open source project to facilitate community feedback and analysis. However, we <strong>cannot yet endorse its appropriateness for production systems</strong> without further peer review. Please collaborate with us if you have relevant expertise!</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🥷 Do not deploy the SSH3 server on your production servers for now</h3><a id="user-content--do-not-deploy-the-ssh3-server-on-your-production-servers-for-now" aria-label="Permalink: 🥷 Do not deploy the SSH3 server on your production servers for now" href="#-do-not-deploy-the-ssh3-server-on-your-production-servers-for-now"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Given the current prototype state, we advise <em>testing SSH3 in sandboxed environments or private networks</em>. Be aware that making experimental servers directly Internet-accessible could introduce risk before thorough security vetting.</p>
<p dir="auto">While <a href="#-your-ssh3-public-server-can-be-hidden">hiding</a> servers behind secret paths has potential benefits, it does not negate the need for rigorous vulnerability analysis before entering production. We are excited by SSH3's future possibilities but encourage additional scrutiny first.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🥷 Your SSH3 public server can be hidden</h2><a id="user-content--your-ssh3-public-server-can-be-hidden" aria-label="Permalink: 🥷 Your SSH3 public server can be hidden" href="#-your-ssh3-public-server-can-be-hidden"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Using SSH3, you can avoid the usual stress of scanning and dictionary attacks against your SSH server. Similarly to your secret Google Drive documents, your SSH3 server can be hidden behind a secret link and only answer to authentication attempts that made an HTTP request to this specific link, like the following:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="ssh3-server -bind 192.0.2.0:443 -url-path <my-long-secret>"><pre><code>ssh3-server -bind 192.0.2.0:443 -url-path &lt;my-long-secret&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">By replacing <code>&lt;my-long-secret&gt;</code> by, let's say, the random value <code>M3MzkxYWMxMjYxMjc5YzJkODZiMTAyMjU</code>, your SSH3 server will only answer to SSH3 connection attempts made to the URL <code>https://192.0.2.0:443/M3MzkxYWMxMjYxMjc5YzJkODZiMTAyMjU</code> and it will respond a <code>404 Not Found</code> to other requests. Attackers and crawlers on the Internet can therefore not detect the presence of your SSH3 server. They will only see a simple web server answering 404 status codes to every request.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>NOTE WELL</strong>: placing your SSH3 server behind a secret URL may reduce the impact of scanning attacks but will and must <em>never</em> replace classical authentication mechanisms. The secret link should only be used to avoid your host to be discovered. Knowing the secret URL should not grant someone access to your server. Use the classical authentication mechanisms described above to protect your server.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">💐 SSH3 is already feature-rich</h2><a id="user-content--ssh3-is-already-feature-rich" aria-label="Permalink: 💐 SSH3 is already feature-rich" href="#-ssh3-is-already-feature-rich"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">SSH3 provides new feature that could not be provided by the SSHv2 protocol.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Brand new features</h3><a id="user-content-brand-new-features" aria-label="Permalink: Brand new features" href="#brand-new-features"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>UDP port forwarding</strong>: you can now access your QUIC, DNS, RTP or any UDP-based server that are only reachable from your SSH3 host.
UDP packets are forwarded using QUIC datagrams.</li>
<li><strong>X.509 certificates</strong>: you can now use your classical HTTPS certificates to authenticate your SSH3 server. This mechanism is more secure than the classical SSHv2 host key mechanism. Certificates can be obtained easily using LetsEncrypt for instance.</li>
<li><strong>Hiding</strong> your server behind a secret link.</li>
<li><strong>Keyless</strong> secure user authentication using <strong>OpenID Connect</strong>. You can connect to your SSH3 server using the SSO of your company or your Google/Github account, and you don't need to copy the public keys of your users anymore.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Famous OpenSSH features implemented</h3><a id="user-content-famous-openssh-features-implemented" aria-label="Permalink: Famous OpenSSH features implemented" href="#famous-openssh-features-implemented"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This SSH3 implementation already provides many of the popular features of OpenSSH, so if you are used to OpenSSH, the process of adopting SSH3 will be smooth. Here is a list of some OpenSSH features that SSH3 also implements:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Parses <code>~/.ssh/authorized_keys</code> on the server</li>
<li>Certificate-based server authentication</li>
<li><code>known_hosts</code> mechanism when X.509 certificates are not used.</li>
<li>Automatically using the <code>ssh-agent</code> for public key authentication</li>
<li>SSH agent forwarding to use your local keys on your remote server</li>
<li>Direct TCP port forwarding (reverse port forwarding will be implemented in the future)</li>
<li>Proxy jump (see the <code>-proxy-jump</code> parameter). If A is an SSH3 client and B and C are both SSH3 servers, you can connect from A to C using B as a gateway/proxy. The proxy uses UDP forwarding to forward the QUIC packets from A to C, so B cannot decrypt the traffic A&lt;-&gt;C SSH3 traffic.</li>
<li>Parses <code>~/.ssh/config</code> on the client and handles the <code>Hostname</code>, <code>User</code>, <code>Port</code> and <code>IdentityFile</code> config options (the other options are currently ignored). Also parses a new <code>UDPProxyJump</code> that behaves similarly to OpenSSH's <code>ProxyJump</code>.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🙏 Community support</h2><a id="user-content--community-support" aria-label="Permalink: 🙏 Community support" href="#-community-support"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Help us progress SSH3 responsibly! We welcome capable security researchers to review our codebase and provide feedback. Please also connect us with relevant standards bodies to potentially advance SSH3 through the formal IETF/IRTF processes over time.</p>
<p dir="auto">With collaborative assistance, we hope to iteratively improve SSH3 towards safe production readiness. But we cannot credibly make definitive security claims without evidence of extensive expert cryptographic review and adoption by respected security authorities. Let's work together to realize SSH3's possibilities!</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installing SSH3</h2><a id="user-content-installing-ssh3" aria-label="Permalink: Installing SSH3" href="#installing-ssh3"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">You can either download the last <a href="https://github.com/francoismichel/ssh3/releases">release binaries</a>,
<a href="#installing-ssh3-and-ssh3-server-using-go-install">install it using <code>go install</code></a> or generate these binaries yourself by compiling the code from source.</p>
<div dir="auto"><p dir="auto">Tip</p><p dir="auto">SSH3 is still experimental and is the fruit of a research work. If you are afraid of deploying publicly a new SSH3 server, you can use the
<a href="#-your-ssh3-public-server-can-be-hidden">secret path</a> feature of SSH3 to hide it behing a secret URL.</p>
</div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installing ssh3 and ssh3-server using Go install</h3><a id="user-content-installing-ssh3-and-ssh3-server-using-go-install" aria-label="Permalink: Installing ssh3 and ssh3-server using Go install" href="#installing-ssh3-and-ssh3-server-using-go-install"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="go install github.com/francoismichel/ssh3/cmd/...@latest"><pre>go install github.com/francoismichel/ssh3/cmd/...@latest</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Compiling SSH3 from source</h3><a id="user-content-compiling-ssh3-from-source" aria-label="Permalink: Compiling SSH3 from source" href="#compiling-ssh3-from-source"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">You need a recent <a href="https://go.dev/dl/" rel="nofollow">Golang</a> version to do this.
Downloading the source code and compiling the binaries can be done with the following steps:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/francoismichel/ssh3    # clone the repo
cd ssh3
go build -o ssh3 cmd/ssh3/main.go                        # build the client
CGO_ENABLED=1 go build -o ssh3-server cmd/ssh3-server/main.go   # build the server, requires having gcc installed"><pre>git clone https://github.com/francoismichel/ssh3    <span><span>#</span> clone the repo</span>
<span>cd</span> ssh3
go build -o ssh3 cmd/ssh3/main.go                        <span><span>#</span> build the client</span>
CGO_ENABLED=1 go build -o ssh3-server cmd/ssh3-server/main.go   <span><span>#</span> build the server, requires having gcc installed</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">If you have root/sudo privileges and you want to make ssh3 accessible to all you users,
you can then directly copy the binaries to <code>/usr/bin</code>:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="cp ssh3 /usr/bin/ &amp;&amp; cp ssh3-server /usr/bin"><pre>cp ssh3 /usr/bin/ <span>&amp;&amp;</span> cp ssh3-server /usr/bin</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Otherwise, you can simply add the executables to your <code>PATH</code> environment variable by adding
the following line at the end of your <code>.bashrc</code> or equivalent:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="export PATH=$PATH:/path/to/the/ssh3/directory"><pre><span>export</span> PATH=<span>$PATH</span>:/path/to/the/ssh3/directory</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Deploying an SSH3 server</h3><a id="user-content-deploying-an-ssh3-server" aria-label="Permalink: Deploying an SSH3 server" href="#deploying-an-ssh3-server"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Before connecting to your host, you need to deploy an SSH3 server on it. There is currently
no SSH3 daemon, so right now, you will have to run the <code>ssh3-server</code> executable in background
using <code>screen</code> or a similar utility.</p>
<div dir="auto"><p dir="auto">Note</p><p dir="auto">As SSH3 runs on top of HTTP/3, a server needs an X.509 certificate and its corresponding private key. Public certificates can be generated automatically for your public domain name through Let's Encrypt using the <code>-generate-public-cert</code> command-line argument on the server. If you do not want to generate a certificate signed by a real certificate authority or if you don't have any public domain name, you can generate a self-signed one using the <code>-generate-selfsigned-cert</code> command-line argument. Self-signed certificates provide you with similar security guarantees to SSHv2's host keys mechanism, with the same security issue: you may be vulnerable to machine-in-the-middle attacks during your first connection to your server. Using real certificates signed by public certificate authorities such as Let's Encrypt avoids this issue.</p>
</div>
<p dir="auto">Here is the usage of the <code>ssh3-server</code> executable:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="Usage of ./ssh3-server:
  -bind string
        the address:port pair to listen to, e.g. 0.0.0.0:443 (default &quot;[::]:443&quot;)
  -cert string
        the filename of the server certificate (or fullchain) (default &quot;./cert.pem&quot;)
  -key string
        the filename of the certificate private key (default &quot;./priv.key&quot;)
  -enable-password-login
        if set, enable password authentication (disabled by default)
  -generate-public-cert value
        Automatically produce and use a valid public certificate usingLet's Encrypt for the provided domain name. The flag can be used several times to generate several certificates.If certificates have already been generated previously using this flag, they will simply be reused without being regenerated. The public certificates are automatically renewed as long as the server is running. Automatically-generated IP public certificates are not available yet.
  -generate-selfsigned-cert
        if set, generates a self-self-signed cerificate and key that will be stored at the paths indicated by the -cert and -key args (they must not already exist)
  -url-path string
        the secret URL path on which the ssh3 server listens (default &quot;/ssh3-term&quot;)
  -v    verbose mode, if set
  -version
        if set, displays the software version on standard output and exit"><pre><code>Usage of ./ssh3-server:
  -bind string
        the address:port pair to listen to, e.g. 0.0.0.0:443 (default "[::]:443")
  -cert string
        the filename of the server certificate (or fullchain) (default "./cert.pem")
  -key string
        the filename of the certificate private key (default "./priv.key")
  -enable-password-login
        if set, enable password authentication (disabled by default)
  -generate-public-cert value
        Automatically produce and use a valid public certificate usingLet's Encrypt for the provided domain name. The flag can be used several times to generate several certificates.If certificates have already been generated previously using this flag, they will simply be reused without being regenerated. The public certificates are automatically renewed as long as the server is running. Automatically-generated IP public certificates are not available yet.
  -generate-selfsigned-cert
        if set, generates a self-self-signed cerificate and key that will be stored at the paths indicated by the -cert and -key args (they must not already exist)
  -url-path string
        the secret URL path on which the ssh3 server listens (default "/ssh3-term")
  -v    verbose mode, if set
  -version
        if set, displays the software version on standard output and exit
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">The following command starts a public SSH3 server on port 443 with a valid Let's Encrypt public certificate
for domain <code>my-domain.example.org</code> and answers to new sessions requests querying the <code>/ssh3</code> URL path:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="ssh3-server -generate-public-cert my-domain.example.org -url-path /ssh3"><pre><code>ssh3-server -generate-public-cert my-domain.example.org -url-path /ssh3
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">If you don't have a public domain name (i.e. only an IP address), you can either use an existing certificate
for your IP address using the <code>-cert</code> and <code>-key</code> arguments or generate a self-signed certificate using the
<code>-generate-selfsigned-cert</code> argument.</p>
<p dir="auto">If you have existing certificates and keys, you can run the server as follows to use them=</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="ssh3-server -cert /path/to/cert/or/fullchain -key /path/to/cert/private/key -url-path /ssh3"><pre><code>ssh3-server -cert /path/to/cert/or/fullchain -key /path/to/cert/private/key -url-path /ssh3
</code></pre></div>
<div dir="auto"><p dir="auto">Note</p><p dir="auto">Similarly to OpenSSH, the server must be run with root priviledges to log in as other users.</p>
</div>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Authorized keys and authorized identities</h4><a id="user-content-authorized-keys-and-authorized-identities" aria-label="Permalink: Authorized keys and authorized identities" href="#authorized-keys-and-authorized-identities"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">By default, the SSH3 server will look for identities in the <code>~/.ssh/authorized_keys</code> and <code>~/.ssh3/authorized_identities</code> files for each user.
<code>~/.ssh3/authorized_identities</code> allows new identities such as OpenID Connect (<code>oidc</code>) discussed <a href="#openid-connect-authentication-still-experimental">below</a>.
Popular key types such as <code>rsa</code>, <code>ed25519</code> and keys in the OpenSSH format can be used.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Using the SSH3 client</h3><a id="user-content-using-the-ssh3-client" aria-label="Permalink: Using the SSH3 client" href="#using-the-ssh3-client"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Once you have an SSH3 server running, you can connect to it using the SSH3 client similarly to what
you did with your classical SSHv2 tool.</p>
<p dir="auto">Here is the usage of the <code>ssh3</code> executable:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="Usage of ssh3:
  -pubkey-for-agent string
        if set, use an agent key whose public key matches the one in the specified path
  -privkey string
        private key file
  -use-password
        if set, do classical password authentication
  -forward-agent
        if set, forwards ssh agent to be used with sshv2 connections on the remote host
  -forward-tcp string
        if set, take a localport/remoteip@remoteport forwarding localhost@localport towards remoteip@remoteport
  -forward-udp string
        if set, take a localport/remoteip@remoteport forwarding localhost@localport towards remoteip@remoteport
  -proxy-jump string
    	if set, performs a proxy jump using the specified remote host as proxy
  -insecure
        if set, skip server certificate verification
  -keylog string
        Write QUIC TLS keys and master secret in the specified keylog file: only for debugging purpose
  -use-oidc string
        if set, force the use of OpenID Connect with the specified issuer url as parameter
  -oidc-config string
        OpenID Connect json config file containing the &quot;client_id&quot; and &quot;client_secret&quot; fields needed for most identity providers
  -do-pkce
        if set, perform PKCE challenge-response with oidc
  -v    if set, enable verbose mode"><pre><code>Usage of ssh3:
  -pubkey-for-agent string
        if set, use an agent key whose public key matches the one in the specified path
  -privkey string
        private key file
  -use-password
        if set, do classical password authentication
  -forward-agent
        if set, forwards ssh agent to be used with sshv2 connections on the remote host
  -forward-tcp string
        if set, take a localport/remoteip@remoteport forwarding localhost@localport towards remoteip@remoteport
  -forward-udp string
        if set, take a localport/remoteip@remoteport forwarding localhost@localport towards remoteip@remoteport
  -proxy-jump string
    	if set, performs a proxy jump using the specified remote host as proxy
  -insecure
        if set, skip server certificate verification
  -keylog string
        Write QUIC TLS keys and master secret in the specified keylog file: only for debugging purpose
  -use-oidc string
        if set, force the use of OpenID Connect with the specified issuer url as parameter
  -oidc-config string
        OpenID Connect json config file containing the "client_id" and "client_secret" fields needed for most identity providers
  -do-pkce
        if set, perform PKCE challenge-response with oidc
  -v    if set, enable verbose mode
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Private-key authentication</h4><a id="user-content-private-key-authentication" aria-label="Permalink: Private-key authentication" href="#private-key-authentication"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">You can connect to your SSH3 server at my-server.example.org listening on <code>/my-secret-path</code> using the private key located in <code>~/.ssh/id_rsa</code> with the following command:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="  ssh3 -privkey ~/.ssh/id_rsa username@my-server.example.org/my-secret-path"><pre><code>  ssh3 -privkey ~/.ssh/id_rsa username@my-server.example.org/my-secret-path
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Agent-based private key authentication</h4><a id="user-content-agent-based-private-key-authentication" aria-label="Permalink: Agent-based private key authentication" href="#agent-based-private-key-authentication"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The SSH3 client works with the OpenSSH agent and uses the classical <code>SSH_AUTH_SOCK</code> environment variable to
communicate with this agent. Similarly to OpenSSH, SSH3 will list the keys provided by the SSH agent
and connect using the first key listen by the agent by default.
If you want to specify a specific key to use with the agent, you can either specify the private key
directly with the <code>-privkey</code> argument like above, or specify the corresponding public key using the
<code>-pubkey-for-agent</code> argument. This allows you to authenticate in situations where only the agent has
a direct access to the private key but you only have access to the public key.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Password-based authentication</h4><a id="user-content-password-based-authentication" aria-label="Permalink: Password-based authentication" href="#password-based-authentication"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">While discouraged, you can connect to your server using passwords (if explicitly enabled on the <code>ssh3-server</code>)
with the following command:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="  ssh3 -use-password username@my-server.example.org/my-secret-path"><pre><code>  ssh3 -use-password username@my-server.example.org/my-secret-path
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Config-based session establishment</h4><a id="user-content-config-based-session-establishment" aria-label="Permalink: Config-based session establishment" href="#config-based-session-establishment"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><code>ssh3</code> parses your OpenSSH config. Currently, it only handles the <code>Hostname</code>; <code>User</code>, <code>Port</code> and <code>IdentityFile</code> OpenSSH options.
It also adds new option only used by SSH3, such as <code>URLPath</code> or <code>UDPProxyJump</code>. <code>URLPath</code> allows you to omit the secret URL path in your
SSH3 command. <code>UDPProxyJump</code> allows you to perform SSH3 (#proxy-jump)[Proxy Jump] and has the same meaning as the <code>-proxy-jump</code> command-line argument.
Let's say you have the following lines in your OpenSSH config located in <code>~/.ssh/config</code> :</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="IgnoreUnknown URLPath
Host my-server
  HostName 192.0.2.0
  User username
  IdentityFile ~/.ssh/id_rsa
  URLPath /my-secret-path"><pre><code>IgnoreUnknown URLPath
Host my-server
  HostName 192.0.2.0
  User username
  IdentityFile ~/.ssh/id_rsa
  URLPath /my-secret-path
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Similarly to what OpenSSH does, the following <code>ssh3</code> command will connect you to the SSH3 server running on 192.0.2.0 on UDP port 443 using public key authentication with the private key located in <code>.ssh/id_rsa</code> :</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="  ssh3 my-server/my-secret-path"><pre><code>  ssh3 my-server/my-secret-path
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">If you do not want a config-based utilization of SSH3, you can read the sections below to see how to use the CLI parameters of <code>ssh3</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">OpenID Connect authentication (still experimental)</h4><a id="user-content-openid-connect-authentication-still-experimental" aria-label="Permalink: OpenID Connect authentication (still experimental)" href="#openid-connect-authentication-still-experimental"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This feature allows you to connect using an external identity provider such as the one
of your company or any other provider that implements the OpenID Connect standard, such as Google Identity,
Github or Microsoft Entra. The authentication flow is illustrated in the GIF below.</p>
<div dir="auto">
<p><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/francoismichel/ssh3/blob/main/resources/figures/ssh3_oidc.gif"><img src="https://github.com/francoismichel/ssh3/raw/main/resources/figures/ssh3_oidc.gif" width="75%" data-animated-image=""></a></p><p dir="auto"><em>Secure connection without private key using a Google account.</em></p>
</div>
<p dir="auto">The way it connects to your identity provider is configured in a file named <code>~/.ssh3/oidc_config.json</code>.
Below is an example <code>config.json</code> file for use with a Google account. This configuration file is an array
and can contain several identity providers configurations.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="[
    {
        &quot;issuer_url&quot;: &quot;https://accounts.google.com&quot;,
        &quot;client_id&quot;: &quot;<your_client_id>&quot;,
        &quot;client_secret&quot;: &quot;<your_client_secret>&quot;
    }
]"><pre>[
    {
        <span>"issuer_url"</span>: <span><span>"</span>https://accounts.google.com<span>"</span></span>,
        <span>"client_id"</span>: <span><span>"</span>&lt;your_client_id&gt;<span>"</span></span>,
        <span>"client_secret"</span>: <span><span>"</span>&lt;your_client_secret&gt;<span>"</span></span>
    }
]</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">This might change in the future, but currently, to make this feature work with your Google account, you will need to setup a new experimental application in your Google Cloud console and add your email as authorized users.
This will provide you with a <code>client_id</code> and a <code>client_secret</code> that you can then set in your <code>~/.ssh3/oidc_config.json</code>. On the server side, you just have to add the following line in your <code>~/.ssh3/authorized_identities</code>:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="oidc <client_id> https://accounts.google.com <email>"><pre><code>oidc &lt;client_id&gt; https://accounts.google.com &lt;email&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">We currently consider removing the need of setting the client_id in the <code>authorized_identities</code> file in the future.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Proxy jump</h4><a id="user-content-proxy-jump" aria-label="Permalink: Proxy jump" href="#proxy-jump"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">It is often the case that some SSH hosts can only be accessed through a gateway. SSH3 allows you to perform a Proxy Jump similarly to what is proposed by OpenSSH.
You can connect from A to C using B as a gateway/proxy. B and C must both be running a valid SSH3 server. This works by establishing UDP port forwarding on B to forward QUIC packets from A to C.
The connection from A to C is therefore fully end-to-end and B cannot decrypt or alter the SSH3 traffic between A and C.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[First Malicious MCP in the Wild: The Postmark Backdoor Stealing Your Emails (218 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.koi.security/blog/postmark-mcp-npm-malicious-backdoor-email-theft</link>
            <guid>45395957</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 14:23:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.koi.security/blog/postmark-mcp-npm-malicious-backdoor-email-theft">https://www.koi.security/blog/postmark-mcp-npm-malicious-backdoor-email-theft</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45395957">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="blog-rich-text"><p>You know MCP servers, right? Those handy tools that let your AI assistant send emails, run database queries, basically handle all the tedious stuff we don't want to do manually anymore. Well, here's the thing not enough people talk about: we're giving these tools god-mode permissions. Tools built by people we've never met. People we have zero way to vet. And our AI assistants? We just... trust them. Completely.</p><p>Which brings me to why I'm writing this. <code>postmark-mcp</code> - downloaded <strong>1,500 times every single week</strong>, integrated into hundreds of developer workflows. Since version <code>1.0.16</code>, it's been quietly copying every email to the developer's personal server. I'm talking password resets, invoices, internal memos, confidential documents - everything.</p><p>This is the<strong> world’s first sighting of a real world malicious MCP server</strong>. The attack surface for endpoint supply chain attacks is slowly becoming the enterprise’s biggest attack surface.</p><h2>So… What Did Our Risk Engine Detect?</h2><p>Here's how this whole thing started. Our risk engine at Koi flagged <code>postmark-mcp</code> when version <code>1.0.16</code> introduced some suspicious behavior changes. When our researchers dug into it, like we do to any malware our risk engine flags, what we found was very disturbing.</p><p>On paper, this package looked perfect. The developer? Software engineer from Paris, using his real name, GitHub profile packed with legitimate projects. This wasn't some shady anonymous account with an anime avatar. This was a real person with a real reputation, someone you'd probably grab coffee with at a conference.</p><p>For 15 versions - FIFTEEN - the tool worked flawlessly. Developers were recommending it to their teams. "Hey, check out this great MCP server for Postmark integration." It became part of developer’s daily workflows, as trusted as their morning coffee.</p><p>Then version 1.0.16 dropped. Buried on line 231, our risk engine found this gem:</p><figure><p><img src="https://cdn.prod.website-files.com/689ad8c5d13f40cf59df0e0c/68d2dbea5498f5d66a60eaea_carbon%20(11)%20(1).png" loading="lazy" alt=""></p><figcaption>A simple line that steals thousands of emails</figcaption></figure><p>One single line. And boom - every email now has an unwanted passenger.</p><p>Here's the thing - there's a completely legitimate GitHub repo with the same name, officially maintained by Postmark (ActiveCampaign). The attacker took the legitimate code from their repo, added his malicious BCC line, and published it to npm under the same name. Classic impersonation.</p><p>Look, I get it. Life happens. Maybe the developer hit financial troubles. Maybe someone slid into his DMs with an offer he couldn't refuse. Hell, maybe he just woke up one day and thought "I wonder if I could get away with this." We'll never really know what flips that switch in someone's head - what makes a legitimate developer suddenly decide to backstab 1,500 users who trusted them.</p><p>But that's exactly the point. We CAN'T know. We can't predict it. And when it happens? Most of us won't even notice until it's way too late. For modern enterprises the problem is even more severe. As security teams focus on traditional threats and compliance frameworks, developers are independently adopting AI tools that operate completely outside established security perimeters. These MCP servers run with the same privileges as the AI assistants themselves - full email access, database connections, API permissions - yet they don't appear in any asset inventory, skip vendor risk assessments, and bypass every security control from DLP to email gateways. By the time someone realizes their AI assistant has been quietly BCCing emails to an external server for months, the damage is already catastrophic.</p><h2>Lets Talk About the Impact</h2><p>Okay, bear with me while I break down what we're actually looking at here.</p><p>You install an MCP server because you want your AI to handle emails, right? Seems reasonable. Saves time. Increases productivity. All that good stuff. But what you're actually doing is handing complete control of your entire email flow to someone you've never met.&nbsp;</p><p>We can only guestimate the impact:</p><ul role="list"><li>1,500 downloads every single week</li><li>Being conservative, maybe 20% are actively in use</li><li>That's about 300 organizations</li><li>Each one probably sending what, 10-50 emails daily?</li><li>We're talking about 3,000 to 15,000 emails EVERY DAY flowing straight to giftshop.club</li></ul><p>And the truly messed up part? The developer didn't hack anything. Didn't exploit a zero-day. Didn't use some sophisticated attack vector. We literally handed him the keys, said "here, run this code with full permissions," and let our AI assistants use it hundreds of times a day. We did this to ourselves.</p><figure><p><img src="https://cdn.prod.website-files.com/689ad8c5d13f40cf59df0e0c/68d2e7796d400a7fb93e983c_Screenshot%202025-09-23%20at%2021.29.33%20(1).png" loading="lazy" alt=""></p><figcaption>Koidex report for postmark-mcp</figcaption></figure><p>I've been doing security for years now, and this particular issue keeps me up at night. Somehow, we've all just accepted that it's totally normal to install tools from random strangers that can:</p><ul role="list"><li>Send emails as us (with our full authority)</li><li>Access our databases (yeah, all of them)</li><li>Execute commands on our systems</li><li>Make API calls with our credentials</li></ul><p>And once you install them? Your AI assistant just goes to town. No review process. No "hey, should I really send this email with a BCC to giftshop.club?" Just blind, automated execution. Over and over. Hundreds of times a day.</p><p>There's literally no security model here. No sandbox. No containment. Nothing. If the tool says "send this email," your AI sends it. If it says "oh, also copy everything to this random address," your AI does that too. No questions asked.</p><p>The postmark-mcp backdoor isn't sophisticated - it's embarrassingly simple. But it perfectly demonstrates how completely broken this whole setup is. One developer. One line of code. Thousands upon thousands of stolen emails.</p><figure><p><img src="https://cdn.prod.website-files.com/689ad8c5d13f40cf59df0e0c/68d2e67416d1614856d43205_Screenshot%202025-09-23%20at%2021.26.25.png" loading="lazy" alt=""></p><figcaption>postmark-mcp NPM page</figcaption></figure><h2>The Attack Timeline</h2><p><strong>Phase 1: Build a Legitimate Tool</strong><br>Versions 1.0.0 through 1.0.15 work perfectly. Users trust the package.</p><p><strong>Phase 2: Add One Line</strong><br>Version 1.0.16 adds the BCC. Nothing else changes.</p><p><strong>Phase 3: Profit</strong><br>Sit back and watch emails containing passwords, API keys, financial data, and customer information flow into giftshop.club.</p><p>This pattern absolutely terrifies me. A tool can be completely legitimate for months. It gets battle-tested in production. It becomes essential to your workflow. Your team depends on it. And then one day - BAM - it's malware. By the time the backdoor activates, it's not some random package anymore. It's trusted infrastructure.</p><p>Oh, and <code>giftshop.club</code>? Looks like it might be another one of the developer's side projects. But now it's collecting a very different kind of gift. Your emails are the gifts.</p><figure><p><img src="https://cdn.prod.website-files.com/689ad8c5d13f40cf59df0e0c/68d2dfc7f12afe4d7c64ce5e_Screenshot%202025-09-23%20at%2020.57.31.jpg" loading="lazy" alt=""></p><figcaption>Another side-project by the same developer was used as the C2 server</figcaption></figure><p>When we reached out to the developer for clarification, we got silence. No explanation. No denial. Nothing. But he did take action - just not the kind we hoped for. He promptly deleted the package from npm, trying to erase the evidence.</p><p>Here's the thing though: deleting a package from npm doesn't remove it from the machines where it's already installed. Every single one of those 1,500 weekly downloads? They're still compromised. Still sending BCCs to <code>giftshop.club</code>. The developer knows this. He's banking on victims not realizing they're still infected even though the package has vanished from npm.</p><h2>Why MCP's Entire Model Is Fundamentally Broken</h2><p>Let me be really clear about something: MCP servers aren't like regular npm packages. These are tools specifically designed for AI assistants to use autonomously. That's the whole point.</p><p>When you install postmark-mcp, you're not just adding some dependency to your package.json. You're giving your AI assistant a tool it will use hundreds of times, automatically, without ever stopping to think "hmm, is something wrong here?"</p><p>Your AI can't detect that BCC field. It has no idea emails are being stolen. All it sees is a functioning email tool. Send email. Success. Send another email. Success. Meanwhile, every single message is being silently exfiltrated. Day after day. Week after week.</p><p>The postmark-mcp backdoor isn't just about one malicious developer or 1,500 weekly compromised installations. It's a warning shot about the MCP ecosystem itself.</p><p>We're handing god-mode permissions to tools built by people we don't know, can't verify, and have no reason to trust. These aren't just npm packages - they're direct pipelines into our most sensitive operations, automated by AI assistants that will use them thousands of times without question.</p><p>The backdoor is actively harvesting emails as you read this. We've reported it to npm, but here's the terrifying question: how many other MCP servers are already compromised? How would you even know?</p><p>At Koi, we detect these behavioral changes in packages because the MCP ecosystem has no built-in security model. When you're trusting anonymous developers with your AI's capabilities, you need verification, not faith. Our risk engine automatically caught this backdoor the moment version 1.0.16 introduced the BCC behavior - something no traditional security tool would flag. But detection is just the first step. Our supply chain gateway ensures that malicious packages like this never make it into your environment in the first place. It acts as a checkpoint between your developers and the wild west of npm, MCP servers, and browser extensions - blocking known threats, flagging suspicious updates, and requiring approval for packages that touch sensitive operations like email or database access. While everyone else is hoping their developers make good choices, we're making sure they can only choose from verified, continuously monitored options.</p><p>If you're using <code>postmark-mcp</code> version <code>1.0.16</code> or later, you're compromised. Remove it immediately and rotate any credentials that may have been exposed through email. But more importantly, audit every MCP server you're using. Ask yourself: do you actually know who built these tools you're trusting with everything?</p><p>Stay paranoid. With MCPs, paranoia is just good sense.</p><h2>IOCs</h2><p><strong>Package:</strong> postmark-mcp (npm)<br><strong>Malicious Version:</strong> 1.0.16 and later<br><strong>Backdoor Email:</strong> phan@giftshop[.]club<br><strong>Domain:</strong> giftshop[.]club</p><p><strong>Detection:</strong></p><ul role="list"><li>Check for BCC headers to giftshop.club in email logs</li><li>Audit MCP server configurations for unexpected email parameters</li><li>Review npm packages for version 1.0.16+ of postmark-mcp</li></ul><p><strong>Mitigation:</strong></p><ul role="list"><li>Immediately uninstall postmark-mcp</li><li>Rotate any credentials sent via email during the compromise period</li><li>Audit email logs for sensitive data that may have been exfiltrated</li><li>Report any confirmed breaches to appropriate authorities</li></ul><p>‍</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Samsung now owns Denon, Bowers and Wilkins, Marantz, Polk, and more audio brands (234 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theverge.com/news/784390/samsung-harman-masimo-audio-acquisition-complete</link>
            <guid>45395396</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 13:05:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/784390/samsung-harman-masimo-audio-acquisition-complete">https://www.theverge.com/news/784390/samsung-harman-masimo-audio-acquisition-complete</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45395396">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><p><a href="https://www.theverge.com/authors/jess-weatherbed"><img alt="Jess Weatherbed" data-chromatic="ignore" loading="lazy" width="36" height="36" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://platform.theverge.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/chorus/author_profile_images/195820/JESSICA_WEATHERBED.0.jpg?quality=90&amp;strip=all&amp;crop=0%2C0%2C100%2C100&amp;w=48 1x, https://platform.theverge.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/chorus/author_profile_images/195820/JESSICA_WEATHERBED.0.jpg?quality=90&amp;strip=all&amp;crop=0%2C0%2C100%2C100&amp;w=96 2x" src="https://platform.theverge.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/chorus/author_profile_images/195820/JESSICA_WEATHERBED.0.jpg?quality=90&amp;strip=all&amp;crop=0%2C0%2C100%2C100&amp;w=96"></a></p><div><p><span aria-expanded="false" aria-haspopup="true" role="button" tabindex="0"><span id="follow-author-standard_article_details-dmcyOmF1dGhvclByb2ZpbGU6OTU="><span><span><svg width="9" height="9" viewBox="0 0 9 9" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" aria-label="Follow"><path d="M5 0H4V4H0V5H4V9H5V5H9V4H5V0Z"></path></svg></span></span><span>Jess Weatherbed</span></span></span></p> <p><span>is a news writer focused on creative industries, computing, and internet culture. Jess started her career at TechRadar, covering news and hardware reviews.</span></p></div></div><div id="zephr-anchor"><p>Samsung subsidiary Harman has completed its acquisition of Sound United, Masimo’s former audio business, adding a sizable expansion to Samsung’s audio brand portfolio. The $350 million deal was <a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/662437/samsung-harman-masimo-aquisition-audio-empire">first announced in May</a>, and brings Bowers &amp; Wilkins, Denon, Marantz, Definitive Technology, Polk Audio, HEOS, Classé, and Boston Acoustics under the same roof as JBL, Harman Kardon, and other audio brands that Samsung acquired when it <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2016/11/14/13620812/samsung-cars-harman-acquisition-8-billion">purchased Harman for $8 billion</a> in 2016.</p><p>”Sound United’s impressive roster of brands is rooted in a deep passion for sound, innovation, and commitment to quality that aligns with Harman’s own values,” Harman’s lifestyle lead, Dave Rogers, <a href="https://news.harman.com/releases/harman-completes-sound-united-acquisition-to-expand-premium-audio-leadership">said in a statement</a>. “This transaction unlocks meaningful growth opportunities for everyone. It bolsters Harman’s strategy to build on its unparalleled success story and scale to unprecedented heights as an audio leader.”</p><p>Sound United will operate as a standalone business under Harman’s lifestyle division to ensure that each audio brand preserves its identity and customer base. With the sale now completed, Masimo can focus its attention on the <a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/763291/apple-masimo-blood-oxygen-patent-customs-lawsuit">Apple Watch lawsuit</a> it launched against US Customs and Border Protection in August.</p><div><p><span><strong>Follow topics and authors</strong> from this story to see more like this in your personalized homepage feed and to receive email updates.</span></p><ul><li id="follow-author-article_footer-dmcyOmF1dGhvclByb2ZpbGU6OTU="><span aria-expanded="false" aria-haspopup="true" role="button" tabindex="0"><span><span><svg width="9" height="9" viewBox="0 0 9 9" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" aria-label="Follow"><path d="M5 0H4V4H0V5H4V9H5V5H9V4H5V0Z"></path></svg></span><span>Jess Weatherbed</span></span></span></li><li></li><li></li><li></li><li></li></ul></div></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ishkur's Guide to Electronic Music (225 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://music.ishkur.com/</link>
            <guid>45394642</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 10:38:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://music.ishkur.com/">http://music.ishkur.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45394642">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Typst: A Possible LaTeX Replacement (633 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lwn.net/Articles/1037577/</link>
            <guid>45393842</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 07:31:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/1037577/">https://lwn.net/Articles/1037577/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45393842">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<p>
<a href="https://typst.app/">Typst</a> is a program for document
typesetting. It is especially well-suited to technical material
incorporating elements such as mathematics, tables, and floating
figures. It produces high-quality results, comparable to the gold standard,
<a href="https://www.latex-project.org/">LaTeX</a>, with a simpler markup
system and easier customization, all while compiling documents
more quickly. Typst is free software, Apache-2.0 licensed, and is written in Rust.
</p>

<h4 id="the-desire-for-a-latex-replacement">Desire for a LaTeX replacement</h4>

<p>
LaTeX is a document typesetting system built on the foundation of Donald
Knuth's <a href="https://tug.org/whatis.html">TeX</a>. LaTeX has become the
standard tool for the preparation of scholarly papers and books in several
fields, such as mathematics and computer science, and widely adopted in
others, such as physics. TeX and LaTeX, which <a href="https://www.latex-project.org/publications/2001-CAR-LaTeX-legacy.pdf">predate
Linux</a>, are early free software <a href="https://www.tug.org/TUGboat/tb24-1/gaudeul.pdf">success
stories</a>. The quality of TeX's (and therefore LaTeX's) output rivals the
work of skilled hand typesetters for both text and mathematics.
</p>

<blockquote>
<b><tt>$ sudo subscribe today</tt></b>
<p>
Subscribe today and elevate your LWN privileges. You’ll have
access to all of LWN’s high-quality articles as soon as they’re
published, and help support LWN in the process.  <a href="https://lwn.net/Promo/nst-sudo/claim">Act now</a> and you can start with a free trial subscription.
</p></blockquote>


<p>
Despite the acclaim earned by LaTeX, its community of users has been
griping about it for years, and wondering aloud whether one day a
replacement might arrive. There are several reasons for this
dissatisfaction: the LaTeX installation is huge, compilation of large
documents is not fast, and its error messages are riddles delivered by an
infuriating oracle. In addition, any nontrivial customization or alteration to the
program's behavior requires expertise in an arcane macro-expansion
language.
</p>

<p>
Along with the griping came resignation: after decades of talk about a
LaTeX replacement with nothing plausible on the horizon, and with the
recognition that LaTeX's collection of specialized packages would take
years to replace, it seemed impossible to dislodge the behemoth from its
exalted position.
</p>

<h4 id="introducing-typst">Introducing Typst</h4>

<p>
In 2019 two German developers, Laurenz
Mädje and Martin Haug, decided to try to write a LaTeX replacement "<a href="https://archive.li/LN3xb">just for fun</a>". In 2022, Mädje wrote his 
computer science <a href="https://laurmaedje.github.io/programmable-markup-language-for-typesetting.pdf">master's
thesis about Typst</a>. In March 2023, its
first pre-release beta version <a href="https://typst.app/blog/2023/beta-oss-launch">was announced</a>; a
month later, semantic versioning was adopted with the <a href="https://github.com/typst/typst/releases/tag/v0.1.0">release of
v0.1.0.</a> Typst is now at <a href="https://typst.app/blog/2025/typst-0.13">v.0.13.1</a> and shows
365&nbsp;contributors on its <a href="https://github.com/typst/typst?tab=readme-ov-file#--">GitHub repository</a>.
</p>

<p>
I had been aware of this project for over a year but had not paid much
attention, assuming it to be yet another attempt to supplant LaTeX that was
doomed to fail. A rising chorus of enthusiasm among early
adopters, and the beginnings of <a href="https://juti.if.its.ac.id/index.php/juti/index">acceptance</a> of
Typst manuscripts by scholarly journals, made me curious enough
to take the young project for a spin.
</p>

<p>
Typst is available as Rust source and as a compiled binary. To install,
visit the <a href="https://github.com/typst/typst/releases">releases
page</a> and download the appropriate archive. There are options for Linux,
macOS and Windows; I used the
precompiled Linux version for my testing.
</p>

<p>
The "<tt>typst</tt>" command accepts several subcommands. Entering
"<tt>typst fonts</tt>" lists all of the usable fonts to be found in
standard locations on the machine; nonstandard font directories can be
added manually. In my case, Typst found all of my 476&nbsp;fonts instantly;
the only ones omitted were some ancient PostScript Type&nbsp;1 fonts used
by LaTeX. Users who have LaTeX installed will have a large collection of
OpenType and TrueType math and text fonts on their machines; Typst can
use all of these. But Typst will work fine without them, as the program has
a small collection of fonts built in (try "<tt>typst fonts
--ignore-system-fonts</tt>" to see them).
</p>

<p>
Two other subcommands to explore are
"<tt>compile</tt>", which generates the output (PDF by default, with PDF/A,
SVG, and PNG available, along with HTML under development) from a source file, and
"<tt>watch</tt>" for interactive editing. The <tt>watch</tt> subcommand keeps a Typst process running that
incrementally and automatically compiles the document to PDF in response to
changes in the source. To use "<tt>typst watch</tt>" effectively, the
screen should be divided into three windows: a small terminal window to monitor
the <tt>typst</tt> output for error (or success) messages, the editing
window, and an area for any PDF reader that automatically reloads the
displayed document when it changes (many, such as my favorite, <a href="https://github.com/ahrm/sioyek?tab=readme-ov-file#sioyek">Sioyek</a>, do this). The result is a
responsive live preview, even of large documents, due to Typst's speed and
incremental compilation. For example, Frans Skarman <a href="https://fransskarman.com/phd_thesis_in_typst.html">described</a>
his experience writing his doctoral thesis in Typst, and noted
that he was able to enjoy nearly instant previews of content changes to
the book-length document. 
</p>

<h4 id="how-typst-improves-on-latex">How Typst improves on LaTeX</h4>

<p>
Typst output is quite close to that of LaTeX. It uses the same <a href="https://gwern.net/doc/design/typography/tex/1981-knuth.pdf">line-breaking
algorithm</a> developed by Donald Knuth and Michael Plass for TeX, so it
creates nicely balanced paragraphs of regular text. Its mathematical
typesetting algorithms are <a href="https://typst.app/blog/2023/january-update">based closely</a> on the
TeX algorithms, and indeed mathematical rendering is nearly
indistinguishable between the two systems.
</p>

<p>
Getting started with LaTeX can be confusing for newcomers, because it comes
with several alternative "engines" reflecting the long and complex history
of the project. These are the various binaries such as "<tt>pdflatex</tt>",
"<tt>tex</tt>", "<tt>xelatex</tt>", "<tt>luatex</tt>", "<tt>lualatex</tt>",
and more, each with somewhat different capabilities. For Typst there is
only "<tt>typst</tt>".
</p>

<p>
Markup in Typst is less verbose and easier to read than in LaTeX. It
dispenses with the plethora of curly brackets and backslashes littering
LaTeX documents by adopting, for prose, syntax in the style of <a href="https://www.markdownguide.org/basic-syntax">Markdown</a>, and, for
equations, a set of conventions designed for easy input. The
fact that curly brackets and backslashes are awkward to type on German
keyboards may have provided a little extra impetus for the developers to
create an alternative markup system that doesn't require a forest of these
symbols.
</p>

<p>
When users make syntax errors in markup or programming, inevitable
even in Typst, the system presents them with another dramatic improvement
over LaTeX (and TeX): error messages using colored glyphs that
clearly point out exactly where the problem is. I've even discovered that
Typst will save me from trying to run a syntactically correct infinite
loop.
</p>

<p>
Here is a bit of Typst markup for a shopping list, with
the resulting rendering to the right:
</p>

<p><img src="https://static.lwn.net/images/2025/typst-list.png" alt="[Rendered list]" title="Rendered list" width="235" height="291"></p><pre>   = Shopping List
   
   == Vegetables
   
   + Broccoli
   + Asparagus (*fresh only*)
   + Plantains (_ripe and green_)
   
   == Booze
   
   + Rum
     - White
     - Dark
   + #underline[Good] gin  
</pre>

<p>
The example gives a flavor of Typst's terse markup syntax. Headings are
indicated with leading <tt>=</tt> signs. Automatically numbered lists are
created by prepending <tt>+</tt> signs to items, and bulleted lists with
<tt>-</tt> signs; lists can be nested. Delimiters are shown for bold text
and italics. These are shortcuts, or markup syntax sugar, for Typst
functions for transforming text. Not every function has a corresponding
shortcut; in those cases one needs to call the function explicitly, as in
the final item.
</p>

<p>
Typst input is always within one of three modes. Markup (text) mode is the
default. The <tt>#</tt> sign preceding the function call in the last line
of the example
places Typst in "code mode". The "<a href="https://typst.app/docs/reference/text/underline/"><tt>underline()</tt></a>" function accepts a number of keyword arguments that affect its behavior, and one trailing argument, in square brackets, containing the text that it modifies. In the example, we've stuck with the default behavior, but if we wanted, for example, a red underline, we could use "<tt>#underline(stroke: red)[Good] gin</tt>". Following the square-bracketed text argument, Typst returns to interpreting input in text mode.
</p>

<p>Other functions produce output directly, rather than modifying a text argument. This bit of Typst input:</p>

<pre>    #let word = "Manhattan"
    There are #str.len(word) letters in #word.
</pre>

<p>produces the output (in typeset form) "There are 9 letters in Manhattan.". The "<a href="https://typst.app/docs/reference/foundations/str/#definitions-len"><tt>len()</tt></a>" function is part of the
"<a href="https://typst.app/docs/reference/foundations/str/"><tt>str</tt></a>" module, so it needs the namespace.</p>
 
<p>
Let's take a look at the LaTeX equivalent for the first half of the
shopping list for comparison:
</p>

<pre>   \documentclass[12pt]{article}
   \begin{document}
   \section*{Shopping List}
   
   \subsection*{Vegetables}
   
   \begin{enumerate}
   \item Broccoli
   \item Asparagus ({\bfseries fresh only})
   \item Plantains (\emph{ripe and green})
   \end{enumerate}
   \end{document}   
</pre>

<p>
The first two and the last line are boilerplate that is not required in
Typst. The difference in verbosity level and ease of reading the source is
clear.
</p>

<p>
The third Typst mode, in addition to markup and code, is math mode,
delimited by dollar signs. This is also best illustrated by an example:
</p>

<pre>   $ integral_0^1 (arcsin x)^2 (dif x)/(x^2 sqrt(1-x^2)) = π ln 2 $  
</pre>

<p>
When this is compiled by Typst, it produces the result shown below:
</p>

<blockquote>
<img src="https://static.lwn.net/images/2025/typst-series.png" width="800" alt="[Rendered integral]" title="Rendered integral">
</blockquote>

<p>
Those who've used LaTeX will begin to see from this example how math in
Typst source is less verbose and easier to read than in LaTeX. Greek
letters and other Unicode symbols can be used directly, as in modern LaTeX
engines such as <tt>lualatex</tt>, which we <a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/731581/">looked at back in 2017</a>, but with no
imports required.
</p>

<p>
The advent of the LuaTeX and LuaLaTeX projects provided users who wanted to
incorporate programming into their documents a more pleasant alternative to
the TeX macro language. As powerful as the embedded Lua system is, however,
it betrays its bolted-on status, requiring users to negotiate the interface
between Lua data structures and LaTeX or TeX internals. In Typst,
programming is thoroughly integrated into the system, with no seams between
the language used for calculation and the constructs that place characters
in the final PDF. Typst programs are invariably <a href="https://lee-phillips.org/TLexamples/">simpler</a> than their LuaLaTeX
equivalents. All authors using Typst will make at least some simple use of
its programming language, as such basic necessities as changing fonts, or
customizations such as changing the style of section headings, are
accomplished by calling Typst functions.
</p>

<p>
The Typst language is somewhat similar to Rust, perhaps
unsurprisingly. Most Typst functions are <em>pure</em>: they have no side effects and
always produce the same result given the same arguments (aside from certain
functions that mutate their arguments, such as <a href="https://typst.app/docs/reference/foundations/array/#definitions-push"><tt>array.push()</tt></a>). This
aspect reduces the probability of difficult-to-debug conflicts among
packages that plague LaTeX, and makes it easier to debug Typst documents.
</p>

<p>
Although Typst uses the same line-breaking algorithm as LaTeX, its internal
approach to overall page layout is <a href="https://laurmaedje.github.io/posts/layout-models">distinct</a>. Some
consequences are that Typst does a better job at handling movable elements
such as floating figures, and can, for example, easily split large tables
across page breaks, something that LaTeX struggles with even with
specialized packages.
</p>

<h4 id="typst-drawbacks">Typst drawbacks</h4>

<p>
Typst's page layout algorithm doesn't always permit the refinements that 
LaTeX is capable of.
For example, Typst is not as good
as LaTeX at avoiding <a href="https://practicaltypography.com/widow-and-orphan-control.html">widows
and orphans</a>.
Another salient deficiency is Typst's relative lack of specialized packages,
compared with the vast ecosystem produced by LaTeX's decades of community
involvement. However, the relative ease of programming in Typst (and the
well-organized and extensively commented underlying Rust code) suggests
that this drawback may be remedied before a comparable number of decades
have elapsed. Indeed, there are already <a href="https://typst.app/universe">over 800&nbsp;packages available</a>. Typst still cannot do
everything that LaTeX can, but the breadth of its package collection is
encouraging.
</p>

<p>
Almost no journals that provide LaTeX templates for submissions offer a
Typst option, so physicists and mathematicians adopting Typst will need to
find a way to convert their manuscripts. This is made easier for those who
use <a href="https://pandoc.org/">Pandoc</a>, as that conversion program
handles Typst.
</p>

<p>
Another drawback is the difficulty of learning Typst. The <a href="https://typst.app/docs">official documentation</a> is confusingly
organized, with information scattered unpredictably among "Tutorial",
"Reference", and "Guides" sections. Concepts are not always clearly
explained, and sometimes not presented in a logical order. The manual is
not keeping up with the rapid development of the program, and contains some
out-of-date information and errors. None of this is surprising considering
how quickly the project is moving, its early stage, and its
small core team. A work-in-progress called the <a href="https://sitandr.github.io/typst-examples-book/book"><em>Typst
Examples Book</em></a> has appeared, which may be a better starting point
than the official documentation.
</p>

<p>
There are other minor deficiencies compared with LaTeX, such as the
inability to include PDF documents. Typst provides no analogue to LaTeX's
<tt>parshape</tt> command, which lets authors mold paragraphs to, for
example, wrap around complex illustrations. The situation is likely to
change, however, as something like <tt>parshape</tt> is <a href="https://forum.typst.app/t/is-there-an-equivalent-to-latex-s-parshape/1006">being
considered</a> for the future.
</p>

<p>
More serious is the possibility of breaking changes as the system evolves,
always a risk of early adoption. I suspect, however, that these will require
only minor edits to documents in most cases. Progress seems to be steady,
rational, and <a href="https://typst.app/docs/roadmap">responsive to
user requests</a>.
</p>

<h4 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h4>

<p>
I'm using Typst in real work right now to write a physics paper. I will
need to submit my manuscript using the journal's LaTeX template, but I'm
taking advantage of Typst to make the entry of the paper's many equations
simpler, and I'll <a href="https://lee-phillips.org/typstfilters/">transform</a> the result to
LaTeX with Pandoc without needing any manual adjustment. The tooling is excellent, as my preferred editor, <a href="http://neovim.io/">Neovim</a>, has <a href="https://github.com/nvim-treesitter/nvim-treesitter?tab=readme-ov-file#nvim-treesitter">support</a>
for the <a href="https://tree-sitter.github.io/tree-sitter/">Tree-sitter
incremental parser</a>
for Markdown and Typst, which provides syntax-aware highlighting
and navigation of the source files. I use Typst's fast incremental
compilation to get live feedback as I fiddle with my math markup.
</p>

<p>
I was skeptical when I downloaded Typst to try it out, but became
enthusiastic within minutes, as I saw the first (of many) of its lovely
error messages, and remained sanguine as I saw the quality of its output. I
predict that Typst will eventually take the place of LaTeX. But even if
that never comes to pass, it is a useful tool right now.
</p><br clear="all"><table>
           <tbody><tr><th colspan="2">Index entries for this article</th></tr>
           <tr><td><a href="https://lwn.net/Archives/GuestIndex/">GuestArticles</a></td><td><a href="https://lwn.net/Archives/GuestIndex/#Phillips_Lee">Phillips, Lee</a></td></tr>
            </tbody></table><br clear="all">
<hr>
            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Lifetime of social ties adds up to healthy aging at molecular level (162 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.cornell.edu/stories/2025/09/lifetime-social-ties-adds-healthy-aging</link>
            <guid>45393501</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 06:00:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://news.cornell.edu/stories/2025/09/lifetime-social-ties-adds-healthy-aging">https://news.cornell.edu/stories/2025/09/lifetime-social-ties-adds-healthy-aging</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45393501">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><span>The cumulative effect of social advantages across a lifetime&nbsp;– from parental warmth in childhood to friendship, community engagement and religious support in adulthood&nbsp;– may slow the biological processes of aging itself. These social advantages appear to set back “epigenetic clocks” such that a person’s biological age, as measured by analyzing DNA methylation patterns, is younger than their chronological age.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>The&nbsp;research, which appeared&nbsp;</span><a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2666354625001541"><span>in the October issue</span></a><span> of the journal Brain, Behavior and Immunity - Health, drew on data from more than 2,100 adults in the long-running Midlife in the United States (MIDUS) study.</span></p><p><span>First author&nbsp;</span><a href="https://psychology.cornell.edu/anthony-ong"><span>Anthony Ong</span></a><span>, psychology professor and director of the Human Health Labs in the College of Human Ecology,&nbsp;and fellow researchers found that people with higher levels of what they called “cumulative social advantage” showed slower epigenetic aging and lower levels of chronic inflammation.</span></p><p><span>"This paper builds on a foundational study we published last year showing how cumulative social advantage relates to positive health outcomes," Ong said. "This new study digs deeper into the same data to understand the biological mechanisms - essentially, how social connections get under our skin to affect aging at the molecular level."</span></p><p><span>The study focused on so-called epigenetic clocks, molecular signatures that estimate the pace of biological aging. Two in particular&nbsp;– GrimAge and DunedinPACE&nbsp;– are considered especially predictive of morbidity and mortality. Adults with stronger, more sustained social networks showed significantly younger profiles on both clocks.</span></p><p><span>"Cumulative social advantage is really about the depth and breadth of your social connections over a lifetime,” Ong said. “We looked at four key areas: the warmth and support you received from your parents growing up, how connected you feel to your community and neighborhood, your involvement in religious or faith-based communities, and the ongoing emotional support from friends and family."</span></p><p><span>The researchers hypothesized that sustained social advantage becomes reflected in core regulatory systems linked to aging, including epigenetic, inflammatory and neuroendocrine pathways. And indeed, they&nbsp;found that higher social advantage was linked to lower levels of interleukin-6, a pro-inflammatory molecule implicated in heart disease, diabetes and neurodegeneration. But interestingly, there were no significant associations with short-term stress markers like cortisol or catecholamines.</span></p><p><span>Unlike many earlier studies that looked at social factors in isolation&nbsp;– whether a person is married, for example, or how many friends they have&nbsp;– this work conceptualized “cumulative social advantage” as a multidimensional construct. And by combining both early and later-life relational resources, the measure reflects the ways advantage clusters and compounds.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>"What's striking is the cumulative effect - these social resources build on each other over time,” Ong said. “It's not just about having friends today; it's about how your social connections have grown and deepened throughout your life. That accumulation shapes your health trajectory in measurable ways."</span></p><p><span>This perspective draws on cumulative advantage theory, which holds that resources, whether economic or social, tend to accrue, widening disparities across the life course. This underscores a sobering reality: Access to these social resources is not evenly distributed. Race, class and educational attainment shape the likelihood of growing up with supportive parents, finding belonging in community institutions or having friends and partners who provide steady support.</span></p><p><span>That means those already disadvantaged in material ways may also be biologically disadvantaged by a relative lack of sustained social support, potentially accelerating the processes of aging and illness.</span></p><p><span>The findings dovetail with the “weathering hypothesis,” a framework developed by public health scholar Arline Geronimus, which suggests that chronic exposure to adversity and structural inequality leads to earlier health deterioration in marginalized groups. Here, researchers extend that framework to show how accumulated relational advantage, the other side of the coin, may confer resilience at the molecular level.</span></p><p><span>This doesn’t mean a single friendship or volunteer stint can turn back the biological clock. But the authors, including Frank Mann at Stony Brook University and Laura Kubzansky at Harvard University, suggest that the depth and consistency of social connection, built across decades and different spheres of life, matters profoundly. The study adds weight to the growing view that social life is not just a matter of happiness or stress relief but a core determinant of physiological health.</span></p><p><span>"Think of social connections like a retirement account," Ong said. “The earlier you start investing and the more consistently you contribute, the greater your returns. Our study shows those returns aren't just emotional; they're biological. People with richer, more sustained social connections literally age more slowly at the cellular level. Aging well means both staying healthy and staying connected - they're inseparable."</span></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[GPT-OSS Reinforcement Learning (149 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://docs.unsloth.ai/new/gpt-oss-reinforcement-learning</link>
            <guid>45392744</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 02:01:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://docs.unsloth.ai/new/gpt-oss-reinforcement-learning">https://docs.unsloth.ai/new/gpt-oss-reinforcement-learning</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45392744">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><header id="site-header"></header><div><main><header><nav aria-label="Breadcrumb"><ol><li><a href="https://docs.unsloth.ai/new">New</a></li></ol></nav><h2><svg style="mask-image:url(https://ka-p.fontawesome.com/releases/v6.6.0/svgs/regular/lightbulb-cfl-on.svg?v=2&amp;token=a463935e93);-webkit-mask-image:url(https://ka-p.fontawesome.com/releases/v6.6.0/svgs/regular/lightbulb-cfl-on.svg?v=2&amp;token=a463935e93);mask-repeat:no-repeat;-webkit-mask-repeat:no-repeat;mask-position:center;-webkit-mask-position:center"></svg>gpt-oss Reinforcement Learning</h2></header><!--$--><div><p>You can now train OpenAI <a href="https://docs.unsloth.ai/new/gpt-oss-how-to-run-and-fine-tune">gpt-oss</a> with RL and GRPO via Unsloth. Unsloth now offers the <span><strong>fastest inference</strong></span> (3x faster), <strong>lowest VRAM</strong> (50% less) and <strong>most context</strong> (8x longer) for gpt-oss RL vs. any implementation - with no accuracy loss.

Since RL on gpt-oss isn't yet vLLM compatible, we rewrote Transformers inference code to deliver 3x faster inference for gpt-oss at ~21 tokens/s. For BF16, Unsloth also achieves the fastest inference (~30 tokens/s), especially relative<strong> </strong>to VRAM usage, using 50% less VRAM vs. any implementation.</p><ul><li></li></ul><p>With Unsloth, you can train gpt-oss-20b with GRPO on 15GB VRAM and <strong>free</strong> on Colab. Unsloth's new inference runs faster on <strong>any</strong> GPU including A100, H100 and old T4's. gpt-oss-120b fits on 80GB VRAM.</p><p>Unsloth is the only framework to support 4-bit RL for gpt-oss. All performance gains are due to Unsloth's unique <a href="https://docs.unsloth.ai/get-started/reinforcement-learning-rl-guide#what-unsloth-offers-for-rl">weight sharing</a>, <a href="https://docs.unsloth.ai/get-started/reinforcement-learning-rl-guide/memory-efficient-rl">Flex Attention</a>, <a href="https://docs.unsloth.ai/get-started/reinforcement-learning-rl-guide/memory-efficient-rl#unsloth-standby">Standby</a> and custom kernels.</p><div aria-label="Warning" role="note"><p>Reminder: <span>Flash Attention 3 (FA3) is </span><a href="https://docs.unsloth.ai/new/gpt-oss-how-to-run-and-fine-tune/long-context-gpt-oss-training#introducing-unsloth-flex-attention-support"><span>unsuitable for gpt-oss</span></a><span> training</span> since it currently doesn’t support backward passes for attention sinks, causing incorrect training loss. If you’re <strong>not</strong> using Unsloth, FA3 may be enabled by <span>default</span>, so please double-check it’s not in use!</p></div><h2 id="making-inference-much-faster"><div>⚡Making Inference Much Faster</div></h2><p>Inference is crucial in RL training. To achieve the fastest inference speed for gpt-oss without vLLM, we rewrote Transformers inference and integrated many innovations including custom algorithms like Unsloth <a href="https://docs.unsloth.ai/new/gpt-oss-how-to-run-and-fine-tune/long-context-gpt-oss-training#introducing-unsloth-flex-attention-support">Flex Attention</a>, torch.compile. The new inference was evaluated against an already optimized baseline (2x faster than native Transformers).</p><p>vLLM does not support RL for gpt-oss since it lacks bf16 training and LoRA support for gpt-oss. Without Unsloth, only training via bf16 works, making <span>memory use even </span><span><strong>800%+ higher</strong></span>. Most frameworks enable FA3 by default (which reduces VRAM use &amp; increases speed) <strong>but this causes incorrect training loss</strong>. You must disable FA3, though that prevents long-context training, so instead, we implemented <a href="https://docs.unsloth.ai/new/gpt-oss-how-to-run-and-fine-tune/long-context-gpt-oss-training">Unsloth Flex Attention</a>.</p><p>We evaluated gpt-oss RL inference by benchmarking BitsandBytes 4-bit and also did separate tests for BF16. Unsloth’s 4-bit inference is ~4x faster, and BF16 is also more efficient, especially in VRAM use.</p><p>The best part about Unsloth's gpt-oss RL is that it can work on any GPU, even those that do not support bf16. Our free gpt-oss-20b Colab notebooks use older 15GB T4 GPUs, so the inference examples work well!</p><h2 id="gpt-oss-flex-attention-issues-and-quirks"><div>🛠️ gpt-oss Flex Attention Issues and Quirks</div></h2><p>Masking was a tricky issue to deal with. We found that we had to, not only account for KV Cache prefill during  generations of tokens (this is necessary for efficient inference as we need to know what KVCache corresponds to what token in what layer), but also account for a unique amount of pad tokens in each prompt for batch generations which would change the way we would need to store the block mask. Example of such can be seen below:</p><p><strong>Normal Causal Mask:</strong></p><div><pre><code id=":S1:"><span><span>   k0 k1 k2 k3 k4   &lt;-- keys<!-- -->
</span></span><span><span>q0 X<!-- -->
</span></span><span><span>q1 X X<!-- -->
</span></span><span><span>q2 X X X<!-- -->
</span></span><span><span>q3 X X X X<!-- -->
</span></span><span><span>q4 X X X X X &lt;-- last query row (most important for decoding)</span></span></code></pre></div><p><strong>For inference in general case (decoding)</strong></p><!--$--><div aria-busy="false"><pre><code id="«R8a6jtt9lffffffb»"><span><span>    k0 k1 k2 k3 k4<!-- -->
</span></span><span><span>q0<!-- -->
</span></span><span><span>q1<!-- -->
</span></span><span><span>q2<!-- -->
</span></span><span><span>q3<!-- -->
</span></span><span><span>q4   X  X  X  X  X</span></span></code></pre></div><!--/$--><p><strong>If we naively use the same masking strategy </strong></p><!--$--><div aria-busy="false"><pre><code id="«R9a6jtt9lffffffb»"><span><span>    k0 k1 k2 k3 k4<!-- -->
</span></span><span><span>q0<!-- -->
</span></span><span><span>q1<!-- -->
</span></span><span><span>q2<!-- -->
</span></span><span><span>q3<!-- -->
</span></span><span><span>q4  X   (note that q4 is with q_idx 0 as this is the first query in current setup)</span></span></code></pre></div><!--/$--><p>For generation (decoding phase), we usually only care about the last row of the attention matrix, since there’s just one query token attending to all previous key tokens. If we naïvely apply the causal mask (q_idx ≥ k_idx), it fails as our single query has index 0, while there are n_k key tokens. To fix this, we need an offset in mask creation to decide which tokens to attend. But a naïve approach is slow, since offsets change each step, forcing mask and kernel regeneration. We solved this with cache and compile optimizations.</p><p>The harder part is batch generation. Sequences differ in length, so padding complicates mask creation. Flex Attention had a lot of <a href="https://github.com/meta-pytorch/attention-gym/issues/15#issuecomment-2284148665" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">challenges<svg style="mask-image:url(https://ka-p.fontawesome.com/releases/v6.6.0/svgs/regular/arrow-up-right.svg?v=2&amp;token=a463935e93);-webkit-mask-image:url(https://ka-p.fontawesome.com/releases/v6.6.0/svgs/regular/arrow-up-right.svg?v=2&amp;token=a463935e93);mask-repeat:no-repeat;-webkit-mask-repeat:no-repeat;mask-position:center;-webkit-mask-position:center"></svg></a> and dynamic masks are tricky. Worse, if not compiled, it falls back to eager attention which is slow and memory-heavy (quadratic vs. linear in sequence length). Ultimately, the mask must dynamically handle prefill vs decode with KVCache, batch and padding tokens per sequence, remain torch.compile friendly, and support sliding windows.</p><h3 id="flashattention-investigation"><div>🔍 FlashAttention Investigation</div></h3><p>Another interesting direction we explored was integrating FlashAttention. Its advantages are widely recognized, but one limitation is that it does not support attention sinks during the backward pass for gpt-oss. To work around this, we restructured the attention mechanism so that it operates solely on the attention output and the log-sum-exp values that FlashAttention readily provides. Given these benefits, it seemed like an obvious choice to try.</p><p>However, we soon began noticing issues. While the first few layers behaved as expected, the later layers, particularly layers 18 through 24, produced outputs that diverged significantly from the eager-mode implementation in <i>transformers</i>. Importantly, this discrepancy cannot be attributed to error accumulation, since the inputs to each method are identical at every layer. For further validation, we also compared the results against Unsloth <strong>FlexAttention</strong>.</p><p>This needs further investigation into why only the last few layers show such a drastic difference between flash attention implementation vs. the others.</p><h4 id="flash-attention-3"></h4><p>FA3 is often enabled by default for most training packages (not Unsloth), but this is incorrect for gpt-oss. Using FA3 will make training loss completely wrong as FA3 doesn’t support gpt-oss backward passes for attention sinks. Many people are still unaware of this so please be cautious!</p><h2 id="can-we-counter-reward-hacking"><div>⚠️ Can We Counter Reward Hacking?</div></h2><p>The ultimate goal of RL is to maximize some reward (say speed, revenue, some metric). But RL can <strong>cheat.</strong> When the RL algorithm learns a trick or exploits something to increase the reward, without actually doing the task at end, this is called "Reward Hacking". It's the reason models learn to modify unit tests to pass coding challenges, and these are critical blockers for real world deployment. Some other good examples are from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reward_hacking" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wikipedia<svg style="mask-image:url(https://ka-p.fontawesome.com/releases/v6.6.0/svgs/regular/arrow-up-right.svg?v=2&amp;token=a463935e93);-webkit-mask-image:url(https://ka-p.fontawesome.com/releases/v6.6.0/svgs/regular/arrow-up-right.svg?v=2&amp;token=a463935e93);mask-repeat:no-repeat;-webkit-mask-repeat:no-repeat;mask-position:center;-webkit-mask-position:center"></svg></a>.</p><p>In our notebook we explore how to counter reward hacking in a code generation setting and showcase tangible solutions to common error modes. We saw the model edit the timing function, outsource to other libraries, cache the results, and outright cheat. After countering, the result is our model generates genuinely optimized matrix multiplication kernels, not clever cheats.</p><h2 id="from-openais-labs-to-your-laptop"><div>💫 From OpenAI's Labs to Your Laptop</div></h2><p>gpt-oss is a legitimate frontier-class architecture from OpenAI that could power breakthrough AI applications. Until now, training these models with RL was exclusively limited to well-funded labs with H100s to spare. </p><p><strong>Today, that changes.</strong> You can train gpt-oss-20b with GRPO on a free Google Colab tier <a href="https://colab.research.google.com/github/unslothai/notebooks/blob/main/nb/gpt-oss-(20B)-GRPO.ipynb" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here<svg style="mask-image:url(https://ka-p.fontawesome.com/releases/v6.6.0/svgs/regular/arrow-up-right.svg?v=2&amp;token=a463935e93);-webkit-mask-image:url(https://ka-p.fontawesome.com/releases/v6.6.0/svgs/regular/arrow-up-right.svg?v=2&amp;token=a463935e93);mask-repeat:no-repeat;-webkit-mask-repeat:no-repeat;mask-position:center;-webkit-mask-position:center"></svg></a>. <strong>Free, Frontier Model, Training</strong>.</p></div><!--/$--></main></div><!--$--><!--/$--></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>