<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 12:30:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tiny electric motor outperforms record holder by 40% (181 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://supercarblondie.com/electric-motor-yasa-more-powerful-tesla-mercedes/</link>
            <guid>45797242</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 09:20:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://supercarblondie.com/electric-motor-yasa-more-powerful-tesla-mercedes/">https://supercarblondie.com/electric-motor-yasa-more-powerful-tesla-mercedes/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45797242">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>








<p>UK-based YASA has just built a tiny electric motor that makes Tesla motors look like slackers, and this invention could potentially reshape the future of EVs.</p>



<p>The company has unveiled a new prototype that’s breaking records for power and performance density.</p>



<p>It’s smaller and lighter than traditional motors, yet it’s somehow more powerful.</p>



<p>Perhaps the best part is that it’s a fully functional motor, rather than some lab-only concept.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://sbxcars.com/?utm_source=supercarblondie.com&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=article-link" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">SBX CARS</a>&nbsp;– View live supercar auctions powered by Supercar Blondie</strong></p>



<h2>This tiny electric motor can produce more than 1,000 horsepower</h2>



<p>The new YASA axial flux motor weighs just 28 pounds, or about the same as a small dog. </p>



<figure>
<figure><a href="https://supercarblondie.com/wp-content/uploads/YASA-tiny-electric-motor.webp" data-lightbox="159709" data-title="YASA"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="100%" height="200" data-id="159720" src="https://supercarblondie.com/wp-content/uploads/YASA-tiny-electric-motor-1024x640.webp" alt="Tiny electric motor is as powerful as four Tesla motors put together and outperforms record holder by 40%" srcset="https://supercarblondie.com/wp-content/uploads/YASA-tiny-electric-motor-1024x640.webp 1024w, https://supercarblondie.com/wp-content/uploads/YASA-tiny-electric-motor-500x313.webp 500w, https://supercarblondie.com/wp-content/uploads/YASA-tiny-electric-motor-768x480.webp 768w, https://supercarblondie.com/wp-content/uploads/YASA-tiny-electric-motor.webp 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a><figcaption>YASA</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>However, it delivers a jaw-dropping 750 kilowatts of power, <a href="https://supercarblondie.com/hennessey-unveils-cadillac-le-monstre-1950s-cadillac-tribute-to-le-mans/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="">which is the equivalent of 1,005 horsepower</a>. </p>



<p>That’s about the same as two <a href="https://supercarblondie.com/bmw-m8-drag-race-tesla-model-3-performance/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="">Tesla Model 3 Performance cars</a> combined, or four individual Tesla motors.</p>



<p>In comparison, the previous record holder, which was also produced by the same company, weighed 28.8 pounds, and achieved a peak power of 550 kilowatts (737 horsepower).</p>



<p>This makes the current electric motor 40 percent better than the previous edition.</p>



<p>It can also sustain between 350 and 400 kilowatts (469–536 horsepower) continuously, meaning it’s not just built for short bursts, as it can deliver massive power all day long.</p>



<p>According to <a href="https://yasa.com/news/yasa-smashes-own-unofficial-power-density-world-record-pushing-state-of-the-art-electric-motor-to-staggering-new-59kw-kg-benchmark/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" title="">YASA</a>, this is achieved without using exotic or expensive materials, so the design could actually be scalable once the demand kicks in.</p>



<p>“This record demonstrates what makes YASA unique,” said CEO Joerg Miska. </p>



<p>“With three times the performance density of today’s leading radial flux motors, we’re redefining what’s possible in electric motor design.”</p>



<p>In simpler terms, the company has made a motor that is small, light, and ridiculously powerful.</p>



<figure>
<figure><a href="https://supercarblondie.com/wp-content/uploads/YASA-motor.png" data-lightbox="159709" data-title="YASA"><img decoding="async" width="100%" height="200" data-id="159718" src="https://supercarblondie.com/wp-content/uploads/YASA-motor-1024x640.png" alt="Tiny electric motor from YASA is as powerful as four Tesla motors put together and outperforms record holder by 40%" srcset="https://supercarblondie.com/wp-content/uploads/YASA-motor-1024x640.png 1024w, https://supercarblondie.com/wp-content/uploads/YASA-motor-500x313.png 500w, https://supercarblondie.com/wp-content/uploads/YASA-motor-768x480.png 768w, https://supercarblondie.com/wp-content/uploads/YASA-motor.png 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a><figcaption>YASA</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<h2>YASA already produces motors for many expensive cars</h2>



<p>That’s a big deal for <a href="https://supercarblondie.com/cars/ev/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="">EVs</a>. </p>



<p>A lighter motor means a lighter car, which means better efficiency, faster acceleration, and longer range from the same battery.</p>



<p>For EVs, every pound matters, so saving weight without compromising performance could be a gamechanger.</p>



<p>YASA, which is a wholly owned subsidiary of <a href="https://supercarblondie.com/cars/manufacturers/mercedes-benz/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="">Mercedes-Benz</a>, already produces motors that power some of the world’s fastest and most expensive cars. </p>



<p>These include <a href="https://supercarblondie.com/first-ever-look-at-mercedes-amg-gtxx-concept/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="">the Mercedes-AMG GT XX concept</a>, and <a href="https://supercarblondie.com/ferrari-296-gtb-representing-gulf-nation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="">the Ferrari 296 GTB</a>.</p>



<figure>
<figure><a href="https://supercarblondie.com/wp-content/uploads/Mercedes-AMG-GT-XX-Concept-car.webp" data-lightbox="159709" data-title="YASA"><img decoding="async" width="100%" height="200" data-id="159719" src="https://supercarblondie.com/wp-content/uploads/Mercedes-AMG-GT-XX-Concept-car-1024x640.webp" alt="Tiny electric motor is as powerful as four Tesla motors put together and outperforms record holder by 40%" srcset="https://supercarblondie.com/wp-content/uploads/Mercedes-AMG-GT-XX-Concept-car-1024x640.webp 1024w, https://supercarblondie.com/wp-content/uploads/Mercedes-AMG-GT-XX-Concept-car-500x313.webp 500w, https://supercarblondie.com/wp-content/uploads/Mercedes-AMG-GT-XX-Concept-car-768x480.webp 768w, https://supercarblondie.com/wp-content/uploads/Mercedes-AMG-GT-XX-Concept-car.webp 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a><figcaption>YASA</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Perhaps as production scales and prices drop, these ultra-efficient motors could find their way into <a href="https://supercarblondie.com/new-303-mile-nissan-leaf-ev-becomes-the-cheapest-ev-in-the-us/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="">everyday EVs</a>, like the Nissan Leaf EV, which is the cheapest EV in the US.</p>



<p>For now, the company’s tiny electric motor proves that big things can come in small packages, and that performance need not be sacrificed.</p>
<p><strong>
                            DISCOVER SBX CARS:
                            <a href="https://sbxcars.com/?utm_source=supercarblondie.com&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=article-link" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">
                                The global premium car auction platform powered by Supercar Blondie
                            </a></strong></p>
                </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[China intimidated UK university to ditch human rights research, documents show (169 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cq50j5vwny6o</link>
            <guid>45796907</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 08:15:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cq50j5vwny6o">https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cq50j5vwny6o</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45796907">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><div data-testid="byline-new" data-component="byline-block"><p><span data-testid="byline-new-contributors"><div data-testid="byline-new-contributors-contributor-0"><p><span>Damian Grammaticas</span><span data-testid="byline-new-contributors-contributor-0-role-location">Political correspondent</span></p></div></span></p></div><figure><div data-component="image-block"><p><img src="https://static.files.bbci.co.uk/bbcdotcom/web/20251021-134202-667692b2c6-web-2.32.2-1/grey-placeholder.png" aria-label="image unavailable"><img sizes="(min-width: 1280px) 50vw, (min-width: 1008px) 66vw, 96vw" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/b704/live/2b97e130-b678-11f0-8e54-b35e49a65740.jpg.webp 240w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/b704/live/2b97e130-b678-11f0-8e54-b35e49a65740.jpg.webp 320w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/b704/live/2b97e130-b678-11f0-8e54-b35e49a65740.jpg.webp 480w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/b704/live/2b97e130-b678-11f0-8e54-b35e49a65740.jpg.webp 640w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/b704/live/2b97e130-b678-11f0-8e54-b35e49a65740.jpg.webp 800w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1024/cpsprodpb/b704/live/2b97e130-b678-11f0-8e54-b35e49a65740.jpg.webp 1024w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1536/cpsprodpb/b704/live/2b97e130-b678-11f0-8e54-b35e49a65740.jpg.webp 1536w" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/b704/live/2b97e130-b678-11f0-8e54-b35e49a65740.jpg.webp" loading="eager" alt="Laura Murphy Laura Murphy, a young woman with black curly hair and octagonal silver earrings, smiles at the camera against a neutral, light blue background"><span>Laura Murphy</span></p></div><p data-component="caption-block"><figcaption>Professor Laura Murphy says her academic freedom was traded for access to the Chinese student market</figcaption></p></figure><div data-component="text-block"><p>China waged a campaign of harassment and intimidation directed at a UK university to get it to shut down sensitive research into alleged human rights abuses, documents seen by the BBC show.</p><p>Sheffield Hallam University staff in China were threatened by individuals described by them as being from China's National Security Service who demanded the research being  done in Sheffield be halted.</p><p>And access to the university's websites from China was blocked, impeding its ability to recruit Chinese students, in a campaign of threats and intimidation lasting more than two years.</p><p>In an internal email from July 2024, university officials said "attempting to retain the business in China and publication of the research are now untenable bedfellows".</p><p>When the UK government learned of the case, the then Foreign Secretary David Lammy issued a warning to his Chinese counterpart that it would not tolerate attempts to suppress academic freedoms at UK universities, the BBC understands.</p><p>The issue was also raised with China's most senior education minister.</p><p>China was seeking to halt research by Laura Murphy, professor of human rights and contemporary slavery at Sheffield Hallam, into allegations Uyghur Muslims in the north-western region of Xinjiang were subject to forced labour.</p><p>China <a target="_self" href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-china-22278037">has faced accusations</a> – always firmly denied – that it has committed crimes against humanity and possibly genocide against the Uyghur population.</p><p>In late 2024, following pressure from the Chinese state and a separate defamation law suit against the university, Sheffield Hallam decided not to publish a final piece of research by Prof Murphy and her team into forced labour.</p><p>And in early 2025, university administrators told her that she could "not continue with her research into supply chains and forced labour in China".</p><p>She initiated legal action against the university for failing in its duty to protect her academic freedom and she submitted a "subject access request" demanding Sheffield Hallam hand over any relevant internal documents.</p><p>The documents she obtained showed the university "had negotiated directly with a foreign intelligence service to trade my academic freedom for access to the Chinese student market," she told the BBC.</p><p>She added: "I'd never seen anything quite so patently explicit about the extent to which a university would go to ensure that they have Chinese student income."</p></div><figure><div data-component="image-block"><p><img src="https://static.files.bbci.co.uk/bbcdotcom/web/20251021-134202-667692b2c6-web-2.32.2-1/grey-placeholder.png" aria-label="image unavailable"><img sizes="(min-width: 1280px) 50vw, (min-width: 1008px) 66vw, 96vw" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/ba97/live/4c80d460-b7f4-11f0-9026-ddc9ee71c10d.jpg.webp 240w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/ba97/live/4c80d460-b7f4-11f0-9026-ddc9ee71c10d.jpg.webp 320w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/ba97/live/4c80d460-b7f4-11f0-9026-ddc9ee71c10d.jpg.webp 480w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/ba97/live/4c80d460-b7f4-11f0-9026-ddc9ee71c10d.jpg.webp 640w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/ba97/live/4c80d460-b7f4-11f0-9026-ddc9ee71c10d.jpg.webp 800w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1024/cpsprodpb/ba97/live/4c80d460-b7f4-11f0-9026-ddc9ee71c10d.jpg.webp 1024w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1536/cpsprodpb/ba97/live/4c80d460-b7f4-11f0-9026-ddc9ee71c10d.jpg.webp 1536w" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/ba97/live/4c80d460-b7f4-11f0-9026-ddc9ee71c10d.jpg.webp" loading="lazy" alt="Getty Images A young Uyghur women,  with a small child on her knee, sits next to two older women on a street in Kashgar City, Xinjiang. All three are dressed in traditional garments with head scarves"><span>Getty Images</span></p></div><p data-component="caption-block"><figcaption>The Uyghurs are the largest minority ethnic group in China's north-western region of Xinjiang</figcaption></p></figure><div data-component="text-block"><p>Sheffield Hallam has now apologised to Prof Murphy and said she can resume her work.</p><p>A spokesperson said "the university's decision to not continue with Professor Laura Murphy's research was taken based on our understanding of a complex set of circumstances at the time, including being unable to secure the necessary professional indemnity insurance".</p><p>They said the university wished to "make clear our commitment to supporting her research and to securing and promoting freedom of speech and academic freedom within the law".</p><p>But the general secretary of the University and College Union, Jo Grady, said "it is incredibly worrying that Sheffield Hallam appears to have attempted to silence its own professor on behalf of a foreign government".</p><p>She added: "Given the censorship Hallam has seemingly engaged in, it now needs to set out how it will ensure its academics will be supported to research freely and protected from overreach by foreign powers."</p><p>A government spokesperson told the BBC "any attempt by a foreign state to intimidate, harass or harm individuals in the UK will not be tolerated, and the government has made this clear to Beijing after learning of this case". </p></div><figure><div data-component="image-block"><p><img src="https://static.files.bbci.co.uk/bbcdotcom/web/20251021-134202-667692b2c6-web-2.32.2-1/grey-placeholder.png" aria-label="image unavailable"><img sizes="(min-width: 1280px) 50vw, (min-width: 1008px) 66vw, 96vw" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/4ef1/live/19b27c70-b81f-11f0-bc92-6d9c8de2f782.jpg.webp 240w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/4ef1/live/19b27c70-b81f-11f0-bc92-6d9c8de2f782.jpg.webp 320w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/4ef1/live/19b27c70-b81f-11f0-bc92-6d9c8de2f782.jpg.webp 480w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/4ef1/live/19b27c70-b81f-11f0-bc92-6d9c8de2f782.jpg.webp 640w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/4ef1/live/19b27c70-b81f-11f0-bc92-6d9c8de2f782.jpg.webp 800w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1024/cpsprodpb/4ef1/live/19b27c70-b81f-11f0-bc92-6d9c8de2f782.jpg.webp 1024w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1536/cpsprodpb/4ef1/live/19b27c70-b81f-11f0-bc92-6d9c8de2f782.jpg.webp 1536w" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/4ef1/live/19b27c70-b81f-11f0-bc92-6d9c8de2f782.jpg.webp" loading="lazy" alt="A partly redacted internal document marked confidential which shows Sheffield Hallam university's concerns about pressure from China"></p></div><p data-component="caption-block"><figcaption>Internal documents shared with the BBC show Sheffield Hallam under pressure</figcaption></p></figure><div data-component="text-block"><p>It all began so differently.</p><p>When, in 2021, Prof Murphy published <a target="_blank" href="https://shura.shu.ac.uk/29640/">a major report into Uhygur forced labour in the solar panel industry</a>, the director of the Helena Kennedy Centre (HKC), the department in which her unit was based, wrote to congratulate her.</p><p>"This is an exceptional moment in the history of the HKC... we are all exceptionally proud of this body of work which rightly shines light on the blatant abuse of Uyghur tights (sic) in China.. Well done Laura!"</p><p>Over the following months her unit published four reports, including into car parts and cotton for clothing, trying to trace supply chains and highlight where goods reaching western consumers may have been produced with inputs made with forced labour in Xinjiang.</p><p>China denies such practices occur.</p><p>The Chinese Embassy in London told the BBC "the Helena Kennedy Centre at the Sheffield Hallam University has released multiple fake reports on Xinjiang that are seriously flawed".</p><p>"It has been revealed that some authors of these reports received funding from certain US agencies," the Embassy added.</p><p>Prof Murphy told the BBC she has received funding over the course of her career from the US National Endowment for Humanities for work on slave narratives, the US Department of Justice for work on human trafficking in New Orleans, and more recently from USAID, the US State Department and the UK Foreign Office for her work on China.</p><p>The Chinese Embassy said the allegations of "forced labor" in her reports "cannot withstand basic fact-check".</p><p>"While presenting itself as an academic body, the Centre has in practice acted as a vehicle for politicised and disinformation-driven narratives deployed by anti-China forces," the embassy added.</p><p>The university realised it was coming in for criticism from China as far back as 2022.</p><p>An internal university email from August of that year, seen by the BBC, said China's foreign ministry had issued a statement "denouncing us as being in the 'disreputable vanguard of anti-China rhetoric'".</p><p>The email said the university had admitted 500 Chinese students in 2018, but numbers had collapsed in the pandemic and had not bounced back like it had in other markets. </p><p>It expressed concern that the Chinese government's criticisms could result in a "boycott" by prospective students and recruitment agents. </p><p>In total, the documents show Sheffield had earned £3.8m in 2021/22 from China and Hong Kong.</p><p>Later in August 2022 the university's English language testing website used by Chinese students to take tests before coming to Sheffield had been "shut down in China temporarily".</p><p>Over the next two years the pressure escalated dramatically leading university officials to write in an email in May 2024 that "the continuation of the university's scholarly activity with and in China and Hong Kong has been placed at risk because of the research activities, led by Professor Laura Murphy, in relation to alleged persecution of Uyghur Muslims in Xinjiang, China".</p><p>An internal "risk summary," dated 9 December 2024, detailed what had happened.</p><p>In August 2022, China had blocked access to the university's websites. All email communication from and to the university was disabled.</p><p>It meant students in China due to study at Sheffield Hallam were unable to access the enrolment website, arrange their welcome or airport pick up in the UK, or course information.</p><p>The university said this had "undoubtedly had a negative impact on recruitment" in 23/24, with "anticipated further decline in 24/25".</p><p>And, in 2024, the intimidation began.</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>"Things in Beijing have kicked off," an internal email from 18 April 2024 said.</p><p>The risk summary detailed that "three officers of the National Security Service" visited Sheffield Hallam's office in China.</p><p>A local staff member was "questioned for two hours regarding the HKC research and future publications. </p><p>"The tone was threatening and message to cease the research activity was made clear."</p><p>At another visit, security officers said the internet issues were because the Uyghur research was available on the university website.</p><p>Finally, in September 2024, the document states "a decision by the university not to publish a final phase of the research on forced labour in China was communicated to the National Security Service .. immediately relations improved and the threat to staff wellbeing appears to be removed".</p><p>Sheffield Hallam says these internal communications need to be seen in context and do not represent university policy.</p><p>Complicating things for Sheffield Hallam had been a report by its Forced Labour Lab published December 2023 into clothing supply chains connected to Xinjiang.</p><p>Smart Shirts Ltd, a Hong Kong supplier of garments with customers in the UK, brought a claim for libel, alleging it had been defamed as its name was included.</p><p>A preliminary ruling at the High Court in London in December 2024 found that report had been "defamatory".</p><p>A full trial in that case is yet to take place at which Sheffield Hallam will be able to put forward its defence to the company's claim, but the university was told by its insurers that "any defamation, libel or slander" claims linked to its entire Social and Economic Research Institute were no longer covered.</p><p>Professor Murphy had, meanwhile, built an international profile.</p></div><figure><div data-component="image-block"><p><img src="https://static.files.bbci.co.uk/bbcdotcom/web/20251021-134202-667692b2c6-web-2.32.2-1/grey-placeholder.png" aria-label="image unavailable"><img sizes="(min-width: 1280px) 50vw, (min-width: 1008px) 66vw, 96vw" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/a4f2/live/ed9f3490-b678-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp 240w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/a4f2/live/ed9f3490-b678-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp 320w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/a4f2/live/ed9f3490-b678-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp 480w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/a4f2/live/ed9f3490-b678-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp 640w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/a4f2/live/ed9f3490-b678-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp 800w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1024/cpsprodpb/a4f2/live/ed9f3490-b678-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp 1024w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1536/cpsprodpb/a4f2/live/ed9f3490-b678-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp 1536w" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/a4f2/live/ed9f3490-b678-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp" loading="lazy" alt="UK Parliament Baroness Helena Kennedy KC in a purple jacket with a fur collar against a neutral grey backdrop"><span>UK Parliament</span></p></div><p data-component="caption-block"><figcaption>Baroness Kennedy says UK universities are vulnerable to pressure from China</figcaption></p></figure><div data-component="text-block"><p>Her work had been cited in the UK parliament, in Canada and in Australia. She had taken a career break in late 2023 to work for the US Department of Homeland Security, helping it with the implementation of their Uyghur Forced Labour Prevention Act.</p><p>In her absence, and amid the pressure from China and the lawsuit, Sheffield Hallam decided her unit would close in early 2025.</p><p>"Despite significant offers of continued funding we have decided it is in our best interests to terminate the research," an email of August 2024 said.</p><p>It added that by not publishing the final report under the university's auspices it hoped "we can minimise the possibility of any further scrutiny of our operations .. thereby attending to related duty of care issues".</p><p>But failing to publish the report was a breach of the terms agreed with the external groups who had agreed to fund the research.</p><p>So the university decided to close the unit and not use any outstanding funds.</p><p>Sheffield Hallam said it was normal practice for research groups to stand down at the end of an external contract.</p></div><figure><div data-component="image-block"><p><img src="https://static.files.bbci.co.uk/bbcdotcom/web/20251021-134202-667692b2c6-web-2.32.2-1/grey-placeholder.png" aria-label="image unavailable"><img sizes="(min-width: 1280px) 50vw, (min-width: 1008px) 66vw, 96vw" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/b315/live/2cc37370-b679-11f0-8e54-b35e49a65740.jpg.webp 240w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/b315/live/2cc37370-b679-11f0-8e54-b35e49a65740.jpg.webp 320w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/b315/live/2cc37370-b679-11f0-8e54-b35e49a65740.jpg.webp 480w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/b315/live/2cc37370-b679-11f0-8e54-b35e49a65740.jpg.webp 640w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/b315/live/2cc37370-b679-11f0-8e54-b35e49a65740.jpg.webp 800w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1024/cpsprodpb/b315/live/2cc37370-b679-11f0-8e54-b35e49a65740.jpg.webp 1024w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1536/cpsprodpb/b315/live/2cc37370-b679-11f0-8e54-b35e49a65740.jpg.webp 1536w" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/b315/live/2cc37370-b679-11f0-8e54-b35e49a65740.jpg.webp" loading="lazy" alt="Sign saying Sheffield Hallam University on a modern steel and concrete building"></p></div><p data-component="caption-block"><figcaption>Sheffield Hallam says China is no longer a significant student market for the university</figcaption></p></figure><div data-component="text-block"><p>When Prof Murphy returned from her career break in early 2025, the university told her of its "decision not to continue with her research into supply chains and forced labour in China due to .. the corporate insurance position .. and our duty of care to colleagues working in both China and the UK".</p><p>Any other work or public engagements outside the university would also have to be checked for "conflict of interest".</p><p>Seeking to continue her work, Prof Murphy began her legal action and made a subject access request to the university requiring it to turn over relevant internal documents.</p><p>"What about the duty of care to me and the duty of care to the rest of my research team?," Prof Murphy told the BBC.</p><p>"They laid off my entire research team. Sent them away. They sent back all of our research funding, and they shuttered the entire programme without regard for the people who worked with us on that project, so many of them Uyghur folks."</p><p>She added: "As long as the university system in the UK is so wildly underfunded as it is now, universities will be vulnerable to attacks like this."</p><p>After receiving her apology from the university and a pledge to protect her academic freedom, she is not currently pursuing her legal action.  </p><p>Her case had been built on the Higher Education (Freedom of Speech) Act 2023, which places on universities a duty to promote freedom of speech and academic freedom for their staff.</p><p>Her solicitors, Leigh Day, had argued that a lack of insurance  and "unspecified" concerns about staff safety do not provide universities carte blanche to restrict freedoms.</p><p>The law firm believes refusing to authorise any research on a particular country would be unlawful.</p><p>Sheffield Hallam's spokesperson said: "For the avoidance of doubt, the decision was not based on commercial interests in China.</p><p>"Regardless, China is not a significant international student market for the university."</p><p>The university only enrolled 73 students from China in 2024/25.</p><p>The Chinese Embassy said "there are over 200,000 Chinese students in the UK, making China the largest source of international students in the UK,"  adding "educational cooperation has become a driving force in bilateral ties".</p><p>Baroness Helena Kennedy KC, patron of the centre that bears her name, said UK universities were "vulnerable" to pressure from China because "bringing in Chinese students is one of the ways of dealing with the financial crises that universities are facing".</p><p>"If we see limitations being made on the kind of research that goes on in these universities, I think we should be alarmed," added the Labour peer, who has herself been sanctioned by China for speaking out about issues related to Xinjiang.</p></div><figure><div data-component="image-block"><p><img src="https://static.files.bbci.co.uk/bbcdotcom/web/20251021-134202-667692b2c6-web-2.32.2-1/grey-placeholder.png" aria-label="image unavailable"><img sizes="(min-width: 1280px) 50vw, (min-width: 1008px) 66vw, 96vw" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/6133/live/2bce6ee0-0b00-11f0-97d3-37df2b293ed1.png.webp 240w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/6133/live/2bce6ee0-0b00-11f0-97d3-37df2b293ed1.png.webp 320w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/6133/live/2bce6ee0-0b00-11f0-97d3-37df2b293ed1.png.webp 480w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/6133/live/2bce6ee0-0b00-11f0-97d3-37df2b293ed1.png.webp 640w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/6133/live/2bce6ee0-0b00-11f0-97d3-37df2b293ed1.png.webp 800w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1024/cpsprodpb/6133/live/2bce6ee0-0b00-11f0-97d3-37df2b293ed1.png.webp 1024w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1536/cpsprodpb/6133/live/2bce6ee0-0b00-11f0-97d3-37df2b293ed1.png.webp 1536w" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/6133/live/2bce6ee0-0b00-11f0-97d3-37df2b293ed1.png.webp" loading="lazy" alt="Thin, red banner promoting the Politics Essential newsletter with text saying, “Top political analysis in your inbox every day”. There is also an image of the Houses of Parliament."></p></div></figure></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Oxy is Cloudflare's Rust-based next generation proxy framework (2023) (123 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.cloudflare.com/introducing-oxy/</link>
            <guid>45795511</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 03:13:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/introducing-oxy/">https://blog.cloudflare.com/introducing-oxy/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45795511">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post"><article><p>2023-03-02</p><section><p>10 min read</p><img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/PBSyqFHas7ImWMdl4kWb1/1fc2829eceb9baff576b0ec6f2f105b8/introducing-oxy.png" alt=""><div><p>In this blog post, we are proud to introduce Oxy - our modern proxy framework, developed using the Rust programming language. Oxy is a foundation of several Cloudflare projects, including the <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/products/zero-trust/gateway/">Zero Trust Gateway</a>, the iCloud Private Relay <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/icloud-private-relay/">second hop proxy</a>, and the internal <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/cloudflare-servers-dont-own-ips-anymore/">egress routing service</a>.</p><p>Oxy leverages our years of experience building high-load proxies to implement the latest communication protocols, enabling us to effortlessly build sophisticated services that can accommodate massive amounts of daily traffic.</p><p>We will be exploring Oxy in greater detail in upcoming technical blog posts, providing a comprehensive and in-depth look at its capabilities and potential applications. For now, let us embark on this journey and discover what Oxy is and how we built it.</p>
    <p>
      <h2 id="what-oxy-does">What Oxy does</h2>
      
    </p>
    <p>We refer to Oxy as our "next-generation proxy framework". But what do we really mean by “proxy framework”? Picture a server (like NGINX, that reader might be familiar with) that can proxy traffic with an array of protocols, including various predefined common traffic flow scenarios that enable you to route traffic to specific destinations or even egress with a different protocol than the one used for ingress. This server can be configured in many ways for specific flows and boasts tight integration with the surrounding infrastructure, whether telemetry consumers or networking services.</p><p>Now, take all of that and add in the ability to programmatically control every aspect of the proxying: protocol decapsulation, traffic analysis, routing, tunneling logic, DNS resolution, and so much more. And this is what Oxy proxy framework is: a feature-rich proxy server tightly integrated with our internal infrastructure that's customizable to meet application requirements, allowing engineers to tweak every component.</p><p>This design is in line with our belief in an iterative approach to development, where a basic solution is built first and then gradually improved over time. With Oxy, you can start with a basic solution that can be deployed to our servers and then add additional features as needed, taking advantage of the many extensibility points offered by Oxy. In fact, you can avoid writing any code, besides a few lines of bootstrap boilerplate and get a production-ready server with a wide variety of startup configuration options and traffic flow scenarios.</p>
            <figure>
            
            <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/5nk7Ri6viC85BdWoRSiB9v/f40a9971fdad71cb07ee0b3aebf99fd9/image3-2.png" alt="High-level Oxy architecture" width="1999" height="1478" loading="lazy">
            
            </figure><p><i>High-level Oxy architecture</i></p><p>For example, suppose you'd like to implement an HTTP firewall. With Oxy, you can proxy HTTP(S) requests right out of the box, eliminating the need to write any code related to production services, such as request metrics and logs. You simply need to implement an Oxy hook handler for HTTP requests and responses. If you've used <a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/workers/examples/respond-with-another-site/">Cloudflare Workers</a> before, then you should be familiar with this extensibility model.</p><p>Similarly, you can implement a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OSI_model">layer 4</a> firewall by providing application hooks that handle ingress and egress connections. This goes beyond a simple block/accept scenario, as you can build authentication functionality or a traffic router that sends traffic to different destinations based on the geographical information of the ingress connection. The capabilities are incredibly rich, and we've made the extensibility model as ergonomic and flexible as possible. As an example, if information obtained from layer 4 is insufficient to make an informed firewall decision, the app can simply ask Oxy to decapsulate the traffic and process it with HTTP firewall.</p><p>The aforementioned scenarios are prevalent in many products we build at Cloudflare, so having a foundation that incorporates ready solutions is incredibly useful. This foundation has absorbed lots of experience we've gained over the years, taking care of many sharp and dark corners of high-load service programming. As a result, application implementers can stay focused on the business logic of their application with Oxy taking care of the rest. In fact, we've been able to create a few privacy proxy applications using Oxy that now serve massive amounts of traffic in production with less than a couple of hundred lines of code. This is something that would have taken multiple orders of magnitude more time and lines of code before.</p><p>As previously mentioned, we'll dive deeper into the technical aspects in future blog posts. However, for now, we'd like to provide a brief overview of Oxy's capabilities. This will give you a glimpse of the many ways in which Oxy can be customized and used.</p>
    <p>
      <h3 id="on-ramps">On-ramps</h3>
      
    </p>
    <p>On-ramp defines a combination of transport layer socket type and protocols that server listeners can use for ingress traffic.</p><p>Oxy supports a wide variety of traffic on-ramps:</p><ul><li><p>HTTP 1/2/3 (including various CONNECT protocols for layer 3 and 4 traffic)</p></li><li><p>TCP and UDP traffic over Proxy Protocol</p></li><li><p>general purpose IP traffic, including ICMP</p></li></ul><p>With Oxy, you have the ability to analyze and manipulate traffic at multiple layers of the OSI model - from layer 3 to layer 7. This allows for a wide range of possibilities in terms of how you handle incoming traffic.</p><p>One of the most notable and powerful features of Oxy is the ability for applications to force decapsulation. This means that an application can analyze traffic at a higher level, even if it originally arrived at a lower level. For example, if an application receives IP traffic, it can choose to analyze the UDP traffic encapsulated within the IP packets. With just a few lines of code, the application can tell Oxy to upgrade the IP flow to a UDP tunnel, effectively allowing the same code to be used for different on-ramps.</p><p>The application can even go further and ask Oxy to sniff UDP packets and check if they contain <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/performance/what-is-http3/">HTTP/3 traffic</a>. In this case, Oxy can upgrade the UDP traffic to HTTP and handle HTTP/3 requests that were originally received as raw IP packets. This allows for the simultaneous processing of traffic at all three layers (L3, L4, L7), enabling applications to analyze, filter, and manipulate the traffic flow from multiple perspectives. This provides a robust toolset for developing advanced traffic processing applications.</p>
            <figure>
            
            <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/4tVlLbQeNVeN2lYN9ovJNH/d87cc5adb53ff0fc441530520540f781/image1-1.png" alt="Multi-layer traffic processing in Oxy applications" width="1999" height="817" loading="lazy">
            
            </figure><p><i>Multi-layer traffic processing in Oxy applications</i></p>
    <p>
      <h3 id="off-ramps">Off-ramps</h3>
      
    </p>
    <p>Off-ramp defines a combination of transport layer socket type and protocols that proxy server connectors can use for egress traffic.</p><p>Oxy offers versatility in its egress methods, supporting a range of protocols including HTTP 1 and 2, UDP, TCP, and IP. It is equipped with internal DNS resolution and caching, as well as customizable resolvers, with automatic fallback options for maximum system reliability. Oxy implements <a href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc8305">happy eyeballs</a> for TCP, advanced tunnel timeout logic and has the ability to route traffic to internal services with accompanying metadata.</p><p>Additionally, through collaboration with one of our internal services (which is an Oxy application itself!) <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/geoexit-improving-warp-user-experience-larger-network/">Oxy is able to offer geographical egress</a> — allowing applications to route traffic to the public Internet from various locations in our extensive network covering numerous cities worldwide. This complex and powerful feature can be easily utilized by Oxy application developers at no extra cost, simply by adjusting configuration settings.</p>
    <p>
      <h3 id="tunneling-and-request-handling">Tunneling and request handling</h3>
      
    </p>
    <p>We've discussed Oxy's communication capabilities with the outside world through on-ramps and off-ramps. In the middle, Oxy handles efficient stateful tunneling of various traffic types including TCP, UDP, QUIC, and IP, while giving applications full control over traffic blocking and redirection.</p><p>Additionally, Oxy effectively handles HTTP traffic, providing full control over requests and responses, and allowing it to serve as a direct HTTP or API service. With built-in tools for streaming analysis of HTTP bodies, Oxy makes it easy to extract and process data, such as form data from uploads and downloads.</p><p>In addition to its multi-layer traffic processing capabilities, Oxy also supports advanced HTTP tunneling methods, such as <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc9298">CONNECT-UDP</a> and <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-masque-connect-ip/">CONNECT-IP</a>, using the latest extensions to HTTP 3 and 2 protocols. It can even process HTTP CONNECT request payloads on layer 4 and recursively process the payload as HTTP if the encapsulated traffic is HTTP.</p>
            <figure>
            
            <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/4a80AwmzUmUyxx7q8j2hcK/c2bcd1903e037852e57186510f6bac58/image2-2.png" alt="Recursive processing of HTTP CONNECT body payload in HTTP pipeline" width="1999" height="685" loading="lazy">
            
            </figure><p><i>Recursive processing of HTTP CONNECT body payload in HTTP pipeline</i></p>
    <p>
      <h3 id="tls">TLS</h3>
      
    </p>
    <p>The modern Internet is unimaginable without traffic encryption, and Oxy, of course, provides this essential aspect. Oxy's cryptography and TLS are based on BoringSSL, providing both a FIPS-compliant version with a limited set of certified features and the latest version that supports all the currently available TLS features. Oxy also allows applications to switch between the two versions in real-time, on a per-request or per-connection basis.</p><p>Oxy's TLS client is designed to make HTTPS requests to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Upstream_server">upstream servers</a>, with the functionality and security of a browser-grade client. This includes the reconstruction of certificate chains, certificate revocation checks, and more. In addition, Oxy applications can be secured with TLS v1.3, and optionally mTLS, allowing for the extraction of client authentication information from x509 certificates.</p><p>Oxy has the ability to inspect and filter HTTPS traffic, including HTTP/3, and provides the means for dynamically generating certificates, serving as a foundation for implementing data loss prevention (DLP) products. Additionally, Oxy's internal fork of BoringSSL, which is not FIPS-compliant, supports the use of <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc7250">raw public keys</a> as an alternative to WebPKI, making it ideal for internal service communication. This allows for all the benefits of TLS without the hassle of managing root certificates.</p>
    <p>
      <h3 id="gluing-everything-together">Gluing everything together</h3>
      
    </p>
    <p>Oxy is more than just a set of building blocks for network applications. It acts as a cohesive glue, handling the bootstrapping of the entire proxy application with ease, including parsing and applying configurations, setting up an asynchronous runtime, applying seccomp hardening and providing automated graceful restarts functionality.</p><p>With built-in support for panic reporting to Sentry, Prometheus metrics with a Rust-macro based API, Kibana logging, distributed tracing, memory and runtime profiling, Oxy offers comprehensive <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/application-services/solutions/app-performance-monitoring/">monitoring</a> and analysis capabilities. It can also generate detailed audit logs for layer 4 traffic, useful for billing and network analysis.</p><p>To top it off, Oxy includes an integration testing framework, allowing for easy testing of application interactions using TypeScript-based tests.</p>
    <p>
      <h3 id="extensibility-model">Extensibility model</h3>
      
    </p>
    <p>To take full advantage of Oxy's capabilities, one must understand how to extend and configure its features. Oxy applications are configured using YAML configuration files, offering numerous options for each feature. Additionally, application developers can extend these options by leveraging the convenient macros provided by the framework, making customization a breeze.</p><p>Suppose the Oxy application uses a key-value database to retrieve user information. In that case, it would be beneficial to expose a YAML configuration settings section for this purpose. With Oxy, defining a structure and annotating it with the <code>#[oxy_app_settings]</code> attribute is all it takes to accomplish this:</p>
            <pre><code>///Application’s key-value (KV) database settings
#[oxy_app_settings]
pub struct MyAppKVSettings {
    /// Key prefix.
    pub prefix: Option&lt;String&gt;,
    /// Path to the UNIX domain socket for the appropriate KV 
    /// server instance.
    pub socket: Option&lt;String&gt;,
}</code></pre>
            <p>Oxy can then generate a default YAML configuration file listing available options and their default values, including those extended by the application. The configuration options are automatically documented in the generated file from the Rust doc comments, following best Rust practices.</p><p>Moreover, Oxy supports multi-tenancy, allowing a single application instance to expose multiple on-ramp endpoints, each with a unique configuration. But, sometimes even a YAML configuration file is not enough to build a desired application, this is where Oxy's comprehensive set of hooks comes in handy. These hooks can be used to extend the application with Rust code and cover almost all aspects of the traffic processing.</p><p>To give you an idea of how easy it is to write an Oxy application, here is an example of basic Oxy code:</p>
            <pre><code>struct MyApp;

// Defines types for various application extensions to Oxy's
// data types. Contexts provide information and control knobs for
// the different parts of the traffic flow and applications can extend // all of them with their custom data. As was mentioned before,
// applications could also define their custom configuration.
// It’s just a matter of defining a configuration object with
// `#[oxy_app_settings]` attribute and providing the object type here.
impl OxyExt for MyApp {
    type AppSettings = MyAppKVSettings;
    type EndpointAppSettings = ();
    type EndpointContext = ();
    type IngressConnectionContext = MyAppIngressConnectionContext;
    type RequestContext = ();
    type IpTunnelContext = ();
    type DnsCacheItem = ();

}
   
#[async_trait]
impl OxyApp for MyApp {
    fn name() -&gt; &amp;'static str {
        "My app"
    }

    fn version() -&gt; &amp;'static str {
        env!("CARGO_PKG_VERSION")
    }

    fn description() -&gt; &amp;'static str {
        "This is an example of Oxy application"
    }

    async fn start(
        settings: ServerSettings&lt;MyAppSettings, ()&gt;
    ) -&gt; anyhow::Result&lt;Hooks&lt;Self&gt;&gt; {
        // Here the application initializes various hooks, with each
        // hook being a trait implementation containing multiple
        // optional callbacks invoked during the lifecycle of the
        // traffic processing.
        let ingress_hook = create_ingress_hook(&amp;settings);
        let egress_hook = create_egress_hook(&amp;settings);
        let tunnel_hook = create_tunnel_hook(&amp;settings);
        let http_request_hook = create_http_request_hook(&amp;settings);
        let ip_flow_hook = create_ip_flow_hook(&amp;settings);

        Ok(Hooks {
            ingress: Some(ingress_hook),
            egress: Some(egress_hook),
            tunnel: Some(tunnel_hook),
            http_request: Some(http_request_hook),
            ip_flow: Some(ip_flow_hook),
            ..Default::default()
        })
    }
}

// The entry point of the application
fn main() -&gt; OxyResult&lt;()&gt; {
    oxy::bootstrap::&lt;MyApp&gt;()
}</code></pre>
            
    <p>
      <h2 id="technology-choice">Technology choice</h2>
      
    </p>
    <p>Oxy leverages the safety and performance benefits of Rust as its implementation language. At Cloudflare, Rust has emerged as a popular choice for new product development, and there are ongoing efforts to migrate some of the existing products to the language as well.</p><p>Rust offers memory and concurrency safety through its ownership and borrowing system, preventing issues like null pointers and data races. This safety is achieved without sacrificing performance, as Rust provides low-level control and the ability to write code with minimal runtime overhead. Rust's balance of safety and performance has made it popular for building safe performance-critical applications, like proxies.</p><p>We intentionally tried to stand on the shoulders of the giants with this project and avoid reinventing the wheel. Oxy heavily relies on open-source dependencies, with <a href="https://github.com/hyperium/hyper">hyper</a> and <a href="https://github.com/tokio-rs/tokio">tokio</a> being the backbone of the framework. Our philosophy is that we should pull from existing solutions as much as we can, allowing for faster iteration, but also use widely battle-tested code. If something doesn't work for us, we try to collaborate with maintainers and contribute back our fixes and improvements. In fact, we now have two team members who are core team members of tokio and hyper projects.</p><p>Even though Oxy is a proprietary project, we try to give back some love to the open-source community without which the project wouldn’t be possible by open-sourcing some of the building blocks such as <a href="https://github.com/cloudflare/boring">https://github.com/cloudflare/boring</a> and <a href="https://github.com/cloudflare/quiche">https://github.com/cloudflare/quiche</a>.</p>
    <p>
      <h2 id="the-road-to-implementation">The road to implementation</h2>
      
    </p>
    <p>At the beginning of our journey, we set out to implement a proof-of-concept &nbsp;for an HTTP firewall using Rust for what would eventually become Zero Trust Gateway product. This project was originally part of the <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/1111-warp-better-vpn/">WARP</a> service repository. However, as the PoC rapidly advanced, it became clear that it needed to be separated into its own Gateway proxy for both technical and operational reasons.</p><p>Later on, when tasked with implementing a relay proxy for iCloud Private Relay, we saw the opportunity to reuse much of the code from the Gateway proxy. The Gateway project could also benefit from the HTTP/3 support that was being added for the Private Relay project. In fact, early iterations of the relay service were forks of the Gateway server.</p><p>It was then that we realized we could extract common elements from both projects to create a new framework, Oxy. The history of Oxy can be traced back to its origins in the commit history of the Gateway and Private Relay projects, up until its separation as a standalone framework.</p><p>Since our inception, we have leveraged the power of Oxy to efficiently roll out multiple projects that would have required a significant amount of time and effort without it. Our iterative development approach has been a strength of the project, as we have been able to identify common, reusable components through hands-on testing and implementation.</p><p>Our small core team is supplemented by internal contributors from across the company, ensuring that the best subject-matter experts are working on the relevant parts of the project. This contribution model also allows us to shape the framework's API to meet the functional and ergonomic needs of its users, while the core team ensures that the project stays on track.</p>
    <p>
      <h2 id="relation-to">Relation to <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/how-we-built-pingora-the-proxy-that-connects-cloudflare-to-the-internet/">Pingora</a></h2>
      
    </p>
    <p>Although Pingora, another proxy server developed by us in Rust, shares some similarities with Oxy, it was intentionally designed as a separate proxy server with a different objective. Pingora was created to serve traffic from millions of our client’s upstream servers, including those with ancient and unusual configurations. Non-UTF 8 URLs or TLS settings that are not supported by most TLS libraries being just a few such quirks among many others. This focus on handling technically challenging unusual configurations sets Pingora apart from other proxy servers.</p><p>The concept of Pingora came about during the same period when we were beginning to develop Oxy, and we initially considered merging the two projects. However, we quickly realized that their objectives were too different to do that. Pingora is specifically designed to establish Cloudflare’s HTTP connectivity with the Internet, even in its most technically obscure corners. On the other hand, Oxy is a multipurpose platform that supports a wide variety of communication protocols and aims to provide a simple way to develop high-performance proxy applications with business logic.</p>
    <p>
      <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
      
    </p>
    <p>Oxy is a proxy framework that we have developed to meet the demanding needs of modern services. It has been designed &nbsp;to provide a flexible and scalable solution that can be adapted to meet the unique requirements of each project and by leveraging the power of Rust, we made it both safe and fast.</p><p>Looking forward, Oxy is poised to play one of the critical roles in our company's larger effort to modernize and improve our architecture. It provides a solid block in foundation on which we can keep building the better Internet.</p><p>As the framework continues to evolve and grow, we remain committed to our iterative approach to development, constantly seeking out new opportunities to reuse existing solutions and improve our codebase. This collaborative, community-driven approach has already yielded impressive results, and we are confident that it will continue to drive the future success of Oxy.</p><p>Stay tuned for more tech savvy blog posts on the subject!</p></div></section><div><p>Cloudflare's connectivity cloud protects <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/network-services/" rel="noreferrer">entire corporate networks</a>, helps customers build <a target="_blank" href="https://workers.cloudflare.com/" rel="noreferrer">Internet-scale applications efficiently</a>, accelerates any <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/performance/accelerate-internet-applications/" rel="noreferrer">website or Internet application</a>, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/ddos/" rel="noreferrer">wards off DDoS attacks</a>, keeps <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/application-security/" rel="noreferrer">hackers at bay</a>, and can help you on <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/products/zero-trust/" rel="noreferrer">your journey to Zero Trust</a>.</p><p>Visit <a target="_blank" href="https://one.one.one.one/" rel="noreferrer">1.1.1.1</a> from any device to get started with our free app that makes your Internet faster and safer.</p><p>To learn more about our mission to help build a better Internet, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/what-is-cloudflare/" rel="noreferrer">start here</a>. If you're looking for a new career direction, check out <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/careers" rel="noreferrer">our open positions</a>.</p></div><astro-slot> <!--[if astro]>server-island-start<![endif]--> </astro-slot><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/proxying/">Proxying</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/rust/">Rust</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/performance/">Performance</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/edge/">Edge</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/icloud-private-relay/">iCloud Private Relay</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/gateway/">Cloudflare Gateway</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/oxy/">Oxy</a></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Simple trick to increase coverage: Lying to users about signal strength (340 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nickvsnetworking.com/simple-trick-to-increase-coverage-lying-to-users-about-signal-strength/</link>
            <guid>45795036</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 01:27:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nickvsnetworking.com/simple-trick-to-increase-coverage-lying-to-users-about-signal-strength/">https://nickvsnetworking.com/simple-trick-to-increase-coverage-lying-to-users-about-signal-strength/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45795036">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="page" role="main">

			
				
<article id="post-7762">
	<!-- .entry-header -->

		<div>
		
<p>Poking around in Android the other day <a href="https://android.googlesource.com/platform//frameworks/base/+/7a964f2199474ee99cc4a69e1654925ef4c4c09c/telephony/java/android/telephony/CarrierConfigManager.java#1156" data-type="link" data-id="https://android.googlesource.com/platform//frameworks/base/+/7a964f2199474ee99cc4a69e1654925ef4c4c09c/telephony/java/android/telephony/CarrierConfigManager.java#1156">I found this nugget in Carrier Config manager</a>; a flag (KEY_INFLATE_SIGNAL_STRENGTH_BOOL) to always report the signal strength to the user as one bar higher than it really is.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="233" src="https://nickvsnetworking.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/image-2-1024x233.png" alt="" srcset="https://nickvsnetworking.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/image-2-1024x233.png 1024w, https://nickvsnetworking.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/image-2-300x68.png 300w, https://nickvsnetworking.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/image-2-768x175.png 768w, https://nickvsnetworking.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/image-2.png 1373w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>It’s <a href="https://developer.android.com/reference/android/telephony/CarrierConfigManager" data-type="link" data-id="https://developer.android.com/reference/android/telephony/CarrierConfigManager">not documented in the Android docs</a>, but it’s there in the source available for any operator to use.</p>



<p>Notably both <a href="https://github.com/AOSPA/android_packages_apps_CarrierConfig/blob/bf2410198baf884c05d3ccac36bdcff6aceaba9f/assets/carrier_config_carrierid_1187_AT%26T.xml#L74" data-type="link" data-id="https://github.com/AOSPA/android_packages_apps_CarrierConfig/blob/bf2410198baf884c05d3ccac36bdcff6aceaba9f/assets/carrier_config_carrierid_1187_AT%26T.xml#L74">AT&amp;T</a> and <a href="https://github.com/AOSPA/android_packages_apps_CarrierConfig/blob/bf2410198baf884c05d3ccac36bdcff6aceaba9f/assets/carrier_config_carrierid_1839_Verizon-Wireless.xml#L171" data-type="link" data-id="https://github.com/AOSPA/android_packages_apps_CarrierConfig/blob/bf2410198baf884c05d3ccac36bdcff6aceaba9f/assets/carrier_config_carrierid_1839_Verizon-Wireless.xml#L171">Verizon</a> have this flag enabled on their networks, I’m not sure who was responsible for requesting this to be added to Android, nor could I find it in the <code>git-blame</code>, but we can see it in the <a href="https://nickvsnetworking.com/android-carrier-privileges/" data-type="post" data-id="2778">CarrierConfig</a> which <a href="https://nickvsnetworking.com/android-apn-master-config/" data-type="post" data-id="1130">contains all the network settings</a> for each of these operators.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="532" src="https://nickvsnetworking.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/image-5-1024x532.png" alt="" srcset="https://nickvsnetworking.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/image-5-1024x532.png 1024w, https://nickvsnetworking.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/image-5-300x156.png 300w, https://nickvsnetworking.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/image-5-768x399.png 768w, https://nickvsnetworking.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/image-5.png 1375w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>Operators are always claiming to have the biggest coverage or the best network, but stuff like this, along with the fake 5G flags, don’t help build trust, especially <a href="https://nickvsnetworking.com/using-fancy-test-kit-to-measurecell-antenna-stickers/" data-type="post" data-id="6970">considering the magic mobile phone antennas</a> which negate the need for all this deception anyway.</p>
	</div><!-- .entry-content -->
	
	<!-- .entry-meta -->
</article><!-- #post -->
						<nav>
		<h2>
			Post navigation		</h2>
		<!-- .nav-links -->
	</nav><!-- .navigation -->
						
<!-- #comments -->

			
		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Facts about throwing good parties (746 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.atvbt.com/21-facts-about-throwing-good-parties/</link>
            <guid>45794032</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 22:32:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.atvbt.com/21-facts-about-throwing-good-parties/">https://www.atvbt.com/21-facts-about-throwing-good-parties/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45794032">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
             

            <div><p><em>For New York’s No 1 Socialite, </em><a href="https://x.com/chengela?ref=atvbt.com" rel="noreferrer"><em>Angela.</em></a></p><p>1) Prioritize your ease of being over any other consideration: parties are like babies, if you’re stressed while holding them they’ll get stressed too. Every other decision is downstream of your serenity: e.g. it's better to have mediocre pizza from a happy host than fabulous hors d'oeuvres from a frazzled one.</p><p>2) Advertise your start time as a quarter-to the hour. If you start an event at 2:00, people won't arrive till 2:30; if you make it 1:45, people will arrive at 2:00.</p><p>3) Invite a few close friends to come 30-60 mins earlier to set up / eat dinner with you / hang out / whatever, so that when the start time approaches you’re already having fun instead of stressing that nobody will come.</p></div><p>4) Most people will only go to a party where they expect to know 3+ others already. </p><p>5) Use an app like Partiful or Luma that shows the guest list to invitees. Start by inviting your closest friends, get some yesses, then expand from there.</p><p>6) Send the invites in chat groups (or visibly cc’ed emails) to clusters of 4-5 people who know each other, so they can see that their friends are also going.</p><p>7) When inviting people individually, namedrop mutual friends who are invited or coming.</p><p>8) In a small group, the quality of the experience will depend a lot on whether the various friends blend together well. Follow your instinct on this, even if your instinct feels rude. It’s like cooking a dish, two ingredients can each be fabulous and still not go well together.</p><p>9) A large party is more like an Everything Soup: you mainly need to avoid ingredients that ruin the flavor for everyone else; beyond that you can mostly throw in whatever and see what works.</p><p>10) Regardless, try not to feel bad about not-inviting someone if your heart says they would make the party less-fun for others. Make peace with gatekeeping because if you don't exclude a small % of people you will ultimately lose everyone else. Someone can be a good person and a bad fit for your party, so don't think of it as a judgement on their soul. All of this is easier in theory than in practice.</p><p>11) Most events are better when roughly gender-balanced. Prioritize inviting people of the gender you’d likely have fewer of, then top up invites with the other. Once an event crosses a threshold (maybe 70%?) of male-or-female dominance, most people of the other gender are likely to decline (or just not-come to your next party) as a result. So there's ultimately two equilibria, "roughly gender balanced" and "extremely uncomfortably unbalanced," and you need to stay in the attraction basin for balance. To do this, keep your invite ratio at worst 60-40 in either direction, in order to prevent a downward spiral.</p><p>12) Co-host parties with someone you like a lot but who isn't in your exact social circle, so that your two friend-sets can intermingle.</p><p>13) Figure out the flake rate in your social circles (the % of people who will RSVP yes and flake on the day), and set your invite numbers with that in mind.&nbsp; In my circles, consistently 1/3rd of people who say they will be there will actually not. </p><p>14) Couples often flake together. This changes the probability distribution of attendees considerably, and so your chance of losing a quorum in a small-group setting. Small-group couple-events (e.g. 3-4 couple dinner parties) are very hard to manage in a high-flake society, as a result.</p><p>15) Create as much circulation at your party as you can. People circulate more when standing than when sitting, so try to encourage standing for those who can e.g. by having high-top tables, or taking away chairs from around tables, or leaving shelves and counter-tops open for people to rest their plates and drinks.</p><p>16) Put the food in one part of the room and the drinks in another, or spread the food and drinks out around the space, so that people have lots of excuses to move around the room.</p><p>17) If someone arrives at your party and doesn’t know anybody, welcome them and then place them with another group or person. Ideally you can pick someone they’d specifically get along well with, at second-best just someone who’s friendly and easy to talk to, but ultimately you can just insert them in any group that’s nearby and open. The main point is to prevent them having to butt in on strangers themselves, which for many people is mortifying, while your Host Privilege allows you to do it for them.</p><p>18) To leave a group conversation, just slowly step back and then step away. Don't draw attention to your leaving or you’ll be pulled back in. It feels mildly weird to do this but it’s worth it. </p><p>19) Throughout the party, prioritize introducing people to each other and hosting the people who are new or shy, even at the cost of getting less time hanging out with your best friends yourself. Parties are a public service, and the guests will (hopefully) pay you back for this by inviting you to parties of their own.</p><p>20) Let me repeat that: Parties are a public service, you’re doing people a favor by throwing them. Someone might meet their new best friend or future lover at your gathering. In the short term, lovely people may feel less lonely, and that's thanks to you. In the long term, whole new children may ultimately exist in the world because you bothered to throw a party. Throwing parties is stressful for most people, but a great kindness to the community, so genuinely pat yourself on the back for doing this.</p><p>21) The biggest problem at many parties is an endless escalation of volume. If you know how to fix this, let me know.</p><div><p>💡</p><p>Look I'm sorry but I must plug: the <i><em>best</em></i> way to throw a party is to buy my party game <a href="https://want.persondothing.com/?ref=atvbt.com" rel="noreferrer">Person Do Thing</a>, for fans of games like Charades, Taboo and Monikers.</p></div>

                

            
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Paris Had a Moving Sidewalk in 1900, and a Thomas Edison Film Captured It (2020) (325 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.openculture.com/2020/03/paris-had-a-moving-sidewalk-in-1900.html</link>
            <guid>45793466</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 21:08:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.openculture.com/2020/03/paris-had-a-moving-sidewalk-in-1900.html">https://www.openculture.com/2020/03/paris-had-a-moving-sidewalk-in-1900.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45793466">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
			<div>
<p><span><iframe title="YouTube video player" type="text/html" width="640" height="505" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/l2tmmIQm5x8?wmode=transparent&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en&amp;showsearch=0&amp;rel=0&amp;theme=dark" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" loading="lazy"></iframe></span>
	</p>
</div>

<p>It’s fair to say that few of us now mar­vel at mov­ing walk­ways, those stan­dard infra­struc­tur­al ele­ments of such util­i­tar­i­an spaces as air­port ter­mi­nals, sub­way sta­tions, and big-box stores. But there was a time when they astound­ed even res­i­dents of one of the most cos­mopoli­tan cities in the world. The inno­va­tion of the mov­ing side­walk demon­strat­ed at the Paris Expo­si­tion of 1900 (pre­vi­ous­ly seen here on Open Cul­ture when we fea­tured <a href="http://www.openculture.com/2018/12/pristine-footage-lets-you-revisit-life-in-paris-in-the-1890s.html">Lumière Broth­ers footage of that peri­od</a>) com­mand­ed even Thomas Edis­on’s atten­tion. As <a href="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/history/moving-sidewalks-before-the-jetsons-17484942/" rel="nofollow">Pale­o­fu­ture’s Matt Novak tells it at <em>Smith­son­ian&nbsp;</em>mag­a­zine</a>, “Thomas Edi­son sent one of his pro­duc­ers, James Hen­ry White, to the Expo­si­tion and Mr. White shot at least 16 movies,” a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l2tmmIQm5x8">clip of which footage</a> you can see above.</p>
<p>White “had brought along a new pan­ning-head tri­pod that gave his films a new­found sense of free­dom and flow. Watch­ing the film, you can see chil­dren jump­ing into frame and even a man doff­ing his cap to the cam­era, pos­si­bly aware that he was being cap­tured by an excit­ing new tech­nol­o­gy while a fun nov­el­ty of the future chugs along under his feet.”</p>


<p>Novak also includes hand-col­ored pho­tographs from the Paris Exhi­bi­tion and quotes a&nbsp;<em>New York Observ­er</em> cor­re­spon­dent describ­ing the mov­ing side­walk as a “nov­el­ty” con­sist­ing of “three ele­vat­ed plat­forms, the first being sta­tion­ary, the sec­ond mov­ing at a mod­er­ate rate of speed, and the third at the rate of about six miles an hour.” Thus “the cir­cuit of the Expo­si­tion can be made with rapid­i­ty and ease by this con­trivance. It also affords a good deal of fun, for most of the vis­i­tors are unfa­mil­iar with this mode of tran­sit, and are awk­ward in its use.”</p>
<div>
<p><span><iframe title="YouTube video player" type="text/html" width="640" height="505" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/CMlLPgAL2h0?wmode=transparent&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en&amp;showsearch=0&amp;rel=0&amp;theme=dark" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" loading="lazy"></iframe></span>
	</p>
</div>

<p>Novak fea­tures con­tem­po­rary images of the Paris Exhi­bi­tion’s mov­ing side­walk <a href="https://paleofuture.com/blog/2013/8/13/rare-photos-of-pariss-mechanical-moving-sidewalks-from-1900">at Pale­o­fu­ture</a>, found in the book&nbsp;<a href="https://amzn.to/2xf3ZD4"><em>Paris</em> <em>Expo­si­tion Repro­duced From the Offi­cial Pho­tographs</em><span>.</span></a>&nbsp;Its authors describe the <em>trot­toir roulant&nbsp;</em>as “a detached struc­ture like a rail­way train, arriv­ing at and pass­ing cer­tain points at stat­ed times” with­out a break. “In engi­neers’ lan­guage, it is an ‘end­less floor’ raised thir­ty feet above the lev­el of the ground, ever and ever glid­ing along the four sides of the square — a wood­en ser­pent with its tail in its mouth.” But the his­to­ry of the mov­ing walk­way did­n’t start in Paris:&nbsp;“In 1871 inven­tor Alfred Speer patent­ed a sys­tem of mov­ing side­walks that he thought would rev­o­lu­tion­ize pedes­tri­an trav­el in New York City,” as Novak notes, and the first one actu­al­ly built was built for Chicago’s 1893 Columbian Expo­si­tion — but it cost a nick­el to ride and “was unde­pend­able and prone to break­ing down,” mak­ing Paris’ ver­sion the more impres­sive spec­ta­cle.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" src="https://cdn8.openculture.com/2020/03/08220330/1900-paris-expo-moving-sidewalk-hand-painted-sm.jpg" alt="" width="550" height="415" srcset="https://cdn8.openculture.com/2020/03/08220330/1900-paris-expo-moving-sidewalk-hand-painted-sm.jpg 550w, https://cdn8.openculture.com/2020/03/08220330/1900-paris-expo-moving-sidewalk-hand-painted-sm-360x272.jpg 360w, https://cdn8.openculture.com/2020/03/08220330/1900-paris-expo-moving-sidewalk-hand-painted-sm-240x181.jpg 240w, https://cdn8.openculture.com/2020/03/08220330/1900-paris-expo-moving-sidewalk-hand-painted-sm-300x226.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" data-old-src="https://www.openculture.com/wp-content/plugins/native-lazyload/assets/images/placeholder.svg" data-src="https://cdn8.openculture.com/2020/03/08220330/1900-paris-expo-moving-sidewalk-hand-painted-sm.jpg" data-srcset="https://cdn8.openculture.com/2020/03/08220330/1900-paris-expo-moving-sidewalk-hand-painted-sm.jpg 550w, https://cdn8.openculture.com/2020/03/08220330/1900-paris-expo-moving-sidewalk-hand-painted-sm-360x272.jpg 360w, https://cdn8.openculture.com/2020/03/08220330/1900-paris-expo-moving-sidewalk-hand-painted-sm-240x181.jpg 240w, https://cdn8.openculture.com/2020/03/08220330/1900-paris-expo-moving-sidewalk-hand-painted-sm-300x226.jpg 300w"></p>
<p>Still, the Columbian Expo­si­tion’s vis­i­tors must have got a kick out of glid­ing down the pier with­out hav­ing to do the walk­ing them­selves. You can learn more about this first mov­ing walk­way and its suc­ces­sors, the one at the Paris Exhi­bi­tion includ­ed, from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CMlLPgAL2h0">the Lit­tle Car video above</a>. How­ev­er much these ear­ly mod­els may look like quaint turn-of-the cen­tu­ry nov­el­ties, some still see in the tech­nol­o­gy gen­uine promise for the future of pub­lic tran­sit. Mov­ing walk­ways work well, <a href="https://www.treehugger.com/public-transportation/paris-had-marvellous-moving-sidewalk-1900.html">writes Tree­hug­ger’s Lloyd Alter</a>, “when the walk­ing dis­tance and time is just a bit too long.” And they remind us that “trans­porta­tion should be about more than just get­ting from A to B; it should be a plea­sure as well.” Parisians “kept the Eif­fel Tow­er from the exhi­bi­tion” — it had been built for the 1889 World’s Fair — but “it is too bad they did­n’t keep this, a sort of mov­ing High Line that is both trans­porta­tion and enter­tain­ment.”</p>
<p><strong>Relat­ed Con­tent:</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://www.openculture.com/2018/12/pristine-footage-lets-you-revisit-life-in-paris-in-the-1890s.html">Pris­tine Footage Lets You Revis­it Life in Paris in the 1890s: Watch Footage Shot by the Lumière Broth­ers</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.openculture.com/2020/03/watch-scenes-from-belle-epoque-paris-vividly-restored-with-artificial-intelligence-circa-1890.html">Watch Scenes from Belle Époque Paris Vivid­ly Restored with Arti­fi­cial Intel­li­gence (Cir­ca 1890)</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.openculture.com/2015/11/beautiful-color-photographs-of-paris-taken-100-years-ago.html">Beau­ti­ful, Col­or Pho­tographs of Paris Tak­en 100 Years Ago—at the Begin­ning of World War I &amp; the End of&nbsp;<em>La Belle Époque</em></a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.openculture.com/2019/04/paris-in-beautiful-color-images-from-1890-the-eiffel-tower-notre-dame-the-pantheon-and-more-1890.html">Paris in Beau­ti­ful Col­or Images from 1890: The Eif­fel Tow­er, Notre Dame, The Pan­théon, and More (1890)</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.openculture.com/2015/09/how-french-artists-in-1899-envisioned-life-in-the-year-2000.html">How French Artists in 1899 Envi­sioned Life in the Year 2000: Draw­ing the Future</a></p>
<p><em>Based in Seoul,&nbsp;<a href="http://blog.colinmarshall.org/">Col­in Mar­shall</a>&nbsp;writes and broad­casts&nbsp;on cities, lan­guage, and cul­ture.&nbsp;His projects include the book&nbsp;</em>The State­less City: a Walk through 21st-Cen­tu­ry Los Ange­les&nbsp;<em>and the video series&nbsp;</em><a href="https://vimeo.com/channels/thecityincinema">The City in Cin­e­ma</a><em>. Fol­low him on Twit­ter at&nbsp;<a href="https://twitter.com/#%21/colinmarshall" rel="nofollow">@colinmarshall</a>&nbsp;or on&nbsp;<a href="https://www.facebook.com/colinmarshallessayist">Face­book</a>.</em></p>
<br>		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Alleged Jabber Zeus Coder 'MrICQ' in U.S. Custody (153 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://krebsonsecurity.com/2025/11/alleged-jabber-zeus-coder-mricq-in-u-s-custody/</link>
            <guid>45793244</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 20:40:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2025/11/alleged-jabber-zeus-coder-mricq-in-u-s-custody/">https://krebsonsecurity.com/2025/11/alleged-jabber-zeus-coder-mricq-in-u-s-custody/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45793244">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
												<p>A Ukrainian man indicted in 2012 for conspiring with a prolific hacking group to steal tens of millions of dollars from U.S. businesses was arrested in Italy and is now in custody in the United States, KrebsOnSecurity has learned.</p>
<p>Sources close to the investigation say <strong>Yuriy Igorevich Rybtsov</strong>, a 41-year-old from the Russia-controlled city of Donetsk, Ukraine, was previously referenced in U.S. federal charging documents only by his online handle “<strong>MrICQ</strong>.” According to <a href="https://www.justice.gov/iso/opa/resources/2162014411104532407242.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a 13-year-old indictment</a> (PDF) filed by prosecutors in Nebraska, MrICQ was a developer for a cybercrime group known as “<strong>Jabber Zeus</strong>.”</p>
<div id="attachment_72498"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-72498" decoding="async" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/rybtsov-lockedup.png" alt="" width="749" height="678" srcset="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/rybtsov-lockedup.png 861w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/rybtsov-lockedup-768x695.png 768w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/rybtsov-lockedup-782x708.png 782w" sizes="(max-width: 749px) 100vw, 749px"></p><p id="caption-attachment-72498">Image: lockedup dot wtf.</p></div>
<p>The Jabber Zeus name is derived from the malware they used — a custom version of the <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/?s=zeus+trojan" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ZeuS banking trojan</a> — that stole banking login credentials and would send the group a Jabber instant message each time a new victim entered a one-time passcode at a financial institution website. The gang targeted mostly small to mid-sized businesses, and they were an early pioneer of so-called “man-in-the-browser” attacks, malware that can silently intercept any data that victims submit in a web-based form.</p>
<p>Once inside a victim company’s accounts, the Jabber Zeus crew would modify the firm’s payroll to add dozens of “money mules,” people recruited through elaborate work-at-home schemes to handle bank transfers. The mules in turn would forward any stolen payroll deposits — minus their commissions — via wire transfers to other mules in Ukraine and the United Kingdom.</p>
<p>The 2012 indictment&nbsp;targeting the Jabber Zeus crew named MrICQ as “<strong>John Doe #3</strong>,” and said this person handled incoming notifications of newly compromised victims. The Department of Justice (DOJ) said MrICQ also helped the group launder the proceeds of their heists through electronic currency exchange services.</p>
<p>Two sources familiar with the Jabber Zeus investigation said Rybtsov was arrested in Italy, although the exact date and circumstances of his arrest remain unclear. A <a href="https://www.cortedicassazione.it/resources/cms/documents/Rassegna_mensile_MAGGIO_2025__settore_penale.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">summary of recent decisions</a> (PDF) published by the Italian Supreme Court states that in April 2025, Rybtsov lost a final appeal to avoid extradition to the United States.</p>
<p>According to the mugshot website <strong>lockedup[.]wtf</strong>, Rybtsov arrived in Nebraska on October 9, and was being held under an arrest warrant from the <strong>U.S. Federal Bureau of Investigation</strong> (FBI).</p>
<p>The data breach tracking service <a href="https://constella.ai/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Constella Intelligence</a> found breached records from the business profiling site bvdinfo[.]com showing that a 41-year-old Yuriy Igorevich Rybtsov worked in a building at 59 Barnaulska St. in Donetsk. Further searching on this address in Constella finds the same apartment building was shared by a business registered to <strong>Vyacheslav “Tank” Penchukov</strong>, the leader of the Jabber Zeus crew in Ukraine.</p>
<div id="attachment_61804"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-61804" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/tank-dj.png" alt="" width="743" height="587"></p><p id="caption-attachment-61804">Vyacheslav “Tank” Penchukov, seen here performing as “DJ Slava Rich” in Ukraine, in an undated photo from social media.</p></div>
<p>Penchukov was <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2022/11/top-zeus-botnet-suspect-tank-arrested-in-geneva/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">arrested in 2022</a> while traveling to meet his wife in Switzerland. Last year, a federal court in Nebraska <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/vyacheslav-igorevich-penchukov-tank-zeus-malware-sentencing/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sentenced Penchukov to 18 years in prison</a> and ordered him to pay more than $73 million in restitution.<span id="more-72496"></span></p>
<p><strong>Lawrence Baldwin</strong> is founder of <a href="https://mynetwatchman.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">myNetWatchman</a>, a threat intelligence company based in Georgia that began tracking and disrupting the Jabber Zeus gang in 2009. myNetWatchman had secretly gained access to the Jabber chat server used by the Ukrainian hackers, allowing Baldwin to eavesdrop on the daily conversations between MrICQ and other Jabber Zeus members.</p>
<p>Baldwin shared those real-time chat records with multiple state and federal law enforcement agencies, and with this reporter. Between 2010 and 2013, I spent several hours each day alerting small businesses across the country that their payroll accounts were about to be drained by these cybercriminals.</p>
<p>Those notifications, and Baldwin’s tireless efforts, saved countless would-be victims a great deal of money. In most cases, however, we were already too late. Nevertheless, the pilfered Jabber Zeus group chats provided the basis for dozens of stories published here about <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/category/smallbizvictims/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">small businesses fighting their banks</a> in court over six- and seven-figure financial losses.</p>
<p>Baldwin said the Jabber Zeus crew was far ahead of its peers in several respects. For starters, their intercepted chats showed they worked to create a highly customized botnet directly with the author of the original Zeus Trojan — <strong>Evgeniy Mikhailovich Bogachev</strong>, a Russian man who has long been on the FBI’s “Most Wanted” list. The feds have a <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2015/02/fbi-3m-bounty-for-zeus-trojan-author/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">standing $3 million reward</a> for information leading to Bogachev’s arrest.</p>
<div id="attachment_49974"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-49974" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/bogachev.png" alt="" width="743" height="456"></p><p id="caption-attachment-49974">Evgeniy M. Bogachev, in undated photos.</p></div>
<p>The core innovation of Jabber Zeus was an alert that MrICQ would receive each time a new victim entered a one-time password code into a phishing page mimicking their financial institution. The gang’s internal name for this component was “<strong>Leprechaun</strong>,” (the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UiAg3puABeA" target="_blank" rel="noopener">video below</a> from myNetWatchman shows it in action). Jabber Zeus would actually re-write the HTML code as displayed in the victim’s browser, allowing them to intercept any passcodes sent by the victim’s bank for multi-factor authentication.</p>
<p>“These guys had compromised such a large number of victims that they were getting buried in a tsunami of stolen banking credentials,” Baldwin told KrebsOnSecurity. “But the whole point of Leprechaun was to isolate the highest-value credentials — the commercial bank accounts with two-factor authentication turned on. They knew these were far juicier targets because they clearly had a lot more money to protect.”</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" title="YouTube video player" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UiAg3puABeA?si=pEHck5AXQ5mBKhz9" width="740" height="315" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></p>
<p>Baldwin said the Jabber Zeus trojan also included a custom “backconnect” component that allowed the hackers to relay their bank account takeovers through the victim’s own infected PC.</p>
<p>“The Jabber Zeus crew were literally connecting to the victim’s bank account from the victim’s IP address, or from the remote control function and by fully emulating the device,” he said. “That trojan was like a hot knife through butter of what everyone thought was state-of-the-art secure online banking at the time.”</p>
<p>Although the Jabber Zeus crew was in direct contact with the Zeus author, the chats intercepted by myNetWatchman show Bogachev frequently ignored the group’s pleas for help. The government says the real leader of the Jabber Zeus crew was <strong>Maksim Yakubets</strong>, a 38-year Ukrainian man with Russian citizenship who went by the hacker handle “<strong>Aqua</strong>.”</p>
<div id="attachment_49935"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-49935" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/yukabets.png" alt="" width="750" height="611"></p><p id="caption-attachment-49935">Alleged Evil Corp leader Maksim “Aqua” Yakubets. Image: FBI</p></div>
<p>The Jabber chats intercepted by Baldwin show that Aqua interacted almost daily with MrICQ, Tank and other members of the hacking team, often facilitating the group’s money mule and cashout activities remotely from Russia.</p>
<p>The government says Yakubets/Aqua would later emerge as the leader of an elite cybercrime ring of at least 17 hackers that referred to themselves internally as “<strong>Evil Corp</strong>.” Members of Evil Corp developed and used the <strong>Dridex</strong> (a.k.a. <strong>Bugat</strong>) trojan, which helped them siphon more than $100 million from hundreds of victim companies in the United States and Europe.</p>
<p><a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2019/12/inside-evil-corp-a-100m-cybercrime-menace/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">This 2019 story about the government’s $5 million bounty</a> for information leading to Yakubets’s arrest includes excerpts of conversations between Aqua, Tank, Bogachev and other Jabber Zeus crew members discussing stories I’d written about their victims. Both Baldwin and I were interviewed at length for a new weekly six-part podcast by the <strong>BBC</strong> that delves deep into the history of Evil Corp. <a href="https://www.bbc.com/audio/play/w3ct89y8" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Episode One</a> focuses on the evolution of Zeus, while <a href="https://www.bbc.com/audio/play/w3ct89y9" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the second episode</a> centers on an investigation into the group by former FBI agent <strong>Jim Craig</strong>.</p>
<div id="attachment_72504"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-72504" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/bbc-cyberhack.png" alt="" width="747" height="423"></p><p id="caption-attachment-72504">Image: https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/w3ct89y8</p></div>
											</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Lisp: Notes on its Past and Future (1980) (178 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www-formal.stanford.edu/jmc/lisp20th/lisp20th.html</link>
            <guid>45792579</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 19:05:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www-formal.stanford.edu/jmc/lisp20th/lisp20th.html">https://www-formal.stanford.edu/jmc/lisp20th/lisp20th.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45792579">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
 <a name="tex2html15" href="https://www-formal.stanford.edu/jmc/lisp20th/node1.html"><img width="37" height="24" alt="next" src="http://www-leland.stanford.edu/icons/latex2html//next_motif.gif"></a> <img width="26" height="24" alt="up" src="http://www-leland.stanford.edu/icons/latex2html//up_motif_gr.gif"> <img width="63" height="24" alt="previous" src="http://www-leland.stanford.edu/icons/latex2html//previous_motif_gr.gif">   <br>
<b> Next:</b> <a name="tex2html16" href="https://www-formal.stanford.edu/jmc/lisp20th/node1.html">Introduction</a>
 
<p><strong>
<b>John McCarthy</b> <br> 
Computer Science Department <br> 
Stanford University <br> 
Stanford, CA 94305 <br> 
<tt>jmc@cs.stanford.edu</tt> <br> 
<tt>http://www-formal.stanford.edu/jmc/</tt></strong></p><p><strong>
JanFebMarAprMayJun
JulAugSepOctNovDec , :&lt; 10 0 </strong></p><h3>Abstract:</h3>
<p>LISP has survived for 21 years because it is
an approximate local optimum in the space of programming
languages.  However, it has accumulated some barnacles
that should be scraped off, and some long-standing
opportunities for improvement have been neglected.
It would benefit from some co-operative maintenance
especially in creating and maintaining program libraries.
Computer checked proofs of program correctness are now
possible for pure LISP and some extensions, but more theory
and some smoothing of the language itself are required before
we can take full advantage of LISP's mathematical basis.
</p><p>
1999 note: This article was included in the 1980 Lisp conference held
at Stanford.  Since it almost entirely corresponds to my present
opinions, I should have asked to have it reprinted in the 1998 Lisp
users conference proceedings at which I gave a talk with the same
title.
</p><hr>
<ul> 
<li> <a name="tex2html17" href="https://www-formal.stanford.edu/jmc/lisp20th/node1.html#SECTION00010000000000000000">Introduction</a>
</li><li> <a name="tex2html18" href="https://www-formal.stanford.edu/jmc/lisp20th/node2.html#SECTION00020000000000000000">The Survival of LISP</a>
</li><li> <a name="tex2html19" href="https://www-formal.stanford.edu/jmc/lisp20th/node3.html#SECTION00030000000000000000">Improvements</a>
</li><li> <a name="tex2html20" href="https://www-formal.stanford.edu/jmc/lisp20th/node4.html#SECTION00040000000000000000">Proving Correctness of LISP Programs</a>
</li><li> <a name="tex2html21" href="https://www-formal.stanford.edu/jmc/lisp20th/node5.html#SECTION00050000000000000000">Mysteries and other Matters</a>
</li><li> <a name="tex2html22" href="https://www-formal.stanford.edu/jmc/lisp20th/node6.html#SECTION00060000000000000000">References</a>
</li><li> <a name="tex2html23" href="https://www-formal.stanford.edu/jmc/lisp20th/node7.html#SECTION00070000000000000000">References</a>
</li><li> <a name="tex2html24" href="https://www-formal.stanford.edu/jmc/lisp20th/node8.html#SECTION00080000000000000000">  About this document ... </a>
</li></ul>
<br> <hr>
<address>
<i>John McCarthy <br>
Mon Mar 22 17:10:06 PST 1999</i>
</address>


</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Linux gamers on Steam cross over the 3% mark (745 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.gamingonlinux.com/2025/11/linux-gamers-on-steam-finally-cross-over-the-3-mark/</link>
            <guid>45792503</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 18:54:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.gamingonlinux.com/2025/11/linux-gamers-on-steam-finally-cross-over-the-3-mark/">https://www.gamingonlinux.com/2025/11/linux-gamers-on-steam-finally-cross-over-the-3-mark/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45792503">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
						<p>It finally happened. Linux gamers on Steam as of the Steam Hardware &amp; Software Survey for October 2025 have crossed over the elusive 3% mark. The trend has been clear for sometime, and with Windows 10 ending support, it was quite likely this was going to be the time for it to happen as more people try out Linux.</p>

<p>As of the October 2025 survey the operating system details:</p>

<ul>
	<li>Windows 94.84% -0.75%</li>
	<li>Linux 3.05% +0.41%</li>
	<li>macOS 2.11% +0.34%</li>
</ul>

<p>The snapshot chart from our <a href="https://www.gamingonlinux.com/steam-tracker/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">dedicated Steam Tracker page</a> shows the clear trend:</p>

<p><a data-fancybox="images" href="https://uploads.golmedia.net/uploads/articles/article_media/1139496631762087838gol1.png" rel="noopener nofollow" target="_blank"><img src="https://uploads.golmedia.net/uploads/articles/article_media/1139496631762087838gol1.png"></a></p>

<p>Overall, 3% might not seem like much to some, but again - that trend is very clear and equates to millions of people. The last time Valve officially gave a proper monthly active user count was in 2022, and we know Steam has grown a lot since then, but even going by that original number would put monthly active Linux users at well over 4 million. Sadly, Valve have not given out a more recent monthly active user number but it's likely a few million higher, especially with the Steam Deck selling millions.</p>

<p>And if we look at the distribution breakdown chart from our page:</p>

<p><a data-fancybox="images" href="https://uploads.golmedia.net/uploads/articles/article_media/21445529501762087839gol1.png" rel="noopener nofollow" target="_blank"><img src="https://uploads.golmedia.net/uploads/articles/article_media/21445529501762087839gol1.png"></a></p>

<p>The overall distribution numbers for October 2025:</p>

<ul>
	<li><strong>SteamOS Holo 64 bit</strong> - 27.18% (-0.47%)</li>
	<li><strong>Arch Linux 64 bit</strong> - 10.32% (-0.66%)</li>
	<li><strong>Linux Mint 22.2 64 bit</strong> - 6.65% (+6.65%)</li>
	<li><strong>CachyOS 64 bit</strong> - 6.01% (+1.32%)</li>
	<li><strong>Ubuntu Core 22 64 bit</strong> - 4.55% (+0.55%)</li>
	<li><strong>Freedesktop SDK 25.08 (Flatpak runtime) 64 bit</strong> - 4.29% (+4.29%)</li>
	<li><strong>Bazzite 64 bit</strong> - 4.24% (+4.24%)</li>
	<li><strong>Ubuntu 24.04.3 LTS 64 bit</strong> - 3.70% (+3.70%)</li>
	<li><strong>Linux Mint 22.1 64 bit</strong> - 2.56% (-5.65%)</li>
	<li><strong>EndeavourOS Linux 64 bit</strong> - 2.32% (-0.08%)</li>
	<li><strong>Freedesktop SDK 24.08 (Flatpak runtime) 64 bit</strong> - 2.31% (-3.98%)</li>
	<li><strong>Fedora Linux 42 (KDE Plasma Desktop Edition) 64 bit</strong> - 2.12% (+0.19%)</li>
	<li><strong>Manjaro Linux 64 bit</strong> - 2.04% (-0.31%)</li>
	<li><strong>Pop!_OS 22.04 LTS 64 bit</strong> - 1.93% (-0.04%)</li>
	<li><strong>Fedora Linux 42 (Workstation Edition) 64 bit</strong> - 1.75% (-0.43%)</li>
	<li><strong>Other</strong> - 18.04% (-4.28%)</li>
</ul>

<p>The numbers are still being massively pumped up by the Steam Deck with SteamOS Linux, which is not surprising considering that the Steam Deck is still in the top 10 of the global top sellers on Steam constantly. And with all the rumours and leaks surrounding the upcoming Steam Frame, which will hopefully be a SteamOS Linux powered VR kit, we could see the numbers just continue to jump higher.</p>

<p>Source: <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/hwsurvey/?platform=combined" rel="noopener nofollow" target="_blank">Valve</a></p>
						<p><span>Article taken from <a href="https://www.gamingonlinux.com/">GamingOnLinux.com.</a></span>
						
					</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Reproducing the AWS Outage Race Condition with a Model Checker (128 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://wyounas.github.io/aws/concurrency/2025/10/30/reproducing-the-aws-outage-race-condition-with-model-checker/</link>
            <guid>45792373</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 18:37:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://wyounas.github.io/aws/concurrency/2025/10/30/reproducing-the-aws-outage-race-condition-with-model-checker/">https://wyounas.github.io/aws/concurrency/2025/10/30/reproducing-the-aws-outage-race-condition-with-model-checker/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45792373">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><p>Oct 30, 2025</p><p>AWS published a post-mortem about a recent outage [1]. Big systems like theirs are complex, and when you operate at that scale, things sometimes go wrong. Still, AWS has an impressive record of reliability.</p><p>The post-mortem mentioned a race condition, which caught my eye. I don’t know all the details of AWS’s internal setup, but using the information in the post-mortem and a few assumptions, we can try to reproduce a simplified version of the problem.</p><p>As a small experiment, we’ll use a model checker to see how such a race could happen. Formal verification can’t prevent every failure, but it helps us think more clearly about correctness and reason about subtle concurrency bugs. For this, we’ll use the Spin model checker, which uses the Promela language.</p><p>There’s a lot of detail in the post-mortem, but for simplicity we’ll focus only on the race-condition aspect. The incident was triggered by a defect in DynamoDB’s automated DNS management system. The components of this system involved in the incident were the DNS Planner, DNS Enactor, and Amazon Route 53 service.</p><p>The DNS Planner creates DNS plans, and the DNS Enactors look for new DNS plans and apply them to the Amazon Route 53 service. Three Enactors operate independently in three different availability zones.</p><p>Here is an illustration showing these components (if the images appear small, please open them in a new browser tab):</p><p><img loading="lazy" src="https://wyounas.github.io/images/2025-10-30-aws-outage-race-conditions/aws-dns.png" alt="aws dns management system"></p><p>My understanding of how the DNS Enactor works is as follows: it picks up the latest plan and, before applying it, performs a one-time check to ensure the plan is newer than the previously applied one. It then applies the plan and invokes a clean-up process. During the clean-up, it identifies plans significantly older than the one it just applied and deletes them.</p><p>Using the details from the incident report, we could sketch an interleaving that could explain the race condition. Two Enactors running side by side: Enactor 2 applies a new plan and starts cleaning up, while the other, running just a little behind, applies an older plan, making it an active one. When the Enactor 2 finishes its cleanup, it deletes that plan, and the DNS entries disappear. Here’s what that sequence looks like:</p><p><img loading="lazy" src="https://wyounas.github.io/images/2025-10-30-aws-outage-race-conditions/race-condition-interleaving.png" alt="aws dns race condition"></p><p>Let’s try to uncover this interleaving using a model checker.</p><p>In Promela, you can model each part of the system as its own process. Spin then takes those processes, starts from the initial state, and systematically applies every possible transition, exploring all interleavings to build the set of reachable states [2]. It checks that your invariants hold in each one, and if it finds a violation, it reports a counterexample.</p><p>We’ll create a DNS Planner process that produces plans, and DNS Enactor processes that pick them up. The Enactor will check whether the plan it’s about to apply is newer than the previous one, update the state of certain variables to simulate changes in Route 53, and finally clean up the older plans.</p><p>In our simplified model, we’ll run one DNS Planner process and two concurrent DNS Enactor processes. (AWS appears to run three across zones; we abstract that detail here.) The Planner generates plans, and through Promela channels, these plans are sent to the Enactors for processing.</p><p>Inside each DNS Enactor, we track the key aspects of system state. The Enactor keeps the current plan in <em>current_plan</em>, and it represents DNS health using <em>dns_valid</em>. It also records the highest plan applied so far in <em>highest_plan_applied</em>. The incident report also notes that the clean-up process deletes plans that are “significantly older than the one it just applied.” In our model, we capture this by allowing an Enactor to remove only those plans that are much older than its current plan. To simulate the deletion of an active plan, the Enactor’s clean-up process checks whether <em>current_plan</em> equals the plan being deleted. If it does, we simulate the resulting DNS failure by setting <em>dns_valid</em> to false.</p><p>Here’s the code for the DNS Planner:</p><pre><code>active proctype Planner() {
    byte plan = 1;
    
    do
    :: (plan &lt;= MAX_PLAN) -&gt;
        latest_plan = plan;
        plan_channel ! plan; 
        printf("Planner: Generated Plan v%d\n", plan);
        plan++;
    :: (plan &gt; MAX_PLAN) -&gt; break;
    od;
    
    printf("Planner: Completed\n");
}
</code></pre><p>It creates plans and sends them over a channel (<em>plan</em> is being sent to the channel <em>plan_channel</em>) to be picked up later by the DNS Enactor.</p><p>We start two concurrent DNS Enactor processes by specifying the number of enactors after the <em>active</em> keyword.</p><pre><code>active [NUM_ENACTORS] proctype Enactor() 
</code></pre><p>The DNS Enactor waits for plans and receives them (? opertaor receives a plan from the channel <em>plan_channel</em>). It then performs a staleness check, updates the state of certain variables to simulate changes in Route 53, and finally cleans up the older plans.</p><pre><code>:: plan_channel ? my_plan -&gt;
    snapshot_current = current_plan;

    // staleness check    
    if
    :: (my_plan &gt; snapshot_current || snapshot_current == 0) -&gt;

        if
            :: !plan_deleted[my_plan] -&gt;
                /* Apply the plan to Route53 */
                
                current_plan = my_plan;
                dns_valid = true;
                initialized = true;
               /* Track highest plan applied for regression detection */
                if 
                :: (my_plan &gt; highest_plan_applied) -&gt;
                    highest_plan_applied = my_plan;
                fi 
            
            // runs the clean-up process (omitted for brevity, included in the 
            // code linked below)
        fi
    fi

</code></pre><p>How do we discover the race condition? The idea is this: we express as an invariant what must always be true of the system, and then ask the model checker to confirm that it holds in every possible state. In this case, we can set up an invariant stating that the DNS should never be deleted once a newer plan has been applied. (With more information about the real system, we could simplify or refine this rule further.)</p><p>We specify this invariant formally as follows:</p><pre><code>/*

A quick note on some of the keywords used in the invariant below:

ltl - keyword that declares a temporal property to verify (ltl: linear temporal logic lets you specify properties about all possible executions of your program.)

[] - "always" operator (this must be true at every step forever)

-&gt; - "implies" (if left side is true, then right side must be true)

*/

ltl no_dns_deletion_on_regression {
    [] ( (initialized &amp;&amp; highest_plan_applied &gt; current_plan 
            &amp;&amp; current_plan &gt; 0) -&gt; dns_valid )
}



</code></pre><p>When we start the model checker, one DNS Planner process begins generating plans and sending them through channels to the DNS Enactors. Two Enactors receive these plans, perform their checks, apply updates, and run their cleanup routines. As these processes interleave, the model checker systematically builds the set of reachable states, allowing the invariant to be checked in each one.</p><p>When we run the model with this invariant in the model checker, it reports a violation. Spin reports one error and writes a trail file that shows, step by step, how the system reached the bad state.</p><div><pre><code>
<span>$ </span>spin <span>-a</span> aws-dns-race.pml
<span>$ </span>gcc <span>-O2</span> <span>-o</span> pan pan.c                                                       
<span>$ </span>./pan <span>-a</span> <span>-N</span> no_dns_deletion_on_regression  

pan: wrote aws-dns-race.pml.trail

<span>(</span>Spin Version 6.5.2 <span>--</span> 6 December 2019<span>)</span>

State-vector 64 byte, depth reached 285, errors: 1
    23201 states, stored
    11239 states, matched
    34440 transitions <span>(=</span> stored+matched<span>)</span>
  <span>(</span>truncated <span>for </span>brevity....<span>)</span>

</code></pre></div><p>The trail file in the repository below shows how the race happens. The trail file shows that two Enactors operate side by side: the faster one applies plan 4 and starts cleaning up. Because cleanup only removes plans much older than the one just applied, it deletes 1 and 2 but skips 3. The slower Enactor then applies plan 3 and makes it active, and when the faster Enactor picks up cleanup again, it deletes 3 and the DNS goes down.</p><p>Here’s an illustration of the interleaving reconstructed from the trail:</p><p><img loading="lazy" src="https://wyounas.github.io/images/2025-10-30-aws-outage-race-conditions/race-condition-spin-inteleaving.png" alt="aws dns race condition simulated by spin"></p><p>Before publishing, I reread the incident report and noted: “Additionally, because the active plan was deleted, the system was left in an inconsistent state…”. This suggests a direct invariant: the active plan must never be deleted.</p><pre><code>ltl never_delete_active {
    [] ( current_plan &gt; 0 -&gt; !plan_deleted[current_plan] )
}
</code></pre><p>Running the model checker with this invariant produces essentially the same counterexample as before: one Enactor advances to newer plans while the other lags and applies an older plan, thereby making it active. When control returns to the faster Enactor, its cleanup deletes that now-active plan, violating the invariant.</p><p>Invariants are invaluable for establishing correctness. If we can show that an invariant holds in the initial state, in every state reachable from it, and in the final state as well, we gain confidence that the system’s logic is sound.</p><p>To fix the code, we execute the problematic statements atomically. You can find both versions of the code, the one with the race and the fixed one, along with the interleaving trail in the accompanying repository [3]. I’ve included detailed comments to make it self-explanatory, as well as instructions on how to run the model and explore the trail.</p><p>Some of the assumptions in this model are necessarily simplified, since I don’t have access to AWS’s internal design details. Without that context, there will naturally be gaps between this abstraction and the real system. This model was created in a short time frame for experimental purposes. With more time and context, one could certainly build a more accurate and refined version.</p><p><em>Please keep in mind that I’m only human, and there’s a chance this post contains errors. If you notice anything off, I’d appreciate a correction. Please feel free to <a href="mailto:waqas.younas@gmail.com">send me an email</a>.</em></p><h2 id="references">References</h2><ol><li><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/message/101925/">AWS Post-Incident Summary — October 2025 Outage</a></li><li><a href="https://wyounas.github.io/concurrency/2024/12/12/how-concurrency-works-a-visual-guide/">How concurrency works: A visual guide</a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/wyounas/aws-dns-outage-oct-2025-modeling/">Source code repository</a></li><li><a href="https://spinroot.com/">Spin model checker</a></li></ol><hr><p><a href="https://wyounas.github.io/articles">← Back to all articles</a></p></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Anti-cybercrime laws are being weaponized to repress journalism (300 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cjr.org/analysis/nigeria-pakistan-jordan-cybercrime-laws-journalism.php</link>
            <guid>45792209</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 18:12:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cjr.org/analysis/nigeria-pakistan-jordan-cybercrime-laws-journalism.php">https://www.cjr.org/analysis/nigeria-pakistan-jordan-cybercrime-laws-journalism.php</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45792209">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                

                <p><em>Sign up for the daily <a href="https://www.cjr.org/email" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>CJR newsletter</strong></a>.</em></p>
                
                
<p>In May 2024, Daniel Ojukwu, a twenty-six-year-old reporter for the Foundation for Investigative Journalism, a Nigerian nonprofit, was grabbed off the streets of Lagos by armed police and bundled into a vehicle. For the next several days, he was held in a cell incommunicado—first in Lagos, and later in the federal capital, Abuja—without being told exactly what he’d been arrested for. “It was more of an abduction,” Ojukwu recalled recently, via WhatsApp. Finally, on the fourth day, the authorities informed him that he was being accused of breaching a 2015 law known as the Cybercrime Act. His violation: an <a href="https://fij.ng/article/special-report-2-weeks-before-end-of-buharis-tenure-special-assistant-adejoke-adefulire-paid-a-restaurant-n147-1m-to-build-classrooms-in-lagos-a-lot-was-amiss/">article he wrote</a> about alleged corruption in the office of the president.</p>



<p>The Cybercrime Act was introduced to combat a growing trend of internet fraud and other criminal activity within Nigeria, but it has instead frequently been used to suppress journalism published online. One provision in particular—Section 24, which made it illegal to publish false information online that was deemed to be “grossly offensive,” “indecent,” or even merely an “annoyance”—has been especially ripe for abuse. In 2019, for instance, Agba Jalingo, a journalist and publisher of <em>CrossRiverWatch</em>, in Nigeria’s Cross River State, was <a href="https://cpj.org/2023/03/nigerian-journalist-agba-jalingo-detained-on-cybercrime-charges/">arrested and charged under Section 24</a> after he published articles accusing the state’s governor of corruption. (He was later <a href="https://cpj.org/2024/07/nigerian-court-acquits-publisher-agba-jalingo-of-cybercrime-charges/">acquitted</a>.) In February 2024, Nigerian lawmakers amended Section 24 to remove some of its most egregious elements, but the new language still makes it illegal, and punishable by up to three years in jail, to “knowingly or intentionally” communicate online anything that is “false, for the purpose of causing a breakdown of law and order [or] posing a threat to life.”</p>



<p>“This vague text is still used to unfairly prosecute journalists, particularly those who regularly publish investigative reports implicating political or institutional forces,” said Sadibou Marong, the sub-Saharan Africa bureau director of Reporters Without Borders. “Authorities are intent on gagging investigative journalism uncovering corruption and governance issues in the country. The continued implementation of this law constitutes a real threat.”</p>



<p>Nigeria is not the only country using laws designed to legitimately combat online misbehavior to instead repress journalism. In neighboring Niger, Abdourahamane Tchiani, who seized power in a coup in 2023, signed an <a href="https://mfwa.org/issues-in-focus/niger-reintroduces-prison-sentences-for-cybercrime/">order amending three articles of the country’s cybercrime law</a> to reinstate prison sentences for “defamation,” “insults,” and the “dissemination of data likely to disturb public order or undermine human dignity” when these offenses are committed electronically. The law, originally enacted in 2019, had previously been softened to remove prison sentences for such offenses, in part owing to <a href="https://monitor.civicus.org/explore/niger-adopts-law-human-rights-defenders-restrictive-cybercrime-law-reviewed/">how the law had been abused</a> to repress journalists.<em> </em>In <a href="https://www.voanews.com/a/cybercrime-laws-risk-steady-criminalization-of-journalists-analysts-warn/7989674.html">Pakistan</a>, <a href="https://www.ned.org/big-question-how-are-cybercrime-laws-weaponized-to-legalize-repression-2/">Georgia</a>, and <a href="https://cpj.org/2025/03/new-turkish-law-criminalizes-false-reporting-on-cybersecurity-related-data-leaks/">Turkey</a>, among others, recent laws meant to limit nefarious activity online, or the spread of misinformation, have been used to restrict acts of journalism. <a href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2024/08/jordan-new-cybercrimes-law-stifling-freedom-of-expression-one-year-on/">According to Amnesty International</a>, at least fifteen people in <a href="https://rsf.org/en/jordan-s-cybercrime-law-tool-repressing-journalists">Jordan</a> have been prosecuted under a 2023 expansion of the country’s Cybercrimes Law, for offenses ranging from “spreading fake news” to “threatening society peace.”</p>



<p>“Unfortunately, most of the laws being passed will have little effect in actually curbing misinformation, but instead may give governments far more authority to control content they deem false or misleading,” said Gabrielle Lim, a doctoral fellow at the Citizen Lab at the University of Toronto, who recently <a href="https://www.cima.ned.org/publication/chilling-legislation/">coauthored a paper</a> tracking the misuse of “fake news” laws around the world. “For some governments, the threat of misinformation provides a convenient justification for censorship. This is compounded by the fact that liberal democracies are also considering or passing similar laws, which can give cover to authoritarian regimes who want to do the same.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>In Nigeria, more than two dozen journalists have faced prosecution under the Cybercrime Act, according to the Committee to Protect Journalists. In most cases, the journalists have been accused of cyberbullying, cyberstalking, or attempting to overthrow the government. On February 16, 2024—two weeks before the amended Cybercrime Act was signed into law—four journalists of <em>The Informant247</em>, an independent online newspaper based in Nigeria’s Kwara State, were <a href="https://cpj.org/2024/02/4-nigerian-journalists-charged-with-cybercrime-defamation-over-fraud-investigation/amp/">arrested</a> and briefly detained after they published a <a href="https://theinformant247.com/just-a-paint-job-inside-kwara-polytechnics-shoddy-project-commissioning-part-1/">two-part investigative</a> <a href="https://theinformant247.com/how-kwara-polytechnic-rector-made-false-claims-about-institutions-financial-status-commissioned-shoddy-uncompleted-projects/">series</a> that alleged a corrupt atmosphere at a state-run polytechnic institute. “The experience was profoundly disturbing,” said Salihu Ayatullahi, the publication’s editor in chief and one of the arrested journalists. “We were locked in a dark, cramped cell with hardened criminals. The psychological impact was heavier than the physical discomfort: I couldn’t sleep, not because of the poor conditions, but because I couldn’t stop thinking about how broken our system had become and how the corrupt could illegally summon the police to punish those who expose them.” The case was dismissed eleven months later without any evidence presented against the reporters.</p>




<p>Solomon Okedara, a Nigerian digital rights lawyer and researcher, notes that the use of the Cybercrime Act has created a chilling effect in the nation’s civic space. “It is even more worrisome that most of the time, the prosecution cannot establish ingredients of the offense to the point of conviction,” Okedara said. “Knowing a fellow journalist has faced arrest, harassment, and detention, or endless trials, can force others to drop an investigative story idea.”</p>



<p>Despite their ordeals, both Ojukwu and Ayatullahi say they are more determined than ever to use their craft to hold public officials accountable. “As a journalist, the whole experience has made me understand that there is more work to do,” Ojukwu said. “And since there is no limit to which the corrupt are willing to go, there is also none for me.<em> </em>The Cybercrime Act remains a thorn in the flesh of journalists in Nigeria.”</p>
<!-- CONTENT END 1 -->

                                      	                     
                        <center><p><em>Has America ever needed a media defender more than now? Help us by <a href="https://members.cjr.org/member/?a=interior-hasamerica&amp;utm_source=cjr-org&amp;utm_medium=cjr-interior&amp;utm_campaign=m-land">joining CJR today</a>.</em></p></center>
                        
                
                </div><p><small><strong>Nalova Akua&nbsp;is an award-winning Cameroonian freelance journalist. He has appeared in outlets including the BBC, Al Jazeera, <i>African Arguments</i>, and <i>El País</i>.<span><br></span></strong></small>
   

            
            </p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Is Your Bluetooth Chip Leaking Secrets via RF Signals? (124 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Is-Your-Bluetooth-Chip-Leaking-Secrets-via-RF-Ji-Dubrova/c1d3ceb47ea6f9cc4f29929e2f97d36862a260a2</link>
            <guid>45792166</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 18:06:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Is-Your-Bluetooth-Chip-Leaking-Secrets-via-RF-Ji-Dubrova/c1d3ceb47ea6f9cc4f29929e2f97d36862a260a2">https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Is-Your-Bluetooth-Chip-Leaking-Secrets-via-RF-Ji-Dubrova/c1d3ceb47ea6f9cc4f29929e2f97d36862a260a2</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45792166">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[At the end you use Git bisect (197 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://kevin3010.github.io/git/2025/11/02/At-the-end-you-use-git-bisect.html</link>
            <guid>45791882</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 17:24:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://kevin3010.github.io/git/2025/11/02/At-the-end-you-use-git-bisect.html">https://kevin3010.github.io/git/2025/11/02/At-the-end-you-use-git-bisect.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45791882">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div aria-label="Content">
        <article itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/BlogPosting">

  

  <div itemprop="articleBody">
    <p>People rant about having to learn algorithmic questions for interviews. I get it — interview system is broken, but you ought to learn binary search at least.</p>

<p>Anyways, yet again I came across a real life application of Algorithms. This time in the OG tool <code>git</code>. <code>git bisect - Use binary search to find the commit that introduced a bug</code> <a href="https://kevin3010.github.io/git/2025/11/02/](https://git-scm.com/docs/git-bisect)">ref</a>. And Leetcode wanted you to know it <a href="https://leetcode.com/problems/first-bad-version/description/?envType=problem-list-v2&amp;envId=binary-search">First Bad Version</a></p>

<p>We use a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monorepo">monorepo</a> at work. And people tend to make hundreds, if not thousands, commit in a single repo a day. On this day, our tests started failing, and the logs weren’t enough to debug or trace the root cause. The failing method depended on a configuration file that made a remote call using a specific role to obtain a token for running the tests. At some point, that configuration had been changed — a string was updated to reference a different account — which caused the failure.</p>

<p>Somehow, the bad change slipped through integration tests unnoticed. It was difficult to manually find the exact file or commit that introduced the issue since many commits had been made across the repository over the past few days.</p>

<p>That’s when a teammate from another team — who was facing the same test failures — ran a few “magical” commands and quickly identified the exact commit where things started to break. The basic idea was simple but brilliant: pick a known good commit and a known bad one, then run a binary search to find the exact commit that caused the failure.</p>

<p>It took a while since each test run was time-consuming, but eventually, it pinpointed the precise commit that introduced the issue. And sure enough, after reverting that commit, everything went back to green.</p>

<p>Here’s a small demo repository that shows how <code>git bisect</code> finds the first bad commit.</p>

<p>File tree:</p>

<div><pre><code>git-bisect-demo/
├── calc.py           # the library under test
├── test_calc.py      # a pytest test for calc.add
└── test_script.sh    # wrapper used by `git bisect run`
</code></pre></div>

<p>Good version of <code>calc.py</code> (commit where tests pass):</p>

<div><pre><code>def add(a, b):
    return a + b

if __name__ == "__main__":
    print(add(2, 3))
</code></pre></div>

<p>Bad version of <code>calc.py</code> (commit that introduced the bug):</p>

<div><pre><code>def add(a, b):
    # accidental string concatenation when inputs are coerced to str
    return str(a) + str(b)

if __name__ == "__main__":
    print(add(2, 3))
</code></pre></div>

<p><code>test_calc.py</code> (pytest):</p>

<div><pre><code>import calc

def test_add():
    assert calc.add(2, 3) == 5, "Addition failed!"
</code></pre></div>

<p><code>test_script.sh</code> — used by <code>git bisect run</code> to return exit code 0 on success and non-zero on failure:</p>

<div><pre><code>#!/usr/bin/env bash
set -e
pytest -q
</code></pre></div>

<p>Example commit history (chronological):</p>

<ul>
  <li>Commit 1: Initial commit (good)</li>
  <li>Commit 2: Small refactor (still good)</li>
  <li>Commit 3: Bug introduced (bad)</li>
  <li>Commits 4..10: Non-functional edits / comments (remain bad)</li>
</ul>

<p>We can run <code>git bisect</code> like this:</p>

<div><pre><code>git bisect start
git bisect bad HEAD
git bisect good HEAD~9
git bisect run ./test_script.sh
</code></pre></div>

<div><pre><code>status: waiting for both good and bad commits
status: waiting for good commit(s), bad commit known
Bisecting: 4 revisions left to test after this (roughly 2 steps)
[8dad374fd7c097c4fa3521c0b259e1eefe533520] Commit 5: more changes
running  './test_script.sh'
Bisecting: 1 revision left to test after this (roughly 1 step)
[b982ed9373fe235fe61c74b15faf264bc7142398] Commit 3: introduced bug
running  './test_script.sh'
Bisecting: 0 revisions left to test after this (roughly 0 steps)
[7b59759ca785572797e04f6b313bb0b735c22529] Commit 2: minor refactor
running  './test_script.sh'
b982ed9373fe235fe61c74b15faf264bc7142398 is the first bad commit
commit b982ed9373fe235fe61c74b15faf264bc7142398
Author: Kevin
Date:   Sun Nov 2 10:54:47 2025 -0500

    Commit 3: introduced bug

 calc.py | 10 +---------
 1 file changed, 1 insertion(+), 9 deletions(-)
</code></pre></div>

<p><code>git bisect</code> will checkout intermediate commits and run <code>./test_script.sh</code> until it finds the first commit that makes the tests fail.</p>

  </div>
</article>

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[New South Korean national law will turn large parking lots into solar farms (188 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://electrek.co/2025/11/02/new-national-law-will-turn-large-parking-lots-into-solar-power-farms/</link>
            <guid>45790867</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 15:12:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://electrek.co/2025/11/02/new-national-law-will-turn-large-parking-lots-into-solar-power-farms/">https://electrek.co/2025/11/02/new-national-law-will-turn-large-parking-lots-into-solar-power-farms/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45790867">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
					
<figure>

	<img width="1600" height="800" src="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/11/korea-solar.jpg?quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;w=1600" alt="Mandatory Installation of Solar Panels in Public Parking Lots to Apply Retroactively to Existing Facilities" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/11/korea-solar.jpg?w=320&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 320w, https://i0.wp.com/electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/11/korea-solar.jpg?w=640&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 640w, https://i0.wp.com/electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/11/korea-solar.jpg?w=1024&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/11/korea-solar.jpg?w=1500&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 1500w" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high">
	</figure>

<p>Starting this month, parking lots in South Korea with more than 80 spaces will be <em>required</em> to install solar canopies and carports. But, unlike similar laws that have been proposed in the US, this new law doesn’t just apply to new construction –&nbsp;existing lots will have to comply as well!</p>



<p>South Korea’s Ministry of Trade, Industry and Energy announced in August that it has prepared an amendment to the Enforcement Decree of the Act on the Promotion of the Development, Use, and Diffusion of New and Renewable Energy to the effect that all publicly- and privately-owned parking lots in the Asian country with room for more than 80 vehicles will be compelled to add solar panels to their lots in a move designed to proactively expand renewable energy and create more solar and construction jobs.</p>



<p>In addition to creating jobs and working to stabilize the local grid with more renewable energy, the proposed solar canopies will offer a number of practical, day-to-day benefits for Korean drivers, as well.</p>



<p>The shaded structures will protect vehicles from heavy rain, snow, and the blistering summer sun — keeping interiors cooler, extending the life of plastics and upholstery, and even helping to preserve battery range in EVs and PHEVs by reducing their AC loads (and, of course, provide charging while the cars are parked).</p>	
	



<p>To their credit, Ministry officials absolutely get it. “Through this mandatory installation,” one unnamed official told <em><a href="https://cm.asiae.co.kr/en/article/2025081311085933266" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Asia Business Daily</a></em>, “we expect to expand the distribution of eco-friendly renewable energy generation facilities while providing tangible benefits to the public. By utilizing idle land such as parking lots, we can maximize land use efficiency. In addition, installing canopy-type solar panels can provide shade underneath, offering noticeable comfort to people using parking lots during hot weather.”</p>



<p>The new rule was approved in late September, <a href="https://cm.asiae.co.kr/en/article/2025100108130055075#:~:text=The%20Industrial%20Economy,amended%20in%20May." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">and is expected to go into effect later this month</a>, with new installation projects set to begin immediately.</p>



<h2 id="h-it-could-work-here">It could work here</h2>



<hr>



<figure><img decoding="async" height="576" width="1024" src="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/11/NW-Fire-main.jpg?quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;w=1024" alt="" srcset="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/11/NW-Fire-main.jpg 1600w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/11/NW-Fire-main.jpg?resize=150,84 150w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/11/NW-Fire-main.jpg?resize=300,169 300w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/11/NW-Fire-main.jpg?resize=768,432 768w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/11/NW-Fire-main.jpg?resize=1024,576 1024w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/11/NW-Fire-main.jpg?resize=1536,864 1536w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/11/NW-Fire-main.jpg?resize=350,197 350w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/11/NW-Fire-main.jpg?resize=140,79 140w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption>Solar carport; by Standard Solar.</figcaption></figure>



<p>South Korea is proving that an idea like is practical. Here in the US, we’re proving that out, too – the Northwest Fire District in Arizona partnered with <a href="https://standardsolar.com/project/northwest-fire-district/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">Standard Solar</a> to build a conceptually similar, 657 kW solar carport system across 12 parking lots (shown, above) that delivers more than 1.23 <em>million</em> kWh of clean, emissions-free power annually and offsets the equivalent of 185,000 vehicles’ worth of harmful carbon emissions.</p>



<p>That’s just Arizona. <a href="https://electrek.co/2023/12/08/new-york-city-opens-8500-acres-parking-lots-to-solar-canopies/?utm_source=chatgpt.com">In New York</a>, a new initiative to help expand solar into parking lots has more than doubled commercially zoned land where EV charging stations can be sited, “freeing up” an additional 400 million square feet of space throughout the city.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Sun-rich states like <a href="https://electrek.co/2025/10/24/texas-power-demand-surges-solar-wind-and-storage-carry-the-load/">Texas</a>, <a href="https://electrek.co/2025/10/16/nacfe-study-electric-semi-trucks-can-go-the-distance-today/">New Mexico</a>, and <a href="https://floridaman.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Florida</a> could also benefit, and even if we’re “just” adding fresh energy sources to municipal parking, dealer lots, and public schools, we could do a lot to reduce the cost of energy generation for the entire community. And, for what it’s worth, <a href="https://electrek.co/2025/10/19/survey-sunday-we-asked-why-you-chose-home-solar-you-answered/">that seems to be right in line with the big reasons why people are choosing to add solar to their homes today</a>.</p>




	<p>What do you guys think –&nbsp;would something like this work in the US, or are we too far gone down the sophomoric, pseudo-libertarian rabbit hole to ever dig our way out? Let us know your take in the comments.</p>







<p><strong>SOURCE | IMAGES</strong>: <a href="https://cm.asiae.co.kr/en/article/2025081311085933266" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Asia Business Daily</a>, via <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/assaadrazzouk_south-korea-mandates-solar-pv-for-every-parking-activity-7390558326901661696-DRMg?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop&amp;rcm=ACoAAADiW9sB6rTK_7ndTdN_qPI5TNzFN2DOnic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">LinkedIn</a>; <a href="https://standardsolar.com/project/northwest-fire-district/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Standard Solar</a>.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.dpbolvw.net/click-101288862-16942853" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="750" height="150" src="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/03/DES-1038_Electrek-Banners_EVs_0797c2.png" alt="" srcset="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/03/DES-1038_Electrek-Banners_EVs_0797c2.png 750w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/03/DES-1038_Electrek-Banners_EVs_0797c2.png?resize=150,30 150w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/03/DES-1038_Electrek-Banners_EVs_0797c2.png?resize=300,60 300w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/03/DES-1038_Electrek-Banners_EVs_0797c2.png?resize=350,70 350w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2025/03/DES-1038_Electrek-Banners_EVs_0797c2.png?resize=140,28 140w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 750px) 100vw, 750px"></a></figure>



<hr>



<p><em>If you’re considering going solar, it’s always a good idea to get quotes from a few installers. To make sure you find a trusted, reliable solar installer near you that offers competitive pricing, check out&nbsp;</em><a href="https://www.dpbolvw.net/click-101288862-16942853" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>EnergySage</em></a><em>, a free service that makes it easy for you to go solar. It has hundreds of pre-vetted solar installers competing for your business, ensuring you get high-quality solutions and save 20-30% compared to going it alone. Plus, it’s free to use, and you won’t get sales calls until you select an installer and share your phone number with them.&nbsp;</em></p>



<p><em>Your personalized solar quotes are easy to compare online and you’ll get access to unbiased Energy Advisors to help you every step of the way.&nbsp;</em><a href="https://www.dpbolvw.net/click-101288862-16942853" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Get started here</em></a>.</p>
	<p>
				<a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://news.google.com/publications/CAAqBwgKMKqD-Qow6c_gAg?hl=en-US&amp;gl=US&amp;ceid=US:en">
			<em>Add Electrek to your Google News feed.</em>&nbsp;
					</a>
			</p>
	<p><em>FTC: We use income earning auto affiliate links.</em> <a href="https://electrek.co/about/#affiliate">More.</a></p>				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why don't you use dependent types? (238 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io//2025/11/02/Why-not-dependent.html</link>
            <guid>45790827</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 15:06:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io//2025/11/02/Why-not-dependent.html">https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io//2025/11/02/Why-not-dependent.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45790827">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section>

      
<p>02 Nov 2025</p>

<span>[
  
    
    <a href="https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io/tag/memories"><code><nobr>memories</nobr></code>&nbsp;</a>
  
    
    <a href="https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io/tag/AUTOMATH"><code><nobr>AUTOMATH</nobr></code>&nbsp;</a>
  
    
    <a href="https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io/tag/LCF"><code><nobr>LCF</nobr></code>&nbsp;</a>
  
    
    <a href="https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io/tag/type_theory"><code><nobr>type theory</nobr></code>&nbsp;</a>
  
    
    <a href="https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io/tag/Martin-L%C3%B6f_type_theory"><code><nobr>Martin-Löf type theory</nobr></code>&nbsp;</a>
  
    
    <a href="https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io/tag/NG_de_Bruijn"><code><nobr>NG de Bruijn</nobr></code>&nbsp;</a>
  
    
    <a href="https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io/tag/ALEXANDRIA"><code><nobr>ALEXANDRIA</nobr></code>&nbsp;</a>
  
]</span>

<p>To be fair, nobody asks me this exact question.
But people have regularly asked why Isabelle dispenses with proof objects.
The two questions are essentially the same, 
because proof objects are intrinsic to all the usual type theories.
They are also completely unnecessary and a huge waste of space.
As described in an <a href="https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io/2022/01/05/LCF.html">earlier post</a>,
type checking in the <em>implementation language</em> (rather than in the logic)
can ensure that only legitimate proof steps are executed.
Robin Milner had this fundamental insight 50 years ago,
giving us the LCF architecture with its proof kernel.
But the best answer to the original question is simply this: 
I did use dependent types, for years.</p>

<h3 id="my-time-with-automath">My time with AUTOMATH</h3>

<p>I was lucky enough to get some personal time with N G de Bruijn
when he came to Caltech in 1977 to lecture about
<a href="https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io/2021/11/03/AUTOMATH.html">AUTOMATH</a>.
I never actually got to use this system.
Back then, researchers used the nascent Internet (the ARPAnet)
not to download software so much as 
to run software directly on the host computer, 
since most software was not portable.
But Eindhoven University was not on the ARPAnet,
and AUTOMATH was configured to run on 
<a href="https://automath.win.tue.nl/archive/pdf/aut034.pdf">a computer we did not have</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Until September 1973, the computer was the Electrologica X8, after that
Burroughs 6700. In both cases the available multiprogranming systems
required the use of ALGOL 60.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I did however read many of the research reports, including 
the <a href="https://automath.win.tue.nl/archive/pdf/aut046.pdf">PhD dissertation</a> by LS Jutting,
where he presents his translation 
of Landau’s text <em>Grundlagen der Analysis</em> (described <a href="https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io/2025/10/15/Proofs-trivial.html">last time</a>)
from German into AUTOMATH.
It is no coincidence that many of my papers, from the
<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0167-6423(85)90009-7">earliest</a>
to the <a href="https://doi.org/10.4230/LIPIcs.ITP.2025.18">latest</a>,
copied the idea of formalising a text
and attempting to be faithful to it, if possible line by line.</p>

<p>As an aside, note that while AUTOMATH was a system of dependent types,
it did not embody the 
<a href="https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io/2023/08/23/Propositions_as_Types.html">Curry–Howard correspondence</a>
(sometimes wrongly called the Curry–Howard–de Bruijn correspondence).
That correspondence involves having a type theory strong enough
to represent the predicate calculus directly in the form of types.
In AUTOMATH you had to introduce the symbols and inference rules 
of your desired calculus in the form of axioms, much as you do with Isabelle.
In short, AUTOMATH was a <a href="https://pure.tue.nl/ws/files/1892191/597622.pdf">logical framework</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>like a big restaurant that serves all sorts of food: vegetarian, kosher, or anything else the customer wants</p>
</blockquote>

<p>De Bruijn
<a href="https://pure.tue.nl/ws/portalfiles/portal/4428179/597611.pdf">did not approve</a> 
of the increasingly powerful type theories being developed in the 1990s.
AUTOMATH was a weak language, 
a form of λ-calculus including a general product construction just
powerful enough to express the inference rules of a variety of formalisms
and to make simple definitions, again clearly the inspiration for Isabelle.
Isabelle aims to be <a href="https://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/techreports/UCAM-CL-TR-130.html"><em>generic</em></a>, like the big AUTOMATH restaurant.
Only these days everybody prefers the same cuisine,
higher-order logic, so Isabelle/HOL has become dominant.
Unfortunately, I last spoke to Dick (as he was known to friends)
when I was putting all my effort into Isabelle/ZF.
He simply loathed set theory and saw mathematics as essentially typed.
He never lived to see the enormous amount of advanced mathematics
that would be formalised using types in Isabelle/HOL.</p>

<p>I annoyed him in another way. I kept asking,
AUTOMATH looks natural, but how do we know that it is right?
He eventually sent me a 300 page volume entitled
<a href="https://automath.win.tue.nl/archive/pdf/aut073.pdf">The Language Theory of Automath</a>.
It describes AUTOMATH’s formal properties such as 
strong normalisation and Church–Rosser properties,
but this was not the answer I wanted at all.
I got that answer for a quite different type theory.</p>

<h3 id="martin-löf-type-theory">Martin-Löf type theory</h3>

<p>In response to kind invitations from Bengt Nordström and Kent Petersson,
I paid a number of visits to Chalmers University in Gothenburg
to learn about Martin-Löf type theory.
I was particularly impressed by its promise 
of a systematic and formal approach to program synthesis.
I had already encountered <a href="https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io/2021/11/24/Intuitionism.html">intuitionism</a>
through a course on the philosophy of mathematics at Stanford University,
as I recall taught by <a href="https://www.pet.cam.ac.uk/news/professor-ian-macdougall-hacking-1936-2023">Ian Hacking</a>.
The “rightness” of Martin-Löf type theory was obvious, 
because it directly embodied the principles of intuition truth
as outlined by Heyting: for example, that
a proof of $A\land B$ consists of a proof of $A$ paired with a proof of $B$.</p>

<p>I devoted several years of research to Martin-Löf type theory.
This included a whole year of intricate hand derivations to produce a 
<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0747-7171(86)80002-5">paper</a> 
that I once thought would be important,
and the <a href="https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io/2022/07/13/Isabelle_influences.html">very first version</a> 
of Isabelle.
Yes: Isabelle began as an implementation of Martin-Löf type theory,
which is <a href="https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io/2022/11/30/CTT_in_Isabelle-II.html">still included</a> 
in the distribution even today as Isabelle/CTT.
But eventually I tired of what seemed to me a doctrinaire attitude
bordering on a cult of personality around Per Martin-Löf.
The sudden switch to intensional equality 
(everyone was expected to adopt the new approach) wrecked most of my work.
Screw that.</p>

<p>You might ask, what about the calculus of constructions,
which arose during that time and eventually gave us Rocq and Lean?
(Not to mention <a href="https://www.lfcs.inf.ed.ac.uk/reports/92/ECS-LFCS-92-211/">LEGO</a>.)
To me they raised, and continue to raise, the same question I had put to de Bruijn.
Gérard Huet said something like “it is nothing but function application”,
which did not convince me.
It’s clear that I am being fussy,<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>
because thousands of people find these formalisms perfectly natural and believable.
But it is also true that the calculus of constructions 
underwent numerous changes over the past four decades.
There seem to be several optional axioms that people sometimes adopt
while attempting to minimise their use, 
like dieters enjoying an occasional croissant.</p>

<h3 id="decisions-decisions">Decisions, decisions</h3>

<p>We can see all this as an example of the choices we make in research.
People were developing new formalisms. This specific fact was the impetus
for making Isabelle generic in the first place.
But we have to choose whether to spend our time developing formalisms 
or instead to choose a fixed formalism and see how far you can push it.
Both are legitimate research goals.</p>

<p>For example, already in 1985, Mike Gordon 
was using higher-order logic <a href="https://doi.org/10.48456/tr-77">to verify hardware</a>.
He was not distracted by the idea that some dependent type theory might work better
for <em>n</em>-bit words and the like.
The formalism that he implemented was essentially the same as the 
<a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/type-theory-church/">simple theory of types</a> 
outlined by Alonzo Church in 1940.
He made verification history using this venerable formalism, 
and John Harrison later found
a clever way to <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/11541868_8">encode the dimension</a>
of vector types including words.
Isabelle/HOL also implements Church’s simple type theory,
with one extension: <a href="https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io/2022/03/02/Type_classes.html">axiomatic type classes</a>.
Isabella users also derive much power from the <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10817-019-09537-9">locale concept</a>, 
a kind of module sysstem that lies outside any particular logic.</p>

<p>During all this time, both Martin-Löf type theory and the calculus of constructions
went through several stages of evolution. It’s remarkable how the Lean community,
by running with a certain version of the calculus,
quickly formalised a <a href="https://leanprover-community.github.io/mathlib-overview.html">vast amount of mathematics</a>.</p>

<h3 id="pushing-higher-order-logic-to-its-limit">Pushing higher-order logic to its limit</h3>

<p>I felt exceptionally lucky to win 
<a href="https://cordis.europa.eu/project/id/742178">funding from the European Research Council</a>
for the advanced grant <a href="https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io/2021/12/08/ALEXANDRIA.html">ALEXANDRIA</a>.
When I applied, homotopy type theory was still all the rage,
so <a href="https://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/~lp15/Grants/Alexandria/Part-B2.pdf">the proposal</a>  emphasised Isabelle’s specific advantages: its automation,
its huge libraries and the legibility of its proofs.</p>

<p>The team started work with enthusiasm.
Nevertheless, I fully expected that we would hit a wall, 
reaching mathematical material
that could not easily be formalised in higher-order logic.
Too much of Isabelle’s analysis library identified topological spaces
with types.
Isabelle’s abstract algebra library was old and crufty.
A number of my research colleagues were convinced
that higher-logic was not adequate for serious mathematics.
But Anthony Bordg took up the challenge, leading a subproject
to <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/10586458.2022.2062073">formalise Grothendieck schemes</a>.</p>

<p>For some reason I had a particular fear of the field extension $F[a]$,
which extends the field $F$ with some $a$ postulated to be 
a root of some polynomial over $F$.
(For example, the field of complex numbers is precisely $\mathbb{R}[i]$, 
where $i$ is postulated to be a root a root of $x^2+1=0$.)
And yet an early outcome of ALEXANDRIA was<a href="https://rdcu.be/cIK3W"> a proof</a>,
by Paulo Emílio de Vilhena and Martin Baillon,
that every field admits an algebraically closed extension. 
This was the first proof of that theorem in any proof assistant, 
and its proof involves an infinite series of field extensions.</p>

<p>We never hit any wall.
As our group went on to formalise 
<a href="https://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/~lp15/Grants/Alexandria/">more and more advanced results</a>,
such as the <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3573105.3575680">Balog–Szemerédi–Gowers theorem</a>,
people stopped saying “you can’t formalise mathematics without dependent types”
and switched to saying “dependent types give you nicer proofs”.
But they never proved this claim.</p>

<p>Now that dependent type theory has attained maturity 
and has an excellent tool in the form of Lean, shall I go back to dependent types?
I am not tempted. The only aspects of Lean that I envy are its huge community and
the <a href="https://github.com/PatrickMassot/leanblueprint">Blueprint tool</a>.
I hear too many complaints about Lean’s performance.
I’ve heard of too many cases where dependent types played badly 
with intensional equality – I sat through an entire talk on this topic – or otherwise made life difficult. 
Quite a few people have told me that 
the secret of dependent types is knowing when <strong>not</strong> to use them.
And so, to me, they have too much in common 
with Tesla’s <a href="https://electrek.co/2025/10/29/tesla-full-self-driving-v14-disappoints-with-hallucinations-brake-stabbing-speeding/">Full Self-Driving</a>.</p>







      


    </section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[MySafeSpace – Whitehouse.gov (103 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.whitehouse.gov/mysafespace/</link>
            <guid>45790447</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 14:04:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/mysafespace/">https://www.whitehouse.gov/mysafespace/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45790447">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><header>
<div data-wp-interactive="whitehouse-header" data-wp-context="{&quot;popover&quot;: null, &quot;stickyThreshold&quot;: &quot;300px&quot;, &quot;stuckHeaderHeight&quot;: null}" data-wp-on-async-window--scroll="callbacks.handleWindowScroll">
	<div>
			<div>
				
				<p><span>President Donald J. Trump</span>
				</p>
			</div>
			
			<div>
					<a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/" rel="home" title="The White House">
						<picture>
							<source type="image/webp" srcset="https://www.whitehouse.gov/wp-content/themes/whitehouse/assets/img/whitehouse-47-logo.webp">
							<img src="https://www.whitehouse.gov/wp-content/themes/whitehouse/assets/img/whitehouse-47-logo.png" alt="" width="868" height="404" loading="eager" fetchpriority="high">
						</picture>
					</a>
				</div>
		</div>
	<div id="wp-block-whitehouse-header-6__popover" role="dialog" data-wp-watch="callbacks.initPopover" data-wp-class--is-open="callbacks.isPopoverOpen" data-wp-on-async-document--keydown="callbacks.handlePopoverKeydown" aria-modal="true">
			<nav data-wp-class--is-visible="callbacks.isMenuPopoverOpen" data-wp-bind--data-submenu-level="state.currentPopoverMenuActiveItemDepth" data-wp-on--click="actions.setCurrentPopoverMenuActiveItem" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuResize" data-wp-watch="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuBlur" data-wp-init="callbacks.init">
				<div>
					<ul id="menu-popover-navigation"><li id="menu-item-40" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/news/">News</a>
<ul data-wp-class--has-active="callbacks.isSubmenuActivePopoverMenuItem">
	<li id="menu-item-6693" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/articles/">Articles</a></li>
	<li id="menu-item-6695" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefings-statements/">Briefings &amp; Statements</a></li>
	<li id="menu-item-6694" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/fact-sheets/">Fact Sheets</a></li>
	<li id="menu-item-6692" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/presidential-actions/">Presidential Actions</a>
	<ul data-wp-class--has-active="callbacks.isSubmenuActivePopoverMenuItem">
		<li id="menu-item-6752" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/presidential-actions/executive-orders/">Executive Orders</a></li>
		<li id="menu-item-6753" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/presidential-actions/nominations-appointments/">Nominations &amp; Appointments</a></li>
		<li id="menu-item-6754" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/presidential-actions/presidential-memoranda/">Presidential Memoranda</a></li>
		<li id="menu-item-6755" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/presidential-actions/proclamations/">Proclamations</a></li>
	</ul>
</li>
	<li id="menu-item-6696" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/remarks/">Remarks</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li id="menu-item-39" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/administration/">Administration</a>
<ul data-wp-class--has-active="callbacks.isSubmenuActivePopoverMenuItem">
	<li id="menu-item-6700" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/administration/donald-j-trump/">Donald J. Trump</a></li>
	<li id="menu-item-6699" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/administration/jd-vance/">JD Vance</a></li>
	<li id="menu-item-6698" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/administration/melania-trump/">Melania Trump</a></li>
	<li id="menu-item-6701" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/administration/usha-vance/">Usha Vance</a></li>
	<li id="menu-item-6697" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/administration/the-cabinet/">The Cabinet</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li id="menu-item-8075" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout">Media</a>
<ul data-wp-class--has-active="callbacks.isSubmenuActivePopoverMenuItem">
	<li id="menu-item-12363" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/videos/">Video Library</a></li>
	<li id="menu-item-6595" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/gallery/">Gallery</a></li>
	<li id="menu-item-22505" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/live/">Live News</a></li>
	<li id="menu-item-10948" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/wire/">White House Wire</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li id="menu-item-38" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/issues/">Issues</a></li>
<li id="menu-item-7480" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout">History</a>
<ul data-wp-class--has-active="callbacks.isSubmenuActivePopoverMenuItem">
	<li id="menu-item-9424" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/america250/">America 250</a></li>
	<li id="menu-item-15752" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/america250/founders-museum/">The Founders Museum</a></li>
	<li id="menu-item-8466" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/founding-fathers/">America’s Founding Fathers</a></li>
	<li id="menu-item-16229" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/america250/founders-museum/major-events/">Moments That Made Us</a>
	<ul data-wp-class--has-active="callbacks.isSubmenuActivePopoverMenuItem">
		<li id="menu-item-16228" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/america250/founders-museum/major-events/timeline/">Road to Revolution: A Timeline</a></li>
	</ul>
</li>
	<li id="menu-item-16230" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/america250/founders-museum/signers/profiles/">Signers of the Declaration of Independence</a></li>
	<li id="menu-item-8597" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/government/">Our Government</a></li>
	<li id="menu-item-27698" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/about-the-white-house/the-white-house/">About The White House</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li id="menu-item-7479" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout">Get in Touch</a>
<ul data-wp-class--has-active="callbacks.isSubmenuActivePopoverMenuItem">
	<li id="menu-item-1063" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/contact/">Contact</a></li>
	<li id="menu-item-1271" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/visit/">Visit</a></li>
	<li id="menu-item-7864" data-wp-class--is-active="callbacks.isActivePopoverMenuItem"><a data-wp-on-async--mouseenter="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseover" data-wp-on-async--mouseleave="callbacks.handlePopoverMenuMouseout" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/internships/">Internships</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>				</div>
				<div>
				

<ul>
	<li><a rel="noopener nofollow" target="_blank" href="https://x.com/whitehouse"><span>X</span></a></li>

	<li><a rel="noopener nofollow" target="_blank" href="https://www.instagram.com/whitehouse/"><span>Instagram</span></a></li>

	<li><a rel="noopener nofollow" target="_blank" href="https://www.facebook.com/WhiteHouse/"><span>Facebook</span></a></li>
</ul>

				</div>
				<figure>
					<svg width="1044" height="1050" viewBox="0 0 522 525" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
<g>
<path opacity="0.4" d="M228.628 3.1663L225.223 13.8974L215.511 14.7357L222.99 19.9336L223.492 30.1616L230.581 23.5106L238.898 28.429L235.158 18.8716L242.47 11.7176L232.702 12.2206L228.628 3.1663ZM196.086 9.20252L194.412 20.2689L184.979 22.5046L192.961 26.5287L194.635 36.7008L200.775 29.0997L209.706 32.9562L204.794 24.0695L211.269 15.9653L201.612 17.8097L196.086 9.20252ZM164.773 19.4306L164.606 30.497L155.675 34.0181L163.992 36.9803L166.783 46.7053L172.141 38.4335L181.407 41.0044L175.434 32.8444L180.904 23.9577L171.304 27.0876L164.773 19.4306ZM135.134 33.571L136.307 44.4697L127.823 48.7174L136.53 50.7854L140.381 60.2309L144.623 51.2884L154.335 52.6298L147.414 45.5316L151.656 35.8066L142.447 40.1661L135.134 33.571ZM107.505 51.2325L110.073 61.74L102.314 67.2173L110.91 68.391L116.101 76.9423L119.059 67.6644L128.939 68.1115L120.957 61.6282L124.027 51.4561L115.599 56.9893L107.505 51.2325ZM82.3876 72.1357L86.0715 82.3078L79.2619 88.7912H87.8577L93.8859 96.7277L95.672 87.1144L105.552 86.1084L96.9558 80.9664L98.6303 70.6266L91.1509 77.11L82.3876 72.1357ZM60.0051 96.0011L65.0286 105.558L59.0004 112.824L67.3171 111.651L74.4058 118.972L75.0198 108.912L84.8994 106.844L75.3547 102.764L75.8013 92.5359L69.2707 99.634L60.0051 96.0011ZM40.6925 122.605L46.7207 131.212L41.8088 139.317L50.0697 136.913L57.9957 143.564L57.3259 133.224L66.8706 130.095L57.1026 127.021L56.2654 116.96L50.4046 124.897L40.6925 122.605ZM24.8405 151.389L32.0967 159.158L28.0221 168.212L36.0039 164.523L44.7113 170.168L42.6461 159.996L51.521 155.413L41.5856 153.96L39.5204 144.067L34.7201 152.507L24.8405 151.389ZM12.7841 181.905L20.8776 188.556L17.9193 198.002L25.5662 193.587L34.7759 198.002L31.6502 188.165L39.7994 182.52L29.7524 182.017L26.0685 172.739L22.4962 181.682L12.7841 181.905ZM4.85813 213.707L13.5097 219.52L11.8352 228.966L18.5332 223.656L28.4128 226.786L24.0591 217.564L31.6502 211.08L21.5474 211.751L16.8029 202.865L14.5144 212.31L4.85813 213.707ZM0.671875 246.459L10.1049 250.707L9.60256 260.6L15.6308 254.284L25.7336 256.24L20.3752 247.521L26.9058 240.2L16.8587 242.435L11.2212 234.163L10.0491 243.609L0.671875 246.459ZM0.671875 279.1L10.7189 282.23L11.3329 292.122L16.6355 285.024L26.8499 285.527L20.4868 277.87L26.1243 269.598L16.5238 272.84L9.88164 265.574V275.131L0.671875 279.1ZM4.85813 311.796L15.2401 313.696L16.9146 323.421L21.1566 315.764L31.5386 314.982L24.1149 308.163L28.5245 299.22L19.4821 303.636L12.1701 297.264L13.1748 306.822L4.85813 311.796ZM12.8399 343.598L23.5568 344.101L26.4592 353.658L29.8641 345.33L39.9111 343.374L31.8176 337.673L35.3341 328.06L26.7383 333.761L18.6449 328.284L20.8776 337.562L12.8399 343.598ZM25.008 374.003L35.7248 373.332L39.7436 382.386L41.9763 373.499L51.5768 370.425L42.8694 365.675L45.1578 355.894L37.3993 362.433L28.5803 358.241L32.1525 367.128L25.008 374.003ZM40.9158 402.898L51.2419 400.495L56.5445 409.102L57.7166 399.88L66.8148 395.688L57.7166 392.167L58.5539 381.939L51.4651 389.708L42.2554 386.578L46.6649 394.906L40.9158 402.898ZM60.2284 429.335L70.1079 425.925L76.2478 433.918V424.36L84.8436 418.995L75.2989 416.591L74.8524 406.419L69.0474 414.747L59.3353 412.847L64.8612 420.504L60.2284 429.335ZM82.8342 453.312L92.0439 448.561L99.1885 455.883L97.8489 446.269L105.831 440.121L96.0628 438.836L94.7232 429.055L89.8113 437.998L79.9317 437.159L86.5739 443.978L82.8342 453.312ZM108.175 474.271L116.603 468.123L124.697 474.327L122.129 465.049L129.218 457.951L119.338 458.062L116.715 448.449L113.143 458.007L103.375 458.51L110.631 464.49L108.175 474.271ZM135.86 491.653L143.619 484.667L152.494 489.864L148.586 481.034L154.894 472.762L144.847 474.383L140.995 465.105L138.595 475.277L129.05 477.009L136.809 481.872L135.86 491.653ZM165.555 505.737L172.085 497.745L181.797 501.769L176.774 493.497L182.076 484.778L172.197 487.405L167.452 478.686L166.169 488.579L157.071 491.653L165.387 495.509L165.555 505.737ZM196.756 515.798L202.226 507.191L212.273 509.817L206.301 502.049L210.543 492.938L201.11 496.515L195.082 488.579V498.975L186.486 503.166L195.193 505.737L196.756 515.798ZM228.795 522.002L233.372 512.388L243.419 514.009L236.889 507.191L239.679 497.298L230.804 502.328L223.995 495.174L225.167 505.402L217.185 510.432L226.283 511.885L228.795 522.002ZM261.615 524.07L264.685 514.009L274.9 514.345L267.253 508.197L269.151 498.136L260.89 504.172L253.41 498.024L255.699 507.917L248.443 513.953L257.485 514.4L261.615 524.07ZM294.324 522.002L296.557 511.662L306.436 510.376L298.343 505.514L298.845 495.118L291.198 502.272L282.937 497.13L286.454 506.743L280.258 513.73L289.133 513.059L294.324 522.002ZM326.474 515.798L327.144 505.29L337.191 502.887L328.316 499.142L327.535 488.467L321.06 496.515L312.018 492.156L316.874 501.601L311.404 509.37L320.111 507.47L326.474 515.798ZM357.564 505.57L356.95 495.062L366.551 491.373L357.341 488.579L355.388 478.351L349.75 487.237L340.484 484.108L346.457 492.659L342.047 501.266L350.643 498.192L357.564 505.57ZM387.091 491.597L384.97 481.089L394.403 476.339L384.803 474.886L381.845 464.713L377.156 474.327L367.611 472.371L374.421 480.195L371.184 489.138L379.165 485.114L387.091 491.597ZM415 473.935L411.483 464.043L420.079 458.062L410.311 457.615L405.958 447.89L402.72 458.062L393.175 457.559L400.822 464.21L398.757 473.656L406.181 468.458L415 473.935ZM440.396 452.865L435.373 443.307L443.466 436.489L433.419 437.159L428.061 428.384L426.107 438.612L416.842 439.115L425.159 445.096L424.154 454.541L430.684 448.505L440.396 452.865ZM463.002 428.943L456.36 420.057L463.672 412.12L453.793 414.356L447.597 406.252L446.927 416.48L437.829 418.268L446.536 422.963L446.983 432.688L452.844 425.925L463.002 428.943ZM481.924 402.563L474.668 394.459L480.808 385.572L471.207 388.981L464.063 381.715L464.677 391.888L455.634 394.682L465.235 398.427L466.575 408.152L471.486 400.495L481.924 402.563ZM497.553 373.499L489.459 366.401L494.483 357.179L485.385 361.762L477.403 355.391L479.189 365.284L470.761 369.028L480.808 371.487L483.096 381.045L487.338 372.605L497.553 373.499ZM509.888 342.704L500.79 336.835L504.363 326.942L496.102 332.923L487.506 327.445L490.464 337.17L482.371 342.033L492.697 343.207L496.269 352.093L499.227 343.374L509.888 342.704ZM517.982 310.902L508.27 306.151L510.67 295.923L502.744 302.742L494.036 298.382L498.055 307.604L490.632 313.584L500.846 313.473L505.423 321.745L507.377 312.69L517.982 310.902ZM522.001 278.205L511.954 274.796L512.902 264.289L505.925 272.057L496.66 268.928L501.683 277.535L495.041 284.465L505.144 283.124L510.949 290.781L511.786 281.503L522.001 278.205ZM521.666 245.342L511.34 243.05L511.172 232.71L505.144 241.317L495.432 239.194L501.628 247.13L496.102 254.62L505.646 251.993L512.735 259.091L512.121 249.533L521.666 245.342ZM517.647 212.869L506.93 211.751L505.256 201.355L500.567 211.08L490.687 209.963L497.999 217.117L493.143 225.444L502.353 221.532L510.335 227.568L508.66 218.123L517.647 212.869ZM509.386 180.844L498.669 181.458L495.599 171.23L492.194 181.458L482.315 181.626L490.408 187.662L486.724 196.605L495.32 191.575L503.804 196.493L500.902 187.55L509.386 180.844ZM497.218 150.495L486.836 152.116L482.482 142.838L480.026 153.01L470.258 154.742L479.301 159.773L476.901 168.883L484.994 162.847L493.702 166.703L490.129 158.152L497.218 150.495ZM481.478 121.487L471.263 124.617L465.737 115.731L464.9 126.07L455.188 129.033L464.788 132.61L463.337 142.335L470.817 135.069L479.859 138.143L475.003 130.15L481.478 121.487ZM462.165 95.1627L452.397 99.5222L445.922 91.4739L446.034 101.702L436.992 105.894L446.871 108.185L446.425 117.966L453.067 109.862L462.667 111.651L456.639 104.385L462.165 95.1627ZM439.615 71.1855L430.182 76.7187L422.87 69.6206L424.489 79.681L416.005 84.9906L426.107 85.9966L427.224 95.8893L432.582 86.9468L442.294 87.3939L435.373 81.19L439.615 71.1855ZM414.218 50.3941L405.734 56.8775L397.752 50.8971L400.32 60.5104L392.673 67.1614L402.553 66.9937L404.841 76.2716L408.916 66.9937L418.963 66.1554L410.981 60.6222L414.218 50.3941ZM386.422 32.6208L378.942 40.0543L370.346 35.3595L374.03 44.5815L367.388 51.9032L376.989 50.45L380.673 59.5043L383.296 49.7793L393.175 47.8231L384.524 43.4078L386.422 32.6208ZM356.727 18.9275L350.085 26.9199L341.043 23.3988L345.787 32.006L340.261 40.1102L349.471 37.5392L354.383 46.0905L355.499 36.0302L365.546 32.7885L356.281 29.3791L356.727 18.9275ZM325.581 8.86717L320.056 17.7538L310.343 15.2946L316.372 23.5665L311.683 32.1737L320.893 28.4849L326.419 36.2537V25.9698L335.852 21.7221L326.14 19.3188L325.581 8.86717ZM293.487 2.83096L288.798 12.1088L278.919 10.9351L286.007 18.5922L282.435 27.6465L290.919 22.784L297.729 29.8822L296.445 19.9336L305.32 14.2886L295.608 13.1149L293.487 2.83096ZM260.611 0.930664L257.094 10.5439H247.326L255.308 17.1949L252.852 26.8082L260.611 20.8278L268.369 26.8082L265.802 17.1949L273.895 10.5439H263.848L260.611 0.930664Z" fill="white"></path>
<path opacity="0.7" d="M404.899 223.941L410.248 208.75L395.957 217.655L401.042 218.615L387.978 235.116L382.104 238.958L384.647 239.394L379.474 245.767L380.877 239.045L402.269 206.829L404.987 210.758L408.845 195.304L395.518 205.345L400.603 205.868L391.661 219.314L393.853 206.392L392.801 207.353L394.642 193.995L380.263 207.702H380.439L368.34 221.496L373.863 220.972L368.077 234.767L367.288 222.719L358.959 234.418L357.819 228.481L349.928 243.323L354.75 241.664L348.876 271.785C341.424 267.157 335.813 280.865 335.725 280.865C329.062 280.865 323.801 277.809 320.733 276.499C320.558 272.658 318.716 271.174 317.489 270.475C317.489 270.475 318.366 268.816 318.366 268.729C316.612 263.491 308.283 261.046 308.283 260.697C308.283 258.514 304.426 257.728 301.269 256.07C299.516 255.109 297.236 253.625 295.571 252.665C296.097 251.18 296.623 249.783 297.061 248.387C301.532 253.101 301.708 245.855 301.883 246.029C307.582 251.792 307.231 240.442 307.406 240.529C317.752 248.561 314.245 237.648 314.42 237.823C322.311 243.236 319.681 232.235 319.944 232.322C329.325 237.823 325.292 226.473 325.467 226.56C336.251 233.37 331.517 221.409 331.517 221.409C341.336 228.044 335.725 214.25 335.725 214.25C347.649 219.314 341.161 208.575 341.161 208.575C351.156 210.059 343.353 201.852 343.791 201.852C358.608 201.503 346.947 193.122 347.561 193.034C363.167 188.756 349.84 184.478 350.016 184.391C367.814 179.327 349.753 176.272 350.279 176.01C368.866 166.93 351.419 166.231 351.506 166.057C369.041 152.175 357.117 153.397 357.117 153.397C370.093 142.047 358.959 142.746 359.046 142.571C374.038 128.602 362.641 129.999 362.641 129.999C385.348 110.355 381.14 102.148 381.14 102.148C376.055 103.633 367.989 108.609 346.772 120.832C304.864 145.627 302.146 159.596 306.267 167.716C308.809 172.954 311.702 178.367 311.702 178.454C310.3 184.216 314.42 189.367 314.42 189.367C308.722 194.78 307.669 200.717 307.494 200.717C303.9 200.717 300.656 201.59 298.551 202.289C297.236 195.915 295.746 191.637 294.957 191.201L294.08 190.677L293.203 191.114C291.275 192.249 289.346 193.122 287.592 193.907C286.54 190.939 284.874 187.709 283.209 185.002L283.384 185.177C283.209 185.002 283.033 184.74 282.946 184.566C282.595 184.042 282.157 183.431 281.893 182.907C275.318 171.295 278.737 151.215 271.636 147.46L274.266 147.111C268.567 143.27 262.781 140.912 258.485 139.865C242.09 136.198 241.476 143.706 241.476 143.706C241.213 144.055 224.643 142.484 234.024 159.421C234.024 159.421 234.374 154.881 238.67 153.31C241.827 154.445 247.788 157.326 249.367 163.612C250.419 168.065 245.684 172.867 240.424 177.145C233.848 182.208 232.358 183.78 232.533 184.042C229.815 187.185 227.887 190.939 226.484 193.907C224.643 193.122 222.626 192.249 220.61 191.026L219.733 190.59L218.856 191.114C218.067 191.55 216.577 195.828 215.262 202.202C213.07 201.416 209.914 200.63 206.319 200.63C206.231 200.63 205.267 194.78 199.48 189.28C199.393 189.28 201.234 182.47 199.743 176.621C199.743 176.446 230.604 162.39 167.041 120.832C146.526 107.474 137.758 103.633 132.936 102.148C132.936 102.148 128.816 110.355 151.348 129.999C151.172 129.999 140.301 128.777 155.118 142.571C155.205 142.833 143.895 142.135 156.959 153.397C156.959 153.397 145.035 152.175 162.57 166.057C162.745 166.231 145.298 167.017 163.797 176.01C164.323 176.272 146.175 179.327 163.973 184.391C164.236 184.478 150.909 188.756 166.603 193.034C166.953 193.122 155.381 201.59 170.285 201.852C170.636 201.852 163.008 210.059 173.003 208.575C173.003 208.575 166.515 219.314 178.351 214.25C178.351 214.25 172.74 227.957 182.472 221.409C182.472 221.409 178 233.37 188.434 226.56C188.784 226.473 184.751 237.823 194.22 232.322C194.483 232.235 191.765 243.236 199.48 237.823C199.743 237.648 196.236 248.561 206.582 240.529C206.845 240.442 206.319 251.792 212.193 246.029C212.368 245.855 212.544 253.014 216.927 248.474C217.716 250.744 218.418 253.014 219.47 255.284C218.593 255.808 217.629 256.419 216.664 256.943C213.508 258.689 209.738 259.649 209.738 261.744C209.738 262.094 201.409 264.364 199.568 269.602C199.568 269.689 200.62 271.348 200.62 271.348C199.393 272.221 197.639 273.531 197.289 276.761C194.132 278.158 189.223 280.952 182.822 280.952C182.735 280.952 177.036 266.11 168.707 278.769C167.83 278.158 167.129 277.46 166.252 276.848C168.444 276.761 170.11 275.102 170.11 272.92C170.11 271.523 169.321 270.3 168.269 269.602C170.723 266.983 174.932 264.189 181.332 262.443C190.625 259.824 187.995 253.101 194.132 248.387C194.132 248.387 185.014 245.418 176.422 252.927C176.422 252.927 178.263 247.252 177.387 243.236C176.51 240.18 178.439 237.299 179.578 236.862C179.578 236.862 167.041 234.33 162.57 262.443C160.816 262.705 159.501 264.276 159.501 266.197C159.501 267.681 160.466 268.991 161.781 269.602C161.693 270.562 161.605 271.523 161.518 272.483C161.518 272.832 155.118 269.515 156.17 262.705C156.52 262.792 156.959 262.879 157.309 262.879C159.326 262.879 161.079 261.221 161.079 259.125C161.079 257.816 160.29 256.593 159.326 255.982C159.414 255.808 159.589 255.633 159.677 255.458C160.027 254.935 163.359 248.212 162.482 239.394C162.131 235.465 160.29 233.806 162.044 228.655C162.044 228.655 154.153 238.259 152.575 241.489C150.559 245.418 149.682 248.998 149.419 252.403C149.243 252.403 149.068 252.315 148.893 252.315C148.104 252.315 147.49 252.49 146.876 252.839C146.789 251.879 146.789 250.918 146.789 249.783C148.191 249.347 149.331 247.95 149.331 246.379C149.331 244.807 148.279 243.41 146.876 242.974C149.243 240.791 152.4 236.338 152.137 226.909C152.137 226.123 152.312 217.48 154.065 214.861C154.065 214.861 142.756 218.528 141.879 229.267C141.528 229.179 141.09 229.092 140.739 229.092C139.073 229.092 137.671 230.489 137.671 232.148C137.671 233.108 138.021 233.894 138.723 234.505C138.547 234.679 137.32 235.64 137.32 236.949C137.32 236.949 133.199 232.671 140.651 222.282C140.914 221.845 145.386 216.607 143.632 204.559C143.369 203.424 141.967 199.059 144.509 195.13C144.509 195.13 137.583 196.614 136.092 204.384C136.092 204.384 135.04 199.932 132.936 197.225C132.585 196.789 131.183 194.78 131.358 191.288C131.358 191.288 124.344 196.003 126.185 211.805C126.185 211.805 121.626 208.4 119.084 207.178C116.717 206.043 115.752 205.694 114.086 202.725C114.086 202.725 111.193 221.584 127.413 229.441C128.026 230.401 129.079 230.925 130.306 230.925C130.481 230.925 130.657 230.925 130.832 230.925C131.183 231.013 131.709 231.187 132.059 231.275C132.41 231.362 132.059 233.283 133.287 235.203C133.287 235.203 130.306 231.886 122.766 231.187C121.363 230.925 118.645 230.14 115.577 226.211C115.577 226.211 111.982 234.854 121.451 239.831C121.451 239.831 115.401 241.402 111.105 238.172C111.105 238.172 113.034 253.625 134.339 252.403C134.251 252.752 134.164 253.188 134.164 253.625C134.164 255.633 135.829 257.292 137.846 257.292C139.599 257.292 141.09 255.982 141.528 254.323C142.843 255.371 143.808 256.855 143.72 259.038C143.72 259.125 137.846 256.506 129.692 257.292C129.079 257.466 117.506 257.816 115.84 254.935C115.84 254.935 115.664 261.832 122.591 263.491C122.591 263.491 119.697 266.459 113.736 266.459C113.736 266.459 119.96 275.801 140.476 269.34C140.476 269.34 140.651 269.253 140.827 269.166C141.441 269.777 142.405 270.3 143.457 270.3C145.386 270.3 146.876 268.816 147.139 266.983C150.033 266.721 153.364 267.507 156.082 271.785C156.082 271.785 155.644 271.872 154.942 271.959C154.329 270.912 153.189 270.3 151.874 270.3C149.945 270.3 148.454 271.697 148.104 273.531C147.753 273.444 147.49 273.356 147.052 273.356C145.649 273.356 144.421 274.142 143.808 275.277C140.651 276.674 137.583 278.507 135.566 280.952C134.427 282.349 133.813 285.579 126.185 289.071C126.185 289.071 133.638 292.738 143.369 289.421C143.369 289.421 136.881 296.842 140.914 309.414C140.914 309.414 143.72 304.35 149.769 301.207C151.348 300.247 155.293 296.23 156.959 288.111C157.485 288.984 158.449 289.857 159.677 290.905C160.115 291.429 154.329 299.374 165.551 300.159C166.515 300.247 169.847 306.62 173.354 302.953C173.354 303.04 173.441 303.128 173.441 303.128C173.441 303.128 180.105 301.731 183.173 297.715C187.82 304.088 191.414 311.509 190.888 318.406C190.362 322.772 189.836 327.224 193.782 327.835C195.973 328.01 201.935 314.303 184.664 293.699C184.664 292.826 184.576 291.952 184.225 290.905C183.787 289.683 196.324 285.928 202.724 284.27C202.111 285.055 201.497 285.841 201.497 286.452C201.497 286.627 205.091 287.5 206.319 287.5C206.319 287.5 205.881 288.111 205.881 288.897C205.881 288.897 212.018 290.119 219.908 286.539C221.399 285.928 224.029 285.317 226.133 282.698C227.273 281.476 233.41 278.682 235.777 278.42C235.953 278.42 236.128 278.42 236.303 278.333C236.479 278.507 236.742 278.682 236.917 278.857C237.355 281.301 238.057 284.619 238.846 284.968C239.021 285.055 238.495 287.151 239.021 289.333C232.884 294.397 219.119 307.144 217.979 321.549C217.979 322.16 221.574 321.2 223.678 320.065C223.766 319.89 221.925 324.692 223.065 330.542C223.065 330.891 226.659 329.931 228.588 328.097C228.851 327.835 227.799 334.209 230.341 339.098C230.517 339.36 234.637 337.614 236.04 336.129C236.303 335.78 236.303 344.074 240.512 348.003C240.862 348.352 244.72 345.995 247.701 341.455C247.788 341.193 250.156 348.003 256.03 351.932C256.468 352.281 262.43 348.003 266.025 340.32C266.025 339.971 270.321 345.559 274.091 346.519C274.266 346.694 276.721 344.773 278.211 337.09C278.387 336.653 280.754 339.273 283.822 339.534C284.173 339.534 286.277 335.606 286.452 329.32C286.452 328.97 289.609 331.066 293.116 330.629C293.466 330.629 294.08 324.169 292.853 319.192C292.853 318.668 295.308 320.851 298.025 320.24C298.464 320.24 297.938 302.342 275.932 286.976C276.019 286.365 276.107 285.928 276.195 285.841C276.984 285.579 277.422 281.738 277.773 278.857C278.737 277.983 279.614 277.198 280.491 276.325C281.28 276.936 282.157 277.46 283.121 277.547C285.576 277.634 290.836 280.428 291.801 281.825C294.08 284.357 297.061 285.143 298.464 285.841C306.53 289.246 312.842 288.024 312.842 287.762C312.842 286.976 312.316 286.452 312.316 286.452C313.719 286.452 317.314 285.404 317.314 285.317C317.314 285.055 317.138 284.793 316.875 284.27C323.451 285.928 335.462 289.595 335.199 290.817C334.41 293 334.673 294.746 335.287 296.23L333.709 297.802L328.01 297.715L307.319 317.009L312.579 317.097H312.755L310.738 319.716L314.333 320.589L313.807 321.637L315.648 322.859L314.596 326.264L321.259 326.002L322.662 326.526L323.977 330.367L328.711 329.32L327.922 330.978L330.377 331.851L331.254 330.105L332.656 332.55L337.04 330.542L338.531 331.764L340.459 331.153L343.791 333.336L348.35 308.715L345.194 304.612L345.457 303.215C345.632 303.302 345.807 303.302 345.807 303.302C345.807 303.302 345.807 303.215 345.895 303.04C349.139 306.882 352.646 300.334 353.698 300.247C364.833 299.635 359.046 291.603 359.572 290.992C365.972 285.754 362.816 282.873 360.712 281.65L396.833 254.149L398.061 258.689L406.478 244.807L390.696 250.569L395.518 252.752L379.299 265.062L384.822 252.839L382.543 253.974L391.31 245.069L391.398 245.244L391.485 244.894L404.812 231.449L406.653 235.902L413.404 221.147L398.324 228.568L403.321 229.965L392.976 240.616L396.395 230.14L393.59 231.973L403.058 220.099L404.899 223.941ZM388.68 208.75L389.644 209.884L386.926 212.329L388.68 208.75ZM380.789 224.552L384.384 217.48H386.225L381.228 226.211L381.491 223.854L380.789 224.552ZM380.965 207.702L385.699 207.615L380.526 217.742L380.965 207.702ZM380.614 231.1L387.891 218.266L390.17 221.06L380.088 236.076L380.614 231.1ZM140.213 245.244C140.213 245.244 137.846 237.997 138.81 235.203C138.898 235.116 138.898 234.941 138.898 234.854C139.249 235.029 139.687 235.116 140.125 235.116C140.651 235.116 141.177 234.941 141.616 234.767C141.879 237.735 142.142 242.013 140.213 245.244ZM142.317 248.736C142.756 249.172 143.457 249.609 144.071 249.783C143.983 251.355 144.071 253.188 144.421 254.236C144.509 254.149 142.317 251.792 142.317 248.736ZM147.928 259.475C148.016 259.475 148.104 259.475 148.191 259.475C148.542 259.475 148.98 259.387 149.331 259.3C149.682 261.046 150.296 262.618 150.734 264.014C150.822 264.102 149.331 262.53 147.928 259.475ZM266.638 282.698V223.155H273.477V277.547C271.373 279.38 269.093 281.039 266.638 282.698ZM260.326 286.365C259.186 286.976 257.959 287.587 256.731 288.111C255.504 287.587 254.276 286.889 253.137 286.365V223.068H260.238L260.326 286.365ZM246.912 282.785C244.457 281.214 242.177 279.468 239.986 277.634V223.242H246.912V282.785ZM233.761 271.61C231.218 268.816 228.939 265.848 226.922 262.705V223.242H233.761V271.61ZM220.522 249.347C220.259 248.474 219.996 247.601 219.645 246.728C217.103 238.521 216.314 230.489 216.226 223.155H220.522V249.347ZM279.877 223.155H286.803V262.443C284.787 265.673 282.507 268.642 279.877 271.523V223.155ZM297.324 223.155C297.324 230.401 296.36 238.434 293.992 246.64C293.729 247.601 293.466 248.474 293.028 249.434V223.242H297.324V223.155ZM220.347 194.78C239.46 204.995 252.786 194.169 256.731 190.241C258.309 191.899 261.553 194.693 266.112 196.701C271.986 199.32 281.455 201.067 293.203 194.78C294.255 198.098 296.798 207.265 297.236 218.964H216.226C216.84 207.265 219.295 198.185 220.347 194.78ZM386.751 239.831L387.102 239.918L381.754 246.029L386.751 239.831ZM378.685 248.474L379.123 248.91L378.247 249.871L378.685 248.474ZM376.581 221.933L377.896 223.242L373.775 231.449L371.759 233.457L376.581 221.933ZM374.915 248.998L376.756 251.617L357.819 273.531L374.915 248.998ZM361.063 265.411L370.794 247.863L373.249 248.037L361.063 265.411ZM373.249 243.497L375.879 238.783L377.282 240.267L373.249 243.497ZM369.918 237.561L373.074 237.473L359.572 261.919L369.918 237.561ZM362.553 235.203L360.274 241.926L359.134 235.902L362.553 235.203ZM351.331 268.292L356.679 241.664L359.66 243.672L351.331 268.292ZM352.909 270.213L364.482 235.902L366.674 237.648L352.909 270.213ZM354.838 280.166L371.32 260.959L374.301 261.919L354.926 280.166C354.926 280.166 354.926 280.166 354.838 280.166ZM358.082 280.603C357.906 280.515 357.731 280.515 357.556 280.428L375.967 263.141L377.107 266.284L358.082 280.603ZM375.967 256.943L373.951 258.078L388.768 240.966L389.995 242.974L375.967 256.943Z" fill="white"></path>
<path d="M220.348 428.216C216.351 428.216 213.088 427.171 210.558 425.081C208.028 422.991 206.469 420.113 205.883 416.446H213.143C213.473 418.39 214.279 419.893 215.563 420.956C216.883 422.02 218.423 422.551 220.183 422.551C222.126 422.551 223.703 421.91 224.913 420.626C226.159 419.343 226.783 417.363 226.783 414.686C226.783 412.083 226.178 410.121 224.968 408.801C223.794 407.445 222.218 406.766 220.238 406.766C218.954 406.766 217.799 407.041 216.773 407.591C215.746 408.141 214.976 408.911 214.463 409.901H207.973L209.898 388.066H232.063V393.731H212.813L216.333 392.741L215.233 406.326L213.033 405.941C213.913 404.585 215.049 403.503 216.443 402.696C217.836 401.89 219.596 401.486 221.723 401.486C224.253 401.486 226.453 402.036 228.323 403.136C230.229 404.236 231.714 405.776 232.778 407.756C233.878 409.7 234.428 412.046 234.428 414.796C234.428 417.62 233.841 420.04 232.668 422.056C231.494 424.036 229.863 425.558 227.773 426.621C225.683 427.685 223.208 428.216 220.348 428.216Z" fill="white"></path>
<path d="M188.02 427.666V417.216L188.35 416.116V393.511L191.1 394.721L174.82 416.556L171.685 413.971H199.625V419.636H168.605V414.191L188.24 388.066H195.335V427.666H188.02Z" fill="white"></path>
<line x1="261.93" y1="369.881" x2="261.93" y2="446.402" stroke="white" stroke-opacity="0.4" stroke-width="2.39129"></line>
<path d="M329.486 427.942C330.036 421.672 331.558 415.585 334.051 409.682C336.544 403.778 339.899 398.132 344.116 392.742L344.226 394.007H322.336V388.342H350.716V393.457C348.076 397.27 345.802 401.047 343.896 404.787C342.026 408.49 340.523 412.248 339.386 416.062C338.286 419.875 337.589 423.835 337.296 427.942H329.486Z" fill="white"></path>
<path d="M306.45 427.942V417.492L306.78 416.392V393.787L309.53 394.997L293.25 416.832L290.115 414.247H318.055V419.912H287.035V414.467L306.67 388.342H313.765V427.942H306.45Z" fill="white"></path>
</g>
<defs>

<rect width="521.329" height="523.139" fill="white" transform="translate(0.671875 0.930664)"></rect>

</defs>
</svg>
				</figure>
			</nav>
			<search data-wp-class--is-visible="callbacks.isSearchPopoverOpen">
				
			</search>
		</div>
</div>
</header>


<main>
	<div>
<p><strong>Hakeem is in your extended shutdown network</strong></p>




</div>
</main>



</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Writing FreeDOS Programs in C (118 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.freedos.org/books/cprogramming/</link>
            <guid>45790293</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 13:43:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.freedos.org/books/cprogramming/">https://www.freedos.org/books/cprogramming/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45790293">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section>




<p>Teach yourself how to write programs with the C programming language. We'll start with simple command line programs, and work our way up to writing a turn-based game.</p>

<h3>Table of Contents</h3>
<ul>
	<li><a href="https://www.freedos.org/books/cprogramming/part1/">Part 1. Let’s Learn Coding</a> (general overview)</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.freedos.org/books/cprogramming/part2/">Part 2. Introduction to C Programming</a> (<code>#include</code>, <code>#define</code>, <code>main()</code>, data types, operators, … and more)</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.freedos.org/books/cprogramming/part3/">Part 3. Flow Control</a> (flow control and loops)</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.freedos.org/books/cprogramming/part4/">Part 4. Functions</a> (user-defined, standard library, and recursion)</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.freedos.org/books/cprogramming/part5/">Part 5. Arrays</a> (fixed-size arrays, pointers, variable-sized arrays)</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.freedos.org/books/cprogramming/part6/">Part 6. Files</a> (reading and writing files)</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.freedos.org/books/cprogramming/part7/">Part 7. Advanced Programming</a> (realloc and getline)</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.freedos.org/books/cprogramming/part7.5/">Part 7½. Advanced Programming</a> (binary, iteration shorthands, …)</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.freedos.org/books/cprogramming/part8/">Part 8. Console Programming</a> (conio)</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.freedos.org/books/cprogramming/part9/">Part 9. Putting it Together</a> (writing a turn-based game)</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.freedos.org/books/cprogramming/bonus/">Bonus Programming Videos</a></li>
</ul>

<div>

<article>
<h3>This project was backed by Patreon supporters</h3>
<p>This web programming guide started out as a video series on YouTube, supported through Patreon. Patrons at the "C programming" level and above (Patreon) got access to these extras:</p>

<ul>
	<li>Early access to the "C programming" videos</li>
	<li>Exclusive access to the rest of the "programming guide" with more detail and information that didn't make it into the videos</li>
	<li>A weekly Patreon forum to ask questions about that week's "C programming" topics (if you were following along with the videos and need help, this was the place to ask)</li>
	<li>After the video series was finished, I edited the programming guide into a "teach yourself programming" book, via publishing partner Lulu. Patrons could purchase the book at cost.</li>
</ul>
</article>

<article>
<h3>Thanks to our supporters on Patreon</h3>
<p>I'd like to thank everyone who supported this project on Patreon, including Jason Pittman, Alexander Shendi, Gustavo Pezzi, Scott Bollinger, Ryan Harris, Rafael Campos, K MI, Nikola Markovic BGD, Wade Brainerd, Mike Garcia, Philip Espi, Vlastimil Holer, Dan Mons, Stephen Smoogen, Bill Marshall, Patater, Brett Owen, Ronald Eichler, Tom Dison, Joe Walker, Magnus Wild, Kwang Lee, Mitchel Valentino, TheGreatCodeholio, Bérenger Doneux, Daniel Monteiro, Mark Eichin, Sparheld International GmbH, Hallmentum LLC, Eric LeBlanc, Luke Abbott, John Paul Wohlscheid, Sean Dobes, Tom Dearden, Eric Smith, SuperIlu, and Dwayne.</p>
<nav><a href="https://www.freedos.org/patreon/">Jim's Patreon</a></nav>
</article>

</div>

<p>Published under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0) license.</p>

</section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[X.org Security Advisory: multiple security issues X.Org X server and Xwayland (179 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/2025-October/003635.html</link>
            <guid>45790015</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 13:07:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/2025-October/003635.html">https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/2025-October/003635.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45790015">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
   
    <b>Olivier Fourdan</b> 
    <a href="mailto:xorg-announce%40lists.x.org?Subject=Re%3A%20X.Org%20Security%20Advisory%3A%20multiple%20security%20issues%20X.Org%20X%20server%20and%0A%20Xwayland&amp;In-Reply-To=%3C56a279d8-697f-44fd-8c58-6ed912d03417%40redhat.com%3E" title="X.Org Security Advisory: multiple security issues X.Org X server and Xwayland">ofourdan at redhat.com
       </a><br>
    <i>Tue Oct 28 13:22:18 UTC 2025</i>
    <ul>
        <li>Previous message (by thread): <a href="https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/2025-October/003634.html">[ANNOUNCE] libdrm 2.4.127
</a></li>
        <li>Next message (by thread): <a href="https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/2025-October/003636.html">[ANNOUNCE] xorg-server 21.1.19
</a></li>
         <li> <b>Messages sorted by:</b> 
              <a href="https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/2025-October/date.html#3635">[ date ]</a>
              <a href="https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/2025-October/thread.html#3635">[ thread ]</a>
              <a href="https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/2025-October/subject.html#3635">[ subject ]</a>
              <a href="https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/2025-October/author.html#3635">[ author ]</a>
         </li>
       </ul>
    <hr>  
<!--beginarticle-->
<pre>======================================================================
X.Org Security Advisory: October 28, 2025

Issues in X.Org X server prior to 21.1.18 and Xwayland prior to 24.1.8
======================================================================

Multiple issues have been found in the X server and Xwayland implementations
published by X.Org for which we are releasing security fixes for in
xorg-server-21.1.19 and xwayland-24.1.9.

1) CVE-2025-62229: Use-after-free in XPresentNotify structures creation

    Using the X11 Present extension, when processing and adding the
    notifications after presenting a pixmap, if an error occurs, a dangling
    pointer may be left in the error code path of the function causing a
    use-after-free when eventually destroying the notification structures
    later.

    Introduced in: Xorg 1.15
    Fixed in: xorg-server-21.1.19 and xwayland-24.1.9
    Fix: <a href="https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/xorg/xserver/-/commit/5a4286b1">https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/xorg/xserver/-/commit/5a4286b1</a>
    Found by: Jan-Niklas Sohn working with Trend Micro Zero Day Initiative.

2) CVE-2025-62230: Use-after-free in Xkb client resource removal

    When removing the Xkb resources for a client, the function
    XkbRemoveResourceClient() will free the XkbInterest data associated
    with the device, but not the resource associated with it.

    As a result, when the client terminates, the resource delete function
    triggers a use-after-free.

    Introduced in: X11R6
    Fixed in: xorg-server-21.1.19 and xwayland-24.1.9
    Fix: <a href="https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/xorg/xserver/-/commit/99790a2c">https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/xorg/xserver/-/commit/99790a2c</a>
         <a href="https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/xorg/xserver/-/commit/10c94238">https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/xorg/xserver/-/commit/10c94238</a>
    Found by: Jan-Niklas Sohn working with Trend Micro Zero Day Initiative.

3) CVE-2025-62231: Value overflow in Xkb extension XkbSetCompatMap()

    The XkbCompatMap structure stores some of its values using an unsigned
    short, but fails to check whether the sum of the input data might
    overflow the maximum unsigned short value.

    Introduced in: X11R6
    Fixed in: xorg-server-21.1.19 and xwayland-24.1.9
    Fix: <a href="https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/xorg/xserver/-/commit/475d9f49">https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/xorg/xserver/-/commit/475d9f49</a>
    Found by: Jan-Niklas Sohn working with Trend Micro Zero Day Initiative.
   
------------------------------------------------------------------------

X.Org thanks all of those who reported and fixed these issues, and those
who helped with the review and release of this advisory and these fixes.
-------------- next part --------------
A non-text attachment was scrubbed...
Name: OpenPGP_0x14706DBE1E4B4540.asc
Type: application/pgp-keys
Size: 2988 bytes
Desc: OpenPGP public key
URL: &lt;<a href="https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/attachments/20251028/ff11c77e/attachment.key">https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/attachments/20251028/ff11c77e/attachment.key</a>&gt;
-------------- next part --------------
A non-text attachment was scrubbed...
Name: OpenPGP_signature.asc
Type: application/pgp-signature
Size: 203 bytes
Desc: OpenPGP digital signature
URL: &lt;<a href="https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/attachments/20251028/ff11c77e/attachment.sig">https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/attachments/20251028/ff11c77e/attachment.sig</a>&gt;
</pre>


<!--endarticle-->
    <hr>
    <ul>
        <!--threads-->
	<li>Previous message (by thread): <a href="https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/2025-October/003634.html">[ANNOUNCE] libdrm 2.4.127
</a></li>
	<li>Next message (by thread): <a href="https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/2025-October/003636.html">[ANNOUNCE] xorg-server 21.1.19
</a></li>
         <li> <b>Messages sorted by:</b> 
              <a href="https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/2025-October/date.html#3635">[ date ]</a>
              <a href="https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/2025-October/thread.html#3635">[ thread ]</a>
              <a href="https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/2025-October/subject.html#3635">[ subject ]</a>
              <a href="https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/2025-October/author.html#3635">[ author ]</a>
         </li>
       </ul>

<hr>
<a href="https://lists.x.org/mailman/listinfo/xorg-announce">More information about the xorg-announce
mailing list</a><br>

</div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>