<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 23:30:02 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[LA wildfires force thousands to evacuate, NASA JPL closed (127 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theregister.com/2025/01/08/los_angeles_fires_jpl/</link>
            <guid>42638735</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 21:40:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/01/08/los_angeles_fires_jpl/">https://www.theregister.com/2025/01/08/los_angeles_fires_jpl/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42638735">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="body">
<p>With several major wildfires raging out of control in Los Angeles County, fire crews are risking their lives to protect people, homes, and a key NASA facility.</p>
<p>At the time of the writing, about 70,000 people were told to evacuate their homes as the fires erupted after a dry winter, and hurricane-force winds howling across Southern California spread the flames <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.nbclosangeles.com/news/california-wildfires/map-la-county-wildfires-palisades-eaton-hurst/3597500/">over thousands of acres</a>. Some 400,000 residents are without power, and water pressure needed to fight the blazes is reportedly failing, with hydrants said to be running dry.</p>
<p>Two people so far are reported dead, more than 1,000 structures have been destroyed, and California Governor Gavin Newsom has declared a state of emergency. The National Guard - along with thousands of firefighters (many of them prisoners <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.davispoliticalreview.com/article/the-use-of-inmate-firefighters-and-its-injustices">working</a> for $10 a day or less) - have been deployed to help tackle the conflagration.</p>

    

<p>"This is a highly dangerous windstorm that’s creating extreme fire risk – and we’re not out of the woods. We’re already seeing the destructive impacts with this fire in Pacific Palisades that grew rapidly in a matter of minutes," Newsom <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.gov.ca.gov/2025/01/07/governor-newsom-proclaims-state-of-emergency-meets-with-first-responders-in-pacific-palisades-amid-dangerous-fire-weather/">said</a>.</p>

        


        

<p>"Our deepest thanks go to our expert firefighters and first responders who jumped quickly into fighting this dangerous fire."</p>
<p>A crew has been deployed to protect NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory, which houses top science talent - not to mention the primary control stations for the agency's Mars and outer space hardware. The site is on emergency lockdown and several staff report losing their homes to wildfire.</p>

        

<p>"JPL is closed except for emergency personnel," <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://x.com/LaurieofMars/status/1877033688539468061">tweeted</a> the site's director Laurie Leshin. "No fire damage so far (some wind damage) but it is very close to the lab. Hundreds of JPLers have been evacuated from their homes &amp; many have lost homes. Special thx to our emergency crews. Pls keep us in your thoughts &amp; stay safe."</p>
<ul>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/12/16/fossil_fuels_wildfires/">Shame about those wildfires. We'll just let the fossil fuel giants off the hook, then?</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/08/18/ai_maui_fire_book/">'AI-written history' of Maui wildfire becomes Amazon bestseller, fuels conspiracies</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2022/10/20/california_wildfires_co2e/">California wildfires hit CTRL+Z on 18 years of CO2e removal</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/11/28/voyager_engineer_feature/">'Best job at JPL': What it's like to be an engineer on the Voyager project</a></li>
</ul>
<p>"My heart goes out to those affected by the Palisades Fire in Southern California," <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://x.com/SenBillNelson/status/1877023652501151950">said</a> NASA Administrator Bill Nelson. "Many in our NASA family, including our teams at Armstrong and JPL, are affected. Grace and I are praying for their safety and the safety of the first responders battling the blaze."</p>
<p>Should the worst happen to JPL, NASA has backup plans in place. Control of the Mars rovers and spacecraft will be shifted to the Goldstone Deep Space Network just north of Barstow, California. But generations of scientific data and hardware could be lost.</p>
<p>With the fires <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cnn.com/weather/live-news/los-angeles-pacific-palisades-eaton-wildfires-01-08-25/index.html">still largely unconfined</a>, and no sign of letup from the winds spreading the blazes, the loss of JPL is looking increasingly likely. ®</p>                                
                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I had to take down my course-swapping site or be expelled (132 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.linkedin.com/posts/jdkaim_github-jdkaimhuskyswap-huskyswap-project-activity-7282609173316415488-1jdb</link>
            <guid>42638626</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 21:27:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/jdkaim_github-jdkaimhuskyswap-huskyswap-project-activity-7282609173316415488-1jdb">https://www.linkedin.com/posts/jdkaim_github-jdkaimhuskyswap-huskyswap-project-activity-7282609173316415488-1jdb</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42638626">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main-content" role="main">
      <section>
              <h2>                  JD Kaim’s Post</h2>

                
    

    
      

    <article data-activity-urn="urn:li:activity:7282609173316415488" data-featured-activity-urn="urn:li:activity:7282609173316415488" data-attributed-urn="urn:li:share:7282609172460793856">
<!---->
      
              
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    

    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    

    
    

<!---->  
        

      <div data-test-id="main-feed-activity-card__entity-lockup">
          <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jdkaim?trk=public_post_feed-actor-image" data-tracking-control-name="public_post_feed-actor-image" data-tracking-will-navigate="">
            
      
  
<!---->          </a>
      <div>
        

            <p>
<!---->                CS @ UW | Prev @ GitHub
            </p>

            <p><span>
                <time>
                  

    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    

    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    

      19h
  
<!---->                </time>
<!---->            </span>
                </p></div>

<!---->    </div>

      
            
            
  <p dir="ltr" data-test-id="main-feed-activity-card__commentary">Welp, looks I might be getting expelled from the University of Washington.
&nbsp;
As many of you know, last quarter I built an initial version of HuskySwap for a class project. It was a simple app designed to help students find partners to trade spots in critical classes after they filled up. I’m sure other people have pursued this kind of thing before, but there’s no go-to solution at UW and I wanted to contribute something cool for everyone.
&nbsp;
At first it was a fun project to catch up to the latest versions of .NET and Angular with some practice implementing features around database abstraction, real-time chat, and the full stack challenges associated with things like role-based permissions. I was probably going to build it anyway, so it was great that I could actually get course credit for CSE 403.
&nbsp;
I was really proud of the MVP and excited that the people I demoed it for actually wanted to use it. So I set aside some time in my winter quarter schedule to start hardening it so I could launch ahead of spring quarter registration.
&nbsp;
Then I came across the swagger docs for integrating with the registration system. The site says:
&nbsp;
“The Student Web Service gives your application access to information in the Student database such as course data, registration data, section data, person data, and term data (general academic data).”
&nbsp;
I got excited because it sounded like they were supportive of scenarios like mine. After all, UW aspires to be top ranked in both CS and business. Of course they would F/foster :P an entrepreneurial spirit!
&nbsp;
I reached out to request an access token. I wasn’t too ambitious up front; all I wanted was read-only access to automate the course catalog import instead of having to manually enter every class. But if things went well it would be awesome to automate the process further or even find other gaps I could fill to improve the community experience.
&nbsp;
Several hours later I received an unambiguous response: a “Notice of Violation of Registration Tampering Abuse Policy”. I was instructed to take down my demo site (and its handful of fake demo classes) or else they would begin the process that would culminate with my expulsion. I had originally reached out hoping to make the school experience better for everyone and they immediately went nuclear.
&nbsp;
I’m not too worried about the threat since taking down the demo site is no big deal. But I’m a little heartbroken to see how the school views me. I thought they’d be excited about what I was pursuing—or at least that I was pursuing anything—but instead they’d rather have me simply leave.
&nbsp;
I’m scheduled to graduate in a few months and am eager to move on to projects that don’t need to be cleared with the UW Registrar. If you know of anyone looking for a full-time software engineer with a knack for getting the attention of senior leadership, please send them my way! I can start full-time in June.
&nbsp;
Link to repo: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/redir/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Flnkd%2Ein%2FgXKEBtQi&amp;urlhash=Q6nu&amp;trk=public_post-text" target="_self" rel="nofollow" data-tracking-control-name="public_post-text" data-tracking-will-navigate="">https://lnkd.in/gXKEBtQi</a></p>



        

        
            
      
<!---->      
    
    
    

    
      <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/redir/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fgithub%2Ecom%2FJDKaim%2FHuskySwap&amp;urlhash=IUnT&amp;trk=public_post_feed-article-content" target="_self" data-tracking-control-name="public_post_feed-article-content" data-tracking-will-navigate="" data-test-id="article-content">
        

      
<!---->      <section>
        <header>
            

            <h3 data-test-id="article-content__subtitle">
                github.com
            </h3>
        </header>
<!---->      </section>
    
      </a>
  
  
  
      
  
                  

      
          
        

      
          
        

      
            
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    

    
    

      
  
  
        

      
                
    
    
    

    
  
                      

      
              
            

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    

      
  
  
            

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    

      
  
  
            

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    

      
  
  
            

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    

      
  
  
            

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    

      
  
  
            

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    

      
  
  
            

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    

      
  
  
            

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    

      
  
  
            

    
    
    
    
    
    

<!---->
    

    
    

      
  
  
              <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/signup/cold-join?session_redirect=https%3A%2F%2Fwww%2Elinkedin%2Ecom%2Fposts%2Fjdkaim_github-jdkaimhuskyswap-huskyswap-project-activity-7282609173316415488-1jdb&amp;trk=public_post_see-more-comments" data-test-id="main-feed-activity-card-with-comments__see-more-comments" data-tracking-control-name="public_post_see-more-comments" data-tracking-will-navigate="">
                See more comments
              </a>
      
        

      
              

    
    
    
    
    
    

    
  
        
    </article>
  
      
  
  
            </section>
      <section>

            <h2>
              Explore topics
            </h2>

<!---->
        
      </section>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Facebook is removing stories about pornographic ads (187 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.404media.co/facebook-is-censoring-404-media-stories-about-facebooks-censorship/</link>
            <guid>42637267</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 18:55:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.404media.co/facebook-is-censoring-404-media-stories-about-facebooks-censorship/">https://www.404media.co/facebook-is-censoring-404-media-stories-about-facebooks-censorship/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42637267">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
  
<!--kg-card-begin: html-->

<!--kg-card-end: html-->
<p>In early December I got the kind of tip we’ve been getting a lot over the past year. A reader had noticed a post from someone on Reddit complaining about a very graphic sexual ad appearing in their Instagram Reels. I’ve seen a lot of ads for scams or shady dating sites recently, and some of them were pretty suggestive, to put it mildly, but the ad the person on Reddit complained about was straight up a close up image of a vagina.&nbsp;</p><p>The reader who tipped 404 Media did exactly what I would have done, which is look up the advertiser in Facebook’s Ad Library, and found that the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/ads/library/?active_status=all&amp;ad_type=all&amp;country=ALL&amp;is_targeted_country=false&amp;media_type=all&amp;search_type=page&amp;view_all_page_id=450572341476695"><u>same advertiser</u></a> was running around 800 ads across all of Meta’s platforms in November, the vast majority of which are just different close-up images of vaginas. When clicked, the ad takes users to a variety of sites for "confidential dating” or “hot dates” in your area. Facebook started to remove some of these ads on December 13, but at the time of writing, most of them were still undetected by its moderators according to the Ad Library.</p><p>Like I said, we get a lot of tips like this these days. We get so many, in fact, that we don’t write stories about them unless there’s something novel or that our readers need to know about them. Facebook taking money to put explicit porn in its ads despite it being a clear violation of its own policies is not new, but definitely a new low for the company and a clear indicator of <a href="https://www.404media.co/has-facebook-stopped-trying/"><u>Facebook’s “fuck it” approach</u></a> to content moderation, and moderation of its ads specifically.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
</div><div>
  <div>
    <h2>This post is for paid members only</h2>
    <p>Become a paid member for unlimited ad-free access to articles, bonus podcast content, and more.</p>
    <p><a href="https://www.404media.co/membership/">Subscribe</a>
  </p></div>
  <div>
    <h2>Sign up for free access to this post</h2>
    <p>Free members get access to posts like this one along with an email round-up of our week's stories.</p>
    <p><a href="https://www.404media.co/signup/">Subscribe</a>
  </p></div>
  <p>Already have an account? <a href="https://www.404media.co/signin/" data-portal="signin">Sign in</a></p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[NeuralSVG: An Implicit Representation for Text-to-Vector Generation (285 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://sagipolaczek.github.io/NeuralSVG/</link>
            <guid>42636873</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 18:16:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://sagipolaczek.github.io/NeuralSVG/">https://sagipolaczek.github.io/NeuralSVG/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42636873">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">




<div>
                    

                    
                                        
                    <p><span>1 - Tel Aviv University</span>
                    </p>
                    <p><span>2 - MIT CSAIL</span>
                    </p>
                                                    
                    

                </div>

<section>
    <!-- <div class="hero-body"> -->
    <div>
                            <p><img src="https://sagipolaczek.github.io/NeuralSVG/static/figures_nsvg/teaser-1.png" alt="NeTI"></p><h2>
                                NeuralSVG generates vector graphics from text prompts with ordered and editable shapes. 
                                Our method supports dynamic conditioning, such as background color, which facilitating the generation 
                                of multiple color palettes for a single learned representation.
                            </h2>
                        </div>

    <div>
                    <!-- div class="item">
                      <p style="margin-bottom: 30px">
                    <video poster="" id="tree" autoplay controls muted loop height="100%">
                      <source src="static/figures/video.mp4"
                      type="video/mp4">
                    </video>
                    </p>
                    </div -->
                    <h2>Abstract</h2>
                    <p>
                            Vector graphics are essential in design, providing artists with a versatile medium for creating resolution-independent
                             and highly editable visual content. Recent advancements in vision-language and diffusion models have fueled interest 
                             in text-to-vector graphics generation. However, existing approaches often suffer from over-parameterized outputs or 
                             treat the layered structure --- a core feature of vector graphics --- as a secondary goal, diminishing their practical 
                             use. Recognizing the importance of layered SVG representations, we propose NeuralSVG, an implicit neural representation
                              for generating vector graphics from text prompts. Inspired by Neural Radiance Fields (NeRFs), NeuralSVG encodes the 
                              entire scene into the weights of a small MLP network, optimized using Score Distillation Sampling (SDS). To encourage 
                              a layered structure in the generated SVG, we introduce a dropout-based regularization technique that strengthens the 
                              standalone meaning of each shape. We additionally demonstrate that utilizing a neural representation provides an added 
                              benefit of inference-time control, enabling users to dynamically adapt the generated SVG based on user-provided inputs, 
                              all with a single learned representation. Through extensive qualitative and quantitative evaluations, we demonstrate that 
                              NeuralSVG outperforms existing methods in generating structured and flexible SVG.
                        </p>
                </div>

    <!-- <section class="hero is-small">
      <div class="hero-body">
        <div class="container">
          <h2 class="title has-text-centered">Video</h2>
          <center>
            <iframe width="630" height="354" src="" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" 
            allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" 
            allowfullscreen></iframe>
          </center>
        </div>
      </div>
    </section> -->

    <div>
                <h2>Examples of Text-to-Vector Generation <br> with NeuralSVG
                </h2>
                
            </div>

    <div>
                    <h2>How Does it Work?</h2>
                    
                    <p><img src="https://sagipolaczek.github.io/NeuralSVG/static/figures_nsvg/method.png" alt="neuralsvg">
                    </p>
                    <ul>
                      <li> We learn an implicit neural representation for generating vector graphics from text prompts. We encode the SVG into the weights of a small MLP network, optimized using an Score Distillation Sampling (SDS).
                      </li>
                      <br>
                      <li> To promote an ordered representation, we use a dropout-based technique to encourages each learned shape to have a meaningful and ordered role in the overall scene.
                      </li>
                      <br>
                      <li> Our neural representation enables inference-time control over the generated asset such as dynamically adjusting the color palette or aspect ratio of the generated SVG, all with a single learned representation.
                      </li>
                      <br>
                    </ul>
                </div>

    <div>
            <div>
                    <h2>What Can it Do?</h2>
                    
                    <h3>Encouraging Ordered Representation with Nested Dropout</h3>
                    <p>
                        We show results generated by our method when keeping a varying number of learned shapes in the final rendering. Even with a small number of shapes, our approach effectively captures the coarse structure of the scene.
                    </p>
                </div>
            

            <div>
                  
                  <h3>Color Palette Control</h3>
                  <p> 
                    Given a learned representation, we render the result using different background colors specified by the user, resulting in varying color palettes in the resulting SVGs. The upper row shows colors observed during training while the bottom row shows unobserved (generalized) colors.
                  </p>
              </div>
          

          <div>
                
                <h3>Aspect Ratio Control</h3>
                <p>
                    We present results from optimizing NeuralSVG with aspect ratios of 1:1 and 4:1. In each pair, the left image displays the generated SVG with a 1:1 aspect ratio (square format), while the right image shows the model's output with a 4:1 aspect ratio.
                </p>
            </div>
        

          <div>
                
                <h3>Sketch Generation</h3>
                <p>
                    NeuralSVG generates sketches with varying numbers of strokes using a single network, without any modifications to the framework.
                </p>
            </div>
        

        </div>


    



</section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Bringing SerenityOS to real hardware, one driver at a time (169 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/</link>
            <guid>42636086</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 16:54:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/">https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42636086">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><h3>Bringing SerenityOS to real hardware, one driver at a time</h3>
<p><img src="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/img/cover.png" alt="cover image. the serenityos logo is in the middle, with more colorful squiggly lines around it. the whole image is purposefully pixelated, and the palette used has maybe 8 colors tops.">
<small>img by <a href="https://mastodon.catgirl.cloud/@multisn8">Multisn8</a>, derivative of <a href="https://github.com/SerenityOS/artwork/blob/master/images/ladyball_vector/shaded.svg">the ladyball logo</a> by frhun. Licensed under CC BY-SA 4.0</small></p><hr>

<p>Many moons ago, around the time when Andreas formally resigned from being Serenity's BDFL, I decided that I want to get involved in the project more seriously. Looking at it from a perspective of "what do I <i>not</i> like about this (codebase)", the first thing that came to mind was that it runs HERE <b>points at QEMU</b> and not THERE <b>points at real hardware</b>. Obvious oversight, let's fix it.</p>

<hr>

<p>First thing I looked at was UEFI support, but there's an ongoing effort by spholz which I didn't want to hijack. For my purposes, kernel from the master branch successfully boots from GRUB running on a TianoCore UEFI runtime, so this is <i>fine</i>.</p>

<p>Debugging the OS on the same machine as your main isn't fun, and I wanted to focus my efforts on porting it to something I'd actually want to daily drive - which limited me to recent-ish hardware. I went onto Allegro (polish online auction site) and searched for the cheapest Chromebook I could find. After discarding the literal <i>cheapest</i> option (due to it being a fire hazard), I ended up with a Dell 3100 (baseboard Octopus, model Fleex) for a whopping 95PLN (~25EUR). The specs are as follows:</p>

<ul>
	<li>Intel Celeron N4020 (2 cores, no HT)</li>
	<li>4GB of DDR4</li>
	<li>32GB of eMMC on-board storage</li>
	<li>1366x768 TN screen driven by the UHD600 IGP</li>
	<li>2x USB-A, 2x USB-C, 3.5mm jack</li>
	<li>a keyboard that's somehow better than Dell's top-end business laptops</li>
</ul>
<p>(<i>note: starting here, i'll refer to this laptop simply as <span>octopus</span>, lowercase. it's a cute hostname</i>)</p>

<p>I had a few reasons for picking a Chromebook. The most notable one is that Cr50, the security chip / embedded controller, gives literal superpowers with regards to closed-case debugging <small>(foreshadowing...)</small>. Chromebooks are also plentiful and cheap, so not only is it easy to replace mine if I break it, it's also an easily obtainable target for others.</p>

<h3>cros_ec woes</h3>

<div><p><img src="https://sdomi.pl/img/haruhi.jpg"></p><h3>Haruhi says...</h3><p><span>"This post goes off-the-rails quite quickly. Next section isn't about Serenity directly, rather about prep work and cursed hardware hacks that ensued.<p>Feel free to <a href="#serenity">skip</a> ahead if this doesn't interest you...<br>But we all know this is exactly what you came here for. Strap on."</p></span></p></div>
<p>For the uninitiated, almost all chromebooks from ~2018 onwards have one USB-C port that, with a SuzyQ cable, can be used for debugging. Cr50 exposes three ttyUSB devices:</p>

<ul>
	<li>internal Cr50 console</li>
	<li>AP console (aka: chromebook's serial port)</li>
	<li>cros_ec console (aka: the embedded controller)</li>
</ul>
<p>The general idea was to use this to get easy, portable access to the serial console without needing to keep the laptop open with wires hanging off it. cros_ec can also do some cool stuff such as emulating keypresses and controlling the power state, so a "KVM" solution wasn't out of the question.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, reality had different plans:</p>

<p><img src="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/img/1.png" alt="IM screenshot. I'm talking with Alicja, who tells me that fleex, my laptop, is missing some resistors for SuzyQ. I'm responding with a mix of bargaining, sadness and anger.">
	<small>Picture 1 - my disappointment was immense and my day was ruined</small>
</p>

<p>I made a new SuzyQ cable to check if my old one broke. I triple-checked it with another chromebook to verify that it's really soldered correctly. Then I went to ask others, and I learned that octopus is one of the few laptops where Cr50 <i>doesn't</i> work for CCD; Dell cheaped out and didn't include a few resistors on the board. Some have reported limited success, but only under specific constraints ("debug works only in the left port, upside down, and the right port has to have a charger connected"), but I wasn't able to get this working <i>at all</i>. I shelved the project for the rest of the day out of pure disappointment.</p>

<h3>Alternatives</h3>

<p>Well, I already have the device, and I kinda started to like it.<br>
Can I do <b>anything</b> to make it useful?</p>

<p><img src="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/img/2.jpg">
<small>Picture 2 - lots of test pads. sadly, none of them relevant</small></p><p>I spent some time poking around the Nuvoton and H1B2C chips (first one implements the EC, second one the Cr50 debug bridge). As far as I understood the scraps of knowledge around the web, bridging <i>something</i> here would make it talk over USB, but I didn't figure anything out. At a few points octopus stopped turning on, but thankfully there was no permanent damage - this laptop is a heavy, stable cookie. Of note: my current sources tell me that the missing resistors are only supposed to affect SPI flashing, not the USB bridge itself - therefore it is unknown why I couldn't (and still can't) get Cr50 debug to work at all.</p>

<hr>

<p>Out of options and desperate for answers, <strike>I booked a flight to Japan</strike> I checked whether a generic Pi Pico board could fit inside the empty space inside the laptop. And, yes, quite easily!</p>

<p><img src="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/img/3.jpg" alt="Pi Pico board laid down on top of another PCB in the case"><img src="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/img/4.jpg" alt="Same thing, but the lower PCB is chomped off. Pi Pico now lays flush.">
<small>Pictures 3, 4 - this would be a perfect place if not for that daughterboard... <b>CHOMP</b></small></p><p>I found some schematics for similar laptops online, but none for <i>exactly</i> octopus. My board had two big debug ports - one of them turned out to be some Intel crap, containing an underdocumented JTAG and a bunch of test points irrelevant for my purposes. The other one was Google Servo, which is equally hard to search for due to name reuse - Google churned out a bunch of different debug probes under the name "Servo", gave them really confusing names and published little to no docs about them, beyond <a href="https://chromium.googlesource.com/chromiumos/third_party/hdctools/+/HEAD/docs/servo.md">one docs page</a>.</p>

<p><img src="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/img/5.jpg" alt="Screenshot of a technical drawing of the Google Servo connector">
<small>Picture 5 - presumed pinout, found in some leaked schematics</small></p><p>In the end, I took my <a href="https://glasgow-embedded.org/">Glasgow</a>, launched the UART applet with frequency detection, and started probing. The procedure was literally to slowly tap a male end of a dupont-style cable to the suspected UART TX, while Linux was sending a bunch of <span>meow</span>s in a loop to <span>/dev/ttyS1</span>.</p>

<p><img src="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/img/6.jpg" alt="board from octopus is laid out belly-up, still connected to power and a wifi antenna">
<small>Picture 6 - the 4W TDP means that not only is this Celeron passively cooled - it barely gets warm without a heatsink. In this picture, octopus is turned on, and it's still just 37°C CPU die</small></p><p>Finding the proper TX pad took me maybe a few minutes of probing. Doing the same for RX was a bit tougher: you need to be actively transmitting, and if you hit the wrong line, you're at risk of resetting the board. Exactly that has happened two times before I found the pin - luckily, no permanent harm was done.</p>

<p><img src="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/img/7.png" alt="IM screenshot. I pasted a terminal screenshot of my contraption communicating through serial. I labelled the picture 'Bonjour'">
	<small>Picture 7 - Top terminal is on a Pi Pico, bottom terminal is octopus' serial port over SSH</small>
</p>

<p>Hooray, we have both pins! I looked for two more RX/TX pins for the EC; Surprisingly, through cross-referencing pinouts I found with what I already soldered onto, it took me maybe ten minutes to find those, too. Now, onto soldering:</p>

<p><img src="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/img/8.jpg" alt="some shoddy soldering to the servo port. 5 cables in total, 4 red, one blue.">
<small>Picture 8 - after seeing this, WeirdTreeThing was flabbergasted that I was able to solder to a pitch this small</small></p><p>Thankfully, I didn't lift any pads! I used some epoxy to secure all the wires so they wouldn't lift; deciding against kapton tape or hot glue was instrumental for longevity of those connections, and I'm happy to report that in the past 6 months I haven't had a single problem with those hacky connections.</p>

<p><img src="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/img/9.jpg" alt="more shoddy soldering, this time to a flash chip on the opposite side of the board. all the cables are nicely attached to the board with epoxy">
<small>Picture 9 - UV-cure epoxy changed my life. Also visible: Bringus-inspired<br>method of asserting dominance in the Write-Protect realm: Just Bridge It(tm)</small></p><p>RP2040 can also use SPI peripherals, and comparing to the Servo connector, soldering 6 cables to the flash chip was a walk in the park. I did a small hack with cutting the trace going to the write-protect pin and bridging it to ground. This gave me full write access without needing to ask the Cr50 security chip for permission.</p>

<p><img src="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/img/10.jpg" alt="rat's nest of cables. oh god what happened here">
<small>Picture 10 - it's not the prettiest, but who's checking</small>

<img src="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/img/11.jpg" alt="nice end result, showcasing an additional cable now sticking out of the laptop">
<small>Picture 11 - end result; I cut an additional hole in the side of the case</small></p><p>On the software side of things, I chose CircuitPython (because it exposes USB mass storage for script/data upload). Bridging an UART to the cdc_acm usb device was trivial, but since I hooked up the SPI flash too, it would be neat to be able to flash it, too - and that's more complicated.</p>

<p>In the OSS realm, EEPROM flashing (especially SPI) is usually done through <a href="https://flashrom.org/">flashrom</a>. It supports quite a bunch of different flashing methods; The one most relevant to me was <a href="https://www.flashrom.org/supported_hw/supported_prog/serprog/overview.html">serprog</a>, which is a light protocol to proxy SPI over UART. There already was an <a href="https://github.com/stacksmashing/pico-serprog">impl for the Pico</a> written by stacksmashing in C, but using that one would require me to reflash the pico every time I wanted to flash the BIOS...</p>

<p>So instead I wrote an implementation in CircuitPython. I based it heavily on <a href="https://github.com/GlasgowEmbedded/glasgow/blob/main/software/glasgow/applet/interface/spi_flashrom/__init__.py">the serprog Glasgow applet</a>, because even though it's Amaranth, it was the clearest, easiest to understand implementation I found - and parts of it I could copy 1:1.</p>

<p><img src="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/img/12.png" alt="terminal screenshot. i'm running flashrom -p serprog:dev=/dev/ttyACM1; the output says that Programmer name is PicoCCD, meow~!"></p><hr>
<p><img src="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/img/13.png" alt="terminal screenshot. first successful read from serprog">
<small>Pictures 12, 13 - first signs of life, and first successful read</small>Sometime after the 1st flash, I randomly noticed how the datasheet said (in very big letters) that my chip was 1.8V. I... somehow never noticed that, and used 3.3V for it. Regardless, it was already soldered, glued, closed in the case... The mistake lives to this day (and hasn't caused any harm... so far).</p>

<p><img src="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/img/14.png" alt="IM screenshot. i pasted a screenshot from the datasheet, which clearly says that my SPI flash chip is 1.8V. I comment 'hey did you know this also works with 3.3?'">
	<small>Picture 14 - Oops?</small>
</p>

<p>All of my code is consolidated into PicoCCD, a quick-and-dirty closed-case-debug solution. The <a href="https://git.sakamoto.pl/domi/PicoCCD">repo is on my Forgejo</a>.</p>

<p><img src="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/img/lell.jpg" alt="a 'lell' laptop, booting modified coreboot with a blobcat in the middle">
<small>Picture 15 - <a href="https://donotsta.re/notice/Aj479A11wZbCQnp452">"i don't need anything else here, it's already perfect"</a></small></p><h3 id="serenity">Finally, time for SerenityOS</h3>

<p>For debugging purposes, I set up Alpine Linux with a bunch of basic utilities for fetching an externally-built SerenityOS kernel. Over time, this grew into a bigger contraption, which notably includes a GRUB entry that automatically downloads artifacts from my build machine, decompresses and overwrites the Kernel, and unpacks a .tar with the userspace. At the time of writing, iteration time (between making a change and testing a change) is around 20 seconds, which is quite respectable for hacking on baremetal.</p>

<p>Anyhoo, first test run: I prepared a GRUB boot entry (that essentially boiled down to <span>multiboot /Kernel serial_debug</span>), eagerly waited for it to show something, and... nothing. Neither on the screen, nor on the serial port. What gives?</p>

<p>Lack of any output on the screen lead me to some StackExchange post which suggested adding <span>insmod all_video</span> to the boot entry. It didn't fix anything by itself (some kernel fixes were still necessary), but it was the right call anyways. Moving onto serial, the lack of output was more worrying - especially since I was getting logs from coreboot just a few seconds prior.</p>

<h3>A primer on 16550 UART</h3>

<p><img src="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/img/15.jpg" alt="screencap from a Cathode Ray Dude video. Gravis is sitting on the right of the frame, the left is occupied by text immitating a dictionary definition. Serial Port - a hole into which you can throw bytes, and they come out somewhere else. thats it - abraham lincoln">
<small>Picture 16 - "sometimes they don't come out and it makes me sad" ~ irth<br>(screencap from a <a href="https://youtube.com/watch?v=7mqkTFq7Ekg">CRD video on dialup VoIP</a>, licensed under CC-BY. greetz to Gravis)</small></p><p>What we call "serial", in reality can be anything from classic RS-232, through TTL UART (RS-232, but lower voltages), or in rare cases, some wholly unrelated low pin-count bus (USB is serial, technically). It has to transmit data in series (one bit at a time), as opposed to in parallel (<i>at least</i> 2 bits at a time, in most cases 8 or more) - but even that requirement is blurry. Originally, RS-232 also transmitted some metadata (hardware flow control, etc), but today it's <i>really</i> rare to see UART with more than two wires and ground.</p>

<p>From the perspective of a user, the lowest common denominator is that UART transmits data, and is usually quite slow (although even this isn't always true, see HSUART). On all but the lowest layer, the bit-by-bit nature is abstracted away, and one just sees <b>bytes</b> passing through - not bits. Thus, even the "serial" part becomes irrelevant.</p>

<p>Similarly, from the programmer's perspective, serial is just a place to read and write bytes from. Even on the lowest abstraction layer, in virtually all cases you <b>will send bytes</b>. The only defining quirk of the standard is stripped away as soon as possible.</p>

<p>But there's a missing link: we need something to convert those bytes into a series of bits, and then into actual electrical signals. Ever since the first IBM PC, this was the job of a serial interface chip - historically, either an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/8250_UART">8250</a> or the newer drop-in replacement, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/16550_UART">16550</a>. Nowadays, the serial controller is tightly integrated into the chipset, but virtually all of them still use the same register map as a 40+ year old chip would. Thanks to this, as vague as it may be, serial is one of the very few standard interfaces which are present on <i>almost</i> all PCs in some shape or form.</p>

<h3>16550: The interface</h3>

<p>Historically, all external devices on the IBM PC were port-mapped to the x86 CPU. Thus, to interface with them, one would use a special instruction like <span>outb</span> for writes or <span>inb</span> for reads. This Was Widely Regarded As A Bad Move, because it made things <i>slow as molasses</i>. Then, MMIO (Memory-Mapped IO) came, and with it, hacks like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Direct_memory_access">DMA</a> became possible - and really fast in comparison. A lot of devices moved onto MMIO for the faster speeds and lower CPU overhead.</p>

<p>But serial generally didn't. By the time DMA became viable on consumer-grade machines, serial didn't need to compete to be high-speed; It got superseded by faster parallel ports, USB, and briefly - SCSI. This put it in a great place for being a generic debug port, because as long as one can physically access the RX/TX pins, executing <span>outb 0x3f8, 0x41</span> will get yield an <span>A</span> on the other side. The initialization sequence is around 5 instructions, and it's trivial to implement even in small projects.</p>

<p>... except, as I wrote: "generally". A lot of sources online insist that 16550-compatibles were always port-mapped, but my laptop here begs to differ:</p>



<p><code>domi@octopus:~$ doas dmesg | grep 16550
[    0.501954] Serial: 8250/16550 driver, 4 ports, IRQ sharing enabled
[    4.278345] dw-apb-uart.5: ttyS0 at MMIO 0x9112f000 (irq = 4, base_baud = 115200) is a 16550A
[    4.299158] dw-apb-uart.6: ttyS1 at MMIO 0x180000000 (irq = 6, base_baud = 115200) is a 16550A
</code>
<small>Figure 1 - Linux kernel logs, showing MMIO and some addresses</small></p><p>Digging further, I found out that the whole thing is provided by a PCI device:</p>



<p><code>domi@octopus:~$ lspci | grep UART
00:18.0 Signal processing controller: Intel Corporation Celeron/Pentium Silver Processor Serial IO UART Host Controller (rev 06)
00:18.2 Signal processing controller: Intel Corporation Celeron/Pentium Silver Processor Serial IO UART Host Controller (rev 06)
</code>
<small>Figure 2 - lspci output</small></p><p>This is <i>bad</i>, because PCI is infamously hard to setup. Serenity has a PCI bus implementation, but we're so early in the boot process that it's a no-go. Even if it wasn't, our generic PCISerialDevice so far hasn't been used in a MMIO context; Hacking up a driver for this without any debug output would be less than ideal.</p>

<h3>Horrors beyond our comprehension feat. port80</h3>

<p>One of the more peculiar features of the embedded controller on chromeos devices is that it logs all writes to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power-on_self-test#Progress_and_error_reporting">IO port 0x80</a>. Traditionally, this port is used for POST status reporting. If your motherboard has a 7-segment boot code display, <b>it's decoding port 80</b>! And well, nothing stops you from writing to port 80 <i>after</i> your BIOS finishes the POST.</p>



<p><code>#!/bin/bash
# silly hack: write to a port from userspace on Linux
if [[ ! $2 ]]; then
	echo "usage: $0 &lt;port&gt; &lt;byte&gt;"
	exit 1
fi
doas dd seek=$((0x$1)) bs=1 count=1 of=/dev/port &lt; &lt;(xxd -p -r &lt;&lt;&lt; "$2")
</code>


<small>Figure 3 - save this as <span>outb</span>, chmod +x and run <span>./outb 80 ff</span>, then look at your POST code display</small></p><p>I tested my hypothesis with the above script under linux, and sure enough, I was able to read the bytes back on the cros_ec console!</p>

<p>Armed with.. all of this, I got to work. Serenity starts execution at <a href="https://github.com/SerenityOS/serenity/blob/b5c6e656f84ec2b3f5a8ae343feeee914a42dd89/Kernel/Arch/init.cpp#L165">Kernel/Arch/init.cpp</a>, so I spread a bunch of <span>IO::out8(0x80, 1);</span> around to track how far it got. I narrowed it down to crashing on <span>Memory::MemoryManager::initialize(0);</span>, and then decided that my manual debugging approach isn't gonna cut it long-term.</p>

<h3>What is port 0x80, if not a "serial" port?</h3>

<p>So, one could wonder, what would happen if in <a href="https://github.com/SerenityOS/serenity/blob/b5c6e656f84ec2b3f5a8ae343feeee914a42dd89/Kernel/Arch/x86_64/DebugOutput.cpp#L52">the serial write routine</a> the address grew legs and walked back from 0x3f8 to 0x80?</p>

<p><img src="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/img/16.png" alt="terminal output from cros_ec. we're dumping bytes - care to decode what they do? :3">
	<small>Picture 17 - view from the cros_ec console after enabling <span>port80 intscroll</span></small>
</p>

<p>Answer is - briefly, a lot of bytes. Then something overflows, and cros_ec stops being able to reliably relay data. Even later, something else breaks even further and corrupts the whole cros_ec log output (not visible above). Oops?</p>

<p>We can work around that by <a href="https://github.com/SerenityOS/serenity/blob/4723c905e6e29bfe12e3dd3283b12683938f2350/Kernel/Arch/x86_64/DebugOutput.cpp#L46-L59">inserting a bunch of dummy waitstates</a> between writes - it sucks, it's slow, but it will have to do. A real serial IO chip would have a big buffer to make sure this doesn't happen, but we don't get that luxury here.</p>



<pre><code>void debug_output_cool(char ch)
{
	static bool was_cr = false;
	if (ch == 'n' &amp;&amp; !was_cr) {
		IO::out8(serial_com1_io_port, 'r');
		for (int i=0; i&lt;27768000; i++)
			asm volatile("nop");
	}

	IO::out8(serial_com1_io_port, ch);

	for (int i=0; i&lt;27768000; i++)
		asm volatile("nop");

	was_cr = ch == 'r';
}
</code></pre>
<p><small>Figure 4 - artisanally crafted for loops, for a balance of "perf" and "reliability"</small></p><p>We also need some abstraction to automatically parse lines from cros_ec and decode the bytes as ASCII. I'm doing this with a horrifying bash oneliner:</p>


<p><code># first, launch picocom
picocom -b 115200 --logfile /tmp/log /dev/ttyACM1

# then, in a second shell..
watch -n 1 "cat /tmp/log | tr '\r' '\n' | grep -a -i port | sed 's/.*: //;s/]//;s/0x07//;s/0x//' | cut -c 1-2 | xxd -p -r | tail -n 50"
</code>
<small>Figure 5 - absolutely incomprehensible bash oneliner</small></p><p>Printing all boot messages through this makes the system go from "boots in a few seconds" to "boots in a few minutes", but this is a price I was willing to pay.</p>

<hr>

<video controls="" src="https://f.sakamoto.pl/weblog-content/23/serial.webm"></video>
<p><small><b>WARNING: This video is a bit flickery</b></small></p><h3>serenity, again</h3>

<p>Armed with boot logs, I asked for support from the community.. or that's what I should have done. Instead, I spent a few days reading through the codebase, frantically trying to make sense of everything at once, only to finally give up and ask for help anyways. If you're in this situation, just ask. Open-source folks usually don't bite (as long as you search beforehand, and <a href="https://dontasktoask.com/">formulate your questions correctly</a>), and that very much applies to all frequent Serenity developers; they're a bunch of really nice folks :3</p>

<p>After some back-and-forth, spholz linked me <a href="https://github.com/SerenityOS/serenity/pull/24435">this MR</a>, which at the time was still open. Building from this branch made the generic framebuffer work!</p>

<p><img src="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/img/17.png">
	<small>Picture 19 - task failed successfully</small>
</p>

<h3>The eMMC saga</h3>

<p>Previously mentioned StorageManagement crash looked something like this:</p>

<p><code>136.086 [init_stage2(1:1)]: PCI: Failed to initialize SD Host Controller (PCI [0000:00:1c:00] - PCI::HardwareID [8086:31cc]): Error(errno=74)
[init_stage2(1:1)]: ASSERTION FAILED: !m_controllers.is_empty()
[init_stage2(1:1)]: ./Kernel/Devices/Storage/StorageManagement.cpp:168 in void Kernel::StorageManagement::enumerate_storage_devices()
[init_stage2(1:1)]: KERNEL PANIC! :^(
</code>
<small>Figure 6 - SerenityOS crash debug output</small></p><p>As I wrote before, octopus has a 32GB eMMC chip. Serenity already had <i>some</i> SD drivers, so one could assume that making MMC work with those won't be a lot of work. Unfortunately: reality struck.</p>

<h3>What is MMC, anyways?</h3>

<p>If you got this far, I suspect you know that a long time ago MMC was a thing. Then SD became a thing too, and MMC died within just a few years. The details on <i>how</i> and <i>why</i> all of this happened are a story in itself, a part of which I researched and wrote down in a <a href="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/21-nobody-knows-what-happened-at-mmca/">previous blogpost</a>.</p>

<p>For the purposes of this post, all one needs to know is that MMC is <i>similar</i> to SD (but with a different init sequence), and that it never truly died: it haunts eMMC chips.</p>

<h3>Write the damn driver already!!</h3>

<p>In somewhat oversimplified terms, to get an SD / MMC card to work, we need:</p>

<ol>
	<li>a Host Controller; they used to come in a large variety of shapes and sizes, but nowadays it's usually an SDHCI (SD Host Controller), as specified by <a href="https://www.sdcard.org/downloads/pls/">the SD Association</a></li>
	<li>a bus to connect that host controller to; in our case, PCI</li>
	<li>the proper protocol implemented to talk between the host and the card</li>
</ol>

<p>As showcased by the crash log, we already had the first two. The protocol is publicly specified, but only for SD cards, not MMC - ever since that became a JEDEC standard in 2007, you need to <a href="https://archive.org/download/SD-specs/JESD84-B51.pdf">pay up to get it in a legit way</a>. Having to marry two diverging standards lead me into a rabbithole of comparing several different versions of both to figure out what's what, how it evolved, and what exactly I need to implement.</p>

<p>As an aside: JEDEC's standard is considered "open", but SD Association's is "proprietary", just because of the SD security extensions, even though the base version is available for free. I love vendor associations.</p>

<h3>SD vs MMC vs eMMC: the differences</h3>

<p>Depending on the source, you'll get vastly different stories on what differs between what. At the time, I cared most about the card initialization sequence; <a href="https://github.com/SerenityOS/serenity/blob/94a5e88aa879869de57060d5504134ff81157100/Kernel/Devices/Storage/SD/SDHostController.cpp#L160-L162">In serenity</a>, we start with sending CMD0 and waiting for a response. This should pass both on SD as well as MMC. Then, we send CMD8 to begin the voltage setup - MMC doesn't support this, so we should get an error. At that point, some sources suggest trying to reset the card (or the whole controller) and assuming that the card is MMC from here on out. Other sources, such as <a href="https://forum.microchip.com/s/topic/a5C3l000000M1X0EAK/t235946?comment=P-1847318">this wonderful forum thread</a> suggest a much more... comprehensive approach:</p>




<p><span>According to the SD spec (SD Specifications, Part 1, Physical Layer, Simplified Specification, Version 2.00, July 27, 2006) figure 7-2: SPI Mode Initialization Flow, there are 5 possible outcomes:<p>
1) CMD8 fails and CMD58 fails: must be MMC, thus initialize using CMD1<br>
2) CMD8 fails and CMD58 passes: must be Ver1.x Standard Capacity SD Memory Card<br>
3) CMD8 passes and CMD58 passes (CCS = 0): must be Ver2.00 or later Standard Capacity SD Memory Card<br>
4) CMD8 passes and CMD58 passes (CCS = 1): must be Ver2.00 or later High Capacity SD Memory Card<br>
5) CMD8 passes and CMD58 passes but indicates non compatible voltage range: unusable card</p><p>
I'm not sure whether knowing the Version of the SD Card makes any difference to the reading/writing/erasing logic.</p><p>
<b>~ Spruce, 28th September 2006</b></p></span></p><p>Anyhoo, I chose to only implement basic checks - and unless we run into some weird compat issues, we probably won't bother with the more advanced ones. I don't exactly yearn to code up this vendor-flavored spaghetti.</p>

<hr>

<p>The rest of the initialization flow also differs from SD, but it boils down to:</p>

<ol>
	<li>After the reset, set the clock to 400KHz</li>
	<li>"wait for 1ms, then wait for 74 more clock cycles" (sic!)</li>
	<li>Send CMD0, wait for response</li>
	<li>Send CMD1 in a loop (!) until 31st bit from the response is 1 (JEDEC standard is slightly misleading on this point)</li>
	<li>Once the loop finishes, save the value. That's our Operating Conditions register</li>
	<li>Continue with the SD initialization algo, sans for querying SD-specific registers</li>
	<li>Optionally, probe for High-Speed compatibility and turn on one of the <i>various</i> HS modes (there are more than 4, along with two different ways of compatibility probing!)</li>
</ol>

<p>My code was getting to around point 4, but no matter what I did further down the line, my card wouldn't respond to <i>any</i> requests. I spent a <b>days</b> trying to debug what was going wrong, and I couldn't find anything. One evening during a routine session of pulling my hair out, I randomly removed all the parts responsible for the controller reset - and while that didn't fix it entirely, the eMMC started responding! This suggested that the <a href="https://github.com/SerenityOS/serenity/blob/94a5e88aa879869de57060d5504134ff81157100/Kernel/Devices/Storage/SD/SDHostController.cpp#L520-L532">reset function</a> was to blame:</p>

<p><code>ErrorOr<void> SDHostController::reset_host_controller()
{
	m_registers-&gt;host_configuration_0 = 0;
	m_registers-&gt;host_configuration_1 = m_registers-&gt;host_configuration_1 | software_reset_for_all;
	if (!retry_with_timeout(
		[&amp;] {
			return (m_registers-&gt;host_configuration_1 &amp; software_reset_for_all) == 0;
		})) {
		return EIO;
	}

	return {};
}
</void></code>
<small>Figure 7 - fragment of SDHostController.cpp</small></p><p>First weird thing about this function: no standard I found defined a <span>host_configuration</span> register. There was a Host Control register which was roughly in the same spot as our weird 32bit blob, but nothing seemed to fully match. AS IT TURNS OUT: the previous entity touching this code grouped a bunch of registers into two arbitrary <span>host_configuration</span> groups, then never fully finished initializing them - see how we just set the 1st register to 0.</p>

<p>Why is this important? The first group contains a smaller <i>Power Control</i> register, controlling the power regulator for the card. On some hardware implementations (including all that use eMMC) this register is <b>required to power on the card itself</b>, while other designs (that connect the power rail directly to the slot) may ignore it entirely - hence the misconfiguration.</p>

<p>As a temporary hack, I just stole the value initially contained in <span>host_configuration_0</span> and rolled with that.</p>

<p><b>tl;dr: talking to the card is significantly easier if we power it on.</b></p><hr>

<p>After figuring this <i>tiny</i> detail out, I needed a few more hours to debug and disable specific commands in the sequence that were only valid for SD cards. The rest went quite unremarkably - finally getting sensible debug output from the controller helped my nerves a lot, too.</p>

<div><p>Soon, we (really slowly) spawned a (partially corrupted) graphical session, which (unfortunately) quickly locked up. Debugging all of those issues will be described in a future part of this series (if attention span allows).</p><p>I don't have a good picture of that semi-broken state, so please enjoy one from when I managed to unbreak the framebuffer - something I will (hopefully) describe in detail in the next post.</p></div>

<p><img src="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/23-serenityos-realhw/img/alive.jpg" alt="picture of a laptop screen. there are two terminal windows and a taskbar running">
<small>Picture 20 - (out of the lack of a better picture) finally! it's alive!</small></p><p>This post itself took me on a learning journey that spanned around 6 months, many of them busy with other things that got in the way (wink wink, <a href="https://sdomi.pl/weblog/?id=22">Project SERVFAIL</a>). I plan to finish up cleaning up and upstreaming my patches sometime this year.</p>

<hr>



<hr><p><a href="https://ko-fi.com/sdomi/"><img alt="Support me on ko-fi!" src="https://sdomi.pl/img/ko-fi.png"></a></p><hr><h3>Comments:</h3></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: The Atlas of Space (314 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://atlasof.space/</link>
            <guid>42634787</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 14:47:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://atlasof.space/">https://atlasof.space/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42634787">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://atlasof.space/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Fidget (338 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.mattkeeter.com/projects/fidget/</link>
            <guid>42634624</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 14:30:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.mattkeeter.com/projects/fidget/">https://www.mattkeeter.com/projects/fidget/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42634624">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.mattkeeter.com/projects/fidget/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Robotics 101 at UMich: Applied numerical linear algebra as intro linear algebra (169 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://robotics.umich.edu/academics/courses/course-offerings/rob101-fall-2020/</link>
            <guid>42633805</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 13:11:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://robotics.umich.edu/academics/courses/course-offerings/rob101-fall-2020/">https://robotics.umich.edu/academics/courses/course-offerings/rob101-fall-2020/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42633805">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="page">
		<main id="main">

			
<article id="post-6411" class="page">

	<div>
				
			
<h2>Fall 2020 (or <a href="https://robotics.umich.edu/academic-program/course-offerings/rob101-fall-2022/">see Fall 2022</a>)</h2>



<figure><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="512" src="https://robotics.umich.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/ROB101-landscape-clena-copy@4x-100-1024x512.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://robotics.umich.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/ROB101-landscape-clena-copy@4x-100-1024x512.jpg 1024w, https://robotics.umich.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/ROB101-landscape-clena-copy@4x-100-300x150.jpg 300w, https://robotics.umich.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/ROB101-landscape-clena-copy@4x-100-768x384.jpg 768w, https://robotics.umich.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/ROB101-landscape-clena-copy@4x-100-1536x768.jpg 1536w, https://robotics.umich.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/ROB101-landscape-clena-copy@4x-100-2048x1024.jpg 2048w, https://robotics.umich.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/ROB101-landscape-clena-copy@4x-100-1200x600.jpg 1200w, https://robotics.umich.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/ROB101-landscape-clena-copy@4x-100-1400x700.jpg 1400w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" data-old-src="//robotics.umich.edu/wp-content/plugins/a3-lazy-load/assets/images/lazy_placeholder.gif" data-src="https://robotics.umich.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/ROB101-landscape-clena-copy@4x-100-1024x512.jpg" data-srcset="https://robotics.umich.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/ROB101-landscape-clena-copy@4x-100-1024x512.jpg 1024w, https://robotics.umich.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/ROB101-landscape-clena-copy@4x-100-300x150.jpg 300w, https://robotics.umich.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/ROB101-landscape-clena-copy@4x-100-768x384.jpg 768w, https://robotics.umich.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/ROB101-landscape-clena-copy@4x-100-1536x768.jpg 1536w, https://robotics.umich.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/ROB101-landscape-clena-copy@4x-100-2048x1024.jpg 2048w, https://robotics.umich.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/ROB101-landscape-clena-copy@4x-100-1200x600.jpg 1200w, https://robotics.umich.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/ROB101-landscape-clena-copy@4x-100-1400x700.jpg 1400w"></figure>



<div>
<p>Computational Linear Algebra is a pilot first-semester, first-year undergraduate course that will show how mathematics and computation are unified for reasoning about data and making discoveries about the world.</p>



<p>Linear algebra and coding are rapidly becoming an essential foundation for the modern engineer in a computational world.&nbsp; Students in this course will gain insights into the mathematical theory of linear algebra and its realization in practical computational tools.&nbsp; </p>



<p>Math is the language of engineering, but coding is believing and realizing it. The mathematical content of ROB 101 will be built around systems of linear equations, their representation as matrices, and numerical methods for their analysis. These methods will be given life through the lens of robotics and contemporary intelligent systems and their compelling applications.</p>




</div>



<figure><div>
<p><iframe title="Flipping the script on engineering education" width="905" height="509" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4oXJTSBCe_U?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>
</div></figure>



<div><details open=""><summary>What are the topics covered in this course?</summary><div>
<ul><li><a href="https://julialang.org/">Julia</a> as an open-source “dynamic” programming language. Quoting from Wikipedia: “Julia is a high-level, high-performance, dynamic programming language. While it is a general-purpose language and can be used to write any application, many of its features are well-suited for high-performance numerical analysis and computational science.” All of the mathematical topics treated in the course will be made operational through computational exercises in Julia. </li><li>Small sets of linear equations, their solvability, and how to find solutions: underdetermined, overdetermined, and just right. Scaling up to large sets of equations (thousands of variables) through vectors, matrices, determinants, and matrix inverses. </li><li>Regression as a means of building models and making predictions. </li><li>A camera pin-hole model and camera calibration via regression. </li><li>Concept of factoring a matrix. Inner products and orthogonal vectors. Symmetric matrices and orthogonal matrices. </li><li>Finding solutions to nonlinear equations via gradient descent. </li><li>Optimization as a tool for solving robot perception problems. </li><li>Linear transformations with applications to spatial coordinates. </li><li>LiDAR point clouds and blobs. </li><li>Accelerometers, single-axis gyroscopes, encoders, and what is an ODE.</li></ul>
</div></details></div>



<div><details><summary>Why should I take ROB 101. What is so special about it?</summary><div>
<p>Engineering math education is stuck in the Sputnik era: we force you to do four semesters of calculus before you can do anything interesting in engineering. ROB 101 seeks to break through with new ideas. You will see how engineers are using mathematics and computing to solve large and important problems. You will still do drill problems to firm up concepts with teeny tiny problems with two or three variables, but you will also solve problems in the Julia programming language with hundreds of variables.</p>



<p>Instead of seeing the “rules of calculus” as your introduction to college mathematics, you will experience the “raison d’etre of mathematics in engineering”, in other words, why we employ it so heavily in engineering in the first place. And instead of starting mathematics by learning the innumerable ways to get a closed-form expression by a change of variable in an integral, you will learn how to formulate and perform relevant computations with algorithms. In short, you will have a palpable understanding that computation and mathematics are your friends instead of hoops to be jumped through on the way to a degree.&nbsp;</p>
</div></details></div>



<div><details><summary>What do I need to know to be successful in this course?</summary><p>We assume no prior knowledge of Linear Algebra or programming. We assume that you have completed a high school Algebra course where you learned how to solve quadratic equations. That is it.</p></details></div>



<div><details><summary>What personal characteristics are needed for this course?</summary><div>
<p>You have been admitted to U-M Engineering — that tells us that you are up for a challenge! You’re smart,&nbsp;and you want to become a good engineer. We also need you to be a person who respects others and demonstrates humility. The field of Robotics is so broad that no one person can master even ⅓ of the subject. </p>



<p>The first thing we teach our graduate students is to say the words: “Can you help me with this?” In Robotics, asking for help is not a sign of weakness. It is a sign that you respect and appreciate a fellow human being. If you cannot bring yourself to ask for help, then you’re probably not the right person for ROB 101.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
</div></details></div>



<div><details><summary>What technology do I need to succeed in this course?</summary><p>You need to be able to access the web. The course will use the Julia programming language delivered to you in the form of Jupyter notebooks that can be run in a web browser. If you can access the U-M course learning site, Canvas, then you can access all of the course materials and turn in all of the homework assignments and projects.</p></details></div>



<div><details><summary>Will I need to be on campus to take exams or to attend lectures?</summary><div>
<p>No. The class is being offered in hybrid mode: your instructors will lecture in a classroom to anyone who wishes to attend. The lecture will be simultaneously broadcast on Zoom and recorded. The recorded lectures will be posted on the ROB 101 Canvas site.&nbsp; A student instructor will help the faculty member to monitor the chatbox on Zoom. You will be encouraged to participate. We’ll have anonymous means to ask your opinions about stuff.&nbsp;</p>



<p>All exams and quizzes will be conducted in electronic form. There will be a window of time during which they can be completed. ROB 101 will be much different than a typical college course: we are not planning on two midterms and a final exam. We are planning on course projects to be where you demonstrate your ability to synthesize information.</p>
</div></details></div>



<div><details><summary>What requirement will ROB 101 meet?</summary><div>
<p>ROB 101 is intended to fulfill the linear algebra prerequisite of many courses in Engineering, with specific attention to more streamlined preparation for Robotics and AI courses.</p>



<p>Right now, it does not replace any required course, which is normal in the pilot semester of a new course. We are working with individual departments to see if they might accept it in place of linear algebra requisites (Math 214 and Math 217, for example) for other Engineering courses (computer vision, for example). You may not have a definite answer before you begin the course.</p>
</div></details></div>



<div><details><summary>How many students are you planning to admit?</summary><p>In this pilot phase, only 30 students maximum will be admitted.</p></details></div>



<div><details><summary>What is Linear Algebra?</summary><p>Roughly speaking, it’s a branch of mathematics that deals with linear equations in several variables. It also includes a number of tools, such as vectors, matrices, spaces of vectors, and linear transformations.</p></details></div>



<div><details><summary>Why is Linear Algebra so important?</summary><p>It has become the language of computer vision, machine learning, robotics, and autonomy. It provides very compact and insightful ways to manipulate information. Linear Algebra and programming go together like hand and glove.</p></details></div>



<div><details><summary>What about Matlab? Why are you using the Julia Programming Language?</summary><p>Robotics and many other fields are supporting open-source tools of all kinds. When researchers submit papers nowadays, they are expected to share software that supports the mathematical and experimental concepts in the paper. In the past, many researchers indeed used MATLAB. While it’s a great programming environment, it’s also very expensive. Also, you must have a local copy on your computer in order to use it. Julia, on the other hand, is open-source software and we can deliver it to you via a browser. This provides near-universal accessibility.&nbsp;</p></details></div>



<div><details><summary>If I need MATLAB in another course, will I be at a disadvantage?</summary><p>The programming structures in Julia and MATLAB are very similar. It will probably take you two weeks to get up to speed in MATLAB once you learn Julia. In addition, learning Julia will help your acquisition of C++.</p></details></div>



<div><details><summary>What are the downsides to Julia?</summary><p>It’s a new language. The help pages are not as beautifully organized as the help pages for MATLAB. You’ll learn to google a lot as you acquire skills in Julia.</p></details></div>



<div><details><summary>Is Linear Algebra hard to learn?</summary><p>Your instructors believe that linear algebra is easier to learn than calculus and they 100% know that it is much easier to begin doing meaningful things in engineering with Linear Algebra than it is with Calculus. We’ll do three projects in the course. In the first one, we’ll have you building a map that a robot could use to navigate on the North Campus Grove.</p></details></div>



<div><details><summary>Why is it a new thing to be teaching Linear Algebra to first-semester, first-year undergraduate students?</summary><p>That is a very good question! A number of us have been advocating for it for a long time. The Robotics faculty at Michigan, led by Professor <a href="https://robotics.umich.edu/profile/chad-jenkins/">Chad Jenkins</a>, finally decided to do something about it. Normally, mathematics courses are developed through the Department of Mathematics. We want you to see how engineers use math and think about math. Other schools are starting to do this as well. Professor Steven Boyd has introduced a Linear Algebra course at Stanford that is required for first-year engineering students. Will ROB 101 be a required course at Michigan someday? Hard to say! We have to survive the pilot offering first.&nbsp;</p></details></div>



<div><details><summary>Do I actually need to be available MWF, 10-11am, since lectures are recorded?</summary><p>It is fine to follow the course asynchronously, which means you watch the recorded lectures at a time of your choosing. You are not required to attend in person.</p></details></div>



<div><details><summary>What section should I choose, and what is the difference between hybrid (001) or distance (881)?</summary><p>No one is obliged or even encouraged to attend in person. Attendance in person is a personal choice. We suggest you select the hybrid section if you are planning to be in Ann Arbor for Fall 2020. If you are not planning to be in Ann Arbor for the fall term, due to concerns of COVID-19, for example, then we suggest the distance learning section.</p></details></div>



<div><details><summary>Where will the in-person class be held?</summary><p>We plan for the course to meet in person in the new <a href="https://robotics.umich.edu/about/ford-motor-company-robotics-building/" title="Ford Robotics Building">Robotics Building</a> on North Campus. But again, attendance in person is a personal choice. No one is obliged to attend in person. </p></details></div>



<div><details><summary>How will grades be assigned?</summary><div>
<p>Fairly! Here is what we are currently thinking. We are open to suggestions.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<ul><li>15% Ten (10) roughly weekly homework sets. This is where mistakes have almost no cost.&nbsp;</li><li>60% Projects (Three&nbsp;projects at 20% each)</li><li>15% Quizzes (Four to six very short quizzes offered online, so obviously, you can consult the web when doing them)&nbsp;</li><li>5% Final presentation (Two minute video on some aspect of&nbsp; “Computational Mathematics for Engineering”; you will have a lot of freedom in the topic. )</li><li>5% Class engagement with online tools such as piazza (online chat for math), constructive comments on posted course notes, HW sets, recorded lectures, other videos, etc.</li></ul>




</div></details></div>

			</div><!-- .post-content-->

</article><!-- #post-## -->

		</main><!-- #main -->
	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[We Cracked a 512-Bit DKIM Key for Less Than $8 in the Cloud (542 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://dmarcchecker.app/articles/crack-512-bit-dkim-rsa-key</link>
            <guid>42633501</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 12:32:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://dmarcchecker.app/articles/crack-512-bit-dkim-rsa-key">https://dmarcchecker.app/articles/crack-512-bit-dkim-rsa-key</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42633501">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>In our <a href="https://dmarcchecker.app/articles/spf-dkim-dmarc-adoption-2024">study on the SPF, DKIM, and DMARC records of the top 1M websites</a>, we were surprised to uncover more than 1,700 public DKIM keys that were shorter than 1,024 bits in length. This finding was unexpected, as RSA keys shorter than 1,024 bits are considered insecure, and their use in DKIM has been deprecated since the introduction of <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc8301" target="_blank">RFC 8301</a> in 2018.</p><p>Driven by curiosity, we decided to explore whether we could crack one of these keys. Our goal was to extract the private key from a public RSA key, enabling us to sign emails as if we were the original sender. We were also curious to see whether emails signed with this compromised key would pass the DKIM verification checks of major email providers like Gmail, Outlook.com, and Yahoo Mail, or if they would outright refuse to verify a signature generated with such a short key.</p><p>For our experiment, we chose redfin.com after discovering a 512-bit RSA public key at <i>key1._domainkey.redfin.com</i> (now no longer available):</p><pre>$ dig +short TXT key1._domainkey.redfin.com
"k=rsa; p=MFwwDQYJKoZIhvcNAQEBBQADSwAwSAJBAMx7VnoRmk/wFPeFWxrVUde6AJQI51/uPFL2CbiHGMnRSnLjPs72AgxAVHIe5QrNQ2riR5+7u47Sgh5R5va/d0cCAwEAAQ=="</pre><h2>Decoding the RSA Public Key</h2><p>The public key, located in the DKIM record’s <code>p</code> tag, is encoded in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X.690#DER_encoding" target="_blank">ASN.1 DER format</a>, and further encoded as Base64. To decode the key to obtain the modulus (<i>n</i>) and the public exponent (<i>e</i>), we used a couple of lines of Python code:</p><pre>$ python3
&gt;&gt;&gt; from Crypto.PublicKey import RSA
&gt;&gt;&gt; RSA.import_key('-----BEGIN PUBLIC KEY-----\n' + 'MFwwDQYJKoZIhvcNAQEBBQADSwAwSAJBAMx7VnoRmk/wFPeFWxrVUde6AJQI51/uPFL2CbiHGMnRSnLjPs72AgxAVHIe5QrNQ2riR5+7u47Sgh5R5va/d0cCAwEAAQ==' + '\n-----END PUBLIC KEY-----')
RsaKey(n=10709580243955269690347257968368575486652256021267387585731784527165077094358215924099792804326677548390607229176966588251215467367272433485332943072098119, e=65537)</pre><h2>Factorizing the RSA Modulus</h2><p>With the modulus <i>n</i> in hand, our next step was to identify the two prime numbers, <i>p</i> and <i>q</i>, whose product equals <i>n</i>. This process, known as factoring, can be quite challenging to perform efficiently. Fortunately, we found a powerful open-source tool called <a href="https://cado-nfs.gitlabpages.inria.fr/" target="_blank">CADO-NFS</a>, which offers an easy-to-use implementation of the Number Field Sieve (NFS) algorithm — the most efficient method available for factoring large integers.</p><p>Since factoring takes a lot of computing power and we didn’t want to tie up our computers for days, we went with renting a cloud server. We chose a server with 8 dedicated vCPUs (AMD EPYC 7003 series) and 32 GB of RAM from Hetzner, installing Ubuntu as the OS. Setting up CADO-NFS was straightforward:</p><pre>git clone https://gitlab.inria.fr/cado-nfs/cado-nfs.git
cd cado-nfs
make</pre><p>To ensure the server had enough memory for the task, we added 32 GB of swap space:</p><pre>sudo fallocate -l 32G /swapfile
sudo chmod 600 /swapfile
sudo mkswap /swapfile
sudo swapon /swapfile</pre><p>We started the factorization by calling the <code>cado-nfs.py</code> script with <i>n</i> as the input:</p><pre>./cado-nfs.py 10709580243955269690347257968368575486652256021267387585731784527165077094358215924099792804326677548390607229176966588251215467367272433485332943072098119</pre><p>The process took approximately 86 hours on our 8-vCPU server, successfully factorizing <i>n</i> into <i>p</i> and <i>q</i>:</p><pre>Info:Complete Factorization / Discrete logarithm: Total cpu/elapsed time for entire Complete Factorization 2.20529e+06/309865 [3d 14:04:25]
97850895333751392558280999318309697780438485965134147739065017624372104720767 109447953515671602102748820944693252789237215829169932130613751100276125683257</pre><p>Although opting for a more powerful server or distributing the workload across several systems (a process simplified by CADO-NFS) could have expedited the task, we weren’t pressed for time and didn’t mind the wait.</p><h2>Constructing the RSA Private Key</h2><p>After determining <i>p</i> and <i>q</i>, we had all the necessary components to construct the RSA private key. The process involved using Python and the PyCryptodome library:</p><pre>$ python3
&gt;&gt;&gt; from Crypto.PublicKey import RSA
&gt;&gt;&gt; from Crypto.Util.number import inverse
&gt;&gt;&gt; p = 97850895333751392558280999318309697780438485965134147739065017624372104720767
&gt;&gt;&gt; q = 109447953515671602102748820944693252789237215829169932130613751100276125683257
&gt;&gt;&gt; e = 65537
&gt;&gt;&gt; n = p * q
&gt;&gt;&gt; phi = (p-1) * (q-1)
&gt;&gt;&gt; d = inverse(e, phi)
&gt;&gt;&gt; key = RSA.construct((n, e, d, p, q))
&gt;&gt;&gt; private_key = key.export_key()
&gt;&gt;&gt; print(private_key.decode())</pre><p>These Python lines output the private key in PEM format, ready for use:</p><pre>-----BEGIN RSA PRIVATE KEY-----
MIIBOgIBAAJBAMx7VnoRmk/wFPeFWxrVUde6AJQI51/uPFL2CbiHGMnRSnLjPs72
AgxAVHIe5QrNQ2riR5+7u47Sgh5R5va/d0cCAwEAAQJAPliEv2dKk4DyA54nbwEH
mSzfLEOiuD8dKXZW9GpMhou72DYYcc5YD0PeQW0uGGsusnTZXRU3Kd3cmVfeR+np
4QIhANhVpOQ440Gqlda3nqCOAag12jq8ET+qr1G7VL8x9PF/AiEA8flYr5rUO6Io
/5HRoHq6p7dA75PRK+7v79o0/ijfTjkCIEdWPpCPfckKomxykllpWnyIfZT+rUVs
WHHAL1r480erAiAz3xD87ALtGbESQE8gyM50n5sjAJwJf/odf7h2d4qPOQIhAKwr
Nv6s5cQiwbYgm1KND83nrkxe6uFQlu9ilkdwAIY4
-----END RSA PRIVATE KEY-----</pre><h2>Sending DKIM-Signed Test Mails From @redfin.com</h2><p>With the RSA private key integrated into our OpenDKIM setup, we proceeded to the testing phase. We crafted a simple email with a FROM address of security@redfin.com, then sent it to a variety of email hosting services. Although most providers correctly identified the 512-bit key as insecure and rejected our DKIM signature, three major providers — Yahoo Mail, Mailfence, and Tuta — reported a <code>dkim=pass</code> result.</p><p><img src="https://dmarcchecker.app/assets/images/articles/dkim-pass-redfin-yahoo.png" alt="Yahoo Mail: Authentication Results"></p><p>Here’s how each provider responded:</p><ul><li>Gmail: <span>FAIL</span></li><li>Outlook: <span>FAIL</span></li><li>Yahoo Mail: <span><strong>PASS</strong></span></li><li>Zoho: <span>FAIL</span></li><li>Fastmail: <span>FAIL</span></li><li>Proton Mail: <span>FAIL</span></li><li>Mailfence: <span><strong>PASS</strong></span></li><li>Tuta: <span><strong>PASS</strong></span></li><li>GMX: <span>FAIL</span></li><li>OnMail: <span>FAIL</span></li></ul><p>Given that redfin.com also has a valid DMARC record (<code>v=DMARC1;p=reject;pct=100;rua=mailto:a+99923342@fdmarc.net;ruf=mailto:f+99923342@fdmarc.net;ri=3600;fo=1;</code>), passing the DKIM check for <code>redfin.com</code> also means that our email passed DMARC verification and met the requirements for <a href="https://bimigroup.org/" target="_blank">BIMI</a>.</p><h2>Final Thoughts</h2><p>Three decades ago, breaking a 512-bit RSA public key was a feat achievable only with a supercomputer. Today, it’s possible to do so in just a few hours for less than US$8 on a cloud server. And if you have a powerful computer at home with 16 or more cores, you could accomplish this even more swiftly and cost-effectively.</p><p>There’s no good reason to use 512 or 768-bit keys these days. Email providers should automatically reject any DKIM signature generated with an RSA key shorter than 1,024 bits. We’ve alerted Yahoo, Mailfence, and Tuta about our findings and shared this advice with them.</p><p>Domain owners must also take action by reviewing their DNS settings for any outdated DKIM records that don’t comply with the 1,024-bit minimum standard. A simple way to check a DKIM record’s <code>p</code> tag is to count its Base64 characters: a 1,024-bit RSA public key will have at least 216 characters.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Bye-bye Windows gaming? SteamOS officially expands past the Steam Deck (206 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/01/bye-bye-windows-gaming-steamos-officially-expands-past-the-steam-deck/</link>
            <guid>42633269</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 11:56:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/01/bye-bye-windows-gaming-steamos-officially-expands-past-the-steam-deck/">https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/01/bye-bye-windows-gaming-steamos-officially-expands-past-the-steam-deck/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42633269">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                      
                      
          <p>Almost exactly a year ago, we were <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2024/01/why-more-pc-gaming-handhelds-should-ditch-windows-for-steamos/">publicly yearning</a> for the day when more portable gaming PC makers could ditch Windows in favor of SteamOS (without having to resort to <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/06/the-linux-coders-turning-the-rog-ally-and-other-handhelds-into-steam-deck-clones/">touchy unofficial workarounds</a>). Now, that day has finally come, with Lenovo <a href="https://news.lenovo.com/pressroom/press-releases/lenovo-legion-unleashes-next-gen-gaming-power-at-ces-2025/">announcing</a> the upcoming Legion Go S as the first non-Valve handheld to come with an officially licensed copy of SteamOS preinstalled. And Valve promises that it will soon ship a beta version of SteamOS for users to "download and test themselves."</p>
<p>As Lenovo's slightly downsized followup to <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2023/09/lenovo-legion-go-suggests-gaming-portables-arent-big-enough-need-a-mouse/">2023's massive Legion Go</a>, the Legion Go S won't feature the detachable controllers of its predecessor. But the new PC gaming handheld will come in two distinct versions, one with the now-standard Windows 11 installation and another edition that's the first to sport the (<a href="https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2024/12/the-return-of-steam-machines-valve-rolls-out-new-powered-by-steamos-branding/">recently leaked</a>) "Powered by SteamOS" branding.</p>
<p>The lack of a Windows license seems to contribute to a lower starting cost for the "Powered by SteamOS" edition of the Legion Go S, which will start at $500 when it's made available in May. Lenovo says the Windows edition of the device—available starting this month—will start at $730, with "additional configurations" available in May starting as low as $600.</p>
<figure>
    <p><img width="1024" height="493" src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/legiongoswindows.png" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/legiongoswindows.png 1024w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/legiongoswindows-640x308.png 640w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/legiongoswindows-768x370.png 768w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/legiongoswindows-980x472.png 980w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">
                  </p>
          <figcaption>
        <div>
    
    <p>
      The Windows version of the Legion Go S will come with a different color and a higher price.

              <span>
          Credit:

                      <a href="https://news.lenovo.com/pressroom/press-releases/lenovo-legion-unleashes-next-gen-gaming-power-at-ces-2025/" target="_blank">
          
          Lenovo

                      </a>
                  </span>
          </p>
  </div>
      </figcaption>
      </figure>

<p>Both the Windows and SteamOS versions of the Legion Go S will weigh in at 1.61 lbs with an 8-inch 1200p 120 Hz LCD screen, up to 32GB of RAM, and either AMD's <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/01/amds-new-ryzen-z2-cpus-boost-gaming-handhelds-if-you-buy-the-best-one/">new Ryzen Z2 Go chipset</a>&nbsp;or an older Z1 core.</p>
<h2>Watch out, Windows?</h2>
<p>Valve <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/news/app/593110/view/529834914570306831">said in a blog post on Tuesday</a> that the Legion Go S will sport the same version of SteamOS currently found on the Steam Deck. The company's work getting SteamOS onto the Legion Go S will also "improve compatibility with other handhelds," Valve said, and the company "is working on SteamOS support for more devices in the future."</p>

          
                      
                  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Comet is a handheld Linux computer that brings extensibility (129 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://mecha.so/comet</link>
            <guid>42632865</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 10:44:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://mecha.so/comet">https://mecha.so/comet</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42632865">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://mecha.so/comet: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Aging Programmer (203 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mVWQQeSOD0M</link>
            <guid>42632772</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 10:22:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mVWQQeSOD0M">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mVWQQeSOD0M</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42632772">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mVWQQeSOD0M: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Operating System in 1,000 Lines – Intro (727 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://operating-system-in-1000-lines.vercel.app/en</link>
            <guid>42631873</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 07:18:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://operating-system-in-1000-lines.vercel.app/en">https://operating-system-in-1000-lines.vercel.app/en</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42631873">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Hey there! In this book, we're going to build a small operating system from scratch, step by step.</p>
<p>You might get intimidated when you hear OS or kernel development, the basic functions of an OS (especially the kernel) are surprisingly simple. Even Linux, which is often cited as a huge open-source software, was only 8,413 lines in version 0.01. Today's Linux kernel is overwhelmingly large, but it started with a tiny codebase, just like your hobby project.</p>
<p>We'll implement basic context switching, paging, user mode, a command-line shell, a disk device driver, and file read/write operations in C. Sounds like a lot, however, it's only 1,000 lines of code!</p>
<p>One thing you should remember is, it's not easy as it sounds. The tricky part of creating your own OS is debugging. You can't do <code>printf</code> debugging until you implement it. You'll need to learn different debugging techniques and skills you've never needed in application development. Especially when starting "from scratch", you'll encounter challenging parts like boot process and paging. But don't worry! We'll also learn "how to debug an OS" too!</p>
<p>The tougher the debugging, the more satisfying it is when it works. Let's dive into exciting world of OS development!</p>
<ul>
<li>You can download the implementation examples from <a href="https://github.com/nuta/operating-system-in-1000-lines">GitHub</a>.</li>
<li>This book is available under the <a href="https://creativecommons.jp/faq">CC BY 4.0 license</a>. The implementation examples and source code in the text are under the <a href="https://opensource.org/licenses/MIT">MIT license</a>.</li>
<li>The prerequisites are familiarity with C language and with UNIX-like environment. If you've <code>gcc hello.c &amp;&amp; ./a.out</code>, you're good to go!</li>
<li>This book was originally written as an appendix of my book <em><a href="https://www.shuwasystem.co.jp/book/9784798068718.html">Design and Implementation of Microkernels</a></em> (written in Japanese).</li>
</ul>
<p>Happy OS hacking!</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Gate-level simulation of ASIC in browser (172 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://znah.net/tt09/</link>
            <guid>42631629</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 06:38:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://znah.net/tt09/">https://znah.net/tt09/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42631629">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    <h2>TT09 VGA CA</h2>
    
    <p>
        This is a gate-level simulation of my <a href="https://tinytapeout.com/">TinyTapeout</a> '09 submission running directly in your browser. The circuit occupies a single 160x100 μm tile on a multiproject chip and generates a 60fps 640x480 VGA signal that forms a scrolling animation of several <a href="https://mathworld.wolfram.com/ElementaryCellularAutomaton.html">elementary 1D cellular automata</a> rules. Most of the tile area is occupied by two 160-bit shift registers: one (left) stores the current image line, while another (right) stores the first line of the next frame (4th line of the current).
    </p>
    <p>
        This demo combines a tiny custom WebAssembly gate-level <a href="https://github.com/znah/tt09/blob/main/gates.c">simulator</a> with a <a href="https://google.github.io/swissgl/">SwissGL</a>-based interactive visualization of gate activations. The overlay displays the content of the simulated VGA screen and the current ray position.
    </p>
    <p>Links:</p>
    <ul>
        <li><a href="https://github.com/znah/tt09-vga-ca">ASIC design repository</a> (<a href="https://github.com/znah/tt09-vga-ca/blob/main/src/project.v">project.v</a>)</li>
        <li><a href="https://github.com/znah/tt09">Demo page repository</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://tinytapeout.com/runs/tt09/tt_um_znah_vga_ca">TinyTapeout'09 tile</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://znah.net/tt09-vga-ca/">Circuit 3D view</a></li>
    </ul>

    <iframe id="video" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/XtRncOmQN7c?si=HIwZzaOeo9nyTHsK" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>


</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Annual 'winners' for most egregious US healthcare profiteering announced (152 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/jan/07/annual-awards-healthcare-profiteering</link>
            <guid>42630030</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 01:48:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/jan/07/annual-awards-healthcare-profiteering">https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/jan/07/annual-awards-healthcare-profiteering</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42630030">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p>The 2024 “winners” of the annual <a href="https://lowninstitute.org/projects/2024-shkreli-awards/" data-link-name="in body link">Shkreli awards</a>, given each year to perpetrators of the most egregious examples of profiteering and dysfunction within the healthcare industry, have been released from the Lown Institute, an independent healthcare thinktank.</p><p>The recipients are chosen by a panel made up of health policy experts, clinicians, journalists and advocates. The awards are named after <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/martin-shkreli" data-link-name="in body link">Martin Shkreli</a>, the infamous “pharma bro” who rose to international notoriety after increasing the price of lifesaving anti-parasitic drug Daraprim 50-fold.</p><p>“All these stories paint a picture of a healthcare industry in desperate need of transformation. In 2024, healthcare practices were put in the spotlight,” Vikas Saini, president of the Lown Institute, said during the ceremony.</p><p>“But doing these awards every year shows us that this is nothing new. We’re hoping that these stories illuminate what changes are needed.”</p><p>The No 10 spot this year went to the University of North Texas health science center in Fort Worth for allegedly neglecting to notify next of kin before selling body parts of deceased people.</p><p>An <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/university-north-texas-corpses-dissected-unclaimed-bodies-rcna170478" data-link-name="in body link">NBC News</a> investigation uncovered that the school did not properly receive consent from the deceased or their family members before dissecting and distributing unclaimed bodies, despite the network finding that said family members were fairly easy to identify and contact.</p><p>The ninth spot was given to the outdated practice of baby tongue-tie cutting, which continues to be falsely touted as a cure for several ailments, from sleep apnea to nursing trouble, according to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/07/29/health/tongue-tie-releases-aap.html#:~:text=One%20study%20estimated%20an%20800,Serious%20complications%20are%20rare." data-link-name="in body link">the New York Times</a>.</p><p>Shady billing practices from Zynex Medical, a company specializing in nerve-stimulation devices used for pain management, took the No 8 slot. Patients received Zynex devices understanding the expense would be covered by insurance, according to a report from <a href="https://www.statnews.com/2024/06/04/zynex-medical-pain-patient-tens-unit-batteries-electrodes-bills/" data-link-name="in body link">Stat News</a>. Users then got unsolicited supplies of items like batteries and electrode pads delivered to them (often excessive quantities), which they ultimately got charged for. The report states<em> </em>that almost 70% of Zynex’s $184m in revenue in 2023 came from batteries and electrode pads.</p><p>“This is just classic over-billing. It’s fraud,” Patricia Kelmar, a senior director at the research group US Pirg and judge on the panel, said. “The patients feel that they owe the money because they already received the supplies. We see a lot of this kind of abuse within the pain-management field.”</p><p>The seventh spot was given to Sara England and her infant son, Amari Vaca. After the three-month-old experienced severe respiratory distress two months after open-heart surgery, doctors at Natividad medical center in Salinas, California, chose to have him <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/health-coverage-medical-debt-air-ambulance-kff-sara-england-amari/" data-link-name="in body link">transferred via air ambulance</a> to a medical center in San Francisco. He recovered and Cigna later deemed the service “not medically necessary”. The family was given a $97,599 bill.</p><p>“This is happening everywhere,” Kelmar said. “The insurance denial here is that it should have been a ground ambulance instead of air, but how is the patient supposed to know that? This is a mother taking medical advice from the doctors.”</p><p>At No 6 was Medicare’s mass billing for urinary catheters. As many as 450,000 beneficiaries had bills for catheters submitted on their behalf in 2023, representing an 800% increase over previous years. Just <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/texas/news/i-team-texas-company-connected-to-alleged-scheme-that-billed-medicare-3b-for-urinary-catheters/" data-link-name="in body link">seven suppliers</a> were responsible for $2bn of these suspicious charges.</p><p>Taking the No 5 spot was Memorial medical center (a former non-profit turned for-profit) in Las Cruces, New Mexico, for allegations of <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/health/cancer/cancer-patients-say-new-mexico-hospital-turned-them-away-rcna147184" data-link-name="in body link">refusing cancer treatment to patients</a> or demanding upfront payments, even from those with insurance.</p><p>ProPublica’s uncovering of a once-celebrated oncologist’s pattern of <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/thomas-weiner-montana-st-peters-hospital-oncology" data-link-name="in body link">malpractice and trails of suspicious deaths</a> came in at No 4. Dr Thomas C Weiner of Helena, Montana, reportedly subjected one patient to unnecessary cancer treatments for more than a decade, amid a myriad of other shocking revelations.</p><p>Lumakras, a cancer drug from Amgen that was <a href="https://kffhealthnews.org/news/article/amgen-cancer-drug-sotorasib-lumakras-high-dosage-fda-dosing-trials/" data-link-name="in body link">granted accelerated FDA approval</a> at a daily dose of 960mg, despite findings that a 240mg dose offered similar efficacy with reduced toxicity and risk of side effects, grabbed the third spot.</p><p>“Pharma companies have that same incentive to get a return on profits,” said Kelmar. “The healthcare industry is a business, and businesses will try to get the highest profits possible.”</p><p>At No 2 was the <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2024/dec/14/unitedhealth-group-chief-andrew-witty-new-york-times-essay" data-link-name="in body link">behemoth that is UnitedHealth</a> and how it’s become the fourth-largest business in the nation. Doctors for United have reported pressure to reduce time spent with patients, and make patients seem as sick as possible through aggressive medical coding tactics.</p><p>In a highly competitive year, the top spot went to Steward Health Care, whose CEO, Ralph de la Torre, is accused of <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2024/sep/25/ralph-de-la-torre-congress-criminal-contempt" data-link-name="in body link">prioritizing private-equity profits</a> over patient care. His financial scheming led to bankruptcy, leaving hospitals in shambles, employees laid off and communities with less healthcare access.</p><p>“I want to say that this is our backyard,” said Saini.</p><p>“What was going on here was on the grapevine for many years. And if we knew about it, then we have to ask: ‘Where are the regulators? Where are the people who should’ve known better?”</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Oracle Will Not Voluntarily Withdraw JavaScript Trademark (146 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/deno_land/status/1876728474666217739</link>
            <guid>42629256</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:01:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/deno_land/status/1876728474666217739">https://twitter.com/deno_land/status/1876728474666217739</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42629256">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A day in the life of a prolific voice phishing crew (265 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://krebsonsecurity.com/2025/01/a-day-in-the-life-of-a-prolific-voice-phishing-crew/</link>
            <guid>42629163</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 23:51:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2025/01/a-day-in-the-life-of-a-prolific-voice-phishing-crew/">https://krebsonsecurity.com/2025/01/a-day-in-the-life-of-a-prolific-voice-phishing-crew/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42629163">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
												<p>Besieged by scammers seeking to phish user accounts over the telephone, <strong>Apple</strong> and <strong>Google</strong> frequently caution that they will never reach out unbidden to users this way. However, new details about the internal operations of a prolific voice phishing gang show the group routinely abuses legitimate services at Apple and Google to force a variety of outbound communications to their users, including emails, automated phone calls and system-level messages sent to all signed-in devices.</p>
<div id="attachment_69859"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-69859" decoding="async" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/thumb-mobile.png" alt="" width="701" height="413"></p><p id="caption-attachment-69859">Image: Shutterstock, iHaMoo.</p></div>
<p>KrebsOnSecurity recently told the saga of a cryptocurrency investor named <strong>Tony</strong> who was robbed of more than $4.7 million in <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2024/12/how-to-lose-a-fortune-with-just-one-bad-click/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an elaborate voice phishing attack</a>. In Tony’s ordeal, the crooks appear to have initially contacted him via <strong>Google Assistant</strong>, an AI-based service that can engage in two-way conversations. The phishers also abused legitimate Google services to send Tony an email from google.com, and to send a Google account recovery prompt to all of his signed-in devices.</p>
<p>Today’s story pivots off of Tony’s heist and new details shared by a scammer to explain how these voice phishing groups are abusing a legitimate Apple telephone support line to generate “account confirmation” message prompts from Apple to their customers.</p>
<p>Before we get to the Apple scam in detail, we need to revisit Tony’s case. The phishing domain used to steal roughly $4.7 million in cryptocurrencies from Tony was <strong>verify-trezor[.]io</strong>. This domain was featured in <a href="https://www.lookout.com/threat-intelligence/article/cryptochameleon-fcc-phishing-kit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a writeup from February 2024</a> by the security firm <strong>Lookout</strong>, which found it was one of dozens being used by a prolific and audacious voice phishing group it dubbed “<strong>Crypto Chameleon</strong>.”</p>
<p>Crypto Chameleon was brazenly trying to voice phish employees at the <strong>U.S. Federal Communications Commission</strong> (FCC), as well as those working at the cryptocurrency exchanges <strong>Coinbase</strong> and <strong>Binance</strong>. Lookout researchers discovered multiple voice phishing groups were using a new phishing kit that closely mimicked the single sign-on pages for <strong>Okta</strong> and other authentication providers.</p>
<p>As we’ll see in a moment, that phishing kit is operated and rented out by a cybercriminal known as “<strong>Perm</strong>” a.k.a. “<strong>Annie</strong>.” Perm is the current administrator of <strong>Star Fraud</strong>, one of the more consequential cybercrime communities on Telegram and one that has emerged as a foundry of innovation in voice phishing attacks.</p>
<p>A review of the many messages that Perm posted to Star Fraud and other Telegram channels showed they worked closely with another cybercriminal who went by the handles “<strong>Aristotle</strong>” and just “<strong>Stotle</strong>.”</p>
<p>It is not clear what caused the rift, but at some point last year Stotle decided to turn on his erstwhile business partner Perm, sharing extremely detailed videos, tutorials and secrets that shed new light on how these phishing panels operate.</p>
<p>Stotle explained that the division of spoils from each robbery is decided in advance by all participants. Some co-conspirators will be paid a set fee for each call, while others are promised a percentage of any overall amount stolen. The person in charge of managing or renting out the phishing panel to others will generally take a percentage of each theft, which in Perm’s case is 10 percent.</p>
<p>When the phishing group settles on a target of interest, the scammers will create and join a new <strong>Discord</strong> channel. This allows each logged on member to share what is currently on their screen, and these screens are tiled in a series of boxes so that everyone can see all other call participant screens at once.</p>
<p>Each participant in the call has a specific role, including:</p>
<p>-The Caller: The person speaking and trying to social engineer the target.<br>
-The Operator: The individual managing the phishing panel, silently moving the victim from page to page.<br>
-The Drainer: The person who logs into compromised accounts to drain the victim’s funds.<br>
-The Owner: The phishing panel owner, who will frequently listen in on and participate in scam calls.</p>
<h2>‘OKAY, SO THIS REALLY IS APPLE’</h2>
<p>In one video of a live voice phishing attack shared by Stotle, scammers using Perm’s panel targeted a musician in California. Throughout the video, we can see Perm monitoring the conversation and operating the phishing panel in the upper right corner of the screen.</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" title="YouTube video player" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/F44un1_y2fs?si=fmYxbcLS3TDtHjrs" width="750" height="315" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"><span data-mce-type="bookmark" style="display: inline-block; width: 0px; overflow: hidden; line-height: 0;" class="mce_SELRES_start">﻿</span></iframe></p>
<p>In the first step of the attack, they <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2024/03/recent-mfa-bombing-attacks-targeting-apple-users/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">peppered the target’s Apple device with notifications from Apple</a> by attempting to reset his password. Then a “<strong>Michael Keen</strong>” called him, spoofing Apple’s phone number and saying they were with Apple’s account recovery team.</p>
<p>The target told Michael that someone was trying to change his password, which Michael calmly explained they would investigate. Michael said he was going to send a prompt to the man’s device, and proceeded to place a call to an automated line that answered as Apple support saying, “I’d like to send a consent notification to your Apple devices. Do I have permission to do that?”</p>
<p>In this segment of the video, we can see the operator of the panel is calling the real Apple customer support phone number <strong>800-275-2273</strong>, but they are doing so by spoofing the target’s phone number (the victim’s number is redacted in the video above). That’s because calling this support number from a phone number tied to an Apple account and selecting “1” for “yes” will then send an alert from Apple that displays the following message on all associated devices:</p>
<div id="attachment_70000"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-70000" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/appleconfirmation.png" alt="" width="393" height="448"></p><p id="caption-attachment-70000">Calling the Apple support number 800-275-2273 from a phone number tied to an Apple account will cause a prompt similar to this one to appear on all connected Apple devices.</p></div>
<p>KrebsOnSecurity asked two different security firms to test this using the caller ID spoofing service shown in Perm’s video, and sure enough calling that 800 number for Apple by spoofing my phone number as the source caused the Apple Account Confirmation to pop up on all of my signed-in Apple devices.</p>
<p>In essence, the voice phishers are using an automated Apple phone support line to send notifications from Apple and to trick people into thinking they’re really talking with Apple. The phishing panel video leaked by Stotle shows this technique fooled the target, who felt completely at ease that he was talking to Apple after receiving the support prompt on his iPhone.</p>
<p>“Okay, so this really is Apple,” the man said after receiving the alert from Apple. “Yeah, that’s definitely not me trying to reset my password.”</p>
<p>“Not a problem, we can go ahead and take care of this today,” Michael replied. “I’ll go ahead and prompt your device with the steps to close out this ticket. Before I do that, I do highly suggest that you change your password in the settings app of your device.”</p>
<p>The target said they weren’t sure exactly how to do that. Michael replied “no problem,” and then described how to change the account password, which the man said he did on his own device. At this point, the musician was still in control of his iCloud account.</p>
<p>“Password is changed,” the man said. “I don’t know what that was, but I appreciate the call.”</p>
<p>“Yup,” Michael replied, setting up the killer blow. “I’ll go ahead and prompt you with the next step to close out this ticket. Please give me one moment.”</p>
<p>The target then received a text message that referenced information about his account, stating that he was in a support call with Michael. Included in the message was a link to a website that mimicked Apple’s iCloud login page — <strong>17505-apple[.]com</strong>. Once the target navigated to the phishing page, the video showed Perm’s screen in the upper right corner opening the phishing page from their end.</p>
<p>“Oh okay, now I log in with my Apple ID?,” the man asked.</p>
<p>“Yup, then just follow the steps it requires, and if you need any help, just let me know,” Michael replied.</p>
<p>As the victim typed in their Apple password and one-time passcode at the fake Apple site, Perm’s screen could be seen in the background logging into the victim’s iCloud account.</p>
<p>It’s unclear whether the phishers were able to steal any cryptocurrency from the victim in this case, who did not respond to requests for comment. However, shortly after this video was recorded, someone leaked several music recordings stolen from the victim’s iCloud account.</p>
<p>At the conclusion of the call, Michael offered to configure the victim’s Apple profile so that any further changes to the account would need to happen in person at a physical Apple store. This appears to be one of several scripted ploys used by these voice phishers to gain and maintain the target’s confidence.</p>
<p>A tutorial shared by Stotle titled “Social Engineering Script” includes a number of tips for scam callers that can help establish trust or a rapport with their prey. When the callers are impersonating Coinbase employees, for example, they will offer to sign the user up for the company’s free security email newsletter.</p>
<p>“Also, for your security, we are able to subscribe you to Coinbase Bytes, which will basically give you updates to your email about data breaches and updates to your Coinbase account,” the script reads. “So we should have gone ahead and successfully subscribed you, and you should have gotten an email confirmation. Please let me know if that is the case. Alright, perfect.”</p>
<p>In reality, all they are doing is entering the target’s email address into Coinbase’s public email newsletter signup page, but it’s a remarkably effective technique because it demonstrates to the would-be victim that the caller has the ability to send emails from Coinbase.com.</p>
<p>Asked to comment for this story, Apple said there has been no breach, hack, or technical exploit of iCloud or Apple services, and that the company is continuously adding new protections to address new and emerging threats. For example, it said it has implemented rate limiting for multi-factor authentication requests, which <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2024/03/recent-mfa-bombing-attacks-targeting-apple-users/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have been abused by voice phishing groups to impersonate Apple</a>.</p>
<p>Apple said its representatives will never ask users to provide their password, device passcode, or two-factor authentication code or to enter it into a web page, even if it looks like an official Apple website. If a user receives a message or call that claims to be from Apple, <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/120569" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here is what the user should expect</a>.</p>

<h2>AUTODOXERS</h2>
<p>According to Stotle, the target lists used by their phishing callers originate mostly from a few crypto-related data breaches, including the 2022 and <a href="https://blog.trezor.io/trezor-security-update-stay-vigilant-against-potential-phishing-attack-bb05015a21f8?gi=4a9e1da3b8b2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2024 breaches</a> involving user account data stolen from cryptocurrency hardware wallet vendor <strong>Trezor</strong>.</p>
<p>Perm’s group and other crypto phishing gangs rely on a mix of homemade code and third-party data broker services to refine their target lists. Known as “<strong>autodoxers</strong>,” these tools help phishing gangs quickly automate the acquisition and/or verification of personal data on a target prior to each call attempt.</p>
<div id="attachment_69998"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-69998" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/vbals-autodoxer.png" alt="" width="748" height="592" srcset="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/vbals-autodoxer.png 1067w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/vbals-autodoxer-768x607.png 768w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/vbals-autodoxer-782x619.png 782w" sizes="(max-width: 748px) 100vw, 748px"></p><p id="caption-attachment-69998">One “autodoxer” service advertised on Telegram that promotes a range of voice phishing tools and services.</p></div>
<p>Stotle said their autodoxer used a Telegram bot that leverages hacked accounts at consumer data brokers to gather a wealth of information about their targets, including their full Social Security number, date of birth, current and previous addresses, employer, and the names of family members.</p>
<p>The autodoxers are used to verify that each email address on a target list has an active account at Coinbase or another cryptocurrency exchange, ensuring that the attackers don’t waste time calling people who have no cryptocurrency to steal.</p>
<p>Some of these autodoxer tools also will check the value of the target’s home address at property search services online, and then sort the target lists so that the wealthiest are at the top.</p>
<h2>CRYPTO THIEVES IN THE SHARK TANK</h2>
<p>Stotle’s messages on Discord and Telegram show that a phishing group renting Perm’s panel voice-phished tens of thousands of dollars worth of cryptocurrency from the billionaire <strong>Mark Cuban</strong>.</p>
<p>“I was an idiot,” Cuban told KrebsOnsecurity when asked about <a href="https://www.dallasnews.com/business/2024/06/23/mark-cubans-public-email-was-hacked-after-receiving-call-from-a-fake-google-rep/?outputType=amp" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the June 2024 attack</a>, which he first disclosed in a short-lived post on Twitter/X. “We were shooting Shark Tank and I was rushing between pitches.”</p>
<div id="attachment_70008"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-70008" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/sharktank.png" alt="" width="749" height="435" srcset="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/sharktank.png 780w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/sharktank-768x446.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 749px) 100vw, 749px"></p><p id="caption-attachment-70008">Image: Shutterstock, ssi77.</p></div>
<p>Cuban said he first received a notice from Google that someone had tried to log in to his account. Then he got a call from what appeared to be a Google phone number. Cuban said he ignored several of these emails and calls until he decided they probably wouldn’t stop unless he answered.</p>
<p>“So I answered, and wasn’t paying enough attention,” he said. “They asked for the circled number that comes up on the screen. Like a moron, I gave it to them, and they were in.”</p>
<p>Unfortunately for Cuban, somewhere in his inbox were the secret “seed phrases” protecting two of his cryptocurrency accounts, and armed with those credentials the crooks were able to drain his funds. All told, the thieves managed to steal roughly $43,000 worth of cryptocurrencies from Cuban’s wallets — a relatively small heist for this crew.</p>
<p>“They must have done some keyword searches,” once inside his Gmail account, Cuban said. “I had sent myself an email I had forgotten about that had my seed words for 2 accounts that weren’t very active any longer. I had moved almost everything but some smaller balances to Coinbase.”</p>
<h2>LIFE IS A GAME: MONEY IS HOW WE KEEP SCORE</h2>
<p>Cybercriminals involved in voice phishing communities on Telegram are universally obsessed with their crypto holdings, mainly because in this community one’s demonstrable wealth is primarily what confers social status. It is not uncommon to see members sizing one another up using a verbal shorthand of “figs,” as in figures of crypto wealth.</p>
<p>For example, a low-level caller with no experience will sometimes be mockingly referred to as a 3fig or 3f, as in a person with less than $1,000 to their name. Salaries for callers are often also referenced this way, e.g. “Weekly salary: 5f.”</p>
<div id="attachment_70058"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-70058" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/howitstartedhowitsgoing.png" alt="" width="749" height="416" srcset="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/howitstartedhowitsgoing.png 1265w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/howitstartedhowitsgoing-768x426.png 768w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/howitstartedhowitsgoing-782x434.png 782w" sizes="(max-width: 749px) 100vw, 749px"></p><p id="caption-attachment-70058">This meme shared by Stotle uses humor to depict an all-too-common pathway for voice phishing callers, who are often minors recruited from gaming networks like Minecraft and Roblox. The image that Lookout used in its blog post for Crypto Chameleon can be seen in the lower right hooded figure.</p></div>
<p>Voice phishing groups frequently require new members to provide “proof of funds” — screenshots of their crypto holdings, ostensibly to demonstrate they are not penniless — before they’re allowed to join.</p>
<p>This proof of funds (POF) demand is typical among thieves selling high-dollar items, because it tends to cut down on the time-wasting inquiries from criminals who can’t afford what’s for sale anyway. But it has become so common in cybercrime communities that there are now several services designed to create fake POF images and videos, allowing customers to brag about large crypto holdings without actually possessing said wealth.</p>
<p>Several of the phishing panel videos shared by Stotle feature audio that suggests co-conspirators were practicing responses to certain call scenarios, while other members of the phishing group critiqued them or tried disrupt their social engineering by being verbally abusive.</p>
<p>These groups will organize and operate for a few weeks, but tend to disintegrate when one member of the conspiracy decides to steal some or all of the loot, referred to in these communities as “snaking” others out of their agreed-upon sums. Almost invariably, the phishing groups will splinter apart over the drama caused by one of these snaking events, and individual members eventually will then re-form a new phishing group.</p>
<p><strong>Allison Nixon</strong> is the chief research officer for <a href="https://www.unit221b.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Unit 221B</a>, a cybersecurity firm in New York that has worked on a number of investigations involving these voice phishing groups. Nixon said the constant snaking within the voice phishing circles points to a psychological self-selection phenomenon that is in desperate need of academic study.</p>
<p>“In short, a person whose moral compass lets them rob old people will also be a bad business partner,” Nixon said. “This is another fundamental flaw in this ecosystem and why most groups end in betrayal. This structural problem is great for journalists and the police too. Lots of snitching.”</p>
<h2>POINTS FOR BRAZENNESS</h2>
<p>Asked about the size of Perm’s phishing enterprise, Stotle said there were dozens of distinct phishing groups paying to use Perm’s panel. He said each group was assigned their own subdomain on Perm’s main “command and control server,” which naturally uses the domain name <strong>commandandcontrolserver[.]com</strong>.</p>
<p>A review of that domain’s history via <strong>DomainTools.com</strong> shows there are at least 57 separate subdomains scattered across commandandcontrolserver[.]com and two other related control domains — <strong>thebackendserver[.]com</strong> and <strong>lookoutsucks[.]com</strong>. That latter domain was created and deployed shortly after Lookout published its blog post on Crypto Chameleon.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://urlscan.io/search/#page.url%3A%22captcha%3Forigin%3D%22" target="_blank" rel="noopener">dozens of phishing domains that phone home to these control servers</a> are all kept offline when they are not actively being used in phishing attacks. A social engineering training guide shared by Stotle explains this practice minimizes the chances that a phishing domain will get “redpaged,” a reference to the default red warning pages served by Google Chrome or Firefox whenever someone tries to visit a site that’s been flagged for phishing or distributing malware.</p>
<p>What’s more, while the phishing sites are live their operators typically place a CAPTCHA challenge in front of the main page to prevent security services from scanning and flagging the sites as malicious.</p>
<p>It may seem odd that so many cybercriminal groups operate so openly on instant collaboration networks like Telegram and Discord. After all, this blog is replete with stories about cybercriminals getting caught thanks to personal details they inadvertently leaked or disclosed themselves.</p>
<p>Nixon said the relative openness of these cybercrime communities makes them inherently risky, but it also allows for the rapid formation and recruitment of new potential co-conspirators. Moreover, today’s English-speaking cybercriminals tend to be <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2024/10/lamborghini-carjackers-lured-by-243m-cyberheist/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more afraid of getting home invaded or mugged by fellow cyber thieves</a> than they are of being arrested by authorities.</p>
<p>“The biggest structural threat to the online criminal ecosystem is not the police or researchers, it is fellow criminals,” Nixon said. “To protect them from themselves, every criminal forum and marketplace has a reputation system, even though they know it’s a major liability when the police come. That is why I am not worried as we see criminals migrate to various ‘encrypted’ platforms that promise to ignore the&nbsp;police. To protect themselves better against the&nbsp;law, they have to ditch their protections against fellow&nbsp;criminals and that’s not going to happen.”</p>
											</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>