<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 14:30:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Finland's National Allergy Program Successfully Reduces Allergic Diseases (159 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://publications.ersnet.org/content/erj/49/6/1700470</link>
            <guid>43370956</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 08:23:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://publications.ersnet.org/content/erj/49/6/1700470">https://publications.ersnet.org/content/erj/49/6/1700470</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43370956">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://publications.ersnet.org/content/erj/49/6/1700470: Error [ERR_FR_TOO_MANY_REDIRECTS]: Maximum number of redirects exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Transformers Without Normalization (149 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://jiachenzhu.github.io/DyT/</link>
            <guid>43369633</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 03:12:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://jiachenzhu.github.io/DyT/">https://jiachenzhu.github.io/DyT/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43369633">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <!-- Figure Section -->
        <div id="figure">
                <p><img src="https://jiachenzhu.github.io/DyT/webpage_assets/before_after.svg" alt="Dynamic Tanh (DyT) as a replacement for normalization in Transformers"></p><p><em>Left:</em> original Transformer block. <em>Right:</em> block with our proposed Dynamic Tanh (DyT) layer. <br>
                    DyT is a straightforward replacement for commonly used Layer Norm or RMSNorm layers. <br>
                    Transformers with DyT match or exceed the performance of their normalized counterparts.
                </p>
            </div>

        <!-- Abstract Section -->
        <section id="abstract">
            <h2>Abstract</h2>
                <p>
                    Normalization layers are ubiquitous in modern neural networks and have long been considered essential.
                    This work demonstrates that Transformers without normalization can achieve the same or better performance using a remarkably simple technique.
                    We introduce Dynamic Tanh (DyT), an element-wise operation $$\mathrm{DyT}(\boldsymbol{x}) = \tanh(\alpha \boldsymbol{x}),$$ as a drop-in replacement for normalization layers in Transformers.
                    DyT is inspired by the observation that layer normalization in Transformers often produces tanh-like, S-shaped input-output mappings.
                    By incorporating DyT, Transformers without normalization can match or exceed the performance of their normalized counterparts, mostly without hyperparameter tuning.
                    We validate the effectiveness of Transformers with DyT across diverse settings, ranging from recognition to generation, supervised to self-supervised learning, and computer vision to language models.
                    These findings challenge the conventional understanding that normalization layers are indispensable in modern neural networks, and offer new insights into their role in deep networks.
                </p>
        </section>
        
        <!-- Implementation Section -->
        <section id="implementation">
            <h2>Implementation</h2>
            <p>
                DyT module can be implemented in a few lines of PyTorch code:
            </p>
            
            <div>
                <pre id="code-block-dyt"><code>class DyT(nn.Module):
    def __init__(self, num_features, alpha_init_value=0.5):
        super().__init__()
        self.alpha = nn.Parameter(torch.ones(1) * alpha_init_value)
        self.weight = nn.Parameter(torch.ones(num_features))
        self.bias = nn.Parameter(torch.zeros(num_features))
    
    def forward(self, x):
        x = torch.tanh(self.alpha * x)
        return x * self.weight + self.bias</code></pre>
            </div>
        </section>

        <!-- Key Findings Section -->
        <section id="key-findings">
            <h2>Key Findings</h2>
            
            <div>
                    
                            <h4>Layer Normalization Behaves Like Scaled Tanh Function</h4>
                            <p>Our analysis shows that layer normalization (LN) in Transformers generates input-output mappings that closely resemble scaled tanh functions. In the earlier layers, these mappings are mostly linear. However, in deeper layers, they take on distinct S-shaped curves characteristic of tanh functions.</p>
                            
                            <div>
                                <p><img src="https://jiachenzhu.github.io/DyT/webpage_assets/figures/inout_vit.png" alt="Input-output relationships in ViT normalization layers">
                                </p>
                                <p><img src="https://jiachenzhu.github.io/DyT/webpage_assets/figures/inout_w2v.png" alt="Input-output relationships in wav2vec 2.0 normalization layers">
                                </p>
                                <p><img src="https://jiachenzhu.github.io/DyT/webpage_assets/figures/inout_dit.png" alt="Input-output relationships in DiT normalization layers">
                                </p>
                                <p><em>Output vs. input of selected LN layers in Vision Transformer (ViT), wav2vec 2.0 (a Transformer model for speech), and Diffusion Transformer (DiT). We plot the input/output values of four LN layers in each model. The S-shaped curves highly resemble that of a tanh function.</em>
                                </p>
                            
                            </div>
                        
                </div>


        <!-- Evaluation Section -->
        <section id="evaluation">
            <h2>Evaluation</h2>
            <p>
                We present a comprehensive evaluation of DyT across a diverse range of architectures and tasks, highlighting its effectiveness and generalizability.  
                Our experiments cover supervised learning in vision (<b>ViT</b> and <b>ConvNeXt</b>), self-supervised learning in vision (<b>MAE</b> and <b>DINO</b>), diffusion models (<b>DiT</b>), large language models (<b>LLaMA</b>), self-supervised learning in speech (<b>wav2vec 2.0</b>), and DNA sequence modeling (<b>HyenaDNA</b> and <b>Caduceus</b>).  
                In every case, Transformers with DyT achieves similar or better performance than their normalized counterparts.  
                For detailed results and comparisons, please refer to our paper.    
            </p>
        </section>                    
                        

            

        <!-- Resources Section -->
        <section id="resources">
            <h2>Resources</h2>
            <div>
                <div>
                            <h5><i></i>Paper</h5>
                            <p>Download our paper for all the details about our research.</p>
                            <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10622">Download Paper</a>
                        </p></div>
                <div>
                            <h5><i></i>Code</h5>
                            <p>Check out our repository for implementation details.</p>
                            <p><a href="https://github.com/jiachenzhu/DyT">View on GitHub</a>
                        </p></div>
                <div>
                            <h5><i></i>Summary</h5>
                            <p>Read a concise summary of our research findings on X.</p>
                            <p><a href="https://x.com/liuzhuang1234/status/1900370738588135805">View Summary</a>
                        </p></div>
            </div>
        </section>

        <!-- Citations Section -->
        <!-- Citations Section -->
<!-- Citations Section -->
<section id="citations">
    <h2>BibTeX</h2>
            <div>
                <pre id="code-block-citation"><code>@inproceedings{Zhu2025DyT,
  title={Transformers without Normalization},
  author={Zhu, Jiachen and Chen, Xinlei and He, Kaiming and LeCun, Yann and Liu, Zhuang},
  booktitle={Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)},
  year={2025}
}</code></pre>

    </div>
</section>

        <section>
            <h2>Correspondence</h2>
            <div>
                <p>jiachen [dot] zhu [at] nyu [dot] edu</p>
                <p>zhuangl [at] princeton [dot] edu</p>
                <!-- <p></p> -->
            </div>
        </section>
    </section></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google Being Forced to Sell Chrome Is Not Good for the Web (149 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://chriscoyier.net/2025/03/14/google-being-forced-to-sell-chrome-is-not-good-for-the-web/</link>
            <guid>43369230</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 01:57:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://chriscoyier.net/2025/03/14/google-being-forced-to-sell-chrome-is-not-good-for-the-web/">https://chriscoyier.net/2025/03/14/google-being-forced-to-sell-chrome-is-not-good-for-the-web/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43369230">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        
<p>You’ve got a monopoly on lemonade because you pay all the grocery stores to be the default lemonade. </p>



<p>So we’re going to force you sell your car. </p>



<p>What’s with the weird redirect? If the monopoly is directly caused by paying the grocery stores for placement, then stop <em>that part.</em> </p>



<p>We can see this exact redirect happening in the ruling in the U.S. vs Google court case.</p>



<blockquote>
<div><p>Google is a monopolist, and it has acted as one to maintain its monopoly. </p><p>[…]</p><p>For years, Google has secured default placements through distribution contracts. It has entered into such agreements with browser developers, mobile device manufacturers, and wireless carriers.</p><p>[…]</p><p>Because many users simply stick to searching with the default, Google receives billions of queries every day through those access points. </p></div>
<cite>Judge Mehta</cite></blockquote>



<p>In the document:</p>







<p>It’s spelled out quite clearly that being the default is the monopolistic part and that’s caused by paying for it (which is then self-perpetuating as the placement is so valuable, the money generated by it pays for those default placements.)</p>



<p>Fair enough! Let’s stop that. </p>



<p>Let’s stop the monopoly by telling Google they can’t pay (certain? all?) companies to be the default search engine anymore. A step further could be forcing browsers should ask users what they want their default search engine to be.</p>



<p>This would be in line with how Apple was forced to <a href="https://developer.apple.com/support/browser-choice-screen/">allow for browser choice</a>:</p>



<figure><img data-recalc-dims="1" fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="612" data-attachment-id="12076" data-permalink="https://chriscoyier.net/2025/03/14/google-being-forced-to-sell-chrome-is-not-good-for-the-web/screenshot-2025-03-12-at-12-52-03-pm/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-12-at-12.52.03%E2%80%AFPM.png?fit=1620%2C968&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="1620,968" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Screenshot 2025-03-12 at 12.52.03 PM" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-12-at-12.52.03%E2%80%AFPM.png?fit=300%2C179&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-12-at-12.52.03%E2%80%AFPM.png?fit=1024%2C612&amp;ssl=1" src="https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-12-at-12.52.03%E2%80%AFPM.png?resize=1024%2C612&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-12-at-12.52.03%E2%80%AFPM.png?resize=1024%2C612&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-12-at-12.52.03%E2%80%AFPM.png?resize=300%2C179&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-12-at-12.52.03%E2%80%AFPM.png?resize=768%2C459&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-12-at-12.52.03%E2%80%AFPM.png?resize=1536%2C918&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-12-at-12.52.03%E2%80%AFPM.png?w=1620&amp;ssl=1 1620w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px"></figure>



<p>That’s a straight line from problem to solution. </p>



<p>A weird curvy-ass line between problem and solution is this strange solution that is being relentlessly proposed that Google should be forced to <em>sell Chrome.</em></p>



<p>There is a recent round of news covering this that all point to the curvy-ass-line solution. </p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/tech/2025/03/11/google-sell-chrome-doj-antitrust/82277792007/">USA Today</a>: “Google&nbsp;will have to part with its dominant Chrome browser if&nbsp;the U.S. Department of Justice&nbsp;has its way.”</li>



<li><a href="https://www.wired.com/story/the-doj-still-wants-google-to-divest-chrome/">WIRED</a>: “the Department of Justice reiterated that Google should stop paying partners for search placement—and divest its dominant Chrome browser.”</li>



<li><a href="https://arstechnica.com/google/2025/03/doj-google-must-sell-chrome-android-could-be-next/">Ars Technica</a>: “the government maintains that Chrome must go if the playing field is to be made level again.”</li>
</ul>



<p>It’s true that Chrome ships with Google as the default search engine, because, ya know, they invested billions in Chrome and that’s how business works. But still, a more direct line from problem to solution is forcing default search engine choice, not a forced sale of Chrome itself. </p>



<p>Why do I care? The sale of Chrome is bad for the web.</p>



<p><a href="https://chriscoyier.net/2025/01/29/a-little-arm-chair-businessin-about-chrome/">I’ve written before</a> that Chrome is unusual in that it’s really only particularly useful to Google:</p>



<blockquote>
<p>Users don’t pay for Chrome. There aren’t ads in Chrome. There is no&nbsp;<em>direct</em>&nbsp;business model for Chrome. Unlike Safari and Firefox, nobody writes checks to Chrome to make a certain search engine the default.</p>



<p>The value of Chrome is all tangential — it provides value to Google. Whoever buys it does not inherit that same tangential value, they would need to redirect what little of it they can somewhere else, likely fighting against the natural flow that has been baked into it since the beginning.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>I’m not saying Google shouldn’t be forced to sell Chrome just because it’s only valuable to Google. But I do think Google should be allowed to have a browser. Google is a web business, that’s their whole thing. They <em>made</em> a browser to invest in the web itself because what is good for the web is good for Google, and happens to be good for all of us. </p>



<p>Allow me to be more clear about why Chrome is good for all of us. </p>



<p>When you look at (or otherwise experience) anything on a digital device, you’re looking at an operating system. That operating system was probably made by a private company who has total control over it. They have the right to do that, but that operating system exists to serve that company only and entirely. </p>



<p>If you make a native app for mobile devices, it is at the pleasure of the companies who build mobile operating systems and you’ll do it with the technology they allow. Making an app for iOS vs Android is super different and the companies behind them and never going to shake hands and make it easier for developers. It’s largely the same making a native app for desktop computers. While there is a bit more freedom of what you can install there, making a macOS app and a Windows app is two entirely separate endeavors. </p>



<p>Not so with the web. The web is a set of protocols and languages and file formats and other technology that congeal to make digital experiences. No one company owns or controls it. It is designed to be open and it’s <em>good</em> when companies build new things and support web standards. It’s a modern miracle that we have such a thing and it’s on us to protect it. </p>



<p>If I go to a <em>website</em> on iOS, Android, macOS, Windows, some Linux distro, my Samsung phone, or whatever device I have that has a web browser on it,<strong> it really is the same set of files</strong> that deliver that experience. You and I and every company in the world can build things once that go everywhere. That’s how it should be. It’s fair and efficient. It’s good for the world. It’s much better than a world where we are forced to build things only for companies proprietary operating systems.</p>



<p>Google, by virtue of having Chrome, invests heavily in <em>the web itself.</em> Not just Chrome-the-browser, but the web standards that power the web. I can’t claim to know every detail of that investment, but I personally know people employed by Google that literally just try to make the web better all day. </p>



<p>It’s not hard to poke around the W3C specs themselves and see them littered with Google employees. </p>



<figure data-carousel-extra="{&quot;blog_id&quot;:1,&quot;permalink&quot;:&quot;https:\/\/chriscoyier.net\/2025\/03\/14\/google-being-forced-to-sell-chrome-is-not-good-for-the-web\/&quot;}">
<figure><img data-recalc-dims="1" decoding="async" width="1024" height="820" data-attachment-id="12105" data-permalink="https://chriscoyier.net/2025/03/14/google-being-forced-to-sell-chrome-is-not-good-for-the-web/screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8-23-29-am/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.23.29%E2%80%AFAM.png?fit=1064%2C852&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="1064,852" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Screenshot 2025-03-14 at 8.23.29 AM" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.23.29%E2%80%AFAM.png?fit=300%2C240&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.23.29%E2%80%AFAM.png?fit=1024%2C820&amp;ssl=1" data-id="12105" src="https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.23.29%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=1024%2C820&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.23.29%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=1024%2C820&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.23.29%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=300%2C240&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.23.29%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=768%2C615&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.23.29%E2%80%AFAM.png?w=1064&amp;ssl=1 1064w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px"></figure>



<figure><img data-recalc-dims="1" decoding="async" width="812" height="462" data-attachment-id="12103" data-permalink="https://chriscoyier.net/2025/03/14/google-being-forced-to-sell-chrome-is-not-good-for-the-web/screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8-22-26-am/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.22.26%E2%80%AFAM.png?fit=812%2C462&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="812,462" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Screenshot 2025-03-14 at 8.22.26 AM" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.22.26%E2%80%AFAM.png?fit=300%2C171&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.22.26%E2%80%AFAM.png?fit=812%2C462&amp;ssl=1" data-id="12103" src="https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.22.26%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=812%2C462&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.22.26%E2%80%AFAM.png?w=812&amp;ssl=1 812w, https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.22.26%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=300%2C171&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.22.26%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=768%2C437&amp;ssl=1 768w" sizes="(max-width: 812px) 100vw, 812px"></figure>



<figure><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="812" height="490" data-attachment-id="12104" data-permalink="https://chriscoyier.net/2025/03/14/google-being-forced-to-sell-chrome-is-not-good-for-the-web/screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8-20-27-am/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.20.27%E2%80%AFAM.png?fit=812%2C490&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="812,490" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Screenshot 2025-03-14 at 8.20.27 AM" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.20.27%E2%80%AFAM.png?fit=300%2C181&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.20.27%E2%80%AFAM.png?fit=812%2C490&amp;ssl=1" data-id="12104" src="https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.20.27%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=812%2C490&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.20.27%E2%80%AFAM.png?w=812&amp;ssl=1 812w, https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.20.27%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=300%2C181&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/chriscoyier.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Screenshot-2025-03-14-at-8.20.27%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=768%2C463&amp;ssl=1 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 812px) 100vw, 812px"></figure>
</figure>



<p>And there are evangelists, and documentation writers, and other people who aren’t working directly on Chrome, but really the web itself. </p>



<p>Will Google continue to invest like this if they are forced to sell Chrome? It would be hard to blame them if they did not. </p>



<p>Assuming they find a buyer, that buyer will be scrambling to find a way to make that investment worth it. Will they be choosing to employ people who are just <em>abstractly making the web better?</em> I would think not. </p>



<p>The web will suffer should Google be forced to sell Chrome. I think a fair assumption that overall investment and contribution to the open web will take a dive. </p>



<p>Sure, there will be some canonical fork of Chromium that keeps the sure-to-be-shunned buyer company out of it. Sure, the <a href="https://www.linuxfoundation.org/press/linux-foundation-announces-the-launch-of-supporters-of-chromium-based-browsers">Linux Foundation is getting their ducks in a row</a> to have contributors ready. But I can’t see it going well. </p>



<p>It won’t happen overnight, but stagnation will set in. A stagnated web is incentive for the operating system makers of the world to invest in pulling developers toward those proprietary systems. The browser wars sucked but at least we were still making websites. Being <em>forced</em> to make proprietary apps to reach people is an expensive prospect for the rest of us companies of the world, it will probably be done poorly, and we’ll all suffer for it. Heck, those operating systems aren’t required to ship a web browser <em>at all.</em></p>



<p>Whatever way this goes is bad for Mozilla. It’s possible Google is forced to not pay them for default search engine placement anymore, but even if they aren’t, you can imagine Google’s appetite for cutting that check is severely diminished. Mozilla’s <a href="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2020/08/firefox-maker-mozilla-lays-off-250-workers-says-covid-19-lowered-revenue/">2020 layoffs</a> that was publicly about reducing platform development still has me thinking they aren’t entirely serious about pushing the web forward, particularly with much less help. </p>



<p>And bad things happening for Mozilla is <em>also</em> bad for the web, so another domino may fall. Diminishing investments in the web generally will keep knocking over dominos. </p>



<p>I’ve typed enough. Google does all kinds of shitty stuff. Their surely the worst offenders of user surveillance on the web. Let’s not let them off the hook on that. Let’s see the DOJ get involved in that stuff. But forcing a sale of Chrome is not the way. </p>


        
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Popular GitHub Action tj-actions/changed-files is compromised (265 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://semgrep.dev/blog/2025/popular-github-action-tj-actionschanged-files-is-compromised/</link>
            <guid>43368870</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 00:43:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://semgrep.dev/blog/2025/popular-github-action-tj-actionschanged-files-is-compromised/">https://semgrep.dev/blog/2025/popular-github-action-tj-actionschanged-files-is-compromised/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43368870">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                    <p>Popular GitHub Action <a rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/tj-actions/changed-files">tj-actions/changed-files</a>&nbsp;has been compromised (<a rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/tj-actions/changed-files/issues/2463">GitHub issue</a>) with a payload that appears to attempt to dump secrets, impacting thousands of CI pipelines.&nbsp;This isn’t the first security issue with tj-actions/changed-files—see prior vulnerability <a rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://www.cve.org/CVERecord?id=CVE-2023-51664">CVE-2023-51664</a>.</p><h3>What you should do</h3><ol start="1"><li><p><strong>Find out where you're affected</strong></p><ol start="1"><li><p>The simplest way to find this is to grep for <code>tj-actions</code> in your codebase.</p></li><li><p>If you're on GitHub, look at the results of this query, replacing YOURORG with your organization's name on GitHub:&nbsp;<br><a href="https://github.com/search?q=org%3A">https://github.com/search?q=org%3A</a><a href="https://github.com/search?q=org%3A%3CYOURORG%3E+uses%3A+tj-actions%2F&amp;type=code">&lt;YOURORG&gt;+uses%3A+tj-actions%2F&amp;type=code</a></p></li><li><p>Arguably, Semgrep is overkill for this case. But Lewis Ardern on our team <a href="https://semgrep.dev/playground/r/10Uz5qo/semgrep.tj-actions-compromised">wrote a Semgrep rule to find usages of tj-actions</a>, which you can run locally (without sending code to the cloud) via: <code>semgrep --config r/10Uz5qo/semgrep.tj-actions-compromised</code>. And if we find more information about what tags &amp; commits are affected, we can update the rule over time to become more precise about whether or not you could be impacted. At time of writing, it looks like all versions are compromised.</p></li><li><p>For users of <a href="https://semgrep.dev/login">Semgrep AppSec Platform</a>, we recommend placing <a href="https://semgrep.dev/playground/r/10Uz5qo/semgrep.tj-actions-compromised">the detection rule in blocking mode immediately</a>: visit the rule, click “add to policy”, and select “blocking mode.”</p></li></ol></li></ol><ol start="2"><li><p><strong>Stop using </strong><code>tj-actions/changed-files</code><strong> immediately.</strong> Switch to a safer alternative or inline your file-change detection logic.</p><ol start="1"><li><p>Just removing it from the main branch of your repository won’t be enough — it could still run on other branches depending on how your actions are configured. So you need to remove it from <strong>all</strong> branches to be safe.</p></li><li><p>As an alternative, <a href="https://docs.github.com/en/organizations/managing-organization-settings/disabling-or-limiting-github-actions-for-your-organization#allowing-select-actions-and-reusable-workflows-to-run">GitHub has a feature that lets you allow-list GitHub actions</a> so you can ensure it won’t run, even if it’s still in your code.</p><ol start="1"><li><p>You’ll need a list of GitHub Actions used at your org. Run this query on your codebase:</p><pre><code>$ semgrep -e 'uses: $ACTION' -l yaml --json .github  | jq -r '.results[].extra.metavars["$ACTION"].abstract_content' | grep -vE '^(actions/|docker://|[.]/[.]github/|tj-actions/)' | awk -F'@' '{print $1 "@*,"}' | sort | uniq
DataDog/synthetics-ci-github-action@*,
actions-rs/toolchain@*,
astral-sh/setup-uv@*,
aws-actions/amazon-ecr-login@*,</code></pre></li><li><p>Remove tj-actions/changed-files from the list of GitHub Actions.</p></li><li><p>Go to GitHub settings and configure like this at:<br><a href="https://github.com/semgrep/semgrep-app/settings/actions">https://github.com/semgrep/semgrep-app/settings/actions</a><br><img src="https://semgrep.dev/assets/github-settings-configuration.png"></p></li></ol></li><li><p><strong>Generally, pin all GitHub Actions to specific commit SHAs (rather than version tags) you know are safe.</strong> In this case, it appears that all versions are compromised.</p></li><li><p><strong>Audit past workflow runs for signs of compromise.</strong> Check logs for suspicious outbound network requests. Prioritize repos where your CI runner logs are public, as secrets are dumped to stdout in the payload.</p></li></ol></li></ol><h3>Affected versions</h3><p>At time of writing (2025-03-14T23:55:00Z), we assessed by inspecting tag pointers in the source repo that all versions of tj-actions/changed-files are compromised. Users may verify with <code>git tag --points-at 0e58ed8</code> . See <a href="https://github.com/tj-actions/changed-files/commit/0e58ed8671d6b60d0890c21b07f8835ace038e67">commit 0e58ed8</a> in <a href="https://github.com/tj-actions/changed-files.">https://github.com/tj-actions/changed-files.</a></p><h3>Further reading</h3><ul><li><p><a href="https://www.stepsecurity.io/blog/harden-runner-detection-tj-actions-changed-files-action-is-compromised">StepSecurity’s Incident Analysis</a></p></li><li><p><a href="https://github.com/tj-actions/changed-files/issues/2463">https://github.com/tj-actions/changed-files/issues/2463</a></p></li><li><p><a href="https://www.cve.org/CVERecord?id=CVE-2023-51664">CVE-2023-51664</a></p></li></ul>
                  </div><div>
  <header>
    <h4>About</h4>
    <img src="https://semgrep.dev/build/assets/semgrep-logo-dark-F_zJCZNg.svg">
  </header>
  <p>
    Semgrep lets security teams partner with developers and shift left organically, without introducing friction. Semgrep gives security teams confidence that they are only surfacing true, actionable issues to developers, and makes it easy for developers to fix these issues in their existing environments. 
  </p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[New York Times shut down Tor Onion service (224 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://open.nytimes.com/https-open-nytimes-com-the-new-york-times-as-a-tor-onion-service-e0d0b67b7482</link>
            <guid>43368183</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 22:53:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://open.nytimes.com/https-open-nytimes-com-the-new-york-times-as-a-tor-onion-service-e0d0b67b7482">https://open.nytimes.com/https-open-nytimes-com-the-new-york-times-as-a-tor-onion-service-e0d0b67b7482</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43368183">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://open.nytimes.com/https-open-nytimes-com-the-new-york-times-as-a-tor-onion-service-e0d0b67b7482: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Everything you say to your Echo will be sent to Amazon starting on March 28 (196 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/03/everything-you-say-to-your-echo-will-be-sent-to-amazon-starting-on-march-28/</link>
            <guid>43367536</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 21:33:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/03/everything-you-say-to-your-echo-will-be-sent-to-amazon-starting-on-march-28/">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/03/everything-you-say-to-your-echo-will-be-sent-to-amazon-starting-on-march-28/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43367536">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          
          
<p>If that's not enough to deter you from sharing voice recordings with Amazon, note that the company allowed <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2019/04/amazon-admits-that-employees-review-small-sample-of-alexa-audio/">employees to listen to Alexa voice recordings.</a> In 2019, Bloomberg reported that Amazon employees listened to as many as 1,000 audio samples during their nine-hour shifts. Amazon <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/help/customer/display.html?nodeId=201602230">says</a> it allows employees to listen to Alexa voice recordings to train its speech recognition and natural language understanding systems.</p>
<p>Other reasons why people may be hesitant to trust Amazon with personal voice samples include the previous usage of Alexa voice recordings <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2018/11/amazon-must-give-up-echo-recordings-in-double-murder-case-judge-rules/">in criminal trials </a>and Amazon <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2023/06/ftc-amazon-ring-workers-illegally-spied-on-users-of-home-security-cameras/">paying a settlement</a> in 2023 in relation to allegations that it allowed "thousands of employees and contractors to watch video recordings of customers' private spaces" taken from Ring cameras, per the Federal Trade Commission.</p>
<h2>Save recordings or lose functionality</h2>
<p>Likely looking to get ahead of these concerns, Amazon said in its email today that by default, it will delete recordings of users’ Alexa requests after processing. However, anyone with their Echo device set to “Don’t save recordings” will see their already-purchased devices’ Voice ID feature bricked. Voice ID <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/help/customer/display.html?nodeId=GYCXKY2AB2QWZT2X">enables Alexa</a> to do things like share user-specified calendar events, reminders, music, and more. Previously, Amazon <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/help/customer/display.html?nodeId=201602230">has said</a> that "if you choose not to save any voice recordings, Voice ID may not work." As of March 28, broken Voice ID is a guarantee for people who don't let Amazon store their voice recordings.</p>
<p>Amazon's email says:</p>
<blockquote><p>Alexa voice requests are always encrypted in transit to Amazon’s secure cloud, which was designed with layers of security protections to keep customer information safe. Customers can continue to choose from a robust set of controls by visiting the Alexa Privacy dashboard online or navigating to More &gt; Alexa Privacy in the Alexa app.</p></blockquote>
<p>Amazon is forcing Echo users to make a couple of tough decisions: Grant Amazon access to recordings of everything you say to Alexa or stop using an Echo; let Amazon save voice recordings and have employees listen to them or lose a feature set to become more advanced and central to the next generation of Alexa.</p>
<p>However, Amazon is betting big that Alexa+ can dig the voice assistant out of a <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2024/07/alexa-had-no-profit-timeline-cost-amazon-25-billion-in-4-years/">financial pit</a>. Amazon has publicly committed to keeping the free version of Alexa around, but Alexa+ is viewed as Amazon's last hope for keeping Alexa alive and making it profitable. Anything Amazon can do to get people to pay for Alexa takes precedence over other Alexa user demands, including, it seems, privacy.</p>


          
                  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[FBI, EPA, and Treasury told Citibank to freeze funds to claw back climate money (192 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://techcrunch.com/2025/03/13/fbi-epa-and-treasury-told-citibank-to-freeze-funds-as-trump-administration-tries-to-claw-back-climate-money/</link>
            <guid>43366530</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 19:52:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/03/13/fbi-epa-and-treasury-told-citibank-to-freeze-funds-as-trump-administration-tries-to-claw-back-climate-money/">https://techcrunch.com/2025/03/13/fbi-epa-and-treasury-told-citibank-to-freeze-funds-as-trump-administration-tries-to-claw-back-climate-money/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43366530">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p id="speakable-summary">Citibank revealed in court filings on Wednesday that the FBI, the EPA, the EPA inspector general, and the Treasury Department have all requested that the bank freeze accounts of several nonprofits and state government agencies.</p>

<p>The accounts were frozen in February, but the <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/25559919-citibank-ggrf-funds-lawsuit-filing-3-12-25/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">new documents</a> make public details that had previously been unknown, including a full list of the nonprofits under FBI scrutiny.</p>







<p>The funds were disbursed as part of the $27 billion Greenhouse Gas Reduction Fund, which was created by the Inflation Reduction Act, a law <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/08/16/winners-losers-abound-as-inflation-reduction-act-becomes-law/">passed by Congress in 2022</a>. Of that, the EPA received <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/04/05/us-greenhouse-gas-reduction-fund/">$14 billion for a National Clean Investment Fund</a>, which provides grants to green banks.</p>

<p>Green banks use those funds to provide financing for clean technology projects around the country. Startups that have technologies that are ready to scale commercially were eligible to receive financing to make projects a reality.</p>

<p>The funding was mostly to be used for loans, which were to be paid back and recycled for future lending. Green banks tend to have delinquency rates on par with commercial and residential portfolios held by other commercial lenders.</p>

<p>Citibank was selected as the financial agent to administer that money, holding it in accounts under the names of the awardees. It is also administering a separate, $6 billion Clean Communities Investment Accelerator program. The EPA’s contract with Citibank was publicly announced in April 2024.</p>

<p>The FBI has requested that Citibank place 30-day administrative freezes on accounts held by nonprofits that were recipients of the green bank funding. It also asked the bank to freeze other nonprofit and state government agency accounts, including Habitat for Humanity, United Way, the Colorado Clean Energy Fund, and New York State Department of Taxation and Finance.</p>


<p>Three nonprofits that received green bank funds have sued Citibank, asking the bank to release the money in their accounts.</p>

<p>EPA administrator Lee Zeldin has said that the Greenhouse Gas Reduction Fund doesn’t align with the agency’s priorities and that he has concerns about fraud, though he has not provided evidence to support that claim.</p>

<p>In a hearing on Wednesday, a judge in the U.S. District Court for the District of Columbia questioned a Justice Department attorney representing the EPA.</p>







<p>“Can you proffer any evidence that [the grant] was illegal, or evidence of abuse or fraud or bribery — that any of that was improperly or unlawfully done, other than the fact that Mr. Zeldin doesn’t like it?” Judge Tanya Chutkan <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/03/12/judge-epa-climate-grant-cancellations-00227643">said</a>.</p>

<p>Judge Chutkan also ordered the Justice Department to provide the court with details about the alleged fraud, “because I don’t have the credible evidence that’s required.”</p>

<p><em>Update 3/13/25: Added details from the Wednesday hearing.</em></p>
</div><div>
	
	
	
	

	
<div>
	<p>
		Tim De Chant is a senior climate reporter at TechCrunch. He has written for a wide range of publications, including Wired magazine, the Chicago Tribune, Ars Technica, The Wire China, and NOVA Next, where he was founding editor. De Chant is also a lecturer in MIT’s Graduate Program in Science Writing, and he was awarded a Knight Science Journalism Fellowship at MIT in 2018, during which time he studied climate technologies and explored new business models for journalism. He received his PhD in environmental science, policy, and management from the University of California, Berkeley, and his BA degree in environmental studies, English, and biology from St. Olaf College.	</p>
</div>


	
	<p>
		<a data-ctatext="View Bio" data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/author/tim-de-chant/" data-event="button" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/tim-de-chant/">View Bio <svg style="width: 1em;" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="none" viewBox="0 0 24 24"><path fill="var(--c-svg, currentColor)" d="M16.5 12 9 19.5l-1.05-1.05L14.4 12 7.95 5.55 9 4.5z"></path></svg></a>
	</p>
	
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Kerning, the Hard Way (194 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://home.octetfont.com/blog/kerning-hard.html</link>
            <guid>43366479</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 19:47:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://home.octetfont.com/blog/kerning-hard.html">https://home.octetfont.com/blog/kerning-hard.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43366479">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>

<time>2025-03-14</time>
<address>by David Jones</address>
<p>Here is a font i am working on; i hope you like it.</p>
<p><img alt="" src="https://home.octetfont.com/blog/image/kerninghard/010stork.png"></p>
<p>The letterforms are reversed out against a vertically striped background.
In a manner similar to <a href="https://fontsinuse.com/typefaces/32260/schaefer-versalien">Schaeffer
Versalien</a>.
The graphic effect is inspired-by/stolen-from Schaefer Versalien, but
the letterforms are modified from my found stencil font
<a href="https://drj11.itch.io/arugula-font">Arugula</a>.</p>
<p>Bear in the mind that with a font like this, the parts that are drawn
are the black parts.</p>
<p>So, let's consider a word like SALTY:</p>
<p><img alt="" src="https://home.octetfont.com/blog/image/kerninghard/020salty.png"></p>
<p>Looks okay? Perhaps you think is fine and there is nothing to comment on.</p>
<p>What about the kerning, in this case between <strong>L</strong> and <strong>T</strong>?
In the good old days of metal type the only kerns were when <code>/f</code> projected
outside the edge of its body.
This would not have been kerned and we were ok with that
(larger wooden type may have been kerned with a saw or a file, but
in this design, the cuts would have to be made to line up the stripes
exactly; tricky business).</p>
<p>Here’s what this particular example looks like without kerning:</p>
<p><img alt="" src="https://home.octetfont.com/blog/image/kerninghard/030saltynokern.png"></p>
<p>I’m not going to go back and forth over the merits of kerning,
i‘m here for the nerdy technical details.</p>
<p>In most, normal, fonts kerning is done with position rules (GPOS lookups);
that doesn’t work here, because if we reposition <strong>T</strong> to
be slightly further left, we get something like this disaster:</p>
<p><img alt="" src="https://home.octetfont.com/blog/image/kerninghard/040saltybad.png"></p>
<p>It looks a bit like <strong>L</strong> and <strong>T</strong> have been clipped, but in fact
they’ve been drawn over. Black parts of <strong>L</strong> overlap
the <strong>T</strong>, and vice versa: black parts of the
<strong>T</strong> overlap <strong>L</strong>.
The effect is what you can see, where <strong>L</strong> and <strong>T</strong> share a space,
the black bars overlap and are solid, obliterating the reversed out
letterforms.</p>
<p>So how do i kern this font, if not with GSPOS lookups?</p>
<p>With GSUB lookups! GSUB (for substitution) lookups substitute
one sequence of glyphs for another.
The details can get quite complicated, but the way i use them here
is relatively simple.</p>
<p>I split <strong>L</strong> and <strong>T</strong> into two pieces each, and recombine
the middle two pieces into the drawing of the kerned part.</p>
<p>I’ll illustrate the steps. With glyphs that have been articifically spaced out,
so that you can see each individual glyph.</p>
<p><strong>L</strong> and <strong>T</strong> as individual glyphs</p>
<p><img alt="" src="https://home.octetfont.com/blog/image/kerninghard/050LTspace.png"></p>
<p>Each of <strong>L</strong> and <strong>T</strong> is split into two pieces. So we get 4 glyphs:
<code>/L.left</code> <code>/L.right</code> <code>/T.left</code> <code>T.right</code>.
This is done with GSUB lookup rule like <code>sub L by L.left L.right ;</code>.</p>
<p><img alt="" src="https://home.octetfont.com/blog/image/kerninghard/060split.png"></p>
<p>The two middle pieces, <code>/L.right</code> and <code>T.left</code>, get replaced with
what i call a <em>joiner</em> the kerned piece in the middle shared by
both <strong>L</strong> and <strong>T</strong>.</p>
<p>Here the GSUB rules look like <code>sub L.right T.left by L_T.joiner ;</code>.</p>
<p><img alt="" src="https://home.octetfont.com/blog/image/kerninghard/070joined.png"></p>
<p>That’s actually it. The next image is just the previous one without
the extra spacing, and is how it would actually appear.</p>
<p><img alt="" src="https://home.octetfont.com/blog/image/kerninghard/080LTcomplete.png"></p>
<h2>Notes</h2>
<p>The pattern of vertical stripes means that kerns can only be a multiple
of the stripe repeat (not quite true, and i have sketched out more
general versions of this, but it <em>is</em> true for this font).</p>
<p>The gaps in the pattern help avoid solid black-to-black joins, which
might work when everything is a vector, but tend to leave sub-1-pixel
gaps when rasterised.
The gaps are also why a glyph isn’t split down the middle to
make the <code>.left</code> and <code>.right</code> parts.
That would leave a sub-1-pixel gap when rejoining.
Better to split at a gap.</p>
<p>The glyph names, used in the rules above, don’t matter at that level,
but i suspect affect the PDF; in particular cutting-and-pasting
from PDF, so there might be some tweaking of names.</p>
<p>For each letter (glyph) that participates in kerning, there
are two more glyphs for its <code>.left</code> and <code>.right</code> parts.
And...</p>
<p>For each <em>kerned pair</em> there is a glyph for its joiner, because
each one is unique.
Those are going to mount up quickly, which suggests kerning
only when strictly necessary.</p>
<p>None of the splits and joiners are drawn by hand, and
none of the GSUB rules are made by hand.
In both cases it is a <em>Small Matter of Programming</em>,
also known as Custom Python Scripts.
The libraries <a href="https://github.com/fonttools/fonttools">fontTools</a> and
<a href="https://github.com/simoncozens/fontFeatures">fontFeatures</a> were <em>invaluable</em> in this.</p>
<p>This font is not yet complete, but right now it is a real font and
really does work like this.
I've only kerned <strong>L</strong>, so there’s a few more kerns to do.
And right now is has a very basic alphabet, just A to Z;
i will draw some more letters and a few more decorative items, but
i plan for it to have a fairly small repertoire, partly because the
kerning and the vertical stripe design add to the constraints.</p>
<p>And if you thought kerning was problematic (and hopefully now you do),
consider how accents and other diacritics are going to work. ;)</p>
<h2>END</h2>
</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Decrypting encrypted files from Akira ransomware using a bunch of GPUs (208 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://tinyhack.com/2025/03/13/decrypting-encrypted-files-from-akira-ransomware-linux-esxi-variant-2024-using-a-bunch-of-gpus/</link>
            <guid>43365083</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 17:45:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://tinyhack.com/2025/03/13/decrypting-encrypted-files-from-akira-ransomware-linux-esxi-variant-2024-using-a-bunch-of-gpus/">https://tinyhack.com/2025/03/13/decrypting-encrypted-files-from-akira-ransomware-linux-esxi-variant-2024-using-a-bunch-of-gpus/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43365083">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The School Car Pickup Line Is a National Embarrassment (207 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://collegetowns.substack.com/p/the-school-car-pickup-line-is-a-national</link>
            <guid>43364761</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 17:16:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://collegetowns.substack.com/p/the-school-car-pickup-line-is-a-national">https://collegetowns.substack.com/p/the-school-car-pickup-line-is-a-national</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43364761">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://collegetowns.substack.com/p/the-school-car-pickup-line-is-a-national: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Making Postgres scale (189 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://pgdog.dev/blog/you-can-make-postgres-scale</link>
            <guid>43364668</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 17:07:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://pgdog.dev/blog/you-can-make-postgres-scale">https://pgdog.dev/blog/you-can-make-postgres-scale</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43364668">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://pgdog.dev/blog/you-can-make-postgres-scale: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Samsung bricked their home theater systems through automated firmware update (581 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://us.community.samsung.com/t5/Home-Theater/Samsung-Q990D-unresponsive-after-1020-firmware-update/td-p/3168571</link>
            <guid>43364016</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 16:10:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://us.community.samsung.com/t5/Home-Theater/Samsung-Q990D-unresponsive-after-1020-firmware-update/td-p/3168571">https://us.community.samsung.com/t5/Home-Theater/Samsung-Q990D-unresponsive-after-1020-firmware-update/td-p/3168571</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43364016">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://us.community.samsung.com/t5/Home-Theater/Samsung-Q990D-unresponsive-after-1020-firmware-update/td-p/3168571: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A 2FA app that tells you when you get `314159` (2024) (206 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.jacobstechtavern.com/p/building-a-2fa-app-that-detects-patterns</link>
            <guid>43363918</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 16:00:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.jacobstechtavern.com/p/building-a-2fa-app-that-detects-patterns">https://blog.jacobstechtavern.com/p/building-a-2fa-app-that-detects-patterns</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43363918">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://blog.jacobstechtavern.com/p/building-a-2fa-app-that-detects-patterns: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why do transit agencies keep falling for the hydrogen bus myth? (208 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://cleantechnica.com/2025/03/13/why-do-transit-agencies-keep-falling-for-the-hydrogen-bus-myth/</link>
            <guid>43363293</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 15:03:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://cleantechnica.com/2025/03/13/why-do-transit-agencies-keep-falling-for-the-hydrogen-bus-myth/">https://cleantechnica.com/2025/03/13/why-do-transit-agencies-keep-falling-for-the-hydrogen-bus-myth/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43363293">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
	
<p><a href="https://cleantechnica.fundjournalism.org/contribute/"><img decoding="async" src="https://cleantechnica.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/CleanTechnica-Subscriber-Pitch-Banner-4.png" alt="" width="1600" height="960" srcset="https://cleantechnica.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/CleanTechnica-Subscriber-Pitch-Banner-4.png 1600w, https://cleantechnica.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/CleanTechnica-Subscriber-Pitch-Banner-4-400x240.png 400w, https://cleantechnica.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/CleanTechnica-Subscriber-Pitch-Banner-4-800x480.png 800w, https://cleantechnica.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/CleanTechnica-Subscriber-Pitch-Banner-4-768x461.png 768w, https://cleantechnica.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/CleanTechnica-Subscriber-Pitch-Banner-4-1536x922.png 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 1600px) 100vw, 1600px"></a>
<em>Sign up for <a href="https://mailchi.mp/cleantechnica/daily-newsletter">daily news updates from CleanTechnica</a> on email. Or <a href="https://news.google.com/publications/CAAqLQgKIidDQklTRndnTWFoTUtFV05zWldGdWRHVmphRzVwWTJFdVkyOXRLQUFQAQ">follow us on Google News</a>!</em></p><hr>
<p>In recent months I’ve assembled a <a href="https://cleantechnica.com/2024/10/24/how-many-hydrogen-transit-trial-failures-are-enough/">long, long list of hydrogen bus trials</a> that ended up with the transit agencies realizing what should have been obvious before they started: hydrogen buses are a lot more expensive and battery electric buses are much cheaper and more reliable. More come out of the woodwork regularly, for example <a href="https://cleantechnica.com/2025/03/11/the-hydrogen-bus-illusion-essen-mulheims-costly-reality/">Essen and Munheim in Germany</a>, stuck with 19 buses that they have to drive a long way to refuel at great overall expense, something I wrote about this week.</p>
<p>The head of <em>CleanTechnica</em>, Zach Shahan, was stunned by this as he was finalizing the story for publication, <a href="https://cleantechnica.com/2025/03/12/why-hydrogen-electric-bus-programs-totally-confuse-me/">asking</a>:</p>
<p><em>How is the hydrogen bus market not completely dead by now?</em></p>
<p>Having had the discussion with multiple transit professionals now, I can tell you what I consider the reasons.</p>
<p>First, transit agencies excel at keeping buses moving and commuters satisfied, mastering logistics through decades of practical experience. They are extraordinarily good at moving their passengers reliably day after day, month after month, and year after year on low budgets. Yet, when it comes to evaluating novel claims — especially around emerging technologies — they can be surprisingly vulnerable.</p>
<p>As Daniel Kahneman highlights in <em>Thinking, Fast and Slow</em>, decision-makers often default to intuitive judgments (System 1 thinking), which can leave them susceptible to accepting persuasive narratives without adequate critical scrutiny. Agencies typically lack deep internal expertise on technical innovation or energy alternatives. Without robust analytical capabilities, they become reliant on compelling yet potentially misleading stories.</p>
<p>Next, transit agencies pay meticulous attention to day-to-day details — like the repeatedly vandalized bus stop on route 47 — but rarely pause to reconsider the bigger picture. Their thinking, shaped by decades of routine, reflects the intuitive, narrow focus of Kahneman’s “System 1.”</p>
<p>The last significant shift most agencies faced was replacing trolley buses with diesel models decades ago — a transition largely driven by persuasive suppliers, not rigorous analysis. Since then, their attention has stayed fixed on immediate, local issues rather than broader strategic choices.</p>
<p>Transit agencies suffer from what Kahneman calls “what you see is all there is” (WYSIATI): they’re deeply aware of familiar, visible problems — like the route 47 bus stop — but don’t know what’s happening in the next town’s transit agency, never mind China. To future-proof transit, agencies need to look beyond familiar horizons and question comfortable assumptions, moving past intuition and local crises toward evidence-driven, strategic thinking.</p>
<p>Then transit agencies are often told a compelling but deeply misleading story: hydrogen buses are a simple drop-in replacement. Just swap the vehicle, change the fuel, and everything else magically stays the same.&nbsp;It’s a seductive idea. Agencies, already focused heavily on daily operational challenges, rarely probe beneath the surface. The promise of easy solutions taps into their intuitive desire for minimal disruption, bypassing critical analysis and masking significant technical and logistical realities.</p>
<p>Without deeper scrutiny, agencies risk investing in a solution that seems frictionless but, in reality, demands costly and complex infrastructure changes. Understanding this cognitive bias can help transit leaders resist appealing oversimplifications and pursue genuinely effective, evidence-based solutions.</p>
<p>Then there is the reality of range. Hydrogen fuel-cell buses often promise impressive 1,000 km ranges, appealing directly to transit managers who feel pressured to decarbonize their longest routes immediately. Yet most urban transit routes don’t require that kind of extreme range. While some available battery-electric buses offer limited ranges (200–300 km), many already comfortably serve average daily needs. Today’s battery buses routinely deliver 300–400 km, with leading-edge models like Solaris and BYD already exceeding 500 km — more than sufficient for the vast majority of urban routes.</p>
<p>Back to WYSIATI. Transit operators see the gap between the longest route and current battery ranges and conclude they must immediately adopt hydrogen buses. They overlook the steady, rapid progress in battery range and falling costs, which will close this gap entirely within just a few years. A smarter approach would involve electrifying average routes first, capitalizing on battery technology today, and phasing in longer-range electric buses as technology inevitably improves.</p>
<p>Then there’s winter range. Transit managers accustomed to diesel buses rarely think about winter heating. Diesel buses effortlessly heat passengers and drivers with abundant waste heat from their inefficient engines — free warmth, no extra cost, no fuss. Fuel cell buses do produce sufficient waste heat, but here’s the problem: it’s exceptionally expensive heat. Every degree of warmth comes from hydrogen — a fuel that’s costly to produce, store, and transport. Unlike diesel, heating with hydrogen’s waste heat is technically easy but economically painful.</p>
<p>Battery-electric buses face a different challenge. The ones with limited range see further range issues further as batteries power heating directly, cutting operational mileage precisely when range is already tightest — in winter. That makes today’s battery buses less forgiving during cold snaps.</p>
<p>Traditional bus makers mostly aren’t insulating their buses more and investing in heat pumps, so they are again inefficient. As I noted recently, Harbin in northern China, which has a two-month ice city festival which is an international attraction, gets by just fine with electric buses that are <a href="https://cleantechnica.com/2024/12/22/heat-pumps-for-electric-buses-blow-another-meme-out-of-water/">insulated, have heat pumps, and have radiative electric heaters</a> in with the passengers.</p>
<p>Of course, this is a double-edged sword, because fuel cell and diesel buses have to power air conditioning in the summer with range hits as well, and both lose range in winter too, just less impactfully. This isn’t all a one-way bus route. But once again, long range buses exist, more will arrive, and they’ll get cheaper. All bus companies, not just BYD and Yutong, will figure out insulation and heat pumps.</p>
<p>To be clear, there have been some notable failures among electric bus manufacturers on both sides of the Atlantic, which hydrogen lobbyists have been quick to amplify.</p>
<p>In North America, Proterra’s bankruptcy left several transit agencies wary of battery-electric buses — though, perhaps their skepticism should have focused on the risks of purchasing critical fleet infrastructure from startups.</p>
<p>Similarly, in Europe, Keolis Nederland faced substantial reliability issues with 250 BYD electric buses delivered in late 2020. Quality concerns and frequent breakdowns caused operational disruptions, again giving hydrogen proponents ammunition to cast doubt on battery-electric solutions. Lots of work was done by Keolis and BYD to resolve them, BYD stood behind its contract, and compensation to Keolis was agreed to, with the amount undisclosed. The fixes and BYD standing behind its products don’t get reported, but the initial problem does.</p>
<p>This was also a relatively isolated issue for BYD. In 2013, Schiermonnikoog introduced six BYD electric buses, marking one of Europe’s early adoptions of such technology. An independent survey in 2014 rated this fleet as the best in the Netherlands, highlighting passenger satisfaction with low noise levels, ease of boarding, and overall comfort. ​In 2015, Amsterdam Schiphol Airport incorporated 35 BYD K9 electric buses for passenger transfers between terminals and gates. There have been no significant reports of operational problems with this fleet. But transit teams and hydrogen lobbyists don’t talk about all the successes with battery electric and its dominance in markets globally, they talk about the relatively rare problems.</p>
<p>Finally, <a href="https://cleantechnica.com/2025/02/24/hydrogen-electrolysis-cost-projections-from-major-organizations-low-by-60-to-300/">transit agencies have been consistently misled by credible organizations</a> — such as the IEA, IRENA, BloombergNEF, the Hydrogen Council, and CSIRO — which have repeatedly understated the real-world costs of hydrogen electrolyzers and green hydrogen itself.</p>
<p>These optimistic projections began around 2020, promising a future of cheap hydrogen, but they’ve been repeatedly revised upward each year. Despite these corrections, even the latest figures from these reputable organizations still significantly underestimate actual project costs. Transit agencies, relying on these authoritative but flawed analyses, were led to believe hydrogen buses would soon be economically competitive with battery-electric alternatives.</p>
<p>Research by Visa Siekkinen and Andrew Fletcher shows that real electrolyzer projects consistently cost significantly more than forecasts from respected groups. Fletcher highlights that current real-world system costs average around $3,000 per kW, nearly double CSIRO’s projections. The consistent underestimation stems from ignoring balance-of-plant expenses, infrastructure requirements, and overly aggressive assumptions on learning-curve-driven cost declines.</p>
<p>Transit agencies have fallen victim to anchoring, a cognitive bias described in <em>Thinking, Fast and Slow</em>. Anchored to early, overly optimistic hydrogen cost projections from seemingly credible sources, these agencies made procurement decisions based on unrealistic expectations. Hydrogen lobbyists reinforced this bias by continually referencing these low estimates, effectively preventing agencies from adjusting their expectations upward, despite clear evidence that real-world costs are far higher. This anchoring has resulted in wasted resources and delayed transitions to proven, more cost-effective solutions like battery-electric buses.</p>
<p>Organizations like BloombergNEF have started admitting previous projections were far too optimistic — recently tripling its 2050 hydrogen cost estimates — but even these updated numbers remain unrealistically low. The result? Transit managers continue chasing the mirage of cheap hydrogen buses, misallocating investments instead of moving forward with demonstrably cheaper, proven electric alternatives.</p>
<p>We urgently need these major forecasting institutions to openly acknowledge their errors, recalibrate forecasts based on actual data, and transparently communicate realistic costs. Otherwise, transit agencies and policymakers will remain trapped in decisions driven by wishful thinking and cognitive biases rather than rigorous economic analysis.</p>
<p>Of course, in Canada there’s another problem, which is that the transit “think” tank which is supposed to look around the world at leading practices, is supposed to be analytical, is supposed to be good at transformation and is supposed to avoid bias, the Canadian Urban Transit Research and Innovation Consortium (CUTRIC), is <a href="https://cleantechnica.com/2024/11/19/canadian-transit-think-tank-cutric-riddled-with-conflicts-of-interest/">riddled with conflicts of interest and bias toward hydrogen</a>.</p>
<p>So, the answer to Zach’s question is that transit agencies repeatedly stumble into the same trap due to overlapping cognitive and institutional blind spots. Anchored to early, overly optimistic hydrogen cost projections from trusted but flawed organizations, they fail to adjust expectations as real-world costs become clear. Their operational focus on day-to-day logistics creates tunnel vision — WYSIATI — leaving them vulnerable to persuasive lobbying narratives promising easy drop-in replacements. Simultaneously, their lack of in-house expertise and analytical rigor leads them to trust reassuring external sources rather than questioning overly optimistic claims.</p>
<p>These reinforcing factors — anchoring, limited analytical depth, and susceptibility to appealing narratives — lock agencies into repeating costly mistakes instead of pivoting rapidly toward genuinely effective electrification strategies.</p>
<div>

<p><em>Whether you have solar power or not, please complete <a href="https://www.surveymonkey.com/r/YM6VXK5">our latest solar power survey</a>.</em></p><hr>

<iframe width="840" height="472" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/zFQEzBRss5s?si=ZIrwa-fekuxur9f8" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe loading="lazy" width="840" height="472" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_fafTf8n4qQ?si=3N3CSruYU_6ZkBTA" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe loading="lazy" width="840" height="472" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/iQEoB5-chgA?si=oDDp14KiwkW32XG-" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<hr>

<p><strong><em>Chip in a few dollars a month to <a href="https://cleantechnica.fundjournalism.org/contribute/">help support independent cleantech coverage</a> that helps to accelerate the cleantech revolution!</em></strong></p><hr>

<p><em>Have a tip for CleanTechnica? Want to advertise? Want to suggest a guest for our CleanTech Talk podcast? <a href="https://cleantechnica.com/contact/">Contact us here</a>.</em></p><hr>

<p><em>Sign up for our daily newsletter for <a href="https://mailchi.mp/cleantechnica/daily-newsletter">15 new cleantech stories a day</a>. Or sign up for <a href="https://mailchi.mp/cleantechnica/weekly-newsletter">our weekly one</a> if daily is too frequent.</em></p><hr>

<center><bold>Advertisement</bold></center>

<center><!-- CT new after-post -->
<ins data-ad-client="ca-pub-1552008901061842" data-ad-slot="4461458457"></ins>
</center>&nbsp;

<hr>

<p><em><span>CleanTechnica uses affiliate links. See our policy <a href="https://cleantechnica.com/cleantechnica-editorial-ethics/">here</a>.</span></em></p><p><b><em><a href="https://cleantechnica.com/cleantechnica-comment-policy/">CleanTechnica's Comment Policy</a></em></b></p>

<hr>

</div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Block Diffusion: Interpolating between autoregressive and diffusion models (140 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09573</link>
            <guid>43363247</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 14:58:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09573">https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09573</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43363247">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content-inner">
    
    
                
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2503.09573">View PDF</a></p><blockquote>
            <span>Abstract:</span>Diffusion language models offer unique benefits over autoregressive models due to their potential for parallelized generation and controllability, yet they lag in likelihood modeling and are limited to fixed-length generation. In this work, we introduce a class of block diffusion language models that interpolate between discrete denoising diffusion and autoregressive models. Block diffusion overcomes key limitations of both approaches by supporting flexible-length generation and improving inference efficiency with KV caching and parallel token sampling. We propose a recipe for building effective block diffusion models that includes an efficient training algorithm, estimators of gradient variance, and data-driven noise schedules to minimize the variance. Block diffusion sets a new state-of-the-art performance among diffusion models on language modeling benchmarks and enables generation of arbitrary-length sequences. We provide the code, along with the model weights and blog post on the project page: <a href="https://m-arriola.com/bd3lms/" rel="external noopener nofollow">this https URL</a>
    </blockquote>

    <!--CONTEXT-->
    
  </div><div>
      <h2>Submission history</h2><p> From: Marianne Arriola [<a href="https://arxiv.org/show-email/a8effc12/2503.09573" rel="nofollow">view email</a>]      <br>    <strong>[v1]</strong>
        Wed, 12 Mar 2025 17:43:40 UTC (294 KB)<br>
</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: I'm Peter Roberts, immigration attorney who does work for YC and startups. AMA (246 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43363056</link>
            <guid>43363056</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 14:39:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43363056">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43363056: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Briar: Peer to Peer Encrypted Messaging (334 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://briarproject.org/how-it-works/</link>
            <guid>43363031</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 14:36:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://briarproject.org/how-it-works/">https://briarproject.org/how-it-works/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43363031">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="wrapper">
    <p>Briar is a messaging app designed for activists, journalists, and anyone
else who needs a safe, easy and robust way to communicate. Unlike
traditional messaging apps, Briar doesn’t rely on a central server –
messages are synchronized directly between the users’ devices. If the
Internet’s down, Briar can sync via Bluetooth, Wi-Fi or memory cards, keeping the
information flowing in a crisis. If the Internet’s up, Briar can sync
via the Tor network, protecting users and their relationships from
surveillance.</p>
<p>Users who are online at different times can use <a href="https://briarproject.org/mailbox">Briar
Mailbox</a> to deliver their messages securely.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://briarproject.org/quick-start">quick start guide</a> and
the <a href="https://briarproject.org/manual">manual</a> describe how to use Briar
and the features that are available. Technical details are available on
the <a href="https://code.briarproject.org/briar/briar/wikis">wiki</a>
and explained in this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sKuljekMzTc">video</a>.</p>
<figure><a href="https://briarproject.org/img/howitworks1.svg"><img src="https://briarproject.org/img/howitworks1.svg" alt="Briar"></a><figcaption>
            <p>Briar uses direct, encrypted connections between users to prevent surveillance and censorship.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<figure><a href="https://briarproject.org/img/howitworks2.svg"><img src="https://briarproject.org/img/howitworks2.svg" alt="Typical messaging software"></a><figcaption>
            <p>Typical messaging software relies on central servers and exposes messages and relationships to surveillance.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<figure><a href="https://briarproject.org/img/howitworks3.svg"><img src="https://briarproject.org/img/howitworks3.svg" alt="Sharing data with Briar via Wi-Fi, Bluetooth and Internet"></a><figcaption>
    <p>Briar can share data via Wi-Fi, Bluetooth and the Internet.</p>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure><a href="https://briarproject.org/img/howitworks3(mobile).svg"><img src="https://briarproject.org/img/howitworks3(mobile).svg" alt="Sharing data with Briar via Wi-Fi, Bluetooth and Internet"></a><figcaption>
    <p>Briar can share data via Wi-Fi, Bluetooth and the Internet.</p>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Briar provides private messaging, public forums and blogs that are
protected against the following surveillance and censorship threats:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Metadata surveillance.</strong> Briar uses the Tor network to prevent
eavesdroppers from learning which users are talking to each other.
Each user’s contact list is encrypted and stored on her own device.</li>
<li><strong>Content surveillance.</strong> All communication between devices is
encrypted end-to-end, protecting the content from eavesdropping
or tampering.</li>
<li><strong>Content filtering.</strong> Briar’s end-to-end encryption prevents
keyword filtering, and because of its decentralized design there are
no servers to block.</li>
<li><strong>Takedown orders.</strong> Every user who subscribes to a forum keeps a
copy of its content, so there’s no single point where a post can
be deleted.</li>
<li><strong>Denial of service attacks.</strong> Briar’s forums have no central server
to attack, and every subscriber has access to the content even if
they’re offline.</li>
<li><strong>Internet blackouts.</strong> Briar can operate over Bluetooth and Wi-Fi
to keep information flowing during blackouts.</li>
</ul>
<p>Briar is designed to resist surveillance and censorship by an adversary
with the following capabilities:</p>
<ul>
<li>All long-range communication channels (internet, phone network, etc)
are comprehensively monitored by the adversary.</li>
<li>The adversary can block, delay, replay and modify traffic on
long-range communication channels.</li>
<li>The adversary has a limited ability to monitor short-range
communication channels (Bluetooth, WiFi, etc).</li>
<li>The adversary has a limited ability to block, delay, replay and
modify traffic on short-range communication channels.</li>
<li>The adversary can deploy an unlimited number of devices
running Briar.</li>
<li>There are some users who can keep their devices secure - those who
can’t are considered, for the purposes of the threat model, to be
controlled by the adversary.</li>
<li>The adversary has a limited ability to persuade users to trust the
adversary’s agents - thus the number of social connections between
the adversary’s agents and the rest of the network is limited.</li>
<li>The adversary can’t break standard cryptographic primitives.</li>
</ul>
<p>Our long-term plans go far beyond messaging: we’ll use Briar’s data
synchronization capabilities to support secure, distributed applications
including crisis mapping and collaborative document editing. Our goal is
to enable people in any country to create safe spaces where they can
debate any topic, plan events, and organise social movements.</p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Stoicism's Appeal to the Rich and Powerful (2019) (189 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.exurbe.com/stoicisms-appeal-to-the-rich-and-powerful/</link>
            <guid>43363014</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 14:35:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.exurbe.com/stoicisms-appeal-to-the-rich-and-powerful/">https://www.exurbe.com/stoicisms-appeal-to-the-rich-and-powerful/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43363014">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><figure id="attachment_5194"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" src="https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/depositphotos_7098045-stock-photo-statue-of-cicero-200x300.jpg" alt="" width="200" height="300" srcset="https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/depositphotos_7098045-stock-photo-statue-of-cicero-200x300.jpg 200w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/depositphotos_7098045-stock-photo-statue-of-cicero-220x330.jpg 220w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/depositphotos_7098045-stock-photo-statue-of-cicero-400x600.jpg 400w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/depositphotos_7098045-stock-photo-statue-of-cicero-660x990.jpg 660w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/depositphotos_7098045-stock-photo-statue-of-cicero.jpg 682w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px"><figcaption>Cicero, one of our major sources for stoic thought.</figcaption></figure>
<p>I was recently interviewed for a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/03/26/style/silicon-valley-stoics.html">piece in the Times</a> on why the philosophy of stoicism has become very popular in the Silicon Valley tech crowd. Only a sliver of my thoughts made it into the article, but the question from <a href="https://twitter.com/nelliebowles">Nellie Bowles</a> was very stimulating so I wanted to share more of my thoughts.</p>
<p>To begin with, like any ancient philosophy, stoicism has a physics and metaphysics–how it thinks the universe works–and separately an ethics–how it advises one to live, and judge good and bad action. The ethics is based on the physics and metaphysics, but can be divorced from it, and the ethics has long been far more popular than the metaphysics.&nbsp; This is a big part of why stoic texts surviving from antiquity focus on the ethics; people transcribing manuscripts cared more about these than about the others.&nbsp; And this is why thinkers from <span>Cicero</span> to Petrarch to today have celebrated stoicism’s moral and ethical advice while following utterly different cosmologies and metaphysicses.&nbsp; (For serious engagement with stoic ontology &amp; metaphysics you want Spinoza.)&nbsp; The current fad for stoicism, like all past fads for stoicism (except Spinoza) focuses on the ethics.</p>
<h3>Thinking Spots: Stoic Metaphysics and Ontology</h3>
<div>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Large_UO-740-300x300.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="300" srcset="https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Large_UO-740-300x300.jpg 300w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Large_UO-740-150x150.jpg 150w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Large_UO-740-200x200.jpg 200w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Large_UO-740-220x220.jpg 220w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Large_UO-740-400x400.jpg 400w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Large_UO-740-660x660.jpg 660w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Large_UO-740-24x24.jpg 24w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Large_UO-740-36x36.jpg 36w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Large_UO-740-48x48.jpg 48w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Large_UO-740-64x64.jpg 64w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Large_UO-740-96x96.jpg 96w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Large_UO-740.jpg 700w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px">Stoic ontology and metaphysics are sufficiently awesome that I must give it a couple paragraphs before I move to the ethics, though the ethics are the core of its popularity today.&nbsp; Stoics were <strong>monists</strong>; if dualists like Plato and Descartes believe there are fundamentally two things (matter and non-matter, for example), monists believe there is fundamentally one thing.&nbsp; Not just one category of thing (Epicurean atomists, for example, think there is only one <em>kind of </em>thing: atoms) but actually one single thing.&nbsp; The stoics posited that the universe is one enormous contiguous single object.&nbsp; Different parts of it manifest different <em>qualities</em>, but are the same.&nbsp; Just as polkadot fabric may manifest blueness here and whiteness there but remains the same object, so the part of the universe which is your hand manifests firmness and warmth and opacity, and the part which is the air manifests softness and transparency, but they are the same object.&nbsp; And when you seem to move your hand, in fact there is no motion, rather the part of the universe that was manifesting the transparency and softness of air before is manifesting the firmness and opacity of arm now and vice versa. Think of the pixels on a screen: what seem to be objects moving are in fact different parts of the screen changing color (i.e. changing&nbsp;<em>quality</em>) in sequence, creating the illusion of motion whereas in fact there is only variation in the surface of an object.&nbsp; (This is the stoic solution to Zeno’s paradoxes of motion <a href="https://www.exurbe.com/sketches-of-a-history-of-skepticism-part-i-classical-eudaimonia/">discussed here</a>). The stoic living universe is thus somewhat like the skin of a <a href="https://www.facebook.com/watch/?v=670116563163326">mimic octopus</a>, able to seem to be become a myriad different things while it remains one.&nbsp; And in addition to blueness, and whiteness, and opacity, and warmth, other attributes the universe manifests more in some places than others include what we would call in modern terms sentience, self-awareness, and reason–thus the human being is a spot of sentience against a background of less sentient substance, like a white spot on blue. But, the stoics argue, any property which is possessed by the part is possessed by the whole, so while sentience and reason are concentrated in the spots which are living humans, the whole thing is a vast, intelligent, rational whole, and when we die we merge back into it. Thus there is no individual immortality, but we are all part of something greater which is eternal, wise, and infinite.</p>
<p>Stoicism was likely influenced by Buddhism through contact with India during the wars of Alexander the Great, and shares a lot with Buddhism: the whole universe is one vast, living, divine whole.&nbsp; Life is full of suffering, but that suffering is a path to understanding a larger good.&nbsp; And there is a universal justice on the large scale beyond what a human from our limited P.O.V. can understand.&nbsp; In Buddhism this is karma, while for the stoics it is Providence, the same concept of Providence that Christianity later borrowed, which argues that everything in the world which seems bad is actually good in a way we cannot fully understand because of our limited perspective. It is as if we are a fingertip; we cannot understand why we must suffer the evil of being repeatedly banged against a hard, unyielding surface, because we don’t have the means to understand that the larger organism is typing up a blog post about stoicism, but if we did have the means to understand we would recognize that it’s worth-it on the large scale.&nbsp;&nbsp;The stoic justification for claiming the universe is perfect is the patterns we see in nature: trees have roots to drink the water they need, woodpeckers that eat bugs have beaks the shape they need to be, woodland animals have woodland camouflage, desert animals have desert camouflage, everything fits together in a vast, functional whole which (without Darwin to offer an alternative) the Greeks agreed implied intelligence, either in a creator (Aristotle’s demiurge), a source (Plato’s Good), or, for the stoics, the universe itself.</p>
</div>

<div>
<figure id="attachment_5181"><img decoding="async" src="https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/tied2-300x249.jpg" alt="Dog tied waiting outside a store." width="300" height="249" srcset="https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/tied2-300x249.jpg 300w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/tied2-768x636.jpg 768w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/tied2-1024x848.jpg 1024w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/tied2-1200x994.jpg 1200w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/tied2-220x182.jpg 220w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/tied2-400x331.jpg 400w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/tied2-660x547.jpg 660w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/tied2-1100x911.jpg 1100w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"><figcaption>If you’ve walked by shops where dogs are tied outside you’ve experienced the radical differences in their behavior: anxious waiting, frightened waiting, calm confident waiting; the latter experiences less unhappiness.</figcaption></figure>
<p>The stoics also argued (followed by some Christian thinkers) that there is no self-determination.&nbsp; We will all end up going where the Plan will have us go no matter what, but the one thing we do have power over is our own <em>inner&nbsp;</em>responses to the path fate gives us: do we curse, complain, fight, shake our fists at the heavens, or do we ascent, accept, relax, and gaze in happy awe on the vastness of which we are a part?&nbsp; A classic stoic image (and after this I’ll turn to ethics and the tech crowd) is that the human being is like a dog tied behind a cart.&nbsp; The cart is going somewhere, and there is absolutely nothing the dog can do to change the course the cart will take.&nbsp; The dog has freewill only in one thing: the dog can fight, snarl, tug at the collar, gnaw on the rope, dig its claws into the dirt until it bleeds, and exhaust itself with fighting, or it can trot along contentedly and trust the driver.</p>
</div>
<h3>An Action Ethics</h3>
<p>The majority of surviving stoic writings focus, not on the metaphysics, but on the actionable conclusion: given all this, how do we teach ourselves to assent?&nbsp; To become the contented dog who trusts in Providence enough to follow where our paths lead without being made miserable by anxiety, fear, and resistance?&nbsp; Stoics therefore teach self-mastery and detachment: you can’t keep terrible things from happening but you can control your own internal reaction to them and work on preventing yourself from being overwhelmed by them.&nbsp; You wake up to some terrible news in the morning: do you brood on it all day and lose your productivity and wellbeing? Or do you take control and carry on?</p>

<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/FeastColor-300x219.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="219" srcset="https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/FeastColor-300x219.jpg 300w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/FeastColor-768x561.jpg 768w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/FeastColor-1024x747.jpg 1024w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/FeastColor-220x161.jpg 220w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/FeastColor-400x292.jpg 400w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/FeastColor-660x482.jpg 660w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/FeastColor-1100x803.jpg 1100w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/FeastColor.jpg 1159w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"></p>
<div>
<p>A lot of the surviving stoic writings are maxims, short pieces for contemplation designed to help you dwell less on bad things that are happening, sometimes more imagery than argument.&nbsp; Imagine–for example–that life is like being a guest at a banquet.&nbsp; Platters are being passed around and people are reaching out and taking what is offered them.&nbsp; Some platters come to you and you take of them–other platters never make it to you, or are empty when they do.&nbsp; But you are a guest, these things were not yours, they were offered as gifts, so you have no reason to be angry that you can only taste some of them–better to enjoy the platters that do reach you, and remember that the host who offered them is kind.</p>
<p>This is where stoicism serves very much like a self-help book, or more generally as philosophical therapy, which is what classical philosophies largely aimed to provide.&nbsp; Stoicism’s recommendations for how to resist pain are exquisite, as in this example from the Meditations. And the metaphysics crops up mainly as a way to justify the advice:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>XXV. What a small portion of vast and infinite eternity it is, that is allowed unto every one of us, and how soon it vanisheth into the general age of the world: of the common substance, and of the common soul also what a small portion is allotted unto us: and in what a little clod of the whole earth (as it were) it is that thou doest crawl. After thou shalt rightly have considered these things with thyself; fancy not anything else in the world any more to be of any weight and moment but this, to do that only which thine own nature doth require; and to conform thyself to that which the common nature doth afford.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The ontology here serves the therapy.&nbsp; You lost the election?&nbsp; Got passed over for promotion?&nbsp; Got a bad review?&nbsp; These things are small and fleeting within the larger whole, all wealth will perish in infinity, all fame fade, nothing serious was really lost.&nbsp; You lost your arm to disease?&nbsp; It was not yours to begin with, it was leant to you be a kind universe which has a right to take it back again.&nbsp; You lost your best friend?&nbsp; Again, this was a brief good thing the universe leant you, don’t dwell on it, look instead to the other good things that still surround you.&nbsp; Goods are real, evils an illusion, and if you can believe that it becomes easier–the stoics promise–to let go.&nbsp; The approach works, sometimes.&nbsp; Scientific studies tell us that pain is more emotionally terrible when we know/believe it’s actually damaging us, i.e. that the same number of nerves firing off is more upsetting when than when we believe it’s permanently damaging a body part than when we know it’s hot wax or an electroshock and the effects won’t be lingering.&nbsp; So if you can actually convince yourself that nothing really important has been destroyed when something affects your fame, or fortune, it does hurt less.&nbsp; And millions of people over thousands of years have found stoicism a comfort on life’s tumultuous sea.</p>
<h3><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Cicero-216x300.gif" alt="" width="216" height="300" srcset="https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Cicero-216x300.gif 216w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Cicero-220x306.gif 220w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Cicero-400x557.gif 400w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 216px) 100vw, 216px">An Ethics for the Rich and Powerful</h3>
<div>
<p>At this point I want to remind the reader that I personally&nbsp;<em>love&nbsp;</em>stoicism.&nbsp; It’s gorgeous.&nbsp; It’s brilliant.&nbsp; Revisiting it I find it always challenges assumptions, pushes me to hold myself to high standards, gives me new ideas to chew on.&nbsp; Its major texts, Epictetus, Marcus Aurelius, Seneca, are ones I love to teach, love to revisit, love to grapple with again and again.&nbsp; I will continue to praise, and teach, and write about, and read, and make use of stoicism all the days of my life.&nbsp; But…</p>
<p>The new popularity of stoicism among the tech crowd, and also on Wall Street which is another place that’s been reading and naming things after stoics recently, is strikingly similar to stoicism’s popularity among the powerful elites of ancient Rome.&nbsp; In Hellenistic Greece, stoicism had been one of several different popular philosophical schools, along with Platnonism, skepticism, Pythagoreanism, cynicism, Aristotelianism, Hedonism etc.&nbsp; (Quick tip: names of philosophical systems are generally capitalized when named after people, not capitalized when named after other stuff, as in cynicism from <em>cynos</em>, dog; stoicism from <em>stoa</em>, porch, where the first stoics held their classes.)&nbsp; And like the rest of these ancient schools, stoicism focused on <em>eudaimonia</em>, i.e. happiness or the good life, the idea that the purpose of philosophical study was not primarily to understand everything, or to achieve power through knowledge, but to achieve personal happiness, usually through inner tranquility and armoring the soul against the slings and arrows of outrageous fortune (<a href="https://www.exurbe.com/sketches-of-a-history-of-skepticism-part-i-classical-eudaimonia/">see my essay on eudaimonia for more</a>.)&nbsp; Stoicism was one of a number of methods to attempt this, so like all ancient schools it fulfilled the roles of a self-help book and Science 101 textbook rolled into one.</p>
</div>

<div>
<figure id="attachment_5187"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/America%E2%80%99s-1970s-Hippie-Communes-9.jpg" alt="Hippie commune" width="437" height="291" srcset="https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/America%E2%80%99s-1970s-Hippie-Communes-9.jpg 790w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/America%E2%80%99s-1970s-Hippie-Communes-9-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/America%E2%80%99s-1970s-Hippie-Communes-9-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/America%E2%80%99s-1970s-Hippie-Communes-9-220x147.jpg 220w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/America%E2%80%99s-1970s-Hippie-Communes-9-400x267.jpg 400w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/America%E2%80%99s-1970s-Hippie-Communes-9-660x440.jpg 660w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 437px) 100vw, 437px"><figcaption>Cross a hippie commune with a monastic order and you have something like most Greek philosophical schools.</figcaption></figure>
<p>But in Rome stoicism surged in popularity compared to all the other systems, because it was the one Greek ethics which worked well for the rich and powerful.&nbsp; Other schools like Platonism, cynicism, and Epicureanism warned followers that participation in politics and the pursuit of wealth, power, or honor would only lead to stress and risk, and were incompatible with happiness.&nbsp; Epicurus said the happy life was found by leaving the political urban world to sit in a secluded garden, eating a simple meal while conversing with good friends. Cynicism advocated the more extreme step of renouncing personal property and living like a stray dog scrounging beside the road, which has no fear of being robbed or losing its status because it has nothing to lose.&nbsp; The Pythagoreans and many other sects lived in isolated communities not unlike monastic orders, and used strict diets, ascetic dress codes, even vows of silence.&nbsp; Plato too specified that the philosopher kings of the republic are made unhappy by the stress of having to rule, and a number of ancient figures even used the stress of rule to argue that the gods can’t possibly hear and act on human prayers or else the gods would be perpetually harassed and unhappy.</p>
<p>Stoicism, on the other hand, stressed the idea that everyone is part of a large perfect whole and thus that it’s everyone’s duty to fulfill the role Fate allots.&nbsp; In the ordering of nature the woodpecker should peck, the deer should graze, the bee should pollinate, and the wolf should hunt and kill.&nbsp; We too as humans have a duty to fulfill our roles, be that as servant, merchant, slave, or king.&nbsp; Some stoic authors were slaves themselves, like Epictetus author of the beautiful stoic handbook <em>Enchiridion</em>, and many stoic writings focus on providing therapies for armoring one’s inner self against such evils as physical pain, illness, losing friends, disgrace, and exile. But other stoic philosophers were great leaders of states, including leading statesmen like Cicero and Seneca, and the Emperor Marcus Aurelius.</p>
<p>Stoicism caught on among Roman elites because it was the one form of philosophical guidance that didn’t urge them to renounce wealth or power.&nbsp; Politics is stressful, but rather than giving it up to live like a monk or a dog, stoicism says you should continue the hard work seek to attain an inner attitude in which you will not suffer misery when you do fail, when you do lose the election, face the criticism, suffer the setback, feel the blows of fortune.&nbsp; Stoicism alone recommended inner detachment, not walking away.&nbsp; For Roman patrician statesmen with long family traditions of political leadership, walking away from civic participation was a non-starter (especially since Roman ancestor worship meant that achieving a name in politics was also a religious duty which your very afterlife depended on!).&nbsp; Stoicism finally offered a philosophical ethics useful to the statesman, which is why Cicero–a skeptic who engaged with many sects of philosophy–favors it in his dialogs more consistently than any other sect (this may not sound like a strong endorsement but is a high a <a href="https://www.exurbe.com/sketches-of-a-history-of-skepticism-part-3-cicero-through-scholasticism/"><em>very high bar</em> for Cicero</a>.&nbsp; And Cicero is a <em>very big deal</em>).</p>
</div>

<div>
<figure id="attachment_5186"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/RomanFamily-56aaada33df78cf772b4691a.jpg" alt="Roman family tomb" width="768" height="320" srcset="https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/RomanFamily-56aaada33df78cf772b4691a.jpg 768w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/RomanFamily-56aaada33df78cf772b4691a-300x125.jpg 300w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/RomanFamily-56aaada33df78cf772b4691a-220x92.jpg 220w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/RomanFamily-56aaada33df78cf772b4691a-400x167.jpg 400w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/RomanFamily-56aaada33df78cf772b4691a-660x275.jpg 660w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px"><figcaption>Posthumous honor was everything to Roman political families, and renouncing office a betrayal of generations. The hippie commune is right out!</figcaption></figure>
</div>

<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/51izQ0-OyXL-188x300.jpg" alt="" width="188" height="300" srcset="https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/51izQ0-OyXL-188x300.jpg 188w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/51izQ0-OyXL-220x351.jpg 220w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/51izQ0-OyXL.jpg 313w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 188px) 100vw, 188px"></p>
<div>
<p>Thus, turning to the questions that Nellie asked me for her article, when I see a fad for stoicism among today’s rising rich, I see a good side and a bad side. The good side is that stoicism, sharing a lot with Buddhism, teaches that the only real treasures are inner treasures–virtue, self-mastery, courage, charity–and that all things in existence are part of one good, divine, and sacred whole, a stance which can combat selfishness and intolerance by encouraging self-discipline and teaching us to love and value every stranger as much as we love our families and ourselves.&nbsp; But on the negative side, stoicism’s Providential claim that everything in the universe is already perfect and that things which seem bad or unjust are secretly good underneath (a claim Christianity borrowed from Stoicism) can be used to justify the idea that the rich and powerful are <i>meant&nbsp;</i>to be rich and powerful, that the poor and downtrodden are&nbsp;<i>meant&nbsp;</i>to be poor and downtrodden, and that even the worst actions are actually good in an ineffable and eternal way.&nbsp; Such claims can be used to justify complacency, social callousness, and even exploitative or destructive behavior.</p>
<p>Seen in the best light, a wealthy person excited by stoicism is seeking a philosophy that helps the mind resist greed and the capitalist rat race and offers a wiser perspective and inner happiness; seen in the worst light it can be a tool for justifying keeping one’s wealth and power and not trying to help others.&nbsp; In that sense it reminds me of the profession of <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/oct/17/wealth-therapy-tackles-woes-of-the-rich-its-really-isolating-to-have-lots-of-money">wealth therapists</a> who help the uber-wealthy stop feeling guilty about spending $2,000 on bed sheets or millions on a megayacht.&nbsp; Wealth does come with real emotional challenges, but as society calls more and more for fundamental reform to close the wealth gap and reduce the power wielded by the 1%, cultivating a pro-status-quo attitude can also be a way to deflect pressure to try to address society’s ills.</p>
</div>
<div>
<figure id="attachment_5189"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/download-1.jpg" alt="Bust of Seneca" width="183" height="275"><figcaption>Bust of Seneca, looking wise and careworn.</figcaption></figure>
</div>
<div>
<p>Seneca, an author I absolutely love, wrote exquisite maxims about selflessness and virtue which have been backbones of moral and political education for two millenia.&nbsp; So powerful are his arguments that Petrarch, when comparing the strengths of the ancient Romans and ancient Greeks in different arts (Homer v. Virgil in poetry, Demosthenes v. Cicero in oratory, Thucydides v. Livy in history etc.) concluded that Seneca alone makes the Latins wholly superior to the Greeks in matters of ethics.&nbsp; Seneca also risked his life trying to curb the tyranny of Nero, and eventually died for it.&nbsp; But for all Seneca’s powerful advice about the big picture and the meaninglessness of wealth, he was also a slave-owner who, when alerted that his male slaves were sexually abusing his female slaves, set up a brothel in his estate so he could make his male slaves pay him for the privilege of abusing his female slaves–not quite the behavior we imagine when Seneca says money is meaningless and all living beings are sacred.&nbsp; But stoicism urges us to turn our critical eye inward and improve ourselves, not to turn it outward and improve our worlds.&nbsp; It gave Seneca the courage and resolve to face the danger of Nero’s deadly whims day by day in order to do his duty to the Roman political elite, but it didn’t encourage him to question his world order.</p>
<figure id="attachment_5191"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/statues-voltaire-bust-by-houdon-bookshelf-statue-12h-tal498-2_1200x1200-200x300.jpeg" alt="Bust of voltaire, smiling." width="200" height="300" srcset="https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/statues-voltaire-bust-by-houdon-bookshelf-statue-12h-tal498-2_1200x1200-200x300.jpeg 200w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/statues-voltaire-bust-by-houdon-bookshelf-statue-12h-tal498-2_1200x1200-220x330.jpeg 220w, https://www.exurbe.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/statues-voltaire-bust-by-houdon-bookshelf-statue-12h-tal498-2_1200x1200.jpeg 333w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px"><figcaption>Bust of Voltaire, looking kind.</figcaption></figure>
<p>Stoicism is an intellectually rich and stimulating system, and wonderful therapy against grief, against dwelling on setbacks, and against getting caught up in the chase for fame and fortune and the blinders of the rat race.&nbsp; It reminds us to zoom out from a world of praise, and blame, and status, and cruel things people said on Twitter, and the competition to see made the most sales, or had the most hits, or got the largest raise, all things which can be genuinely emotionally devastating if we let ourselves get too caught up in them.&nbsp; In all those ways stoicism is a great match for Silicon Valley, for Wall Street, also for my world of academia and tenure and their stresses and injustices.&nbsp; It’s also a great match for congresspeople, authors, journalists, actors, entrepreneurs, everyone whose life contains stresses and setbacks and moments when we need help to let us to take a deep breath and let it go.&nbsp; But Cicero was not Voltaire, and did not look at the evils and injustices around him and conclude that he should wield his power to make a fundamentally better world–he focused only on coping with the world as it already was, and fulfilling his duties within it.&nbsp; Stoicism predates <a href="https://www.exurbe.com/on-progress-and-historical-change/">the concept of human-generated progress</a> by more than a millennium. It doesn’t teach us how to change the terrible aspects of the world, it teaches us how to adapt ourselves to them, and to accept them, presuming that they fundamentally cannot be fixed.&nbsp; But we have two millenia more experience than Seneca.&nbsp; We know many of life’s evils can’t be fixed, but we also know, with human teamwork and the scientific method and a dose of Bacon and Voltaire, some of them can.</p>
<p>That’s why when I hear that rich, powerful people are into stoicism I think it’s great that people are excited by the idea that we should hold all life sacred and look for meaning beyond wealth and worldly power.&nbsp; I think it’s a great philosophy for anyone, and certainly for those who need help zooming out from a high-stress, high-competition world to think about the human and humane big picture, and to pay more attention to self-care, and loving others.&nbsp; But it also makes me a little wary.&nbsp; Because I think it’s important that we mingle some Voltaire in with our Seneca, and remember that stoicism’s invaluable advice for taking better care of ourselves <em>inside</em> can–if we fail to mix it with other ideas–come with a big blind spot regarding the world <em>outside</em> ourselves, and whether we should change it.&nbsp; An activist can be a stoic–activism absolutely needs some way to help cope with the pain when we pour our hearts and hours into trying to help someone, or pass new legislation, or resist, and fail.&nbsp; For such moments, stoicism is a precious remedy against despair and burn-out, but it doesn’t in itself offer us the impetus toward activism and resistance in the first place. That we need to get from somewhere else.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p><a href="#" rel="nofollow" onclick="window.print(); return false;" title="Printer Friendly, PDF &amp; Email">
                    <img decoding="async" src="https://cdn.printfriendly.com/buttons/printfriendly-button.png" alt="Print Friendly, PDF &amp; Email">
                    </a>
                </p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>