<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 May 2024 07:30:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Nonprofit Industrial Complex and the Corruption of the American City (162 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://americanaffairsjournal.org/2024/05/the-nonprofit-industrial-complex-and-the-corruption-of-the-american-city/</link>
            <guid>40497106</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2024 03:38:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://americanaffairsjournal.org/2024/05/the-nonprofit-industrial-complex-and-the-corruption-of-the-american-city/">https://americanaffairsjournal.org/2024/05/the-nonprofit-industrial-complex-and-the-corruption-of-the-american-city/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40497106">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
			<p><span>T</span>he act of naming is always a form of propaganda. When you name something, you are never perfectly describing what it is, but are instead influencing how it is perceived.</p>
<p>Marketers know this better than anyone. Prior to 1977, there was no such thing as the Chilean sea bass; the fish was called, instead, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patagonian_toothfish">the Pata­gonian toothfish</a>. The Chilean sea bass <a href="https://priceonomics.com/the-invention-of-the-chilean-sea-bass/">isn’t a type of bass at all</a>, and most of them do not come from Chile. It was purely a marketing invention: an entrepreneur named Lee Lantz intuited that the American market might enjoy the <em>taste</em> of the Patagonian toothfish, but would never buy it under its given name. First, he chose to falsely call it a “bass” because Americans were comfortable with that type of fish. He then rejected the names “Pacific sea bass” and “South American sea bass,” on the grounds that they were too generic, and eventually settled on “Chilean sea bass” as a more exotic alternative.</p>
<p>The name of one of the most popular fish in the world therefore has nothing to do with what the fish really is. A type of cod that is primarily farmed near Antarctica became the Chilean sea bass as a Goldilocks branding compromise. The familiarity of the bass was married to the perceived exoticism of Chile so that an American entrepreneur could sell a fish nobody had ever heard of to high-end restaurants in the United States. This ploy worked so well that today nobody has ever heard of the Patagonian toothfish, while the Chilean sea bass has a secure and inalienable position on restaurant menus from sea to shining sea.</p>
<p>So its name is propaganda, but nobody cares. A lie that makes money will always be preferable to a truth that does not. Once you realize that <em>every name is propaganda</em>, it becomes readily apparent how much misconduct, greed, and corruption can be concealed behind an innocuously disingenuous name, especially a name that successfully evokes positive emotions in the general public.</p>
<p>Consider the word “nonprofit.” Whoever came up with the idea of calling these organizations “nonprofits” was a marketing genius on the level of Steve Jobs. When someone hears the word nonprofit, they assume that such an organization is working for the public good; that it serves the homeless, protects the weak, exists for the benefit and the betterment of society at large. Hearing that something is a “nonprofit” immediately gives a sense that the organization is trustworthy and the people running it are driven by a charitable agenda. It’s a word that shuts down the critical faculties and grants an instantaneous moral stature to any organization to which it is applied. Consequently, non­profits receive a benefit of the doubt that would not be granted to any other form of private corporation.</p>
<p>Yet nonprofit organizations are frequently the exact opposite of what they appear to be. As a consequence of the benefit of the doubt provided to nonprofits, there is rarely enough oversight to guarantee that they are doing what we pay them to do. In some cities, upwards of a billion dollars of public funds are paid to nonprofit organizations every year with glaringly insufficient safeguards to ensure that the money is used in a manner likely to serve the public interest.</p>
<p>This money is then spent in ways that would shock the taxpayers whose hard-earned dollars are being effectively stolen from them. Non­profits that self-righteously declare themselves providers of homeless services actively lobby to make homelessness worse in order to increase their own funding; nonprofit organizations hire convicted <span>felons—including</span> murderers, gang leaders, sex offenders, and <span>rapists—who</span> go on to commit more felonies while receiving hundreds of thousands of dollars in government contracts; and the executives of nonprofits, the very people in charge of institutions whose stated purpose is not to make money, earn millions of dollars while catastrophically failing to deliver the public services we are paying them to provide.</p>
<p>And as all of that is going on, the nonprofits in question receive tax breaks from the IRS, ensuring that the incompetent organizations wors­ening your city’s homelessness crisis exert their corrupting influence all the way to the halls of power in Washington, D.C.</p>
<h3><span><strong>Money for Nothing</strong></span></h3>
<p>There is a notorious nonprofit in San Francisco called the Tenants and Owners Development Corporation, or <span>todco</span> for short. The Tenants and Owners Development Corporation, despite containing the word “development” in its name, has not developed a single property <a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/sf/article/He-s-been-blamed-for-killing-housing-but-16630332.php">in approximately twenty years</a>. More and more, <span>todco</span> isn’t spending its money to help its current tenants, either. The <em>San Francisco Standard</em> found that <span>todco</span>’s spending on resident services declined from 62 percent of revenue in 2012 <a href="https://sfstandard.com/2023/03/09/sf-housing-nonprofit-todco-politics-tenants-infestations-drug-overdose/">to only 45 percent eight years later</a>. The Standard interviewed tenants in one of <span>todco</span>’s buildings and was deluged with complaints about decaying accommodations and rodent infestations. A woman told them bluntly that there were rats in the walls and complaints to management went nowhere; the tap water tasted foul and she sometimes found roaches in her food. One man felt a bite on his neck and assumed at first that he’d been bitten by one of the multitude of vermin that crawled through the building’s light fixtures; in fact, he’d been accidentally shot and the bullet hole was still visible in his wall when reporters interviewed him several months after the fact.</p>
<p>It turned out that instead of spending money on housing development and tenant support, <span>todco</span> boosted executive pay and funneled millions into lobbying. As <span>todco</span>’s spending on its tenants declined by 17 percentage points, executive pay quadrupled. Meanwhile, <span>todco</span>’s president, John Elberling, launched the Yerba Buena Neighborhood Consortium, a political lobbying organization. Between 2012 and 2020, <span>todco</span>’s direct lobbying of legislative bodies increased <em>95 times</em>, from $5,000 to $470,000. The Yerba Buena Neighborhood Consortium spent another $1.35 million on ballot referenda between 2016 and 2021, and within the small pond of municipal politics, that much money, if strategically deployed, can buy a shocking amount of influence.</p>
<p>Here’s where the story gets strange. Although <span>todco</span>’s nonprofit status is predicated on helping poor people afford housing, <span>todco</span> lobbies incessantly to prevent the construction of affordable units in some of San Francisco’s most expensive neighborhoods. In 2018, <span>todco</span> sued to prevent the construction of a mixed-use building on the grounds <a href="https://sfstandard.com/2023/03/09/sf-housing-nonprofit-todco-politics-tenants-infestations-drug-overdose/">that it would cast “new shadows”</a> on a community garden; <span>todco</span> then agreed to drop this lawsuit after the building’s developer paid them $98,000, raising questions as to whether <span>todco</span> was merely using San Francisco’s byzantine permitting process to extract a bribe from another developer. In another case, <span>todco</span> lobbied to block a <a href="https://sfstandard.com/2021/10/28/supervisors-under-fire-vote-against-proposed-soma-apartment-building-sparks-furor-may-violate-state-law/">495-unit housing development</a> that would have included over a hundred affordable units. In other words, an affordable housing nonprofit has repeatedly sued other developers to prevent the construction of the same affordable units that it is supposed to be working to provide.</p>
<p>And then, in July of 2020, the strangest of <span>todco</span>’s fiascos took place. That year, <span>todco</span>&nbsp;<a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/sf/bayarea/heatherknight/article/san-francisco-housing-17408816.php">prevented the construction</a> of over one thousand new apartments, including 350 affordable units, so it could run a “racial equity study,” which it then never bothered to conduct. San Francisco Supervisor Dean <span>Preston—a</span> <span>todco</span> political <span>ally—convinced</span> the land use committee to put off the development for six months, during which time <span>todco</span> would supposedly analyze the development’s impact on minority residents in the neighborhood.</p>
<p>By August 2022, <span>todco</span> had not even begun the study that was supposed to have been completed eighteen months earlier. When asked by reporters from the <em>San Francisco Chronicle</em> why the study had never been done, <span>todco</span>’s president told the <em>Chronicle</em> that Covid interfered with their plans and a consulting group they’d been relying on had dropped out. Both of these excuses are highly dubious. When <span>todco</span> lobbied to delay the housing development so it could run its mythic study, Covid had already been rampaging through the United States for six months, meaning that <span>todco</span> was not blindsided by Covid and cannot use it as an excuse for failure. Furthermore, one consulting group dropping out should not indefinitely delay a study when the organization running it has millions of dollars in annual revenue, tens of millions of dollars in total assets, and a bevy of political connections. If <span>todco</span> wanted to run the study they could have done so, but they have exhibited no sense of urgency despite the fact that their failure to conduct the promised study has indefinitely prevented the existence of 350 units of affordable housing.</p>
<p><span>Todco</span> is a nonprofit whose mandate is to provide affordable housing. Over the last twenty years, however, <span>todco</span> has produced no additional units of affordable housing, has allowed the units it already owns to decay, and has spent millions of dollars preventing other developers from building thousands of apartments and hundreds of affordable units. Paradoxically, a nonprofit meant to provide affordable housing is spending taxpayer money to prevent affordable housing from being built; an organization that exists with the explicit mandate to help alleviate San Francisco’s housing crisis is instead working tirelessly to make that crisis worse. How can this be explained?</p>
<p>To understand <span>todco</span>’s behavior, you need to know something about the business model of affordable housing nonprofits. An afford­able housing NGO makes more money as rents rise in the area where its buildings are located. Government subsidies make up the difference between what the NGO’s tenants are paying and what they <em>could be paying</em> if the building charged them the market rate. This means that a nonprofit, despite its name, has the <em>same profit incentive</em> as any other landlord, in that a lack of housing construction increases its profit margins by driving up rents. The only difference is that a nonprofit benefits from high rents through government subsidies instead of from directly charging its tenants.</p>
<p>And that is an obvious conflict of interest. Nonprofit housing providers <em>benefit financially</em> if less housing gets built because high rents increase their subsidies. Affordable housing nonprofits are therefore incentivized to work against housing affordability if they want to increase the amount their executives get paid. Everything <span>todco</span> is doing is a natural consequence of the nonprofit industrial complex. T<span>odco</span>’s subsidies rise in concert with rents; it then funnels the money it receives from the government back into lobbying the same politicians responsible for funding it; those politicians prevent the construction of housing on <span>todco</span>’s behalf, thereby ensuring that rents remain high and <span>todco</span> rakes in millions of additional dollars in government subsidies; and <span>todco</span>’s executives receive enormous boosts to personal compensation and buy million-dollar houses in the suburbs. It is a kickback scheme so ingenious it would make Al Capone green with envy.</p>
<p>This propensity for nonprofits to privilege their own finances over the needs of the poor is not unique to San Francisco. Last year, an initiative to establish a public social housing developer in Seattle <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20220713083723/https:/www.seattletimes.com/seattle-news/homeless/a-new-tool-or-a-distraction-seattle-social-housing-initiative-faces-early-opposition/">was opposed by the Housing Development Consortium</a>, a lobbying organ­ization for affordable housing nonprofits. The <em>Seattle Times’</em> reporting on this initiative is revealing:</p>
<blockquote><p>The Housing Development Consortium, a lobbying group whose members include King County’s major low-income housing de­velopers, financial institutions and governmental development agencies, <em>doesn’t want to compete with a new organization for funding</em>.</p>
<p>The Housing Development Consortium argues that Seattle should focus its resources on the existing system . . . <em>which in­volves a collaboration between the largely federally funded Seattle Housing Authority, local public development agencies and other nonprofit organizations</em> [emphasis added].</p></blockquote>
<p>In other words, a lobbying organization for affordable housing nonprofits advocated against a social housing initiative on the grounds that it would direct funds away from its members. Many of the people involved in these affordable housing nonprofits would describe them­selves as socialists, and yet they argued <em>against</em> a more socialist form of public housing development and in favor of the privatized, complex, and inefficient system that just so happens to financially benefit themselves.</p>
<p>In the event that America tried to dramatically increase the amount of public housing, a policy advocated by many progressives, it is likely that some of the fiercest opponents would be nonprofit landlords who would be outraged at the prospect of direct competition from government-owned housing. This is normal behavior for a private organization that relies on the government as its primary revenue source, but it is directly contrary to what the term “nonprofit” would seem to imply. Despite their trustworthy name, nonprofits are not <span>now—nor</span> have they ever <span>been—the</span> uncorrupted agents of the public good that their defend­ers would have us believe.</p>
<h3><span><strong>Crime Inc.</strong></span></h3>
<p>Exacerbating the profound conflicts of interest created by outsourcing government services to private nonprofits is the near total lack of oversight of these nonprofits, particularly with respect to how their money is spent and whom they hire to provide their services. It is a regular occurrence that money given to nonprofits is misdirected in a way ruinously contrary to the public interest. In especially egregious cases, money given to nonprofits finds its way into the pockets of people who never would have been hired by a government agency due to either a lack of competence or a disqualifying criminal history.</p>
<p>For instance, San Francisco gave tens of millions of dollars to a nonprofit called the United Council of Human Services over the course of two decades; <a href="https://sfstandard.com/2023/02/10/sf-homeless-nonprofit-ceo-lavish-lifestyle-illegal-activity-lawsuit/">their CEO proceeded to spend large sums of money in a totally illegal manner</a>, buying at least five vehicles for herself and family members and driving around with a trunk full of expensive jewelry. She also allowed twenty of her friends, family, and employees to occupy government-subsidized apartments which were meant to be used as housing for low-income San Franciscans.</p>
<p>There is always going to be <em>some</em> level of malfeasance when large sums of money are involved, but what makes the United Council’s criminality inexcusable is that Gwendolyn Westbrook, the CEO who stole taxpayer dollars and spent them on herself, <a href="https://www.sfgate.com/news/article/port-official-to-be-arraigned-in-embezzling-3109308.php">pleaded guilty in 1997 to stealing thousands of dollars in parking lot collections</a> while working for the Port of San Francisco. A nonprofit run by a woman with a proven history of stealing from government agencies was given tens of millions of dollars to provide affordable housing services, and San Francisco’s political class was somehow surprised when, true to her previous track record, she stole that money, too.</p>
<p>Following Westbrook’s fall from grace, a <em>San Francisco Standard</em> investigation discovered that the city had paid <a href="https://sfstandard.com/2023/01/12/san-francisco-nonprofits-revoked-suspended-delinquent-millions/">tens of millions of dollars to nonprofits that were ineligible for government funding</a>: $25 million went to charities that were either delinquent or suspended and another $65 million went to nonprofits that were later declared ineligible. At the time of the <em>Standard</em>’s investigation, San Francisco had another $300 million of future contractual obligations to NGOs it was not legally allowed to fund.</p>
<p>Although San Francisco is one of the worst cities when it comes to nonprofits behaving badly, these same problems exist in every city that makes excessive use of the nonprofit sector. Seattle, in particular, has a rather distressing tendency to give exorbitant sums of taxpayer money to convicted felons, up to and including violent criminals and registered sex offenders. In 2001, a man named Khalid Adams was convicted of first degree theft in an incident in which he allegedly <a href="https://archive.seattletimes.com/archive/?date=20010329&amp;slug=mardigras29m1">groped his victim while shouting racial slurs</a>; two years later Adams was convicted again, this time of first degree robbery and unlawful possession of a firearm. Adams’s <span>third—but</span> not <span>final—conviction</span> came in 2021 when he pled guilty to unlawful possession of a firearm by a previously convicted felon.</p>
<p>Only a year after Adams’s third conviction, however, he was hired to work as a “violence interrupter” by a government-funded Seattle-area nonprofit called Community Passageways. In November 2022, while receiving a salary from King County taxpayers to prevent gun violence, <a href="https://www.kuow.org/stories/king-county-gave-millions-to-no-new-youth-jail-activists-to-help-kids-then-they-looked-away">Adams broke into his ex-girlfriend’s apartment, held her new boyfriend at gunpoint, and was subsequently shot by the ex’s eighteen-year-old cousin</a>. Adding a surreal element to this already incredible story, Savior Wheeler, the young cousin who shot Khalid Adams, <em>was a client of Community Passageways</em>, one of the same at-risk young people that Adams was supposed to keep away from gun violence. A Seattle nonprofit therefore hired a three-time convicted felon who was fresh out of prison to work as a mentor for at-risk youths, and he was subsequently shot by one of those very at-risk youths while threatening an ex-girlfriend at gunpoint.</p>
<p>This is a surprisingly common occurrence in Seattle. In 2022, the city <a href="https://www.kuow.org/stories/renegades-for-life">gave $260,000 dollars to a registered sex offender who was operating under a fake name and credentials</a> to mentor at-risk young people. In 2020, they gave a $3 million no-bid <span>contract—one</span> of the largest grants in city <span>history—to</span> a nonprofit called Freedom Project <a href="https://sccinsight.com/2021/03/08/black-brilliance-research-project-wraps-up-with-allegations-recriminations-but-no-city-investigation/">to run a “racial equity study.”</a> Freedom Project’s executive director at the time <a href="https://sccinsight.com/2021/07/29/the-black-brilliance-research-project-beginning-to-end-part-2/">was David Heppard</a> who was convicted as a teenager <a href="https://washington.lexroll.com/in-re-personal-restraint-of-heppard-25154-0-ii-wash-app-2-9-2001/">for taking part in the gang rape of a pregnant seventeen-year-old</a>. Freedom Project’s finance director, <a href="https://freedomprojectwa.org/staff/">Quddafi Howell</a>, <a href="https://casetext.com/case/state-v-howell-57/#f33e5844-49ea-4a7e-a9aa-8d5835fe0078-fn1">once shot up a man’s house as an intimidation tactic to prevent him from snitching on Howell’s drug dealing</a>.</p>
<p>Believe it or not, the $3 million Seattle handed over to a bunch of convicted felons was somehow mismanaged. A local political blog called <em>Seattle City Council Insight</em> looked into the paperwork behind this contract and discovered that <a href="https://sccinsight.com/2021/07/29/the-black-brilliance-research-project-beginning-to-end-part-3/">hundreds of thousands of dollars were handed out to subcontractors for minimal work</a> and the project’s lead was paid <em>$300 per hour</em> while publicly claiming to be a volunteer.</p>
<p>In another case, a homelessness nonprofit called share (the Seattle Housing and Resource Effort) <a href="https://www.seattletimes.com/seattle-news/politics/seattle-weighs-charges-over-homeless-nonprofits-use-of-unlicensed-accountant/">turned out to employ an unlicensed accountant</a> at the same time they were handling millions of dollars in government funds. Share claimed that they were the victim in this case, as they were unknowingly defrauded by a man who held himself out as a legitimate accountant. Fair enough. Share, however, might have noticed that their accountant was unlicensed were it not for the fact that share’s <em>treasurer</em>, the man presumably responsible for handling all their money, <a href="https://projects.propublica.org/nonprofits/display_990/911577965/12_2017_prefixes_84-91%2F911577965_201612_990_2017121215021639">was Lantz Rowland</a>, <a href="https://www.seattletimes.com/seattle-news/tent-city-dispute-sends-homeless-packing/">an unqualified homeless man who lived in a tent</a>. This nonprofit <a href="https://projects.propublica.org/nonprofits/organizations/911577965">had total annual revenue of approximately a million dollars in 2016</a>, which included grants from King County and the City of Seattle, and the people responsible for handling that money were an illegal accountant and a sixty-year-old homeless tent dweller with no discernible qualifications.</p>
<p>Leaving the West Coast for a moment, one finds similar outcomes arising from the overuse of nonprofits in the Windy City. In Chicago, an anti-violence nonprofit called CeaseFire has had a shocking number of its “violence interrupters” <a href="https://chicago.suntimes.com/2018/4/10/18328589/ceasefire-worker-gets-27-months-in-prison-for-federal-gun-conviction">arrested for serious crimes since its incep­tion</a>. This ought to surprise nobody given that these “violence interrupters” are almost universally convicted felons. Ceasefire workers convicted of crimes while employed by the organization include <a href="https://chicago.suntimes.com/2018/4/10/18328589/ceasefire-worker-gets-27-months-in-prison-for-federal-gun-conviction">a fifty-one-year-old arrested for illegal gun possession</a>, whom authorities alleged was also moonlighting as a national gang leader; a convicted felon <a href="https://nypost.com/2023/01/13/chicago-police-arrest-jerel-taylor-for-guns-and-drugs/">caught naked under his bed with $50,000, an illegal firearm, crack cocaine, and heroin</a>; and a woman who was hired despite four prior felony convictions and <a href="https://www.nbcchicago.com/news/local/ceasefire-worker-charged-in-diamond-theft/64106/">subsequently stole $10,000 worth of diamonds</a>.</p>
<p>Chicago also has a state-funded <a href="https://www.illinois.gov/news/press-release.26485.html#:~:text=CHICAGO%E2%80%94Ahead%20of%20Memorial%20Day,in%20the%20City%20of%20Chicago.">“Peacekeepers” program</a> in which “community-based organizations” deploy former convicts to act as vio­lence interrupters during times when tensions are expected to be high. Last Memorial Day, a “Peacekeeper” named Oscar Montes <a href="https://www.nbcchicago.com/news/local/man-in-peacekeepers-vest-charged-with-robbing-beating-man-in-little-village/3150581/">assaulted a motorist while on duty</a>, leaving the man with potentially permanent eye damage. Montes was hired by the Peacekeepers program only a year after serving a ten-year prison sentence for shooting a rival gang member.</p>
<p>What is instantly noticeable about the above examples is that none of these people could draw a government paycheck <em>unless it was laundered through a nonprofit</em>. A police department could never hire a convicted felon with long-term ties to street gangs, but a private nonprofit has looser standards regarding who is allowed access to public funds. This not only squanders money on people who are not capable of performing the roles they’re assigned, but is an active threat to public safety in circumstances where the state uses convict-staffed nonprofits for duties that ought to be reserved for the police.</p>
<h3><span><strong>The Progressive Doom Loop</strong></span></h3>
<p>At the start of this piece, I said that “the act of naming is a form of propaganda,” an aphorism which applies to nonprofits because the name they’ve been given is a marketing device, rather than an objective representation of their conduct and behavior. It’s important to recognize, though, that nonprofits aren’t the only group relevant to this story that has been given an inaccurate name as a marketing ploy. The political ideology that supports the nonprofit industrial complex is generally referred to as “progressivism,” which calls to mind the socialist-leaning Progressive movement of the early twentieth century. In spite of sharing a common name, however, today’s “progressivism” has nothing in common with the Progressive movements of the last century, is not socialist in any real sense, and is, if anything, an extremist libertarian movement that destroys the ability of the government to function, rather than using state power for the betterment of the poor.</p>
<p>Once you start digging into the evidence, you find that the places where “progressives” wield the most power are some of the <em>least</em> socialist governments in the country. In 2022, San Francisco <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20230327233844/https:/www.sfchronicle.com/projects/2023/san-francisco-contracts/">spent $5.8 billion on private contracts</a>, over 40 percent of all city government spending, while the entire budget of Houston, a city 2.5 times as large, <a href="https://communityimpact.com/houston/heights-river-oaks-montrose/government/2022/06/02/houston-city-council-approves-fiscal-year-2022-23-budget/">was only $5.7 billion</a>. It is a strange form of socialism that runs more than two-fifths of its government through private contractors, instead of using publicly owned developers and social housing.</p>
<p>Portland, Oregon, meanwhile, has been suffering from a serious trash crisis for the past several years, due both to the city’s soaring homeless population and the government’s refusal to enforce antidumping laws. Portland’s response to the festering trash piles now blighting a once-beautiful city has not been to dramatically increase the government’s capacity to pick up and process garbage; instead, Portland, in conjunction with the state of Oregon, <a href="https://www.opb.org/article/2023/06/15/oregon-multnomah-county-fund-portland-trash-clean-up-program/">has paid millions of dollars to </a><a href="https://www.opb.org/article/2023/06/15/oregon-multnomah-county-fund-portland-trash-clean-up-program/">nonprofits</a><a href="https://www.opb.org/article/2023/06/15/oregon-multnomah-county-fund-portland-trash-clean-up-program/"> to deal with the trash problem</a>.</p>
<p>As Portland outsourced trash collection to private nonprofit organi­zations, the ability of the <em>government</em> to collect trash has been gutted by budget cuts and a lack of resources. According to <a href="https://www.kgw.com/article/news/local/the-story/portland-task-force-trash-garbage-cleanup-downtown-central-city/283-2d09202c-837c-4147-b47d-69da51dfdd32">local activist Frank Moscow</a>, Portland used to sweep every street as a matter of course, but currently only has one functioning street sweeper in the entire city. Not that it matters much, <a href="https://www.portland.gov/transportation/maintenance/street-sweeping#:~:text=street%20cleaning%20pilot-,Overview,street%20sweeping%20June%2030%2C%202023.">since Portland’s Bureau of Transportation sus­pended all street sweeping activities last June after another series of budget cuts</a>.</p>
<p>Adding to Portland’s trash-addled misery is the city’s inability to stop anyone from dumping their trash where it is not legally allowed to do so. In 2016, <a href="https://www.oregonmetro.gov/news/illegal-dumping-year-numbers">the city issued thirty-one citations for illegal dumping</a>; in 2021, <a href="https://kpic.com/news/local/homeless-not-only-ones-contributing-to-portlands-trash-problem">they issued a grand total of one citation</a>, for a measly $154. <a href="https://www.oregonlive.com/opinion/2022/03/opinion-volunteers-alone-cant-clean-up-portlands-trash.html">An opinion column published in the <em>Oregonian</em> in 2022</a> asserted confidently that “you could dump 10 large bags of garbage in Pioneer Square tonight and drive off without fear of being caught or penalized,” before going on to complain that Portland picks up trash from residential units <em>every two weeks,</em> instead of offering weekly trash pickup like almost every other city of comparable size.</p>
<p>This is the state of affairs in almost every city where “progressives” have a large impact on local politics. Progressives claim to support government spending programs, but <em>also</em> have an anarchistic, anti-governmental attitude that can be seen in their support for policies like <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/06/12/opinion/sunday/floyd-abolish-defund-police.html">police abolition in 2020</a>. Although progressives want the government to <em>fund</em> public programs, their opposition to centralized state power means they often don’t want the government to <em>run</em> the programs being funded.</p>
<p>The cities progressives control therefore tend to underfund core government agencies in favor of “community-based organizations,” by which they mean NGOs and nonprofits. Once the government can no longer meet its responsibilities, progressive cities outsource those ser­vices to nonprofit organizations, effectively privatizing the government.</p>
<p>A serious problem then occurs. Using several nonprofits instead of one government agency is inherently inefficient due to weak oversight and an inability to take advantage of economies of scale. That’s why cities on the West Coast spend so much on homelessness to no end whatsoever. San Francisco’s spending on homeless services increased from <a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/projects/2022/san-francisco-sros/">$200 million in 2016 to an astronomical $1.1 billion in 2021</a>. Despite this incredible investment, on an average night <a href="https://missionlocal.org/2022/05/sf-homeless-drop-pit-count-sip-hotels/">there were a thousand more homeless San Franciscans in 2022 than there were in 2015</a>. In fairness, there was a decline in the city’s homeless population between 2019 and 2022, leading the deputy director at the San Francisco Department of Homelessness and Supportive Housing to declare that “investment works.” Yet San Francisco’s population <a href="https://datacommons.org/tools/timeline#&amp;place=geoId/0667000&amp;statsVar=Count_Person">fell by seventy thousand resi­dents between 2019 and 2022</a>, meaning the miniscule re­duction in homelessness was likely a mere by-product of massive population loss.</p>
<p>Nor are the problems that cities like San Francisco, Portland, and Seattle have with falling population unrelated. By funding inefficient nonprofits instead of more centralized, accountable government initia­tives, progressive cities have high <em>taxes</em> but poor <em>services</em>; residents receive nothing in return for the taxes they pay. <a href="https://www.koin.com/news/portland/report-high-tax-rates-could-be-driving-people-out-of-portland/#:~:text=According%20to%20their%20data%2C%20Portland's,have%20to%20make%20%2425%20million.">Portland has one of the highest municipal income tax burdens in the country</a>, <a href="https://www.wweek.com/news/2022/09/28/portland-ranks-48th-among-50-big-cities-for-cops-per-capita/">but is forty-eighth out of the fifty largest cities in police staffing</a>, has piles of festering, uncollected garbage littering its streets, and only has two thousand shelter beds <a href="https://www.portland.gov/wheeler/homelessness#:~:text=The%20complexity%20of%20the%20homelessness,from%201%2C887%20to%206%2C297%20individu">for a homeless population of 6,300</a>, requiring four thousand homeless Portlanders to sleep outside even if every one of them wanted a bed.</p>
<p>Contrary to the conservative assumption that high taxes are an inherent evil, people are often fine with higher taxes provided that the taxes are utilized to improve local living standards. What is taking place in America’s most performatively socialist urban areas is that taxes are constantly raised in order to fund public services, resulting in some of the most heavily taxed populations in the country. But this tax revenue is then squandered on private contracts to unaccountable nonprofit organizations whose activities do little to rectify the problems they are nominally being funded to address.</p>
<p>Taxes soar in concert with the collapse in local living standards and the decay in public services. Public parks where children used to play fill up with homeless drug addicts who leave used needles near jungle gyms; a six-year-old girl in California mistook a syringe for a thermometer <a href="https://abc7news.com/needles-found-in-sf-left-on-streets-report-study-san-francisco/2226877/">and put it in her mouth</a>, and an eleven-year-old stepped on a needle while swimming in Santa Cruz. The streets grow increasingly unsanitary due to spiraling homelessness, reintroducing diseases once considered eradi­cated by civilized living. Los Angeles <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2023/08/03/health/fleaborne-typhus-la-county-cdc-wellness/index.html">had three deaths from flea-borne typhus in 2022</a>, the first such deaths in three decades; a reverend who works on Skid Row <a href="https://www.dailynews.com/2016/12/10/homeless-advocate-who-lost-leg-walking-skid-row-returns-to-the-streets/">lost both legs to an infection he contracted simply walking the neighborhood’s streets</a>; and Portland’s Old Town recently experienced an outbreak of Shigella, a disease mostly seen in developing countries that <a href="https://www.kgw.com/article/news/local/homeless/contagious-illness-spreads-old-town-hospital/283-c5856d2a-c962-4270-b5b9-4d111abe9697">spreads through fecal matter</a>.</p>
<p>The inability of nonprofits to properly manage services results in European taxes for third-world state capacity. Residents don’t know what the problem is: they don’t know that their taxes go to “violence interrupters” who are convicted felons; they don’t know affordable housing nonprofits use taxpayer money to lobby against affordable housing; and they don’t know money is being misallocated due to insuf­ficient oversight of nonprofits.</p>
<p>All they know is they pay high taxes for no reason. And so they leave. Oregon’s largest county <a href="https://www.oregonlive.com/politics/2023/03/multnomah-county-lost-residents-faster-than-any-other-oregon-county-census-bureau-says.html#:~:text=a%20million%20people.-,Oregon's%20largest%20county%20shed%202.5%25%20of%20its%20population%20from%20April,lost%20more%20than%2010%2C500%20residents.">lost 2.5 percent of its population between 2020 and 2022</a>. As the population declines, the tax base shrinks. San Francisco’s sales tax revenue <a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/article/downtown-sf-retail-18076696.php">fell 22 percent between 2019 and 2022</a>, with the worst decline seen downtown, where office buildings <a href="https://sfstandard.com/2023/04/05/downtown-san-francisco-vacancies-hit-record-high-as-city-nears-breaking-point/">now have record-high vacancy rates</a>.</p>
<p>Many articles have been written recently about the threat such cities face <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/10/06/the-urban-doom-loop-threatening-cities-like-new-york-and-san-francisco.html">of an “urban doom loop,”</a> in which a falling population guts tax revenue, which forces cuts to city services, thus reducing livability and causing an accelerating population exodus in a vicious cycle. To my knowledge, however, nobody has ever argued that a major contributor to this death spiral is outsourcing government services to unaccountable nonprofit organizations, rather than increasing state capacity and im­proving the government’s ability to solve problems itself. In this contrarian narrative, American cities are not failing because they’re too socialist; they’re failing because they aren’t socialist enough.</p>
<p>And that, alas, is the state of the great American city in the early twenty-first century, where nothing is as it seems. Ours is a country where “progressivism” has nothing in common with the movement from which it takes its name; where “socialists” privatize government services at every opportunity; and where countless “nonprofits” exist solely for the misbegotten profit of the people who run them. Again and again, the names we use to explain the realities of modern urban politics are propagandistic marketing terms and not an accurate representation of what is taking place.</p>
<p>Just like with the invention of the Chilean Sea Bass, <span>however—which</span> is neither Chilean nor a <span>bass—many</span> people are making money off the scheme. Who cares if it’s all a lie?</p>
<h6><i>This article originally appeared in </i>American Affairs<i> Volume VIII, Number 2 (Summer 2024): 134–45.</i></h6>
<!-- AddThis Advanced Settings above via filter on the_content --><!-- AddThis Advanced Settings below via filter on the_content --><!-- AddThis Advanced Settings generic via filter on the_content --><!-- AddThis Share Buttons above via filter on the_content --><!-- AddThis Share Buttons below via filter on the_content --><!-- AddThis Share Buttons generic via filter on the_content -->		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[WP21 (222 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ma.tt/2024/05/wp21/</link>
            <guid>40496858</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2024 02:40:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ma.tt/2024/05/wp21/">https://ma.tt/2024/05/wp21/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40496858">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="page" role="main">

			
				
<article id="post-114533">
	<!-- .entry-header -->

		<div>
		
<p>It seems like just yesterday WordPress was <a href="https://ma.tt/2016/05/wordpress-is-a-teenager/">becoming a teenager</a>, and in a blink of the eye it’s now old enough to drink! 21 years since <a href="https://mikelittle.org/">Mike</a> and I did the first release of WordPress, forking <a href="https://miche.lv/">Michel’s</a> work on b2/cafélog.</p>



<p>There’s been many milestones and highlights along the way, and many more to come. I’ve been thinking a lot about elements that made WordPress successful in its early years that we should keep in mind as we build this year and beyond. Here’s 11 opinions:</p>



<ol>
<li>Simple things should be easy and intuitive, and complex things possible.</li>



<li>Blogging, commenting, and pingbacks need to be fun. Static websites are fine, but dynamic ones are better. Almost every site would be improved by having a great blog.</li>



<li>Wikis are amazing, and our documentation should be wiki-easy to edit.</li>



<li>Forums should be front and center in the community. <a href="https://bbpress.org/">bbPress</a> and <a href="https://buddypress.org/">BuddyPress</a> need some love.</li>



<li>Every plugin and theme should have all the infrastructure that we use to build WordPress itself—version control, bug trackers, forums, documentation, internationalization, chat rooms, P2, and easy pathways for contribution and community. We shouldn’t be uploading ZIPs in 2024!</li>



<li>Theme previews should be great, and a wide collection of non-commercial themes with diverse aesthetics and functionality are crucial. </li>



<li>We can’t over-index for guidelines and requirements. Better to have good marketplace dynamics and engineer automated feedback loops and transparency to users. Boundaries in functionality and design should be pushed. (But spam and spammy behavior deserves zero tolerance.)</li>



<li>Feedback loops are so important, and should scale with usage and the entire community rather than being reliant on gatekeepers.</li>



<li>Core should be opinionated and quirky: Easter eggs, language with personality even if it’s difficult to translate, jazzy.</li>



<li>Everyone developing and making decisions for software needs to use it.</li>



<li>It’s important that we all do support, go to meetups and events, anything we can to stay close to regular end-users of what we make.</li>
</ol>



<p>What would you add?</p>



<p>Fun fact: On May 27, 2003 I blogged “Working backwards, earlier tonight was great. Put&nbsp;WordPress&nbsp;out, which felt great.” as one sentence in a <a href="https://ma.tt/2003/05/locked-out/">953-word entry written from the porch of my parent’s house</a> where I was accidentally locked out all night until my Dad left in the morning to go to work. Had no idea WordPress would be as big as it is. Earlier that night had set up WP for my friend Ramie Speight, and done some phone tech support for another friend Mike Tremoulet I had met through the local blogger meetup. My friends from high school all had their own domains with WP and that feedback loop was magical for shaping the software.</p>

	</div><!-- .entry-content -->
	
	<!-- .entry-meta -->
</article><!-- #post -->
						<nav>
		<h2>
			Post navigation		</h2>
		<!-- .nav-links -->
	</nav><!-- .navigation -->
						
<!-- #comments -->
			
		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Grokked Transformers Are Implicit Reasoners (118 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15071</link>
            <guid>40495149</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 21:58:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15071">https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15071</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40495149">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content-inner">
    
    
                
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.15071">View PDF</a>
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/html/2405.15071v2">HTML (experimental)</a></p><blockquote>
            <span>Abstract:</span>We study whether transformers can learn to implicitly reason over parametric knowledge, a skill that even the most capable language models struggle with. Focusing on two representative reasoning types, composition and comparison, we consistently find that transformers can learn implicit reasoning, but only through grokking, i.e., extended training far beyond overfitting. The levels of generalization also vary across reasoning types: when faced with out-of-distribution examples, transformers fail to systematically generalize for composition but succeed for comparison. We delve into the model's internals throughout training, conducting analytical experiments that reveal: 1) the mechanism behind grokking, such as the formation of the generalizing circuit and its relation to the relative efficiency of generalizing and memorizing circuits, and 2) the connection between systematicity and the configuration of the generalizing circuit. Our findings guide data and training setup to better induce implicit reasoning and suggest potential improvements to the transformer architecture, such as encouraging cross-layer knowledge sharing. Furthermore, we demonstrate that for a challenging reasoning task with a large search space, GPT-4-Turbo and Gemini-1.5-Pro based on non-parametric memory fail badly regardless of prompting styles or retrieval augmentation, while a fully grokked transformer can achieve near-perfect accuracy, showcasing the power of parametric memory for complex reasoning.
    </blockquote>

    <!--CONTEXT-->
    
  </div><div>
      <h2>Submission history</h2><p> From: Boshi Wang [<a href="https://arxiv.org/show-email/33f4e04a/2405.15071">view email</a>]      <br>            <strong><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15071v1">[v1]</a></strong>
        Thu, 23 May 2024 21:42:19 UTC (7,877 KB)<br>
    <strong>[v2]</strong>
        Mon, 27 May 2024 03:55:35 UTC (7,877 KB)<br>
</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Notepad Tab (127 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://notepadtab.com/</link>
            <guid>40494793</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 21:15:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://notepadtab.com/">https://notepadtab.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40494793">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><header>

  <div><p><a rel="author" href="https://notepadtab.com/">Notepad Tab</a></p></div>
</header>
<main aria-label="Content">
      
    </main>



</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[GTFL – A Graphical Terminal for Common Lisp (101 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://www.martin-loetzsch.de/gtfl/</link>
            <guid>40494097</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 20:00:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://www.martin-loetzsch.de/gtfl/">http://www.martin-loetzsch.de/gtfl/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40494097">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><h3>Abstract</h3><p>GTFL is a graphical terminal for Common Lisp. The client is a
         html page running in a web browser and GTFL provides
         mechanisms for sending content to the client page from within
         Lisp (using <a href="http://www.weitz.de/hunchentoot/">HUNCHENTOOT</a> and <a href="http://martin-loetzsch.de/ht-simple-ajax">HT-SIMPLE-AJAX</a>).</p><p>It is meant for Lisp programmers who want to debug or
         visualize their own algorithms. Instead of printing tracing
         information to the Lisp listener (which everybody normally
         does to understand what's going on), more readable graphical
         representations of the algorithm's internals are sent to the
         GTFL client page.</p><p>GTFL also comes with mechanisms for visualizing
         complex (hierarchical) data or control structures. It
         provides functions for drawing trees and for hiding
         complexity in elements that expand when the user clicks on
         them.</p><p>Two real-life examples for an application of GTFL can be found <a href="http://www.martin-loetzsch.de/gtfl/application-example-1/">here</a> and <a href="http://www.martin-loetzsch.de/gtfl/application-example-2/">here</a>. These are debug traces of linguistic parsing and production in the <a href="http://fcg-net.org/">Fluid Construction Grammar</a> (FCG) framework. Such traces help the developers FCG to
        understand and debug their programs and they help users of FCG
        to see what their linguistic rules are doing. By encapsulating
        visualizations for representations in expandable html
        elements, the complete trace fits into one browser window and
        still includes every little detail and intermediate processing
        step of the involved FCG algorithms (which would be thousands
        of pages debugging output to the listener).</p><p>Below is another example of using GTFL for visualizing Lisp
         data structures. It was created with a few lines of code (<a href="http://www.martin-loetzsch.de/gtfl/examples/asdf-dependency-tree.lisp">examples/asdf-dependency-tree.lisp</a>) and shows the dependencies of an asdf system. Click
         on the black nodes to reveal details about the systems
         and click them a second time to hide the details again:</p><div id="asdf-dependencies"><h2>dependencies for asdf system GTFL</h2></div><p>GTFL comes with a <a href="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/bsd-license.php">BSD-style license</a> so you can basically do with it whatever you want.</p><p><span>Download shortcut:</span> <a href="http://martin-loetzsch.de/gtfl/gtfl.tar.gz">http://martin-loetzsch.de/gtfl/gtfl.tar.gz</a>.</p></div><hr><p>Sponsored links</p><hr><h3>Contents</h3><ol><li><a href="#download-and-installation">Download and installation</a></li><li><a href="#browser-compatibility">Browser compatibility</a></li><li><a href="#the-gtfl-terminal">The GTFL terminal</a><ol><li><a href="#start-gtfl"><tt>start-gtfl</tt></a></li><li><a href="#_gtfl-address_"><tt>*gtfl-address*</tt></a></li><li><a href="#_gtfl-port_"><tt>*gtfl-port*</tt></a></li><li><a href="#gtfl-out"><tt>gtfl-out</tt></a></li><li><a href="#replace-element-content"><tt>replace-element-content</tt></a></li><li><a href="#append-to-element"><tt>append-to-element</tt></a></li><li><a href="#reset-gtfl"><tt>reset-gtfl</tt></a></li><li><a href="#_reset-functions_"><tt>*reset-functions*</tt></a></li><li><a href="#who"><tt>who</tt></a></li><li><a href="#who2s"><tt>who2s</tt></a></li><li><a href="#who-lambda"><tt>who-lambda</tt></a></li><li><a href="#define-css"><tt>define-css</tt></a></li><li><a href="#define-js"><tt>define-js</tt></a></li><li><a href="#make-id-string"><tt>make-id-string</tt></a></li></ol></li><li><a href="#expandable-elements">Expandable elements</a><ol><li><a href="#make-expandable_collapsable-element"><tt>make-expandable/collapsable-element</tt></a></li><li><a href="#make-expand_collapse-link"><tt>make-expand/collapse-link</tt></a></li><li><a href="#make-expand_collapse-all-link"><tt>make-expand/collapse-all-link</tt></a></li><li><a href="#_create-static-expandable_collapsable-elements_"><tt>*create-static-expandable/collapsable-elements*</tt></a></li></ol></li><li><a href="#tree-drawing">Tree drawing</a><ol><li><a href="#draw-node-with-children"><tt>draw-node-with-children</tt></a></li></ol></li><li><a href="#resizing-s-expressions">Resizing s-expressions</a><ol><li><a href="#html-pprint"><tt>html-pprint</tt></a></li></ol></li><li><a href="#acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</a></li></ol><h3 id="download-and-installation">Download and installation</h3><p>GTFL together with examples and this documentation can be downloaded from <a href="http://martin-loetzsch.de/gtfl/gtfl.tar.gz">http://martin-loetzsch.de/gtfl/gtfl.tar.gz</a>. The current version is 0.1.3.</p><p>GTFL directly relies on <a href="http://www.weitz.de/cl-who/">CL-WHO</a> for html generation, <a href="http://www.weitz.de/hunchentoot/">HUNCHENTOOT</a> (version &gt;= 1.1.0) for running the web server and <a href="http://martin-loetzsch.de/ht-simple-ajax">HT-SIMPLE-AJAX</a> for the asynchrounous client/server communication. And these
        libraries themselves require quite a number of other
        libraries (see the dependency
        graph <a href="#asdf-dependencies">above</a>). Make sure you have recent versions of everything.</p><p>If you don't want to download all these libraries manually, you can use <a href="http://www.quicklisp.org/">Quicklisp</a> or <a href="http://www.cliki.net/ASDF-Install">ASDF-INSTALL</a>:</p><pre>(ql:quickload "gtfl")</pre><pre>(asdf-install:install 'gtfl)</pre><p>Once everything is installed, GTFL is compiled and loaded with:</p><pre>(asdf:operate 'asdf:load-op :gtfl)</pre><h3 id="browser-compatibility">Browser compatibility</h3><p>As of 2012, all contemporary web browsers except Internet
        Explorer work well with gtfl.</p><p>The output of GTFL is XHTML 1.0 Strict and CSS level 2.1
        conform as can be checked below (this page is a document
        created with GTFL):<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<a href="http://validator.w3.org/check?uri=http://martin-loetzsch.de/gtfl/"><img src="http://www.martin-loetzsch.de/gtfl/valid-xhtml10.png" alt="Valid XHTML 1.0 Strict"></a>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<a href="http://jigsaw.w3.org/css-validator/validator?uri=http://martin-loetzsch.de/gtfl/"><img src="http://www.martin-loetzsch.de/gtfl/valid-css21.gif" alt="Valid CSS level 2.1"></a></p><h3 id="the-gtfl-terminal">The GTFL terminal</h3><p>GTFL consists of two main components that are defined in <a href="http://www.martin-loetzsch.de/gtfl/gtfl.lisp"><i>gtfl.lisp</i></a>: a html client page running in a web browser and a Lisp web
        server that mediates between your program and the client page.
        In order to push stuff from Lisp to the client, the Lisp side
        of GTFL maintains a "request list" into which the
        output routines put their content. The client page has a
        continuously running event loop that polls this list every
        200ms using asynchronous AJAX calls.</p><p>Here's now some basic usage examples:</p><pre>(<a href="#start-gtfl"><tt>start-gtfl</tt></a>)</pre><p>This starts the web server. You should see now the client page at <a href="http://localhost:8000/">http://localhost:8000</a> (or the address and port you have set).</p><p>Now you can push any content there, for example</p><pre>(<a href="#gtfl-out"><tt>gtfl-out</tt></a> (:h1 "hello world"))</pre><div><tt>=&gt;</tt><p>This will show up in the client page:</p></div><p><h2>hello world</h2></p><p>GTFL uses <a href="http://www.weitz.de/cl-who/">CL-WHO</a> for rendering s-expressions into XHTML. If you are not familiar
        with CL-WHO then read its documentation first.</p><p>More examples:</p><pre>(<a href="#gtfl-out"><tt>gtfl-out</tt></a> (:p "some text, " (:span :style "color:red;" "and some in red."))
          (:p "and a second paragraph"))</pre><p><tt>=&gt;</tt></p><div><p>some text, <span>and some in red.</span></p><p>and a second paragraph</p></div><pre>(defparameter *element-id* nil)

(<a href="#gtfl-out"><tt>gtfl-out</tt></a> (:p "a paragraph, " 
              (:span :id (setf *element-id* (<a href="#make-id-string"><tt>make-id-string</tt></a>)) :style "border:1px solid red"
                     "and a span as child element")))</pre><p><tt>=&gt;</tt></p><p>a paragraph, <span>and a span as child element</span></p><pre>(<a href="#replace-element-content"><tt>replace-element-content</tt></a> *element-id* "and " (:b "new") " span content")</pre><p><tt>=&gt;</tt></p><p>a paragraph, <span>and <b>new</b> span content</span></p><pre>(<a href="#gtfl-out"><tt>gtfl-out</tt></a> (:p "a paragraph, " 
              (:span :id (setf *element-id* (<a href="#make-id-string"><tt>make-id-string</tt></a>)) :style "border:1px solid red"
                     "and a span as child element")))</pre><p><tt>=&gt;</tt></p><p>a paragraph, <span>and a span as child element</span></p><pre>(<a href="#append-to-element"><tt>append-to-element</tt></a> *element-id* ", and " (:b "more") " content")</pre><p><tt>=&gt;</tt></p><p>a paragraph, <span>and a span as child element, and <b>more</b> content</span></p><p>The address to use for the web server. Default: "localhost".</p><p>The port to use for the web server. Default: 8000.</p><p>Starts the web server at the specified address.</p><p>Adds some content to the bottom of the client page.</p><p><i>expressions</i> is something that's ok within CL-WHO's <tt>with-html-output</tt> macro.</p><p>See examples above.</p><p id="replace-element-content">[Macro]<br><b>replace-element-content </b><i>id <tt>&amp;rest</tt> expressions</i> <tt>=&gt;</tt> <i>no values</i></p><p>Replaces the content of the element with <i>id</i> (a string) by <i>expressions</i>.</p><p>See examples above.</p><p>Appends <i>expressions</i> to the element with <i>id</i>.</p><p>See examples above.</p><p>Clears the content area of the client page and resets things on the Lisp side.</p><p>This function is called either</p><ul><li>directly,</li><li>when the 'reset' button on the client page was clicked,</li><li>when the client page is (re)loaded.</li></ul><p>A list of functions that are called by <a href="#reset-gtfl"><tt>reset-gtfl</tt></a>. If you want to reset some of your stuff in this case, add your function here: <tt>(pushnew #'my-reset-function *reset-functions*)</tt>.</p><p>Writes rendered html to <tt>*standard-output*</tt>. This is a shortcut for <tt>(with-html-output (*standard-output*) &lt;expressions&gt;)</tt>.</p><p><i>expressions</i> is something that's ok within CL-WHO's <tt>with-html-output</tt> macro.</p><p>Example:</p><pre>GTFL&gt; (<a href="#who"><tt>who</tt></a> (:div :foo "bar" "baz"))
&lt;div foo="bar"&gt;baz&lt;/div&gt;
NIL</pre><p>Renders expression into a html string. This is a shortcut for <tt>(with-html-output-to-string (*standard-output*) &lt;expressions&gt;)</tt>.</p><p>Example:</p><pre>GTFL&gt; (<a href="#who2s"><tt>who2s</tt></a> (:div :foo "bar" "baz"))
"&lt;div foo="bar"&gt;baz&lt;/div&gt;"</pre><p>Makes an anonymous function that writes the rendered html to <tt>*standard-output*</tt>.</p><p>Example:</p><pre>GTFL&gt; (<a href="#who-lambda"><tt>who-lambda</tt></a>) (:div :foo "bar" "baz"))
#&lt;Anonymous Function #x300043366A4F&gt;
GTFL&gt; (funcall *)
&lt;div foo="bar"&gt;baz&lt;/div&gt;
NIL</pre><p>Adds css fragments to the client page. When the client page is
     created, all these code fragments are concatenated into one big
     inline css. Note that you will have to reload the client page
     when you change css definitions.</p><p><i>id</i> is an id for the code fragment. Repeated calls with
    the same id overwrite previous definitions. <i>css</i> is 
    the css code fragment. You are responsible for adding line endings.</p><p>Example:</p><pre>(<a href="#define-css"><tt>define-css</tt></a> 'foo "
div.foo {font-weight:bold;}
")</pre><p>The same as <a href="#define-css"><tt>define-css</tt></a> above, but for javascript code.</p><pre>(<a href="#define-js"><tt>define-js</tt></a> 'bar "
function bar () { return (1 + 1); }
")</pre><p>Creates an uniquely numbered id string that can be used as 
                 an id for html elements.</p><p><i>base</i> is the prefix of the id (default: "id").</p><p>Example:</p><pre>GTFL&gt; (<a href="#make-id-string"><tt>make-id-string</tt></a>)
"id-1"
GTFL&gt; (<a href="#make-id-string"><tt>make-id-string</tt></a>)
"id-2"
GTFL&gt; (<a href="#make-id-string"><tt>make-id-string</tt></a> "foo")
"foo-1"
GTFL&gt; (<a href="#make-id-string"><tt>make-id-string</tt></a> "foo")
"foo-2"</pre><h3 id="expandable-elements">Expandable elements</h3><p>The file <a href="http://www.martin-loetzsch.de/gtfl/expandable-elements.lisp"><i>expandable-elements.lisp</i></a> contains
        functionality to create html elements that expand when the
        user clicks on them and that collapse again when they are
        clicked a second time. Furthermore, several elements can be
        expanded/ collapsed at once using another button.</p><p>In order to save browser resources (memory, time), the
        expanded and collapsed version of each element are kept in
        Lisp and are only sent to the browser when needed: the version
        that is initally sent to the client contains only the
        collapsed version and when the expand link is clicked, it is
        replaced with the expanded version stored on the lisp side.</p><p>Example:</p><pre>(<a href="#gtfl-out"><tt>gtfl-out</tt></a> 
 (:div 
   (let ((expand/collapse-all-id (<a href="#make-id-string"><tt>make-id-string</tt></a>))
         (<a href="#_create-static-expandable_collapsable-elements_"><tt>*create-static-expandable/collapsable-elements*</tt></a> t))
         (<a href="#make-expandable_collapsable-element"><tt>make-expandable/collapsable-element</tt></a> 
          (<a href="#make-id-string"><tt>make-id-string</tt></a>) expand/collapse-all-id
          (<a href="#who2s"><tt>who2s</tt></a> (<a href="#make-expand_collapse-all-link"><tt>make-expand/collapse-all-link</tt></a> expand/collapse-all-id t nil "expand all"))
          (<a href="#who2s"><tt>who2s</tt></a> (<a href="#make-expand_collapse-all-link"><tt>make-expand/collapse-all-link</tt></a> expand/collapse-all-id nil nil "collapse all")))
         (loop repeat 3
            for element-id = (<a href="#make-id-string"><tt>make-id-string</tt></a>)
            do (htm (:div :style "border:1px solid #aaa;display:inline-block;margin-left:10px;"
                          (<a href="#make-expandable_collapsable-element"><tt>make-expandable/collapsable-element</tt></a> 
                           element-id expand/collapse-all-id
                           (<a href="#who2s"><tt>who2s</tt></a> (:div (<a href="#make-expand_collapse-link"><tt>make-expand/collapse-link</tt></a> element-id t nil "expand")
                                        (:br) "collapsed"))
                           (<a href="#who2s"><tt>who2s</tt></a> (:div (<a href="#make-expand_collapse-link"><tt>make-expand/collapse-link</tt></a> element-id nil nil "collapse") 
                                        (:br) (:div :style "font-size:150%" "expanded"))))))))))</pre><p><tt>=&gt;</tt></p><p id="make-expandable_collapsable-element">[Function]<br><b>make-expandable/collapsable-element </b><i>element-id expand/collapse-all-id collapsed-element expanded-element <tt>&amp;key</tt> expand-initially</i> <tt>=&gt;</tt> <i>no values</i></p><p>Creates an element that allows to switch between an expanded
     and a collapsed version.</p><p><i>element-id</i> (a string) is the id given to the element so that
     function <a href="#make-expand_collapse-link"><tt>make-expand/collapse-link</tt></a> can reference it. <i>expand/collapse-all-id</i> (a string) is the id of a group of elements that can be
    expanded/collapsed at the same time (see <a href="#make-expand_collapse-all-link"><tt>make-expand/collapse-all-link</tt></a>).</p><p><i>collapsed-element</i> and <i>expanded-element</i> are the collapsed and expanded version of the element. They can
       be either an expression that evaluates to a html string, e.g. <tt>"&lt;div foo/&gt;"</tt> or <tt>(<a href="#who2s"><tt>who2s</tt></a> :div "foo")</tt>, or an anonymous function
      that writes an html string, e.g. <tt>(<a href="#who-lambda"><tt>who-lambda</tt></a> (:div "foo"))</tt> or <tt>#'(lambda () (princ "&lt;div foo/&gt;"))</tt>. In the latter case the expanded version only gets computed when
       requested by the client, which avoids unneccessary computation.</p><p>When <i>expand-initially</i> is <tt>t</tt> then the
       expanded version is shown initially.</p><p id="make-expand_collapse-link">[Macro]<br><b>make-expand/collapse-link </b><i>element-id expand? title <tt>&amp;rest</tt> content</i> <tt>=&gt;</tt> <i>no values</i></p><p>Makes a link for expanding/collapsing an element.</p><p><i>element-id</i> is the id of the element to expand
     or collapse. When <i>expand?</i> is <tt>t</tt>, then the
     element gets expanded, otherwise collapsed. <i>title</i> is
     the title of the link (shown when the mouse is over the
     link). When nil, then "expand" or "collapse"
     are used. <i>body</i> is the content of the link (a cl-who
     expression).</p><p>Example:</p><pre>GTFL&gt; (<a href="#make-expand_collapse-link"><tt>make-expand/collapse-link</tt></a> "foo" t nil "expand")
&lt;a href="javascript:expand('foo');" title="expand"&gt;expand&lt;/a&gt;
NIL
GTFL&gt; (<a href="#make-expand_collapse-link"><tt>make-expand/collapse-link</tt></a> "foo" nil "click here to collapse" (:b "collapse"))
&lt;a href="javascript:collapse('foo');" title="click here to collapse"&gt;&lt;b&gt;collapse&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
NIL</pre><p id="make-expand_collapse-all-link">[Macro]<br><b>make-expand/collapse-all-link </b><i>expand/collapse-all-id expand? title <tt>&amp;rest</tt> content</i> <tt>=&gt;</tt> <i>no values</i></p><p>Makes a link for expanding/collapsing a group of elements.</p><p><i>expand/collapse-all-id</i>is the id of the
     element group to expand/collapse. All other parameters as
     above.</p><p id="_create-static-expandable_collapsable-elements_">[Special variable]<br><b>*create-static-expandable/collapsable-elements* </b><i></i></p><p>When this is set to <tt>t</tt>, both the expanded
     and collapsed version will be embedded in the html code (one
     visible and the other hidden). This makes the html code
     bigger (and thus rendering slower), but allows to save generated
     html pages, with the expand/collapse functionality still working
     when not connected to the web server. Note that in the example
     above this was also set to <tt>t</tt>, because otherwise the
     example would not work in this static html page that is not
     connected to the lisp server.</p><h3 id="tree-drawing">Tree drawing</h3><p>In <a href="http://www.martin-loetzsch.de/gtfl/tree-drawing.lisp"><i>tree-drawing.lisp</i></a> there is a function for recursively drawing trees. It takes
       html expressions for drawing a node and its children (which can
       be trees themselves) and connects them with horizontal and
       vertical lines. The decision how to layout the tree (i.e. how
       wide to draw each node) is left to the html rendering engine of
       the web browser.</p><p>Examples (resize the browser window to see the dynamic layout
        in action):</p><pre>(defparameter *example-tree* 
  '("top node."
    ("child node one with three children" 
     ("first out of three children") ("second out of three children") ("third out of three children"))
    ("child node two with one child" 
     ("very long text. very long text. very long text. very long text. 
       very long text. very long text. very long text."))))

(defun draw-node (string) 
  (<a href="#who"><tt>who</tt></a> 
   (:div :style "padding:4px;border:1px solid #888;margin-top:4px;margin-bottom:4px;background-color:#eee;"
         (princ string))))


(defun draw-tree* (tree) 
  (<a href="#draw-node-with-children"><tt>draw-node-with-children</tt></a> 
   (<a href="#who-lambda"><tt>who-lambda</tt></a> (draw-node (car tree)))
   (mapcar #'(lambda (x) (<a href="#who-lambda"><tt>who-lambda</tt></a> (draw-tree* x))) (cdr tree))))

(<a href="#gtfl-out"><tt>gtfl-out</tt></a> (draw-tree* *example-tree*))
</pre><p><tt>=&gt;</tt></p><div><table><tbody><tr><td><p>top node.</p></td><td></td><td><div><table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><div><table><tbody><tr><td><p>child node one with three children</p></td><td></td><td><div><table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><div><p>first out of three children</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div><div><table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><div><p>second out of three children</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div><div><table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><div><p>third out of three children</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div><div><table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><div><table><tbody><tr><td><p>child node two with one child</p></td><td></td><td><div><table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><div><p>very long text. very long text. very long text. very long text. very long text. very long text. very long text.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div><table><tbody><tr><td>With parameters <tt>:right-to-left t :color "green" :style "dotted"</tt> <tt>=&gt;</tt><div><table><tbody><tr><td><div><table><tbody><tr><td><div><table><tbody><tr><td><div><table><tbody><tr><td><div><p>first out of three children</p></div></td><td></td></tr></tbody></table></div><div><table><tbody><tr><td><div><p>second out of three children</p></div></td><td></td></tr></tbody></table></div><div><table><tbody><tr><td><div><p>third out of three children</p></div></td><td></td></tr></tbody></table></div></td><td></td><td><p>child node one with three children</p></td></tr></tbody></table></div></td><td></td></tr></tbody></table></div><div><table><tbody><tr><td><div><table><tbody><tr><td><div><table><tbody><tr><td><div><p>very long text. very long text. very long text. very long text. very long text. very long text. very long text.</p></div></td><td></td></tr></tbody></table></div></td><td></td><td><p>child node two with one child</p></td></tr></tbody></table></div></td><td></td></tr></tbody></table></div></td><td></td><td><p>top node.</p></td></tr></tbody></table></div></td><td>With parameters <tt>:color "#33a" :line-width "2px"</tt> <tt>=&gt;</tt><div><table><tbody><tr><td><p>top node.</p></td><td></td><td><div><table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><div><table><tbody><tr><td><p>child node one with three children</p></td><td></td><td><div><table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><div><p>first out of three children</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div><div><table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><div><p>second out of three children</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div><div><table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><div><p>third out of three children</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div><div><table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><div><table><tbody><tr><td><p>child node two with one child</p></td><td></td><td><div><table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><div><p>very long text. very long text. very long text. very long text. very long text. very long text. very long text.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div></td></tr></tbody></table><p>A function for recursively drawing trees in html. It draws a node
with connections to it's children (which can be trees themselves).</p><p><i>node</i> is a parameterless function that creates the html
    code for the parent node. <i>children</i> is a list of
    functions for drawing the children of the node. The reason to use
    closures instead of for example strings here is both
    efficiency (no intermediate structures are built) and to allow for
    re-ordering of elements (when the tree is drawn from right to left.</p><p>When <i>right-to-left</i> is <tt>t</tt>, then the top node
    of the tree is drawn at the right. <i>color</i> sets the color
    of the connecting lines (e.g. "#ff0000" or
    "red", default is "#888"), <i>width</i>
    the the width of the horizontal connectors (e.g. "25px",
    default is "10px"), <i>line-width</i> the the
    thickness of the lines (e.g. "3px", default is
    "1px") and style the line style ("solid",
    "dotted" or "dashed", default is "solid").</p><h3 id="resizing-s-expressions">Resizing s-expressions</h3><p>File <a href="http://www.martin-loetzsch.de/gtfl/html-pprint.lisp"><i>html-pprint.lisp</i></a> provides the function <a href="#html-pprint"><tt>html-pprint</tt></a> to display
        s-expressions in html. This could of course be done
        with <tt>(:pre (pprint x))</tt>, but this has the disadvantage that the result will have a
        fixed width. <a href="#html-pprint"><tt>html-pprint</tt></a> produces output that is
        very similar to the one of <tt>pprint</tt> but that also
        dynamically resizes depending on the available width (while 
        maintaining proper indentation).</p><p>Examples (resize browser window to see the dynamic relayout
   and click on the symbols to highlight other symbols with the same
   name):</p><pre>(defparameter *example-list*
  `((("foo-1" "bar-1") (foo-2 bar-2) (:foo-3 :bar-3) 
     (,(make-symbol "FOO-4") ,(make-symbol "BAR-4"))
     (foo-5 . bar-5))
    ((0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9) ,(asdf:find-system :gtfl))))

(<a href="#gtfl-out"><tt>gtfl-out</tt></a> (:div :style "border:1px solid #aaa;" (<a href="#html-pprint"><tt>html-pprint</tt></a> *example-list*)))</pre><p><tt>=&gt;</tt></p><div><p><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span>"foo-1"</span></span> <span><span>"bar-1")</span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-197" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-2','s-197','#FFFF99');"><a name="FOO-2"></a>foo-2</span></span> <span><span id="s-198" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-2','s-198','#CCCCCC');"><a name="BAR-2"></a>bar-2<span>)</span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-199" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-3','s-199','#66FF99');"><a name="FOO-3"></a>:foo-3</span></span> <span><span id="s-200" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-3','s-200','#CCFF99');"><a name="BAR-3"></a>:bar-3<span>)</span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-201" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-4','s-201','#CCFFFF');"><a name="FOO-4"></a>#:foo-4</span></span> <span><span id="s-202" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-4','s-202','#CCFFCC');"><a name="BAR-4"></a>#:bar-4<span>)</span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-203" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-5','s-203','#66FF99');"><a name="FOO-5"></a>foo-5</span></span></span><span><span><span>&nbsp;.&nbsp;</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-204" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-5','s-204','#CCFF99');"><a name="BAR-5"></a>bar-5<span>))</span></span></span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span>0</span></span> <span><span>1</span></span> <span><span>2</span></span> <span><span>3</span></span> <span><span>4</span></span> <span><span>5</span></span> <span><span>6</span></span> <span><span>7</span></span> <span><span>8</span></span> <span><span>9)</span></span></span></span> <span><span>#&lt;asdf:system "gtfl"&gt;))</span></span></span></span></span></span></p></div><pre>(<a href="#gtfl-out"><tt>gtfl-out</tt></a>
 (:table :style "border-collapse:collapse;"
         (:tr (loop for i from 1 to 3 
                 do (htm (:td :style "border:1px solid #aaa;"
                              (<a href="#html-pprint"><tt>html-pprint</tt></a> *example-list*)))))))
</pre><p><tt>=&gt;</tt></p><div><table><tbody><tr><td><p><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span>"foo-1"</span></span> <span><span>"bar-1")</span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-205" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-2','s-205','#FFFF99');"><a name="FOO-2"></a>foo-2</span></span> <span><span id="s-206" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-2','s-206','#CCCCCC');"><a name="BAR-2"></a>bar-2<span>)</span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-207" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-3','s-207','#66FF99');"><a name="FOO-3"></a>:foo-3</span></span> <span><span id="s-208" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-3','s-208','#CCFF99');"><a name="BAR-3"></a>:bar-3<span>)</span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-209" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-4','s-209','#CCFFFF');"><a name="FOO-4"></a>#:foo-4</span></span> <span><span id="s-210" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-4','s-210','#CCFFCC');"><a name="BAR-4"></a>#:bar-4<span>)</span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-211" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-5','s-211','#66FF99');"><a name="FOO-5"></a>foo-5</span></span></span><span><span><span>&nbsp;.&nbsp;</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-212" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-5','s-212','#CCFF99');"><a name="BAR-5"></a>bar-5<span>))</span></span></span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span>0</span></span> <span><span>1</span></span> <span><span>2</span></span> <span><span>3</span></span> <span><span>4</span></span> <span><span>5</span></span> <span><span>6</span></span> <span><span>7</span></span> <span><span>8</span></span> <span><span>9)</span></span></span></span> <span><span>#&lt;asdf:system "gtfl"&gt;))</span></span></span></span></span></span></p></td><td><p><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span>"foo-1"</span></span> <span><span>"bar-1")</span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-213" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-2','s-213','#FFFF99');"><a name="FOO-2"></a>foo-2</span></span> <span><span id="s-214" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-2','s-214','#CCCCCC');"><a name="BAR-2"></a>bar-2<span>)</span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-215" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-3','s-215','#66FF99');"><a name="FOO-3"></a>:foo-3</span></span> <span><span id="s-216" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-3','s-216','#CCFF99');"><a name="BAR-3"></a>:bar-3<span>)</span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-217" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-4','s-217','#CCFFFF');"><a name="FOO-4"></a>#:foo-4</span></span> <span><span id="s-218" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-4','s-218','#CCFFCC');"><a name="BAR-4"></a>#:bar-4<span>)</span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-219" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-5','s-219','#66FF99');"><a name="FOO-5"></a>foo-5</span></span></span><span><span><span>&nbsp;.&nbsp;</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-220" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-5','s-220','#CCFF99');"><a name="BAR-5"></a>bar-5<span>))</span></span></span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span>0</span></span> <span><span>1</span></span> <span><span>2</span></span> <span><span>3</span></span> <span><span>4</span></span> <span><span>5</span></span> <span><span>6</span></span> <span><span>7</span></span> <span><span>8</span></span> <span><span>9)</span></span></span></span> <span><span>#&lt;asdf:system "gtfl"&gt;))</span></span></span></span></span></span></p></td><td><p><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span>"foo-1"</span></span> <span><span>"bar-1")</span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-221" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-2','s-221','#FFFF99');"><a name="FOO-2"></a>foo-2</span></span> <span><span id="s-222" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-2','s-222','#CCCCCC');"><a name="BAR-2"></a>bar-2<span>)</span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-223" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-3','s-223','#66FF99');"><a name="FOO-3"></a>:foo-3</span></span> <span><span id="s-224" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-3','s-224','#CCFF99');"><a name="BAR-3"></a>:bar-3<span>)</span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-225" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-4','s-225','#CCFFFF');"><a name="FOO-4"></a>#:foo-4</span></span> <span><span id="s-226" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-4','s-226','#CCFFCC');"><a name="BAR-4"></a>#:bar-4<span>)</span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-227" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-5','s-227','#66FF99');"><a name="FOO-5"></a>foo-5</span></span></span><span><span><span>&nbsp;.&nbsp;</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-228" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-5','s-228','#CCFF99');"><a name="BAR-5"></a>bar-5<span>))</span></span></span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span>0</span></span> <span><span>1</span></span> <span><span>2</span></span> <span><span>3</span></span> <span><span>4</span></span> <span><span>5</span></span> <span><span>6</span></span> <span><span>7</span></span> <span><span>8</span></span> <span><span>9)</span></span></span></span> <span><span>#&lt;asdf:system "gtfl"&gt;))</span></span></span></span></span></span></p></td></tr></tbody></table></div><div><p><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span>"foo-1"</span></span> <span><span>"bar-1")</span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-229" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-2','s-229','#FFFF99');"><a name="FOO-2"></a>foo-2</span></span> <span><span id="s-230" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-2','s-230','#CCCCCC');"><a name="BAR-2"></a>bar-2<span>)</span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-231" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-3','s-231','#66FF99');"><a name="FOO-3"></a>:foo-3</span></span> <span><span id="s-232" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-3','s-232','#CCFF99');"><a name="BAR-3"></a>:bar-3<span>)</span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-233" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-4','s-233','#CCFFFF');"><a name="FOO-4"></a>#:foo-4</span></span> <span><span id="s-234" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-4','s-234','#CCFFCC');"><a name="BAR-4"></a>#:bar-4<span>)</span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-235" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-5','s-235','#66FF99');"><a name="FOO-5"></a>foo-5</span></span></span><span><span><span>&nbsp;.&nbsp;</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-236" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-5','s-236','#CCFF99');"><a name="BAR-5"></a>bar-5<span>))</span></span></span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span>0</span></span> <span><span>1</span></span> <span><span>2</span></span> <span><span>3</span></span> <span><span>4</span></span> <span><span>5</span></span> <span><span>6</span></span> <span><span>7</span></span> <span><span>8</span></span> <span><span>9)</span></span></span></span> <span><span>#&lt;asdf:system "gtfl"&gt;))</span></span></span></span></span></span></p></div><div><p><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span>"foo-1"</span></span> <span><span>"bar-1")</span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-237" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-2','s-237','#FFFF99');"><a name="FOO-2"></a>foo-2</span></span> <span><span id="s-238" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-2','s-238','#CCCCCC');"><a name="BAR-2"></a>bar-2<span>)</span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-239" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-3','s-239','#66FF99');"><a name="FOO-3"></a>:foo-3</span></span> <span><span id="s-240" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-3','s-240','#CCFF99');"><a name="BAR-3"></a>:bar-3<span>)</span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-241" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-4','s-241','#CCFFFF');"><a name="FOO-4"></a>#:foo-4</span></span> <span><span id="s-242" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-4','s-242','#CCFFCC');"><a name="BAR-4"></a>#:bar-4<span>)</span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-243" onclick="highlightSymbol('FOO-5','s-243','#66FF99');"><a name="FOO-5"></a>foo-5</span></span></span><span><span><span>&nbsp;.&nbsp;</span></span></span><span><span><span id="s-244" onclick="highlightSymbol('BAR-5','s-244','#CCFF99');"><a name="BAR-5"></a>bar-5<span>))</span></span></span></span></span></span></span> <span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span><span><span>(</span></span></span><span><span><span>0</span></span> <span><span>1</span></span> <span><span>2</span></span> <span><span>3</span></span> <span><span>4</span></span> <span><span>5</span></span> <span><span>6</span></span> <span><span>7</span></span> <span><span>8</span></span> <span><span>9)</span></span></span></span> <span><span>#&lt;asdf:system "gtfl"&gt;))</span></span></span></span></span></span></p></div><p>Displaying an x-expression in the html. The result lookes like
     coming from pprint (proper indention), but the layout is dynamic
     depending on the available width.</p><p><i>thing</i> is the thing to display. <i>max-width</i>limits
    the width of the result (in characters). When <tt>nil</tt>, then 
    the full available width is used</p><h3 id="acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</h3><p>GTFL was initially developed as part of the Babel2 framework (<a href="http://emergent-languages.org/">http://emergent-languages.org/</a>).</p><p><a href="http://arti.vub.ac.be/~jorisb/">Joris Bleys</a> and <a href="http://arti.vub.ac.be/~pieter/">Pieter Wellens</a> have helped a lot in improving the system by finding bugs and
       suggesting many of its current features.</p><p>This page was created with GTFL itself (see <a href="http://www.martin-loetzsch.de/gtfl/examples/index-html.lisp">examples/index-html.lisp</a>). The layout and structure is heavily inspired by (or
       directly copied from) <a href="http://weitz.de/documentation-template/">DOCUMENTATION-TEMPLATE</a>.</p><p>Last change: 2012/01/25 15:05:34 by <a href="http://martin-loetzsch.de/">Martin Loetzsch</a></p><hr><p>Sponsored links</p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[More Itertools (169 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/</link>
            <guid>40493074</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 18:03:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/">https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40493074">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section id="more-itertools" itemprop="articleBody" role="main" itemscope="itemscope" itemtype="http://schema.org/Article">

<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/"><img alt="https://readthedocs.org/projects/more-itertools/badge/?version=latest" src="https://readthedocs.org/projects/more-itertools/badge/?version=latest"></a>
<p>Python’s <code><span>itertools</span></code> library is a gem - you can compose elegant solutions
for a variety of problems with the functions it provides. In <code><span>more-itertools</span></code>
we collect additional building blocks, recipes, and routines for working with
Python iterables.</p>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr><td><p>Grouping</p></td>
<td><p><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.chunked">chunked</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.ichunked">ichunked</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.chunked_even">chunked_even</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.sliced">sliced</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.constrained_batches">constrained_batches</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.distribute">distribute</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.divide">divide</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.split_at">split_at</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.split_before">split_before</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.split_after">split_after</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.split_into">split_into</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.split_when">split_when</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.bucket">bucket</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.unzip">unzip</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.batched">batched</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.grouper">grouper</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.partition">partition</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.transpose">transpose</a></p></td>
</tr>
<tr><td><p>Lookahead and lookback</p></td>
<td><p><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.spy">spy</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.peekable">peekable</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.seekable">seekable</a></p></td>
</tr>
<tr><td><p>Windowing</p></td>
<td><p><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.windowed">windowed</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.substrings">substrings</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.substrings_indexes">substrings_indexes</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.stagger">stagger</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.windowed_complete">windowed_complete</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.pairwise">pairwise</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.triplewise">triplewise</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.sliding_window">sliding_window</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.subslices">subslices</a></p></td>
</tr>
<tr><td><p>Augmenting</p></td>
<td><p><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.count_cycle">count_cycle</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.intersperse">intersperse</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.padded">padded</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.repeat_each">repeat_each</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.mark_ends">mark_ends</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.repeat_last">repeat_last</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.adjacent">adjacent</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.groupby_transform">groupby_transform</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.pad_none">pad_none</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.ncycles">ncycles</a></p></td>
</tr>
<tr><td><p>Combining</p></td>
<td><p><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.collapse">collapse</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.sort_together">sort_together</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.interleave">interleave</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.interleave_longest">interleave_longest</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.interleave_evenly">interleave_evenly</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.zip_offset">zip_offset</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.zip_equal">zip_equal</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.zip_broadcast">zip_broadcast</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.dotproduct">dotproduct</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.convolve">convolve</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.flatten">flatten</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.roundrobin">roundrobin</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.prepend">prepend</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.value_chain">value_chain</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.partial_product">partial_product</a></p></td>
</tr>
<tr><td><p>Summarizing</p></td>
<td><p><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.ilen">ilen</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.unique_to_each">unique_to_each</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.sample">sample</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.consecutive_groups">consecutive_groups</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.run_length">run_length</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.map_reduce">map_reduce</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.exactly_n">exactly_n</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.is_sorted">is_sorted</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.all_equal">all_equal</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.all_unique">all_unique</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.minmax">minmax</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.first_true">first_true</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.quantify">quantify</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.iequals">iequals</a></p></td>
</tr>
<tr><td><p>Selecting</p></td>
<td><p><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.islice_extended">islice_extended</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.first">first</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.last">last</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.one">one</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.only">only</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.strictly_n">strictly_n</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.strip">strip</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.lstrip">lstrip</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.rstrip">rstrip</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.filter_except">filter_except</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.map_except">map_except</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.filter_map">filter_map</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.iter_suppress">iter_suppress</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.nth_or_last">nth_or_last</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.unique_in_window">unique_in_window</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.before_and_after">before_and_after</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.nth">nth</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.take">take</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.tail">tail</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.unique_everseen">unique_everseen</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.unique_justseen">unique_justseen</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.duplicates_everseen">duplicates_everseen</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.duplicates_justseen">duplicates_justseen</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.classify_unique">classify_unique</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.longest_common_prefix">longest_common_prefix</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.takewhile_inclusive">takewhile_inclusive</a></p></td>
</tr>
<tr><td><p>Combinatorics</p></td>
<td><p><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.distinct_permutations">distinct_permutations</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.distinct_combinations">distinct_combinations</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.circular_shifts">circular_shifts</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.partitions">partitions</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.set_partitions">set_partitions</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.product_index">product_index</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.combination_index">combination_index</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.permutation_index">permutation_index</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.combination_with_replacement_index">combination_with_replacement_index</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.gray_product">gray_product</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.outer_product">outer_product</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.powerset">powerset</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.random_product">random_product</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.random_permutation">random_permutation</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.random_combination">random_combination</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.random_combination_with_replacement">random_combination_with_replacement</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.nth_product">nth_product</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.nth_permutation">nth_permutation</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.nth_combination">nth_combination</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.nth_combination_with_replacement">nth_combination_with_replacement</a></p></td>
</tr>
<tr><td><p>Wrapping</p></td>
<td><p><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.always_iterable">always_iterable</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.always_reversible">always_reversible</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.countable">countable</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.consumer">consumer</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.with_iter">with_iter</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.iter_except">iter_except</a></p></td>
</tr>
<tr><td><p>Others</p></td>
<td><p><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.locate">locate</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.rlocate">rlocate</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.replace">replace</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.numeric_range">numeric_range</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.side_effect">side_effect</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.iterate">iterate</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.difference">difference</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.make_decorator">make_decorator</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.SequenceView">SequenceView</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.time_limited">time_limited</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.map_if">map_if</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.iter_index">iter_index</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.consume">consume</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.tabulate">tabulate</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.repeatfunc">repeatfunc</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.polynomial_from_roots">polynomial_from_roots</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.polynomial_eval">polynomial_eval</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.polynomial_derivative">polynomial_derivative</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.sieve">sieve</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.factor">factor</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.matmul">matmul</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.sum_of_squares">sum_of_squares</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.totient">totient</a>,
<a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#more_itertools.reshape">reshape</a></p></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<section id="getting-started">
<h2>Getting started<a href="#getting-started" title="Permalink to this heading"></a></h2>
<p>To get started, install the library with <a href="https://pip.pypa.io/en/stable/">pip</a>:</p>
<div><pre><span></span>pip<span> </span>install<span> </span>more-itertools
</pre></div>
<p>The recipes from the <a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/itertools.html#itertools-recipes">itertools docs</a>
are included in the top-level package:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>&gt;&gt;&gt; </span><span>from</span> <span>more_itertools</span> <span>import</span> <span>flatten</span>
<span>&gt;&gt;&gt; </span><span>iterable</span> <span>=</span> <span>[(</span><span>0</span><span>,</span> <span>1</span><span>),</span> <span>(</span><span>2</span><span>,</span> <span>3</span><span>)]</span>
<span>&gt;&gt;&gt; </span><span>list</span><span>(</span><span>flatten</span><span>(</span><span>iterable</span><span>))</span>
<span>[0, 1, 2, 3]</span>
</pre></div>
<p>Several new recipes are available as well:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>&gt;&gt;&gt; </span><span>from</span> <span>more_itertools</span> <span>import</span> <span>chunked</span>
<span>&gt;&gt;&gt; </span><span>iterable</span> <span>=</span> <span>[</span><span>0</span><span>,</span> <span>1</span><span>,</span> <span>2</span><span>,</span> <span>3</span><span>,</span> <span>4</span><span>,</span> <span>5</span><span>,</span> <span>6</span><span>,</span> <span>7</span><span>,</span> <span>8</span><span>]</span>
<span>&gt;&gt;&gt; </span><span>list</span><span>(</span><span>chunked</span><span>(</span><span>iterable</span><span>,</span> <span>3</span><span>))</span>
<span>[[0, 1, 2], [3, 4, 5], [6, 7, 8]]</span>

<span>&gt;&gt;&gt; </span><span>from</span> <span>more_itertools</span> <span>import</span> <span>spy</span>
<span>&gt;&gt;&gt; </span><span>iterable</span> <span>=</span> <span>(</span><span>x</span> <span>*</span> <span>x</span> <span>for</span> <span>x</span> <span>in</span> <span>range</span><span>(</span><span>1</span><span>,</span> <span>6</span><span>))</span>
<span>&gt;&gt;&gt; </span><span>head</span><span>,</span> <span>iterable</span> <span>=</span> <span>spy</span><span>(</span><span>iterable</span><span>,</span> <span>n</span><span>=</span><span>3</span><span>)</span>
<span>&gt;&gt;&gt; </span><span>list</span><span>(</span><span>head</span><span>)</span>
<span>[1, 4, 9]</span>
<span>&gt;&gt;&gt; </span><span>list</span><span>(</span><span>iterable</span><span>)</span>
<span>[1, 4, 9, 16, 25]</span>
</pre></div>
<p>For the full listing of functions, see the <a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html">API documentation</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="links-elsewhere">
<h2>Links elsewhere<a href="#links-elsewhere" title="Permalink to this heading"></a></h2>
<p>Blog posts about <code><span>more-itertools</span></code>:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://www.bbayles.com/index/decorator_factory">Yo, I heard you like decorators</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://martinheinz.dev/blog/16">Tour of Python Itertools</a> (<a href="https://dev.to/martinheinz/tour-of-python-itertools-4122">Alternate</a>)</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.gidware.com/real-world-more-itertools/">Real-World Python More Itertools</a></p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="development">
<h2>Development<a href="#development" title="Permalink to this heading"></a></h2>
<p><code><span>more-itertools</span></code> is maintained by <a href="https://github.com/erikrose">@erikrose</a>
and <a href="https://github.com/bbayles">@bbayles</a>, with help from <a href="https://github.com/more-itertools/more-itertools/graphs/contributors">many others</a>.
If you have a problem or suggestion, please file a bug or pull request in this
repository. Thanks for contributing!</p>
</section>
<section id="version-history">
<h2>Version History<a href="#version-history" title="Permalink to this heading"></a></h2>
<p>The version history can be found in <a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/versions.html">documentation</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="contents">
<h2>Contents<a href="#contents" title="Permalink to this heading"></a></h2>
<div>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html">API Reference</a><ul>
<li><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#grouping">Grouping</a></li>
<li><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#lookahead-and-lookback">Lookahead and lookback</a></li>
<li><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#windowing">Windowing</a></li>
<li><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#augmenting">Augmenting</a></li>
<li><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#combining">Combining</a></li>
<li><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#summarizing">Summarizing</a></li>
<li><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#selecting">Selecting</a></li>
<li><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#combinatorics">Combinatorics</a></li>
<li><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#wrapping">Wrapping</a></li>
<li><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/api.html#others">Others</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/license.html">License</a></li>
<li><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/testing.html">Testing</a></li>
<li><a href="https://more-itertools.readthedocs.io/en/stable/versions.html">Version History</a></li>
</ul>
</div>
</section>
</section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tantivy – full-text search engine library inspired by Apache Lucene (262 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy</link>
            <guid>40492834</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 17:30:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy">https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40492834">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><a href="https://docs.rs/crate/tantivy/" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/102c9fd1bd8ec7abc5df0458aed45bb3b399fdf7308e34c43c184063e8e433f6/68747470733a2f2f646f63732e72732f74616e746976792f62616467652e737667" alt="Docs" data-canonical-src="https://docs.rs/tantivy/badge.svg"></a>
<a href="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy/actions/workflows/test.yml"><img src="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy/actions/workflows/test.yml/badge.svg" alt="Build Status"></a>
<a href="https://codecov.io/gh/quickwit-oss/tantivy" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/6145ca36a601089a4326b0b791612cb11d18c19bf501732b973555b40a567baf/68747470733a2f2f636f6465636f762e696f2f67682f717569636b7769742d6f73732f74616e746976792f6272616e63682f6d61696e2f67726170682f62616467652e737667" alt="codecov" data-canonical-src="https://codecov.io/gh/quickwit-oss/tantivy/branch/main/graph/badge.svg"></a>
<a href="https://discord.gg/MT27AG5EVE" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/bd0cd277f63ca78e33ea3f4ba2d09776e1fdb2179e82357ffecf33a7b3e166df/68747470733a2f2f736869656c64732e696f2f646973636f72642f3930383238313631313834303238323632343f6c6162656c3d636861742532306f6e253230646973636f7264" alt="Join the chat at https://discord.gg/MT27AG5EVE" data-canonical-src="https://shields.io/discord/908281611840282624?label=chat%20on%20discord"></a>
<a href="https://opensource.org/licenses/MIT" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/a4426cbe5c21edb002526331c7a8fbfa089e84a550567b02a0d829a98b136ad0/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f4c6963656e73652d4d49542d79656c6c6f772e737667" alt="License: MIT" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/License-MIT-yellow.svg"></a>
<a href="https://crates.io/crates/tantivy" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/30ac9ff4efaac16e68e7784141cad32e51125d3416e6a82d7a8ebe6d5924265b/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6372617465732f762f74616e746976792e737667" alt="Crates.io" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/crates/v/tantivy.svg"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/15079bc13c67479b2800d5cdc52bc11dda6cb6990e8acd9bb06d7f9df7220975/68747470733a2f2f74616e746976792d7365617263682e6769746875622e696f2f6c6f676f2f74616e746976792d6c6f676f2e706e67"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/15079bc13c67479b2800d5cdc52bc11dda6cb6990e8acd9bb06d7f9df7220975/68747470733a2f2f74616e746976792d7365617263682e6769746875622e696f2f6c6f676f2f74616e746976792d6c6f676f2e706e67" alt="Tantivy, the fastest full-text search engine library written in Rust" height="250" data-canonical-src="https://tantivy-search.github.io/logo/tantivy-logo.png"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Fast full-text search engine library written in Rust</h2><a id="user-content-fast-full-text-search-engine-library-written-in-rust" aria-label="Permalink: Fast full-text search engine library written in Rust" href="#fast-full-text-search-engine-library-written-in-rust"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>If you are looking for an alternative to Elasticsearch or Apache Solr, check out <a href="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/quickwit">Quickwit</a>, our distributed search engine built on top of Tantivy.</strong></p>
<p dir="auto">Tantivy is closer to <a href="https://lucene.apache.org/" rel="nofollow">Apache Lucene</a> than to <a href="https://www.elastic.co/products/elasticsearch" rel="nofollow">Elasticsearch</a> or <a href="https://lucene.apache.org/solr/" rel="nofollow">Apache Solr</a> in the sense it is not
an off-the-shelf search engine server, but rather a crate that can be used to build such a search engine.</p>
<p dir="auto">Tantivy is, in fact, strongly inspired by Lucene's design.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Benchmark</h2><a id="user-content-benchmark" aria-label="Permalink: Benchmark" href="#benchmark"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The following <a href="https://tantivy-search.github.io/bench/" rel="nofollow">benchmark</a> breakdowns
performance for different types of queries/collections.</p>
<p dir="auto">Your mileage WILL vary depending on the nature of queries and their load.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy/blob/main/doc/assets/images/searchbenchmark.png"><img src="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy/raw/main/doc/assets/images/searchbenchmark.png"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Details about the benchmark can be found at this <a href="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/search-benchmark-game">repository</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Features</h2><a id="user-content-features" aria-label="Permalink: Features" href="#features"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Full-text search</li>
<li>Configurable tokenizer (stemming available for 17 Latin languages) with third party support for Chinese (<a href="https://crates.io/crates/tantivy-jieba" rel="nofollow">tantivy-jieba</a> and <a href="https://crates.io/crates/cang-jie" rel="nofollow">cang-jie</a>), Japanese (<a href="https://github.com/lindera-morphology/lindera-tantivy">lindera</a>, <a href="https://crates.io/crates/vaporetto_tantivy" rel="nofollow">Vaporetto</a>, and <a href="https://crates.io/crates/tantivy-tokenizer-tiny-segmenter" rel="nofollow">tantivy-tokenizer-tiny-segmenter</a>) and Korean (<a href="https://github.com/lindera-morphology/lindera-tantivy">lindera</a> + <a href="https://github.com/lindera-morphology/lindera-ko-dic-builder">lindera-ko-dic-builder</a>)</li>
<li>Fast (check out the 🐎 ✨ <a href="https://tantivy-search.github.io/bench/" rel="nofollow">benchmark</a> ✨ 🐎)</li>
<li>Tiny startup time (&lt;10ms), perfect for command-line tools</li>
<li>BM25 scoring (the same as Lucene)</li>
<li>Natural query language (e.g. <code>(michael AND jackson) OR "king of pop"</code>)</li>
<li>Phrase queries search (e.g. <code>"michael jackson"</code>)</li>
<li>Incremental indexing</li>
<li>Multithreaded indexing (indexing English Wikipedia takes &lt; 3 minutes on my desktop)</li>
<li>Mmap directory</li>
<li>SIMD integer compression when the platform/CPU includes the SSE2 instruction set</li>
<li>Single valued and multivalued u64, i64, and f64 fast fields (equivalent of doc values in Lucene)</li>
<li><code>&amp;[u8]</code> fast fields</li>
<li>Text, i64, u64, f64, dates, ip, bool, and hierarchical facet fields</li>
<li>Compressed document store (LZ4, Zstd, None)</li>
<li>Range queries</li>
<li>Faceted search</li>
<li>Configurable indexing (optional term frequency and position indexing)</li>
<li>JSON Field</li>
<li>Aggregation Collector: histogram, range buckets, average, and stats metrics</li>
<li>LogMergePolicy with deletes</li>
<li>Searcher Warmer API</li>
<li>Cheesy logo with a horse</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Non-features</h3><a id="user-content-non-features" aria-label="Permalink: Non-features" href="#non-features"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Distributed search is out of the scope of Tantivy, but if you are looking for this feature, check out <a href="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/quickwit/">Quickwit</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Getting started</h2><a id="user-content-getting-started" aria-label="Permalink: Getting started" href="#getting-started"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Tantivy works on stable Rust and supports Linux, macOS, and Windows.</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://tantivy-search.github.io/examples/basic_search.html" rel="nofollow">Tantivy's simple search example</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy-cli">tantivy-cli and its tutorial</a> - <code>tantivy-cli</code> is an actual command-line interface that makes it easy for you to create a search engine,
index documents, and search via the CLI or a small server with a REST API.
It walks you through getting a Wikipedia search engine up and running in a few minutes.</li>
<li><a href="https://docs.rs/tantivy/" rel="nofollow">Reference doc for the last released version</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How can I support this project?</h2><a id="user-content-how-can-i-support-this-project" aria-label="Permalink: How can I support this project?" href="#how-can-i-support-this-project"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">There are many ways to support this project.</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Use Tantivy and tell us about your experience on <a href="https://discord.gg/MT27AG5EVE" rel="nofollow">Discord</a> or by email (<a href="mailto:paul.masurel@gmail.com">paul.masurel@gmail.com</a>)</li>
<li>Report bugs</li>
<li>Write a blog post</li>
<li>Help with documentation by asking questions or submitting PRs</li>
<li>Contribute code (you can join <a href="https://discord.gg/MT27AG5EVE" rel="nofollow">our Discord server</a>)</li>
<li>Talk about Tantivy around you</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing code</h2><a id="user-content-contributing-code" aria-label="Permalink: Contributing code" href="#contributing-code"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">We use the GitHub Pull Request workflow: reference a GitHub ticket and/or include a comprehensive commit message when opening a PR.
Feel free to update CHANGELOG.md with your contribution.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Tokenizer</h3><a id="user-content-tokenizer" aria-label="Permalink: Tokenizer" href="#tokenizer"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">When implementing a tokenizer for tantivy depend on the <code>tantivy-tokenizer-api</code> crate.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Clone and build locally</h3><a id="user-content-clone-and-build-locally" aria-label="Permalink: Clone and build locally" href="#clone-and-build-locally"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Tantivy compiles on stable Rust.
To check out and run tests, you can simply run:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy.git
cd tantivy
cargo test"><pre>git clone https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy.git
<span>cd</span> tantivy
cargo <span>test</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Companies Using Tantivy</h2><a id="user-content-companies-using-tantivy" aria-label="Permalink: Companies Using Tantivy" href="#companies-using-tantivy"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy/blob/main/doc/assets/images/etsy.png"><img src="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy/raw/main/doc/assets/images/etsy.png" alt="Etsy" height="25" width="auto"></a>&nbsp;
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy/blob/main/doc/assets/images/Nuclia.png#gh-light-mode-only"><img src="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy/raw/main/doc/assets/images/Nuclia.png#gh-light-mode-only" alt="Nuclia" height="25" width="auto"></a> &nbsp;
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy/blob/main/doc/assets/images/humanfirst.png#gh-light-mode-only"><img src="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy/raw/main/doc/assets/images/humanfirst.png#gh-light-mode-only" alt="Humanfirst.ai" height="30" width="auto"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy/blob/main/doc/assets/images/element.io.svg#gh-light-mode-only"><img src="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy/raw/main/doc/assets/images/element.io.svg#gh-light-mode-only" alt="Element.io" height="25" width="auto"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy/blob/main/doc/assets/images/nuclia-dark-theme.png#gh-dark-mode-only"><img src="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy/raw/main/doc/assets/images/nuclia-dark-theme.png#gh-dark-mode-only" alt="Nuclia" height="35" width="auto"></a> &nbsp;
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy/blob/main/doc/assets/images/humanfirst.ai-dark-theme.png#gh-dark-mode-only"><img src="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy/raw/main/doc/assets/images/humanfirst.ai-dark-theme.png#gh-dark-mode-only" alt="Humanfirst.ai" height="25" width="auto"></a>&nbsp; &nbsp;
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy/blob/main/doc/assets/images/element-dark-theme.png#gh-dark-mode-only"><img src="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy/raw/main/doc/assets/images/element-dark-theme.png#gh-dark-mode-only" alt="Element.io" height="25" width="auto"></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">FAQ</h2><a id="user-content-faq" aria-label="Permalink: FAQ" href="#faq"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Can I use Tantivy in other languages?</h3><a id="user-content-can-i-use-tantivy-in-other-languages" aria-label="Permalink: Can I use Tantivy in other languages?" href="#can-i-use-tantivy-in-other-languages"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Python → <a href="https://github.com/quickwit-oss/tantivy-py">tantivy-py</a></li>
<li>Ruby → <a href="https://github.com/baygeldin/tantiny">tantiny</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">You can also find other bindings on <a href="https://github.com/search?q=tantivy">GitHub</a> but they may be less maintained.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What are some examples of Tantivy use?</h3><a id="user-content-what-are-some-examples-of-tantivy-use" aria-label="Permalink: What are some examples of Tantivy use?" href="#what-are-some-examples-of-tantivy-use"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/matrix-org/seshat/">seshat</a>: A matrix message database/indexer</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/baygeldin/tantiny">tantiny</a>: Tiny full-text search for Ruby</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/lnx-search/lnx">lnx</a>: adaptable, typo tolerant search engine with a REST API</li>
<li>and <a href="https://github.com/search?q=tantivy">more</a>!</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">On average, how much faster is Tantivy compared to Lucene?</h3><a id="user-content-on-average-how-much-faster-is-tantivy-compared-to-lucene" aria-label="Permalink: On average, how much faster is Tantivy compared to Lucene?" href="#on-average-how-much-faster-is-tantivy-compared-to-lucene"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>According to our <a href="https://tantivy-search.github.io/bench/" rel="nofollow">search latency benchmark</a>, Tantivy is approximately 2x faster than Lucene.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Does tantivy support incremental indexing?</h3><a id="user-content-does-tantivy-support-incremental-indexing" aria-label="Permalink: Does tantivy support incremental indexing?" href="#does-tantivy-support-incremental-indexing"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Yes.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How can I edit documents?</h3><a id="user-content-how-can-i-edit-documents" aria-label="Permalink: How can I edit documents?" href="#how-can-i-edit-documents"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Data in tantivy is immutable. To edit a document, the document needs to be deleted and reindexed.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">When will my documents be searchable during indexing?</h3><a id="user-content-when-will-my-documents-be-searchable-during-indexing" aria-label="Permalink: When will my documents be searchable during indexing?" href="#when-will-my-documents-be-searchable-during-indexing"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Documents will be searchable after a <code>commit</code> is called on an <code>IndexWriter</code>. Existing <code>IndexReader</code>s will also need to be reloaded in order to reflect the changes. Finally, changes are only visible to newly acquired <code>Searcher</code>.</li>
</ul>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Controlling the Taylor Swift Eras Tour wristbands with Flipper Zero (692 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.jgc.org/2024/05/controlling-taylor-swift-eras-tour.html</link>
            <guid>40492515</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 16:55:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.jgc.org/2024/05/controlling-taylor-swift-eras-tour.html">https://blog.jgc.org/2024/05/controlling-taylor-swift-eras-tour.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40492515">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post-body-4308511000929231325" itemprop="description articleBody">
<p>Many large concerts feature wristbands that light up on command. They are used to produce varied visual effects across a stadium. One company that makes these is <a href="https://pixmob.com/">PixMob</a>. Their controllable, illuminated wristbands are currently being used as part of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Eras_Tour">Taylor Swift's Eras Tour</a>. A short Wired article <a href="https://wired.me/technology/the-tech-behind-taylor-swift-concert-wristbands/">here</a> gives some details and here's a video from the Wall Street Journal:</p><p><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/GCsmZA08oD8?si=e3755KHJFdna_zBV" title="YouTube video player" width="560"></iframe></p><p>For the Eras Tour the company's X2 product is being used. It looks like this:</p><p><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiQg9Q19zegc3hBuX2vNtiBNssn2XKYwLKBcAw1y34T1bEwMY3ITvksGMnVa4Ifzt_yaCsWHZf8AJjHRMoiodRsSMp8nKfm13E-oldA1RQ9UEqRxJkF98UzunZfGwo49Nwp7xjCMGl56Prugv67T6tXT9msEmRpl2FDuvLMXef31xgDZij7j-5sdg/s3731/eras-1.jpg"><img data-original-height="1340" data-original-width="3731" height="230" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiQg9Q19zegc3hBuX2vNtiBNssn2XKYwLKBcAw1y34T1bEwMY3ITvksGMnVa4Ifzt_yaCsWHZf8AJjHRMoiodRsSMp8nKfm13E-oldA1RQ9UEqRxJkF98UzunZfGwo49Nwp7xjCMGl56Prugv67T6tXT9msEmRpl2FDuvLMXef31xgDZij7j-5sdg/w640-h230/eras-1.jpg" width="640"></a></p><p>Since these wristbands are designed for reuse they are easily opened revealing two batteries and a lovely little circuit board:</p><p><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjQsQ3X_JVN4fln9WOBbyohyphenhyphenrSuV8jFu_Cm-oYlf9pa7o5_2pv4AEzpDbRNTPGZcfA4bDvzVM_4qpvNB-jZRUuawJo28u9fjCIFNDXEh8SkR5TYxMGBi3B9qNBfNOf6ihbqAn23fhXdwywkCpLqO1nNZ6IroifiZtGkviBfCfKDQtivvgyy07zg-g/s2823/eras-2.jpg"><img data-original-height="2234" data-original-width="2823" height="506" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjQsQ3X_JVN4fln9WOBbyohyphenhyphenrSuV8jFu_Cm-oYlf9pa7o5_2pv4AEzpDbRNTPGZcfA4bDvzVM_4qpvNB-jZRUuawJo28u9fjCIFNDXEh8SkR5TYxMGBi3B9qNBfNOf6ihbqAn23fhXdwywkCpLqO1nNZ6IroifiZtGkviBfCfKDQtivvgyy07zg-g/w640-h506/eras-2.jpg" width="640"></a></p><p>Here's that circuit board:</p><p><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgu9JtblHe06nqdgEHaGGxg7jAha5zSxrJnkZYcUoCdAz3jHfeZ07_9waLR0RW8SvvyjkHfDqz_ak_M0bIZCrE0v-08Q5raviX844Mgm_bZf9gpQROLKtlUwuatt0_2ErTXD6HEAsR-vCm8HmYFADwmYYJo490ez5xksNqmlm8v63vBefTl6PQqCg/s3483/eras-3.jpg"><img data-original-height="1996" data-original-width="3483" height="366" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgu9JtblHe06nqdgEHaGGxg7jAha5zSxrJnkZYcUoCdAz3jHfeZ07_9waLR0RW8SvvyjkHfDqz_ak_M0bIZCrE0v-08Q5raviX844Mgm_bZf9gpQROLKtlUwuatt0_2ErTXD6HEAsR-vCm8HmYFADwmYYJo490ez5xksNqmlm8v63vBefTl6PQqCg/w640-h366/eras-3.jpg" width="640"></a></p><p>On that board are two RGB LEDs, a little microcontroller, a little bit of EEPROM and an infrared diode to receive a signal. So, simply put, PixMob works by installed a really big (and moveable) IR remote control (you can read about this on their website <a href="https://pixmob.com/our-effects">here</a>) and transmitting commands to the bracelets to produce colours, fades, flashes, etc. Cute.</p><p>There are a bunch of hardware details <a href="https://yeokhengmeng.com/2019/08/teardown-of-ndp2019-led-wristband/">here</a>.</p><p>Since they are projecting infrared with moveable projector they can sweep effects around the stadium, and cover the projector with cut outs to make things like hearts. It's simple technology that works very nicely. And, of course, there's a reverse engineering community built up around this.</p><p>The best place to start learning about that is <a href="https://github.com/danielweidman/pixmob-ir-reverse-engineering">this</a> GitHub repository. It brings together a bunch of reverse engineering efforts that have looked into the IR protocol. These have been somewhat successful and, since the <a href="https://flipperzero.one/">Flipper Zero</a> has IR capability, there's a <a href="https://github.com/danielweidman/flipper-pixmob-ir-codes">project</a> that makes it control the wristband.</p><p>Here's a short video of me making the wristbands fade orange.</p><p>Such nice simple technology that produces very cool effects.</p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[British Museum gems for sale on eBay – how a theft was exposed (128 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/articles/cpegg27g74do</link>
            <guid>40492393</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 16:41:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/articles/cpegg27g74do">https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/articles/cpegg27g74do</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40492393">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><header data-component="topper-block"><div><figure><p><span><picture><source srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/400/cpsprodpb/887d/live/a6374660-19da-11ef-a13a-0b8c563da930.png.webp 400w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/640/cpsprodpb/887d/live/a6374660-19da-11ef-a13a-0b8c563da930.png.webp 640w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/960/cpsprodpb/887d/live/a6374660-19da-11ef-a13a-0b8c563da930.png.webp 960w" sizes="(min-width: 900px) 50vw, 100vw"><img alt="Gem composite image with British Museum ceiling montage" loading="eager" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/1056/cpsprodpb/887d/live/a6374660-19da-11ef-a13a-0b8c563da930.png" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/400/cpsprodpb/887d/live/a6374660-19da-11ef-a13a-0b8c563da930.png 400w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/640/cpsprodpb/887d/live/a6374660-19da-11ef-a13a-0b8c563da930.png 640w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/960/cpsprodpb/887d/live/a6374660-19da-11ef-a13a-0b8c563da930.png 960w" sizes="(min-width: 900px) 50vw, 100vw" width="1056" height="1056"></picture></span></p></figure></div></header><div data-component="text-block" width="wide"><p><b>In 2020, Danish antiquities dealer Dr Ittai Gradel began to suspect an eBay seller he had been buying from was a thief who was stealing from the British Museum.</b></p><p>More than two years later, the museum would announce that thousands of objects were missing, stolen or damaged from its collection. It had finally believed Dr Gradel - but why had it taken so long for it to do so?</p></div><div width="wide"><p data-component="subheadline-block"><h2 id="The-first-clue" tabindex="-1"><span role="text">The first clue</span></h2></p></div><div data-component="text-block" width="wide"><p>“The gems that fascinate me are nothing so boring as diamonds,” says Dr Gradel from his attic study, lined with display cabinets of treasures.</p><p>He collects ancient gemstones carved with intricate figures or motifs - they help paint a picture of what life was like in the classical world and were often used as jewellery.</p><p>It is a niche passion. The circle of dealers is small - so the internet has become a vital trading tool and eBay in particular a rich source of bargains.</p><p>Millions of miscellaneous items are posted for sale each day, but on 7 August 2016, something unusual happened.</p></div><div data-component="image-block" width="wide"><figure><figcaption><span>Image caption, </span><p>Dr Ittai Gradel collects ancient gemstones</p></figcaption></figure></div><div data-component="text-block" width="wide"><p>A grey and white piece of a cameo gemstone featuring Priapus - the Greek god of fertility - was posted by a user called "sultan1966" for just £40.</p><p>The listing was taken down after a few hours, unsold.</p><p>Priapus is one of the more memorable gods - often depicted with his oversized genitals on show. The seller may have hoped Priapus' brief appearance online had gone unnoticed - but alas not.</p><p>It was spotted by Dr Gradel, who says he was born with a photographic memory.</p><p>He says the unusual skill has helped him identify rare finds. In this case, it would also help him uncover the identity of a suspected thief.</p><p>Dr Gradel had been buying gemstones from sultan1966 on eBay for almost two years. The seller had told him his name was Paul Higgins and that he had inherited the gems from a grandfather. They were being sold at bargain prices but Dr Gradel could tell many were very valuable.</p><p>This time, he knew he had seen the Priapus cameo before. He was sure it featured in an old gems catalogue he owned from one of the world’s most famous institutions, the British Museum.</p><p>“There was no doubt it was the same object and I was confused,” he says.</p></div><div data-component="image-block" width="wide"><figure><figcaption><span>Image caption, </span><p>The Priapus cameo listed on eBay matched a picture in the Walters 1926 catalogue and an image on the British Museum website</p></figcaption></figure></div><div data-component="text-block" width="wide"><p>The museum has since said in documents filed at the High Court that it believes the cameo had been taken from a storeroom in the Greece and Rome department by a senior curator, Dr Peter Higgs, just a week before it appeared for sale.</p><p>Dr Higgs started working at the British Museum in 1993 as a research assistant, having studied archaeology at the University of Liverpool.</p><p>Living in an ordinary semi-detached house in Hastings on the south coast, he was later described by the museum’s chairman as a “rather quiet, introverted” person.</p></div><div data-component="image-block" width="wide"><figure><figcaption><span>Image caption, </span><p>Dr Peter Higgs started working at the museum in 1993</p></figcaption></figure></div><div data-component="text-block" width="wide"><p>Within hours of removing the eBay listing in 2016, the museum believes Dr Higgs logged into its database and attempted to tamper with the Priapus cameo's catalogue entry.</p><p>An estimated 2.4 million items at the museum are uncatalogued, or partially uncatalogued, out of its total collection of 8 million. The museum, which has now brought a civil court case against Dr Higgs, believes he was mostly targeting these uncatalogued artefacts - and that, this time, he had made a mistake.</p><p>Dr Higgs would have been able to see the cameo was a catalogued item, searchable by the public and staff alike. It was even on the museum’s website - it was not the kind of item that could disappear and not be missed.</p><p>If his tampering had been successful, says the museum in its court papers, it would have hidden the database photo of the cameo from view - but it says he failed.</p><p>The next day, Dr Higgs is known to have returned alone to the storeroom where the cameo was kept, the museum says. It believes this was so he could return it.</p></div><div data-component="text-block" width="wide"><p>Thief at the British Museum is available on <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/sounds/play/p0hz3hz1#xtor=CS8-1000-%5BEditorialPromo_Box%5D-%5BNewsEditorial_Promo%5D-%5BNewsEditorial_Promo%5D-%5BPS_SOUNDS~N~p0hz3hz1~P_BritishMuseumIntro%5D">BBC Sounds</a> or you can hear it on Radio 4, weekdays at 13:45, between 27 May and 6 June.</p><p>You can watch a documentary of the same name on <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/iplayer/episode/m001zrbs#xtor=CS8-1000-%5BEditorialPromo_Box%5D-%5BNewsEditorial_Promo%5D-%5BNewsEditorial_Promo%5D-%5BPS_IPLAYER~N~m001zrbs~P_BritishMuseum%5D">BBC iPlayer</a> or on BBC Two at 19:00 on 27 May.</p></div><div data-component="text-block" width="wide"><p>However, something valuable remained missing - the cameo's gold mount. The museum believes it was removed by Dr Higgs and sold to a scrap dealer.</p><p>The cameo’s value is estimated at £15,000. It would be worth double that, says the museum, if it still had its gold mount.</p><p>Dr Gradel says it is “totally bizarre” that he could sit at a computer on a small Danish island and be the first person to discover something was awry at the British Museum.</p><p>He wrote to sultan1966, the man he knew as Paul Higgins, asking why the Priapus cameo had been withdrawn. The seller replied saying it had been a mistake - it belonged to his sister, who didn't want him to sell it.</p><p>Dr Gradel chose not to alert sultan1966 about his suspicions. “That would enable him to cover his tracks,” he said.</p><p>Instead he decided to keep an eye on him - to see if any other pieces belonging to the museum appeared.</p><p>Four years would pass before the next clue - when Dr Gradel would make the shocking discovery that it appeared to be an inside job.</p></div><div width="wide"><p data-component="subheadline-block"><h2 id="The-second-clue" tabindex="-1"><span role="text">The second clue</span></h2></p></div><div data-component="text-block" width="wide"><p>In May 2020, Dr Gradel noticed an image in a newly published book on gemstones.</p><p>Figure 736 was a gem featuring a man who resembled the Roman Emperor Augustus. It was labelled as belonging to the British Museum.</p><p>The figure portrayed on the gem had an usual hairstyle for the period.</p><p>Suspicious once again, Dr Gradel looked through his records. </p><p>He matched the image in the book to a photograph on his computer hard drive of an olive-green gem fragment that he had previously been offered for sale by a British dealer called Malcolm Hay.</p><p>Dr Gradel told him about his suspicions around the gem right away.</p></div><div data-component="image-block" width="wide"><figure><figcaption><span>Image caption, </span><p>Photos of gem casts resembled the gem fragment. The production process would have reversed the cast imprint - hence the face on the gem looks to the left</p></figcaption></figure></div><div data-component="text-block" width="wide"><p>But when Malcolm Hay wrote to the museum to make enquiries about the startling similarity, he was told it was closed because of the Covid lockdown.</p><p>“[Deputy Director] Jonathan Williams replied to me, and he said, of course, there's no way of confirming anything at the moment because no-one could get into the museum,” Mr Hay said. “He asked me to hold it.”</p><p>Luckily, the person who had first sold it to Mr Hay happened to be a mutual friend of Dr Gradel’s - a gallery-owner in Bath called Rolf von Kiaer. Dr Gradel got in touch with him immediately.</p><p>Rolf replied that he had bought the olive-green gem on eBay a few years before.</p><p>The name of the seller? Sultan1966.</p><p>At this point, Dr Gradel feared something was very wrong. He began to comb through computer files and paper records of everything he had bought from sultan1966.</p><p>He meticulously went through eBay listings, correspondences and transaction receipts, dating back to his very first purchase from sultan1966 in 2014.</p><p>An online receipt provided a crucial clue - apparently revealing the seller's real name. It was listed as Peter Higgs rather than Paul Higgins.</p><p>“A PayPal receipt has to be attached to a real bank account,” Dr Gradel explains. “So this had to be his real name.”</p></div><div data-component="text-block" width="wide"><p>He immediately called Rolf von Kiaer once again.</p><p>“[Rolf] then said to me, ‘Ittai, you do realise that is the name of a curator in the British Museum Greece and Rome department, don't you?’ And I remember that distinctly, my hair stood on end, I was absolutely shocked by this.”</p><p>Over the coming days, Dr Gradel continued to unearth new connections between the online seller and Peter Higgs.</p><p>He discovered that “sultan1966” was also Dr Higgs’s account name on Twitter - now known as X - and that 1966 was the year he was born.</p><p>“The email address on the PayPal account was Bodrum1966,” said Dr Gradel. “His specialty was actually working on sculpture from ancient Halicarnassus in modern day Turkey. And the modern name of that place is Bodrum.”</p><p>Finally, Dr Gradel found an eBay receipt for a gem he had bought from sultan1966 that gave a full private address. Dr Gradel decided to check it against property records - and the name given was Peter Higgs, the British Museum curator.</p><p>Everything suddenly made sense to the Danish collector with the photographic memory.</p><p>“There was no other possible conclusion to draw from this. It was what it seemed to be - that the British Museum curator was pilfering his own museum,” says Dr Gradel.</p><p>Dr Higgs has since denied all the allegations and is defending the civil claim the British Museum is bringing against him.</p></div><div width="wide"><p data-component="subheadline-block"><h2 id="Someone-could-be-framing-him" tabindex="-1"><span role="text">'Someone could be framing him'</span></h2></p></div><div data-component="text-block" width="wide"><p>While Dr Gradel was combing through his receipts, Peter Higgs’ career seemed to be going from strength to strength.</p><p>In January 2021, he was promoted to acting head of the Department of Greece and Rome, having built a reputation for helping track down stolen antiquities around the globe.</p><p>He had been described by the UK government as “a world-renowned curator” in 2015 after helping to return a stolen 2,000-year-old statue to Libya. Dr Higgs later appeared on BBC’s Crimewatch to describe his work.</p><p>When Dr Gradel emailed the museum’s management in February 2021 with his concerns about Dr Higgs, he got a return acknowledgement from deputy director Jonathan Williams but that was all.</p><p>Dr Gradel was unaware the management had already heard about the allegations against Dr Higgs just a day earlier, accompanied by a warning he might be being framed.  Dr Higgs had been tipped off by another archaeologist - Dorothy Lobel King, after Dr Gradel had approached her on social media for advice.</p><p>Ms Lobel King had become concerned Dr Higgs was being set up. She had emailed him, and he had forwarded the email on to Dr Williams the deputy director - the court documents now say.</p><p>The museum did investigate Dr Gradel’s concerns - but as it did so, Dr Higgs was allowed to keep running his department. He tried to throw colleagues off his scent, the museum says, by altering computer records and implying that items had gone missing decades earlier.</p></div><div data-component="image-block" width="wide"><figure><figcaption><span>Image caption, </span><p>The museum believes Dr Higgs covered his tracks by writing a note and making it appear as though it had been written in 1963</p></figcaption></figure></div><div data-component="text-block" width="wide"><p>The day after Dr Gradel emailed his allegations, according to the museum’s court documents, it believes Dr Higgs made a report falsely claiming that the olive-green gem, which had been bought by Malcolm Hay, had actually been lost decades ago.</p><p>The museum also believes Dr Higgs marked the item as lost in its catalogue entry by inserting a note made to look like it had been written in 1963.</p><p>The British Museum chairman, George Osborne, says the museum’s court evidence suggested the thief had gone to “pretty elaborate lengths” to cover his tracks.</p><p>In May 2021, Malcolm Hay was invited to a meeting to hand back his gem. He said the museum was not really interested in where he had got it: “They were just happy to have it back.”</p><p>Meanwhile, Dr Gradel was growing increasingly anxious that he hadn’t heard anything back about his allegations, despite asking for an update several times. </p><p>Finally, in July 2021, he received a reply from deputy director Dr Williams saying the museum had carried out a “thorough investigation”. All objects had been accounted for, he was told, and there was no suggestion of wrongdoing by staff.</p><p>Dr Gradel says this was “bizarre to say the least - totally absurd”.</p><p>He knew Mr Hay’s gem had gone missing, been bought online and was only in the collection after being handed back. When Dr Gradel tried to find out more, the museum told him details were confidential.</p></div><div width="wide"><p data-component="subheadline-block"><h2 id="Gouging-marks-left-by-pliers" tabindex="-1"><span role="text">Gouging marks left by pliers</span></h2></p></div><div data-component="text-block" width="wide"><p>Inside the museum however, that was not the end of it.</p><p>In December 2021, a routine spot-check revealed items were missing in the Greece and Rome department and a top-secret second investigation was launched. The following April, a curator was hired to check every single item - although under the supervision of department head, Peter Higgs.</p><p>Nevertheless, it was becoming clear that something was very wrong.</p><p>The museum says the hired curator discovered that more than 300 registered items, many with gold mounts, had been damaged or stolen. Some of those remaining had deep gouging and scratches, which looked like marks left by pliers.</p><p>When the curator went on to look at the unregistered items contained in one particular storeroom, court documents claim she discovered that 1,161 items were missing - more than three-quarters of its entire contents.</p><p>The curator handed over preliminary reports to her boss, Dr Higgs, in late December 2022 and the museum’s court documents claim Peter Higgs tried to delay escalating the findings several times.</p><p>At first, he said it wouldn’t be good to announce the news before a weekend or Christmas, the documents claim - then, they continue, he said it was his birthday and he didn’t want to deal with the matter.</p><p>But, according to the museum, the curator insisted and her findings quickly made their way to the top.</p><p>The museum’s director at the time, Hartwig Fisher, shared the information with chairman George Osborne.</p><p>Two months before, Dr Gradel had managed to reach Mr Osborne to tell him about his suspicions. Mr Osborne told us he had been assured at the time, that they had already been investigated.</p><p>This fresh information, however, seemed too much of a coincidence.</p></div><div data-component="image-block" width="wide"><figure><figcaption><span>Image caption, </span><p>George Osborne says it was “pretty traumatic” for museum investigators as the scale of the thefts emerged</p></figcaption></figure></div><div data-component="text-block" width="wide"><p>“I immediately said: ‘Well, hold on, that must be linked to that email that I saw a couple of months ago,’” Mr Osborne told the BBC.</p><p>They decided to call the police immediately and Dr Higgs was suspended.</p><p>“It took us some time as an institution to accept the betrayal of trust that these thefts represented,” Dr Fischer later told the BBC. “Betrayal by an insider has been a hard lesson to learn, and hard to prepare for”. </p><p>He later resigned from his position early over the response to Dr Gradel’s allegations.</p><p>“I think it was pretty traumatic for the people who were investigating this, particularly as the scale of the thefts emerged,” said Mr Osborne.</p><p>Both Dr Higgs’ workspace and home were raided by the Metropolitan Police over the subsequent months.</p><p>According to the museum’s High Court documents, police found handwritten notes and printed instructions on editing museum records at his work, while at home they seized items believed to have come from the museum's collections.</p><p>“I'm 100% certain we've got our man, we know who has stolen these items,” says Mr Osborne, “missing coins were found in his house”.</p><p>Dr Higgs has denied the coins came from the museum, stating they belonged to a dead relative.</p><p>He was finally dismissed from the museum in July 2023 - more than two years after Dr Gradel first raised the alarm.</p><p>Mr Osborne told the BBC the Danish antiques dealer had done the museum a great service, and he was sorry he had not been listened to initially.</p><p>“I hope he can look at the changes… and see that some good has come out of what has been a very sad and unfortunate series of events,” said Mr Osborne.</p><p>These include a commitment to catalogue every single item in the collections and tighten security processes, ensuring no member of staff can enter a storeroom alone.</p></div><div data-component="image-block" width="wide"><figure><figcaption><span>Image caption, </span><p>A drawer of artefacts Dr Ittai Gradel says are from the British Museum, at his home in Denmark</p></figcaption></figure></div><div data-component="text-block" width="wide"><p>Police say the investigation is ongoing and nobody has been arrested or charged with any offence.</p><p>As for Dr Gradel, he has handed back more than 360 gemstones he believes belong to the museum, including some he had sold to other dealers and tracked down to return.</p><p>“I encourage everybody who has come by these gems to do what I've done and just hand the gems back to the museum,” he said.</p><p>The British Museum’s lack of cataloguing means Dr Gradel has had to donate items that were in his possession, while the museum tries to prove ownership. </p><p>It is considering how to reimburse buyers who unwittingly bought items online and which it believes are from its collections.</p><p>Buyers like Ittai Gradel, who says he is still working out how much money he has lost paying for gems which shouldn't have been up for sale in the first place.</p><p>“I don't think there's much more I can do to assist the museum in retrieving gems,” he says. “It's like a sort of a closure.”</p></div><div data-component="text-block" width="wide"><p>Thief at the British Museum is available on <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/sounds/play/p0hz3hz1#xtor=CS8-1000-%5BEditorialPromo_Box%5D-%5BNewsEditorial_Promo%5D-%5BNewsEditorial_Promo%5D-%5BPS_SOUNDS~N~p0hz3hz1~P_BritishMuseumIntro%5D">BBC Sounds</a> or you can hear it on Radio 4, weekdays at 13:45, between 27 May and 6 June.</p><p>You can watch a documentary of the same name on <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/iplayer/episode/m001zrbs#xtor=CS8-1000-%5BEditorialPromo_Box%5D-%5BNewsEditorial_Promo%5D-%5BNewsEditorial_Promo%5D-%5BPS_IPLAYER~N~m001zrbs~P_BritishMuseum%5D">BBC iPlayer</a> or on BBC Two at 19:00 on 27 May.</p></div><div data-component="embed-ugc-uploader-block" id="uploader-33-u175515924" width="wide"><h2>Get in touch</h2><div><p>Do you have information about the British Museum thefts?</p></div></div><div data-component="topic-list" width="wide"><ul role="list" spacing="2"><li><a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/topics/cywd23g0wydt">George Osborne</a></li><li><a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/topics/cz5jl0zr0gmt">British Museum</a></li></ul></div></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Helix-gpui: A simple GUI for the Helix editor (138 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/polachok/helix-gpui</link>
            <guid>40492300</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 16:32:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/polachok/helix-gpui">https://github.com/polachok/helix-gpui</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40492300">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          <nav aria-label="Global">
            <ul>
                <li>
      
      <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Actions&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Actions;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/actions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Actions</p><p>
        Automate any workflow
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Packages&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Packages;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/packages">
      
      <div>
        <p>Packages</p><p>
        Host and manage packages
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Security&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Security;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/security">
      
      <div>
        <p>Security</p><p>
        Find and fix vulnerabilities
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Codespaces&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Codespaces;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/codespaces">
      
      <div>
        <p>Codespaces</p><p>
        Instant dev environments
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Copilot&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Copilot;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/copilot">
      
      <div>
        <p>Copilot</p><p>
        Write better code with AI
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Code review&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Code review;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/code-review">
      
      <div>
        <p>Code review</p><p>
        Manage code changes
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Issues&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Issues;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/issues">
      
      <div>
        <p>Issues</p><p>
        Plan and track work
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Discussions&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Discussions;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/discussions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Discussions</p><p>
        Collaborate outside of code
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
</li>


                <li>
      
      
</li>


                <li>
      
      <div>
          <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Open Source&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to GitHub Sponsors&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:GitHub Sponsors;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/sponsors">
      
      <div>
        <p>GitHub Sponsors</p><p>
        Fund open source developers
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
          <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Open Source&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to The ReadME Project&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:The ReadME Project;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/readme">
      
      <div>
        <p>The ReadME Project</p><p>
        GitHub community articles
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
          
      </div>
</li>


                <li>
    <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header menu top item (logged out)&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Pricing&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Pricing;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/pricing">Pricing</a>
</li>

            </ul>
          </nav>

        <div>
                


<qbsearch-input data-scope="repo:polachok/helix-gpui" data-custom-scopes-path="/search/custom_scopes" data-delete-custom-scopes-csrf="HY6k6C8eDeEJveScuwxtQmm9pulJ5tgW_0AHmlC24uF3auj-W97cha9yINZLSsOmGjmkJrIJaC-6AjuOpQy66g" data-max-custom-scopes="10" data-header-redesign-enabled="false" data-initial-value="" data-blackbird-suggestions-path="/search/suggestions" data-jump-to-suggestions-path="/_graphql/GetSuggestedNavigationDestinations" data-current-repository="polachok/helix-gpui" data-current-org="" data-current-owner="polachok" data-logged-in="false" data-copilot-chat-enabled="false" data-blackbird-indexed-repo-csrf="<esi:include src=&quot;/_esi/rails_csrf_token_form_hidden?r=CirrynkaB%2FTQJzLfgqaQHo3dcQkygM9Oy1%2BqfHJCy7Ja%2FXsdhqCVztgi7724G2mFjzVFJ5uUllfirBUcCdevhp4x0exZTcyeuwhjlfRQgMoBmUvxHYirknLhpC1LA93tY15S5ZYTFatd0nLIf%2FQ%2F1060KotoCairzm1ZgNja0%2FMwvc%2FaGxA8a%2Ff3RZSEThzjrBzfowfrzNnAQLJ1W%2B1wsN0SIvOGWtmHpllpMSvmlqgIR3Qyu2EWN2Z%2BUtc9QKSzPQQKODZ%2Brp5rgufp1Zu3pO0UskOFWgVIkafnbZb8J%2Fo%2FhCd3GeaStToqkBk8xm30MMxG6azH6iI93ZCK7YJPU%2FuJiWw2DSS2rqW8y2GrKMhOwkxztGaQUuTgfNISOa%2F%2BeGThrrzB5IJXFNfX59wkhKmX%2BOGa0PIy8HfBR3DMNuK8LMroeG54jPR68NRGOjobbeUBFM8phQhydHjm%2FvTDNwIYehSSWuPh5OgQ2PAw0EBwIm3dHyP9xyfrD1I7bVSv4cf1V9pKRTek4bSykArPDleT--TfjyJmXWbXmGIBzd--vHCY3q5qeZeyhYYPz3W1Yw%3D%3D&quot; />">
  <div data-modal-dialog-overlay="" data-action="click:qbsearch-input#searchInputContainerClicked">
  <modal-dialog data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleClose" data-target="qbsearch-input.searchSuggestionsDialog" role="dialog" id="search-suggestions-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="search-suggestions-dialog-header" data-view-component="true">
      <h2 id="search-suggestions-dialog-header">Search code, repositories, users, issues, pull requests...</h2>
    
</modal-dialog></div>
  
  <div>
    
<dialog-helper>
  <dialog data-target="qbsearch-input.feedbackDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" id="feedback-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="feedback-dialog-title" aria-describedby="feedback-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="feedback-dialog-title">
        Provide feedback
      </h2>
        
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="feedback-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</dialog></dialog-helper>

    <custom-scopes data-target="qbsearch-input.customScopesManager">
    
<dialog-helper>
  <dialog data-target="custom-scopes.customScopesModalDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" id="custom-scopes-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="custom-scopes-dialog-title" aria-describedby="custom-scopes-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        Saved searches
      </h2>
        <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-description">Use saved searches to filter your results more quickly</h2>
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</dialog></dialog-helper>
    </custom-scopes>
  </div>
</qbsearch-input>

            <p><a href="https://github.com/signup?ref_cta=Sign+up&amp;ref_loc=header+logged+out&amp;ref_page=%2F%3Cuser-name%3E%2F%3Crepo-name%3E&amp;source=header-repo&amp;source_repo=polachok%2Fhelix-gpui" data-hydro-click="{&quot;event_type&quot;:&quot;authentication.click&quot;,&quot;payload&quot;:{&quot;location_in_page&quot;:&quot;site header menu&quot;,&quot;repository_id&quot;:null,&quot;auth_type&quot;:&quot;SIGN_UP&quot;,&quot;originating_url&quot;:&quot;https://github.com/polachok/helix-gpui&quot;,&quot;user_id&quot;:null}}" data-hydro-click-hmac="797f1deae7c937739b7a8a81042bab50aed6b503e509ab0b188dc5906427de21" data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Sign up&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to sign up for account&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_page:/<user-name>/<repo-name>;ref_cta:Sign up;ref_loc:header logged out&quot;}">
              Sign up
            </a>
        </p></div>
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Internet Archive is under a DDoS attack (368 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://bsky.app/profile/archive.org/post/3ktiatctiqm2r</link>
            <guid>40492264</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 16:28:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/archive.org/post/3ktiatctiqm2r">https://bsky.app/profile/archive.org/post/3ktiatctiqm2r</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40492264">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Surveilling the masses with wi-fi-based positioning systems (257 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14975</link>
            <guid>40492234</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 16:25:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14975">https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14975</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40492234">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content-inner">
    
    
                
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.14975">View PDF</a>
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/html/2405.14975v1">HTML (experimental)</a></p><blockquote>
            <span>Abstract:</span>Wi-Fi-based Positioning Systems (WPSes) are used by modern mobile devices to learn their position using nearby Wi-Fi access points as landmarks. In this work, we show that Apple's WPS can be abused to create a privacy threat on a global scale. We present an attack that allows an unprivileged attacker to amass a worldwide snapshot of Wi-Fi BSSID geolocations in only a matter of days. Our attack makes few assumptions, merely exploiting the fact that there are relatively few dense regions of allocated MAC address space. Applying this technique over the course of a year, we learned the precise locations of over 2 billion BSSIDs around the world.
<br>The privacy implications of such massive datasets become more stark when taken longitudinally, allowing the attacker to track devices' movements. While most Wi-Fi access points do not move for long periods of time, many devices -- like compact travel routers -- are specifically designed to be mobile. We present several case studies that demonstrate the types of attacks on privacy that Apple's WPS enables: We track devices moving in and out of war zones (specifically Ukraine and Gaza), the effects of natural disasters (specifically the fires in Maui), and the possibility of targeted individual tracking by proxy -- all by remotely geolocating wireless access points. We provide recommendations to WPS operators and Wi-Fi access point manufacturers to enhance the privacy of hundreds of millions of users worldwide. Finally, we detail our efforts at responsibly disclosing this privacy vulnerability, and outline some mitigations that Apple and Wi-Fi access point manufacturers have implemented both independently and as a result of our work.
    </blockquote>

    <!--CONTEXT-->
    
  </div><div>
      <h2>Submission history</h2><p> From: Erik Rye [<a href="https://arxiv.org/show-email/70fb0214/2405.14975">view email</a>]      <br>    <strong>[v1]</strong>
        Thu, 23 May 2024 18:22:12 UTC (3,376 KB)<br>
</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Internet Archive is under a DDoS attack (137 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://mastodon.archive.org/@internetarchive/112513905401989149</link>
            <guid>40492076</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 16:08:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://mastodon.archive.org/@internetarchive/112513905401989149">https://mastodon.archive.org/@internetarchive/112513905401989149</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40492076">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Should I use JWTs for authentication tokens? (374 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.ploetzli.ch/2024/should-i-use-jwt-for-authentication/</link>
            <guid>40491694</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 15:31:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.ploetzli.ch/2024/should-i-use-jwt-for-authentication/">https://blog.ploetzli.ch/2024/should-i-use-jwt-for-authentication/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40491694">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Instead of "auth", we should say "permissions" and "login" (507 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ntietz.com/blog/lets-say-instead-of-auth/</link>
            <guid>40491480</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 15:11:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ntietz.com/blog/lets-say-instead-of-auth/">https://ntietz.com/blog/lets-say-instead-of-auth/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40491480">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Most computer systems we interact with have an auth system of some kind.
The problem is, that sentence is at best unclear and at worst nonsense.
"Auth" can mean at least two things: authentication or authorization<sup><a href="#or-verb-forms">1</a></sup>.
Which do we mean for an "auth system"?
It's never perfectly clear and, unfortunately, we often mean <em>both</em>.</p>
<p>This is a widespread problem, and it's well known.
One common solution, using the terms "authn" and "authz", doesn't solve the problem.
And this isn't just confusing, it leads to bad abstractions and general failures!</p>
<p><img src="https://ntietz.com/images/comics/logging-in.png" alt="Comic about an ambiguity in the term &quot;log in.&quot;" title="Tech support thought they had seen it all, but they hadn't met Sam yet"></p>
<h2 id="the-current-terms-fall-short">The current terms fall short</h2>
<p>Calling things just "auth" is common.
It's used in library names (<a href="https://docs.allauth.org/en/latest/">django-allauth</a> is for authentication, and <a href="https://github.com/go-pkgz/auth">go-auth</a> is also authentication), package names (<code>django.contrib.auth</code>, which does both authentication and authorization), and even <a href="https://auth0.com/">company names</a>.</p>
<p>Since "auth" can mean two things, this naming leads to ambiguities.
When you see a new auth library or product, you don't know right away what it's able to handle.
And when you talk about it, it's also not clear what you're referring to.</p>
<p>The canonical solution is to call these "authn" and "authz", the n and z evoking the longer words.
Thes are just not satisfactory, though.
They're clunky and hard to understand: they're not universal enough to be able to skip explanation; they're easy to mishear and are close together; and what verb forms would we even use?</p>
<p>It's not just about bad communication, though.
This terminology implies that the two concepts, authentication and authorization, are more closely related than they are.
It encourages bad abstractions to combine them, because we have one word, so we feel like they <em>should</em> belong together.
But they are two pretty fundamentally distinct problems: checking who you are<sup><a href="#other-assertions">2</a></sup>, and specifying access rights.</p>
<p>There are some links between auth and auth<sup><a href="#sorry">3</a></sup>, because what you can do is tied to who you are.
But they're also very different, and deserve to be treated that way.
At the very least, recognizing that they're different leads to recognition that solving one does <em>not</em> solve the other.</p>
<h2 id="intead-use-permissions-and-login">Intead, use "permissions" and "login"</h2>
<p>We should always use the most clear terms we have.
Sometimes there's not a great option, but here, we have <em>wonderfully</em> clear terms.
Those are "login" for authentication and "permissions" for authorization.
Both are terms that will make sense with little explanation (in contrast to "authn" and "authz", which are confusing on first encounter) since almost everyone has logged into a system and has run into permissions issues.</p>
<p>There are two ways to use "login" here: the noun and the verb form.
The noun form is "login", which refers to the information you enter to gain access to the system.
And the verb form is "log in", which refers to the <em>action</em> of entering your login to use the system.</p>
<p>"Permissions" is just the noun form.
To use a verb, you would use "check permissions."
While this is long, it's also just... fine?
It hasn't been an issue in my experience.</p>
<p>Both of these are abundantly clear even to our peers in disciplines outside software engineering.
This to me makes it worth using them from a clarity perspective alone.
But then we have the big benefit to abstractions, as well.</p>
<p>When we call both by the same word, there's often an urge to combine them into a single module just by dint of the terminology.
This isn't necessarily wrong—there is certainly some merit to put them together, since permissions typically require a login.
But it's not necessary, either, and our designs will be stronger if we don't make that assumption and instead make a reasoned choice.</p>
<hr>



</div><p>
    If this post was enjoyable or useful for you, <strong>please share it!</strong>
    If you have comments, questions, or feedback, you can email <a href="mailto:me@ntietz.com">my personal email</a>.
    To get new posts and support my work, subscribe to the <a href="https://ntietz.com/newsletter/">newsletter</a>. There is also an <a href="https://ntietz.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a>.
  </p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Reclaiming IPv4 Class E's 240.0.0.0/4 (173 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.benjojo.co.uk/post/class-e-addresses-in-the-real-world</link>
            <guid>40491038</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 14:28:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.benjojo.co.uk/post/class-e-addresses-in-the-real-world">https://blog.benjojo.co.uk/post/class-e-addresses-in-the-real-world</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40491038">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<h3>May 27 2024</h3>


<p><img src="https://blog.benjojo.co.uk/asset/zwn3aTE6nw" alt="social medai"></p>
<p>Ever since the supply of fresh IPv4 address blocks was depleted there has been a number of interesting market changes, mostly around the costs to either acquire or lease IPv4 address blocks. Since the demand for IPv4 addressing has not changed that much, prices have gone up, and more providers like AWS, Hetzner, OVH, etc who were previously pricing in the cost of IPv4, are now charging for it separately.</p>
<p>For some people this has been a bit of a pay day, while if you were to have had a block assigned to you in 2016, you would have gotten 4 /24’s (a /24 is the minimum you can reasonably route on the BGP backed internet), however if you were setting up shop in the 2000’s you could easily acquire a 256 /24’s in a single allocation!</p>
<p>These entities are now selling off (if they can) these blocks at prices 10,000+ USD per /24!</p>
<p>But for other networks this development in pricing has been devastating to the costs of business, industries that were used to assigning a single IPv4 address (or more) to every subscriber began to find that this model is unsustainable, and have had no option other than to deploy Carrier Grade NAT.</p>
<p>So what if we technically had another 524288 /24’s worth of IPv4 hanging around in standardisation limbo? It turns out, we do! It’s called “Class E space”</p>
<h2>The IPv4 Class E Origin Story</h2>
<p>Class E space as defined in <a href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc1112.html">RFC1112</a> lives at the end of IPv4 address space between 240.0.0.0 and 255.255.255.254, Right after the space used for IPv4 multicast. This space in this state has existed since 1989, however it has been mostly ignored as a relic of time until the existing IPv4 unicast space allocations had been mostly assigned.</p>
<p>Class E is not actually the only space that is now being reviewed. During the standardisation of where IPv4 blocks would go, several unnecessarily large allocations were made due to technical limitations at the time. Some obvious ones include 0.0.0.0/8 (A block where 0.0.0.0/24 would have been sufficient in hindsight), and 127.0.0.0/8 (the local loopback block, where 127.0.0.0/16 would have been sufficient).</p>
<p>Since the internet was at the start not obviously going to be used, the minimum allocation size for an address block was a /8 at the start, later on we got “classful” allocations where a /16 would be assigned instead (this is why you often see /16s assigned to universities or institutions of similar ages), later on we moved to being able to assign /24’s, later on the internet moved to <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc1519">CIDR</a>’s to better address various addressing needs. However the older allocations for 0.0.0.0/8, 127.0.0.0/8, and 240.0.0.0/4 were never revisited.</p>
<p>The best I can understand from talking to people. 240.0.0.0/4 was assigned for a future where a 3rd (and still mythical) type of routing was invented that was not unicast or multicast.</p>
<p>While there are somewhat ongoing efforts to see 0.0.0.0/8, 127.0.0.0/8 become routable unicast space, I will focus for the rest of this post on 240.0.0.0/4, since it is the largest, and most technically interesting, not to mention that Class E’s reimplementation as unicast space shares almost all of the same issues as the other blocks.</p>
<h2>Realistic expectations</h2>
<p>Ultimately the answer to the depletion of IPv4 and its effects on the wider ability for networks to acquire IPv4 space, is to deploy IPv6. However since IPv6 requires all networks to also implement, networks are likely going to see a need for at least some IPv4 space for a very long time, even if it is relegated to increasingly slower and unreliable CGNAT technologies.</p>
<p>As for Class E space, it is unlikely that we will ever see such space widely accepted into the internet routing table. This is because of known equipment and endpoint incompatibilities that already exist today that would have to be overcome globally, and doing any upgrade action on the internet globally is nearly impossible. Because of this, even if people were offered Class E space it is unclear who would want IP addresses that only work for a subset of users (there is a joke somewhere here that we already have this, it’s called IPv6!)</p>
<h2>Class E as a local unicast space</h2>
<p>However global routing is not the only usage for IP addresses, plenty of addresses get consumed today in local networks, or for network infrastructure itself! Since these use cases tend to use <a href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc1918.html">RFC1918</a> (10.0.0.0, 192.168.0.0, etc space), it is unlikely we will see such tech deployed in the home.</p>
<p>However there are a number of places where you can easily “run out” of local addresses. For that, Class E space is a useful addition due to its size and its implicit incompatibilities with the rest of the world. This allows you to build out a large network with these addresses, and save the address space that is usable for interoperation with other networks or customer equipment.</p>
<p>We already see some uses of this today, For example:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0tcR-iQce7s&amp;t=1709s">AWS uses 240.0.0.0/4 for some of their network devices</a></li>
<li><a href="https://blog.benjojo.co.uk/post/ip-address-squatting">Evidence of Class E space usage in some home/SMB has been spotted</a></li>
<li><a href="https://labs.ripe.net/author/qasim-lone/2404-as-seen-by-ripe-atlas/">Some non AWS networks are also using Class E space</a></li>
<li><a href="https://canonical.com/blog/introducing-the-fan-simpler-container-networking">“Fan” networking by Canonical uses Class E space</a></li>
</ul>
<p>In addition, Cloudflare has a option to have <a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/network/pseudo-ipv4/">IPv6 addresses hashed into a Class E address</a> as a way to allow systems not capable of handling IPv6 addresses to still be accessed with IPv6, this is ultimately a huge hack, and it’s unclear if anyone seriously uses this feature.</p>
<h2>How is vendor support?</h2>
<p>Any deployment discussion is only academic if we do not have equipment that is capable of handling such addresses. At the time of writing, the support for such addresses is quite patchy.</p>
<p>Endpoint (aka, users) software that works:</p>
<ul>
<li>Linux distros post 2008</li>
<li>Android 2009</li>
<li>MacOS/OSX post 2009 (with Apple iOS being included)</li>
<li>OpenBSD post October 2022</li>
</ul>
<p>Endpoint stuff that does not work:</p>
<ul>
<li>All known Windows versions</li>
<li>NetBSD/FreeBSD</li>
</ul>
<p>For actual networking equipment, the story is more complicated. To test compatibility I built a virtual network vendor testing lab:</p>
<p><img src="https://blog.benjojo.co.uk/asset/ys4UwXWEYZ" alt=""></p>
<p>The goal is to test two questions</p>
<ol>
<li>Can Class E be used for addresses between routers?</li>
<li>Can Class E be used with routing protocols like OSPF and BGP?</li>
</ol>
<p>Some router vendors are able to set Class E addresses out of the box, others need special configuration. For example JunOS needs <code>routing-options martians 240/4 orlonger allow</code> to be set in configuration before such addresses are allowed, similarly Arista EOS needs <code>use ipv4 routable 240.0.0.0/4</code> set before Class E addresses are accepted.</p>
<p>Other vendors flat out refuse to set Class E addresses on their interfaces.</p>
<p>The other question is that if dynamic routing protocols correctly function when Class E CIDRs are used? The answer is, sometimes:</p>

<table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>Vendor</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>Static Link IP</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>Routed OSPF Works</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>Arista EOS 4.29</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>Yes (Extra Config)</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>Unknown</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>JunOS 22</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>Yes (Extra Config)</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>Yes</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>RouterOS 7.7</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>Yes</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>Yes</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>Cisco IOS XR</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>Yes</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>Yes</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>Cisco IOS XE 16.12</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>No</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>No</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>Nokia SR-OS 21.7</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>No</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>No</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>Huawei VRP</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>No</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>No</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>Extreme EXOS 32</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>No</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><span>No</span></p></td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>However, there are some very sharp edges to using protocols like OSPF/IS-IS with such address space that you should be aware of if you are planning to deploy this in your own environment:</p>
<h2>OSPF Surprises</h2>
<p><img src="https://blog.benjojo.co.uk/asset/52oVWQIdbp" alt=""></p>
<p>In the following example, we have two routers, one that supports Class E space being installed into the data (forwarding) plane, and the other (Nokia) that does not. However, because of how OSPF works, the routes will be carried by the Nokia router as if it can route for them, but since it never installs these routes it will drop traffic for it. (or worse, use a default route instead)</p>
<p>If ask the MikroTik to traceroute to a class E address that is behind the Nokia router, it knows to try and send it to the Nokia router, however the traffic is lost, when trying the same with a “regular” unicast address (of 6.6.6.6), then traffic is forwarded:</p>
<p><img src="https://blog.benjojo.co.uk/asset/mpxz2aXZwO" alt=""></p>
<p>This means that if you wish to deploy Class E space in such an environment, you must be sure that all devices in the path (and possible backup paths) can support it, else traffic may be dropped when they get used.</p>
<h2>Surprise real world test</h2>
<p>Because of the previously mentioned issues, I would not have thought it was worthwhile to try and test in in the real world, however you can imagine my surprise that a few days afterwards I got this email from a Internet Exchange mailing list</p>
<pre><code>Dear peering partners,

We started to announce a prefix 242.242.0.0/16 from our experimental ASN
8747.  242.242.1.1 should be pingable if such a route passes your
filters and router setup.

Current test results are that IOS XR supports class E routes with no
issues by default. With JunOS, using a command "set routing-options
martians" etc. is necessary.  Your feedback regarding other platforms is
appreciated.


--
S pozdravem/Best Regards,

Zbyněk Pospíchal
Quantcom, a.s.
</code></pre>
<p>This was super surprising to see! Quantcom staff had decided to give Class E a go, and since they had real customers with RIPE Atlas probes, we could run “best case” tests to see how real “SOHO” hardware handled class E space:</p>
<p><img src="https://blog.benjojo.co.uk/asset/9RUe9SWzhS" alt=""></p>
<p>… and it was about 50%, not terrible, but still far away from the numbers you would want to see. Usefully Quantcom also have BGP downstreams with RIPE Atlas probes, so I tested those too:</p>
<p><img src="https://blog.benjojo.co.uk/asset/lbTWR7NLeW" alt=""></p>
<p>Also 50%! Since most RIPE Atlas hardware is deployed inside homes and small businesses we can predict that if Class E was deployed today, the maximum acceptance on end devices is about 50%</p>
<p>I got in touch with Zbyněk from Quantcom, and he agreed to setup a IPv4 scan of the internet from the announced Class E space. This is helpful because it allows us to determine which of Quantcom’s BGP peers accepted the prefix (Implying a total lack of BGP filtering), and whose infrastructure can actually route class E IP addresses.</p>
<p>The scan concluded that 184,496 IP addresses responded to the ping, using bgp.tools’es <a href="https://map.bgp.tools/">map data</a> we would expect a fully reachable prefix to have 380,286,307 responses, so this puts the full reachability of this test Quantcom prefix at 0.04%.</p>
<p>This low reachability is without a doubt caused by the fact that Quantcom can only give the test prefix to their downstreams and direct BGP peers over internet exchanges, since their transit providers and internet exchange route servers will filter this out automatically preventing other networks from learning the prefix.</p>
<p>Networks that seem to have accepted the prefix directly include:</p>
<ul>
<li>AS2686 AT&amp;T EMEA</li>
<li>AS3216 VEON / Beeline / VimpelCom</li>
<li>AS5416 Bahrain Telecommunications Company</li>
<li>AS6740 InterneXt 2000</li>
<li>AS8926 Moldtelecom</li>
<li>AS9050 Orange Romania</li>
<li>AS13335 Cloudflare (Prague PoP only)</li>
<li>AS16625 Akamai</li>
<li>AS19281 Quad9</li>
<li>AS20485 TransTeleKom (and some of their downstreams)</li>
<li>AS25424 InterneXt</li>
<li>AS28725 CETIN</li>
</ul>
<p>Some of these results surprised me, since they imply that for these networks involved, you could announce almost anything (maybe not RPKI invalids, who knows though) and they would accept and propagate across their network, including their downstreams!</p>
<p><img src="https://blog.benjojo.co.uk/asset/OwaPhiDY9v" alt=""></p>
<p>In the case of AS20485 TransTeleKom, their acceptance of the route allowed the bulk of the 184,496 IP’s to be able to respond. As I have only listed the networks that appear to have directly accepted the route over an IXP.</p>
<p>Maybe we still have a long way to go with BGP filtering in practice! It is also entirely possible that more networks that directly peer with Quantcom would have accepted this route if it was better supported by vendors out of the box.</p>
<p>Closing up, we can now better answer the root question of this entire post…</p>
<h2>Should you use Class E space?</h2>
<p>The short version is, Typically no. Unless you have supernatural control of your network vendor decisions, and cannot migrate to IPv6 for all workloads. However Class E could be very useful if you have control over your entire network for the use cases of local/private addressing.</p>
<p>As for Class E being globally reachable space, It is clear that there lies ahead major roadblocks for Class E space adoption. Not only does it require changes to user software that has an installation count of at least 1 billion, but it also requires that a policy be created within IANA and the IETF to change the purpose of this space.</p>
<p>Now, Having gone through the IETF recently for something unrelated to this, I can only assume that if such a thing is ever accepted, it would be a considerably long battle. It also opens up a second battle over what regional RIRs get the newly created address space. There are 5 RIRs, but 8 /8’s worth of address space up for grabs in Class E. It is not clear how you would split this up.</p>
<p>Finally, changing software is extremely hard, and getting Class E prompts some extremely difficult software deployment challenges. Since the customers/members of the RIRs would be reluctant to accept address space that does not work for all users. If we are going to start using address space that might not work for all users, it would be wise to pick the address space that we already have a considerable head start on getting accepted: IPv6.</p>
<hr>
<p>If you want to stay up to date with the blog you can use the <a href="https://blog.benjojo.co.uk/rss.xml">RSS feed</a> or you can follow me on Fediverse <a href="https://benjojo.co.uk/u/benjojo">@benjojo@benjojo.co.uk</a>!</p>
<p>Until next time!</p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Priced out of home ownership (260 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/articles/cmj66r4lvzzo</link>
            <guid>40490610</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 13:39:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/articles/cmj66r4lvzzo">https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/articles/cmj66r4lvzzo</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40490610">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><main id="main-content" data-testid="main-content"><article><header data-component="headline-block"><h2 id="main-heading" type="headline" tabindex="-1"><span role="text">Priced out of home ownership - 'It makes me want to throw up'</span></h2></header><div data-component="image-block"><figure><p><span><picture><source srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/1eaa/live/5c4b5060-147a-11ef-87f2-97663bbe6622.jpg.webp 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/1eaa/live/5c4b5060-147a-11ef-87f2-97663bbe6622.jpg.webp 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/1eaa/live/5c4b5060-147a-11ef-87f2-97663bbe6622.jpg.webp 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/624/cpsprodpb/1eaa/live/5c4b5060-147a-11ef-87f2-97663bbe6622.jpg.webp 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/1eaa/live/5c4b5060-147a-11ef-87f2-97663bbe6622.jpg.webp 800w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/976/cpsprodpb/1eaa/live/5c4b5060-147a-11ef-87f2-97663bbe6622.jpg.webp 976w" type="image/webp"><img alt="Nathan Wilkins" loading="eager" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/1eaa/live/5c4b5060-147a-11ef-87f2-97663bbe6622.jpg" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/1eaa/live/5c4b5060-147a-11ef-87f2-97663bbe6622.jpg 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/1eaa/live/5c4b5060-147a-11ef-87f2-97663bbe6622.jpg 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/1eaa/live/5c4b5060-147a-11ef-87f2-97663bbe6622.jpg 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/624/cpsprodpb/1eaa/live/5c4b5060-147a-11ef-87f2-97663bbe6622.jpg 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/1eaa/live/5c4b5060-147a-11ef-87f2-97663bbe6622.jpg 800w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/976/cpsprodpb/1eaa/live/5c4b5060-147a-11ef-87f2-97663bbe6622.jpg 976w" width="640" height="360"></picture></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Nathan Wilkins</span></p></figure></div><div data-component="text-block"><p><b>When Nathan Wilkins moved back in with his mother and sister in 2019, he hoped it would help him save money to buy a home. </b></p><p>But in the years since, the US housing market has been transformed by rising rents, surging home prices, and a massive jump in mortgage rates, making homeownership seem ever more impossible. </p><p>He and his sister are making more money than ever, the 32-year-old insurance adjuster from Utah says. But shelling out $2,500 (£1,960) a month in rent doesn't leave much left over. </p><p>“It’s like I’m playing a game that you can’t win,” he says. “The fact that we’re being priced out just makes me want to throw up.”</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Such frustrations are spreading, fuelling dissatisfaction and contributing to the widespread pessimism about the US economy that is looming over the country's upcoming election.</p><p>The <a href="https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/MSPUS">median home sale price<span>, <!-- -->external</span></a> in the US has jumped by nearly 30% since the end of 2019, hitting $420,000 this spring. </p><p>At a time of rising property values globally, the leap has been one of the most dramatic in the world, <a href="https://www.imf.org/en/Blogs/Articles/2024/01/11/housing-affordability-remains-stretched-amid-higher-interest-rate-environment">according to the International Monetary Fund.<span>, <!-- -->external</span></a></p><p>And that's not factoring in the added costs from higher interest rates, which now stand at roughly 7% for the 30-year, fixed-rate mortgage that is typical in the US, up from about 3% in 2020.</p><p>Homebuyers today need an annual income of more than $100,000 - well above the country's household median of about $75,000 - to comfortably afford a home in most places in the US, research firms such as <a href="https://www.zillow.com/research/buyers-income-needed-33755/">Zillow<span>, <!-- -->external</span></a> and <a href="https://www.bankrate.com/real-estate/home-affordability-in-current-housing-market-study/">Bankrate<span>, <!-- -->external</span></a> say, and face monthly payments that have <a href="https://www.kansascityfed.org/research/charting-the-economy-archive/monthly-mortgage-payments-for-homebuyers-continue-to-soar/">roughly doubled<span>, <!-- -->external</span></a> in just four years.</p></div><div data-component="image-block"><figure><p><span><span></span></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Getty Images</span></p><figcaption><span>Image caption, </span><p>Megan Holter (right) and her wife Sonia outside their new home in Columbus, Ohio</p></figcaption></figure></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>“It makes me cry a bit,” says Megan Holter, who started looking to buy in Austin, Texas, back in 2019, when banks were offering her a 30-year fixed rate of about 4.75%.</p><p>She halted her search when the pandemic hit, priced out by the surging cost of building materials and homes. </p><p>She and her wife finally bought a home this year, but only after swallowing a 6.625% rate  - and moving 1,200 miles north to Columbus, Ohio, a spot selected from a spreadsheet she created of cities with lower costs.</p><p>“Housing affordability was the number one thing that we’ve been considering for five years,” says the 30-year-old, who also switched jobs from the public sector to the private sector to make homebuying happen. </p><p>“We have moved mountains to make it possible.</p><p>“I’m just eternally grateful that we can afford it. I know a lot of other people cannot," she adds.</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Just 40.1% of renters expect to ever own a home one day, according to the <a href="https://www.newyorkfed.org/newsevents/news/research/2024/20240506">New York Federal Reserve<span>, <!-- -->external</span></a>, the smallest share since the bank started asking renters the question in 2014.</p><p>Even homeowners, whose long-term mortgages shield them from immediate financial impact and who benefit from rising property values, <a href="https://michiganross.umich.edu/news/professor-brian-connolly-comments-survey-finds-rare-bipartisan-agreement-housing-issues-among">tell pollsters<span>, <!-- -->external</span></a> that the changes in the market are a source of concern  – as they push up property taxes and insurance costs, while making moving a less affordable prospect.</p><p>Nearly one third of all households now spend more than a third of their income on housing - the standard cut-off for affordability - the highest level since 2015, <a href="https://www.jchs.harvard.edu/blog/more-42-million-us-households-were-cost-burdened-2022">according to Harvard's Joint Center for Housing Studies<span>, <!-- -->external</span></a>. </p><p>A <a href="https://theharrispoll.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/State-of-Real-Estate-2024-March-2024.pdf">recent Harris poll<span>, <!-- -->external</span></a> found more than 70% of Americans believe the market is only going to get worse. </p></div><div data-component="image-block"><figure><p><span><span></span></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Getty Images</span></p></figure></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>The issue is feeding into wider worries about rising living costs, which have jumped 20% since 2021.</p><p>It is among the biggest challenges facing President Joe Biden, whose time in office has coincided with the housing market's transformation and who receives dismal ratings for his handling of the economy in national polls.</p><p>Challenger Donald Trump, who fares better, has sought to blame Mr Biden for inflation, and though he does not typically call out housing specifically, he regularly spotlights "skyrocketing" interest rates to argue that the economy is heading in the wrong direction.</p><p>"Inflation has been a political noose for Biden in recent years," says Brian Connolly, professor of business law at the University of Michigan's Ross School of Business, whose work focuses on housing issues. "Housing costs are another place where people are experiencing this financial squeeze."</p><p>In recent months, the White House has tried to address concerns about affordability head on, offering proposals such as rules to limit closing costs and a $10,000 tax credit for first time homebuyers.</p><p>It marks a shift in tone, after years of focusing on the economy's strengths, including low unemployment. But with few immediate levers for Mr Biden to pull, it's not clear the efforts are resonating. </p><p>His support has especially eroded among younger people - whose record turnout in 2020 helped put him in office. Voters in this demographic are least likely to own homes and most likely to see housing affordability as a top concern. </p><p>"I don't see any platform that purposely looks out for somebody like first-time homebuyers, wanting to ease their pain," says Braiden Dogherty, a 30-year-old from Florida who works in manufacturing and has been checking for houses daily for three years. </p><p>Despite a $50,000 inheritance, no debt, and decent jobs, he and his wife can't find an affordable two-bedroom near their families in the Orlando area.  </p><p>He says the problem of housing costs is too big to blame on any one politician or party, but the seeming lack of solutions has contributed to his wider political disillusionment. He is uncertain how he will vote in November.</p><p>"I'm fed up," he says. "Housing is part of it."</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>The growing outcry has raised pressure on the US central bank to cut interest rates to bring relief, a move Federal Reserve chairman Jerome Powell has said is likely at some point.</p><p>But expectations that a cut would happen early this year, helping to improve the country's mood, have been steadily pushed back. This reflects concerns that progress in lowering inflation - which was hovering at 3.4% in April, still well above the bank's 2% target - could be stalling.</p></div><div data-component="image-block"><figure><p><span><span></span></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Julia Mokhnatkiina (JM Photos Inc)</span></p><figcaption><span>Image caption, </span><p>Mimi Than and her husband are among those affected by the rise in interest rates this year</p></figcaption></figure></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Instead, since January mortgage rates have mostly moved higher. </p><p>Mimi Than, a 29-year-old who recently bought a three-bedroom condo in the Boston, Massachusetts area, says she is facing roughly $200 more in monthly costs than when she and her husband were pre-approved for a loan in March. </p><p>They did not lock in the rate then, unaware borrowing costs might shift significantly. When they returned to their lender in April after making an offer, the interest rate they were offered was 6.9%, up from 6.5%.</p><p>She’s hoping that they will drop back later this year, allowing them to refinance.</p><p>"I'm obsessively checking the rates," she says. </p><p>Many analysts maintain it is only a matter of time until inflation slows down, clearing the way for a cut. </p><p>They note reports by private firms that show rental increases - which play a big role in calculations of US inflation - cooling from the torrid pace of the pandemic amid a jump in apartment supply.</p><p>With wages growing, an increase in new homes under construction and rents and home prices rising more slowly,  Orphe Divounguy, senior economist at the housing site Zillow, says he sees affordability challenges easing as well - albeit not in time for November's election.</p></div><div data-component="image-block"><figure><p><span><span></span></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Getty Images</span></p><figcaption><span>Image caption, </span><p>New home construction has increased significantly from pre-pandemic levels, but supplies still fall short of demand</p></figcaption></figure></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>"It's working itself out," he says. "We still have a long way to go, of course, but we're seeing some improvement and I think we're going to see more improvement."</p><p>But there's a gloomier view. </p><p>With more people priced out of homeownership, rental rates may prove more resilient than expected, keeping inflation elevated.</p><p>And if mortgage rates do not drop significantly, the step-change in borrowing costs may act as a long-term constraint on supply, as builders pull back and homeowners who secured mortgages when rates were lower forego moving.  </p><p>Braiden, from Florida, sees no easy fix from the Fed, which he fears helped shape the current crisis by letting rates stay unusually low in the decade after the 2008 financial crisis. </p><p>"No matter what happens - whether they raise, lower or hold them - I feel as though the next decade is probably just going to be difficult no matter what for most people," he says.</p></div><div data-component="embed-ugc-uploader-block" id="uploader-16-u175766247"><h2>Get in touch</h2><div><p>Are you affected by issues covered in this story?</p></div></div><section data-component="links-block"><p><h2 type="normal">More on this story</h2></p></section></article></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Linux virtual machines, with a focus on running containers (105 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lima-vm.io/</link>
            <guid>40490154</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 12:30:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lima-vm.io/">https://lima-vm.io/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40490154">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><strong>What is Lima?</strong></p><p>Lima launches Linux virtual machines with automatic file sharing and port forwarding (similar to WSL2).</p></div><section><h4>Lima is a <a href="https://cncf.io/">CNCF</a> sandbox project</h4><img src="https://lima-vm.io/images/cncf-color-bg.svg" alt="Cloud Native Computing Foundation logo"></section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Resume Tip: Hacking "AI" screening of resumes (343 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.solipsys.co.uk/images/ResumeTip.png</link>
            <guid>40489596</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 11:01:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.solipsys.co.uk/images/ResumeTip.png">https://www.solipsys.co.uk/images/ResumeTip.png</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40489596">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Possible association between tattoos and lymphoma (185 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.lunduniversity.lu.se/article/possible-association-between-tattoos-and-lymphoma-revealed</link>
            <guid>40489486</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 10:39:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.lunduniversity.lu.se/article/possible-association-between-tattoos-and-lymphoma-revealed">https://www.lunduniversity.lu.se/article/possible-association-between-tattoos-and-lymphoma-revealed</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40489486">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>
      A new study from Lund University in Sweden suggests that tattoos could be a risk factor for cancer in the lymphatic system, or lymphoma. Now, the researchers underline the need for more research on the topic.<br>

  </p><div><p><span lang="EN-US" dir="ltr">Our knowledge regarding the long-term health effects of tattoos is currently poor, and there is not a lot of research within this area. Now a research group at Lund University has investigated the association between tattoos and lymphoma.</span></p><p><span lang="EN-US" dir="ltr">“We have identified people diagnosed with lymphoma via population registers. These individuals were then matched with a control group of the same sex and age, but without lymphoma. The study participants answered a questionnaire about lifestyle factors to determine whether they were tattooed or not”, says Christel Nielsen, the researcher at Lund University who led the study.</span></p><p><span lang="EN-US" dir="ltr">In total, the entire study included 11,905 people. Of these, 2,938 people had lymphoma when they were between 20 and 60 years old. Among them, 1,398 people answered the questionnaire, while the number of participants in the control group was 4,193. In the group with lymphoma, 21 percent were tattooed (289 individuals), while 18 percent were tattooed in the control group without a lymphoma diagnosis (735 individuals).</span></p><p><span lang="EN-US" dir="ltr">“After taking into account other relevant factors, such as smoking and age, we found that the risk of developing lymphoma was 21 percent higher among those who were tattooed. It is important to remember that lymphoma is a rare disease and that our results apply at the group level. The results now need to be verified and investigated further in other studies and such research is ongoing”, says Christel Nielsen.</span></p><p><span lang="EN-US" dir="ltr">A hypothesis that Christel Nielsen's research group had before the study was that the size of the tattoo would affect the lymphoma risk. They thought that a full body tattoo might be associated with a greater risk of cancer compared to a small butterfly on the shoulder, for example. Unexpectedly, the area of tattooed body surface turned out not to matter.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span lang="EN-US" dir="ltr">“We do not yet know why this was the case. One can only speculate that a tattoo, regardless of size, triggers a low-grade inflammation in the body, which in turn can trigger cancer. The picture is thus more complex than we initially thought.” &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;</span></p><p><span lang="EN-US" dir="ltr">Most people get their first tattoo at a young age, which means that you are exposed to tattoo ink for a large part of your life. Even so, research has only scratched the surface of the long-term health effects of tattoos.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span lang="EN-US" dir="ltr">“We already know that when the tattoo ink is injected into the skin, the body interprets this as something foreign that should not be there and the immune system is activated. A large part of the ink is transported away from the skin, to the lymph nodes where it is deposited”, says Christel Nielsen.</span></p><p><span lang="EN-US" dir="ltr">The research group will now proceed with studies of whether there is any association between tattoos and other types of cancer. They also want to do further research on other inflammatory diseases to see if there is a link to tattoos.</span></p><p><span lang="EN-US" dir="ltr">“People will likely want to continue to express their identity through tattoos, and therefore it is very important that we as a society can make sure that it is safe. For the individual, it is good to know that tattoos can affect your health, and that you should turn to your health care provider if you experience symptoms that you believe could be related to your tattoo”, concludes Christel Nielsen.</span></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[My new PSU burns out I fix it, and torture it by cracking water (166 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://tomscii.sig7.se/2024/05/PSU-burnout-and-torture-cracking-water</link>
            <guid>40489269</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 09:55:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://tomscii.sig7.se/2024/05/PSU-burnout-and-torture-cracking-water">https://tomscii.sig7.se/2024/05/PSU-burnout-and-torture-cracking-water</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40489269">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <article itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/BlogPosting">
  
  <div itemprop="articleBody">
    <p><a href="https://tomscii.sig7.se/2024/04/300W-Linear-DualTracking-Lab-PSU">My brand new PSU</a>, the
most complicated circuit I designed and built just recently, started
life in October 2023. It seemed to work pretty well, at least I got
through the long and dark winter with it feeding my LED Superlamp.
(Most of the time. The rest of that time, I was using it for something
it was actually intended for, i.e., the feeding of an experimental
new circuit. By the light of a torch.)</p>

<!--more-->

<h2 id="mind-the-gap---or-blow-a-pcb-track">Mind the gap - or blow a PCB track!</h2>

<p>Then one day towards early Spring, while I was just sitting there,
<em>something</em> happened. I remember I was not doing anything in
particular when my subconscious alerted me to some weirdness going
on. I slowly came to realise that the weirdness was a really sharp bad
smell. A smell of something burning, or close to burning. I looked at
my bench supply – I clearly remember it was turned on but there
was nothing connected to it at the moment. And it seemed to be OK, at
least all the LED displays were lit up. But the voltage indicator was
strangely zeroed out, clearly in spite of the control settings.</p>

<p>Instinctively, I turned the instrument off, probably even before all
the above has fully gone through my head. Sniffing closer confirmed my
suspicion that the smell was indeed coming from my bench supply. I was
more than a little bit confused – what could cause such a sudden
and seemingly unprovoked failure (at idle load!) after several months
of trouble-free operation?  I mean, design errors would surely have
come out by now, and being relatively fresh off the proverbial factory
line, we are hopefully still a long way from any possible component
wear-out… I was intrigued. It was late in the day and it was already
dark (and I just lost the only power supply to my Superlamp), so I
called it a day.</p>

<p>And by the first rays of light of the next dawn, this is what I saw:</p>

<p><a href="https://tomscii.sig7.se/images/linear-dual-lab-psu/pcb-fail1.jpg"><img src="https://tomscii.sig7.se/images/linear-dual-lab-psu/pcb-fail1-thumb.jpg" alt=""></a><br>
<em>PCB failure (click to enlarge)</em></p>

<p>Ouch, that PCB track in the middle got badly burned. So badly, in
fact, that a couple millimeters of the track simply disappeared (right
under the large C7 capacitor, left of the heatsinked Q9). Not for the
faint of heart!</p>

<p>Strange that the 2.5A primary side fuse (integrated into the AC inlet)
did not melt. And strangely, all the components seemed intact. I would
have expected a blown up capacitor or a shattered transistor or IC.
But nothing of that sort of catastrophe in sight – everything in
seemingly pristine condition. Except for the PCB itself.</p>

<p>Here is a better picture I took after disconnecting the wiring and
freeing the board for even closer inspection:</p>

<p><a href="https://tomscii.sig7.se/images/linear-dual-lab-psu/pcb-fail2.jpg"><img src="https://tomscii.sig7.se/images/linear-dual-lab-psu/pcb-fail2-thumb.jpg" alt=""></a><br>
<em>Same failure after disassembly, board plane view (click to enlarge)</em></p>

<p>So it looks like the VIN+ track (coming right from the unregulated
supply) got shorted to the ground plane, right below the ground
connection of C7. That track is 80&nbsp;mils (2&nbsp;mm) wide,
carefully sized to withstand 5A of steady current with only a
+20°C rise in temperature. So that alone cannot be the problem
– and again, there was zero load when this happened.</p>

<p>Apparently, the 8-mil (0.2&nbsp;mm) clearance between VIN+ and ground
was simply not enough to keep the 40-or-so volts apart. (It was not a
turn-on inrush event, as the instrument has been powered on for a
while.) Maybe the gap between the copper tracks was dirty (flux
remains?) which lead to increased conduction? Maybe the capacitor
being there had something to do with it? I did not really know.</p>

<p>Doing some further research I found
<a href="http://creepage.com/">creepage.com</a>, which contains an online
calculator of safety distances for <em>creepage</em>. This term refers to the
event of conduction across the surface of an insulator (such as the
gap across PCB tracks). The website allows you to get a safe distance
between conductors in the face of various voltages and environmental
conditions, according to several different industry standards.</p>

<p>So I played around with it and the result I got was (according to the
various environmental parameters, coating materials, and safety
standards I chose) somewhere between 1.0&nbsp;mm and 1.2&nbsp;mm. How
embarrassing! My PCB design is thus entirely worthless, because I did
not pay any attention to this – and the required distances are
<em>much</em> larger than I would have thought.  Another hard-earned lesson!</p>

<h2 id="mending-it">Mending it</h2>

<p>Okay, so can we salvage our wreck? After careful inspection and
ultimate removal of the charred remains of the track, I reached the
conclusion (supported by several measurements) that the rest of the
PCB survived intact, including all the components on it. The only
actual victim was the positive-side outboard pass transistor, which
did not show any external signs of damage, but DMM readouts were
contrary to what I would expect of an NPN power transistor that is
still kicking alive. So I swapped in a new part there. And I put in a
nice and thick insulated copper wire between the screw terminals of
VIN+ and the collector of Q5, the only connection that got severed by
the burn.</p>

<p>And after some further deliberation (what could possibly go wrong?) I
flipped the power on…</p>

<p><em>And it worked!</em> At least voltages seemed okay (without any load), the
readouts reacted to knob action, and no part started to burn.  All
good?</p>

<p>In a sigh of relief, I said to myself <em>I’m just gonna have to give this
baby a good workout!</em></p>



<p>While originally testing the PSU, I used some wire-wound power
inductors in the range of a few to a couple dozen Watts. Now I wanted
something bigger and badder: a test load that could steadily sink lots
of amperes (at a mostly-resistive impedance) without getting into any
trouble!</p>

<p>Enter the old classroom physics experiment I always wanted to try
myself:
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electrolysis_of_water">electrolysis</a>.
That requires a hefty source of DC current, and this seemed like the
perfect occasion.</p>

<p><a href="https://tomscii.sig7.se/images/linear-dual-lab-psu/cracker-parts.jpg"><img src="https://tomscii.sig7.se/images/linear-dual-lab-psu/cracker-parts-thumb.jpg" alt=""></a><br>
<em>All you need to build an electrolysis device (click to enlarge)</em></p>

<p>Above you can see all it takes to build an electrolysis tank on a
close to zero budget: a lunchbox (of the vertically aligned type), a
pair of PET bottles, a pair of stainless steel balloon whisks and
steel wool.</p>

<p>The design of my electrolysis tank was greatly inspired by <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=d85OX6yEwE0">this
video</a>. I highly
recommend watching it all the way through – I found it to be an
excellent source of practical ideas and overall inspiration!</p>

<p>My lunchbox-tank has a well fitting top (with a small, sealable
opening useful for pouring stuff in, then closing it for safety).
Still, I opted for the milder <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sodium_bicarbonate">sodium
bicarbonate</a>
(<em>baking soda</em>) as the electrolyte instead of the more commonly used
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sodium_hydroxide">sodium hydroxide</a>
(<em>caustic soda</em>) or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Potassium_hydroxide">potassium
hydroxide</a>, as
those are dangerously strong bases. This means less conductivity
between the electrodes, but also the absence of hazardous material.
Note that the bottle caps are drilled through so the gases are let out
at the top. They never mix within the tank.</p>

<p>I poured exactly one liter of warm water into the tank and started to
record the current at every five volts, from 5V to 35V. After each
round, I increased the concentration by adding one scoop (5&nbsp;ml)
of baking soda to the tank. I read voltages and currents directly off
the PSU’s digital displays. Here is a plot of the results:</p>

<p><a href="https://tomscii.sig7.se/files/linear-dual-lab-psu/crack-graph.png"><img src="https://tomscii.sig7.se/files/linear-dual-lab-psu/crack-graph.png" alt=""></a></p>

<p>Download the <a href="https://tomscii.sig7.se/files/linear-dual-lab-psu/crack-data.csv">raw data</a> and
the <a href="https://tomscii.sig7.se/files/linear-dual-lab-psu/crack-graph.plt">gnuplot script</a> if
you wish.</p>

<p>In line with prior expectations, conductivity of the electrolytic
solution of sodium bicarbonate increases in proportion with the
concentration of charged particles (ions) in the water. At a given
concentration, the tank behaves pretty much as a resistor (with a
linear relationship between its DC voltage and current).</p>

<p>The very first measurement round was made with pure tap water (indexed
with the number 0, as there were zero scoops of baking soda in it).
There is <em>some</em> current flowing, but very little, equivalent to about
2&nbsp;kΩ of resistance. That resistance dropped to around
40Ω after the first scoop of soda, 14Ω after 5 scoops,
8Ω after 10 scoops and 6Ω after 15 scoops.</p>

<p>It also seems like there is a tapering effect: the additional
conductivity yielded by each new scoop of soda is diminishing. I don’t
know enough about the science of this to judge whether this effect is
real, but moving upwards, the space between adjacent curves seems to
be shrinking.  There is some irregularity to it (visible as a gap
between graphs 7 and 8, and a smaller one between 4 and 5), but I
think that might be due to me not mixing the contents of the tank well
enough to dissolve all newly added powder. This might also explain the
slight convexity seen in curves 1 and 2: I did not yet realize that I
have to mix the tank, so the soda dissolved gradually while I was
moving towards higher voltages.</p>

<p>I got a little impatient towards the end, so after the tenth scoop I
started adding more at once. First a double (reaching 12 scoops) and
then three more (for a total of 15). The bench supply did its part,
but it reached the limits of what the mains transformer could supply
– above 4 amps, the secondary voltage started to drop below 36V.
But the electronics took the beating and nothing melted or burned.</p>

<p>The intensity of bubbling in the tank increased in direct proportion
to the current (again, as expected). And the tank also got quite warm,
due to the substantial power dissipated in its volume of water.</p>

<p><a href="https://tomscii.sig7.se/images/linear-dual-lab-psu/cracker-action.jpg"><img src="https://tomscii.sig7.se/images/linear-dual-lab-psu/cracker-action-thumb.jpg" alt=""></a><br>
<em>In action, with some 120 Watts absorbed by the tank (click to enlarge)</em></p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>So the clearances between some of the higher voltage tracks have
serious violations of the required distances to be safe from
creepage. As a result, one of the tracks has spontaneously
self-destructed, but there are a couple more places on the PCB where a
similar thing could happen basically any time. I am curious (in a less
than ideal way) of whether that would in fact happen…</p>

<p>At the end of the day, this is just another one of several design
flaws that would need to be addressed if I ever made a second build of
this kind of power supply. But for the time being, I will definitely
keep using this device. I have put it through some serious testing and
it passed with flying colours. We will see how it holds up, and (if it
should come to that) which part of the PCB will give in next!</p>

<p>Having tasted the sweet fruit of 8-mil tracks (and clearances)
bringing the ability to design fairly dense circuits, I need to
remember the lesson: there must be some real <em>distance</em> to insulate
voltages higher than a couple volts. As a reminder, there is this
ticking bomb sitting right here on my desk…</p>

<p>What? Did you say I should not be making gaseous hydrogen right next
to it? I mean, what could <em>possibly</em> <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hindenburg_disaster">go
wrong</a>?</p>



<p><em>Update:</em> this article was discussed on the <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40489269">orange
site</a>.</p>

  </div>
</article>

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Big data is dead (2023) (515 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://motherduck.com/blog/big-data-is-dead/</link>
            <guid>40488844</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 08:30:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://motherduck.com/blog/big-data-is-dead/">https://motherduck.com/blog/big-data-is-dead/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40488844">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>For more than a decade now, the fact that people have a hard time gaining actionable insights from their data has been blamed on its size. “Your data is too big for your puny systems,” was the diagnosis, and the cure was to buy some new fancy technology that can handle massive scale. Of course, after the Big Data task force purchased all new tooling and migrated from Legacy systems, people found that they still were having trouble making sense of their data. They also may have noticed, if they were really paying attention, that data size wasn’t really the problem at all.</p>
<p>The world in 2023 looks different from when the Big Data alarm bells started going off. The data cataclysm that had been predicted hasn’t come to pass. Data sizes may have gotten marginally larger, but hardware has gotten bigger at an even faster rate. Vendors are still pushing their ability to scale, but practitioners are starting to wonder how any of that relates to their real world problems.</p>
<section><h2 id="who-am-i-and-why-do-i-care">Who am I and why do I care?</h2><p>For more than 10 years, I was one of the acolytes beating the Big Data drum. I was a founding engineer on Google BigQuery, and as the only engineer on the team that actually liked public speaking, I got to travel to conferences around the world to help explain how we were going to help folks withstand the coming data explosion. I used to query a petabyte live on stage, demonstrating that no matter how big and bad your data was, we would be able to handle it, no problem.</p><img alt="Jordan Tigani at Big Data Spain" sizes="90vw,
                        (min-width: 728px) 688px,
                        (min-width: 960px) 840px,
                        (min-width: 1302px) 816px," srcset="https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_1_94000dd99e.jpg&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_1_94000dd99e.jpg&amp;w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_1_94000dd99e.jpg&amp;w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_1_94000dd99e.jpg&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_1_94000dd99e.jpg&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_1_94000dd99e.jpg&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_1_94000dd99e.jpg&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_1_94000dd99e.jpg&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_1_94000dd99e.jpg&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" loading="lazy"><p><i>This photo was me at Big Data Spain in 2012, warning of the dangers of giant datasets and promising relief if they just use our technology.</i></p><p>Over the next few years I spent a lot of time debugging problems that customers were having with BigQuery. I co-wrote two books and really dug into how the product was being used. In 2018, I switched to product management, and my job was split between talking to customers, many of whom were the largest enterprises in the world, and analyzing product metrics.</p><p>The most surprising thing that I learned was that most of the people using “Big Query” don’t really have Big Data. Even the ones who do tend to use workloads that only use a small fraction of their dataset sizes. When BigQuery came out, it was like science fiction for many people-- you literally couldn’t process data that fast in any other way. However, what was science fiction is now commonplace, and more traditional ways of processing your data have caught up.</p><p><strong>About this post</strong></p><p>This post will make the case that the era of Big Data is over. It had a good run, but now we can stop worrying about data size and focus on how we’re going to use it to make better decisions. I’ll show a number of graphs; these are all hand-drawn based on memory. If I did have access to the exact numbers, I wouldn’t be able to share them. But the important part is the shape, rather than the exact values.</p><p>The data behind the graphs come from having analyzed query logs, deal post-mortems, benchmark results (published and unpublished), customer support tickets, customer conversations, service logs, and published blog posts, plus a bit of intuition.</p></section>
<section><h2 id="the-obligatory-intro-slide">The obligatory intro slide</h2><p>For the last 10 years, every pitch deck for every big data product starts with a slide that looks something like this:
<img alt="data generated over time increasing" sizes="90vw,
                        (min-width: 728px) 688px,
                        (min-width: 960px) 840px,
                        (min-width: 1302px) 816px," srcset="https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_2_0f68796072.jpg&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_2_0f68796072.jpg&amp;w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_2_0f68796072.jpg&amp;w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_2_0f68796072.jpg&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_2_0f68796072.jpg&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_2_0f68796072.jpg&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_2_0f68796072.jpg&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_2_0f68796072.jpg&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_2_0f68796072.jpg&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" loading="lazy"></p><p>We used a version of this slide for years at Google. When I moved to SingleStore, they were using their own version that had the same chart. I’ve seen several other vendors with something similar. This is the “scare” slide. Big Data is coming! You need to buy what I’m selling!</p><p>The message was that old ways of handling data were not going to work. The acceleration of data generation was going to leave the data systems of yesteryear stuck in the mud, and anyone who embraced new ideas would be able to leapfrog their competitors.</p><p>Of course, just because the amount of data being generated is increasing doesn’t mean that it becomes a problem for everyone; data is not distributed equally. Most applications do not need to process massive amounts of data. This has led to a resurgence in data management systems with traditional architectures; SQLite, Postgres, MySQL are all growing strongly, while “NoSQL” and even “NewSQL” systems are stagnating.</p><img alt="DB Engines scores over time MongoDB versus MySQL" sizes="90vw,
                        (min-width: 728px) 688px,
                        (min-width: 960px) 840px,
                        (min-width: 1302px) 816px," srcset="https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_3_311addb207.jpg&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_3_311addb207.jpg&amp;w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_3_311addb207.jpg&amp;w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_3_311addb207.jpg&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_3_311addb207.jpg&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_3_311addb207.jpg&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_3_311addb207.jpg&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_3_311addb207.jpg&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_3_311addb207.jpg&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" loading="lazy"><p>MongoDB is the highest ranked NoSQL or otherwise scale-out database, and while it had a nice run-up over the years, it has been declining slightly recently, and hasn’t really made much headway against MySQL or Postgres, two resolutely monolithic databases. If Big Data were really taking over, you’d expect to see something different after all these years.</p><p>Of course, the picture looks different in analytical systems, but in OLAP you see a massive shift from on-premise to cloud, and there aren’t really any scale-up cloud analytical systems to compare against.</p></section>
<section><h2 id="most-people-dont-have-that-much-data">Most people don’t have that much data</h2><p>The intended takeaway from the “Big Data is coming” chart was that pretty soon, everyone will be inundated by their data. Ten years in, that future just hasn’t materialized. We can validate this several ways: looking at data (quantitatively), asking people if it is consistent with their experience (qualitatively), and thinking it through from first principles (inductively).</p><p>When I worked at BigQuery, I spent a lot of time looking at customer sizing. The actual data here is very sensitive, so I can’t share any numbers directly. However, I can say that the vast majority of customers had less than a terabyte of data in total data storage. There were, of course, customers with huge amounts of data, but most organizations, even some fairly large enterprises, had moderate data sizes.</p><p>Customer data sizes followed a power-law distribution. The largest customer had double the storage of the next largest customer, the next largest customer had half of that, etc. So while there were customers with hundreds of petabytes of data, the sizes trailed off very quickly.  There were many thousands of customers who paid less than $10 a month for storage, which is half a terabyte. Among customers who were using the service heavily, the median data storage size was much less than 100 GB.</p><img alt="Customer size of data as power law distribution" sizes="90vw,
                        (min-width: 728px) 688px,
                        (min-width: 960px) 840px,
                        (min-width: 1302px) 816px," srcset="https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_4_d512a09905.jpg&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_4_d512a09905.jpg&amp;w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_4_d512a09905.jpg&amp;w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_4_d512a09905.jpg&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_4_d512a09905.jpg&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_4_d512a09905.jpg&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_4_d512a09905.jpg&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_4_d512a09905.jpg&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_4_d512a09905.jpg&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" loading="lazy"><p>We found further support for this when talking to industry analysts (Gartner, Forrester, etc). We would extol our ability to handle massive data sets, and they would shrug. “This is nice,” they said, “but the vast majority of enterprises have data warehouses smaller than a terabyte.” The general feedback we got talking to folks in the industry was that 100 GB was the right order of magnitude for a data warehouse. This is where we focused a lot of our efforts in benchmarking.</p><p>One of our investors decided to find out how big analytical data sizes really are and surveyed his portfolio companies, some which were post-exit (either had IPO’d or been acquired by larger organizations). These are tech companies, which are likely going to skew towards larger data sizes. He found that the largest B2B companies in his portfolio had around a terabyte of data, while the largest B2C companies had around 10 Terabytes of data. Most, however, had far less data.</p><p>In order to understand why large data sizes are rare, it is helpful to think about where the data actually comes from. Imagine you’re a medium sized business, with a thousand customers. Let’s say each one of your customers places a new order every day with a hundred line items. This is relatively frequent, but it is still probably less than a megabyte of data generated per day. In three years you would still only have a gigabyte, and it would take millenia to generate a terabyte.</p><p>Alternately, let’s say you have a million leads in your marketing database, and you’re running dozens of campaigns. Your leads table is probably still less than a gigabyte, and tracking each lead across each campaign still probably is only a few gigabytes. It is hard to see how this adds to massive data sets under reasonable scaling assumptions.</p><p>To give a concrete example, I worked at SingleStore in 2020-2022, when it was a fast-growing Series E company with significant revenue and a unicorn valuation. If you added up the size of our finance data warehouse, our customer data, our marketing campaign tracking, and our service logs, it was probably only a few gigabytes. By any stretch of the imagination, this is not big data.</p></section>
<section><h2 id="the-storage-bias-in-separation-of-storage-and-compute">The storage bias in separation of storage and compute.</h2><p>Modern cloud data platforms all separate storage and compute, which means that customers are not tied to a single form factor. This, more than scale out, is likely the single most important change in data architectures in the last 20 years. Instead of “shared nothing” architectures which are hard to manage in real world conditions, shared disk architectures let you grow your storage and your compute independently. The rise of scalable and reasonably fast object storage like S3 and GCS meant that you could relax a lot of the constraints on how you built a database.</p><p>In practice, data sizes increase much faster than compute sizes. While popular descriptions of the benefits of storage and compute separation make it sound like you may choose to scale either one at any time, the two axes are not really equivalent. Misunderstanding of this point leads to a lot of the discussion of Big Data, because techniques for dealing with large compute requirements are different from dealing with large data. It is helpful to explore why this may be the case.</p><img alt="compute power increasing faster than data sizes" sizes="90vw,
                        (min-width: 728px) 688px,
                        (min-width: 960px) 840px,
                        (min-width: 1302px) 816px," srcset="https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_5_81566ed0de.jpg&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_5_81566ed0de.jpg&amp;w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_5_81566ed0de.jpg&amp;w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_5_81566ed0de.jpg&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_5_81566ed0de.jpg&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_5_81566ed0de.jpg&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_5_81566ed0de.jpg&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_5_81566ed0de.jpg&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_5_81566ed0de.jpg&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" loading="lazy"><p>All large data sets are generated over time. Time is almost always an axis in a data set. New orders come in every day. New taxi rides. New logging records. New games being played. If a business is static, neither growing or shrinking, data will increase linearly with time. What does this mean for analytic needs? Clearly data storage needs will increase linearly, unless you decide to prune the data (more on this later). But compute needs will likely not need to change very much over time; most analysis is done over the recent data. Scanning old data is pretty wasteful; it doesn’t change, so why would you spend money reading it over and over again? True, you might want to keep it around just in case you want to ask a new question of the data, but it is pretty trivial to build aggregations containing the important answers.</p><p>Very often when a data warehousing customer moves from an environment where they didn’t have separation of storage and compute into one where they do have it, their storage usage grows tremendously, but their compute needs tend to not really change. In BigQuery, we had a customer who was one of the largest retailers in the world. They had an on-premise data warehouse that was around 100 TB of data. When they moved to the cloud, they ended up with 30 PB of data, a 300x increase. If their compute needs had also scaled up by a similar amount, they would have been spending billions of dollars on analytics. Instead, they spent a tiny fraction of that amount.</p><p>This bias towards storage size over compute size has a real impact in system architecture. It means that if you use scalable object stores, you might be able to use far less compute than you had anticipated. You might not even need to use distributed processing at all.</p></section>
<section><h2 id="workload-sizes-are-smaller-than-overall-data-sizes">Workload sizes are smaller than overall data sizes</h2><p>The amount of data processed for analytics workloads is almost certainly smaller than you think. Dashboards, for example, very often are built from aggregated data. People look at the last hour, or the last day, or the last week’s worth of data. Smaller tables tend to be queried more frequently, giant tables more selectively.</p><p>A couple of years ago I did an analysis of BigQuery queries, looking at customers spending more than $1000 / year. 90% of queries processed less than 100 MB of data. I sliced this a number of different ways to make sure it wasn’t just a couple of customers who ran a ton of queries skewing the results. I also cut out metadata-only queries, which are a small subset of queries in BigQuery that don’t need to read any data at all. You have to go pretty high on the percentile range until you get into the gigabytes, and there are very few queries that run in the terabyte range.</p><blockquote>
<p>Customers with giant data sizes almost never queried huge amounts of data</p>
</blockquote><p>Customers with moderate data sizes often did fairly large queries, but customers with giant data sizes almost never queried huge amounts of data. When they did, it was generally because they were generating a report, and performance wasn’t really a priority. A large social media company would run reports over the weekend to prepare for executives on Monday morning; those queries were pretty huge, but they were only a tiny fraction of the hundreds of thousands of queries they ran the rest of the week.</p><img alt="most query workloads are less than 10GB" sizes="90vw,
                        (min-width: 728px) 688px,
                        (min-width: 960px) 840px,
                        (min-width: 1302px) 816px," srcset="https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_6_b1fb1ad998.jpg&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_6_b1fb1ad998.jpg&amp;w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_6_b1fb1ad998.jpg&amp;w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_6_b1fb1ad998.jpg&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_6_b1fb1ad998.jpg&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_6_b1fb1ad998.jpg&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_6_b1fb1ad998.jpg&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_6_b1fb1ad998.jpg&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_6_b1fb1ad998.jpg&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" loading="lazy"><p>Even when querying giant tables, you rarely end up needing to process very much data. Modern analytical databases can do column projection to read only a subset of fields, and partition pruning to read only a narrow date range. They can often go even further with segment elimination to exploit locality in the data via clustering or automatic micro partitioning. Other tricks like computing over compressed data, projection, and predicate pushdown are ways that you can do less IO at query time. And less IO turns into less computation that needs to be done, which turns into lower costs and latency.</p><p>There are acute economic pressures incentivizing people to reduce the amount of data they process. Just because you can scale out and process something very fast doesn’t mean you can do so inexpensively. If you use a thousand nodes to get a result, that is probably going to cost you an arm and a leg. The Petabyte query I used to run on stage to show off BigQuery cost $5,000 at retail prices. Very few people would want to run something so expensive.</p><p>Note that the financial incentive to processing less data holds true even if you’re not using a pay-per-byte-scanned pricing model. If you have a Snowflake instance, if you can make your queries smaller, you can use a smaller instance, and pay less. Your queries will be faster, you can run more concurrently, and you generally will pay less over time.</p></section>
<section><h2 id="most-data-is-rarely-queried">Most data is rarely queried</h2><p>A huge percentage of the data that gets processed is less than 24 hours old. By the time data gets to be a week old, it is probably 20 times less likely to be queried than from the most recent day. After a month, data mostly just sits there. Historical data tends to be queries infrequently, perhaps when someone is running a rare report.</p><img alt="as data gets older, it's processed much less" sizes="90vw,
                        (min-width: 728px) 688px,
                        (min-width: 960px) 840px,
                        (min-width: 1302px) 816px," srcset="https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_7_c4ff57600f.jpg&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_7_c4ff57600f.jpg&amp;w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_7_c4ff57600f.jpg&amp;w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_7_c4ff57600f.jpg&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_7_c4ff57600f.jpg&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_7_c4ff57600f.jpg&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_7_c4ff57600f.jpg&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_7_c4ff57600f.jpg&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_7_c4ff57600f.jpg&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" loading="lazy"><p>Data storage age patterns are a lot flatter. While a lot of data gets discarded pretty quickly, a lot of data just gets appended to the end of tables. The most recent year might only have 30% of the data but 99% of data accesses. The most recent month might have 5% of data but 80% of data accesses.</p><p>The quiescing of data means that data working set sizes are more manageable than you would expect. If you have a petabyte table that has 10 years worth of data, you might rarely access any of the data older than the current day, which might have less than 50 GB compressed.</p></section>
<section><h2 id="the-big-data-frontier-keeps-receding">The Big Data Frontier keeps receding</h2><p>One definition of “Big Data” is “whatever doesn’t fit on a single machine.. By that definition, the number of workloads that qualify has been decreasing every year.</p><p>In 2004, when the Google MapReduce paper was written, it would have been very common for a data workload to not fit on a single commodity machine. Scaling up was expensive. In 2006, AWS launched EC2, and the only size of instance you could get was a single core and 2 GB of RAM. There were a lot of workloads that wouldn’t fit on that machine.</p><p>Today, however, a standard instance on AWS uses a physical server with 64 cores and 256 GB of RAM.  That’s two orders of magnitude more RAM. If you’re willing to spend a little bit more for a memory-optimized instance, you can get another two orders of magnitude of RAM. How many workloads need more than 24TB of RAM or 445 CPU cores?</p><img alt="single machines are capable of processing a much greater percentage of workloads as time goes on and technology advances" sizes="90vw,
                        (min-width: 728px) 688px,
                        (min-width: 960px) 840px,
                        (min-width: 1302px) 816px," srcset="https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_8_35f21f407c.jpg&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_8_35f21f407c.jpg&amp;w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_8_35f21f407c.jpg&amp;w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_8_35f21f407c.jpg&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_8_35f21f407c.jpg&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_8_35f21f407c.jpg&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_8_35f21f407c.jpg&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_8_35f21f407c.jpg&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://motherduck.com/_next/image/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fweb-assets-prod.motherduck.com%2Fassets%2Fimg%2Fimage_8_35f21f407c.jpg&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" loading="lazy"><p>It used to be that larger machines were a lot more expensive. However, in the cloud, a VM that uses a whole server only costs 8x more than one that uses an 8th of a server. Cost scales up linearly with compute power, up through some very large sizes. In fact, if you look at the benchmarks published in the original dremel paper using 3,000 parallel nodes, you can get similar performance on a single node today (more on this to come).</p></section>
<section><h2 id="data-is-a-liability">Data is a Liability</h2><p>An alternate definition of Big Data is “when the cost of keeping data around is less than the cost of figuring out what to throw away.” I like this definition because it encapsulates why people end up with Big Data. It isn’t because they need it; they just haven’t bothered to delete it. If you think about many data lakes that organizations collect, they fit this bill entirely: giant, messy swamps where no one really knows what they hold or whether it is safe to clean them up.</p><p>The cost of keeping data around is higher than just the cost to store the physical bytes. Under regulations like GDPR and CCPA, you are required to track all usage of certain types of data. Some data needs to be deleted within a certain period of time. If you have phone numbers in a parquet file that sit around for too long in your data lake somewhere, you may be violating statutory requirements.</p><p>Beyond regulation, data can be an aid to lawsuits against you. Just as many organizations enforce limited email retention policies in order to reduce potential liability, the data in your data warehouse can likewise be used against you. If you’ve got logs from five years ago that would show a security bug in your code or missed SLA, keeping old data around can prolong your legal exposure. There is a possibly apocryphal story I’ve heard about a company keeping its data analytics capabilities secret in order to prevent them from being used during a legal discovery process.</p><p>Code often suffers from what people call “bit rot” when it isn’t actively maintained. Data can suffer from the same type of problem; that is, people forget the precise meaning of specialized fields, or data problems from the past may have faded from memory. For example, maybe there was a short-lived data bug that set every customer id to null. Or there was a huge fraudulent transaction that made it look like Q3 2017 was a lot better than it actually was. Often business logic to pull out data from a historical time period can get more and more complicated. For example, there might be a rule like, “ if the date is older than 2019 use the revenue field, between 2019 and 2021 use the revenue_usd field, and after 2022 use the revenue_usd_audited field.” The longer you keep data around, the harder it is to keep track of these special cases. And not all of them can be easily worked around, especially if there is missing data.</p><p>If you are keeping around old data, it is good to understand why you are keeping it. Are you asking the same questions over and over again? If that is the case, wouldn’t it be far less expensive in terms of storage and query costs to just store aggregates? Are you keeping it for a rainy day? Are you thinking that there are new questions you might want to ask? If so, how important is it? How likely is it that you’ll really need it? Are you really just a data hoarder? These are all important questions to ask, especially as you try to figure out the true cost of keeping the data.</p></section>
<section><h2 id="are-you-in-the-big-data-one-percent">Are you in the BIg Data One Percent?</h2><p>Big Data is real, but most people may not need to worry about it. Some questions that you can ask to figure out if you’re a “Big Data One-Percenter”:</p><ul>
<li>Are you really generating a huge amount of data?</li>
<li>If so, do you really need to use a huge amount of data at once?</li>
<li>If so, is the data really too big to fit on one machine?</li>
<li>If so, are you sure you’re not just a data hoarder?</li>
<li>If so, are you sure you wouldn’t be better off summarizing?</li>
</ul><p>If you answer no to any of these questions, you might be a good candidate for a new generation of data tools that help you handle data at the size you actually have, not the size that people try to scare you into thinking that you might have someday.</p></section></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>