<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 21:30:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Senators strike bipartisan deal for ban on stock trading by members of Congress (107 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cnbc.com/2024/07/10/senators-strike-bipartisan-deal-for-a-ban-on-stock-trading-by-members-of-congress.html</link>
            <guid>40929679</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 18:08:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/07/10/senators-strike-bipartisan-deal-for-a-ban-on-stock-trading-by-members-of-congress.html">https://www.cnbc.com/2024/07/10/senators-strike-bipartisan-deal-for-a-ban-on-stock-trading-by-members-of-congress.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40929679">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="RegularArticle-ArticleBody-5" data-module="ArticleBody" data-test="articleBody-2" data-analytics="RegularArticle-articleBody-5-2"><div id="ArticleBody-InlineImage-108003954" data-test="InlineImage"><p>Senator Jeff Merkley (D-OR) speaks alongside members of the U.S. Senate Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs Committee during a news conference to discuss the details of the Ending Trading and Holdings in Congressional Stocks (ETHICS) Act at the U.S. Capitol in Washington, D.C., U.S., April 18, 2023.&nbsp;</p><p>Sarah Silbiger | Reuters</p></div><div><p>A bipartisan group of senators on Wednesday launched a renewed effort to ban members of <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2022/02/09/congress-moves-towards-banning-members-from-trading-stocks.html">Congress</a> from trading stock.</p><p>"Congress&nbsp;should not be here to make a buck," Sen. Josh Hawley, R-Mo., said at a press conference Wednesday on Capitol Hill. "There is no reason why members of&nbsp;Congress&nbsp;ought to be profiting off of the information that only they get."</p><p>The proposal is the latest chapter in a yearslong <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2021/12/15/house-speaker-nancy-pelosi-opposes-banning-stock-buys-by-congress-members.html">saga</a> in Congress to pass regulations that limit lawmakers' ability to buy and sell stocks, and the first one to get formal consideration by a Senate committee — in this case the Homeland Security &amp; Governmental Affairs&nbsp;Committee&nbsp;on July 24.</p><p>Ethics experts say that legislators' access to the kind of information they receive gives them the potential of having an unfair advantage to the investing public.</p><p>Wednesday's amendment to an existing stock trading ban bill would immediately forbid members of Congress, the president and the vice president from purchasing stocks and other covered investments. It would also give lawmakers 90 days to sell their stocks.</p><p>Sens. Hawley, Jon Ossoff, D-Ga., Jeff Merkley, D-Ore., and Gary Peters, D-Mich., negotiated and announced the new details.</p><p>If passed, the bill would also prohibit lawmakers' spouses and dependent children from trading stocks, beginning March 2027. Also starting that year, the U.S. president, vice president and all members of Congress would have to divest from any covered investments.</p><p>The penalty for violating the divestment mandate, as proposed by the senators, would cost a lawmaker&nbsp;the greater amount of&nbsp;either their monthly salary, or 10% of the value of each covered asset in violation.</p><p>The effort to bar members of Congress from trading stocks has been an uphill battle since at least the start of the Biden administration.</p><p>Ossoff first introduced a ban in 2021 and put his own stock portfolio in a blind trust as an example.</p><p>The effort was turbocharged by disclosures that several senators made very profitable trades in the early days of the Covid-19 pandemic, when members of Congress were getting classified briefings that warned of how disastrous the virus could be for the U.S. economy. The FBI launched insider trading investigations into three senators, but eventually ended the probe without making any charges.</p><p>The effort picked up more steam ahead of the 2022 midterm elections, after former Democratic House Speaker <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2021/12/15/house-speaker-nancy-pelosi-opposes-banning-stock-buys-by-congress-members.html">Nancy Pelosi</a> dropped her opposition to it.</p><p>Pelosi's husband is a multimillionaire investor Paul Pelosi, who regularly makes large and profitable stock trades. The then-speaker had previously written off the trading ban as a misguided effort to prevent lawmakers from participating in the "free market economy."</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Zed on Linux Is Here (336 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://zed.dev/linux</link>
            <guid>40928893</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 16:56:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://zed.dev/linux">https://zed.dev/linux</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40928893">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>To install Zed on most Linux distributions, run the shell script below.</p><div><div><p><a href="https://zed.dev/blog/zed-on-linux">Blog post →</a><a href="https://zed.dev/docs/linux">Docs →</a></p></div><div><pre><code>curl https://zed.dev/install.sh | sh</code></pre></div></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Weird things I learned while writing an x86 emulator (189 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.timdbg.com/posts/useless-x86-trivia/</link>
            <guid>40927438</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 14:42:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.timdbg.com/posts/useless-x86-trivia/">https://www.timdbg.com/posts/useless-x86-trivia/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40927438">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div><p>If you’ve read my <a href="https://www.timdbg.com/posts/fakers-guide-to-assembly">first post about assembly language</a>, you might expect that this is another post on how to understand assembly language. I will write more about that at some point, but this post is not that. Instead, this post is going to talk about some of the weird things and random trivia I learned while writing an x86 and amd64 emulator. The emulator I wrote was for <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows-hardware/drivers/debugger/time-travel-debugging-overview">Time Travel Debugging</a>. One piece of TTD is a CPU emulator, which is used to record the entire execution of a process at an instruction level. The first version of TTD was called iDNA, and the emulator for iDNA was written almost completely in assembly code, which was fast but difficult to maintain and extend.</p><p>I wasn’t involved in the first version of TTD, but I was involved in the second version where we rewrote the emulation portion (and eventually most other parts). The new one was written in C++, and we aimed to achieve most of the performance of the assembly language version while having a more maintainable code base. Writing a CPU emulator is, in my opinion, the best way to <em>REALLY</em> understand how a CPU works. You need to pay attention to every detail. This post is a somewhat random collection of the things I learned. If you have a lot of experience with x86 these might be old news, but maybe a few are things you haven’t seen before.</p><h2 id="useless-x86-encoding-trivia">Useless x86 encoding trivia</h2><p>The x86 encoding scheme is a bit funny in that there are often multiple ways to encode the exact same instruction. The <code>int 3</code> instruction can be encoded as <code>CD 03</code>, but can also be encoded in a single byte of <code>CC</code>. This is a very useful encoding because <code>int 3</code> is used as a software breakpoint. That way, it’s always possible to set a breakpoint at any point in a function, even if it’s an instruction that lands at the end of a memory page (with no page mapped after it). Many of these alternate encodings are designed to be shorter for some common case. For instance, adding an immediate value to <code>EAX</code> or <code>RAX</code> with the <code>ADD</code> instruction can be expressed in a compact form that’s shorter than the more general instruction. An <code>add eax, ...</code> instruction can be encoded like this:</p><pre tabindex="0"><code>05cccccccc      add     eax,0CCCCCCCCh
</code></pre><p>Doing the same for ECX takes an extra byte:</p><pre tabindex="0"><code>81c1cccccccc    add     ecx,0CCCCCCCCh
</code></pre><p>So while both registers are general purpose, the fact that <code>EAX</code> is called the “Accumulator register” is not just a convention, it actually makes a difference to the encoding (and potentially the performance, as a result). Compilers tend to be very smart, and can take advantage of these shorter encodings whenever possible. Shorter instructions mean less data transferred from main memory, and more instructions that can fit in the instruction cache, which is good for performance.</p><p>There are other ways to have equivalent instructions besides just alternate encodings. Instructions in x86 can take “prefix bytes” which modify the behavior of the instruction. The “REX” set of prefixes are commonly used in 64 bit code to access a wider range of registers compared to 32-bit code (and make code sequences <a href="https://www.timdbg.com/posts/recognizing-patterns">easier to recognize</a>). An x86 CPU will happily take one of these prefixes, even if it doesn’t have any effect. Put a “REX” byte on an 8-bit add, and it does nothing:</p><pre tabindex="0"><code>4004cc          add     al,0CCh
</code></pre><p>In fact, you can put TWO of these prefixes on. Many disassemblers (including the one in WinDbg) will get confused, but the CPU will execute it just fine:</p><pre tabindex="0"><code>0:000&gt; rrax=0
0:000&gt; u . L2
00007ff8`22160950 40              ???
00007ff8`22160951 4004cc          add     al,0CCh
0:000&gt; t
00007ff8`22160954 cc              int     3
0:000&gt; rrax
rax=00000000000000cc
</code></pre><p>Can we add as many prefixes as we want? You can add quite a few until you get to 15 bytes<sup>1</sup>. This length is a hard limit on current x86-compatible CPUs. Any instruction longer than 15 bytes is considered invalid and will generate an exception.</p><p>There are also some other weird prefixes that you might not know about. The “Address override” prefix can be used to reference a 32-bit address when running in 64-bit mode.</p><pre tabindex="0"><code>488d0424        lea     rax,[rsp]
67488d0424      lea     rax,[esp] # Note the extra '0x67' prefix
</code></pre><p>And when running 32-bit code, it will switch the address mode to 16-bit addresses! I don’t know that I’ve ever seen a compiler generate code like that, but it’s there. Something interesting to note, however, is that disassembling or interpreting these bytes correctly relies on knowing the default operand size and address size of a code segment (which can be <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Segment_descriptor">configured by the kernel</a>). If we disassemble the same bytes in 32-bit mode and 64-bit mode, we can get different results.</p><p>In 32-bit mode:</p><pre tabindex="0"><code>8b0424          mov     eax,dword ptr [esp]
</code></pre><p>In 64-bit mode:</p><pre tabindex="0"><code>8b0424          mov     eax,dword ptr [rsp]
</code></pre><p>It’s not just address sizes either. The entire range that was previous dedicated to <code>INC reg</code> and <code>DEC reg</code> on x86 (40-4F) is now used for the <a href="https://twitter.com/ivanrouzanov/status/1616933010707972097">REX prefix bytes</a> on x64!</p><p>In 32-bit mode, we have this:</p><pre tabindex="0"><code>48              dec     eax
030424          add     eax,dword ptr [esp]
</code></pre><p>But in 64-bit mode, those two instructions have merged to form a single instruction!</p><pre tabindex="0"><code>48030424        add     rax,qword ptr [rsp]
</code></pre><p>The encoding space used by <code>INC</code> and <code>DEC</code> was quite large, so it’s understandable why the AMD64 designers decided to use these bytes for the new prefixes to expand the register set in 64 bit mode. There was already a different encoding for these instructions that supported both registers and memory locations, so nothing was really lost (except a slightly larger encoding for a somewhat infrequent instruction).</p><p>I’ll also note that due to this peculiarity and due to the fact that WinDbg will always assemble instructions as if they are in 32-bit mode, trying to assemble an “INC reg” instruction will always fail, because it will generate the single byte form which is actually a REX prefix.</p><pre tabindex="0"><code>0:000&gt; a. 
00007ff8`4bfc0950 inc eax
00007ff8`4bfc0951 
0:000&gt; u .
ntdll!LdrpDoDebuggerBreak+0x30:
00007ff8`4bfc0950 40eb00          jmp     ntdll!LdrpDoDebuggerBreak+0x33 (00007ff8`4bfc0953)
</code></pre><p>The <code>inc eax</code> here got turned into a useless REX prefix modifying the next instruction, instead of actually being an <code>inc</code> instruction.</p><h2 id="odd-flag-quirks">Odd flag quirks</h2><p>Speaking of <code>INC</code> and <code>DEC</code>, there’s a slightly odd aspect of these instructions that’s worth noting. You might thing that <code>INC EAX</code> does the same thing as <code>ADD EAX, 1</code>, but they are slightly different. An <code>ADD</code> instruction will update the carry flag but the <code>INC</code> instruction does not! This is an easy thing to miss, and when writing the TTD emulator I got this wrong initially, until I caught it with some unit tests.</p><p>There are a few other outliers worth mentioning. Most arithmetic and logical operations will set the overflow, sign, zero, auxiliary carry, parity, and carry flags. That includes the <code>CMPXCHG</code> (compare and exchange) instruction. Interestingly, it does not include the <code>CMPXCHG8B</code>/<code>CMPXCHG16B</code> instructions, which will only modify the zero flag. Weird, right?</p><p>Other instructions leave some of the flags in an undefined state, although in some cases they are <em>conditionally</em> undefined. The shift and rotate instructions leave the overflow flag undefined if the shift amount was more than one. It seems that the actual behavior of the undefined flags is related to the internal implementation of the shift operation, and is different between different architectures. I’ve heard that the Atom line of CPUs used a cheaper/slower way of doing bit shifts in the ALU, which results in the undefined flags having different values, although I haven’t tested this myself.</p><h2 id="more-surprises-with-shift-instructions">More surprises with shift instructions</h2><p>Consider this instruction:</p><pre tabindex="0"><code>66c1e810        shr     ax,10h
</code></pre><p>This instruction is to shift the <code>ax</code> register by 16 bits. Since this is a 16 bit register, it will clear the register to zero. Now consider this instruction:</p><pre tabindex="0"><code>c1e820          shr     eax,20h
</code></pre><p>This instruction says that it will shift the eax register 0x20 (32 decimal) bits to the right. Since this is a 32 bit register, you might think that it will clear the <code>eax</code> register. In reality, the value of eax is unchanged! If you read the details of this instruction in the Intel SDM, you’ll see that the count is masked against 1FH, essentially using only the lowest five bits of the rotation.<sup>2</sup> If the <code>REX.W</code> prefix is used, the mask will be 3FH, meaning the maximum shift is 63 bits.</p><h2 id="segment-overrides">Segment overrides</h2><p>While segmented memory might make you think we are back in the days of 16-bit code, it turns out that segments are alive and well in 32-bit and 64-bit code, and they can have real effects. We tend not to think about them very much because for the most part every OS uses a mostly-flat memory model and all of the segments have a base address of 0.<sup>3</sup> The exception to this tends to be for thread local storage, where one of the “extra segment registers” is used, either <code>FS</code> or <code>GS</code> (or both).</p><p><del>What can complicate things is the fact that usermode code doesn’t have access to the CPU configuration that determines the base address of the FS or GS segments. So if you want to know what flat address corresponds to <code>GS:0x12345678</code>, there’s no way to determine that directly unless the OS has a way of querying this information.</del></p><p><strong>CORRECTION</strong>: <a href="https://twitter.com/sixtyvividtails/status/1621532553873080322">Sixtyvividtails points out</a> that you can read the base of fs/gs segs using the rdfsbase/wrfsbase/rdgsbase/wrgsbase instructions, which are available in unprivileged code. These instructions are available starting on Ivy Bridge (from 2012). Thanks for the correction, sixtyvividtails!</p><p>On Windows, these registers are used for referring to the TEB (Thread Execution Block), and these structures conveniently have a “self” pointer with a flat address to the start of the structure, which also happens to be the base of the segment.</p><p>In 32-bit processes, the TEB is located using <code>FS</code>. We can see how the OS does this by looking at the disassembly of the GetLastError function, which simply accesses a field out of the TEB.</p><pre tabindex="0"><code>0:000&gt; u kernelbase!GetLastError
KERNELBASE!GetLastError:
773e4080 64a118000000    mov     eax,dword ptr fs:[00000018h]   # Grab the TEB.NtTib.Self
773e4086 8b4034          mov     eax,dword ptr [eax+34h]        # Grab the "LastErrorValue" field out of the TEB
773e4089 c3              ret
</code></pre><p>Looking at this using public symbols, you can see what those offsets correspond to:</p><pre tabindex="0"><code>0:000&gt; dt -r1 _TEB
ntdll!_TEB
   +0x000 NtTib            : _NT_TIB
      +0x000 ExceptionList    : Ptr32 _EXCEPTION_REGISTRATION_RECORD
...
      +0x018 Self             : Ptr32 _NT_TIB
   +0x01c EnvironmentPointer : Ptr32 Void
...
   +0x034 LastErrorValue   : Uint4B
</code></pre><p>In 64-bit processes, the TEB is located using <code>GS</code>:</p><pre tabindex="0"><code>0:000&gt; u kernelbase!GetLastError
KERNELBASE!GetLastError:
00007ff8`4960cd60 65488b042530000000 mov   rax,qword ptr gs:[30h]
00007ff8`4960cd69 8b4068          mov     eax,dword ptr [rax+68h]
00007ff8`4960cd6c c3              ret
</code></pre><p>It might seem odd that that 64-bit processes use a different segment register for the TEB than a 32-bit process, but there is a very good reason for this. A 32-bit process on a 64-bit OS will have both a 32-bit TEB <em>and</em> a 64-bit TEB, and in some contexts it can be useful to have access to both TEBs (such as the 64-bit WOW code that runs in a 32-bit process).</p><h2 id="segment-overrides-more-trivia">Segment overrides: More trivia</h2><p>I mentioned earlier that the base address of the FS segment and GS segment is determined by CPU configuration. You might be wondering “what CPU configuration?” And the answer is “it depends”. Specifically, it depends on whether you’re in 32-bit mode or 64-bit mode. In 32-bit mode, the actual value of the segment register is used to reference a segment descriptor (defined by the <a href="https://wiki.osdev.org/Global_Descriptor_Table">Global Descriptor Table</a> and <a href="https://wiki.osdev.org/Local_Descriptor_Table">Local Descriptor Table</a>). But in 64-bit mode, the base is controlled by two MSRs, the FS Base (IA32_FS_BASE in the Intel SDM) and GS Base (IA32_GS_BASE). A side effect of this scheme is that the actual value of FS and GS don’t matter at all in 64-bit mode. You can see the effect of this in WinDbg by trying to directly read from something in one of those segments. When debugging a 32-bit process, you can dump the contents of the “FS segment” by using the value of the FS register:</p><pre tabindex="0"><code>0:000&gt; rfs
fs=00000053
0:000&gt; db 53:0
0053:00000000  60 f2 2f 03 00 00 30 03-00 30 20 03 00 00 00 00 `./...0..0 .....
</code></pre><p>If you try the same thing on a 64-bit process, it doesn’t work because the segment values don’t matter, only the segment override prefixes!</p><pre tabindex="0"><code>0:000&gt; rfs
fs=0053
0:000&gt; db 53:0
0053:00000000`00000000  ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ??-?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ??  ????????????????
0:000&gt; rgs
gs=002b
0:000&gt; db 2b:0
002b:00000000`00000000  ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ??-?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ??  ????????????????
</code></pre><h2 id="roll-credits">Roll credits</h2><p>This turned out to be a pretty random list of x86 trivia. Most of it totally useless unless you want to write an emulator (which I <em>highly</em> recommend if you ever get the chance). I still think it’s sort of interesting, and gives a little bit of insight into how things “really work”. Some of this I learned through trial and error, but I had some great mentors while writing an x86 emulator, one of whom was Darek Mihocka, who has been doing emulators long enough that he owns <a href="http://emulators.com/">emulators.com</a>. I’d never claim to be an expert myself, but if this sort of thing is interesting to you make sure to check out the fantastic resources on <a href="https://www.agner.org/optimize/">Agner Fog’s website</a>. As usual, if I made any mistakes or if you have any questions, let me know on <a href="https://twitter.com/timmisiak">Twitter</a> or <a href="https://dbg.social/@tim">Mastodon</a>!</p><p><sup>1</sup> There are some other limits on prefixes on older CPUs, but the 15 byte limit applies even on newer CPUs. Besides the length limitation, some prefixes are also more strict about when they can be used, such as the <code>LOCK</code> prefix (F0)</p><p><sup>2</sup> This actually came up in an interview question at Microsoft. My interviewer was asking me all the ways you could clear a 32-bit register in a single instruction. He was convinced that using a shift would work and didn’t believe me when I said it wasn’t possible.</p><p><sup>3</sup> When executing in 64-bit mode, the segment base of CS, DS, ES, and SS are always treated as 0 by the CPU.</p></div></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Vision language models are blind (214 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://vlmsareblind.github.io/</link>
            <guid>40926734</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 13:35:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://vlmsareblind.github.io/">https://vlmsareblind.github.io/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40926734">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
  
  <div>
            <h2>
              Vision language models are blind <i></i>
            </h2>
            <div>
              <p><span>

                <span>
                  
                  <p><span><sup>*</sup>Equal contribution</span>
                  </p>
                  <p><span><sup>1</sup>Auburn University,</span>
                    <span><sup>2</sup>University of Alberta,</span>
                  </p>
                </span>


            </span></p></div>
            
            

            
          </div>

  <div>
          <h2>Abstract</h2>
          <p>
              Large language models with vision capabilities (VLMs), e.g., <span>GPT-<span>4o</span></span> and <span>Gemini-<span>1.5</span>
                Pro</span> are
              powering countless image-text processing applications and scoring high on existing vision-understanding
              benchmarks.
              Yet, we find that VLMs fail on 7 visual tasks <em>absurdly easy</em> to humans such as identifying (a)
              whether two
              circles overlap; (b) whether two lines intersect; (c) which letter is being circled in a word; and (d)
              counting the
              number of circles in an Olympic-like logo.
              The shockingly poor performance of four state-of-the-art VLMs suggests their vision is, at best, like that
              of a person
              with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Myopia" target="_blank">myopia</a> seeing fine details as
              blurry, and at
              worst, like an intelligent person who is blind making
              educated
              guesses.
            </p>
        </div>

  

  






  <!-- TASK 1 Begins -->
  <div id="task1">
      <h2>Task 1: Counting line intersections <img src="https://vlmsareblind.github.io/static/images/logo/two_lines.svg" alt="Two intersecting lines"></h2>

      <div>
        <p>
          Given the impressive accuracy of VLMs on answering questions on diagrams and charts (e.g., <span>Sonnet-<span>3.5</span></span> scoring 94.7% on AI2D and 90.8% on
          ChartQA) <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.10244">[1]</a>, a reasonable hypothesis is that VLMs must be able
          to see whether two graphs
          intersect in a
          chart. Here, we test this hypothesis by asking VLMs to count the number of intersections between two 2-segment
          piece-wise linear functions.
        </p>

        <h3>Images</h3>
        <p>
          We create 150 images (see Figure 1) of 2D line plots drawn on a white canvas. Each line plot consists of two
          line
          segments, defined by three points whose x-coordinates are fixed and equally spaced. The y-coordinates are
          randomly
          sampled to create two plots that intersect at exactly 0, 1 or 2 points. See Appendix A for more details.
        </p>

        
        <figcaption>Fig. 1: Examples of 2D line plots used in the task, showing different numbers of intersections.
        </figcaption>

        <h3>Prompts</h3>
        <div>
          <p>
            We ask each question using two different wordings:
          </p>
          <ol>
            <li><em>"How many times do the blue and red line plots cross each other?"</em></li>
            <li><em>"How many times do the blue and red lines intersect?"</em></li>
          </ol>

          <h3>Groundtruth</h3>
          <p>
              Answers are ∈ {0, 1, 2} (random-baseline accuracy: 33%).
            </p>




          <h2>Results</h2>
          <p>
            The following table shows the performance of the four models on the task of counting line intersections.
          </p>

          <table>
            <tbody><tr>
              <th>Thickness</th>
              <th>
                <p><span>GPT-<span>4o</span></span>
                </p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p><span>Gemini-<span>1.5</span> Pro</span>
                </p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p><span>Sonnet-<span>3</span></span>
                </p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p><span>Sonnet-<span>3.5</span></span>
                </p>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>2</td>
              <td>45.00</td>
              <td>70.00</td>
              <td>64.00</td>
              <td>80.00</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>3</td>
              <td>47.00</td>
              <td>68.00</td>
              <td>66.00</td>
              <td>79.00</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>4</td>
              <td>54.00</td>
              <td>71.00</td>
              <td>62.00</td>
              <td>73.00</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td><strong>Average</strong></td>
              <td>48.67</td>
              <td>69.67</td>
              <td>64.00</td>
              <td>77.33</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody></table>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <h2>Qualitative samples</h2>
        <div>
          
          <figcaption>Fig. 2: VLMs cannot reliably count the intersections.</figcaption>
        </div>
  </div></div>
  <!-- TASK 1 Ends -->

  <hr>
  <!-- TASK 2 Begins -->
  <div id="task2">

      <h2>Task 2: Two circles <img src="https://vlmsareblind.github.io/static/images/logo/two-colored-circles-svg.svg" alt="Two intersecting lines"></h2>



      <div>
        <p>
          In contrast to Task 1 where we tested VLMs on thin lines, here we evaluate their ability to perceive
          interactions
          between larger objects - specifically, two same-sized filled circles. This task assesses VLMs' capability to
          detect
          (1) small gaps between circles and (2) overlapping circles.
        </p>

        <h3>Images</h3>
        <p>
          We generate 672 images of two circles on a white canvas. The circles vary in size, distance, and orientation:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>Circle diameters: 1/4, 1/5, 1/6, or 1/7 of the canvas size</li>
          <li>Distances between circle perimeters: -0.15 to 0.5 times the diameter</li>
          <li>Orientations: 90°, 0°, -45°, and 45° angles with the x-axis</li>
          <li>Canvas sizes: 384, 769, and 1155 pixels</li>
        </ul>

        
        <figcaption>Fig. 3: Examples of two-circle images used in the task, showing different configurations.
        </figcaption>
      </div>

      <h3>Prompts</h3>
      <div>
        <p>
          We ask each question using two different wordings:
        </p>
        <ol>
          <li><em>"Are the two circles touching each other? Answer with Yes/No."</em></li>
          <li><em>"Are the two circles overlapping? Answer with Yes/No."</em></li>
        </ol>

        <h3>Groundtruth</h3>
        <div>
          <p>
            Answers are based on the distance d between circle perimeters:
          </p>
          <ul>
            <li>d &lt; 0: Overlapping and touching</li>
            <li>d = 0: Non-overlapping but touching</li>
            <li>d &gt; 0: Non-overlapping and non-touching</li>
          </ul>
          <p>Random-baseline accuracy: 50%.</p>
        </div>




        <h2>Results</h2>
        <p>
          The following table shows the performance of the four models on the task of counting line intersections.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tbody><tr>
            <th></th>
            <th>
              <p><span>GPT-<span>4o</span></span>
              </p>
            </th>
            <th>
              <p><span>Gemini-<span>1.5</span> Pro</span>
              </p>
            </th>
            <th>
              <p><span>Sonnet-<span>3</span></span>
              </p>
            </th>
            <th>
              <p><span>Sonnet-<span>3.5</span></span>
              </p>
            </th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Overlapping</td>
            <td>71.27</td>
            <td>93.30</td>
            <td>88.09</td>
            <td>88.83</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Touching</td>
            <td>74.10</td>
            <td>92.26</td>
            <td>80.95</td>
            <td>94.49</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><strong>Average</strong></td>
            <td>72.69</td>
            <td>92.78</td>
            <td>84.52</td>
            <td>91.66</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody></table>

        <h2>Qualitative samples</h2>
      </div>

      <div>
          
          <figcaption>Fig. 4: VLMs consistently fail at smaller distances. However, at a large gap, <span>GPT-<span>4o</span></span> remains unreliable (rightmost). <span>Sonnet-<span>3.5</span></span> tends to conservatively answer "No"
            regardless of the actual distance
            between the two circles.</figcaption>
        </div>
  </div>
  <!-- TASK 2 Ends -->

  <hr>
  <!-- TASK 3 Begins -->
  <div id="task3">

      <h2>Task 3: The circled letter <img src="https://vlmsareblind.github.io/static/images/logo/acknowledgement-svg.svg" alt="Two intersecting lines"></h2>



      <div>
        <p>
          Consistent with prior reports <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.06712">[2]</a><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.11441">[3]</a><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.17421">[4]</a>, we find
          that VLMs can
          100%
          accurately identify a primitive shape (e.g., a red circle ⭕)<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.06712">[2]</a>
          and can perfectly read an English word (e.g.,
          <span>Subdermatoglyphic</span>) alone. Here, we superimposed the red circle on every
          letter, one at a time, in the word,
          and ask
          VLMs to identify which letter is being circled. While the task is easy to humans, our hypothesis is that if a
          VLM's
          vision is "blurry", it might not be able to identify the exact letter being circled since there is tiny
          spacing
          between the adjacent letters.
        </p>

        <h3>Images</h3>
        <p>
          We choose three strings <span>Acknowledgement</span>, <span>Subdermatoglyphic</span>, and tHyUiKaRbNqWeOpXcZvM because they contain
          characters
          of variable widths and heights. Furthermore, all four tested VLMs can read out all characters in these strings
          when
          they are input to the models as an image. While <span>Acknowledgement</span> is a common
          English word, <span>Subdermatoglyphic</span> is
          the
          longest word without repetitive letters. We also test VLMs on the random string <span>tHyUiKaRbNqWeOpXcZvM</span> to
          estimate how
          much model accuracy is due to its familiarity with the word.
        </p>
        <p>
          For each (string, circled-letter) pair, we render a 512×512 image by choosing among 3 red oval line-thickness
          levels,
          2 font sizes, and 4 random positions in the canvas for a total of 24 images. That is, we generate 360, 408,
          and 480
          images for <span>Acknowledgement</span> (15 letters), <span>Subdermatoglyphic</span> (17 letters), and
          <span>tHyUiKaRbNqWeOpXcZvM</span> (20
          letters),
          respectively. We ensure each letter to be circled fits completely the oval.
        </p>

        
        <figcaption>Fig. 5: Examples of circled letter images used in the task, showing different words and circled
          letters.
        </figcaption>
      </div>

      <h3>Prompts</h3>
      <div>
        <p>
          We ask each question using two different wordings:
        </p>
        <ol>
          <li><em>"Which letter is being circled?"</em></li>
          <li><em>"Which character is being highlighted with a red oval?"</em></li>
        </ol>

        <h3>Groundtruth</h3>
        <p>
            Letters need to match predicted letters exactly (case-insensitive).
          </p>




        <h2>Results</h2>
        <p>
          The following table shows the performance of the four models on the task of identifying the circled letter.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tbody><tr>
            <th>Word</th>
            <th>
              <p><span>GPT-<span>4o</span></span>
              </p>
            </th>
            <th>
              <p><span>Gemini-<span>1.5</span> Pro</span>
              </p>
            </th>
            <th>
              <p><span>Sonnet-<span>3</span></span>
              </p>
            </th>
            <th>
              <p><span>Sonnet-<span>3.5</span></span>
              </p>
            </th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><span>Acknowledgement</span></td>
            <td>69.03</td>
            <td>97.50</td>
            <td>82.64</td>
            <td>91.11</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><span>Subdermatoglyphic</span></td>
            <td>63.60</td>
            <td>91.05</td>
            <td>71.45</td>
            <td>94.49</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><span>tHyUiKaRbNqWeOpXcZvM</span></td>
            <td>77.92</td>
            <td>89.90</td>
            <td>65.94</td>
            <td>82.08</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><strong>Average</strong></td>
            <td>70.18</td>
            <td>92.81</td>
            <td>73.34</td>
            <td>89.22</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody></table>
      </div>
      <div>
        <h2>Qualitative samples</h2>
        <div>
          
          <figcaption>Fig. 6: Identifying the letter being circled is non-trivial for VLMs across both English words
            (<span>Acknowledgement</span> &amp; <span>Subdermatoglyphic</span>)
            and a random string
            (<span>tHyUiKaRbNqWeOpXcZvM</span>). When making mistakes, VLMs
            tend to
            predict letters adjacent to the circled one.</figcaption>

        </div>
      </div>
  </div>
  <!-- TASK 3 Ends -->



  <hr>
  <!-- TASK 4 Begins -->
  <div id="task4">

      <h2>Task 4: Counting overlapping shapes <img src="https://vlmsareblind.github.io/static/images/logo/olympic-rings-svg.svg" alt="Two intersecting lines"></h2>



      <div>
        <p>
          Aligned with prior research <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.17421">[4]</a>, we also find VLMs to be able
          to count disjoint circles. Yet, here, we test
          VLMs on
          counting circles that are <em>intersecting</em> like in the Olympic logo—a common cognitive development
          exercise for
          preschoolers <a href="https://www.myteachingstation.com/preschool/math/numbers/count-shapes-printables">[5]</a><a href="https://depositphotos.com/vector/how-many-counting-game-with-color-simple-geometric-shapes-for-kids-educational-maths-task-for-266096226.html">[6]</a>.
          Our hypothesis is that a "blurry" vision may not see the
          intersection between two circles
          clearly
          and therefore unable to trace circles and count them. For generalization of our findings, we repeat the
          experiment
          with pentagons as well.
        </p>

        <h3>Images</h3>
        <p>
          In an image of size C×C, where C ∈ {384, 769, 1155}px, we draw N ∈ {5, 6, 7, 8, 9} overlapping, same-sized
          circles
          arranged in two rows like the Olympic logo. A circle diameter φ ∈ {C/5, C/10}. We repeat the images with two
          different
          line thickness for rendering circles. This procedure renders 3 resolutions × 5 × 2 diameters = 60 images. We
          repeat
          for pentagons in addition to circles, resulting in 60 × 2 shapes = 120 images in total. For pentagons, their
          side
          length d ∈ {C/5, C/10}.
        </p>


        
        <figcaption>Fig. 7: Examples of Olympic-like logo images used in the task, showing different numbers of shapes,
          sizes,
          and colors.</figcaption>
      </div>

      <h3>Prompts</h3>
      <div>
        <p>
          We ask each question using two different wordings:
        </p>
        <ol>
          <li><em>"How many {shapes} are in the image? Answer with only the number in numerical format."</em></li>
          <li><em>"Count the {shapes} in the image. Answer with a number in curly brackets e.g. {3}."</em></li>
        </ol>
        <p>
          Where {shapes} is either "circles" or "pentagons" depending on the image.
        </p>
        <h3>Groundtruth</h3>
        <p>
            Answers are ∈ {5, 6, 7, 8, 9} (random-baseline accuracy: 20%).
          </p>


        <h2>Results</h2>
        <p>
          The following table shows the performance of the four models on the task of identifying the circled letter.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tbody><tr>
            <th></th>
            <th>
              <p><span>GPT-<span>4o</span></span>
              </p>
            </th>
            <th>
              <p><span>Gemini-<span>1.5</span> Pro</span>
              </p>
            </th>
            <th>
              <p><span>Sonnet-<span>3</span></span>
              </p>
            </th>
            <th>
              <p><span>Sonnet-<span>3.5</span></span>
              </p>
            </th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Circles</td>
            <td>42.50</td>
            <td>20.83</td>
            <td>31.66</td>
            <td>44.16</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Pentagons</td>
            <td>19.16</td>
            <td>9.16</td>
            <td>11.66</td>
            <td>75.83</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody></table>

      </div>

      <div>
        <h2>Qualitative samples</h2>

        <div>
          
          <figcaption>Fig. 8: <span>Gemini-<span>1.5</span>
              Pro</span> often predicts "5" circles.</figcaption>

        </div>
      </div>
  </div>
  <!-- TASK 4 Ends -->



  <hr>
  <!-- TASK 5 Begins -->
  <div id="task5">


      <h2>Task 5: Counting the nested squares <img src="https://vlmsareblind.github.io/static/images/logo/nested-squares-svg.svg" alt="Two intersecting lines"></h2>


      <div>
        <p>
          Motivated by the findings that VLMs struggle in counting the intersected circles (Task 4), here, we arrange
          the shapes
          differently so that their edges do <em>not</em> intersect.
          That is, each shape is nested entirely inside another. For completeness, we test squares in this task.
        </p>

        <h3>Images</h3>
        <p>
          In a canvas of size C×C, we render N ∈ {2, 3, 4, 5} nested squares.
          The outermost square is rendered first using a random edge length d and a line thickness ∈ {2, 3, 4}px.
          The remaining N-1 squares are drawn using a size reduction factor, 0.75 × d and placed at a random coordinate
          that
          ensures they do not touch outer squares.
          For each line thickness, we generate 10 images (where squares have different, random locations) to create 3 ×
          10 = 30
          images.
          Repeating the process for all N values results in 4 × 30 = 120 images.
        </p>
        
        <figcaption>Fig. 9: Examples of nested square images used in the task, showing different numbers of squares.
        </figcaption>
      </div>

      <h3>Prompts</h3>
      <div>
        <p>
          We ask each question using the following wording:
        </p>
        <ol>
          <li><em>"Count the total number of squares in the image."</em></li>
        </ol>
        <p>
          Where {shapes} is either "circles" or "pentagons" depending on the image.
        </p>
        <h3>Groundtruth</h3>
        <p>
            Answers are ∈ {2, 3, 4, 5} (random-baseline accuracy: 25%).
          </p>


        <h2>Results</h2>
        <p>
          The following table shows the performance of the four models on the task of counting nested squares.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tbody><tr>
            <th></th>
            <th>
              <p><span>GPT-<span>4o</span></span>
              </p>
            </th>
            <th>
              <p><span>Gemini-<span>1.5</span> Pro</span>
              </p>
            </th>
            <th>
              <p><span>Sonnet-<span>3</span></span>
              </p>
            </th>
            <th>
              <p><span>Sonnet-<span>3.5</span></span>
              </p>
            </th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Squares</td>
            <td>48.33</td>
            <td>80.00</td>
            <td>55.00</td>
            <td>87.50</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody></table>

      </div>

      <div>

        <h2>Qualitative samples</h2>
        <div>
          
          <figcaption>Fig. 10: Only <span>Sonnet-<span>3.5</span></span> can count
            the
            squares in a majority of the images.</figcaption>
        </div>
      </div>
  </div>
  <!-- TASK 5 Ends -->




  <hr>
  <!-- TASK 6 Begins -->
  <div id="task6">

      <h2>Task 6: Counting the rows and columns of a grid <img src="https://vlmsareblind.github.io/static/images/logo/grid-3x4-svg.svg" alt="Two intersecting lines"></h2>


      <div>
        <p>
          The results from prior tasks show VLMs cannot always count shapes that are overlapping (Task 4) or nested
          (Task 5).
          What about adjacent shapes? Here, we tile up shapes (specifically, squares) into a grid and challenge VLMs to
          count—a
          task that is supposedly simple to VLMs given their remarkable performance (≥ 90% accuracy) on DocVQA, which
          includes
          many questions with tables.
          To simplify the task, we ask models to count the number of rows and columns in a given table.
        </p>

        <h3>Images</h3>
        <p>
          A grid may have N×N, N×N', or N'×N cells, where N∈{3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9} and N' = N + 1.
          Each grid is rendered with two different line-thicknesses on a canvas of size C×C where C∈{500, 1250, 2000}px.
          Besides empty grids, we also replicate the procedure to make grids contain text (which is more common in
          real-world
          tables) where each cell contains a single random word.
          Two versions combined have 2×222 = 444 images.
        </p>
        
        <figcaption>Fig. 9: Examples of grid images used in the task, showing text-filled and empty grids with various
          dimensions.</figcaption>
      </div>

      <h3>Prompts</h3>
      <div>
        <p>
          We ask each question using two different wordings:
        </p>
        <ol>
          <li><em>"Count the number of rows and columns and answer with numbers in curly brackets. For example, rows={5}
              columns={6}"</em></li>
          <li><em>"How many rows and columns are in the table? Answer with only the numbers in a pair (row, column),
              e.g.,
              (5,6)"</em></li>
        </ol>

        <h3>Groundtruth</h3>
        <p>
            Answers include both the number of rows and columns. An answer is correct when both column and row counts
            are
            correctly predicted.
          </p>

        <h2>Results</h2>
        <p>
          The following table shows the performance of the four models on the task of counting rows and columns in
          grids.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tbody><tr>
            <th>Grid type</th>
            <th>
              <p><span>GPT-<span>4o</span></span>
              </p>
            </th>
            <th>
              <p><span>Gemini-<span>1.5</span> Pro</span>
              </p>
            </th>
            <th>
              <p><span>Sonnet-<span>3</span></span>
              </p>
            </th>
            <th>
              <p><span>Sonnet-<span>3.5</span></span>
              </p>
            </th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Blank</td>
            <td>26.13</td>
            <td>25.75</td>
            <td>25.00</td>
            <td>59.84</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Text</td>
            <td>53.03</td>
            <td>45.83</td>
            <td>47.34</td>
            <td>88.68</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><strong>Average</strong></td>
            <td>39.58</td>
            <td>35.79</td>
            <td>36.17</td>
            <td>74.26</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody></table>

      </div>

      <div>
        <h2>Qualitative samples</h2>
        <div>
          
          <figcaption>Fig. 12: Examples from the benchmark show that models consistently fail at counting rows and
            columns of
            blank grids.</figcaption>
        </div>
      </div>

      

      <div>
          
          <figcaption>Fig. 13: When text is included in the cells of the grid, the performance of all VLMs improves,
            especially
            <span>Sonnet-<span>3.5</span></span>.
          </figcaption>
        </div>
  </div>
  <!-- TASK 6 Ends -->


  <hr>
  <!-- TASK 7 Begins -->
  <div id="task7">

      <h2>Task 7: Following single-colored paths <img src="https://vlmsareblind.github.io/static/images/logo/subway-map-svg.svg" alt="Two intersecting lines"></h2>



      <div>
        <p>
          It is important for VLMs to be able to follow paths in order to read maps or charts, interpret graphs, and
          understand
          user notations (e.g., arrows) in input images. To assess path-following capability, this task asks models to
          count the
          unique-color paths between two given stations in a simplified subway map. This is another easy-to-humans task
          that
          challenges VLMs significantly.
        </p>

        <h3>Images</h3>
        <p>
          We create each subway map on an image of size C×C, where C ∈ {512, 1024}px. We write 4 station names (A, B, C,
          D) at 4
          fixed coordinates. We divide the canvas into an invisible grid of 18×18 cells and initialize 3 path-starting
          points
          C/18px away from each station. We draw a path, using the depth-first search algorithm starting from a random
          station
          and a random starting point, where a valid move is one cell in any direction: North, south, east or west. We
          repeat
          the process so that each station has exactly N ∈ {1, 2, 3} outgoing paths, for a total of 180 maps.
        </p>

        
        <figcaption>Fig. 14: Examples of subway map images used in the task, showing different numbers of paths and
          variations
          in path thickness.</figcaption>
      </div>

      <h3>Prompts</h3>
      <div>
        <p>
          We ask each question using two different wordings:
        </p>
        <ol>
          <li><em>"How many single-colored paths go from A to C? Answer with a number in curly brackets, e.g., {3}"</em>
          </li>
          <li><em>"Count the one-colored routes that go from A to C. Answer with a number in curly brackets, e.g.,
              {3}."</em>
          </li>
        </ol>

        <h3>Groundtruth</h3>
        <p>
            Answers are ∈ {0, 1, 2, 3} (random-baseline accuracy: 25%).
          </p>

        <h2>Results</h2>
        <p>
          The following table shows the performance of the four models on the task of counting single-colored paths
          between
          stations.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tbody><tr>
            <th>Paths</th>
            <th>
              <p><span>GPT-<span>4o</span></span>
              </p>
            </th>
            <th>
              <p><span>Gemini-<span>1.5</span> Pro</span>
              </p>
            </th>
            <th>
              <p><span>Sonnet-<span>3</span></span>
              </p>
            </th>
            <th>
              <p><span>Sonnet-<span>3.5</span></span>
              </p>
            </th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>67.50</td>
            <td>85.41</td>
            <td>23.75</td>
            <td>95.00</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>2</td>
            <td>44.37</td>
            <td>28.75</td>
            <td>37.18</td>
            <td>56.25</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>3</td>
            <td>36.71</td>
            <td>25.78</td>
            <td>15.42</td>
            <td>25.39</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><strong>Average</strong></td>
            <td>45.89</td>
            <td>40.01</td>
            <td>23.78</td>
            <td>50.18</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody></table>
      </div>
      <div>
        <h2>Qualitative samples</h2>
        <div>
          
          <figcaption>Fig. 15: Some VLMs (<span>Gemini-<span>1.5</span></span>,
            <span>Sonnet-<span>3</span></span>)
            surprisingly fail in even extremely easy cases (leftmost).
            As the
            number of paths exiting each station increases, VLMs tend to perform worse.
          </figcaption>

        </div>
      </div>
  </div>
  <!-- TASK 7 Ends -->




  
  <!-- Add this script at the end of the body -->



</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AMD to buy Finnish start-up Silo AI for $665M (365 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ft.com/content/7b8d2057-2687-45b3-bae4-1488a75ac5b2</link>
            <guid>40926648</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 13:26:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/7b8d2057-2687-45b3-bae4-1488a75ac5b2">https://www.ft.com/content/7b8d2057-2687-45b3-bae4-1488a75ac5b2</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40926648">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="barrier-page">
<div data-component="articleHeaderHeroOffer" data-component-unique-name="EU-Print"><div data-o-grid-colspan="12 L6"><p><span></span><span></span><span></span><span>Subscribe to unlock this article</span><span></span></p></div><div data-o-grid-colspan="12 L6"><p><h2>Try unlimited access<br><strong>Only 1 € for 4 weeks</strong></h2></p><p>Then 69 € per month.<br>Complete digital access to quality FT journalism on any device. Cancel anytime during your trial.</p></div></div>
<div id="recommendedOffers-EU-Print" data-component="recommendedOffers" data-component-unique-name="EU-Print"><p><h2 data-tiles="" data-o-grid-colspan="12">Explore more offers.</h2></p><div data-o-grid-colspan="12"><div data-offer-type="premium" data-o-grid-colspan="12" data-tile=""><div><p><img src="https://www.ft.com/__origami/service/image/v2/images/raw///financial-times-financial-times.cdn.zephr.com/assets/icons/primary_product_icon_premium.svg?source=next-barrier-page&amp;format=svg" alt=""></p><p data-offer-type="premium"><h3>Standard Digital</h3><h3>Weekend Print + Standard Digital</h3></p></div><p>Complete digital access to quality FT journalism with expert analysis from industry leaders. Pay a year upfront and save 20%.</p></div><div data-offer-type="weekend_premium" data-o-grid-colspan="12" data-tile=""><div><p><img src="https://www.ft.com/__origami/service/image/v2/images/raw///financial-times-financial-times.cdn.zephr.com/assets/icons/primary_product_icon_weekend_premium.svg?source=next-barrier-page&amp;format=svg" alt=""></p><p data-offer-type="weekend_premium"><h3>Standard Digital</h3><h3>Weekend Print + Standard Digital</h3></p></div><p>FT Weekend newspaper delivered Saturday plus complete digital access.</p></div><div data-offer-type="bundle" data-o-grid-colspan="12" data-tile=""><div><p><img src="https://www.ft.com/__origami/service/image/v2/images/raw///financial-times-financial-times.cdn.zephr.com/assets/icons/primary_product_icon_bundle.svg?source=next-barrier-page&amp;format=svg" alt=""></p><p data-offer-type="bundle"><h3>Standard Digital</h3><h3>Weekend Print + Standard Digital</h3></p></div><p>Billed Quarterly at 265 €. Complete digital access plus the FT newspaper delivered Monday-Saturday.</p></div></div></div>
<div data-component="subscriptionOptionsV2" data-component-unique-name="UK-Print"><h2>Explore our full range of subscriptions.</h2></div>
<div data-component="whyFT" data-component-unique-name="default"><div><h2>Why the FT?</h2><p>See why over a million readers pay to read the Financial Times.</p></div><p><a href="https://subs.ft.com/whytheft">Find out why</a></p></div>


</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: I made a Note-Taking app for people who keep texting themselves (166 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://strflow.app</link>
            <guid>40925906</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 11:54:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://strflow.app">https://strflow.app</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40925906">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="page" role="main">
        
          
<article id="sections" data-page-sections="651f69a1c37d4b6c547c0385">
  
  
    
    


  




  
    
    


  


<div data-fluid-engine="true" data-test="page-section" data-section-theme="light" data-section-id="651f69a1c37d4b6c547c039d" data-controller="SectionWrapperController" data-current-styles="{
&quot;imageOverlayOpacity&quot;: 0.15,
&quot;backgroundWidth&quot;: &quot;background-width--full-bleed&quot;,
&quot;sectionHeight&quot;: &quot;section-height--custom&quot;,
&quot;customSectionHeight&quot;: 0,
&quot;horizontalAlignment&quot;: &quot;horizontal-alignment--center&quot;,
&quot;verticalAlignment&quot;: &quot;vertical-alignment--middle&quot;,
&quot;contentWidth&quot;: &quot;content-width--wide&quot;,
&quot;customContentWidth&quot;: 50,
&quot;sectionTheme&quot;: &quot;light&quot;,
&quot;sectionAnimation&quot;: &quot;none&quot;,
&quot;backgroundMode&quot;: &quot;image&quot;
}" data-current-context="{
&quot;video&quot;: {
&quot;playbackSpeed&quot;: 0.5,
&quot;filter&quot;: 1,
&quot;filterStrength&quot;: 0,
&quot;zoom&quot;: 0,
&quot;videoSourceProvider&quot;: &quot;none&quot;
},
&quot;backgroundImageId&quot;: null,
&quot;backgroundMediaEffect&quot;: {
&quot;type&quot;: &quot;none&quot;
},
&quot;divider&quot;: {
&quot;enabled&quot;: false
},
&quot;typeName&quot;: &quot;page&quot;
}" data-animation="none" data-fluid-engine-section=""><div data-blend-mode="NORMAL" data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-2659fd9934d3977fbbaa">

<p>
  <h2><span><strong>Take notes as if you're chatting</strong></span></h2>
</p>




















  
  



</div><div data-blend-mode="NORMAL" data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-ff52209be6e698fb7503">
  <p><span>Strflow is a note-taking app designed for intuitive and seamless jotting.</span></p><p><span>Every note you type accumulates in chronological order with its timestamp. Built on this straightforward mechanism, we offer a refreshingly effortless note-taking experience.</span></p>
</div><div data-animation-role="image" data-test="image-block-fluid-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1696898101652_7087">
                
            
            
            
            
            
            
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/90fa1dab-6312-4201-bd17-b4a9e6d02ffa/ezgif.com-crop-2+copy.gif" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/90fa1dab-6312-4201-bd17-b4a9e6d02ffa/ezgif.com-crop-2+copy.gif" data-image-dimensions="1119x720" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/90fa1dab-6312-4201-bd17-b4a9e6d02ffa/ezgif.com-crop-2+copy.gif" width="1119" height="720" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 37.5vw" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/90fa1dab-6312-4201-bd17-b4a9e6d02ffa/ezgif.com-crop-2+copy.gif?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/90fa1dab-6312-4201-bd17-b4a9e6d02ffa/ezgif.com-crop-2+copy.gif?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/90fa1dab-6312-4201-bd17-b4a9e6d02ffa/ezgif.com-crop-2+copy.gif?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/90fa1dab-6312-4201-bd17-b4a9e6d02ffa/ezgif.com-crop-2+copy.gif?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/90fa1dab-6312-4201-bd17-b4a9e6d02ffa/ezgif.com-crop-2+copy.gif?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/90fa1dab-6312-4201-bd17-b4a9e6d02ffa/ezgif.com-crop-2+copy.gif?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/90fa1dab-6312-4201-bd17-b4a9e6d02ffa/ezgif.com-crop-2+copy.gif?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs"></p>
          
              </div></div>

  
    
    


  


<div data-fluid-engine="true" data-test="page-section" data-section-theme="light-bold" data-section-id="65254cd78174d8468cd0f38b" data-controller="SectionWrapperController" data-current-styles="{
&quot;imageOverlayOpacity&quot;: 0.15,
&quot;backgroundWidth&quot;: &quot;background-width--full-bleed&quot;,
&quot;sectionHeight&quot;: &quot;section-height--custom&quot;,
&quot;customSectionHeight&quot;: 0,
&quot;horizontalAlignment&quot;: &quot;horizontal-alignment--center&quot;,
&quot;verticalAlignment&quot;: &quot;vertical-alignment--middle&quot;,
&quot;contentWidth&quot;: &quot;content-width--wide&quot;,
&quot;customContentWidth&quot;: 50,
&quot;sectionTheme&quot;: &quot;light-bold&quot;,
&quot;sectionAnimation&quot;: &quot;none&quot;,
&quot;backgroundMode&quot;: &quot;image&quot;
}" data-current-context="{
&quot;video&quot;: {
&quot;playbackSpeed&quot;: 0.5,
&quot;filter&quot;: 1,
&quot;filterStrength&quot;: 0,
&quot;zoom&quot;: 0,
&quot;videoSourceProvider&quot;: &quot;none&quot;
},
&quot;backgroundImageId&quot;: null,
&quot;backgroundMediaEffect&quot;: {
&quot;type&quot;: &quot;none&quot;
},
&quot;divider&quot;: {
&quot;enabled&quot;: false
},
&quot;typeName&quot;: &quot;page&quot;
}" data-animation="none" data-fluid-engine-section=""><div data-blend-mode="NORMAL" data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-86925d906e71fc721d6f">

<p>
  <h2><strong>Build Your Timeline</strong></h2>
</p>




















  
  



</div><div data-blend-mode="NORMAL" data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-e08fa865ab206507ee39">
  <p><span>As you jot down notes, a timeline naturally forms just for you. </span></p><p><span>With tags, you can also create timelines centered around specific topics.</span></p>
</div><div data-animation-role="image" data-test="image-block-fluid-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1717461272179_66950">
                
            
            
            
            
            
            
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/843dd5f6-e4b1-43ce-8bee-ba73f9694036/sidebar-screenshot.png" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/843dd5f6-e4b1-43ce-8bee-ba73f9694036/sidebar-screenshot.png" data-image-dimensions="722x1481" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/843dd5f6-e4b1-43ce-8bee-ba73f9694036/sidebar-screenshot.png" width="722" height="1481" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 75vw, 25vw" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/843dd5f6-e4b1-43ce-8bee-ba73f9694036/sidebar-screenshot.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/843dd5f6-e4b1-43ce-8bee-ba73f9694036/sidebar-screenshot.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/843dd5f6-e4b1-43ce-8bee-ba73f9694036/sidebar-screenshot.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/843dd5f6-e4b1-43ce-8bee-ba73f9694036/sidebar-screenshot.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/843dd5f6-e4b1-43ce-8bee-ba73f9694036/sidebar-screenshot.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/843dd5f6-e4b1-43ce-8bee-ba73f9694036/sidebar-screenshot.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/843dd5f6-e4b1-43ce-8bee-ba73f9694036/sidebar-screenshot.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs"></p>
          
              </div><div data-animation-role="image" data-test="image-block-fluid-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1698021991738_5676">
                
            
            
            
            
            
            
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e4a71efb-aaae-4b1f-84ac-f901ce82b010/IMG_8468.jpeg" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e4a71efb-aaae-4b1f-84ac-f901ce82b010/IMG_8468.jpeg" data-image-dimensions="1630x2126" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e4a71efb-aaae-4b1f-84ac-f901ce82b010/IMG_8468.jpeg" width="1630" height="2126" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 37.5vw, 50vw" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e4a71efb-aaae-4b1f-84ac-f901ce82b010/IMG_8468.jpeg?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e4a71efb-aaae-4b1f-84ac-f901ce82b010/IMG_8468.jpeg?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e4a71efb-aaae-4b1f-84ac-f901ce82b010/IMG_8468.jpeg?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e4a71efb-aaae-4b1f-84ac-f901ce82b010/IMG_8468.jpeg?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e4a71efb-aaae-4b1f-84ac-f901ce82b010/IMG_8468.jpeg?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e4a71efb-aaae-4b1f-84ac-f901ce82b010/IMG_8468.jpeg?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e4a71efb-aaae-4b1f-84ac-f901ce82b010/IMG_8468.jpeg?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs"></p>
          
              </div></div>

  
    
    


  


<div data-fluid-engine="true" data-test="page-section" data-section-theme="light-bold" data-section-id="6535cfb4c6408833cb8e7f82" data-controller="SectionWrapperController" data-current-styles="{
&quot;imageOverlayOpacity&quot;: 0.15,
&quot;backgroundWidth&quot;: &quot;background-width--full-bleed&quot;,
&quot;sectionHeight&quot;: &quot;section-height--custom&quot;,
&quot;customSectionHeight&quot;: 0,
&quot;horizontalAlignment&quot;: &quot;horizontal-alignment--center&quot;,
&quot;verticalAlignment&quot;: &quot;vertical-alignment--middle&quot;,
&quot;contentWidth&quot;: &quot;content-width--wide&quot;,
&quot;customContentWidth&quot;: 50,
&quot;sectionTheme&quot;: &quot;light-bold&quot;,
&quot;sectionAnimation&quot;: &quot;none&quot;,
&quot;backgroundMode&quot;: &quot;image&quot;
}" data-current-context="{
&quot;video&quot;: {
&quot;playbackSpeed&quot;: 0.5,
&quot;filter&quot;: 1,
&quot;filterStrength&quot;: 0,
&quot;zoom&quot;: 0,
&quot;videoSourceProvider&quot;: &quot;none&quot;
},
&quot;backgroundImageId&quot;: null,
&quot;backgroundMediaEffect&quot;: {
&quot;type&quot;: &quot;none&quot;
},
&quot;divider&quot;: {
&quot;enabled&quot;: false
},
&quot;typeName&quot;: &quot;page&quot;
}" data-animation="none" data-fluid-engine-section=""><div data-blend-mode="NORMAL" data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-4b8fef85255ad64d235c">

<p>
  <h2><strong>Quick Note Anywhere</strong></h2>
</p>




















  
  



</div><div data-animation-role="image" data-test="image-block-fluid-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1704104696298_31875">
                
            
            
            
            
            
            
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/c9b53a29-493f-4fef-a365-d169164a3dce/macbookpro-share-cut1.png" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/c9b53a29-493f-4fef-a365-d169164a3dce/macbookpro-share-cut1.png" data-image-dimensions="1479x1520" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/c9b53a29-493f-4fef-a365-d169164a3dce/macbookpro-share-cut1.png" width="1479" height="1520" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 87.5vw, 45.83333333333333vw" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/c9b53a29-493f-4fef-a365-d169164a3dce/macbookpro-share-cut1.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/c9b53a29-493f-4fef-a365-d169164a3dce/macbookpro-share-cut1.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/c9b53a29-493f-4fef-a365-d169164a3dce/macbookpro-share-cut1.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/c9b53a29-493f-4fef-a365-d169164a3dce/macbookpro-share-cut1.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/c9b53a29-493f-4fef-a365-d169164a3dce/macbookpro-share-cut1.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/c9b53a29-493f-4fef-a365-d169164a3dce/macbookpro-share-cut1.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/c9b53a29-493f-4fef-a365-d169164a3dce/macbookpro-share-cut1.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs"></p>
          
              </div><div data-blend-mode="NORMAL" data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-e0644ddb3a8264c5a879">
  <p><span>Sync quickly and take notes from anywhere. </span></p><p><span>Open the app and start typing instantly, access strflow from the share sheet, or use a shortcut key on macOS. </span></p>
</div><div data-animation-role="image" data-test="image-block-fluid-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1719880185048_53537">
                
            
            
            
            
            
            
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e3c51e9a-eefd-4ceb-ae2d-2ff54ff69350/chatting.png" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e3c51e9a-eefd-4ceb-ae2d-2ff54ff69350/chatting.png" data-image-dimensions="711x1457" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e3c51e9a-eefd-4ceb-ae2d-2ff54ff69350/chatting.png" width="711" height="1457" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 37.5vw, 37.5vw" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e3c51e9a-eefd-4ceb-ae2d-2ff54ff69350/chatting.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e3c51e9a-eefd-4ceb-ae2d-2ff54ff69350/chatting.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e3c51e9a-eefd-4ceb-ae2d-2ff54ff69350/chatting.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e3c51e9a-eefd-4ceb-ae2d-2ff54ff69350/chatting.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e3c51e9a-eefd-4ceb-ae2d-2ff54ff69350/chatting.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e3c51e9a-eefd-4ceb-ae2d-2ff54ff69350/chatting.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e3c51e9a-eefd-4ceb-ae2d-2ff54ff69350/chatting.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs"></p>
          
              </div><div data-animation-role="image" data-test="image-block-fluid-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1719880185048_37588">
                
            
            
            
            
            
            
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/4664dbd5-6c49-4ca1-8288-48c499c01722/share-sheet.png" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/4664dbd5-6c49-4ca1-8288-48c499c01722/share-sheet.png" data-image-dimensions="668x1369" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/4664dbd5-6c49-4ca1-8288-48c499c01722/share-sheet.png" width="668" height="1369" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 37.5vw, 25vw" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/4664dbd5-6c49-4ca1-8288-48c499c01722/share-sheet.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/4664dbd5-6c49-4ca1-8288-48c499c01722/share-sheet.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/4664dbd5-6c49-4ca1-8288-48c499c01722/share-sheet.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/4664dbd5-6c49-4ca1-8288-48c499c01722/share-sheet.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/4664dbd5-6c49-4ca1-8288-48c499c01722/share-sheet.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/4664dbd5-6c49-4ca1-8288-48c499c01722/share-sheet.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/4664dbd5-6c49-4ca1-8288-48c499c01722/share-sheet.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs"></p>
          
              </div></div>

  
    
    


  


<div data-fluid-engine="true" data-test="page-section" data-section-theme="light-bold" data-section-id="6534d75164f101328bb8c260" data-controller="SectionWrapperController" data-current-styles="{
&quot;imageOverlayOpacity&quot;: 0.15,
&quot;backgroundWidth&quot;: &quot;background-width--full-bleed&quot;,
&quot;sectionHeight&quot;: &quot;section-height--custom&quot;,
&quot;customSectionHeight&quot;: 0,
&quot;horizontalAlignment&quot;: &quot;horizontal-alignment--center&quot;,
&quot;verticalAlignment&quot;: &quot;vertical-alignment--middle&quot;,
&quot;contentWidth&quot;: &quot;content-width--wide&quot;,
&quot;customContentWidth&quot;: 50,
&quot;sectionTheme&quot;: &quot;light-bold&quot;,
&quot;sectionAnimation&quot;: &quot;none&quot;,
&quot;backgroundMode&quot;: &quot;image&quot;
}" data-current-context="{
&quot;video&quot;: {
&quot;playbackSpeed&quot;: 0.5,
&quot;filter&quot;: 1,
&quot;filterStrength&quot;: 0,
&quot;zoom&quot;: 0,
&quot;videoSourceProvider&quot;: &quot;none&quot;
},
&quot;backgroundImageId&quot;: null,
&quot;backgroundMediaEffect&quot;: {
&quot;type&quot;: &quot;none&quot;
},
&quot;divider&quot;: {
&quot;enabled&quot;: true,
&quot;type&quot;: &quot;wavy&quot;,
&quot;width&quot;: {
&quot;unit&quot;: &quot;vw&quot;,
&quot;value&quot;: 100.0
},
&quot;height&quot;: {
&quot;unit&quot;: &quot;vw&quot;,
&quot;value&quot;: 6.0
},
&quot;isFlipX&quot;: false,
&quot;isFlipY&quot;: true,
&quot;offset&quot;: {
&quot;unit&quot;: &quot;px&quot;,
&quot;value&quot;: 0.0
},
&quot;stroke&quot;: {
&quot;style&quot;: &quot;none&quot;,
&quot;color&quot;: {
&quot;type&quot;: &quot;THEME_COLOR&quot;
},
&quot;thickness&quot;: {
&quot;unit&quot;: &quot;px&quot;,
&quot;value&quot;: 6.0
},
&quot;dashLength&quot;: {
&quot;unit&quot;: &quot;px&quot;,
&quot;value&quot;: 5.0
},
&quot;gapLength&quot;: {
&quot;unit&quot;: &quot;px&quot;,
&quot;value&quot;: 15.0
},
&quot;linecap&quot;: &quot;square&quot;
}
},
&quot;typeName&quot;: &quot;page&quot;
}" data-animation="none" data-fluid-engine-section=""><div data-blend-mode="NORMAL" data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-27ef835851c96824441e">

<p>
  <h2><strong>Privacy Above All</strong></h2>
</p>




















  
  



</div><div data-blend-mode="NORMAL" data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-d7a9bc7d83c7a595ddb2">
  <p><span>All data remains exclusively on your devices and within your iCloud account. We can't access it in any way.</span></p><p><span>When saved to iCloud, your data is encrypted using your iCloud Keychain. This ensures compliance with </span><a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT202303#advanced"><span>Advanced Data Protection</span></a><span>, which offers</span> <span><strong>end-to-end encryption</strong>.</span></p>
</div><div data-animation-role="image" data-test="image-block-fluid-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1697961755408_8939">
                
            
            
            
            
            
            
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/38ad7381-a208-4cba-802a-7fa228c5ab3f/Screenshot+2023-10-22+at+18.06.30.png" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/38ad7381-a208-4cba-802a-7fa228c5ab3f/Screenshot+2023-10-22+at+18.06.30.png" data-image-dimensions="478x586" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/38ad7381-a208-4cba-802a-7fa228c5ab3f/Screenshot+2023-10-22+at+18.06.30.png" width="478" height="586" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 75vw, 12.5vw" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/38ad7381-a208-4cba-802a-7fa228c5ab3f/Screenshot+2023-10-22+at+18.06.30.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/38ad7381-a208-4cba-802a-7fa228c5ab3f/Screenshot+2023-10-22+at+18.06.30.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/38ad7381-a208-4cba-802a-7fa228c5ab3f/Screenshot+2023-10-22+at+18.06.30.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/38ad7381-a208-4cba-802a-7fa228c5ab3f/Screenshot+2023-10-22+at+18.06.30.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/38ad7381-a208-4cba-802a-7fa228c5ab3f/Screenshot+2023-10-22+at+18.06.30.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/38ad7381-a208-4cba-802a-7fa228c5ab3f/Screenshot+2023-10-22+at+18.06.30.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/38ad7381-a208-4cba-802a-7fa228c5ab3f/Screenshot+2023-10-22+at+18.06.30.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs"></p>
          
              </div></div>

  
    
    


  


<div data-fluid-engine="true" data-test="page-section" data-section-theme="light-bold" data-section-id="6596bbbdb14c802aa4434af3" data-controller="SectionWrapperController" data-current-styles="{
&quot;imageOverlayOpacity&quot;: 0.15,
&quot;backgroundWidth&quot;: &quot;background-width--full-bleed&quot;,
&quot;sectionHeight&quot;: &quot;section-height--small&quot;,
&quot;customSectionHeight&quot;: 1,
&quot;horizontalAlignment&quot;: &quot;horizontal-alignment--center&quot;,
&quot;verticalAlignment&quot;: &quot;vertical-alignment--middle&quot;,
&quot;contentWidth&quot;: &quot;content-width--wide&quot;,
&quot;customContentWidth&quot;: 50,
&quot;backgroundColor&quot;: &quot;&quot;,
&quot;sectionTheme&quot;: &quot;light-bold&quot;,
&quot;sectionAnimation&quot;: &quot;none&quot;,
&quot;backgroundMode&quot;: &quot;image&quot;
}" data-current-context="{
&quot;video&quot;: {
&quot;playbackSpeed&quot;: 0.5,
&quot;filter&quot;: 1,
&quot;filterStrength&quot;: 0,
&quot;zoom&quot;: 0,
&quot;videoSourceProvider&quot;: &quot;none&quot;
},
&quot;backgroundImageId&quot;: null,
&quot;backgroundMediaEffect&quot;: {
&quot;type&quot;: &quot;none&quot;
},
&quot;divider&quot;: {
&quot;enabled&quot;: true,
&quot;type&quot;: &quot;wavy&quot;,
&quot;width&quot;: {
&quot;unit&quot;: &quot;vw&quot;,
&quot;value&quot;: 100.0
},
&quot;height&quot;: {
&quot;unit&quot;: &quot;vw&quot;,
&quot;value&quot;: 6.0
},
&quot;isFlipX&quot;: false,
&quot;isFlipY&quot;: true,
&quot;offset&quot;: {
&quot;unit&quot;: &quot;px&quot;,
&quot;value&quot;: 0.0
},
&quot;stroke&quot;: {
&quot;style&quot;: &quot;none&quot;,
&quot;color&quot;: {
&quot;type&quot;: &quot;THEME_COLOR&quot;
},
&quot;thickness&quot;: {
&quot;unit&quot;: &quot;px&quot;,
&quot;value&quot;: 6.0
},
&quot;dashLength&quot;: {
&quot;unit&quot;: &quot;px&quot;,
&quot;value&quot;: 5.0
},
&quot;gapLength&quot;: {
&quot;unit&quot;: &quot;px&quot;,
&quot;value&quot;: 15.0
},
&quot;linecap&quot;: &quot;square&quot;
}
},
&quot;typeName&quot;: &quot;page&quot;
}" data-animation="none" data-fluid-engine-section=""><div data-blend-mode="NORMAL" data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1704374471344_19958">

<p>
  <h2><strong>And so much more</strong></h2>
</p>




















  
  



</div><div data-animation-role="image" data-test="image-block-fluid-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1704374471344_28008">
                
            
            
            
            
            
            
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/35eb042b-f1f3-4f5f-84fa-b0c81e4e7e43/image.png" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/35eb042b-f1f3-4f5f-84fa-b0c81e4e7e43/image.png" data-image-dimensions="811x582" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/35eb042b-f1f3-4f5f-84fa-b0c81e4e7e43/image.png" width="811" height="582" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 29.166666666666668vw" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/35eb042b-f1f3-4f5f-84fa-b0c81e4e7e43/image.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/35eb042b-f1f3-4f5f-84fa-b0c81e4e7e43/image.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/35eb042b-f1f3-4f5f-84fa-b0c81e4e7e43/image.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/35eb042b-f1f3-4f5f-84fa-b0c81e4e7e43/image.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/35eb042b-f1f3-4f5f-84fa-b0c81e4e7e43/image.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/35eb042b-f1f3-4f5f-84fa-b0c81e4e7e43/image.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/35eb042b-f1f3-4f5f-84fa-b0c81e4e7e43/image.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs"></p>
          
              </div><div data-animation-role="image" data-test="image-block-fluid-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1704374471344_29874">
                
            
            
            
            
            
            
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/f031e16f-00e8-44eb-a73d-02d0405379ec/drag+image.png" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/f031e16f-00e8-44eb-a73d-02d0405379ec/drag+image.png" data-image-dimensions="362x267" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/f031e16f-00e8-44eb-a73d-02d0405379ec/drag+image.png" width="362" height="267" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 20.833333333333336vw" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/f031e16f-00e8-44eb-a73d-02d0405379ec/drag+image.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/f031e16f-00e8-44eb-a73d-02d0405379ec/drag+image.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/f031e16f-00e8-44eb-a73d-02d0405379ec/drag+image.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/f031e16f-00e8-44eb-a73d-02d0405379ec/drag+image.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/f031e16f-00e8-44eb-a73d-02d0405379ec/drag+image.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/f031e16f-00e8-44eb-a73d-02d0405379ec/drag+image.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/f031e16f-00e8-44eb-a73d-02d0405379ec/drag+image.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs"></p>
          
              </div><div data-animation-role="image" data-test="image-block-fluid-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1704374471344_35012">
                
            
            
            
            
            
            
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/57fabfc1-297d-4c89-a194-9a8fd6cff210/text+formatting.png" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/57fabfc1-297d-4c89-a194-9a8fd6cff210/text+formatting.png" data-image-dimensions="908x577" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/57fabfc1-297d-4c89-a194-9a8fd6cff210/text+formatting.png" width="908" height="577" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 33.33333333333333vw" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/57fabfc1-297d-4c89-a194-9a8fd6cff210/text+formatting.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/57fabfc1-297d-4c89-a194-9a8fd6cff210/text+formatting.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/57fabfc1-297d-4c89-a194-9a8fd6cff210/text+formatting.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/57fabfc1-297d-4c89-a194-9a8fd6cff210/text+formatting.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/57fabfc1-297d-4c89-a194-9a8fd6cff210/text+formatting.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/57fabfc1-297d-4c89-a194-9a8fd6cff210/text+formatting.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/57fabfc1-297d-4c89-a194-9a8fd6cff210/text+formatting.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs"></p>
          
              </div><div data-animation-role="image" data-test="image-block-fluid-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1704374471344_26044">
                
            
            
            
            
            
            
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/0c85d109-7385-4c91-b0ed-5e50b2e1ea9c/note+link.png" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/0c85d109-7385-4c91-b0ed-5e50b2e1ea9c/note+link.png" data-image-dimensions="962x328" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/0c85d109-7385-4c91-b0ed-5e50b2e1ea9c/note+link.png" width="962" height="328" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 33.33333333333333vw" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/0c85d109-7385-4c91-b0ed-5e50b2e1ea9c/note+link.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/0c85d109-7385-4c91-b0ed-5e50b2e1ea9c/note+link.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/0c85d109-7385-4c91-b0ed-5e50b2e1ea9c/note+link.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/0c85d109-7385-4c91-b0ed-5e50b2e1ea9c/note+link.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/0c85d109-7385-4c91-b0ed-5e50b2e1ea9c/note+link.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/0c85d109-7385-4c91-b0ed-5e50b2e1ea9c/note+link.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/0c85d109-7385-4c91-b0ed-5e50b2e1ea9c/note+link.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs"></p>
          
              </div><div data-animation-role="image" data-test="image-block-fluid-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1704374471344_31847">
                
            
            
            
            
            
            
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/95c59b0f-a300-449d-a9e0-7e90edc7603d/link+preview.png" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/95c59b0f-a300-449d-a9e0-7e90edc7603d/link+preview.png" data-image-dimensions="874x548" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/95c59b0f-a300-449d-a9e0-7e90edc7603d/link+preview.png" width="874" height="548" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 29.166666666666668vw" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/95c59b0f-a300-449d-a9e0-7e90edc7603d/link+preview.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/95c59b0f-a300-449d-a9e0-7e90edc7603d/link+preview.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/95c59b0f-a300-449d-a9e0-7e90edc7603d/link+preview.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/95c59b0f-a300-449d-a9e0-7e90edc7603d/link+preview.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/95c59b0f-a300-449d-a9e0-7e90edc7603d/link+preview.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/95c59b0f-a300-449d-a9e0-7e90edc7603d/link+preview.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/95c59b0f-a300-449d-a9e0-7e90edc7603d/link+preview.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs"></p>
          
              </div></div>

  
    
    


  


<div data-fluid-engine="true" data-test="page-section" data-section-theme="" data-section-id="659606750720f5331ddcb2e4" data-controller="SectionWrapperController" data-current-styles="{
&quot;imageOverlayOpacity&quot;: 0.15,
&quot;backgroundWidth&quot;: &quot;background-width--full-bleed&quot;,
&quot;sectionHeight&quot;: &quot;section-height--small&quot;,
&quot;customSectionHeight&quot;: 1,
&quot;horizontalAlignment&quot;: &quot;horizontal-alignment--center&quot;,
&quot;verticalAlignment&quot;: &quot;vertical-alignment--middle&quot;,
&quot;contentWidth&quot;: &quot;content-width--wide&quot;,
&quot;customContentWidth&quot;: 50,
&quot;backgroundColor&quot;: &quot;&quot;,
&quot;sectionTheme&quot;: &quot;&quot;,
&quot;sectionAnimation&quot;: &quot;none&quot;,
&quot;backgroundMode&quot;: &quot;image&quot;
}" data-current-context="{
&quot;video&quot;: {
&quot;playbackSpeed&quot;: 0.5,
&quot;filter&quot;: 1,
&quot;filterStrength&quot;: 0,
&quot;zoom&quot;: 0,
&quot;videoSourceProvider&quot;: &quot;none&quot;
},
&quot;backgroundImageId&quot;: null,
&quot;backgroundMediaEffect&quot;: {
&quot;type&quot;: &quot;none&quot;
},
&quot;divider&quot;: {
&quot;enabled&quot;: false
},
&quot;typeName&quot;: &quot;page&quot;
}" data-animation="none" data-fluid-engine-section=""><div data-blend-mode="NORMAL" data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1704338771685_55025">

<p>
  <h2>Price</h2>
</p>




















  
  



</div><div data-block-type="44" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1704330191098_39117"><h3>Unlimited Free Use</h3>
<p>Access all of Strflow's essential features for free, including unlimited notes, tags, and attachments.</p>
<h3>Strflow Plus</h3>
<p>For power users, the Strflow Plus plan offers advanced functionalities. Priced at <strong>$1.49/month or $14.99/year</strong>, Strflow Plus includes:</p>

</div><div data-blend-mode="NORMAL" data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1704330191098_54361">

<p><strong>ICloud Sync &amp; Backup: </strong>Keep your notes updated and backed up across all devices with iCloud.</p>




















  
  



</div><div data-animation-role="image" data-test="image-block-fluid-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1704330191098_47009">
                
            
            
            
            
            
            
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/498dc58c-4f05-48c2-9485-0dfaa15ef82b/checkmark.icloud.png" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/498dc58c-4f05-48c2-9485-0dfaa15ef82b/checkmark.icloud.png" data-image-dimensions="614x464" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/498dc58c-4f05-48c2-9485-0dfaa15ef82b/checkmark.icloud.png" width="614" height="464" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 12.5vw, 4.166666666666666vw" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/498dc58c-4f05-48c2-9485-0dfaa15ef82b/checkmark.icloud.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/498dc58c-4f05-48c2-9485-0dfaa15ef82b/checkmark.icloud.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/498dc58c-4f05-48c2-9485-0dfaa15ef82b/checkmark.icloud.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/498dc58c-4f05-48c2-9485-0dfaa15ef82b/checkmark.icloud.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/498dc58c-4f05-48c2-9485-0dfaa15ef82b/checkmark.icloud.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/498dc58c-4f05-48c2-9485-0dfaa15ef82b/checkmark.icloud.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/498dc58c-4f05-48c2-9485-0dfaa15ef82b/checkmark.icloud.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs"></p>
          
              </div><div data-blend-mode="NORMAL" data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-f865da2b387d00cc38ac">

<p><strong>Data Protection: </strong>Your data is encrypted using your iCloud Keychain when saved to iCloud.</p>




















  
  



</div><div data-animation-role="image" data-test="image-block-fluid-outer-wrapper" data-block-type="5" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1704330191098_49309">
                
            
            
            
            
            
            
            <p><img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e7a773fe-749b-448e-b3d4-8c2be902a92e/lock.icloud.png" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e7a773fe-749b-448e-b3d4-8c2be902a92e/lock.icloud.png" data-image-dimensions="614x464" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e7a773fe-749b-448e-b3d4-8c2be902a92e/lock.icloud.png" width="614" height="464" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 12.5vw, 4.166666666666666vw" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e7a773fe-749b-448e-b3d4-8c2be902a92e/lock.icloud.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e7a773fe-749b-448e-b3d4-8c2be902a92e/lock.icloud.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e7a773fe-749b-448e-b3d4-8c2be902a92e/lock.icloud.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e7a773fe-749b-448e-b3d4-8c2be902a92e/lock.icloud.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e7a773fe-749b-448e-b3d4-8c2be902a92e/lock.icloud.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e7a773fe-749b-448e-b3d4-8c2be902a92e/lock.icloud.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/e7a773fe-749b-448e-b3d4-8c2be902a92e/lock.icloud.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs"></p>
          
              </div></div>

  
    
    


  


<div data-animation-role="image" data-test="page-section" data-block-type="5" id="block-8191205525e45ae4e8d5" data-fluid-engine="true" data-section-theme="" data-section-id="653dd32ed55a322bc6c16e99" data-controller="SectionWrapperController" data-current-styles="{
&quot;imageOverlayOpacity&quot;: 0.15,
&quot;backgroundWidth&quot;: &quot;background-width--full-bleed&quot;,
&quot;sectionHeight&quot;: &quot;section-height--custom&quot;,
&quot;customSectionHeight&quot;: 15,
&quot;horizontalAlignment&quot;: &quot;horizontal-alignment--center&quot;,
&quot;verticalAlignment&quot;: &quot;vertical-alignment--middle&quot;,
&quot;contentWidth&quot;: &quot;content-width--wide&quot;,
&quot;customContentWidth&quot;: 50,
&quot;backgroundColor&quot;: &quot;&quot;,
&quot;sectionTheme&quot;: &quot;&quot;,
&quot;sectionAnimation&quot;: &quot;none&quot;,
&quot;backgroundMode&quot;: &quot;image&quot;
}" data-current-context="{
&quot;video&quot;: {
&quot;playbackSpeed&quot;: 0.5,
&quot;filter&quot;: 1,
&quot;filterStrength&quot;: 0,
&quot;zoom&quot;: 0,
&quot;videoSourceProvider&quot;: &quot;none&quot;
},
&quot;backgroundImageId&quot;: null,
&quot;backgroundMediaEffect&quot;: {
&quot;type&quot;: &quot;none&quot;
},
&quot;divider&quot;: {
&quot;enabled&quot;: false,
&quot;type&quot;: &quot;wavy&quot;,
&quot;width&quot;: {
&quot;unit&quot;: &quot;vw&quot;,
&quot;value&quot;: 100.0
},
&quot;height&quot;: {
&quot;unit&quot;: &quot;vw&quot;,
&quot;value&quot;: 6.0
},
&quot;isFlipX&quot;: false,
&quot;isFlipY&quot;: true,
&quot;offset&quot;: {
&quot;unit&quot;: &quot;px&quot;,
&quot;value&quot;: 0.0
},
&quot;stroke&quot;: {
&quot;style&quot;: &quot;none&quot;,
&quot;color&quot;: {
&quot;type&quot;: &quot;THEME_COLOR&quot;
},
&quot;thickness&quot;: {
&quot;unit&quot;: &quot;px&quot;,
&quot;value&quot;: 6.0
},
&quot;dashLength&quot;: {
&quot;unit&quot;: &quot;px&quot;,
&quot;value&quot;: 5.0
},
&quot;gapLength&quot;: {
&quot;unit&quot;: &quot;px&quot;,
&quot;value&quot;: 15.0
},
&quot;linecap&quot;: &quot;square&quot;
}
},
&quot;typeName&quot;: &quot;page&quot;
}" data-animation="none" data-fluid-engine-section="">
          

          
          

          
            <a href="https://apps.apple.com/app/strflow-notes-journal/id6468486339">
              
            
            
            
            
            
            
            <img data-stretch="false" data-src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/4bcdee8a-cacc-4468-8824-054ae2726c5c/Download_on_the_App_Store_Badge_US-UK_RGB_blk_092917.png" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/4bcdee8a-cacc-4468-8824-054ae2726c5c/Download_on_the_App_Store_Badge_US-UK_RGB_blk_092917.png" data-image-dimensions="294x99" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/4bcdee8a-cacc-4468-8824-054ae2726c5c/Download_on_the_App_Store_Badge_US-UK_RGB_blk_092917.png" width="294" height="99" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 50vw, 25vw" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/4bcdee8a-cacc-4468-8824-054ae2726c5c/Download_on_the_App_Store_Badge_US-UK_RGB_blk_092917.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/4bcdee8a-cacc-4468-8824-054ae2726c5c/Download_on_the_App_Store_Badge_US-UK_RGB_blk_092917.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/4bcdee8a-cacc-4468-8824-054ae2726c5c/Download_on_the_App_Store_Badge_US-UK_RGB_blk_092917.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/4bcdee8a-cacc-4468-8824-054ae2726c5c/Download_on_the_App_Store_Badge_US-UK_RGB_blk_092917.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/4bcdee8a-cacc-4468-8824-054ae2726c5c/Download_on_the_App_Store_Badge_US-UK_RGB_blk_092917.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/4bcdee8a-cacc-4468-8824-054ae2726c5c/Download_on_the_App_Store_Badge_US-UK_RGB_blk_092917.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651f699cfe8e8424501d9e86/4bcdee8a-cacc-4468-8824-054ae2726c5c/Download_on_the_App_Store_Badge_US-UK_RGB_blk_092917.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            
              
            
            
          
            </a>
          

        </div>

  
</article>


          

          
            
          
        
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[ML Code Exercises (194 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.deep-ml.com/</link>
            <guid>40925896</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 11:53:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/">https://www.deep-ml.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40925896">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    <h2>ML Code Challenges</h2>
    
    <table>
        <thead>
            <tr>
                <th>Title</th>
                <th>Category</th>
                <th>Difficulty</th>
                <th>Status</th>
            </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody id="problemsContainer">
            
            <tr data-difficulty="easy" data-category="linear algebra" data-solved="unsolved">
                <td><a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/problem/1">Matrix times Vector</a></td>
                <td>linear algebra</td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Easy</span>
                    
                </td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Unsolved</span>
                    
                </td>
            </tr>
            
            <tr data-difficulty="medium" data-category="linear algebra" data-solved="unsolved">
                <td><a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/problem/10">Calculate Covariance Matrix</a></td>
                <td>linear algebra</td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Medium</span>
                    
                </td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Unsolved</span>
                    
                </td>
            </tr>
            
            <tr data-difficulty="medium" data-category="linear algebra" data-solved="unsolved">
                <td><a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/problem/11">Solve Linear Equations using Jacobi Method</a></td>
                <td>linear algebra</td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Medium</span>
                    
                </td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Unsolved</span>
                    
                </td>
            </tr>
            
            <tr data-difficulty="hard" data-category="linear algebra" data-solved="unsolved">
                <td><a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/problem/12">Singular Value Decomposition (SVD)</a></td>
                <td>linear algebra</td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Hard</span>
                    
                </td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Unsolved</span>
                    
                </td>
            </tr>
            
            <tr data-difficulty="hard" data-category="linear algebra" data-solved="unsolved">
                <td><a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/problem/13">Determinant of a 4x4 Matrix using Laplace's Expansion</a></td>
                <td>linear algebra</td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Hard</span>
                    
                </td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Unsolved</span>
                    
                </td>
            </tr>
            
            <tr data-difficulty="easy" data-category="machine learning" data-solved="unsolved">
                <td><a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/problem/14">Linear Regression Using Normal Equation</a></td>
                <td>machine learning</td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Easy</span>
                    
                </td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Unsolved</span>
                    
                </td>
            </tr>
            
            <tr data-difficulty="easy" data-category="machine learning" data-solved="unsolved">
                <td><a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/problem/15">Linear Regression Using Gradient Descent</a></td>
                <td>machine learning</td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Easy</span>
                    
                </td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Unsolved</span>
                    
                </td>
            </tr>
            
            <tr data-difficulty="easy" data-category="machine learning" data-solved="unsolved">
                <td><a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/problem/16">Feature Scaling Implementation</a></td>
                <td>machine learning</td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Easy</span>
                    
                </td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Unsolved</span>
                    
                </td>
            </tr>
            
            <tr data-difficulty="medium" data-category="machine learning" data-solved="unsolved">
                <td><a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/problem/17">K-Means Clustering</a></td>
                <td>machine learning</td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Medium</span>
                    
                </td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Unsolved</span>
                    
                </td>
            </tr>
            
            <tr data-difficulty="medium" data-category="machine learning" data-solved="unsolved">
                <td><a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/problem/18">Cross-Validation Data Split Implementation</a></td>
                <td>machine learning</td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Medium</span>
                    
                </td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Unsolved</span>
                    
                </td>
            </tr>
            
            <tr data-difficulty="medium" data-category="machine learning" data-solved="unsolved">
                <td><a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/problem/19">Principal Component Analysis (PCA) Implementation</a></td>
                <td>machine learning</td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Medium</span>
                    
                </td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Unsolved</span>
                    
                </td>
            </tr>
            
            <tr data-difficulty="easy" data-category="linear algebra" data-solved="unsolved">
                <td><a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/problem/2">Transpose of a Matrix</a></td>
                <td>linear algebra</td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Easy</span>
                    
                </td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Unsolved</span>
                    
                </td>
            </tr>
            
            <tr data-difficulty="hard" data-category="machine learning" data-solved="unsolved">
                <td><a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/problem/20">Decision Tree Learning</a></td>
                <td>machine learning</td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Hard</span>
                    
                </td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Unsolved</span>
                    
                </td>
            </tr>
            
            <tr data-difficulty="advanced" data-category="machine learning" data-solved="unsolved">
                <td><a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/problem/21">Pegasos Kernel SVM Implementation</a></td>
                <td>machine learning</td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Hard</span>
                    
                </td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Unsolved</span>
                    
                </td>
            </tr>
            
            <tr data-difficulty="easy" data-category="deep learning" data-solved="unsolved">
                <td><a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/problem/22">Sigmoid Activation Function Understanding</a></td>
                <td>deep learning</td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Easy</span>
                    
                </td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Unsolved</span>
                    
                </td>
            </tr>
            
            <tr data-difficulty="easy" data-category="deep learning" data-solved="unsolved">
                <td><a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/problem/23">Softmax Activation Function Implementation</a></td>
                <td>deep learning</td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Easy</span>
                    
                </td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Unsolved</span>
                    
                </td>
            </tr>
            
            <tr data-difficulty="easy" data-category="deep learning" data-solved="unsolved">
                <td><a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/problem/24">Single Neuron</a></td>
                <td>deep learning</td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Easy</span>
                    
                </td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Unsolved</span>
                    
                </td>
            </tr>
            
            <tr data-difficulty="medium" data-category="deep learning" data-solved="unsolved">
                <td><a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/problem/25">Single Neuron with Backpropagation</a></td>
                <td>deep learning</td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Medium</span>
                    
                </td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Unsolved</span>
                    
                </td>
            </tr>
            
            <tr data-difficulty="medium" data-category="deep learning" data-solved="unsolved">
                <td><a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/problem/26">Implementing Basic Autograd Operations</a></td>
                <td>deep learning</td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Medium</span>
                    
                </td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Unsolved</span>
                    
                </td>
            </tr>
            
            <tr data-difficulty="easy" data-category="linear algebra" data-solved="unsolved">
                <td><a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/problem/3">Reshape Matrix</a></td>
                <td>linear algebra</td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Easy</span>
                    
                </td>
                <td>
                    
                    <span>Unsolved</span>
                    
                </td>
            </tr>
            
        </tbody>
    </table>

    <!-- Pagination controls -->
    <div>
        
        
        <p><a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/?page=1&amp;difficulty=&amp;category=&amp;solved=">1</a>
        
        <a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/?page=2&amp;difficulty=&amp;category=&amp;solved=">2</a>
        
        
        <a href="https://www.deep-ml.com/?page=2&amp;difficulty=&amp;category=&amp;solved=">Next</a>
        
    </p></div>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Girls in Tech closes its doors after 17 years (167 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://venturebeat.com/games/girls-in-tech-closes-its-doors-after-17-years/</link>
            <guid>40925471</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 10:25:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://venturebeat.com/games/girls-in-tech-closes-its-doors-after-17-years/">https://venturebeat.com/games/girls-in-tech-closes-its-doors-after-17-years/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40925471">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
		
		<section>
			
			<p><time title="2024-07-08T16:31:00+00:00" datetime="2024-07-08T16:31:00+00:00">July 8, 2024 9:31 AM</time>
			</p>
			
		</section>
		<div>
					<p><img width="750" height="686" src="https://venturebeat.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/girls-3.jpg?w=750" alt="Adriana Gascoigne was founder and CEO of Girls in Tech. Pictured in 2022."></p><div><p><span>Adriana Gascoigne is founder and CEO of Girls in Tech.</span></p><p><em>Image Credit: Girls in Tech</em></p></div>		</div><!-- .article-media-header -->
	</div><div id="primary">

		<article id="content">
			<div>
				<div id="boilerplate_2567078"><div dir="auto" data-qa="virtual-list-item" role="listitem" data-qa-hover="true" data-qa-unprocessed="false" data-qa-placeholder="false" id="1695760337.229209" data-item-key="1695760337.229209">
<p><em><span>GamesBeat is excited to partner with Lil Snack to have customized games just for our audience! We know as gamers ourselves, this is an exciting way to engage through play with the GamesBeat content you have already come to love. Start playing games </span><a href="https://venturebeat.com/gamesbeat-lil-snack/"><span>here</span></a><span>.&nbsp;</span></em>

</p>
</div>

<hr></div><p>The <a href="https://girlsintech.org/">Girls in Tech </a>nonprofit women’s tech community is closing its doors after 17 years, according to a newsletter from founder <a href="https://venturebeat.com/business/adriana-gascoigne-on-how-girls-in-tech-can-get-women-to-infiltrate-silicon-valley/">Adriana Gascoigne</a>.</p>



<p>Gascoigne said the decision was made with “sadness and devastation” and was not made lightly.</p>



<p>“It is with a heavy heart that I share the news that Girls in Tech will be closing its doors. This decision was not made lightly, and the sadness and devastation we feel cannot be overstated,” Gascoigne wrote. “For 17 incredible years, we have offered a welcoming community based on empowerment, support, and inspiration for women in the tech industry. Together, we have made a profound impact, helping women reach for the stars and excel in their careers, while working tirelessly to eliminate the gender gap in tech worldwide.”</p>



<figure><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="5616" height="3744" src="https://venturebeat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/adriana-2.jpg?w=800" alt="" srcset="https://venturebeat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/adriana-2.jpg 5616w, https://venturebeat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/adriana-2.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://venturebeat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/adriana-2.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://venturebeat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/adriana-2.jpg?resize=800,533 800w, https://venturebeat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/adriana-2.jpg?resize=1536,1024 1536w, https://venturebeat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/adriana-2.jpg?resize=2048,1365 2048w, https://venturebeat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/adriana-2.jpg?resize=400,267 400w, https://venturebeat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/adriana-2.jpg?resize=750,500 750w, https://venturebeat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/adriana-2.jpg?resize=578,385 578w, https://venturebeat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/adriana-2.jpg?resize=930,620 930w" sizes="(max-width: 5616px) 100vw, 5616px"><figcaption>Adriana Gascoigne (center) founded Girls in Tech 17 years ago.</figcaption></figure>



<p>The group reached more than 250,000 individuals across 35 chapters in 30 countries on six continents. It was founded in Silicon Valley, but <a href="https://venturebeat.com/games/adriana-gascoigne-why-girls-in-tech-moved-to-nashville/">Gascoigne relocated the group to Nashville</a>, Tennessee, in 2022 during the pandemic. I interviewed her numerous times about the group’s mission and goals, and how it rose to greater relevance in fighting the “<a href="https://venturebeat.com/business/girls-in-techs-adriana-gascoigne-fights-the-toxic-culture-of-silicon-valley/">toxic culture</a>” of Silicon Valley.</p>



<div id="boilerplate_2707617"><!-- wp:separator -->
<hr>
<!-- /wp:separator -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong>Lil Snack &amp; GamesBeat</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>GamesBeat is excited to partner with Lil Snack to have customized games just for our audience! We know as gamers ourselves, this is an exciting way to engage through play with the GamesBeat content you have already come to love. <a href="https://venturebeat.com/gamesbeat-lil-snack/">Start playing games now</a>!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:separator -->
<hr>
<!-- /wp:separator --></div><p>“Girls in Tech has always been more than just an organization; it has been a community built on love—love for technology and love for one another. The passion to support, uplift, and inspire each other is what has truly set us apart. I am immensely proud of what we have built together and the lasting impact we have made,” Gascoigne said in the newsletter.</p>



<p>The group’s programs included a mentorship program, hackathons, coding bootcamps, the Girls in Tech Conference, a startup challenge, global classroom, podcast, blog, jobs board, and shop. The group organized thousands of in-person and virtual events, producing educational and engaging content. </p>



<figure><img decoding="async" width="1200" height="800" src="https://venturebeat.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/girls-in-tech-nyse.jpg?w=800" alt="" srcset="https://venturebeat.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/girls-in-tech-nyse.jpg 1200w, https://venturebeat.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/girls-in-tech-nyse.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://venturebeat.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/girls-in-tech-nyse.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://venturebeat.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/girls-in-tech-nyse.jpg?resize=800,533 800w, https://venturebeat.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/girls-in-tech-nyse.jpg?resize=400,267 400w, https://venturebeat.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/girls-in-tech-nyse.jpg?resize=750,500 750w, https://venturebeat.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/girls-in-tech-nyse.jpg?resize=578,385 578w, https://venturebeat.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/girls-in-tech-nyse.jpg?resize=930,620 930w" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px"><figcaption>Adriana Gascoigne (in blue) after ringing closing bell at NYSE on Dec. 27 in 2016.</figcaption></figure>



<p>“To everyone who poured their heart into building this wonderful community where women in tech could have a voice, learn, grow, and be celebrated just as they are—I am profoundly grateful,” Gascoigne said. “A special thanks to all of our members, who established such a friendly, warm, and collaborative environment and culture; the managing directors and advisory board teams who led our chapters; our staff at headquarters who managed and grew the organization; our sponsors who funded our programs and events; and our board of directors.”</p>



<p>Without explanation, Gascoigne said in closing, “Though Girls in Tech is closing its doors, the movement we started must and will continue. I encourage each of you to carry on the fight to eliminate the gender gap in tech. Our mission will live on in other forms, driven by the same passion and commitment that have always defined us. I will miss you all deeply. Thank you for being a part of this incredible journey.”</p>
<div id="boilerplate_2663995">
				<p><strong>GB Daily</strong></p>
				<p>Stay in the know! Get the latest news in your inbox daily</p>
				
				<p>By subscribing, you agree to VentureBeat's <a href="https://venturebeat.com/terms-of-service/">Terms of Service.</a></p>
				<p id="boilerplateNewsletterConfirmation">
					Thanks for subscribing. Check out more <a href="https://venturebeat.com/newsletters/">VB newsletters here</a>.
				</p>
				<p>An error occured.</p>
			</div>			</div><!-- .article-content -->

							
			
		</article><!-- #content .article-wrapper -->

	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Plausible Community Edition (121 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://plausible.io/blog/community-edition</link>
            <guid>40925266</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 09:48:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://plausible.io/blog/community-edition">https://plausible.io/blog/community-edition</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40925266">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div> <p><strong>TL;DR</strong>: We’re introducing the “free as in beer”, self-hosted and AGPL-licensed Plausible Community Edition (CE). <a href="https://github.com/plausible/community-edition/">Installation instructions are here</a>.</p> <p>In October 2020, we changed <a href="https://plausible.io/blog/open-source-licenses">from the MIT to the AGPL license</a> to prevent corporations from exploiting our code without giving back.</p> <p>As mentioned at the time, we wanted a “don’t be evil” license. Here’s the quote of what we wrote more than three years ago on what we were trying to accomplish with the license change:</p> <blockquote> <ul> <li>We want to prevent corporations from taking our code and using it as part of their closed-source proprietary products</li> <li>We want to prevent corporations from offering Plausible as a service without contributing to the open source project</li> <li>We want to prevent corporations from confusing people and making them think that the service they sell is in any shape or form approved by the original team</li> </ul> <p>And we don’t want this to in any way impact the actual use case Plausible is built for. A completely open source and self-hostable web analytics tool that helps people de-Googlify their sites and respect the privacy of their visitors.</p> </blockquote> <p>That license change has helped us build <a href="https://plausible.io/blog/open-source-saas">a sustainable open source project</a> with 8 core team members and several paid external contributors at the time of writing. We don’t have any investors, so all this is solely funded by the fees our 12,000+ subscribers pay us.</p> <p>As we’ve progressed in our journey, we’ve become aware that despite its advantages, the AGPL license doesn’t go far enough to protect us against all the threats we face. To better protect our project in the future, we’re changing some things about our self-hosted release. These changes don’t affect anyone subscribing to the Plausible Analytics managed hosting in the cloud. Everything stays the same there.</p> <p>If you have a blog, a personal site or a business site, we want you to be able to self-host our code on your servers without needing to pay us any fees if that’s your preference. Nothing changes about this either. Our self-hosted code continues being AGPL-licensed, “free as in beer” and is the same code running in the production on our Plausible Analytics managed hosting in the cloud.&nbsp;</p> <p>Here’s more on what’s being changed and why.</p> <ol id="markdown-toc"> <li><a href="#threats-were-facing" id="markdown-toc-threats-were-facing">Threats we’re facing</a></li> <li><a href="#sticking-to-the-agpl-license" id="markdown-toc-sticking-to-the-agpl-license">Sticking to the AGPL license&nbsp;</a></li> <li><a href="#changes-were-making-to-our-self-hosted-release" id="markdown-toc-changes-were-making-to-our-self-hosted-release">Changes we’re making to our self-hosted release</a> <ol> <li><a href="#our-self-hosted-release-will-be-called-plausible-community-edition" id="markdown-toc-our-self-hosted-release-will-be-called-plausible-community-edition">Our self-hosted release will be called Plausible Community Edition</a></li> <li><a href="#a-stronger-moat-for-our-official-managed-hosting" id="markdown-toc-a-stronger-moat-for-our-official-managed-hosting">A stronger moat for our official managed hosting</a></li> <li><a href="#features-to-be-offered-on-top-of-plausible-ce" id="markdown-toc-features-to-be-offered-on-top-of-plausible-ce">Features to be offered on top of Plausible CE</a></li> </ol> </li> <li><a href="#ensuring-the-continuous-sustainability" id="markdown-toc-ensuring-the-continuous-sustainability">Ensuring the continuous sustainability</a></li> </ol> <h2 id="threats-were-facing">Threats we’re facing</h2> <p>We want to reduce the threat from businesses such as hosting companies and other resellers who try to commercialize popular open source projects. We’ve seen our self-hosted code being used in a way it was never intended for by corporations that don’t care about us or open source. Our license doesn’t prevent these corporations from using the Plausible Analytics name and logo either, as these are a part of our self-hosted code.</p> <p>We face threats both from single-tenant and multi-tenant hosts and resellers. These entities compete against us using our work and brand without contributing back. For them it’s a business opportunity to commercialize open source software. They are even damaging our brand. We’ve had cases of these entities:</p> <ul> <li>Confusing people and making them think that we approve of the service they run</li> <li>Reselling our self-hosted code while running Google Analytics and other surveillance capitalism scripts on their site</li> <li>Using Google and Amazon-owned servers despite promising that they’re running on <a href="https://plausible.io/blog/google-analytics-illegal">EU-owned infrastructure</a></li> <li>Having a bad user experience with under provisioned servers, slow loading time, frequent downtime and no support&nbsp;</li> <li>Running paid advertising on Google and paying referral fees for people to promote them. Both marketing tactics that <a href="https://plausible.io/blog/best-marketing-practices">we say no to ourselves</a></li> </ul> <p>These use cases were never the intention behind our self-hosted release. We wanted to give site owners a way to de-Google their sites even if they didn’t want to or couldn’t use our managed service. Now, we’re facing situations where companies much larger than us with much bigger resources use our brand to compete against us and gain a business advantage.</p> <p>It’s telling that these entities rarely decide to build their brand on top of our code. They prefer to use the brand we’ve built instead as it gives them a better and easier starting point. These actions not only threaten our sustainability but also mislead people who trust the Plausible Analytics name. We want to ensure that anyone using or considering our services knows precisely what they’re getting, without confusion or misrepresentation.</p> <h2 id="sticking-to-the-agpl-license">Sticking to the AGPL license&nbsp;</h2> <p>We’re real people who have rent to pay and mouths to feed. We make $300 per month from donations from our self-hosted users. It would take us more than ten years of donations to pay one month of salary for our small team. If we cannot capture the economic value of our work, the project will become unsustainable and die.</p> <p>We believe this would not only hurt us as people but also all of the users of the product. Our self-hosted users directly benefit from the investments we can put into product development. All this is made possible and solely funded by the revenue we get from our managed hosting in the cloud.</p> <p>We’ve learned that being open source and transparent has costs. Dealing with these threats is an incredibly taxing and time-consuming distraction for our small team. It’s something our proprietary competitors never even have to think about.</p> <p>Several popular open source projects have shifted away from traditional models in the last few years because of similar threats that we’re facing. They’re adopting licenses such as the Business Source License (BSL) or the Server Side Public License (SSPL) as these licenses more directly address the concerns about resellers and hosting companies.</p> <p>These licenses are <a href="https://opensource.org/licenses/">not approved nor recognized by the Open Source Initiative (OSI)</a>, which is why we’re not interested in switching to them. We want to stay open source to continue providing a transparent and privacy-friendly web analytics tool with a “free as in beer” self-hosted release.</p> <h2 id="changes-were-making-to-our-self-hosted-release">Changes we’re making to our self-hosted release</h2> <p>Here’s how we’ll proceed with our self-hosted release. These changes will go live with the next version of our self-hosted release (2.1.0).&nbsp;<a href="https://github.com/plausible/analytics/releases/tag/v2.1.0-rc.0">Release notes are here</a>.</p>  <p>Our self-hosted release will be renamed Plausible Community Edition (or Plausible CE). Plausible CE will also have a different logo from the Plausible Analytics managed hosting in the cloud. This is the main change you’ll see if you’re running our self-hosted code on your server.&nbsp;</p> <p>Plausible CE continues to be AGPL-licensed and “free as in beer”. It continues to be the same code running in the production on our managed hosting. As we’ve done so far, we’ll keep maintaining, improving and adding features to the Plausible CE with new releases twice annually.</p> <p>To further protect our brand from threats, we’ve registered trademarks for Plausible Analytics on both sides of the Atlantic.&nbsp;</p> <h3 id="a-stronger-moat-for-our-official-managed-hosting">A stronger moat for our official managed hosting</h3> <p>We’re excluding features we use to manage Plausible Analytics at scale, such as the sites API and customer relationship management system, from Plausible CE. As a self-hoster, you likely haven’t noticed these features, as they’ve been undocumented and are primarily helpful when providing web analytics as a service.</p> <p>We’re also keeping some of the newly released business and enterprise features (<a href="https://plausible.io/docs/funnel-analysis">funnels</a> and <a href="https://plausible.io/docs/ecommerce-revenue-tracking">ecommerce revenue metrics</a> at the time of being) exclusive to the business plan subscribers on our Plausible Analytics managed hosting.&nbsp;</p> <p>The code for all these features is still available to the public so it can be reviewed and inspected, but these features will not be a part of Plausible CE and they’ll have a different license.</p> <p>This change also means that if you want to contribute to our codebase in the future as an external contributor, you’ll need to sign a Contributor License Agreement (CLA).</p> <p>To provide a better service and experience to people who pay our bills, Plausible CE will continue to not have any premium customer support and is <a href="https://plausible.io/blog/building-open-source">community-supported only</a>.</p> <p>This open core model is something that GitLab and other open source projects have championed and we believe it’s the best and most open source friendly approach for the situation we’re in.</p> <h3 id="features-to-be-offered-on-top-of-plausible-ce">Features to be offered on top of Plausible CE</h3> <p>The plan moving forward is to carefully consider which features to keep exclusive to our managed cloud hosting. These will predominantly be features that help us run our managed hosting at scale and enterprise features. We aim always to ensure a protective barrier around our cloud offering.</p> <p>This doesn’t mean that all business and enterprise features won’t ever make it to the Plausible CE. Nothing from Plausible CE will be taken away in the future and we plan to periodically evaluate business and enterprise features to be added to Plausible CE.&nbsp;</p> <p>For instance, we’ve already decided to release <a href="https://plausible.io/docs/custom-props/introduction">custom properties</a> (another business feature in the cloud) as part of the Plausible CE. We’ll update the release notes with any new features making their way to Plausible CE in the future.</p> <h2 id="ensuring-the-continuous-sustainability">Ensuring the continuous sustainability</h2> <p>These changes will affect corporations that take our code to compete directly against us as it will create a more substantial moat and better protection for our official managed hosting. It will get more challenging for them to misrepresent their association with us or use our brand and logo misleadingly. And they won’t be able to offer a fully featured Plausible Analytics product with all the enterprise features included either.</p> <p>Many indie hackers that contact us about our experience of running an open source startup tell us that their main concern about open sourcing their code is the risk that large corporations will resell that code and take advantage of their project. It’s a valid concern. We hope that our new approach mitigates most potential downsides and still allows the upsides of releasing our code free to the world.&nbsp;</p> <p>With the change of our self-hosted release name and logo, the registration of our trademarks and the exclusive availability of certain enterprise features to our managed cloud hosting, we aim to better ensure the sustainability of Plausible Analytics in the face of external threats in the future. Thank you for your support!</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://github.com/plausible/community-edition/">Plausible CE installation instructions</a></li> <li><a href="https://github.com/plausible/analytics/releases/tag/v2.1.0-rc.0">Plausible CE 2.1.0&nbsp;release notes</a>.</li> <li>Complete overview of differences <a href="https://plausible.io/self-hosted-web-analytics">between Plausible Analytics Cloud and Plausible CE</a></li> </ul> </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[SimSig: Railway Signalling Simulations (167 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.simsig.co.uk/</link>
            <guid>40925025</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 09:02:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.simsig.co.uk/">https://www.simsig.co.uk/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40925025">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
				



<h2>Welcome to the home of Railway Signalling Simulations</h2>

<h2>So what is SimSig?</h2>

<p>
    Welcome to the world of railway signalling! SimSig brings the signal box to your home PC and with it the enjoyment and frustrations of running today's (and some of yesterday's) railways. How often has your train been delayed because of "signal failure" and you've wondered why trains can't be routed around the problem - or why it is even a problem in the first place? You'll soon see exactly why - with SimSig!
</p>
<p>
    SimSig puts you in the seat of a signaller, also called a Dispatcher or Network Control Officer, operating signalling screens based on the widely used IECC and Westcad graphics used in the UK. That is, you operate the signals and points/switches
    in order to get trains to their destinations on time. SimSig has a wide range of areas you can operate including large portions of the UK, a small US
    simulation, and a couple of Australian areas. Each has its own challenges and skill level, the latter ranging from easy to mentally complicated.
</p>
<table>
    <tbody><tr>
        <td>
            <img height="240" src="https://www.simsig.co.uk/Media/CScot.jpg">
            <p><small><i>A desk in Edinburgh Signalling Centre - Glasgow Queen Street area.<br>Used with permission from <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/llangollen_signalman/22343617026/in/album-72157657838220013/">Andrew Gardiner.</a></i></small></p>
        </td>
        <td>
            <img height="240" src="https://www.simsig.co.uk/Media/CScot2.jpg">
            <p><small><i>A signalling screen in Edinburgh Signalling Centre - Glasgow Queen Street.<br>Used with permission from <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/llangollen_signalman/22181604250/in/album-72157657838220013/">Andrew Gardiner.</a></i></small></p>
        </td>
    </tr>
</tbody></table>

<h3>The Brief Specs</h3>
<ul>
    <li>Replicates the operation of British IECCs (Integrated Electronic Control Centres)</li>
    <li>All signalling equipment simulated (track circuits, points, signals, etc.)</li>
    <li>Correct signalling (overlaps, aspect sequencing, approach control)</li>
    <li>Emphasis is on quality and realism, not quantity</li>
    <li>Used by signallers, drivers, and other professionals from all over the world</li>
    <li>User oriented - tell us what you want, we'll try to produce it!</li>
    <li>Free demo downloads of every simulation available right now</li>
</ul>

<p>SimSig runs on Windows 8.1 and 10.</p>

<p>
    <i>
        SimSig also runs on <a href="https://www.simsig.co.uk/Wiki/Show?page=usertrack:install">emulators such as Wine for Linux and Crossover for Mac</a>. This is not guaranteed but we try to keep such emulators supported.
        Tablets and phones are not supported.
    </i>
</p>

<h2>How much is it?</h2>

<p>
    You can peruse prices in our <a href="https://www.simsig.co.uk/Store">Shop</a> but we have several <b>free</b> simulations, then range from under £10 upwards,
    depending on the complexity of the simulation. All simulations come with an evaluation period so you can try before you buy.
</p>

<h2>Can I play with friends?</h2>

<p>
    Yes! Many of our simulations are suitable for multiplayer. The larger simulations have as many as nine positions keeping people busy. But many
    simulations also have optional automation such as ARS (Automatic Route Setting) which means you can run a larger simulation by yourself.
</p>

<p>
    Multiplayer works over the Internet, or your home LAN. One person acts as the host while others connect with an IP address and port number. We
    have run multiplayers across the world with members in the UK, the US, Australia, Europe, and elsewhere.
</p>

<p>Many simulations can be "chained", which is where adjacent areas can be linked together to form a larger area.</p>

<h2>Can I contribute?</h2>

<p>
    Unlike other products, anybody can write a timetable using the in-built timetable editor. We also do not charge for extra timetables. Our files
    area has plenty of user-contributed timetables to download.
</p>

<p><i>Sorry, users cannot produce simulations themselves.</i></p>

<h2>What does it look like?</h2>

<p><img src="https://www.simsig.co.uk/Media/LivSt2.gif"></p><p>
    Here we have the free Liverpool Street simulation running. ARS (automatic route setting) is setting the routes but we can easily take over.
    The eighteen platforms at Liverpool Street in London are very busy during the morning rush hour that we see here. The blue four-character
    labels are the train descriptions (like a flight number) such as 2H07. The signaller can identify the routing and destination of the train
    from that train description. The flashing white blobs indicate that a train is ready to depart. White lines show route set for trains, while
    you can see the signals showing red (stop), yellow (caution), double yellow (preliminary caution), or green.
</p>
<p><i>This animated GIF is running at approximately 4x normal speed.</i></p>
<center>
    
    
    <p><i><small>You must download and install the system files (from the <b>Download Now!</b> link above; under 3MB) before any simulations can be played</small></i></p>
    <br>
</center>

			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Europe's new Ariane 6 rocket powers into space (306 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.esa.int/Enabling_Support/Space_Transportation/Ariane/Europe_s_new_Ariane_6_rocket_powers_into_space</link>
            <guid>40924915</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 08:42:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.esa.int/Enabling_Support/Space_Transportation/Ariane/Europe_s_new_Ariane_6_rocket_powers_into_space">https://www.esa.int/Enabling_Support/Space_Transportation/Ariane/Europe_s_new_Ariane_6_rocket_powers_into_space</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40924915">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>

<header>
	<span>Enabling &amp; Support</span>
	
	<p><span>09/07/2024</span>
				<span><span id="viewcount">16881</span><small> views</small></span>
										<span><span id="ezsr_total_26221596">131</span><small> likes</small></span>
				
	</p>
</header>




<p>Europe's new heavy-lift rocket, Ariane 6, made its inaugural flight from Europe's Spaceport in French Guiana at 16:00 &nbsp;local time on 9 July (20:00 BST, 21:00 CEST).</p>
			
    
							
														
																	



							
				
								
						
								
												<div>
				<figure>
					<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/07/Ariane_6_takes_flight">
				<img src="https://www.esa.int/var/esa/storage/images/esa_multimedia/images/2024/07/ariane_6_takes_flight/26221386-1-eng-GB/Ariane_6_takes_flight_article.jpg" alt="Ariane 6 takes flight">
			</a>
				<figcaption>
							<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/07/Ariane_6_takes_flight">Ariane 6 takes flight</a>
								</figcaption>
	</figure>	
		<p>Ariane 6 is the latest in Europe's Ariane rocket series, taking over from Ariane 5, and featuring a modular and versatile design that can launch missions from low-Earth orbit and farther out into deep space.</p><p>"A completely new rocket is not launched often, and success is far from guaranteed. I am privileged to have witnessed this historic moment when Europe's new generation of the Ariane family lifted off – successfully – effectively reinstating European access to space,” said ESA's Director General Josef Aschbacher.</p><p>"An inaugural launch is a huge undertaking from thousands of people who have worked relentlessly for years. To see it perform wonderfully at the first attempt is testament to their dedication and a demonstration of European excellence in engineering and technology. Heartfelt thanks go to the teams at ESA, CNES, ArianeGroup and Arianespace for their hard work to get to this point. I also want to sincerely thank our Member States for having enabled and supported the Ariane 6 programme along the way. Not always easy, but the endurance shown has paid off handsomely today."</p>	</div>	
    
							
														
																	



							
				
								
						
								
												<div>
				<figure>
					<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/06/Installing_first_passengers_on_Ariane_6">
				<img src="https://www.esa.int/var/esa/storage/images/esa_multimedia/images/2024/06/installing_first_passengers_on_ariane_6/26185257-2-eng-GB/Installing_first_passengers_on_Ariane_6_article.jpg" alt="Installing first passengers on Ariane 6">
			</a>
				<figcaption>
							<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/06/Installing_first_passengers_on_Ariane_6">Installing first passengers on Ariane 6</a>
								</figcaption>
	</figure>	
		<p>This inaugural flight, designated VA262, is a demonstration flight whose aim is to show the capabilities and prowess of Ariane 6 in escaping Earth's gravity and operating in space. Nevertheless, it had several passengers on board.</p><p>At 21:06 BST, 22:06 CEST,&nbsp;one hour after liftoff, the first set of satellites on board Ariane 6 were released from the upper stage and placed into an orbit 600 km above Earth. Satellites and experiments from various space agencies, companies, research institutes, universities and young professionals were included on this inaugural flight.</p>	</div>	
    
							
														
																	



							
				
								
						
								
												<div>
				<figure>
					<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/07/Ariane_6_from_above_in_the_final_hours_before_liftoff">
				<img src="https://www.esa.int/var/esa/storage/images/esa_multimedia/images/2024/07/ariane_6_from_above_in_the_final_hours_before_liftoff/26220789-1-eng-GB/Ariane_6_from_above_in_the_final_hours_before_liftoff_article.jpg" alt="Ariane 6 from above in the final hours before liftoff">
			</a>
				<figcaption>
							<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/07/Ariane_6_from_above_in_the_final_hours_before_liftoff">Ariane 6 from above in the final hours before liftoff</a>
								</figcaption>
	</figure>	
		<p>In addition to the rocket, the liftoff demonstrated the functioning of the launch pad and operations on the ground at Europe's Spaceport. The new custom-built dedicated launch zone was built by France's space agency CNES and allows for a faster turnover of Ariane launches.</p><p>On the occasion of the launch, Philippe Baptiste, CEO of CNES, said: “With this first successful launch by Ariane 6, Europe has finally recovered its capacity to access space. Beyond the great emotion I am feeling right now, my first thoughts are for all the teams in Kourou, Paris, Vernon, Les Mureaux, Toulouse, Bremen, Lampoldshausen, Liège, Barcelona, Colleferro, Zürich and everywhere else in Europe who made this success possible. I would like to acknowledge the commitment of the employees of CNES, ESA, ArianeGroup, Arianespace and our subcontractors. The last few months have been intense, and I would like to thank them all. Europe can be proud of its space programme, Europe can be proud of its knowledge and expertise. Together, let's prepare the future of launchers and space.”</p>	</div>	
    
						
			<p>Ariane 6 was built by prime contractor and design authority ArianeGroup. “With the successful first flight of Ariane&nbsp;6, the European space industry has moved into a new era,” said Martin Sion, CEO of ArianeGroup. “This historic launch demonstrates the unfailing commitment of our teams and partners, whom I would like to thank warmly for this success, which reflects on the entire European industry. Seeing Europe’s new launcher lift off into space marks the culmination of an outstanding technical and technological adventure, and the beginning of a long history of Ariane&nbsp;6 operations. The next flight models are already in production and the stages of the second model will be shipped to the Guiana Space Centre this autumn for the first commercial flight of Ariane&nbsp;6.”</p>	
	<div>
	<h2>Next: tech demos, controlled deorbit and capsule separation</h2>
	    
							
														
																	



							
				
								
						
								
											<figure>
					<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/07/Ariane_6_first_flight_timeline">
				<img src="https://www.esa.int/var/esa/storage/images/esa_multimedia/images/2024/07/ariane_6_first_flight_timeline/26212783-1-eng-GB/Ariane_6_first_flight_timeline_article.jpg" alt="Ariane 6 first flight timeline">
			</a>
				<figcaption>
							<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/07/Ariane_6_first_flight_timeline">Ariane 6 first flight timeline</a>
								</figcaption>
	</figure>	
		<p>With the placement of satellites into orbit, Ariane 6 has demonstrated that it can successfully launch its payloads into space, but ground control has more in store for its inaugural flight. Over the next hour, Ariane 6's upper stage will show again that it can restart its Vinci engine using the novel auxiliary propulsion unit. This restart capability will allow Ariane 6 to drop off multiple passengers into different orbits on future flights and deorbit itself through Earth’s atmosphere at the end of its mission, to ensure it does not become space debris.</p><p>On this flight the Ariane 6 upper stage is set to release two reentry capsules as it enters Earth's atmosphere for a clean disposal to burn up harmlessly, leaving no space debris in orbit.</p>	</div>	
    
							
														
																	



							
				
								
						
								
												<div>
				<figure>
					<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/03/Artist_s_view_of_the_Ariane_6">
				<img src="https://www.esa.int/var/esa/storage/images/esa_multimedia/images/2024/03/artist_s_view_of_the_ariane_6/25987586-2-eng-GB/Artist_s_view_of_the_Ariane_6_article.jpg" alt="Artist's view of the Ariane 6">
			</a>
				<figcaption>
							<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/03/Artist_s_view_of_the_Ariane_6">Artist's view of the Ariane 6</a>
								</figcaption>
	</figure>	
		<p>The next Ariane 6 is planned for launch this year on its first commercial flight under Arianespace as operator and launch service provider. “The success of this first flight marks the start of Ariane&nbsp;6’s operational career, giving Europe an autonomous access to space,” added Stéphane Israël, CEO of Arianespace. “The new launcher’s order book is proof of the versatility of Ariane 6 and of its capacity to accomplish a wide range of missions into multiple orbits. It reflects the confidence that customers have in Ariane 6 for both their institutional and commercial missions. We are eager to begin operating our new launcher.”</p>	</div>	
    
						
    
						
    
						
    
					



</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Children's daily sugar consumption halved just a year after tax, study finds (108 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/society/article/2024/jul/09/childrens-daily-sugar-consumption-halves-just-a-year-after-tax-study-finds</link>
            <guid>40924527</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 07:36:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/society/article/2024/jul/09/childrens-daily-sugar-consumption-halves-just-a-year-after-tax-study-finds">https://www.theguardian.com/society/article/2024/jul/09/childrens-daily-sugar-consumption-halves-just-a-year-after-tax-study-finds</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40924527">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p>The amount of sugar consumed by children from soft drinks in the UK halved within a year of the sugar tax being introduced, a study has found.</p><p>The tax, which came into force in April 2018, has been so successful in improving people’s diets that experts have said an expansion to cover other high sugar food and drink products is now a “no-brainer”.</p><p>The <a href="https://jech.bmj.com/lookup/doi/10.1136/jech-2023-221051" data-link-name="in body link">research</a>, published in the Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health, looked at responses from 7,999 adults and 7,656 children between 2008 and 2019 to the annual nationally representative UK National Diet and Nutrition Survey.</p><p>It showed that the daily sugar intake for children fell by about 4.8g, and for adults 10.9g, in the year after the levy’s introduction.</p><p>The total dietary free sugars, including food and drink, in children was about 70g a day at the beginning of the study, but this fell to about 45g by the end.</p><p>For adults, the study found that the total dietary free sugar consumption stood at about 60g a day, and fell to about 45g a day by the end of the study.</p><p>But despite this reduction, the amount of sugar consumed by adults and children still remains above the recommended guidelines and is contributing to high levels of tooth decay, obesity, diabetes and other illnesses.</p><p>The study found that compared to the period before the sugar tax was announced in 2016, free sugars consumed from all soft drinks reduced by around a half in children, and by a third in adults, after the levy was announced.</p><p>The researchers also note that the fall in consumption of free sugars observed in the whole diet rather than just from soft drinks suggests that consumption of free sugar from food was also falling from as early as 2008.</p><p>Eddie Crouch, the chair of the British Dental Association, said that the sugar tax was delivering “tangible results” and was effective.</p><p>He added: “Extending it to the likes of cereals is a no-brainer for any government that cares about prevention. This needn’t add to the cost of living. Where voluntary action on reformulation has failed, the levy forces the food industry to do the right thing.”</p><p>According to the World <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/society/health" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">Health</a> Organization and the UK Scientific Advisory Committee on Nutrition, the consumption of free sugar should be below 5% of a person’s total calorie intake. For adults, this would be limited to 30g of sugar a day, 24g for children aged between 7 and 10, and 19g for children aged between 4 and 6.</p><p>Dr Nina Rogers, the lead author of the study and part of the University of Cambridge School of Clinical Medicine, said: “The findings of our study are encouraging and show that the UK soft drinks industry levy is linked to a significant reduction in daily sugar intake in adults and children. These results are consistent with previous research which show a reduction in household purchasing of sugar from soft drinks one year after adoption of the levy.”</p><figure id="c7041e84-e774-4012-b332-a1c667e8109c" data-spacefinder-role="richLink" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.RichLinkBlockElement"><gu-island name="RichLinkComponent" priority="feature" deferuntil="idle" props="{&quot;richLinkIndex&quot;:13,&quot;element&quot;:{&quot;_type&quot;:&quot;model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.RichLinkBlockElement&quot;,&quot;prefix&quot;:&quot;Related: &quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Does Australia need a sugar tax to tackle diabetes, and how would it work?&quot;,&quot;elementId&quot;:&quot;c7041e84-e774-4012-b332-a1c667e8109c&quot;,&quot;role&quot;:&quot;richLink&quot;,&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/article/2024/jul/04/australia-sugar-tax-diabetes-parliamentary-report&quot;},&quot;ajaxUrl&quot;:&quot;https://api.nextgen.guardianapps.co.uk&quot;,&quot;format&quot;:{&quot;display&quot;:0,&quot;theme&quot;:0,&quot;design&quot;:0}}"></gu-island></figure><p>She added: “The new UK government might want to consider extending the tax to other (currently exempt) drinks which have a high sugar content, or even to some foods. They might also want to look at restructuring the tax to apply a per gram of sugar/100mls rather than threshold-based levy.”</p><p>Dr Kawther Hashem, a lecturer in Public Health Nutrition at Queen Mary University of London, said: “This new analysis drives home the importance of policies designed to improve the nutritional quality of food and drink. In particular, the soft drinks industry levy (SDIL) in the UK has proven to be an effective lever to encourage food and drink manufacturers to reduce sugar.</p><p>“With a new government now in place, policymakers are urged to consider applying a similar levy to other discretionary products that are key contributors to sugar intake, such as chocolate confectionery, to shift diets towards a healthier direction.”</p><p>A Department of Health and Social Care spokesperson said: “This government will take action to prevent ill-health and tackle the obesity crisis head on, easing the strain on the <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/society/nhs" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">NHS</a> and helping people to live well for longer.</p><p>“We will introduce tight restrictions on advertising junk food, alongside banning children from being able to purchase sugary, high-caffeine energy drinks.</p><p>“By building a healthier society, we will help to build a healthy economy.”</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Well, it's just an AWS Account ID (103 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://mail.cloudsecurity.club/p/well-just-aws-account-id</link>
            <guid>40923188</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 02:21:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://mail.cloudsecurity.club/p/well-just-aws-account-id">https://mail.cloudsecurity.club/p/well-just-aws-account-id</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40923188">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content-blocks"><div><p><img alt="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/84f13d14-127d-45ba-ba1e-8e45e34a6e59/Well__it_s_just_an_AWS_Account_ID_.jpg?t=1720417241"></p></div><p> Let’s dive into a highly debated topic common in the AWS Security Community: <b>AWS Account IDs</b>. </p><p> You might think, "It's just a number, right?" Well, let’s see if you hold on to the same opinion by the end of this post. </p><p id="whats-the-big-deal-with-aws-account"><h2>What's the Big Deal with AWS Account IDs?</h2></p><p> First things first, let's get our basics straight. </p><p> Every AWS account has a unique 12-digit identifier. </p><div><ol start="1"><li><p> These IDs are part of most AWS resource's <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/IAM/latest/UserGuide/reference-arns.html?utm_source=mail.cloudsecurity.club&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=well-it-s-just-an-aws-account-id" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">Amazon Resource Name</a> (ARN). </p></li><li><p> They're crucial for sharing resources between accounts (using resource policies or Resource Access Manager) </p></li><li><p> They're used in sharing resources outside your AWS accounts, especially with external vendors. </p></li></ol></div><p> In simple terms, your AWS Account ID is your identity in the AWS cloud. If someone needs to access your resources or if you need to intentionally share your resources with others, you need to provide them with your AWS Account ID. </p><p id="the-power-of-knowing-an-account-id"><h2>The Power of Knowing an Account ID</h2></p><p> Imagine you're a red teamer or black box pentester (or worse, an attacker). With just an Account ID, you can: </p><p><b>Bruteforce IAM Entities:</b> You can bruteforce for the existence of common IAM users and roles. This information is gold for phishing attacks, social engineering, or password spraying. You can also see the user name patterns for IAM users (especially those of the target’s infra or DevOps team). An attacker with this information could craft convincing phishing emails or vishing scripts targeting the company's cloud team. </p><div><p><span>Tool Spotlight: Check out the </span><span><a href="https://github.com/dagrz/aws_pwn/blob/master/reconnaissance/validate_iam_principals.py?utm_source=mail.cloudsecurity.club&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=well-it-s-just-an-aws-account-id" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">validate_iam_principals.py</a></span><span> script in the </span><span><a href="https://github.com/dagrz/aws_pwn?utm_source=mail.cloudsecurity.club&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=well-it-s-just-an-aws-account-id" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">aws_pwn</a></span><span> GitHub repository. It allows you to test for the existence of IAM users and roles when you know the Account ID.</span></p></div><p><b>Discover Services in Use: </b>By checking for specific <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/IAM/latest/UserGuide/id_roles_terms-and-concepts.html?utm_source=mail.cloudsecurity.club&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=well-it-s-just-an-aws-account-id#iam-term-service-linked-role" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">AWS Service Linked Roles</a>, you can deduce which AWS services or third-party security tools a company uses. </p><p> Example: If you find a role named <code>AWSServiceRoleForAmazonGuardDuty</code>, the account might use GuardDuty for threat detection. I say “might” here because enabling an AWS service like GuardDuty will create the service-linked role. But if you turn it off, AWS will not delete the role. If the role doesn’t exist, it's 100% certain that GuardDuty is not enabled in the target account. </p><p> Note: You can use the same technique to determine whether the target AWS account uses services like EKS or ECS, allowing you to fine-tune your attacks and web app payloads. </p><p><b>Find Public Resources:</b> You can search for the target company's unintentional public resources, from public EBS snapshots to AMIs. </p><div><ul><li><p> EBS Snapshots: <a href="https://us-east-1.console.aws.amazon.com/ec2/home?region=us-east-1&amp;utm_source=mail.cloudsecurity.club&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=well-it-s-just-an-aws-account-id#Snapshots:visibility=public;sort=snapshotId" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">https://us-east-1.console.aws.amazon.com/ec2/home?region=us-east-1#Snapshots:visibility=public;sort=snapshotId</a></p></li><li><p> RDS Snapshots: <a href="https://us-east-1.console.aws.amazon.com/rds/home?region=us-east-1&amp;utm_source=mail.cloudsecurity.club&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=well-it-s-just-an-aws-account-id#snapshots-list:tab=public" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">https://us-east-1.console.aws.amazon.com/rds/home?region=us-east-1#snapshots-list:tab=public</a></p></li><li><p> DocumentDB Snapshots: <a href="https://us-east-1.console.aws.amazon.com/docdb/home?region=us-east-1&amp;utm_source=mail.cloudsecurity.club&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=well-it-s-just-an-aws-account-id#snapshots" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">https://us-east-1.console.aws.amazon.com/docdb/home?region=us-east-1#snapshots</a></p></li><li><p> Neptune Snapshots: <a href="https://us-east-1.console.aws.amazon.com/neptune/home?region=us-east-1&amp;utm_source=mail.cloudsecurity.club&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=well-it-s-just-an-aws-account-id#snapshots:type=public" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">https://us-east-1.console.aws.amazon.com/neptune/home?region=us-east-1#snapshots:type=public</a></p></li><li><p> Public AMIs: <a href="https://us-east-1.console.aws.amazon.com/ec2/home?region=us-east-1&amp;utm_source=mail.cloudsecurity.club&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=well-it-s-just-an-aws-account-id#Images:visibility=public-images" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">https://us-east-1.console.aws.amazon.com/ec2/home?region=us-east-1#Images:visibility=public-images</a></p></li></ul></div><p><b>Correlate Resources (Niche):</b> You can confirm if a leaked resource belongs to a specific company. </p><p> Account IDs can be crucial in HackerOne or other bug bounty reports where you can correlate a misconfigured S3 bucket leaking PII belonging to the target company by matching Account IDs. </p><p><b>Evade Detection (Niche):</b> Some security tools, like <a href="https://canarytokens.org/?utm_source=mail.cloudsecurity.club&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=well-it-s-just-an-aws-account-id" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">CanaryTokens.org</a>, create credentials from known AWS accounts. Identifying the account ID of these intentionally leaked credentials before checking out their permissions will avoid triggering alarms. </p><p id="realworld-example"><h2>Real-world example</h2></p><p> Imagine you found a public object hosted on your target’s S3 bucket. It could be anything - a PDF, an image file, or just some javascript and CSS files: </p><div><pre><code>https://cloudsecclub-bucket.s3.amazonaws.com/some.jpg</code></pre></div><p> You can extract the Account ID from this URL with <a href="https://github.com/WeAreCloudar/s3-account-search?utm_source=mail.cloudsecurity.club&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=well-it-s-just-an-aws-account-id" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">s3-account-search</a> tool. Now what? </p><div><ol start="1"><li><p> You can look for public EBS snapshots, RDS backups, or AMIs. </p></li><li><p> You can even try to guess IAM user names (just search for the target’s employees on LinkedIn). </p></li><li><p> You can enumerate IAM service-linked roles to check out the AWS services in use (probably). Or even stumble upon any security tools they use in the company (Wiz, Datadog, etc.) </p></li></ol></div><p> Each piece of information you gather paints a clearer picture of the company's AWS footprint. And remember, we started with just a bucket URL! </p><p id="the-recon-goldmine"><h2>The Recon Goldmine</h2></p><p> In my cloud security research, I've seen Account IDs pop up in multiple places: </p><div><ul><li><p> GitHub repositories (especially in IaC code) </p></li><li><p> Error logs on Stack Overflow </p></li><li><p> Public Docker images (including public ECR images) </p></li><li><p> Even in the documentation of security vendors! </p></li></ul></div><p id="the-bigger-picture"><h2>The Bigger Picture</h2></p><div><p><img alt="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/6022f7a5-c5e2-49a2-8521-413dba809619/image.png?t=1720417161"></p><p><small><p>Well, it’s just an AWS Account ID!</p></small></p></div><p id="so-is-the-aws-account-id-a-security"><h2>So, Is the AWS Account ID a Security Risk?</h2></p><div><p><img alt="man thinking - scratching head" src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1592827086844-b20636fd80c9?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3w0ODM4NTF8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHwxfHx0aGlua2luZyUyMG1hbnxlbnwwfHx8fDE3MjA0MTY5OTF8MA&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080&amp;utm_source=beehiiv&amp;utm_medium=referral"></p></div><p> Here's my take: The Account ID is useless and not a direct weakness. It's more like a key that helps with other cloud attacks. </p><p> Knowing someone's home address isn't a security breach. But if that address helps a burglar plan their approach, it becomes part of the security equation. </p><p><b>The sensitivity of AWS Account IDs arises from their ability to fetch and correlate resources and gather information for other attacks.</b></p><p> What I do know is it’s a powerful technique in your recon or red team process. </p><p> Worried about your AWS Account exposing public resources? </p><p> What if you could ensure you have no unintended public assets to begin with? </p><p> My upcoming course, "<a href="https://courses.cloudsecurity.club/courses/Securing-AWS-Strategies-for-Lean-Teams-from-Chandrapal-Badshah-666415ee3a16ef700a69c1c5?utm_source=mail.cloudsecurity.club&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=well-it-s-just-an-aws-account-id" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">Secure AWS: Strategies for Lean Teams</a>," teaches you to lock down your entire AWS environment, not just manage Account IDs. Learn to prevent resource exposure, implement robust controls, and avoid costly mistakes - all tailored for lean teams. 🔥&nbsp; </p><p> Early Bird Alert: Enroll now for a <b>60% discount </b>and transform your AWS security posture from reactive to proactive! </p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A New Age of Materials Is Dawning, for Everything from Smartphones to Missiles (114 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wsj.com/tech/composites-manufacturing-boeing-drones-arris-9t-orbital-a422de1b</link>
            <guid>40923124</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 02:09:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/composites-manufacturing-boeing-drones-arris-9t-orbital-a422de1b">https://www.wsj.com/tech/composites-manufacturing-boeing-drones-arris-9t-orbital-a422de1b</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40923124">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.wsj.com/tech/composites-manufacturing-boeing-drones-arris-9t-orbital-a422de1b: Error: Request failed with status code 401]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Seal Failure in the SRB That Doomed Challenger (2021) (111 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://exrocketman.blogspot.com/2021/12/the-seal-failure-in-srb-that-doomed.html</link>
            <guid>40922874</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 01:11:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://exrocketman.blogspot.com/2021/12/the-seal-failure-in-srb-that-doomed.html">https://exrocketman.blogspot.com/2021/12/the-seal-failure-in-srb-that-doomed.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40922874">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post-body-820673899835426973" itemprop="description articleBody">
<p><b>Update 4-8-2024:</b>&nbsp;
Should any readers want to learn how to do what I do (estimating
performance of launch rockets or other space vehicles),&nbsp;&nbsp; be aware that I have created a series of
short courses in how to go about these analyses,&nbsp; complete with effective tools for actually
carrying it out.&nbsp; These course materials are
available for free from a drop box that can be accessed from the Mars Society’s
“New Mars” forums,&nbsp; located at <a href="http://newmars.com/forums/">http://newmars.com/forums/</a>,&nbsp; in the “Acheron labs” section,&nbsp; “interplanetary transportation” topic,&nbsp; and conversation thread titled “orbital
mechanics class traditional”.&nbsp; You may
have scroll down past all the “sticky notes”.&nbsp;
<o:p></o:p></p><p>The first posting in that thread has a list of the classes
available,&nbsp; and these go far beyond just the
two-body elementary orbital mechanics of ellipses.&nbsp; There are the empirical corrections for
losses to be covered,&nbsp; approaches to use
for estimating entry descent and landing on bodies with atmospheres,&nbsp; and spreadsheet-based tools for estimating
the performance of rocket engines and rocket vehicles. &nbsp;The same thread has links to all the materials
in the drop box.&nbsp; <o:p></o:p></p><p>The New Mars forums would also welcome your
participation.&nbsp; Send an email to <a href="mailto:newmarsmember@gmail.com">newmarsmember@gmail.com</a> to find out
how to join up. <o:p></o:p></p><p>A lot of the same information from those short courses is
available scattered among the postings here.&nbsp;
There is a sort of “technical catalog” article that I try to main
current.&nbsp; It is titled “Lists of Some
Articles by Topic Area”,&nbsp; posted 21
October 2021.&nbsp; There are categories for
ramjet and closely-related,&nbsp;
aerothermodynamics and heat transfer,&nbsp;
rocket ballistics and rocket vehicle performance articles (<u>of
specific interest here</u>),&nbsp; asteroid
defense articles,&nbsp; space suits and
atmospheres articles,&nbsp; radiation hazard
articles,&nbsp; pulsejet articles,&nbsp; articles about ethanol and ethanol blends in
vehicles,&nbsp; automotive care articles,&nbsp; articles related to cactus eradication,&nbsp; and articles related to towed decoys.&nbsp; All of these are things that I really
did.&nbsp; <o:p></o:p></p><p>To access quickly any article on this site,&nbsp; use the blog archive tool on the left.&nbsp; All you need is the posting date and the
title.&nbsp; Click on the year,&nbsp; then click on the month,&nbsp; then click on the title if need be (such as if
multiple articles were posted that month).&nbsp;
Visit the catalog article and just jot down those you want to go see. <o:p></o:p></p><p>Within any article,&nbsp;
you can see the figures enlarged, &nbsp;by the expedient of just clicking on a
figure.&nbsp; You can scroll through all the
figures at greatest resolution in an article that way,&nbsp; although the figure numbers and titles are
lacking.&nbsp; There is an “X-out” top right
that takes you right back to the article itself.&nbsp; <o:p></o:p></p><p>----------&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;<o:p></o:p></p><p><span><b><u>Update 10-29-2023</u>:</b>&nbsp; recently,&nbsp; I have received "comments" on this article that are nothing but ad solicitations from the makers of O-ring products,&nbsp; usually from overseas.&nbsp; They picked this article precisely because it mentions O-rings,&nbsp; which tells me this was the result of a keyword search of published articles on the internet.&nbsp; My blog site is not a monetized,&nbsp; commercial site.&nbsp; I do not accept any advertising from anyone.&nbsp; When I find them,&nbsp; I delete them.</span></p><p>-------</p><p>I have real difficulty with the fact that,&nbsp; even after all these years,&nbsp; it is still necessary to explain to people
what really destroyed Space Shuttle Challenger and killed her crew,&nbsp; back in January 1986.&nbsp; It was really two very seriously-bad upper
management decisions at NASA,&nbsp; one long
before the launch:&nbsp;</p>

<p>(1) to insist on poorly-designing the O-ring seal joints with
3 interacting serious errors,<span>&nbsp; </span>and <o:p></o:p></p>

<p>(2) to fly soaked-out colder than had ever been tested, <span>&nbsp;</span>when everybody’s engineers did not want to. <o:p></o:p></p>

<p><b>Background<o:p></o:p></b></p>

<p>First,<span>&nbsp; </span>you have to
understand what really happens in federal government contracting.<span>&nbsp; </span>There is only one customer,<span>&nbsp; </span>and <u>he thinks he is always right about
every decision that he makes</u>.<span>&nbsp; </span>If you
do not do it exactly the way he wants,<span>&nbsp; </span><u>no
matter how wrong he might be</u>,<span>&nbsp; </span>then
you lose the contract and you don’t get paid.<span>&nbsp;
</span><b><i>And,<span>&nbsp; </span>the government is
quite often wrong about how best to do things!</i></b><span>&nbsp; </span>That’s not to say the contractors are always
right,<span>&nbsp; </span>but they are wrong a lot less
often than the government. <o:p></o:p></p>

<p>You also have to understand that NASA never did know,<span>&nbsp; </span>and <u>still</u> does <u>not</u> know, <span>&nbsp;</span>the art of building reliable solid propellant
rockets.<span>&nbsp; </span>Essentially, <span>&nbsp;</span>no one at NASA ever did that kind of
work.<span>&nbsp; </span>They buy these things from
contractors who (by definition) know much more of the science, <span>&nbsp;</span><u>and especially the art</u>, <span>&nbsp;</span>than anyone at NASA knows.<span>&nbsp; </span>The “science” is that knowledge which was written
down.<span>&nbsp; </span>The “art” is the knowledge that
was <u>not</u> written down,<span>&nbsp; </span>usually because
no one wanted to pay for the writing.<o:p></o:p></p>

<p>I can tell you <u>from experience as an insider within the
business</u>, <span>&nbsp;</span>that “rocket science”
isn’t really “science”!<span>&nbsp; </span>It is only about
40% science,<span>&nbsp; </span>about 50% art,<span>&nbsp; </span>and about 10% blind dumb luck.<span>&nbsp; </span>And that’s in production work!<span>&nbsp; </span>In new product development work,<span>&nbsp; </span>the art and luck percentages are even
higher.<span>&nbsp; </span><o:p></o:p></p>

<p>Further,<span>&nbsp; </span>this same
sentiment applies to pretty much any type of engineering effort,<span>&nbsp; </span>not just rocket work.<span>&nbsp; </span>That explains a lot,<span>&nbsp; </span>about a lot of things, <span>&nbsp;</span>doesn’t it?<o:p></o:p></p>

<p><b>Poorly-Designed O-Ring Seal Joints<o:p></o:p></b></p>

<p>What I show in <b>Figure 1</b> is <u>how such joints should
be designed and built</u>.<span>&nbsp; </span>This is the
design that most solid rocket motors use, <span>&nbsp;</span>very successfully,<span>&nbsp; </span>whether large or small.<span>&nbsp; </span>In most rocket motors,<span>&nbsp; </span>you need only join the aft and forward
closures to the case cylinder.<span>&nbsp; </span>Only in some
of the really large motors,<span>&nbsp; </span>the case
cylinder itself is divided into segments that must be joined,<span>&nbsp; </span>usually to limit the size of the case-bonded propellant
masses that must be cast and cured within them. <o:p></o:p></p>

<p>The sketch in the figure is what mechanical engineers call a
“radial static seal”.<span>&nbsp; </span>It is “radial”
because the O-ring lies between an inner and an outer surface,<span>&nbsp; </span>that must include a gap of tightly-controlled
size between the two parts,<span>&nbsp; </span>for
assembly.<span>&nbsp; </span>One part stabs into/inside the
other,<span>&nbsp; </span>in order to join them,<span>&nbsp; </span>in this case by a row of pins.<span>&nbsp; </span>It is “static”,<span>&nbsp; </span>because the parts,<span>&nbsp; </span>once joined,<span>&nbsp;
</span>do not move anymore.<span>&nbsp; </span>There are
strict but well-published guidelines and procedures for sizing the O-ring
groove dimensions,<span>&nbsp; </span>the gap for
assembly,<span>&nbsp; </span>and the size of the
O-ring,<span>&nbsp; </span>as well as its material
composition and its hardness.<span>&nbsp; </span>These
guidelines and procedures are used precisely because they work so very
well.<span>&nbsp;&nbsp; </span>Examples:<span>&nbsp; </span><b>Refs. 1 and 2.</b><o:p></o:p></p>

<p>Something also shown in the figure is peculiar to solid
rocket motors,<span>&nbsp; </span>especially those that are
segmented-case designs.<span>&nbsp; </span>There is a joint
in the insulation (and thus also the propellant) that leads to the sealing
surface gap, <span>&nbsp;</span>that in turn leads directly
to the O-ring in its groove.<span>&nbsp; </span><b><i>You <u>DO
NOT obstruct</u> this path with sealants,<span>&nbsp;
</span>putties,<span>&nbsp; </span>greases,<span>&nbsp; </span>or anything else!<span>&nbsp; </span></i></b>But there does need to be a
right-angle bend,<span>&nbsp; </span>to stop radiant heat transfer
from the flame in the motor from heating the O-ring directly. <o:p></o:p></p>

<p>The air in this path is what gets suddenly compressed upon
motor pressurization,<span>&nbsp; </span>and which in turn
forces the O-ring to the far side of its groove,<span>&nbsp; </span>where it gets squeezed against that surface
to seal.<span>&nbsp; </span>This is called “seating the
O-ring”,<span>&nbsp; </span>and until it is properly seated,<span>&nbsp; </span>it CANNOT seal,<span>&nbsp; </span>and so it briefly leaks!<o:p></o:p></p><p><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgy3G06GH8JoAli9mSuLMYWEs_XSnlRMONXhTkLZcoP3lR8-blQHj6nixYc3cdejlmtaeaT0S_YSJYKjvfVFCwbt_KCYqUjp-spbow1OApR5tM2Wh2ZjaiVyYLRLwBvgkwMSbwb-O09NEMy/s1153/F1+SRB+O+ring+joint+1.png"><img data-original-height="621" data-original-width="1153" height="215" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgy3G06GH8JoAli9mSuLMYWEs_XSnlRMONXhTkLZcoP3lR8-blQHj6nixYc3cdejlmtaeaT0S_YSJYKjvfVFCwbt_KCYqUjp-spbow1OApR5tM2Wh2ZjaiVyYLRLwBvgkwMSbwb-O09NEMy/w400-h215/F1+SRB+O+ring+joint+1.png" width="400"></a></p><p><b>Figure 1 – A Properly Designed O-Ring Seal Joint<o:p></o:p></b></p>

<p>It is the air in the path that gets compressed against the
O-ring,&nbsp; with hot booster gases and hot
solids filling most of the path volume that the air formerly occupied.&nbsp; But the air cools by convection to the steel
much more effectively and faster than to the O-ring itself.&nbsp; THAT is how the O-ring is not damaged by the hot
air,&nbsp; or the hot gases! &nbsp;The hot solids are stopped by the right-angle
bend.&nbsp; This is a rapid transient on a
time scale equal to,&nbsp; or shorter than, &nbsp;the motor pressurization event.&nbsp; <o:p></o:p></p>

<p>What you <u>DO NOT want</u> is contact of the hot gases (and
especially the hot solids) upon the O-ring!&nbsp;
The “hot sandblast” effect of that outcome would cut through the O-ring almost
instantaneously.<o:p></o:p></p>

<p>Note that these two design requirements of (1) one O-ring
and (2) an unobstructed pressurization path,&nbsp;
will interact very strongly with how one verifies proper assembly of the
motor!&nbsp; You <u>must</u> do a pressure
leak check of the motor to verify sealing,&nbsp;
but you <u>must do it by pressurizing the entire motor</u>!&nbsp; <b><i>However,&nbsp; you <u>NEED NOT pressurize the motor to its
full operating pressure</u> to do this verification!&nbsp; <o:p></o:p></i></b></p>

<p>You only need an atmosphere or so of pressure difference to
seat any O-ring and then verify its sealing.&nbsp;
If it holds at that low pressure,&nbsp;
<u>and you followed the design guidelines correctly</u>,&nbsp; it will hold at full motor operating pressure!&nbsp; <b><i><u>THAT</u> is what you verify when you
do motor case hydroburst testing,&nbsp; long
before you ever cast propellant to make a live motor!</i></b>&nbsp; That’s the way the real solid rocket motor
manufacturers prefer to do it.&nbsp; And it
works to very high reliability levels,&nbsp;
as indicated in the figure. <o:p></o:p></p>

<p>However,&nbsp; <u>that is
NOT what NASA insisted upon doing</u>!&nbsp;
In the <u>mistaken belief</u> that a second back-up O-ring increases
sealing reliability,&nbsp; they insisted upon
the two O-ring design indicated in <b>Figure 2</b>.&nbsp; Thiokol complied,&nbsp; lest they lose the contract.&nbsp; In the <u>mistaken belief</u> that they had
to pressure leak check at full motor operating pressure,&nbsp; NASA did not want to risk fully pressurizing
a live loaded motor (and rightly so).&nbsp; And
so NASA insisted on a way to apply air pressure at full motor operating
pressure, &nbsp;<u>between </u>each pair of
O-rings at every joint,&nbsp; instead of any motor
pressurization.&nbsp;&nbsp; This is shown in the
figure.<o:p></o:p></p>

<p>What this does is drive the downstream (backup) O-ring to
the correct side of the groove,&nbsp; thus
seating it for motor operation.&nbsp;
But,&nbsp; <u>it also drives the
upstream (primary) O-ring to the wrong side of its groove</u>,&nbsp; from which motor pressurization upon ignition
must unseat it,&nbsp; drive it across its
groove,&nbsp; and re-seat it on the correct
side!&nbsp; Until and unless it re-seats on
that correct side,&nbsp; the upstream
(primary) seal ALWAYS leaks!&nbsp;
Period!&nbsp; There is NO WAY AROUND
that outcome!&nbsp; And <u>THAT</u> lets hot
gases and solids reach the primary O-ring,&nbsp;
simply because the re-seating process takes a longer time than
pressurization!<o:p></o:p></p><p><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEitSgMvC-kHc-pXjpAneBgWumvE-O7_Aco_meCBmalzOqJW_fuxhkaRNb9Yz6AFjVcYcJaapSjfjjcZrN61FzpucGV6M9VdPg421qtjkVUpyWnTRMenhPnFM0fUWIrp2AlQXxHI2b7Yk2ZX/s1153/F2+SRB+O+ring+joint+2.png"><img data-original-height="621" data-original-width="1153" height="215" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEitSgMvC-kHc-pXjpAneBgWumvE-O7_Aco_meCBmalzOqJW_fuxhkaRNb9Yz6AFjVcYcJaapSjfjjcZrN61FzpucGV6M9VdPg421qtjkVUpyWnTRMenhPnFM0fUWIrp2AlQXxHI2b7Yk2ZX/w400-h215/F2+SRB+O+ring+joint+2.png" width="400"></a></p><p><b>Figure 2 – The Improperly-Designed 2 O-ring Joint That
Flew, &nbsp;Up Through Challenger<o:p></o:p></b></p>

<p><b><i>NASA made a third mistake:</i></b>&nbsp; <b><i>in the <u>mistaken belief</u> that it
would prevent hot gases and hot solids from reaching the O-ring,&nbsp; they insisted on obstructing the
pressurization path by filling the insulation joint with “heat protective”
putty</i></b> (zinc chromate putty actually).&nbsp;
This is also shown in the figure. <o:p></o:p></p>

<p>This last mistake makes a bad risk even far worse,&nbsp; because high pressure gases always
(ALWAYS!!!) “wormhole-through” a not-solid material (like putty or grease) at a
single point!&nbsp; THIS effect is also shown
in the figure.&nbsp; That re-distributes the
“push” of the gas from a broad front all around the O-ring,&nbsp; <u>to a single point upon the O-ring</u>,&nbsp; as indicated in the figure.&nbsp; The delay unseating the ring,&nbsp; pushing it to the other side of the
groove,&nbsp; and reseating it,&nbsp; almost guarantees that the compressed air
leaks past it,&nbsp; so that booster hot gases
and solids can reach the O-ring.&nbsp; <u>And
those will cut a hole right through it</u>.<o:p></o:p></p>

<p>“Half-moon slices” right through the primary upstream O-ring
were seen,&nbsp; upon SRB motor disassembly,&nbsp; in a rather significant percentage of the
SRB’s recovered and refurbished.&nbsp; That
verifies what I just said about the upstream O-ring being cut!&nbsp; There is no surprise there,&nbsp; once you understand the process!</p>

<p>The <u>difference</u> between this point load problem,&nbsp; and what NASA analyzed in its structural
calculations for the O-ring seal <u>is quite stark</u>! &nbsp;The structural analysts were assuming
pressurization on a broad front.&nbsp; They
did <u>not</u> model the point load effect of the hot gases and solids
wormholing-through the putty obstructing the pressurization path.&nbsp; <b><i>Quite simply,&nbsp; what was built was NOT what was analyzed!</i></b><o:p></o:p></p>

<p><b>Unnecessary Risk to Fly Too Cold<o:p></o:p></b></p>

<p>If the motor is sufficiently cold-soaked,&nbsp; the primary upstream O-ring loses its flexibility
and resilience (as do all of them).&nbsp;
Pushing the entire embrittled O-ring across its groove all at once is
risky enough,&nbsp; but if you concentrate the
“push” at one single location by the wormhole effect,&nbsp; <u>you essentially guarantee snapping the
O-ring apart at that point</u>!&nbsp; This
cold brittleness effect was amply demonstrated by Dr. Feynman at the Rogers
Commission hearings (assisted by Gen. Kutyna),&nbsp;
when he stirred his sample of the O-ring material in his glass of ice
water,&nbsp; and then demonstrated its non-resilience.
<o:p></o:p></p>

<p>Any failure of the primary upstream O-ring,&nbsp; whether by hot sandblast cutting,&nbsp; or by cold brittle fracture from the point
jet force load,&nbsp; then puts a single-point
hot sandblast jet impacting onto the downstream O-ring,&nbsp; <u>simply because it is nearby</u>!&nbsp; <b><i>Thus, &nbsp;a sort of “cascade failure” is a very high
risk indeed!</i></b><o:p></o:p></p>

<p>The post-Challenger “fix” was a third O-ring in every
joint.&nbsp; This just set up the cascade
failure as a longer chain,&nbsp; as indicated
in <b>Figure 3</b>.&nbsp; The <u>only</u>
reason the Challenger disaster did not repeat is that they never flew that cold
again.&nbsp; But the 1/51 failure rate
demonstrated by loss of Challenger speaks for itself!<o:p></o:p></p><p><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiAgbkJu1b4mGz70Jrniya3VTRCegbo9Me1Mrm_an8gTBBZm9GopbjeaXB6TOcAwJoNtXNy1JlwmJW7ni4tTgcPqNFerTkq81qK4vt7iintrjc3qimNR-5ksnmKheNkb0jWEC6qtGRGffdi/s1153/F3+SRB+O+ring+joint+3.png"><img data-original-height="621" data-original-width="1153" height="215" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiAgbkJu1b4mGz70Jrniya3VTRCegbo9Me1Mrm_an8gTBBZm9GopbjeaXB6TOcAwJoNtXNy1JlwmJW7ni4tTgcPqNFerTkq81qK4vt7iintrjc3qimNR-5ksnmKheNkb0jWEC6qtGRGffdi/w400-h215/F3+SRB+O+ring+joint+3.png" width="400"></a></p><p><b>Figure 3 – The Cascade Failure Risk Was Compounded By the
Redesigned Joint<o:p></o:p></b></p>

<p><b>Fatal Consequences We All Saw</b></p>

<p>The photography obtained during the launch and loss of
Challenger confirms everything claimed here.&nbsp;
The seal failed upon motor ignition and pressurization,&nbsp; as shown quite clearly in <b>Figure 4</b>.&nbsp; The dark grey plume is carbon soot-bearing
hot gases spewing through the <u>two failed O-rings</u> at the aft segment joint.&nbsp;<o:p></o:p></p><p><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEg2f7gKyFLxHvdu8siPV81GcoGynssuzMAmjgh6baoNZjBos_PulJDwtoDm8I1DgwCMwUb_UR5GvbFTfcwSacMS8TIPujAkSaywqWqQnlGj85xIdzHOGIz2xzYJMpMCIjlQ2NQjjf-B0p9E/s330/F4+330px-STS-51-L_grey_smoke_on_SRB.jpg"><img data-original-height="247" data-original-width="330" height="300" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEg2f7gKyFLxHvdu8siPV81GcoGynssuzMAmjgh6baoNZjBos_PulJDwtoDm8I1DgwCMwUb_UR5GvbFTfcwSacMS8TIPujAkSaywqWqQnlGj85xIdzHOGIz2xzYJMpMCIjlQ2NQjjf-B0p9E/w400-h300/F4+330px-STS-51-L_grey_smoke_on_SRB.jpg" width="400"></a></p><p><b>Figure 4 – Seal Leak Upon Ignition Seen In Photography<o:p></o:p></b></p>

<p>This leak miraculously “cured” itself by plugging-up with
aluminum oxide-carbon slag from the metallized propellant.&nbsp; This slag-plugging just happened to hold
pressure like that, &nbsp;until the Challenger
encountered a wind shear while at “max-Q”, &nbsp;where it was also most highly stressed by
aerodynamic forces.&nbsp; The slag plug
failed,&nbsp; letting the hot motor gases and
solids rush through the hole again.&nbsp; This
is shown quite clearly as the anomalous bright-but-small extra plume in <b>Figure
5</b> below. <o:p></o:p></p>

<p>This jet of leaking hot gases and solids finally got so big that
it cut through one of the aft struts holding the SRB to the center tank.&nbsp; There is always hydrogen leaking from the
center tank’s hydrogen tank,&nbsp; <u>and in
this case the leaked plume probably burned a hole in that hydrogen tank</u>.&nbsp; With the strut cut,&nbsp; the bottom of the SRB moved outboard.&nbsp; That pushed the nose of the SRB inboard,&nbsp; such that the nose of the SRB poked a hole in
the side of the center tank’s oxygen tank.&nbsp;
<o:p></o:p></p>

<p>Suddenly dumping oxygen into a base-burning hydrogen-air
fire caused an explosion in the wake behind the center tank that both
overheated and structurally overloaded it.&nbsp;
The tank collapsed,&nbsp; letting both
SRB’s and the orbiter fly free.&nbsp;&nbsp; The
released propellants burned explosively as this happened.&nbsp; All this happened in an instant,&nbsp; so it looks like just the one sudden explosion.<o:p></o:p></p><p><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjSTGQupKkSfEGOAjivR4UfYCZFsK0sy_zMChLxNPnAAghvyksgacH1ajKxMbnxKbERILiBeE-P6-ID7oVpmMKXgkKvzD0x1eP8jv743iQDZ3tmO6C5FULw3fRwxH2-_PZpvhCco07-i4wG/s330/F5+255px-Booster_Rocket_Breach_-_GPN-2000-001425.jpg"><img data-original-height="330" data-original-width="255" height="400" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjSTGQupKkSfEGOAjivR4UfYCZFsK0sy_zMChLxNPnAAghvyksgacH1ajKxMbnxKbERILiBeE-P6-ID7oVpmMKXgkKvzD0x1eP8jv743iQDZ3tmO6C5FULw3fRwxH2-_PZpvhCco07-i4wG/w309-h400/F5+255px-Booster_Rocket_Breach_-_GPN-2000-001425.jpg" width="309"></a></p><p><b>Figure 5 – Leakage Resumed After Being Shaken By Wind
Shear at Max Q<o:p></o:p></b></p>

<p>The released SRB’s continued to “fly” out-of-control under
their own thrusts,&nbsp; as we all saw.&nbsp; This is shown in <b>Figure 6</b>.&nbsp; The orbiter’s engines were pointed through a
center of gravity that suddenly no longer existed,&nbsp; so they forced the orbiter to pitch-up
violently,&nbsp; before starving for lack of
propellant from the suddenly-missing center tank.&nbsp; The pitched-up orbiter went broadside to the
supersonic wind,&nbsp; which tore it to
pieces.&nbsp; This is how those pieces, &nbsp;that we all saw fall into the sea, &nbsp;came to be.&nbsp;&nbsp;<o:p></o:p></p><p><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiKgK1-ROe1DyuLho5OBw950YXMds6GAjvtMD-XqaPjkF2ooheJO1Y0sxbDr56uqdHLDsxHpBTRO5siWfDRNhQ9uvCalOzuya0GI4r2xhH6KzXOLgqIm9Lbj6A3jMs0PKRPu6nv-mcjrFlE/s390/F6+Challenger_disaster_explosion.jpg"><img data-original-height="316" data-original-width="390" height="324" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiKgK1-ROe1DyuLho5OBw950YXMds6GAjvtMD-XqaPjkF2ooheJO1Y0sxbDr56uqdHLDsxHpBTRO5siWfDRNhQ9uvCalOzuya0GI4r2xhH6KzXOLgqIm9Lbj6A3jMs0PKRPu6nv-mcjrFlE/w400-h324/F6+Challenger_disaster_explosion.jpg" width="400"></a></p><p><b>Figure 6 – The SRB Did Not Explode,&nbsp; But It Punched a Hole In the Center Tank<o:p></o:p></b></p>

<p><b>Final Remarks<o:p></o:p></b></p>

<p>The two O-ring joint was a NASA-mandated design
mistake,&nbsp; compounded by mandating putty
obstructing the O-ring pressurization paths.&nbsp;
<b><i>The “customer is always right” in government contracting,&nbsp; except that he was <u>lethally and fatally
wrong about this one</u>!&nbsp; </i></b>See
also Ref. 3.<o:p></o:p></p>

<p>The decision to fly cold-soaked <u>colder than the SRB’s had
ever been tested</u>, &nbsp;was also a NASA management
decision.&nbsp; Both NASA and Thiokol
engineers objected,&nbsp; but were
over-ruled.&nbsp; Thiokol upper management
also over-ruled their own engineers,&nbsp; and
told NASA to go ahead and launch.&nbsp; Thus
emboldened by Thiokol management,&nbsp; NASA
launched the thing,&nbsp; thus killing its
crew. <o:p></o:p></p>

<p>The stand-down to “correct” this problem was nearly 2 years
long and horribly expensive.&nbsp; Which just
goes to prove what I like to say to anyone who will listen:&nbsp; <b><i>“there is nothing as expensive as a
dead crew,&nbsp; especially one dead from a
bad management decision”.&nbsp; <o:p></o:p></i></b></p>

<p>The only problem with that return-to-flight effort is that <u>they
did not correct the real problems</u> upon return-to-flight,&nbsp; they actually made them worse with a 3-O-ring
joint,&nbsp; and by keeping the putty
obstructions.&nbsp; The ONLY thing they did “right”
was <u>never to fly that cold again</u>!&nbsp;
<u>Which is very likely the ONLY reason that the Challenger disaster did
not repeat itself before the Shuttle got retired</u>,&nbsp; since there were more than 51 more flights
after the Challenger disaster!<o:p></o:p></p>

<p>By the way,&nbsp; the <u>crew
did not die in the tank explosion</u> and subsequent ripping-apart of the
orbiter by air loads.&nbsp; The telemetry
showed no high-gee accelerations at all!&nbsp;
The crew was still alive in the orbiter cabin until it finally hit the
sea,&nbsp; which is about a 200-gee stop,&nbsp; since it hit dead broadside. &nbsp;See <b>Figure 7</b>.<o:p></o:p></p><p><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhl16NqI2ouIQygLDduyoOffBl-8qLkt3Ye3E7JkaDfhufzBjUmA5BW1ZmHXs9oA__S5CWEX25F0jExya36cz1b1w2BLxt3bD3G_Cu6aLY2qMR1bPLEWEpRZBAxnxRJot7moP77w38Xsn2Y/s330/F7+330px-Challenger_breakup_cabin.jpg"><img data-original-height="242" data-original-width="330" height="294" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhl16NqI2ouIQygLDduyoOffBl-8qLkt3Ye3E7JkaDfhufzBjUmA5BW1ZmHXs9oA__S5CWEX25F0jExya36cz1b1w2BLxt3bD3G_Cu6aLY2qMR1bPLEWEpRZBAxnxRJot7moP77w38Xsn2Y/w400-h294/F7+330px-Challenger_breakup_cabin.jpg" width="400"></a></p><p><b>Figure 7 – The Crew Was Still Alive In This Cabin Section
(Arrow) That Is Falling Back<o:p></o:p></b></p>

<p>I say what I said about the crew because the flight deck
back-seaters leaned forward and flipped on the breathing-air packs for the
front-seater pilots.&nbsp; They would not have
done that unless they knew the cabin had depressurized,&nbsp; and <u>that</u> would have been <u>significantly
AFTER the explosion</u> and ripping-apart of the orbiter.&nbsp; They were tumbling clear of the explosion
cloud by that time,&nbsp; as illustrated in
the figure.&nbsp; <o:p></o:p></p>

<p>Those two flight deck pilots had breathed-up all the oxygen
in their breathing packs by the time they hit the sea,&nbsp; something confirmed by the empty breathing
packs that were recovered.&nbsp; <u>Which
means they were alive when they hit the sea</u>!&nbsp; By extension,&nbsp;
so were the back-seaters,&nbsp; plus
the three down on the mid-deck. <o:p></o:p></p>

<p>They did not have pressure suits,&nbsp; parachutes,&nbsp;
breathing bottles,&nbsp; and a hatch
they could blow open (basic bail-out gear).&nbsp;
<b><i>More importantly,&nbsp; there was
no way to take the spin off the tumbling cabin.</i></b>&nbsp; Spinning like that,&nbsp; there was no way to reach and exit the
hatch,&nbsp; even if they had the other basic
bailout gear!&nbsp; <b><i><u>But a small
drogue parachute from the nose of the cabin section would have taken off the
spin</u>!</i></b>&nbsp; <b><i>That plus the basic
bail-out gear just listed could have saved that crew!&nbsp; It took almost 5 minutes to hit the sea.&nbsp; They had the time to bail out.<o:p></o:p></i></b></p>

<p>I submitted that means for bail-out to NASA,&nbsp; <u>but I was ignored</u>.&nbsp; Coming from an outsider,&nbsp; my idea was “not invented here”,&nbsp; as far as NASA was concerned.&nbsp; Yet,&nbsp; something
rather like it might even have worked for Columbia some years later:&nbsp; the 3 mid-deck occupants were still alive inside
a tumbling cabin section as it approached impact near Tyler,&nbsp; Texas, &nbsp;well after the breakup during re-entry.&nbsp;&nbsp; Time was short for a bail-out,&nbsp; but without the de-spin drogue,&nbsp; they could not reach the hatch at all.&nbsp; <o:p></o:p></p>

<p><b>References<o:p></o:p></b></p>

<p>#1. Parker O-ring Handbook ORD 5700,&nbsp; copyright 2021,&nbsp; original release 1957,&nbsp; Parker O-Ring and Engineered Seals
Division,&nbsp; Lexington,&nbsp; KY, available from parkerorings.com&nbsp; <o:p></o:p></p>

<p>#2. Seal Design Guide,&nbsp;
Apple Rubber Products,&nbsp; Lancaster
NY,&nbsp; available from AppleRubber.com<o:p></o:p></p>

<p>#3. Wikipedia article “Rogers Commission Report”,&nbsp; in this case accessed 11-26-2021<o:p></o:p></p>

<p><b>Final Notes<o:p></o:p></b></p>

<p>There are different design rules for static radial and
static face seals,&nbsp; and different rules
yet for dynamic radial seals (as on a piston moving inside a cylinder, &nbsp;like a syringe or a hydraulic cylinder).&nbsp; The Shuttle SRB joints fall into the static
radial classification.&nbsp; <o:p></o:p></p>

<p>The appropriate set of rules specifies O-ring sizes and
hardness,&nbsp; groove dimensions,&nbsp; and when to use back-up rings. &nbsp;You just follow the design rules,&nbsp; and make sure that only compressed air
reaches the O-ring (and on a broad front),&nbsp;
upon solid propellant motor ignition. &nbsp;<o:p></o:p></p>

<p>You accomplish that broad-front pressurization with the
90-degree bend geometry to stop the hot solids and radiant heat transfer,&nbsp; and by NEVER obstructing the O-ring pressurization
path with anything!&nbsp; Even too close a fit
between the hard parts, &nbsp;can cause
problems with the transient pressurizing flow. <o:p></o:p></p>

<p>You verify your seal design,&nbsp;
your case structural design,&nbsp; <u>and
your leak check procedure</u>,&nbsp; during
case hydroburst testing,&nbsp; <u>long before
you ever cast a live motor</u>!&nbsp; You
NEVER delete the hydroburst testing step in your development effort.&nbsp; Never!&nbsp;
Not for any reason at all!&nbsp; <o:p></o:p></p>

<p>Then you test live motors at every environmental extreme
condition in which you think you might possibly operate. &nbsp;If any redesigns (of anything) are
needed,&nbsp; you go back and verify them in all
the tests,&nbsp; from hydroburst all the way
forward.&nbsp; <u>No motor goes to production</u>,&nbsp; until its <u>exact design configuration</u>
has been verified in every test at every test condition! <o:p></o:p></p>

<p>Once your design has passed all those tests,&nbsp; you stick with your verified leak check
procedure as if it were a religious mandate!&nbsp;
You add rigorous quality control (of the “total quality management”
type),&nbsp; for production.&nbsp; That includes <u>X-raying every single item</u>,&nbsp; to verify that there are no casting voids in
the propellant,&nbsp; no unbonds between
propellant and case liner,&nbsp; and no other propellant
grain cracks or other problems.&nbsp; And then
you NEVER operate a motor outside the conditions for which it was tested!&nbsp; <o:p></o:p></p>

<p><b><i>THAT is the way to achieve <u>no-more-than-1-in-a-million</u>
failure rates,&nbsp; with solid propellant
rocket motors!<o:p></o:p></i></b></p>

<p>The “bean counters” and “management professionals” will
absolutely hate that prescription as “too expensive”,&nbsp; but killing a crew with a bad design just costs
a whole lot more, &nbsp;than the cost of
following that prescription.&nbsp; We’ve
already seen that with Apollo-1,&nbsp;
Challenger,&nbsp; and Columbia.<o:p></o:p></p>

<p>Simple as that.&nbsp; <o:p></o:p></p>

<p>And just as hard to sell to the “bean counters” and
“management professionals”, &nbsp;as you might
fear.&nbsp;&nbsp;<o:p></o:p></p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Awsviz.dev simplifying AWS IAM policies (156 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.awsviz.dev/</link>
            <guid>40922740</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 00:35:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.awsviz.dev/">https://www.awsviz.dev/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40922740">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[RouteLLM: A framework for serving and evaluating LLM routers (198 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM</link>
            <guid>40922739</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 00:35:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM">https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40922739">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">RouteLLM</h2><a id="user-content-routellm" aria-label="Permalink: RouteLLM" href="#routellm"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">RouteLLM is a framework for serving and evaluating LLM routers.<br>
[ <a href="http://lmsys.org/blog/2024-07-01-routellm/" rel="nofollow">Blog</a> ] [ <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18665" rel="nofollow">Paper</a> ]</p>
<p dir="auto">
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM/blob/main/assets/router.png"><img src="https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM/raw/main/assets/router.png" width="50%"></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto">Our core features include:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Drop-in replacement for OpenAI's client (or launch an OpenAI-compatible server) to route simpler queries to cheaper models.</li>
<li>Trained routers are provided out of the box, which we have shown to <strong>reduce costs by up to 85%</strong> on widely-used benchmarks such as MT Bench while maintaining <strong>95% GPT-4 performance</strong>.</li>
<li>Easily extend the framework to include new routers and compare the performance of routers across multiple benchmarks.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h2><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>From PyPI</strong></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="pip install &quot;routellm[serve,eval]&quot;"><pre><code>pip install "routellm[serve,eval]"
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><strong>From source</strong></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM.git
cd RouteLLM
pip install -e .[serve,eval]"><pre><code>git clone https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM.git
cd RouteLLM
pip install -e .[serve,eval]
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Quickstart</h2><a id="user-content-quickstart" aria-label="Permalink: Quickstart" href="#quickstart"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Let's walkthrough replacing an existing OpenAI client to route queries between LLMs instead of using only a single model.</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>First, let's replace our OpenAI client by initializing the RouteLLM controller with the <code>mf</code> router. By default, RouteLLM will use the best-performing config:</li>
</ol>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="import os
from routellm.controller import Controller

os.environ[&quot;OPENAI_API_KEY&quot;] = &quot;sk-XXXXXX&quot;
# Replace with your model provider, we use Anyscale's Mixtral here.
os.environ[&quot;ANYSCALE_API_KEY&quot;] = &quot;esecret_XXXXXX&quot;

client = Controller(
  routers=[&quot;mf&quot;],
  strong_model=&quot;gpt-4-1106-preview&quot;,
  weak_model=&quot;anyscale/mistralai/Mixtral-8x7B-Instruct-v0.1&quot;,
)"><pre><span>import</span> <span>os</span>
<span>from</span> <span>routellm</span>.<span>controller</span> <span>import</span> <span>Controller</span>

<span>os</span>.<span>environ</span>[<span>"OPENAI_API_KEY"</span>] <span>=</span> <span>"sk-XXXXXX"</span>
<span># Replace with your model provider, we use Anyscale's Mixtral here.</span>
<span>os</span>.<span>environ</span>[<span>"ANYSCALE_API_KEY"</span>] <span>=</span> <span>"esecret_XXXXXX"</span>

<span>client</span> <span>=</span> <span>Controller</span>(
  <span>routers</span><span>=</span>[<span>"mf"</span>],
  <span>strong_model</span><span>=</span><span>"gpt-4-1106-preview"</span>,
  <span>weak_model</span><span>=</span><span>"anyscale/mistralai/Mixtral-8x7B-Instruct-v0.1"</span>,
)</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Above, we pick <code>gpt-4-1106-preview</code> as the strong model and <code>anyscale/mistralai/Mixtral-8x7B-Instruct-v0.1</code> as the weak model, setting the API keys accordingly. You can route between different model pairs or providers by updating the model names as described in <a href="#model-support">Model Support</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Want to route to local models? Check out <a href="https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM/blob/main/examples/routing_to_local_models.md">Routing to Local Models</a>.</p>
<ol start="2" dir="auto">
<li>Each routing request has a <em>cost threshold</em> that controls the tradeoff between cost and quality. We should calibrate this based on the types of queries we receive to maximize routing performance. As an example, let's calibrate our threshold for 50% GPT-4 calls using data from Chatbot Arena.</li>
</ol>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="> python -m routellm.calibrate_threshold --routers mf --strong-model-pct 0.5 --config config.example.yaml
For 50.0% strong model calls for mf, threshold = 0.11593"><pre><code>&gt; python -m routellm.calibrate_threshold --routers mf --strong-model-pct 0.5 --config config.example.yaml
For 50.0% strong model calls for mf, threshold = 0.11593
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">This means that we want to use <code>0.11593</code> as our threshold so that approximately 50% of all queries (those that require GPT-4 the most) will be routed to it (see <a href="#threshold-calibration">Threshold Calibration</a> for details).</p>
<ol start="3" dir="auto">
<li>Now, let's update the <code>model</code> field when we generate completions to specify the router and threshold to use:</li>
</ol>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="response = client.chat.completions.create(
  # This tells RouteLLM to use the MF router with a cost threshold of 0.11593
  model=&quot;router-mf-0.11593&quot;,
  messages=[
    {&quot;role&quot;: &quot;user&quot;, &quot;content&quot;: &quot;Hello!&quot;}
  ]
)"><pre><span>response</span> <span>=</span> <span>client</span>.<span>chat</span>.<span>completions</span>.<span>create</span>(
  <span># This tells RouteLLM to use the MF router with a cost threshold of 0.11593</span>
  <span>model</span><span>=</span><span>"router-mf-0.11593"</span>,
  <span>messages</span><span>=</span>[
    {<span>"role"</span>: <span>"user"</span>, <span>"content"</span>: <span>"Hello!"</span>}
  ]
)</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">That's it! Now, requests with be routed between the strong and weak model depending on what is required, <strong>saving costs while maintaining a high quality of responses</strong>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Depending on your use case, you might want to consider using a different model pair, modifying the configuration, or calibrating the thresholds based on the types of queries you receive to improve performance.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Server &amp; Demo</h3><a id="user-content-server--demo" aria-label="Permalink: Server &amp; Demo" href="#server--demo"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Instead of using the Python SDK, you can also launch an OpenAI-compatible server that will work with any existing OpenAI client, using similar steps:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="> export OPENAI_API_KEY=sk-XXXXXX
> export ANYSCALE_API_KEY=esecret_XXXXXX
> python -m routellm.openai_server --routers mf --strong-model gpt-4-1106-preview --weak-model anyscale/mistralai/Mixtral-8x7B-Instruct-v0.1
INFO:     Application startup complete.
INFO:     Uvicorn running on http://0.0.0.0:6060 (Press CTRL+C to quit)"><pre><code>&gt; export OPENAI_API_KEY=sk-XXXXXX
&gt; export ANYSCALE_API_KEY=esecret_XXXXXX
&gt; python -m routellm.openai_server --routers mf --strong-model gpt-4-1106-preview --weak-model anyscale/mistralai/Mixtral-8x7B-Instruct-v0.1
INFO:     Application startup complete.
INFO:     Uvicorn running on http://0.0.0.0:6060 (Press CTRL+C to quit)
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Once the server is launched, you can start a local router chatbot to see how different messages are routed.</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="python -m examples.router_chat --router mf --threshold 0.11593"><pre><code>python -m examples.router_chat --router mf --threshold 0.11593
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM/blob/main/assets/chat-interface.png"><img src="https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM/raw/main/assets/chat-interface.png" width="50%"></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Model Support</h3><a id="user-content-model-support" aria-label="Permalink: Model Support" href="#model-support"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">In the above examples, GPT-4 and Mixtral 8x7B are used as the model pair, but you can modify this using the <code>strong-model</code> and <code>weak-model</code> arguments.</p>
<p dir="auto">We leverage <a href="https://github.com/BerriAI/litellm">LiteLLM</a> to support chat completions from a wide-range of open-source and closed models. In general, you need a setup an API key and point to the provider with the appropriate model name. Alternatively, you can also use <strong>any OpenAI-compatible endpoint</strong> by prefixing the model name with <code>openai/</code> and setting the <code>--base-url</code> and <code>--api-key</code> flags.</p>
<p dir="auto">Note that regardless of the model pair used, an <code>OPENAI_API_KEY</code> will currently still be required to generate embeddings for the <code>mf</code> and <code>sw_ranking</code> routers.</p>
<p dir="auto">Instructions for setting up your API keys for popular providers:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Local models with Ollama: see <a href="https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM/blob/main/examples/routing_to_local_models.md">this guide</a></li>
<li><a href="https://litellm.vercel.app/docs/providers/anthropic#api-keys" rel="nofollow">Anthropic</a></li>
<li><a href="https://litellm.vercel.app/docs/providers/gemini#sample-usage" rel="nofollow">Gemini - Google AI Studio</a></li>
<li><a href="https://litellm.vercel.app/docs/providers/bedrock#required-environment-variables" rel="nofollow">Amazon Bedrock</a></li>
<li><a href="https://litellm.vercel.app/docs/providers/togetherai#api-keys" rel="nofollow">Together AI</a></li>
<li><a href="https://litellm.vercel.app/docs/providers/anyscale#api-key" rel="nofollow">Anyscale Endpoints</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">For other model providers, find instructions <a href="https://litellm.vercel.app/docs/providers" rel="nofollow">here</a> or raise an issue.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Motivation</h2><a id="user-content-motivation" aria-label="Permalink: Motivation" href="#motivation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Different LLMs vary widely in their costs and capabilities, which leads to a dilemma when deploying them: routing all queries to the most capable model leads to the highest-quality responses but can be very expensive, while routing queries to smaller models can save costs but may result in lower-quality responses.</p>
<p dir="auto"><em>LLM routing</em> offers a solution to this. We introduce a router that looks at queries and routes simpler queries to smaller, cheaper models, saving costs while maintaining quality. We focus on routing between 2 models: a stronger, more expensive model and a cheaper but weaker model. Each request is also associated with a <em>cost threshold</em> that determines the cost-quality tradeoff of that request - a higher cost threshold leads to lower cost but may lead to lower-quality responses.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Server</h2><a id="user-content-server" aria-label="Permalink: Server" href="#server"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">RouteLLM offers a lightweight OpenAI-compatible server for routing requests based on different routing strategies:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="python -m routellm.openai_server --routers mf --config config.example.yaml"><pre><code>python -m routellm.openai_server --routers mf --config config.example.yaml
</code></pre></div>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>--routers</code> specifies the list of routers available to the server. For instance, here, the server is started with one available router: <code>mf</code> (see below for the list of routers).</li>
<li><code>--config</code> specifies the path to the configuration file for the routers. If unspecified, the server will default to using our best-performing configuration (see <a href="#configuration">Configuration</a> for details).</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">For most use-cases, <strong>we recommend the <code>mf</code> router</strong> as we have evaluated it to be very strong and lightweight.</p>
<p dir="auto">When making a request to the server, clients specify the router and cost threshold to use for each request using the <code>model</code> field in the following format <code>router-[ROUTER NAME]-[THRESHOLD]</code>. For instance, using a <code>model</code> of <code>router-mf-0.5</code> specifies that the request should be routed using the <code>mf</code> router with a threshold of 0.5.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Threshold Calibration</h3><a id="user-content-threshold-calibration" aria-label="Permalink: Threshold Calibration" href="#threshold-calibration"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The threshold used for routing controls the cost-quality tradeoff. The range of meaningful thresholds varies depending on the type of router and the queries you receive. Therefore, we recommend calibrating thresholds using a sample of your incoming queries, as well as the % of queries you'd like to route to the stronger model.</p>
<p dir="auto">By default, we support calibrating thresholds based on the public <a href="https://huggingface.co/datasets/lmsys/lmsys-arena-human-preference-55k" rel="nofollow">Chatbot Arena dataset</a>. For example, to calibrate the threshold for the <code>mf</code> router such that 50% of calls are routed to the stronger model:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="> python -m routellm.calibrate_threshold --task calibrate --routers mf --strong-model-pct 0.5 --config config.example.yaml
For 50.0% strong model calls for mf, threshold = 0.11593"><pre><code>&gt; python -m routellm.calibrate_threshold --task calibrate --routers mf --strong-model-pct 0.5 --config config.example.yaml
For 50.0% strong model calls for mf, threshold = 0.11593
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">This means that the threshold should be set to 0.1881 for the <code>mf</code> router so that approximately 50% of calls are routed to the strong model i.e. using a <code>model</code> field of <code>router-mf-0.1159</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto">However, note that because we calibrate the thresholds based on an existing dataset, the % of calls routed to each model will differ based on the actual queries received. Therefore, we recommend calibrating on a dataset that closely resembles the types of queries you receive.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Evaluation</h2><a id="user-content-evaluation" aria-label="Permalink: Evaluation" href="#evaluation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">RouteLLM also includes a evaluation framework to measure the performance of different routing strategies on benchmarks.</p>
<p dir="auto">To evaluate a router on a benchmark, you can use the following command:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="python -m routellm.evals.evaluate --routers random sw_ranking bert --benchmark gsm8k --config config.example.yaml "><pre><code>python -m routellm.evals.evaluate --routers random sw_ranking bert --benchmark gsm8k --config config.example.yaml 
</code></pre></div>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>--routers</code> specifies the list of routers to evaluate, for instance, <code>random</code> and <code>bert</code> in this case.</li>
<li><code>--benchmark</code> specifies the specific benchmark to evaluate the routers on. We currently support: <code>mmlu</code>, <code>gsm8k</code>, and <code>mt-bench</code>.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Evaluation results will be printed to the console. A plot of router performance will also be generated in the current directory (override the path using <code>--output</code>). To avoid recomputing results, the results for a router on a given benchmark is cached by default. This behavior can be overridden by using the <code>--overwrite-cache</code> flag, which takes in a list of routers to overwrite the cache for.</p>
<p dir="auto">The results for all our benchmarks have been cached. For MT Bench, we use the precomputed judgements for the desired model pair. For MMLU and GSM8K, we utilized <a href="https://github.com/sgl-project/sglang">SGLang</a> to compute the results for the desired model pair - the full code for this can be found in the benchmark directories if you would like to evaluate a different model pair.</p>
<p dir="auto">By default, GPT-4 and Mixtral are used as the model pair for evaluation. To modify the model pair used, set them using the <code>--strong-model</code> and <code>--weak-model</code> flags.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Routers</h2><a id="user-content-routers" aria-label="Permalink: Routers" href="#routers"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Out of the box, RouteLLM supports 4 routers trained on the <code>gpt-4-1106-preview</code> and <code>mixtral-8x7b-instruct-v0.1</code> model pair.</p>
<p dir="auto">The full list of routers:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li><code>mf</code>: Uses a matrix factorization model trained on the preference data (recommended).</li>
<li><code>sw_ranking</code>: Uses a weighted Elo calculation for routing, where each vote is weighted according to how similar it is to the user's prompt.</li>
<li><code>bert</code>: Uses a BERT classifier trained on the preference data.</li>
<li><code>causal_llm</code>: Uses a LLM-based classifier tuned on the preference data.</li>
<li><code>random</code>: Randomly routes to either model.</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto">While these routers have been trained on the <code>gpt-4-1106-preview</code> and <code>mixtral-8x7b-instruct-v0.1</code> model pair, we have found that these routers generalize well to other strong and weak model pairs as well. Therefore, you can replace the model pair used for routing without having to retrain these models!</p>
<p dir="auto">For the full details, refer to our <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18665" rel="nofollow">paper</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Configuration</h2><a id="user-content-configuration" aria-label="Permalink: Configuration" href="#configuration"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The configuration for routers is specified in either the <code>config</code> argument for <code>Controller</code> or by passing in the path to a YAML file using the <code>--config</code> flag. It is a top-level mapping from router name to the keyword arguments used for router initialization.</p>
<p dir="auto">An example configuration is provided in the <code>config.example.yaml</code> file - it provides the configurations for routers that have trained on Arena data augmented using GPT-4 as a judge. The models and datasets used are all hosted on Hugging Face under the <a href="https://huggingface.co/routellm" rel="nofollow">RouteLLM</a> and <a href="https://huggingface.co/lmsys" rel="nofollow">LMSYS</a> organizations.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contribution</h2><a id="user-content-contribution" aria-label="Permalink: Contribution" href="#contribution"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">We welcome contributions! Please feel free to open an issue or a pull request if you have any suggestions or improvements.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Adding a new router</h3><a id="user-content-adding-a-new-router" aria-label="Permalink: Adding a new router" href="#adding-a-new-router"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To add a new router to RouteLLM, implement the abstract <code>Router</code> class in <code>routers.py</code> and add the new router to the <code>ROUTER_CLS</code> dictionary. Then, you can use immediately the new router in the server or evaluation framework.</p>
<p dir="auto">There is only a single method to implement: <code>calculate_strong_win_rate</code>, which takes in the user prompt and returns the win rate for the strong model conditioned on that given prompt - if this win rate is great than user-specified cost threshold, then the request is routed to the strong model. Otherwise, it is routed to the weak model.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Adding a new benchmark</h3><a id="user-content-adding-a-new-benchmark" aria-label="Permalink: Adding a new benchmark" href="#adding-a-new-benchmark"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To add a new benchmark to RouteLLM, implement the abstract <code>Benchmark</code> class in <code>benchmarks.py</code> and update the <code>evaluate.py</code> module to properly initialize the new benchmark class. Ideally, the results for the benchmark should be precomputed to avoid having to regenerate the results for each evaluation run -- see the existing benchmarks for examples on how to do this.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Citation</h2><a id="user-content-citation" aria-label="Permalink: Citation" href="#citation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The code in this repository is based on the research from the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18665" rel="nofollow">paper</a>. Please cite if you find the repository helpful.</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="@misc{ong2024routellmlearningroutellms,
      title={RouteLLM: Learning to Route LLMs with Preference Data},
      author={Isaac Ong and Amjad Almahairi and Vincent Wu and Wei-Lin Chiang and Tianhao Wu and Joseph E. Gonzalez and M Waleed Kadous and Ion Stoica},
      year={2024},
      eprint={2406.18665},
      archivePrefix={arXiv},
      primaryClass={cs.LG},
      url={https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18665},
}"><pre><code>@misc{ong2024routellmlearningroutellms,
      title={RouteLLM: Learning to Route LLMs with Preference Data},
      author={Isaac Ong and Amjad Almahairi and Vincent Wu and Wei-Lin Chiang and Tianhao Wu and Joseph E. Gonzalez and M Waleed Kadous and Ion Stoica},
      year={2024},
      eprint={2406.18665},
      archivePrefix={arXiv},
      primaryClass={cs.LG},
      url={https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18665},
}
</code></pre></div>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Multi-agent chatbot murder mystery – AI Alibis (free, in-browser) (156 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ai-murder-mystery.onrender.com/</link>
            <guid>40921989</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 22:34:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ai-murder-mystery.onrender.com/">https://ai-murder-mystery.onrender.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40921989">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>