<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 16:00:06 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Apple Introduces M4 Chip (332 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2024/05/apple-introduces-m4-chip/</link>
            <guid>40286029</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 14:37:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2024/05/apple-introduces-m4-chip/">https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2024/05/apple-introduces-m4-chip/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40286029">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">


	
    







 
<nav id="ac-localnav" lang="en-US" role="navigation" aria-label="Newsroom" data-analytics-region="local nav" data-sticky="">
	
    
    
        




    
    

</nav>



<main id="main" role="main"> 



<span id="opens-in-new-window">opens in new window</span>
<section>
<article data-analytics-activitymap-region-id="article">









    
    
    









    





    <div>
        

        <div>
                    
                    
                        <span>PRESS RELEASE</span>
                    
                    
                        <span>May 7, 2024</span>
                    
                    
                </div>

        <div>
                
                
                
                    <h2>
                        
    
        Apple introduces M4&nbsp;chip
    

                    </h2>
                
            </div>

        <div>
                
                
                    M4 enables the breakthrough design and stunning display of the new iPad Pro, while delivering a giant leap in performance
                
            </div>

        
            
    
    
    
    
    

        

    </div>







    
    
    






  
    
    
    
    
      <figure aria-label="Media, A graphic representing the new M4 chip.">
        <div>
             
              
              <div>
                M4 is a system on a chip (SoC) that advances the industry-leading power-efficient performance of Apple silicon.
              </div>
            
            
            
            
            <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/images/2024/05/apple-introduces-m4-chip/article/Apple-M4-chip-badge-240507.zip" download="" data-analytics-title="download image - Apple-M4-chip-badge-240507_big" aria-label="Download media, A graphic representing the new M4 chip."></a>
          </div>
      </figure>
    
  






    
    
    


     
     
    
    
        <div>
             
                 <div><span>CUPERTINO, CALIFORNIA</span> Apple today announced M4, the latest chip delivering phenomenal performance to the all-new <a href="https://www.apple.com/ipad-pro/" target="_blank">iPad Pro</a>. Built using second-generation 3-nanometer technology, M4 is a system on a chip (SoC) that advances the industry-leading power efficiency of Apple silicon and enables the incredibly thin design of iPad Pro. It also features an entirely new display engine to drive the stunning precision, color, and brightness of the breakthrough Ultra Retina XDR display on iPad Pro. A new CPU has up to 10 cores, while the new 10-core GPU builds on the next-generation GPU architecture introduced in M3, and brings Dynamic Caching, hardware-accelerated ray tracing, and hardware-accelerated mesh shading to iPad for the first time. M4 has Apple’s fastest Neural Engine ever, capable of up to 38 trillion operations per second, which is faster than the neural processing unit of any AI PC today. Combined with faster memory bandwidth, along with next-generation machine learning (ML) accelerators in the CPU, and a high-performance GPU, M4 makes the new iPad Pro an outrageously powerful device for artificial intelligence.
</div>
                 
             
                 <div>“The new iPad Pro with M4 is a great example of how building best-in-class custom silicon enables breakthrough products,” said Johny Srouji, Apple’s senior vice president of Hardware Technologies. “The power-efficient performance of M4, along with its new display engine, makes the thin design and game-changing display of iPad Pro possible, while fundamental improvements to the CPU, GPU, Neural Engine, and memory system make M4 extremely well suited for the latest applications leveraging AI. Altogether, this new chip makes iPad Pro the most powerful device of its kind.”
</div>
                 
             
         </div>
 

    
    
    


    
    
        
        
        
            <div role="group" aria-label="gallery" data-component-list="MixinGallery" id="m4-chip-details">
            <nav role="presentation">
                <ul role="tablist">
                    
                        <li role="presentation">
                            <a id="gallery-dotnav-979da046cb16ff15fd1167f945854cc2" href="#gallery-979da046cb16ff15fd1167f945854cc2" data-ac-gallery-trigger="gallery-979da046cb16ff15fd1167f945854cc2"><span>1) tandem OLED support, 2) brightness and color compensation, and 3) 10Hz-120Hz ProMotion support.</span></a>
                        </li>
                    
                        <li role="presentation">
                            <a id="gallery-dotnav-e3799518bb7991a67a224c3bb9214f1e" href="#gallery-e3799518bb7991a67a224c3bb9214f1e" data-ac-gallery-trigger="gallery-e3799518bb7991a67a224c3bb9214f1e"><span>A graphic representing the new M4 chip, highlighting its four performance cores and detailing their 1) improved branch prediction, 2) wider decode and execution engines, and 3) next-generation ML accelerators. The graphic also highlights M4’s six efficiency cores, and details their 1) improved branch prediction, 2) deeper execution engine, and 3) next-generation ML accelerators.</span></a>
                        </li>
                    
                        <li role="presentation">
                            <a id="gallery-dotnav-31a22c8e5118787e7dfbb9ca9d773f37" href="#gallery-31a22c8e5118787e7dfbb9ca9d773f37" data-ac-gallery-trigger="gallery-31a22c8e5118787e7dfbb9ca9d773f37"><span>A graphic representing the new M4 chip, highlighting its 10-core GPU and detailing its 1) next-generation architecture, 2) Dynamic Caching, 3) mesh shading, and 4) ray tracing.</span></a>
                        </li>
                    
                        <li role="presentation">
                            <a id="gallery-dotnav-2b86549e45af2f7ca2c474fdbd78716f" href="#gallery-2b86549e45af2f7ca2c474fdbd78716f" data-ac-gallery-trigger="gallery-2b86549e45af2f7ca2c474fdbd78716f"><span>A graphic representing the new M4 chip, highlighting its Neural Engine and detailing its 1) 16-core design and 2) that it’s faster and more efficient.</span></a>
                        </li>
                    
                </ul>
            </nav>
            <div>
                
                    
                        
                        <div id="gallery-979da046cb16ff15fd1167f945854cc2" aria-labelledby="gallery-dotnav-979da046cb16ff15fd1167f945854cc2" data-gallery-item="">
                            <figure role="presentation" data-analytics-activitymap-region-id="Gallery:display-engine">
                                
                                <div>
                                    <div>M4 features a new display engine enabling the stunning precision, color accuracy, and brightness uniformity of the Ultra Retina XDR display.</div>
                                    
                                    
                                    <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/images/2024/05/apple-introduces-m4-chip/article/Apple-M4-chip-display-engine-240507.zip" download="" data-analytics-title="download image - Apple-M4-chip-display-engine-240507_big" aria-label="Download media, 1) tandem OLED support, 2) brightness and color compensation, and 3) 10Hz-120Hz ProMotion support."></a>
                                </div>
                            </figure>
                        </div>
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                        <div id="gallery-e3799518bb7991a67a224c3bb9214f1e" aria-labelledby="gallery-dotnav-e3799518bb7991a67a224c3bb9214f1e" data-gallery-item="">
                            <figure role="presentation" data-analytics-activitymap-region-id="Gallery:performance-cores-efficiency-cores">
                                
                                <div>
                                    <div>The new CPU of M4 delivers up to 1.5x faster CPU performance over the powerful M2 in the previous iPad Pro.</div>
                                    
                                    
                                    <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/images/2024/05/apple-introduces-m4-chip/article/Apple-M4-chip-new-CPU-240507.zip" download="" data-analytics-title="download image - Apple-M4-chip-new-CPU-240507_big" aria-label="Download media, A graphic representing the new M4 chip, highlighting its four performance cores and detailing their 1) improved branch prediction, 2) wider decode and execution engines, and 3) next-generation ML accelerators. The graphic also highlights M4’s six efficiency cores, and details their 1) improved branch prediction, 2) deeper execution engine, and 3) next-generation ML accelerators."></a>
                                </div>
                            </figure>
                        </div>
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                        <div id="gallery-31a22c8e5118787e7dfbb9ca9d773f37" aria-labelledby="gallery-dotnav-31a22c8e5118787e7dfbb9ca9d773f37" data-gallery-item="">
                            <figure role="presentation" data-analytics-activitymap-region-id="Gallery:ten-core-gpu">
                                
                                <div>
                                    <div>Pro rendering with the new up-to-10-core GPU of M4 is now up to four times faster than on M2.</div>
                                    
                                    
                                    <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/images/2024/05/apple-introduces-m4-chip/article/Apple-M4-chip-10-core-CPU-240507.zip" download="" data-analytics-title="download image - Apple-M4-chip-10-core-CPU-240507_big" aria-label="Download media, A graphic representing the new M4 chip, highlighting its 10-core GPU and detailing its 1) next-generation architecture, 2) Dynamic Caching, 3) mesh shading, and 4) ray tracing."></a>
                                </div>
                            </figure>
                        </div>
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                        <div id="gallery-2b86549e45af2f7ca2c474fdbd78716f" aria-labelledby="gallery-dotnav-2b86549e45af2f7ca2c474fdbd78716f" data-gallery-item="">
                            <figure role="presentation" data-analytics-activitymap-region-id="Gallery:Neural-Engine">
                                
                                <div>
                                    <div>M4 includes Apple’s most powerful Neural Engine ever, capable of 38 trillion operations per second — 60x faster than the first Neural Engine in A11 Bionic.</div>
                                    
                                    
                                    <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/images/2024/05/apple-introduces-m4-chip/article/Apple-M4-chip-Neural-Engine-240507.zip" download="" data-analytics-title="download image - Apple-M4-chip-Neural-Engine-240507_big" aria-label="Download media, A graphic representing the new M4 chip, highlighting its Neural Engine and detailing its 1) 16-core design and 2) that it’s faster and more efficient."></a>
                                </div>
                            </figure>
                        </div>
                        
                    
                
            </div>
            
                
                
                <nav role="presentation">
                    
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    
                </nav>
            
        </div>
    


    
    
    


     
     
    
    
        <div>
             
                 <h2>New Technologies Enabling the New iPad Pro
</h2>
                 
             
                 <div>Delivering a giant leap in performance over the previous iPad Pro with M2, M4 consists of 28 billion transistors built using a second-generation 3-nanometer technology that further advances the power efficiency of Apple silicon. M4 also features an entirely new display engine designed with pioneering technologies, enabling the stunning precision, color accuracy, and brightness uniformity of the Ultra Retina XDR display, a state-of-the-art display created by combining the light of two OLED panels.
</div>
                 
             
         </div>
 

    
    
    


    
        
        
        
        
            <figure aria-label="Media, Two new iPad Pro devices are shown from the back in silver and space black.">
                <div>
                         
                            
                            <div>
                                M4 is designed with pioneering technologies that help enable the incredibly thin design of iPad Pro.
                            </div>
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/images/2024/05/apple-introduces-m4-chip/article/Apple-M4-chip-iPad-Pro-silver-and-space-black-240507.zip" download="" data-analytics-title="download image - Apple-M4-chip-iPad-Pro-silver-and-space-black-240507_inline" aria-label="Download media, Two new iPad Pro devices are shown from the back in silver and space black."></a>
                    </div>
            </figure>
        
    










    
    
    


     
     
    
    
        <div>
             
                 <h2><strong>New 10-core CPU</strong>
</h2>
                 
             
                 <div>M4 has a new up-to-10-core CPU consisting of up to four performance cores and now six efficiency cores. The next-generation cores feature improved branch prediction, with wider decode and execution engines for the performance cores, and a deeper execution engine for the efficiency cores. And both types of cores also feature enhanced, next-generation ML accelerators.
</div>
                 
             
                 <div>M4 delivers up to 1.5x faster CPU performance over the powerful M2 in the previous iPad Pro.<sup>1</sup> Whether working with complex orchestral music files in Logic Pro or adding highly demanding effects to 4K video in LumaFusion, M4 boosts performance across pro workflows.
</div>
                 
             
         </div>
 

    
    
    






  
    
    
    
    
      <figure aria-label="Media, Logic Pro is shown on the new iPad Pro.">
        <div>
             
              
              <div>
                M4 delivers up to 1.5x faster CPU performance over the powerful M2 in the previous iPad Pro, boosting performance across pro workflows in apps like Logic Pro.
              </div>
            
            
            
            
            <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/images/2024/05/apple-introduces-m4-chip/article/Apple-M4-chip-ChromaGlow-240507.zip" download="" data-analytics-title="download image - Apple-M4-chip-ChromaGlow-240507_big" aria-label="Download media, Logic Pro is shown on the new iPad Pro."></a>
          </div>
      </figure>
    
  






    
    
    


     
     
    
    
        <div>
             
                 <h2>GPU Brings New Capabilities to iPad Pro
</h2>
                 
             
                 <div>The new 10-core GPU of M4 builds upon the next-generation graphics architecture of the M3 family of chips. It features Dynamic Caching, an Apple innovation that allocates local memory dynamically in hardware and in real time to dramatically increase the average utilization of the GPU. This significantly increases performance for the most demanding pro apps and games.
</div>
                 
             
         </div>
 

    
    
    


    
    <div data-component-list="ScrollAnimationDefault AutoPlayVideo">
        <div>The new GPU of M4&nbsp;will bring&nbsp;hardware-accelerated ray tracing to iPad for the first time, enabling even more realistic shadows and reflections in games like Diablo Immortal, and other graphically rich experiences.</div>
        
            <a aria-label="Download video: Diablo Immortal Gameplay on iPad Pro" data-analytics-title="Download video - Diablo Immortal Gameplay on iPad Pro" download="" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/videos/diablo-immortal/downloads/Apple-M4-chip-Diablo-Immortal-240507.zip">
            </a>
        
    </div>






    
    
    


     
     
    
    
        <div>Hardware-accelerated ray tracing comes to iPad for the first time, and enables even more realistic shadows and reflections in games and other graphically rich experiences. Hardware-accelerated mesh shading is also built into the GPU, and delivers greater capability and efficiency in geometry processing, enabling more visually complex scenes in games and graphics-intensive apps. Pro rendering performance in apps like Octane gets a huge boost with M4, and is now up to four times faster than on M2.<sup>1</sup> With these improvements to the CPU and GPU, M4 maintains Apple silicon’s industry-leading performance per watt. M4 can deliver the same performance as M2 using just half the power. And compared with the latest PC chip in a thin and light laptop, M4 can deliver the same performance using just a fourth of the power.<sup>2</sup>
</div>
 

    
    
    






  
    
    
    
    
      <figure aria-label="Media, Octane is shown on the new iPad Pro.">
        <div>
             
              
              <div>
                Pro rendering performance in apps like Octane gets a huge boost with M4, and is now up to four times faster than on iPad Pro with M2.
              </div>
            
            
            
            
            <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/images/2024/05/apple-introduces-m4-chip/article/Apple-M4-chip-Octane-240507.zip" download="" data-analytics-title="download image - Apple-M4-chip-Octane-240507_big" aria-label="Download media, Octane is shown on the new iPad Pro."></a>
          </div>
      </figure>
    
  






    
    
    


     
     
    
    
        <div>
             
                 <h2><strong>The Most Powerful Neural Engine Ever</strong>
</h2>
                 
             
                 <div>M4 has a blazing-fast Neural Engine — an IP block in the chip dedicated to the acceleration of AI workloads. This is Apple’s most powerful Neural Engine ever, capable of an astounding 38 trillion operations per second — a breathtaking 60x faster than the first Neural Engine in A11 Bionic. Together with next-generation ML accelerators in the CPU, the high-performance GPU, and higher-bandwidth unified memory, the Neural Engine makes M4 an outrageously powerful chip for AI. And with AI features in iPadOS like Live Captions for real-time audio captions, and Visual Look Up, which identifies objects in video and photos, the new iPad Pro allows users to accomplish amazing AI tasks quickly and on device.
</div>
                 
             
                 <div>iPad Pro with M4 can easily isolate a subject from its background throughout a 4K video in Final Cut Pro with just a tap, and can automatically create musical notation in real time in StaffPad by simply listening to someone play the piano. And inference workloads can be done efficiently and privately while minimizing the impact on app memory, app responsiveness, and battery life. The Neural Engine in M4 is Apple’s most capable yet, and is more powerful than any neural processing unit in any AI PC today.
</div>
                 
             
         </div>
 

    
    
    


    
    <div data-component-list="ScrollAnimationDefault AutoPlayVideo">
        <div>M4 has a blazing-fast Neural Engine that can easily isolate a subject from its background throughout a 4K video in Final Cut Pro with just a tap.</div>
        
            <a aria-label="Download video: Final Cut Pro Scene Removal Mask" data-analytics-title="Download video - Final Cut Pro Scene Removal Mask" download="" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/videos/apple-m4-chip-final-cut-pro-ipad-pro/downloads/Apple-M4-chip-Final-Cut-Pro-iPad-Pro-240507.zip">
            </a>
        
    </div>






    
    
    


     
     
    
    
        <div>
             
                 <h2><strong>Advanced Media Engine for Smooth, Efficient Streaming</strong>
</h2>
                 
             
                 <div>The Media Engine of M4 is the most advanced to come to iPad. In addition to supporting the most popular video codecs, like H.264, HEVC, and ProRes, it brings hardware acceleration for AV1 to iPad for the first time. This provides more power-efficient playback of high-resolution video experiences from streaming services.
</div>
                 
             
                 <h2>Better for the Environment
</h2>
                 
             
                 <div>The power-efficient performance of M4 helps the all-new iPad Pro meet Apple’s high standards for energy efficiency and deliver all-day battery life. This results in less time needing to be plugged in and less energy consumed over its lifetime.
</div>
                 
             
                 <div>Today, Apple is carbon neutral for global corporate operations, and by 2030, plans to be carbon neutral across the entire manufacturing supply chain and life cycle of every product.
</div>
                 
             
         </div>
 

    
    
    




    
    
        
    


    
    
    



    
    
    




    




    
    
    





    
    
    <div>
            <ol>
<li>Testing was conducted by Apple in March and April 2024. See <a href="https://www.apple.com/ipad-pro/" target="_blank">apple.com/ipad-pro</a> for more information.</li>
<li>Testing was conducted by Apple in March and April 2024 using preproduction 13-inch iPad Pro (M4) units with a 10-core CPU and 16GB of RAM. Performance was measured using select industry‑standard benchmarks. PC laptop chip performance data is from testing ASUS Zenbook 14 OLED (UX3405MA) with Core Ultra 7 155H and 32GB of RAM. Performance tests are conducted using specific computer systems and reflect the approximate performance of iPad Pro.</li>
</ol>

        </div>



    
    
    






    
















	
	
	
		















	
	

</article>



</section>
</main>


	

</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Microsoft closes several large Bethesda affiliated game studios (147 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ign.com/articles/microsoft-closes-redfall-developer-arkane-austin-hifi-rush-developer-tango-gameworks-and-more-in-devastating-cuts-at-bethesda</link>
            <guid>40285476</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 13:53:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.ign.com/articles/microsoft-closes-redfall-developer-arkane-austin-hifi-rush-developer-tango-gameworks-and-more-in-devastating-cuts-at-bethesda">https://www.ign.com/articles/microsoft-closes-redfall-developer-arkane-austin-hifi-rush-developer-tango-gameworks-and-more-in-devastating-cuts-at-bethesda</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40285476">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section><p>Microsoft has closed a number of Bethesda studios, including <a href="https://www.ign.com/games/redfall">Redfall</a> maker Arkane Austin, <a href="https://www.ign.com/games/hi-fi-rush">Hi-Fi Rush</a> and <a href="https://www.ign.com/games/the-evil-within">The Evil Within</a> developer Tango Gameworks, and more in devastating cuts at Bethesda, IGN can confirm.</p><p>Alpha Dog Games, maker of mobile game <a href="https://www.ign.com/games/mighty-doom">Mighty Doom</a>, will also close. Roundhouse Studios will be absorbed by <a href="https://www.ign.com/games/the-elder-scrolls-online">The Elder Scrolls Online</a> developer ZeniMax Online Studios. Microsoft, currently valued at over $3 trillion, did not say how many staff will lose their jobs, but significant layoffs are inevitable. IGN has asked Bethesda for comment. Microsoft declined to expand further when contacted by IGN.</p><p>On Redfall, the disastrous vampire co-op game will now not receive promised updates, including an offline mode and new character DLC, as Microsoft has ended all development on the game. Microsoft said Redfall will remain online to play, and it will provide a "make-good" offer for those who bought the Hero DLC.</p><blockquote data-theme="light"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Signup here <a href="https://t.co/wb1R4m4emj" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://t.co/wb1R4m4emj</a> to receive details on how eligible players can receive this credit. <a href="https://t.co/69Os17kpQ8" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">pic.twitter.com/69Os17kpQ8</a></p>— Arkane Studios (@ArkaneStudios) <a href="https://twitter.com/ArkaneStudios/status/1787837804287860886?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">May 7, 2024</a></blockquote> <p>Arkane Lyon, which is working on <a href="https://www.ign.com/games/blade-arkane">Marvel's Blade</a>, survives the cull, as does Bethesda Game Studios (Fallout, The Elder Scrolls, Starfield), and Machine Games (<a href="https://www.ign.com/games/indiana-jones-and-the-great-circle">Indiana Jones and The Great Circle</a>). Doom developer id Software is also unaffected.</p><div data-cy="quoteBox"><p>"This reprioritization of titles and resources means a few teams will be realigned to others and that some of our colleagues will be leaving us.&nbsp;</p></div><p>In an email to staff sent by Matt Booty, head of Xbox Game Studios, Microsoft blamed the cuts on a “reprioritization of titles and resources”. The email, verified by IGN, is below:</p><blockquote>Today I’m sharing changes we are making to our Bethesda and ZeniMax teams. These changes are grounded in prioritizing high-impact titles and further investing in Bethesda’s portfolio of blockbuster games and beloved worlds which you have nurtured over many decades. </blockquote><blockquote>To double down on these franchises and invest to build new ones requires us to look across the business to identify the opportunities that are best positioned for success. This reprioritization of titles and resources means a few teams will be realigned to others and that some of our colleagues will be leaving us.  </blockquote><blockquote>Here are the changes going into effect: </blockquote><blockquote>Arkane Austin – This studio will close with some members of the team joining other studios to work on projects across Bethesda. Arkane Austin has a history of making impactful and innovative games and it is a pedigree that everyone should be proud of. Redfall’s previous update will be its last as we end all development on the game. The game and its servers will remain online for players to enjoy and we will provide make-good offers to players who purchased the Hero DLC. </blockquote><blockquote>Alpha Dog Studios – This studio will also close. We appreciate the team’s creativity in bringing Doom to new players. Mighty Doom will be sunset on August 7 and we will be turning off the ability for players to make any purchases in the game.  </blockquote><blockquote>Tango Gameworks – Tango Gameworks will also close. We are thankful for their contributions to Bethesda and players around the world. Hi-Fi Rush will continue to be available to players on the platforms it is today.  </blockquote><blockquote>Roundhouse Games – The team at Roundhouse Games will be joining ZeniMax Online Studios (ZOS). Roundhouse has played a key role in many of our recent game launches and bringing them into ZOS to work on The Elder Scrolls Online will mean we can do even more to grow the world that millions of players call home.  </blockquote><blockquote>With this consolidation of our Bethesda studio teams, so that we can invest more deeply in our portfolio of games and new IP, a small number of roles across select Bethesda publishing and corporate teams will also be eliminated. </blockquote><blockquote>Those whose roles will be impacted will be notified today, and we ask that you please treat your departing colleagues with respect and compassion. We will provide our full support to those who are impacted in today’s notifications and through their transitions, including severance benefits informed by local laws.  </blockquote><blockquote>These changes are not a reflection of the creativity and skill of the talented individuals at these teams or the risks they took to try new things. I acknowledge that these changes are also disruptive to the various support teams across ZeniMax and Bethesda that bring our games to market. We are making these tough decisions to create capacity to increase investment in other parts of our portfolio and focus on our priority games. </blockquote><blockquote>Bethesda remains one of the key pillars of Xbox with a strong portfolio of amazing games and thriving communities. As we look to the future, there is an impressive line-up of games on the horizon. In 2024 alone we have Starfield Shattered Space, Fallout 76 Skyline Valley, Indiana Jones and The Great Circle, and The Elder Scrolls Online’s Golden Road. As we align our plans and resources to best set ourselves up for success in this complex and changing industry, our teams across Arkane Lyon, Bethesda Game Studios, id Software, MachineGames, ZeniMax Online Studios and the Bethesda publishing and corporate teams will be well-positioned to build new IP, explore new game concepts, and expand on our existing franchises.  </blockquote><blockquote>- Matt</blockquote><p>Microsoft's announcement of the cuts at Bethesda come over three months after <a href="https://www.ign.com/articles/microsoft-lays-off-1900-staff-from-its-video-game-workforce">the company announced plans to cut 1,900 staff from its video game workforce</a>, and amid a boom time for Bethesda's Fallout series following the breakout hit Prime Video TV show. The closure of Tango Gameworks hits just over a year after the launch of Hi-Fi Rush, what many considered to be <a href="https://www.ign.com/articles/hi-fi-rush-review">one of the best Xbox games in recent years</a>. <a href="https://twitter.com/aarongreenberg/status/1649431572137779203" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tweeting</a> in April 2023, Aaron Greenberg, VP, Xbox Games Marketing at Microsoft, addressed concern that Hi-Fi Rush had failed to meet sales targets, calling the game "a break out hit for us and our players in all key measurements and expectations." Greenberg continued: "We couldn’t be happier with what the team at Tango Gameworks delivered with this surprise release." <a href="https://www.ign.com/articles/xbox-game-hi-fi-rush-confirmed-for-ps5-release-date-announced">Hi-Fi Rush launched on PS5</a> as part of Microsoft's new multi-platform push in March.</p><blockquote data-theme="light"><p lang="zxx" dir="ltr"><a href="https://t.co/KhhqgR902g" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">pic.twitter.com/KhhqgR902g</a></p>— Tango Gameworks (EN) (@TangoGameworks) <a href="https://twitter.com/TangoGameworks/status/1787837929332601189?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">May 7, 2024</a></blockquote> <p>In <a href="https://twitter.com/DBakaba/status/1787839169588265251" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">a series of tweets</a>, Arkane Lyon chief Dinga Bakaba hit out at the cuts, calling them "absolutely terrible." "To any executive reading this, friendly reminder that video games are an entertainment/cultural industry, and your business as a corporation is to take care of your artists/entertainers and help them create value for you," Bakaba continued.</p><p>"Don't throw us into gold fever gambits, don't use us as strawmen for miscalculations/blind spots, don't make our work environments darwinist jungles. You say we make you proud when we make a good game. Make us proud when times are tough. We know you can, we seen it before.</p><p>"For now, great teams are sunsetting before our eyes again, and it's a fucking gut stab. Lyon is safe, but please be tactful and discerning about all this, and respect affected folks' voice and leave it room to be heard, it's their story to tell, their feelings to express.</p><p>"Inside baseball, but if I read 'immersive sim curse' from the community, especially from a fellow dev, I swear to God... Please, let's talk about the *real* challenges instead of rehashing irrational anxieties of the past.</p><p>"Even more inside baseball, but with a very, very wide range, as a wise and sorely missed man said: 'Please Stop.' "</p><p>Layoffs are sweeping the video game industry, with a number of high-profile studios cutting staff or shutting down. In stark contrast to a year of blockbuster video game hits, one of the biggest ongoing industry trends in 2023 was the prevalence of mass layoffs, and they have continued into 2024. While actual figures are difficult to obtain, estimates suggest the number of workers laid off in games last year approached or exceeded 10,000. A recent GDC survey of developers suggests one-third of all game developers were impacted by layoffs last year, either directly or by witnessing them happen at their company.</p><p><em>Wesley is the UK News Editor for IGN. Find him on Twitter at @wyp100. You can reach Wesley at wesley_yinpoole@ign.com or confidentially at wyp100@proton.me.</em></p></section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Raspberry Pi Connect (118 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.raspberrypi.com/news/raspberry-pi-connect/</link>
            <guid>40284994</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 13:07:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.raspberrypi.com/news/raspberry-pi-connect/">https://www.raspberrypi.com/news/raspberry-pi-connect/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40284994">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.raspberrypi.com/news/raspberry-pi-connect/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cold brew coffee in 3 minutes using acoustic cavitation (118 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.unsw.edu.au/newsroom/news/2024/05/Ultrasonic_cold_brew_coffee_ready_under_three_minutes</link>
            <guid>40284823</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 12:46:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.unsw.edu.au/newsroom/news/2024/05/Ultrasonic_cold_brew_coffee_ready_under_three_minutes">https://www.unsw.edu.au/newsroom/news/2024/05/Ultrasonic_cold_brew_coffee_ready_under_three_minutes</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40284823">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p><span data-component_type="column-layout" data-component_id="column_layout-643782508" data-component_title="Hear that? That’s the sound of an ultrasonic cold brew coffee ready in under three minutes">


<div>

    
        <div>
            <p><span data-component_type="column-layout" data-component_id="column_layout-556150652" data-component_title="Hear that? That’s the sound of an ultrasonic cold brew coffee ready in under three minutes">


<div>
            <p><span data-component_type="column-layout" data-component_id="column_layout-1042562652" data-component_title="Hear that? That’s the sound of an ultrasonic cold brew coffee ready in under three minutes">


<div>
            
<p><span data-component_type="text" data-component_id="text-1734502318" data-component_title="Hear that? That’s the sound of an ultrasonic cold brew coffee ready in under three minutes">
<div>
    <p><span><strong>UNSW Sydney engineers have utilised sound waves to cut the time it takes to make a cold brew coffee from many hours down to mere minutes.</strong></span></p>
<p>Fans of cold brew coffee often rave about the smoother, less acidic and less bitter taste compared to a regular hot brew.</p>
<p>There’s just one major problem – it takes anywhere from 12 to 24 hours to fully steep the grounds and allow the flavours to slowly be extracted using only cold water.</p>
<p>That’s far from ideal if you want or need your caffeine fix in a hurry in the morning.</p>
<p>However, engineers from UNSW have now developed a new way to make cold brew coffee in under three minutes – just like a regular hot brew – without sacrificing on the taste experience.</p>
<p>The process involves using an ultrasonic reactor to speed up the brew of the grounded coffee beans, with the research published in <a><i></i></a><a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1350417724001330" target="_blank" data-click_category="TextComponentRichText" data-click_id="text_Ultrasonics Sonochemistry" data-click_title="RichText" data-click_name="Ultrasonics Sonochemistry">Ultrasonics Sonochemistry</a>.</p>

<p>Addressing the challenge of speeding up the brewing process of a cold brew, the UNSW team led by <a href="https://www.unsw.edu.au/staff/francisco-trujillo" target="_blank" data-click_category="TextComponentRichText" data-click_id="text_Dr Francisco Trujillo" data-click_title="RichText" data-click_name="Dr Francisco Trujillo">Dr Francisco Trujillo</a>, used an existing model of a Breville espresso machine and superimposed their own patented sound transmission system.</p>
<p>The system connects a bolt-clamped transducer with the brewing basket via a metallic horn – transforming a standard espresso filter basket into a powerful ultrasonic reactor.</p>
<p>The reactor works by injecting sound waves at a frequency of 38.8 kHz at multiple points through its walls – generating multiple regions for acoustic cavitation within the reactor.</p>

</div>

    

</span>


</p>
<p><span data-component_type="image" data-component_id="image-2055060212" data-component_title="Hear that? That’s the sound of an ultrasonic cold brew coffee ready in under three minutes">
<div data-cmp-is="image" data-cmp-src="/content/unsw-sites/au/en/newsroom/news/2024/05/Ultrasonic_cold_brew_coffee_ready_under_three_minutes/_jcr_content/root/responsivegrid-layout-fixed-width/responsivegrid-full-top/column_layout_1/par_2_1_75/column_layout/par_1/column_layout/par_1/image.coreimg.82{.width}.jpeg/1714373105656/coffee-setup.jpeg" data-cmp-widths="335,700,1170,1280,1920" data-asset="/content/dam/images/photos/news/2024/2024-05-coldbrewcoffee/coffee setup.tif" data-title="The new faster cold brew system subjects coffee grounds in the filter basket to ultrasonic sound waves from a transducer, via a specially adapted horn. " itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/ImageObject">
            
                
                
                
                
                <p><span itemprop="caption">The new faster cold brew system subjects coffee grounds in the filter basket to ultrasonic sound waves from a transducer, via a specially adapted horn. </span>
                    
                    <span itemprop="subtitle">UNSW/Francisco Trujillo</span>
                </p>
            
        </div>
</span>
</p>


        </div>



</span></p>


        </div>



</span></p>


        </div>
    
        <div>
            <p><span data-component_type="column-layout" data-component_id="column_layout-2111749184" data-component_title="Hear that? That’s the sound of an ultrasonic cold brew coffee ready in under three minutes">


<div>
            
<p><span data-component_type="text" data-component_id="text-753195978" data-component_title="Hear that? That’s the sound of an ultrasonic cold brew coffee ready in under three minutes">
<div>
    <h3>Media enquiries</h3>
<p>For enquiries about this story and interview requests please contact&nbsp;<strong>Neil Martin.</strong></p>
<p>Email:&nbsp;<a href="mailto:n.martin@unsw.edu.au" data-click_category="TextComponentRichText" data-click_id="text_n.martin@unsw.edu.au" data-click_title="RichText" data-click_name="n.martin@unsw.edu.au">n.martin@unsw.edu.au</a></p>

</div>

    

</span>


</p>

<div data-component_type="featured-experts" data-component_id="featured_experts-1761997953" data-component_title="Featured experts">
    <p><img src="https://api.research.unsw.edu.au/sites/default/files/images/profile/img_9934_francisco_trujillo.jpg" alt="Francisco Trujillo">
    </p>
  </div>


        </div>



</span></p>


        </div>
    
</div>



</span></p><p><span data-component_type="text" data-component_id="text-567635428" data-component_title="Hear that? That’s the sound of an ultrasonic cold brew coffee ready in under three minutes">
<div>
    <p>The study also found that this setup can double the extraction yield and caffeine concentration compared to unsonicated samples.</p>
<p>Dr Trujillo, corresponding author of the paper and UNSW food processing engineer in the <a href="https://www.unsw.edu.au/engineering/our-schools/chemical-engineering" target="_blank" data-click_category="TextComponentRichText" data-click_id="text_School of Chemical Engineering" data-click_title="RichText" data-click_name="School of Chemical Engineering">School of Chemical Engineering</a>, says the ultrasound process speeds up the extraction of the oils, flavours and aroma of the ground coffee.</p>
<p>“Ultrasounds accelerate the extraction process due to acoustic cavitation,” he says.</p>
<p>“When acoustic bubbles collapse near the grounded coffee, they generate micro-jets with enough force to pit and fracture the coffee grounds – intensifying the extraction of the aroma and flavours of the brew.</p>
<p>“And the acceleration is enormous – we are reducing what would typically take 12 to 24 hours to less than three&nbsp; minutes.”</p>

</div>

    

</span>


</p><p><span data-component_type="text" data-component_id="text-108096714" data-component_title="Hear that? That’s the sound of an ultrasonic cold brew coffee ready in under three minutes">
<div>
    <p>Dr. Trujillo says the aim was to make the process as easy as making a regular espresso coffee.</p>
<p>“We’re able to demonstrate that this can be adapted to existing espresso machine,” he says.</p>
<p>“We are very excited about developing this technology that can be used by companies that already manufacture coffee machines, so consumers can enjoy an ultrasonic cold brew at home in less than three minutes.</p>
<p>“Very importantly, this breakthrough opens the door for coffee shops and restaurants to produce on-demand brews comparable to 24-hour cold brews, supplying the rising demand while eliminating the need for large semi-industrial brewing units and the associated requirement for extensive refrigeration space.”</p>

</div>

    

</span>


</p><p><span data-component_type="image-full-width" data-component_id="image-full-width-1429422735" data-component_title="Hear that? That’s the sound of an ultrasonic cold brew coffee ready in under three minutes">
<div data-cmp-is="image" data-cmp-src="/content/unsw-sites/au/en/newsroom/news/2024/05/Ultrasonic_cold_brew_coffee_ready_under_three_minutes/_jcr_content/root/responsivegrid-layout-fixed-width/responsivegrid-full-top/image-full-width.coreimg.82{.width}.jpeg/1714372914850/img-0072b.jpeg" data-cmp-widths="335,700,1170,1280,1920" data-asset="/content/dam/images/photos/news/2024/2024-05-coldbrewcoffee/IMG_0072b.jpg" data-title="The UNSW team who developed the three-minute cold brew - Shih-Hao Chiu, Dr Francisco Trujillo and Nikunj Naliyadhara. " itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/ImageObject">
            
                
                
                
                
                <p><span itemprop="caption">The UNSW team who developed the three-minute cold brew - Shih-Hao Chiu, Dr Francisco Trujillo and Nikunj Naliyadhara. </span>
                    
                    <span itemprop="subtitle">UNSW/Cecilia Duong</span>
                </p>
            
        </div>
</span>
</p><p><span data-component_type="text" data-component_id="text-2081832358" data-component_title="Hear that? That’s the sound of an ultrasonic cold brew coffee ready in under three minutes">
<div>
    <h2><strong>Same taste in less time</strong><br>
</h2>
<p>Collaborating with researchers from University of Queensland, samples of coffee were sent to the <a href="https://qaafi.uq.edu.au/" target="_blank" data-click_category="TextComponentRichText" data-click_id="text_Queensland Alliance for Agriculture and Food" data-click_title="RichText" data-click_name="Queensland Alliance for Agriculture and Food">Queensland Alliance for Agriculture and Food</a> (QAAFI) where they underwent a thorough sensory analysis.</p>
<p>The samples included cold brew sonicated at room temperature for one minute, the second was sonicated for 3 minutes, and the third was a regular 24 hours stepped brew at four degrees Celsius without sonication.</p>
<p>They were evaluated on their aroma, texture, flavour, and aftertaste attributes.</p>
<p>“Compared to the 24-hour brew, the sonicated one-minute brew sample received similar ratings, especially in flavour, aftertaste attributes including bitterness, sourness, fullness texture and aroma,” says Dr. Trujillo.</p>
<p>“However, it scored lower in aroma intensity and dark chocolate aroma. This suggests that the sonicated 1-minute sample is slightly under-extracted compared to the 24-hour cold brew.</p>
<p>“Meanwhile, the sonicated three-minute sample provided a similar dark chocolate aroma and aroma intensity to the 24-hour cold brew, but slightly more bitter.</p>
<p>“The results of the sensory study showed that a sonication time between one and three minutes is ideal for creating a coffee comparable with 24-hour cold brew coffee, depending on the interest of customers.”</p>
<p>University of Queensland Sensory Scientist and Flavour Chemist <a href="https://qaafi.uq.edu.au/profile/33/heather-smyth" target="_blank" data-click_category="TextComponentRichText" data-click_id="text_Professor Heather Smyth" data-click_title="RichText" data-click_name="Professor Heather Smyth">Professor Heather Smyth</a>, a co-author of the paper, said the new method created a coffee as good as cold brew steeped overnight.</p>
<p>“Our trained sensory panel tastings proved that we can get a very similar taste profile to either a traditional cold brew or an espresso in the time it takes to brew a hot espresso,” Prof. Smyth said.</p>
<p>“Further work could explore different types of beans, different regions of beans and for companies or cafes that specialise in single origin or high-quality beans, this would be another string to the bow to show yet another dimension of coffee.</p>
<p>“Once again, Australia has new technology at our fingertips that moves on from traditional methods to modern methods of coffee making to give consumers a new premium experience.”</p>
<h2><strong>Shaking up the beverage industry</strong></h2>
<p>Ultrasounds can be applied to several areas across the food industry including drying, extraction, emulsification and crystallisation – making the process faster and more efficient.</p>
<p>Dr. Trujillo says this technology can be also used to speed up the brewing process of teas as well.</p>
<p>“With this technology, we’re offering coffee shops, restaurants and even home coffee-brewers the chance to produce on-demand brews, eliminating the need for large brewing and refrigeration units.”</p>

</div>

    

</span>


</p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Boeing faces new US investigation into 'missed' 787 inspections (188 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/business/article/2024/may/07/boeing-us-investigation-787-inspections-faa</link>
            <guid>40284389</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 11:41:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/article/2024/may/07/boeing-us-investigation-787-inspections-faa">https://www.theguardian.com/business/article/2024/may/07/boeing-us-investigation-787-inspections-faa</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40284389">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p>Boeing faces a new investigation after the planemaker told US regulators it might have failed to properly carry out some quality inspections on its 787 Dreamliner planes.</p><p>The US Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) said it was “investigating whether Boeing completed the inspections and whether company employees may have falsified aircraft records”.</p><p>The regulator said that while the investigation was under way, Boeing employees would reinspect the Dreamliners that had not been delivered to airline customers yet, and the company would develop an “action plan” for the planes that are already in service.</p><figure id="8cc83683-68b1-4b2d-8db3-0b032471c387" data-spacefinder-role="richLink" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.RichLinkBlockElement"><gu-island name="RichLinkComponent" priority="feature" deferuntil="idle" props="{&quot;richLinkIndex&quot;:3,&quot;element&quot;:{&quot;_type&quot;:&quot;model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.RichLinkBlockElement&quot;,&quot;prefix&quot;:&quot;Related: &quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Boeing’s first astronaut launch called off due to faulty valve&quot;,&quot;elementId&quot;:&quot;8cc83683-68b1-4b2d-8db3-0b032471c387&quot;,&quot;role&quot;:&quot;richLink&quot;,&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/business/article/2024/may/06/boeing-starliner-launch-scrubbed&quot;},&quot;ajaxUrl&quot;:&quot;https://api.nextgen.guardianapps.co.uk&quot;,&quot;format&quot;:{&quot;display&quot;:0,&quot;theme&quot;:0,&quot;design&quot;:0}}" config="{&quot;renderingTarget&quot;:&quot;Web&quot;,&quot;darkModeAvailable&quot;:false,&quot;assetOrigin&quot;:&quot;https://assets.guim.co.uk/&quot;}"></gu-island></figure><p>The FAA said Boeing “voluntarily informed us in April that it may not have completed required inspections to confirm adequate bonding and grounding where the wings join the fuselage on certain 787 Dreamliner airplanes”.</p><p>The Boeing executive overseeing the 787 programme, Scott Stocker, wrote in an internal memo, seen by the Guardian, that the problem was reported by an employee and was an instance of “misconduct,” but not “an immediate safety of flight issue”.</p><p>The memo said the company concluded that “several people had been violating company policies by not performing a required test, but recording the work as having been completed”.</p><p>“We promptly informed our regulator about what we learned and are taking swift and serious corrective action with multiple teammates,” the memo added.</p><p>Stocker said the company would “celebrate” the employee who spoke up.</p><p>Last month, a whistleblower came forward with different quality allegations about several Boeing models and urged <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/boeing" data-link-name="in body link">Boeing</a> to ground every 787 Dreamliner jet worldwide, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2024/apr/16/boeing-whistleblower-787-dreamliner" data-link-name="in body link">warning they were at risk of premature failure</a>.</p><figure data-spacefinder-role="inline" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.NewsletterSignupBlockElement"><a data-ignore="global-link-styling" href="#EmailSignup-skip-link-10">skip past newsletter promotion</a><p id="EmailSignup-skip-link-10" tabindex="0" aria-label="after newsletter promotion" role="note">after newsletter promotion</p></figure><p>The Boeing engineer Sam Salehpour claimed that the company took shortcuts to reduce production bottlenecks while making the 787. He also raised issues about the production of the 777, another wide-body jet. The FAA is investigating these allegations.</p><p>Salehpour, who has worked at Boeing for more than a decade, said he faced retaliation, including threats and exclusion from meetings, after raising concerns over problem including a gap between parts of the fuselage of the 787.</p><p>In January, a door panel was blown out of a Boeing 737 Max aircraft on an Alaska Airlines flight in mid-air, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2024/jan/06/alaska-airlines-grounds-boeing-737-max-9-planes-after-mid-air-window-blowout" data-link-name="in body link">forcing the aircraft into an emergency landing</a>.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Pyspread – The Most Pythonic Spreadsheet (147 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://pyspread.gitlab.io/</link>
            <guid>40284219</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 11:08:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://pyspread.gitlab.io/">https://pyspread.gitlab.io/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40284219">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        

<p><em>pyspread</em> is a non-traditional spreadsheet application that is based on and written in the programming language Python.
The goal of <em>pyspread</em> is to be the most pythonic spreadsheet.</p>

<p><em>pyspread</em> expects Python expressions in its grid cells, which makes a spreadsheet specific language obsolete. Each cell returns a
Python object that can be accessed from other cells. These objects can represent anything including lists or matrices.</p>

<p><em>pyspread</em> is free software. It is released under the GPL v3 licence.</p>

<p>The latest release is <a href="https://pypi.org/project/pyspread/" target="blank">pyspread v2.2.3</a> (<a href="https://gitlab.com/pyspread/pyspread" target="blank">source code</a>). It requires Python 3.6+.</p>

<p>The last (outdated) release that is compatible with Python 2.x is pyspread v1.1.3.</p>

<p><img src="https://pyspread.gitlab.io/images/screenshot_sinus_large.png" alt="Pyspread example"></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Cells accept Python code and return Python objects</li>
  <li>Access to Python modules from within cells including e.g. <a href="https://numpy.org/" target="blank">NumPy</a></li>
  <li>Imports CSV, SVG</li>
  <li>Exports CSV, SVG, PDF*</li>
  <li>Cells may display text, markup, images, dates** or charts**</li>
  <li><a href="https://matplotlib.org/" target="blank">Matplotlib</a> and <a href="https://www.r-project.org/" target="blank">R</a> charts. <a href="https://plotnine.readthedocs.io/en/stable/index.html" target="blank">Plotnine</a> and R packages <a href="https://www.rdocumentation.org/packages/graphics" target="blank">graphics</a>, <a href="https://lattice.r-forge.r-project.org/" target="blank">lattice</a>, <a href="https://ggplot2.tidyverse.org/" target="blank">ggplot2</a> supported via dialog.**</li>
  <li>Spell checker**</li>
  <li>git-able pysu save file format</li>
  <li>blake2b based save file signatures that prevent foreign code execution</li>
</ul>

<p>Notes: * PDF export via print to file, ** requires optional dependencies</p>

<h2 id="target-user-group">Target User Group</h2>

<p>Directly using Python code in a grid is a core feature of <em>pyspread</em>. The target user group has
experience with or wants to learn the programming language Python:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Clara is a research engineer. She systematically compares results of different parameter sets.
She is proficient with Python and has used it for her scientific analyses. Clara wants a quick initial overview
of how changing specific parameters affects her results. With <em>pyspread</em>, Clara is displaying each result in one cell.
This allows her to quickly figure out, which parameters she is going to focus on next.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Peter is using spreadsheets to prepare business decisions. 
He separates data from code by keeping his business data in CSV files and accessing these files from <em>pyspread</em>. 
Furthermore, Peter is worried about algorithmic errors and calculation inaccuracies is his complicated tables. 
He is importing the <em>Money</em> datatype from <a href="https://github.com/py-moneyed/py-moneyed" target="blank">py-moneyed</a>
in the Macro panel. The dedicated Money class helps him avoiding floating point errors. 
Peter has implemented his analysis tools together with unit tests in a separate Python module, 
which he is importing as well. Therefore, he is worrying less about wrong results 
that may lead to bad business decisions.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Not part of the target user group are Donna and Jack:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Donna is looking for a free replacement for Ms. Excel. She does not know any programming language, and she has no time to learn Python.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Jack does computation intensive data analysis. He is looking for a spreadsheet that can parallelize calculations - ideally out of the box as a cluster or a cloud solution.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>This does not mean that Donna or Jack cannot work with <em>pyspread</em>. However, Donna might find the learning
curve for using Python code in cells too steep. Jack on the other hand might be disappointed because he has to 
ensure manually that his long running tasks are not locking up pyspread.</p>



<p>For user questions or user feedback please use the
<a href="https://gitter.im/pyspread/community" target="blank">pyspread community board</a>
on gitter.</p>

<p>For contributions, patches, development discussions and ideas please create an issue using the <em>pyspread</em> issue tracker</p>

    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Dotfiles: Unofficial Guide to Dotfiles on GitHub (115 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://dotfiles.github.io/</link>
            <guid>40284164</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 10:58:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://dotfiles.github.io/">https://dotfiles.github.io/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40284164">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      <header>
        <img alt="Forktocat" src="https://dotfiles.github.io/images/dotfiles-logo.png">
        <p>
          <em>Your unofficial guide to dotfiles on GitHub.</em>
        </p>
        <a href="https://dotfiles.github.io/">Home</a><br>
        <a href="https://dotfiles.github.io/tutorials/">Tutorials</a><br>
        <a href="https://dotfiles.github.io/utilities/">General-purpose utilities</a><br>
        <a href="https://dotfiles.github.io/frameworks/">Tool-specific frameworks</a><br>
        <a href="https://dotfiles.github.io/bootstrap/">Bootstrap repositories</a><br>
        <a href="https://dotfiles.github.io/inspiration/">Inspiration</a><br>
        <a href="https://dotfiles.github.io/tips/">Tips and tricks</a><br>
        <a href="https://dotfiles.github.io/faq/">FAQ</a>
      </header>
      <section>
        

<p>Why would I want my dotfiles on GitHub?</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong><em>Backup</em></strong>, <strong><em>restore</em></strong>, and <strong><em>sync</em></strong> the prefs and settings for your
toolbox. Your dotfiles might be the most important files on your machine.</li>
  <li><strong><em>Learn</em></strong> from the community. Discover new tools for your toolbox and new
tricks for the ones you already use.</li>
  <li><strong><em>Share</em></strong> what you’ve learned with the rest of us.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="navigating-this-site">Navigating this site</h2>

<p>If you’re just starting out, before you go symlinking everything in <code>~/*</code>, you
might want to check out some <a href="https://dotfiles.github.io/tutorials/">tutorials</a> that discuss how you can
organize your dotfiles. Next, you could look through the <a href="https://dotfiles.github.io/utilities/">general-purpose
dotfiles utilities</a> to find a system you can use to manage your
dotfiles. Some <a href="https://dotfiles.github.io/frameworks/">tool-specific frameworks</a> could save you time in
customizing specific programs like your shell.</p>

<p>Prefer to start from a popular base configuration? Check out dotfiles
<a href="https://dotfiles.github.io/bootstrap/">bootstrap repositories</a>. Or just looking for inspiration, to see
how others are doing things? Check out other GitHub users’
<a href="https://dotfiles.github.io/inspiration/">dotfiles</a> or Reddit’s <a href="https://reddit.com/r/dotfiles">r/dotfiles</a>
subreddit.</p>

<h2 id="contribute">Contribute</h2>

<p>Want to help out? Great! Submit a <a href="https://github.com/dotfiles/dotfiles.github.com/issues">feature request</a>, <a href="https://github.com/dotfiles/dotfiles.github.com/issues">open an issue</a>, or <a href="https://github.com/dotfiles/dotfiles.github.com">submit a patch</a>.</p>

      </section>
      
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Caniwebview.com – Like Caniuse but for Webviews (178 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://caniwebview.com/</link>
            <guid>40284147</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 10:54:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://caniwebview.com/">https://caniwebview.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40284147">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
		
		<p>
			Launched and maintained by <a href="https://github.com/WebView-CG">W3C WebView Community Group</a>.
		</p>
		<p>
			Site design and code is based on <a href="https://www.caniemail.com/">caniemail.com</a> by <a href="https://mastodon.social/@HTeuMeuLeu">@HTeuMeuLeu</a> and the team at <a href="https://www.tilt-studio.fr/">Tilt Studio</a>.<br>
			That based their's from <a href="https://www.caniuse.com/">caniuse.com</a> by <a href="https://front-end.social/@Fyrd">@Fyrd</a> and designed by <a href="https://mastodon.world/@lensco">@Lensco</a>.<br>
			Also based on the original name and idea by <a href="https://mastodon.social/@M_J_Robbins">@M_J_Robbins</a>
			and the team at <a href="https://www.gorebel.com/">Rebel</a>.<br>
		</p>
		<p>
			Support data contributions by the <a href="https://www.w3.org/community/webview/">WebView Community
				Group</a>.
		</p>
		<p>
			If you see something wrong, please <a href="https://github.com/WebView-CG/Compatibility-Data-Project/issues">report bugs on
				GitHub</a>.
		</p>
	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Novel attack against virtually all VPN apps neuters their entire purpose (139 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/security/2024/05/novel-attack-against-virtually-all-vpn-apps-neuters-their-entire-purpose/</link>
            <guid>40284111</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 10:47:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/security/2024/05/novel-attack-against-virtually-all-vpn-apps-neuters-their-entire-purpose/">https://arstechnica.com/security/2024/05/novel-attack-against-virtually-all-vpn-apps-neuters-their-entire-purpose/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40284111">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <h4>
      VPN BUSTER    —
</h4>
            
            <h2 itemprop="description">TunnelVision vulnerability has existed since 2002 and may already be known to attackers.</h2>
                    </div><div itemprop="articleBody">
                                    
<figure>
  <img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/vpn-tunnel-800x625.jpg" alt="Novel attack against virtually all VPN apps neuters their entire purpose">
      <figcaption><p>Getty Images</p></figcaption>  </figure>

  




<!-- cache hit 81:single/related:dd31fda08d2692c665d23175c356f19f --><!-- empty -->
<p>Researchers have devised an attack against nearly all virtual private network applications that forces them to send and receive some or all traffic outside of the encrypted tunnel designed to protect it from snooping or tampering.</p>
<p>TunnelVision, as the researchers have named their attack, largely negates the entire purpose and selling point of VPNs, which is to encapsulate incoming and outgoing Internet traffic in an encrypted tunnel and to cloak the user’s IP address. The researchers believe it affects all VPN applications when they’re connected to a hostile network and that there are no ways to prevent such attacks except when the user's VPN runs on Linux or Android. They also said their attack technique may have been possible since 2002 and may already have been discovered and used in the wild since then.</p>
<h2>Reading, dropping, or modifying VPN traffic</h2>
<p>The effect of TunnelVision is “the victim's traffic is now decloaked and being routed through the attacker directly,” a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ajsLmZia6UU">video demonstration</a> explained. “The attacker can read, drop or modify the leaked traffic and the victim maintains their connection to both the VPN and the Internet.”</p>
<figure><p><iframe type="text/html" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ajsLmZia6UU?si=kroidLuk1JIYZpl_?start=0&amp;wmode=transparent" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p><figcaption><p>TunnelVision - CVE-2024-3661 - Decloaking Full and Split Tunnel VPNs - Leviathan Security Group.</p></figcaption></figure>
<p>The attack works by manipulating the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynamic_Host_Configuration_Protocol">DHCP server</a> that allocates IP addresses to devices trying to connect to the local network. A setting known as <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc3442">option 121</a>&nbsp;allows the DHCP server to override default routing rules that send VPN traffic through a local IP address that initiates the encrypted tunnel. By using option 121 to route VPN traffic through the DHCP server, the attack diverts the data to the DHCP server itself. Researchers from Leviathan Security explained:</p>                                            
                                                        
<blockquote><p>Our technique is to run a DHCP server on the same network as a targeted VPN user and to also set our DHCP configuration to use itself as a gateway. When the traffic hits our gateway, we use traffic forwarding rules on the DHCP server to pass traffic through to a legitimate gateway while we snoop on it.</p>
<p>We use DHCP option 121 to set a route on the VPN user’s routing table. The route we set is arbitrary and we can also set multiple routes if needed. By pushing routes that are more specific than a /0 CIDR range that most VPNs use, we can make routing rules that have a higher priority than the routes for the virtual interface the VPN creates. We can set multiple /1 routes to recreate the 0.0.0.0/0 all traffic rule set by most VPNs.</p>
<p>Pushing a route also means that the network traffic will be sent over the same interface as the DHCP server instead of the virtual network interface. This is intended functionality that isn’t clearly stated in the RFC. Therefore, for the routes we push, it is never encrypted by the VPN’s virtual interface but instead transmitted by the network interface that is talking to the DHCP server. As an attacker, we can select which IP addresses go over the tunnel and which addresses go over the network interface talking to our DHCP server.</p>
<figure><a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/TunnelVision_Diagram_DHCP_121_Reroute_Traffic.png" data-height="1891" data-width="1430" alt="A malicious DHCP option 121 route that causes traffic to never be encrypted by the VPN process."><img alt="A malicious DHCP option 121 route that causes traffic to never be encrypted by the VPN process." src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/TunnelVision_Diagram_DHCP_121_Reroute_Traffic-640x846.png" width="640" height="846" srcset="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/TunnelVision_Diagram_DHCP_121_Reroute_Traffic-1280x1693.png 2x"></a><figcaption><p><a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/TunnelVision_Diagram_DHCP_121_Reroute_Traffic.png" data-height="1891" data-width="1430">Enlarge</a> <span>/</span> A malicious DHCP option 121 route that causes traffic to never be encrypted by the VPN process.</p><p>Leviathan Security</p></figcaption></figure>
<p>We now have traffic being transmitted outside the VPN’s encrypted tunnel. This technique can also be used against an already established VPN connection once the VPN user’s host needs to renew a lease from our DHCP server. We can artificially create that scenario by setting a short lease time in the DHCP lease, so the user updates their routing table more frequently. In addition, the VPN control channel is still intact because it already uses the physical interface for its communication. In our testing, the VPN always continued to report as connected, and the kill switch was never engaged to drop our VPN connection.</p></blockquote>
<p>The attack can most effectively be carried out by a person who has administrative control over the network the target is connecting to. In that scenario, the attacker configures the DHCP server to use option 121. It’s also possible for people who can connect to the network as an unprivileged user to perform the attack by setting up their own rogue DHCP server.</p>                                            
                                                        
<p>The attack allows some or all traffic to be routed through the unencrypted tunnel. In either case, the VPN application will report that all data is being sent through the protected connection. Any traffic that’s diverted away from this tunnel will not be encrypted by the VPN and the Internet IP address viewable by the remote user will belong to the network the VPN user is connected to, rather than one designated by the VPN app.</p>
<p>Interestingly, Android is the only operating system that fully immunizes VPN apps from the attack because it doesn't implement option 121. For all other OSes, there are no complete fixes. When apps run on Linux there’s a setting that minimizes the effects, but even then TunnelVision can be used to exploit a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Side-channel_attack">side channel</a> that can be used to de-anonymize destination traffic and perform targeted denial-of-service attacks. Network firewalls can also be configured to deny inbound and outbound traffic to and from the physical interface. This remedy is problematic for two reasons: (1) a VPN user connecting to an untrusted network has no ability to control the firewall and (2) it opens the same side channel present with the Linux mitigation.</p>
<p>The most effective fixes are to run the VPN inside of a virtual machine whose network adapter isn’t in bridged mode or to connect the VPN to the Internet through the Wi-Fi network of a cellular device. The research, from Leviathan Security researchers Lizzie Moratti and Dani Cronce, is available <a href="https://www.leviathansecurity.com/blog/tunnelvision">here</a>.</p>

                                                </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google Fit APIs get shut down in 2025, might break fitness devices (120 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2024/05/google-fit-apis-get-shut-down-in-2025-might-break-fitness-devices/</link>
            <guid>40284091</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 10:42:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2024/05/google-fit-apis-get-shut-down-in-2025-might-break-fitness-devices/">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2024/05/google-fit-apis-get-shut-down-in-2025-might-break-fitness-devices/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40284091">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <header>
            <h4>
      Isn't Health Connect just worse?    —
</h4>
            
            <h2 itemprop="description">Scales, trackers, and other fitness devices that don't get updated will stop syncing</h2>
                    </header>
        <div itemprop="articleBody">
                                    
<figure>
  <img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/23-800x445.jpg" alt="Google Fit seems like it's on the way out.">
      <figcaption><p><a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/23.jpg" data-height="669" data-width="1202">Enlarge</a> <span>/</span> Google Fit seems like it's on the way out.</p><p>Ron Amadeo / Google</p></figcaption>  </figure>

  




<!-- cache miss 51:single/related:d03e7bdb9fb55c2913b9e234b80a5a0d --><!-- empty -->
<p>Google is killing off the Google Fit APIs. The platform originally existed to sync health data from third-party fitness devices to your Google account, but now it's <a href="https://android-developers.googleblog.com/2024/05/evolving-health-on-android-migrating-from-google-fit-apis-to-android-health.html">being killed off</a>. Deprecation of the APIs happened on May 1, and Google has stopped accepting new sign-ups for the API. The official shutdown date is June 30, 2025.</p>
<p>The Google Fit API was launched <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2014/06/google-previews-google-fit-apis-for-sharing-fitness-logging-info/">in 2014</a>, just a few weeks after Apple announced <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2014/06/apple-announces-ios-8-at-wwdc/">Healthkit</a> in iOS 8. The goal of both platforms is to be a central repository for health data from various apps and services. Instead of seeing steps in one app and weight in another, it could all be mushed together into a one-stop-shop for health metrics. Google had a lot of big-name partners at launch, like Nike+, Adidas, Withings, Asus, HTC, Intel, LG, and app makers like Runtastic and RunKeeper.</p>
<p>Fast-forward to 2024, and we get the <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2021/08/a-decade-and-a-half-of-instability-the-history-of-google-messaging-apps/">familiar story</a> of Google being unable to throw its weight behind a single solution. Today, Google has <em>three</em> competing fitness APIs. There is a "<a href="https://developer.android.com/health-and-fitness/guides/health-connect/migrate/comparison-guide">Comparison Guide</a>" on the Android Developer site detailing the differences between the "Health Connect" API, the "Fitbit Web API" and the "Google Fit REST API."</p>
<p>Besides killing off the API, Google Fit in general seems like a dead product. Google's deal to acquire Fitbit <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2021/01/google-closes-the-fitbit-acquisition-pledges-to-not-use-data-for-ads/">closed in 2021</a>, making Fitbit the shiny new fitness brand and bringing with it fitness API No. 2. New Google products like the Pixel Watch and Pixel phones come with the Fitbit app as the built-in fitness solution instead of Google Fit, and the Google Fit app hasn't seen a significant upgrade in a while.</p>
<figure><img alt="Google's Fit API shutdown timeline. " src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/fit-timeline.png" width="960" height="192"><figcaption><p>Google's Fit API shutdown timeline. </p><p>Google</p></figcaption></figure>
<p>Google's new fitness API, Health Connect, has had a "beta" app on the Play Store since 2022 that only works with Android 13, and in Android 14, Health Connect became baked into the OS as an open source framework for storing health data. That Android 14 launch was only seven months ago, and with Android's slow update schedule and even slower developer feature adoption, it's hard to say too much about Health Connect. Google notes that the Play Store version of Health Connect and the Android 14 version of Health Connect are not the same thing (!), and an automatic <a href="https://developer.android.com/health-and-fitness/guides/health-connect/migrate/migrate-from-android-13-to-14">"migration" pop-up screen</a> and <em>device reboot</em> is needed to move to the Android 14 version. Google hasn't said anything about compatibility with versions of Android older than Android 14 (or 13?), so even in 2025, Android's slow update speed means this is going to be an API with low device support.</p>                                            
                                                        
<p>One change pointed out by Google's comparison guide is that while the Fitbit API syncs health data to your Fitbit account (Fitbit accounts are also <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2022/09/google-will-start-assimilating-fitbit-accounts-next-year/">being shut down</a> in 2025), and the Google Fit API syncs health data to your Google account, Health Connect doesn't sync to any cloud provider. The documentation around Health Connect never talks about the cloud at all. From a platform perspective, not having cloud sync makes Health Connect more of a neutral, not-Google-affiliated standard for health data storage. Google also pitches the lack of cloud storage as a privacy feature. And just like how Google and Samsung <a href="https://youtu.be/d14GVcnbTeo?t=263">teamed up</a> for Wear OS (I assume this was a related project) Samsung has agreed to give up on the "<a href="https://developer.android.com/health-and-fitness/guides/health-services/health-platform">Health Platform API</a>" and is a <a href="https://developer.samsung.com/health/health-connect-faq.html">launch partner</a> for Health Connect.</p>
<p>From a user perspective, with no cloud syncing, what happens to my health data if I switch devices or if my phone breaks? Can I ever easily look at my health data in a more capable tablet or web app, or will that not work? For now, all talk of "sharing" is limited to local apps or devices that directly sync to your phone, like a smartwatch. The Fitbit app can show third-party <a href="https://blog.google/products/android/new-android-features-february-2024/">Health Connect</a> data right now, but it's unclear if it will sync third-party data to the cloud. Google notes that "Our Android Health API offerings have moved to an on-device model, so there will not be an alternative to the Fit REST API." (A <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/REST">REST API</a>, by definition, is over the Internet.)</p>
<p>The company's <a href="https://developer.android.com/health-and-fitness/guides/health-connect/migrate/migration-guide">migration guide</a> notes that the Google Fit and Health Connect APIs aren't compatible, and for now Google recommends supporting both while users and manufacturers transition from one API to the other. The guide also flatly says, "We don't recommend migrating to Health Connect if you're an existing Google Fitbit Web API developer," and then offers no alternative, so it sounds like the goal is siloed on-device data only, and any devices that use the web APIs will stop syncing in 2025.</p>
<p>By the way, despite being the same age, Apple's Healthkit ecosystem<em> isn't</em> being shut down and will continue running. While Google starts over, Healthkit will continue growing its ecosystem and its already significant lead, and Apple will continue to build user and developer trust.</p>

                                                </div>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[GCC 14.1 (124 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://gcc.gnu.org/gcc-14/</link>
            <guid>40283139</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 07:07:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://gcc.gnu.org/gcc-14/">https://gcc.gnu.org/gcc-14/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40283139">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">






<p>May 7, 2024</p>

<p>The GCC developers are pleased to announce the release of GCC 14.1.</p>

<p>This release is a major release, containing new features (as well
as many other improvements) relative to GCC 13.x.</p>

<h2>Release History</h2>

<dl>

<dt>GCC 14.1</dt>
<dd>May 7, 2024
    (<a href="https://gcc.gnu.org/gcc-14/changes.html">changes</a>,
     <a href="http://gcc.gnu.org/onlinedocs/14.1.0/">documentation</a>)
</dd>

</dl>

<h2>References and Acknowledgements</h2>

<p>GCC used to stand for the GNU C Compiler, but since the compiler
supports several other languages aside from C, it now stands for the
GNU Compiler Collection.</p>

<p>The GCC developers would like to thank the numerous people that have
contributed new features, improvements, bug fixes, and other changes as
well as test results to GCC.
This <a href="http://gcc.gnu.org/onlinedocs/gcc-14.1.0/gcc/Contributors.html">amazing
group of volunteers</a> is what makes GCC successful.</p>

<p>For additional information about GCC please refer to the
<a href="https://gcc.gnu.org/index.html">GCC project web site</a> or contact the
<a href="mailto:gcc@gcc.gnu.org">GCC development mailing list</a>.</p>

<p>To obtain GCC please use <a href="https://gcc.gnu.org/mirrors.html">our mirror sites</a>
or <a href="https://gcc.gnu.org/git.html">our version control system</a>.</p>




<!-- ==================================================================== -->



<!-- ==================================================================== -->



</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[We've been put in the vibe space (135 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://vickiboykis.com/2024/05/06/weve-been-put-in-the-vibe-space/</link>
            <guid>40282856</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 06:10:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://vickiboykis.com/2024/05/06/weve-been-put-in-the-vibe-space/">https://vickiboykis.com/2024/05/06/weve-been-put-in-the-vibe-space/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40282856">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><a href="https://twitter.com/corychainsman/status/1786574177333334431">Jakob’s Law of UX</a> goes something <a href="https://lawsofux.com/jakobs-law/">like this</a>. I, as a user online, spend my time on many sites. As such, when I come to your site, I am already used to the way the other sites work, and I don’t want to learn new paradigms. <a href="https://twitter.com/vboykis/status/1786557956617601486">Some also call these preconceived notions</a> user mental models or affordances.</p><p>I like to call it the user-site contract.</p><p>For years, we have been conditioned to navigate sites along several axes as content consumers: along search and recommendations, and along ecommerce and social.</p><figure><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/veekaybee/veekaybee.github.io/main/static/images/vibespace1.png" width="400"></figure><p>Each of these four quadrants has their particular nuances, but we primarily understand what each is for.</p><p>On ecommerce search, we are conditioned to enter keywords stripped of context like monosyllabic cavepeople until we get what we want: “adidas sneakers white size 6 small.” Here, we are squarely in the goal space, and we are conducting mostly keyword search.</p><p>When we go to Twitter/Bluesky/Instagram/Discord/<a href="https://twitter.com/ThatSamWinkler/status/1591990980387147777">OpenTwang</a> and we are served channel or post or image recommendations, we recognize that we are in the vibe space and can only influence these through our explicit and implicit behavior on a given site, which goes to some <a href="https://vickiboykis.com/what_are_embeddings/">great matrix factorization in the sky</a> and pulls out recommended items into a stream, or a timeline, or a carousel. We do this all publicly with the expectation that all our data is harvested and reintegrated into <a href="https://github.com/igorbrigadir/awesome-twitter-algo">The Algorithm</a>.</p><figure><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/veekaybee/veekaybee.github.io/main/static/images/flutter.png" width="400"></figure><p>On social-type searches like Google, results are mixed because we perform hybrid search, a combination of <a href="https://opensearch.org/blog/semantic-search-solutions/">keyword and semantic search</a> that moves us closer to the vibe space: sometimes we want to search for “what minivan to buy”, sometimes “restaurants with mexican food and good music near me”, sometimes “tell me more about transformer models.”</p><p>On ecommerce recommendations, we are presented with items based on our browsing history, such as in our Instagram reels feeds, but we have no control over what those items are, other than we spent <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dwell_time">10 seconds dwelling</a> on a <a href="https://creators.instagram.com/blog/instagram-recommendations-eligibility-tips-creators?locale=en_US">video of people drinking Chianti</a> and get an ad for tickets to Rome.</p><figure><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/veekaybee/veekaybee.github.io/main/static/images/vibespace2.png" width="400"></figure><p>For a long time, these four quadrants have been pretty distinct, because search and recommendations, while they occupy opposite ends of the same spectrum conceptually, have different tooling and architectures, and machine learning goals. You can even tell the way org structure of companies who hire for the teams have developed: usually there are distinct search and recommendations teams.</p><p>What happens in today’s world, when we have LLMs? We now have the collision of three different sets of user expectations.</p><ol><li><p>First, we expect all LLM experiences to be like ChatGPT, because ChatGPT was the first LLM product to truly hit the market in a customer-facing way, and all products are in some way modeled on it. This cascades down even to the API, where many backend API products (VLLM, Ray, Llamafile), even if they don’t use the OpenAI API, are compliant with it; both the UX and dev-ex have become industry standard. The ChatGPT user experience is an open textbox that will allow you to get an answer about anything in freeform. We expect to be able to interact with this in natural language.</p></li><li><p>Second, we have our old expectation that <a href="https://vickiboykis.com/2024/04/25/how-i-search-in-2024/">search boxes are open-ended</a>, but bounded by how we search: by keyword or short phrases, and that we will iterate on those short phrases to get what we need.</p></li><li><p>Third, we have our expectation that unclear results or results generated from semantic similarity or work in the latent space will be served to us as recommendations and tagged as such.</p></li></ol><p>All of these are a clash of expectations that now need to be managed carefully, especially because, as I found in <a href="https://vickiboykis.com/2024/01/05/retro-on-viberary/">building semantic search products</a>, it’s hard to guide customer intent in an open-ended solution space (i.e. what does it mean to search for a “vibe?”)</p><p>What then to make of Meta’s latest decision to put Llama3, <a href="https://about.fb.com/news/2024/04/meta-ai-assistant-built-with-llama-3/">a generative open-ended autoregressive model that can generate open-ended content</a>, into every search bar in all of their platform properties?</p><figure><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/veekaybee/veekaybee.github.io/main/static/images/llamabar.png" width="400"></figure><p>These are four very hard design principles to square, because now, with open-ended models, we end up migrating all our use-cases to the center space.</p><figure><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/veekaybee/veekaybee.github.io/main/static/images/vibespace3.png" width="400"></figure><p>Even when we open up Instagram search to perform a directed search, we’re greeted with The AI Box, which asks us to learn about K-pop.</p><figure><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/veekaybee/veekaybee.github.io/main/static/images/llamabar2.png" width="400"></figure><p>But I don’t want to ask Meta AI about the best history podcasts or ask about k-pop, I want to find the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JBMLHFSZlEg">video of the trained raven I saw a couple weeks ago.</a> I want to perform social keyword search. And on Whatsapp, I want to talk to people on Whatsapp directly, without a chatbot in the middle.</p><p>I want to be in my four quadrants. And, because I’ve been conditioned by 15 years of past internet history to be in those quadrants, I’m annoyed by being pushed to the middle everywhere across all interfaces.</p><p>This is going to be a frustrating time for consumers until we get specific LLM use-cases sorted out and made less general. Interestingly enough, <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/unsexy-future-generative-ai-enterprise-apps/">this is already happening to some extent in the enterprise space</a>. It will be interesting to see what happens for us end-users and the contract. Until then, see you in the middle at the ✨.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google, Meta 'break' Apple's device fingerprinting rules (103 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theregister.com/2024/05/07/apple_fingerprinting_rules/</link>
            <guid>40281588</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 02:11:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/05/07/apple_fingerprinting_rules/">https://www.theregister.com/2024/05/07/apple_fingerprinting_rules/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40281588">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="body">
<p>Last week, Apple began requiring iOS developers justify the use of a specific set of APIs that could be used for device fingerprinting. Yet the iGiant doesn't appear to be making much effort to ensure that Google, Meta, and Spotify comply with the rules, it's claimed.</p>
<p>Device fingerprinting involves collecting information about various device settings and components, then combining those into a single identifier that's likely to be unique and thus useful for targeting people with ads and other stuff tailored to their individual interests and circumstances.</p>
<p>There are other forms of fingerprinting involving browser settings, the HTML Canvas element, WebGL, fonts, and so on, some of which have legitimate commercial applications, such as bot detection. But digital fingerprinting can also be used to violate privacy and track people online.</p>
<blockquote>

<p>We found out that apps such as Google Chrome, Instagram, Spotify, and Threads don’t adhere to their declared reasons</p>
</blockquote>
<p>While Apple allows user tracking if permission has been granted, it mostly <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2023/10060/?time=457">forbids</a> device-level fingerprinting on iOS, at least in theory. It made that policy official in a recent <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://developer.apple.com/support/third-party-SDK-requirements/">blog post</a>.</p>
<p>As such the iBiz now requires app developers to supply among other things reasons for using any of its designated "required reason APIs" that can be used for device fingerprinting.</p>

    

<p>Crucially, data collected from these interfaces, which could be used for fingerprinting, must stay on the user's device to maximize privacy.</p>

        


        

<p>The iPhone maker explains as much in its developer documentation. "Some APIs that your app uses to deliver its core functionality — in code you write or included in a third-party SDK — have the potential of being misused to access device signals to try to identify the device or user, also known as fingerprinting," the Apple's developer website <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/bundleresources/privacy_manifest_files/describing_use_of_required_reason_api">states</a>. "Regardless of whether a user gives your app permission to track, fingerprinting is not allowed."</p>
<p>Examples of these fingerprint-friendly APIs include: File timestamp APIs, System boot time APIs, Disk space APIs, Active keyboard APIs, and User defaults APIs.</p>

        

<p>As of May 1, 2024, apps that fail to include reasons for using these APIs in their privacy manifest file won't be accepted in the iOS App Store. Previously, Apple just sent non-compliant developers an email warning.</p>
<p>According to developers Talal Haj Bakry and Tommy Mysk, several major app makers are simply ignoring Apple's requirements, and using tracker-happy APIs without sticking to the rules. Big Tech players like Google, Meta, and Spotify - the duo claim - are providing reasons for this API usage, collecting that data, and then not abiding by the requirement to keep that information on the device.</p>
<p>In other words, Google, Meta, and Spotify are all collecting at least some info from these APIs and then sending that data off-device against Apple's rules, we're told.</p>

        

<p>"To prevent misuse of these APIs, Apple will reject apps that don’t describe their use of the APIs in their privacy manifest file," the pair explain in an <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.mysk.blog/2024/05/03/apple-required-reason-api/">advisory</a>. "However, we found out that apps such as Google Chrome, Instagram, Spotify, and Threads don’t adhere to their declared reasons."</p>
<ul>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/07/29/apple_developer_api/">Apple demands app makers explain use of sensitive APIs</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/10/06/link_tracking_privacy/">Online tracking is alive and well in link decoration</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2022/04/08/apple_ios_privacy/">Apple iOS privacy clampdown 'did little' to reduce tracking</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2021/09/30/apple_google_privacy/">What do iOS and Android have in common? Their apps suck at privacy, boffins say</a></li>
</ul>
<p><em>The Register</em> asked Google, Meta, and Spotify whether they are in fact using these "required reason APIs" for iOS device fingerprinting and beaming that data off to backend servers, and we've not heard back from the last two. A Google spokesperson confirmed it is looking into the report, but didn't immediately have a response.</p>
<p>"It's hard to tell if the apps are using the information for fingerprinting or not," said Mysk in a message to <em>The Register</em>. "But Apple already classified a set of APIs that can potentially be used for fingerprinting. Apps accessing such APIs must declare the reasons why they need such access."</p>
<p>Apple has published a <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/bundleresources/privacy_manifest_files/describing_use_of_required_reason_api">list of valid reasons</a> for using certain APIs that reveal information useful for fingerprinting. For example, iOS provides an API called <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/foundation/processinfo/1414553-systemuptime">systemUptime</a> that can be queried to provide the time elapsed since the device was last restarted.</p>
<p>Developers who want to use this API can select from several allowed reasons, one which must be declared in a manifest file. Google for example has chosen 35F9.1, with italics added by us for emphasis:</p>

<p>Although Apple's rule plainly states that uptime data cannot be sent off-device, Google Chrome appears to be doing just that, based on network data analysis from Bakry and Mysk. The rule does allow for an exception, but one that doesn't apply to Chrome.</p>
<p>"No, this exception is about using the system uptime on-device locally to order events for example," Mysk told <em>The Register</em>, explaining that Google has the option to transmit relative time intervals between two events but not the absolute device uptime number.</p>
<p>Mysk argues that Apple's "required reason APIs," like its Privacy Nutrition Labels, amount to privacy theater because there appears to be no enforcement.</p>
<p>"Just like the Privacy Nutrition Labels, developers are free to enter what they please," said Mysk.</p>
<p>"Apple doesn't seem to review if the description is accurate or not. While the nutrition labels are visible to the users, the required reason API isn't. So, it is not clear how that is going to prevent fingerprinting and enhance user privacy if Apple doesn't check the reasons developers submit."</p>
<p>Cupertino did not respond to a request for comment. ®</p>                                
                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[New black hole visualization takes viewers beyond the brink (126 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://phys.org/news/2024-05-black-hole-visualization-viewers-brink.html</link>
            <guid>40281340</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 01:32:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://phys.org/news/2024-05-black-hole-visualization-viewers-brink.html">https://phys.org/news/2024-05-black-hole-visualization-viewers-brink.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40281340">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
										
<div data-thumb="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2024/new-nasa-black-hole-vi.jpg" data-src="https://scx2.b-cdn.net/gfx/news/2024/new-nasa-black-hole-vi.jpg" data-sub-html="Credit: NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center/J. Schnittman and B. Powell">
        <figure>
            <img src="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/800a/2024/new-nasa-black-hole-vi.jpg" alt="New NASA Black Hole Visualization Takes Viewers Beyond the Brink" title="Credit: NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center/J. Schnittman and B. Powell" width="800" height="301">
             <figcaption>
                Credit: NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center/J. Schnittman and B. Powell
            </figcaption>        </figure>
    </div><p>Ever wonder what happens when you fall into a black hole? Now, thanks to a new, immersive visualization produced on a NASA supercomputer, viewers can plunge into the event horizon, a black hole's point of no return.</p>


										      
																																	<p>"People often ask about this, and simulating these difficult-to-imagine processes helps me connect the mathematics of relativity to actual consequences in the real universe," said Jeremy Schnittman, an astrophysicist at NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center in Greenbelt, Maryland, who created the visualizations. "So I simulated two different scenarios, one where a camera—a stand-in for a daring astronaut—just misses the event horizon and slingshots back out, and one where it crosses the boundary, sealing its fate."</p>
<p>The visualizations are available in multiple forms. Explainer videos act as sightseeing guides, illuminating the bizarre effects of Einstein's general theory of relativity. Versions rendered as 360-degree videos let viewers look all around during the trip, while others play as flat all-sky maps.</p>
<p>To create the visualizations, Schnittman teamed up with fellow Goddard scientist Brian Powell and used the Discover supercomputer at the NASA Center for Climate Simulation. The project generated about 10 terabytes of data—equivalent to roughly half of the estimated text content in the Library of Congress—and took about 5 days running on just 0.3% of Discover's 129,000 processors. The same feat would take more than a decade on a typical laptop.</p>
<p>The destination is a <a href="https://phys.org/tags/supermassive+black+hole/" rel="tag">supermassive black hole</a> with 4.3 million times the mass of our sun, equivalent to the monster located at the center of our Milky Way galaxy.</p>

<figure itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/VideoObject">
    <meta itemprop="name" content="New NASA Black Hole Visualization Takes Viewers Beyond the Brink">
    <meta itemprop="url" content="https://www.youtube.com/watch/?v=chhcwk4-esM">
    <meta itemprop="description" content="In this visualization of a flight toward a supermassive black hole, labels highlight many of the fascinating features produced by the effects of general relativity along the way. Produced on a NASA supercomputer, the simulation tracks a camera as it approaches, briefly orbits, and then crosses the event horizon—the point of no return—of a monster black hole much like the one at the center of our galaxy. Credit: NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center/J. Schnittman and B. Powell">
    <meta itemprop="uploadDate" content="2024-05-06T15:03:07-04:00">    
        <meta itemprop="embedUrl" content="https://www.youtube.com/embed/chhcwk4-esM">
    <meta itemprop="thumbnailUrl" content="https://img.youtube.com/vi/chhcwk4-esM/maxresdefault.jpg">
         <p>
             <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/chhcwk4-esM?color=white" loading="lazy" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
         </p>
        <figcaption itemprop="caption">In this visualization of a flight toward a supermassive black hole, labels highlight many of the fascinating features produced by the effects of general relativity along the way. Produced on a NASA supercomputer, the simulation tracks a camera as it approaches, briefly orbits, and then crosses the event horizon—the point of no return—of a monster black hole much like the one at the center of our galaxy. Credit: NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center/J. Schnittman and B. Powell</figcaption>  
</figure><p>"If you have the choice, you want to fall into a supermassive black hole," Schnittman explained. "Stellar-mass black holes, which contain up to about 30 <a href="https://phys.org/tags/solar+masses/" rel="tag">solar masses</a>, possess much smaller event horizons and stronger tidal forces, which can rip apart approaching objects before they get to the horizon."</p>

																																						
																																			<p>This occurs because the <a href="https://phys.org/tags/gravitational+pull/" rel="tag">gravitational pull</a> on the end of an object nearer the black hole is much stronger than that on the other end. Infalling objects stretch out like noodles, a process astrophysicists call spaghettification.</p>
<p>The simulated black hole's event horizon spans about 16 million miles (25 million kilometers), or about 17% of the distance from Earth to the sun. A flat, swirling cloud of hot, glowing gas called an accretion disk surrounds it and serves as a visual reference during the fall. So do glowing structures called photon rings, which form closer to the black hole from light that has orbited it one or more times. A backdrop of the starry sky as seen from Earth completes the scene.</p>
<p>As the camera approaches the black hole, reaching speeds ever closer to that of light itself, the glow from the <a href="https://phys.org/tags/accretion+disk/" rel="tag">accretion disk</a> and background stars becomes amplified in much the same way as the sound of an oncoming race car rises in pitch. Their light appears brighter and whiter when looking into the direction of travel.</p>
<p>The movies begin with the camera located nearly 400 million miles (640 million kilometers) away, with the black hole quickly filling the view. Along the way, the black hole's disk, photon rings, and the night sky become increasingly distorted—and even form multiple images as their light traverses the increasingly warped <a href="https://phys.org/tags/space-time/" rel="tag">space-time</a>.</p>

<figure itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/VideoObject">
    <meta itemprop="name" content="New NASA Black Hole Visualization Takes Viewers Beyond the Brink">
    <meta itemprop="url" content="https://www.youtube.com/watch/?v=dGEIsnBRWGs">
    <meta itemprop="description" content="Tour an alternative visualization that tracks a camera as it approaches, falls toward, briefly orbits, and escapes a supermassive black hole. This immersive 360-degree version allows viewers to look around during the flight. Credit: NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center/J. Schnittman and B. Powell">
    <meta itemprop="uploadDate" content="2024-05-06T15:03:55-04:00">    
        <meta itemprop="embedUrl" content="https://www.youtube.com/embed/dGEIsnBRWGs">
    <meta itemprop="thumbnailUrl" content="https://img.youtube.com/vi/dGEIsnBRWGs/maxresdefault.jpg">
         <p>
             <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/dGEIsnBRWGs?color=white" loading="lazy" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
         </p>
        <figcaption itemprop="caption">Tour an alternative visualization that tracks a camera as it approaches, falls toward, briefly orbits, and escapes a supermassive black hole. This immersive 360-degree version allows viewers to look around during the flight. Credit: NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center/J. Schnittman and B. Powell</figcaption>  
</figure><p>In real time, the camera takes about 3 hours to fall to the event horizon, executing almost two complete 30-minute orbits along the way. But to anyone observing from afar, it would never quite get there. As space-time becomes ever more distorted closer to the horizon, the image of the camera would slow and then seem to freeze just shy of it. This is why astronomers originally referred to black holes as "frozen stars."</p>

																																			<p>At the event horizon, even space-time itself flows inward at the speed of light, the cosmic speed limit. Once inside it, both the camera and the space-time in which it's moving rush toward the black hole's center—a one-dimensional point called a singularity, where the laws of physics as we know them cease to operate.</p>
<p>"Once the camera crosses the horizon, its destruction by spaghettification is just 12.8 seconds away," Schnittman said. From there, it's only 79,500 miles (128,000 kilometers) to the singularity. This final leg of the voyage is over in the blink of an eye.</p>
<p>In the alternative scenario, the camera orbits close to the <a href="https://phys.org/tags/event+horizon/" rel="tag">event horizon</a> but it never crosses over and escapes to safety. If an astronaut flew a spacecraft on this 6-hour round trip while her colleagues on a mothership remained far from the black hole, she'd return 36 minutes younger than her colleagues. That's because time passes more slowly near a strong gravitational source and when moving near the speed of light.</p>
<p>"This situation can be even more extreme," Schnittman noted. "If the black hole were rapidly rotating, like the one shown in the 2014 movie 'Interstellar,' she would return many years younger than her shipmates."</p>

																																																					
																					
																					
                              										                                        
										<!-- print only -->
										<div>
											 <p><strong>Citation</strong>:
												New black hole visualization takes viewers beyond the brink (2024, May 6)
												retrieved 7 May 2024
												from https://phys.org/news/2024-05-black-hole-visualization-viewers-brink.html
											 </p>
											 <p>
											 This document is subject to copyright. Apart from any fair dealing for the purpose of private study or research, no
											 part may be reproduced without the written permission. The content is provided for information purposes only.
											 </p>
										</div>
                                        
									</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Vets fret as private equity snaps up clinics, pet care companies (230 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://stateline.org/2024/03/29/vets-fret-as-private-equity-snaps-up-clinics-pet-care-companies/</link>
            <guid>40281274</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 01:18:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://stateline.org/2024/03/29/vets-fret-as-private-equity-snaps-up-clinics-pet-care-companies/">https://stateline.org/2024/03/29/vets-fret-as-private-equity-snaps-up-clinics-pet-care-companies/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40281274">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="dataContent">
                                    <p>HUNTSVILLE, Ala. — About a year ago, veterinarian Melissa Ezell started noticing subtle changes at the midsized animal clinic in Huntsville, Alabama, where she works.</p>
	
	
<p>She said she and other vets were feeling pressure from management to make a certain amount of money from every appointment. If a pet owner wasn’t going to spend enough, the message from management was to offer more services. She was urged to pack in more patients outside of normal business hours.</p>
<p>“Before, I never felt any pressure to be making a certain amount of money in a day,” Ezell, who started working at the clinic in 2021, told Stateline. “It was just, ‘Fill your schedule, practice good medicine, everything else will come.’”</p>
<p>The clinic is owned by National Veterinary Associates, one of the largest veterinary chains in the nation. In 2020 the company was acquired by JAB Consumer Partners, a global private equity firm based in Luxembourg. By early 2023, Ezell said, she felt a shift in atmosphere at the clinic and a greater focus on increasing profits.</p>
<p>Private equity’s foray into the human health care industry in recent years has <a target="_blank" href="https://stateline.org/2024/01/18/shell-game-when-private-equity-comes-to-town-hospitals-can-see-cutbacks-closures/">drawn public outrage and legislative scrutiny</a> as firms have been blamed for increasing prices, slashing services and shuttering hospitals to maximize shareholder profits.</p>
<p>Now, some veterinarians and advocates are sounding the alarm that private equity’s entry into the pet health care industry could lead to similar results.</p>
<p>Some states already have laws that prohibit non-veterinarians from owning veterinary practices, and some consumer advocates want states to review large-scale acquisitions in the industry.</p>
<p>“A large number of these funds are seeing veterinary medicine as a good profit center,” said Dr. Grant Jacobson, an Iowa veterinarian who serves on the board of the Independent Veterinary Practitioners Association. He said he’s seen corporate-owned chains in his region drive up prices for consumers, suppress market competition and skirt state laws that ostensibly prohibit veterinary practices from being owned by non-veterinarians.</p>
<p>Private equity firms such as Shore Capital Partners, KKR, TSG Consumer and JAB Consumer Partners have spent billions over the past few years on veterinary practices, specialty animal hospitals, pet insurance services and pet food companies. Among the companies owned by private equity are PetSmart, PetVet Care Centers, FIGO, Thrive Pet Healthcare and ASPCA Pet Health Insurance.</p>
<p>Private equity firms say those investments are giving clinics and other providers the capital they need to buy better technology, and that they are improving efficiency. And in many cases, corporate chains can offer their employees better workplace benefits, such as health insurance.</p>
<p>In a statement to Stateline, National Veterinary Associates said its corporate philosophy is “grounded in vets making medical decisions and not a corporate office,” and that its program of shared ownership by veterinarians is “the industry’s largest such program and unique among our peers.”</p>
<p>“Our vision is to build a community of hospitals that pet owners trust, are easy to access, and provide the best possible care,” National Veterinary Associates said in the statement.</p>
<p>JAB Consumer Partners did not respond to Stateline’s request for comment.</p>
    <h4>More pets, more money</h4>

	
<p>Private equity uses pooled investment money from pension funds, endowments and wealthy individuals to buy controlling stakes in companies. The firms typically look for a quick return on their investment before selling it within a few years. They have been gobbling up small businesses in myriad industries in recent years — from <a target="_blank" href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2023/12/24/nursing-homes-private-equity-fraud-00132001">nursing homes</a> to <a target="_blank" href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/private-equity-wants-to-wash-your-car-11660968031">car washes</a>.</p>
<blockquote data-secret="lzVYrrJo9E"><p><a target="_blank" href="https://stateline.org/2024/01/18/shell-game-when-private-equity-comes-to-town-hospitals-can-see-cutbacks-closures/">‘Shell game’: When private equity comes to town, hospitals can see cutbacks, closures</a></p></blockquote>

<p>As <a target="_blank" href="https://www.avma.org/resources-tools/reports-statistics/us-pet-ownership-statistics">pet ownership soared</a> during the COVID-19 pandemic, private equity followed close behind. The pandemic years of 2020-2022 were “the peak years for private equity acquisitions of veterinary services and practices,” said Michael Fenne, senior coordinator for health care at the Private Equity Stakeholder Project, a nonprofit watchdog group that advocates for communities affected by private equity ownership.</p>
<p>Americans spent a record $147 billion on pet products and services last year. From 2017 to 2022, <a target="_blank" href="https://pitchbook.com/news/articles/pe-deals-veterinary-clinics-pet-care">private equity spent $45 billion</a> on deals in the veterinary sector, according to PitchBook, which tracks investment data.</p>
<p>The vet industry is attractive because it’s mostly made up of small, privately owned businesses that corporations can buy and consolidate into larger chains. And it’s mainly a cash-based business: Unlike in human health care, veterinary customers typically pay out of pocket, rather than rely on third-party payers such as insurance companies.</p>
<p>In some cases, private equity firms and other corporations buy community clinics from the veterinarians who own them for two, five or even 10 times their value. Then the firms roll them up into a larger chain of clinics that can corner a regional market.</p>
<p>It’s a strategy that can push other private owners out of the business, said Jacobson, the Iowa veterinarian. He spent nearly 20 years working at a privately owned practice in Iowa and had hoped to buy it when the original founder retired.</p>
<p>But the founder sold the practice to a large veterinary chain owned by Mars Inc. — the private company best known for owning candy brands that include M&amp;Ms — for more than $1 million above his offer, Jacobson said. Mars, while not a private equity firm, is the biggest consolidator of pet care companies in the United States, owning pet food companies, pet pharmacies and veterinary care clinic chains such as Banfield Pet Hospitals and BluePearl.</p>

<div>
	
	<p>You feel like you don’t have the time with the doctor, and you leave not fully understanding what was done to your pet or what is wrong with your pet if they’re sick.</p>
		<p><b>– Melissa Ezell, veterinarian</b></p>
	</div>

	
<p>About a quarter of general veterinary practices and about three-quarters of specialty practices, such as emergency and surgery care, are now owned by large corporations, according to John Volk of Brakke Consulting, a veterinary management consulting firm.</p>
<p>Some private equity-backed chains, such as National Veterinary Associates, buy community-based veterinary practices like Ezell’s without rebranding them under the chain’s name. As a result, clients might not be aware of the ownership change.</p>
<p>“It can appear you’re getting community-oriented care when there’s actually this set of big-box incentives underlying [the clinic] that comes from their private equity owners,” Fenne said.</p>
    <h4>Where vets want to work</h4>

	
<p>Lori Kogan, a clinical sciences professor at Colorado State University’s College of Veterinary Medicine and Biomedical Sciences, surveyed nearly 900 veterinarians in 2022 about their experiences and perceptions of <a target="_blank" href="https://avmajournals.avma.org/view/journals/javma/261/12/javma.23.06.0326.xml">corporate vs. privately owned veterinary clinics</a>.</p>
<blockquote data-secret="0DBBSnGFD1"><p><a target="_blank" href="https://stateline.org/2024/01/31/private-equitys-growing-footprint-in-home-health-care-draws-scrutiny/">Private equity’s growing footprint in home health care draws scrutiny</a></p></blockquote>

<p>Even though most of the veterinarians surveyed reported working for corporate-owned clinics, Kogan found more than half said they would prefer to work in privately owned clinics. The benefits offered by corporate chains, such as health insurance, didn’t seem strong enough to override other preferences, Kogan told Stateline.</p>
<p>“Feeling like they have a voice in decision-making, feeling like they’re recognized as an individual, those are things that are really important to people,” she said. “I think corporate ownership could accomplish those things, but it will take paying attention.”</p>
<p>Ezell, the veterinarian who left National Veterinary Associates, said the pressure has an impact on patients and their humans as well.</p>
<p>“Either you’re getting talked into additional services that may or may not actually be necessary, or your feel like you’re being rushed,” Ezell said. “You feel like you don’t have the time with the doctor, and you leave not fully understanding what was done to your pet or what is wrong with your pet if they’re sick.”</p>
<p>In its statement to Stateline, National Veterinary Associates noted that it has made “continued investment in technology and infrastructure, pioneering clinical research, industry-leading continuing education programs and wellbeing initiatives.”</p>
    <h4>Could states step in?</h4>

	
<p>Last August, Thrive Pet Healthcare announced it would be closing the only 24-hour emergency veterinary clinic in the Rochester, New York, metro area. Thrive is a chain of&nbsp;more than 380 veterinary hospitals&nbsp;based in Austin, Texas, that is owned by private equity firm TSG Consumer.</p>
<p>“The thought of having the only 24-hour emergency pet care center in our entire metro area close was really scary,” said Rachel Barnhart, a Democratic member of the Monroe County Legislature in New York who has taken her dogs to the clinic. “We are a community of more than a million people. The idea that we can’t support a 24-hour pet facility is outrageous.”</p>
<p>Barnhart wrote a letter to the Federal Trade Commission, asking it to look into Thrive, which operates more than a dozen clinics in Rochester. She said she’d seen the FTC act against anticompetitive practices in the veterinary industry elsewhere, and she felt Thrive deserved similar scrutiny.</p>
<p>Thrive leadership&nbsp;said in a letter to Barnhart and in media reports that a shortage of ER veterinarians made it impossible to hire enough workers to keep the 24-hour clinic open. But Barnhart suspected the company wanted to shutter the clinic because its staff&nbsp;<a target="_blank" href="https://www.whec.com/archive/vses-first-veterinary-practice-on-east-coast-to-unionize/">recently voted to unionize.</a> CEO Tad Stahel said in the letter to Barnhart that the closure was unrelated to the staff unionization.</p>
<blockquote data-secret="3HcbVh4fzw"><p><a target="_blank" href="https://stateline.org/2022/09/02/should-you-insure-your-pet-without-state-oversight-its-hard-to-say/">Should You Insure Your Pet? Without State Oversight, It’s Hard to Say.</a></p></blockquote>

<p>In 2022, the FTC took action against JAB Consumer Partners, which recently acquired an array of veterinary and pet service companies. The FTC required the firm to divest some of its vet clinics in California, Colorado, Texas, Virginia and Washington, D.C., as a condition of approving its multibillion-dollar purchases of two other multistate veterinary care chains.</p>
<p>If states were to authorize officials or agencies to review similar large-scale mergers and acquisitions in the veterinary industry, that “would be a good first step” toward protecting consumers, said Fenne, of the advocacy group.</p>
<p>Many states already have laws that prohibit non-veterinarians from owning veterinary practices, including Iowa, Minnesota, New Jersey, New York and North Carolina. The idea is to prevent corporate interests from guiding veterinarians’ medical judgment.</p>
<p>Experts and advocates expect to see further corporatization in veterinary care as more companies acquire not just vet clinics, but also other businesses across the pet care spectrum.</p>
<p>In February, asset management behemoth Blackstone Inc. <a target="_blank" href="https://www.blackstone.com/news/press/blackstone-completes-acquisition-of-rover/">acquired Rover</a>, the nation’s largest online platform for pet sitting, dog walking and other services. In the past two years, JAB has acquired several of the largest pet insurance companies in the United States and Europe.</p>
<p>Ezell, the Alabama veterinarian, eventually decided to take a job at another clinic in town that’s privately owned. She will start there in a few weeks.</p>
<p>“Not all corporate medicine is horrible, and you can find amazing veterinarians and caring support staff anywhere,” she told Stateline.</p>
<p>“But it’s easy to lose sight of your values. The whole reason we’re doing this is we want to make a difference in animals’ and people’s lives. If we’re unable to do that, shouldn’t we try to fix that?”</p>
<div dir="ltr">
<p><i>Editor’</i><i>s note: This story has been updated to correct the number of Thrive veterinary hospitals.</i></p>
</div>
    <a href="https://stateline.org/donate">
    
    </a>
	
                                </div><div>
                                            
                                            <p>Our stories may be republished online or in print under Creative Commons license CC BY-NC-ND 4.0. We ask that you edit only for style or to shorten, provide proper attribution and link to our website. AP and Getty images may not be republished. Please see our <a href="https://stateline.org/republishing-guidelines/" target="_blank">republishing guidelines</a> for use of any other photos and graphics.</p>
                                        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Boeing Starliner's first crewed mission scrubbed (125 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://techcrunch.com/2024/05/06/boeing-starliners-first-crewed-mission-scrubbed/</link>
            <guid>40281272</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 01:18:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/05/06/boeing-starliners-first-crewed-mission-scrubbed/">https://techcrunch.com/2024/05/06/boeing-starliners-first-crewed-mission-scrubbed/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40281272">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
				<p>Boeing’s <a href="https://twitter.com/elonmusk/status/1787531120852312388">Starliner</a> launch tonight has been postponed “out of an abundance of caution” scarcely two hours before the historic liftoff. The scrub is reportedly due to an issue with the oxygen relief valve on the Atlas V rocket’s upper stage.</p>
<p id="speakable-summary">There are backup launch opportunities on May 7, 10 and 11. After years of delays and over $1 billion in cost overruns, the mission is set to be Boeing’s first attempt to transport astronauts to the International Space Station.</p>
<p>Once the issue is resolved with the upper stage, the United Launch Alliance Atlas V will carry the CST-100 Starliner capsule to orbit along with the two onboard astronauts — Butch Wilmore and Sunny Williams — from Florida’s Cape Canaveral at 10:34 PM local time Monday evening. The mission also marks the first time ULA’s Atlas will carry crew. The rocket boasts a success rate of 100% across 99 missions. (ULA is a joint venture of Boeing and Lockheed Martin.)</p>
<p>The astronauts would now dock at the station at the earliest on Thursday, where they would remain for at least eight days. The two astronauts will return to Earth in the capsule no earlier than May 16.</p>
<p>If all goes to plan, Boeing will be able to finally certify its Starliner for human transportation and begin fulfilling the terms of its $4.2 billion NASA astronaut taxi contract. That contract, under the agency’s Commercial Crew Program, was awarded in 2014. Elon Musk’s SpaceX was also granted a contract under that program, for its Crew Dragon capsule, and has been transporting astronauts to and from the ISS since 2020.</p>
<p>While SpaceX has soared in its human transportation services, flying over a dozen crewed missions and also racking up private flights with Axiom Space and billionaire Jared Isaacman, Boeing has fallen sharply behind. The aerospace giant originally attempted an uncrewed mission to the ISS in 2019, though <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2019/12/20/boeings-starliner-crew-capsule-fails-to-enter-planned-target-orbit-for-space-station-docking/">that failed due to technical issues</a>; further problems delayed the next attempt, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/05/25/starliner-returns-to-earth-after-a-successful-first-trip-to-iss/">until it was finally accomplished in 2022.</a></p>
<p>As of last year, Boeing had rung up $1.5 billion in charges due to the long-delayed Starliner program.</p>
<p>But despite the technical snags, both NASA and Boeing have stressed their commitment to the mission, and to the safety of the two astronauts.</p>
<p>“The lives of our crew members,&nbsp;Suni Williams&nbsp;and&nbsp;Butch Wilmore, are at stake,” NASA’s associate administrator Jim Free said in a press conference late last month. “We don’t take that lightly at all.”</p>
<p>Indeed, for NASA a successful mission bring the agency one step closer to having two operational transportation providers, bringing critical redundancy to the Commercial Crew program. Per Boeing’s contract, it is on the line for six astronaut missions.</p>
<p>Musk took to X, the social media platform he also owns, to comment on the mission, noting that “although Boeing got $4.2 billion to develop an astronaut capsule and SpaceX only got $2.6 billion, SpaceX finished 4 years sooner.”</p>
<div>
<blockquote data-width="550" data-dnt="true">
<p lang="en" dir="ltr">Although Boeing got $4.2 billion to develop an astronaut capsule and SpaceX only got $2.6 billion, SpaceX finished 4 years sooner. </p>
<p>Note, the crew capsule design of Dragon 2 has almost nothing in common with Dragon 1. </p>
<p>Too many non-technical managers at Boeing. <a href="https://t.co/bTXWAfxfrh">https://t.co/bTXWAfxfrh</a></p>
<p>— Elon Musk (@elonmusk) <a href="https://twitter.com/elonmusk/status/1787531120852312388?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">May 6, 2024</a></p></blockquote>
</div>
			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How Python asyncio works: recreating it from scratch (209 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://jacobpadilla.com/articles/recreating-asyncio</link>
            <guid>40281139</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:50:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://jacobpadilla.com/articles/recreating-asyncio">https://jacobpadilla.com/articles/recreating-asyncio</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40281139">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main-content">
<!-- 🌟 START OF MAIN CONTENT 🌟 -->
<p>Right now, asyncio is one of the trendier topics in Python, and rightfully so – It’s a great way to handle I/O-bound programs! When I was learning about asyncio, It took me a while to understand how it actually worked. But later, I came to find out that it’s basically just a really nice layer on top of Python Generators. In this article, I’m going to create a simplified version of asyncio using just Python generators. Then, I’m going to refactor the example to use the <code>async</code> and <code>await</code> keywords with the help of the <code>__await__</code> dunder method before coming full circle and swapping out my version for the real asyncio. By building a simple version of asyncio, hopefully, by the end of this article, you’ll be able to get a better grasp of how it does its magic!</p>

<h2 id="generators-review">Generators Review</h2>

    <p>If you're already familiar with generators skip this part, but if you aren't, it's what asyncio is built off of, so it's very important to understand how they work.</p>
    <p>First of all, the reason why generators are a thing is because they allow you to make your code more memory efficient. Imagine if you had the following loop:</p>

    <pre><code>for i in range(100_000_000):
&nbsp; &nbsp; print(i)</code></pre>

    <p>If <code>range</code> wasn't a generator, but rather was a function that returned a list for you to then loop over, code like the example above would be very memory inefficient since you would be creating a list with 100 million elements… However, because <code>range</code> is a generator, at least in Python 3+, you only generate the numbers as they are needed, one by one, without ever storing the entire sequence in memory.</p>
    <p>There are a few ways to create generators, but we're going to focus on generator functions. These generators are defined like any other function but use the <code>yield</code> statement to return data. This statement turns a regular function into a generator that, instead of executing all at once, can pause and resume its state when calling <code>next(iterator)</code>.</p>
    <p>Take the following generator function, for example:</p>

    <pre><code>def generator():
&nbsp; &nbsp;yield 'hello'
&nbsp; &nbsp;yield 'world'

iterator = generator()</code></pre>

    <p>When you call the generator, instead of running the code inside of the function like Python normally would, it sees the <code>yield</code> keyword and, therefore, returns a generator object. Once we have the generator object, we can then call <code>next(iterator)</code>, which will run the function’s code up until the first/next <code>yield</code> statement:</p>

    <pre><code>print(next(iterator)) &nbsp;# Output: hello
print(next(iterator)) &nbsp;# Output: world</code></pre>

    <p>If we try calling <code>next(iterator)</code> again, the generator will raise a <code>StopIteration</code> exception because there are no more yield statements in the generator function.</p>
    <p>Another cool feature of Python generators is <code>yield from</code>, which lets a generator call a sub-generator or an iterable object, enabling you to create a chain of generators!</p>

    <pre><code>def generator():
&nbsp; &nbsp;yield 'hello'

def another_generator():
&nbsp; &nbsp;yield from generator()

iterable = another_generator()
print(next(iterable)) &nbsp;# Output: hello</code></pre>

    <p>There’s a bit more to generators than I’m talking about, such as generator comprehensions, which are like list comprehensions but created with parentheses instead of brackets, and the ability to send data to generators with <code>iterator.send(value)</code>. However, for this article, the important thing to remember about generators is that they allow a function to be started and stopped while maintaining its state!</p>

<h2 id="the-event-loop">The Event Loop</h2>

    <p>The event loop, which is in charge of running and managing all of the current tasks, is the core of asyncio and is the first thing we’ll recreate with generators. While the asyncio event loop is written in C, an easy way to think about it is as a list that holds all of the current tasks. For now, think of these tasks as just generator objects. The event loop manager will loop through each task in the list and use the <code>next(task)</code> function to run each of them. That task will then run, and when it's doing I/O-bound work like sleeping, it’ll use the <code>yield</code> keyword to pause its execution and give control back to this event loop, which will then go on to the next task in the loop.</p>
    <p>Here’s an example of that — we have two tasks that both print their task number and then yield, which stops their execution. Since the event loop manager is the one that calls <code>next()</code>, after the task yields, it gets back control and then goes to run the next task in the loop.</p>

    <pre><code>def task1():
&nbsp; &nbsp;while True:
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;print('Task 1')
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;yield

def task2():
&nbsp; &nbsp;while True:
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;print('Task 2')
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;yield

event_loop = [task1(), task2()]

while True:
&nbsp; &nbsp;for task in event_loop:
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;next(task)</code></pre>

    <p>Subsequently, the output of this code is going to look like the following and will go on forever since both of the generator functions never finish due to the <code>while True</code> loops.</p>

    <pre><code>Task 1
Task 2
Task 1
Task 2
…</code></pre>


<h2 id="sleeping">Sleeping</h2>

    <p>If we take the same code from above, we can add sub-generators to our tasks via the use of <code>yield from</code>. Below, I added a sleeping generator which will pause the execution of the tasks until the specified time is up. This works because <code>sleep</code> will keep yielding until a certain amount of seconds has passed, at which point it will leave the <code>while</code> loop. Since there are no more <code>yield</code> statements in <code>sleep</code>, a <code>StopIteration</code> exception is raised which signals to the <code>yield from</code> in the task functions to continue to the next line of code.</p>

    <pre><code>import time

def sleep(seconds):
&nbsp; &nbsp;start_time = time.time()
&nbsp; &nbsp;while time.time() - start_time &lt; seconds:
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;yield

def task1():
&nbsp; &nbsp;while True:
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;print('Task 1')
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;yield from sleep(1)

def task2():
&nbsp; &nbsp;while True:
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;print('Task 2')
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;yield from sleep(5)

event_loop = [task1(), task2()]

while True:
&nbsp; &nbsp;for task in event_loop:
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;next(task)</code></pre>

    <p>Output:</p>

    <pre><code>Task 1
Task 2
Task 1
Task 1
Task 1
Task 1
Task 2
Task 1
…</code></pre>


<h2 id="yield-to-await">Yield to Await</h2>

    <p>We can now take the above code, and transition from using <code>yield</code> to <code>await</code> by using the <code>__await__</code> dunder method and the <code>async</code> keyword. When a class has the <code>__await__</code> method, we can use the <code>await</code> keyword in front of an instance of the class to call it. In asyncio, you are generally working with <code>Task</code> objects via a function like <code>asyncio.create_task</code>. These <code>Task</code> objects inherit from the asyncio <code>Future</code> object, which has the <code>__await__</code>  method. We can also use <code>await</code> in front of a coroutine, which is an object created when calling a function with the <code>async</code> keyword in front of it. Coroutines are similar to generator functions in the sense that a coroutine’s execution can also be paused and resumed.</p>
    <p>You can think of the <code>await</code> keyword as just a synonym for <code>yield from</code> with some extra validation rules. So, when writing the code <code>await object</code>, you are basically saying to either yield from the <code>__await__</code> method in the “object” class instance OR “object” could be another coroutine (like a sub-generator).</p>
    <p>You can actually look in the Asyncio <a href="https://github.com/python/cpython/blob/main/Lib/asyncio/futures.py" target="_blank">source code</a> and see that the <code>__await__</code> method inside of the <code>Future</code> object basically just calls <code>yield</code> if the future (or task) is not done completing:</p>

    
    <p><img src="https://jacobpadilla.com/articles/blog_posts/recreating-asyncio/static/images/yield-to-await-193740693.png" alt="Asyncio source code. The __await__ method in the Future object"></p><p>To move the code that we wrote in the above section to using <code>async</code> and <code>await</code>, we first need to make our own <code>Task</code> class since a function can’t have the <code>__await__</code> dunder method. Below is a simple version that I came up with:</p>

    <pre><code>from queue import Queue


event_loop = Queue()

class Task():
&nbsp; &nbsp; def __init__(self, generator):
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; self.iter = generator
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; self.finished = False

&nbsp; &nbsp; def done(self):
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; return self.finished

&nbsp; &nbsp; def __await__(self):
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; while not self.finished:
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; yield self


def create_task(generator):
&nbsp; &nbsp; task = Task(generator)
&nbsp; &nbsp; event_loop.put(task)

&nbsp; &nbsp; return task</code></pre>

    <p>This time, instead of using a Python list to create the event loop, we’re using a queue, which makes a bit more sense since we want to be able to add and delete tasks from the loop in constant time.</p>
    <p>For our <code>Task</code> class, we store the generator object in <code>self.iter</code> and also set <code>self.finished</code> to <code>False</code>, which will keep track of if the generator is done running (It’s done running when it raises <code>StopIteration</code>). Our <code>Task</code> object also has an <code>__await__</code> dunder method, which will just keep yielding control back to the event loop until the task is finished. Lastly, after creating the <code>Task</code> object with the <code>create_task</code> helper function, we add it to the event loop, which schedules it to be run.</p>
    <p>Now, let’s build the event loop manager, which will run the tasks:</p>

    <pre><code>def run(main):
&nbsp; &nbsp; event_loop.put(Task(main))

&nbsp; &nbsp; while not event_loop.empty():
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; task = event_loop.get()
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; try:
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; task.iter.send(None)
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; except StopIteration:
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; task.finished = True
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; else:
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; event_loop.put(task)</code></pre>

    <p>You may notice that this is starting to mimic the actual asyncio API since to start the event loop, we need to call <code>run</code> with an initial function. The function first wraps the main function in a <code>Task</code> object and adds it to the event loop. The <code>while</code> loop will then run, and for each cycle, will get the next task to run via the queue. Instead of using <code>next(task.iter)</code>, we now need to use <code>task.iter.send(None)</code>, which is just a weird quirk of working with the async/await keywords, but it does the same thing. We also want to wrap this call in a try-except block since if a <code>StopIteration</code> exception is thrown, we can set <code>task.finished</code> to <code>True</code>, but if no exceptions are raised, the code will go to the <code>else</code> statement which adds the task back to the event loop to be run again.</p>
    <p>Next, we need to make the sleep function async-compliant. Before, we were using a generator function with a while-loop and one <code>yield</code> to handle the sleeping. I like this approach, but you can’t use the <code>await</code> keyword in combination with a generator function - it needs to be an object with the <code>__await__</code> dunder method or a coroutine function. So, to solve this, I moved the code to another function, and now the actual <code>sleep</code> function creates a task object and then awaits it. This <code>await</code> will call the <code>__await__</code> method inside of the Task object, which will then yield, letting the event loop move to another task. When the event loop gets to the new <code>_sleep</code> task, it will check the time, and if not enough has passed, will also call <code>yield</code> to give control back to the event loop. If the task that is sleeping is called via the event loop again, like how a generator stores its state, the coroutine would still be waiting for <code>sleep</code> to return, and since <code>sleep</code> would still be awaiting the <code>_sleep</code> task to finish, the <code>__await__</code> dunder method of the task will be called again and since the task isn't finished, the yield in the dunder method will be called.</p>

    <pre><code>import time

def _sleep(seconds):
&nbsp; &nbsp; start_time = time.time()
&nbsp; &nbsp; while time.time() - start_time &lt; seconds:
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; yield


async def sleep(seconds):
&nbsp; &nbsp; task = create_task(_sleep(seconds))
&nbsp; &nbsp; return await task</code></pre>

    <p>Here’s all of the code put together:</p>

    <pre><code>from queue import Queue
import time


event_loop = Queue()


def _sleep(seconds):
&nbsp; &nbsp; start_time = time.time()
&nbsp; &nbsp; while time.time() - start_time &lt; seconds:
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; yield


async def sleep(seconds):
&nbsp; &nbsp; task = create_task(_sleep(seconds))
&nbsp; &nbsp; return await task


class Task():
&nbsp; &nbsp; def __init__(self, generator):
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; self.iter = generator
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; self.finished = False

&nbsp; &nbsp; def done(self):
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; return self.finished

&nbsp; &nbsp; def __await__(self):
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; while not self.finished:
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; yield self


def create_task(generator):
&nbsp; &nbsp; task = Task(generator)
&nbsp; &nbsp; event_loop.put(task)

&nbsp; &nbsp; return task


def run(main):
&nbsp; &nbsp; event_loop.put(Task(main))

&nbsp; &nbsp; while not event_loop.empty():
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; task = event_loop.get()
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; try:
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; task.iter.send(None)
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; except StopIteration:
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; task.finished = True
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; else:
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; event_loop.put(task)</code></pre>

    <p>Now that we’ve built the event loop, a way to create tasks, and a sleep function, we can import the file (called “jacobio.py”) and take the code from back when we were using yields and replace all of the <code>yield from</code> statements with <code>await</code>, add <code>async</code> to the functions with the <code>await</code> keyword to signify that those functions can be awaited, and then create a main function, like you would in asyncio, to add the tasks to the event loop:</p>

    <pre><code>import jacobio

async def task1():
&nbsp; &nbsp; for _ in range(2):
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; print('Task 1')
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; await jacobio.sleep(1)

async def task2():
&nbsp; &nbsp; for _ in range(3):
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; print('Task 2')
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; await jacobio.sleep(0)

async def main():
&nbsp; &nbsp; one = jacobio.create_task(task1())
&nbsp; &nbsp; two = jacobio.create_task(task2())

&nbsp; &nbsp; await one
&nbsp; &nbsp; await two
&nbsp; &nbsp; 
&nbsp; &nbsp; print('done')


if __name__ == '__main__':
&nbsp; &nbsp; jacobio.run(main())</code></pre>

    <p>Output:</p>

    <pre><code>Task 1
Task 2
Task 2
Task 2
Task 1
done</code></pre>


<h2 id="await-with-asyncio">Await with AsyncIO</h2>

    <p>We can now take our code from above and replace all occurrences of “jacobio” with “asyncio” and we’re now fully using the asyncio package!</p>

    <pre><code>import asyncio

async def task1():
&nbsp; &nbsp; for _ in range(2):
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; print('Task 1')
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; await asyncio.sleep(1)

async def task2():
&nbsp; &nbsp; for _ in range(3):
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; print('Task 2')
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; await asyncio.sleep(0)

async def main():
&nbsp; &nbsp; one = asyncio.create_task(task1())
&nbsp; &nbsp; two = asyncio.create_task(task2())

&nbsp; &nbsp; await one
&nbsp; &nbsp; await two
&nbsp; &nbsp; 
&nbsp; &nbsp; print('done')


if __name__ == '__main__':
&nbsp; &nbsp; asyncio.run(main())</code></pre>

    <p>Asyncio does a lot more behind the scenes, but we were able to go from basic generators to recreating the core parts of asyncio from scratch! I tried to make the event loop manager as simple as possible, and while this is the basic idea behind asyncio, given the scale and complexity of the actual package, my implementation is slightly different from the flow of the actual source code. Also, now that we have the full power of the real asyncio package, we don’t need to create two tasks just to await both; instead, we can use a function such as <code>asyncio.gather()</code>to handle multiple tasks. If you’re curious about all of the ways to manage tasks in asyncio, check out my article on <a href="https://jacobpadilla.com/articles/handling-asyncio-tasks">handling asyncio tasks like a pro</a>!</p>
<!-- 🌟 END OF MAIN CONTENT 🌟 -->
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Proton Mail discloses user data leading to arrest in Spain (335 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://restoreprivacy.com/protonmail-discloses-user-data-leading-to-arrest-in-spain/</link>
            <guid>40280689</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 23:34:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://restoreprivacy.com/protonmail-discloses-user-data-leading-to-arrest-in-spain/">https://restoreprivacy.com/protonmail-discloses-user-data-leading-to-arrest-in-spain/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40280689">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<figure><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="950" height="450" src="https://cdn-resprivacy.pressidium.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/ProtonMail-Discloses-User-Data-Leading-to-Arrest-in-Spain.jpg" alt="ProtonMail Discloses User Data Leading to Arrest in Spain" srcset="https://cdn-resprivacy.pressidium.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/ProtonMail-Discloses-User-Data-Leading-to-Arrest-in-Spain-300x142.jpg 300w, https://cdn-resprivacy.pressidium.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/ProtonMail-Discloses-User-Data-Leading-to-Arrest-in-Spain-768x364.jpg 768w, https://cdn-resprivacy.pressidium.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/ProtonMail-Discloses-User-Data-Leading-to-Arrest-in-Spain.jpg 950w" sizes="(max-width: 950px) 100vw, 950px" data-old-src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg'%20viewBox='0%200%20950%20450'%3E%3C/svg%3E" data-lazy-srcset="https://cdn-resprivacy.pressidium.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/ProtonMail-Discloses-User-Data-Leading-to-Arrest-in-Spain-300x142.jpg 300w, https://cdn-resprivacy.pressidium.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/ProtonMail-Discloses-User-Data-Leading-to-Arrest-in-Spain-768x364.jpg 768w, https://cdn-resprivacy.pressidium.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/ProtonMail-Discloses-User-Data-Leading-to-Arrest-in-Spain.jpg 950w" data-lazy-src="https://cdn-resprivacy.pressidium.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/ProtonMail-Discloses-User-Data-Leading-to-Arrest-in-Spain.jpg"></figure>



<p>Proton Mail has come under scrutiny for its role in a legal request involving the Spanish authorities and a member of the Catalan independence organization, Democratic Tsunami.</p>



<p>Proton Mail is a <a href="https://restoreprivacy.com/email/secure/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">secure email</a> service based in Switzerland, renowned for its commitment to privacy through end-to-end encryption and a strict no-logs policy. In 2021, Proton Mail <a href="https://restoreprivacy.com/protonmail-logs-users/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">faced controversy</a> when it complied with a legal request that led to the arrest of a French climate activist. Under Swiss law, Proton Mail was compelled to collect and provide information on the individual’s IP address to Swiss authorities, who then shared it with French police.</p>



<p>The recent case involving the Spanish police this time, highlights privacy concerns and the limits of encrypted communication services under national security pretexts, and brings a long-debated subject to the forefront once again.</p>



<p>The core of the controversy stems from Proton Mail <a href="https://www.elnacional.cat/en/politics/judge-garcia-castellon-accuse-mossos-police-officer-tsunami_1202609_102.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">providing the Spanish police</a> with the recovery email address associated with the Proton Mail account of an individual using the pseudonym ‘Xuxo Rondinaire.’ This individual is suspected of being a member of the Mossos d’Esquadra (Catalonia’s police force) and of using their internal knowledge to assist the Democratic Tsunami movement. </p>



<p>Upon receiving the recovery email from Proton Mail, Spanish authorities <a href="https://www.vilaweb.cat/noticies/tsunami-democratic-xuxo-rondinaire-mossos/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">further requested Apple</a> to provide additional details linked to that email, leading to the identification of the individual.</p>



<p>This case is particularly noteworthy because it involves a series of requests across different jurisdictions and companies, highlighting the complex interplay between technology firms, user privacy, and law enforcement. The requests were made under the guise of anti-terrorism laws, despite the primary activities of the Democratic Tsunami involving protests and roadblocks, which raises questions about the proportionality and justification of such measures.</p>



<p>Like before, Proton Mail’s compliance with these requests is bound by Swiss law, which mandates cooperation with international legal demands that are formalized through proper channels (Swiss court system). </p>



<p>Last year, when we noted that <a href="https://restoreprivacy.com/protonmail-data-requests-user-logs/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Proton Mail complied with nearly 6,000 data requests</a> in 2022, Proton provided us with an explanation that inbox contents remain secure.</p>



<blockquote>
<p><em>Please note that in all cases email content, attachments, files etc are always encrypted and cannot be read.</em></p>
<cite>Proton <a href="https://restoreprivacy.com/protonmail-data-requests-user-logs/">statement to RestorePrivacy last year</a></cite></blockquote>



<p>Looking at Proton’s <a href="https://proton.me/legal/transparency" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">transparency report</a>, we find that Proton Mail complied with 5,971 data requests last year alone, up slightly from the year before.</p>


<div>
<figure><img decoding="async" width="568" height="286" src="https://cdn-resprivacy.pressidium.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Proton-Mail-logs.png" alt="Proton Mail logs" srcset="https://cdn-resprivacy.pressidium.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Proton-Mail-logs-300x151.png 300w, https://cdn-resprivacy.pressidium.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Proton-Mail-logs.png 568w" sizes="(max-width: 568px) 100vw, 568px" data-old-src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg'%20viewBox='0%200%20568%20286'%3E%3C/svg%3E" data-lazy-srcset="https://cdn-resprivacy.pressidium.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Proton-Mail-logs-300x151.png 300w, https://cdn-resprivacy.pressidium.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Proton-Mail-logs.png 568w" data-lazy-src="https://cdn-resprivacy.pressidium.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Proton-Mail-logs.png"><figcaption>Proton Mail complied with 5,971 data requests in 2023.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>With so many data requests going on in the background, it is all the more important to safeguard the data you share with various services. </p>



<h3 id="h-the-importance-of-good-opsec">The importance of good OPSEC</h3>



<p>This situation serves as a critical reminder of the importance of maintaining stringent OPSEC (operational security). One should always be aware of the potential vulnerabilities that come with linking recovery information or secondary services (like Apple accounts) that may not have the same privacy safeguards as a primary encrypted email service. </p>



<p>For users concerned about privacy, particularly those involved in sensitive or political activities, OPSEC should be a top concern when using <a href="https://restoreprivacy.com/privacy-tools/">privacy tools</a>. It’s advisable to:</p>



<ul>
<li>Avoid linking recovery emails or phone numbers that can directly tie back to personal identities or primary business activities.</li>



<li>Consider using secondary, <a href="https://restoreprivacy.com/email/temporary-disposable/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">disposable emails</a> or virtual phone numbers that offer an additional layer of anonymity.</li>



<li>Use a <a href="https://restoreprivacy.com/vpn/best/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">good VPN service</a> to hide your IP address whenever possible. (Failure to do this is what <a href="https://restoreprivacy.com/protonmail-logs-users/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">compromised a Proton Mail user in France</a> who was arrested after after police obtained IP logs.)</li>



<li>Consider purchasing services using an <a href="https://restoreprivacy.com/private-anonymous-payment-methods/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">anonymous payment method</a>.</li>



<li>Stay informed about the legal obligations and policies of communication service providers, especially regarding their compliance with international law enforcement requests.</li>
</ul>



<p>While Proton Mail and similar services offer substantial protections and end-to-end encryption on their email platform, they are not immune to legal and governmental pressures. Users must navigate these waters carefully, balancing the need for security with the potential legal obligations of their service providers.</p>



<p>RestorePrivacy has reached out to Proton Mail for a comment on the case and their exact involvement, but a statement wasn’t immediately available. We will update this article as soon as we hear back.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Caniemail.com – like caniuse but for email content (672 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.caniemail.com/</link>
            <guid>40280490</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 23:03:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.caniemail.com/">https://www.caniemail.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40280490">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
	<div>
		
		<main role="main">
			<div>
	<div>
		<h2><a href="https://www.caniemail.com/features/">Latest features</a></h2>
		<ol>
			
			
				
				
			<li>
<a href="https://www.caniemail.com/features/css-text-wrap/">CSS text-wrap</a>, April 03, 2024</li>
			
				
				
			<li>
<a href="https://www.caniemail.com/features/css-transition/">CSS transition</a>, March 29, 2024</li>
			
				
				
			<li>
<a href="https://www.caniemail.com/features/css-word-spacing/">CSS word-spacing</a>, March 13, 2024</li>
			
				
				
			<li>
<a href="https://www.caniemail.com/features/css-shape-margin/">CSS shape-margin</a>, March 13, 2024</li>
			
				
				
			<li>
<a href="https://www.caniemail.com/features/css-shape-outside/">CSS shape-outside</a>, February 28, 2024</li>
			
		</ol>
		<p><a href="https://www.caniemail.com/features/">View all features</a>
	</p></div>
	<div>
		<h2><a href="https://www.caniemail.com/news/">Latest news</a></h2>
		<ul>
			
			<li>
<a href="https://www.caniemail.com/news/2024-03-29-march-updates/">March 2024 updates</a>, March 29, 2024</li>
			
			<li>
<a href="https://www.caniemail.com/news/2024-02-29-february-updates/">February 2024 updates</a>, February 29, 2024</li>
			
			<li>
<a href="https://www.caniemail.com/news/2024-01-29-new-outlook-macos/">The new Outlook on macOS</a>, January 29, 2024</li>
			
			<li>
<a href="https://www.caniemail.com/news/2023-12-16-december-updates/">December 2023 updates</a>, December 16, 2023</li>
			
			<li>
<a href="https://www.caniemail.com/news/2023-04-30-april-updates/">April 2023 updates</a>, April 30, 2023</li>
			
		</ul>
		<p><a href="https://www.caniemail.com/news/">View all news</a>
	</p></div>
	
</div>
		</main>
		

	</div>
	

</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Attackers Can Decloak Routing-Based VPNs (405 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.leviathansecurity.com/blog/tunnelvision</link>
            <guid>40279632</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 21:19:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.leviathansecurity.com/blog/tunnelvision">https://www.leviathansecurity.com/blog/tunnelvision</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40279632">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-89b404859ec5dd2d13df">
  <p>Recently, we identified a novel network technique that bypasses VPN encapsulation. An attacker can use this technique to force a target user’s traffic off their VPN tunnel using built-in features of DHCP (Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol). The result of this is the user transmits packets that are never encrypted by a VPN, and an attacker can snoop their traffic. We are using the term <strong>decloaking</strong> to refer to this effect. Importantly, the VPN control channel is maintained so features such as kill switches are never tripped, and users continue to show as connected to a VPN in all the cases we’ve observed. </p><p>We’ve spent extensive time exploring this capability and attempting to notify as many affected parties as possible. We also know it is our responsibility as security researchers to inform the security and privacy community, as well as the general public, about this threat. We also believe this technique may have been possible as far back as 2002 and could have already been discovered<strong>*</strong> and potentially used in the wild. For that reason, we believe it is critical for us to disclose publicly because notifying every VPN provider, operating system maintainer, self-hosted VPN admin, and VPN user is far beyond the capacity of our small research team.</p><p>We've seen one mitigation for this technique, as well as identified a fix that exists on Linux-based operating systems. However, the mitigation offers a side channel that could be used for targeted denial-of-service censorship, as well as to de-anonymize the destination of traffic via traffic analysis. In some places in the world, the side-channel alone could lead to imprisonment or death for those who rely on VPNs for safety such as journalists or whistleblowers <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/07/19/1017774097/private-spyware-was-used-to-hack-cellphones-of-journalists-activists-worldwide" target="_blank">who are common targets of surveillance or spyware.</a> </p><p>It is not feasible to fix the issue by simply removing support for the DHCP feature because this could break Internet connectivity in some legitimate cases. The strongest recommendation we have is for VPN providers to implement network namespaces on operating systems that support them, similar to the method described in <a href="https://www.wireguard.com/netns/#the-new-namespace-solution" target="_blank">WireGuard’s documentation</a>. Network namespaces are a Linux feature that can segment interfaces and routing tables away from the local network’s control, and other operating system maintainers should consider whether namespaces are feasible to implement.</p><p>To help make this work accessible to as many people as possible, we are structuring this blog post to walk through the fundamentals of networking, VPN technology, and DHCP to fully explain the decloaking behavior. <strong>Advanced readers are welcome to jump straight to the proof-of-concept section.</strong></p><p> <strong>*</strong> After publication we’ve received notice that there are references to this decloaking behavior on <a href="https://mstdn.io/@jomo/98981403329690455" target="_blank">social media</a>. This further showcases the important of informing audiences outside of the technology sector of the existence of our technique.</p><h2>Decloaking Primer: Low-level Networking</h2><h3>What is a network?</h3><p>A computer network is a group of computer devices that are connected to each other and can send and receive data to and from one another. </p><p>A basic example of this is to connect two laptops with an Ethernet cable to network them together. However, there’s more than meets the eye when it comes to low-level networking that’s hidden from the average user. The laptops are using a system of rules to talk to each other, which we call <strong>protocols</strong>. Each protocol has its own purpose and operates at what we call a <strong>layer</strong>.</p><p>These layers are intended to solve different types of problems and are built such that they do not need to know what’s happening at a higher or lower layer. This is called <strong>encapsulation</strong>. For example, a user can trust that the layers lower than their browser (HTTP) are determining how to send electricity over a cable (Coax), knows who to talk to (Ethernet, IP), and ensure correct data delivery to the recipient server (TCP). This is like how someone writing a letter needs only to think about what they want to write or what the other person wrote. They do not need to care about how it got there.</p><p>When we’re referring to layers in this blogpost, we are talking about the practical <strong>TCP/IP model</strong>, which is implemented on almost every device and network. We also decided to use the 5-layer variant of the model because it doesn’t combine the lower layers together; this is why there might be a discrepancy when viewing other TCP/IP model diagrams. When we’re referring to data that’s been packaged by all these layers, we generally refer to it as a <strong>packet</strong>.</p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1714393040309_31260">
  <h3>What is a network interface?</h3><p>The most basic example of a network interface is a physical device such as a wireless or network card attached to a computer's motherboard. These devices allow the computer to transmit bits of data over a physical medium (e.g., a copper wire, fiber optic cable, or radio frequency). They are a fundamental part of networking as they are what allows computers to talk to each other over a distance.</p><p>There are two types of network interfaces:</p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p>Physical Network Interfaces</p></li><li><p>Virtual Network Interfaces</p></li></ul><p>Importantly, both types of interfaces are designed for encapsulation so they can be interacted with by higher layers in the same way. </p><p>This is where Virtual Network Interfaces, a critical component of VPN clients and server, come in. Instead of using physical hardware, Virtual Network Interfaces create a <strong>file</strong> <strong>descriptor</strong> that can be read from or written to via software applications. Because file descriptors exist only in the memory of a host, Virtual Network Interfaces are especially useful for virtualized environments where traffic might never need to be transmitted over a physical medium.</p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1714393040309_4403">

<p>However, there are use cases in which a user might want a virtual interface to be able to send traffic over a physical medium. For those cases, the virtual interface can also be backed by a physical network interface. Behind the scenes, the virtual interface forwards outbound traffic to a physical network interface.</p>




















  
  



</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1714393040309_15603">
  <h3>What is a VPN?</h3><p>A Virtual Private Network (VPN) allows users to create a <strong>tunnel</strong> for network traffic between their host device and a server on a different network. The resulting <strong>virtual network</strong> is not confined by geographic location while behaving identically to a physical network. </p><p>To achieve this, VPN clients create a virtual network interface and use the underlying file descriptor to encrypt/decrypt traffic at a higher layer before sending it to a physical network interface.</p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1714393040309_18104">
  <p>VPN use is designed to be as simple as possible for a user. Often, they do not need to do much besides log in and click a button to connect to their server.</p><p>What a user does:</p><ol data-rte-list="default"><li><p>Select the settings they want on the VPN Client</p></li><li><p>Click a button to connect</p></li><li><p>Log in (optional in some cases, depending on the client)</p></li><li><p>Read the confirmation from the VPN they are connected</p></li><li><p>Use remote resources from the VPN</p></li></ol><p>Importantly, VPNs actually <em>increase </em>the host’s attack surface because traffic from lower networking layers is send over the Internet. VPNs work by encapsulating lower layers inside of higher layers to create local area networks (LAN) over the Internet. LAN traffic is considered to be more privileged than traffic that is intended to be sent over the Internet. Attackers with LAN access have many more passive and active attack options than an attacker outside of the LAN. By creating a LAN over the Internet, VPNs extend the LAN attack surface to external attackers. Commonly, VPNs mitigate this attack surface by using compensating controls such as packet encryption.</p><p>This is an often-misunderstood fact about VPNs. The reason for encryption is not to increase the security of using the physical LAN, but rather to mitigate the added risk that VPNs introduce when they create a virtualized LAN over the Internet. <strong><em>VPNs do not secure you from local network attacks on the physical LAN</em> <em>despite common VPN marketing material and widely given advice.</em></strong></p><h3>How do VPNs use virtual network interfaces?</h3><p>The VPN client process creates an encrypted version of the packet it originally received from the file descriptor associated with its virtual network interface. It places this encrypted <strong>payload</strong> in the layer for its underlying VPN protocol, then uses that protocol to talk to the VPN server.</p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1714393040309_32168">
  <p>There’s quite a long process for how a VPN sends that packet to the VPN Server. We are including a more exhaustive list of steps in the Appendix for security researchers or developers who might need even more granular details.</p><p>A simplified version of that process:</p><ol data-rte-list="default"><li><p>A VPN client establishes a “control channel” connection to a VPN server. If the VPN features a kill switch, then losing connection to this channel will result in a lockdown</p></li><li><p>The VPN client creates a virtual network interface</p></li><li><p>The VPN client optionally runs a startup script to configure the host. It may configure routing rules, the DNS server to use, host-based firewall rules, or other settings</p></li><li><p>A process on the host attempts to send network traffic to a destination (i.e., Internet browsing)</p></li><li><p>Routing rules select the VPN’s interface to send the traffic through</p></li><li><p>The VPN client receives and encrypts that traffic</p></li><li><p>The VPN client sends the encrypted traffic over a physically backed network interface to the VPN server</p></li><li><p>The VPN server receives and decrypts that traffic from the VPN client</p></li><li><p>The VPN server forwards that traffic to the destination. If the destination is outbound, the VPN will send your traffic as though it is its own. This behavior is what VPN providers describe as “IP cloaking” or “IP hiding”</p></li><li><p>The VPN server receives a reply from the destination, encrypts the response, and sends it to the VPN client</p></li><li><p>The VPN client decrypts the response, and the originating process finally receives the traffic</p></li></ol><p>It can be quite hard to understand fully since there are many steps involved. For that reason, we’ve made our own detailed diagram of a mental model we use for how a VPN client sends and receives information (Figure 4).</p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1714393040309_41563">
  <h3>How do routing based VPNs configure a host?</h3><p>Once a user connects to a VPN server, their VPN client process will configure the host’s settings to route traffic through the tunnel that it established. If all traffic* is routed through the VPN, we refer to it as a “full-tunnel VPN”. &nbsp;If there are user-defined exceptions for traffic, such as local network traffic, we refer to it as a “split-tunnel VPN”. The VPN client can also configure other settings on the host, such as the host’s firewall. Later, we’ll discuss a mitigation we observed using the host-based firewall.</p><p>Commonly, these configuration changes are made by “up scripts” and “down scripts” when a connection is established or disconnected. The runtime process for a VPN client may also perform configuration changes, but this varies from vendor to vendor.</p><p>*Note: When we say, “all traffic”, we really mean “all traffic except the traffic necessary to keep the VPN in a working state.” For example, VPNs create an exception to their own previously configured routing rules. All traffic sent to the VPN servers IP address must be sent over a hardware backed interface instead of its own tunnel. Otherwise, it would break the hosts connection to the VPN server and the VPN client would be unable to send encrypted packets. In addition, there are other configuration exceptions made for DHCP traffic since the VPN must maintain its hosts IP address lease. </p><h3>What are routes and routing tables?</h3><p><strong>Routes</strong> are how we describe where to send traffic based on the destination. <strong>Routing tables</strong> are a collection of routes that are used by the <strong>network stack</strong>. Consider a network stack to just be all the code on an operating system that deals with sending and receiving data from a network.</p><p>A common route is sending all traffic (<code>0.0.0.0/0</code> in <strong>Classless</strong> Inter-Domain Routing [CIDR] notation) to your router (<code>192.168.1.1</code>) over the physical network interface (<code>eth0</code>).</p><p>An example of that rule in the table would be:</p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1714393040309_74810">
  <p>Another behavior of routing tables is that by default (in most network stacks) the most specific <strong>prefix length</strong> for the CIDR range has the highest priority. The prefix length for the range <code>192.168.1.1/32</code> is <code>32</code> and the prefix length for the range <code>0.0.0.0/0</code> is <code>0</code>. The highest numerical value of a prefix length will take priority for routing selection (unless configured otherwise).</p><p>For example:</p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1714393040309_76210">
  <p>In this situation, if we sent traffic to <code>10.10.10.2</code>, the most specific rule is the <code>/32</code> rule and it would therefore be the rule the network stack uses despite matching the other two rules above it.</p><p>Most full-tunnel VPNs use the least specific rule possible to capture all traffic. Note that the following example includes an exception route for the hypothetical VPN server address (<code>12.34.56.78</code>) as well.</p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1714393040309_77388">

<p>Alternatively, providers may use two <code>/1</code> rules to gain priority over the default route. It's common in even non-adversarial environments for DHCP to set a default route to the physical gateway.</p>




















  
  



</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1714393040309_80151">
  <h3>What is DHCP?</h3><p>DHCP was originally developed as a robust way to dynamically issue IP addresses to devices on a local network as opposed to manually addressing each device. All modern operating systems have their own DHCP client that will automatically request an IP address. </p><p>The main concept to understand is that DHCP provides a time-based <strong>lease</strong> for IP addresses, and it contains many additional features called <strong>options</strong> that allow you to adjust the configuration of devices remotely and dynamically. Some notable options include setting the <strong>default</strong> <strong>gateway</strong> that acts as the primary route to the Internet or DNS (Domain Name System) servers, which resolve domain names like “google.com” to an IP address.</p><p>A client who wants an IP address uses a <strong>broadcast</strong> to send a <strong>DHCPDISCOVER</strong> packet to the entire local subnet. Other hosts will ignore this, except for the server who will respond with a <strong>DHCPOFFER </strong>unicasted directly to the client to offer it a time-bound lease.</p><p>Alternatively, if a client knows who the DHCP server is, it has the option to unicast the DHCPDISCOVER to a DHCP server instead of broadcasting. Usually, this is used for renewing its lease.</p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1714393040309_83258">
  <p>As seen in the above diagram, once a DHCP server makes an offer, the client can choose to accept or decline the offer. For example, if it receives multiple offers, it will choose the best one. The selection most often implemented by DHCP clients is “first come, first serve.” The servers that aren’t selected will be sent a <strong>DHCPDECLINE</strong> message from the client. Notably, the DHCPOFFER will include the options.</p><h3>What is DHCP option 121?</h3><p>In 1997, the DHCP <strong>RFC</strong> had option 33, which allowed network administrators to specify a static route to install into a client’s routing table. However, this used <em>classful</em> static routes, which fell out of favor over time as public IP space became limited. In 2002, RFC 3442 introduced option 121 classless static routes and obsoleted option 33 (which still should be supported, <a href="https://github.com/systemd/systemd/issues/7792#issuecomment-355068519" target="_blank">depending on who you ask</a>). Option 121 also allows administrators to add static routes to a client’s routing table, but with classless ranges instead. There is no limit besides packet size to how many different routes can be installed at once.</p><p>An interesting quirk of DHCP option 121 is that the network interface device for the route it installs cannot be specified by the DHCP server. Below you can see a DHCPOFFER packet that was captured in Wireshark. It specifies the <em>CIDR range </em>and the <em>router</em> to use but has no interface device.</p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1714393040309_86829">
  <p>Instead, the DHCP client will implicitly choose the network interface that the client is talking to the DHCP server on when installing its routing rules for this option. </p><h2>Decloaking Attacks</h2>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1714927966073_13397">
  <h3>Requirements for decloaking VPN traffic</h3><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p>The targeted host must accept a DHCP lease from the attacker-controlled server</p></li><li><p>The targeted host’s DHCP client must implement DHCP option 121</p></li></ul><p>We want to stress that <strong>there are ways an attacker who is on the same network as a targeted user might be able to become their DHCP server</strong>:</p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p>A rogue DHCP server using a DHCP starvation attack against the true DHCP, then responding to new clients. We have achieved this in lab environments and are working on a follow-up blog post.</p></li><li><p>A rogue DHCP server racing to respond to DHCPDISCOVER broadcasts to abuse DHCP clients’ common behavior where they implement first-offer lease selection.&nbsp; </p></li><li><p>ARP spoofing to intercept traffic between the true DHCP server and client, then waiting for a client to renew their lease. </p></li></ul><h3>Performing the attack</h3><p>Our technique is to run a DHCP server on the same network as a targeted VPN user and to also set our DHCP configuration to use itself as a gateway. When the traffic hits our gateway, we use traffic forwarding rules on the DHCP server to pass traffic through to a legitimate gateway while we snoop on it.</p><p>We use DHCP option 121 to set a route on the VPN user’s routing table. The route we set is arbitrary and we can also set multiple routes if needed. By pushing routes that are more specific than a <code>/0</code> CIDR range that most VPNs use, we can make routing rules that have a higher priority than the routes for the virtual interface the VPN creates. We can set multiple <code>/1</code> routes to recreate the <code>0.0.0.0/0</code> all traffic rule set by most VPNs.</p><p>Pushing a route also means that the network traffic will be sent over the same interface as the DHCP server instead of the virtual network interface. This is intended functionality that isn’t clearly stated in the RFC. Therefore, for the routes we push, it is never encrypted by the VPN’s virtual interface but instead transmitted by the network interface that is talking to the DHCP server. As an attacker, we can select which IP addresses go over the tunnel and which addresses go over the network interface talking to our DHCP server.</p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1714393040309_95776">
  <p>We now have traffic being transmitted outside the VPN’s encrypted tunnel. This technique can also be used against an already established VPN connection once the VPN user’s host needs to renew a lease from our DHCP server. We can artificially create that scenario by setting a short lease time in the DHCP lease, so the user updates their routing table more frequently. In addition, the VPN control channel is still intact because it already uses the physical interface for its communication. In our testing, the VPN always continued to report as connected, and the kill switch was never engaged to drop our VPN connection.</p><h3>Proof of Concept</h3><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p>Video proof of concept:</p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ajsLmZia6UU" target="_blank">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ajsLmZia6UU</a></p></li></ul></li><li><p>Lab Setup Code:</p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p><a href="https://github.com/leviathansecurity/TunnelVision" target="_blank">https://github.com/leviathansecurity/TunnelVision</a></p></li></ul></li><li><p>DHCP Server image:</p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1WLJGs3ZUypf6hLh5WL4AJmsKdUOZo5yZ" target="_blank">https://drive.google.com/file/d/1WLJGs3ZUypf6hLh5WL4AJmsKdUOZo5yZ</a></p></li></ul></li></ul><p><br>The lab scenarios are built to represent:</p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p>An attacker compromises a DHCP server/access point</p></li><li><p>A rogue administrator owns the infrastructure themselves and maliciously configures it</p></li><li><p>An attacker sets up an evil twin wireless AP in a physical location such as a coffee shop or corporate office</p></li><li><p>One we release our tool, ArcaneTrickster, the lab can also be used to mimic an attacker who has an adjacent host on the network na dis otherwise not in a privileged network position</p></li></ul><h3>Fixes</h3><h4><strong>Network Namespaces</strong></h4><p>Using network namespaces on Linux can completely fix this behavior. However, in our experience, it is less commonly implemented.</p><p><a href="https://www.wireguard.com/netns/#the-new-namespace-solution" target="_blank">WireGuard’s documentation</a> shows how it’s possible to use a namespace for all applications with traffic that should be using a VPN before sending it to another namespace that contains a physical interface. However, this appears to be Linux-specific functionality and it’s not clear if there is a solution for Windows, MacOS, or other operating systems with the same amount of robustness.</p><h3>Mitigations</h3><h4><strong>Firewall Rules</strong></h4><p>We’ve observed VPN providers denying all inbound and outbound traffic to and from the physical interface via firewall rules. An exception was necessary for the DHCP and VPN server IPs because they are necessary to remain connected to the LAN and VPN server. Deep packet inspection could also allow only the DHCP and VPN protocols instead but would likely incur a performance penalty.</p><h4><strong>Problems with Firewall Rule Mitigations</strong></h4><p>Firewall mitigations create a selective denial of service for traffic using the DHCP route and introduce a side-channel. An attacker can use this side-channel to determine the destination of traffic. To determine the traffic’s destination, an attacker could perform traffic analysis on the volume of VPN encrypted traffic a user sends. The attacker would need a baseline volume of traffic where no malicious are installed. Then the attacker would need to modify the lease configuration to install routes that deny traffic and observe the difference in volume.</p><p>With enough samples, it would be possible to statistically prove whether the targeted user is sending traffic to a specific destination. For the average internet user, most internet traffic is already secured by TLS. Therefore, traffic intercepted by TunnelVision will mostly be unreadable except for the destination and protocols. This means that this side-channel has nearly the same impact and should be considered insufficient.</p><p>The side-channel is flexible in use:</p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p>The traffic can be checked against a predefined list.</p></li><li><p>The traffic can be selectively denied as a censorship mechanism.</p></li><li><p>The attacker can use IP space denial with binary search to determine all current connections in logarithmic time.</p></li></ul><h4><strong>Ignore Option 121</strong></h4><p>Another possible mitigation is ignoring option 121 while the VPN is on. We noted that because Android does not implement support for DHCP option 121, it was uniquely unaffected. The downside is that option 121 exists for a reason, and ignoring these routes can break network connectivity (<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=34145080" target="_blank">something that is frequently brought up as a reason to implement i</a>t on Android). If this mitigation is implemented, it must be mandatory because attackers could simply deny network access until the VPN or user re-enables option 121.</p><h4><strong>Use a Hot Spot or VM</strong></h4><p>Hot spots are temporary Wi-Fi networks controlled by a cellular device. They create a password-locked LAN with automatic network address translation. Because this network is completely controlled by the cellular device and requires a password, an attacker should not have local network access. A virtual machine would also work similarly as long as the VM’s network adapter is not in bridged mode.</p><h4><strong>Do not use untrusted networks if you need absolute confidentiality of your traffic</strong></h4><h2>Industry Impact</h2><h3>Is TunnelVision a vulnerability?</h3><p>This is debatable. We’re calling it a technique because TunnelVision doesn’t rely on violating any security properties of the underlying technologies. From our perspective, TunnelVision is how DHCP, routing tables, and VPNs are intended to work.</p><p>However, it contradicts VPN providers’ assurances that are commonly referenced in marketing materials; in our opinion, TunnelVision becomes a vulnerability when a VPN provider makes assurances that their product secures a customer from an attacker on an untrusted network. There’s a big difference between protecting your data in transit and protecting against all LAN attacks. VPNs were not designed to mitigate LAN attacks on the physical network and to promise otherwise is dangerous.</p><p>In our technique, we have not broken the VPN’s cryptographically secured protocol, and the VPN is still fully functional. An attacker is instead forcing a target user to not use their VPN tunnel. Regardless of whether we classify this as a technique, VPN users are affected when they rely on assurances that a VPN can secure them from attackers on their local network.</p><h3>Affected Operating Systems</h3><p>In our testing, we observed that any operating system that implements a DHCP client according to its RFC specification and has support for DHCP option 121 routes is affected. This includes Windows, Linux, iOS, and MacOS. Notably, it does not affect Android as they do not have support for DHCP option 121.</p><h3>Affected VPN Providers and VPN Protocols</h3><p>We found that VPNs that solely rely on routing rules to secure the host’s traffic are vulnerable. Those who are hosting their own VPN servers (e.g., system administrators) and are not hardening their VPN client configurations will likely be vulnerable as well. We have observed a mitigation from some VPN providers that drops traffic to non-VPN interfaces via firewall rules. It’s possible there are other methods that we did not encounter during testing to mitigate or fix this.</p><p>As previously mentioned, we observed the same behavior on each operating system we tested, save one. Furthermore, the strength of the encryption algorithm a VPN uses makes no difference. TunnelVision’s effect is independent of the underlying VPN protocol (e.g., WireGuard, OpenVPN, or IPsec) because it reconfigures the operating system network stack the VPN relies on.</p><h2>Conclusion</h2><h3>Call to Action</h3><p>We have a limitation as a research team of two– there are simply too many VPNs on the market to test each one individually. The first approach we took was to notify companies via bug bounties or security disclosure email, but that quickly became unscalable. We’ve also engaged the EFF and CISA to help disclose as broadly as possible prior to publicly releasing this research. We thank them tremendously for their help. Our hope is that by publishing our work, we can reach more affected parties, especially because we believe the technique has been feasible since as early as 2002.</p><p>Although the public disclosure of this technique affects each party differently, ultimately there is a shared responsibility.</p><p>Users should be made aware of this technique and for sensitive traffic they should be warned against using untrusted networks. If they must use an untrusted network, they should use a VPN provider that has an effective mitigation against this technique. To determine if a provider has an effective mitigation or fix, our lab setup is available for testing and VPN providers themselves will be able to speak to the specifics of their existing mitigations in their documentation. If a VPN decloak does occur, most user data will not be visible to local network attackers assuming they are accessing websites with HTTPS, which has <a href="https://w3techs.com/technologies/details/ce-httpsdefault" target="_blank">become increasingly common</a>.</p><p>It is common for corporate VPNs to be used in areas such as coffee shops, hotels, or airports. Network administrators should inform employees that working from such places carries risks and should be avoided when possible. If such a policy is not practical, then administrators should advise using VPNs that enable the previously mentioned mitigations or fixes. Some alternatives would be to use a trusted hot spot and then connect to the VPN. Lastly, running the VPN inside of a VM that obtains a lease from a virtualized DHCP server would prevent the local networks DHCP server from installing routes altogether.</p><p>Companies that control their own networks or have site-to-site VPNs should review the switches they use and enable features such as DHCP snooping and ARP protections.&nbsp; These layer 2 protections help prevent rogue DHCP servers but do not eliminate a rogue administrator scenario. In addition, implementing HTTPS or other protocols with encryption for internal resources will prevent data leakage from VPN users connecting from untrusted networks.</p><p>VPN providers can add features to clients to configure firewall rules that drop outbound packets to network interfaces. However, such a setting will mean that a VPN user will be isolated from interacting with local network resources. If the VPN client is for Linux and is intended to be a full tunnel, using network namespaces for isolation. As such, VPN providers should publicly provide documentation about any mitigations or fixes they have for TunnelVision and warn their end users about TunnelVision’s existence. We also recommend reviewing their marketing material and cease marketing claims that VPNs protect customers on untrusted networks until it can be proven.</p><p>Operating system maintainers (outside of Linux) should determine whether adding or enhancing features related to network namespaces is feasible. </p><h3>Upcoming Research</h3><p>During the disclosure process, we encountered multiple cases in which the entities we disclosed to did not see this as a serious problem. They assumed that the prerequisite conditions included privileged positions or accounts, despite the only prerequisite being local network access. This assumption was partially fueled by our intentionally simplistic lab setup where we were the only DHCP server, and what we perceive as the entity’s lack of familiarity with low-level networking.</p><p>With this feedback, we decided to develop a robust adversarial infrastructure library to enable further LAN security research and demonstrate practical attacks. For example, we can demonstrate that it’s possible to consistently perform TunnelVision while simply being adjacent to the target host on the same LAN. We’re calling it “ArcaneTrickster” and plan on releasing it at a later date. However, we feature a demo in our videos, which are available in the proof of concept section.</p>
</div><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1714393040309_196438">
  <h2>Credits</h2><p><strong>Authors:</strong></p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p>Lizzie Moratti</p></li><li><p>Dani Cronce</p></li></ul><p><strong>Acknowledgements:</strong></p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p>Sofia Aberegg</p></li><li><p>TC Johnson</p></li><li><p>Brian Campbell</p></li><li><p>Martin Bogomolni</p></li><li><p>Brad Haines</p></li><li><p>Frank Heidt</p></li></ul><p><strong>Special Thanks to:</strong></p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p>Electronic Frontier Foundation (EFF)</p></li><li><p>United States Cybersecurity Infrastructure and Security Agency (CISA)</p></li></ul><h2>Appendix</h2><h3>Prior research related to TunnelVision</h3><p>We found research related to <a href="https://petsymposium.org/popets/2015/popets-2015-0006.pdf" target="_blank">DHCP leaking default routes</a> over an incorrect interface as far back as 2015. However, it was implied that DHCP only pushed default routes and did not account for DHCP option 121.</p><p>In August 2023, <a href="https://tunnelcrack.mathyvanhoef.com/#summary" target="_blank">a paper</a> was published demonstrating that routing rules can be attacked in different ways to leak VPN traffic. The paper details two methods of leaking VPN traffic:</p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p>Abusing non-RFC1918 IP ranges to leak traffic. </p></li><li><p>DNS spoofing the VPN server’s domain name to trick the VPN client into adding a routing rule exception for an IP address.</p></li></ul><p>However, neither technique described in the August 2023 paper leveraged DHCP option 121 to push routes. Pushing routes through DHCP has a significantly higher impact from the same attacker vantage point (the ability to hand out IP leases for a non-RFC1918 range or spoofing DNS replies).</p><h3>In-Depth Diagram Explanation</h3><p>For posterity and because we haven’t encountered another diagram like ours (Figure 4), below are the steps from the diagram in as much detail as we could reasonably provide. We feel it could be useful to a future security researcher or a developer trying to understand the technology, so we are including it for their benefit.</p><ol data-rte-list="default"><li><p>An application process sends a payload to a socket it creates.</p></li><li><p>The socket formats the payload into a packet and sends it to the routing table to determine which interface it should be sent through.</p></li><li><p>The routing table determines that the packet should be sent through tun0.</p></li><li><p>The routing table sends the packet to the firewall.</p></li><li><p>The firewall rules allow the packet to continue to tun0.</p></li><li><p>The network interface serializes the packet and writes it into a file descriptor at /dev/net/tun in userland.</p></li><li><p>The VPN client process reads the unencrypted raw bytes of the packet in the file descriptor.</p></li><li><p>The VPN process creates an encrypted payload and sends it to a socket the VPN made.</p></li><li><p>The socket formats the payload into a packet that is bound for the VPN’s server and sends it to the routing table to determine which interface it should be sent through.</p></li><li><p>The routing table determines that the packet must be sent over the wlan0 interface.</p></li><li><p>The routing table sends the packet to the firewall.</p></li><li><p>The firewall rules determine that the outbound packet may continue using wlan0.</p></li><li><p>The network interface transfers the packet to its Wi-Fi driver.</p></li><li><p>The Wi-Fi driver sends the VPN-bound packet to the physical network interface card (NIC).</p></li><li><p>The packet is sent across the internet to the VPN server.</p></li><li><p>The VPN server sends a packet in response back to the physical NIC.</p></li><li><p>The NIC sends the response packet to the Wi-Fi driver.</p></li><li><p>The Wi-Fi driver delivers the response packet to wlan0.</p></li><li><p>The response packet is sent to the firewall.</p></li><li><p>The firewall rules allow the packet to continue.</p></li><li><p>The packet is returned to the VPN socket.</p></li><li><p>The socket receives the packet and sends the packet’s encrypted payload to the VPN client process.</p></li><li><p>The VPN client process decrypts the payload and writes the unencrypted raw bytes of the response packet to the file descriptor.</p></li><li><p>The tun0 interface deserializes the bytes from the file descriptor and formats it into a packet.</p></li><li><p>The tun0 interface sends the packet to the firewall.</p></li><li><p>The firewall rules allow the packet to continue.</p></li><li><p>The packet is returned to the socket opened by the user’s application process.</p></li><li><p>The payload from the packet is returned to the application process.</p></li></ol>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[An infinite canvas for code exploration (183 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://territory.dev</link>
            <guid>40279499</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 21:03:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://territory.dev">https://territory.dev</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40279499">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                <div>
                    <p><img src="https://territory.dev/assets/img/maximize.svg" id="maximize"></p><video id="video" width="684" height="348" autoplay="" muted="" loop="">
                        <source src="https://pub-8ffb893e922642ffa7c0ce0e3570b044.r2.dev/maps_demo_full.mov">
                    </video>
                </div>
                <div><p>
                    Humankind produces more and more code everyday, meanwhile a single person’s ability to comprehend it stays constant. We want to make everyone better at understanding these vast territories. We built a tool to help you chart codebases of any size and get the answers you need.
                    </p><p>
                    
                    Territory is a code graph browser. You can think of it as your editor’s “Go To Definition” function with superpowers. See the entire control flow at a glance and never lose context.
                </p></div>
            </div><p>Great news! Your account is ready to go. Check your email for a password reset link.</p><p>Thank you for your interest! We will let you know as soon as your invite is available.</p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[TOTP Authenticator for PalmOS (178 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nkorth.com/palm/apps/#totp-authenticator</link>
            <guid>40279305</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 20:45:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nkorth.com/palm/apps/#totp-authenticator">https://www.nkorth.com/palm/apps/#totp-authenticator</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40279305">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
    
<p>These apps run on <a href="https://www.nkorth.com/palm/">Palm OS</a> devices, and emulators such as <a href="https://www.nkorth.com/palm/cloudpilot.html">Cloudpilot</a>.</p>
<ul>
<li>To install on a device, if you’re using Palm Desktop you can simply double-click each PRC/PDB file.<ul>
<li>If you’re on Linux, install <a href="https://www.nkorth.com/palm/pilot-link.html">pilot-link</a> and use <code>pilot-xfer</code>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>To install on Cloudpilot, drag files one at a time onto the emulator screen, or use the install button on the top bar. If updating an existing app, make sure you open a different app before attempting to install. (Returning to the launcher isn’t always enough.)</li>
</ul>


<h2 id="totp-authenticator">TOTP Authenticator</h2>
<p><img src="https://www.nkorth.com/palm/apps/totp_screen.png"></p>
<p>Get your 2-factor codes on your Palm, just like Google Authenticator. Unlike <a href="https://palmdb.net/app/totp-authenticator-app">Hotpants</a> (an old port of a J2ME phone app), this version takes up much less space and supports all Palm OS versions.</p>
<p>Download:
<img src="https://www.nkorth.com/palm/apps/totp_icon.png">
<a href="https://www.nkorth.com/palm/apps/TOTPAuth-1.0.zip">TOTPAuth-1.0.zip</a></p>
<p>Source: <a href="git://shinonomelaboratory.com/palm-totp.git">palm-totp.git</a></p>
<h2 id="rosary">Rosary</h2>
<p><img src="https://www.nkorth.com/palm/apps/rosary_screen.png"></p>
<p>A guide to praying the Rosary. It automatically selects the mysteries based on the weekly schedule, with options for both new and old forms. You can even choose to see the prayers in Latin.</p>
<p>Download:
<img src="https://www.nkorth.com/palm/apps/rosary_icon.png">
<a href="https://www.nkorth.com/palm/apps/Rosary-1.1.zip">Rosary-1.1.zip</a>
<img src="https://www.nkorth.com/etc/flags/us.png" title="English (US)">
<img src="https://www.nkorth.com/etc/flags/fr.png" title="French"></p>
<h2 id="bible-in-a-year">Bible in a Year</h2>
<p><img src="https://www.nkorth.com/palm/apps/biy_screen.png"></p>
<blockquote>
<p>If you’ve struggled to read the Bible, this podcast is for you.</p>
<p>Ascension’s <a href="https://ascensionpress.com/biy">Bible in a Year Podcast</a>, hosted by Fr. Mike Schmitz and featuring Jeff Cavins, guides Catholics through the Bible in 365 daily episodes starting January 1st, 2021.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This unofficial app shows each day’s readings, and remembers where you left off.</p>
<p>Download:
<img src="https://www.nkorth.com/palm/apps/biy_icon.png">
<a href="https://www.nkorth.com/palm/apps/BInAYear-1.0.zip">BInAYear-1.0.zip</a></p>
<h2 id="catechism-in-a-year">Catechism in a Year</h2>
<p><img src="https://www.nkorth.com/palm/apps/ciy_screen.png"></p>
<p>The <a href="https://ascensionpress.com/ciy">Catechism in a Year podcast</a>, hosted by Fr. Mike Schmitz and published in 2023, goes through the entire Catechism of the Catholic Church in one year of daily readings.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If you have ever wanted to understand what it means to be Catholic and allow those truths to shape your life—this podcast is for you!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This unofficial app shows each day’s readings, and remembers where you left off.</p>
<p>Download:
<img src="https://www.nkorth.com/palm/apps/ciy_icon.png">
<a href="https://www.nkorth.com/palm/apps/CInAYear-1.2.zip">CInAYear-1.2.zip</a></p>
  

</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Ask HN: What nonfiction books do you keep rereading? (146 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40277933</link>
            <guid>40277933</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 18:33:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40277933">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <tbody><tr id="40279148"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279148" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279148&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>"Project Management for the Unofficial Project Manager". Many knowledge workers manage projects on a daily or weekly basis, yet most, including myself, don't have formal training in it and will profusely reject the title "Project Manager". The book gives a no-bullshit guide to manage things—deliverables, deadlines, schedules, and scope—and how to lead people—team members, customers, etc.<p>"The Emperor of All Maladies". A haunting, personal, and intimate biography of cancer. Having been on the peripherals of several cancer patients, I find the book an incredible overview of the disease, and how to deal with its physical, mental, and societal consequences.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279273"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279273" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279273&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span><i>Interconnections: Bridges, Routers, Switches, and Internetworking Protocols 2nd Edition</i> - Radia Perlman<p>Every 2-3 years, particularly in the periods when I'm <i>not</i> actively in network engineering, I re-read this book from start-finish - and it just completely centers my mindset with regards to pretty much every fundamental topic in Network Engineering.   There almost didn't need to be a 2nd Edition - most of the major topics were covered in 1st edition - the only major difference is the use of lots of protocol examples.   The core material itself is timeless.</p><p>Here is just one gem from Chapter 5 - "Hubs, Switches, Virtual Lans and Fast Ethernet"</p><p>"I originally resisted adopting the term <i>switch</i>. Unlike <i>thing</i>, <i>switch</i> sounds like a word you'd apply to a well-defined concept, so it makes people assume that there is a crisp definition that everyone else knows. I thought the world was already confusing enough with the terms <i>bridge</i> and <i>router</i>. Unfortunately, people coined the word <i>switch</i> assuming they were inventing a new concept, somehow different from a <i>bridge</i> or a <i>router</i>. And there were various independent product concepts named <i>switch</i>. As "switch" vendors expanded the capabilities of their products, the products wound up being functionally the same as bridges and routers, usually a hybrid or superset. One cynical (and ungrammatical) definition I use for <i>switch</i> is "a marketing term that means fast." Almost all products these days are some hybrid or superset of bridges and routers. So maybe it's right for the industry to settle on a new word, <i>switch</i>, as a more generic term for a box that moves data."
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40281145"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40281145" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40281145&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>My copy had a blurb from tptacek on the cover. I don't know which edition that was.<p>After reading your comment I'm sorry I didn't keep the book!
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40282825"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40282825" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40282825&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>It's the 2nd edition. I can't tell you how weird it was to be asked for that blurb. I was 22!<p>It is a great book, though.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="40280539"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40280539" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40280539&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>I don’t know if my understanding is correct but I always thought of a switch in contrast to a network hub. A hub broadcasts incoming packets to all its ports while a switch keeps a table and broadcasts only to the port that MAC is plugged into. That table is likely called a “routing table”, which probably drives some confusion. I always thought of a router as an internet connected switch. In addition, I always thought of a modem as something that can speak the language of the line (phone lines originally) instead of just the network protocol.<p>I’m not a network pro and these concepts could be totally wrong in my mind. Not sure why I’m spewing them out, other than to give myself something to solidify in the future.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40283318"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40283318" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40283318&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>You're mostly there - your hub definition is spot on - it's basically an electrical repeater and doesn't inspect the packet in any way* and operates at half-duplex.<p>Switches (specifically Layer 2 switches) will send broadcast frames to all ports*, but traffic that is unicast to a specific MAC address will only be sent to the port where that MAC address was learnt.  To keep track of the MAC address to port mappings, a switch will have one or more "forwarding" or "MAC-address" tables.</p><p>Routers (and Layer 3 switches) are not necessarily Internet connected, but will mostly be seen in larger networks.  Being mostly Ethernet-based these days, they maintain two tables - an ARP table (mapping IP Addresses to MAC Addresses) and a routing table (mapping IP prefixes/routes to destination IP addresses).  When an IP packet comes into a port, the router will consult it's routing table and find the most specific route that matches the destination of the packet.  From the destination IP of the route, it will then determine the egress interface that it should send the packet towards, then use the ARP table to work out the destination Ethernet MAC address for the Ethernet frame it will construct to transport the IP packet in on it's way to the next-hop router.</p><p>* During the early 00s there were "Dual-Speed Hubs", which were basically two hubs (one 10Mbps, one 100Mbps) joined together internally via a two-port Ethernet switch.  Fortunately the price of 100Mbps Ethernet switches kept falling and they weren't around too long.</p><p>* Provided those ports are all members of the same broadcast domain/VLAN
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="40283141"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40283141" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40283141&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>The Reign of Quantity and the Signs of the Times - Rene Guenon (1945).<p>An esoteric book that summarises everything as a direction which moves away from quality and towards quantity. Here is an excerpt that uses this system to analyse modern workplace anonymity:</p><p>"[...] tendency to uniformity demands that individuals shall be treated as mere numerical 'units', thus realizing equality by a leveling down, for that is the only direction in which equality can be reached 'in the limit' [...] Anyone who wonders what happens to the individual in such conditions will find that [...] he is so to speak reduced to his substantial aspect, and this amounts to saying that he becomes scarcely more than [...] 'a body without a soul'. From such an individual the qualitative or essential aspect has indeed almost disappeared ('almost', because the limit can never actually be reached); and [...] the individual really no longer has any 'name' that belongs to him, because he is emptied of the qualities which that name should express; he is thus really 'anonymous', but in the inferior sense of the word. This is the anonymity of the 'masses' of which the individual is part and in which he loses himself, those 'masses' that are no more than a collection of similar individuals, regarded purely and simply as so many arithmetical 'units'. 'Units' of that sort can be counted, and the collectivity they make up can thus be numerically evaluated, the result being by definition only a quantity; but in no way can each one of them be given a denomination indicating that he is distinguished from the others by some qualitative difference."
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279045"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279045" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279045&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>I'm re-reading Tracy Kidder's "The Soul of a New Machine" at the moment.  It's about Data General and the development of a new minicomputer.  I read it at the dawn of my IT career in the 1990s and found much of was still relevant then.  (the book was written in 1981)  Thirty years later, I'm mostly just nodding as I follow along; yep, yep, yep. "Engineering" is a distant second to corporate politics and office pecking order.<p>Reading Brian Shul's "Sled Driver" autobiography on the tablet.  Shul was an SR-71 pilot, and the book is about 10% Shul and 90% SR-71.  It reads fast and it's interesting, with unexpected bits of information.</p><p>Just finished David Goggins' "Can't Hurt Me."  It's supposed to be a "motivational" autobiography.  I can't say I felt motivated.  Most of his problems were self-inflicted, and he treated his family and children like dirt.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40280011"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40280011" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40280011&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>As for David Goggins, I mostly agree, his level of drive is impressive at some level, but also just insane- he pushes himself to do things likely to cause permanent lasting injuries just because he can. It seems like he couldn't even get along with other Navy Seals, because they weren't disciplined and motivated enough for him, and wouldn't accept ideas like training to the point of serious injury or disability. But it makes zero sense- how can you be ready for a mission when you're injured? Ultimately, it seems like he's addicted to self harming to escape emotional trauma/pain, not because he's disciplined.<p>Jocko Willink is a similar "Navy seal teaching you the secrets to becoming a badass" but his approach seems a lot more sane and useful, and has been more effective in his own life.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279413"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279413" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279413&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I looked up Sled Driver and the cheapest I can find is $350 on eBay (with $475 being the next best price). Where did you find the book?</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40280963"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="40281398"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40281398" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40281398&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>If you like history you should check out 19th Century Swiss historian Jacob Burckhardt's collection of essays Force and Freedom - I read it every 2 years or so. It's great summary of the different sources of power in society and how they interact during different periods. Highly recommended.<p>"In Force and Freedom, Burckhardt reduced the main elements of history to the state, religion, and culture, discussing the hypothetical and actual supremacy of each over the other two. “Culture” comes out best, religion worst in his value system, but the state has its dangers too..."</p><p><a href="https://www.encyclopedia.com/people/history/historians-european-biographies/jacob-christoph-burckhardt" rel="nofollow">https://www.encyclopedia.com/people/history/historians-europ...</a>
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279581"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279581" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279581&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span><i>Glenn Gould Reader</i>, a collection of writings by Canadian pianist Glenn Gould<p><i>Eye, Brain, Vision</i> by David Hubel, IMO an excellent introduction to visual neuroscience for the layperson and a really, really nice example of good scientific writing</p><p><i>Huygens and Barrow, Newton and Hooke</i> by VI Arnold, for the density of ideas</p><p><i>Perceptrons</i> by Minsky and Papert, mainly as an example of clear mathematical exposition
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279466"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279466" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279466&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>The Abolition of Man - C. S. Lewis<p>All Things Considered - G. K. Chesterton</p><p>Some others I daren't mention.</p><p>Category Theory for Programmers - Bartosz Milewski</p><p>The Design of Relational Databases -  Heikki Mannila, Kari-Jouko Raiha
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40281821"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40281821" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40281821&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>C.S. Lewis and G.K. Chesterton are great authors. I rather enjoy them along with Tolkien from that period and part of the world.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="40279034"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279034" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279034&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span><i>Trade Wars are Class Wars</i> by Klein and Pettis<p>I was originally pointed to this book as an answer to my persistent question "I love manufacturing, but it seems like the US economy hates manufacturing, why?" and while it <i>did</i> give me a satisfactory grasp of the macroeconomics involved, it also became my reference for a handful of trade policy / macroeconomic points that are, shall we say, less frequently bubbled up by The Submarine (in reference to the Paul Graham essay).
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40278733"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40278733" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40278733&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>- Zero to One, Peter Thiel<p>Always makes me feel that I’m not ambitious enough. And that too many smart people are in the wrong industry (finance).</p><p>- The Dip, Seth Godin</p><p>Don’t give up. Unless you’re in a cul-de-sac.</p><p>- Obviously Awesome, April Dunford</p><p>Your competitor is often not who you think it is.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40279216"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279216" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279216&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Same here - Zero to one - really inspiring book!<p>And Lean startup - far too ambitious for me at the moment, but I learned a lot from it.</p><p>4 hour work week - I would say it’s more like a fiction book, but still fun to read.</p><p>7 habits of highly effective people - it’s saved my life in high school, I knew some parts of it by heart.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40279445"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279445" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279445&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>I share your taste in books. 7 Habits in particular absolutely changed my life. I’ve always thought that its title doesn’t really do it justice. There is a lot more depth to that book than you’d think based on the title alone. It has helped set my moral compass.<p>Lean startup is a recent discovery for me - and boy do I wish I’d read it sooner!</p><p>Edit: also I highly recommend Stephen Covey’s audiobooks of 7 Habits and First Things First (read by him)
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="40280803"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40280803" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40280803&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>The War of Art by Pressfield, Natural Meditation by Dean Sluyter, Meditations by Marcus Aurelius and Art of Worldly Wisdom by Baltasar Gracián are books I often come back to ever couple of years.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40281894"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="40281810"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40281810" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40281810&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Walden, in which the author, Henry David Thoreau, builds a cabin in the woods and lives there for two years, two months, and two days. He gives up many of modern life’s luxuries and makes some incredibly profound observations on how much unnecessary bloat we have in modern life. It was published in 1854 yet remains relevant.<p>Henry David Thoreau was part of the Transcendentalist movement, so the book reflects a lot of that philosophy. I am revisiting it after first reading it a decade ago and am finding it really fascinating now that I’m older and have spent a bit of time in the workforce and in society.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40280820"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40280820" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40280820&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Why are most of you just listing books? At least explain why you reread those particular books, that's what's actually valuable here.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40281535"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40281535" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40281535&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>I agree that it'd be much more useful if people did that.<p>Without that information, I assume that the books that are mentioned more than once are the ones that I should look into.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="40283042"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40283042" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40283042&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I think Xenophon's Anabasis is an excellent treatise on leadership and crisis management, and his Hellenica is also a great look at the sources of and risks to moral authority.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40278885"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40278885" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40278885&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Never Split the Difference: Negotiating as if Your Life Depended on It - Chris Voss<p>Clear actionable direction on how to negotiate.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40279565"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279565" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279565&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I have gotten hundreds of thousands of dollars of value with “would it be ridiculous if”</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279069"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279069" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279069&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>It's a good book, but I've read it a few years ago and already forgot most of it. I gather you need to refresh this knowledge just before you negotiate.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                            <tr id="40282991"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40283213"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="40282780"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40282813"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="40279382"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40278312"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40278312" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40278312&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>When I reread these, I always pick up some details that I missed in the earlier reads:<p>- On the shortness of life
- Traction: How Any Startup Can Achieve Explosive Growth
- Show your work and Steal like an artist
- Domain modeling made functional
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40279635"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="40281718"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279561"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279561" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279561&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>For me is<p>the psychology of money</p><p>getting things done, first edition</p><p>How to Win Friends and Influence People (Unfortunate title for one of the best books on plain common sense when it comes to interacting with people)
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40279662"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40280248"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40280248" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40280248&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>"The one book we encourage startup founders to read is Dale Carnegie's How to Win Friends and Influence People. It's critically important for anyone in business. Try to get a used copy printed before the 1960s; after Carnegie died, the book continued to be "updated" by a committee, and the changes were not for the better."<p><a href="https://paulgraham.com/startupfaq.html" rel="nofollow">https://paulgraham.com/startupfaq.html</a>
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40282237"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="40282891"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40282891" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40282891&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>&gt;&gt;&gt; Unfortunate title for one of the best books on plain common sense when it comes to interacting with people)<p>Many say the same of the infamous “the art of the deal” from Donald J Trump” in 1989.</p><p>He, (pretty much), defines a base framework he still follows himself vehemently, today.</p><p>The way he executes today becomes a little less exciting, imo, each time he takes over headlines.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="40279505"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279505" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279505&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>The Beginning of Infinity by David Deutsch. Has an exceptionally high density of good ideas.<p>The first time I read it, I didn't love it and only engaged with it superficially. But gradually I began thinking about it more and came back to it, and I read it with more attention. After re-reading it several times I think it is one of the deepest and most important books I have ever read. It has changed how I see the world.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40282937"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40282954"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279279"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40280984"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40280984" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40280984&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>The Power of Now - Eckhart Tolle<p>Letting Go - David R Hawkins</p><p>Both books provide amazing reminders for the best ways to approach life and handle stress.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40282842"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279566"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279566" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279566&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>The Discourses of Epictetus - This is useful to re-read frequently while thinking about any new challenges in my life, as these are powerful tools for managing hardship and generally living well.<p>When I say no, I feel guilty by Manuel J. Smith - a book on assertive and non-manipulative communication. This has been incredibly valuable for improving my personal relationships and work. It's also allowed me to recognize and defend myself against emotional manipulation, which is more common than I realized. For many people that is the main way they communicate- by trying to control others with guilt through manipulation.. and I used to be both unaware and extremely vulnerable to it. It is useful to re-read and practice frequently, as these are skills that require practice.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40278808"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40278808" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40278808&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Offhand I can think of a few that I've read at least 2-3 times. And in a couple of cases, maybe as many as 4 or 5 times. There are probably some others that just aren't jumping to mind, but suffice it to say that these are all books I've found very valuable.<p><i>The Four Steps to the Epiphany</i> - Steve Blank</p><p><i>The Discipline of Market Leaders</i> - Michael Treacy and Fred Wiersema</p><p><i>Society of Mind</i> - Marvin Minsky</p><p><i>Mastering the Complex Sale</i> - Jeff Thull</p><p><i>How to Measure Anything</i> - Douglas Hubbard</p><p><i>The Selfish Gene</i> - Richard Dawkins
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40281082"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40281082" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40281082&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>&gt; The Selfish Gene - Richard Dawkins<p>I read this book a long time ago ... 2006, I think? I should re-read it. And read the author's sequel books to it.</p><p>Out of curiosity, would you say your understanding changed or deepened upon re-reading it?
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40281682"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40281682" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40281682&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>&gt; Out of curiosity, would you say your understanding changed or deepened upon re-reading it?<p>It's hard to do justice to that in a few words. I think I had a different reason for reading it the second time, as opposed to the first time.</p><p>The first time around, I think I was more reading it because I like to think of myself as an educated, scientific-minded person, and it was one of "those books" that any self-respecting "educated, scientific-minded person" was sort of "supposed to" have read. That and I was mentally already in a place somewhere in the nether regions between "agnostic" and "atheist" and I knew of Dawkins as a strong advocate for atheist thinking, and I guess I was looking for something that might convince me one way or the other. Or maybe that's just post-hoc rationalization on my part, but that's what I felt like I found. I felt much better about just calling myself an atheist after reading the book.</p><p>Anyway... one thing I was struck by though, was his discussion of things like kin altruism and reciprocal altruism and some of the game theoretical stuff, including mentions of Robert Axelrod and his research. So the second time I read the book, I was really looking to focus more on those sections, and take notes and do some further research. And all of that was really driven by my interest in evolutionary computing / genetic algorithms / etc. and a thought that I might find something there that I could apply to those areas. I wound up buying Axelrod's book <i>The Evolution of Cooperation</i>, but I sadly have not quite gotten around to reading it yet.</p><p>&gt; And read the author's sequel books to it.</p><p>I've also read <i>The Blind Watchmaker</i> twice, although that was sort of by accident. I forgot I'd already read it, and I was moderately deep into the second read before I realized I'd read it before. It was worth it though.</p><p>I still have <i>Climbing Mount Improbable</i>, <i>The God Delusion</i>, <i>The Ancestor's Tale</i>, and a couple of other Dawkins books queued up to read as well.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="40279360"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279360" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279360&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Atomic Habits.<p>It's a simple book that can be summarized in an essay, but listening to it repeatedly while driving helps me keep my life on track.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40279612"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279612" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279612&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Seems like a great idea/book, but I've never managed to make any of the advice work, despite trying pretty hard. I suspect this has something to do with having ADHD. In general there are a ton of productivity books out there that seem to be great advice, but are missing some steps that make it possible to implement for some people with ADHD.<p>In the same category, I also love the book "Deep Work" by Cal Newport, but also haven't gotten much real world traction from it.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40279762"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279762" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279762&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Tiny Habits by BJ Fogg might be a better book for you. The key to building habits is to start with a habit that is ridiculously small and once you feel like you've got that locked in, you can add another ridiculously small habit on top of it.<p>e.g. To build a flossing habit, floss just one tooth a day. Once you've got into the habit of pulling out floss and flossing just one tooth, you can move onto flossing two teeth and so on.</p><p>If at any point you feel resistance to doing the bigger habit you're trying to build up, you can always revert back to doing the initial tiny habit of flossing just one tooth.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40282053"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40282053" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40282053&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I think there needs to be some feedback that the goal is sustainable, one tooth a day to an adhd mind is just as bad as not doing anything as it's still a very tall staircase to climb. Too granular a step</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40282537"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40282537" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40282537&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>There is a reward at the end. That is an important requirement for this method.<p>It’s easy to try this out in a little more structured way and with assistance. Tiny habits [1] has a free five day program where you can try it and seek assistance from a person trained in this method. I tried it and it didn’t really stick for me, but I wouldn’t say that it was a total waste of my time. I could relate to the advice and I plan to read the book sometime.</p><p>[1]: <a href="https://tinyhabits.com/" rel="nofollow">https://tinyhabits.com</a>
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                              <tr id="40280116"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40280116" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40280116&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Has someone properly summarized Atomic Habits in an essay or perhaps a podcast episode? I'd rather just read an essay or listen to an episode repeatedly.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279582"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="40282011"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279570"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40282222"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279303"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279303" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279303&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>"Range: How generalists triumph in a specialized world"
"How to win friends and influence people"
"The History of Western Philosophy" Russell...though the Anthony Kenny series is at least as good.
"The Making of the Atomic Bomb" open at any page and there is an interesting story.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40280184"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40280184" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40280184&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>A Guide to the Good Life: The Ancient Art of Stoic Joy by William Irvine is great. I read it a couple of years ago and just recently listened to the audiobook. It definitely gives you a different perspective on how to approach life.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279392"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279392" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279392&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span><i>Profiles in Courage</i> by JFK (probably ghost written)<p>I go back to the section on Daniel Webster and the compromise of 1850 a lot. It always stuck with me how much courage it took to advocate for compromise and peace rather than head into a civil war.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279494"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40281284"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279562"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40282157"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="40280027"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40280027" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40280027&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>In no particular order...<p>0. Made in Japan: Akio Morita and Sony, by Akio Morita, Edwin M. Reingold, Mitsuko Shimomura</p><p>1. The Practice of Programming (TPOP) , by Brian W. Kernighan, Rob Pike</p><p>2. Wings of Fire, by A.P.J. Abdul Kalam, Arun Tiwari
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279274"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279274" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279274&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>The Myth of Sisyphus By Albert Camus. A great philosophy book, not that hard to read, about the absurdity of life. Camus talks about suicide in this context, and why life still has meaning despite its absurdity.
The Art of Not Giving A Fuck by Mark Manson. As the title implies, it talks about caring less about what other think (while not being a narcissist). And how it can make you more happy and more likeable.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40279309"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="40281633"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279255"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279255" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279255&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Isaacson's Steve Jobs. It's incredibly well executed in terms of writing and structure. A piece of art.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40279869"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="40279468"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40278854"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279130"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40278680"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279359"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40282103"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279535"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279577"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40277942"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40279401"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279401" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279401&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span><pre><code>    If the stars fall down on me
    And the sun refused to shine
    Then may the shackles be undone
    May all the old words cease to rhyme
    If the sky turned into stone
    It will matter not at all
    For there is no Heaven in the sky
    Hell does not wait for our downfall</code></pre></span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="40280220"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40280220" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40280220&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Eric Hoffer's "The True Believer"<p>Cicero's "How to Grow Old"</p><p>John Derbyshire's "Prime Obsession"
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40279007"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40279007" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40279007&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40277933"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>The Coming of Neo-Feudalism - Joel Kotkin (its a brainful)<p>Algorithns to live by - Brian Christian</p><p>Thinking Fast and Slow - Daniel khaneman</p><p>The Machiavellians: Defenders of Freedom - James Burnham
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40279292"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40281720"><td></td></tr>
                            </tbody></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[New way to have complex discussions (461 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://cq2.co/blog/the-best-way-to-have-complex-discussions</link>
            <guid>40277547</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 18:02:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://cq2.co/blog/the-best-way-to-have-complex-discussions">https://cq2.co/blog/the-best-way-to-have-complex-discussions</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40277547">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>We love complex, deep discussions.</p><p>We've seen or been part of many discussions — strategic discussions at work, discussions on<!-- --> <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/uMQ3cqWDPHhjtiesc/agi-ruin-a-list-of-lethalities">AI alignment</a>,<!-- --> <a href="https://discuss.python.org/t/pep-736-shorthand-syntax-for-keyword-arguments-at-invocation/43432">technical design documents</a>, public policy, etc. For us, the most frustrating issues with discussions are: impulsive responses and lack of structure.</p><p>The default way of discussions — in-person ones — are highly susceptible to impulsive responses and are extremely hard to provide a good structure for, making them the worst for complex topics.</p><p>The first issue of impulsive responses is a hard nut to crack. Practising and advocating for active listening is the ideal solution but it's not guaranteed to work every time and in every team. That's why we prefer written, async discussions over in-person ones for complex topics — they help prevent impulsive responses to an extent (and even more with features like slow mode) and promote thoughtful responses. But the second issue still remains — written, async discussions lack structure too. If you've used chat/forum platforms like Slack and Discourse for complex discussions, you know how hard it is to follow comments there.</p><p><span>Discourse</span>In Discourse, discussions are a stream of unorganised comments. This way of discussion — where people talk over one another and topics get mixed up — doesn't work for deep dives into complex and lengthy topics. For such topics, the discussion needs to be carefully written and organised.</p><p>There's no concept of “where” you are in Discourse discussions. There's only “when” you are, since the comments are ordered only by time. Discourse does provide some organisation to see the replies to a comment at one place. However if you need to see the replies to a particular reply inside a comment, you need to scroll down through other comments, find that particular reply (repeated as a comment!) and then check its replies:</p><p><img alt="CQ2 demo screenshot" fetchpriority="high" width="702" height="960" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://cq2.co/_next/static/media/discourse-comment-replies.02481816.png"></p><p><span>Slack</span>Slack is not really built for written, async discussions, but since it's widely used, let's talk about it. Discussions there are a stream of unorganised comments too, but at least Slack has threads to discuss a particular comment in detail in a separate pane. However, if you want to discuss a comment inside a thread in detail (i.e., create a new thread from a thread), you can't — Slack allows only one level of threads. Moreover, Slack feels too chatty — it feels impossible to have a long-running async discussion there. Its UI encourages sending bursts of fast, short comments instead of well-formed thoughts, and the typing indicator keeps everyone else distracted while one person tries to form their idea.</p><p><span>Quote hell</span>Now behold the common annoyance in all chat/forum platforms — the quote hell. What's that? Let's say Ava puts a comment about something. Then Caleb puts a comment with his replies to some quotes from Ava's comment. Now Ava puts a comment with her replies to Caleb's replies in quotes. What's happening? Replies to a topic are spread across different comments and you're forced to mentally manage all those quotes and their replies! On top of that, there are unrelated comments between that break your flow. These problems might not seem big for a discussion between two people, but a complex and lengthy discussion with 5+ participants quickly turns into a huge mess. Here's what a quote hell looks like:</p><p>After being frustrated with Slack, Discourse, etc., we started searching for a tool specifically built for complex discussions. We found none, began exploring how such a tool would work and look like, and started building:</p><p><span>CQ2</span>It's a free and open source tool for complex discussions. It's in its early stages, but it's the start of something that we think will both make discussions immensely enjoyable and radically increase productivity. We simulated a<!-- --> <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/uMQ3cqWDPHhjtiesc/agi-ruin-a-list-of-lethalities#sSfjskRzAuDcWmFWg">small discussion</a> <!-- -->from LessWrong on CQ2. Check it out on the live demo,<!-- --> <a href="https://cq2.co/app/demo">here</a>! It turned out to be much better organised and easier to follow.</p><p>In CQ2, there's no mess of unorganised comments — create threads inside threads so that each thread stays on topic and organised. Forget quote hell — create threads around specific quotes and find all replies related to a topic at one place. Never lose context of where you are — see all parent threads of the current thread in the same view. Focus on what matters — see which threads have unread comments, which are concluded and quickly go to a particular thread using CQ2's tree. Conclude threads — add conclusions to resolved threads and to the whole discussion once it's resolved.</p></div><div><p><span>Commenting and creating threads</span>General comments about the discussion go in the main (first and leftmost) thread. To reply to a particular text from the main description or from any comment, select the text, click on the popped-up “Reply in new thread” button to create a new thread around that specific quote, and reply there. You can reply to the whole comment as well, instead of a particular text inside it, by using the reply button on the top-right of the comment.</p></div><div><p><span>Opening threads</span>If someone has already created a thread for a particular quote, the quote would appear highlighted. You can click on it to open its corresponding thread and continue the discussion there. If someone has already created a thread for a whole comment, there would be a highlighted comments button on the top-right of the comment which you can click on to open the corresponding thread.</p></div><div><p><span>Navigating</span>To move between different threads, you can scroll using a trackpad or using your mouse's scroll wheel with the shift key. You can also use the tree from the navigation bar to quickly go to a particular thread. The tree also shows the number of comments in a thread, the number of unread comments and whether the thread has been concluded.</p></div><div><p><span>Concluding</span>You can conclude a thread by using the “Conclude thread” button on top of the thread. Concluded threads have a green badge on top and the conclusion comment in green. To conclude the whole discussion, use the “Conclude discussion” button in the navigation bar.</p></div><div><p>Try creating some threads and adding some comments in the demo,<!-- --> <a href="https://cq2.co/app/demo">here</a>!</p><p>We have many more interesting and useful features planned, including rich text, workspaces, custom titles for threads, mentions, slow mode, useful reactions (and not just emojis) and even an AI assistant to help you find overlooked parts of the discussion.</p><p>With CQ2, we want to help people have better discussions, and ultimately, systematically arrive at truth, better understand others and make better decisions. If you resonate with CQ2's mission, we would love for you to try it out, provide your feedback<!-- --> <a href="https://github.com/orgs/cq2-co/discussions/1">here</a> <!-- -->and share this post with your friends!</p><p>Get early access,<!-- --> <a href="https://tally.so/r/meB0yJ">here</a>.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Results of the Grand C++ Error Explosion Competition (2014) (234 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://tgceec.tumblr.com/post/74534916370/results-of-the-grand-c-error-explosion</link>
            <guid>40277469</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 17:57:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://tgceec.tumblr.com/post/74534916370/results-of-the-grand-c-error-explosion">https://tgceec.tumblr.com/post/74534916370/results-of-the-grand-c-error-explosion</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40277469">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Patagonia's New Study Finds Fleece Jackets Are a Serious Pollutant (2016) (123 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.outsideonline.com/outdoor-gear/gear-news/patagonias-new-study-finds-fleece-jackets-are-serious-pollutant/</link>
            <guid>40276957</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 17:18:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.outsideonline.com/outdoor-gear/gear-news/patagonias-new-study-finds-fleece-jackets-are-serious-pollutant/">https://www.outsideonline.com/outdoor-gear/gear-news/patagonias-new-study-finds-fleece-jackets-are-serious-pollutant/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40276957">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>
      Heading out the door? Read this article on the Outside app available now on iOS devices for members!
      <a href="https://outsideapp.onelink.me/wOhi/6wh1kbvw" data-analytics-event="click" data-analytics-data="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;Element Clicked&quot;,&quot;props&quot;:{&quot;destination_url&quot;:&quot;https://outsideapp.onelink.me/wOhi/6wh1kbvw&quot;,&quot;domain&quot;:&quot;<<analytics_vars.domain>>&quot;,&quot;name&quot;:&quot;in-content-cta&quot;,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;link&quot;}}">Download the app</a>.
    </p><div data-inject-ads="true" data-inject-ads-options="{&quot;markup&quot;:[&quot;<div class='o-ad-wrap'><div class='js-ad js-scroll-load' data-child-zone='in-content-leaderboard-ool' data-size='[\&quot;fluid\&quot;,[300,250],[1,1]]'><\/div><\/div>&quot;],&quot;filter&quot;:{&quot;nextExceptions&quot;:&quot;img, blockquote, div&quot;,&quot;nextContainsExceptions&quot;:&quot;img, blockquote, a.btn, a.o-button&quot;},&quot;renderIntial&quot;:true,&quot;wordCount&quot;:350}">
      <p>It all started on a beach in southwestern England in the early 2000s. Richard Thompson, then a senior lecturer at Plymouth University (where he now serves as professor of marine biology),&nbsp;was leading a team of graduate students researching microplastics in marine environments. Examining samples of sandy sediment, they expected to find degraded bits of marine plastic from decades-old flotsam&nbsp;or plastic beads that were becoming widely used in cleaners. To their surprise, most of the plastic fragments were fibrous, which meant they&nbsp;likely came from clothing, rope, or some types of packaging.</p>
<p>Then, in 2011, Mark Browne, one of Thompson’s former graduate students, published a study in which he examined sediment sampled from 15 beaches around the world. He&nbsp;found high concentrations of polyester and acrylic fibers in samples taken near wastewater treatment plants. He then ran a polyester fleece jacket through the wash and filtered 1,900 fibers from the wastewater—fibers that otherwise would&nbsp;have gone to the local wastewater treatment plant. Browne started reaching out to apparel makers to see if they’d help fund research to study this issue more deeply—eventually, he hoped, finding tweaks to fabric design or apparel construction that would stop the&nbsp;microfibers from entering wastewater. He received&nbsp;one offer of help—from women’s clothing brand Eileen Fisher—but Patagonia, Columbia, and other big brands declined, saying they didn’t know if the fibers were anything they needed to worry about.</p>
<div data-animation=""><blockquote><p>During laundering, a single fleece jacket sheds as many as 250,000 synthetic fibers—significantly more than the 1,900 fibers Browne first recorded. Based on an estimate of consumers across the world laundering 100,000 Patagonia jackets each year, the amount of fibers being released into public waterways is equivalent to the amount of plastic in&nbsp;up to&nbsp;11,900 grocery bags.</p></blockquote></div>
<p>Fast-forward four more years, and the fibers finally got everyone’s attention. <a href="https://www.outsideonline.com/1998166/plastics">The science was piling on</a>, showing that wastewater treatment plants couldn’t filter out all synthetic fibers,&nbsp;and that toxins such as DDT and PCBs can bind to them as they make their way into watersheds. It also showed&nbsp;that small aquatic species ingest the fibers, and that fish and bivalves sold for human consumption also contain microfibers. Experiments have&nbsp;shown that&nbsp;microplastics can lead to&nbsp;poor health outcomes in some species, and research is underway to find out how the plastics affect humans.</p>
<p>Jill Dumain, director of environmental strategy at&nbsp;<a href="http://www.patagonia.com/us/home" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Patagonia</a>, was one of the people paying attention to all the news. In early 2015, she&nbsp;and the&nbsp;company’s leadership decided to commission a study to find out if and how Patagonia’s iconic and well-loved fleeces and some other synthetic products were contributing to the problem.&nbsp;The results recently came&nbsp;in, and they’re not good.</p>
<p><a href="http://brenmicroplastics.weebly.com/project-findings.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The study</a>, performed by graduate students at the <a href="http://www.esm.ucsb.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bren School of Environmental Science and&nbsp;Management</a> at the University of California, Santa Barbara, found that during laundering, a single fleece jacket sheds as many as 250,000 synthetic fibers—significantly more than the 1,900 fibers Browne first recorded. Based on an estimate of consumers across the world laundering 100,000 Patagonia jackets each year, the amount of fibers being released into public waterways is equivalent to the amount of plastic in up to&nbsp;11,900 grocery bags.</p>
<p>The experiment involved five pieces of apparel: three Patagonia fleece jackets,&nbsp;each with slightly different construction, as well as a nylon shell jacket that contains polyester insulation, plus a fifth specimen—a “budget”&nbsp;fleece jacket made by an undisclosed brand. Replicates of each jacket&nbsp;were washed multiple times, both in front-loading and top-loading washing machines. The effluent from each cycle was collected and put through a two-step filtration system that captured fibers with both a 333- and 20-micrometer mesh screen.</p>
<p>The jackets were then put through a 24-hour “killer wash,”&nbsp;which Patagonia uses to simulate the aging of a garment. The researchers did this to test whether older garments might shed more fibers as they age. After repeating the washing tests on these artificially aged jackets, they saw that age&nbsp;indeed increases fiber release&nbsp;by 80&nbsp;percent.</p>
<p>In previous studies, researchers counted the total number of fibers, but that was not a viable path for this study, which instead calculated their mass. “We fully intended to do counts, but in the volumes of water that we collected and filtered, there were simply so many—hundreds of thousands—of fibers [from each test], we knew quickly that even with five of us [on the research team] we did not have time or energy to [do individual counts],”&nbsp;says Stephanie Karba, the lead researcher on the UCSB team.</p>
<p>Using an equation widely used in the textile industry to determine fiber count based on mass, researchers found that the highest estimate of fibers released from a single jacket was 250,000, and the average across all jackets was 81,317&nbsp;fibers.</p>
<p>Hoping to publish its detailed methodology in a science journal, the team hasn’t revealed all its findings. But in addition to data about fiber release, the Patagonia report shows that fiber loss is directly related to the type of washing machine and the age of the garment.&nbsp;Garments released five times as many microfibers when washed in top-loading washing machines&nbsp;compared to front-loaders. And aging&nbsp;affected fiber loss differently for different garments&nbsp;based on the type of washer. For example, compared to Patagonia jackets, the average mass of fiber shed from the budget jacket of undisclosed origin was much higher when it was washed at the new stage&nbsp;in a front-loader. But after all the jackets were aged, the Patagonia jackets shed a comparable amount of fibers to the budget jacket. In top-loaders, the budget jacket shed a comparable amount of fiber, on average, to the others when new.</p>
<p>Another surprise: The nylon shell jacket actually released a comparable amount of fiber to the fleece jackets in some tests, and even more in other tests, seeming to indicate that the polyester fill escaped through seams or the shell fabric.</p>
<p>Having reviewed the findings, Richard Thompson, the Plymouth University scientist whose work knocked over&nbsp;the first domino, says Patagonia’s report might be more useful for Patagonia than for the scientific community&nbsp;because it does not take a vastly different approach that Browne’s research. He says he’d have preferred if Patagonia’s tests had been done with the use of detergent (the UCSB researchers say detergent would have clogged the filters, which is also why Browne did not use detergent in his 2011 research) and on a wider selection of apparel items.</p>
<p>“The budget jacket seems to perform worse in some tests but better in others, but even if it performed consistently better or worse, you can still only reach the conclusion for that one budget jacket of unknown origin,”&nbsp;he says. Still, he thinks it was an important first move by industry. “Honestly, some companies might shy away from this; they might not want to open a can of worms. So it’s a environmentally responsible move&nbsp;and potentially quite risky, since there is not much data out there on everyone else’s apparel.”</p>
<p>Add to the list of concerns unique to the outdoor industry: chemical additives in performance apparel (think&nbsp;waterproof-breathable duds) that enter the water along with the fibers.</p>
<p>Of course, apparel companies are far from the only stakeholders being thrust into the spotlight. The role washing machines play in microfiber pollution is also a major concern, and scientists and apparel companies are calling on appliance manufacturers to investigate the efficacy of adding filters to washing machines to capture fibers before they enter wastewater. The problem will&nbsp;grow with the rise in the number of washing machines coming into use globally—Swedish statistician <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6sqnptxlCcw" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hans Rosling</a> says 2 billion of the 7 billion people on earth used washing machines in 2010, but he predicts that 5 billion out of the 9 billion humans expected to populate the earth by 2050 will use the appliances.</p>
<p>A <a href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/acs.est.5b05416" target="_blank" rel="noopener">study published last month</a>&nbsp;showed that while wastewater treatment plants remove more than 98 percent of plastic fragments from wastewater, they still send an estimated 65 million pieces of microplastics into watersheds each day. Polyester, the main fiber used in fleece, makes up the largest share of the plastics that get through—even though it only accounts for 10.8 percent of the plastic in influent wastewater (water that enters the plant). Also, many fibers that do get captured often end up in environmental sludge, which is sometimes added to fertilizer.</p>
<p>To try to get ahead of the problem, Patagonia and other apparel companies have said they want to research new yarn and fabric constructions to determine whether microfiber shedding can be addressed through better design, something that’s already happening in Europe.</p>
<p>After a 2013 European Commission–funded research program called Mermaids found that surfactants in detergents lead to much higher fiber loss—on the order of 1 million fibers shed from a single fleece jacket—textile specialists in Spain and Italy were tasked with developing a special coating or impregnation that would be applied to the fabric during manufacture and, in theory, reduce the amount of fiber loss. More details on the program are expected in December, but researchers say the coatings being tested and developed are environmentally benign.</p>
<p>The Mermaids program, promoted through the Plastic Soup Foundation, an NGO based in the Netherlands, has also released some guidelines based on its initial research, including suggestions to avoid the use of detergents with high pH, powder detergents, and the use of oxidizing agents. It also suggests washing clothing in cold water&nbsp;and softening hard water, and it released a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b8OZ_6YwTUE" target="_blank" rel="noopener">cheeky video</a>&nbsp;to drive its point home. Clothing company G-Star, which integrates synthetic fibers sourced from plastic ocean debris into the denim jeans it sells, has partnered with the Plastic Soup Foundation to promote the Mermaid program.</p>
<p>In August, at the Outdoor Retailer trade show in Salt Lake City, Patagonia will present the findings to its industry peers. It hopes to partner with the Outdoor Industry Association to turn the UCSB researchers’ testing protocol&nbsp;into an industry standard that would enable all clothing manufacturers to set a benchmark for fiber release from their apparel products. Dumain says it’s important that companies outside the outdoor niche start tracking microfiber issues&nbsp;as well. And she thinks an international third-party testing standards group, such as the ASTM, which has developed testing methods for factors such as sewn seams and flammability of apparel textiles, could also take the protocol and run with it. “It’s right up their alley,”&nbsp;Dumain says.</p>
<p>Unlike laws that restrict manufacturers from adding plastic microbeads to cleaning products, no obvious legislative approaches limit&nbsp;microfiber pollution, and apparel makers would likely prefer to self-impose approaches to reducing fiber loss rather than find themselves in the crosshairs of regulators&nbsp;should scientific evidence that microfibers pose environmental dangers continue to mount.</p>
<p>“We knew this would be step one in testing—to prove the methodology, to understand where we were contributing to the problem, where the industry could be contributing to the problem,”&nbsp;says Dumain. “From here, it’s going to set up a whole lot of testing that needs to happen throughout the apparel industry.”</p>

    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Show HN: Peerdb Streams – Simple, native Postgres change data capture (160 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40276768</link>
            <guid>40276768</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 17:00:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40276768">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><td colspan="2"></td><td><div><p>Hello HN, I am Sai Srirampur, one of the Co-founders of PeerDB. (<a href="https://github.com/PeerDB-io/peerdb">https://github.com/PeerDB-io/peerdb</a>). We spent the past 7 months building a solid experience to replicate data from Postgres to data warehouses. Now we're expanding to queues.</p><p>PeerDB Streams provides a simple and native way to replicate changes as they happen in Postgres to Queues (Kafka, Redpanda, Google PubSub, etc). We use Postgres logical decoding to enable Change Data Capture (CDC).</p><p>Blog post here: <a href="https://blog.peerdb.io/peerdb-streams-simple-native-postgres-change-data-capture">https://blog.peerdb.io/peerdb-streams-simple-native-postgres...</a>. 10-min quickstart here: <a href="https://docs.peerdb.io/quickstart/streams-quickstart">https://docs.peerdb.io/quickstart/streams-quickstart</a>.</p><p>We chose queues as many users found that existing tools are complex. Debezium is the most used tool for this use-case. It has large production usage. However, a common pain point among our users is that it has a significant learning curve taking months to productionize.</p><p>A few issues are: a) Interacting through a command line interface, understanding the various settings, and learning best practices for running it in production is not trivial. Debezium UI, released to address usability concerns [1], is still in an incubating state [2]. Additionally, reading Debezium resources to get started can be overwhelming [3]. 
b) Supporting data formats and transformations isn’t easy. It needs a Java project, building JAR packages and setting up a runtime path on the kafka connect plugin. c)Debezium is not as native as Kafka for other queues and doesn’t offer the same level of configurability. For example, with Event Hubs, it is difficult to stream to topics spread across namespaces and subscriptions.</p><p>TL;DR Debezium aims to provide a comprehensive experience for engineers to implement CDC rather than making it dead simple for them. So you can do a lot with Debezium but need to know a lot about it.</p><p>At PeerDB, we are building a simple yet comprehensive experience for Postgres CDC. The goal is to enable engineers to build prod-grade Postgres CDC with a minimal learning curve, within a few days.</p><p>PeerDB’s feature-set isn't at Debezium's level yet, and as we evolve, we might face similar challenges. However, we're putting usability at the forefront and we believe that we can achieve the above goal.</p><p>First, PeerDB offers a simple UI to set up Postgres and Kafka by creating PEERs and initiating CDC by creating a MIRROR. Through the UI, users can monitor the progress of CDC, including throughput and latency; set up alerts to Slack/Email based on replication slot growth; investigate Postgres-native metrics, including slot size, etc. Here is a demo showing of PeerDB UI in action:</p><p><a href="https://www.loom.com/share/ebcfb7646a1e48738835853b760e5d04" rel="nofollow">https://www.loom.com/share/ebcfb7646a1e48738835853b760e5d04</a></p><p>Second, for users who prefer a CLI, we provide a Postgres-compatible SQL layer to manage CDC. This offers the same level of features as the UI and is more intuitive compared to bash scripts.</p><p>Third, users can perform row-level transformations using Lua scripts executed at runtime. This enables features such as encrypting/masking PII data, supporting various data formats (JSON, MsgPack, Protobuf, etc.), and more. We offer a script editor along with a bunch of useful templates [5].</p><p>Fourth, we provide native connectors to non-Kafka targets. We also provide native configurability options tailored to these platforms. For example, with Event Hubs, users can perform CDC to topics distributed across different namespaces and subscriptions [4].</p><p>Finally, We are laser focused on Postgres, enabling specific optimizations like native metrics for replication, wait-events, and # of connections. Features like faster initial loads through parallel snapshotting and decoding transactions in-flight are in private beta.</p><p>Our hope is to provide the best data-movement experience for Postgres. PeerDB Streams is another step in that direction. We would love to get your feedback on product experience, our thesis and anything else that comes to your mind. It would be super useful for us. Thank you!</p><p>References:</p><p>[1] <a href="https://debezium.io/blog/2020/10/22/towards-debezium-ui/" rel="nofollow">https://debezium.io/blog/2020/10/22/towards-debezium-ui/</a>
[2] <a href="https://debezium.io/documentation/reference/stable/operations/debezium-ui.html" rel="nofollow">https://debezium.io/documentation/reference/stable/operation...</a>
[3] <a href="https://medium.com/@cooper.wolfe/i-hated-debezium-so-much-i-did-it-myself-b43b0efc20a9" rel="nofollow">https://medium.com/@cooper.wolfe/i-hated-debezium-so-much-i-...</a>
[4] <a href="https://blog.peerdb.io/enterprise-grade-replication-from-postgres-to-azure-event-hubs">https://blog.peerdb.io/enterprise-grade-replication-from-pos...</a>
[5] <a href="https://github.com/PeerDB-io/examples">https://github.com/PeerDB-io/examples</a>
[5] <a href="https://app.peerdb.cloud/" rel="nofollow">https://app.peerdb.cloud</a>
[6] <a href="https://github.com/PeerDB-io/PeerDB">https://github.com/PeerDB-io/PeerDB</a></p></div></td></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[German public broadcasters open source their streaming platforms (208 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.heise.de/en/news/ARD-und-ZDF-wollen-ihren-Streaming-Code-als-Open-Source-anbieten-9709177.html</link>
            <guid>40276714</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 16:56:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.heise.de/en/news/ARD-und-ZDF-wollen-ihren-Streaming-Code-als-Open-Source-anbieten-9709177.html">https://www.heise.de/en/news/ARD-und-ZDF-wollen-ihren-Streaming-Code-als-Open-Source-anbieten-9709177.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40276714">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="ltr">
    

      

<div>
  <p><em>This article was originally published in German and has been automatically translated.</em>
  </p>
</div>


<p>The streaming media libraries of the public broadcasters ARD and ZDF are also growing together technically: The broadcasters want to develop a joint "streaming OS", they announced on Monday. The code is also to be made publicly available as part of "one of the largest open source initiatives in Germany".</p>

    
  

  
  <a-paternoster height="360" media="(min-width: 320px) and (max-width: 767px)">
    

  
    
    
  

  </a-paternoster>



<p>Competitors should also be able to use the Streaming OS code in this way, ARD Chairman Kai Gniffke commented on the initiative. He can imagine a cross-provider German streaming network. "If other institutions – including media companies that compete with us – use the software, then you can also imagine it as the nucleus for a large German-language platform."</p>
<p>ARD and ZDF media libraries also want to use the shared technical foundation to manage user data across the board. Meanwhile, it is still unclear which parts of Streaming OS will be made publicly available. In addition to the streaming player itself, the broadcasters' joint streaming software will also bundle the login system, code for recommendations and the "core of the design system". ARD and ZDF are thus also placing their media libraries on a common technical basis, <a href="https://www.heise.de/news/ARD-und-ZDF-verknuepfen-ihre-Mediatheken-9331478.html?from-en=1">having already grown together in terms of content in recent years</a>.</p>

  





<h3 id="nav__giving__0">"Giving something back to society"</h3>
<p>In addition to private providers, educational institutions can also benefit from the broadcasters' planned open source code, according to the broadcasters. "In this way, we are giving something back to society for which it has paid us," comments ZDF Director General Norbert Himmler on the project. Cooperation with European partners is also conceivable, according to a statement.</p>
<p>ARD and ZDF are setting up a joint office for the streaming OS, where the project will be managed. The technical development of the operation is to take place in a commercial subsidiary, which will be founded under the management of ARD. The broadcasters hope that Streaming OS will be ready in spring 2025.</p>
<p>

<!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->
<span>(<a href="mailto:dahe@heise.de" title="Daniel Herbig">dahe</a>)</span>
<!-- RSPEAK_START -->
</p>

      <!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->

      

      

      

      

      <!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->

    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Spending an afternoon in the Sizewell control-room simulator (103 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bentasker.co.uk/posts/blog/general/an-afternoon-in-sizewell-b-control-room-simulator.html</link>
            <guid>40276442</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 16:27:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bentasker.co.uk/posts/blog/general/an-afternoon-in-sizewell-b-control-room-simulator.html">https://www.bentasker.co.uk/posts/blog/general/an-afternoon-in-sizewell-b-control-room-simulator.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40276442">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p>A few weeks ago, I was fortunate enough to be invited to tag along on a trip to the Operations Training Simulator at <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sizewell_nuclear_power_stations">Sizewell B Nuclear power station</a>.</p>
<p>Located on the Suffolk coast, Sizewell B is currently the UKs only <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pressurized_water_reactor">Pressurised Water Reactor (PWR)</a> and is operated by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EDF_Energy">EDF Energy</a> (I've also previously accidentally <a href="https://www.bentasker.co.uk/bucket_day/">met some of their police force</a>).</p>
<p>The simulator is a high fidelity reproduction of the site's control room. They've reproduced the original to the extent that one of the walls even sports painted-on doors (complete with a view into the "kitchen") because that's where the doors are in the real room.</p>
<p>Aside from the carpet being somewhat less worn, a huge amount of effort has been put into ensuring that it is essentially a 1:1 reproduction of the actual control room.</p>
<!-- TEASER_END -->

<hr>

<h4>The Reactor</h4>
<p>The reactor is a Westinghouse PWR, running two steam turbines.</p>
<p>As you enter the training centre, there's a model showing the contents of Sizewell's dome</p>
<p><img alt="Photo of a model of the reactor dome. The reactor is encased in concrete and there're turbines etc." src="https://www.bentasker.co.uk/images/BlogItems/sizewell_control_room/reactor_model.jpg"></p>
<p>Sizewell currently consists of two sites - <code>A</code> and <code>B</code>. </p>
<p><code>A</code> shut-down back in 2007 and is being decommissioned. The James Bond-esque building on the left is its turbine hall (sadly <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20240503105106/https://www.eadt.co.uk/news/23268431.sizewell-turbine-hall-set-bulldozed-summer/">scheduled for demolition this summer</a>). </p>
<p><img alt="Photo of Sizewall take from the beach in 2020. There's a large concrete building - A - and just behind it a much shorter blue building with a white dome coming out of it" src="https://www.bentasker.co.uk/images/BlogItems/sizewell_control_room/sizewell_A_and_B.jpg"></p>
<p>The blue building with the golf-ball dome is Sizewell B.</p>
<p>When it's built <a href="https://www.edfenergy.com/energy/nuclear-new-build-projects/sizewell-c">Sizewell C</a> will be a little bit further down, just beyond <code>B</code>.</p>
<hr>

<h4>The Simulator</h4>
<p>When someone says "nuclear control room" there's a certain image that springs to mind - one of a room with beige panels <em>covered</em> in switches.</p>
<p>Sizewell... does not disappoint:</p>
<p><img alt="Photo of a bank of control panels. They're L shaped, beige and covered in switches eeeeee" src="https://www.bentasker.co.uk/images/BlogItems/sizewell_control_room/control_room.jpg"></p>
<p>Each of the switches can illuminate. If the system detects that something has changed state (for example, a valve has opened) and disagrees with the control, the switch will light up (and an alert will sound).</p>
<p>Changes are staged by turning the relevant switch (causing it to flash) and then effectively committed by pushing the switch in. Somewhere in the plant, something moves and the light stops flashing once plant and switch are back in agreement.</p>
<p>There's a big panel at the back of the room, covered in gauges and red switches</p>
<p><img alt="Photo of the panel at the back. The vertical plane is covered in dials and gauges. The horizontal plane has red toggle switches, each with a cover to prevent accidental knocks" src="https://www.bentasker.co.uk/images/BlogItems/sizewell_control_room/trip_panel.jpg"></p>
<p>Each of these switches allow the operator to trigger some form of protection routine if they feel that the system <em>hasn't</em> done something that it should have. </p>
<p>The big round button in the bottom left is the Reactor Trip (SCRAM to the Americans) button - hitting it causes the control rods to be dropped into the core, taking the reactor offline and protecting the plant (<strong>Obviously</strong> this got pressed whilst we were there, simulating a trip).</p>
<p>The simulator also includes a reproduction of the backup room</p>
<p><img alt="Photo of the backup room - it's a straight bank of panels. Very few switches on this one" src="https://www.bentasker.co.uk/images/BlogItems/sizewell_control_room/backup_bridge.jpg"></p>
<p>There are very few switches in this room - it's much more about being able to see the state of systems than it is about interacting with them.</p>
<hr>

<h4>Operational Discipline</h4>
<p>We were <strong>extremely</strong> fortunate in that we were being shown around by someone who's worked in Sizewell's control room for a <em>long</em> time, making it a <strong>hugely</strong> educational experience.</p>
<p>Unsurprisingly the processes involved in operating a nuclear power station are <strong>very</strong> strict and well codified. Operating procedures are clearly defined by the regulator (the <a href="https://www.onr.org.uk/">ONR</a>) and laid out across a massive set of binders in a way that reminded me, very much, of dealing with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joint_Service_Publication">JSPs</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Everything</strong> that an operator does is subject to scrutiny: If something happens, there's a (sometimes lengthy) review, with procedures adjusted as needed to mitigate any perceived risk that it highlights.</p>
<p>There are simple physical safeguards too. There's a border of purple carpet which runs along the front of all the panels:</p>
<p><img alt="There's purple carpet just in front of the panels whereas the centre of the room has blue carpet" src="https://www.bentasker.co.uk/images/BlogItems/sizewell_control_room/border.jpg"></p>
<p>Operators don't step inside this border without permission from the operations manager. The idea being that, outside of this area, a trip or stumble is extremely unlikely to actuate any switches. </p>
<p>Similarly, no-one simply walks into the room - they have to wait at the red line (on the left) until the manager tells them they can enter (ensuring that someone entering doesn't distract from anything that might be ongoing).</p>
<hr>

<h4>Terminology</h4>
<p>It's always interesting seeing how things work in a different industry. Operational doctrine is almost always the same (albeit with different levels of rigour), but the terminology used can be <em>very</em> different.</p>
<p>The phrase <strong>reactor trip</strong>, for example, sounds like it could be <em>really bad</em>. But, actually, it refers to the reactor having been <em>made safe</em>: The control rods are fully inserted, absorbing neutrons and essentially stopping the reactor. <em>Something</em> led to that happening, of course, but the trip itself isn't automatically a problem (in fact, it's the safeguard working <em>exactly as intended</em>).</p>
<p>Similarly, the word <strong>outage</strong> was used <em>a lot</em>. But, although it makes me think "oh no, <code>x</code> is down, incident channel <strong>now</strong>", it's actually referring to planned downtime: Every 18 months, the plant stops supplying the grid for maintenance and refuelling.</p>
<p>Clearly, it's quite easy to hear some of the terms and think "DANGER", but actually they're all fairly innocuous in this context. </p>
<hr>

<h4>Technology</h4>
<p>The simulator is an impressive beast. </p>
<p>It's not just a bank of switches and LEDs, they're all controlled by a computer which knows how to work out what should happen if you've opened valve A but closed valve B. It reliably simulates the behaviour of the real plant and wasn't at all phased by our chaos-monkey-esque attempts to introduce problems.</p>
<p>The simulator allows operators to build and run scenarios, but also allows trainers to manually change the state of components (perhaps to cause a light to flash on a panel that someone's looking towards and check that they react to it).</p>
<p>The control systems can automatically respond to issues - the role that humans play is primarily one of oversight and review: are the control systems reacting to a change in the defined way? </p>
<p>If not, then the human intervenes and triggers the necessary actions, even being able to manually raise and lower the control rods if needed</p>
<p><img alt="There is even a joystick which can be used to manually raise and lower the controls rods. Nuclear tetris eh?" src="https://www.bentasker.co.uk/images/BlogItems/sizewell_control_room/rod_control.jpg"></p>
<p>To make changes, operators don't need to put the system into any kind of "manual override" mode, so in the unlikely event that they make a mistake, the system is still able to catch and react to it (potentially tripping the reactor and taking the plant offline).  There's something <em>very</em> symbiotic about the design really.</p>
<p>Both the simulator and the operations room collect <em>copious</em> amounts of time-series data - in principle, it's possible to say what position any given switch was in at any given time since the plant started operating.</p>
<hr>

<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>The control room is built upon 1980's technology (and American technology at that) - after all, it's not exactly cheap or easy to do a hardware refresh in the control room of a tightly regulated and licensed operation. </p>
<p>But, it also means that nearly half a century of experience has been poured into ensuring that things can keep running safely.</p>
<p>That experience isn't just built locally either, operators and regulators at plants around the world share experience and knowledge in order to help improve safety. If something <strong>does</strong> happen at a plant, lessons are fed back (for example, systems around the world were updated after <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three_Mile_Island_accident">Three Mile Island</a> to ensure that pumps couldn't be disabled in the way they had been there).</p>
<p>The control system has all sorts of little touches that make you go "<em>oh, that's a <strong>good</strong> idea</em>". For example, there are multiple alarms that can sound, potentially simultaneously. The timbre and frequency of them has been chosen so that it's easily possible to tell if more than one is sounding (as well as which).</p>
<p>Apparently, Sizewell C's control room will use touch screens instead of tactile switches. Although likely easier to maintain and repair, I think it'll lose <em>something</em> as a result of this teslaisation .</p>
<p>Still, once it's built, I'd love to get to have a look at that too, this <strong>really</strong> was an <em>excellent</em> way to spend an afternoon.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>